<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "imh_issue.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="VAA4025-028-2">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Indiana Magazine of History</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoded by</resp>
               <name>Aptara Inc.</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <date>2007</date>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>Copyright 2007 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
               <p>Indiana University provides the information contained in this file for non-commercial,
        personal, or research use only. All other use, including but not limited to commercial or
        scholarly reproductions, redistribution, publication or transmission, whether by electronic
        means or otherwise, without prior written permission of the copyright holder is strictly
        prohibited.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Indiana Magazine of History</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title>Indiana Magazine of History</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Indiana University Department of History in cooperation with the Indiana
                                Historical Society</publisher>
                     <date>1932</date>
                     <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="volume">28</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="pages">73-148</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07-24</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Annette D. Richmond</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Changed VAA4025-028-2-a05 from scholarlyArticle to editorialMaterial. Split VAA4025-028-2-a08 into
                    two pieces; the first was left as type bookReview and the second was created as type
                    editorialMaterial with id VAA4025-028-2-a11. Inserted missing footnotes, corrected spelling of
                    blockquote, encoded letters and diaries.</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n="[]" id="VAA4025-028-2-001"/>
         <pb n="[]" id="VAA4025-028-2-002"/>
      </front>
      <body>
         <pb n="[73]" id="VAA4025-028-2-003"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-028-2-a01">
            <head>Editor John B. Stoll</head>
            <byline>By H. S. K. BARTHOLOMEW</byline>
            <p>During the last quarter of the nineteenth century a number of editors of note lived and worked in our
                    Hoosier state whose names were household words in their own sections while several men were well
                    known throughout the commonwealth. Each one of them came to be so closely identified with the
                    journal over which he presided that mention of one immediately suggested the other. In the capital
                    city, the name of John C. New brought to mind the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Journal</hi> and Samuel E. Morse the <hi rend="i">Sentinel.</hi> The Fort <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wayne</region>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Sentinel</hi> and E. A. K. Hackett; the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Terre Haute</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi> and William C. Ball; the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Evansville</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Courier</hi> and John Gilbert Shanklin—in each case the man and his
                    newspaper were in a certain sense synonymous. So, too, in the extreme north end of the state, was
                    John B. Stoll and his <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">South Bend</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Times.</hi> Mr. Stoll outlived all of the others listed. Like them he wielded a great
                    influence for many years and his utterances were greeted with respect far and wide. For some years
                    before he died, he was styled the Nestor of Indiana journalism.</p>
            <p>John B. Stoll was born in Wurtemburg, <placeName>
                        <country reg="gw">Germany</country>
                    </placeName> on March 13, 1843. Several months before his birth, his father was drowned in the River
                    Nurg. He left a rich landed estate, but his wife married again and in the course of a few years the
                    estate was squandered by the second husband, leaving the mother and son, then ten years old, in
                    poverty.</p>
            <p>The mother had heard that America offered better opportunities than her native land, so she decided
                    to emigrate and, crossing the Atlantic, located in <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Harrisburg</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>
               </placeName>. Two
                    years later she died leaving her son to make his way alone. He worked at anything he could find to
                    do to support. himself <pb n="74" id="VAA4025-028-2-004"/> and finally secured employment in the
                    office of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Harrisburg</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Telegraph.</hi> There he not only thoroughly mastered the printer's trade but
                    became an omnivorous reader. His education in the schools of <placeName>
                        <country reg="gw">Germany</country>
                    </placeName> was very meager. Besides that, he had to master a new language when he came to this
                    country, which was an additional handicap for him. However, his ambition knew no bounds and he was
                    determined that no obstacle should stand in the way of his advancement. By making use of all of his
                    spare time in study he overcame the disadvantages of his early life and by the time he had reached
                    his majority he was a well educated man.</p>
            <p>At an early age he became interested in politics. His study of history and government gave him a keen
                    insight into the questions which were then uppermost in the public mind. He identified himself with
                    the Democratic party and before he was of age sat as a delegate in the convention which nominated
                    Stephen A. Douglas for the presidency. At that time he became an ardent admirer—almost a
                    worshipper—of the "Little Giant" and remained so until the untimely
                    death of his idol.</p>
            <p>In 1863 he became the owner of a newspaper, the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Middlebury</settlement>
                    </placeName> (<placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>
                    </placeName>) <hi rend="i">People's Friend.</hi> A little later he disposed of that
                    publication and bougth the Johnstown <hi rend="i">Observer.</hi> His apprenticeship had brought to
                    him a complete mastery of the mechanical department and his diligent study and wide reading had
                    given him a vast fund of knowledge which equipped him for editorship. In both of those <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>
                    </placeName> communities he wielded a wide and steadily growing influence. About the time that he
                    embarked in journalism on his own account, he was united in marriage with Miss Mary F. Snyder, a
                    descendant of Simon Snyder, one of the early governors of the Keystone state. She was a splendid
                    type of genuine womanhood who proved a true helpmeet to her husband for half a century.</p>
            <p>Obeying the teachings of his hero, Stephen A. Douglas, at the opening of the Civil War, young Stoll
                    gave himself heart and soul to the Union cause, continuing to do so as long as that struggle lasted.
                    After the war was over, he concluded that better opportunities for advancement in his chosen
                    vocation could be found farther west and he came to Indiana in quest of a location. He selected the
                    thriving town of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Ligonier</settlement>
                    </placeName> where he established the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Ligonier</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Banner</hi>, putting out his first issue on May 3, 1865. The era of so-called
                    reconstruction was one <pb n="75" id="VAA4025-028-2-005"/> of bitter political controversies and
                    Stoll became one of the fighting editors of that time. He espoused the cause of President Andrew
                    Johnson in the strenuous conflicts between the Executive and the "Jacobins" in
                    Congress. The latter were led by Thaddeus Stevens, Benj. F. Wade, James Ashley and others. Although
                    published in a country town the <hi rend="i">Banner</hi> was widely read and its vigorous editorials
                    wielded a potent influence throughout northeastern Indiana. Its every issue severely arraigned those
                    individuals who trampled upon the policy that had been formulated by Abraham Lincoln for the
                    restoration of the Southern states to their place in the Union—a policy which Andrew
                    Johnson was faithfully endeavoring to carry out. As Mr. Stoll had in his Johnstown paper vigorously
                    upheld the war for the maintenance of the Union under the Constitution, he now just as vigorously
                    opposed the assaults that were being made upon the Constitution. Could the reader go over the files
                    of the <hi rend="i">Banner</hi> during those memorable years, he would become thorougly informed
                    concerning the odious carpet-bag era in the South and the nefarious methods which were employed by
                    the majority in Congress to uphold the adventurers from the North who were plundering the southern
                    people.</p>
            <p>Stoll's work on the <hi rend="i">Banner</hi> not only satisfied Democrats but it soon
                    attracted the attention of Republicans, who felt the effects of it. They began to lay plans to tempt
                    the fighting editor to leave his party, join them, and man one of their organs. The late Hiram
                    Iddings of Kendallville, a personal friend, invited Stoll to call at his office in that city on a
                    certain day for an interview. The journalist at that time, held a minor office in the internal
                    revenue department of the government and had occasion to visit Kendallville every week on official
                    business. He timed his visit that particular week so that he would be able to comply with the
                    request of Iddings, having not the least idea of the purport of the interview. When he arrived at
                    the appointed place, Stoll found with Iddings a number of the Republican leaders of Noble county.
                    They proposed to him that he should become editor of the Kendallville <hi rend="i">Standard</hi>,
                    the leading Republican paper of the County, at that time a prosperous publication. They offered to
                    buy the paper and turn it over to him free of cost on his part if he would come to Kendallville and
                    take charge. He replied to them substantially in these words: "Gentlemen, should <pb n="76" id="VAA4025-028-2-006"/> the time ever come when I see fit to join the Republican party, I will
                    do so of my own free will and without any financial inducements whatsoever." He then bowed
                    himself out of the room. The negotiators were fairly stunned by his abrupt refusal, for they seemed
                    to feel that the offer would be one that he could not resist.</p>
            <p>A year or so later Stoll was visited in his own office by an emissary of Senator Oliver P. Morton who
                    made him a still more tempting offer. This time the young editor was offered the old Fort <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wayne</region>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi>, again without cost to himself. Besides, the Senator, who was the absolute
                    dictator of the Republican party in Indiana, offered to obtain for him an office, a mere sinecure,
                    which would have paid him a handsome salary. The acceptance of the offer would probably have trebled
                    the income derived from the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Ligonier</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Banner</hi>, but again Stoll gave a peremptory refusal. He was told afterwards that his
                    refusal to accept that offer was a great disappointment to Senator Morton, who was not accustomed to
                    have his requests turned down and who was not over scrupulous as to the methods which he employed to
                    accomplish his purposes.</p>
            <p>Not only did Mr. Stoll establish a reputation as an able and fearless editor but he also became
                    widely known as a public speaker. In every campaign for many years he spoke in every section of the
                    state. His services on the stump brought him in contact with all of Indiana's Democratic
                    leaders and he was acknowledged to be the peer of any of them. For years he was on intimate terms
                    with Thomas A. Hendricks, Joseph E. McDonald, Daniel W. Vorhees, David Turpie, William S. Holman,
                    Joseph A. S. Mitchell, and many more of the outstanding Democrats of the state. When momentous
                    questions of party policy were discussed his counsel was frequently sought. In 1872 he was nominated
                    for auditor of state and after a thorough canvass was defeated by 273 votes. That was the year of
                    the Greeley fiasco when many Democrats, disgusted with the endorsement of the Liberal Republican
                    ticket, stayed away from the polls. But two men on the Democratic state ticket were elected that
                    year and their election was due to their personal popularity throughout the state. These two were
                    Thomas A. Hendricks, for many years the idol of the Indiana Democracy, who was chosen governor, and
                    Milton B. Hopkins, one of the leaders in the Disciples' Church, who was re-elected State
                    Superintendent of Public Instruction.</p>
            <pb n="77" id="VAA4025-028-2-007"/>
            <p>Defeat did not cool the ardor nor did it diminish in the least the loyalty to the Democratic party or
                    Democratic principles of the militant editor. The off-year campaign found him again on the stump
                    battling as valiantly for the state ticket as he had done when he was a candidate. In the
                    Presidential campaign of 1876, the centennial year, he reached his climax as a campaign speaker. An
                    ardent admirer of Gov. Samuel J. Tilden, in complete sympathy with the party's platform and
                    thoroughly believing in the need of a change from an administration which even many of the
                    Republican leaders acknowledged to be notoriously corrupt, he threw himself into the canvass with
                    all the ardor of a crusader. The writer of this sketch, then a small boy, saw and heard him that
                    year for the first time when he spoke at a night rally in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Goshen</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Another speaker of the evening was Major C. H. Shriner of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>
                    </placeName>, with whom Stoll had become well acquainted before he left the Keystone state. The
                    speakers were introduced by Llewellyn Wanner, a young lawyer, also a Pennsylvanian who had located
                    in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Goshen</settlement>
                    </placeName> two years before. Those were the first campaign speeches which the writer ever heard
                    and they made on him a deep impression. On thing in particular is still remembered and that is the
                    striking contrast between the two speakers—Mr. Stoll, slow, careful and deliberate, as if
                    weighing every word that was spoken; Major Shriner, fiery and impetuous, dealing sledge hammer blows
                    right and left. Two years later Stoll was nominated for Congress and ran against the Hon. John H.
                    Baker of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Goshen</settlement>
                    </placeName>, who was then serving his second term. Although Baker was re-elected, his antagonist
                    gave him a lively race reducing his majority of two years before.</p>
            <p>Mr. Stoll, then twenty-six years of age, was the principal mover in establishing the Northern Indiana
                    Editorial Association which was organized in 1869. He was its first president, serving six years.
                    Among those who were active in the organization during its earliest years were A. B. Miller,
                    publisher of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">South Bend</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Tribune</hi>; Charles L. Murray and W. A. Beane of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Goshen</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Democrat</hi>; Daniel McDonald of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Plymouth</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Democrat</hi>; Dr. J. H. Rerick of the LaGrange <hi rend="i">Standard</hi>; C. O. Myers
                    of the Kendallville <hi rend="i">Standard</hi>; Reub Williams and A. Hossler of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Warsaw</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Northern Indianian</hi>; C. H. Chase of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Elkhart</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Review</hi>; Englebert Zimmerman of the Valpariso <hi rend="i">Messenger</hi>; and J.
                    P. Prickett of the Albion <hi rend="i">New Era.</hi> Mr. <pb n="78" id="VAA4025-028-2-008"/> Stoll
                    was the last survivor of this notable group. In 1881 he helped to organize the Indiana Democratic
                    Editorial Association which still survives and which includes all of the leading Democratic editors
                    of the state. He attended all of its meetinys for many years and remained a member until his death.</p>
            <p>In 1882 concluding that he would like to engage in the publication of a daily, he sold the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Ligonier</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Banner</hi>, which was a weekly, and bought the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Elkhart</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Democrat.</hi> This journal he published for something over a year, changing its name
                    to the <hi rend="i">Monitor.</hi> For some reason he was not satisfied in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Elkhart</settlement>
                    </placeName>, so he sold his paper to W. H. Norton, formerly of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Goshen</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Democrat.</hi> At that time an opening in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">South Bend</settlement>
                    </placeName> presented itself to him. The Times Printing Company had been organized a year before,
                    had taken over the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">South Bend</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Herald</hi> and changed its name to the <hi rend="i">Times.</hi> The enterprise was
                    about to fail when the Democrats of that city asked Stoll to take over the paper. He bought part of
                    the stock and several of the stockholders presented him with their shares giving him a controlling
                    interest. Eventually he came into full possession. He founded the daily edition but continued to
                    publish also a weekly edition for more than a quarter of a century. The <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">South Bend</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Times</hi> soon became the Democratic organ of the north half of Indiana, while its
                    editorials were quoted not only all over the state but throughout the Middle West. After a long,
                    hard struggle the enterprise became financially profitable.</p>
            <p>After <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cleveland</settlement>
                    </placeName>'s first election to the presidency, Stoll became an active aspirant for the
                    office of public printer at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName>, fully expecting to receive the appointment. In fact it is said that the appointment
                    was promised him, but for some reason E. C. Benedict of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                    </placeName> was selected in his stead. His failure to receive this mark of favor was a bitter
                    disappointment to him for a time, and had something to do with his change of attitude toward affairs
                    political. While he continued to give his party active support in every campaign, his editorials
                    became less fiery. Years afterward he told the writer, who was a member of his editorial staff, that
                    this circumstance led him to resolve that never again would he be a candidate for any political
                    office either appointive or elective, but that he would give his undivided interest to the
                    publication of his paper. He added that this change of attitude toward public office proved
                    altogether for the best, as the close attention which he gave to his publishing business brought him
                        <pb n="79" id="VAA4025-028-2-009"/> better financial returns than office holding could have
                    done. It also brought contentment instead of anxiety since he could feel that he was under
                    obligations to nobody but could pursue his own course without fear or favor.</p>
            <p>That the editor of the <hi rend="i">Times</hi> still wielded a potent influence in the Democratic
                    party in Indiana was evidenced by the part he played in shaping the campaign in 1890. After the
                    Republicans nominated <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Milton</settlement>
                    </placeName> Trusler, master of the State Grange, for Secretary of State, the highest office to be
                    voted for that year, Stoll concluded that it would be the part of wisdom for the Democrats to
                    nominate a farmer for that position, provided the right kind of a man could be found among the
                    tillers of the soil. Meeting his old friend Senator Daniel W. Voorhees in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> shortly after the Republican state convention, he suggested that this would be the wise
                    thing to do. The Senator agreed with him and said that he knew a man who fully measured up to the
                    requirement, mentioning Claude Matthews, a prominent farmer and stock raiser of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Vermillion County</region>
                    </placeName>. Upon returning to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">South Bend</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Mr. Stoll wrote an editorial proposing that Mr. Matthews should head the ticket. The
                    editorial was quoted in many of the Democratic papers of the state, and the suggestion was very
                    favorably received. After giving the matter due consideration, Mr. Matthews consented to let his
                    name go before the convention. Mr. Stoll, Senator Voorhees and a number of other prominent Democrats
                    used their influence in his behalf both before and in the convention and he was easily nominated. He
                    proved to be a strong candidate and at the election in November defeated his farmer rival by a
                    handsome majority.</p>
            <p>In 1888 and again in 1892, Mr. Stoll supported Mr. Cleveland for the presidency, but not with the old
                    enthusiasm of 1884. From that time on his support of his party's ticket was more or less
                    perfunctory. Although he had been an advocate of bimetallism for years, for some reason or other he
                    did not take kindly to the free coinage of silver as advocated by William Jennings Bryan, giving
                    only nominal support to Bryan both in 1896 and 1900. He was on the ticket for elector-at-large in
                    the former year. In 1904 he gave hearty support to Judge Alton B. Parker, only to see his party go
                    down in crushing defeat. In 1908 he again supported Bryan, this time with more enthusiasm than in
                    either of the Nebraskan's previous campaigns. This was the last campaign in which he
                    participated <pb n="80" id="VAA4025-028-2-010"/> actively, as he sold the <hi rend="i">Times</hi> in
                    1912. He continued as editor for a year or more, then severed his connection with it entirely.</p>
            <p>This, however, did not terminate his work in journalism. Almost to the day of his death he was
                    writing for one paper or another every day. For a year or more he had charge of a magazine called
                        <hi rend="i">The Editorial</hi>, published at South <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Whitley</region>
                    </placeName> by Frank B. Mine. Mr. Stoll did some of his best writing for this periodical, besides
                    selecting all of the other matter that went into it. The magazine never paid its publisher
                    financially and after a little less than two years it suspended publication. For the next several
                    years, Stoll furnished a column of editorial comment for the Kendallville <hi rend="i">News-Sun</hi>, under the heading "Observed and Noted". Still later he prepared a column every day
                    for about two years for the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Star</hi> under the caption, "From the Watch Tower". In all of these
                    publications he discussed current issues. Matters political were included but not from a party
                    standpoint. In fact during the last ten years that he owned the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">South Bend</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Times</hi>, there was little party politics in its editorial columns except during
                    campaigns. He did not take the active part on the stump after 1884 that he had taken in former
                    campaigns. This was due to a large extent to increasing age, since he felt that he could not endure
                    the strain which strenuous activity in campaign work entailed. Besides, age had mellowed him to a
                    considerable degree and he no longer retained the taste for fighting which had earlier influenced
                    him. This almost alienated some of his old political associates who felt that he ought to continue
                    to be the fighting Democrat that he was while editing the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Ligonier</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Banner.</hi> It seems to the writer that his critics misinterpreted his attitude and
                    his motives. The change which naturally came with changing circumstances and added years was
                    considered by them as total indifference to his party's welfare and sometimes almost as
                    party treachery. By them he was looked upon as a sort of Democratic "mugwump."
                    Naturally this became known among Republicans and they began to entertain hopes that Stoll would
                    eventually come over to them and make the <hi rend="i">Times</hi> a Republican paper. While no
                    offers were made to buy him as in his younger days, one of his personal friends on the other side of
                    the political fence once ventured to ask him what stood in the way of his becoming a Republican.
                    This awakened for the moment at least his old time party loyalty and his <pb n="81" id="VAA4025-028-2-011"/> reply was characteristic of the days when he so vigorously fought the
                    battles of the Democratic party. He said there were three momentous acts of the Republican party
                    which he could never forget or condone: the first was the impeachment of Andrew Johnson for trying
                    to carry out the reconstruction policy of Abraham Lincoln; the second was the enfranchisement of the
                    Negroes at a time when they were not fit for the exercise of political rights; the third was the
                    "stealing" of the presidency from Samuel J. Tilden after he had been fairly
                    elected. These three acts, he declared, would forever preclude him from affiliating with the
                    Republican party. That reply convinced his friends that while he might not be in complete accord
                    with his own party particularly with its leaders, he was as far as ever from being a Republican.</p>
            <p>During all of the years that he owned and edited papers, Mr. Stoll was also active outside of his
                    editorial work. His campaign services for many years have been mentioned. In addition he served in
                    various other capacities. For six years he was a member of the school board at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Ligonier</settlement>
                    </placeName>, and for nine years he later held a similar position in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">South Bend</settlement>
                    </placeName>. In both cities he served faithfully and labored for the best interests of the schools.
                    Having enjoyed little in the way of school privileges when young, he was determined that the youth
                    of a later generation should have the best that could be provided for them. Although almost entirely
                    self-educated, he could meet on a common level the best educators of the land. Besides, he was in
                    demand on many occasions, outside of political meetings, as a public speaker. He appeared frequently
                    before various organizations, his addresses covering a wide range of subjects. For a number of years
                    he was invited to speak at farmers' institutes and, while he had never lived on a farm a
                    day in his life, he had studied farm problems along with other things and was able to deliver
                    addresses that were helpful to the tillers of the soil. His long experience on the stump had trained
                    him to think on his feet and his wide and varied reading together with a retentive memory enabled
                    him to speak on almost any subject at a moment's notice.</p>
            <p>Some time in December, 1898, he was invited to deliver an evening lecture at the <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Elkhart county</region>
                    </placeName> Farmers' Institute in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Goshen</settlement>
                    </placeName>, the subject assigned to him being, "Interdependence of City and
                    Country". He accepted the invitation and appeared at the appointed time. Some time before
                    the evening <pb n="82" id="VAA4025-028-2-012"/> session, several friends including the writer called
                    on him and the other visiting speakers at the hotel for a little chat. As we were all starting for
                    the opera house, where the Institute was being held, some one of the company asked Stoll what he was
                    going to say. His reply was, "I haven't the slightest idea". Yet, when
                    his time came to speak, he delivered one of the best addresses of the entire Institute. He always
                    spoke slowly and deliberately and was sometimes prolix, but he was an able orator and, when he
                    became well warmed with his subject, eloquent. No matter what was the subject upon which he spoke,
                    his speeches were instructive and interesting and he had no difficulty in holding his audience.</p>
            <p>I wish to add here a personal word concerning my relations with John B. Stoll. In 1899 I accepted a
                    position on his editorial staff, which I held for nearly two years. While in this position, I had an
                    opportunity to become well acquainted with him. Going from my father's farm into his
                    office, with no experience in newspaper work except as an occasional contributor to the <hi rend="i">Farmers' Guide</hi> for several years previous to that time, he gave me a training
                    which could scarcely have been obtained anywhere else. He always held before me high ideals of
                    journalism and impressed upon me the desirability of conducting a clean newspaper. My connection
                    with him as associate editor was always pleasant. I should not have left my position but for the
                    fact that what seemed to be an excellent opportunity to engage in the newspaper business on my own
                    account presented itself at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Warsaw</settlement>
                    </placeName>. When the offer came I conferred with him concerning it. He then told me that, while he
                    disliked to part with my services, when an employee of his had an opportunity to engage in business
                    which promised him an advancement, it had always been his policy to advise him to embrace that
                    opportunity. Our separation was the most cordial and he always took an interest in my welfare both
                    while I was engaged in journalism and after my return to the farm. When I was conducting the
                    LaGrange <hi rend="i">Democrat-Call</hi>, which was the last paper I owned, and he was writing for
                    the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Star</hi>, he frequently quoted from my paper and commented upon my writings in his
                    column. I could not but feel flattered at this recognition from one who held so high a place in the
                    newspaper world. Although he was many years older than I, so much older and so much more capable
                    that I <pb n="83" id="VAA4025-028-2-013"/> always felt myself a boy in his presence, the warmest
                    friendship existed betwen us from our first acquaintance. I never failed to visit him when I went to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">South Bend</settlement>
                    </placeName> and those visits were most enjoyable to me. I shall never cease to be grateful to him
                    for the splendid training and the helpful advice he gave me when I was associated with him in the
                    office of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">South Bend</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Times.</hi> After his death in 1926, tributes to his memory appeared in the press
                    throughout Indiana. All of the editors realized that a giant among them had fallen.</p>
            <p rend="right">H. S. K. B.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="84" id="VAA4025-028-2-014"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-028-2-a02">
            <head>The Story of the "Spring Mill" Water Wheel</head>
            <byline>By DENZIL DOCGETT</byline>
            <p>The present restoration of Spring Mill village is located in Spring Mill State Park, three miles east
                    of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Mitchell</settlement>
                    </placeName>, in Lawrence County, Indiana. At about the time that a mill in this location was first
                    considered, practically all of the grinding, carding, weaving, etc., that supplied the early
                    pioneers with food and clothing, was done by hand, by horse-power, or by water power. Spring Mill
                    owed its existence to the presence of a plentiful supply of water which could be used for the
                    development of power by its proper application to a water wheel.</p>
            <p>When Spring Mill was being considered as a possible state park, Mr. Richard Lieber, Director of the
                    Department of Conservation, remarked that here was a locality which combined several desirable
                    features: an example of the virgin timber of the early days of Indiana, which our Division of
                    Forestry in some measure is trying to restore; limestone caverns, which the Division of Geology
                    studies for information regarding the state's geology; and a village which if properly
                    restored by the Division of Lands and Waters would show the people of the state, in a practical way,
                    the great progress made in improved living conditions in the past hundred years.</p>
            <p>The land which contains this village was acquired by Samuel Jackson, in 1814, as a reward for his
                    services in the War of 1812. In 1817 it was sold to two Kentuckians, Thomas and Cuthbert Bullitt. A
                    quarry was opened and the building of a stone mill was started the same year, which was completed in
                    1818. The mill was sold to the <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Montgomery</region>
                    </placeName> Brothers in 1823. To the activities of milling and sawing of lumber from the timber
                    surrounding the mill the new owners added a distillery. In 1825, the combined enterprises were sold
                    to the brothers, Hugh and John Hamer, who came from <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Albany</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
               </placeName>. Under the
                    guidance of Hugh Hamer, the mills and distillery were surrounded by homes of workers, a tavern, an
                    apothecary's shop, a general store, a hat shop, and all those trades necessary to the
                    pioneer settlement. With the coming of the railroad, the inland village gradually fell into decay
                    and was finally abandoned in its entirety in the late eighties.</p>
            <p>In 1927, the land surrounding and containing the village <pb n="85" id="VAA4025-028-2-015"/> site was
                    given to the State of Indiana for park purposes by the corporation then owning it, the Lehigh <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Portland</settlement>
                    </placeName> Cement Company. This action was brought about through the efforts of Mr. Lieber and
                    General Trexler, chairman of the board of directors of the Cement Company.</p>
            <p>In the spring of 1931 the task of planning and restoring the flume and water wheel of the mill was
                    given to the Division of Engineering. Then began a systematic research into the details of
                    construction and use of the types of water wheel in Indiana early in the nineteenth Century. This
                    research turned in two directions: detailed investigation of the history of the overshot water wheel
                    of the mill in Spring Mill State Park, and a study of the details of other overshot water wheels
                    which were known to be contemporary with this one.</p>
            <p>In the former study, local residents who remembered the old water wheel at the mill were sought out
                    and interviewed concerning details as to diameter, width, method of framing, materials used, etc.
                    Considerable information of this type was gained from William Lynn who lives adjacent to the park. A
                    study of the local conditions at the mill, which might give some clue to the details as to size and
                    construction, was also made. The lime marks on the stoné walls of the mill, caused by the
                    splashing of the water from the wheel, gave us information which checked that given by Mr. Lynn
                    relative to the diameter of the wheel, which was determined to be twenty-four feet. A segment of the
                    rim of the original water wheel was found by a workman in a pile of drift a mile or so below the
                    mill. The diameter deduced from the curve of this segment checked our previous calculations. The
                    width of the tail-race was such that the width of the bucket had to be something less than five and
                    a half or six feet. From observation of timbers which were found buried in the mud and debris of the
                    abandoned tail-race, it was decided that the former width of the water wheel was four feet.</p>
            <p>When it came to determining detailed methods of planning and fabricating the wheel, it was found
                    necessary to seek other sources of information, as no pictures of the old water wheel used at the
                    mill could be located. A picture of the water wheel of the John Paul Mill at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">St. Paul</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indiana, yielded considerable information as to methods of framing such a wheel. This
                    information was supplemented through verbal information on this subject, by <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Marion</region>
                    </placeName> Owen of near Moscow in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Rush County</region>
                    </placeName>, <pb n="86" id="VAA4025-028-2-016"/> who built the last water wheel used at the Owen
                    Mill at Moscow. All through the period of planning and construction Mr. Owen helped in making the
                    details of construction authentic for the period of history which the reconstruction was designed to
                    illustrate. True, some variations have been made to aid in the ease of operation and to prolong the
                    life of the wheel but these details are camouflaged to retain the appearance of former years. The
                    actual work of construction was carried on under the direction of Oren Reed, a field Engineer of the
                    Division.</p>
            <p>The hub of the great wheel was made from a thirty-six inch white oak log twenty-four feet long, which
                    was cut near Henryville. From a count of the annual rings of the log its age was determined to be
                    one hundred ninety-five years. All of the timber used in the construction was of the best quality of
                    white oak that could be located. The design of parts of the wheel was such that this timber could be
                    purchased from local saw mills. Rough sawed lumber was used throughout. The entire wheel was framed
                    in accordance with the practices followed in the decade from 1820 to 1830.</p>
            <p>Mill fittings, including gudgeons, bearings, etc., for a grist mill of this date were purchased from <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Marion</region>
                    </placeName> Owen, the last owner and operator of the Owen Mill at Moscow, Indiana. He had preserved
                    this material when this mill was dismantled in 1912 or 1913. This material is being used in the
                    reconstruction of the grist mill (and the sash type saw mill, as well) at Spring Mill Park.</p>
            <p>The lay-out of the wooden parts of the wheel was made in the area adjacent to the mill, the laborers
                    carrying on the work in the same manner as of 1820 or 1830, except with the improved tools of today.
                    The assembling of the parts was made in place due to the weight involved. The calculated weight of
                    the wheel when completely assembled and in operation (with buckets filled) is 8,500 pounds. The
                    horse-power which the wheel will deliver is approximately twenty-five.</p>
            <p>The flume which carries the water from Hamer's cave to the mill is about 600 feet in length
                    and is designed to give the appearance of the wooden conduit formerly used. An iron pipe twenty
                    inches in diameter actually carries the water for the wheel from the temporary concrete-arch dam
                    which has been erected on land that was retained by the Lehigh <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Portland</settlement>
                    </placeName> Cement Company to protect the water rights of the cor-poration.</p>
            <pb n="87" id="VAA4025-028-2-017"/>
            <p>This dam is in no sense a reconstruction, it is frankly a temporary expedient which is designed to
                    catch the overflow from the Cement Company's dam. However, the outward details of the
                    wooden flume and its supporting stone piers are historically correct.</p>
            <p>The historic research for this work, as well as the planning and reconstruction of the water wheel
                    and flume, has been an interesting assignment for those of the Division of Engineering who have had
                    an intimate connection with it.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="88" id="VAA4025-028-2-018"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-028-2-a03">
            <head>A Quaint, Little, Old Indiana City</head>
            <byline>By JULIA LE CLERC KNOX</byline>
            <p>The old river town of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName> stretches along in some half dozen streets between the <geogName>Ohio River</geogName>
                    and the hills and nods and dreams and dozes, resting calmly on its past laurels. A casual visitor
                    would not realize that it was once the foremost city of the state, and in the "splendid
                    idle forties" it was not <hi rend="i">idle</hi> though somewhat splendid, thanks to the
                    humble <hi rend="i">pig.</hi> For <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName> owed much of its commercial importance to this lowly animal, and was, at one time, the
                    third pork packing point in the west.</p>
            <p>One of these old slaughter-houses was destined after it no longer housed porcine choruses, to re-echo
                    to the marvelous tones of Jenny Lind, which must have much surprised its walls, if indeed walls have
                    ears, as the old adage says. I remember hearing my father tell of being present, in his boyhood, at
                    the concert of the Swedish Nightingale. It seems there was no other building in the town, at that
                    time, large enough to house the immense crowd, so, after much cleaning and scouring, the old packing
                    plant was elevated to this great honor.</p>
            <p>
               <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName> was founded in 1808 by John Paul, for whom the D.A.R. have named the little ravine park
                    at the back of the town. The location was then, commercially speaking, considered good. It was on
                    the river between <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Louisville</settlement>
                    </placeName> which made shipping an easy matter. The site drew thither men of energy and vision,
                    from all directions and for some years preceding the Civil War, the citizenry of the town was
                    superior to any other in the state of Indiana.</p>
            <p>So, the place has a great heritage which gives it a grave and dignified charm not easily matched. It
                    unhurriedly sits apart from the pace that kills, in independent ease and seems to look askance upon
                    those who do not share its composure.</p>
            <p>
               <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName> may well be called the city of interesting old homes. It would be hard to find a place
                    of the same size that has so many mansion-like houses that seem so "to the manner
                    born", with salon-like rooms of palatial dimensions. The Lanier Home, of course, strikes
                    the highest note along this line, though there are many not far behind. A northern Indiana visitor
                    to the place recently, expressed astonishment that <pb n="89" id="VAA4025-028-2-019"/> people
                    anywhere in the middle west lived in the lap of luxury a hundred years ago, as that stately mansion
                    signifies.</p>
            <p>Every interesting historic landmark has back of it some great pioneer character whose memorial it is.
                    So it is with the Lanier Home whose original owner, James <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Franklin</settlement>
                    </placeName> Doughty Lanier, represented that best pioneer type "that brought to the making
                    of a new state the finest capital". By his integrity and industry he rose from humble
                    financial circumstances to a position where he helped very substantially to make our great state
                    what it is today. By a loan of $420,000, he enabled Governor Morton to equip the
                    necessary state troops during a part of the Civil War. Again, his bank let Morton have
                    $640,000 to pay off state debts, a total of $1,040,000 in the face of imminent
                    risk, at the darkest hour of the conflict. So, the nation, as well as Indiana, owes Lanier a debt of
                    gratitude for unselfish patriotism.</p>
            <p>The proud old mansion stands, a mute monument to the grand old patriot, its builder. It represents
                    the best taste in architecture of the pre-War period savoring, in its dignified simplicity, of the
                    Classic revival. At the time it was completed, in 1844, it was said to surpass any building of like
                    nature in either <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName> or <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Louisville</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Even yet it seems to have no rival of the kind in Indiana, at least. The Harrison
                    Home, at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName>, still not completely furnished, but interesting and dignified in its barreness, can
                    not compare with the Lanier Home as to grandeur and setting. The nearest peer it has in the state is
                    Lane Place in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Crawfordsville</settlement>
                    </placeName>, which though neither so large nor so imposing, still preserves the intimacy of
                    occupancy and whose setting, in all but the river view, is more beautiful. The Old <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> Home at Federal Hill, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Bardstown</settlement>
                    </placeName>, is built more nearly on the same lines, though not so large nor so handsome. Yet the
                    furnishings seem more comparable.</p>
            <p>The finest mansion in the west, we may well imagine the Lanier Mansion the scene of many notable
                    affairs in our early history, a hospitable place where famous men and women fore-gathered. Thomas
                    Buchanan Read, the author of "Sheridan's Ride" and "The
                    Rising", spent some time there, painting the portraits of the family, one of which is that
                    of Mrs. Lanier, now hanging in the home.</p>
            <p>As you enter the broad hall you see, as a picture in a frame, <pb n="90" id="VAA4025-028-2-020"/> the
                    lovely <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> and the background of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> hills, through the open door (if it be summer) at the end. This may tempt you to make
                    your way at once to the back veranda, with its massive pillars, which leads down into a wide expanse
                    of lawn on the river front, an ideal setting for a performance of <hi rend="i">As You Like It</hi>
                    or other woodland drama or pageant. It is said that it has actually been put to some such uses.</p>
            <p>If this view does not draw you too soon, you will note the circular stair case at your left, winding
                    up to the glassed lantern of the third floor which lets in the light. Many noble old pieces of
                    furniture lend grace and beauty to the great hall and still leave the impression of spaciousness.
                    Two great horsehair sofas, a grandfather's clock, a hatrack, some Windsor chairs and an
                    immense Japanese floor-vase intrigue the eye. A large oil portrait of Mr. Lanier occupies a
                    shrine-like place over a pier-table of mahogany graced by two brass sperm or lard lamps of the kind
                    that antedated the use of kerosene.</p>
            <p>On your right as you enter, are the magnificent double parlors with graceful columns. They are
                    furnished in the prevailing parlor style of the time, mantel mirrors, crystal chandeliers, mahogany
                    center tables, a quaint old piano, handsome bookcases, Dresden china vases and other pieces in
                    keeping. Two sofas and eight chairs of the French Empire period were imported from <placeName>
                        <country reg="fr">France</country>
                    </placeName> by Mr. Lanier. These are upholstered in purple and grey to match the heavy window
                    draperies and give the color scheme to the rooms. Two pieces of sculpture, Mary Lanier, in the charm
                    of first youth and George Grey Barnard's "Crouching Venus" adorn these
                    lovely twin apartments.</p>
            <p>The dining room, which is on your left as you enter, is rich in old mahoganies, silver and china. The
                    Sheraton chairs were imported from <placeName>
                        <country reg="enk">England</country>
                    </placeName>. The chandelier is magnificent as are also the candelabra and the walls are decorated
                    with Audubons. Here again is the mantel mirror. The great fly brush of peacock feathers, without
                    which no pioneer dining room considered itself respectable, occupies a conspicuous place. The
                    kitchen must have been at some distance, but with plenty of servants that was not important.</p>
            <p>A small passage way separates the dining room from the sitting room, the color scheme of which is a
                    warm crimson, <pb n="91" id="VAA4025-028-2-021"/> reflected in window draperies, upholstery and
                    carpet. A great rosewood bookcase gives another interesting touch. There is an ormolu mantel clock
                    and a chandelier to match. But the crowning piece of furniture is a wonderful old fire screen that
                    tips at different angles and which so obviously belongs to another day that it at once becomes the
                    center of attention because its like is so seldom seen.</p>
            <p>By the wonderful spiral staircase you ascend to the wide upper hall of the second floor. Here is an
                    old <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New Orleans</settlement>
                    </placeName> triple wardrobe of mahogany, a grandfather's clock and some Windsor chairs. At
                    each end of the hall is a small apartment, quaintly and attractively furnished. There are two large
                    bedrooms on both sides of the hall, each furnished in a distinctive style, with color schemes
                    carefully carried out in the minutest particulars, with canopied four posters, braided rugs, brass
                    candle sticks, bureaus and the invariable wash stand with bowl and pitcher, great-grandparents of
                    the modern bath room. There are hand-woven counterpanes, some being heavily embossed with
                    candle-wick embroidery, fiddle-back chairs and old engravings galore. A trundle bed is a center of
                    interest.</p>
            <p>The nursery on the third floor is especially intriguing. No part of this lovely old mansion is more
                    charming. Here are queer old dolls, and their furniture-beds, cradles, dressers, chairs, tables,
                    cupboards, dishes, tubs and trunks and doll clothes stretched out on a line. Even the
                    "grown up" and the "grown old" little girls are spellbound with the lure
                    of it all, The servants quarters and the children's bedrooms adjoining, are not without
                    their interest.</p>
            <p>In refurnishing this old home it was impossible to restore all of the original articles but the style
                    and atmosphere of a typical pre-War mansion have been successfully aimed at, and it is worth
                    travelling many miles to see.</p>
            <p>The first recollections of this delightfuly old place were, when as a child, the writer heard of it
                    at the home of Mr. Alex, the son of the original Lanier. He was spoken of as a mysterious recluse
                    who, on account of an unlucky love affair, had shut himself off from the world. And so, the old home
                    was given a halo by romantic sentiment. Later it was learned that this hero of romance had been
                    rewarded by finally winning <pb n="92" id="VAA4025-028-2-022"/> the hand of his first and only love,
                    who had become widowed by the death of his friend whom she had married.</p>
            <p>Francis Costigan, architect and builder of the Lanier Home, was an eastern man who lived during the
                    last twenty years of his life in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName>. He left quite a number of other notable buildings as monuments to his skill and taste,
                    not only in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName> but in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> as well. The old Institute for the Blind, recently razed, is an example. His influence
                    was great on other architects in near by towns, for instance George Kyle of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vevay</settlement>
                    </placeName> used much the same plan when building the old U. P. Schenck mansion in that place. He
                    even improved on the veranda, facing the river at the back of the house, by making it three storied.
                    Its classic lines are a well known land-mark up and down the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName>. Kyle also built the Schenck staircase circular, supporting itself, rising from the
                    center of the hall and winding its way to the third story. The <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vevay</settlement>
                    </placeName> architect may, however, have copied the stair in the old Shrewsbury Mansion of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName>, also the work of Costigan. This too is a noteworthy building. The hall is wide but
                    rather shorter than that of the Schenck Home and the circular stair seems to crowd it more. On the
                    left are stately double parlors, separated by graceful columns that give an air of grandeur. On the
                    right, again are double parlors, and beyond the front parlor is a spacious dining room which leads
                    off into an entry and yet another apartment, making this old house four rooms wide at the front. The
                    Jefferson Hotel, another of Costigan's designs, is built on the same grand lines. It used
                    to sport colored waiters in dress suits, silver dishes and every thing that went to make up the
                    ideal southern hostelry.</p>
            <p>The home that Costigan built for himself on Third Street is by no means the least interesting of the
                    grand old mansions that he erected in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName>. The doorway is especially noteworthy. A step or two ascends to a small square
                    platform, supported by graceful, fluted columns. From the dome of this stoop or entry is suspended a
                    chandelier. The hall is too tiny for a door to swing back into it, so the architect solved this
                    problem by making a sliding door. From this diminutive reception hall, you walk through a tall,
                    fourteen feet portal whose door curves with the curve of the front wall in the most unique way
                    imaginable, the front window ledge being uneven with this odd curve. You enter a great salon-like
                    apartment of some forty feet in length, with ceiling so high it resembles <pb n="93" id="VAA4025-028-2-023"/> the palaces and castles of the old world. There is a second high door
                    on the right side of the room, about half way down the length. From this magnificent drawing room
                    the house seems to reach a sort of anti-climax in two tiny rooms at the rear, significant of a later
                    annex, a sort of after thought, as it were.</p>
            <p>From the front entrance a steep flight of steps at the right of the magnificently large parlor, leads
                    to the second floor where it ends for a minute, as it were, in a very narrow landing and then takes
                    a stiff plunge to the ground floor again. To prevent the unwary from doing the same thing, a gate
                    has been placed as a safeguard for the uninitiated. There are several bedrooms on the second with
                    ceilings as high as those of the ground floor, but somehow they do not look it. One wonders how that
                    immense drawing room could be heated in zero weather but the present owners, Mr. and Mrs. C. E.
                    Hinton, solve the problem by wintering in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="flu">Florida</region>
                    </placeName>.</p>
            <p>Hon. Marcus R. Sulzer and family occupy the house next door and the narrow area between the two
                    buildings is closed by a quaint old door, thought by some to bear the ear marks of Costigan. The
                    Sulzer home is flush with the street as are so many of these houses of that architectural era. Large
                    double parlors, separated by fluted columns, terminate in a narrow entry that leads to the square
                    dining room while on the left the entry opens on a side porch. From the dining room you pass through
                    the kitchen to a flower garden, resplendent with Japanese morning glories and scarlet sage. A path
                    extending to the next street, has its edges abloom with a bright riot of petunias and other gay
                    flowers. Stairs in the back parlor lead to a succession of bedrooms and bath.</p>
            <p>Mr. and Mrs. J. Inglis have a very palatial residence on Main Street with a quaint, charming doorway,
                    opening on a wide hall that leads through a narrow entry into a succession of rooms. The hall at the
                    right opens on large double parlors, characteristic of all these old mansions. The upper floor
                    duplicates the great hall, with a long string of rooms on one side, only. Here are many priceless
                    antiques and art treasurers picked up by Mrs. Inglis, on her travels abroad.</p>
            <p>The old William Stapp home on lower Main Street is another notable, old mansion. It is situated on a
                    rising knoll, back quite a bit from the street. The tree on the lawn, under which <pb n="94" id="VAA4025-028-2-024"/> Henry Clay once spoke, has long since gone the way of all trees. Also a
                    wing at the left of the house has been torn away. The conventional broad hall has double rooms on
                    both sides while a dining room branches off at one side and the kitchen occupies an ell. A broad
                    stairway leads to an upper floor, with some twenty rooms in all. In the time of the Stapp occupancy
                    the back yard reached to Third Street with croquet grounds, rockeries and pansy beds.</p>
            <p>Besides the old family dwellings of which there are too many to enumerate, there are many other
                    interesting places about <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName>. The fountain which graces <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Broadway</settlement>
                    </placeName>, is a duplicate of the one that took a prize at the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Philadelphia</settlement>
                    </placeName> Centennial in 1876. There is a George Grey Barnard Museum in an old church donated by
                    Miss Drusilla Cravens, the fairy godmother of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName>, who has done so much in restoring the Lanier Home, which was built by her grandfather.</p>
            <p>George Grey Barnard is a <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName> product. His father, a minister of the Presbyterian Church, looked like a twin brother
                    of the poet, Longfellow. His mother had a face as delicate as an old cameo and a charming grace. At
                    the time the writer was fortunate enough to see them in their own home, they occupied a stately old
                    house on Second Street, of much the same architectural plan as most of the houses already described.
                    Mrs. Barnard, with pardonable pride, exhibited a scrap book, containing the newspaper comments on
                    her son's work. About the house were models and replicas of his well known sculpture. The
                    Joan of Arc and Lincoln stand out most strongly in memory. Mingled strangely with these were the
                    trophies and souvenirs sent home by the son on the western plains. As a climax, the gentle hostess
                    seated herself at the old time spinet, a family heirloom, and from the yellowed ivory keys drew
                    forth an air that attuned with the old time atmosphere of the place. Mrs. Barnard passed away
                    shortly after that and the good Doctor followed not far behind.</p>
            <p>
               <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName> has sent forth many sons and daughters, who, in widely different walks of life, have
                    brought her renown. Besides George Grey Barnard, whose fame as a sculptor is more than national, a
                    few others are: Jesse D. Bright, <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> Senator; David Graham Phillips, novelist; Irene Dunn, movie star. <hi rend="i">Susan
                        Lennox,</hi> by Phillips, has recently been seen in the movies with Greta Garbo in the title
                    role. This story is said to be based on actual facts and the scenes depicted are <pb n="95" id="VAA4025-028-2-025"/> pointed out near <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Miss Dunn starred in "Cimarron," in which her work as the heroine
                    has been commented on very favorably by critics.</p>
            <p>The oldest railroad in the state, the J. M. &amp; I., was constructed between <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName>, down through that cut in the hills which is a wonderful feat of engineering. Buses and
                    autos have driven the railroad from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Columbus</settlement>
                    </placeName> to North <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName> out of business, and its place is now taken by an electric tram.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="96" id="VAA4025-028-2-026"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-028-2-a04">
            <head>A Hoosier Arcadia</head>
            <byline>By GEORGE S. COTTMAN</byline>
            <p>
               <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indiana, now an integral part of the city of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, vaguely defined in its boundaries, and its name unrecognized by the Post Office
                    Department, was for more than a score of years a distinct entity. More than that, it was so
                    positively distinct, it is hardly straining a point to say that during its period of infancy and
                    youth it was unique. The present generation of residents for the most part know it as a
                    well-improved residential section with a reputation for respectability, where they come to their
                    homes each night from their down-town vocations. They do not even know of certain antecedents that
                    have contributed to the present desirability of that section, and much less of the idealistic and
                    "literatesque" history of the old <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName>. A year or so since, the present writer placed in the branch library there a collection
                    of material preserved through the years which contains within itself, and with tolerable
                    completeness, the data for such history. It was hoped that in a community of many literary clubs,
                    and in this day of much seeking after local history material someone would discover the interest
                    that inheres in the collection referred to, and make use of the same. So far as is known to the
                    writer, no one has done so, and lest they should not, the task is here essayed of gathering up in a
                    fashion the story of early <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName>, the separate town.</p>
            <p>
               <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName>, platted in 1870, was the first of that belt of suburbs that during the
                    'seventies and 'eighties grew up around the capital city. In its reasons for
                    being, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> was different from all the others, with the possible exceptions of Woodruff Place and
                    Stratford. The latter was indeed an ephemeral venture that drew its inspiration from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName>. With these exceptions, the other detached communities were so many overflowings from
                    the industrial expansion of the city, but <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> had for its inception and motive a distinct ideal of social betterment as sharply
                    defined, though not so radical, as the ideas that led Robert Owen to establish the colony of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New Harmony</settlement>
                    </placeName>. After the initial experiment <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName>'s ideal, like that of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New Harmony</settlement>
                    </placeName>, was much modified by those conflicting influences that have their birth in human
                    nature and which so fatally thwart Utopians — as will be <pb n="97" id="VAA4025-028-2-027"/> shown. Its establishment as an <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> suburb was, in the first instance, largely accidental, the primary cause being a bitter
                    county seat war which resulted in the removal of the seat of justice of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wayne County</region>
                    </placeName> from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Centerville</settlement>
                    </placeName> to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName>. This meant the collapse of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Centerville</settlement>
                    </placeName>'s prosperity, and by reason of it two citizens of the town, Jacob Julian and
                    Sylvester Johnson, were disposed to shift their activities to fresh fields and pastures new. Julian,
                    seems to have been the first to entertain the idea of starting a new community founded on certain
                    ideal principles, but the proposition, when suggested to Mr. Johnson, was met half way.</p>
            <p>Contingency number two occurred when Jacob Julian on a business trip to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> chanced to meet the Rev. T. A. Goodwin, who, besides being a Methodist minister and an
                    editor did some real estate business on the side. Goodwin had in hand for sale a tract of land which
                    he thought admirably adapted to Julian's contemplated social center, being but five miles
                    from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, favorably situated on high ground, and of sufficient extent for the desired
                    purpose-the price $100 per acre. This sounded so alluring to Julian that he went out to
                    look at it. Subsequently he came again in company with Sylvester Johnson, and, to shorten that part
                    of the narrative, the two of them purchased the solid holding of about 304 acres from its
                    non-resident owner, Jacob Sandusky<hi rend="sup">1.</hi> The tract is now bounded on the east and
                    west, respectively, by Arlington and Ritter avenues, while north and south most of the space between
                    the C. H. &amp; D. R.R. track and Pleasant Run was taken up. The first plat of the town
                    comprised this area, but it was soon enlarged. Happily for the furtherance of the scheme, Dr. Levi
                    Ritter, who owned the farm of 80 acres adjoining the Sandusky purchase on the west, fell heartily in
                    with the new town project with its unusual features. He coöperated with the original
                    proprietors by laying out an addition that carried the boundary westward to the present Hawthorne
                    Lane. This was in September, 1871.</p>
            <p>Here then the idealists began to work out their conceptions of a model community. The original town
                    plat showed at a glance that it was something different, with its looped and curving streets
                    wandering in all directions and lying on the map in a tangle. Its unique character was carried out
                    in <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">1</hi> Jacob Sandusky, a Pole, who sometimes wrote his name Sowdusky. as
                            property abstracts show, acquired much cheap land in various parts of the West. Sandusky, <placeName>
                                <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                            </placeName>, is said to have been named for him.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="98" id="VAA4025-028-2-028"/> other ways. Most towns make a bid for industries as a means to
                    prosperity, but instead this one banned factories and the like. The desire was to found a place for
                    residence which would draw its subsistence from the adjacent city. Here the business man might enjoy
                    a home life of idyllic pleasures, his children guarded from social evils. The town was spaced
                    accordingly, the lots containing from one to three acres, while the stipulated cost of houses was to
                    be not less than $6,000—which meant a mansion in those days. A very few of
                    those stately old buildings that must have cost far in excess of the sum named, still remain,
                    testifying to the opulent tastes of those who may be called the charter members of the community<hi rend="sup">2.</hi> The chief promoters, Jacob Julian and Sylvester Johnson, set the pace by
                    erecting two great brick structures very much alike in design and appearance. Their spacious grounds
                    were in keeping and their owners were exemplars of what suburban residents should be, with their
                    love of trees, shrubbery and general rusticity. This was especially true of Mr. Johnson, who was a
                    skilled horticulturist, and up to the time of his death his ample acreage was enriched by choice
                    fruits. His faith in the adage that "an apple a day keeps the doctor away" was
                    amplified to the belief that more than one a day was better, and a lingering memory of him in his
                    latter days is the picture of the old gentleman, distinguished by his bushy white beard and
                    venerable "plug" hat, munching apples as he walked down the street. With the
                    first-comers generally floral beautification seems to have been an aspiration and a delight, for we
                    are told by a reminiscent writer of "old-fashioned flower beds designed as stars, crescents
                    and triangles, and gorgeous in mid-summer with geraniums, verbenas, cigar plants, touch-me-nots,
                    fuschias, heliotropes, tuberoses" and so on, while another says "it seemed that
                    every lady spent hours daily during the summer months digging in her flower beds and arranging
                    bouquets to send sick neighbors."<hi rend="sup">3</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this was but part and parcel of the cultural and esthetic ideas that lay back of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> experiment. The peculiarities of the town plat, to return to that feature, while
                    suggested by those of a <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName> suburb known as Glendale, were modified according to the topography of the Sandusky
                        <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">2</hi> The George W. Julian residence, still standing, was built at a coat
                            of more than $18,000, as revealed by Yr. Julian's diary.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">3</hi> These intimate descriptions are gleaned from articles by Mrs. Grace
                            Julian Clarke daughter of George W. Julian, and Mrs. Joseph Hunter, whose above
                            contributions are in the branch library collection referred to.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="99" id="VAA4025-028-2-029"/> purchase, the building sites occupying the higher spots and the
                    drives more or less following the drainage depressions with but secondary attention to the customary
                    rectangular system of streets. If an especially fine tree contested a right of way the tree remained
                    and the thoroughfare curved accordingly. Thoughts of a future automobile age with its feverish mania
                    for getting there quickly troubled the primitive Irvingtonians not at all-what they preferred was
                    the curved line of beauty flowing freely through the landscape. This ideal was further enhanced by
                    two circles symmetrically placed and ingeniously made a part of the system of sinuous streets. One
                    of these was to be a little public place, specifically named "Irving Park," and
                    the other (where the Methodist church now stands) was designated "College Circle,"
                    the intention being to establish there a girl's school of higher education.</p>
            <p>The ideas, respectively, of Jacob Julian and Sylvester Johnson diverged in wrtain respects and yet
                    worked together admirably to fix the character of the suburb. Julian gave the cultural impulse. He
                    it was who bestowed the name "<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName>," in token of his admiration of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> Irving, one of his desires being that a statue of the author should stand in Irving
                    Circle. Doubtless he may also be credited with the idea of the school in College Circle. He left
                    evidence that he was a man of fine tastes, literary and otherwise, who should be generously honored
                    in view of the fact that influences which he set in motion grew and expanded till the town became an
                    acknowledged seat of culture. After the part which he played in the realizing of his dream, he died
                    very poor having been obliged to relinquish his fine home.</p>
            <p>Sylvester Johnson's especial <hi rend="i">bete noire</hi> was the liquor traffic and it is
                    safe to say that his greatest incentive to the promoting of a new community was the establishing of
                    preventive conditions. I have heard him say that he yielded to certain notions entertained by his
                    fellow-promoter on condition that Julian would allow him a free hand in the matters he had most at
                    heart. What he regarded as his proudest accomplishment was the incorporation into the title-deeds of
                    lots the following clause which is filed with the plat in the county recorder's office:
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The grantee accepts this deed from the grantor with the express condition that he, his heirs
                            and assigns will not erect or maintain, or suffer to be erected or maintained, on the real
                            estate herein conveyed <pb n="100" id="VAA4025-028-2-030"/> any distillery, brewery, soap
                            factory, pork house, slaughter house, or any other establishment offensive to the people,
                            and that he will not erect or maintain or suffer to be erected or maintained on said
                            premises any stable, hog pen or other offensive building, stall or shed within fifty feet of
                            any avenue in said town, and that he will not sell or suffer to be sold on said premises any
                            intoxicating liquors except for medical, sacramental or mechanical purposes strictly, and he
                            accepts this deed on the further agreement that the right to enforce and compel compliance
                            of the above conditions rests not only in the grantor, his heirs and assigns, but in all the
                            property holders and inhabitants of said town.</p>
                    </quote>These provisions, especially as regards liquor, have held to the. present day. <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> in all its sixty-two years of history has never had an open drinking place, and this
                    has given a lasting character to it as a temperance community.</p>
            <p>On April 7, 1873, about two and a half years after the first platting, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> became an incorporated town, and on April 7 of that year the town board held its first
                    meeting. The first ordinances passed were in line with the ideas of the proprietors. One was to
                    plant trees wherever needed along the streets;<hi rend="sup">4</hi> one was to protect birds; and
                    another was to forbid livestock running at large. Before long self-government and the problems of
                    law making for a bucolic community took on a humorous aspect-but that is another thread of the
                    story. Let one thread at a time be developed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">The Golden Age.</hi> Not all the history of early <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> is suggestive of Arcadian dreams, but the idealistic spirit of the founders continued
                    for years to tincture that less lovely current of life that takes its trend from the kinks of human
                    nature and sordid necessities. Mrs. Clarke, whose memory goes back to the beginning, has given us
                    some pleasant pictures of the pristine period when there were enough like-minded families of means
                    to give the community the distinctive character originally intended. In its first steps the venture
                    was as intriguing asl that of the famous "Brook Farm," without the radical labor
                    requirements that were fatal to the New <placeName>
                        <country reg="enk">England</country>
                    </placeName> colony. The dream of these first-comers generally, doubtless, was much the same as that
                    of George W. Julian, who, fortunately, <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">4</hi> That the proprietors were lovers of trees is indicated by such
                            street on the original plat as Cherry, Elm Walnut Maple, Oak, and Beechwood. This sentiment
                            long persisted and in the course of the years <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                            </placeName> people have fought to protect their trees against devastating utilities. On one
                            occasion of these utility corporations ruthlessly multilated some fine forest specimens that
                            stood on the edge of <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Butler</settlement>
                            </placeName> campus so as to interfere with their wiring operations. The college authorities
                            applied to law so promptly and so vigorously as to leave a department salutary
                        effect.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="101" id="VAA4025-028-2-031"/> recorded in diary form, the lure to him.<hi rend="sup">5</hi>
                    He wanted seclusion and aloofness from the turmoil of life, but not isolation. He expresses a desire
                    for "libraries and society" and to be within touch of civilization with its onward
                    movement advantages which this location afforded. "The city of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>," he says, "is destined to be one of the largest in the Northwest,
                    and the town of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> will be one of the handsomest in the state, and singularly accessible to the
                    city." This "singular accessibility," before even a mule-car
                    traversed' the five miles between the two points indicates how undemanding the satisfaction
                    of the simple life could be in those days.</p>
            <p>It all depends upon the spirit. With the good old family nag as an aid and a disposition to take
                    things in a leisurely fashion, the first Irvingtonians got along enviably well. Neighbors in the
                    full sense of the term, there was not a little visiting to and fro between families, with games of
                    croquet in the big grassy yards by summer and euchre of winter evenings, not to mention other forms
                    of innocuous recreation. The country-like spaces in all directions with places to explore and things
                    to discover were an abiding delight to the children. As child nourishment compare that, if you will,
                    with the perpetual, vicious diet fed out so copiously to the rising generation by that form of
                    poison known as the "movie." Glimpses of an intellectual atmosphere are afforded
                    by the free loaning of books from private libraries, and if the collection of Mr. George Julian,
                    which still remains intact, is one to judge by, the literary culture was of the solid and classic
                    brand.</p>
            <p>A year or so after its incorporation the little town was stirred by a new and glowing hope. The
                    Northwestern Christian University, a promising school of higher education, which had been in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> for twenty years, was outgrowing its original plant and casting about for a more
                    commodious home. As a community asset, it was considered valuable enough to stimulate rivalry for
                    its capture. As has already been said the first plan of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> had included the proposal of a school of the higher sort, "College
                    Circle" having been offered for that purpose. Thus far nothing had ever come of this little
                    sub-dream, but now <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Providence</settlement>
                    </placeName> was playing directly into the hands of the Utopians. That they were quick to appreciate
                    their <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">5</hi> George W. Julian, a brother of Jacob Julian, was one of the valued
                            additions to the village. He was first elected to Congress in 1849, and later served several
                            terms in the period of the Civil War and reconstruction. A noted Free Soiler, he was one of
                            the best known men in Indiana.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="102" id="VAA4025-028-2-032"/> chance is shown by the sequel. <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> sought the school vigorously. Raising a bonus of $150,000 and offering in
                    addition twenty-five acres of land for a campus, by the liberality of the community, the institution
                    was obtained in the face of competitative inducements. It was a good investment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Town and Gown.</hi> This assimilation was a happy and logical union for both <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> and the College, the detachment and idealistic atmosphere of the former according well
                    with the "classic shades" of tradition. From 1876, the year that <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Butler</settlement>
                    </placeName> University opened at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName>, throughout the town period the institution gave a tone and character and a prestige to
                    the community.<hi rend="sup">6</hi> The "Classic Suburb" it came to be called, and
                    though that was often in a spirit of raillery, underneath lay the serious recognition that the
                    appellation was fitting. One of the effects immediately following the acquisition of the College was
                    a stimulation of real estate values in the vicinity of its site and a platting of additions there
                    that, had there been building in proportion the center of population would have been shifted to a
                    locality quite outside of the original plats. Some of the many contemplated houses were constructed,
                    and to this day there are some of the once fine residences of the 'seventies scattered to
                    the southwest of the old campus.</p>
            <p>Following the changes of time came other mutual benefits, more intimate and more enduring than
                    profits to real estate agents. The aftermath of the panic of 1873 seems to have reached <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> rather tardily; but it came. After five or six years of booming and high realty values
                    things collapsed with the proverbial "dull, sickening thud," and for years they
                    stayed "collapsed." Houses and lots once fancy-priced could be had at pretty much
                    the purchasers own terms; platted areas became obliterated by weeds, and numerous tracts fenced in
                    for cow pastures patterned the town with barbed wire entanglements. Meantime <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> had grown from a village to a town, but not exactly along the lines anticipated by the
                    founders. The increase of population, some of it caused by the coming of the college, represented in
                    the main people of modest means who could not hope to own $6,000 homes with generous,
                    beautified surroundings. The idealistic sentiment now most in <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">6</hi> The name Northwestern Christian University was changed to that of <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Butler</settlement>
                            </placeName> University in 1877, in honor of Ovid <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Butler</settlement>
                            </placeName>, recognizing his gifts and services. Subsequently it was known as <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Butler</settlement>
                            </placeName> College, but now again it is called <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Butler</settlement>
                            </placeName> University.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="103" id="VAA4025-028-2-033"/> evidence among the dwellers in Arcadia was an appreciation of
                    the institution in their midst where their children might have educational advantages above the
                    usual. "Town and gown" were most happily paired. The loyalty of the citizens to
                    the school took the form of a lively interest in its intellectual and social affairs. The College
                    was at once their pride and the main source of public entertainment. The exercises of the literary
                    and oratorical societies, the chapel addresses and many of the receptions to students were more or
                    less shared in by the townsmen, while commencement week was a sort of annual festival of the spirit,
                    when everybody was regaled with lofty thinking. Also, the college folk were sharers in the town
                    life. The professors, for the most part, were personally acquainted with the man on the street; now
                    and then one of them figured in town politics, and there are traditions of some of the earlier
                    faculty members descending to the plebeian level by doing public work on the town thoroughfares
                    under the road laws then prevailing. More conspicuously the occupants of the chairs took part in the
                    indigenous culture of the citizenry, especially through the medium of a literary club. President A.
                    R. Benton, of the College, was also president of the club for several years. Other faculty men, not
                    infrequently, contributed to the program along the lines of their specialties.</p>
            <p>This home-made club, by the way, was so unusual in character as to merit further notice. The
                    "Citizens' Club" it was called, which was an appropriate name, for it was
                    every-body's organization-if, indeed, it could be called an organization. It had no fixed
                    membership, no dues or assessments, and no fixed place of meeting. Its monthly sessions were held at
                    the homes of first one townsman and then another as the spirit of hospitality moved this one or that
                    one to proffer entertainment-which hospitality usually included what the small town newspaper
                    designates as "delicious refreshments." The intellectual and gustatory offerings
                    of the occasion were as free as salvation, or even more so, for no collection was taken up, and
                    whosoever would might come and partake. As traversing the streets by night and afoot was somewhat
                    difficult, they tried as far as practicable, to keep to a moonlight schedule for their meetings.
                    When fixing the time for a subsequent meeting, the calendar was always called for to determine the
                    time of full moon. If for any reason the queen of night failed as a luminary, then the seekers after
                    culture wended their ways <pb n="104" id="VAA4025-028-2-034"/> along winding muddy thoroughfares
                    depending on the aid of lanterns to escape the dangers of ditches and puddles. The papers presented
                    for consideration and discussion, which left the subjects to the free choice of the contributors,
                    were as varied as the characters and interests of the diverse gatherings. One man, I remember, who
                    had given his life to the subject, proved by exhaustive arguments and charts that the earth had
                    attained to its present rotund proportions by accretions from outer space, and that it had also
                    expanded so as to unfold the continents of North and South America which were once doubled together
                    like a jack-knife. When, by the aid of the charts, the two coast lines were laid together-lo! there
                    they were, and no professor present could say a word so smitten were they with a sense of their own
                    inadequacy. All of which adds to the piquancy of those old-time memories.</p>
            <p>To return from this divergence, there was also a business bond between <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName>, and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Butler</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Not only did the citizens feel a sort of proprietary relationship and think of it as
                        <hi rend="i">our</hi> College, when sentimentally considered, and not only did <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> contribute her quota to the student body, but the segregation of about three hundred
                    young people, who had to be fed and lodged created an industry that in those tight times was a
                    godsend to many a thrifty housewife who had to turn an honest penny; and this, of course,
                    strengthened the union. Another thing that made for solidarity was, doubtless, the comparative
                    isolation of the place. Despite Mr. Julian's "singular accessibility,"
                    the distanca to the city with the transportation facilities of those days did not conduce to much
                    running back and forth and that made very good reasons why the suburban unit should be sufficient
                    unto itself. In the beginning the only public service was furnished by the two railroads which ran
                    the customary accommodation trains. Then with the advent of the College came a mule-car service, or
                    rather alleged service, which was such a joke that to this day the mention of it excites the
                    risibles of those who remember it. This vehicular traffic line, seeking its goal from the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> end, furtively sneaked through an obscure section of the city to the southeast till it
                    found English Avenue. Along this roadway it took a straight shoot to a point on the eastern horizon;
                    thence three or four miles, more or less, to a point south of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Butler</settlement>
                    </placeName> College where it dodged around a corner of the campus to make its way slaunchwise
                    through a weed-grown common till it found <pb n="105" id="VAA4025-028-2-035"/> an <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> street. It finally wound up at a turntable near the hub of the town from which it went
                    back by the same route to the place of beginning. Cost of the tour, ten cents each way; time
                    consumed, dependent upon good or iil luck.</p>
            <p>The cars supplied for this conveyance of the populace to and fro were of the
                    "dinky" or "bob-tailed" variety, engineered by a crew of one,
                    and with slots and a long tube running down either side of the car in lieu of a conductor. A nickle
                    dropped in a slot rolled down the sloping tube till it was caught in a sort of glass box which the
                    driver on the front platform could look into, thus keeping track of his fares. If the nickles and
                    the passengers didn't tally in numbers-and sometimes they didn't-as likely as not
                    Jehu would stop all progress and, holding the innocent and the guilty alike responsible, decline to
                    go further until the requisite number of coins emerged into view. The fare for the journey was
                    collectible in two installments, five cents carrying one to Sherman Drive at Stratford, the half-way
                    point. Here the driver would open the front door, poke his head through and bleat out in persuasive
                    tones: "An-other fare, please."</p>
            <p>The transportation equipment of that seemingly far-off time and place should be described with some
                    minuteness for the benefit of a generation that hardly knows a mule, much less a mule-car. The
                    "bob-tail" vehicle spoken of, with its rear omnibus-like step instead of a
                    platform, was drawn by a pair of attenuated mules equipped with little whisk-broom tails and long
                    waving ears. The value of the ears is unknown, but the tails evidently served the same purpose as a
                    crank on a model T Ford, for, whenever the driver as an initial step toward starting things leaned
                    over his dashboard with a gad or switch hook and proceeded to dust the mules' hides, the
                    tails would set up a brisk rotary motion, generating sundry groans and internal rumblings as the
                    little beasts strained at the collars. Presently everything would be under way-no mean miracle when
                    a car was packed to the limit with human freight. When a crowd of effervescent students made up the
                    cargo, they added to the gaities of the situation according to the contagion of their inspirations,
                    and, as they are prolific of inspirations, their performances were sometimes extremely diverting.
                    Among the lingering recollections of their pranks is that of a college chorus accompanied by hideous
                    squeaks and shrieks which student "strap-hangers" had learned to produce by a <pb n="106" id="VAA4025-028-2-036"/> certain peculiar swing on the hand straps. The concerted
                    swaying which was imparted to the car, threatened to derail it, to the wrath of the driver and the
                    demoralization of the laboring mules. On one occasion when travel was suspended by reason of an
                    unpaid fare and the driver came back in the car to reason about it, a college girl slipped out on
                    the front platform, fastened the door behind her and whipped up the mules to stop speed before the
                    official driver realized what was happening.</p>
            <p>A particularly adventurous transportation risk was taken when one tried to get home by the last night
                    car. If all those aboard could be compressed into the "bob-tail," well and good;
                    if not it was for the unaccommodated, neither well nor good. The writer remembers at least one
                    enforced jaunt when he with two companions walked the five miles eastward after theater hours; after
                    all, this was not much harder than trying to get there by a jammed car subject to mishaps. At the
                    sharp street turnings on the city end of the route it was no uncommon thing for the clumsy vehicle,
                    which had no bogie-truck, to be pulled off the track. That meant that it had to disgorge its
                    passengers in order to be put back. After this there would be a grand scramble for seats, when many
                    who had been fortunate before now became strap-hangers. The adventures were varied. One night a
                    party of students bound <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName>-ward in a snow stom had to get out repeatedly to help push the car through the drifts.
                    At the stables, near the edge of town, the driver, in this instanw, objected to going farther,
                    declaring that he would not be able to get back alone. His decision meant a mile, more or less, of
                    snow wading for the students. In the midst of his troubles with snow-drifts, the conductor-driver
                    had neglected to collect the second fares at Sheridan Drive. He was now informed that no more would
                    be paid until he had discharged his full obligation. This turned the tables, so two or three stable
                    hands were rousted out to go along as assistants on the return and the run was completed.
                    Incidentally, the extra nickles were not dropped in the slots but delievered by hand. Another
                    fugitive tradition is that on a certain day the car broke down, leaving the passengers marooned in a
                    sea of mud far from their destinations. They were rescued by "Tip" Shank, a local
                    live-stock dealer, who happened along with a big-empty cattle-wagon and took them all to town.</p>
            <pb n="107" id="VAA4025-028-2-037"/>
            <p>The comedies of the transportation service did not end with the mule-cars. In course of time, the
                    "back-door route" from the city to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> was changed to a more direct one by way of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> Street and the National Road, and new types of cars were experimented with. First the
                    company tried a steam "dummy" till one day it ran off the track and into a ditch,
                    injuring several persons, then they turned to electricity. The first venture with the new motive
                    power was a big storage-battery car that was brought from <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York City</region>
                    </placeName>. It had been troubled with chronic ailments there, but evidently it was thought by our
                    car company that a change of climate would restore it to health, so it was bought. They or we or
                    somebody proudly christened it "Jumbo," and by that name it always went. Like the
                    famous elephant whose cognomen it bore, "Jumbo" was impressive in appearance but
                    did not specialize as a runner. However, as a balker the big car was in a class by itself. To see it
                    start out in the morning with its capacious interior full of men and women bound for their daily
                    work in the city was a striking illustration of the truth, that hope springs eternal in the human
                    breast. Time after time it was thought that at last the problem of transportation was to be solved,
                    but somewhere down the line the car would stop stock still without apparent reason. Then would
                    follow a clinical diagnosis of "Jumbo's" internal troubles by the
                    motorman and conductor which would eventually result in a new release of energy. Meanwhile, of
                    course, the time scheduled for beginning office work was clocking on without intermission, and,
                    whenever "Jumbo's" exasperating balk continued too long, fuming
                    passengers would begin to "pile off" and scurry on afoot till overtaken again. One
                    passenger, an Englishman, who by virtue of his nationality and his profession as a teacher of music,
                    was irascible and temperamental, would regulary walk off his wrath in this fashion.</p>
            <p>A newspaper wag of the day made the most of this system of transportation. He dubbed the new line the
                    "get-off-and-push route," affirming that "Jumbo," like any big
                    box on castors, would run fairly well down hill but that a pushing contingent was called for to help
                    make the grades. The balking, he maintained, the same as with a horse, was an indignant protest
                    against overloading. His theory seems not unlikely when it is known that a load consisted of
                    "Seventy-five or eighty passengers with a proportionate number of baskets, <pb n="108" id="VAA4025-028-2-038"/> boxes, rolls and bundles all jammed together in one mass."
                    "One day," the facetious writer continued, "there will be an item for the
                    newspapers when the tail-gate gives way and a few tons of compressed humanity are spilled along the
                    track." In a similar vein he added that "when that autocrat of the road, the
                    haughty conductor, comes along he wedges, burrows and squirms his way through the car, walking over
                    the weak, planting his foot in an occasional market basket and setting his heel wherever he can find
                    a cherished corn. When his gentle presence is gone the killed and maimed are piled up in a
                    corner." This disproportion between the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> traveling public and the traveling accommodations long continued to invite the
                    attention of the humorist and the veracious chronicler above quoted, gives further curious and
                    interesting facts: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>By reason of the improved packing system the <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                            </placeName> people are undergoing a strange amalgamation process, being so ground into each
                            other by intimate contact that in many cases their respective indentities are quite
                            destroyed. But recently two men were so mixed up at the end of their ride that each took the
                            other's basket and went to the house of the other under the impression that he was
                            that man. If this thing continues the domestic and other complications threaten to become
                            embarrassing. If some of our reliable straight-ticket Democrats or Republicans should become
                            adulterated in this manner it might operate as an unexpected factor in our next election.<hi rend="sup">7</hi>
                  </p>
                    </quote>
            </p>
            <p>In due course "Jumbo" and patent insides as well went the way of all failures and
                    was succeeded by the over-head trolley. This was the beginning of car service that was not a
                    "joke", and added to natural gas, which came a little earlier, marked the
                    beginning of a new era for <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> and the passing of the old regime.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">The Fate of Arcadia.</hi> As may be gathered from the foregoing narrative <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName>, partly by reason of its intimate touch with <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Butler</settlement>
                    </placeName> College, retained for twenty years or more a distinctive character, not, indeed, quite
                    in line with the original conceptions of the founders, but one which, in the retrospect, offers much
                    that is pleasing, and unforgettable to those whose <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">7</hi> I venture to add another chronicle of the mule-car period from the
                            same Ananias: "Recently", he says in one of his characteristic accounts,
                            "a countryman,with a load of hay drove along the track in front of us, and our
                            mules, ate their way into the load like a pair of bugs into a mellow apple till their heads
                            and attenuated necks as far as the withers had quite disappeared from view, while their
                            hitherto scrawny bodies gradually swelled out in semblance of two inflated bladders. When,
                            finally, the man discovered that there was a cavity as big as a hogshead in the rear of his
                            cargo he lifted up the strains of his dulcet voice and blue flame and brimstone came forth
                            like the fiery breath of Apollyn. His team, being brisk walkers, had got us to town twenty
                            minutes sooner than we had anticipated, and so we appeased him by a collection and assured
                            him that he might make a good thing out of it if he would drive up and down the track
                            tolling the omnivorous mule."</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="109" id="VAA4025-028-2-039"/> memories love to turn back to it. Nevertheless the changes came
                    for natural reasons, and in the transition from the original community with its Arcadian ideas to
                    that of the less romantic present we can trace the social forces that have always thwarted Utopian
                    dreams. No community, it would seem, can for long be made up of people who think alike along
                    idealistic lines, and who can afford to indulge their ideals. With the rank and file it is, in the
                    nature of things, a struggle for existence, and the struggle must follow along ordained prosaic ways
                    of living. To do the work of a town laborers must be comparatively numerous, and workingmen can not
                    own big houses on big tracts. Since the Julian-Johnson plan made no provision for the housing of the
                    humbler class, it was inevitable that the big tracts, or at least many of them, should in time be
                    divided and subdivided for cheaper homes for more people, and that stipulated costs for houses could
                    not hold in the great majority of cases. Hence, before very long, we find <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName>, as a growing town, swinging away from the original intent. The new trend was aided by
                    the long period of depression which followed the financial slump of 1873, when a general stagnation,
                    commercially speaking, settled upon the place.</p>
            <p>But the inability to maintain a program of opulence was not the only nor even the chief factor in
                    changing the character of the community as it advanced from village to town. Most of the people who
                    gravitated to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> as a desirable living place brought with them no "hifalutin"
                    delusions about an Arcadian existence. Instead they represented a practical and democratic
                    Americanism with a strong leaning toward all that the constitutional Bill of Rights gave them. The
                    first line of cleavage to manifest itself seems to have been on the question of the divine right of
                    a poor man's live stock and the rights of the esthetes to have their flowers and shrubbery
                    protected against the incursions of destroying beasts. In the endeavor to satisfy first the one and
                    then the other of these two classes, the Town Board was from the beginning of its governing
                    functions kept jumping from the frying pan into the fire and back again. At the first sitting, an
                    ordinance was passed in favor of the landscape gardeners which forbade owners to permit hogs and
                    cattle to run at large in the streets. Not long after mules, horses and sheep were added to the
                    outlaw list. We may judge that this class legislation stirred up the possessors <pb n="110" id="VAA4025-028-2-040"/> of the hogs and cattle to the point of rebellion, for presently this
                    indiscriminating ordinance was modified to one against "vicious and breachy
                    cattle", and which now prohibited animals "known to be in the habit of jumping,
                    opening gates or pushing down fences," to pasture on the streets and commons. In regard to
                    well-behaved live stock, it was provided that "no owner shall be entitled to have more than
                    three such cattle running at large at any time unless herded by a competent herder."
                    Another provision, which seemed to be a concession to Cerberus, was that "it shall not be
                    unlawful for any horse, mule or ass having its head tied to its foreleg … so that its
                    head can not be elevated above a level with the lower portion of its body, to run at
                    large."</p>
            <p>But no amount of ordaining, however judiciously modified, served to harmonize the two classes that
                    opposed each other on the question of free pasture rights within the corporation. The family cow,
                    particularly, was an asset too valuable to be dispensed with, and the unfenced areas of the little
                    town offered succulent grasses too tempting to be safe from the devouring jaws of Sukey. Memory says
                    that as late as the later'eighties there was a vigorous war for more drastic legislation on
                    the cow issue. Even after the sought-for protective ordinances were permanentjy established on the
                    record books of the corporation, the local humorist gives us a picture, through the medium of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">News,</hi> of the town marshal using his family clothesline for a lariat and dragging
                    in to the pound reluctant bovine culprits "all shorn of their ferocity and weighed down
                    with a sense of guilt."<hi rend="sup">8</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The division of the town into these particular factions from inherent causes was but the forerunner
                    of cleavages that were conspiciously in evidence as long as <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> remained an independent corporation. Doubtless they existed and still exist in all
                    American communities, but, in this vanishing Arcadia, the principle of getting what you want by
                    fighting for it was exercised with exceptional vigor-so much so, in fact, that for years <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> matters furnished material for no end of facetious copy for the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> papers, and the "Classic Suburb" was considered a fair preserve for
                    smart cub reporters, with no closed season. The general line of separation <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">8</hi> By this time, too, the ordinance promoters had secured laws against
                            chickens, and the local funny man, in his plain, unvarnished fashion, related how the town
                            mahhal, yclept "chief of police", was embarrased by private garden patches
                            and barbed wire fences, when he attempted to arrest law-breaking fowls.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="111" id="VAA4025-028-2-041"/> that came to be established, after the acute live stock period,
                    was between those who held to a broad guage idea of improvements and those who regarded internal
                    improvements as infernal improvements, beyond certain limits-which limits meant very few public
                    works. This ever-recurring bone of contention so dominated the politics of the town as to give rise
                    to two local parties, the regulation Republican and Democratic organizations being supplanted by
                    temporary groups known as the "Home Rulers" and the "People's
                    Party." Between these the pot of town politics was kept boiling, sometimes furiously, as
                    the fires were fed by such issues as streets and sidewalks, street lighting, fire protection, water
                    supply and what not. No proposition of any kind, ever came to the fore, but had two sides, and the
                    town hall was the public arena where all those forensically talented, or who thought they were,
                    might have a chance to prove it.</p>
            <p>Between the crossfires of opposing advocates the Town Board was a sort of buffer or shock absorber.
                    In those pre-movie days when entertainment was rarer than now, that was one of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName>'s ways of getting thrills, relished all the more when a little political
                    chicanery was thrown in. A good example was furnished when the People's Party called a
                    great mass meeting to discuss indignantly a "burning issue", and the leaders of
                    the Home Rulers wedged themselves in with a carefully-prepared and studied method of procedure and
                    audaciously captured the meeting. One of the comedies of these occasions was the case of a young man
                    living at the edge of town who was studying law and who found excellent training at the Town Board
                    hearings. He was an eloquent advocate and, no doubt, was considered a valuable asset to the side he
                    happened to be on, till some one remembered that his home was outside the corporation, so that he
                    was not entitled to any voice whatever in the affairs of the town.</p>
            <p>Thus it is within the bounds of truth to say that most of the major improvements, that have converted
                    the primitive <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> that was into the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> that is, had to fight their way step by step. For example, the paving of the main
                    thoroughfare (now <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> Street) had one long history of opposition, punctuated with injunction suits and
                    delays.</p>
            <p>An unsettled problem for a long time, made more acute with every fire that occurred, was the
                    inadequacy of the water supply for fire protection. The demand for some sort <pb n="112" id="VAA4025-028-2-042"/> of equipment other than the "bucket brigade" was a
                    matter of perennial agitation, and the present writer recalls one occasion when competitive dealers
                    in such equipment brought their various types of hand engines to the town for demonstration, and a
                    spectacular squirting contest was staged down in the bottom lands by Pleasant Run, where sundry
                    shacks had been built for the sole purpose of burning. The exciting exhibit of flaming sheds and
                    their extinguishment by water pumped furiously from the creek caused a complete muster of the boys
                    of the town who enjoyed a memorable treat.</p>
            <p>The question of an adequate water supply, indeed, played a prominent part in the movement that ended
                    in the annexation of the suburb to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> in 1902. The last-named issue, quite in keeping with the habits of the town, developed
                    vehement and rival partisan groups. Everybody wanted water, but some wanted to get it in one way and
                    some in another. One faction was for bonding the town; the others advocated the surrender of the
                    town's autonomy for the sake of annexation to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, which would automatically take care of the water predicament as well as several other
                    vexatious problems of government.</p>
            <p>This fight was the last of the long series that had given character and piquancy to the history of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName>. The annexationists abetted by the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis City</settlement>
                    </placeName> Council had their way, and the city, anaconda-like swallowed up the suburb and
                    proceeded to make it over. The post office department tried to obliterate it as an entity, but still
                    it retains its identity and continues to bear the name its founders gave it. One point to be
                    remembered is that the little community which the writer has ventured to call a "Hoosier
                    Arcadia" did not, for inevitable reasons, grow according to the plans and specifications of
                    its founders, and yet much of what was best in those plans persisted in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> and gave an idealistic reality to its history. The safeguards that Sylvester Johnson
                    threw around it have operated to the present day. The educational and cultural dreams of Jacob
                    Julian, through the medium of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Butler</settlement>
                    </placeName> College, have affected more lives than anybody can estimate, and still leave mellow and
                    inspiring memories with those who are old enough to hark back to that first chapter. Such memories
                    are quickened and saddened by the thought of the old college halls now standing, empty and forlorn,
                    but once vibrant with young <pb n="113" id="VAA4025-028-2-043"/> and hopeful life-a center where
                    dreams and aspirations were nurtured.<hi rend="sup">9</hi>
            </p>
            <list type="footnotes">
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">9</hi> In 1876 (the Centennial year) a presidential proclamation called upon
                        the authorities of several cities and town "to collect in proper form the prominent
                        facts connected with their rise and progress with a view to their preservation and transmission
                        to posterity." A resolution of the <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                        </placeName> Town Board dated July 4 of the year named appointed John F. Julian, the town clerk,
                        to prepare such a history. If the work was done the writer has been unable to find trace of it.
                        Such a contemporary history carefully Prepared would have been a document of interest and
                    value.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <pb n="114" id="VAA4025-028-2-044"/>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-028-2-a05">
            <head>Indiana Historical Society</head>
            <byline>By CHRISTOPHER B. COLEMAN, Secretary</byline>
            <p>The Indiana Historical Society has completed for its William Henry Smith Memorial Library, which is
                    to have a room in the new State Library and Historical Building, a portfolio measuring approximately
                    30 by 27 inches, containing measured drawings, blueprints, detailed studies, and photographs of the
                    former Indiana School for the Blind, which stood on the square bounded by Meridian, St. Clair, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>
                    </placeName>, and North Streets, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>. This material would enable an architectural sculptor to make an exact miniature of the
                    building, and it would be possible to rebuild the structure (removed in 1930-31, to permit the
                    grading of the World War Memorial Plaza) from the drawings and pictures.</p>
            <p>It is the hope of the Society to get similar records of all public buildings of importance in the
                    state which are in danger of being torn down in the near future. The architecture of a country or
                    state is one of the most important evidences of its culture, and is an important contribution, as
                    well, to the education of its citizens. Moreover, the restoration of buildings is now being carried
                    on to such an extent that drawings, details, and models of notable period buildings are certain to
                    be needed in the future. If such information had been at hand in the case of
                    "Wakefield," the birthplace of George <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName>, thousands of dollars would have been saved in its rebuilding for the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> Bicentennial, and one would have far more confidence that the building is accurately
                    reproduced.</p>
            <p>The projects for the restoration of <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Williamsburg</settlement>,
                            <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
               </placeName>, Spring Mill, Indiana, and
                            <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="ilu">Illinois</region>
               </placeName>, afford other illustrations of similar needs. Members of the
                    Historical Society will be doing a service by calling attention to important typical or period
                    buildings anywhere in the state which are in imminent danger of destruction.</p>
            <p>The Society is joining this summer in the archaeological survey of the Whitewater Valley. Glenn A.
                    Black, of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, long an amateur archaeologist and fresh from a year's work with the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> State Archaeological and Historical Society, <pb n="115" id="VAA4025-028-2-045"/> is
                    field director. A number of individuals are co-operating. It is hoped that the Historical Bureau
                    will be able to aid also.</p>
            <p>This work is apparently better understood and appreciated outside of the state than within it.
                    Leading archaeologists in <placeName>
                  <region type="state" reg="miu">Michigan</region>, <region type="state" reg="ilu">Illinois</region>, <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
               </placeName>, and the East, are looking to it for light upon questions raised by the
                    archaeological work carried on in other states. Until the Society and other organizations made their
                    small beginning in this field six years ago, Indiana was one of the most backward states in the
                    Union as far as concerned a scientific study of its prehistoric inhabitants. The public generally in
                    this state has not yet awakened to the interest and importance of this study.</p>
            <p>In the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> at large there has been a veritable archaeological "drive". Some of
                    the ablest men in the country have devoted themselves to solving the many riddles of our prehistory.
                    In Mexico, Central America, and Peru, prehistoric cultures have been unearthed which are nothing
                    less than startling. The present civilization in these countries is now looked upon, in part, as an
                    outgrowth of prehistoric cultures, as well as of European colonization. Yields in the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> have not been quite so significant but have been sufficient to enable scientists to
                    formulate reasonable working hypotheses concerning our prehistory. The importance of a scientific
                    study of mounds, now being rapidly destroyed by pot-hunters, as well as by cultivation, roadbuilding
                    and natural forces, can hardly be overemphasized. The Historical Division of the Carnegie Institute
                    of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> has turned all its resources into the channel of archaeological investigation. While
                    this sudden shifting was unfortunate from the point of view of historians dealing with later times,
                    it is an indication of the significance which archaeological work is now assuming.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="[116]" id="VAA4025-028-2-046"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-028-2-a06">
            <head>Documents</head>
            <head>JOURNAL OF MELVILLE COX ROBERTSON</head>
            <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Foreword</hi>
                </p>
            <p>The soldier who kept the diary here reproduced was the son of James Dowen and Temperance (Gaddy)
                    Robertson. He was born on October 17, 1840, on a farm near <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Paris</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indiana. The town of Deputy, being nearer the old homestead, is now the post office of
                    the family occupying the Robertson farm.<hi rend="sup">1</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Melville C. Robertson attended Asbury College (now DePauw University) and a little later Indiana
                    University where he was a junior in the Law School when he enlisted.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> While a
                    student at Indiana University he was a member of the Athenian Society of which he was chosen
                    president in May, 1862.<hi rend="sup">3</hi> He joined the army in February, 1864, becoming a member
                    of Company E of the Ninety-third Regiment of Indiana volunteers. This Regiment, which formed a part
                    of the Army of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="tnu">Tennessee</region>
                    </placeName>, was transferred to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Memphis</settlement>
                    </placeName> in November, 1863. To this place Private Robertson and other new recruits were sent
                    from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> in the spring of 1863.</p>
            <p>The diary and letters reveal the experiences of the young soldier up to the time of his fatal
                    illness. From the Parole Camp at Vicksburg, the released prisoner of war made the trip to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">St. Louis</settlement>
                    </placeName> on the <hi rend="i">Baltic.</hi> While on the vessel, he wrote home on April 20, 1865,
                    stating that he was quite low with typhoid fever. He asked that his father come to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">St. Louis</settlement>
                    </placeName> to see him. In response to this request, the father, and another son, James Dempster
                    Robertson, journeyed to that city, but death came to the son and brother before their arrival.</p>
            <p>The first sheets of the diary were sent home before the capture of Private Robertson. That portion of
                    the journal written during captivity was entrusted to a comrade along with other possessions before
                    the homeward journey was begun. When delivered to the family, the diary showed hard usage. The
                    faithful friend of the dead soldier had leaped into <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">1</hi> Miss Eleanor M. Robertson of Urbana, Illinois, who sent the journal
                            of Melville C. Robertson to the <hi rend="i">Editor</hi>, also constributed copies of the
                            several letters which are printed in conjunction with the diary. Miss Robertson also kindly
                            supplied biographical data of value.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">2</hi> Theophilus Wylie, <hi rend="i">Indiana University</hi> (1820-1890),
                            369, 444.</item>
                  <item>Melville C. Robertson to his parents, Bloomington, Indiana, May 6, 1862. Cited by Eleanor
                            C. Robertson in biographical data.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="117" id="VAA4025-028-2-047"/> the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName> when escaping from the burning <hi rend="i">Sultana</hi> causing the leaves of the
                    Journal to become soaked. In order to preserve the record, the brother made a copy which he
                    endorsed: "Melville C. Robertson's Journal, A Faithful Transcript, by J. Demp
                    Robertson." This copy, the <hi rend="i">Editor</hi> has in hand and has used it to check
                    the typed copy supplied by Miss Eleanor M. Robertson.</p>
            <p>On a card which he placed in his father's Bible the departing recruit left the following
                    statement: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>At home March 21st, 1864</p>
                        <p>To-day at 2 o'clock P.M. I leave home perhaps forever. If I should return at the end
                            of three years alive I hope to have the proud satisfaction of saying "My country is
                            saved and I have done my duty as one of its citizens." If I fall, let my friends
                                <hi rend="i">forget</hi> my <hi rend="i">faults</hi> and remember me only as a dead
                            soldier of the republic I want no brighter immortality."</p>
                    </quote>
            </p>
            <p>It is of interest that after the body of the deceased soldier had been disinterred, brought from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">St. Louis</settlement>
                    </placeName> and buried in the Pisgah Cemetery near Deputy, Indiana, a stone was set up at the grave
                    bearing words from the above: "Remember me only as a dead soldier of the Republic. I want
                    no brighter immortality."</p>
            <p>On the day previous to the placing of the card in the Bible, the new recruit wrote, at the beginning
                    of his journal, an acknowledgement of the receipt from his brother of the blank book which he was
                    using: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">March 20th, 1864</p>
                        <p>I remarked carelessly, directing my remarks to my brother Dempster, he who aforetime did
                            instruct youth in a common school in Graham Township, that I would have to have a Blank
                            Book. I was going to the wars for three years, my countenance was lengthened, my voice was
                            doleful; his heart was touched by the funeral solemnity that marked all my actions, and as
                            he had no further immediate use for this "book" he generously gave it to
                            me for which I acknowledge myself very much obliged to him.</p>
                        <p rend="right">Yours Soldierly,</p>
                        <p rend="right">"Kraks"</p>
                    </quote>
            </p>
            <p rend="center">[THE JOURNAL]</p>
            <p>
                    <text>
                  <body>
                     <div type="diary">
                        <p>Union Depot <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                                    </placeName> Ind</p>
                        <p>March 30 1864</p>
                        <p>Have been a month in the <placeName>
                                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                                    </placeName> service without seeing any of the realities of war. Am in the cars now
                                    to start for my regiment at <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Memphis</settlement>
                                    </placeName>. What will the next three years bring forth? The bell is ringing. <pb n="118" id="VAA4025-028-2-048"/> The cars move. Farewell, <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                                    </placeName>, farewell Indiana; farewell home, friends, all for the flag.</p>
                        <p>Centralia <placeName>
                                        <region type="state" reg="ilu">Illinois</region>
                                    </placeName> 10 o'clock P M</p>
                        <p>From <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                                    </placeName> to Matoon 150 miles against 4 o'clock P M. There found the
                                    people terribly excited over the prospect of an attack upon the town by butternuts
                                    to-night From there here on the <placeName>
                                        <region type="state" reg="ilu">Illinois</region>
                                    </placeName> Central without any accident All in good Spirits</p>
                        <p>8 ½ o'clock Thursday March 31</p>
                        <p>Am at Cairo this morning. Arrived here about daylight. 'Tis as has been
                                    represented, a delectable place. Will have to stay here till evening anyhow, and
                                    perhaps till to-morrow morning One of our 93rd boys, while gawking around an eating
                                    louse a few minutes ago, was accidently shot in the leg. Nothing serious, however,
                                    is anticipated from it. A mere flesh wound—have, this morning found
                                    myself 325 miles on my road from <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                                    </placeName> to Dixie.</p>
                        <p>Friday morning Apr 1st</p>
                        <p>Left Cairo this morning at a quarter past three. A rainy, gloomy morning. Thoughts of
                                    home and absent friends spring up unbidden. Must crush them out. Prudence tells me
                                    so, though they afford me a pleasure all too melancholy A few minutes ago we passed
                                    the now historic Island No 10. It is but a small place but even a civilian cannot
                                    fail to perceieve the importnce of holding possession of it, if we would command the <placeName>
                                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                                    </placeName>.</p>
                        <p>Saturday April 2nd</p>
                        <p>In <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Memphis</settlement>
                                    </placeName> at last. Got into camp about 9 o'clock. A M <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Memphis</settlement>
                                    </placeName> has been a nice place once and still retains some of its beauties. Our
                                    Camp is in one of the nicest places in the neighborhood of the city. Our camps are
                                        <hi rend="i">camps</hi>, substantial log or plank cabins with brick chimneys.
                                    Soldiering here for three years without a fight would be pleasant, I fancy, I am
                                    highly pleased with my company officers My first impressions are that they are
                                    gentlemen and I have faith to believe that time will show these impressions to be
                                    correct Perhaps my judgment has been biased by the favor they have shown to me a
                                    perfect stranger to them.</p>
                        <p>Sunday April 3rd</p>
                        <p>Today has been my first Sunday in the "Sunny South" The forepart of
                                    the day was splendid—the after part not so much so, for at this writing
                                    (4 o'clock P M) it is cloudy and raining Our chaplain, they say, is gone so
                                    we have had no religious services in Camp today. This evening I witnessed for the
                                    first time the operation of "bucking and gagging" an unruly
                                    soldier Life is sweet but it seems to me, shooting would be preferable to me</p>
                        <p>Monday April 4th</p>
                        <p>When I started from home I expected to find the weather mild and pleasant in this
                                    latitude but I find myself sadly disappointed. Today has been as cold and blustering
                                    as we usually see this time of the year <pb n="119" id="VAA4025-028-2-049"/> in
                                    Indiana Company E is a spunky animal I judge from demonstrations I have witnessed
                                    since I came among them One fight since I have been writing They might hold
                                    themselves profitably I think Forrest may be in before morning and give them a
                                    chance to empty themselves against him He is reported within ten miles of here this
                                    evening There has been skirmishing with some loss on our side today. O what a horrid
                                    thing is <hi rend="i">war</hi> at the best but this war of brothers what pen can
                                    describe its horrors.</p>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>"The bitter tide of hatred stronger runs and deeper grows</p>
                                    <p>As the pleading voice of nature addeth self-reproach to blows"</p>
                                </quote>
                        <p>April 5 1864</p>
                        <p>Tis nearly sundown—one of the most beautiful evenings I ever saw.
                                    Yesterday was a time to make one think of a stormy Indiana March
                                    day—today would have passed for may in that latitude. "Nary a
                                    fight" yet. Forrest didn't come last night and I haven't
                                    heard a word said about the apprehended attack to-day As I write they come around
                                    for three more men from our company to strengthen the pickets to-night. This may
                                    mean something.</p>
                        <p>April 6th</p>
                        <p>Nothing of importance to record to-day except the discovery of an old acquaintance in
                                    the regiment, Mr <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Milton</settlement>
                                    </placeName> Wilson of Scott County I saw him two or three days ago and thought his
                                    face looked familiar This evening on Dress Parade I set myself to work to locate
                                    him, which I soon succeeded in doing We had a pleasant time to-gether talking of old
                                    acquaintances and old times. Weather pleasant to-day, with appearance of rain
                                    shortly.</p>
                        <p>Guard Mounting April 7 1864</p>
                        <p>Orders came around about midnight last night to each company in the regiment to stack
                                    arms in front of their quarters at revielle, and awaith further orders in their
                                    quarters with their accouterments on About sun-rise the regiment was ordered out on
                                    the "Color line" stacked arms and laid by them till breakfast time
                                    when permission was given them to go and eat Troops from front of us have been
                                    moving into town this morning As yet I have seen no enemy nor heard anything
                                    definite regarding one There is, doubtless a pretty large force in the neighbor-hood
                                    somewhere but where it is I cant tell. Some reports place its number at 25,000
                                    Notwithstanding the rumors of the proximity of the enemy I kept my bed till sunrise
                                    and then read the paper till our darky blacked my boots for me</p>
                        <p>Sundown</p>
                        <p>No rebels yet Nothing said about them One man tied to a tree this evening for being
                                    drunk and disorderly. Weather still threatening rain</p>
                        <p>April 8th</p>
                        <p>After dark. To-day has been particularly uneventful to me with the exception of the
                                    reception by me of two letters—the first I have got <pb n="120" id="VAA4025-028-2-050"/> since arriving in <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Memphis</settlement>
                                    </placeName>—One from Demp and one from Florence. They were the richest
                                    treat I have been admited to since leaving <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                                    </placeName>. Company "E" still retains its
                                    combativeness—two of its worthy members had four fights this evening
                                    about their share I think Two of their battles I witnessed myself I have often heard
                                    of men fighting like dogs and then shaking hands in friendship over it afterward but
                                    it was never my fortune to see it done till to-day After the second fight these
                                    fellows came together in perfect good humor—but it was all "no
                                    good" the whisky in them brought them together again in a half an hour</p>
                        <p>Saturday night April 9th</p>
                        <p>Today has been very disagreeable, cold, rainy and windy The weather has been just
                                    right to make one feel cozy and comfortable in the tent by a rousing fire Nothing of
                                    importance to record of camp or rebels today</p>
                        <p>April 10th '64</p>
                        <p>A very pleasant day has Sunday the 10th of April been very unlike yesterday; warm and
                                    sunshiny No fight in company E to-day, consequently no excitement Today may be set
                                    down as dull.</p>
                        <p>April 11th</p>
                        <p>Nothing today</p>
                        <p>April 12th</p>
                        <p>This evening was kindly invited by Quartermaster Quail to ride down town with him The
                                    invitation was accepted with alacrity When I went over to the Adjutants tent to get
                                    my pass countersigned I made the acquaintance of Liet Sid Tinker at present acting
                                    Ad'jt for the regiment He is an old acquaintance of several of my friends
                                    and a school mate of Demp's He went down town with us Is a very pleas-ant
                                    fine little fellow I think. Had a better chance of seeing the city than I have had
                                    before. Went down as far as Fort Pickering Those black looking fellows that command
                                    the town look dangerous</p>
                        <p>Wednesday night April 13th</p>
                        <p>To-day have heard that Fort Pillow is in possession of the rebels—will I
                                    suppose cut off communication with the North for a day or two at least Received a
                                    letter from Cousin Mate to-day She like every one else I have heard from, expresses
                                    her surprise that I had patriotism enough to go into the army. Went to prayer
                                    meeting to-night. Had a very interesting little time; reminded me of similar
                                    gatherings I have attended nearer home.</p>
                        <p>April 15th</p>
                        <p>At work to-day writing.</p>
                        <p>April 17th</p>
                        <p>To-day, I have spent loafing, smoking, reading, writing and going to church. Heard
                                    our Chaplain preach a very good sermon from the words: He that is not for me is
                                    against me; he that gathereth not with me scattereth abroad. One of Co
                                    "E" men went out and got <pb n="121" id="VAA4025-028-2-051"/> his
                                    skull peeled Took it very coolly. Didn't seem to like the sewing up part so
                                    well.</p>
                        <p>Monday April 18th</p>
                        <p>In my juvenile days when paternal thrift and watchfulness was giving me lessons in
                                    practical industry after the plough and at the end of the hoe handle, I had pleasant
                                    dreams of an Elysium where Idleness was the presiding deity. The dream of bliss
                                    however has faded away before an almost entire absence of anything to do in Camp.
                                    Time wears away slowly when I have no employment at all. Oh for a little labor with
                                    the privilege of choosing my own kind. There was a review of the <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Memphis</settlement>
                                    </placeName> militia down town to-day After it was over Gen Hurlbut made a farewell
                                    speech to them He leaves here in a day or two to take command at Cairo. Buckland is
                                    now cock of the walk here Delayed mail came down to-day and I had the good luck to
                                    get nothing where I felt almost confident of two or three letters anyhow.
                                    "Sich is life."</p>
                        <p>Tuesday April 19th</p>
                        <p>I witnessed something to-day that I never expected.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </text>
                </p>
            <p>The diary stops abrutly here. It is probable that some leaves sent home in letters were lost. The
                    following letter will help to fill the gap: <text>
                  <body>
                     <div type="letter">
                        <dateline>
                                    <address>
                              <addrLine>
                                 <placeName>
                                    <settlement type="city">Memphis</settlement>
                                    <region type="state" reg="tnu">Tennessee</region>
                                 </placeName>
                              </addrLine>
                           </address>
                                    <date>April 29th 1864</date>
                                </dateline>
                        <salute>Dear Father,</salute>
                        <p>Orders came to us this evening to draw two days rations and be ready to start on a
                                    march at daylight in the morning. The officers and soldiers are directed to leave
                                    all extra baggage behind. We are not to leave here permanently—it is to
                                    be only a scout of a few days. At least that is the general opinion. There is to be
                                    a strong cavalry force to accompany us I think. The movement is probably to be a
                                    feint on some point to draw the attention of Forrest while something else is done.
                                    Look for stirring news from all quarters within the next six weeks. My opinion is
                                    that this is a part of a general movement of all our forces. = I am fat, hearty, all
                                    right. I haven't time to write a letter tonight. I will let you hear from
                                    me at the earliest moment after I return here—or the first time I have an
                                    opportunity of sending a letter if we do not come back soon.</p>
                        <p>My love to all and every one</p>
                        <closer>
                                    <salute>Your Son</salute>
                                    <signed>Melville</signed>
                                </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </text>
            </p>
            <p>The next entry undoubtedly belongs to the journal. It was mailed home with a letter and not
                    incorporated in the diary when copied by J. Demp Robertson.</p>
            <p>
                    <text>
                  <body>
                     <div type="diary">
                        <p>
                           <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Memphis</settlement>
                                    </placeName>, Ten. May 29" 1864</p>
                        <p>Sunday evening about eight o'clock finds me seated for the purpose of noting
                                    some of the not very startling occurrences that have <pb n="122" id="VAA4025-028-2-052"/> fallen under my observation during the past week, and
                                    of whiling away in writing an idle hour. What a vast amount of moralizing may be the
                                    result of this "sitting" and what an abundance of sage reflections
                                    and trite observations may fall from me before I arise remains yet to be
                                    seen—I commence this under circumstances rather unpromising for either
                                    speed or excellence in execution. The tent is now momentarily empty as the boys
                                    stand in line to answer to their names at roll-call but they will soon be back. If
                                    they were all duly sober my task would not be quite so difficult as I apprehend it
                                    will be as they are For the truth in regard to their condition is that two or three
                                    of them are not "beastly sober." It would be a good thing for our
                                    regiment in several respects if we were in a situation requiring more active service
                                    than we are engaged in here. In the absence of anything else to do a great many of
                                    the boys engage in the pleasant and profitable pastime of getting drunk and raising
                                    "old Harry" in the shape of a fight rather more frequently than is
                                    amusing to me. When men have plenty of hard work to do in the field they do not have
                                    the opportunities for dissipation they have in such a place as this Their habits are
                                    better and a better feeling exists among them. This is the testimony of men who are
                                    supposed to know and it looks reasonable. I have before remarked the great evils
                                    resulting from intemperance in the army and the observations of every day but serve
                                    to confirm and strengthen me in the resolution I have made not to be induced by any
                                    means to touch intoxicating liquors in any form while in the army. I see here men
                                    who were strictly temperate at home forming a habit of tippling which they will one
                                    day regret. And this because they have not moral courage to refuse the offered cup.
                                    It is no difficult task to live temperately here if men will commence right take the
                                    proper stand and there is no great amount of difficulty in adhering to it. And
                                    besides this men are better respected and more confidence is reposed in them even by
                                    those who make a practice of drinking because they are temperate. I have been
                                    faith-fully "tried on" to "take some thing" but
                                    have found no difficulty in refusing. And now that it is known that I do not drink
                                    although the bottle may be offered me out of courtesy the matter is not pressed and
                                    the principle on which I refuse is respected…. But whether it is
                                    respected or not, I do refuse, and will continue to refuse and if men do not have
                                    enough of the spirit of true manhood about them to regard me with at least as much
                                    favor as if I chose to travel the road to ruin with them they shall have the right
                                    to their opinions of me and I will consider myself fortunate in avoiding their
                                    society.</p>
                        <p>The events of the past week have not been of a very startling nature nor very many in
                                    number at least those that effect me. Last Monday a steamboat collapsed her flues at
                                    the landing and killed two or three persons. on Tuesday some guerrillas fired upon
                                    our pickets but did no damage farther than to scare them some and on Thursday
                                    evening friend Mooney presented me with a four dollar hat which last being an
                                    article that I began to stand some what in need of raised rather livelier emotions
                                    in my breast than any thing else <pb n="123" id="VAA4025-028-2-053"/> that has
                                    fallen in my way for some time.</p>
                        <p>We have had our usual number of rumors of marches through the week but the rumors
                                    have not yet moved us from here. To night there seems to be "something in
                                    the wind" Pieces of artillery and stray cavalry men are flying past every
                                    few minutes some towards town and some out. It is probable there is to be a cavalry
                                    raid into the surrounding country somewhere, and that preparations are now being
                                    made to start.</p>
                        <p>Have received no letters from home during the week, the first week I have missed for
                                    some time. Got one from the neighborhood though, from Mary Smith. Also received
                                    letters from Mate &amp; Mal Gasaway, Magg Payne and one from Miss Ollie Maybury.
                                    I received a letter from Benn some time ago in which he told me that Ollie while on
                                    a visit to <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Charlestown</settlement>
                                    </placeName> requested him to tell me to write to her which I accordingly did and
                                    received a prompt answer.</p>
                        <p>Monday morning May 30" /64</p>
                        <p>A splendid morning, and by the way all the mornings of the past week have been that,
                                    ushering in days that, without the dust which abounds, would make a man with an easy
                                    conscience feel "bully" using an <hi rend="i">elegant</hi> but
                                    very expressive phrase. They have been neither too cold nor too hot. The dust
                                    however is getting to be very unpleasantly thick. We have had no rain for some time
                                    and the incessant passing of cavalry camped in front of us, with their horses to the
                                    river for water and back, has loosened up a vast amount of it in the road runing
                                    past our camp.</p>
                        <p>My health still continues good, and my relationship with the Sutler's
                                    establishment unchanged. To the last I am indebted for the good cigar which now
                                    stands out from my mouth an ornamental column to my elegant
                                    "phiz." The regiment is still drilling reularly every day, a
                                    pastime which I am happy to say I am not yet required to indulge in. A slight change
                                    in the order of drill during the week, Brigade Drill on Tuesdays &amp; Thursdays
                                    instead of Battalion Drill. It is a Drill I have not yet witnessed as it takes place
                                    at the old Fair Grounds about a half mile from our camp …. For this time
                                    I stop.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </text>
                </p>
            <p>A letter of May 31 fits in well at this juncture. It is followed immediately by the next entry in the
                    journal, that of June 1.</p>
            <p>
                    <text>
                  <body>
                     <div type="letter">
                        <dateline>
                                    <address>
                              <addrLine>
                                 <placeName>
                                    <settlement type="city">Memphis</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="tnu">Tenn</region>
                                 </placeName>
                              </addrLine>
                           </address>
                                    <date>10 o'clock P.M. May 31st/64</date>
                                </dateline>
                        <salute>Dear Father &amp; Mother</salute>
                        <p>Since dark to night we have received orders to march at five in the morning. We have
                                    been busy making the necessary preparations ever since. I now snatch a few moments
                                    to drop you a note informing you of the fact.</p>
                        <p>Where we are going I cannot tell, certain. Reports are that we move towards Corinth.
                                    From what I can learn there is a large force going. Convalescents, sick, and baggage
                                    are to be left behind. It moved. Convalescents, sick, and baggage are to be left
                                    behind. It <pb n="124" id="VAA4025-028-2-054"/> may be only a scout of a few days,
                                    or it may prove a permanent move and the camp be moved to us. As for myself I am in
                                    excellent trim for it and have worked my plans so well that I have no knapsack to
                                    carry. I am in with the medical department and have managed to have everything
                                    hauled I want to take along. I have no time to write more but will embrace the first
                                    opportunity of informing you of my whereabouts and condition.</p>
                        <closer>
                                    <salute>Your son</salute>
                                    <signed>Mell</signed>
                                </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </text>
                </p>
            <p>
                    <text>
                  <body>
                     <div type="diary">
                        <p>Wednesday June 1st</p>
                        <p>The close of my first day march with a musket on my shoulder. At about 10
                                    o'clock this morning we left the city of <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Memphis</settlement>
                                    </placeName> on the M &amp; C R R. We came on the cars about twenty three or
                                    four miles, passing what once were two or three nice villages, now almost
                                    deserted—leaving the cars we marched three or four miles In about fifteen
                                    minutes after we took the road for it; it commenced to rain and as all my baggage
                                    was in an ambulance I [was] beautifully wet. Stopping in an open field about an hour
                                    ago we have prepared for a bivouac It has stopped raining I have taken a supper of
                                    "hard tack" and onions which some of the boys foraged on the road
                                    and coffee, and feel as well contented with my present situation as I ever did with
                                    one in life Much better than I expected I would be I have made arrangements to sleep
                                    on the ground under the ambulance with my friend Dickey to whom I am indebted for
                                    having my baggage hauled. He is Hospital Steward; is well educated, and is one of
                                    Nature's noblemen.</p>
                        <p>Noon Friday June 3rd</p>
                        <p>Yesterday we staid all day at the place of our encampment the night before. This
                                    morning at 4 o'clock we started out; our brigade in front; our regiment the
                                    third from the front, that is of the infantry, there is a large force of cavalry
                                    ahead. There is another Brigade of whites and one of negroes along. The whole force
                                    is at least between eight and ten thousand We are going in a Southeast direction
                                    towards <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                                        <region type="state" reg="tnu">Tennessee</region>
                                    </placeName>. It has rained on us a good deal of the morning but the roads are not
                                    very slippery except in some places; mud is ten times more disagreeable than dust. I
                                    stand it first rate</p>
                        <p>Lamar Miss 10 A.M. Sat. June 4th</p>
                        <p>About 1 o'clock yesterday evening we started on the road again In about an
                                    hour it commenced raining and continued to rain on till night My oil blanket
                                    protected me for an hour or two after that it came through and I was wet to the skin
                                    long before we got here We marched eight miles and came through without stopping a
                                    moment. The mud was about shoe mouth deep and I felt like I would be about out if we
                                    continued much longer But we had not stopped long before my weariness was all gone.
                                    We stopped in an open field on the east side of what was once the village of Lamar.
                                    Now there is only two or three buildings inhabited There are several others still
                                    standing <pb n="125" id="VAA4025-028-2-055"/> The rain was coming down in torrents
                                    when we stopped and an immediate rush was made for the old buildings, and the fences
                                    around the others for plank and rails to make shelters and for wood A guard had been
                                    stationed to protect these but men wet and cold were not to be easily managed. I
                                    went to an old house and staid during the night. This mornin at 4 o'clock
                                    we started on our way for this place We made an easy march over good roads so far as
                                    condition is concerned although they were rather hilly. We made frequent halts from
                                    one cause and another, arriving here precisely at twelve a distance of ten or twelve
                                    miles Here we have stopped in a nice grove, drawing rations for two days and will
                                    remain until to-morrow The boys are "going" for pigs and chickens.
                                    Dickey and myself captured and confiscated a chicken which didn't go bad by
                                    any means As yet I know nothing of the object or destination of the expedition</p>
                        <p>Way down in <placeName>
                                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                                    </placeName> Tuesday morning June 7th</p>
                        <p>Yesterday morning we started from Camp at 4 o'clock In a few minutes it
                                    commenced raining and rained on us for about three hours, a part of the time about
                                    as hard as it usually rains The roads in consequence became very slippery and bad
                                    and the artillery in front got along very slowly over a bad road. We kept on the
                                    road until about four in the evening making about fifteen miles. The crackers in our
                                    haversacks made our dinners, which we eat when ever we felt like it I was very tired
                                    when we got into camp as it was awful walking over the muddy roads. A good wash,
                                    supper and breakfast has put me in good order again and I feel as much like the work
                                    before me today as any time since I left <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Memphis</settlement>
                                    </placeName> Our regiment is in advance today It is probable there will be
                                    skirmishing to-day. If there is we will be in it.</p>
                        <p>
                           <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Ripley</settlement>
                                    </placeName> Miss June 8th</p>
                        <p>We started from camp yesterday morning about 11 o'clock, changeing our
                                    course from East to nearly due South We got in here a distance of ten or eleven
                                    miles about Sundown. The roads were good and the country more level than it was the
                                    day before but the soil the same sandy as before and the timber pine and oak The
                                    country was more open and more thickly settled than we have passed through since
                                    leaving <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                                    </placeName> We were in the advance and on the lookout for rebels but none were seen
                                    The citizens here say a small squad of thirty or forty passed through here awhile
                                    before we came in They are evidently hovering in our front to Watch and report our
                                    progress The town of <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Ripley</settlement>
                                    </placeName> is the county seat of Tippah county, and was once a beautiful village
                                    Now it wears the same look of desolation that marks all the country we have passed
                                    through The court house is burnt and all the places of business deserted, windows
                                    broken in and doors bursted open as if they had been pillaged Last night I slept in
                                    a building by which we are encamped and which is used for a seminary for young
                                    ladies I am informed there is about a hundred in attendance Some of our men were
                                    taken to account this morning by Col Poole for pillaging houses One of theme was
                                    tied up to a tree <pb n="126" id="VAA4025-028-2-056"/> by the thumbs for his fun
                                    after the stolen article was returned. We are allowed to take what eatables we must
                                    but nothing else.</p>
                        <p>4 miles south of <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Ripley</settlement>
                                    </placeName> Wednesday night June 8th</p>
                        <p>We started from <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Ripley</settlement>
                                    </placeName> about twelve or one o'clock today and got out this far by
                                    four. We move very slowly. The enemy this evening are reported in force ahead, with
                                    what truth or how far ahead I cannot tell We may have a fight tomorrow I think
                                    however he will not make a stand this side of Tupelo if there. To-night promises to
                                    be rainy but friend Dickey and myself are pretty well prepared for it We have
                                    stretched a tent of our oil blankets cut a lot of walnut bushes, made a bed of them
                                    and our woollen blankets and propose to have a good time of it.</p>
                        <p>Thursday morning June 9th</p>
                        <p>It is now 9 o'clock and we have not yet moved I slept well and dry although
                                    it was raining quite hard when I went to sleep. We are camped in a nice grove from
                                    which we miss the pine tree which has been with us for the last few days The timber
                                    is gum, oak hickory and walnut For the last few days water has been plenty owing to
                                    the quantity of rain that has fallen I think that usually water is scarce. From
                                    present indications I think we will move in a few minutes how fast or in what
                                    direction remains yet to be seen A thinning out of our train takes place this
                                    morning All wagons not absolutely necessary for our use, and all surplus baggage are
                                    to be sent back to <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Memphis</settlement>
                                    </placeName> this morning Wrote letters home and to Florence this morning and sent
                                    them back with the train.</p>
                        <p>A little later</p>
                        <p>Still here, have just been up to some prisoners our cavalry captured
                                    yesterday—the first I have seen—there are twenty-two or
                                    three—two Second Lieutenants among them They are about on an average in
                                    appearance with the same number picked at random from our army</p>
                        <p>Friday morning June 10th</p>
                        <p>Moved yesterday about Twelve, our regiment in the rear guarding the train. It was
                                    very nice with the exception of bringing us so late into Camp We got to camp about
                                    eight o'clock, took lodging in a thicket just as it commenced raining. The
                                    rain did not last long and I had a pretty good nights rest. We came eight or ten
                                    miles through the same kind of country we have been passing through for a day or so.
                                    Yesterday evening I passed a little fresh made mound marked "C Rhodes Co B
                                    3rd <placeName>
                                        <region type="state" reg="iau">Iowa</region>
                                    </placeName> Some fond heart will be o'ercast with gloom when the news goes
                                    home that an <placeName>
                                        <region type="state" reg="iau">Iowa</region>
                                    </placeName> soldier was shot by a bushwhacker in Miss while riding along with two
                                    companions. The report is abroad in Camp this morning that <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                                    </placeName> has fallen into our hands. It comes from rebels and as it admits
                                    reverse to their cause is entitled to some credit. I pray it may be so. For all that
                                    we have heard of the world for the last ten days we might about as well be out of it
                                    With the exception of this rumor we have heard no news at all since we left <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Memphis</settlement>
                                    </placeName>.</p>
                        <pb n="127" id="VAA4025-028-2-057"/>
                        <p>Saturday morning June 11th</p>
                        <p>Yesterday morning I was marching on with a proud army, confident in its strength this
                                    morning I am a prisoner and that same army flying in disgrace before the enemy. We
                                    marched about twelve miles yesterday and at about three in the afternoon came upon
                                    the enemy and had a sharp engagement in which we were repulsed A panic followed, our
                                    forces were thrown into the greatest confusion I escaped unhurt with a hole torn in
                                    my pants by a ball and one in my shirt by a like missle. Our Adjutant was shot in
                                    the early part of the action and died almost immediately. He was a noble and brave
                                    man. Lt Col Poole was dangerously wounded and carried from the field near the same
                                    time. I could have escaped with the column but chose to remain behind with Dickey,
                                    Dr. Sackett and Waits to try to get Col Poole off We were all captured together
                                    about six miles from battlefield We have all been detailed by the rebel authorities
                                    to take care of the wounded of which there are something over twenty at this place.</p>
                        <p>Sunday June 12th</p>
                        <p>Am still here. Adjutant and two of our men who died last night were buried to-day
                                    Experienced the kindest treatment from the rebels in charge of us.</p>
                        <p>Monday June 12th [13th]</p>
                        <p>This morning helped to consign another federal soldier to his last humble resting
                                    place This evening was brought to Brices roads the seat of the late battle and was
                                    detailed as nurse in a hospital of Federal-wounded.</p>
                        <p>Wednesday night June 14th</p>
                        <p>At the same old place and a horrid one too. Sixty men here suffering with wounds in
                                    almost every part of the body. Saw a leg and an arm taken off to-day Hospital
                                    visited to-day by several Southern ladies with such delicacies for our wounded as
                                    they could raise. God bless them for their kindness to our poor boys True woman is
                                    an angel everywhere. Cap McGrayel passed here a prisoner today I fear almost our
                                    whole command has been captured.</p>
                        <p>Thursday June 16th</p>
                        <p>Still at the battlefield in the Hospital. The wounded are being moved on to Guntown a
                                    place on the <placeName>
                                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                                    </placeName> &amp; Mobile R. R. from where they are being forwarded to Mobile
                                    Ala All of our wounded but about twelve were moved yesterday The few left and three
                                    nurses besides myself are here expecting to be moved today. The Dr tells me I will
                                    be retained as a nurse. The Surgeon in charge of the Hospital is Dr Mc—
                                    of the 3rd <placeName>
                                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Ky</region>
                                    </placeName>In a conversation yesterday with him he told me he was well acquainted
                                    with my friend Curran Dé Bruler, and roomed with Jim White while at
                                    Medical school in <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Louisville</settlement>
                                    </placeName> He says the <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                                    </placeName> Times is considered in the south as sound on the question of
                                    "Southern Rights" as any southern paper, better than the Mobile
                                    Register. Ladies still keep the Hospital bountifully <pb n="128" id="VAA4025-028-2-058"/> supplied with eatables I had quite a chat with one of
                                    your ardent but sensible ones on the "vexed questions" by the name
                                    of Mr. Tronklin. No proselytes were made by either though the time passed
                                    pleasantly. This morning while dressing the wounds of one of the 81st <placeName>
                                        <region type="state" reg="ilu">Ill</region>
                                    </placeName>the death struggle came on, and it became my melancholly duty to close
                                    the eyes of another Federal soldier</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </text>
                </p>
            <p>A letter of a comrade gives some details of the battle in which Robertson was taken prisoner.
                    Accompanying this letter was a note sent to the Federal camp by the prisoner. It was written on a
                    small scrap of paper, on the other side of which was the soldier's name and address of his
                    father, J. D. Robertson. The message read: "I am well and well treated but have not
                    opportunity to write. Don't be uneasy about me." The Mooney mentioned had been a
                    student at Indiana University, where he and Robertson became friends. While the letter was written
                    June 30, the writer evidently had no news of the transfer of the prisoners to Mobile as detailed in
                    the Journal on June 18.</p>
            <p>
                    <text>
                  <body>
                     <div type="letter">
                        <dateline>
                                    <address>
                              <addrLine>La Grange <placeName>
                                    <region type="state" reg="tnu">Tenn</region>
                                 </placeName>
                              </addrLine>
                           </address>
                                    <date>June 30 [1864]</date>
                                </dateline>
                        <salute>Mr. J. D. Robertson</salute>
                        <salute>Dr Sir</salute>
                        <p>I write to you in relation to Mell. C. Robertson. he was captured at the Battle of
                                    Brice's Cross Roads on the 10th. I suppose you have heard of the Battle ere
                                    this time our forces were defeated. Our Regt (the 93d) was most all captured and
                                    Mell was among the captured. Our Capt. McGrayel was captured Liut Mooney was
                                    wounded, but made his Escape About half of Co. E. was captured or killed. We heard
                                    from the boys that were captured by a flag of truce. they are at Maridean
                                    [Meridian], Miss. they are all well and treated well. Mell sent the little note
                                    which I enclose to the Co. and it was handed to me to write to you as I was one of
                                    his old mess mates. I think you need not be uneasy about him for he says he is well
                                    treated. the 93rd now numbers 160 men for Duty I don't know whether we will
                                    stay here long or not perhaps we will not. We are now guarding the R. R. The Rebs
                                    are reported to be at Corinth we have a large force this time we will make them
                                    skedadle this time sure</p>
                        <closer>
                                    <salute>Yours Respectfully</salute>
                                    <signed>H. D. Castetter<lb/> Co. E. 93rd Regt Ind.</signed>
                                </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </text>
                </p>
            <p>
                    <text>
                  <body>
                     <div type="diary">
                        <p>Mobile Sunday evening June 18th</p>
                        <p>On Thursday evening our wounded was moved to Guntown and the most of them put aboard
                                    of the cars and started to this place The next day I started as a nurse with the
                                    last lot of our wounded and arrived here this morning passing about forty hours on
                                    the cars. On arriving here the wounded were all carried to the wash house and <pb n="129" id="VAA4025-028-2-059"/> cleaned and arrayed in C S A shirts and drawers
                                    before being admitted to the house. I am glad to see them so pleasantly situated
                                    to-night But alas they are far from home. My heart sinks within me as I reflect on
                                    my own situation, how much worse is theirs. If I could only assure my
                                    friends' at home of my safety I would feel so much easier. The
                                    consciousness that they are in suspense in regard to my fate makes me uneasy. Oh!
                                    the trial.</p>
                        <p>Mobile Friday evening June 24, 64</p>
                        <p>In the city of Mobile, a Hospital nurse and a prisoner. One year ago I would have
                                    been somewhat startled if I had been assured that this would be my condition now.
                                    But stranger things have happened. Well, well, so wags the world, and I am meeting
                                    my fate with far more philosophy than I formerly imagined I could bring to my aid
                                    for such an occasion as this … While writing the preceeding, the death
                                    gasp of a fellow soldier called me away I closed his eyes, he lays in the dead house
                                    to-night, tomorrow the enemies of his country will lay him in a nameless grave God
                                    preserve me from such a burial. Let me die and be buried at home by friends no
                                    matter how humble they may be. Oh let affection's tear water the mound that
                                    rises over my lifeless breast.</p>
                        <p>General Hospital Mobile July 4, 1864</p>
                        <p>Last Friday we were all removed from the Hospital to which we were first sent to this
                                    one a distance of 24 of a mile Our party now numbers twenty nine. 23 wounded 2 Drs
                                    and 4 nurses The building we are now in was the old U S Marine Hospital It is a
                                    pleasant place. We have the benefit of a strong breeze from the bay nearly all the
                                    time during the day "The day we celebrate" is passing away in a
                                    manner rather dull to say the least of it. We amuse ourselves in recalling and
                                    recounting the manner in which we spent it in other years.</p>
                        <p>Marine Hospital Mobile July 18th</p>
                        <p>Two weeks have passed since the Fourth the date of my last entry. Patients and nurses
                                    are still here. Our Drs have been sent to <placeName>
                                        <country reg="gau">Georgia</country>
                                    </placeName> to attend to the sick among our prisoners there They left the 15th One
                                    was an old German Ass't Surgeon 2nd <placeName>
                                        <region type="state" reg="nju">N J</region>
                                    </placeName>Cavalry the other Dr Sackett Hospital Stewart of the 93rd, for 8 months
                                    acting Ass't Surg. I hated very much to see him leave He is a splendid boy.
                                    The most of our patients are fast recovering. In the course of two weeks I think the
                                    major part of them will have been sent to camp. Col Poole and some 5 or 6 others are
                                    likely to remain some time I think.</p>
                        <p>Sunday morning July 24, 1864.</p>
                        <p>Five weeks have passed since we arrived in Mobile, weeks that have not been so long
                                    and weary to me as I once imagined prison life would be. If it is supposed we spend
                                    all our time in repining over our hard fate the conjecture is slightly wrong. The
                                    majority of our patients are now able to be up most of the time and we are inclined
                                    to be the most sociable crowd imaginable. The confederacy is most shamefully
                                    ridiculed at times I make it my firm purpose and resolve <pb n="130" id="VAA4025-028-2-060"/> to live through my captivity and come out of the house
                                    of bondage as near new as possible. The weather is remarkably cool to-day indeed we
                                    have never suffered any great deal from heat since we have been here. We are
                                    expecting every day to be moved from here—at least those of us who are
                                    fit for Camp life Our room is beginning to be badly needed.</p>
                        <p>Monday August 8th</p>
                        <p>Last Sunday week July 31st 13 of our wounded were discharged from the Hospital and
                                    sent off to a prison camp in <placeName>
                                        <country reg="gau">Georgia</country>
                                    </placeName>. We suppose the other 3 nurses went with them I was left behind with
                                    ten men who are not yet able to leave among whom are Col Poole and two Caps of the
                                    95th <placeName>
                                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                                    </placeName> of our Brigade, Hanson &amp; Allis. t have been kept quite busy in
                                    attending on all these myself but there has been one great advantage attached and
                                    that is the increased rapidity with which time seems to pass. Last Friday the 5th
                                    our fleet with 3 monitors passed Fort Morgan at the bay of Mobile, with the loss of
                                    one monitor sunk A fight with the rebel fleet ensued resulting in the capture of two
                                    of the enemy's ships, and the breaching of an-ether. The same day the
                                    rebels blew up the works at Fort Powell, and abandoned it. An attack on the city is
                                    apprehended soon, in the meantime we are to be shipped to some point up the <placeName>
                                        <region type="state" reg="alu">Alabama</region>
                                    </placeName> out of reach of the "merciless invader" We expected
                                    to start yesterday but did not get off and are still here momentarily expecting
                                    orders to move.</p>
                        <p>On Board Ariel August 10th</p>
                        <p>Day before yesterday evening we embarked at Mobile for Selma. The "good
                                    Ariel" is a leaky and rickety old craft of tub-like proportions, in the
                                    service of the rebel government. There ar near a hundred prisoners on board all of
                                    whom except seven nurses are wounded Many of them are nearly well and will probably
                                    be sent at once to prison camps. Surgeon in charge talks of leaving some of the
                                    worst wounded at Cahaba 25 miles this side of Selma. Selma is 350 [?] miles from
                                    Mobile The <geogName>Alabama river</geogName> is decidedly the most crooked stream
                                    of any size I ever saw. The country through which we have passed so far is very
                                    rough and sparsely settled. I suppose we have come 250 [?] miles and have not seen a
                                    single town or village however small. We passed a landing at the base of a high hill
                                    at the top of which I was told there was a town. That is the only one I have heard
                                    of on the route.</p>
                        <p>Military Prison Cahaba Ala August 13th</p>
                        <p>Instead of going on to Selma our whole party stopped at this place, landing Thursday
                                    the 11th about noon. More than half was sent at once to prison—the rest
                                    to the Hospital here—which is said to be the best in the
                                    Confederacy—in my capacity of nurse I accompanied them and staid over
                                    night—my services not being required longer, I was yesterday morning with
                                    3 other nurses sent here.</p>
                        <p>Monday evening Aug 15, 1864</p>
                        <p>Prison is becoming an old familiar place already. This morning I washed my pants and
                                    mended them. This evening I washed myself <pb n="131" id="VAA4025-028-2-061"/> and
                                    with head carefully combed am arrayed in clean pants and shirt and am feeling as
                                    comfortable as could be expected under the circumstances Wrote letters to Father and
                                    Callie yesterday and sent them out to-day, the first I have attempted to send since
                                    my capture.</p>
                        <p>Friday evening Aug 19, '64</p>
                        <p>I write this evening because I have nothing else to do—not be-cause I have
                                    anything of importance to record. I have tried life in a good many ways but prison
                                    life is rather the most monotonous thing yet. But where there is so many together as
                                    there is here it can hardly be dull to most of those confined but to myself it
                                    sometimes becomes almost intolerable. There is so little of congeniality of spirit
                                    among those with whom I am associated that I often feel myself almost completely
                                    alone in the midst of 500 men. But when I feel a strong spirit of dissatisfaction
                                    creeping over me, I reflect how much worse my condition might be and soon woo a
                                    feeling of resignation to my fate; if I cannot be completely satisfied. As I cannot
                                    find kindred spirits here I assimilate myself as nearly as possible to those with
                                    whom I am thrown for the time being, in all except their viciousness. I am sensible
                                    that the best thing I can do is to make the best of my condition and I am trying to
                                    do it. I eat my corn-bread, smoke my pipe and look forward for something better.</p>
                        <p>Monday evening Aug 22nd</p>
                        <p>I have my seasons of light and shade here as I have had under more favorable
                                    circumstances. Yesterday evening we had a short sermon by a local preacher belonging
                                    to our regiment The singing and the voice of the prayer brought forcibly to my mind
                                    times agone, when the church bells sounded on my ears sabbath evening The shade fell
                                    on my spirit then and I wondered what old friends, with whom I used to visit the
                                    house of worship, were doing and thinking of. Whether a thought of me sometimes
                                    visited then or not Then came thoughts of home, followed by a flood of pleasant
                                    memories of old associations. I would become almost oblivious to all around me and
                                    then suddenly awake to a sence of my situation The contrast thus afforded depened
                                    the shade till sleep overtook me in melancholy musing. I woke this morning in a fine
                                    humor and have so occupied myself as to keep in it all day.</p>
                        <p>Thursday August 30th</p>
                        <p>Exceedingly [well] with myself and every body else except the confederacy. Had a
                                    splendid bit of watermelon to-day—have had the same thing several times
                                    since I have been in here. Would like to see Yankeedom before watermelons and
                                    peaches are gone. Strong talk of exchange for a week past. <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Providence</settlement>
                                    </placeName> speed it. Yestrday our number was increased to about 700 by 180 or 185
                                    more troubled "Yanks" brought out from <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Memphis</settlement>
                                    </placeName> by the everlasting Forrest in his late raid on that place.</p>
                        <p>Friday Sept 8th '64</p>
                        <p>When I made my last note I had a faint hope that ere this time I should be in our own
                                    line but I am still an inmate of Castle Morgan <pb n="132" id="VAA4025-028-2-062"/>
                                    The authorities still hold out the hope of exchange to us, but my faith in its
                                    taking place anyways soon is not very strong I however think there is still a
                                    possibility of it. We have been told all along that it was to an especial exchange
                                    we were to look for our liberation If that fails we must wait patiently as we may
                                    for a General Exchange. Our number has been swelled by occasional additions to 750
                                    We are getting rather too much crowded for health Ague is becoming quite common and
                                    as the Hospital is full a great many sick are left in here all the time. Medicine is
                                    also very scarce, and the Drs say, with what truth I cannot tell that it cannot be
                                    had. We learned a few days ago by the occupation of <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                                    </placeName> [not taken until Sept. 20th] by Sherman. This is a sad blow to the
                                    Confederates if we may believe them. Their papers have made a point of dilating in
                                    unmeasured terms of its importance (Disaffection and desertion of Guards)</p>
                        <p>Monday Sept 12th, 1864</p>
                        <p>The inmates of Castle Morgan began this week by numerous sundry effects of some half
                                    dozen of their number to demolish one another before breakfast this morning,
                                    consequence was 6 of them were tied up by thumbs for an hour or two. Talk of
                                    exchange yet, but our faith in it grows less every day. Youthful dreams of pleasure
                                    living in a castle dissipated by reality. Present willingness to dismiss my armed
                                    retainers and retire to private life. Could I but hear from home and know all were
                                    well and doing well I could be more content.</p>
                        <p>Monday Sep. 19th</p>
                        <p>A shade of gloom is cast over all this evening by the sudden death of one of our
                                    beloved prisoners. Shot by the guards for stopping a moment in the passage from the
                                    entrance to the yard His name was <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Huntington</settlement>
                                    </placeName> of the 19th Penn Cavalry. Much honor does it do the Confederacy. My
                                    hopes of anything like an immediate exchange have all vanquished</p>
                        <p>Wednesday Sep. 21st</p>
                        <p>Another man shot by same man—my own narrow escape—locality of
                                    the wound.</p>
                        <p>Thursday Sep. 22nd</p>
                        <p>Orders read by Adjutant this morning for 51 to be in readiness to leave for <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Memphis</settlement>
                                    </placeName> for exchange in the morning. Who go? Death of man shot yesterday.</p>
                        <p>Friday Sep. 23rd</p>
                        <p>Departure of men exchanged. Sent letters by them to Demp and Florence</p>
                        <p>Saturday Sep. 24th</p>
                        <p>Planting of cannon at door of prison Rumors of fall of Mobile.</p>
                        <p>Tuesday Oct 4th</p>
                        <p>Last night or rather this morning at half past lo'clock Hugh Roberts of the
                                    9th Minn died in the bunk I sleep in <pb n="133" id="VAA4025-028-2-063"/> Wednesday
                                    5th</p>
                        <p>This morning early a boat from Selma landed near the prison. More
                                    "Yanks" was the cry and we soon learned that 500 or 600 had come
                                    off the boat Night will find 14 of them in here.</p>
                        <p>Monday Oct 10th</p>
                        <p>Am not well to-day nor haven't been since Wednesday last—was
                                    taken with a slight fever of which I have not been entirely clear
                                    since—last night and night before was very cold lying on the plank
                                    without blankets. I thought the night interminable as I rolled around on the board
                                    both fever burnt and cold. Feel better to-day Are 1745 men in here
                                    now—very much crowded—rapidly becoming very unhealthy Still
                                    keep our spirits up with a hope of exchange this Autumn If not ex-changed this
                                    winter God have mercy on us.</p>
                        <p>Wednesday Oct 12th</p>
                        <p>Very sick yesterday, better to-day—30 went out for exchange yesterday. 150
                                    or over came in to-day will soon be full I should imagine.</p>
                        <p>Saturday Oct 15th</p>
                        <p>Very sick Thursday—better yesterday and convalescent today I think.
                                    Addition of about 150 to our number night before last. Over 2,000 in here now.</p>
                        <p>Wednesday Oct 26th</p>
                        <p>Since my last entry about 250 have gone out wheather for exchange or some other
                                    prison we do not know. My prospect of getting out of here soon looks gloomy. I
                                    don't like to give up that that I am to stay here all winter yet. Clothing
                                    sent through to us-not issued yet. Mortality becoming fearful—man died
                                    last night—3 three or four nights ago and one about a week ago under the
                                    bunk I sleep on. My own health as good as usual again with the exception of a bad
                                    cold which is getting better.</p>
                        <p>Tuesday November 8th '64</p>
                        <p>To-day I suppose is the great day of the year up North [Election day]
                                    —down here it is passing pretty much as the rest of them do,—8
                                    years and 4 years ago today The evening of Oct 26th 510 more came in making about
                                    2300. We began to amuse ourselves by conjecturing something of a layer to put on top
                                    of us. On the 29th however they took the 510 and 150 or 200 more out. Sent them to <placeName>
                                        <country reg="gau">Georgia</country>
                                    </placeName> we suppose Stockade has been enlarged in the last two or three weeks so
                                    that we are not so much crowded as we were Have been informed there is General
                                    Exchange going on Don't know whether to credit it or not Have been unwell
                                    for a week past,—have had bad cough with light chills. Took medicine for
                                    chills to-day.</p>
                        <p>December 3rd/ '64</p>
                        <p>Got out for clothing, got shoes, pants and blouse.</p>
                        <p>Prison Hospital December 31st/ '64</p>
                        <p>Came here on the 5th sick—confined to my room 19 days—am quite
                                    weak yet, but hope soon to be well. Gave us a turkey dinner <pb n="134" id="VAA4025-028-2-064"/> Christmas—thought of my turkey dinner last
                                    Christmas and sent gentle thoughts to the friends who were with me then. The last of
                                    '64—an eventful year—to me at least what will
                                    '65 bring forth? Yill I see home before it ends? Weather raw and cold.</p>
                        <p>Prison Hospital Jan 7th/ '65</p>
                        <p>Have about recovered my health—expect to be sent to prison soon On the 1st
                                    inst two men bayoneted one dangerously—on the 2nd another
                                    slightly—on the third a man shot, died next morning. More talk of
                                    exchange—hope there may be something in it.</p>
                        <p>Castle Morgan Jan 20th 1865</p>
                        <p>Left the Hospital on the 12th and was remanded to Prison—found it very
                                    much crowded—400 men who had been in confinement at Meridean had come in
                                    while I was gone—raising the number in here to 2300 I have regained my
                                    health—have been gaining flesh fast. Last night at 1 o'clock I
                                    awoke and learned that there was to be an attempt made to break
                                    prison—time set for half past three. I put on my pants and lay down and
                                    fell asleep. I awoke at half past three and found all quiet,—and
                                    all's well—had hardly passed the guards before all inside the
                                    prison were seized—"fizzle"—after
                                    proceedings.</p>
                        <p>Feb 1st 1865</p>
                        <p>Pleasant weather with prospect of rain. Have had for a few days past quite severe
                                    winter for this latitude Have plenty of blankets to keep warm of nights Talk among
                                    rebs of peace—all would be glad to have it on condition of returning to
                                    allegiance Seem quite aimable since our little rumpus the other night</p>
                        <p>February 23rd 1865</p>
                        <p>A rainy day—warm—no cold weather for some time
                                    past—expect the winter of this climate is about over Some strong talk of
                                    exchange lately I think probably there is some foundation for it Since my last entry
                                    I have made the acquaintance of rheumatism,—was pretty bad off for a few
                                    days, but am now about well. One year ago today I enlisted—81/2 months of
                                    that time I have been a prisoner. On the 7th I received two letters—one
                                    from Demp and the other from Fos &amp; George. The only news I have had from
                                    home since my capture.</p>
                        <p>March 4th 1865</p>
                        <p>To-day will be remembered in the history of the nation as the day of the Second
                                    inauguration of "Old Abe" and in my history as one of the days of
                                    the great flood in castle Morgan. The heavy rains of the past two weeks brought the
                                    water up so that it came into the prison on the 1st—the evening of the
                                    2nd found all over the outer prison and most of the cook yard.—Yesterday
                                    morning (3rd) it was running into the inner prison and before night was over all the
                                    ground inside the stockade. Night before last I suppose there was a thousand men in
                                    the prison who passed the night on their feet half leg deep in water. Hundreds of
                                    rats were driven from their holes and were drowned or killed. They had been working
                                    all over the prison and when the <pb n="135" id="VAA4025-028-2-065"/> water came in
                                    the frames on which the bunks are constructed, settled down and men were up all
                                    night propping them to prevent their falling The one I sleep on fortunately settled
                                    nearly level so that although we slept but little we were not obliged to get down
                                    into the water to work at it. Last night the bunks were all firm and I had a
                                    splendid night's rest All day yesterday the men who have been sleeping on
                                    the ground were busy fixing up small scaffolds of wood' and boards in the
                                    water on which they could make [beds] out of the water Late in the evening a few
                                    hundred were taken out and more have gone this morning The rebs tell us it is for
                                    exchange</p>
                        <p>March 5th The water has begun to fall slowly-more men taken out to-day.</p>
                        <p>Monday March 6th</p>
                        <p>Water still falling—all prisoners taken out this morning but 526. We will
                                    probably go to-morrow, the rebs say on the first boat The boat load that left this
                                    morning went down the river report say [s] it goes to the mouth of the Tombigbee and
                                    from there to Demopolis Those prisoners who left before went up to Selma</p>
                        <p>Castle Morgan Monday March 13th</p>
                        <p>The water out of the prison. I suppose the long talked of ex-change is a fixed fact
                                    at last On Saturday &amp; yesterday were all taken out and signed the parole.
                                    This morning all the skillets were taken out and our blankets taken away from us. We
                                    are now waiting orders to start It is uncertain whether we will go today or not.</p>
                        <p>Selma March 14th</p>
                        <p>Yesterday evening about 4 o'clock we went aboard the St Charles at Cahaba
                                    and without any regret I soon saw the walls of castle Morgan fading from view in the
                                    distance I had been there a prisoner within them seven months and one day In that
                                    time I was outside of the Stockade but 4 times till I went out to sign the parole on
                                    Saturday We got to Selma about 7 or 8 o'clock and was marched out to the
                                    Stockade about 3/4 of a mile from the town This morning were marched to the depot in
                                    the rain and stood there an hour or two then came back. Selma is a nice place</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </text>
                </p>
            <p>During the summer of 1864 and the winter following, the family in Indiana heard nothing directly from
                    Private Robertson. Occasionally a brief letter came from some Union soldier or officer in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName> relative to a prospective exchange of prisoners. One of these was from a paroled
                    prisoner, who believed that Comrade Robertson would also be among those at liberty in a short time.
                    He reported that his friend was "in the very best of good health." This was
                    written October 1, 1864. Robertson was not paroled until the ensuing spring. It was almost a year
                    after his capture that he wrote the following letter.</p>
            <pb n="136" id="VAA4025-028-2-066"/>
            <p>
                    <text>
                  <body>
                     <div type="letter">
                        <dateline>
                                    <address>
                              <addrLine>Parole Camp, Near Vicksburgh Miss.</addrLine>
                           </address>
                                    <date>Wednesday, March 22nd, 1865</date>
                                </dateline>
                        <salute>Dear Bro. Demp.</salute>
                        <p>I have the supreme satisfaction this morning of writing you a letter that will not
                                    have to be subjected to the curious eyes of rebels ere it is permitted to go to you.
                                    I bade farewell to Castle Morgan, Cahaba, and Confederate corn bread last Monday
                                    week and reached this place four miles back from the city yesterday evening. Now
                                    there is a great deal I could tell you and a great deal I would of perils by land
                                    and water, among thieves, false brethren and confederates if I could do it orally
                                    instead of by letter. I will therefore let all these things pass for the present and
                                    content myself [with] a tale short unvarnished and simple. First then, I have reed
                                    one letter only from you and one from Fos. since my capture. They were dated Oct.
                                    30" and reached me the 7" of February. They were promptly
                                    answered. Now the first thing you do after reading if you consult my pleasure will
                                    be to answer this at considerable length giving me all the items of news that will
                                    interest or that concerns me—I am in fine health, weigh 175 or 180 lbs.
                                    but am in rather poor trim for walking having bruised my feet considerably by a
                                    march of about twenty five miles day before yesterday, the most of it in a heavy
                                    rain. We are meeting with the kindest treatment now and will soon recover from all
                                    the effects of our trip. The citizens of Vicksburgh by contributions and the
                                    Christian commission by its agents are attending to our immediate wants, furnishing
                                    us combs, spoons, tobacco, ppies, &amp;. The change from confederate
                                    "grub" to Federal rations is as you may suppose rather comferting
                                    to the physical man. Our men met us with rations night before last and I drank more
                                    real genuine simon pure coffe than I had in eight months before.</p>
                        <p>When we will leave here is uncertain. We are paroled and I understand are to remain
                                    here until rebel prisoners are delivered for us. That may be next week, next month
                                    or possibly three or four months It seems to be the general opinion that we will
                                    have an opportunity afforded us of going home on furlough after we are exchanged.
                                    This is however by no means certain. My regiment I expect is now at Pensacola or
                                    Mobile. It passed down the river twelve days ago.</p>
                        <p>Give my compliments to all my friends and tell them that for a time at least, I have
                                    abandoned my old occupation of looking through windows protected from the weather by
                                    iron bars. Tell them all to write. I will write to them as I get paper and envelopes
                                    which are furnished us by the Christian Commission. My love to Father and Mother.
                                    Direct to Co. &amp; Regt. Parole Camp, Vicksburgh</p>
                        <closer>
                                    <salute>Your Bro.</salute>
                                    <signed>Mell</signed>
                                </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </text>
                </p>
            <p>While on the way to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">St. Louis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, as mentioned in the <hi rend="i">Foreword</hi>, this soldier, who survived many months
                    of prison life but who contracted typhoid fever in the Parole Camp at Vicksburg, wrote another
                    letter home on April 20. Two <pb n="137" id="VAA4025-028-2-067"/> days later, April 22, 1865, he
                    died in the hospital at Jefferson Barracks, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">St. Louis</settlement>
                    </placeName>.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="138" id="VAA4025-028-2-068"/>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-028-2-a07">
            <head>Reviews and Notices</head>
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">A Child's Life of George <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                        </placeName>.</hi> By Louise Embree. Illustrations by Clotilda Embree. E. P. Dutton and Company, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                    </placeName>, 1932. Pp. 255, $2.50.</head>
            <p>Louise Embree of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Princeton</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indiana, has made the life of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> intelligible and interesting to children of school age, even those in the lowest
                    grades. It is a very attractive addition to Indiana's contribution to the George <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> Bicentennial. It may seem at times that Miss Embree "talks down" over
                    much to youthful readers. However, the proof of the pudding is in the eating and the book has
                    already proved its popularity with those for whom it was intended. An account of this sort could not
                    be expected to make new contributions to historical knowledge nor to take a critical attitude toward
                    its subject. Miss Embree, however, has made a very comprehensive and well proportioned story of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName>'s crowded life and diverse activities. There is a short bibliography. Numerous
                    allusions show that the writer has kept up to date about information on <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Her mention of "Wakefield," the birthplace of George <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName>, and other references, would enable well informed readers to date the book, even if the
                    year of publication were omitted.</p>
            <p>A word should be said about the silhouette illustrations by Clotilde Embree (Mrs. Claude Douglass
                    Funk) of <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Princeton</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York City</region>
               </placeName>, and now of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, varying from little insertions to full-page illustrations. They add greatly to the
                    pleasure of the reader with their spirited presentation of eighteenth century citizens. It is
                    surprising how much dramatic interest is contained in some of the black and white sketches, how much
                    pathos has been put into some, and how much cheerfulness and liveliness into others.</p>
            <p>It is to be hoped that many children throughout the country will add to their participation in the
                    Bicenennial activities the reading of this life of the "Father of his Country."
                    They will come from it with a fine appreciation of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName>'s character and services.</p>
            <byline>Christopher B. Coleman</byline>
         </div>
         <pb n="139" id="VAA4025-028-2-069"/>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-028-2-a08">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">George <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                        </placeName>, Patron of Learning.</hi> By Leonard C. Helderman. The Century Company, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                    </placeName>, 1932. Pp. xv + 187, illustrated, $2.50.</head>
            <p>This modest volume is, in the language of the author, "an effort to survey a side of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName>'s career not generally recognized and likely to be overlooked." There
                    is no contention that the leader of the armies during the War of Independence and first President of
                    the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> "was a scholar or even an educator in the fullest sense of the term."
                    Nevertheless, one lays down the book with the feeling that the great Virginian was much interested
                    in education and that his work in promoting the cause was quite important.</p>
            <p>This monograph of Dr. Helderman, who is an associate professor of history at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> and Lee University, contains, besides a history of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName>'s part in the founding of that institution, two chapters (I and II) relative
                    to the project of a National University at the federal capital. The plan to found such a center of
                    learning was one in which <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> was vitally interested. The second of the chapters devoted to this plan is
                    significantly called "The History of an Idea." More than a century rolled by in
                    which period none of the efforts to carry out <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName>'s idea came to fruition. The conclusion of the author is that, "The
                    project … Ianguishes to this day and fails to arouse enthuiasm among educators."
                    In regard to the universities found in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> at the present time, the author writes: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Upon the tapering down of the national university project, certain institutions have been
                            established in the capital city which have aspired to be the heirs of <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                            </placeName>'s idea of a full university. None of these, of course, possess any
                            genetic connection with Geore <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                            </placeName>. The most that is suggested is that by location at the capital, by emphasizing
                            government and diplomacy, and by attracting students from a wide area, they have attempted
                            to set their faces in the direction of his purpose.</p>
                    </quote>
            </p>
            <p>
               <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> was interested in several schools, including the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> Military Academy, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> College at Chestertown, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mdu">Maryland</region>
                    </placeName>, and the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Alexandria</settlement>
                    </placeName> Academy. He was the real founder of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> and Lee University which started as Liberty Hall Academy, later became <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> College, and finally was given its present name. The gift which the "Father of
                    his Country" made to this institution <pb n="140" id="VAA4025-028-2-070"/> constitutes his
                    "largest investment … for the promotion of learning in the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>," and it is the only one that lives.</p>
            <p>The volume will be appreciated by all who are anxious to know more of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName>. It is well and carefully written. The narrative is easy to follow and the book will
                    furnish both useful information and enjoyment to anyone who chooses to read it. In his <hi rend="i">Preface</hi>, the writer says: "From this study the author rises with the profound
                    conviction that George <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> was more than a solemn mediocrity without intellectual interests or
                    influence." With this conclusion readers are quite sure to agree.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-028-2-a11">
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Human Sterilization</hi> is the title of a fascinating, scholarly volume by Dr. J. H.
                    Landman of the faculty of the College of the City of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                    </placeName>. The book seems to present a thorough and unbiased treatment of the many phases of the
                    subject. Among the many valuable characters are the following: "The Eugenics
                    Movement"; "The History of Human Sterilization in the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>"; "The Nature of Our Socially Inadequate People";
                    "Human Sterilization Operations"; "The Ethics of Human
                    Sterilization"; "Whom Shall We Sterilize"; and "Problems in the
                    Administration of the Human Sterilization Laws." The volume contains nearly three hundred
                    pages of reading matter in addition to appendices, bibliography and index. The format of the book is
                    excellent. It is published by The Macmillan Company at a price of $4.00 per copy.</p>
            <p>Many students are now engaged in investigations of various phases of church history in the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>. Such students are especially interested in the publication of local church records or
                    histories of local churches. Some years ago (1882), J. C. Tibbetts prepared a <hi rend="i">History
                        of the Coffee Creek Baptist Association</hi> of southern Indiana. Recently a committee, of which
                    Elijah A. Gladden was made chairman, revised this history and brought it down to 1930. The pamphlet
                    has been extended to one hundred ninety-one pages. It includes an account of each of the present,
                    churches in the Association together with biographical sketches of ministers. Several photographs
                    are reproduced and lists of members presented, <pb n="141" id="VAA4025-028-2-071"/> while some
                    documents are included, such as the "Constitution" of the Association. The
                    pamphlet, which may be obtained from Elijah A. Gladden of Scottsburg, Indiana, is valuable for
                    several reasons. The publication of such histories ought to be encouraged.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">The <geogName>Mississippi valley</geogName> Historical Review</hi> was founded by the
                        <geogName>Mississippi valley</geogName> Historical Association in 1914. The first number of the
                    quarterly appeared in June of that year. The fifteenth volume was completed with the March issue of
                    1929. At the annual meeting of that year, which was held in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName>, the Executive Committee of the Association authorized the preparation and publication
                    of a general index covering the issues of the <hi rend="i">Review</hi> to that date. Miss Louise Rau
                    of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Detroit</settlement>
                    </placeName> Public Library was selected to prepare the <hi rend="i">Index.</hi> Her work has been
                    well done. The result is a handy paper-bound volume of one hundred twenty-seven pages, corresponding
                    in its make-up to an issue of the <hi rend="i">Review.</hi> One regrets that the contents of the
                    several volumes of the <hi rend="i">Proceedings</hi> of the Association, which were published some
                    years ago, could not have been indexed with the contents of the <hi rend="i">Review.</hi> If not
                    possible to prepare a combined index, it would seem that a supplementary index might have been
                    added. The Torch Press of Cedar Rapids which regularly publishes the <hi rend="i">Review</hi>,
                    brought out the <hi rend="i">Index</hi> which may be purchased of Mrs. Clarence S. Paine, secretary
                    of the Association, Lincoln, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="nbu">Nebraska</region>
                    </placeName>, for $5.00.</p>
            <p>The Indiana State Teachers College of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Terre Haute</settlement>
                    </placeName> is preparing to publish within a few months a volume of historical papers which will be
                    dedicated to the late Professor Frank Smith Bogardus. The papers are being prepared and submitted by
                    former students of Prof. Bogardus, who are now engaged in teaching history. Dr. Fred E. Brengle,
                    associate professor of history at the Teachers College, is acting as editor of the volume.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="142" id="VAA4025-028-2-072"/>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-028-2-a09">
            <head>Comment</head>
            <p>In the good old days, unless, as the debunkers would have it, there were no such times, editorials
                    were widely read. Not only that but they were really worthy of attention. This was because most
                    editorial chairs were filled with men of vigor who were known to the public. In recent times,
                    editorials in daily newspapers are read by few. Even when frank and fearless, as is still sometimes
                    true, readers generally can not associate them with any known man. They lack the flavor given in
                    times past by an outstanding personality, and carry little weight as a rule.</p>
            <p>A number of weekly magazines together with a few monthlies furnish readers with editorials that are
                    clear and thought-provoking. They are also read with interest by certain classes in the population,
                    but ignored by a vast portion of the business men of the nation, many of whom take great pride in
                    the fact that they have absolutely nothing to do with magazines that in any degree challenge the
                    accepted notions and shibboleths of the time. This is a bad situation—a very real menace
                    to the future of America.</p>
            <p>Periodicals that are published quarterly are not expected to comment on current problems. A curve
                    showing the number of readers of editorials in daily, weekly, monthly and quarterly publications
                    would come dangerously near the zero line for such periodicals as appear only four times in a year.
                    After having encumbered the pages of a few issues of the <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of
                    History</hi> with a certain amount of editorial matter, the <hi rend="i">Editor</hi> was about to
                    deny himself the privilege of thus expressing his views when he ran into a subscriber who declared
                    that he always turned first to the pages of <hi rend="i">Comment.</hi> In the course of the last
                    year or two, by keeping an ear close to the ground, the discovery has been made that five others
                    likewise read the editorials. To these faithful and intelligent half dozen readers, greetings! To
                    them these pages are dedicated.</p>
            <p>Down with taxes! Down with public expenditures! These are the universal and natural demands of a
                    hard-pressed people. <pb n="143" id="VAA4025-028-2-073"/> There, is, however, great danger in;
                    indiscriminate slashing. Taking advantage of the popular mood, elements that desire to carry on
                    various economic activities without restraint or regulation, regardless of the general welfare, may
                    do much harm. Many things necessary to the health and well-being of society under the complex
                    conditions of today can only be accomplished through public agencies. Other essential processes that
                    could be left to individuals or families can be carried on more cheaply and more effectiently by
                    servants of the whole community who are paid out of taxes. It is easy indeed 'to make
                    serious blunders and take backward steps in a period of depression like the present.</p>
            <p>Several forms of tangible property are taxed excessively, in reference to values, and also out of
                    proportion relative to various forms of intangible wealth. After a careful study, these evils should
                    be fearlessly remedied. At the same time, it should be remembered that while governments, local,
                    state and national, are taking much in taxes, many other charges that must be regularly paid are
                    excessive and disproportionate. Why should telephone service cost as much as when all prices were at
                    the peak? Why should a public utility company be allowed to collect from any consumer a
                    $3.00 per month service charge for which no electric current is furnished? Why should a
                    number of organizations that few business or professional men can refuse to support continue to
                    collect annual dues which were doubled during the period of high prices? These and many other
                    questions are just as legitimate and natural under present conditions as any that are raised in
                    connection with taxes and public expenditures.</p>
            <p>A wise retail merchant knows that he can not sell goods at former prices. The judicious merchant will
                    not therefore stock up very heavily with merchandise which is not quoted at considerably reduced
                    figures by manufacturers or wholesale dealers. He can benefit both himself and his customers by an
                    independent study of the conditions that confront the companies from whom he purchases his stocks.
                    Not all merchants have learned this important lesson. Retail prices have very generally declined
                    somewhat in harmony with the buying power of consumers. On the other hand, many necessary
                    commodities <pb n="144" id="VAA4025-028-2-074"/> for which there is a demand are purchased by retail
                    merchants at unchanged prices. In certain instances, there is no help for this, but in a multitude
                    of cases retail merchants can perform a real service for those whom they serve by re-minding
                    wholesale houses or manufacturers that war prices no longer prevail. By doing this often enough and
                    firmly enough, they can aid their communities about as much as if they join the hue and cry for
                    lower taxes or the demand for indiscriminate slashes in public expenditures.</p>
            <p>An opportunity to view Congress in action at close range during recent months, while a wide-spread
                    and all too successful effort was being made by various interests to bring the national legislative
                    body into disrepute, leads to the making of certain assertions in the interest of truth and justice.
                    There are very able and very honest men in Congress among each of the four
                    groups—progressive Republicans, progressive Democrats, conservative Republicans, and
                    conservative Democrats. There are perhaps a few cheap men in each group. During the present session,
                    the two houses have been confronted with unusually grave problems and impossible tasks have been
                    demanded of them by powerful elements in the nation. Measures have been urged with tremendous force
                    that were unwise, while wise proposals have been resisted with equal force. In spite of great
                    pressure to compel them to support or to oppose certain policies, many Senators and Representatives
                    have acted with a courage that has not been equaled in the whole history of Congress. Any citizen
                    who has been led to place an unusually low estimate on the American Congress in recent months, who
                    will make an unbiased survey of the actual facts, will be certain to revise his judgment.</p>
            <p>Contributors to this issue: H. S. K. Bartholomew, a retired editor, is a dairy farmer and
                    fruit-grower who lives at his country home, Edgewood, near <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Goshen</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indiana (R.F.D., 3); Miss Julia LeClerc <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Knox</region>
                    </placeName> is a teacher of Latin in the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Crawfordsville</settlement>
                    </placeName> High School who has a deep interest in the old homes and old families of the older
                        <geogName>Ohio River</geogName> towns of Indiana; Denzil Doggett is a state engineer in the
                    service of the Department of Conservation of Indiana; George S. Cottman is a retired printer who
                    lives near <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indiana (R.F.D., 5). He <pb n="145" id="VAA4025-028-2-075"/> lived for a long period
                    in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Irvington</settlement>
                    </placeName> and was the first editor of the Indiana Magazine of History; the Journal of Melville
                    Cox Robertson and a few of his letters were kindly loaned to the Magazine by Miss Eleanor M.
                    Robertson of <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Urbana</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="ilu">Illinois</region>
               </placeName>. Miss Robertson is a niece of the soldier whose experiences
                    are recorded in the Journal.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="[146]" id="VAA4025-028-2-076"/>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-028-2-a10">
            <head>Reprints</head>
            <p>Reprints of any paper published in the <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of History</hi> may be obtained
                    by any contributor. Estimates of the cost will be furnished on request and an order placed for as
                    many reprints of any article as may be desired by the author. Requests should be made to the <hi rend="i">Editor</hi> before the issue containing the article of which reprints are desired is
                    published.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-028-2-a12">
            <head>Wanted</head>
            <p>We are sure that some of our readers can aid us to obtain the desired publications listed below. The
                    Library of Indiana University and other libraries in different parts of the country are in need of
                    copies of the issues mentioned in order to complete files. For older and rarer numbers, prices above
                    the regular rates will be paid. Persons possessing any of the de-sired publications, will confer a
                    great favor by writing to the <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of History.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of History.</hi> We have a serious need for copies of issues from 1905
                    to 1913—especially for: the four numbers of volume IV (1908); number one of volume VI
                    (1910); the four numbers of volume VII (1911); the four numbers of volume VIII (1912). We will buy
                    also further copies of the following issues: Mar., 1914; Dec., 1921; Mar., 1922; Sept., 1922; Dec.,
                    1922; June, 1923; and Mar., 1926.</p>
            <p>Full sets of the <hi rend="i">Magazine</hi> can rarely be supplied to libraries or individuals who
                    may desire to purchase. A complete file from 1920 forward can be supplied at fifty-cents a copy, or
                    two dollars per volume, unbound; from 1914 to 1919, the price is one dollar per copy, or four
                    dollars per volume, except in the case of certain numbers which have become very scarce the price is
                    one dollar and a half per copy, causing the price per volume to vary accordingly; single copies from
                    1905-1913, when they can be supplied at all, must be priced at a higher figure.</p>
            <pb n="147" id="VAA4025-028-2-077"/>
            <p>Mr. George S. Cottman, the first editor of the <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of History</hi>, who now
                    resides at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indiana, R. R. 5, has a complete file of the <hi rend="i">Magazine</hi> which he is
                    willing to sell to any library for $200. The first three volumes are bound, but the
                    remaining volumes are unbound. The opportunity to purchase an unbroken file from the beginning is
                    unusual. Anyone desiring to purchase should write to Mr. Cottman, or to the <hi rend="i">Indiana
                        Magazine of History.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Indiana School Journal.</hi> Wanted vol. 37, numbers, 7-8 (1892); vol. 38, numbers 6, 9,
                    10, 11, 12 (1893); vol. 40, numbers 4, 9, 10, 11 (1895).</p>
            <p>National Educational Association <hi rend="i">Proceedings.</hi> Wanted for 1860, 1864, 1872, 1884,
                    and 1885.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">The Indianian.</hi> This magazine was published at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> from 1897 to 1900, six volumes in all. Wanted: Vol. I, number 1 (Dec. 1897), number 2
                    (Jan. 1898), numbers 4 and 5 (March and April, 1898); vol II—number 1 (June, 1898); vol.
                    VI—number 1 (July, 1900), number 3 (Sept., 1900), number 6 (Dec., 1900). Will purchase an
                    extra set of the six numbers of vol. I, bound or unbound.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Indiana, Past and Present.</hi> This little, temporary periodical was published during
                    1914. Wanted a copy of Number 2 (May, 1914).</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">The Mennonite Quarterly Review.</hi> Wanted a copy of vol. I, number 1.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <pb n="[148]" id="VAA4025-028-2-078"/>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI.2>