<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "imh_issue.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="VAA4025-004-3">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Indiana Magazine of History</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoded by</resp>
               <name>Aptara Inc.</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <date>2007</date>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>Copyright 2007 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
               <p>Indiana University provides the information contained in this file for non-commercial,
        personal, or research use only. All other use, including but not limited to commercial or
        scholarly reproductions, redistribution, publication or transmission, whether by electronic
        means or otherwise, without prior written permission of the copyright holder is strictly
        prohibited.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Indiana Magazine of History</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title>Indiana Magazine of History</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Indianapolis, IN</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Published Under the Direction of The Indiana Histoical
                                Society</publisher>
                     <date>1908</date>
                     <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="pages">103-152</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06-19</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Annette D. Richmond</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Changed publication place and publisher, remvoed incorrect blockquotes, marked-up letters</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="[103]" id="VAA4025-004-3-001"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-004-3-a01">
            <head>AUSTIN SEWARD.</head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Read before the <placeName>
                            <region type="county">Monroe County</region>
                        </placeName> Historical Society by H. C. Duncan, March 27, 1908</hi>.</p>
            <p>IN the Dunn burying-ground in the college [Indiana University] campus is a
                        monument<hi rend="sup">*</hi> giving the date of the birth and
                    death of three sisters who sleep within its enclosure. Eleanor Dunn, born in
                    1754, Jennett Irvin, born in 1761 and Agnes Alexander, born in 1763. Their
                    maiden name was Brewster. They were Scotch Presbyterians, were of the landed <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> aristocracy, strong patriots, and their father was at the battle of
                    the Cowpens and with General Greene's army in the South. They came to <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> in the great Presbyterian hegira about 1783. They were experts in
                    the manufacture of woolen cloth, and during the war their loom was always filled
                    with cloth for the army, and, when it was near enough, they helped to supply the
                    soldiers with food. They all died in this county, widows; the husbands of two
                    died in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName>. From these three women descended the Dunns, Alexanders, Sewards
                    and Maxwells of this county.</p>
            <p>Jennett Brewster Irvin was the widow of Samuel Irvin, a Revolutionary soldier and
                    of the War of 1812, who died and was buried at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Corydon</settlement>
                    </placeName>. The story is told that while Irvin was in the war, she was courted
                    by a Mr. Campbell, who asked her hand in marriage but was refused for her
                    soldier lover. After her marriage they all came West, the Campbells settling in
                    the neighborhood of <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Lexington</settlement>,
                            <region type="state" reg="kyu">Ky.</region>
               </placeName>, probably in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Bourbon county</region>
                    </placeName>, and the Irvins in <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>, <region type="county">Madison
                    county</region>
               </placeName>. Some of the Campbells moved to this county and were
                    visited by this relative, who here again met his old <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> sweetheart. But it is only with the Irvin part of the Brewster
                    family this paper deals.</p>
            <list type="footnotes">
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">*</hi> This monument gives also the dedication
                        of the burying-ground by George G. Dunn. It was erected by Austin Seward,
                        about 1856.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="104" id="VAA4025-004-3-002"/>
            <p>Jane Irvin was the wife of Austin Seward. The Sewards were good people. In early
                    times they came from <placeName>
                        <country reg="enk">England</country>
                    </placeName> and settled in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Surry county</region>
                    </placeName>, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName>, but subsequently the ancestors of Austin moved to <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Middlesex county</region>
                    </placeName> on the south banks of the Rappahannock, in the heart of the landed
                    aristocracy. They were Episcopalians and patriots. Austin Seward's
                    father was John, and his mother Mary Daniel. It is thought she was a relative of
                    the celebrated Daniel family of that State, of whom Senator Daniel is a
                    distinguished member. His grandfather's name was Austin, for whom he
                    was named, and his grandmother Almira Mason, a member of the distinguished Mason
                    family. His oldest child, a daughter, was named Mary for his mother, and his
                    second daughter, Almira, for his grandmother; his oldest son, John, for his
                    father, and his son who died in infancy, Austin, for his grandfather.</p>
            <p>John Seward, senior, had two children, Austin, who was born November 22, 1799,
                    and a sister Almira, who was about two years his junior. When they were children
                    his wife died and he remarried, and the stepmother mistreated the children in a
                    way that "only exists in the story books," as a granddaughter
                    expressed it. On account of her cruel and inhuman treatment, when the stepmother
                    was away an aunt—Aunt Sheppard—the mother's
                    sister, carried Almira away and she lived with this aunt and did not join her
                    brother Austin until just prior to the Civil war, when she came to Indiana and
                    made it her home until her death in 1867. It is a tradition in the family told
                    by both Austin and his sister, that the stepmother's cruelty went to
                    the extent of failing to give them enough to eat, both testifying that an old
                    colored "mammy" from her own allowance of corn meal, and the
                    oysters gathered by them from the tide water of the Rappahannock, cooked and fed
                    them in her cabin. They both always insisted these were the best oysters they
                    ever ate.</p>
            <p>When Austin was about ten years old the family moved to a farm near
                            <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="kyu">Ky.</region>
               </placeName> His father lived there
                    about two years. The date of his death is not known. He was thought to be a man
                    of very considerable means, at least his dress and manner of living, as
                    remembered by his son Austin, would so indicate, but nothing whatever was
                    realized from his estate by his <pb n="105" id="VAA4025-004-3-003"/> children.
                    The home being broken up, Austin was apprenticed to learn blacksmithing. While
                    learning the trade, shoeing a vicious horse, he was injured, causing a lameness
                    from which he never recovered. He then learned edge-tool making with Anderson
                    Wood, a noted toolmaker of <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="kyu">Ky.</region>
               </placeName>, for whom he worked about two years.</p>
            <p>On May 18, 1817, near <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>,
                            <region type="state" reg="kyu">Ky.</region>
               </placeName>, he was married
                    to Jane Irvin, a daughter of Samuel Irvin and of Jennett Brewster Irvin, one of
                    the colonial dames buried in the Dunn burying-ground. Samuel Irvin operated a
                    tanyard about three miles from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName>, was a prosperous, well-to-do citizen, lived in a large frame house
                    and gave his daughters the best that <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> at that time afforded. They were fairly well educated, were skilled
                    in all kinds of domestic and culinary labors, moved in the best society, and
                    were well prepared to adorn a home and grace a cabin or a mansion.</p>
            <p>Austin set up a shop at Hay's Ford on Silver creek about seven miles
                    from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName>, worked at the trade for about a year, then moved to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName> and went to work in the shop of Argo &amp; <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Caldwell</settlement>
                    </placeName> as an edge-tool maker. His skill and reputation combined, enabled
                    him to command the highest wages as a journeyman. The descendants of the other
                    two colonial dames had moved to Indiana and had settled in and about
                    Blooming-ton. There Mr. Seward paid them a visit in 1821. He learned the
                    position they occupied in the new community, the influence they exerted, judged
                    of the possible assistance they might render in a new country, and concluded to
                    cast his lot with his kinsmen in the New Purchase. He arrived at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Bloomington</settlement>
                    </placeName> with his wife and two eldest children in September, 1821, moved
                    into a vacant cabin on what is now the Oursler lots, which they occupied
                    temporarily and soon moved into a pretentious building consisting of a double
                    cabin, a loft and a lean-to, situated on the lot now occupied by the Batman
                    building on the southwest corner of Seventh and Walnut streets. He immediately
                    built a log shop on the same lot, in which he began his labor of supplying the
                    wants of the community. The log shop was used until a new one was built on the
                    east side of Walnut street in 1825. This was a one-story brick building of four
                    rooms and is still standing, <pb n="106" id="VAA4025-004-3-004"/> although with
                    an added second story; one room was the gunsmith shop; one was used for storing
                    material and for operating the lathe; one for grindstone and emery wheels and in
                    the fourth was the blacksmith shop with three forges. It is thought this was the
                    third brick house erected in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Bloomington</settlement>
                    </placeName>, preceded only by the old brick near Karsell's mill and
                    the Maxwell, afterwards the Lucas House, burned some twenty years ago, situate
                    just north of the alley on the west side of College avenue, between Sixth and
                    Seventh streets. The brick was made and burned in Walnut street in front of Mrs.
                    W. O. Fee's residence wood cut on the neighboring lots supplying the
                    fuel. There was a wooden structure built on the east side in which there was a
                    horse-power for operating the lathe, grindstones and emery wheels that were used
                    for polishing axes, scythes and other implements as required. As business kept
                    on increasing, demands were made for more room, greater and larger facilities,
                    and these an honest effort was always made to supply. Up to 1842 or 1843, Mr.
                    Seward had only made forged articles such as were first heated and then formed
                    on the anvil, but in a new country the plow proposition was always up. About
                    that time a new plow called the "Peacock," from the name of
                    the inventor, came on the market. I remember them very well. It had a steel
                    share, wrought bar and cast mould board. In that day it was <hi rend="i">the</hi> plow, somewhat after the fashion of the Oliver of the present day. The <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> furnace had been started on the west side of the county and it was
                    hoped iron would be secured there to make and supply the demand for the Peacock
                    plow. To that end Mr. Seward installed a foundry for the manufacture of all
                    kinds of castings, the blast being supplied by horse-power. The use of this
                    power was continued until 1854, when it was superseded by steam, which was used
                    from that time on. The shop was enlarged, a foundry built, more forges installed
                    and the capacity increased. In the early days but little money was paid for
                    labor, or for the products of the field or shop. A system of exchange was
                    established. The river—<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Louisville</settlement>
                    </placeName>—was the market, and in order to dispose of the products
                    received and exchanged for the products of the shop, he had a four-horse wagon
                    made named "The Great Western," which made regular trips to
                    the river, his <pb n="107" id="VAA4025-004-3-005"/> supplies and goods for the
                    merchants being brought back on the return trips. This wagon was started in an
                    early day and continued to run until the advent of the railroad in 1853.</p>
            <p>A list of the articles manufactured and a schedule of the work done by Austin
                    Seward would now be impossible. In order to get even a general idea, the
                    location, the people, the country, the time and its needs must be considered. <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Bloomington</settlement>
                    </placeName> is an inland town. Clear creek, Salt creek and <geogName>White
                        river</geogName> could carry away the products of the county at certain
                    seasons of the year, going with the current, but there were no boats plying any
                    of these streams against the current. There were no canals accessible. The only
                    way any kind of manufactured products could reach this locality was by wagon,
                    and that during almost six months of the year, with great difficulty and often
                    not at all. Austin Seward was a worker in metal. He was a blacksmith, a foundry
                    man, a gunsmith, and, most of all, an edge-tool maker. A heavy forest mas to be
                    subdued and axes were required. A good ax is the work of an artist. It is said
                    that some one told Henry Thoreau, in reply to some of his cynicisms, that it
                    took civilization two hundred years to develop his ax. It took centuries to
                    develop a Peacock plow. He could make them both. Over every fireplace hung a
                    rifle gun. He made them. He hammered, bored and rifled the barrel from bar iron;
                    made the locks, flint-locks at that, made the double triggers, cut a segment of
                    a slick quarter<hi rend="sup">*</hi> for the front sight, rounded out
                    and set the hind sight, made the bullet moulds, stocked it with curly sugar
                    wood, all with his own hands, and no gun could beat his for looks or business.
                    But, as I said, a catalogue of the articles of his handiwork, the products of
                    his shop, would be a catalogue of everything used in Indiana in which iron or
                    steel entered. He made adzes, augers, braces, bits, bells, scythes, files, guns,
                    knives, axes, sickles, shears—sheep shears being a
                    specialty—plows, wagons, carts, horseshoes, horseshoe nails; he shod
                    horses, mules and oxen, and, after his foundry was established, made threshing
                    machines, stoves, skillets, sugar kettles, pots and cane mills. In 1861 he made
                    and mounted a brass cannon. There are certain things at which he excelled. No
                    better axes were ever <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">*</hi> A "slick quarter"
                            was the old Spanish twenty-fire cent piece worn smooth by much
                        use.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="108" id="VAA4025-004-3-006"/> made than came from his shop. They were
                    forged on his anvils from bar iron and cast steel. It may be of interest to know
                    that his old books show that a Mr. Barnes was credited by him with ax bar iron 3
                    1/2 by 5/8 at 8 1–3 cents a pound, and cast steel at 30 cents. It was
                    all hauled from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Louisville</settlement>
                    </placeName> in wagons.</p>
            <p>His axes had a reputation which extended for miles. His son. W. B. Seward,
                    informs me that he has known men to come horseback for more than one hundred
                    miles to get an ax. Then he upset and resteeled axes, and, like Burns's
                    good woman, made them "most as good as new." Captain Fields,
                    whom we all knew and remember, used to tell that when he was a boy, his father
                    lived some sixty or seventy-five miles away from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Bloomington</settlement>
                    </placeName>; that he intended sending him to Mr. Seward's shop to get
                    an ax upset. When it became noised through the country that he was going on this
                    mission, the neighbors all brought their axes until he had as many axes to bring
                    as he had miles to travel. And Seward's axes in looks compared with any
                    "brought on," and in quality excelled them. He knew how to
                    temper. The ax, the chopping ax, must be a certain shape and must be properly
                    hung or it is no good. The steel must be heated just so hot. Kobody can tell how
                    hot. Austin Seward knew. He had many journeymen who made axes in his shop, but
                    of all he would yield the palm to but one man, a dissolute, drunken genius,
                    named Richardson, who worked for him for years and whose presence was only
                    tolerated by reason of his great and peculiar skill. William F. Browning says,
                    "Nobody could equal Seward in making an ax, but Richardson; he could
                    beat him." He was a great gunsmith and was the best offhand shot in the
                    country. Charcoal was used exclusively in his forges and foundry until
                    "stone coal," as it was called, was brought by rail. There was
                    a wood-working department at which wagons were built, plows stocked and such
                    other woodwork done as was necessary to turn out the finished product. The
                    relation he and his business bore to the community is illustrated by what his
                    old friend, Dr. Andrew Wylie, said when it was reported he was about to die.
                    "This community," said Dr. Wylie, "can better spare
                    any man in it, or the college every professor than it can spare Mr. Seward. We
                    can get other citizens and college professors to <pb n="109" id="VAA4025-004-3-007"/> take their places without any trouble, hut no man
                    can take his place."</p>
            <p>As a business man he would not be considered a success. In fact, as the world now
                    looks on business, he was not a business man—certainly not in a
                    financial way. With a genius for manufacturing, with a reputation he so early
                    and justly acquired, with the business he had without competition, many men
                    would have acquired a fortune. His sons, and he had a number of them, all were
                    mechanics, supplementing him and each other. His oldest son, John, was a born
                    machinist and an edge-tool maker. He could pattern anything on the anvil. He
                    could and did command the highest wages. James was a blacksmith pure and simple.
                    At the ordinary work on the anvil and at the forge it is said he could not be
                    excelled. The same thing could be said of Robert. W. B. was a patternmaker.
                    Irvin, a machinist, who always ran the lathe. Bricen, a gunsmith, and so on. In
                    his own family he had the men necessary to carry on an extensive manufacturing
                    business. When John became of age he was taken into partnership by his father;
                    subsequently James was taken in, but no settlements or invoice made. They just
                    stepped in. John concluded to try a new field of labor and just stepped down and
                    out. Still no settlements, no adjustment. W. B. got old enough, the door opened
                    and in he came on the same terms. The father feeling the infirmities of age,
                    quit on the same terms, and William H., son of W. B., stepped in and took up the
                    labors and assumed his share of the responsibilities and went ahead. No books
                    were kept or settlements had as between the partners. They kept on in the same
                    old Seward name with but slight variations as to "Sons,"
                    "Brothers" or "Company." And what is more
                    remarkable, from the time that Austin Seward started his shop in 1821 until this
                    time—eighty-six years, the establishment never failed, never settled
                    with its creditors, never went into bankruptcy, never assigned, never was sued,
                    and never sued except to collect an old account or to take judgment on a long
                    past due note.</p>
            <p>John, it is reported, said of his father, that if he had but one plow for sale
                    and two came for it, one with the money and the other without, the latter got
                    it. His reason was that a man with <pb n="110" id="VAA4025-004-3-008"/> money
                    could buy a plow any place—the man without, couldn't. It was
                    his Christian duty to help the helpless.</p>
            <p>Of Austin Seward's domestic life much could be said. His wife was the
                    daughter of a colonial dame. She had many relatives among the best of the
                    community with whom she and her husband were on terms of the closest intimacy.
                    They lived in the log cabin until 1828 when the old brick at the southwest
                    corner of Seventh and Walnut streets—now the Batman
                    block—-was built and occupied as the family residence. At the time
                    that was the most consequential house in town. It was brick, had two stories,
                    and, what no other house aspired to or presumed to enjoy, it had a hall. In that
                    house they lived until Pllrs. Seward's death in 1865. They always kept
                    open house. No one went from his door hungry. His business was large. He
                    employed journeymen and always had apprentices. The latter always made his house
                    their home, as well as nearly all the unmarried journeymen. They all ate at his
                    table, sat at his fireside and slept in his beds. Of the patrons from a
                    distance, nearly all stayed with him if their business kept them over night,
                    while his neighbors or friends, who called on business or pleasure and were
                    there at noon, stayed and took dinner. In "setting the table,"
                    there were always two extra plates laid for such as "just dropped
                    in"—all without money and without price. Their table was always well
                    supplied from the products of the country, exchanged for the products of the
                    shop. Each, in fact, was a legal tender and freely taken in exchange for the
                    other.</p>
            <p>Their condition in life was as their neighbors. They endured the hardships and
                    privations of the early pioneers. The household appointments were of the most
                    primitive kind. Wearing apparel was largely home spun and made up in the house
                    by women who came to sew. The household labors, cooking, washing, ironing and
                    sewing fell wholly on such of the women of the household as were large enough to
                    take up its burdens, with such help as could be procured in a new country. These
                    labors—the labor of caring for a large household, besides caring for
                    and rearing a family of nine children who grew to maturity, and two who died in
                    infancy—made Mrs. Seward prematurely old and broken, although she
                    always maintained a sunny and happy <pb n="111" id="VAA4025-004-3-009"/>
                    disposition, looked well and faithfully to the household duties, and was indeed
                    a helpmeet. She was well informed on all the issues of the day, was an authority
                    on matters of history, and was reputed to be one of the most handsome women in
                    the New Purchase.</p>
            <p>Austin Seward was born in the center of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> aristocracy holding to the Episcopalian church, and was baptized in
                    that faith. When he emigrated to <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> he settled among Scotch Presbyterians and married into a family of
                    Presbyterians; became a member of that faith, lived and died in it. He was
                    intensely, but not demonstratively religious. In his own cabin he established
                    and set up an altar at which he had family worship during the whole of his life,
                    and in this cabin conducted the first Sunday-school in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Bloomington</settlement>
                    </placeName>. He was superintendent, treasurer, secretary, teacher—in
                    fact everything, and rejoiced that he had for his pupils two governors of
                    Indiana, Whitcomb and Wright, both of whom became also <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> Senators.</p>
            <p>On the separation of the Presbyterians into the old and new school, Austin Seward
                    affiliated with the latter, and for years was a ruling elder. The "new
                    school" church was the frame building just west of the Bowles Hotel,
                    now occupied by the colored people. He was a regular attendant on all the
                    ministrations of the church, led in prayer at the prayer-meetings and in the
                    absence of the regular minister conducted the services. For years he took and
                    read <hi rend="i">The <placeName>
                            <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                        </placeName> Observer</hi> and <hi rend="i">Christian Herald</hi>, both
                    Presbyterian papers, and had on his library table Scott's Commentaries,
                    Barnes's Notes (this he originally took as a serial), besides many
                    other religious works. The spare bedroom in his house was especially set apart
                    to the priesthood, or rather the traveling preachers, and by the family was
                    known as the "apostles' room." It took an overflow to
                    profane that room to sacrilegious uses by permitting it to be occupied by any
                    other than a member of the cloth. Until the day of his death he remained
                    steadfast in the faith once delivered to the saints.</p>
            <p>The Sewards and Brewsters were slave-owners in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName>, although both families were opposed to the institution. Austin
                    Seward was a Henry Clay Whig, and one of the many who went <pb n="112" id="VAA4025-004-3-010"/> into mourning on his idol's defeat in
                    1844. In 1843 he was a candidate for the legislature on the Whig
                    ticket—the only time he was ever a candidate for office, but was
                    defeated after a dirty and scurrilous campaign that reflected neither honor nor
                    credit on his competitor or his supporters. On the disruption of the Whig party,
                    he went naturally into the Republican party and remained in it to his death. He
                    voted for <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Fremont</settlement>
                    </placeName> in 1856. His house in those days was a sort of an impromptu
                    Republican headquarters, while the pavement in front of his house was a typical
                    town meeting. His early political teachings he received from the <hi rend="i">
                  <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Louisville</settlement>
                        </placeName> Journal</hi> at the feet of George D. Prentice. From that he
                    went to the <hi rend="i">
                  <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                        </placeName> Gazette</hi> and the <hi rend="i">
                  <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                        </placeName> Journal</hi>. He also took the <hi rend="i">Scientific
                    American</hi> and an agricultural paper. He always read the papers and skipped
                    nothing, nearly always reading by candle-light which he held between himself and
                    his paper. He was intensely loyal during the war. Every fiber of his being and
                    every prayer of his heart was for a successful prosecution of the war and
                    preservation of the Union. He and his friends furnished the material and he made
                    and mounted a brass six-pound cannon which was used by the government during the
                    war. The good, loyal people of the community, more especially the women, donated
                    their old brass kettles, their brass andirons and candlesticks, and some women,
                    extra zealous in the cause, contributed their brass hoopskirts, all of which was
                    melted and moulded into this cannon. Two of his sons, with his consent and his
                    blessings and with his prayers, were given to the Union army. The combination of
                    his religious and political nature was such that during the war he literally
                    observed all fast days and at all times observed all days of thanksgiving.</p>
            <p>He and his family were musicians. He organized and was leader of the first band
                    ever organized in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Bloomington</settlement>
                    </placeName>,—and for that matter in the New Purchase. To this from
                    time to time all of his sons belonged. He built, at his own expense, a house for
                    band practice, which was used also for years as a sort of dormitory for the shop
                    hands.</p>
            <p>He was a man of great industry. Carrying on his shop took no little time and
                    attention. There was much to be seen after, <pb n="113" id="VAA4025-004-3-011"/>
                    but he attended to it all and did also a man's work at the forge. When
                    the new shop was built, one of the forges was his. When it was reconstructed and
                    enlarged, he had his forge and kept it as long as he was connected with the
                    business. During all of these years of labor—of hard
                    labor—his hand never forgot its cunning.</p>
            <p>In appearance Austin Seward was fair, had blue eyes, brown curly hair, was about
                    five feet ten and a half inches high, slender and active, and notwithstanding
                    his lameness, could get about with the best. His early education was limited,
                    but by extensive reading and close observation, he became a fair scholar and a
                    man of great and varied information. He could transact all of his business,
                    conduct his correspondence and keep his books. That he was an ignorant man is
                    disproved by the fact that on the establishment of the State Board of
                    Agriculture in 1851, one of his old Sunday-school scholars, Governor Joseph A.
                    Wright, appointed him a member, a position he honorably and satisfactorily
                    filled. He was not a good speller; for instance, his son, W. B., tells me that
                    in looking over his old books a few days ago, he found where he had charged a
                    customer with a s-p-a-i-d.</p>
            <p>He claimed among his most intimate friends and associates, the educated and most
                    intelligent men of the community. He hunted and shot with Braynard R. Hall and
                    Dr. David H. Maxwell; talked theology, philosophy and "shop"
                    with Dr. Andrew Wylie; talked politics and discussed the affairs of State with
                    Governor Whitcomb; agriculture and mechanics with Governor Wright, and heard
                    gladly the humor, satire and eloquence of his kinsman, George Grundy Dunn, all
                    of whom in a social way and as his equals, sat at his fireside and broke bread
                    at his table.</p>
            <p>From the time Austin Seward opened his shop in 1821 to the present time, their
                    relations with labor have been the most friendly. There have been no strikes,
                    boycotts or any other labor trouble. In the early days—in fact until
                    recent years—there were always apprentices. I know now of but one
                    living, William J. Alexander, commonly known as "Jim"
                    Alexander, who worked with him for a quarter of a century, and who told me about
                    Mr. and Mrs. Seward from the viewpoint of an apprentice and as a <pb n="114" id="VAA4025-004-3-012"/> journeyman. His statement is substantially as
                    follows: Mr Seward's apprentices served him four years, at a very
                    meager wage, as was the custom in those days; but then they always came through
                    as skilled workmen and able to earn the highest wages They did not stay in and
                    about the shop in a perfunctory way. doing the drudgery of the shop, the house
                    and the stable, but were taught all that pertained to the trade. They made their
                    home with his family, while Mrs. Seward herself saw they were properly supplied
                    with clothing, that it was kept in good repair, and that their physical wants
                    were supplied the same as those of her own children. The hours of labor were
                    long—no eight or ten hours a day was recognized—but
                    journeymen and apprentices were always given the benefit of all work done
                    overtime. Mr. Seward was idolized and revered by every man in his employ. while
                    Mrs. Seward was always by every "cub" and
                    "jour" affectionately called "Mammy."</p>
            <p>"Austin Seward was the biggest hearted man I ever saw. He made
                    money—it was no trouble for him to make money, hut he never
                    collected, or if collected, it was given away," was his language. Mr.
                    Seward was one of the largest subscribers for stock to the railroad, now the
                    Monon, paid every dollar of it and all of it was lost. Soon after the old
                    college was burned. Money was raised to save that and he was one of the heaviest
                    contributors. That, too, was a total financial loss, but the university was
                    retained. When on the separation of the Presbyterian church into the old and the
                    new school, he went into the latter, he gave $500 toward buying a new
                    church; the one which is now occupied by the A. M. E. Church just west of the
                    Bon-les Hotel. "Mammy" Seward afterwards said the hardest
                    times she ever went through mere when they had the loss by the railroad and made
                    the donations to the college and to buying the church.</p>
            <p>Before the advent of the railroad, the traveling was by horseback. All kinds of
                    preachers stopped with him. Before they would go, one of the boys in the shop
                    would be told to get out the horse, examine its hoofs, if not shod or if needing
                    new shoes, to put them on—put it back in the stable and nothing said
                    about it. If a man wanted an implement to work with he always got it <pb n="115" id="VAA4025-004-3-013"/> whether he had money or not. The boys who tended
                    his team told him the corn was going too fast—in short, somebody was
                    stealing it. Mr. Seward remonstrated with him for making such insinuations,
                    saying that as long as he had corn, and any one hadn't it, he could get
                    it by coming to him. The boys were insistent—some corn was arranged
                    so that any disturbance would be noticed, and a single night verified their
                    statement. A hole had been made in the door for the benefit of the cats. Mr.
                    Seward fixed some kind of a trap and fastened it inside, locked the door, but
                    left the hole for the cats. The next morning he found a man fast, unloosed him,
                    filled his basket with corn, told him whenever he wanted any more to come to him
                    and get all he wanted. One or two of the boys knew all about it, but he enjoined
                    on them strict secrecy and never told it himself. At another time
                    "Mammy" Seward found some one—a respectable
                    man—stealing. She filled his basket and to assist him in concealing
                    the crime, covered it with cobs and was terribly outraged at some of the boys
                    who had been watching and knew of the theft.</p>
            <p>When he first moved here he was universally called Seward, pronounced the usual
                    way, but for some unknown reason, the name got changed to Seward, with the e
                    pronounced as long e and bearing the accent. An old paper in the hands of this
                    society shows two advertised uncalled-for letters addressed to him under the
                    phonetic spelling, A. C. Ward. It was no uncommon thing to see his name spelled
                    in this way.</p>
            <p>All of the family have died but two—Williamson Brewster, an honored
                    member of our society and citizen of the State, and Robert D., who after fifty
                    years' work at the anvil, with the respect and confidence of everybody,
                    is now enjoying the rest he so well deserves and has so well earned. Austin
                    Seward himself died October 27, 1872, and is buried in the Dunn burying-ground
                    beside his wife and her sisters.</p>
            <p>Braynard R. Hall, a Presbyterian preacher of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Philadelphia</settlement>
                    </placeName>, a graduate of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Princeton</settlement>
                    </placeName>, opened the State Seminary—the forerunner of the State
                    University—in 1824, and remained until 1831. In 1843 he published a
                    work in two volumes, entitled "The New <pb n="116" id="VAA4025-004-3-014"/> Purchase, or Seven Years in the Far West"
                    under the <hi rend="i">non de plume</hi> of Robert Carleton. It is a very
                    readable book, and, while largely overdrawn, gives a fair representation of this
                    locality at that time. It is true, he puts impossible and unheard of language
                    into the mouths of his characters and generally caricatures the people. He was a
                    scholarly man, an eloquent preacher, but on account of trouble with Dr. Andrew
                    Wylie, left in a huff and never was again reconciled to the country or the
                    people. Every one except members of his own family, Dr. David H. Maxwell and Mr.
                    Seward were ridiculed and lampooned. He gave all assumed names. Dr. Maxwell was
                    Dr. Sylvanus and Mr. Seward was Vulcanus Allheart. To the latter is devoted a
                    whole chapter of his book—the only man to whom was given a chapter.
                    His enthusiastic and generous estimate of Mr. Seward's life and
                    character can be summed up in his closing paragraph: "He was by birth a
                    Virginian, by trade a blacksmith, by nature a gentleman, and by grace a
                    Christian; if more need be said, he was a genius."</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="117" id="VAA4025-004-3-015"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-004-3-a02">
            <head>HENRY CLAY AT RICHMOND.</head>
            <p rend="center">T<hi rend="sc">HE</hi> A<hi rend="sc">BOLITION</hi> P<hi rend="sc">ETITION</hi>.</p>
            <p>[The following articles are the latest, and among the best, discussions of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName>'s visit to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName> in 1842, his speech there, and the presentation of a petition
                    asking him to free his own slaves. A careful reading will show that they differ
                    very little in matters of fact, though taking opposite views of the dignity and
                    appropriateness of the conduct of the leading actors.</p>
            <p>The first article was originally printed in the <hi rend="i">
                  <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                        </placeName> News</hi>, August 24, 1901, and the second was printed at the
                    instance of Judge M. L. Bundy in the <hi rend="i">
                  <placeName>
                            <region type="county">Henry County</region>
                        </placeName> Tribune</hi>, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Spiceland</settlement>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Newcastle</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Ind., January 10, 1908.—E<hi rend="sc">DITOR</hi>.]</p>
            <p rend="center">
               <hi rend="i">Charles W. Osborn's Article</hi>.</p>
            <p>IN the autumn of 1812, Henry Clay, of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName>, an aspirant to the presidency, in the course of an electioneering
                    tour, came to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Ind., and on October 1 spoke to a large concourse of people.</p>
            <p>While on the platform and in the presence of the audience, Hiram Mendenhall
                    presented to <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName> a petition asking him to liberate his slaves. <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName>, in his answer, told Mendenhall to go home and mind his own
                    business. Mendenhall's action in this case has been severely censured.
                    He has been regarded as a kind of gadfly, seeking an opportunity to torment the
                    great statesman in the presence of his political friends. <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName>'s speech at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName> has been regarded as a political blunder that cost him the loss of
                    the presidency in 1844. Most of those who have written upon the subject seem to
                    be ignorant of some of the facts connected with the case.</p>
            <p>Judge Bundy, of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Newcastle</settlement>
                    </placeName>, in an article in the <hi rend="i">
                  <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                        </placeName> Journal</hi> some two years ago, says the speech made the
                    foundation for a third party of political abolitionists, who nominated James G.
                    Birney, who received votes enough in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                    </placeName> alone to defeat <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName>. The Liberty party existed before <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName>'s speech at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName>, and Birney received 7,000 votes for President in 1840. The party
                    was organized in Indiana in February, 1841, and delegates appointed to attend
                    the convention that nominated <pb n="118" id="VAA4025-004-3-016"/> Birney in
                    1844. It would be difficult to determine the cause or causes that increased the
                    abolition vote from 7,000 in 1840 to over 62,000 in 1844. This vote was drawn
                    more largely from the Whigs than from the Democrats, because the former were
                    more anti-slavery than the latter. <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName> was a slave-holder, and in his "<placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="alu">Alabama</region>
                    </placeName>" letter favored the slave-holding measure of the
                    annexation of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="txu">Texas</region>
                    </placeName> under certain conditions. These two things did more, doubtless, to
                    alienate from him the anti-slavery Whigs than his speech at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName>.</p>
            <p>Addison C. Harris, late minister to <placeName>
                        <country reg="au">Austria</country>
                    </placeName>, in an article published in the <hi rend="i">American Friend</hi>,
                    of November 6, 1896, under the title of "A <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Quaker</settlement>
                    </placeName> Episode," attributes the petition to a few so-called
                    anti-slavery Quakers, mostly living at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Newport</settlement>
                    </placeName>, north of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName>, who advocated the doctrine of immediate and unconditional
                    emancipation, and who refused to be switched off of this main track of
                    abolitionism by the unjust and impracticable colonization dodge. That these
                    Quakers on learning that <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName> was to speak in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName> on Saturday before the great Sunday of the Indiana Yearly Meeting,
                    prepared a petition, got it numerously signed, placed it in the hands of one of
                    their number named Mendenhall to be presented privately to <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName> on Friday evening previous to the speaking, but failing to gain his
                    presence, presented it publicly upon the platform the next day. There is much
                    error in this account. The petition originated in the Indiana State Anti-Slavery
                    Society, an organization wholly undenominational but numbering perhaps more
                    Friends or Quakers than any other one denomination. An annual meeting of this
                    society was held at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Newport</settlement>
                    </placeName> (now <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Fountain City</settlement>
                    </placeName>), beginning September 5, 1842, and continuing four days. The
                    attendance was too large for the Friends' meeting-house, and they
                    adjourned to a grove fitted up for the occasion. On the first day of the
                    convention it was "On motion resolved that a committee of three be
                    appointed to prepare a petition to be presented to Henry Clay, of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName>, when he shall arrive at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName>, in his visit to this State as contemplated the present season,
                    calling on him to liberate his slaves, and that H. H. Way, Daniel Worth, Peter
                    Crocker and <placeName>
                        <country reg="is">Israel</country>
                    </placeName> French constitute a committee to present it.</p>
            <pb n="119" id="VAA4025-004-3-017"/>
            <p>"Resolved, That Matthew R. Hull, Benjamin Stanton and Ziba Casterline
                    constitute a committee to draft said petition."</p>
            <p>At the afternoon session I find this record:</p>
            <p>"The committee to prepare a petition to Henry Clay presented one, which
                    was adopted, and is as follows:</p>
            <p>"To Henry Clay:</p>
            <p>"‘We, the undersigned citizens of Indiana, in view of the
                    declarations of rights contained in the charter of American Independence, in
                    view of that justice that is due from man to his fellow-man; in view of all
                    those noble principles which should characterize the patriot, the philanthropist
                    and the Christian, ask you most respectfully to "unloose the heavy
                    burdens," and that you let the oppressed under your control who call
                    you master go free. By doing so you would give liberty to whom liberty is due,
                    and do no more than justice to those under your charge, who hare long been
                    deprived by you of the sacred boon of freedom; and set an example that would
                    result in much good to suffering and debased humanity, and do an act altogether
                    worthy a great and good man.’ "</p>
            <p>Immediately following the petition is this resolution:</p>
            <p>"Resolved, That should Henry Clay refuse to emancipate his slaves, the
                    committee to present the petition be instructed to request him to give his
                    reasons for so refusing."</p>
            <p>
               <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName> attended a very large Whig convention at <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Dayton</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="ohu">O.</region>
               </placeName>, on September 29, which declared for him for
                    President in 1844, and came on to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName>, where he was to speak Saturday, October 1. That the petition might
                    be presented publicly, and that violence had been threatened to the committee of
                    presentation, is evident from an editorial in the <hi rend="i">Free Labor
                        Advocate and Anti-Slavery Chronicle</hi>, of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Newport</settlement>
                    </placeName>, under date of September 24, 1842, in answer to the <hi rend="i">
                  <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                        </placeName> Palladium's</hi> statement that it would be wrong and
                    an insult to <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName> to present such a petition on his visit to Indiana. The <hi rend="i">Advocate and Chronicle</hi> says:</p>
            <p>"We hear there are great threats of violence if the committee should
                    attempt to present the petition; and the <hi rend="i">Palladium</hi> plainly
                    intimates an expectation of that kind, but professes to discourage it, and
                    acknowledge that a violent opposition would be as bad as the presentation of the
                    petition itself."</p>
            <pb n="120" id="VAA4025-004-3-018"/>
            <p>The committee on presentation, in making its report, says: "The first
                    object of your committee was to make themselves acquainted with the time that
                    would be most convenient on the part of Henry Clay for their reception. They
                    accordingly addressed him the appended note: ‘<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName>, October 1, 1842. To Henry Clay—We, who are appointed a
                    committee, by a large convention of people, to present a petition to Henry Clay,
                    signed by near two thousand citizens of Indiana, respectfully ask him to
                    communicate the hour that such interview would be most convenient. Signed,
                    Daniel Worth, Peter Crocker, Hiram Menden-hall and Samuel Mitchell.’
                    The last two names were substituted in the place of H. H. Way and <placeName>
                        <country reg="is">Israel</country>
                    </placeName> French, who were absent. The note was presented to Ervin Reed, one
                    of the <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName> committee of arrangements, by Mendenhall and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Mitchell</settlement>
                    </placeName>."</p>
            <p>Daniel Worth had no further hand in the presentation of the petition, and in
                    explanation of the fact in a letter dated October 13 and published in the <hi rend="i">Advocate and Chronicle</hi> of October 29, says: "It is
                    said to be currently reported in certain quarters that I had too much prudence
                    to make the presentation myself, but was willing to shift it off on friend
                    Mendenhall, who was not known as a member of the committee." Worth
                    further states, "that the reception committee informed them that it was <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName>'s wish to receive them at his hotel on Sunday morning;
                    that he could not possibly see them sooner, to which they assented and their
                    committee separated. A few minutes later James Rariden announced from the stand
                    to the immense multitude that if the abolitionists had any request to make to
                    Mr. Clay, or paper to present to him, it was <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName>'s wish that it should be done publicly and on that
                    occasion, that he might give a public answer thereto and make a public
                    declaration of his sentiments on this delicate subject."</p>
            <p>Worth says, being separated from the other members of the committee, with little
                    chance of finding them in the immense crowd, and being inclined to look upon
                    Rariden's language as a boast, he made no attempt to find the rest of
                    the committee; that in the meantime the other members of the committee (Crocker,
                    Mendenhall and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Mitchell</settlement>
                    </placeName>), having obtained proximity to the stand from which Rariden was
                    speaking, and consulting him <pb n="121" id="VAA4025-004-3-019"/> further on the
                    subject, went and brought the papers and presented them. "This is the
                    reason why Mr. Mendenhall presented the memorial, and I am glad it was in such
                    good hands. I believe this was an arrangement made to defeat the committee in
                    presenting the petition and disingenuous on the part of its authors."
                    Another version of the sudden change of the time and manner of presenting the
                    petition is that it was discussed on the platform by <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName>'s personal friends, and that one of them, of the type
                    known as fire-eaters, said let the abolitionists present their petition now and
                    publicly and then give them hell; and that his counsel prevailed, and the first
                    part at least of his program carried out. Mendenhall said the reason he carried
                    the petition to <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName> was because neither Crocker nor <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Mitchell</settlement>
                    </placeName> would volunteer to do it.</p>
            <p>Mendenhall was a fit person to work his way through a hooting, jeering,
                    threatening crowd, for he was a tall, muscular man, weighing two hundred pounds,
                    then in the prime of manhood, being forty-one years old. He arrived at the
                    speaker's stand with his coat badly cut by the mob, and doubtless would
                    have received personal injury had not <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName> stepped to the front of the platform and begged the crowd for his
                    sake and for God's sake to not insult nor do violence to the committee.
                    Mendenhall stepped upon the platform, handed <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName> the petition, and when he saw they were not going to give him a
                    chair, he sat down on the floor, a little to one side of the speaker.</p>
            <p>
               <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName> read the petition and made it the subject of his discourse. The
                    committee on presentation reported the substance of his speech, of which the
                    following are the principal points: He said the act of presenting the petition
                    was beneath the dignity of an American citizen. "Petitions,"
                    he said, "are from inferiors to superiors, or to those having absolute
                    power. The petition should have been brought to Ashland. The signers were
                    Democrats and those of a shade darker, and its design was to create influence
                    against me. Suppose you were traveling through my country and I should ask you
                    to give up your land? But I am aware that you make a distinction in the
                    different kinds of property. We have an idea that whatever the law secures to us
                    as property is property. The declaration of rights of which you speak was not
                        <pb n="122" id="VAA4025-004-3-020"/> intended by those who formed that
                    document as you interpret it. All thirteen of the States that framed that
                    declaration held slaves at that very time. Yours is a new interpretation.</p>
            <p>"Slavery is a great evil; we are in the midst of it; fastened upon us by
                    Great Britain. There is not a man who deplores slavery more than I do. But the
                    slave must be prepared for freedom before he can receive that great boon. He
                    must have moral cultivation. The Society of Friends takes the right stand in
                    regard to this question. Yours are the revolutionary principles of Thomas Dorr,
                    of <placeName>
                        <country reg="riu">Rhode Island</country>
                    </placeName>, and should the principles of your petition be granted,
                    extermination and blood would be the result. States have rights that you can no
                    more interfere with than you can with nations. I own fifty slaves, and I treat
                    them well; ask my Charles here; he goes as well clad and, I believe, is as
                    honest a man as Mr. Mendenhall. My slaves are worth $15,000, and if
                    the abolitionists will raise and give them the same amount, I will liberate
                    them. You have put back emancipation fifty years. Go home, Mr. Mendenhall and
                    mind your own business."</p>
            <p>Thus it will be seen that Hiram Mendenhall acted only as the agent of the Indiana
                    State Anti-Slavery Society, of which he was a member; that he did not thrust
                    himself upon Henry Clay, but consulted him as to when the interview should take
                    place and whether it should be public or private. The whole affair was simply
                    one of those early moral engagements in the irrepressible conflict of freedom
                    with slavery, which terminated with the close of the War of the Rebellion.</p>
            <p>The vision of the seer was imperfect when it showed him that the zeal of the
                    abolitionist had put back the emancipation of the slave fifty years; for not
                    one-half of that time elapsed until American slavery was a thing of the past.
                    But slavery, the cause of the rebellion, was buried at a fearful cost of blood
                    and treasure. To-day we look upon the two principal actors on that <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName> stage in the light of intervening events, through the vista of
                    fifty-nine years and across seven hundred battle-grounds of the Civil War, and
                    over the graves of 500.000 soldiers of the blue and the gray, and the memory of
                    the apologizers for slavery <pb n="123" id="VAA4025-004-3-021"/> grows dim,
                    while the memory of the advocates of freedom grows brighter as the years go by.</p>
            <p>"Then to side with Truth is noble, when we share her wretched crust</p>
            <p>Ere her cause bring fame and profit, and ‘tis prosperous to be
                    just."</p>
            <p>Such nobility belonged to Hiram Mendenhall and his abolition compeers in the
                    early forties, and to-day we regard them as having been at home and attending to
                    the business that belonged to them as American citizens and patriots while
                    advocating the freedom of the slave.</p>
            <p rend="right">C<hi rend="sc">HARLES</hi> W. O<hi rend="sc">SBORN</hi>.</p>
            <p>Economy, Ind.</p>
            <p rend="center">
               <hi rend="i">Account by Charles and William Coffin</hi>.</p>
            <p>[Charles F. Coffin, of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                    </placeName>, and his brother William, of Pasadena, Cal., I think, are the only
                    persons living who can write a correct history of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName>'s visit to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName>, and the yearly meeting, October, 1842 —sixty-five years
                    ago. Charles drove the carriage that conveyed him to the meeting and listened to
                    his speech. He wrote a history and sent it to me and I advised him to have it
                    published in your paper and he wrote me his consent to my request. M. I. B<hi rend="sc">UNDY</hi>.]</p>
            <p>In October, 1842, Henry Clay passed through <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Ind., on what was probably an electioneering tour for the
                    presidency, though not ostensibly so. He had been prominent before the public as
                    a candidate for President, and had heretofore been unsuccessful. The Yearly
                    Meeting of Friends in Indiana was being held at this time, and his friends
                    evidently arranged for his arrival there during the yearly meeting—as
                    in those days the meetings were very large, and it was thought he would have a
                    good opportunity to present himself before them. He arrived in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName> on the 1st of October, 1842, and stopped at what was then known as
                    the "Nixon Hotel," a small, but very neat hotel, afterward
                    known as the "<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Huntington</settlement>
                    </placeName>." There were, as guests, at the hotel, a number of
                    Friends, amongst others, three bridal couples—James D. Ladd, Brooks
                    Johnson and Samuel R. Lippincott. Rhoda M. Johnson, then an unmarried young
                    lady, who afterward became the wife of Charles F. Coffin, accompanied her
                    brother, Brooks Johnson.</p>
            <pb n="124" id="VAA4025-004-3-022"/>
            <p>Of course the arrival of so distinguished a man as Henry Clay attracted the
                    attention of every one. The brides were introduced to him, and he promptly
                    kissed each one of them. Miss Johnson remarked that she was glad she was not a
                    bride on this occasion, as she did not fancy the looks of Henry Clay. On
                    Saturday afternoon he spoke upon a platform which had been erected on some
                    vacant lots within a block of the hotel. In addition to the large number of
                    Friends attending the yearly meeting, the whole country for miles around turned
                    out to hear this distinguished orator. It was estimated roughly that there were
                    ten thousand persons in sound of his voice. Of course this number was guessed
                    at, but there was certainly a very large number.</p>
            <p>The anti-slavery agitation had become very strong by this time, and a large body
                    of abolitionists resided at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Newport</settlement>
                    </placeName>, ten miles north of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName>. They met and prepared an address to Henry Clay, asking him to
                    liberate his slaves, and appointed a deputation to present it to him. This
                    deputation was headed by Hiram Mendenhall, who became spokesman of the
                    deputation. They made their way to the platform, and handed the petition to
                    James Rariden, the Congressman from that district, and a very warm friend of
                    Henry Clay's. At Henry Clay's request, he read the petition to
                    him. It excited a great commotion in the audience, who felt it was an uncalled
                    for intrusion at this time, and they might have offered violence to the parties
                    presenting it, but Henry Clay arose and earnestly requested them, on his
                    account, not to do so, but to allow the parties full liberty. He then arose and
                    replied to the address, the committee presenting it being seated upon the
                    plaform, and told them that he was opposed to slavery himself; that all the
                    slaves he had, he had inherited from his father—that he had never
                    bought nor sold one—that many of them were old and infirm, and would
                    be unable to provide for themselves if turned loose.</p>
            <p>He turned to his body servant, whom he called "Charles" (a
                    colored man), and said to the company: "Here is Charles—he
                    is in a free State, and entirely at liberty to leave me if he desires to do so,
                    and if you who present this petition will prepare a place for my slaves at home
                    where they can be provided for, and enabled to make their living, I will gladly
                    release them all; but <pb n="125" id="VAA4025-004-3-023"/> as it is, it would be
                    an act of cruelty which I could not perform; and besides, I have grown up
                    amongst them, and have a degree of attachment to them, which would prevent me
                    from turning them out without the means of subsistence." He then turned
                    to the deputation and poured out a volley of eloquence rarely heard, suggesting
                    to them that they were interfering with something with which they had nothing to
                    do. Standing immediately in front of Mendenhall, and bending almost over him, he
                    closed with a peroration like this: "Go home, Mr. Mendenhall, and
                    attend to your own business, and I will endeavor to see after mine."
                    This scathing rebuke of course touched deeply those to whom it was administered,
                    and they did go home, and did all they could to prevent his election for
                    President. Whether they would have pursued the same course otherwise or not, it
                    is uncertain, but it is supposed to have had much to do in defeating him for
                    President.</p>
            <p>On the next day, Sabbath morning, the writer's younger brother, William
                    H. Coffin, stood very near the platform and heard all that was said, the writer
                    himself being a little farther off, but yet heard enough to understand most that
                    was said. Henry Clay desired to attend the large meeting for the public on this
                    Sabbath, and Elijah Coffin, father of the writer, was clerk of the yearly
                    meeting, and consulted with the few leading Friends as to what they should do in
                    the matter. It was concluded to take him to the meeting and place him on one of
                    the raised seats near where the ministers who were to address the meeting sat.
                    An immense crowd came to the meeting, and the writer drove the carriage for his
                    father, who called for Henry Clay, and took him to the meeting house. It was
                    with great difficulty that we could get through the crowd, and it was necessary
                    to drive very slowly, so as to allow people to open a passage way and let the
                    carriage through. On arrival at the meeting house, a tall Friend, named Pleasant
                    Winston, took hold of one of Henry Clay's arms and my father of the
                    other, and then escorted him to the place in the meeting house prepared for him.</p>
            <p>He was sufficiently elevated there to be seen by the whole company, and of course
                    was an object of great attraction. Two ministers delivered addresses: one, John
                    Meader, of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Providence</settlement>
                    </placeName>, <pb n="126" id="VAA4025-004-3-024"/> R. I., and the other, Stephen
                    Grellett, of <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Burlington</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="nju">N. J.</region>
               </placeName> The latter, a
                    Frenchman of distinguished family, who had left <placeName>
                        <country reg="fr">France</country>
                    </placeName> on account of revolutionary proceedings, and after he came to the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>, being thrown with Friends, became a member of the society and
                    ultimately a preacher of the gospel, who traveled over the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> and Europe, and having belonged to a prominent family, was well
                    educated and in every respect a most accomplished gentleman. This enabled him to
                    reach the nobility—in some instances the Kings, and especially the
                    Czar of Russia. His addresses in English were much broken and rather difficult
                    to understand, but were able and eloquent. Henry Clay listened to these speakers
                    with intense interest, turning almost around in his seat in order to see them
                    distinctly, as he was nearly under them. After the close of the meeting the same
                    diCficulty occurred in getting him away that had occurred on his arrival, and I
                    had to drive with very great care, and almost run against people in order to get
                    them out of the way, as their curiosity led them to crowd around the carriage in
                    order to get a view of Henry Clay. He left <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName> the next day, and proceeded on his journey westward.</p>
            <p>This event, unimportant as it may seem, attracted very great attention throughout
                    the country, and was much commented upon. Many narratives of it have appeared,
                    scarcely any one of which was wholly correct, but the position which the writer
                    and his brother occupied, enable them to give the full facts in regard to the
                    matter, as it occurred at the time.</p>
            <p>November 14, 1907. C<hi rend="sc">HARLES</hi> F. C<hi rend="sc">OFFIN</hi>.</p>
            <p>I have carefully read your manuscript, and find it well descriptive of the
                    occasion and subject as I saw it. Henry Clay's speech to Mr. Mendenhall
                    and his compeers was not long, but long enough to well answer the so-called
                    petition, in his lawyer-like, able and senatorial manner. I could almost
                    reproduce it, not in exact words, perhaps, but in sense and point and much of
                    the language used, as I was intensely interested. I was then at heart and
                    conviction, anti-slavery to the bottom, and would have helped in the underground
                    movement, or in any other way to have done any good, practically, in its
                    overthrow.</p>
            <pb n="127" id="VAA4025-004-3-025"/>
            <p>Henry Clay had made a strong and able speech from a Whig standpoint to that great
                    crowd, and this affair was injected to do all possible to hurt him because he
                    was a slave-holder. Under the circumstances the scathing he gave them was
                    merited, although distorted by them and made to appear in altogether a different
                    light, as was also the affair next day of his attendance at the yearly meeting.
                    So, we have so many partly untrue and distorted accounts of it, yours will be
                    the most truthful, plain, unvarnished 2nd impartial account of the whole affair
                    I have ever yet seen written.</p>
            <p>Charles Osborn some years ago wrote a statement of it from his standpoint, which
                    was probably the fairest and most truthful narrative from that side, but he
                    evidently was not present, and gained his information from biased sources.</p>
            <p>After James Rariden had received and read the petition publicly from the platform
                    to Henry Clay, he arose and answered somewhat as follows:—(Condensed)
                    "That this petition to him at this time and place was out of order;
                    that petitions were from inferiors to superiors; that he was now an American
                    citizen traveling through Indiana to meet and see his friends, and in no wise a
                    superior, but on an equality with them; that if they had had a real desire to
                    see and talk with him about the slaves at his home, they should have come to
                    Ashland where he would have guaranteed safety and true hospitality; and used
                    them like gentlemen; that he was opposed to slavery, and believed it to be a
                    great evil, but that it was fastened on the colonies by the British government
                    at an early period of our colonial history, and was now so interwoven into the
                    fabric of our social condition and life, especially in the Southern States, that
                    it would be impossible to uproot it at once without destroying our government;
                    that he had never bought or sold a slave, but had about fifty left him by will
                    from his father's estate; that half of them were along in years, some
                    much older than he was, and the rest mostly their children, who had grown up on
                    the plantation; that they had been the companions of his childhood and youth,
                    and he was much attached to them, and felt morally bound to support them in
                    their old age. Now, gentlemen, I will make you an offer, seeing you have come to
                    me with this affair in this public <pb n="128" id="VAA4025-004-3-026"/> manner;
                    if you will buy a suitable tract of land in northern Indiana, or <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> (which could have been purchased very reasonably), to settle these
                    old and infirm people on, and where they can be comfortably cared for, I will
                    agree to turn them over to you. As to Charles, my body servant, I have brought
                    him into a free State, and by the law, he is free; and if he wants to go with
                    you, he is at perfect liberty to do so." (Charles grinned and showed no
                    disposition to leap into the arms of Mr. Menden-hall and his compeers.)</p>
            <p>Mr. Mendenhall and his company, by this time grown smaller, some having vanished
                    in the great crowd, showed no disposition to accept his offer, and then came his
                    eloquent and scathing peroration over Mr. Mendenhall's head, ending
                    with the words, "Go home, Mr. Mendenhall—do good in your own
                    neighborhood, feed the hungry, clothe the naked, relieve the necessities of the
                    poor, the sick, the fatherless, and the widow; attend to these duties, and I
                    will endeavor to attend to mine." Then came a mighty and prolonged
                    roar, or cheer, you might call it, from the excited ten thousand in which I
                    joined, doing my best, and WIr. Mendenhall went into a hole, and pulled the hole
                    in, and disappeared. As you well say, they did go home, and did attend to their
                    own duties as exhorted, for they were really that kind of philanthropic men; and
                    also saw to it that no votes they could influence in after time were cast for
                    Henry Clay, the great Slave-Holder, whom Indiana yearly meeting set at its head,
                    by the clerk, as they afterward misrepresented and made appear.</p>
            <p>It always, in all the statements of this Henry Clay affair I have seen, made him
                    speak too harshly on the "Go home" part of it. It did not
                    strike me that way at the time, as you can guess by the full text of his speech
                    as I have written in that part of it, but was scathing enough as it really was.</p>
            <p>I want to say further, your account of the attendance of the yearly meeting the
                    next day, was true in every respect as I saw it, and has never before been
                    correctly written.</p>
            <byline>W<hi rend="sc">ILLIAM</hi> H. C<hi rend="sc">OFFIN</hi>.</byline>
         </div>
         <pb n="129" id="VAA4025-004-3-027"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-004-3-a03">
            <head>PIONEER TRANSPORTATION ON THE OHIO RIVER.</head>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="i">BY HON. SAZUEL T. COVINGTON, OF RISING SUN</hi>.</byline>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">From the Rising Sun Local, April 27, 1877</hi>.</p>
            <p>IN the early times of Rising Sun, steamboat accommodations or facilities were not
                    first class. Boats were as angels' visits are said to be, "few
                    and far between." The first passenger to or from Rising Sun on a
                    steamboat was Mr. John James, the proprietor of the town. In 1815 the steamboat
                    "Independence," on a voyage from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New Orleans</settlement>
                    </placeName> to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName>, at the end of four months from the time of starting, arrived at
                    Rising Sun. With the green wood which they were compelled to cut as they needed
                    fuel, she could not make steam enough to stem the current opposite the town, and
                    they bought fence rails of Mr. James, he to take his pay in a passage to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Mr. James remained with the boat until she arrived at North Bend,
                    at which point, becoming tired of the tardiness, he left and walked ahead,
                    arriving at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName> twelve hours ahead of the Independence. That was a specimen of
                    early steamboating.</p>
            <p>But the pioneers of this vicinity did not depend on steamboats to take their
                    produce to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName>, where they purchased their supplies. They preferred a more
                    reliable and rapid mode of transportation. The plain where the town now stands,
                    as well as the surrounding country, abounded in majestic poplars, from which
                    were made canoes and pirogues, many of which were capable of carrying five or
                    more tons of cargo, and it was by means of these vessels that the commerce,
                    between Rising Sun and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName> especially, was transported. With one man at the bow and another at
                    the stern, wielding the setting poles with great dexterity in pushing the canoe
                    forward, it was surprising to see with what speed it was driven against the
                    current. Two men would thus drive a well-laden canoe about as fast as an active
                    man could walk, and thus the voyage to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName> could be made in a little over a day's time. The writer of
                    this has heard his grandfather, Colonel Samuel Fulton, say that on more than <pb n="130" id="VAA4025-004-3-028"/> one occasion he has left Rising Sun at an
                    early hour in the morning with some members of his family who proposed to visit
                    some friends at his former home in <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Newport</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="kyu">Ky.</region>
               </placeName>, as passengers, and some marketing, and land at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Newport</settlement>
                    </placeName> before sundown. On such occasions I suppose the trip was intended
                    especially for passengers, and express freight. In those days Rev. Joshua L.
                    Wilson, then pastor of the First Presbyterian Church at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName>, occasionally preached at the houses of Presbyterians residing in
                    this vicinity—for they had no church buildings—and on some
                    of those occasions Colonel Fulton, who was one of the original members and aided
                    in the organization of the Presbyterian Church here, took his canoe to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName> and brought Mr. Wilson down, and after the meetings were over took
                    him home in the same way.</p>
            <p>As the population increased the commerce increased, and larger vessels were
                    required. The Browns not only had the greatest number of acres under cultivation
                    of any in the vicinity. but they had more intercourse with <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Ethan Allen Brown, one of the brothers, was consecutively Governor
                    of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName>, a Senator in Congress from that State, and a judge of its Supreme
                    Court, during which time his home was, as might be most convenient for himself,
                    at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName> or at the farm just above Rising Sun. The Browns required a larger
                    boat for their own convenience, and as they were very liberal and accommodating
                    people, any respectable neighbor had as free use of it as if it were his own.
                    This boat was made of a large poplar tree and was got out some sixty to
                    sixty-five feet in length as a regular canoe. It was then split in twain
                    lengthwise and widened some four or five feet, by putting in ribs and planking
                    the bottom. This made a boat some seven or eight feet wide, and furnished a
                    carrying capacity of fifteen to twenty tons. Of course such a boat could not be
                    propelled with a man at the bow and another at the stern. Regular walking boards
                    were put on each side, keel-boat fashion, and thus, with setting poles, against
                    one end of which the shoulder was placed, the other being against the bottom of
                    the river, was the boat driven along by men steadily walking and pushing the
                    boat from under them, like a horse walking upon the wheel of a treadmill. This
                    boat was used by <pb n="131" id="VAA4025-004-3-029"/> the Browns for their own
                    needs, and by others who transported the whisky that was made at the little
                    distilleries in the neighborhood of one or two barrels' capacity per
                    day, the farm products, the rags, ginseng, etc., that were taken in exchange for
                    "store goods" by the merchants of that day, and went so
                    frequently that it may be said to have been the first regular packet between
                    Rising Sun and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName>. This large boat, properly manned, would make the voyage to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName> in a day and a half to two days, according to the stage of the
                    river and depth of lading.</p>
            <p>After 1820 steamboats were seen more frequently, but the people rarely shipped or
                    traveled by them. In the first place, there was no certainty as to when the boat
                    might come along. In the next place, there was no certainty that it would take
                    either passengers or cargo when it did come; and in the third place, the voyage
                    could be made by the canoe about as rapidly as by the steamboat, considerably
                    cheaper, and a good deal pleasanter. The average steamboat captain of fifty or
                    sixty years ago seemed to think that profanity, vulgarity and rudeness toward
                    passengers, officers and crew, were as essential to the prosecution of the
                    voyage as was steam. A passenger on one of the slow boats of the day, as it was
                    approaching a place where the current was very rapid, remarked: "There
                    is very strong water just ahead of us, but if there is any virtue in swearing we
                    will be able to stem it." After a hard struggle and much profanity, the
                    boat succeeded in passing the place, when the passenger remarked: "The
                    captain of this boat is about the only man who could swear this boat through
                    that ripple without the aid of rosin." As a specimen of the comparative
                    speed of the steamboats and canoes of that day, it is told of our venerable
                    citizen, Mr. Hathaway, that he had some cargo ready to ship, which a passing
                    boat refused to take on board. He immediately got a pirogue, placed his cargo on
                    board, started after the steamboat, and in good time overtook her, when
                    "they had it nip and tuck," first one ahead and then the other
                    until they came to McCullom's ripple, six miles below <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName>, where Mr. Hathaway, getting the advantage of the gentler current
                    close to the sandbar at that place, got in advance. A favorable breeze springing
                    up at the moment, he spread a <pb n="132" id="VAA4025-004-3-030"/> bed quilt
                    (they always had their own bedding and cooking utensils along) for a sail, and,
                    having been a sailor boy, and knowing how to take advantage of the situation, he
                    beat his competitor to the city wharf an hour or more.</p>
            <p>By slow degrees steamboats inclined to accommodate people along the shore and
                    obtain their business in the way of cargo and passengers. And yet so little
                    reliance could be placed upon them that it was not until after a regular steam
                    packet, the "Dolphin," had been placed in the trade between
                    Rising Sun and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName>, through the enterprise of Colonel P. James, in 1834, that shippers
                    between the two points abandoned the keel and barge boats. When the trade grew
                    so as to require some regularity in means of transportation, AIessrs. Benjamin
                    Bates and George Parker had a light flatboat built expressly and covered with a
                    cargo-box, with which they made regular weekly trips to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Their boat had a mast, and a sail was used when it could be made
                    available. At other times a horse, which they always had with them, with a line
                    attached, was put on the shore and made to pull the boat against the current.
                    Captain Joseph Thompson, than whom there are at the time of writing but very
                    few, if any, older pilots on western waters now living, succeeded Bates and
                    Parker, and did a thriving business for several years. When steam finally drove
                    Captain Thompson out of the trade, he went as pilot with Captain John J. Roe, an
                    old citizen of Rising Sun, who afterward achieved such an enviable reputation
                    and amassed such an immense fortune as a merchant and boat-owner, and the two
                    navigated nearly every navigable stream tributary to the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName>.</p>
            <p>As steamboats more inclined to receive passengers, passengers began to rely upon
                    steamboats instead of taking the canoes or pirogues, or footing it or riding
                    through <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName>, which was frequently done by persons going to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName>. It was by no means a rare occurrence for a party of persons bound
                    for <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName> to divide, one portion taking a steamboat and another at the same
                    time crossing the river and walking to the destination, the walking party being
                    the first to arrive. The following personal experience once occurred. Two
                    persons had decided to go to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName>. When one started across the river in the morning <pb n="133" id="VAA4025-004-3-031"/> to walk through, the other sat down to wait for a
                    boat. The walker was in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName> some time before night. The other waited all day, built a fire on
                    the shore at night and took shelter in an empty flatboat at the landing, and at
                    noon of the second day succeeded in getting on board a steamboat which arrived
                    at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName> some time during that night. Two or three boats had passed up in
                    the meantime but would not stop.</p>
            <p>Old-time steamboatmen used to seem to take a sort of demoniac pleasure in
                    refusing to stop at way places for freight or passengers. They were not content
                    to pass by quietly, but not infrequently, upon being hailed, would yell out some
                    insulting remark to the pitiful creature on shore, who was not only willing to
                    contribute largely to the usually depleted coffers of the boatmen, but was most
                    abject in the presence of the autocrat that controlled the craft. For the sake
                    of being transported the poor passenger would submit to all manner of
                    indignities and impositions. Until a regular steam packet was placed in the
                    trade between Rising Sun and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName>, our people were compelled to pay the most exorbitant prices for
                    freight and passage, and at the same time were furnished with few facilities and
                    very few accommodations. But the times changed. The habits, character and
                    manners of steamboatmen greatly improved. The facilities were largely increased,
                    prices greatly reduced, and accommodations so far superior to those of the olden
                    time as to hardly admit of placing them in the same category.</p>
            <p>Old-time steamboat travel was attended with great danger, There was a
                    carelessness and recklessness, then looked upon as a matter of course, which
                    would not now be tolerated. There was frequent racing, and all considerations of
                    safety were lost in the desire to out-travel a competing boat. There were no
                    laws to regulate the equipments of boats, or require competency on the part of
                    the officers. Any man that an owner chose might go as a captain, engineer or
                    pilot, and once in charge each man was a law unto himself. The frequency of
                    sinkings, burnings and collisions, and the number of lives destroyed was
                    something alarming to all travelers.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="134" id="VAA4025-004-3-032"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-004-3-a04">
            <head>JUDGE ISAAC NAYLOR, 1790–1873.</head>
            <p rend="center">A<hi rend="sc">N</hi> A<hi rend="sc">UTOBIOGRAPHY</hi>.</p>
            <p>[The following autobiographical sketch is contributed by Mr. Morris W. Phillips,
                    of the <hi rend="i">
                  <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Lafayette</settlement>
                        </placeName> Morning Journal</hi>. He found it among Judge Naylor's
                    papers together with the Judge's description of the Battle of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Tippecanoe</region>
                    </placeName>, which was published in this magazine, December, 1906 (Vol. 11, No.
                    4). According to Mrs. Mary Naylor Whiteford, daughter of Judge Naylor, this
                    sketch was written in 1852 for <hi rend="i">Harper's Magazine</hi>, but
                    not published at that time. The introductory and concluding notes are from Mr.
                    Phillips, who, in work upon his lectures on early Indiana history, has become
                    thoroughly familiar with this ground. The article was printed in the <hi rend="i">
                  <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Lafayette</settlement>
                        </placeName> Sunday Leader</hi>, June 24, 1907, and is published here
                    because of its account of early times in this State, and because there is no
                    extended life of Judge Naylor in the various collections of Indiana biography,
                        —E<hi rend="sc">DITOR</hi>.]</p>
            <p>JUDGE NAYLOR was for years circuit judge of the district comprising the counties
                    of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Tippecanoe</region>
                    </placeName>, <placeName>
                        <region type="county">White</region>
                    </placeName>, <placeName>
                  <region type="county">Montgomery</region>, <region type="county">Benton</region>, <region type="county">Jasper</region>
               </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Fountain</region>
                    </placeName>. He was well known all over the State, and respected not only as an
                    able lawyer and judge, but as a student of history, and a veteran of the Indian
                    wars and the War of 1812. He located in 1833 at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Crawfordsville</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Ind., where he remained until his death. on April 26, 1873, and
                    where he is buried in the Masonic cemetery. He was an intimate friend of the
                    late Jonathan W. Gordan, of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, General Lew Wallace, of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Crawfordsville</settlement>
                    </placeName>, and other famous Indianians of his time. The autobiography
                    follows:</p>
            <p>I was born in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Rockingham county</region>
                    </placeName>, in the State of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName>, on the 30th of July, 1790. My parents were born and reared in the
                    same region. In the spring of 1793 my parents emigrated to the State of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName>, and made a short residence in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Bourbon county</region>
                    </placeName>, eight miles from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Paris</settlement>
                    </placeName>, having landed at Limestone, now Maysville, on the same day that
                    General Wayne and his army passed on their way to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Fort Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName>, now <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName>. My memory reaches back to the latter part of this year, and from
                    this period my recollection of facts is clear and vivid.</p>
            <pb n="135" id="VAA4025-004-3-033"/>
            <p>Having lived in the country three years, my father changed his residence to <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Harrison county</region>
                    </placeName> and settled on the Blue Lick fork of <geogName>Licking
                    river</geogName>, twelve miles from Cynthiana, the county seat. Here my father
                    began farming, amid a dense forest of gum, beech, oak and poplar timber. Here I
                    began my physical education at the age of six years. Here I learned to swim, to
                    fish, to paddle and pole the canoe. Here I saw many flatboats passing up and
                    down the river, freighted with the surplus products of the country. Here our
                    neighbors were composed of pioneers, many of whom were hunters and Indian
                    fighters. Our long winter evenings were usually spent in hearing and telling
                    stories of ghosts, of hunting, of Indian skirmishes and Indian campaigns.</p>
            <p>There were no schools in my vicinity until I was nearly ten years old. Having
                    learned to spell at home in three syllables, I was sent to my
                    grandmother's in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Woodford county</region>
                    </placeName>, ten miles from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Lexington</settlement>
                    </placeName>, where I went to school for six months and learned to read and to
                    write a small hand. I then came home and was destined to hard labor on the farm
                    for three years except one month, during which I went to school. I was then sent
                    to the place where my father first located, in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Bourbon county</region>
                    </placeName>, and there I went to school three months, and learned the
                    elementary rules of arithmetic. In the spring of 1805 my father emigrated from <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> and settled in the county of Clarke, Indiana Territory, thirteen
                    miles from the Falls of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName>. Here we commenced making another farm; here in about three years I
                    graduated in the science and art of chopping, rolling and hewing logs and
                    building log cabins. In the meantime I went to the school about four months.
                    Having improved my handwriting, and having learned the principal rules of
                    arithmetic, I became a clerk in a small store which belonged to one of my
                    uncles, a brother of my mother. This was the first store located at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Charlestown</settlement>
                    </placeName>, the county seat of the county of Clarke, Indiana. I mas employed
                    in this store six months, during which time I studied the English grammar under
                    the tuition of the Rev. John Todd. There never was a better man, and to him I
                    owe much gratitude, and to him I am indebted for my present position as jurist.</p>
            <pb n="136" id="VAA4025-004-3-034"/>
            <p>Having acquired a taste for literary studies, and having a strong desire to
                    receive a classical education, by my father's consent I left home to
                    earn the money to accomplish this object. At the age of nineteen I made a
                    contract to work as a hand on a flatboat to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New Orleans</settlement>
                    </placeName>. On the 6th day of January, 1810, in company with my employer and
                    another hand, I crossed the Falls of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> on our voyage to our port of destination, where we arrived on the
                    10th day of the ensuing month of March.</p>
            <p>My employer was a farmer, and after he had sold a large portion of his boatload
                    he returned home. He employed me to sell the residue of his load. Having sold
                    out the residue of the load, I left <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New Orleans</settlement>
                    </placeName> about the 1st of May, and arrived home on the 1st day of June,
                    having received nearly a hundred dollars for my services. In traveling home I
                    passed through many Cheyenne and Chickasaw tribes of Indians. In the journey
                    home I walked about eight hundred miles, swimming across streams, wading through
                    swamps, and sleeping in the open air on the ground. When I arrived home I found
                    a good linguist teaching a school in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Charlestown</settlement>
                    </placeName>, and by the advice of my good friend, Rev. Mr. Todd, I commenced
                    the study of the Latin language under this teacher. His name was Graham. He was
                    an Irishman, and distinguished for his classical learning.</p>
            <p>After reading a few elementary books in Latin, I commenced Ovid's
                    Metamorphosis. Having read a considerable portion of this work during the summer
                    and fall of this year, I found my funds nearly exhausted, and it became
                    necessary that I should procure funds to enable me to prosecute my studies for
                    the ensuing year. Early in the year 1811, I made another contract to work as a
                    hand on a flatboat to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New Orleans</settlement>
                    </placeName>, for the sum of sixty dollars. We commenced our journey in January
                    and arrived at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New Orleans</settlement>
                    </placeName> in February. I received my wages and walked home again. I then read
                    Virgil under Mr. Graham, and continued my Latin studies until September.</p>
            <p>I had resolved when a small boy to accomplish two objects if I had the
                    opportunity to do so. I had determined to go to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New Orleans</settlement>
                    </placeName> on a flatboat, and to go on a campaign against <pb n="137" id="VAA4025-004-3-035"/> the Indians. Having accomplished the former object,
                    I had an opportunity of accomplishing the latter. Indian tribes on the upper <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wabash</region>
                    </placeName> had assumed a hostile attitude under the influence of Tecumseh and
                    his brother, the Prophet. The President of the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> placed under the command of General Harrison the Fourth Regiment of
                    U. S. Infantry, and authorized him to call to his aid such portion of the
                    Indiana militia as he might deem necessary to check the hostile movements of
                    Tecumseh and the Prophet.</p>
            <p>I laid Virgil aside and became a volunteer member of a company of riflemen. On
                    the 12th of September we commenced our march toward <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> and arrived there in about six days, marching 120 miles. We
                    remained there about a week, and then took up the march to a point on the <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wabash</region>
                    </placeName> sixty miles above <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName>, on the east bank of the river, where we erected a stockade fort
                    that we named Fort Harrison, the city of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Terre Haute</settlement>
                    </placeName> now being located three miles below this fort. The name of this
                    fort was given by Colonel Joseph H. Davies, a distinguished lawyer from <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName>, who commanded the dragoons, n-ith the rank of major. Upon this
                    occasion he delivered a beautiful and eloquent speech. He was one of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName>'s most gifted orators. He fell in the Battle of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Tippecanoe</region>
                    </placeName>, gallantly charging the Indians. Peace to his ashes.</p>
            <p>The glorious defense of this fort nine months after it was erected, by Captain Z.
                    Taylor, was the first step in the brilliant military triumph that made him
                    President of the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>.</p>
            <p>The army arrived at the Prophet's Town on the 6th of November, in the
                    evening. We slept on our arms. Two hours before daybreak, on the morning of the
                    7th, the battle commenced. The result is a part of American history. Whilst the
                    leaden messengers of death were doing their fatal deeds in every part of the
                    encampment, I felt a strong mental impression that the God of Battles would
                    preserve my life.</p>
            <p>I mention this fact because many persons who fell in the battle had presentiments
                    of their deaths. Such was the case with a young man who fell at the fire where
                    we both slept. <pb n="138" id="VAA4025-004-3-036"/> Such presentiments belong to
                    the science of the philosophy of our nature. They are facts not to be accounted
                    for by us.</p>
            <p>I returned home late in November and taught school during the winter of 1812, and
                    studied algebra; in the fall of the same year I studied languages. In 1813 and
                    1814, I taught school nine months in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Woodford county</region>
                    </placeName>, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName>, and studied Montesquieu's Spirit of Laws. In the summer
                    of 1814 I taught school in <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Louisville</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="kyu">Ky.</region>
               </placeName>, and boarded at the home of my old friend, Rev. Mr.
                    Todd. During the year of 1816 I was a clerk in the store of John Dauthill, in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Charlestown</settlement>
                    </placeName>. I read this year Dr. Paley's Moral Philosophy and his
                    Natural Theology.</p>
            <p>In the year 1817 I read law in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Gallatin county</region>
                    </placeName>, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName>, six months in the office of Samuel Todd, Esq., who has since been
                    a circuit judge. I am pleased to acknowledge my obligation to this gentleman for
                    his kindness and friendship while I was under his tuition. During the residue of
                    the year I studied law with the Hon. James Scott, one of the first judges of the
                    Supreme Court of Indiana. He was the registrar of the land office at
                    Jef-fersonville, in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clark county</region>
                    </placeName>.</p>
            <p>I was licensed to practice lam by the Supreme Court of Indiana, in October of
                    1818. I resided in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Charlestown</settlement>
                    </placeName> and practiced law in many counties, north and west. The settlements
                    m those counties were new, and having but few roads and no bridges across the
                    streams, I was therefore under necessity of swimming these streams on horseback,
                    whenever too high to be forded. How changed is this country now. In the region
                    of Indiana where I swam these streams, one railroad is completed, and two more
                    are being rapidly constructed. Those works are the enduring monuments of the
                    industry and enterprise of the citizens of Indiana.</p>
            <p>On the 27th day of April, 1826, I was married by Rev. George Bush, now of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New York City</settlement>
                    </placeName>, to Miss Mary Anderson, a daughter of Captain Robert Anderson, a
                    soldier of the Revolution.</p>
            <p>In the spring of 1833 I settled at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Crawfordsville</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Ind., where I have lived since, having a family of daughters and
                    no son to transmit my name to coming generations. All thinking men desire
                    immortality in some form.</p>
            <pb n="139" id="VAA4025-004-3-037"/>
            <p>In December, 1837, I was elected by the Legislature of Indiana the present judge
                    of the first judicial district circuit. In December, 1844, I was re-elected,
                    having been in office fourteen years. By a new constitution I was continued in
                    office until I was superseded by the general election in October. Having a
                    constitution unimpaired, I presided in all the courts in my circuit at every
                    term except in the county of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Benton</region>
                    </placeName>, where there was so little business that I only attended at the
                    fall term. This statement is qualified by the fact that I exchanged courts with
                    another judge twice, he presiding in my circuit and I in his. I mention this
                    fact to show the importance of training the physical as well as the intellectual
                    power of man. There is important truth in the Latin maxim, <hi rend="i">mens
                        sana in corpore sano</hi>.</p>
            <p>When I commenced the practice of law in the spring of 1818 I found the besetting
                    sin of the members of the bar to be intemperance and gambling. About nine-tenths
                    of the members of the bar were slaves and victims to these vices. Many of these
                    men were distinguished by their talents and legal attainments. It is a
                    melancholy reflection to me that almost all these men have gone prematurely to
                    their graves, at a period when their profession and usefulness should have been
                    in its meridian of splendor. I escaped the blighting and destructive influences
                    of these vices by early moral training by religious parents. I am pleased to
                    state the fact that not more than one in twenty of the members of the bar of
                    this circuit is guilty of intemperance or of gambling. The great moral and
                    social reform of the last few years has done a mighty and glorious work among
                    the bar of Indiana.</p>
            <p>This reform is essential with, and necessary to the proper standing and character
                    of this honorable profession. They grow and flourish only in the soil of civil
                    and political liberty. They find no place in the region of despotism; they gave
                    an irresistible impetus to the cause of our glorious Revolution. Twenty-four of
                    the fifty-six immortal signers of the Declaration of Independence were lawyers.
                    How indispensible, therefore, is the obligation of the members of the bar to
                    obey the moral and physical laws of man's nature. The victims of
                    intemperance and gambling <pb n="140" id="VAA4025-004-3-038"/> are the most
                    abject slaves in all God's moral universe. These vices are usually the
                    first steps in the pathway of infamy, and the heralds of the inevitable ruin of
                    their victims.</p>
            <p>As before stated, I had formed in early life two purposes, one to be a merchant
                    and the other to be a classical scholar. I had abandoned the former to
                    accomplish the latter. The latter was defeated by the War of 1812. The war
                    demanded my services in defense of the frontier inhabitants of Indiana, and my
                    own relatives and friends. At the close of the war I was advised to read law and
                    become a member of the legal profession by my very good friend, Mr. Todd. I
                    followed his advice. The result is already stated.</p>
            <p rend="right">I. N<hi rend="sc">AYLOR</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Crawfordsville</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Ind., March 16, 1852.</p>
            <p>The wife of Judge Naylor was a Catharine Anderson, the daughter of Captain
                    Anderson, who was with General Washington at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Valley Forge</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Judge Naylor, at the time of the Pigeon Roost massacre, was a boy
                    working in the field of his frontier home near <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Charlestown</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Ind., and in response to a messenger telling him of the massacre
                    then going on, mounted his horse and rode to the scene rifle in hand, to avenge
                    the death of his neighbors. He also served in the ranks of the American army
                    during the War of 1812. The following children of this famous old Indian fighter
                    still live, and are located as follows: Mrs. Elizabeth Briar, aged seventy-six,
                    Spokane, Wash.; Mrs. Mary Naylor Whiteford, <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Marion</region>
                    </placeName>, Ind., aged seventy-one; Mrs. Catherine Anderson Briar, aged
                    sixty-nine, Oakland, Cal.; and Mrs. Virginia L. Hay, aged sixty-six,
                            <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Evanston</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="ilu">Ill.</region>
               </placeName>
            </p>
         </div>
         <pb n="141" id="VAA4025-004-3-039"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-004-3-a05">
            <head>NORTHERN INDIANA TERRITORY IN 1804.</head>
            <p rend="center">O<hi rend="sc">RIGINAL</hi> D<hi rend="sc">OCUMENT</hi>.</p>
            <p>[For the following petition for the separation from Indiana, and erection into a
                    new territory, of the district north of the present line between Indiana and <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="miu">Michigan</region>
                    </placeName>, we are indebted to Dr. Harlow Lindley, Director of the Department
                    of Archives and History, Indiana State Library. Original printed copies of the
                    Memorial are very rare, and it is often missing in collections of the
                    publications of the early Congress, which are supposed to be complete. Dr.
                    Lindley secured a copy while in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington, D. C.</settlement>
                    </placeName>, this summer. Coming from a section of Indiana which afterward
                    became <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="miu">Michigan</region>
                    </placeName>, the petition is of interest to both States.—E<hi rend="sc">DITOR</hi>.]</p>
            <p rend="center">MEMORIAL<lb/> OF THE<lb/> CITIZENS AND INHABITANTS<lb/> OF THE<lb/>
                    INDIANA TERRITORY<lb/> PRAYING FOR<lb/> THE INTERPOSITION OF CONGRESS<lb/> TO
                    RELIEVE THEM OF<lb/> CERTAIN OPPRESSIONS<lb/> AND<lb/> EMBARRASSMENTS</p>
            <p rend="center">WASHINGTON CITY:<lb/> Printed <hi rend="i">by</hi> William Duane
                    &amp; Son.<lb/> 1804</p>
            <pb n="142" id="VAA4025-004-3-040"/>
            <p>
                    <text>
                  <body>
                     <div type="letter">
                        <head rend="center">MEMORIAL.</head>
                        <salute>
                           <hi rend="i">To the Honorable the Senate, and the Honorable
                                        the House of Representatives of the <placeName>
                                            <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                                        </placeName> of America, in Congress assembled</hi>.</salute>
                        <p>We, the undersigned memorialists, citizens and inhabitants of
                                    that district of the Indiana territory, situate north of an East
                                    and West line, extending through the southerly bend of
                                        <geogName>Lake Michigan</geogName>, humbly pray the speedy
                                    interposition of Congress, in relief of the oppression and
                                    embarrassments under which we at present labor, originating in
                                    local causes, and which your memorialists endeavored to point
                                    out and impress with force, by their petitions, presented to
                                    Congress, at their last session, praying for a separate
                                    territory. Notwithstanding the unhappy fate which those
                                    petitions met with, and the consequent disappointments your
                                    memorialists experienced, on failure of their wishes, yet our
                                    present situation is too distressing to justify our silence upon
                                    a subject of such infinite consequence to the government, to
                                    ourselves, and to our posterity.</p>
                        <p>But one sentiment prevails within this district, upon the
                                    expediency as well as necessity of a separate territory; it is
                                    but too evident, that upon the success of this single measure,
                                    depends the happiness, good order, and prosperity of the
                                    citizens of this district, whilst its failure can not but
                                    produce consequences of a serious and alarming nature, tending
                                    to all the horrors of outlawry, oppression, and anarchy.</p>
                        <p>Impressed with a full belief, that our government are desirous of
                                    increasing the happiness of the citizen, regardless of the
                                    quarter of the union he may inhabit, we are again induced
                                    earnestly to solicit Congress, that our situation may not be
                                    passed over in silence, but that Congress will, at an early
                                    period in the approaching session, take up and reconsider the
                                    prayer of your memorialists, presented at the last session, and
                                    if possible, and consistent with sound policy, grant to your
                                    memorialists a separate, distinct, and independent territory, as
                                    prayed for in said memorial, and for the causes therein named.</p>
                        <p>Did your petitioners conceive it necessary to enumerate new and
                                    additional reasons, shewing the expediency of granting their <pb n="143" id="VAA4025-004-3-041"/> prayers, many might be
                                    adduced. One in particular, we beg leave to state, which shows
                                    forcibly the impossibility of the present government to extend
                                    law to us.</p>
                        <p>From good authority we state, that in the month of September, A.
                                    D. 1803, the legislature of the Indiana territory adopted
                                    several laws, altering, amending and repealing those then in
                                    force, yet those laws, although adopted more than twelve months
                                    past, have never yet been seen in this place, of course have not
                                    come into operation in this district; by stating this fact, we
                                    do not intend to attach any blame or censure upon our governor,
                                    but to demonstrate the impracticability of communicating with
                                    the seat of government.</p>
                        <p>We beg leave further to state, that active measures are now on
                                    foot through the territory, for entering upon the second or
                                    representative grade of government; this step if successful,
                                    will greatly add to the burthens under which we now labor, by an
                                    increase of taxes, without any possible chance of sharing a
                                    proportional degree of benefit.</p>
                        <p>Your petitioners, therefore, do again renew their prayer, that
                                    Congress will erect into a separate territory, that district of
                                    land north of the above mentioned line, and grant your
                                    petitioners a government, similar to the one contemplated by the
                                    ordinance of Congress of 1787, for the organization and
                                    government of the late North West territory.</p>
                        <closer>
                                    <salute>And as in duty bound, will ever <placeName>
                                            <settlement type="city">Detroit</settlement>
                                        </placeName>, 24th October, 1804. Pray.</salute>
                                    <signed rend="right">J<hi rend="sc">AMES</hi> M<hi rend="sc">AY</hi>, <hi rend="sc">AND</hi> O<hi rend="sc">THERS</hi>.</signed>
                                </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </text>
                </p>
         </div>
         <pb n="[144]" id="VAA4025-004-3-042"/>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-004-3-a06">
            <head>EDITORIAL.</head>
            <p>The next annual meeting of the American Historical Association will begin at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Monday, December 28, and will continue at <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="vau">Va.</region>
               </placeName>, from December 29 to Thursday, the 31st. There
                    will doubtless be a large representation from Indiana, attracted both by the
                    unusual interest of the program and the surroundings and by the prospect of
                    getting the 1910 meeting at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>. So far as arranged the program is as follows: Monday evening,
                    December 28, the Honorable James Bryce, president of the American Political
                    Science Association, will address this body and the Historical Association.
                    Tuesday morning the Historical Association will hold a separate session, and
                    Tuesday afternoon those in attendance will be taken by a special train to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName>. In the evening Professor George B. Adams, president of the
                    American Historical Association, will deliver his inaugural address. On
                    Wednesday there will be conferences on the Relation of Geography to History and
                    on the Teaching of History in Secondary Schools, and a general session devoted
                    to papers in European history. Thursday there will be the conference of State
                    and Local Historical Societies, and round-table conferences on English History,
                    American Colonial and Revolutionary history and on Southern history. The
                    Thursday evening session will be addressed by General E. P. Alexander, C. S. A.,
                    and others upon the campaigns of the Civil War in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName>. Between sessions short excursions will run to the battlefields of
                    Petersburg, Seven Pines and Yellow Tavern. After the close of the meeting, on
                    Friday, January 1, there will be an excursion to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Charlottesville</settlement>
                    </placeName> and the University of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName>.</p>
            <p>This meeting will be of great interest to college professors, <pb n="145" id="VAA4025-004-3-043"/> teachers of history in high schools, and to all
                    others as well who are readers of historical works, whether professional
                    historians or not. The trip will be a very convenient one to take from most
                    parts of the State. It may be possible for a large number to go together from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>. All who expect to go, whether from this city or not, are requested
                    to send a card to that effect to the editor, stating so far as possible their
                    plans and desires as to time of departure, route and Indiana headquarters. All
                    who are interested are urged to send in suggestions. Full information will be
                    published in the December number of the Quarterly.</p>
            <p>In our last number, in an editorial under the title Historical Societies, a short
                    account of various societies was given and suggestions were made concerning some
                    possible activities which lay before societies in Indiana. Among the responses
                    received was one which embodied the plan of securing, through the organizations
                    perpetuating the memory of Revolutionary ancestors, a record of the movements of
                    these families, showing date of immigration into this State, location here and
                    other items of value in throwing light upon the populating of the State. This
                    should be feasible and, indeed, steps are being taken in this direction. The
                    development of these and other plans should and doubtless will be carried out by
                    the proper agencies. In this number of the magazine it may be of interest to
                    sketch briefly the work of historical organizations in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="wiu">Wisconsin</region>
                    </placeName>, which in cooperative historical work stands at the head of all our
                    neighboring States. It is not our purpose to show how this preeminence was
                    attained, but to describe briefly the agencies and organizations now at work
                    there. It must, however, be recognized that most of the work is due to the
                    exceptional talents, scholarship and application of the first secretary and
                    superintendent of the State Historical Society of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="wiu">Wisconsin</region>
                    </placeName>, Lyman C. Draper, and his present successor, Reuben G. Thwaites.</p>
            <p>The parent and central organization in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="wiu">Wisconsin</region>
                    </placeName> is the State Historical Society. This is supported by the State at
                    a cost of thousands of dollars annually. It enjoys the possession of a
                    magnificent $600,000 building which houses not only its own museum,
                        <pb n="146" id="VAA4025-004-3-044"/> portrait gallery and library, but the
                    library of the State University and several allied societies. It has an employed
                    secretary, librarian and assistants. Its library is practically the State
                    Library. The management is vested in a board of thirty-six curators chosen for a
                    period of three years, who together with the secretary, librarian, Governor of
                    the commonwealth, Secretary of State and State Treasurer, constitute the
                    executive committee of the society. Local societies in the State are
                    incorporated under the State laws and form auxiliary societies, their members
                    thus becoming auxiliary members of the State Society. The membership of the
                    latter includes, also, life, annual, honorary, corresponding and ex-officio
                    members. The first two classes are open to practically all citizens of the State
                    upon payment of a fee of twenty and of two dollars respectively.</p>
            <p>The work of the State Historical Society of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="wiu">Wisconsin</region>
                    </placeName> may be summed up under the three-fold activity of collecting
                    historical material and books, publications, and meetings.</p>
            <p>Lyman Draper's remarkable It-ork as a collector of historical material
                    has been well followed up. In the first year of his employment by the State
                    Historical Society he secured a thousand volumes and a thousand pamphlets and
                    documents, and in thirty-three years of service he built up a reference library,
                    chiefly of historical publications, of 118,000 books and pamphlets. In 1907 the
                    library contained nearly 300,000 titles. Among the great collections are to be
                    enumerated that of the principal newspapers of the State, and the country at
                    large (said to be the largest outside of the Library of Congress), the
                    department of maps and manuscripts "unexampled in the field of the
                    Middle West and South," tile collection of public documents, the
                    genealogical collection. one of the three or four largest in the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>, and the collation of local American histories.</p>
            <p>The publications of the society, as given in the bulletins of information include
                    public addresses, the well known <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="wiu">Wisconsin</region>
                    </placeName> Historical Collections, library catalogues and lists, reports and
                    proceedings, etc. Unlike most similar organizations, no magazine is published.
                    Instead, bulletins of information are issued from time to time. It is not too
                    much to say that these publications, constituting a small-sized library by
                    themselves, are among <pb n="147" id="VAA4025-004-3-045"/> the most important
                    contributions of the last generation to American history.</p>
            <p>The meetings of the society are held annually and occasionally are combined with
                    State historical conventions held at different cities of the State. Important
                    papers by members and outsiders are read at these meetings. The proceedings of
                    the last meeting. November 7, 1907, at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName>, now published, gives the reports of officers, of nine auxiliary
                    (local) societies, all showing healthy activity, and an interesting-collection
                    of the papers read by Reuben G. Thwaites and others at the meeting. A new
                    activity is favorably reported upon, namely sending out lecturers upon
                    historical subjects to speak wherever local or general interest can be served by
                    such a visit. Numerous other means are resorted to in increasing popular
                    interest and support, such as inspiring historical articles in local newspapers
                    and sending out suggestions to local historians. All in all, the report of the
                    last year's work makes a very impressive recital.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-004-3-a07">
            <head>NOTES.</head>
            <p>A bronze bust of Judge Stephen Neal, of <placeName>
                        <country reg="le">Lebanon</country>
                    </placeName>, was presented on July 10 to the Indiana State Library. Judge Neal
                    was one of the well known jurists of the State and attained a national
                    reputation by drafting the fourteenth amendment to the Constitution of the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> which was presented in Congress by Godlove S. Orth from his
                    district. The bust is one of three designed and executed by Miss Clara Barth
                    Leonard, one of which was given to the <placeName>
                        <country reg="le">Lebanon</country>
                    </placeName> Library and another retained by the donor, Mr. C. F. S. Neal, son
                    of Judge Neal. Miss Leonard worked from photographs and the death mask, and had,
                    also, the benefit of the suggestions and criticisms of the late Louis Gibson, a
                    life-long friend of Judge Neal. The presentation was made by Union B. Hunt, on
                    behalf of Mr. Neal, and the gift was accepted by Demarchus C. Brown, State
                    Librarian, on behalf of the State.</p>
            <p>The <geogName>Ohio Valley</geogName> Historical Association will hold its second
                    annual meeting during the Thanksgiving season of this year. <pb n="148" id="VAA4025-004-3-046"/> Mr. E. A. Randall is president and G. L. Martzolff
                    corresponding secretary of this organization.</p>
            <p>Professor Walter C. Fleming has resigned the position of secretary of the
                    Conference of State and Local Historical Societies, which is to be held at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName> in connection with the next meeting of the American Historical
                    Association at the close of this year. Professor St. George L. Sioussat will
                    take his place.</p>
            <p>The committee of seven appointed at the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName> meeting of the American Historical Association, Dr. Dunbar Rowland,
                    chairman, to arrange for cooperation of the various States, especially in the
                        <geogName>Mississippi Valley</geogName>, in securing transcripts from
                    foreign archives, held a meeting at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> April 16, and. among other things recommends that historical
                    societies, so far as possible, refrain from work of this sort until carefully
                    prepared general lists can be made by joint effort.</p>
            <p>The <geogName>Mississippi Valley</geogName> Historical Association held its first
                    meeting at <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Lake Minnetonka</settlement>,
                            <region type="state" reg="mnu">Minnesota</region>
               </placeName>, June
                    22–23. Professor Clarence W. Alvord, of the University of, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ilu">Illinois</region>
                    </placeName>, was elected president for 1908-'09. State Librarian
                    Demarchus C. Brown attended from Indiana.</p>
            <p rend="center">LOCAL HISTORICAL SOCIETIES.</p>
            <p>The <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Monroe County</region>
                    </placeName> Historical Society is to have a separate room in the new
                    court-house, given for its use and furnished by order of the county
                    commissioners. Interest in the society is reported as constantly increasing. At
                    the last regular meeting, announced for June 26, Mr. Dudley F. Smith read a
                    paper upon The Old-Time Roads and the Old-Time Farming.</p>
            <p rend="center">ACTIVITIES OF STATE HISTORICAL SOCIETIES.</p>
            <p>The <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="oru">Oregon</region>
                    </placeName> Historical Society is planning a series of leaflets on different
                    phases of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="oru">Oregon</region>
                    </placeName> history to be supplied to the pupils of the common schools of the
                    State.</p>
            <p>The <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="oku">Oklahoma</region>
                    </placeName> Historical Society is to have a $25,000 addition to the
                    Carnegie Library at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Oklahoma City</settlement>
                    </placeName> for its exclusive use.</p>
            <p>The <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName> Historical Society has incorporated, May 1, <pb n="149" id="VAA4025-004-3-047"/> 1908, the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName> Association of History Teachers as an auxiliary and is printing the
                    papers of the latter for distribution.</p>
            <p>The <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="nbu">Nebraska</region>
                    </placeName> State Historical Society has obtained an appropriation from the
                    State for a building which is to be devoted to its use.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-004-3-a08">
            <head>REVIEWS OF BOOKS.</head>
            <head>INDIANA BAPTIST HISTORY.</head>
            <p>In "Indiana Baptist History, 1798–1908," Professor
                    William T. Stott offers a desirable contribution to a field wherein we have
                    little and need more. A book or two on Presbyterianism, two or three touching
                    Methodism, a brochure on Congregationalism and this work on the Baptist church
                    virtually comprise what we have; and yet the religious movements within a
                    commonwealth are an integral and very important part of its history,
                    representing, as they do, beliefs that operate through every stratum of society,
                    and which are no small factor in determining the character of the people.
                    Whatever one may think of the merits or absurdities of the diverse dogmas held
                    by the several sects, it is a matter of deep sociologic interest that the church
                    organizations and the conflicts whereby they are strengthened, present in their
                    histories the sterling virtues of righteous ideals, zeal, self-sacrifice and
                    sturdiness to a degree hardly paralleled in any other human activity. An
                    institution that fosters these things surely bears an all-important part in the
                    development of a community, and so, be it repeated, records in this field afford
                    desirable data.</p>
            <p>Professor Stott, for thirty-three years president of Franklin College, the
                    leading Baptist school of the State, was preeminently the man to have written
                    this book. No one, perhaps, could have had access to more material, though,
                    unfortunately, the records of many of the earlier churches are lost beyond all
                    finding. More first-hand information might hale been desired, but nevertheless
                    Mr. Stott has brought within his 374 pages much that will be new to the reader.</p>
            <p>The establishment of the Baptist church in Indiana antedates all others, except
                    the Catholic. The first organization dates <pb n="150" id="VAA4025-004-3-048"/>
                    back to 1798, when four persons, John and Sophia Fisher and John and Cattern
                    Pettet, formed themselves into a church, meeting on Owen's creek and
                    Silver creek, in what is now <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clark county</region>
                    </placeName>. The Baptist churches early attained to an important place, and in
                    many localities they were on the ground and flourishing when the Presbyterian
                    and Methodist denominations made their appearance. In some places, however,
                    these rural Baptist churches were supplanted by other denominations, and the
                    causes of this decadence are attributed by some to the refusal of such churches
                    to "grow" with the general progress of opinion.</p>
            <p>By 1809 two district associations were organized; by 1825 these had grown to
                    eleven, with more than seventy-five churches, estimating those included at dates
                    of organizations. A list of the preachers and laymen who were prominent in these
                    early churches includes many men of force and ability who played their part in
                    the making of the State—the Holmans, Jesse L. and William H., Milton
                    Stapp, the Stotts, the Vawters, Isaac McCoy, and others; and the numerous
                    biographical sketches which form a conspicuous part of 31r. Stott's
                    book are, in many instances, not only interesting studies in character, hut also
                    throw light upon the times. They reveal various virtues and shortcomings of
                    those days—sturdiness, zeal and heroism on the one hand, and on the
                    other a narrowness and intolerance of opinion that seems insufferable at the
                    present day. Judged charitably, these opinions, of course, then had all the
                    sanctity of high truth, and the unyielding tenacity with which they were held
                    was one evidence of the virtues.</p>
            <p>"Indiana Baptist History" is published by the author, 1908, and
                    copies may be had by addressing William T. Stott, superintendent
                    Soldiers' and Sailors' Orphans' Home, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Knightstown</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Ind.</p>
            <byline>G<hi rend="sc">EORGE</hi> S. C<hi rend="sc">OTTMAN</hi>.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-004-3-a09">
            <head>HISTORY OF MICHIGAN CITY.</head>
            <head>[By Rollo B. Oglesbee and Albert Hale. Illustrated by Albert J. Widdell.
                    1908.]</head>
            <p>The preservation of local history is finding some advocates in different parts of
                    the State. This work and the following <pb n="151" id="VAA4025-004-3-049"/>
                    mentioned give evidence of this fact. The authors have been engaged in their
                    professions but have taken time for this public service. Is it not a public
                    service to preserve the historical facts of a community?</p>
            <p>The "History of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Michigan City</settlement>
                    </placeName>" was begun by Mr. Oglesbee in 1905, but in 1907, finding
                    it impossible on account of pressing business duties to complete the work alone,
                    he called on Albert Hale, a friend, with whose aid it has been finished this
                    year. It is with great regret that we have to chronicle almost at the same time,
                    the appearance of this work and the death of its principal author. In his death,
                    which occurred about a month ago, the historical as well as the official circles
                    of the State (Mr. Oglesbee was at the time at the head of the bank department of
                    the State Auditor's office) have suffered loss.</p>
            <p>Mr. Oglesbee has given much time and space to the early struggles in the
                    Northwest Territory long before <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Michigan City</settlement>
                    </placeName> was thought of. This part of the story is by no means new, but it
                    is the best feature of the volume. Mr. Oglesbee contends that the first purchase
                    of land for the city was in November, 1830, instead of September, 1833, as was
                    maintained by others.</p>
            <p>The discussion of the Michigan Road takes up a chapter of considerable interest.
                    The Railroads, Public Improvements and the Indiana Prison are given separate
                    chapters. The last mentioned chapter is a valuable contribution. It is
                    appreciative of the growth of this institution into a modern, well-conducted
                    establishment belonging to all the people of the commonwealth.</p>
            <p>The closing chapters—except the one on the Prison—have been
                    hurriedly written and edited. One chapter is devoted to a private corporation.
                    This is a part of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Michigan City</settlement>
                    </placeName>, it is true, but it resembles advertising, and therefore lessens
                    the value of the book as history.</p>
            <p>The space given to "Schools, Libraries, Churches, Cemeteries, and
                    Parks" amounts to one chapter of ten pages. Mr. Oglesbee himself
                    thought this entirely too insignificant—and rightly—but
                    was forced to yield. The absence of a table of contents and index is a serious
                    oversight.</p>
            <p>Mr. Oglesbee deserves great credit for collecting the facts <pb n="152" id="VAA4025-004-3-050"/> about <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Michigan City</settlement>
                    </placeName>. It is hoped that he may have successors in Indiana.</p>
            <byline>D<hi rend="sc">EMARCHUS</hi> C. B<hi rend="sc">ROWN</hi>.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-004-3-a10">
            <head>A TWENTIETH CENTURY HISTORY OF MARSHALL COUNTY, INDIANA.</head>
            <head>[By Daniel McDonald. Illustrated. Two volumes, $18. Lewis
                    Publishing Co., <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                    </placeName>.]</head>
            <p>Mr. McDonald is the gentleman who, as a member of the Indiana State Senate,
                    secured the passage of a bill to commemorate the removal of the Pottawattomies,
                    and especially to cherish the record of the old chief Menominee. It can readily
                    be understood, therefore, that he writes with interest and some authority about
                    the early history of the northern part of Indiana, and in particular <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Marshall county</region>
                    </placeName>.</p>
            <p>Now that the Indian is a vanishing race, the necessity of recording the life and
                    customs of these people becomes manifest to all, and Mr. McDonald is a leader in
                    perpetuating the good work.</p>
            <p>The prehistoric features, mound builders, and buffaloes, for instance, are not
                    neglected. A large part of the first volume is taken up with the movements of
                    the population and the organization of the county in 1836.</p>
            <p>The main point in the histories of Indiana counties at present is the
                    preservation of the facts. Much will be lost in manuscripts, letters and
                    newspapers unless men like Mr. McDonald collect and preserve them. The writing
                    of a scientific history will come later on. However, Mr. McDonald shows
                    considerable skill in the arrangement of this material and gives the various
                    sections their proportionate value. This is a difficult thing because of local
                    pressure to be represented in the history.</p>
            <p>The second volume contains the biographies of the well-known and older
                    inhabitants of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Marshall county</region>
                    </placeName>, with portraits. It is in this part that local and personal
                    pressure may be put upon an author. Mr. McDonald has done this fairly well, but
                    not so well as the earlier history. One gets the impression that the history has
                    been a work of love and not profit. There is a good table of contents and index.</p>
            <byline>D<hi rend="sc">EMARCHUS</hi> C. B<hi rend="sc">ROWN</hi>.</byline>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>