<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "imh_issue.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="VAA4025-006-1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Indiana Magazine of History</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoded by</resp>
               <name>Aptara Inc.</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <date>2007</date>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>Copyright 2007 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
               <p>Indiana University provides the information contained in this file for non-commercial,
        personal, or research use only. All other use, including but not limited to commercial or
        scholarly reproductions, redistribution, publication or transmission, whether by electronic
        means or otherwise, without prior written permission of the copyright holder is strictly
        prohibited.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Indiana Magazine of History</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title>Indiana Magazine of History</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Indianapolis, IN</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Published Under the Direction of the Indiana Historical Society</publisher>
                     <date>1910</date>
                     <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="volume">6</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="pages">1-61</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06-21</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Natalie E. Whitted</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Changed pubPlace and publisher. Removed unneeded block quotes from editorial notes at beginning of
                    articles. Removed redundant numbering from ordered list. Revised bibliography list in a04: created
                    nested simple lists to better represent printed text and corrected discrepancies (item breaks
                    located at wrong points in text). Changed list type in a05 from type bibliography to simple and
                    corrected mistakes in placement of item tags. Changed article (newspaper index - a05) from
                    editorialMaterial to scholarlyArticle and created independent header..</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n="[]" id="VAA4025-006-1-001"/>
         <pb n="[]" id="VAA4025-006-1-002"/>
         <pb n="[]" id="VAA4025-006-1-003"/>
         <pb n="iv" id="VAA4025-006-1-004"/>
      </front>
      <body>
         <pb n="1" id="VAA4025-006-1-005"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-006-1-a01">
            <head>DIVORCE IN <placeName>
                        <region type="county">MARION COUNTY</region>
                    </placeName>.</head>
            <byline>
                    <hi rend="i">BY WILLIAM S. GARBER, Official Reporter in the <placeName>
                            <region type="county">Marion County</region>
                        </placeName> Courts.</hi>
                </byline>
            <p>[A paper prepared in 1908 for the Century Club of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> and the <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Marion County</region>
                    </placeName> Bar Association.]</p>
            <p>THE increase of divorce in the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> generally seems to have taken place, not through increased laxity of courts or greater
                    liberality of the laws, but quite the reverse. Locally this increase is taking place in spite of
                    vigorous legislative and judicial efforts to prevent the granting of decrees on insufficient grounds
                    and insufficient proof. Lawyers who have been in the practice for a few years can remember the time
                    when a decree of divorce went as a matter of course in every case where the defendant did not appear
                    and oppose it, and then as now that was exceptional. Proof of residence and the applicant's
                    oath to facts constituting a statutory cause, the defendant not appearing, was all that was
                    necessary.</p>
            <p>Down to 1873 the law provided that action for divorce might be maintained by any <hi rend="i">bona
                        fide</hi> resident of the State and county wherein the action was brought, without any
                    requirement as to the time they should have been such <hi rend="i">bona fide</hi> resident; and,
                    after specifying various causes of divorce, the "seventh" was: "And any
                    other cause for which the court shall deem it proper that a divorce should be granted."
                    This practically made divorce obtainable whenever the parties agreed to separate, and opened the
                    courts of Indiana to all the dissatisfied couples in the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>; and yet even under these conditions, and the difference in population considered,
                    there were, compared with the number we have to-day, few divorce cases. This fact deserves to be <pb n="2" id="VAA4025-006-1-006"/> emphasized, as it proves conclusively that the trouble is not in
                    the law, nor in its administration; since the conditions under an infinitely worse law than we have
                    at present were infinitely better.</p>
            <p>I have listened to the evidence in more than five hundred divorce cases in a period of four years,
                    and possibly have some knowledge on the subject that has not come to others. The evidence in these
                    cases, while recorded, is in this county scarcely ever written out from the shorthand notes; and
                    hence the facts brought out at such trials are only to a very limited extent accessible to those who
                    are studying the question. Much of the evidence is heard only by the parties concerned, the judges
                    who try the cases and the official reporters.</p>
            <p>Until 1904 it was not the custom in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Marion county</region>
                    </placeName> to have the evidence in divorce cases taken down stenographically. It was, however,
                    found that parties whose applications failed in one court, profiting by the experience and knowledge
                    gained at that hearing, would file another petition in one of the other four courts of the county
                    having jurisdiction of such matters, alleging totally different grounds, and when the same came to
                    trial, swearing to a totally different and frequently inconsistent state of facts. To protect
                    themselves against this fraud the judges of the superior and circuit courts ordered the eviaence in
                    all divorce cases to be reported. Within the first year the testimony in a half-dozen cases was
                    written out and referred to the grand jury, and effort made to secure the indictment of the parties
                    for perjury. I do not remember that any indictments were returned. I am pretty certain no
                    convictions were ever secured. But the object sought was attained, and, while reckless swearing is
                    still more common in this class of litigation than in any other, there is a great deal less of it
                    than formerly, and the parties are at least careful not to run too great risk of criminal
                    prosecution. When cases involving the same parties are brought a second time, they are now almost
                    invariably filed in the same court that tried the previous case, with such explanation as the
                    circumstances permit.</p>
            <p>The <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> government was engaged for a year or two collecting divorce statistics from all over
                    the country, to be used in the framing of a uniform divorce law to apply all over the <pb n="3" id="VAA4025-006-1-007"/>
                    <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>. For two months ten employes of the Census Bureau at <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="wau">Washington</region>
                    </placeName> were engaged at the court-house in this city going over the papers in divorce cases on
                    file in the clerk's office. They went back as far as the year 1886 and brought their
                    figures down to date. They took the complaints and classified them, according to the causes alleged,
                    and made up a table. Beyond showing the growth of the evil and the ratio of increase to population
                    and marriages, the information thus obtained was not very valuable. Certainly no deductions can be
                    drawn from the classification of causes as set forth in the complaints. Though the complaints are
                    all required to be sworn to by the parties filing them, they seldom state the cause of the domestic
                    unhappiness that has resulted in the application. Indeed, they not infrequently fail to state even
                    the true basis of the application in a legal sense. The real reason why either of the mismated
                    couple desires a separation may not constitute a legal reason. Then a reason that the law recognizes
                    is sought until found. As the statute recognizes several legal grounds for divorce, the real one is
                    often passed over in silence and another is brought forward that will involve less scandal, perhaps,
                    or that possibly will not be fought so vigorously by the defendant. "The statutory grounds
                    alleged are simply the methods whereby the parties comply with the law regulating their
                    separation." For these reasons I say the statistics obtained by the government do not seem
                    to me to be very valuable. They enable us to form some idea of the size of the evil, as it has been
                    found that one marriage in ten ends in divorce, that in some States the ratio is as great as one to
                    five, and that there are more divorces in the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> than in all the rest of the Christian world; but they furnish very little aid in
                    dealing with the question of cause or remedy. That can be gained only by the study of the testimony
                    and evidence in the cases.</p>
            <p>The prevalence of divorce is a condition which can not be much bettered by enacting more stringent
                    divorce laws, or making divorce more difficult. Such a course is merely dealing with the symptoms
                    instead of the disease. It is coming at the proposition from the wrong end. If the divorce evil is
                    to be cured, the cause thereof must be foubd with sufficient definiteness to permit <pb n="4" id="VAA4025-006-1-008"/> the application of a remedy, and that remedy must be sought, found and
                    applied before the unhappy parties have consulted attorneys to know what particular provision of the
                    statute makes for their relief, and before the courts are invoked to grant it. For when this stage
                    has been reached it does not make much difference whether the actual divorce is accorded them by a
                    decree of the court, or whether its issuance is prevented by the strictness of the trial judge or
                    the vigilance of the prosecuting attorney who appears in court to oppose the application where the
                    defendant does not, and where the case would otherwise go by default. The mischief to the community,
                    to the children if there are any, is already done. The number of applications filed is the
                    significant number—not the number of decrees granted.</p>
            <p>The theory, heretofore not much more than a theory, which legislators and courts are now making more
                    a matter of practice, is that there are three parties to every divorce suit, the plaintiff, the
                    defendant and the State. It is in following out this theory that the State has provided that the
                    prosecuting attorney shall appear in person, or by deputy, in every case where the defendant is not
                    otherwise represented. Some fraudulent cases, and cases that are brought by collusion, are detected
                    in this way, and the total number of decrees granted rendered somewhat smaller, and to this extent
                    the community is served; but are the conditions behind the application bettered any by the refusal
                    of applications which the prosecutor defeats?</p>
            <p>But the difficulties intended to be thrown in the way of easy divorce by this statute are sometimes
                    overcome by collusion of attorneys who make a specialty of this practice. For illustration: A and B,
                    divorce lawyers, each file a petition. They do not want the prosecuting attorney making trouble; so
                    B enters appearance for the defendant in A's case, and A does the same in B's
                    case; then there is no occasion for the prosecuting attorney to mix in, and everything is lovely. As
                    a precaution against the practice, the judges now, when they think the circumstances justify it,
                    require written authority from attorneys claiming to represent defendants. By the operation of this
                    statute the scandal involved in a large and increasing number of divorces granted is somewhat
                    lessened, and the parties whose applications are refused are <pb n="5" id="VAA4025-006-1-009"/> thus
                    prevented from marrying again, and again bothering the divorce court for a separation; and this is
                    about the most that can be said for it.</p>
            <p>My observation, as I have said, has been entirely local, but so far as this community is
                    concerned—and I know of no reason why what is true of this community should not be true
                    generally of any commercial or industrial center—I think I am justified in saying that
                    the great increase in the number of applications for divorce comes from the working classes, the
                    poorer people, and that divorces are largely due to financial difficulties; though a very
                    considerable portion of the increase must be attributed to the presence of a large and growing
                    colored population. I do not believe that the number of divorces among those fairly well-to-do in
                    this county has increased very much beyond what would be accounted for by the increase in the
                    population. It is not to be inferred from this fact that the poorer people are any less moral than
                    the well-to-do. It is because they are subject to greater temptations and greater trials. Domestic
                    conditions that are tolerable and bearable in the homes of the prosperous become intolerable and
                    unbearable when there are added the difficulties, privations and disputes that are inseparable from
                    a limited or insufficient income. Shortcomings in either husband or wife that would be overlooked,
                    or only the occasion of mometary irritation, in prosperous households, become causes of serious
                    disagreement in families where from smallness of income or lack of thrift in handling what would
                    otherwise be sufficient, want is always present</p>
            <p>Of course, people who talk too much make a deal of trouble everywhere, and naturally, perhaps, more
                    between husband and wife than elsewhere, but, aside from this general fact, parties to divorce
                    proceedings are frequently so exceedingly and mendaciously garrulous as to suggest that there may be
                    some relation between the inability to get along in the married relation and the sh'allow
                    mentality that is so often accompanied by fluency of speech and extraordinary proficiency in the use
                    of adjectives and epithets. Parties to divorce suits are as a rule more voluble than any other class
                    of litigants. It is almost characteristic. As a rule those who talk a great deal do not consider
                    what they <pb n="6" id="VAA4025-006-1-010"/> say. Often the tongues of these people run faster than
                    their minds; they say things without realizing the force and meaning of their words, and even say
                    things without realizing that they are saying them. I have been called upon to read answers in court
                    that, although not three minutes had elapsed since given, were a surprise to the witness that made
                    them, and it was a genuine surprise, not a simulated one. The witness was simply unconscious of
                    having made such a statement a few moments before. A tongtie working independently like that can
                    make a heap of trouble anywhere, and especially in the family; and it is a question if quite B
                    number of divorce cases can not be traced to this sort of a weakness in one or the other of the
                    contracting parties. Most of us more readily forgive actual wrongs than hard things said to or about
                    us. A man may wrong us, for his own advantage, perhaps, and not dislike us at all, and our pride is
                    not hurt—and we forget and forgive, some easier than others, but almost everybody
                    eventually—but once let him tell us "what he thinks of us," of our want
                    of sense, his opinion of our conduct, or our disposition, and we are likely to remember it for all
                    time; it rankles and festers. But this probably was always so, and it does not bear on the question
                    of the increase in the number of divorce suits, except in so far as it is possible that our modern
                    mode of life develops more of this kind of people.</p>
            <p>One cause for the great increase in the number of divorces in this and other States is to be found in
                    the changed conditions that now surround the men and women who have joined their lives together,
                    supposedly for better or worse, rather than in any difference in the mefi and women themselves.
                    Human nature has not changed materially. At least it has not changed for the worse. Perhaps among
                    native Americans there is a little less thrift than formerly, and that fact is important and
                    deserves serious consideration, for divorces are most frequent among the improvident. But the
                    marriage bond is not more lightly regarded, except as the general tendency toward liberality in
                    thought on all religious or semi-religious subjects has led almost everybody to regard as of less
                    importance the forms and ceremonies of religion. But the marriage bond is subjected to strams now
                    that it <pb n="7" id="VAA4025-006-1-011"/> was not formerly, and therefore proves insufficient in
                    many cases nowadays where it would have held in the olden times.</p>
            <p>In what, then, are present-day conditions different from those of a generation or two ago? And which
                    sex do those conditions most effect? Those are the questions which lie at the root of the divorce
                    trouble. Formerly a woman was dependent upon her father and brothers until sorfie man assumed the
                    burden of her support. Since many women are now financially independent before marriage, they are
                    not of necessity dependent on their husbands for support after marriage, and will not longer accept
                    the conditions of life meekly endured by their mothers. And some husbands, clinging to the old idea,
                    resent this latter-day independence on the part of their wives, and here we have another source of
                    domestic discord.</p>
            <p>But, speaking now more particularly with reference to the working people, this increasing
                    independence of woman, the place she has taken among wage-earners in commercial houses and
                    factories, the rapid growth of artificial wants of all kinds, and the establishment and development
                    of what are known as instalment houses and chattel mortgage loan companies to satisfy those wants
                    before the money is earned that would warrant their gratification, are among the prime causes of so
                    much domestic unhappiness, disagreement and finally divorce.</p>
            <p>While I have no exact figures on the subject, I do not think it is an exaggeration to say that in
                    ninety-five out of a hundred cases the trouble begins about money. Probably before marriage the wife
                    has been working in a store, laundry, factory or domestic service, and has been making from four to
                    ten dollars a week, living at home or at the place of service, paying nominal or no board, and
                    having the bulk of her wages to spend on dress and pleasure. Many of these girls marry to escape the
                    stigma that is supposed to attach to house service, or the grind of the shop and factory. The
                    husband before marriage earned possibly from nine to eighteen dollars a week, and spent most of it
                    on himself. They have married without any adequate realization of how much each must give up of what
                    they formerly enjoyed, although, so far as that is concerned, I doubt if the children of other
                    generations had a very much greater realization, <pb n="8" id="VAA4025-006-1-012"/> at the time of
                    entering the marriage relation, that their life henceforth must be one largely of self-denial, each
                    for the other and both for the children. Generally the first step taken by the newly married is to
                    rent two or three rooms, or a cottage, and the second is to visit an instalment house. The
                    habitation is furnished through this agency. The young couple pprchase everything that a polite and
                    resourceful salesman can, suggest. They ought to have this; it would be nice to have that. Their
                    purchases are not determined by the amount of money in hand, or an intelligent estimate of
                    prospective income. It is not what can we do with, or what can we get along without, but what it is
                    convenient to have, what it would be nice to have, what their friends have. It is so easy to buy
                    when no money is required. There is no temptation to reckless extravagance more alluring or
                    insidious than the salesman's calculation that the weekly or monthly instalments on the
                    whole bill will only amount to twenty-six or thirty-three cents a day. The young couple never think
                    of the persistent regularity of the drain on resources, of the entire absence of elasticity in the
                    arrangement, that it takes no account of a lay-off, of sickness, death, or any of the other
                    inexorable demands on the family purse.</p>
            <p>A lease is executed providing for the payment of the stipulated amount at agreed-upon intervals, and
                    providing that the title to the furniture and furnishings shall remain in the instalment house
                    proprietor until the whole amount shall have been paid, and further providing that on default of any
                    payment the instalment house man may enter and remove his property. Here is the starting point of
                    domestic trouble in many cases. It is soon discovered that the weekly instalments to be paid, no
                    matter what goes unpaid, are very much more burdensome than it was supposed, in the rosy dawn of the
                    honeymoon, they would be. When they are added to the rent and daily household expenses the sum
                    equals or exceeds the husband's earnings. His wages are anticipated, and every Saturday
                    night there is a shortage, instead of something to lay by for sickness, childbirth or the proverbial
                    rainy day, in whatever guise it may come. The wife soon begins to feel the deprivation of pleasures
                    and indulgences to which she has been accustomed. She misses her independence, and especially <pb n="9" id="VAA4025-006-1-013"/> misses having her own money sufficient for her needs, without
                    having to ask anybody for it, or account to anybody for the use she has made of it. She is not as
                    amiable as in the first months of their married life. And the husband has been going through
                    something of the same experience. He misses his tobacco money, his beer money, his occasional game
                    of baseball, his companionship with his comrades, because he has not the money to participate in
                    their amusements; he is harrassed by debt, and his inability- to provide for his wife the things
                    which she formerly provided for herself and considers necessary for her comfort and happiness. He
                    becomes discouraged and out of humor, and it is manifest in his conduct about the house. He is
                    fault-finding and grouchy, and, instead of making the best of the situation, stays out at nights
                    ∗ and spends what money he has in dissipation, the evidence in a number of cases showing
                    the wife to have been left to the chance assistance of neighbors in the supreme hour of confinement.
                    The instalment man becomes importunate and threatens to take possession of the goods and leave the
                    house bare. Perhaps he does remove them. It is not done quietly; can not be, very well. All the
                    wife's neighbors and friends know it. The young wife is mortified and chagrined. She begins
                    to think her husband is not much of a man, or he could earn enough money to take care of her
                    properly, without subjecting her to such humiliations and indignities—other
                    women's husbands do. The man easily comes to the conclusion that the trouble is in the
                    mismanagement of the household, want of capacity and disposition to do the right thing on the part
                    of his wife in looking after current expenses; that, if his wife were not incompetent and careless,
                    she could keep things going without spending all his earnings and running him in
                    debt—other men's wives do. And so each is in a frame of mind to find fault with
                    the other and recrimination begins. Now just assume that there is in either a little more than the
                    ordinary amount of temper, a little more than the usual amount of selfishness, a little less
                    patience and forbearance, a little less sense of obligation of responsibility and duty, and you have
                    the conditions out of which the great majority of the divorce suits in this county grow. In many
                    instances the marriage relation does not continue much beyond <pb n="10" id="VAA4025-006-1-014"/>
                    this point. The instalment house man takes back his furniture, keeping what has been paid on it, the
                    landlord puts a "For Rent" sign on the little cottage, the wife goes back to her
                    folks to live and at the end of two years brings suit for a divorce on the ground of failure to
                    provide and abandonment.</p>
            <p>The chattel mortgage company, resorted to in time of stress, frequently brings about the same chain
                    of consequences.</p>
            <p>In other cases the couple continue to worry along together, but drifting further and further apart.
                    Having given up the cottage and housekeeping, the instalment man having taken back the furniture and
                    house furnishing so sanguinely and unwisely purchased, they rent a room, perhaps two, and endeavor,
                    more or less earnestly, to get along. But they have lost many points in the game. They no longer
                    admire and respect each other; it is a matter of toleration on both sides. At this stage each is a
                    failure in the eyes of the other, and nobody likes failures. The closer they are to us, the less we
                    like them. There are quarrels and hard things are said. Cruel charges, that are without foundation,
                    frequently, are made in anger; each is neglectful and indifferent to the feelings of the other.
                    Mutual respect is destroyed. There may be violence, and then divorce is sought on the ground of
                    cruel and inhuman treatment.</p>
            <p>If neither the husband nor wife has yet reached the point of applying for divorce, and laying bare
                    the sores that every human being instinctively seeks to keep covered, though they continue to live
                    together they get farther apart in spirit and interests until the husband seeks in the society of
                    some other woman, or the wife in the society of some other man, that companionship and sympathy
                    which they have failed to find in each other. Then a decree of separation is asked on the ground of
                    infidelity.</p>
            <p>Of course, there are cases that present a different state of facts. There are cases in which the
                    evidence shows one or the other of the parties to be unmistakably bad, vicious and immoral, and
                    sometimes each is successful in showing the other up in that character. Such cases always have been
                    and always will be, and they do not present any different question now than they have heretofore. No
                    conceivable reform in legislation, or in administering the law, can reach that class of cases. The
                    innocent party <pb n="11" id="VAA4025-006-1-015"/> in such case is entitled to a divorce, and any
                    legislation or judicial interpretation which would make relief impossible or more difficult would be
                    a step backward.</p>
            <p>In cases where both parties are shown to be equally at fault, there can be no divorce in this State.
                    Thus neither of the parties can marry anybody else and bring misery upon them, and eventually more
                    grist to the divorce mill. Can any more than this be said for this provision? Is the morality of the
                    community in any way benefited by keeping such people together?</p>
            <p>The discussion of cases which are brought about by vicious tendencies is not likely to be profitable.
                    They are bound to be until all humanity comes up to a much higher plane. It will not be enough to
                    bring up the average, because an average implies extremes; and so long as there are depraved or weak
                    men and women there will be such cases. I am considering, in the main, cases which there ought to be
                    some hope of preventing, if the cause can be found and the remedy applied. A large proportion of the
                    cases I am familiar with are of that kind. Most of them present the features I have given, with only
                    slight variations in detail. It may be said that such difficulties are trivial, sufficient for
                    children's quarrels, but insufficient to cause grown-up men and women with ordinary
                    affection and the usual sense of duty and responsibility to stifle the promptings of the one, and
                    disregard the plain call of the other. That is true enough, as witness the thousands and thousands
                    who do not permit troubles of this character to drive them into the divorce court, but who in spite
                    of them live on together with a reasonable degree of happiness and raise families that are a credit
                    to themselves and of value to the state. The point to be remembered is that to a very large extent
                    the men and women who figure in divorce proceedings have less than ordinary affection, and more
                    frequently less than ordinary sense of duty and responsibility. They are below the normal standard
                    in each—just a little below perhaps, but below. There is one part of the trouble. And yet
                    they are not so far below the normal standard in either but that they would have got along together
                    well enough under the conditions that existed a'generation or two ago, when the woman had
                    no thought of being independent, or even being an equal partner <pb n="12" id="VAA4025-006-1-016"/>
                    in the domestic establishment, but was contented to regard herself as subordinate to the man, who
                    was the recognized head of the family and of the house. They would have got along together,
                    notwithstanding their weakness in these particulars, before the woman. had experienced the
                    satisfaction of earning and spending her own money, when she was animated by no other thought than
                    to make her husband's wages go as far as possible, when there was not the present
                    temptation which besets the workingman and every member of his family to spend more than they have,
                    when there were not the present facilities, invitations and inducements to get in debt.</p>
            <p>It will be seen, if my analysis of local conditions is correct, that the two most important factors
                    in the situation are want of thrift, and what is popularly termed the emancipation of women. Of the
                    former I have probably said enough. Concerning the other, the change that the last fifty years has
                    brought about in the attitude of the world toward women, and in the attitude of women toward the
                    world, amounts almost to a revolution. This change is generally considered to be a racial advance,
                    and no doubt it is; but, as in most revolutions there are manifestations during the period of
                    transition, while the process of adaptation to the new conditions is going on, that are not wholly
                    desirable, so it may be that society is suffering a little from the recently acquired freedom and
                    independence of the new woman. It may be better for the race that the lives and characters of future
                    mothers shall be broadened and developed according to the methods of the present day; that they
                    shall be capable as well as amiable; self-reliant instead of dependent; assertive instead of
                    submissive; dominant in the home by force of character and ability as well as by love and affection;
                    but it must be conceded that this result can not be reached without the sacrifice of something that
                    has heretofore been esteemed beautiful and worth cherishing.</p>
            <p>In most human institutions one head has been found better than two. Very few business concerns would
                    run successfully with two men exercising equal authority in the same sphere. Where partners have
                    equal financial interest, and, logically, equal authority, it has generally been found expedient to
                    make each <pb n="13" id="VAA4025-006-1-017"/> one supreme in certain departments; and this condition
                    obtained in the old fashioned marriage; but in the undivided territory the husband and father was
                    the undisputed head. In some cases, the wife and mother, by reason of natural gifts, being the
                    stronger character, assumed the headship, and the assumption was acquiesced in by the husband; and
                    so in this case there was a head and no disputed authority. This condition seldom obtains in the
                    modern home. It is now regarded by the wife, and conceded by the husband, to be an equal
                    partnership, wherein every question that arises is to be settled by mutual agreement, and if that
                    can not be arrived at, it continues to be a subject of disagreement and discussion until it is
                    settled by the course of events, or until the children, taking sides, settle it according to their
                    notion or inclination, to the absolute destruction of family discipline; or, if that does not
                    happen, until it becomes a source of serious difference between the parents, leading to other
                    differences that finally result in estrangement.</p>
            <p>I think it is universally regarded that the present condition of woman is an advance. It has been
                    stated that the degree of civilization of any people may be measured by the respect and
                    consideration shown to its women. On the other hand, it is asserted that woman's advance
                    from the inferior station accorded her under old conditions to her present position of wage-earner
                    and controller of affairs, has been followed to a marked degree by a deterioration of the men in
                    families where the women have thus taken over what were supposed to be men's duties; that
                    without the incentive and responsibility of taking care of their women, men lose some of the best
                    qualities of manhood, in that they become willing to sit by and see their mothers, wives and sisters
                    sharing, and ofttimes carrying more than their share of the burden that was formerly carried by the
                    man alone. I do not know whether this is true or not. It is conceivable. If it is true, it is
                    certainly a subject for grave consideration. The world can get along much better with the women only
                    as good as they have been, than with the men any worse. We do not need better women at the price of
                    worse men. We had better get along with the present article in each case. Those who are alarmed by
                    conditions brought about by woman's release from the bondage of <pb n="14" id="VAA4025-006-1-018"/> the past must, however, remember the words of Macauley, "There
                    is only one cure for the evils which newly acquired freedom produces, and that cure is
                    freedom." It may be that thi: evils we seem to see are simply because emancipated woman has
                    not yet learned to use her freedom wisely, and that as the final and permanent fruits of liberty are
                    said to be wisdom, moderation and mercy, in the end we may hope for a better condition of affairs
                    than the world has yet experienced.</p>
            <p>What I have said does not apply so much to divorces among well-to-do people. I do not think the
                    question is so important when considered in its relation to what is understood to be society. It is
                    not so fundamental. The effect of bad example set by people who have had advantages, who are
                    prosperous and conspicuous in the community, is farther reaching; but I do not think the number of
                    such cases is very much in excess of what might be accounted for by the increase in the population,
                    and therefore they do not present the question so much of a growing evil as do the divorces among
                    those less favored by fortune.</p>
            <p>There have been some cases among the prosperous, among the young people, whose course it is not
                    difficult to trace. They often seem to be ihe result of too much self-denial, tenderness and
                    devotion on the part of parents, not tempered by wisdom and good judgment; and this is particularly,
                    though not always, the case where the boy or girl happens to be an only child. In such instances the
                    son or daughter is the first consideration in everything that pertains to the running of the
                    domestic establishment. They are brought up to take everything and give nothing.
                    Everybody's pleasure and convenience is subordinated to their whim and inclination, and
                    they take it all as a matter of course. The boy so spoiled marries a girl so petted. One of the
                    kind, however, is all that is necessary to wreck the home life, unless the other has more than the
                    ordinary amount of good sense, tact and sweetness of disposition. Too frequently each expects from
                    the other the devotion, consideration and sacrifice that they have received from their parents.
                    Neither gets it, and there is disappointment and unhappiness. Where there is good stuff in either or
                    both, the young people eventually find themselves, learn their true relation to each other, adjust
                    themselves to it, and live <pb n="15" id="VAA4025-006-1-019"/> happily ever after, as they say in
                    the story books; but when that is not the case there is a separation and a divorce. Every now and
                    then it happens that one or the other of the parties is not all that could be desired, either in
                    disposition or good sense; and from this dissatisfaction at the start differences result that become
                    irreconcilable. Then' there are the cases involving unfaithfulness, which as I have said
                    always have been and always will be; but which I do not think are increasing to any alarming extent,
                    except as infidelity is brought about by the conditions I have been talking about.</p>
            <p>It is frequently said that marriages are entered upon too lightly nowadays, and that this is the
                    cause of so many divorces; that young people marry with the thought in mind that a divorce is
                    readily obtained if the experiment does not turn out in every way satisfactcrily. I do not think
                    this is true. Some may, but I do not think very many young people about to marry ever contemplate
                    the contingency of their not being happy together, or consider the availability of divorce, any more
                    than the man whose passion is aroused to the point of committing murder weighs the possibility of
                    being hanged for it. Most divorces as well as most marriages are among the young, and youth does not
                    calculate. When young people marry they are generally in love, or think they are, which, as far as
                    the likelihood of their calculating nicely the probabilities for or against a satisfactory wedded
                    career is concerned, amounts to the same thing. While the young people of the present day may not
                    fully realize all that marriage involves in the way of mutual sacrifice and forbearance, we do not
                    know- that the young people of former generations did any more so; and that probably is not as great
                    a factor in the problem as some others.</p>
            <p>Personally, there is nothing so depressing to me as a day of divorce trials, no phase of life that
                    seems so discouraging and hopeless; and one who is brought in contact with these cases constantly
                    needs to remember how many difficult questions this country has settled and settled right, in order
                    to keep his belief in manhood and his faith in womankind. The surprising fact, often remarked by
                    court officials, that the children of these mismated couples are very frequently above the average
                    in industry, <pb n="16" id="VAA4025-006-1-020"/> sense of responsibility and
                    self-denial—in strange contrast to their parents—presents one ray of hope in
                    the situation. It may be that there is something in the law of compensations, and as the infinite
                    unselfishness of loving parents makes selfish children, who in turn make bad husbands and bad wives,
                    so the selfishness and neglect of these husbands and wives, as fathers and mothers, develops
                    unselfishness, self-reliance and capacity in their offspring. If, as is said, struggle is the
                    nursing-mother of greatness, these children are likely to have greatness thrust upon them, for
                    certainly struggle is their portion in life.</p>
            <p>In closing, I might sum up my conclusions as follows: That the increasing number of divorces is
                    largely among the poorer people; that it is not due to loose moral ideas among them so much as it is
                    due to economic conditions, and that it is really an economic question that is presented; that work
                    in the direction of encouraging the formation of habits of thrift and economy in living, and
                    creating a wholesome fear of debt in every form, would do a great deal to help the situation, in
                    this county, at any rate.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="17" id="VAA4025-006-1-021"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-006-1-a02">
            <head>FORMATION OF THE CHRISTIAN CHURCH IN INDIANA.</head>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="i">BY H. CLAY TRUSTY</hi>.</byline>
            <p>[A paper prepared for the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> Christian Ministers' Association.]</p>
            <p>SCHISMS and discontent reigned in the religious circles of the western frontier at the beginning of
                    the nineteenth century, as they did in the East and in <placeName>
                        <country reg="enk">England</country>
                    </placeName>. In the new country in the West men had better opportunities to establish churches free
                    from elements to which they objected. The general unrest in religious society was due mainly to
                    doctrinal creeds. Religious liberties, like political liberty, were sought by throwing off human
                    authority. Thus the new movement took shape first in ridding itself of "man-made
                    creeds." In an account of the "Great Awakening of Eighteen Hundred," L.
                    W. Bacon says: "(There was manifested in various quarters a general revolt against the
                    existence and multiplication of mutually exclusive sects in the Christian family, each limited by
                    humanly devised doctrinal articles and branded with party names." (American Church History,
                    Vol. XIII, p. 241.) These protesting elements in part came together on the basis of a common faith
                    in Christ, and a common acceptance of the divine authority of the Bible. The story of this
                    achievement is the history of the beginnings of the "Disciples of Christ." We
                    shall attempt to trace the development of this movement in Indiana.</p>
            <p>In the first decades of the eighteenth century, the Baptists and Methodists were the principal
                    religious bodies in the southern part of the State, while the Presbyterians were strong in the
                    central and northern parts. (R. T. Brown Pamphlet.) The "protesting element" was
                    having great influence in <placeName>
                  <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>, <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
               </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="tnu">Tennessee</region>
                    </placeName> early in the nineteenth century. Many people were denouncing human creeds and accepting
                    the New Testament as a sufficient rule of faith and practice. ("Many of the sober,
                    peaceful, honest, God fearing and God trusting men and women" who came to Indiana from
                    these States were inoculated with this desire for a common ground of religious service and worship.
                    "These people were poor and had endured many hard <pb n="18" id="VAA4025-006-1-022"/>
                    ships," (R. T. Brown Pamphlet) and they sought religious peace and unity. As a result of
                    this, churches which were founded upon the New Testament alone sprang up in several parts of Indiana
                    independent of each other. The three main independent groups were, first, that in southern Indiana,
                    centered about <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clark</region>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                  <region type="county">Jefferson</region>, <region type="county">Orange</region>
               </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Washington</region>
                    </placeName> counties; second, the developments in eastern Indiana which were centered about <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Rush</region>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Fayette</region>
                    </placeName> counties; third, in western Indiana, in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Montgomery</region>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Putnam</region>
                    </placeName> counties. Later, in the period of organization and cooperation, these movements were
                    all united.</p>
            <p>First, we shall consider the work as it developed in southern Indiana. Churches which took the New
                    Testament as their creed and basis of union were formed very early in nearly every county in
                    southern Indiana. We divide the work: <list type="ordered">
                  <item>
                     <placeName>
                                <region type="county">Washington county</region>
                            </placeName>, led by John Wright.</item>
                  <item>
                     <placeName>
                                <region type="county">Jefferson county</region>
                            </placeName>, led by Beverly Vawter.</item>
                  <item>
                     <placeName>
                                <region type="county">Clark county</region>
                            </placeName>, led by Little and Cole.</item>
                  <item>
                     <placeName>
                                <region type="county">Orange county</region>
                            </placeName>, led by Hostetler.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The development of the religious views held by the "Disciples" is best shown in the
                    lives of the early leaders of the movement. One of the first men in Indiana to begin preaching the
                    doctrines which led to the breaking away from the orthodox custom of the Protestant churches then
                    established, was John Wright. The Wrights, Peter and John, moved from <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> to Indiana in 1807 and settled in Clark's <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Grant</settlement>
                    </placeName>. (Pioneer Preachers, by Evans, p. 30.) In 1830 they moved to <geogName>Blue
                    River</geogName>, <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Washington county</region>
                    </placeName>, four miles south of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                    </placeName>. The Wrights' father was formerly a <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Quaker</settlement>
                    </placeName>, but later united with the Dunkard church. In the year 1810 they organized a
                    "Free Will" Baptist church at <geogName>Blue River</geogName> (Pioneer Preachers,
                    p. 31), out of which grew the famous "<geogName>Blue River</geogName>
                    Association." This association was formed without the usual "Article of
                    Faith." (Pioneer Preachers, p. 31.) It was irregular in this respect. John Wright from the
                    beginning opposed party names and declared for the Bible alone as a rule of faith and practice. He
                    was probably the first man in Indiana (Life of Benjamin Franklin, p. 163) to take the position that
                    the Bible alone was a sufficient basis of church organization. "He <pb n="19" id="VAA4025-006-1-023"/> labored to destroy divisions, and promote union among all the children
                    of God, and in this difficult yet most important service he made his indelible mark."
                    (Pioneer Preachers, p. 31.) He believed that all credal statements are heretical and schismatical.
                    He openly opposed party names in 1819, when he offered, in the church at <geogName>Blue
                    River</geogName>, a resolution in favor of discarding their party name, and recommending that they
                    call themselves by some name authorized in the Scriptures. As individuals he was willing that they
                    be called "Friends," "Disciples" or "Christians"; and
                    as a body "the Church of Christ," or "the Church of God." He
                    opposed the term Christian as applied to the church, because it is not so applied in the writings of
                    the Apostles. His resolution was adopted with more unanimity than was expected; and that Baptist
                    church has since been known as the Church of Christ at <geogName>Blue River</geogName>. This church
                    dates from 1819. (Pioneer Preachers, p. 32.) From this fact some now claim that <geogName>Blue
                    River</geogName> was the first church of Disciples in Indiana. S. P. Mitchel, of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indiana, says: "John Wright was the pioneer in the movement for reform,
                    holding the same views which Campbell held, and was earlier than the Campbells. (Report from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                    </placeName> Church, File Butler College Library.) The Wrights knew nothing of the Campbells at the
                    time of this organization, or after they had adopted the resolution cited above. Others even date
                    the beginning of the reformation and first church at 1810, when Wright organized the first Baptist
                    church at <geogName>Blue River</geogName>.</p>
            <p>From 1819 the Wrights began in earnest the work of reformation in the Baptist church. They met with
                    success, and by the year 1821 nearly all the churches in <geogName>Blue River</geogName> Association
                    had discarded the name Baptist and changed their association into an Annual Meeting. (Pioneer
                    Preachers, p. 32.) About this time fifteen Dunkard churches in this section of the country had
                    united on one immersion as sufficient for baptism. (Life of Benjamin Franklin, p. 164.) At the next
                    annual meeting Wright proposed to send a delegation to the annual conference of the Dunkards with a
                    view to forming a union. The proposition was adopted and John Wright was made leader of the
                    delegation. He succeeded in effecting a permanent union of what were formerly Baptist and Dunkards.
                    At the same annual meeting John Wright <pb n="20" id="VAA4025-006-1-024"/> proposed similar
                    overtures to the "New Lights." He was appointed to conduct this correspondence on
                    the part of his brethren, which he did with such discretion and ability that a joint convention was
                    assembled in 1828 near <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Edinburg</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indiana. (Pioneer Preachers, p. 33.) John Wright was the leader of the "Free
                    Will Baptists," Beverly Vawter of the Christian Connection, and Joseph Hostetler of the
                    Dunkards. (R. T. Brown Pamphlet.) This conference resulted in an agreement to be governed in their
                    labors by the teaching and methods followed by the primitive Evangelists, as set forth in the Acts
                    of Apostles. (R. T. Brown Pamphlet.) This was the beginning of the Southern Indiana Association,
                    which later united with the Silver Creek Association.</p>
            <p>Up to this time Wright had not embraced A. Campbell's teaching. He had held aloof from the
                    Silver Creek Association on account of the Campbellism introduced by the Littells and Cole. On
                    learning the teachings of the Littells, and finding that their only difference was on the design of
                    baptism, Wright was convinced of his error and led the Southern Indiana Association to a union with
                    the Silver Creek Association. "In this union three thousand people were united upon a
                    common basis, forgetting all minor differences in their devotion to the great interests of their
                    Redeemer's Kingdom." This was the greatest achievement of the Wrights. (Pioneer
                    Preachers, p. 33–34.)</p>
            <p>Wright first learned of A. Campbell's teachings through Beverly Vawter, the next leader in
                    southern Indiana that we will consider.</p>
            <p>Beverly Vawter was born in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> in 1789, moved to <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> in 1792, where his father united with the Baptist church. At the age of ten he was
                    baptized into the Baptist church. He remained in the Baptist church until his twenty-second year,
                    when he was excluded. (Pioneer Preachers, p. 105.) He thought no more about religion for five or six
                    years. Vawter was, however, a firm believer in the doctrine of eternal election, and in the direct
                    gift of God through the secret operation of the Holy Spirit. He felt his need of a greater faith,
                    and, in search of "light," applied to a New Light preacher, then to his Baptist
                    uncle, and finally to a Presbyterian preacher. None of these men <pb n="21" id="VAA4025-006-1-025"/>
                    was able to satisfy him. Vawter became interested in the study of Matthew, Mark, and the Acts of the
                    Apostles, and in 1817 began comparing the teachings of these books with the teachings of the Baptist
                    church. He chanced to read B. W. Stone's "Essay on Faith." Among the
                    quotations were Romans 10:17, and John 20:30. T.hese helped him in matters of faith. He became more
                    dissatisfied with the Baptist doctrine. He was still on his quest for pardon when he happened upon
                    these texts: "He that believ-eth and is baptized shall be saved"; "Repent and be
                    baptized, every one of you, in the name of Jesus Christ, for the remission of sins, and you shall
                    receive the gift of the Holy Spirit." Cpon these promises he rested. The question arose as
                    to which church he would join, Baptist or New Light. He attended a meeting at the New Light church
                    and heard John McClung present the Bible alone as the sufficient rule of faith and practice; and
                    with great earnestness urge all who loved the Lord Jesus in sincerity to forsake all human creeds
                    and unite on the Bible as the living creed. This turned the scale in favor of the New Lights, and on
                    the first Sunday in January, 1817, he was immersed by McClung. (Pioneer Preachers, p. 197.)</p>
            <p>Vawter continued to preach in the Baptist churches after he was baptized by McClung, and brought
                    whole churches over into the new movement. This was exemplified at Hogan Creek. (Pioneer Preachers,
                    p. 111.) He removed to his Indiana home a few miles above <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName> in March, 1819, on the west fork of a little creek called Indian <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName>. (Pioneer Preachers, p. 19.)</p>
            <p>When he was preaching in Otto Creek, in 1824, the following incident occurred: "There came
                    to him a woman saying that she had long been ‘seeking religion’ but could not
                    obtain it; and that she greatly desired to be immersed because the Lord had commanded it. He asked
                    her if she believed that Jesus Christ is the Son of God. When she replied in the affirmative, he
                    said, ‘On- this profession I will immerse you. "If thou believest with all thy
                    heart thou mayest," is the language of the Book.’ But she said, ‘My
                    husband has declared that he will whip any man who attempts to baptize me. Must I obey him or my
                    Savior?’ Vawter replied, ‘It is better to obey God than man; come to the
                    baptizing to-morrow and we shall see.’ " He baptized the woman <pb n="22" id="VAA4025-006-1-026"/> the next day and went home with her for dinner. (Pioneer Preachers, p.
                    113.)</p>
            <p>As early as 1824 Vawter preached baptism for the remission of sins and the Bible as the rule of faith
                    and practice, but had not entered fully into the early position of the Disciples. (Pioneer
                    Preachers, p. 113.) Theoretically he was with them and sometimes in practice, but in the main he
                    yielded to the mourners' bench method of conversion. (Pioneer Preachers, p. 113.)</p>
            <p>Vawter's teaching was so much like that of Campbell's that while preaching near <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Greensburg</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indiana, in 1826, he was accused of being a "Campbellite." His
                    colaborer, Douglas, explained to him Campbell's doctrine as it had been preached in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName>. Here the light of the reformation came to him. Returning home from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Greensburg</settlement>
                    </placeName> he came to the home of Thomas Jameson. (Pioneer Preachers, p. 115.) Jameson had been
                    reading the <hi rend="i">Christian Baptist</hi>, though he belonged to the New Light church. It was
                    here that Vawter came directly under the influence of Campbell's teaching, (R. T. Brown)
                    and was more firmly grounded in his doctrines.</p>
            <p>Vawter was the leader of the New Lights in the meeting at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Edinburg</settlement>
                    </placeName> when the union of Dunkards, New Liihts and Baptists was formed in 1828. (Pioneer
                    Preachers, p. 116.) His work was among Baptist and New Light churches. Sectarianism had done its
                    work so well in that community that, out of the fifteen preachers present, Vawter was the only one
                    whose preaching would probably be acceptable to all parties. He preached to them on the
                    "Government and unity of the primitive church," and with such effect that the
                    contemplated union was speedily formed on the Bible creed and Christian name. He organized a church
                    at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kent</settlement>
                    </placeName> in 1830. (Pioneer Preachers, p. 117.)</p>
            <p>Joseph Hostetler, leader of the Dunkards in the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Edinburg</settlement>
                    </placeName> Conference of 1828, came into the reformation in the following way: In 1816, after
                    reading and finding what a believer "must do to be saved," he was baptized at his
                    own request. He was then nineteen years of age. His newly discovered doctrines were, that a believer
                    must repent, confess and be baptized in His name for the remission of sins. (Pioneer Preachers, p.
                    60.) They did not <pb n="23" id="VAA4025-006-1-027"/> at that time understand the Christian system
                    in the same way they did later.</p>
            <p>In 1819 J. Hostetler and John Riddle organized a Dunkard church at Old Liberty, <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Orange county</region>
                    </placeName>, but the organization was irregular from the beginning. When Hostetler was ordained to
                    preach in the Dunkard church, his uncle presented him with a Bible with these words,
                    "Preach and practice what you find in this Book." (Pioneer Preachers, p. 63.) In
                    1825 he was accused by his brethren of preaching heterodox opinions, but no action was taken against
                    him. The <hi rend="i">Christian Baptist</hi> fell into his hands the same year, and in 1826 he
                    preached on primitive Christianity at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Orleans</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indiana. This sermon created great interest in the "reform" movement
                    in the community. Hostetler thus began advocating a union of God's people on the Bible
                    alone as the creed. He was opposed to man-made creeds. He was chosen to speak at the conference
                    ‘at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Edinburg</settlement>
                    </placeName> in 1828, where Vawter and Wright were present with authority to act for rheir
                    respective churches. Public sentiment had grown rapidly in favor of the Bible as the only platform
                    on which Christians could unite. From 1828 Joseph Hostetler is to be regarded as an advocate of the
                    Disciples’ teachings.</p>
            <p>Thus the three leaders, Wright, Vawter and Hostetler, came out in the conference at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Edinburg</settlement>
                    </placeName> in 1828.</p>
            <p>Vawter's labors were in what is now <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Jefferson county</region>
                    </placeName> neat <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName>. The Wrights worked in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Washington county</region>
                    </placeName> near <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                    </placeName>, and Hostetler in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Orange county</region>
                    </placeName>. These churches came into the reformation by way of the New Lights, and it is hard to
                    tell just when they became distinctly Christian (Disciple) churches.</p>
            <p>While Baptists adopting Disciple principles have generally a well-defined line of transition, yet it
                    is often difficult to mark any specific time when the change was made. Perhaps the best defined line
                    of transition is that, when they determined on meeting every Lord's Day to observe the
                    primitive form of worship, and required all their members to be immersed on the confession of faith
                    in Christ. Measured by this standard, we enumerate the church at Thomas Jameson's home,
                    established in 1827, Old Liberty in 1830, and the church at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kent</settlement>
                    </placeName> and Vernon in 1831. Between <pb n="24" id="VAA4025-006-1-028"/> 1830 and 1833 about
                    twenty churches adopted the primitive form of worship in the counties of <placeName>
                  <region type="county">Orange</region>, <region type="county">Harrison</region>, <region type="county">Washington</region>, <region type="county">Floyd</region>, <region type="county">Clark</region>, <region type="county">Jefferson</region>
               </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Jennings</region>
                    </placeName>. These churches were generally reorganized from the Christian Connection (New Light),
                    Baptists and Dunkards. (R. T. Brown Pamphlet.)</p>
            <p>The work in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clark county</region>
                    </placeName> was led by John T. and Absalom Little and Mordecai Cole, who were leaders in the Silver
                    Creek (Baptist) Association. John T. Little, the leading man of the group, was baptized into the
                    Baptist church in 1816. He helped organize the First Baptist (now Christian) church in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New Albany</settlement>
                    </placeName> in 1820. The irregularities in this organization caused it to be excluded from the
                        <geogName>Blue River</geogName> Association, but it was admitted into the Silver Creek
                    Association in 1821.</p>
            <p>The Littles and Cole came under the influence of A. Campbell's teachings in 1826, and they
                    brought a large majority of the churches of the Silver Creek Association into the reformation. As
                    early as 1827 or 1828 they exchanged the name Regular Baptist for Christian, and the Confession of
                    Faith and Rule of Decorum for the Bible alone as their basis of faith and government; they continued
                    their annual meetings, but no legislative business was transacted; letters of encouragement were
                    read. (Christian Record, Vol. 11, p. 82.)</p>
            <p>When the question of church government came up in the Silver Creek church much discussion followed.
                    Resolutions were offered by the Baptist party to offset Campbell's teaching which was being
                    introduced. The members asked "what the faith of the church was when it was
                    organized," and the question was answered, "by the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Philadelphia</settlement>
                    </placeName> Confession." They rested under this for a while but later proposed
                    "That the submission to the confession of faith should be a condition of
                    fellowship."? This proposition met with strong opposition and disturbed the church for a
                    long time. (Pioneer Preachers, p. 49.) Finally a resolution was offered, demanding "to know
                    from this church whether she is governed by the Old and New Testaments or by the
                    ‘Articles of Faith.’" This question was debated and answered by the
                    congregation. "The church says by the Word of God." (Pioneer Preachers, p. 49.)</p>
            <p>The church remained under the rules of the Baptist Association, <pb n="25" id="VAA4025-006-1-029"/>
                    and worshiped in a spirit of compromise until 1835, when the final break came. Division first came
                    in the church in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New Albany</settlement>
                    </placeName>, and soon spread through the whole association. (Pioneer Preachers, p. 51.) The
                    "Reformers" opposed division and tried to persuade their Baptist brethren to
                    accept the Bible as their only rule of faith and practice. (Pioneer Preachers, p. 51.) This was the
                    beginning of the Disciple movement in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clark county</region>
                    </placeName>, and these came directly out of the Baptist churches.</p>
            <p>The Silver Creek Association, led by the Littles, and the Southern Indiana Association, led by the
                    Wrights, united under the influence of these men.</p>
            <p>The second independent movement which resulted in the establishment of Christian churches in Indiana
                    was in the eastern part, principally in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Rush</region>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Fayette</region>
                    </placeName> counties. The work started here in the Calvinistic Baptist church. John T. Thompson, a
                    Baptist preacher, subscribed for the <hi rend="i">Christian Baptist</hi> in 1826. In the same year
                    he went to <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> and found that his people had gone into the Christian (Disciples) church. While in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> he heard John Smith preach and returned home to study the matter out for himself. In
                    Elias Stone's house in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Rush county</region>
                    </placeName>, in the same year, Thompson proclaimed for the first time the gospel as taught in the
                    New Testament, and denounced creeds. This sermon caused much discussion in the community, and the
                    settlers began to study their Bibles and to demand a "thus saith the Lord" for
                    every tenet. Thompson was still regarded as a Baptist preacher, and they undertook to convince him
                    of his error, but failed. This took place in the Flat Rock Baptist cdurFh in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Rush county</region>
                    </placeName>. In 1829 about sixty members withdrew from this church, and, with its consent,
                    established a church at Fay-etteville, taking the Bible as the sole rule of faith and practice. In
                    1827–'08 Thompson went to schoolhouses and private dwellings and preached his
                    new doctrines.</p>
            <p>When the Baptists found they could not win Thompson back to their view, they prepared to cast him out
                    of their church. He was arraigned before the congregation, and the church, by a majority of seven,
                    decided that his teaching was "according to the Word of God." At the next meeting
                    it was agreed that the Baptists <pb n="26" id="VAA4025-006-1-030"/> and the Reformers (as the
                    Disciples were called in this section of the country) should use the church on alternate Sundays for
                    worship. On the fourth Sunday in May, 1830, the majority that saved Thompson from expulsion
                    organized the Christian church known as "The Church of Christ at Little Flat
                    Rock." From this church sprang the <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Columbia</settlement>, <settlement type="city">Connersville</settlement>
               </placeName>, Ben Davis
                    and Rushville churches in the next three years.</p>
            <p>Engaged in the work of the Disciples in the eastern part of the State were such men as Benjamin F.
                    Reeves, who came from <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> to Indiana in 1833. He was a Reformer when he came to the Flat Rock church. Jacob
                    Daubenspeck, who was converted from the Presbyterians by way of the Baptists to the Disciples,
                    brought with him the Ben Davis Creek church in 1832. R. T. Brown, John O'Kane and S. K.
                    Hoshour are three of the most prominent leaders of the State who came from this eastern section.</p>
            <p>R. T. Brown joined the Clifty Baptist church in 1825. He subscribed for the <hi rend="i">Christian
                        Baptist</hi> in 1826, and became indoctrinated with Campbell's teaching. He went to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName> to medical college, and on his return in 1829 was excluded from the Baptist church with
                    the other Reformers. He located in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Connersville</settlement>
                    </placeName> in 1832 and continued to preach in various parts of the State. R. T. Brown's
                    confession of faith follows: "Faith is nothing more nor less than a conviction of the truth
                    of any position from evidence. Faith in Jesus Christ is nothing more than a belief of the facts
                    recorded of Him by the Evangelists, to-wit: That Jesus of Nazareth was the promised Messiah. and
                    that he gave impregnable proof of his divine mission by his miraculous birth, by the numerous
                    miracles which he wrought while living, and by his death, resurrection and asctnsion. The
                    evangelical writings, containing the facts relative to the mighty works which were done by Christ
                    and his apostles, together with the corroborating testimony of the prophecies, form altogether a
                    phalanx of evidence sufficient to convince any reasonable mind that ‘Jesus is the
                    Christ.’ The popular doctrine of a partial atonement, and unconditional election and
                    reprobation, were alike antichristian and un-scriptural." (<hi rend="i">Chrktian
                    Baptist</hi>, June, 1830.) As a result, the Clifty church (Baptist) adopted the following
                    resolution: "Resolved, <pb n="27" id="VAA4025-006-1-031"/> That we will not fellowship the
                    doctrines propagated by A. Campbell, of <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Bethany</settlement>,
                            <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
               </placeName>." From this time Brown
                    preached the doctrines of A. Campbell. It is regarded as the beginning of his public ministry. He
                    was elected to the chair of natural science in the Northwestern Christian University in 1858.</p>
            <p>While the developments already traced in southern and eastern Indiana were progressing, there was
                    still another group of men in western Indiana who were making progress toward a common ground of
                    union. Michael Combs, James Hughs and John Se-crest, ministers of the Christian Connection (New
                    Light) were preaching in several churches of that order in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Montgomery</region>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Putnam</region>
                    </placeName> counties. From 1827 they began to insist on a closer conformity to the
                    "apostolic model of evangelization and primitive order of worship." Thomas
                    Lockhart joined them and began to preach the same doctrines in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Hendricks county</region>
                    </placeName>. (R. T. Brown Pamphlet.)</p>
            <p>Michael Combs was converted to the New Light faith in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wayne county</region>
                    </placeName>, Indiana. In 1826 he moved to <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Montgomery county</region>
                    </placeName>, Indiana, where he organized a little church near or upon his farm. The organization
                    was subsequently removed to Craw-fordsville. From <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Crawfordsville</settlement>
                    </placeName> Combs visited many churches in the <geogName>White river valley</geogName>, and at
                    most, if not all of them, he was the first to oppose human creeds and to plead for the union of all
                    Christians on the Bible alone. (Pioneer Preazhers, p. 147.) About this time he began hearing
                    "startling" rumors concerning "one A. Campbell, who was said to be a
                    great fault-finder at <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Bethany</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
               </placeName>." Combs did not at this time subscribe for
                    the <hi rend="i">Christian Baptist</hi> and continued in the New Light church for the next three or
                    four years. Combs heard Campbell speak on one of his trips west and subscribed for the <hi rend="i">Christian Baptist</hi>. He held the views of Campbell a long time before he preached them,
                    fearing the attitude of the people toward these opinions. But finally, after being urged by his
                    friends, who knew his views, to preach them, he preached that "Men are required to repent
                    and be baptized in the name of Jesus Christ for the remission of sins," for the first time
                    at a protracted meeting at Edgar, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ilu">Illinois</region>
                    </placeName>, in 1833.</p>
            <pb n="28" id="VAA4025-006-1-032"/>
            <p>From this time the "great conflict" began in western Indiana. (Pioneer Preachers,
                    p. 149.) Public debates and private disputations followed. the work in the western part of the State
                    was strengthened by the coming of Job Combs and J. Secrest, both from <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName>.</p>
            <p>This work became associated with the work in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Bartholomew county</region>
                    </placeName> through the New Lights. Michael Combs went to <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Bartholomew county</region>
                    </placeName> on some business. Conversing one day with an old lady and gentleman on the subject of
                    religion, he found that they differed widely, and was drawn into a spirited discussion. Finally the
                    old lady remarked to her husband that "This stranger is like Joe Fasset." Through
                    this remark Combs was led to the "New H.ope" (New Light) church in the community,
                    and found that it was holding views similar to his own. They immediately set about a scheme to unite
                    the New Light churches of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Bartholomew</region>
                    </placeName> and adjpining counties to the north and west with the Disciples of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Montgomery county</region>
                    </placeName>.</p>
            <p>A meeting to this end was held at the bluffs on <geogName>White river</geogName> in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Morgan county</region>
                    </placeName>. Hundreds of people and a great number of preachers of both parties met there. It was
                    agreed that preachers who had been Calvinistic Baptists and those who were called "Arminian
                    New Lights" should preach a few sermons alternately in order to make manifest the
                    difference between the two parties. The meeting continued from Friday evening to Monday morning.
                    Fasset was leader of the New Light movement. Both parties denounced all human creeds, and they both
                    preached "the doctrine of Scripture given by inspiration of God." There appeared
                    no material difference between them, and they were all united in the Christian (Disciple) church at
                    this meeting. (Pioneer Preachers, p. 146–151.)</p>
            <p>About the same time Michael Combs was invited to speak at a meeting at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Bloomington</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indiana. He accepted the invitation and found the people inclined to listen to his
                    "peculiar views." A great interest was awakened in the community, and from this
                    beginning nearly all the New Light churches in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Monroe county</region>
                    </placeName> were won to the Christian (Disciple) church. (Pioneer Preachers, p. 152.) The way in
                    which churches came to accept Campbell's doctrine shows that the influence of
                    Campbell's teaching <pb n="29" id="VAA4025-006-1-033"/> extended for some years farther
                    than his name was known. Those who urged that the Bible alone is a sufficient rule of faith and
                    practice, that faith is a belief, that man is a responsible being, that the followers of the Lord
                    Jesus should be recognized only by Bible names, did not advertise these as Mr. Campbell's
                    views. And so, passing from one to the other, they came to be received by many persons who knew
                    nothing of Mr. Campbell. In some cases men accepted the doctrine of "Baptism for the
                    remission of sins" as taught in the Bible, and at the same time they looked upon Mr.
                    Campbell as a great heretic for preaching "Baptismal regeneration," never once
                    suspecting that this was only a perversion of what he really taught. (Life of Benjamin Franklin, p.
                    167.)</p>
            <p>These facts lead the writer to believe that Mr. Campbell was only the leader of a great host of
                    people who were anxious to get away from the abuses of sectarianism and back (or forward) to the
                    apostolic practices of the Christian church. His success was due to the fact that people were ready
                    to be led to a common basis of unity. It is hard to tell who was the first man to introduce A.
                    Campbell's doctrine into the State. His doctrines were labelled as heresies in Baptist
                    churches early in the 20's and were first known in many quarters as such. Mr. Stott echoes
                    an early Baptist view when he says that Alexander Campbell was known in Baptist churches in southern
                    Indiana as being opposed to missions, education, Sunday-schools, and paid ministry, as early as
                    1819. (Stott, Baptist. History, p. 56.) This surely is a misunderstanding of A. Campbell's
                    views. As early as 1826 the <geogName>White River</geogName> Baptist Association sent out circular
                    letters saying in the fifteenth article: "We reject the doctrines of A. Campbell and advise
                    churches composing our body to do the same, believing them to be contrary to the doctrine of God our
                    Savior." (Stott, Baptist History, p. 106.) In a letter to the churches in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Knox</region>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Gibson</region>
                    </placeName> counties in 1827, the Baptists are strong in their condemnations of the Foreign
                    Missionary Board of the Baptist church and of the brethren holding the views of A. Campbell and his
                    friends. (Stott, Baptist History, p. 63.)</p>
            <p>The earliest account we have of the introduction of A. Carnpbell's <pb n="30" id="VAA4025-006-1-034"/> doctrine into Indiana is through Thomas Jameson, father of Love H.
                    Jameson. Thomas Jameson was a member of the Church of <placeName>
                        <country reg="stk">Scotland</country>
                    </placeName>, but was baptized by John McClung, a New Light preacher, in 1816. In the spring of 1818
                    Thomas Jameson chanced to form the acquaintance of Mr. Joseph Bryant, a brother-in-law of Alexander
                    Campbell. From Mr. Bryant Jameson heard for the first time of Mr. Campbell and of the changes he
                    recommended in the return to the ancient order of worship. Soon after, he received a pamphlet
                    published by Thomas and Alexander Campbell in which was presented at length "The Basis of
                    Christian Union." This pamphlet was published in 1809, three years before the Campbells
                    withdrew from the Presbyterian church. Thomas Jameson was well pleased with the new ideas of the
                    Campbells, and would gladly have read more from the same source. But he heard no more of the
                    Reformation until 1826, when he received the <hi rend="i">Christian Baptist</hi>. (Pioneer
                    Preachers, p. 263.)</p>
            <p>Beverly Vawter learned of the <hi rend="i">Christian Baptist</hi> at Thomas Jameson's home
                    in 1826. After this time Vawter would approach the penitents at the mourners' bench,
                    brought there by Baptists and New Light preachers, with the question, "Why tarriest thou?
                    Arise and be baptized and wash away thy sins, calling on the name of the Lord." Many of
                    them would gladly receive the Word and the same hour of the night would obey from the heart the
                    doctrine delivered to them. (Pioneer Preachers, p. 117.)</p>
            <p>The church in which Thomas Jameson worshiped and to which Vawter came was the "Liberty
                    Church" (New Light) organized by John McClung in 1812. They had no meeting-house but met in
                    the woods. This church was Disciple from 1827. (L. H. Jameson Pamphlet.) Old Liberty was organized
                    in 1830, and the church at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kent</settlement>
                    </placeName> and Vernon in 1831. (R. T. Brown.)</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="i">Christian Baptist</hi> came into Indiana in 1826 chiefly to Baptists and members of
                    the New Light churches. The Baptists stopped taking the paper after 1826–'27.
                    (R. T. Brown.) This accounts for the starting of churches over the State upon the same basis and
                    independent of one another. CampbeIl's teaching came into the Silver Creek (Baptist)
                    Association through the <hi rend="i">Christian Baptist</hi>. In April, 1829, the Silver Creek church
                    renounced its <pb n="31" id="VAA4025-006-1-035"/> former confession of faith and accepted
                    Campbell's doctrine. (Stott, p. 51.)</p>
            <p>The chief point of difference between Reformers and Baptists was as to the article of faith. The
                    question which formed the entering wedge for Campbell's teaching was: "Is it
                    consistent to have articles of faith?" Some churches retained the name Baptist after they
                    had discarded the articles of faith. (Stott, p. 59.)</p>
            <p>In <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Lawrence County</region>
                    </placeName> the work began early. The Indian Creek Christian Church was first organized as a
                    Baptist church in 1818. In 1827, fourteen old school Baptists withdrew from this church and formed a
                    church below Silverville. Those who remained in the church were constituted into the present Indian
                    Creek Christian Church. The principal families entering into this work were the Shorts, Mayfields
                    and Armstrongs. The church at Springville was brought into the Reformation in 1839. Wesley Short
                    introduced the doctrine of A. Campbell and was visited by A. Campbell on his first visit to <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Lawrence County</region>
                    </placeName> in 1848. (History of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Lawrence County</region>
                    </placeName>, Goodspeed.) The church at Letlier-wood, <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Lawrence County</region>
                    </placeName>, was first organized as a Christian church (Disciple) in October, 1830, in the home of
                    Robert Woody, five miles east of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Bedford</settlement>
                    </placeName>. This was the first church in the county which was a Christian church from the very
                    first.</p>
            <p>In 1824 Cary Smith, a young preacher in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wayne county</region>
                    </placeName>, felt himself called to go on a preaching tour through the Southern States. In <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName>, chancing to see some numbers of the <hi rend="i">Christian Baptist</hi>, he became so
                    interested in it that he ordered two copies of the work, so far as published, to be sent, one to
                    hiniself and one to his father. This was the first introduction of Campbell's teachings, so
                    far as is known, in eastern Indiana. (Life of Franklin, p. 130.) J. T. Thompson subscribed for the
                        <hi rend="i">Christialz Bajdst</hi> in 1826, and was influenced by its teachings. (R. T. Brown.)</p>
            <p>The earliest public development in eastern Indiana was in a meeting of the Flat Rock Baptist
                    Association in the fall of 1827, when a motion was made to revise the "Asticles of
                    Faith." This was opposed by Joe Fasset and Irwin, of the New Hope Church, in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Bartholomew county</region>
                    </placeName>. In 1828 the New Hope Church reported to the Baptist Association that the New Testament
                    was a sufficient rule of faith and practice. In 1829 this church dropped the <pb n="32" id="VAA4025-006-1-036"/> name Baptist for the name Christian. The church continued to meet
                    monthly until 1830, when it began to meet every week to "break bread." (R. T.
                    Brown.) There is a difference of opinion as to when this church became Disciple, some dating it soon
                    after a division in the church over the articles of faith in 1825. (Article in <hi rend="i">Christian Evangelist</hi>, May 13, 1909.) This seems to be a case of development from Baptist
                    to New Light in 1825, and then to the position of the Disciples in 1830. Joe Fasset is referred to
                    as a New Light in 1833, when he met Michael Combs.</p>
            <p>Alexander Campbell visited Indiana for the first time in 1826. (<hi rend="i">Christian Baptist</hi>,
                    p. 320.) On his return home he writes describing the deplorable state of family worship in the
                    Baptist churches. He later says: "(1) The counties far remote from each other and without
                    the identifying influence of ecclesiastical jurisdiction, in the form of superintending
                    judicatories, appear to have agreed in making the Scriptures the sole and all sufficient rule of
                    faith and manners without the assistance of any creed or formula of human contrivance. (2) They
                    appear to have drawn from the same source the same general views of the genius and design of the
                    institutions of public weekly meetings of Christians on the first day of the week. (3) They concur
                    in principal items of worship. (4) They have the same regard for nature of the Grace of God and the
                    need for a moral and pious Life." (<hi rend="i">Christian Baptist</hi>, P. 442.)</p>
            <p>Campbell came into Indiana from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName> in 1850. He traveled through the State, and everywhere the people manifested great
                    anxiety to see him. It was difficult to find meeting places large enough to accommodate the
                    assemblies. At <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> the Governor and the whole State convention (assembled to revise the constitution)
                    attended his meeting. He visited <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Bloomington</settlement>,
                            <settlement type="city">Bedford</settlement>
               </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Brookville</settlement>
                    </placeName> on this trip. (Memoirs of Campbell, Richardson, p. 589.)</p>
            <p>In 1857 Campbell visited <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> again. On this trip he spoke at the Y. M. C. A. and at the Christian Church. He was
                    soliciting funds for Bethany College. The third tour was in 1860-'61, with his wife and
                    Isaac Errett. (Memoirs of Campbell, Richardson, Vol. 11, p. 626 and 641.) By this time the Diciples
                    were numerous in the State, and the movement may be said to be well established.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="33" id="VAA4025-006-1-037"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-006-1-a03">
            <head>ANCIENT MOUNDS AND ENCLOSURES IN INDIANA.</head>
            <byline>
                    <hi rend="i">BY BARCUS TICHENOR</hi>
                </byline>
            <p>[A paper prepared for the seminar in local history in Butler College.]</p>
            <p>THE largest group of mounds and enclosures in the region of the Great Lakes, the
                        <geogName>Mississippi valley</geogName> and the Gulf coast seems to have been along the
                        <geogName>Ohio</geogName> and <geogName>Mississippi rivers</geogName>, and especially near their
                    convergence. Judge N. R. Overman says (Prehistoric and Indian History of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Howard</region>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Tipton</region>
                    </placeName> Counties, Indiana, p. 5): "It is probable that at the confluence of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> and <geogName>Mississippi rivers</geogName>, two widely converging lines, the Mound
                    Builders met in solemn council to give laws, adjust and determine difficulties between settlements
                    and states. More than twelve hundred enclosures and ten thousand mounds have been counted in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName>. Indiana, too, is but little less fertile in these antiquities."</p>
            <p>The mounds are generally simple cones in form. Often they are truncated and sometimes terraced. They
                    are also elliptical, pear shaped, or of a square pyramid form. The mounds are generally built of
                    earth. However, stone mounds are often found. The enclosures, too, are generally made of earth and
                    are of all shapes, although many of them are true parallelograms. They seem to have been mostly for
                    defense. The areas within these enclosures vary from less than an acre to twenty or thirty acres. In
                    selecting the sites for their mounds the Mound Builders chose high and prominent places. The mounds
                    are often found where least expected—perhaps overlooking some waterfall. They are
                    generally found along river terraces, which were advantageous from a military point of view, and
                    also near water, fish, and the fertile land of the river valley. These mounds and enclosures are now
                    not nearly so high as they have been in the past. The natural wear of the weather and cultivation
                    during several generations have left them much lower than they were when they were first built.</p>
            <p>Squier and Davis' "Ancient Monuments of the <geogName>Mississippi
                    Valley</geogName>," Volume 1 of Smithsonian Contributions to Knowledge <pb n="34" id="VAA4025-006-1-038"/> (1847), is one of the best authorities upon the subject of mounds and
                    Mound Builders. They divide mounds (p. 140) into four classes: (1) Altar mounds or mounds containing
                    altars, which vary in size from two feet square to fifty feet in length by twelve or fifteen feet in
                    width. (2) Mounds of sepulture, which stand outside the enclosures in a position more or less
                    distant from them. (3) Temple mounds, which have great regularity of form, are generally large, are
                    pyramidal, truncated, and generally have graded avenues to their tops. (4) Anomalous (or
                    miscellaneous) mounds, including mounds of observation. Mounds of observation are generally to be
                    found in the most commanding places, and many of them contain human remains, undoubtedly those of
                    Mound Builders.</p>
            <p>Mounds and enclosures in Indiana are very numerous, although not so much so as in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName>. If we take up, one by one, the counties that have earthworks of importance in them, we
                    see that the number of mounds in the southern part of Indiana is much greater than in the northern.
                    Nevertheless, mounds are found as far north as <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Laporte county</region>
                    </placeName>. Mr. Foster (Prehistoric Races of the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>, p. 143) says that "about twelve miles from Laporte, on the banks of a small
                    tributary of the Kankakee, there are not less than twenty in number, some of which have been
                    explored by Dr. Higday with highly satisfactory results." At different times five skeletons
                    and one skull have been taken! ram various mounds in this place, besides several copper hatchets,
                    some earthen vessels, flint knives and what he calls "copper needles" or awls.
                    These mounds are all different heights, the lowest that he mentions being about six feet high. He
                    mentions one which was fifteen feet in height and another which he says was originally perhaps about
                    twenty feet high (p. 143). Mr. Foster quotes the following from Dr. Higday: "A horizontal
                    layer of ashes, about two inches thick in the middle and thinning out toward the circumference, was
                    struck thirteen feet from the top. Three feet below the ashes we came upon a pipe, a copper needle,
                    pieces of pottery and two adult Skeletons, one of which was nearly entire, lying on what must have
                    been a log of wood, but now so decayed that it could be readily pulverized by the hand" (p.
                    14).</p>
            <pb n="35" id="VAA4025-006-1-039"/>
            <p>Judge N. R. Overman describes the work of the Mound Builders in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Howard</region>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Tipton</region>
                    </placeName> counties. Of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Tipton county</region>
                    </placeName> he says i Prehistoric and Indian History of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Howard</region>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Tipton</region>
                    </placeName> Counties, p. 5): "From the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Wabash</settlement>
                    </placeName> they followed up the Wildcat to its headwaters in the northeast part of the county, and
                    there established a colony and cultivated the soil. The southeast part of the county was still more
                    densely populated. From their metropolis and ancient circle at Strawtown on the <geogName>White
                        river</geogName>, they followed up Duck creek and formed a continuous line of settlements on its
                    bank and through that portion of the county. There, a stone circle, several sacrificial mounds and
                    burial mounds with highly polished implements, bear evidence of their ancient existence. Again, we
                    find remains of that strange people in the southwest part of the county on the banks of Cicero
                    creek." He also says (Prehistoric and Indian History of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Howard</region>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Tipton</region>
                    </placeName> Counties, p. 17): "<placeName>
                        <region type="county">Howard county</region>
                    </placeName> is no less fertile and probably more so than <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Tipton</region>
                    </placeName> in prehistoric remains." Mr. Cox says (Geological Report of Indiana for 1878,
                    p. 128): "There are a number of circular earthwork enclosures in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Hamilton</region>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Tipton</region>
                    </placeName> counties. The principal works in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Tipton county</region>
                    </placeName> are close to Strawtown and in a cultivated field. The largest is a circle with an open
                    gateway on one side. It has been so badly obliterated by the plow that I was unable to make a
                    complete survey of it."</p>
            <p>There are two accounts of the earthworks of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Madison county</region>
                    </placeName>, one of them by E. T. Cox (E. T. Cox: ‘Geological Survey of Indiana for
                    1878. Antiquities, p. 129), published in 1878, the other by Francis A. Walker (Francis A. Walker:
                    Ancient Earthworks near <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Anderson</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indiana, Proceedings of the Indiana Academy of Science for 1892, p. SI), published in
                    1892. The two accounts differ slightly as to the number of mounds and as to the measurements of
                    them. This, however, may be accounted for by the great difference in the time of the two
                    investigations. The works which are known throughout the adjoining country as "The
                    Mounds" are about three miles from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Anderson</settlement>
                    </placeName> on the south bank of <geogName>White river</geogName>. They are situated on a bluff
                    seventy-five feet in height in the highest position in the vicinity. The high location is an
                    important fact, as the mound is one of defense. The system <pb n="36" id="VAA4025-006-1-040"/>
                    consists of one large and six or seven smaller earthworks, the smaller ones lying south and west of
                    the large one.</p>
            <p>The principal work (see map, p. 131 of Geological Survey of Indiana for 1878) is a circular
                    embankment with a ditch on the inside and a mound in the center of the enclosure. The gateway is 30
                    feet wide and opens to the south. The ditch terminates on each side of it, so that carriages may
                    enter and drive around the mound. The work is a true circle, 384 feet in diameter by Cox's
                    measurement (p. 129), or 360 feet, with an area of 2.35 acres, according to Walker (p. 51). The
                    enclosed part within the ditch is about 140 feet in diameter, with an area of about a third of an
                    acre. The ditch is 60 feet wide and is 10 1/2 feet deep according to Mr. Cox, while Mr. Walker
                    estimates its average depth at 6.92 feet The embankment is, at its base, 50 or 60 feet wide and has
                    an average height of 8 or g feet, with a variance of 3.3 feet. The mound in the center is 4 feet
                    high and 30 feet in diameter.</p>
            <p>Mr. Walker says (Proceedings of the Indiana Academy of Science for 1892, p. 53): "About ten
                    years ago the writer and Dr. Joseph Tingley, then of Asbury University, made an excavation in the
                    center of the mound in the main works. At a depth of four feet we found a bed of ashes, charcoal and
                    burned bones, the bones crumbling on exposure to the atmosphere. Dr. Tingley claimed they were not
                    human, but small animal bones. We found no stone or any arrangement of the earth in the form of an
                    altar, and the fire seemed to have been there before the mound was built above it. The earth was
                    baked and reddened by the action of the intense heat of the same. ∗ ∗
                    ∗ We dug down about two feet below this stratum, but found no further evidence of fire or
                    any unusual arrangement of the earth, nor any evidence that the same had been disturbed further than
                    by the construction of the central area, which had been filled as before mentioned" (p.
                    53).</p>
            <p>Of the other seven mounds besides this principal one, four are circular and three are of irregular
                    shape (see map, p. 131 of Geological Survey of Indiana for 1878), one of which has two gateways. One
                    has one gate and another has none visible.</p>
            <p>"On the same section (Geological Survey of Indiana for 1878, p. 133) of land, but half a
                    mile farther up the river and on the <pb n="37" id="VAA4025-006-1-041"/> same side of the stream,
                    there is another cluster of earthworks that are of nearly equal interest. In fact, the principal
                    work is in some respects more remarkable than the large circle above. The outline is irregular (see
                    map on page 135 of Geological Survey of Indiana for 1878), constricted on one end and at the side;
                    at the other end there is a gateway nine feet wide protected by two small mounds now about four feet
                    high. The wall is thirty to thirty-five feet wide at the base and about four feet high. The ditch is
                    eight feet wide."</p>
            <p>In <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Randolph county</region>
                    </placeName>, "besides a number of well-defined made mounds in the neighborhood of Lynn
                    station, there are frequent examples of natural mounds. These are usually much larger than the
                    artificial mounds. Some of these mounds of modified drifts have been utilized by ancient people as
                    burial grounds." (Joseph Moore: "Concerning a Burial Mound Recently Opened in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Randolph County</region>
                    </placeName>," Proceedings of the Indiana Academy of Science for 1894, p. 46.) In one,
                    about 150 yards in circumference, an aqueous deposit, many skeletons have been found. "Some
                    of them were in a sitting posture with the chin crowded upon the knees. The skeletons were of both
                    sexes and various ages, some quite young. There is quite a diversity in the shape of the
                    skulls."</p>
            <p>"The largest walled enclosure in the State (Geological Survey of Indiana for 1878, p. 134)
                    is situated near the town of Winchester in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Randolph county</region>
                    </placeName>. It contains thirty-one acres. The whole thing is now in a fair way to be entirely
                    obliterated. ∗ ∗ ∗ There are two gateways (see p. 137 of Geological
                    Survey of Indiana for 1878), one on! he eastern end which is twelve feet wide and has no defenses,
                    Sugar creek and the intervening bluff probably being deemed sufficient. At the west end there is an
                    embankment in the shape of a half circle which overlaps the gate and complicates the passageway. The
                    enclosure is in the shape of a parallelogram with curved angles. The sides are 1,320 feet long and
                    the ends 1,080 feet. There is a mound in the center one hundred feet in diameter and nine feet high.
                    ∗ ∗ ∗ The location was selected with due regard to proteetion
                    against sudden attack of an enemy. It is at she juncture of Sugar creek <pb n="38" id="VAA4025-006-1-042"/> and <geogName>White river</geogName>, which affords protection to two
                    sides, and the mound in the center serves as a lookout station."</p>
            <p>"Mounds occur in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Fountain county</region>
                    </placeName> near Covington and to the north of Attica; in fact, the whole valley of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Wabash</settlement>
                    </placeName> must have been, in former times, the seat of a numerous population, forming, as it did,
                    the great artery of communication between the <geogName>Ohio river</geogName> and the Lake region to
                    the north." (Foster's Prehistoric Races, etc., p. 143.)</p>
            <p>Mr. T. B. Redding is authority for the following statement as to <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Henry county</region>
                    </placeName> (Prehistoric Earthworks of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Henry county</region>
                    </placeName>, Indiana, in the Proceedings of the Indiana Academy of Science, 1891): "There
                    are twenty artificial mounds and fourteen enclosures within the limits of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Henry county</region>
                    </placeName>. There are also certain mounds or elevations that have much the appearance of
                    artificial mounds, but of which I am not sure, numbering in all twelve to fourteen, and one
                    uncertain enclosure. Of these the strong probability is that some are artificial. There is a
                    circular enclosure in Henry township. Its diameter is 115 feet; the height of embankment, at the
                    highest point from the bottom of the ditch, is about three feet. There is an open space or gateway
                    on the east side about twelve feet wide. There is the appearance of a small mound inside of the
                    enclosure toward the west side, about fifteen feet in diameter and eighteen to twenty-four inches
                    high. I will say here that in all the enclosures in this county the ditches are on the inside of the
                    enclosure."</p>
            <p>A number of mounds are reported in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Vigo</region>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Vermillion</region>
                    </placeName> counties. (Geological Survey of Indiana for 1878, p. 128.)</p>
            <p>Mounds are abundant in Green, <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Owen</region>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Morgan</region>
                    </placeName> counties. In the latter they have furnished a great many interesting relics. Some
                    mounds are said to have existed at one time in the city limits of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, but they have given way to the changes required by the growth and development of the
                    city. (Geological Survey of Indiana for 1878, p. 128.)</p>
            <p>In <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Bartholomew county</region>
                    </placeName> there are several mounds, and several skeletons have been found in them, especially in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Wayne</settlement>
                    </placeName> township. "A circular mound sixty feet in diameter and about three feet high,
                    but by cultivation now almost level with the surface of the field, is situated in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Wayne</settlement>
                    </placeName> township. Some years ago it was <pb n="39" id="VAA4025-006-1-043"/> explored and five
                    skeletons were found besides numerous stone implements. Many articles of stone, together with
                    fragments of hones, have since been obtained." (J. J. Edwards: Mounds and Zxrial Grounds of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Bartholomew county</region>
                    </placeName>, Indiana, Proceedings of Academy of Science for 1901.)</p>
            <p>There is an ancient fort on the hill, north of Hardentown in gearborn county, Indiana. The wall is
                    four feet high in places, and is partly constructed of loose stones and partly of earth. There are
                    two gateways on the north end formed by an earthwork that is nearly circular. The hill is nearly two
                    hundred feet high and commands an extensive view over the country around. On the ridge leading to
                    the northeast and northwest there are eight mounds.</p>
            <p>There are a "large number of mouuntrs in that inviting of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Aurora</settlement>
                    </placeName> and quite a large mound was within the city limits, but was long ago almost entirely
                    removed by cutting a street way through it. (Antiquities: Geological Survey of Indiana for 1878, p.
                    122.)</p>
            <p>Mr. Foster quotes the following from Mr. John Collett's report of the Geological Survey of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Sullivan county</region>
                    </placeName> (Prehistoric Races, etc., p. 14): "Numerous earthworks are found in this
                    region of such an extent as to require for their construction time and persistent labor of many
                    people. Situated on the river bluffs, their location combines picturesque scenery, susceptibility
                    for defense and convenience to transportation; water and productive lands. These are not requisites
                    in the nomadic life of the red men, and identify the Mound Builders as a partly civilized
                    agricultural people."</p>
            <p>The principal earthworks of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Sullivan county</region>
                    </placeName> are on the east bank of the <geogName>Wabash river</geogName> at Merom. This enclosure
                    has been called Fort Azatlan, and is one of the principal ones of Indiana. It is irregular, but on
                    the whole may be called three-sided. (See map, p. 134, of Foster's Prehistoric Races.)
                    "On the river side the bank ∗ ∗ ∗ is very steep, and forms
                    the western line of fortification, while deep ravines add to its strength on the other sides, the
                    weak points being strengthened by earthworks. The general course of the work is from the north,
                    where it is very narrow, not over fifty feet, owing to the formation of the plateau, south along the
                    river bank ∗ ∗ ∗ to its widest portion, which <pb n="40" id="VAA4025-006-1-044"/> is here about 375 feet east and west. ∗ ∗
                    ∗ There is a continued line, in part natural and in part artificial, which if measured in
                    all its ins and outs would not be far from 2,450 feet. ∗ ∗ ∗ This
                    location is the one spot of the region, for several miles along the river, that would be selected
                    to-day for the erection of a fortification in the vicinity, with the addition of the possession of a
                    small eminence to the north." Inside the enclosure there are five mounds and forty-five
                    depressions, all of which are circular except one, and that is oval. (Foster, p. 136.) After having
                    dug into two of the depressions, Mr. Putnam decided that they had been large pits that had been
                    filled up by "the accumulation of vegetable matter and soil that had been deposited by
                    natural action alone." A trench was dug across one of them and "the former bottom
                    was reached at a depth of about five feet. On this bottom ashes and burnt clay gave evidence of an
                    ancient fire, and at a few feet on one side several pieces of pottery, a few bones of animals and
                    one stone arrowhead were found. A spot had evidently been struck where food had been cooked and
                    eaten. ∗ ∗ ∗ The legitimate conclusion to be drawn from the facts
                    is that these pits were the houses of the inhabitants or defenders of the fort, who were probably
                    further protected from the elements and arrows of assailants by a roof of logs and bark or boughs.
                    The position of all the mounds within the enclosure ∗ ∗ ∗ is such
                    as to suggest that they were used as observatories, and it may be questioned if the human and other
                    remains found in them were placed there by the occupants of the fort, or are to be considered under
                    the head of intrusive burials by a later race."</p>
            <p>In <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Knox county</region>
                    </placeName>, near <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName>, there are several mounds of unusual size. (Geological Survey of Indiana for 1878, p.
                    127.) Mr. Foster says (Foster's Prehistoric Races, etc., p. 132): "In 1859,
                    according to Mr. William Pidgeon, it became necessary to remove a mound ∗ ∗
                    ∗ in the suburbs of the city. It was about sixteen feet in height, with a diameter of
                    sixty-six feet and a section of it exhibited five distinct strata. The first or lowest consisted of
                    a bed of human bones arranged in a circle eighteen feet in diameter, closely pressed together.
                    Around the outer edge of this circle the stratum was thinner than in the center. Skulls, tibia, ribs
                    and vertebrae were promiscuously mingled as <pb n="41" id="VAA4025-006-1-045"/> though a pile of
                    bodies had been heaped up. ∗ ∗ ∗ Mr. Pid-geon was disposed to
                    regard this as a ‘battleground’."</p>
            <p>In <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Ohio county</region>
                    </placeName> J. B. Gerard, M. D., in connection with others, opened a mound near the mouth of
                    Laughery creek which was about one hundred feet in diameter and fifteen feet high; excavations were
                    made at several places, and they found human bones, one whole earthen pot and a great many fragments
                    of pottery. "Dr. Gerard has noticed from twenty to thirty mounds along the bluffs of
                    Laughery creek and has opened a number of them, but found nothing of note except ashes, which lay at
                    the base of them all." (Antiquities: Geological Survey of Indiana for 1878, p. 122.)</p>
            <p>The great work of the Mound Builders in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clark county</region>
                    </placeName> is called the "Stone Fort." Mr. Cox says: "At the mouth of
                    Fourteen Mile creek and about three miles from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Charlestown</settlement>
                    </placeName>, the county seat of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clark county</region>
                    </placeName>, there is one of the most remarkable stone fortifications which has ever come under my
                    notice. ∗ ∗ ∗ The locality selected for this fort presents many
                    natural advantages for making it impregnable to the opposing forces of prehistoric times. It
                    occupies the point of an elevated narrow ridge which faces the <geogName>Ohio river</geogName> on
                    the east and is bordered by Fourteen Mile creek on the west side.∗ ∗
                    ∗ Along the greater part of the <geogName>Ohio river</geogName> front there is an abrupt
                    escarpment of rock entirely too steep to be scaled, and a similar natural barrier exists along a
                    portion of the northwest side of the ridge facing the creek. ∗ ∗ ∗
                    Although the locality afforded many natural advantages for a fort or stronghold, one is compelled to
                    admit that much skill was displayed and labor expended in rendering its defense as perfect as
                    possible at all points. Stone axes, pestles, arrowheads, spear points, "totums, charms and
                    flint flakes have been found in great abundance in plowing the field at the foot of the old
                    fort." (Geological Survey of Indiana for 1873, p. 125.)</p>
            <p>In <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Vanderburgh county</region>
                    </placeName> there is an enclosure of considerable size described by Mr. A. H. Purdue. "In
                    the southeast corner of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Vanderburgh county</region>
                    </placeName> is a collection of mounds and earthworks. They are locally known as the
                    ‘Angel Mounds.’ The remains lie between two bayous, one on the south side and
                    one on the north. When in perfect condition there was probably an enclosure, <pb n="42" id="VAA4025-006-1-046"/> formed by the bank of the bayou on the south and an irregularly curved
                    wall, presumably a rampart, either end of which was terminated by the embankment. At the present
                    (1896) there are about 1,400 yards of this wall remaining. At intervals, usually of thirty-seven to
                    forty yards, there are semi-circular mounds with radii of from eight to ten feet joined to the outer
                    side of the wall. On the supposition that the wall was a rampart, these semi-circular projections
                    from it were probably lookouts. The most striking object is the large mound. Its longest diameter is
                    500 feet. The width varies from 175 to 225 feet. With reference to altitude, it is divided into
                    three parts. The third part is a dome, the highest point of which is thirty-nine feet above the
                    ground on which the mound rests. If the trees along the <geogName>Ohio river</geogName> were
                    removed, the top of this dome would afford a commanding view for several miles up and down the
                    river. There are six other mounds within the enclosure. These are circular at the base and have
                    rounded tops, with the exception of one, which is a truncated cone 160 feet in diameter. It is used
                    by the neighborhood for a burying ground. Pieces of pottery such as is now made by the western
                    Indians are common within the enclosure." (A. H. Purdue: Some Mounds of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Vanderburgh county</region>
                    </placeName>, Proceedings of Indiana Academy of Science for 1896.)</p>
            <p>"Going down the <geogName>Ohio river</geogName> to the mouth of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Wabash</settlement>
                    </placeName>, there are a great number of mounds and earthworks of small magnitude. ∗
                    ∗ ∗ Mounds are particularly numerous in the vicinity of <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">New Harmony</settlement>, <region type="county">Posey
                    county</region>
               </placeName>, sixty miles above the mouth of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Wabash</settlement>
                    </placeName>. The town itself occupies the site of an immense group of mounds." (Geological
                    Survey of Indiana for 1878, p. 126.)</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="[43]" id="VAA4025-006-1-047"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-006-1-a04">
            <head>BIBLIOGRAPHY OF INDIANA LOCAL HISTORY CONTAINED IN COUNTY HISTORIES, ATLASES AND COLLECTED
                    BIOGRAPHIES.</head>
            <byline>PREPARED BY MISS HENLEY, INDIANA STATE LIBRARY.</byline>
            <list type="bibliography">
               <item>Adams. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Biographical and historical record of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Adams</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Wells</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind. n. d.</item>
                     <item>Lynch, Mrs. M. C. M. Reminiscences of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Adams</region>,
                                        <region type="county">Jay</region>, <region type="county">Randolph</region>
                        </placeName> counties. n. d.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Allen. <list type="simple">
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Allen county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) history, with illustrations and biographical sketches of some of its
                                prominent men and pioneers. 1880.</item>
                     <item>Knapp, H. S. History of the <geogName>Maumee valley</geogName>. 1872.</item>
                     <item>Valley of the <geogName>Upper Maulhee river</geogName>. zv. 1889.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Bartholomew. <list type="simple">
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Bartholomew county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) atlas, to which are added various general maps, history, statistics.
                                1879.</item>
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Bartholomew county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1888.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Benton. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In Biographical history of Tippecanoe, White, Jasper, Newton, Benton, etc.)</item>
                     <item>(In Counties of Warren, Benton, etc.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Blackford. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Shinn, Benjamin G. Biographical memoirs of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Blackford county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1900.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Boone. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Portrait and biographical record of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Boone</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Clinton</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind., containing biographies of governors of Indiana.
                            1895.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Brown. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In Blanchard, Charles. Counties of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Morgan</region>,
                                        <region type="county">Monroe</region>
                        </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Brown</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1884.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Carroll. <list type="simple">
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Carroll county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) illustrated historical atlas. 1874.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <pb n="44" id="VAA4025-006-1-048"/>
               <item>Cass. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Biographical and genealogical history of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Cass</region>, <region type="county">Miami</region>, <region type="county">Howard</region>
                        </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Tipton</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind. 2v. 1878.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Clark. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Baird, Lewis C. History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Clark county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1909.</item>
                     <item>Gresham, John M. &amp; Co., comp. Biographical and historical souvenir for the
                                counties of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Clark</region>, <region type="county">Crawford</region>, <region type="county">Harrison</region>, <region type="county">Floyd</region>
                        </placeName>, Jderson, <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Jennings</region>, <region type="county">Scott</region>
                        </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Washington</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1889.</item>
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                                </placeName> Falls cities and their counties, with biographical sketches. 2v.
                            1882.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Clay. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Blanchard, Charles, ed. Counties of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Clay</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Owen</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1884.</item>
                     <item>Travis, William. History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Clay county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 2v. 1909.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Clinton. <list type="simple">
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Clinton county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1886.</item>
                     <item>(In Portrait and biographical record of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Boone</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Clinton</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind., containing biographies of governors of Indiana,
                            1895.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Crawford. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In Gresham, John M. &amp; Co., comp. Biographical and historical souvenir for the
                                counties of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Clark</region>, <region type="county">Crawford</region>
                        </placeName>, etc.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Daviess. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Knox</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Daviess</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind. 1886.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Dearborn. <list type="simple">
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Dearborn county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) atlas, from actual of D. J. Lake and B. N. Griffing; to which is
                                added a map of the State of Indiana, also an outline and railroad map of the <placeName>
                                    <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                                </placeName>. 1875. (Contains historical sketch.)</item>
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Dearborn</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind. 1885.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Decatur. <list type="simple">
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Decatur county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) atlas; to which are added various general maps, history, statistics.
                                1882.</item>
                     <item>Historical sketches of Fugit township, <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Decatur county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind., papers read at the old settlers' reunion held at Mt.
                                Carmel, June 6, 1901, and other interesting facts. 1901.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <pb n="45" id="VAA4025-006-1-049"/>
               <item>DeKalb. <list type="simple">
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">DeKalb county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) atlas, to which are added various general maps, history, statistics.
                                1880.</item>
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">DeKalb county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1885.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Delaware. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Ellis, John S. Our county (<placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Delaware</region>
                                </placeName>), its history and early settlement by townships, entry of public lands,
                                present owners, reminiscences of pioneer life, etc. 1898.</item>
                     <item>Portrait and biographical record of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Delaware county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind., containing biographical sketches of prominent and representative
                                citizens, and biographies of the governors of Indiana.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Dubois. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Pike</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Dubois county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1885.)</item>
                     <item>Wilson, George. History and art souvenir of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Dubois county</region>
                                </placeName>. 1896.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Elkhart. <list type="simple">
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Elkhart county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) historical atlas. 1874.</item>
                     <item>Indiana State Library, col. Sketches of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Elkhart county</region>
                                </placeName> history. 1907. (Newspaper clippings mounted.)</item>
                     <item>Pictorial and biographical memoirs of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Elkhart</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">St. Joseph</region>
                                </placeName> counties, together with biographies of many prominent men of northern
                                Indiana. 1893.</item>
                     <item>Stone, Wilbur L. <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Elkhart county</region>
                                </placeName> railroads. 1899. (Clippings from <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Goshen county</region>
                                </placeName> Daily Democrat, Jan. 6, 1899.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Fayette. <list type="simple">
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Fayette county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1885.</item>
                     <item>(In Biographical and genealogical history of Wayne, Fayette, etc.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Floyd. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Bailey, John C. W., comp. <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Floyd county</region>
                                </placeName> gazetteer, containing a directory of the city of <placeName>
                                    <settlement type="city">New Albany</settlement>
                                </placeName>, with an historical and descriptive sketch of the county and a directory of
                                names, occupations and post-office address of the merchants, manufacturers and farmers.
                                1868.</item>
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                                </placeName> Falls cities and their counties, with biographical sketches. 2v. 1882.</item>
                     <pb n="46" id="VAA4025-006-1-050"/>
                     <item>(In Gresham, John M. &amp; Co., comp. Biographical and historical souvenir for the
                                counties of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Clark</region>, <region type="county">Crawford</region>, <region type="county">Harrison</region>, <region type="county">Floyd</region>
                        </placeName>, etc.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Fountain. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Ristine, Joseph. Early settlement in <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Fountain county</region>
                                </placeName> from 1826–1841. 1879 (pam.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Franklin. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Bogart, G. Henri. History of the early courts and courthouses of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Franklin county</region>
                                </placeName>. 1908. (Clippings from the <placeName>
                                    <settlement type="city">Brookville</settlement>
                                </placeName> Democrat, July 30, 1908.)</item>
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Franklin county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) atlas, to which are added various general maps, history, statistics.
                                1882.</item>
                     <item>Indiana State Library, comp. Photographs and views and historic places of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Franklin county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1908.</item>
                     <item>(In Biographical and genealogical history of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Wayne</region>, <region type="county">Fayette</region>, <region type="county">Union</region>
                        </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Franklin</region>
                                </placeName> counties.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Fulton. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Peattie, Mrs. Elia Wilkinson. Pictorial story of <placeName>
                                    <country>America</country>
                                </placeName>, containing the romantic incidents of history from the discovery of <placeName>
                                    <country>America</country>
                                </placeName> to the present time (with a history of Indiana and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Fulton county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind.). 1896.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Grant. <list type="simple">
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Grant county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) combination atlas. 1877.</item>
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Grant county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1886.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Greene. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Baber, Uncle Jack. Early history of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Greene county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1875.</item>
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Greene</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Sullivan</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind. 1884.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Hamilton. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Helm, T. B. History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Hamilton county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1880.</item>
                     <item>Shirts, Augustus Finch. History of the formation, settlement and development of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Hamilton county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind., from 1818 to the close of the Civil war. 1901.</item>
                     <item>(In Portrait and biographical record of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Madison</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Hamilton</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind., containing biographical sketches of prominent and
                                representative citizens of the counties, together with biographies and portraits of all
                                the presidents of the U. S. 1893.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <pb n="47" id="VAA4025-006-1-051"/>
               <item>Hancock. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Binford, J. H. History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Hancock county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind., 1818–1882. 1882.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Harrison. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In Gresham, John M. &amp; Co., comp. Biographical and historical souvenir for the
                                counties of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Clark</region>, <region type="county">Crawford</region>, <region type="county">Harrison</region>
                        </placeName>,
                            etc.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Hendricks. <list type="simple">
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Hendricks</region>
                                </placeName> countj- (Ind.) atlas, to which is added various general maps, history,
                                statistics. 1878.</item>
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Hendriclts county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind., together with sketches of its cities, villages and towns,
                                educational, religious, civil, military and political history, portraits of prominent
                                persons and biographies of representative citizens. 1885.</item>
                     <item>People's guide: a business, political and religious directory of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Hendricks county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind.; also a historical sketch of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Hendricks county</region>
                                </placeName> and a brief history of each township. 1874.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Henry. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Hazzard, George. History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Henry county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind., 1822–1906. 2v. 1906.</item>
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Henry county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) topography, history, art folios, including chronological chart of
                                general, national, State and county history. 1893.</item>
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Henry county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind., together with sketches of its cities, villages and towns, etc. 1884.</item>
                     <item>People's guide; a directory of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Henry county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1874, (Contains a historical sketch.)</item>
                     <item>Pleas, Elwood. <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Henry county</region>
                                </placeName>, 1821–1871. 1871.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Howard. <list type="simple">
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Howard county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) combination atlas map. 1877.</item>
                     <item>Overman, N. R. Prehistoric and Indian history of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Howard</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Tipton</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind. 1883.</item>
                     <item>(In Biographical and genealogical history of Cass, Miami. Howard, etc.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Huntington. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Historical sketch of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Huntington county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind 1877.</item>
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Huntington county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1887.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <pb n="48" id="VAA4025-006-1-052"/>
               <item>Jackson. <list type="simple">
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Jackson county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1886.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Jasper. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In Biographical history of Tippecanoe, White, Jasper, etc.)</item>
                     <item>(In Counties of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Warren</region>, <region type="county">Benton</region>, <region type="county">Jasper</region>
                        </placeName>, etc.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Jay. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Kelley, J. Will, cornp. New atlas of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Jay county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind., comp. from the records 1901. 1901.</item>
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Montgomery</region>
                                </placeName>, M. W. History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Jay county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1864.</item>
                     <item>(In Lynch, Mrs. M. C. M. Reminiscences of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Adams</region>, <region type="county">Jay</region>, <region type="county">Randolph</region>
                        </placeName> counties. n. d.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Jefferson. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Vawter, John. Pioneers of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Jefferson county</region>
                                </placeName>. 1850. (Elvin's Scrap-book, p. 68.)</item>
                     <item>(In 'Gresham, John M. &amp; Co., comp. Biographical and historical
                                souvenir for the counties of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Clark</region>, <region type="county">Crawford</region>, <region type="county">Harrison</region>,
                                        <region type="county">Floyd</region>, <region type="county">Jefferson</region>
                        </placeName>, etc.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Jennings. <list type="simple">
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Jennings county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) atlas. 1884.</item>
                     <item>(In 'Gresham, John M. &amp; Co., comp. Biographical and historical
                                souvenir for the counties of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Clark</region>, <region type="county">Crawford</region>, <region type="county">Harrison</region>,
                                        <region type="county">Floyd</region>, <region type="county">Jefferson</region>,
                                        <region type="county">Jennings</region>
                        </placeName>, etc.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Johnson. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Banta, David Demaree. Historical sketches of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Johnson county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1881.</item>
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Johnson county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1888.</item>
                     <item>(In <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Shelby</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Johnson</region>
                                </placeName> counties (Ind.) plat book. n. d.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Knox. <list type="simple">
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Knox</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Daviess</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind. 1886.</item>
                     <item>Western Sun. Centennial anniversary number, 1804-July, 1904.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Kosciusko. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Biographical and historical record of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Kosciusko county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1887.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Lagrange. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Counties of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Lagrange</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Noble</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind.; historical and biographical. 1882.</item>
                     <pb n="49" id="VAA4025-006-1-053"/>
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Lagrange county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) illustrated atlas and <placeName>
                                    <settlement type="city">Columbia</settlement>
                                </placeName> souvenir, showing its development in the first sixty years since
                                organization. 1893.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Lake. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Ball, Timothy Horton. <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Lake county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind., 1834–1872. 1873.</item>
                     <item>Ball, Timothy Horton, ed. <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Lake county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind., 1884; an account of the semi-centennial celebration of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Lake county</region>
                                </placeName>, Sept. 3 and 4, with historical papers and other interesting records
                                prepared. 1884.</item>
                     <item>(In Goodspeed, W. A., and Blanchard, C. Counties of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Porter</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Lake</region>
                                </placeName>. 1882.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>LaPorte. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Daniels, E. D. Twentieth century history and biographical record of LaPorte county,
                                Ind. 1904.</item>
                     <item>History of LaPorte county, Ind. 1880.</item>
                     <item>Packard, Jasper. History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">LaPorte county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1876.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Lawrence. <list type="simple">
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Lawrence</region>, <region type="county">Orange</region>
                        </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Washington</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind., from the earliest time to the present; together with
                                interesting biographical sketches, reminiscences, notes, etc. 1884.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Madison. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Forkner, J. L., &amp; Dyson, B. H. Historical sketches and reminiscences of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Madison county</region>
                                </placeName>. 1897.</item>
                     <item>Harden, Samuel, comp. History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Madison county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind., 1820–1874. 1874.</item>
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Madison county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind., with illustrations and biographical sketches. 1880.</item>
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Madison county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) atlas and directory, including a directory of free-holders and
                                official register of the county; compiled by the American Atlas Co. 1901.</item>
                     <item>Portrait and biographical record of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Madison</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Hamilton</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind., containing biographical sketches of prominent and
                                representative citizens of the counties, together with biographies and portraits of all
                                the presidents of the u. s. 1892.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Marion. <list type="simple">
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Marion county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) atlas. 1889.</item>
                     <pb n="50" id="VAA4025-006-1-054"/>
                     <item>People's guide; a directory of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Marion county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1874.</item>
                     <item>Pictorial and biographical memoirs of <placeName>
                                    <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Marion county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1893.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Marshall. <list type="simple">
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Marshall county</region>
                                </placeName>. (History of Indiana, Vol. 11. 1890.)</item>
                     <item>McDonald, Daniel. A Twentieth century history of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Marshall county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1908.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Miami. <list type="simple">
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Miami county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1887.</item>
                     <item>(In Biographical and genealogical history of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Cass</region>, <region type="county">Miami</region>
                        </placeName>, etc.)</item>
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Miami county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind., combination atlas-map, comp. by King-man Bros. 1877.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Monroe. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In Blanchard, Charles. Counties of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Morgan</region>,
                                        <region type="county">Monroe</region>
                        </placeName>, etc.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Montgomery. <list type="simple">
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Harrison</region>
                                </placeName>, John W. Some early history. 1909. (Newspaper clippings from Ladoga
                                Leader.)</item>
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Montgomery county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) atlas, to which are added various general maps, history, statistics.
                                1878.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Morgan. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Blanchard, Charles. Counties of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Morgan</region>,
                                        <region type="county">Monroe</region>
                        </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Brown</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1884.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Noble. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In Counties of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Lagrange</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Noble</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind., historical and biographical. 1882.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Newton. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In Biographical history of Tippecanoe, White, Jasper, Newton, etc.)</item>
                     <item>(In Counties of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Warren</region>, <region type="county">Benton</region>, <region type="county">Jasper</region>
                        </placeName>
                                and Newton, Ind., historical and biographical. 1883.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>
                  <placeName>
                            <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                        </placeName>. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Dearborn</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Ohio</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind. 1885.)</item>
                     <item>(In <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Switzerland</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Ohio</region>
                                </placeName> counties (Ind.) atlas. 1883.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Orange. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Rhodes, Andrew Jackson. Wonders of <geogName>Lost River</geogName>; 40 miles of
                                underground river, with its caves and hidden waterfalls, <pb n="51" id="VAA4025-006-1-055"/> blind fish and other wonders. 1905.</item>
                     <item>(In History of <placeName>
                           <settlement type="city">Lawrence</settlement>, <settlement type="city">Orange</settlement>
                        </placeName>, etc.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Owen. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In Blanchard, Charles, ed. Counties of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Clay</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Owen</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1884.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Parke. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Vigo</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Parke</region>
                                </placeName> counties. 1880.)</item>
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Parke county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) atlas, map, comp. by A. T. Andreas. 1874. (Historical and
                                biographical sketches.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Perry. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In History of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Warrick</region>, <region type="county">Spencer</region>
                        </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Perry</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind. 1885.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Pike. <list type="simple">
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Pike</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Dubois</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind. 1885.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>
                  <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Porter</settlement>
                        </placeName>. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Goodspeed, W. A., &amp; Blanchard, C. Counties of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Porter</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Lake</region>
                                </placeName>. 1882.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Posey. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Hovey, Alvin P. Centennial historical sketch of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Posey county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. n. d. pam.</item>
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Posey county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) illustrated atlas. 1900. (Biographical sketches.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Pulaski. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In Biographical history of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Tippecanoe</region>,
                                        <region type="county">White</region>, <region type="county">Jasper</region>
                        </placeName>, Newton, <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Benton</region>,
                                        <region type="county">Warren</region>
                        </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Pulaski</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind. 2v. 1899.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Putnam. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Biographical and historical record of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Putnam county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1887.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Randolph. <list type="simple">
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Randolph county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) atlas, to which is added a map of the State. 1874.</item>
                     <item>Tucker, E. History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Randolph county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind., with illustrations and biographical sketches. 1882.</item>
                     <item>(In Lynch, Mrs. M. C. M. Reminiscences of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Adams</region>, <region type="county">Jay</region>, <region type="county">Randolph</region>
                        </placeName> counties. n. d.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Rush. <list type="simple">
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Rush county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) atlas and directory, historical, educational, biographical,
                                miscellaneous. 1908.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <pb n="52" id="VAA4025-006-1-056"/>
               <item>St. Joseph. <list type="simple">
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">St. Joseph county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1880.</item>
                     <item>Howard, Timothy Edward. History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">St. Joseph county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 2v. 1907.</item>
                     <item>(In Pictorial and biographical memoirs of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Elkhart</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">St. Joseph</region>
                                </placeName> counties, together with biographies of many prominent men of northern
                                Indiana. 1893.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Scott. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In Gresham, John M. &amp; Co., comp. Biographical and historical souvenir for the
                                counties of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Clark</region>, <region type="county">Crawford</region>, <region type="county">Harrison</region>, <region type="county">Floyd</region>, <region type="county">Jefferson</region>, <region type="county">Jennings</region>, <region type="county">Scott</region>
                        </placeName>, etc.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Shelby. <list type="simple">
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Shelby county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1887.</item>
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Shelby county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind., from 1816–1842, by a committee of citizens. 1879. (pam.)</item>
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Shelby</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Johnson</region>
                                </placeName> counties (Ind.) plat book. n. d.</item>
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Shelby county</region>
                                </placeName>, Committee of citizens. History, 1822–1876. 40 pp. 1876.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Spencer. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In History of Warrick, Spencer, etc.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Starke. <list type="simple">
                     <item>McCormick, Chester A. McCormick's guide to <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Starke county</region>
                                </placeName>; or a past and a present view of our territory. 1902.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Steuben</settlement>
                        </placeName>. <list type="simple">
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Steuben county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1885.</item>
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Steuben county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) atlas, art folio, directory. 1898.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Sullivan. <list type="simple">
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Sullivan county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) standard atlas. 1899.</item>
                     <item>Wolfe, Thomas J., ed. History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Sullivan county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 2v. 1909.</item>
                     <item>(In History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Greene</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Sullivan</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind. 1884.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>
                  <placeName>
                            <country reg="sz">Switzerland</country>
                        </placeName>. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Dufour, Perret. History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Switzerland county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. n. d. (Copied from manuscript.)</item>
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <country reg="sz">Switzerland</country>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                                </placeName> counties (Ind.) atlas. 1883.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Tippecanoe. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Biographical history of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Tippecanoe</region>, <region type="county">White</region>, <region type="county">Jasper</region>
                        </placeName>,
                                Newton, <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Benton</region>, <region type="county">Warren</region>
                        </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Pulaski</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind. 2v. 1899.</item>
                     <pb n="53" id="VAA4025-006-1-057"/>
                     <item>Biographical record and portrait album of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Tippecanoe county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1888.</item>
                     <item>Tippecanoe county (Ind.) combination atlas, map, comp. by Kingman Bros. 1878.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Tipton. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In Biographical and genealogical history of Cass, Miami, Howard and Tipton, etc.)</item>
                     <item>(In Orerman, N. R. Prehistoric and Indian history of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Howard</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Tipton</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind. 1883.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Union. <list type="simple">
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Union county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) atlas, to which are added various general maps, history and
                                statistics. 1884.</item>
                     <item>(In Biographical and genealogical history of Wayne, Fayette, Union, etc.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Vanderburgh. <list type="simple">
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Vanderburgh</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Warrick</region>
                                </placeName> counties (Ind.) illustrated plat book. n. d.</item>
                     <item>Elliott, Joseph P. History of <placeName>
                                    <settlement type="city">Evansville</settlement>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Vanderburgh county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1897.</item>
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Vanderburgh county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1889.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Vermillion. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Biographical and historical record of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Vermillion county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind.; portraits, biographies; condensed history of Indiana. 1888.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Vigo. <list type="simple">
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Vigo</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Parke</region>
                                </placeName> counties. 1880.</item>
                     <item>Oakey, C. C. Greater <placeName>
                                    <settlement type="city">Terre Haute</settlement>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Vigo county</region>
                                </placeName>, closing the first century's history of city and county. 2v. 1908.</item>
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Vigo county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) atlas, map, comp. by A. T. Andreas. 1874</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Wabash. <list type="simple">
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Wabash county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1884.</item>
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Wabash county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) atlas, from actual surveys by and under the direction of Hosea Paul.
                                1875.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Warren. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Counties of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Warren</region>, <region type="county">Benton</region>, <region type="county">Jasper</region>
                        </placeName> and Newton,
                                Ind.; historical and biographical. 1883.</item>
                     <pb n="54" id="VAA4025-006-1-058"/>
                     <item>(In Biographical history of Tippecanoe, White, Jasper, Newton, Benton, Warren,
                            etc.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Warrick. <list type="simple">
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Warrick</region>, <region type="county">Spencer</region>
                        </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Perry</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind., from the earliest times to the present, together with
                                interesting biographical sketches, reminiscences, etc. 1885.</item>
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Warrick county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) standard atlas. 1899.</item>
                     <item>(In <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Vanderburgh</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Warrick</region>
                                </placeName> counties (Ind.) illustrated plat book. n. d.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>
                  <placeName>
                            <region type="state" reg="wau">Washington</region>
                        </placeName>. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In Gresham, John M. &amp; Co., comp. Biographical and historical souvenir for the
                                counties of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Clark</region>, <region type="county">Crawford</region>, <region type="county">Harrison</region>, <region type="county">Floyd</region>, <region type="county">Jefferson</region>, <region type="county">Jennings</region>, <region type="county">Scott</region>
                        </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="state" reg="wau">Washington</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1889.)</item>
                     <item>(In History of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Lawrence</region>, <region type="county">Orange</region>
                        </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Washington</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind., from the earliest time to the present; together with
                                interesting biographical sketches, reminiscences, notes, etc. 1884.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Wayne. <list type="simple">
                     <item>Biographical and genealogical history of <placeName>
                           <region type="county">Wayne</region>, <region type="county">Fayette</region>, <region type="county">Union</region>
                        </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Franklin</region>
                                </placeName> counties, Ind. 2v. 1899.</item>
                     <item>History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Wayne county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 2v. 1884.</item>
                     <item>
                        <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Wayne county</region>
                                </placeName> (Ind.) imperial atlas and art folio, including chronological charts,
                                statistical tables. 1853.</item>
                     <item>Young, Andrew White. History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Wayne county</region>
                                </placeName>, Ind. 1872.</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Wells. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In Biographical and historical record of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Adams</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Wells</region>
                                </placeName> counties.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>White. <list type="simple">
                     <item>(In Biographical history of Tippecanoe, White, etc.)</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <pb n="[55]" id="VAA4025-006-1-059"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-006-1-a05">
            <head>INDEX OF HISTORICAL ARTICLES IN INDIANA NEWSPAPERS.</head>
            <head>DECEMBER, 1909–FEBRUARY, 1910.</head>
            <byline>PREPARED BY MISS FLORENCE VENN, Reference Librarian, Indiana State Library.</byline>
            <p rend="center">Abbreviations: Ind., <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>; mag. sec., magazine section; p., page; c., column.</p>
            <list type="simple">
               <item>Bridges. Oldest covered bridge in State spans Whitewater canal at <placeName>
                     <settlement type="city">Brookville</settlement>. <settlement type="city">Terre
                        Haute</settlement>
                  </placeName> Star, Dec. 26, 1909, mag sec., P. 4.</item>
               <item>Brown, George P. Death of prominent Indiana educator. Richmond Palladium, Feb. 3, 1910, p. 8,
                        c. 3.</item>
               <item>
                  <placeName>
                            <region type="county">Brown county</region>
                        </placeName>. Overshot mill built in 1835 still in operation. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Terre Haute</settlement>
                        </placeName> Star, Feb. 5, 1910, p. 5, c. 2.</item>
               <item>Bundy, Martin L. Death of pioneer resident of Indiana. Ind. Star, Feb. 18, 1910, p. 9, c. 1.
                        Ind. News, Feb. 17, 1910, p. 1, c. 2.</item>
               <item>Carpenter, Walter Totten. Sketch of Richmond man who celebrates his ninety-ninth birthday.
                        Ind. News, Jan. 1, 1910, p. 7, c. 5. Richmond Item, Dec. 30, 1909, p. 1, c. 7. Richmond
                        Palladium, Jan. 2, 1910, p. 6, c. 2.</item>
               <item>Christian science. History of, in Indiana. Ind. News, Dec. 25, 1909, p. 11.</item>
               <item>Clark, George Rogers. First and greatest of the winners of the west. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Evansville</settlement>
                        </placeName> Courier, Dec. 25, 1909, p. 8.</item>
               <item>Confederate soldiers. Vandalia railroad deeds to U. S. lots in which Confederate soldiers are
                        buried in <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                        </placeName>. Ind. Star, Jan. 5, 1910, p. 14, c. 3.</item>
               <item>Congregational church. History of First Congregational church in <placeName>
                     <settlement type="city">Terre Haute</settlement>. <settlement type="city">Terre
                        Haute</settlement>
                  </placeName> Star, Dec. 26, 1909, p. 12, c. 6.</item>
               <item>Constitutional elm. D. A. R. cares for it. Ind. Star, Dec. 5, 1909, mag sec., p. 5, c. 2. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Terre Haute</settlement>
                        </placeName> Star, Dec. 5, 1909, mag. sec., P.3.</item>
               <item>Douglass, Frederick. Once attacked at Pendleton. Ind. News, Feb. 19, 1910, p. 5, c. 2.</item>
               <item>Dudley, W. W. Death of. Sketch of life. Ind. Star, Dec. 16, 1909, p. 4, c. 4. Ind. News, Dec.
                        15, 1909, p. 1, c. 2. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                        </placeName>
                        <pb n="56" id="VAA4025-006-1-060"/> Palladium, Dec. 16, 1909, p. 1, c. 7. Richmond Item, Dec.
                        16, p. 1, c. 7.</item>
               <item>Dunning, Ellen Douglas. Death of widow of Paris C. Dunning. Evansville Journal-News, Feb. 1,
                        1910, p. 1, c. 4. Ind. News, Feb. 1, 1910, p. 14, c. 2.</item>
               <item>Eggleston, Edward. Stone bee house mentioned in "Hoosier school-boy." Ind.
                        News, Feb. 7, 1910, p. 14, c. 2.</item>
               <item>Food. Old account books show high prices paid in <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                        </placeName> in 1867. Ind. Star, Feb. 27, 1910, p. 30, c. 2.</item>
               <item>Greene, Nelson. Experience as a circuit rider in early Indiana. Ind. News, Feb. 20, 1910, p.
                        8, c. 4. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Terre Haute</settlement>
                        </placeName> Star, Feb. 24, 1910, p. 7, c. 3. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Muncie</settlement>
                        </placeName> Star, Feb. 21, 1910, p. 3, c. 1.</item>
               <item>Harris, Lee O. Death of. Sketch of life. Ind. News, Dec. 24, 1909, p. 1, c. 2.</item>
               <item>Harrison, William Henry. Mansion at <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                        </placeName> may be removed to Harrison park. Ind. News, Dec. 9, 1909, p. 9, c.
                        2.—May be presented to city of <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                        </placeName>. Ind. Star, Jan. 1, 1910, P. 3, c. 5.—City council refuses to lease
                        mansion. It may be razed. Ind. News, Feb. 15, 1910, p. 2, c. 4.—<placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                        </placeName> up in arms to save mansion. Ind. Star, Feb. 16, 1910, p. 5, c. 2.—List
                        of <placeName>
                            <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                        </placeName> soldiers who fought under <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Harrison</settlement>
                        </placeName> in war of 1812. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Ft. Wayne</settlement>
                        </placeName> Journal-Gazette, Dec. 7, rgq, p. 11, c. 3.</item>
               <item>Heaton, Charles M. Extracts from letters written at <placeName>
                            <region type="state" reg="wau">Washington</region>
                        </placeName> by him during Civil war times. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">South Bend</settlement>
                        </placeName> Tribune, Dec. 18, 1909, pt. 2, pp. 6–7.</item>
               <item>Indiana—History—Civil war. Col. McReynoIds recalls incidents of war in
                        the vicinity of Newburg and <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Evansville</settlement>
                        </placeName>. Evansville Journal-News, Jan. 23, 1910, pt. 2, p. 1, c. 1.—Butternut
                        pin and Lincoln badge recall partisan days in southern Indiana. Ind. Star, Feb. 6, 1910, p. 4,
                        c. 2.</item>
               <item>Indiana State normal school. President Parsons reviews history of. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Terre Haute</settlement>
                        </placeName> Star, Jan. 7, 1910, p. 7, c. 1.</item>
               <item>Indiana University. Chronological tables giving its history. Ind. Star, Jan. 20, 1910, p. 4,
                        c. 3.</item>
               <item>
                  <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                        </placeName>. First play produced in city. Ind. Star, Jan. 23, 1910, mag sec., p. 7. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Terre Haute</settlement>
                        </placeName> Star, Jan. 23, 1910, mag <pb n="57" id="VAA4025-006-1-061"/> sec., p. 3. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Muncie</settlement>
                        </placeName> Star, Jan. 23, 1910, pt. 1, p. 9.—Progress of street railway equipment
                        since granting of first franchise. Ind. News, Feb. 19, 1910, p. 15, c. 2.—Growth of
                        population since 1822. Ind. Star, Dec. 6, 1909, p. 6, c. 4.—List of postmasters since
                        1822. Ind. Star, Dec. 7, 1909, p. 6, c. 4.—List of mayors since 1847. Ind Star, Dec.
                        8, 1909, p. 8, c. 4.—Dates of its various charters. Ind. Star, Dec. 14, 1909, p. 6,
                        c. 4.—History of Woodruff Place. Ind. Star, Dec. 20, 1909, p. 6, c. 4.— As
                        it was in 1860. Ind. News, Jan. 1, 1910, p. 14, c. 1.</item>
               <item>
                  <placeName>
                            <region type="county">Jennings</region>
                        </placeName>, Jonathan. Records of his two marriages found. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">South Bend</settlement>
                        </placeName> Tribune, Jan. 10, 1910, p. 2, c. 4.</item>
               <item>
                  <placeName>
                            <region type="county">Lincoln</region>
                        </placeName>, Abraham. Capt. Foster's impression of him at his visit to <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                        </placeName>. Ind. Star, Feb. 8, 1910, p. 6, c. 6.</item>
               <item>
                  <placeName>
                            <region type="county">Lincoln</region>
                        </placeName>, Nancy Hanks. Poem which roused State to care for her grave. Ind. Star, Feb. 6,
                        1910, mag. sec., p. 7. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Ft. Wayne</settlement>
                        </placeName> Journal-Gazette, Feb. 12, 1910, p. 1, c. 2.</item>
               <item>Martindale, Elijah B. Death of and sketch of life. Ind. News, Feb. 28, 1910, p. 1, c. 3.</item>
               <item>
                  <placeName>
                            <region type="state" reg="miu">Michigan</region>
                        </placeName> and Erie canal. Randall's speech before <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">New York</settlement>
                        </placeName> State waterways convention. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Ft. Wayne</settlement>
                        </placeName> Journal-Gazette, Dec. 1, 1909, p. 1, c. 2.—Beveridge will introduce a
                        bill asking for survey of ship canal via <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Fort Wayne</settlement>
                        </placeName>. Ind. Star, Dec. 6, 1909, p. 8, c. 4.—Bill delayed, having been referred
                        to wrong committee. Ind. News, Feb. 7, 1910, p. 10, c. 3.</item>
               <item>Mills. Overshot mill of 1835 still in operation in <placeName>
                     <region type="county">Brown
                                county</region>. <settlement type="city">Terre Haute</settlement>
                  </placeName> Star, Feb.
                        5, 1910, p, 5, c. 2.</item>
               <item>
                  <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Muncie</settlement>
                        </placeName>, Ind. East side of Walnut street, from Main street to the Big Four tracks, as it
                        was 50 years ago. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Muncie</settlement>
                        </placeName> Press, Feb. 7, 1910, P. 1, c. 4.—West side of Walnut street from Main
                        street to the Big Four tracks, as it was 50 years ago. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Muncie</settlement>
                        </placeName> Press, Feb. 12, 1910, p. 4, c. 2.—East side of Walnut street from Main
                        to the Granville road, 50 years ago. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Muncie</settlement>
                        </placeName> Press, Feb. 26, 1910, p. 8, c. 4.</item>
               <item>Newspapers. History of <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                        </placeName> News. Ind. News, Dec. 7, 1909, p. 8, c. 1.</item>
               <pb n="58" id="VAA4025-006-1-062"/>
               <item>Noble, William T. Death of former Clerk of Supreme Court. Ind. News, Jan. 11, 1910, p. 7, c.
                        2.</item>
               <item>Postal service. Contrast between present methods of delivery and those of early days as
                        recalled by John B. Wirt. Ind. Star, Jan. 9, 1910, p. 12, c. 1.—First rural free
                        delivery made in <placeName>
                            <region type="county">Bartholomew county</region>
                        </placeName> August 1, 1896. Growth of work. Ind. Star., Dec. 5, 1909, p. 8, c. 1. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Terre Haute</settlement>
                        </placeName> Star, Dec. 6, 1909, p. 3, c. 1. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Muncie</settlement>
                        </placeName> Star, Dec. 21, 1909, p. 11, c. 1.</item>
               <item>Shelbyville. History of its development. Ind. Star, Jan. 1, 1910, p. 6, c. 4.</item>
               <item>Spanish-American war veterans. History of organization in Indiana. Ind. Star, Dec. 12, 1909,
                        p. 41, c. 1.</item>
               <item>
                  <geogName>Stone River</geogName>, Battle of. Survivors will celebrate anniversary of battle.
                        Organization of army at battle. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Terre Haute</settlement>
                        </placeName> Star, Dec. 19, 1909, p. 18, c. 1.—Tenth annual meeting of National
                        association of survivors. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Terre Haute</settlement>
                        </placeName> Star, Jan. 1, 1910, p. 16, c. 1.</item>
               <item>U. S.—History—Civil war. Interesting letters of Charles M. Heaton. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">South Bend</settlement>
                        </placeName> Tribune, Dec. 18, 1909, pt. 2, pp. 6–7.</item>
               <item>Vigo, Francis. His work for the conquest of the northwest. Ind. News, Jan. 1, 1910, p. 14.</item>
               <item>Wallace, Lew. Recollections of Captain Negley. Ind. Star, Jan. 9, 1910, mag. sec., p.
                        7.—As Meredith Nicholson knew him. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Muncie</settlement>
                        </placeName> Star, Jan. 9, 1910, sec. 2, p. 2. Ind. Star, Jan. 9, 1910, mag. sec., p.
                        8.—James E. Taylor tells story of Wallace at <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shiloh.</settlement>
                        </placeName> Ind. Star, Jan. 25, 1910, p. 6, c. 5.</item>
               <item>Whitewater canal. Spanned at <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Brookville</settlement>
                        </placeName> by oldest bridge in State. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Terre Haute</settlement>
                        </placeName> Star, Dec. 26, 1909, mag. sec., p. 4.—Section near <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Brookville</settlement>
                        </placeName> used for water power. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Terre Haute</settlement>
                        </placeName> Star, Dec. 26, 1909, mag. sec., p. 4.</item>
               <item>Williams, James D. As recalled by Adlai Stevenson. Ind. News, Jan. 17, 1910, p. 5, c. 6.</item>
               <item>Zollars, Allen. Death of distinguished Indiana jurist. Sketch of his life. <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Ft. Wayne</settlement>
                        </placeName> Journal-Gazette, Dec. 20, 1909, p. 1, c. 7. Ind. News, Dec. 20, 1909, p. 12, c.
                    4.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <pb n="[59]" id="VAA4025-006-1-063"/>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-006-1-a06">
            <head>NOTES.</head>
            <p>The North Central History Teachers' Association meets in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                    </placeName> at the University of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                    </placeName> buildings, Friday and Saturday, April 1 and 2. Among other items on the program is an
                    informal dinner in honor of Professor Frederick J. Turner.</p>
            <p>One of the most interesting sessions in the meeting of the Department of Superintendence of the
                    National Education Association in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> was that of the afternoon of March 2, in which Professor J. H. Robinson read a paper
                    upon "The Place of History in Industrial Schools." His main contention was that
                    industrial development was the most appropriate basis of an outline of general history, and that a
                    course of study thus modeled would be very valuable in industrial education. Superintendent Maxwell,
                    of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New York</settlement>
                    </placeName>, in reviewing the paper, took exception to this Thesis and maintained that industry is
                    but one of the elements in man's progress and that industrial schools should teach general
                    history rather than purely industrial history.</p>
            <p>The annual meeting of the History Section of the State Teachers' Association will be held at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> in May. One or more sessions will be held jointly with the Indiana Historical
                Society.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-006-1-a07">
            <head>REVIEWS OF BOOKS.</head>
            <head>A HISTORY OF CLARK COUNTY.<lb/> [By L. C. Baird. Illustrated. B. F. Bowen &amp; Co., <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>.]</head>
            <p>The author of a local history meets with one very serious difficulty. He is almost compelled to be
                    laudatory, to overpraise citizens who are still living and whose enmity the writer feels that he
                    dare not have. It is praiseworthy, however, that some men in Indiana are trying to preserve the
                    early history of the <pb n="60" id="VAA4025-006-1-064"/> counties in which they live. Much material
                    which the future historian must use is thrown away; a history, then, like L. C. Baird's,
                    deserves commendation because of the author's serious effort to keep intact all the history
                    of his locality. <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clark county</region>
                    </placeName> deserves and has received at the hands of Mr. Baird accurate treatment, especially in
                    its early period. The author devotes his first chapter to the traditional earliest inhabitants of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clark county</region>
                    </placeName>. He has two additional chapters on the history of the county before its organization
                    and while it was a part of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName>. Mr. Baird divides the history of the county into decades and then continues it in a
                    series of chapters under heads like the following: The Military History of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clark county</region>
                    </placeName>, in five chapters; Freemasonry in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clark county</region>
                    </placeName>; The Roman Catholic Church in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clark county</region>
                    </placeName>; Journalism in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clark county</region>
                    </placeName>; The River and Steamboat Building; The Schools in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clark county</region>
                    </placeName>; and quite a number of others.</p>
            <p>The historical field here outlined is a large and important one, because <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clark county</region>
                    </placeName> was the first to be created out of the limits of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Knox county</region>
                    </placeName>, which was organized in 1790. <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clark county</region>
                    </placeName> was, therefore, the second one in the State. The editor's division into
                    decades has some advantages, and makes easy reference to the periods of development in the southern
                    part of the State, and, while the first fourteen chapters are merely annals, they are valuable,
                    distinctly classified and therefore very easy for reference. We believe that Mr. Baird has -done a
                    very valuable work for the history of the State. There is a well-written and valuable account of the
                    town of Springville, founded in 1799. This little town was a distinct American settlement and was
                    the first capital of the county.</p>
            <p>The list of families in the first decade provides an excellent foundation for the future genealogist
                    of southern Indiana. The list includes the Bottorffs, McKinleys, Hawthorns, Carrs and others.</p>
            <p>An interesting item is given about a teacher of an academy before the public schools were
                    established: The old teacher (Zebulon B. Sturgus) was a strict disciplinarian. Tobacco-chewers and
                    swearers were not allowed among his students. It is related that when the first locomotive passed
                    over the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> &amp; <pb n="61" id="VAA4025-006-1-065"/>
                    <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName> railroad, he whipped all the scholars for "imitating the engine."</p>
            <p>The chapters on "Church History" and the "Secret ahd Benevdent
                    Orders" are quite complete and satisfactory. They are much more so than the chapter on
                    "Schools," which is quite defective because it is entirely too brief for a subject
                    of such value to the county as that. The future historian will not be able to tell much of value
                    about the schools from this history. They are 93f greater importance than the "Benevolent
                    Orders," or "Journalism," or "River and Steamboat
                    Building." The reviewer is compelled to call attention to some defects in this otherwise
                    valuable history. There are attempts at fine writing which are not worthy of Mr. Baird. As for
                    instance in the tenth chapter: "Beyond the river lay the Southland, whose legions surged to
                    and from the border, while from the North came untold blue-clad thousands to preserve the Union
                    established by our fathers," and in the nineteenth chapter, "placing the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> before humanity as the greatest benefactor ever known among nations." It is
                    unfortunate also that Mr. Baird should write even one sentence like this: "He went into the
                    tents and examined patients with his own hands, and elevated the abode of his satanic majesty. as
                    only the old general could." There are other instances like this, all of which seriously
                    mar the form.</p>
            <p>In the "biographies" it would have been better to have arranged the families and
                    individuals in alphabetical order. The author of this history was swept off his feet here by his
                    inability to avoid praise for everybody mentioned. A simple, straightforward statement of facts
                    would be much more scientific and creditable. It is very diffcult to avoid praising your fellow
                    townsmen, but the writing of history is a science and when it becomes merely praise it is faulty.</p>
            <p>All the military history should be put together and not in separate chapters. The proofs were not
                    carefully read. For instance, "liquor" is spelled without the 1,
                    "companies" is written "cam," "indefinitely"
                    is written with two f's, and "had laid" and "laying"
                    instead of "lain" and "lying."</p>
            <p>The volume is fairly well illustrated.</p>
            <byline>D<hi rend="sc">EMARCHUS</hi> C. B<hi rend="sc">ROWN</hi>.</byline>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <pb n="[62]" id="VAA4025-006-1-066"/>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI.2>