<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "imh_issue.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="VAA4025-026-4">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Indiana Magazine of History</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoded by</resp>
               <name>Aptara Inc.</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <date>2007</date>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>Copyright 2007 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
               <p>Indiana University provides the information contained in this file for non-commercial,
        personal, or research use only. All other use, including but not limited to commercial or
        scholarly reproductions, redistribution, publication or transmission, whether by electronic
        means or otherwise, without prior written permission of the copyright holder is strictly
        prohibited.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Indiana Magazine of History</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title>Indiana Magazine of History</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Indiana University Department of History in cooperation with the Indiana
                                Historical Society</publisher>
                     <date>1930</date>
                     <biblScope type="issue">4</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="volume">26</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="pages">271-334</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07-20</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Annette D. Richmond</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Split VAA4025-026-4-a04 into two pieces; first was left as type scholarlyArticle and second was
                    created as type scholarlyArticle with id VAA4025-026-4-a10. Encoded letters, corrected blockquote
                    formatting.</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="[271]" id="VAA4025-026-4-001"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-026-4-a01">
            <head>Governor Claude Matthews</head>
            <byline>By H. S. K. B<hi rend="sc">ARTHOLOMEW</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>The State campaign of 1890 in Indiana was one of the most notable for an off year campaign in the
                    last quarter of the nineteenth century. Long before either State concention was held the leaders of
                    both major political parties were looking forward to the contest as a preliminary skirmish for the
                    gubernatorial campaign which was to come two years later. Each party was looking over the field to
                    find the strongest man to head its ticket. The highest State office to be filled in 1890 was that of
                    Secretary of State.</p>
            <p>The Republicans held their State convention first and nominated Hon. <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Milton</settlement>
                    </placeName> Trusler,<hi rend="sup">1</hi> a <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Fayette County</region>
                    </placeName> farmer and a fine type of Indiana manhood. Mr. Trusler was Master of the Indiana State
                    Grange, a position which he was filling capably and conscientiously. He was deservedly popular among
                    the members of that great order. It can be said truthfully that he was in every sense worthy of the
                    honor of being chosen as the leader of a great political party in a contest in which the result was
                    expected to have a potent influence on the more important campaign which was to come two years
                    later.</p>
            <p>The Democratic leaders at once realized that, in nominating Mr. Trusler, their political rivals had
                    executed a master stroke. They recognized in him a candidate who would be hard to defeat. They knew
                    that they must select the best man they could find if they expected to win. A week or so after the
                    Republican Convention, Hon. John B. Stoll, editor of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">South Bend</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Times</hi> and one of the leading Democratic editors <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">1</hi> Mr. Trusler had served as State Representative from <placeName>
                                <region type="county">Fayette</region>
                            </placeName> and Union Counties in 1876 and as State Senator during the years 1876 and 1877.
                            In 1894. he moved from his farm in <placeName>
                                <region type="county">Fayette County</region>
                            </placeName> to East <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Connersville</settlement>
                            </placeName>. See <hi rend="i">Biographical and Genealogical History of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Wayne</region>
                                </placeName>. <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Fayette</region>
                                </placeName>. <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Union</region>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Franklin Counties</region>
                                </placeName>. Indiana</hi> (<placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                            </placeName>, 1899). I, 11-12.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="272" id="VAA4025-026-4-002"/> in the north half of the State, had occasion to make a trip to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, During his stay in the capital city, he met his old friend, Senator Daniel W.
                    Voorhees. Sitting on a divan in the Grand Hotel, they discussed political matters in general and the
                    coming state campaign in particular. Both were aware of the fact that the situation demanded the
                    utmost wisdom in the selection of candidates for the various offices. Mr. Stoll remarked that if
                    there was a farmer of superior intelligence and the requisite qualifications to fill the office of
                    Secretary of State it would be expedient to nominate him to head the ticket. Senator Voorhees
                    replied: "I know where there is a man who measures up fully to those requirements. He lives
                    in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Vermillion County</region>
                    </placeName> and his name is Claude Matthews." Immediately, after his return to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">South Bend</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Mr. Stoll wrote one of his characteristically vigorous editorials urging that
                        Matthews<hi rend="sup">2</hi> be nominated for Secretary of State. The suggestion was favorably
                    received by many of the leading Democrats throughout the State. Other names were announced and when
                    convention day arrived there were several candidates, but Claude Matthews towered above them all in
                    both ability and fitness and was easily nominated. He made a vigorous campaign and was elected by a
                    substantial plurality, carrying the entire ticket with him.<hi rend="sup">3</hi> The only office he
                    had held previously was that of Representative in the lower house of the Indiana Legislature from <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Vermillion County</region>
                    </placeName>.<hi rend="sup">4</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The duties of the office were congenial to him, and he made an ideal officer. In the spring of 1892,
                    he announced himself as a candidate for re-election, but many of the party leaders believed that he
                    would be the strongest man who could be nominated for Governor and at their urgent requested he
                    withdrew his candidacy for Secretary of State and became a candidate for the gubernatorial
                        nomination.<hi rend="sup">5</hi> There were several strong candidates before the convention, the
                    most prominent of whom <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">2</hi> Mr. Matthews was born in <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Bethel</settlement>
                            </placeName>, <placeName>
                                <country reg="kyu">Kentucky</country>
                            </placeName>, in 1845. He moved, in 1868, to a large farm in <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Clinton</settlement>
                            </placeName> Township, near <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Clinton</settlement>
                            </placeName>, Indiana. where he resided until his death. See <hi rend="i">Pictorial and
                                Biographical Memoirs of <placeName>
                                    <settlement type="city">Elkhart</settlement>
                                </placeName> and <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">St. Joseph Counties</region>
                                </placeName>. Indiana</hi> (<placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                            </placeName>, 1893), 17; also <hi rend="i">Biographical and Historical Record of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Vermillion County</region>
                                </placeName>, Indiana</hi> (<placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                            </placeName>. 1888), 489.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">3</hi> His plurality over Trusler was 19,579. See <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                            </placeName>
                            <hi rend="i">News</hi>, Nov. 12. 1890.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">4</hi> He was elected to that office in 1876, receiving a majority of
                            between two and three hundred votes, notwithstanding the fact that <placeName>
                                <region type="county">Vermillion County</region>
                            </placeName> was strongly Republican and that the Republican State ticket was successful. In
                            1830, be was a prominent candidate for the nomination for Lieutenant Governor, but willingly
                            withdrew for the sale of party harmony. In 1882. he was defeated in the race for the office
                            of State Senator by a small margin. <hi rend="i">Historical and Biographical Record of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Vermillion County</region>
                                </placeName>
                     </hi>, 490-91.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">5</hi> For Matthew's letter of consent, see the <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                            </placeName>
                            <hi rend="i">Sentinel</hi>, April 11, 1892.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="273" id="VAA4025-026-4-003"/> was John Gilbert Shanklin, the gifted editor of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Evansville</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Courier</hi> and one of the most knightly figures in southern Indiana history. Hon.
                    Mortimer Nye, former mayor of LaPorte, had a loyal following in the extreme north end of the State,
                    but the real battle was between Matthews and "Gil" Shanklin, as his followers
                    called the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Evansville</settlement>
                    </placeName> editor. After a spirited contest, Matthews won, but by a rather slender margin.<hi rend="sup">6</hi> However, his unsuccessful rivals acquiesced in the decision of the convention
                    and gave him loyal support. Before the campaign had progressed very far, it was evident that the
                    convention had chosen wisely, for the <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Vermillion County</region>
                    </placeName> farmer proved to be a tower of strength to his party. After a thorough canvass of the
                    state he was elected by a handsome plurality, larger than that of any of his colleagues on the
                        ticket.<hi rend="sup">7</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twenty-three years between the time of his graduation from college in 1867<hi rend="sup">8</hi>
                    and his election to the office of Secretary of State had been spent by Mr. Matthews upon his farm.
                    For a time, he engaged quite extensively in the breeding and feeding of Shorthorn, cattle. Later he
                    took up Jersey cattle, and when he left the farm he was regarded as an authority on both breeds.<hi rend="sup">9</hi> Although he followed the admonition of the wise man and was always diligent in
                    his business, his time was not all devoted to his cattle. Through all those years, he was a careful
                    and persistent student, as well as a close observer of men and events. How well he improved the
                    opportunities for growth and the development of that sturdy and genuine manhood which the quiet and
                    uneventful life of the farm affords, was amply illustrated by the success of his administration as
                    Governor of a great State during a period that was eventuful.</p>
            <p>Though his was no ordinary or commonplace task, he showed himself master of the situation from the
                    beginning of his term of office. Had events taken their ordinary course, no one would have known
                    what resources this plain and un-assuming farmer possesed, or how well he was equipped to <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">6</hi> For a report of the Democratic Convention see <hi rend="i">ibid</hi>., April 22, 1892: <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                            </placeName>
                            <hi rend="i">News</hi>. April 21, 1892.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">7</hi> He received 260,601 votes, a plurality of 6,976 over the vote of his
                            nearest rival. See <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                            </placeName>
                            <hi rend="i">Sentinel</hi>, Nov. 29, 1892.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">8</hi> He was graduated from Centre College, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Danville</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                     </placeName>. <hi rend="i">Historical and Biographical Record of <placeName>
                                    <region type="county">Vermillion County</region>
                                </placeName>
                     </hi>. 489.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">9</hi> The Matthews homestead, known as the Hazel Bluff Farm, consisted of
                            about 600 acres. Mr. Matthews owned about 2,000 acres of land in all. He had real estate in <placeName>
                                <region type="state" reg="txu">Texas</region>
                            </placeName>. <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., 490.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="274" id="VAA4025-026-4-004"/> cope with emergencies. Almost from the date of his inauguration
                    he was confronted with difficulties which at times seemed almost insurmountable. For several years
                    the southern part of the State had been terrorized by frequent manifestations of lawlessness known
                    as "white-capping." Several Governors had appealed to the Legislature for
                    assistance in the suppression of this menace, but receiving no aid from that source, had given up
                    further efforts to prevent the outrages. Gov. Matthews made a similar appeal but received no help
                    whatsoever. He then determined to undertake the task with only the aid of local officials who,
                    previous to this time, had been powerless to accomplish anything. He persistently urged upon those
                    who had the authority that they should prosecute and bring to punishment those who were thus
                    violating the law. In many cases, where it seemed necessary, he employed additional counsel to
                    assist in the prosecution. His efforts in that direction were very successful. From the close of the
                    first year of his administration the State was free from outrages committeed by bands of
                    "white-cappers."</p>
            <p>During approximately the same period, he also made war upon prize-fighting. A group of sports from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                    </placeName> had come into <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Lake County</region>
                    </placeName> and organized the Columbian Athletic Club. They built near Roby a great arena which
                    would hold 8,000 or 10,000 people. The contests which were held there were a disgrace to Indiana.
                    Nothing could be done through the sheriff of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Lake County</region>
                    </placeName>. The governor then went into that County himself, gave his personal bond and asked that
                    a receiver be appointed. His plea was granted. One night he sent troops. He expected to arrest the
                    crowd that had assembled there and then install the receiver. The troops were sent because of the
                    danger of riot and lawlessness. Five thousand Chicano toughs would have been a difficult crowd to
                    handle, hut through some channel, the gang learned what had been planned and did not appear that
                    night. Governor Matthews took possession of the property and installed his receiver. Not long
                    afterward, the building was torn down and regular prize-fighting in Indiana ceased. Other States
                    followed Indiana's example in dealing with prize-fights.</p>
            <p>Not long after this the Governor undertook to suppress winter racing which was being conducted by the
                    Roby Racing <pb n="275" id="VAA4025-026-4-005"/> Association. He partially succeeded, but, before he
                    could fully carry out his plans, it was necessary to have some legislation. Upon his recommendation
                    the Legislature, during the session of 1895, enacted a law prohibiting winter racing.<hi rend="sup">10</hi> Then the Racing Association adopted new tactics. Several tracks were built for the
                    purpose of carrying on continuous racing through spring, summer and fall as well as winter. But the
                    Governor was determined not to be baffled in his plans. In a letter to the writer, he declared that,
                    though the monster had as many heads as Hydra, he would arm himself with a club for each one. He
                    began proceedings in the courts and, after an appeal to the Supreme Court of Indiana, won a signal
                    victory. It was only by constant, unremitting warfare that he was able to drive from the State an
                    organization which, in some respects, was even worse than the prize-fight gang. The racing in itself
                    was only a farce which was used as a cloak for a gigantic gambling concern operated in violation of
                    law and demoralizing in the extreme.</p>
            <p>A little over a year before the end of the administration of Governor Matthews, several riotous
                    Sunday picnics were held in the southeastern part of the State. Through the instrumentality of the
                    proper local authorities, he succeeded in stopping them.</p>
            <p>Early in the summer of 1894, there were strikes in the coal regions of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay</region>
                    </placeName> and Sullivan Counties. A little later when the great Pullman strike began in <placeName>
                        <country reg="ilu">Illinois</country>
                    </placeName>, there was a strike of the laboring men at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Hammond</settlement>
                    </placeName>. In each case, it was necessary to call out the militia and quiet was restored without
                    the loss of life or the destruction of property. But this did not end the difficulty. There was no
                    money with which to pay the troops, and none could be appropriated until the assembling of the
                    Legislature in the following January. Many of the men had been in the service for several weeks and
                    during that time had lost the income which they might have received in their regular businesses or
                    employments. They could not afford to wait six months for their pay or to have their warrants
                    discounted as designing men tried to persuade them to do. In order that they might at once receive
                    the remuneration which was due them, Governor Matthews borrowed <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">10</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Laws of the State of Indiana</hi>, 1895, p. 92 ff.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="276" id="VAA4025-026-4-006"/> over $50,000 by giving his personal note. The
                    Legislature, at the next session, very properly reimbursed him.</p>
            <p>These were some of the outstanding occurences in the administration of Gov. Matthews. In each
                    instance, he put forth the most determined effort to uphold the law and maintain the fair name of
                    the State. A less courageous man would have shrunk from the performance of the disagreeable duties
                    which devolved upon him in the several emergencies chronicled. But every temporary defeat, every
                    temporary triumph of lawlessness, only inspired him with greater zeal and spurred him on to fight
                    with more determination than ever for the supremacy of law and order. Nor was he unmindful of the
                    duties of minor importance which belonged to the Governor's office. His messages to the
                    legislature showed him to be thoroughly familiar with the affairs of the commonwealth which had
                    entrusted him with his high office. He took pains from the beginning to make himself master of the
                    situation in which he was placed by the suffrages of his fellow citizens.</p>
            <p>At all times and under all circumstances, Gov. Matthews maintained a manly independence and upheld
                    the dignity of his executive position. A number of times, especially during the first half of his
                    administration, when engaged in the performance of his duties, he found arrayed against him some of
                    the leading politicians of his own party. In none of these instances, did he hesitate to decide upon
                    what course he would pursue. He never for one moment feared to do the right as he saw it and seldom
                    was his judgment at fault. His straight-forward course was commended alike by friends and opponents.</p>
            <p>About the time he was inaugurated as Governor, the writer, in a sketch published in an eastern
                    magazine, said of him: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The people of this great state honor this farmer who has been chosen to fill this exalted
                            position, not simply because he is their chief magistrate, but because he has shown himself
                            worthy of their esteem. They are confident that the affairs of state have been placed in
                            safe hands. His administration is not likely to be a brilliant or showy one, but will rather
                            be marked by careful, painstaking, persevering efforts to promote the welfare of the whole
                            people. He believes that public office is a public trust. Judging the future of his career
                            by what is known of his past life, it may be quite safely concluded that he will leave
                            behind him a record toward which his fellow citizens will have reason to point with
                        pride.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <pb n="277" id="VAA4025-026-4-007"/>
            <p>These utterances were based upon an intimate personal acquaintance with him and a knowledge of the
                    principles by which he was governed throughout his life. Abundant testimony to the correctness of
                    this estimate of him could be quoted from the press of all political parties in the state during the
                    four years of his administration.</p>
            <p>Several times during his term of office, it devolved upon Governor Matthews to represent Indiana at
                    notable assemblages in other States and also to be her spokesman on those occasions. In every
                    instance, he did credit both to himself and to the people of his commonwealth, winning golden
                    opinions from those who heard him. Although he was not an eloquent speaker in the sense of being a
                    master of the art of oratory, he never failed, when he spoke, to command the respectful attention of
                    his hearers. He had the rare faculty of saying the right thing at exactly the right time. There was
                    a simple quality in his speech which never failed to carry conviction with it. It was the eloquence
                    natural to the outpouring of genuine manhood.</p>
            <p>If there was one thing that, more than anything else, characterized him throughout his public career,
                    it was his unswerving devotion to duty. No persuasion, no coercion, no temptation of any kind was
                    ever able to turn him aside from the right. He was an extremely conscientious man who could be
                    trusted in any emergency. Therein was at least one secret of his success as a public official. He
                    sought not the applause of men, but at all times and under all circumstances did as well as he could
                    whatever his hand found to do.</p>
            <p>When his term of office expired, Governor Matthews returned to his farm in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Vermillion County</region>
                    </placeName>, known far and wide as Hazel Bluff Farm, there to live in peace and quiet as he had
                    lived before entering public life. In a private letter to the writer not long before the end of his
                    administration he said that his retirement and especially his return to rural life would bring no
                    regrets to him. There was no reason why it should. He was essentially domestic in his tastes and
                    habits and his home life was an ideal one. His wife, the only daughter of a former Governor, James
                    Whitcomb, was a fine type of Indiana womanhood. Their two daughters and son were worthy of their
                    distinguished parents and contributed their share toward the happiness of the rural home. The
                    pleasant routine of <pb n="278" id="VAA4025-026-4-008"/> country life, which had been interrupted by
                    the six years' stay in the capital city was resumed. Besides, the retiring official had the
                    satisfaction of knowing that he carried with him the confidence and esteem of the people whom he had
                    served faithfully for six years, two as Secretary of State and four as Governor.</p>
            <p>A few days before the end of his administration, John B. Stoll, who has already been quoted, said in
                    the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">South Bend</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Times</hi>: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>It is a source of profound satisfaction to those who were instrumental in securing the
                            nomination and election of Mr. Matthews to the position he is about to vacate, that neither
                            blot nor blemish attaches to any act of his administration, and that in point of faithful
                            devotion to public duty the retiring governor has not been excelled by any of his
                            predecessors. And this satisfaction is heightened by the fact that Gov. Matthews'
                            course in office has amply verified the estimate of his qualities entertained by his friends
                            previous to his being called into public life. They knew him to be a man of high character,
                            rugged honesty and unquestionable courage, and that if elected he would give the people a
                            pure administration of his office. He has more than fulfilled expectations, and again
                            assumes the garb of private citizen with the congratulations of his erstwhile supporters and
                            the commendation of those who opposed him.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>If the files of the press throughout the State at that time should be searched, many similar tributes
                    to his worth and his public service could be found. Nor were those testimonials merely perfunctory.
                    They all had the ring of sincerity.</p>
            <p>Many illustrious men have filled the office of Governor during the history of Indiana for a little
                    more than a century. Conspicuous among these were Jonathan Jennings, her first governor, William
                    Hendricks, James Whitcomb, Ashbel P. Willard, Oliver P. Morton, Conrad Baker, Thomas A. Hendricks,
                    James D. ("Bluejeans") Williams, Albert G. Porter, James A. Mount, Thomas R.
                    Marshall and Samuel M. Ralston. The people of the Hoosier State cherish all these names and will
                    permit none of them to fade from their memory. Among them all there is none that will be remembered
                    with more sincere affection than that of our second farmer-Governor, Claude Matthews.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="[279]" id="VAA4025-026-4-009"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-026-4-a02">
            <head>A History of Hope Congregation, in <placeName>
                        <country reg="ncu">North Carolina</country>
                    </placeName>
               <hi rend="sup">∗</hi>
            </head>
            <byline>BY A<hi rend="sc">DELAIDE</hi> L. F<hi rend="sc">RIES</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>One hundred and fifty years is a long time, but in a certain sense the story of Hope, <placeName>
                        <country reg="ncu">North Carolina</country>
                    </placeName>, is thirty years longer, for it was in 1750 that John Douthit and his family settled a
                    short distance to the west of Muddy Creek, in what was then Rowan County, but is now Clemmonsville
                    Township of Forsyth County. Douthit was born in <placeName>
                        <country reg="ie">Ireland</country>
                    </placeName>,<hi rend="sup">1</hi> came to America about 1724, and settled on the Manokasy, about
                    fifteen miles north of Frederick, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mdu">Maryland</region>
                    </placeName>. There he married Mary Scott, a native of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>
                    </placeName>; and from thence they came to <placeName>
                        <country reg="ncu">North Carolina</country>
                    </placeName>. They were followed the next year by Christopher Elrod<hi rend="sup">2</hi> (or
                    Ellroth), who settled in the same neighborhood. Both of these families had doubtless attended the
                    services held by Moravian ministers at Manokasy during the preceding five years,<hi rend="sup">3</hi> so it was natural that friendship with the Moravians was resumed in 1753 when the village of
                    Bethabara was begun on the Wachovia Tract. Mrs. Douthit died in 1794, and the minister of Hope then
                    stated in a Memoir<hi rend="sup">4</hi> of her, that she and her husband were <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>friendly neighbors, and they aided the Brethren in the beginning of their settlement as far
                            as they knew how and were able. When English services were begun in Bethabara they attended
                            them frequently, and then invited the Brethren to come to their home for the same purpose.
                            The Brn. Ettwein, Utley and others often had opportunity there to witness for the Saviour,
                            and not without blessing.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>A few miles south of Frederick, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mdu">Maryland</region>
                    </placeName>, the Moravians established another preaching place in 1760, popularly known as
                    Carroll's Manor. This mission lasted only about ten years, <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">∗</hi> The author of this article is Archivist of the Moravian
                            Church of America (Southern Province). Her article is published because of its valuable
                            content, but also because of the historical connection between the Hope Congrgation of <placeName>
                                <country reg="ncu">North Carolina</country>
                            </placeName> and the town of Hope. Indiana. This place was founded by pioneers from <placeName>
                                <country reg="ncu">North Carolina</country>
                            </placeName>, several of whom were Moravians. The first Moravian Church established in
                            Indiana, possibly the only independent church of this sect in the State, was composed of
                            Moravians from <placeName>
                                <country reg="ncu">North Carolina</country>
                            </placeName>. The town which — the church was first known as <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Goshen</settlement>
                            </placeName>. The name was changed to Hope when a post office was established. The first
                            pastor of the Moravian church, Martin Hauser, became also, the first post master of the
                                town.—<hi rend="i">Editor</hi>.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">1</hi> Death record in Hope Church Book.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">2</hi> Death record in Hope Church Book.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">3</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Records of Moravians in <placeName>
                                    <country reg="ncu">North Carolina</country>
                                </placeName>
                     </hi>. I. 268.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">4</hi> Files in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>,
                                    <region type="state" reg="ncu">North Carolina</region>
                     </placeName>, Archives.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="280" id="VAA4025-026-4-010"/> when the minister was forced by ill health to return to
                            <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Bethlehem</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>
               </placeName>, and a number of the families to whom he had preached
                    moved to <placeName>
                        <country reg="ncu">North Carolina</country>
                    </placeName>, settling near Douthit and Elrod, both on the east and the west sides of Muddy Creek.
                    Daniel Smith, Henry Slator, Nodley Masters, Mrs. Elizabeth Goslin, and their families came in 1772.
                    The letters of introduction<hi rend="sup">5</hi> which they brought stated that the three men were
                    skilled in raising tobacco, and that Smith, who was an expert fisherman, hoped for good fishing in
                    the <geogName>Yadkin River</geogName> and Muddy Creek. Other early settlers in that neighborhood
                    were James Abraham Wilson, Even Ellis, William Johnson, Robert Elrod, Adam Sells, Henry Hughes,
                    Didwell, Jacob and Martin Hauser and Friedrich Fiscus,<hi rend="sup">6</hi> and to these were added
                    the Padgets, Peddicoarts, and others, who followed the first comers from Carroll's
                        Manor.<hi rend="sup">7</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The first English service held by the Moravians in the Muddy Creek Settlement was on April 4, 1763,
                    in the home of John Douthit, Sr.,<hi rend="sup">8</hi> though he was then still a member of the
                    Church of <placeName>
                        <country reg="enk">England</country>
                    </placeName>.<hi rend="sup">9</hi> In 1767 a School-House was built in the South Fork Settlement
                    (later Friedberg), and the Muddy Creek residents took part in the movement, partly that their
                    children might attend the school which was begun for the children of members, and partly that they
                    might share in the meetings for divine worship, though as the latter were held in the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">German</settlement>
                    </placeName> language it proved to be a rather unsatisfactory arrangement. In 1768 and 1769,
                    therefore, Rev. Richard Utley held services in English about once a month at the home of Valentine
                        Frey,<hi rend="sup">10</hi> who lived just south of John Douthit, Sr.</p>
            <p>In July, 1774, Christopher Elrod was the leader in a movement to build a School-House on the Blanket
                    Bottom Tract,<hi rend="sup">11</hi> between Muddy Creek and the <geogName>Yadkin River</geogName>.
                    Elrod had been raised a Lutheran, but had been much moved by a sermon preached in 1759 by Bishop
                    Spangenberg to the people who had taken refuge at the Bethabara mill because of the Indian war.<hi rend="sup">12</hi> In January, 1774, he became a communicant member of the congregation in
                    Friedberg, but "promoted the building of an <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">5</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Moravians in N. C</hi>., II, 720-723.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">6</hi> Bethabara Diary, Jan. 11, 1763: <hi rend="i">Moravians in N.
                            C</hi>., I, 268.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">7</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Moravians in N. C</hi>., II. 810, 819, 820. 854, 871; III. 1285, 1286.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">8</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Idem</hi>, I. 270.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">9</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., 274.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">10</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., 376, 386.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">11</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Idem</hi>, II. 828.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">12</hi> Death record in Hope Church Book.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="281" id="VAA4025-026-4-011"/> English school and meeting house in Hope with all his
                        might."<hi rend="sup">13</hi> For a reason not stated in the records the site for the
                    English School-House was changed, and on Nov. 8, 1774, the School-House land was laid out<hi rend="sup">14</hi> on the east side of Muddy Creek, just south of the mouth of a stream called
                    Laer on the old maps of Wachovia, but later known as Little Creek. Pending the erection of the
                    School-House (which was to contain a meeting-hall for divine worship), English services were held
                    each month at Friedberg, and Utley preached at John Douthit's home.<hi rend="sup">15</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On Feb. 27, 1775, the first stake was driven at the north corner of the School-House<hi rend="sup">16</hi> and by Nov. 23, 1776, it was so far finished that the first service could be held in the
                    meeting-hall. In spite of a heavy rain the Brn. Graff and Fritz went from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                    </placeName> and met the company of friends who had been in the habit of gathering at John
                    Douthit's. John Christian Fritz preached on the Old Testament text for the day:<hi rend="sup">17</hi>
                    <hi rend="i">Comfort ye, comfort ye my people, saith your God</hi>.<hi rend="sup">18</hi> Bishop
                    Graff baptised a baby boy, William, son of William Douthit. It was arranged that Br. Fritz should
                    hold services there twice a month, but that the consecration of the building should be postponed
                    until it was possible for a pastor and his wife to move into the house.<hi rend="sup">19</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The disturbances incident to the Revolutionary War deferred further development much longer than had
                    been anticipated. Officially and personally the Moravians of <placeName>
                        <country reg="ncu">North Carolina</country>
                    </placeName> were loyal to the new government of the United Colonies.<hi rend="sup">20</hi> The
                    Salem and Bethabara Moravians claimed the right to exemption from military service pledged to them
                    by the Parliament of Great Britain when they sett'ed in America in which they were joined
                    by some members of the other congregations, but it was not until early in 1779 that the Assembly of <placeName>
                        <country reg="ncu">North Carolina</country>
                    </placeName> admitted this claim, permitting those who chose to pay a three-fold state tax instead.
                    For three years, therefore, all the men of Hope<hi rend="sup">21</hi> and of the other Moravian
                        <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">13</hi> Death record in Hope Church Book.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">14</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Moravians in N. C</hi>., II, 821, 829.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">15</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., 860, 863.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">16</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., 867.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">17</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Idem</hi>, III, 1079.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">18</hi>
                            <placeName>
                                <region type="state" reg="txu">Text</region>
                            </placeName> Book for 1776, in <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                            </placeName> Archives.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">19</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Moravians in N. C</hi>., III, 1042.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">20</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., 1297, 1282.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">21</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., 1063, 1151.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="282" id="VAA4025-026-4-012"/> congregations were on the militia rolls and were liable to
                    call. The Moravian church books and catalogues show there were at least thirty-nine older and
                    younger men in the Hope group who were sixteen years of age and over during the Revolution, and of
                    these at least seventeen furnished supplies, or did some individual service for the American cause
                    outside of membership in the militia companies.</p>
            <p>But children grow up in spite of war and, in November, 1779, three house-fathers from the English
                    Settlement, Dan Smith, Henry Slator and John Padget, went to Br. Marshall at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                    </placeName> and made an urgent plea for the sending of a Brother to keep school for their children,
                    who were growing up in ignorance.<hi rend="sup">22</hi> On November 20th it was proposed to Br.
                    (John Christian) and Sr. Fritz that they move to the English School-House and take charge of the
                    souls there, which call they at once accepted.<hi rend="sup">23</hi> On December 25th Rev. Frederic
                    William Marshall went with Br. Fritz to the English School-House. After preaching there was a
                    conference with the house-fathers and mothers. They were asked who and how many would undertake the
                    expenses of the School-House and the support of the Brother and his wife? The families present,
                    fourteen in number, pledged their co-operation.<hi rend="sup">24</hi> John Padget and Dan Smith were
                    elected stewards, or treasurers, of the group supporting the School-House, thereafter known as the
                        Society.<hi rend="sup">25</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The building having been completed, Br. and Sr. Fritz moved thither on March 13, 1780, and
                    "were received with much love by their church-children."<hi rend="sup">26</hi> On
                    the 28th of the same month the meeting-hall was consecrated, Rev. and Mrs. Frederic William
                    Marshall, Bishop and Mrs. Graff, and Br. Praetzel, coming from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                    </placeName> for the day. The <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="txu">Text</region>
                    </placeName> was most appropriate: <hi rend="i">Except the Lord build the house they labor in vain
                        that build it</hi>. During the lovefeast, five unmarried men and nine unmarried women, one
                    married negro and two married negresses were received into the Society. It was officially announced
                    that the congregation would thereafter bear the name of <hi rend="i">Hope</hi>. The <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                    </placeName> Diary says of the services that the <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">22</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., 1318.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">23</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., 1319.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">24</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., 1320.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">25</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., 1321.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">26</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Extract der Diarii der Gemeiner in der Wachau</hi>, March 13, 1780.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="283" id="VAA4025-026-4-013"/> entire group was filled with joy and hope at this gracious
                    visitation from the Saviour.<hi rend="sup">27</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On August 26th of the same year (1780), the congregation of Hope was organized, during a visit from
                    Bishop Reichel and Rev. and Mrs. Marshall. Membership in the Society was not limited to
                    communicants—any person might belong who was willing to support the work. The
                    congregation, on the other hand, was limited to communicant members, their children and those who
                    were candidates for communicant membership. On this occasion, John Padget, his wife, Benjamin Chitty
                    and his wife were received into the congregation of Hope.<hi rend="sup">28</hi> To these were added
                    on Nov. 18th, Henry Slator, his wife, Margaret Booner and Anne Padget, wife of Thomas Padget. The
                    first Communion was celebrated on October 14th, with six members present; and the second on November
                    18th, with eight member.<hi rend="sup">29</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The experiences of this first year of Hope's existence as a Society and Congregation were
                    not all joyous. On January 25th there was the first interment on the tract destined for the Hope
                    graveyard. The youth, Henry Crampton, slipped on the ice while carrying a log of wood, fell and
                    fractured his skull. Br. Fritz made an address and offered prayer at his funeral and so the
                    graveyard was consecrated.<hi rend="sup">30</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were various acts of violence on the part of wandering militia during this year and that which
                    followed. The experience told in most detail in the diaries is that which befell Br. and Sr. Fritz
                    during the night of Sept. 13, 1780. About ten o'clock, when they were already asleep,
                    Captain Holston and sixteen men arrived, forced the door, and with drawn swords compelled Br. and
                    Sr. Fritz to open their chests. After blowing out the light several times the men took the clothing
                    and linen from the chests. Br. Fritz found courage to speak seriously with the Captain, asking
                    whether his men robbed and plundered like Tories, and that from people whom they should protect? The
                    Captain and some of his men knew Br. Fritz well. They became ashamed of the disorderly conduct of
                    their comrades, who had even torn off the shirt Br. Fritz was wearing. They promised that all should
                    be returned to him, saying <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">27</hi>
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                            </placeName> Diary. March 28, 1780.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">28</hi>
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                            </placeName> Diary. Aug. 26, 1780.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">29</hi> Notes filed with Wachovia <hi rend="i">Memorabilia</hi>, 1780.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">30</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Extract der Diarii</hi>, Jan. 25, 1780.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="284" id="VAA4025-026-4-014"/> that the men who had robbed them were drunk. The Captain
                    ordered that all the stolen articles should be brought back into the house and all were returned
                    except one piece of linen. This the Captain found when his men were asleep at Markland's
                    house and sent it back to Br. Fritz.<hi rend="sup">31</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some time during the fall of 1780, the long-desired school for the children was opened.<hi rend="sup">32</hi> On Dec. 24th the children of Hope had their first Christmas lovefeast. Most of the
                    members of the congregation and of the Society were present. They said afterwards that they had
                    never before had so blessed a Christmas service.<hi rend="sup">33</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On March 13, 1785, the "Brotherly Agreement about Rules and Orders for the
                    Brethren's Congregation in and about Hope Settlement"<hi rend="sup">34</hi> was
                    adopted at Hope. This interesting document contains twenty-eight paragraphs, to the provisions of
                    which the members of Hope bound themselves. The following very much condensed summary gives some
                    idea of the scope of the Agreement: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Jesus Christ is the only ground of salvation, and the Bible shall be our only rule of
                            doctrine and behavior (1,2).</p>
                        <p>Ministers are to be appointed by the directing boards of the Unity of Brethren (3).</p>
                        <p>We will faithfully attend the services of the church; will be loyal to duly appointed church
                            officials; will give a decent support to the ministers; will keep houses and graveyards in
                            good repair; will pay the church expenses; will contribute toward the general expenses of
                            the Unity (4, 5, 6).</p>
                        <p>We will render due obedience to the civil authorities; will pay our taxes, and take care of
                            the roads; we will support the Constitution of the State 7).</p>
                        <p>We Will live at peace with all men; will refrain from disputes with members of other
                            denominations; will be loyal to the services of our own church (8, 9, 10).</p>
                        <p>We will not judge or criticise others; we will be just, honest and upright in our dealings
                            with everybody (11).</p>
                        <p>Called by divine grace to be a living congregation of Jesus, members shall measure themselves
                            by this standard. Only those shall be received into the congregation whose heart's
                            desire is to surrender themselves to our dear Saviour (12, 13, 14).</p>
                        <p>We will show brotherly love one to another; bear reproof with meekness; arbitrate any
                            differences that may arise (15, 16, 17).</p>
                        <list type="footnotes">
                     <item>
                        <hi rend="sup">31</hi>
                                <placeName>
                                    <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                                </placeName> Diary, Sept. 14, 1780.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi rend="sup">32</hi> Notes filed with Wachovia <hi rend="i">Memorabilia</hi>, 1780.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi rend="sup">33</hi>
                                <hi rend="i">Extraet der Diarii</hi>, Dee. 24, 1780. The numbers in parentheses indicate
                                the paragraphs of — "Agreement" on which the summarizing
                                statements are based.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi rend="sup">34</hi> Filed in <placeName>
                                    <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                                </placeName> Archives.</item>
                  </list>
                        <pb n="285" id="VAA4025-026-4-015"/>
                        <p>We will be careful in our social behaviour (18).</p>
                        <p>Parents shall bring up their children in the nurture and admonition of the Lord; shall
                            educate them; shall teach them to earn their own living (19, 20, 21, 22).</p>
                        <p>Marriage is honorable, and parents shall be consulted. No frivolous behaviour shall be
                            permitted at wedding dinners (23, 24).</p>
                        <p>We will bear witness for the Saviour, and bring no reproach upon the Gospel (25).</p>
                        <p>We will avoid objectionable pastimes; will promote temperance; will spend Sunday as it
                            becometh the children of God, and without giving offense (26).</p>
                        <p>Every one who shall seduce others by work or example, or resist the higher powers whom God
                            hath ordained, or shall be given to idleness, or defraud his neighbor in dealing or trade,
                            who shall practice lying, backbiting and slandering, who shall allow himself foolish talking
                            and jesting, be a drunkard, run indolently into debt without endeavoring to satisfy his
                            creditors, or live obstinately in any work of the flesh, excludes himself from our Society,
                            as long as he does not show evident signs of repentence (27).</p>
                        <p>The Committee, house-fathers and mothers, and minister, are to see that these rules are
                            observed. If needful the Rules may be amended by the congregation by unanimous action
                        (28).</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>Br. Fritz ended his pastorate in 1788, returned to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                    </placeName> and three years later went as a missionary to the West Indies. John Jacob Welfare and
                    his bride moved to Hope on Aug. 26, 1788, but ministers from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                    </placeName> helped until Welfare was ordained on Oct. 26 of that year<hi rend="sup">35</hi>.
                    Welfare was followed by Samuel Gottlieb Kramsch, who arrived from <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Bethlehem</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>
               </placeName>,
                    on November 19, 1792, and was installed at Hope on December 2, at a lovefeast for Hope Society.<hi rend="sup">36</hi> Abraham Steiner took charge of Hope on December 5, 1802, serving until
                    October 20, 1806, when he was called to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                    </placeName> as the second Principal of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                    </placeName> Academy. He followed Kramsch there as he had followed him at Hope.<hi rend="sup">37</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hope was now served from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                    </placeName> for a few months. There on January 11, 1807, Jacob Welfare was installed for the second
                    time, the service being led by Br. Verbeek, who was on an official visitation from Moravian
                    headquarters in Europe. Welfare lived only a little more than six months, but his widow remained in
                    the School-House until late in <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">35</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Aellesten Conferenz</hi>, June 25, July 24, 30, Aug. 27, 1788.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">36</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., Nov. 14, 21, 1792.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">37</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., Nov. 17, 1802; Sept. 6, Oct. 23, 1806.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="286" id="VAA4025-026-4-016"/> the year, services being held by the Brethren coming from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                    </placeName>.<hi rend="sup">38</hi>
            </p>
            <p>During the interim between Steiner and Welfare, there was a discussion concerning the dropping of the
                    Society at Hope. This course received consideration because at some places in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>
                    </placeName> the Society members had come to outnumber the members of the Congregation, with
                    detriment to the work. It was found that nothing of this sort existed at Hope, where the Society
                    consisted largely of the children of the communicants. When adult years were reached these children
                    married and either joined the congregation there or separated themselves entirely from the
                        Society.<hi rend="sup">39</hi> Since the children of members became eligible for the Society at
                    the age of twelve, it was decided that it was unnecessary to begin their reception into the Choirs
                    of Older Boys and Older Girls.<hi rend="sup">40</hi>
            </p>
            <p>John Lewis Strohle served Hope from November 29, 1807, to November 7, 1813. He and his wife were
                    living in Hope, <placeName>
                        <country reg="nju">New Jersey</country>
                    </placeName>, when called to Hope, <placeName>
                        <country reg="ncu">North Carolina</country>
                    </placeName>. He was transferred to Bethabara in November, 1812, but continued to preach at Hope for
                    another year.<hi rend="sup">41</hi> He was followed by Samuel Gottlief Kramsch, filling a second
                    term extending from November, 1813, to November, 1819, when serious trouble with his eyes forced his
                    retirement to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                    </placeName>.<hi rend="sup">42</hi> Until his successor came, Hope was served from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                    </placeName> by Abraham Steiner.</p>
            <p>Christian Denke had served many years among the northern Indians, but he now accepted the call to
                    Hope and was installed on May 28, 1820.<hi rend="sup">43</hi> In the fall of the following year, it
                    was noted that he and his wife had a persistent fever and that most of the former pastors had
                    suffered in the, same way. The parsonage was in need of repairs, and it was suggested that a new
                    house be built, but the Hope Committee did not see how that could be done as money was scarce just
                    then. It was suggested further that Hope might rent a house and garden in Clemmonstown, where Denke
                    preached at intervals. It was finally decided that Denke and his wife <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">38</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Helfer Conferenz</hi>, Jan. 19, Aug. 7, 1807.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">40</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., Jan. 5, 1807.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">39</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., Dec. 29, 1806.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">41</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., Nov. 2, 24. 1807; Nov. 1, Dec. 24, 1812.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">42</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., Aug. 2, 1813; April 13. 16, Nov. 2, 1819; Jan. 4. 1820.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">43</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., March 14, June 12. 1820: Sept. 23, 1837.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="287" id="VAA4025-026-4-017"/> should move to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                    </placeName> and, as soon as he should recuperate, he was to serve Hope from there. On March 5,
                    1822, Denke took charge of Friedberg, but continued to serve Hope also until the end of 1832, when
                    he retired from both pastorates.<hi rend="sup">44</hi>
            </p>
            <p>During Denke's pastorate the migration from Wachovia to Indiana began. About 1825, a number
                    of families moved to the newly organized <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Bartholomew County</region>
                    </placeName>, Indiana. There they began a settlement which first received the name of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Goshen</settlement>
                    </placeName>, but was later called Hope,<hi rend="sup">45</hi> in remembrance of the Hope in <placeName>
                        <country reg="ncu">North Carolina</country>
                    </placeName> from which some of them had come. This migration continued for a decade and more<hi rend="sup">46</hi> and seriously reduced the membership at Hope, <placeName>
                        <country reg="ncu">North Carolina</country>
                    </placeName>. The loss should have been regained gradually by the enrollment of children of members
                    who remained in Wachovia, but many of them married non-Moravians and did not join Hope congregation.
                    Some entire Moravian families went over to the Methodists, who were very active in the
                        neighborhood.<hi rend="sup">47</hi> Nevertheless, the Hope congregation did not give up. It
                    still lives, and is at present served by Br. Leon Luck-enbach.</p>
            <list type="footnotes">
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">44</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., Sept. 25, Nov. 14, 1821; March 5, 1822; Sept. 14, 1832.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">45</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">A Home Mission History of the Moravian Church in the <placeName>
                                <country reg="xxu">United States</country>
                            </placeName> and <placeName>
                                <country reg="-cn">Canada</country>
                            </placeName>
                  </hi>, <hi rend="sup">41</hi>.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">46</hi> Friedberg and Hope Diary, May 1, 1836: <hi rend="i">Helfer
                        Conferenz</hi>, July 9, 1838, Jan. 17, 1839; Church catalogs of various dates.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">47</hi> Friedberg and Hope Diary. Oct. 1, 17, 1836; Hope catalogs.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <pb n="[288]" id="VAA4025-026-4-018"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-026-4-a03">
            <head>History of Negro Elementary Education in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>.<hi rend="sup">∗</hi>
            </head>
            <byline>By H<hi rend="sc">ERMAN</hi> M<hi rend="sc">URRAY</hi> R<hi rend="sc">ILEY</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>
               <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> was hewn from a wilderness infested with Indians. It was not long after the founding of
                    the new capital city until some Negroes were included in the population. Little was done to provide
                    schools for children, either Caucasians or Negroes, for many years after the admission of Indiana
                    into the Union, though the constitution of 1816 included the following provision: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>It shall be the duty of the General Assembly as soon as circumstances will permit to provide
                            by law for a general system of education, ascending in regular gradation from township
                            schools to a state university, wherein tuition shall be gratis, and equally open to all.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>To such schools as the State had to offer, the authorities gladly admitted Negroes without
                    discrimination: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Colored children were found in many public schools in common with white children. Comparative
                            little prejudice was manifested toward them until about the year 1830 when abolition
                            sentiments created a sensation in the nation. They were then generally excluded from the
                            free schools of the state. Their rights have been restored by the Fifteenth Amendment to the
                            Constitution of the <placeName>
                                <country reg="xxu">United States</country>
                            </placeName>, and in 1869 special legislation was made in their favor.<hi rend="sup">1</hi>
                  </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>A few schools existed in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> to which colored children were admitted. These provided the first elementary education
                    for Negroes in the city, but this was very little.</p>
            <p>By the time the second State constitution was framed, the people were not so friendly to Negro
                    education. This constitution, which was framed in 1850-1851, contained clauses which read: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>No Negro or Mulatto shall come into or settle in the State, after the adoption of this
                            Constitution.</p>
                        <p>All contracts made with any Negro or Mulatto coming into the State, contrary to the foregoing
                            section shall be void: and any person who shall employ such Negro or Mulatto, or other wise
                            encourage him <list type="footnotes">
                        <item>
                           <hi rend="sup">∗</hi> This paper is an abbreviated master's
                                    thesis accepted by the Faculty of Teachers' College <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Columbia</settlement>
                                    </placeName> University.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi rend="sup">1</hi> John M. Alcott, <hi rend="i">Indiana Schools</hi>, p.
                                26.</item>
                     </list>
                            <pb n="289" id="VAA4025-026-4-019"/> to remain in the State, shall be fined in any sum not
                            less than ten dollars, nor more than five hundred dollars.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>These provisions of the constitution were enforced by law after 1852 and Negroes were actually
                    prevented from coming into the State. Sentiment in favor of the anti-negro provisions was strong in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>. So rigidly were the laws arising under the second provision enforced that an incoming
                    negro's marriage was declared void.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> The constitution remained
                    unchanged until 1881, sixteen years after the adding of the Thirteen amendment to the Constitution
                    of the <placeName>
                        <country reg="xxu">United States</country>
                    </placeName>, though, during the years following the Civil War, the Negro population of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> increased rapidly.</p>
            <p>It is obvious that little could or would be done in preparing a race for citizenship through
                    education in the period when anti-Negro sentiment was so strong. Opposition to Negroes was largely
                    economic, just as the use of Negroes as slaves in the South was due to economic interest. Negro
                    competition, the people of Indiana did not desire, hence they attempted to keep the race out of the
                    State. Nevertheless, though in the South, the Negro might eat and sleep and enjoy his dingy cabin,
                    yet in Indiana, including <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, a Negro, desiring to come into the State, could find "no where to lay his
                    head."</p>
            <p>In 1817, a legislative committee included the following in a report to Governor Jonathan Jennings:
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>It is a well known fact, that, whatever may be the opinion of our citizens on the abstract
                            principles of slavery, and however repugnant it may appear, in their estimation, to moral
                            justice, there is but one sentiment prevalent on this subject of people of color migrating
                            in any circumstance to this state. It is believed if not restricted, it would in time,
                            become an evil of not much less magnitude than slavery itself.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>Albert G. Porter, who later become Governor of Indiana, declared in a speech of May 2, 1860, in the
                    national House of Representatives: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>It is not probable, sir, with the prejudices of my early education, that I would be likely to
                            have too great sympathy for Negroes. In Indiana we have adopted a constitutional provision
                            that no negro, whether bound or free, shall be allowed to come within its limits. Why was
                            this provision adopted? Because it was believed that negro labor ought not to be suffered to
                            come into competition with white labor in <list type="footnotes">
                        <item>
                           <hi rend="sup">2</hi> Barkshire v. The State, 7 Ind. 389.</item>
                     </list>
                            <pb n="290" id="VAA4025-026-4-020"/> Indiana. What is the policy of the Republican party? It
                            is to exclude slavery from the Territories for that identical reason; and in the canvass
                            which I made in the sixth district of Indiana, I always took that position. I never
                            advocated the doctrines that negroes ought to be put upon a political or social equality
                            with the white race …. we put our advocacy of the exclusion of negroes upon the
                            same ground on which it was put into our state constitution—that negro labor
                            ought not to be allowed to come into competition with white labor in the
                                terriories….<hi rend="sup">3</hi>
                  </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>With the feelings that existed against Negroes in Indiana, what could be done for them educationally?
                    What type of citizens could they possibly become? No schools, no right to come into the State,
                    suffrage denied to those already in residence, and popular antagonism toward them—these
                    were the clouds they had to face.</p>
            <p>The ancestral background of the Negro was unfavorable for shaping the race into creditable
                    citizenship. In Africa, heathenism, barbarianism, superstition and ignorance prevailed. In America
                    for over two and a half centuries, succeeding generations of the race were denied schools. In <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, during the period of development from a wilderness to a city, Negroes formed an
                    element in the population, but they were left in ignorance.</p>
            <p>The clouds overhanging the Negroes of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> held them in the "gutter", but others were there also. There was a
                    widespread sentiment against providing free, public education for anyone. Negroes could live without
                    but so could white boys and girls. An educational storm was required to remedy matters.</p>
            <p>The first charter for the city of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> included no provision for public schools. When the measure was pending in the
                    Legislature, S. V. B. Noel offered an amendment providing for free schools, and a storm resulted.
                    Opponents of the provision held that they and their fathers had succeeded without public schools. To
                    provide schooling by taxation would lead to extravagance. "A man could keep store, chop
                    wood, physic, plow, plead and preach without an education, and what more was needed?"
                    Continuing, the <hi rend="i">Report</hi> of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> Schools for 1866, summarized the arguments, not without sarcasm: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The fleetest, long-nosed, deep rooting hogs, and most flexible hooppoles <list type="footnotes">
                        <item>
                           <hi rend="sup">3</hi>
                                    <hi rend="i">Cong, Globe</hi>, 36 Gong. 1 Sess., Part 3, p. 1903.</item>
                     </list>
                            <pb n="291" id="VAA4025-026-4-021"/> spring spontaneously from the soil. Without the aid of
                            Science, Nature had enriched us with the fruitfulest power of mud. The wilderness of Indiana
                            had been subdued, and teeming crops grew luxuriant over the graves of the dead savages, all
                            done by unlearned men. Besides it would be a precedent full of evil to set the young city,
                            the seat of the State government, agoing with reckless expenditure foisted into its charter.
                            It might react on the legislature by the influence of example and millions be squandered in
                            internal improvements more mischievous than those they were then staggering under. For their
                            part, "sink or swim," etc., they were opposed to any such
                                fanaticism….<hi rend="sup">4</hi>
                  </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>The enemies of free schools were strong, and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> suffered sadly. Both races were affected. No policy could be inaugurated until an
                    election was held by the inhabitants of the city. The referendum turned in favor of free schools.
                    "The voting of the venerable Judge Blackford was cheered as he openly voted a ballot
                    endorsed ‘Free Schools’ and other citizens followed his lead".<hi rend="sup">5</hi> This step of Judge Blackford led to immediate provision for elementary schools
                    in the city of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, which have so developed until today all citizens may enjoy them whether white or
                    black. In appreciation of Judge Blackford's bold step a street was later named in his
                    honor. Public Elementary School No. 4 for Negro children and a magnificent church of the race grace
                    two of its corners at the present time.</p>
            <p>With this noble step of Judge Blacford and the triumph of free schools, there was an abatement in the
                    storm, but it did not cease. The schools did prosper for a short time. In January, 1853, the Common
                    Council of the city of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> selected the first school trustees. They were Messrs. Henry P. Coburn, Calvin Fletcher
                    and H. P. West. On March 2, 1856, the Board elected the first superintendent of the city
                    schools—Mr. George B. Stone. Under the leadership of these men, the schools
                    "were conducted with vigor and success." Money was wisely invested in school lots
                    and buildings, some of which were converted into elementary schools thirteen years later for
                    Negroes. This "golden age" laid the seed for elementary education for all citizens
                    of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>.</p>
            <p>Many realize their importance and continue to honor members of the first Board of Education.
                    Elementary School No. 66 bears the name, The Henry P. Coburn School. It stands <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">4</hi> See the <hi rend="i">Annual Report of Schools</hi> (<placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                            </placeName>) for 1866. p. 7.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">5</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">lbid</hi>., p. 8.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="292" id="VAA4025-026-4-022"/> at 604 East Maple Road Boulevard, one of the city's
                    most Leautiful thoroughfares. Elementary School No. 8 is today called the Calvin Fletcher School and
                    stands on Fletcher Avenue, both named in honor of Mr. Fletcher. Mr. H. P. West has also been duly
                    honored by naming a street in his honor. The city's new Crispus Attucks High School for
                    Negro children and the largest Negro business establishment of the city are located on West street.
                    A new Y.W.C.A. for Negro girls is now under construction on the same street.</p>
            <p>The "golden age" was rudely ended, when the Supreme Court of Indiana, early in
                    1858, decided that taxes for the payment of tuition (salaries or wages to public school teachers)
                    could not be constitutionally collected by the local units cf the State. The effect was most
                    disastrous. This decision threw the new public schools on the bounty of the interest derived from
                    the State School Fund. This was "sufficient to keep the schools open one feeble
                    ‘free quarter’ each year; and in 1850 even this was altogether omitted for
                    want of money."<hi rend="sup">6</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Adequate schools could not be maintained for any children. In 1867, the Legislature passed a new law
                    providing for the raising of funds for a public school system in the State. Under this law, taxes
                    were levied, collected and an extensive system of schools established. Since the early seventies,
                    when the first funds came into the hands of local school officials under this law of 1867, a short
                    period indeed, the extensive and expensive free school system of Indiana has been developed.</p>
            <p>When the victory was about to be won in 1867, there was uncertainty as to whether Negroes would share
                    in the advantages of the system about to be inaugurated. Would the ideals in regard to Negro
                    training left behind by the Governor of Indiana Territory, William Henry Harrison, by Governor
                    Jonathan Jennings and others be thrust aside?</p>
            <p>In 1866, four men of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> with vision sensed the fact that if the city was to prosper, education for all its
                    citizens alike must be offered. Their appeal for "The Education of Colored Person"
                    included these paragraphs: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>For reasons which cannot be consistently stated or explained by any who approve taxation for
                            the support of the schools, the colored <list type="footnotes">
                        <item>
                           <hi rend="sup">6</hi>
                                    <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., p. 9.</item>
                     </list>
                            <pb n="293" id="VAA4025-026-4-023"/> people of the state and city have from the beginning to
                            this time been deprived of advantages from the school fund, or any privileges of the
                            schools. If general taxation is for the protection of the community and adds to its wealth
                            and greatness, is not that prosperity lessened by so much as any class are permitted to grow
                            up in ignorance? Is an ignorant black man a less evil than an ignorant white? Is a black
                            savage a milder type of heathen than a white one?</p>
                        <p>Unless, then, our law and constitution makers assume that black ignorance is more genial and
                            tolerable than white, and inflicts less injury on the public, then it is obvious that it
                            should be educated and made to add to the prosperity of the community. Or if it is at all an
                            evil then it should have a remedy. If to keep the blacks in ignorance is a gentler curse
                            than to keep the whites in that condition, it seems to follow that black civilization would
                            be of a higher type than white,—a position which the advocates of Negro barbarism
                            would be loth to assume.</p>
                        <p>As the degradation of any class is a radiating evil, and affects all injuriously with no
                            compensating advantage to any, it is important that it should cease, if within the
                            reasonable means or facilities of the public.</p>
                        <p>The constitution of Indiana, never overflowing with kindness toward this people, has yet for
                            fifteen years instructed the general assembly to provide by law for common schools
                            "Where in tuition shall be without charge and equally open to all": and
                            for fifteen years the Negroes of Indiana have been a portion of all.</p>
                        <p>According to the late census of the city taken last summer there are 1,653 colored
                            inhabitants. Of these nearly three hundred are attending private colored pay schools
                            conducted and supported by themselves, and to a very limited extent if at all, dependent on
                            the charities of the public. The large portion of the colored children attending pay school
                            is very creditable to this people and indicates an earnest desire for
                            improvement…. In our judgment, humanity, justice and sound public policy demand
                            that this class of our citizens shall receive the benefit of our common school system.<hi rend="sup">7</hi>
                  </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>The men who prepared and signed this plea were: Thomas B. Elliott, president of the School Board of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>; Clemons Vonnegut, vice-president; W. H. L. Noble, treasurer; and A. C. Shortridge,
                    superintendent of schools. So firmly did these men implant the corner stone of negro education in
                    the city of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> that their spirit and the results of their deeds live after them. The writer desires
                    that every Negro should know and always respect and honor these men who laid the educational corner
                    stone for the Negroes of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> when they were friendless, poverty stricken and ignorant. The writer was recently
                    shocked when conversing <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">7</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">lbid</hi>., pp. 16-17.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="294" id="VAA4025-026-4-024"/> with a veteran leader of the city concerning the work of these
                    men, to find that he was ignorant of this masterly appeal. Every Negro father and mother should know
                    of those who made their prosperity and citizenship possible. They should unveil the deeds of these
                    educatoral martyrs to their children. The race should not forget them but should always accord them
                    respect.</p>
            <p>The city of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> has endeavored to honor these men. A splendid High School has been named the Shortridge
                    High School. Elementary School No. 9 has been named the Clemons Vonnegut School. Noble Street of the
                    city bears its name in honor of the Mr. Noble who signed the appeal of 1866. These men, as others
                    mentioned, have the distinction of having educational institutions and streets of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> named in their honor. Such is indeed distinction. Usually such honors are based on
                    gifts of money with the names of benefactors appended after death. The men here portrayed did not
                    buy distinction. It has been freely given in recognition of their sacred stand when laying an
                    educational corner stone for a helpless race. As a direct result of their efforts, interest and
                    stirring appeal, the race has been able to receive education. Through it, Negroes have been enabled
                    to prove themselves deserving of the country's prided citizenship.</p>
            <p>These men who so nobly placed the corner stone for the education and citizenship of the Negro, also
                    aided in erecting the first educational pillar over this corner stone. It is true in all building
                    that the erection is more difficult than the laying of a single stone. While it took courage to
                    appeal for a race, which was scorned and disliked, yet these brave men met the challenge. That
                    earnest appeal of 1866 was, however, much more easily made than executed. Nevertheless, the builders
                    began their trying and arduous task breaking themselves down in health and body in order to complete
                    it.</p>
            <p>So fully and authentically has Mr. Shortridge traced the struggle in erecting this educational pillar
                    which first granted to the Negro school training, and of such decided value is it, that no apology
                    needs to be offered for giving his account: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The question of proper provision for educating colored children in <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                            </placeName> had been urged by men and women many times and in various ways. The average
                            lawmakers are afraid of certain questions, <pb n="295" id="VAA4025-026-4-025"/> such as the
                            tramp nuisance or the gypsy business, kindred evils and practices which have no right to
                            exist in a civilized country. The question of woman's suffrage never gets a fair
                            hearing. A way can always be found either in caucus or committee to smother it. It was
                            exactly this way for many years with the question of negro education.</p>
                        <p>The lawmaker who come to <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                            </placeName> every two years and promised to do great things for the betterment of
                            conditions throughout the state, could be induced to agree to almost anything; but when it
                            came to a show-down by voting on a few questions, negro education among the number, he was
                            not ready. Colored children were all about us and were rapidly increasing in numbers. More
                            than three hundred years ago, when forcibly brought to the American continent, they early
                            embraced the theory about which we hear so much of late, that it is their duty to mulitply
                            and replenish the earth. In <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                            </placeName> there were hundreds of adult American citizens and there were many hundreds of
                            children, nearly all of whom were illiterate and many of them vicious to our civilization.
                            Were they the less so because covered with a black skin? If they were a menace, what was our
                            plain duty?</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>In regard to the conduct of the Legislature, the venerable educator continued in his newspaper
                    account of 1908: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Fifty years ago the Indiana State Teachers' Association, then and ever since a
                            mighty educational power in the state, began the agitation for colored schools. In ten or
                            twelve years there were signs of approaching success. In 1867 an attempt was made to secure
                            the heeded legislation but without avail. An effort was renewed at the opening session of
                            1869. An amendment to the law was offered and favorable action was taken in the committees
                            and in due time was passed in the Senate. Action at the other end of the capitol was more
                            dilatory. The amendment was hung up till 11:30 the last night of the session and the
                            chairman of the committee said: "‘It is now or
                            never.’" A half dozen persons began the work of getting the members form
                            the cloakroom and lobbies into their seats. I remember that the late Professor Bell, Thomas
                            J. Vater and number of other patriotic and humane men did all that was possible for them to
                            do. But the amendment failed for want of a constitutional majority—fifty-one.
                            Forty-six of the requisite number to pass it were present; it was not enough to pass the
                            measure. But this was the last night of the session and any one who has been present on
                            these occasions knows how things are done. A truthful description of what took place on this
                            particular night would not look well in a newspaper.</p>
                        <p>So it looked at the moment as if black children were doomed to run the streets for another
                            term of two years while their fathers and mothers continued to pay their taxes, by the aid
                            of which the children of the more favored race, were kept in school ten months of the year.
                            For some reason, I do not remember what, the governor found it hecessary to call an extra
                            session of the legislature, and it was at this <pb n="296" id="VAA4025-026-4-026"/> called
                            session, May 13, 1869, that the amendment to the law admitting colored children to the
                            public school privilege was passed.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>This meant that the school authorities must provide a larger number of buildings and spend larger
                    sums for equipment. Says Mr. Shortridge, who was superintendent of schools in 1869, "some
                    of the buildings already abandoned were repaired and replenished; others were rented, properly
                    seated and made quite comfortable. By the first of September [1869] we were ready for all who might
                    apply." It was necessary to find a teaching force to supply the new schools for Negroes.
                    Regarding the problem, the superintendent wrote almost forty years later: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Meanwhile a constant search was kept up for competent colored men and women who could do the
                            teaching. The plan was to use colored teachers when they could be found, and white ones when
                            they could not. During the summer months, Sunday afternoon meetings were held in some of the
                            colored churches, where needful information was given to parents and guardians as to what
                            would be expected of them when their children were to enter school. These meetings were
                            largely attended, and with much enthusiasm in view of the fact ofwhat was soon to occur.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>This must have been interesting and exciting for this ignorant race many of whom so eagerly desired
                    education. For countless centuries in Africa and for two hundred and fifty years in America, the
                    Negro race had been deprived of education. The long looked for and prayed for time was now at hand.</p>
            <p>Mr. Shortridge describes the situation on the day when the Negro schools were opened: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>When the day came the buildings were crowded early with a herd of rowdy and undisciplined
                            blacks, and with a strong teaching force in number about equally divided between the races.
                            Order was at once restored, and the work of classifying and grading was begun. Five years
                            after they were admitted to the schools there were in attendance at both day and night
                            schools over eight hundred pupils.<hi rend="sup">8</hi>
                  </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>Those Negroes who were compelled to work and therefore unable to attend day school went to night
                    school. They have continued to do so. At present there are nine night schools <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">8</hi> For the matter quoted from Mr. A. C. Shortridge. see his article in
                            the <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                            </placeName>
                            <hi rend="i">News</hi> of April 4. 1908. This article is headed "Teachers'
                            Training School", but the last third of it is devoted to the beginnings of
                            elementary education for Negroes in <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                            </placeName>.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="297" id="VAA4025-026-4-027"/> for Negroes held in the fifteen colored schools of the city. In
                    1879, it was said of them: "In the colored [evening] schools so great was the anxiety of
                    the pupils [mostly adults and often gray-headed] to learn that all that was necessary was to provide
                    the opportunity. The pupils in the white schools were quite young, many being but twelve or sixteen
                    years of age, and quite a portion came merely for fun and variety rather than from any appreciation
                    of the importance to them of study…. The white night schools were not worth their cost,
                    while the colored schools were a remunerative investment." This was written about the negro
                    night schools by Mr. H. S. Tarbell just ten years after Negroes were permitted to attend the public
                    schools. Mr. Tarbell was then the superintendent of the city schools.<hi rend="sup">9</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The first pillar of the race was now firmly erected over the corner stone around which the
                    citizenship of the race was to be built. Readin', writin' and 'rithmetic
                    were given at both day and night schools. The race was now getting the tools which were to make them
                    independent. They were learning to read and figure for themselves. They were for the first time in
                    their long history receiving enlightenment. With good books, they were able to drive away their
                    superstitutions, gloom and fears. This precious pillar, made possible by the law of May 13, 1869,
                    was so firmly erected that no cloud, no storm and no Sampson of prejudice can ever destroy or
                    overthrow it. It is a priceless pillar to the race and with it the Negroes of the city of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> have become and are yet becoming more efficient and creditable citizens of the city and
                    nation.</p>
            <p>The public schools of the city were at last giving the Negro race their three "Rs".
                    The schools then were in their primitive stage and learning to read, write, figure and spell meant
                    an education for most people. It, however, did not mean the highest citizenship. In 1874, Mr.
                    Shortridge resigned and Mr. George B. Stone again assumed the superintendency which he held until
                    1879, when Mr. H. S. Tarbell was appointed. Mr. Tarbell saw that the schools were not meeting the
                    civic challenge of the times. This was not only true of the Negro race but of both races. He saw
                    that moral and character training must be given in the schools if they were <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">9</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Annual Report of Schools</hi> (<placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                            </placeName>) for 1879, p. 27.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="298" id="VAA4025-026-4-028"/> to fulfill their mission. He said: "If a boy is going
                    to make a bad man, the less we do for him intellectually the better."<hi rend="sup">10</hi>
                    Education was being given to all, but the lives of the pupils were not guided. Negroes were
                    suffering as were the whites. Observing this fact, Mr. Tarbell stated: "In some sections of
                    our city it is well nigh impossible to rear a child as one would wish." Continuing, the
                    Superintendent described the sad conditions: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>A parent said to me not long ago, "You can not bring up a child without his learning
                            to fight and swear. When we moved here my boy could not go to the grocery without being set
                            upon by the boys of the streets, and he had to fight to take care of himself."</p>
                        <p>The vicious boys in some sections of the city are an annoyance to the adults of their
                            vicinity and a terror to well disposed children. They congregate upon the street corners and
                            in the alleys and upon the vacant lots or in the old buildings and entice away from school
                            those whose tastes lead them to enjoy the freedom and frolic of the streets better than the
                            restraint and study of the school room. It is sad enough to think that these boys are
                            growing up to recruit the criminal and dissolute class, but the sadder thing is that they,
                            like a whirlpool, draw into an equal destruction hundreds that if kept from their influences
                            would make virtuous, industrious citizens. Each year will find it worse in its nucleus and
                            wider reaching in its corruption.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>It is obvious that the schools had not improved much in the city. They were doing the city little
                    good and doing nothing morally. Opponents of free education were beginning to murmur. Mr. Tarbell
                    began to work in earnest for moral and character education to be given in the schools. He saw that
                    the schools, if they were to be a worthy asset to the city, must not only teach the three
                    "Rs" but must have a new and broader duty to perform. Mr. Tarbell declared: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Our duties now evidently are to enter the entire field of public school work and cultivate it
                            thoroughly in its length and its breadth; to improve our process of instruction; to study
                            the child mind and come into sympathy with it so that school life shall be pleasanter and
                            more profitable than now. The direction in which our public schools can secure the most
                            ready and profitable growth is in gathering into them and subjecting to moral ameliorating
                            and helpful influences [the children who were under evil influences]….<hi rend="sup">11</hi>
                  </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <list type="footnotes">
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">10</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., p. 97.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">11</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., p. 96.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="299" id="VAA4025-026-4-029"/>
            <p>Thus was set up the second educational pillar for the Negro race. Negroes were not in the schools.
                    Mr. Tarbell did not intend this moral education for white boys and girls alone, but for all boys and
                    girls of the city. He particularly intended it for those of the lower class who were deprived of
                    elevating home influences. This the Negro had not and knew little of. Jungles had housed their
                    tribal ancestors. Cabins had sheltered their parents in slavery and shanties were sheltering most of
                    the race in the city then. They were also greatly increasing in numbers. In speaking of this, the
                    superintendent said: "In 1869, just ten years ago, the colored of the city were admitted to
                    the privileges of the public schools, but in buildings separate from the white children."</p>
            <p>From 1869 to 1876, the colored element formed quite uniformly five or six per cent of the total
                    population of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>. After 1876, the per cent rapidly increased, becoming nine per cent in 1879. Something
                    more had to be done for the growing numbers of Negro children. Superintendent Tarbell led in a
                    crusade to aid them. He wished to modify the course of study in the colored schools with the idea
                    that their education should "fit them in the briefest possible time for the essential
                    requirements of future years." He wanted them to be taught moral culture, sense training,
                    esthetic training, hand training. He believed it more important for them to know that a cubic foot
                    of ice weighs fifty-eight pounds than that twenty grains make a scruple, and yet he found that the
                    latter was being taught, but not the former.<hi rend="sup">12</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reforms introduced by Superintendent Tarbell were especially valuable for Negro Schools at that
                    time. Many youthful Negroes felt that their newly required liberty and the advantages of education
                    meant license for them. As a result some race riots occurred in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Mr. Tarbell met the challenge. His plan not only gave the Negro education but moral
                    training. He may be called the father of character education in the elementary schools of the city.
                    The new training was a strong pillar which aided the race in the development of a higher
                    citizenship. Negroes received their first lessons in preparing themselves for service and
                    usefulness. Without this, crime would have continued to increase <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">12</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid</hi>., p. 97.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="300" id="VAA4025-026-4-030"/> among them. It made it possible instead for children to rise
                    above the status of their parents.</p>
            <p>No race can reach the zenith of efficient citizenship without good health. The public elementary
                    schools for Negroes promoted habits conducive to health. William A. Bell, one of the leaders
                    favoring the admittance of Negroes into the public schools, may be called the father of health
                    education in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Prior to the year 1887, when Mr. Bell conducted his crusade, the schools did nothing
                    along this line. As early as 1881, he had stated that, "next to moral character the health
                    of a child is of most importance". The School Board was urged to make provision for the
                    health of the children of the city. Many precautionary measures were taken that pure air and light
                    should be furnished in all school buildings. Playgrounds were extended, and third-story schoolrooms
                    were abandoned as rapidly as possible. Halls and stairways were made wider and doors were arranged
                    to open outwards from rooms into hallways and from buildings to the outside. Attention was given to
                    air space, and proper ventilation was provided.</p>
            <p>Health education and sanitation changed the conditions for Negro children while in school, and for
                    adults who attended the night schools. The contrast between the conditions at schoolhouses and in
                    the dingy, dilapidated, unventilated homes of the Negroes was very great. They became dissatisfied
                    and began to feel that they ought to have bigger, better houses. They might have them, if they so
                    desired and labored for them. Their cabins could no longer serve them. Dirt floors and
                    "cat-holes" gradually gave way to floors of wood, and homes with porches and
                    windows came into use.</p>
            <p>Mr. Bell printed rules for the care and protection of the eyes of school children, and copies were
                    distributed to the homes of school children.<hi rend="sup">13</hi> Many people learned simple ways
                    of preventing the impairment of vision, who had never before heard that attention should be given to
                    the eyes. Since that day health education has been extended to cover every detail of health in the
                    elementary city schools under the direction of Dr. Ocker of the public schools and Dr. Morgan of the
                    Board of Health. The health pillar was the third set up for the Negro in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>.</p>
            <list type="footnotes">
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">13</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">idem</hi> for 1880-1881, p. 19.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="301" id="VAA4025-026-4-031"/>
            <p>The last pillar erected over the foundation was the introduction of the teaching of citizenship. This
                    was in 1905, and it has been carried on to the present day. In 1909, Arthur W. Dunn, director of the
                    teaching of civics in the elementary schools of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, stated that the aim of civics is to contribute positively to the cultivation of
                    citizenship. The object should be not merely to furnish pupils with information in regard to the
                    machinery of Government. Such information is desirable, but the child should be "impressed
                    with the idea that good citizenship is a matter of the home, of the school, of the street, of
                    business." He should know that "good citizenship is, after all, only efficient
                    membership in the community in all its relations".<hi rend="sup">14</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The teaching of citizenship in the elementary schools has trained the maturing child for service. It
                    has taught the children of both races. To prepare the child for this new aspect of citizenship the
                    schools have provided courses in cooking, sewing, pressing, woodcarving, chair-caning and repairing,
                    millinery, rug weaving, cement making, electricity, shoe cobbling etc. Many adults who attend
                    evening schools also receive the same training. The schools are not only serving the pupils but the
                    neighborhoods as well.</p>
            <p>Practical results have followed such teaching. for example, "Better taste in the selection
                    of harmonious and becoming colors has been developed." This is true whether it be a dress,
                    necktie, shirt or paint for the house. Habits of neatness, industry, accuracy, thrift, skill,
                    economy, orderliness, punctuality, self denial, perseverance, cleanliness and politeness have been
                    inculcated. This fourth pillar taught them their rights and their duties. It has taught each member
                    of the race his initial duty to provide for himself and to be of usefulness to community, city,
                    State and Nation. So great is the importance of teaching practical citizenship in the schools that
                    greater emphasis is being placed upon the teaching of this important subject. This is not only true
                    in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> but in all schools throughout the country. Comparative studies show that America does
                    more of this because of the many different races that she must instruct.</p>
            <p>The whole amount of money expended upon the Negro elementary school has been large, but the work the
                    schools started in 1869 was large. The task has been successfully <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">14</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Idem</hi> for 1916, p. 168.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="302" id="VAA4025-026-4-032"/> carried on. Within the sixty years from 1869 to 1929, the race
                    has been to a great degree transformed from a "herd of undisciplined blacks" to
                    efficient citizens. Within that little space of time, thousands of black children, each possessing
                    an individual capacity to learn and a peculiar need to be met, have been placed in the elementary
                    schools. With little or no educational heritage the primary school has taken them. The first part of
                    the elementary school problem is particularly diffcult, especially when children come from ignorant
                    homes. The elementary schools of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> are noted for an efficient primary system. Miss Nebraska Cropsey was the first trained
                    primary teacher in the city. She was sent by the school board under Mr. Shortridge's
                    administration to the Oswego Normal School in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                    </placeName> to be especially trained for primary work. Her ideas were given to the many Negro
                    primary teachers and they have accomplished much. Miss Fannie Carter began her work in 1874 and is
                    still living. She exemplifies the importance of that part of the elementary school work devoted to
                    preparing individuals for citizenship. Her work is being extended and carried on by many others,
                    including Mrs. S. DesChamp Riley, wife of the writer, who is a primary instructor and critic teacher
                    in the public schools of the city.</p>
            <p>The intermediate department of the elementary schools has taken children of the race after being
                    prepared in the primary department. Mrs. Lillian Jones Brown has exerted such civic influence upon
                    her pupils that Miss Laura Donnan states of her: "I can always tell the pupils of Mrs.
                    Brown. So well are they instructed that they make the best pupils in my high school classes and are
                    so polite and courteous. They appear to me to make the best citizens of the city in later
                        life."<hi rend="sup">15</hi> Miss Donnan has taken pupils and through her
                    "school senate" has endeavored to prepare all of them for higher citizenship. She
                    possesses the soul of a Short-ridge and has greatly inspired many Negro youths to be worthwhile
                    citizens.</p>
            <p>The departmental grades (seventh and eighth) have also largely contributed to the preparation of
                    Negroes for citizenship. George L. Hayes, who for many years was principal of School No. 17, the
                    only Negro departmental school in <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">15</hi> This statement was made to the writer by Miss Donnan.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="303" id="VAA4025-026-4-033"/> the city, accomplished much for the race. So well have pupils
                    from his school and other elementary schools of the city been prepared for later life as citizens
                    that even though many have stopped with only an elementary, or part of an elementary, training, they
                    have become a creditable asset to the city.</p>
            <p>So well have the elementary schools completed their task that Negro pupils have been admitted to the
                    high schools for fifty-eight years, though the law opposed it. Mr. Shortridge said of this some
                    years ago: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The manner in which the colored children first gained admission to the high schools without
                            the authority of law, I think has never been correctly told. Two or three years after the
                            law of 1869, providing for the education of colored children, was enacted, a few of them had
                            mastered the course of study in the district schools and were prepared to enter the high
                            school. The law, however, provided for their education in separate schools and a high school
                            for a half dozen children was not to be thought of.</p>
                        <p>There were up then for settlement some difficult questions. Early in the vacation of 1872, I
                            think it was a committee of colored men headed by the Rev. Moses Broyles, a prudent man and
                            a good preacher, came to me to ask what they were to do. Of course, I could not tell them
                            what to do, as the law was clearly against them. The committee was of the opinion that the
                            constitution of the <placeName>
                                <country reg="xxu">United States</country>
                            </placeName> ought to admit them, and if it did not, the constitution of the State of
                            Indiana certainly would, as it specifically provided for a system of common schools by the
                            general assembly wherein tuition should be free and equally open to all.</p>
                        <p>Some of the committee were in favor of bringing suit to compel the authorities to admit the
                            children. Here it occurred to me that we could get at the matter in a better way by placing
                            the burden of excluding them on the shoulders of them who wanted to keep them out, and that
                            we could thus avoid the cost and delay to those who were in favor of admitting them. I said:
                            "Get ready one of your brightest children and send her to me on the first day of
                            school." This they did.</p>
                        <p>Early in the morning on the opening day of school Mary Alice Rann, a bright, welldressed
                            girl, came to me and expressed to me a wish to enter the high school. Without asking any
                            questions, I walked with her to the room of the principal, George P. Brown, and without any
                            explanation or request, I said, "Mr. Brown, here is a girl that wishes to enter the
                            high school," and then went back to my work.</p>
                        <p>Mary was admitted and remained in the high school for four years, and at the end of that time
                            received her diploma. Colored children have been admitted to the school ever since without
                            question, now for more than thirty-five years.</p>
                        <p>On Thursday following the admission of the girl to the high school J. J. Bingham, editor at
                            the time of the Daily Sentinel, and member <pb n="304" id="VAA4025-026-4-034"/> of the board
                            of school commissionws, and I were standing in the high school hall, when there came and
                            stood within a few feet of us the girl referred to waiting to ask me some questions, and Mr.
                            Bingham seeing her, said:</p>
                        <p>"I understand you have a nigger in the high school."</p>
                        <p>I could only say, "Probably so, and I suppose that is the girl."</p>
                        <p>At this Mr. Bingham said, "I have a long communication in my pocket now in regard to
                            it."</p>
                        <p>Then I said, "That is a good place for it; better let it stay in your
                            pocket."</p>
                        <p>The communication was never published and that was about the last I ever heard of it.<hi rend="sup">16</hi>
                  </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>This account of Mr. Shortridge is presented to show the effect of the good work of the elementary
                    Negro schools. They prepared Negroes for the high school, college, business professions and labor of
                    many kinds. They have made them efficient to care for the members of their own race. Many leaders of
                    the race are encouraging others to complete their education by making opportunities for them. Many
                    business men and manufacturers of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> employ extensively the Negroes who come out of the elementary schools of the city.</p>
            <p>Clouds of prejudice and obstructions of many kinds against the Negro in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> have been removed. The educational foundation for the race has been firmly imbedded in
                    the city. The laying of the corner stone was completed in 1866. The four precious pillars of the
                    race have been permanently erected, never to be overthrown. This study does in an encyclopedia or
                    text book, but we have laboriously strivan encyclopedia and text book, but we have laboriously
                    striven to unfold to our readers the major events and principal characters that have made citizens
                    of the Negro. "Slow moves the pageant of a climbing race." The colored race is
                    still climbing in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> and the elementary school is aiding its members to plant their feet more firmly upon
                    those levels which make of them better citizens for their community, city, State and our <placeName>
                        <country reg="xxu">United States</country>
                    </placeName> of America.</p>
            <p>We are now at our journey's end. We have not listed all of the results growing out of the
                    work of the elementary schools, as that would be impossible in a single paper. We could not and have
                    not listed all who aided in building up <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">16</hi>
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                            </placeName>
                            <hi rend="i">News</hi>, April 18, 1908.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="305" id="VAA4025-026-4-035"/> the elementary system of the city. If we have accomplished our
                    aim, our readers now get a glimpse of the new Negro and have acquired an understanding of the
                    struggles that have been necessary to elevate the colored race in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>. The Negroes of the city are no longer to be considered an inferior race either
                    mentally or morally.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="[306]" id="VAA4025-026-4-036"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-026-4-a04">
            <head>Documents</head>
            <head>TWO LETTERS OF GOVERNOR CLAUDE MATTHEWS</head>
            <p>[The following letters have been selected from a number sent in by H. S. K. Bartholomew of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Goshen</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indiana, who wrote the sketch of Governor Matthews published in this issue. The first
                    illustrates the spirit of the Governor in his clash with the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                    </placeName> gamblers who attempted to make Indiana a fruitful field of operations. The second
                    letter reveals the farmer-Governor as a sincere Free Silver Democrat shortly before the national
                    convention of 1896.—<hi rend="i">Editor</hi>.]</p>
            <p rend="center">EXECUTIVE DEPARTMENT.</p>
            <p>
                    <text>
                  <body>
                     <div type="letter">
                        <dateline rend="right">
                                    <address>
                              <addrLine>
                                 <placeName>
                                    <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                                 </placeName>, Ind.</addrLine>
                           </address>
                                    <date>July 29th, 1895.</date>
                                </dateline>
                        <salute>Mr. H. S. K. Bartholomew, <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Middlebury</settlement>
                                    </placeName>, Indiana,</salute>
                        <salute>Dear Sir:—</salute>
                        <p>Your favor of 25th. inst. duly received. I thank you for your kind words of
                                    commendation, and congratulations over the close of Roby. It has been gratifying to
                                    me to believe that I had the support and approval of all our better citizens. It has
                                    been a hard fight, with a shrewd, active unscrupulous body of men. I think it is now
                                    down, but it has been such a hydra headed affair all through, that one cannot tell
                                    when or how it may appear. However I will have a club for each head as it rises, and
                                    will keep throwing them until the clubs are exhausted, or they have been. As you
                                    state some of the papers have mentioned my name as a possible candidate for the
                                    Presidency. I am grateful and believe I so appreciate the complimentary expressions,
                                    but I have not, nor can I become an aspirant for that office. I have not yet placed
                                    so high an opinion upon my worth or ability. I am not basing any expectations,
                                    consequently my disappointment cannot be great. I do not think the active seeking of
                                    this nomination has often led to success. The people generally make this
                                selection.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </text>
                </p>
            <p rend="center">EXECUTIVE DEPARTMENT.</p>
            <p>
                    <text>
                  <body>
                     <div type="letter">
                        <dateline rend="right">
                                    <address>
                              <addrLine>
                                 <placeName>
                                    <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                                 </placeName>, Ind.</addrLine>
                           </address>
                                    <date>May 25th, 1896.</date>
                                </dateline>
                        <head>
                                    <hi rend="i">Personal.</hi>
                                </head>
                        <salute>Dear Mr. Bartholomew:—</salute>
                        <p>I steal a moment from a burdensome correspondence to thank you for the copy of your
                                    sketch of my son Seymour. It is a neat and generous tribute to a noble young man, of
                                    high aspirations and worthy ambitions. He was always a good friend of yours, and we
                                    thank you for this kind remembrance.</p>
                        <p>I appreciate your cordial approval of my position on the all absorbing <pb n="307" id="VAA4025-026-4-037"/> issue,—the money question. We are living in
                                    serious times, and the next few months are to determine whether a permanent
                                    prosperity is to be given to the people, or whether we are to be placed in bondage
                                    to the money power. To continue and fasten upon ourselves the single gold standard,
                                    further reducing the value of property, especially farming property and products,
                                    making it still more difficult for the unfortunate now in debt to find relief, as
                                    this will come with the rapid appreciation of gold, so soon as it may be determined
                                    to make this the sole standard and redemption money, and rendering it easy for gold
                                    syndicates in this Country and Europe to have the entire Commercial world at their
                                    feet.</p>
                        <p>This will prove a positive calamity, and the few reap the benefit at the expense and
                                    suffering of the many. Let us declare for the double standard, gold and silver on an
                                    equal footing, and restore silver to its rightful place in the coinage of the
                                    Country as it was prior to 1873.</p>
                        <p>With such a platform we will carry Indiana, and [have] a chance at the Country. It is
                                    important that the friends of silver should be active and wide awake, that the
                                    sentiment of the people shall have voice. We want good, true men as delegates to the
                                    convention, and to otherwise be in attendance. It is a time demanding earnest work,
                                    especially in selecting delegates.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </text>
                </p>
         </div>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-026-4-a10">
            <head>A COLLEGE MAGAZINE OF 1861</head>
            <p>A copy of the <hi rend="i">
                  <placeName>
                            <region type="county">Wabash</region>
                        </placeName> Monthly</hi> for January, 1861, fell into our hands a few years ago. This
                    periodical was "published by an Association of the Students of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wabash</region>
                    </placeName> College". The editorial staff was selected by the Association. Nine numbers a
                    year were published, beginning in November. The subscription price was $1.00 per year.
                    The issue for January, 1861, is marked Volume II, No. 3. The editors were J. E. Cleland, W. T. Hart,
                    W. R. Higgins and R. B. Spillman. The contributions are either unsigned or such signatures as <hi rend="i">Oneiropolis, Cam, Keuah,</hi> and <hi rend="i">P. Roceed</hi> are appended to articles.</p>
            <p>The table of contents for the issue in hand include: "The Fire-Fays" (a long poem);
                    "Three Puffs" (the prophetic vision of a smoker); "Thanksgiving
                    Journal"(printed below); "One Ideaism" (an essay dealing with the dangers
                    of riding a hobby); "Homer—A Dirge" (printed below);
                    "Colloqy" (a dialogue between Dr. Johnson, the man of candor, and Emperor
                    Napoleon, the man of illusions); "Eloquence of the Waters" (an attempt at a prose
                    poem or literary effusion on the beauties of water under various conditions and on the influence of
                    "that most versatile of the elements.") "G'Lang" (a
                    humorous poem of three pages); "The Friendships of College" (a stilted sentimental
                    essay of two pages, followed by a page of miscellaneous sayings); "Editorial
                    Miscellany" (five and one-half <pb n="308" id="VAA4025-026-4-038"/> pages of editorial
                    comment plus three pages regarding <hi rend="i">Exchanges.</hi>)</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="i">Exchanges,</hi> to each of which a short passage is devoted, include: <hi rend="i">The Harvard Magazine</hi> (November, 1860); <hi rend="i">The Amherst Ichnolite</hi> (October);
                        <hi rend="i">The Williams Quarterly</hi>(November); <hi rend="i">The Rutgers College
                    Quarterly</hi> (October); <hi rend="i">The Union College Magazine</hi> (November); <hi rend="i">The
                        Kenyon Collegian</hi>(November); <hi rend="i">The Centre College Magazine</hi> (November); <hi rend="i">
                  <placeName>
                            <country reg="kyu">Kentucky</country>
                        </placeName> Military Institute Magazine</hi> (October); <hi rend="i">Oberlin Students'
                        Monthly</hi> (November); <hi rend="i">Ladies' Pearl</hi> (November). The <hi rend="i">Beloit Monthly</hi> and the <hi rend="i">
                  <placeName>
                            <country reg="vau">Virginia</country>
                        </placeName> University Magazine</hi> for November are mentioned but were received too late for
                    notice of contents.</p>
            <p>The following selections from the pages of the <hi rend="i">Wabask Monthly</hi> described above will
                    furnish some idea of the nature and quality of that college magazine on the eve of the Civil
                        War.—<hi rend="i">Editor.</hi>
            </p>
            <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p rend="center">THANKSGIVING JOURNAL</p>
                    <p>Nov. 29th, SUN RISE.—The amber East brightens into silvery day as the sun approaches
                        his rising. Now he pauses as if caught on the ragged horizon, and pours streams of intercepted
                        light through tree tops and steeples; now he is clear up above tree and spire. Hail, benignant
                        source of joyous, generous light, is the greeting of thousands as they see how well met, good
                        day with shining sun, when they feared clouds. Welcome Sun with thy gift, thou wilt chase base
                        ingratitude and prevent many frowns on this day of thanks; for who could go to church under
                        leaky clouds and through streets of mortar, and yet keep a thankful heart. A discomforting day
                        obliterates a year of blessings. But now thou art come, and the preacher may expect a crowded
                        church, and all may meet smiling faces. Friendship and good feeling will reign to-day. We praise
                        not thee, beneficent ruler of the day, but Him whom thou praisest, the Spiritual Essence of
                        light eternal, whose word placed thee on high, and let forth thy treasured light and effulgence.
                        In thy course this day, which men say shall commemorate the goodness of the Almighty, thou wilt
                        still see the world-worshipper assiduous in his attentions to his chosen god. Fortune will
                        receive many thanks; many curses, too, will be lavished on the fickle handed goddess. Many
                        hearts will be filled with true joy and gladness, returning thanks to the Author of life and all
                        good, yet thou wilt go down upon the wrath of man, and leave many in disappointment in their
                        plans of pleasure and gain.</p>
                    <p>12M.—Church is over. The more pious part of the community have been to the sanctuary
                        as a kind of compensation to their consciences for the unpardonable dinners they expect to eat.
                        The two institutions on Thanksgiving are the sermon and the dinner. The sermon is had first, as
                        being less important and more digestible, and quickly disposed of. <pb n="309" id="VAA4025-026-4-039"/> Thanksgiving sermons are expected to be novelties of the pulpit. On
                        this occasion the preacher is permitted to depart from the weekly track of exegesis, creed and
                        exhortation. He may publicly express his private opinions on politics, government or society.
                        But whatever advantage he takes of the day, it is usually demanded that he will not slight the
                        American Eagle. A peculiar privilege is granted to the famous bird to spread his wings and soar
                        from the sacred desk on this day. And like other extraordinary privileges, it is expected that
                        he will make use of this liberty. But the national bird is sick–diseased in one wing;
                        he cannot expand his pinions for a lofty flight without showing the black plague spot. If the
                        preacher lets him soar loftily he must administer some soothing balm. He need not venture a
                        complete diagnosis, but he must at least offer some consolatory remarks, calculated to soothe
                        the feelings of the bird in view of the loss of <hi rend="i">one</hi> of his diseased quills.
                        This being done, the people and bird are satisfied and depart in peace. And now comes the
                        "sine qua non," of Thanksgiving–the dinner. Indeed we cannot have
                        the emotions appropriate to the occasion until we come to the table. Who does not then feel
                        thankful that the turkies grew so large and adipose. The audience room performance was a mere
                        form, endured with a grace in the anticipation of the more earnest services of the dining room.</p>
                    <p>Especially is the student thankful, for he has fasted all morning that he might the better
                        appreciate the dinner. He has not attended church, but he now pays his
                        "devours" at the feast. Students are not the greatest eaters, but they are the
                        loudest in the praises of their Thanksgiving dinners, as any one would have known by being
                        around College this afternoon. Every one thinks that he has had the best dinner, but those who
                        shared the hospitality of "The Pheenicks Klubbe" declare they were never so
                        elegantly entertained. May the "Klubbe" flourish!</p>
                    <p>8 P.M.—I learn that the student who ate an elephant "stuffed" with
                        oysters, complains of indigestion. This shows the result of inordinate gluttony.</p>
                    <p>9 P.M.—Am invited to spend the last hours of Thanksgiving <hi rend="i">in
                        convivio</hi> with some friends. Of course I will accept, for if on Christmas one may forget the
                        "Star of <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Bethlehem</settlement>
                        </placeName>," on the 22d of February his "Pater Patriae," and on the
                        4th of July, the "nation's birth"—surely it is a duty I
                        owe myself and the rest of mankind, to drown in the uproarious tumult of a <hi rend="i">high old
                            time,</hi> any dim sentiments of gratitude I may have absorbed during the day.</p>
                    <p rend="right">CAM.</p>
                </quote>
            <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p rend="center">HOMER—A DIRGE.</p>
                    <p rend="center">BY ONE OF THE MOURNERS.</p>
                    <p>Not a sigh was heard, not a sob sincere, As on to his funeral we hurried; Not a
                        soph'more shed a farewell tear O'er the spot where old Homer we buried.</p>
                    <pb n="310" id="VAA4025-026-4-040"/>
                    <p>We buried him gladly, one dull afternoon, The sods with our <hi rend="i">memories</hi> turning,
                        By the light which is common to a Greek study room, And the lamps of our genius burning.</p>
                    <p>No useless coffin enclosed his breast, Nor in sheet nor in shroud we wound him; But he lay like a
                        war-horse taking his rest, With all his <hi rend="i">ponies</hi> around him.</p>
                    <p>Few were the farewell words we said, And we scanned and translated in sorrow; And we steadiastly
                        gazed on the <hi rend="i">notes</hi> as we read, And we joyfully thought of tomorrow.</p>
                    <p>We thought as we closed for the last time his lids, On the day of his demise, (a boon dear,) That
                        the bold Sophs of next year would mourn in our stead, And we far away in the <hi rend="i">Jun.</hi> year.</p>
                    <p>Harshly they'll talk of the spirit they've raised, And for <hi rend="i">dim
                            interlinings</hi> upbraid him; But little he'll reck whether censured or praised,
                        While in quiet he sleeps where we laid him.</p>
                    <p>But half satisfaction was given the Prof's, When the college bell tolled for retiring;
                        And we heard the sad moan of some absented Sophs, Who with <hi rend="i">headache</hi> were
                        almost expiring.</p>
                    <p>Quickly and gladly we laid him down, With the charm of his beautiful story; We remembered not a
                        line but <hi rend="i">Glaukopis Athene,</hi> Which is all we have left of his glory.</p>
                </quote>
            <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p rend="center">THE FRIENDSHIPS OF COLLEGE</p>
                    <p>One possessing the heart's true diamond of Friendship with a kindred heart, whether he
                        dwell in marble hall, and revel in the splendor of an imperial court, os as a little sharper on
                        the crowded pavement of a Wall street, who accosts the stranger with, "Newspaper,
                        Sir!" in this holds a treasure and is happy.</p>
                    <p>The gem may be polished, but even though it be "in the rough," the removing of
                        its exterior will not deface, but with a merry sparkle it will please him more.</p>
                    <p>But around such a glorious heart-union cast the halo of a college life, and new beauties,
                        friendships of additional charms will appear clad in all the rainbow hues.</p>
                    <pb n="311" id="VAA4025-026-4-041"/>
                    <p>But who are friends? Not those who love not, for friendship is but a synonym for love. Nor they
                        whose hearts are as the cold ice mountain of the North, down whose sides a stray sunbeam may
                        perchance have forced a little rivulet, only to see it cold and frozen at the bottom. Nor those
                        who are as abiding as leaves on a maple tree in the month of October. These are not college
                        friends. They bear for each other a joyous warm-heartedness which hourly intercourse, time spent
                        in like earnest, active duties, perhaps in contest of opinion, moments which they send winging
                        their way into the mighty past, alike laden with golden hopes and plans of future attainment;
                        plans which they do not believe will be realized but by a noble, manly strife, a
                        warm-heartedness, which these associations will not diminish. They cherish a sympathy, a
                        friendship, that memory will hereafter revive and bring back to the soul in a flood of golden
                        remembrances.</p>
                    <p>To be without a friend is to be without a home; but the heart is home—a palace of
                        friendship, whose marble-white turrets often quiver 'mid the blue heavens above, as
                        responding to the glad echoes of a student's friendly voice.</p>
                    <p>College boys will read each other well, and deeply, and similarities will make them friends.
                        Though ambition be a guest, if it be not that base, ignoble kind which would tower above a
                        fellow by removing his "pegs," there will still be a friendliness, and a
                        natural flow of sympathy, which all, and particularly students, feel in finding those who have
                        the "go" in them.</p>
                    <p>Respect must precede true friendship, and with the student, scholarship is often a standard.</p>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>"Our hearts ne'er bow but to superior worth, Nor ever fail of their
                            allegiance there."</p>
                    </quote>
                    <p>Respecting, admiring the noble efforts of his fellow, each companion is happy in bestowing an
                        honor where he feels 'tis well deserved, and that fellow he is willing to make a
                        friend. But college friendships, true and deep, are few; yet the rarer the gem the higher the
                        price! Time, taken from many, is bestowed upon these few, and friendships, deep as ocean waters,
                        are the results.</p>
                    <p>But those which some students cherish rest on yielding all opinion and action of their own to
                        another, though they will not acknowledge it, after which they are following a blind and gloomy
                        fate—stepping-stones to the imaginary greatness of that poor mortal who makes them
                        such.</p>
                    <p>Real, enduring friendship is not thus—a slave—'tis monarch; and if
                        in thought and feeling it's possessors differs, friendship in it's power
                        o'er-rules the difference, and the sacred, innate right of opinion remains inviolate.</p>
                    <p>Yet descriptions will only paint the pictures of reality. They appear as the objects of a summer
                        scene, clad in winter's garb—true, but still unlike the real; under their
                        cold white shroud lying as dead; all buried, motionless and still.</p>
                    <p>To the heart that has quaffed at the fountain of college friendships these lines may recall the
                        sweetness of those waters.</p>
                </quote>
            <pb n="312" id="VAA4025-026-4-042"/>
            <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p rend="center">EDITORIAL MISCELLANY</p>
                    <p>There may be some other institutions where the spirit of brotherly kindness is as well developed
                        as in <placeName>
                            <region type="county">Wabash</region>
                        </placeName> College, but we are inclined to doubt whether any of them exceed us in that
                        respect. The relations between our literary societies are of the most amicable nature. Think
                        not, reader, that it is from lack of "fire" in the members, for assuredly
                        never was the <hi rend="i">esprit du corps</hi> higher than at the present date. Every term, our
                        public debates evince the truth of this assertion. These contests are of two descriptions. In
                        the one, each society is represented. In the other, the debate is carried on by certain members
                        selected from but one society. The debates are always followed by original oratorical
                        compositions. The participants in all these exercises feel a great interest in them, and
                        therefore make preparations which tend in their results to gratify the audience, and benefit the
                        students. The members of the respective societies of course have and hold their opinionse on the
                        merits and demerits of the performers, but do not give them such unnecessary expression as to
                        embitter the literary associations against each other. The time was when members of one society
                        could not enter the hall of the rival organization without a special vote, and the first time
                        they were admitted even by such a vote, it was considered an act of the most sublime magnanimity
                        and self abnegation. Now, however, by a law to be found on the books of the societies, a member
                        from one can enter the other at any time, except during the reading of the minutes and the
                        transaction of miscellaneous business, whereas a person who does not belong to either society
                        cannot enter unless by special vote. The consequence is that every night of meeting visits are
                        exchanged, and a brotherly spirit is fast taking the place of the old barbarian disposition.
                        Persons who were members of these societies under the old regime, on their occasional visits to
                        college are astonished to find that deadly cuts against the opposition body are not received
                        with the rapturous applause of yore. It appears to this generation as incongruous as the offer
                        by a grimy New Zealander of a piece of roasted "white man" to a member of the
                        American Peace society.</p>
                    <p>The different classes also fraternize more now than in days agone. The great beauty of such
                        dispositions among our students is, that it will have a powerful effect on their future lives.
                        They will not be so much inclined to bigotry in religion, and dogmatism in politics, and
                        prejudice in other things if they, now, even while they have warm hearts and strong passions,
                        learn to <hi rend="i">bear and forbear.</hi> The world will never accomplish its destiny till
                        men begin to give each other the "right hand of fellowship." Then may no
                        "pent up Utica" confine our powers, but may we commence now to be true
                        cosmopolitans, having the green globe for our fatherland, and mankind for our countrymen.</p>
                    <p>—WAR.—We have one southerner in our institution. In consequence of his late
                        attempt at secession we have telegraphed for the <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Lafayette</settlement>
                        </placeName> gun squad and Dodworth's brass band, intending to blow him into three or
                        four septillions of pieces. In the meantime Capt. Blinn has detailed a corporal's guard
                        of seventy-five thousand cadets, who keep watch night and day. They all wear mustaches and pick
                        their teeth with <pb n="313" id="VAA4025-026-4-043"/> sword bayonets. The rest of the cadets are
                        getting their uniforms made. Any further attempts at secession will be promptly met. A
                        deputation of the oldest citizens waits on the perjured sesessionists nineteen times a day, with
                        elaborate and reliable information as to what will follow any of his rash acts. Every train
                        lands multitudes of hardy yoemanry "in our midst." Three hundred and
                        fifty-five powder mills have been erected in the campus, and their "thunderous energy
                        has supplied the red hand of destruction" to things, and smashed them considerably. The
                        young ladies of this city have cut off their ringlets and presented them to the students for
                        beau strings. James Buchanan has ordered two pieces of "ordinance" to be
                        brought to the scene of action from <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">San Francisco</settlement>
                        </placeName> by the pony express. Queen Victoria having heard of the matter through the Atlantic
                        Telegraph has ordered Albert Edward to form the nobility of <placeName>
                            <country reg="enk">England</country>
                        </placeName> into three battallions, and advance to the rescue. The Nuke of Dewcastle is first
                        "sirgent." Lord Brougham carries the trumpet, and the entire corps of the <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">London</settlement>
                        </placeName> Times will accompany the expedition to print bulletins. The population of the
                        Orient, amounting to seven hundred millions, led by Tommy, with three swords, are also coming.
                        The "Great Immense," a new ship thirteen miles long, eighty-seven wide, and
                        three hundred and twenty-nine in depth, has been built especially for this occasion, by Hongti
                        &amp; Co. The Zouaves of the French army began to swim across the Atlantic ocean on the 17th
                        ult. Their splendid bands, playing "Partant pour la Syrie," are carried on the
                        shoulders of the grenadiers of the Imperial Guard who expect to wade across. L. Napoleon
                        Threeeyes, himself, is at the head of the procession, floating by the buoyancy of his moustache.
                        Alexander of Russia is drilling the other monarchs of Europe in "double
                        quick," and expects to come over with his "awkward squad" if the
                        attempt at secession is not quashed by the 4th of July. No southerner can repel, in any short
                        period, at least, the forces we have enumerated.</p>
                </quote>
            <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>We are <hi rend="i">down</hi> on the following things:</p>
                    <p>First, we are down on the sentiment <hi rend="i">vox populi vox die est</hi>.</p>
                    <p>We are down on the idea that practical men are always right.</p>
                    <p>We are down on the idea that practical men are always wrong.</p>
                    <p>We are down on Procrustean ideas generally.</p>
                    <p>We are down on bigots and bigoted anti-bigots.</p>
                    <p>We are down on the sentiment, "our country, right or wrong."</p>
                    <p>We are down on the sentiment that anarchy, in either College or state, is liberty.</p>
                    <p>We are down on the idea that there is any man so wise that his assertions should be swallowed
                        with closed visual orbs.</p>
                    <p>We are down on the idea that some persons can read every other man's character at the
                        distance of four hundred yards.</p>
                    <p>We are down on the idea that a man can drink whisky in this part of the nineteenth century and
                        preserve his self-respect.</p>
                    <pb n="314" id="VAA4025-026-4-044"/>
                    <p>We are down on the idea that brass and blasphemy are essential parts of a gentleman's
                        character.</p>
                    <p>We do not believe that selfishness and dissembling are ever found in a lady's character.</p>
                    <p>Finally, we are <hi rend="i">down</hi> on from sixty-five to eighty-nine millions of the
                        one-eyed, hook-nosed, wooden-legged ideas now found in the world, and wish they were all tied to
                        the tail of Eckne's comet.</p>
                </quote>
         </div>
         <pb n="[315]" id="VAA4025-026-4-045"/>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-026-4-a05">
            <head>Reviews and Notices</head>
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">Constitution Making in Indiana: A Source Book of Constitutional Documents with
                        Historical Introduction and Critical Notes,</hi> vol. III. By C<hi rend="sc">HARLES</hi> K<hi rend="sc">ETTLEBOROUGH</hi>, Ph.D. Historical Bureau of the Indiana Library and Historical
                    Department, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, 1930. Pp. xix + 411.</head>
            <p>This volume by Dr. Kettleborough is the third of three, the whole being a most valuable contribution
                    to Indiana history, which the author began with the publication of the earlier volumes in 1916. The
                    work, prepared under the auspices of the Indiana Historical Bureau, now brings the account of
                    Indiana's attempts to amend her constitution down to date. It also supplements the earlier
                    volumes by incorporating documents that would naturally have fallen in the period covered by them.</p>
            <p>The author has carefully compiled "documents bearing some sanction of authority, including
                    in this instance, activities of the General Assembly, governor's messages, party platforms,
                    official ballots, court decisions, and opinions of attorney-generals." If the reader tends
                    to become weary in perusing the numerous documents; and if at times he feels that there might be
                    needless repetition, he should keep in mind the author's viewpoint: "As all
                    constitutional measures are required to pass through the ordinary legislative process it has seemed
                    necessary to give a detailed description of the adventures of each measure as it was advanced to
                    maturity and the political complexion of the General Assembly having it under consideration, since
                    politics has been a most potent factor in advancing or retarding constitutional amendments (I, vii).
                    The author's usually well worded and clearly expressed introductions to the various
                    documents are marred by such involved phraseology as may be found on pages 109 and 300, as well as
                    by the continuous use of the word "referred".</p>
            <p>The introduction of nineteen pages summarizes the various efforts to ammend the constitution. The
                    appendix contains a group of tables: one gives the number of votes cast by counties on the various
                    amendatory proposals; another summarizes the results of attempts to call a constitutional
                    convention; a third, <pb n="316" id="VAA4025-026-4-046"/> and probably the most valuable of the
                    group, shows what amendments have been proposed to each article and section of the constiution of
                    1851 and the disposition made thereof. The copius index is well prepared.</p>
            <p>The documents and other materials found in this volume will not only be interesting and valuable to
                    the students of the constitutional history of the State but to all those who are interested in
                    revising the fundamental law of Indiana. It is to be hoped that many will give this book careful
                    attention.</p>
            <byline>J<hi rend="sc">OHN</hi> A. C<hi rend="sc">OFFIN</hi>.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-026-4-a06">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">The Political Career of General James H. Lane.</hi> By WENDELL HOLMES STEPHENSON. <placeName>
                        <country reg="ksu">Kansas</country>
                    </placeName> State Historical Society, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Topeka</settlement>
                    </placeName>, 1930. Pp. 196. Illustrated, $1.00.</head>
            <p>Studies dealing with <placeName>
                        <country reg="ksu">Kansas</country>
                    </placeName> in her early, troubled period are of great interest to all readers of American history.
                    The struggles over the Territory produced deeds of violence within her borders, stirring scenes and
                    debates in the halls of Congress, and widespread political agitation, accompanied by a new alignment
                    of voters, during the period of bitter controversy. The careers of many political leaders of the
                    country were made, unmade or profoundly modified by the pent-up forces released by the passage of
                    the <placeName>
                        <country reg="ksu">Kansas</country>
                    </placeName>-<placeName>
                        <country reg="nbu">Nebraska</country>
                    </placeName> Act in 1854.</p>
            <p>Of the politicians who went to <placeName>
                        <country reg="ksu">Kansas</country>
                    </placeName> Territory, none became so forceful or so conspicuous as James H. Lane of Indiana. The
                    late William E. Connelley, long a student of the "grim chieftain", wrote, in a
                    brief introduction for Dr. Stephenson's monograph: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>General James H. Lane was the outstanding figure in <placeName>
                                <country reg="ksu">Kansas</country>
                            </placeName> in the struggle to withstand slavery and found a free state. He possessed an
                            overpowering personality, and was a man of many eccentricities. He was a genius, and the
                            wavy line sepearating genius from insantity is almost imperceptible—is completely
                            so at times. I think there is no doubt that Lane was at times of unbalanced
                            mind…. But that did not hinder him in his enthusiasm for <placeName>
                                <country reg="ksu">Kansas</country>
                            </placeName>. <placeName>
                                <country reg="ksu">Kansas</country>
                            </placeName> was his burden—his song.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>The study under review constitutes an eminently fair, highly informing and very readable biography of
                    Lane, though doctoral dissertations are in bad repute as entertaining reading matter. Professional
                    reviewers, who are enamored of the writings of the present prolific school of journalistic
                    historians <pb n="317" id="VAA4025-026-4-047"/> (whose narratives flow just as smoothly when they do
                    not know the facts as when they do), handle the theses of young doctors with undue severity. Indeed,
                    the prejudices of such reviewers in relation to studies "submitted in partial fulfillment
                    of the requirements for the degree of doctor of philosophy" are so pronounced that there
                    must be a reason for them. An observer is inclined to believe that the real difficulty lies in the
                    fact that university professors attempt to train graduate students to weigh the evidence carefully
                    and to write without bias, making the necessary qualifications. Should these offending experts in
                    historical research be ostracised because they tend to make the reading of history less
                    entertaining? Is there not yet some virtue in the ancient saying, "Know the truth and the
                    truth will make you free"?</p>
            <p>It is not the contention that doctoral dissertations furnish reading matter to the general public
                    with which to while away happily occasional periods of leisure. They are not written for the
                    entertainment of a wide circle of readers, and should not be judged as if so prepared. They should
                    be justly emluated, nevertheless, each according to its individual content and style, since in these
                    respects, they differ much as do other types of historical writing.</p>
            <p>Professor Stephenson's work is not just a doctor's thesis Before submitting it for
                    publication, he rounded it out by a preliminary survey of Lane's Indiana career and by
                    adding chapters at the end to complete the life of his subject. In the June, 1929, issue of the <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of History,</hi> appeared a paper under the caption, "The
                    Transitional Period in the Career of General James H. Lane", in which the transformation of
                    the conservative Hoosier Democrat into the <placeName>
                        <country reg="ksu">Kansas</country>
                    </placeName> Radical is traced and interpreted. In the September, 1930, issue of the <hi rend="i">Magazine</hi> there was published a carefully-prpared study of Amos Lane, the father of Jim
                    Lane. These papers supplement the longer monograph and place students of the later middle period of
                    American history under heavy obligations to Dr. Stephenson.</p>
            <p>In the "balanced biography of Lane", as Mr. Connelley correctly characterized it,
                    we have the career of this meteoric figure calmly and accurately traced. Growing to maturity in
                    southeastern Indiana, Lane participated in the Mexican War, served as Lieutenant Governor of the
                    State, and was a member of the national House of Representatives before going to <pb n="318" id="VAA4025-026-4-048"/>
                    <placeName>
                        <country reg="ksu">Kansas</country>
                    </placeName>. He voted for the <placeName>
                        <country reg="ksu">Kansas</country>
                    </placeName>-<placeName>
                        <country reg="nbu">Nebraska</country>
                    </placeName> Bill in 1854, but was not a candidate for reelection. He started for <placeName>
                        <country reg="ksu">Kansas</country>
                    </placeName> Territory shortly after the end of his term in the House in March, 1855. Concerning his
                    political life to this moment, the author concludes (p. 40) that "there is little in
                    Lane's activities in Indiana which foreshadows his strenuous political career after
                    1855."</p>
            <p>For some time after reaching <placeName>
                        <country reg="ksu">Kansas</country>
                    </placeName>, Lane remained a Democrat, his chief ambition, seemingly being to build up and lead the
                    party in the Territory. Caution marked his movements and utterances. It was the "<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Wakarusa</settlement>
                    </placeName> War" of the fall of 1855 that transformed him. Dormant forces in his soul
                    leaped to the surface, and he became a new man. His caution disappeared, and his mental balance
                    seems to have been thrown somewhat out of adjustment from this time forward. His oratorical feats,
                    his rash acts, his fiery zeal, his defiance of enemies, his inconsistencies and his
                    power–these make the narrative of his life from 1855 to 1865 extremely interesting. Dr.
                    Stephenson portrays General Lane in politics and in camp as he was. He does not condone his faults
                    nor fail to give him credit when due.</p>
            <p>The decade, 1855-1865, was, of course, the most important and stormy part of Lane's life, to
                    this period nine of fifteen chapters are devoted. After following the activities of an extremist
                    through ten strenuous years, one is startled to read: "On the problem of reconstruction,
                    Lane deserted the radicals in Congress and reverted to conservatism". Though he criticized
                    some acts of President Johnson, he was by January, 1866, "intrenched with the
                    administration," his policy of reconstruction being in essential harmony with that of
                    Johnson. The result of this position caused his condemnation to be almost unanimous in <placeName>
                        <country reg="ksu">Kansas</country>
                    </placeName>. In 1866, he bowed to the dictation of his erstwhile political friends among the
                    Radicals and took no part in the campaign of that year in <placeName>
                        <country reg="ksu">Kansas</country>
                    </placeName>. Furthermore, during his last few weeks in the Senate, he voted with the Radical
                    majority. He enaed his spectacular and erratic carrer on July 11, 1866, dying from a self-inflicted
                    bullet wound of July 1.</p>
            <p>In a brief, final chapter, Professor Stephenson discusses the "Character and
                    Leadership" of Lane and undertakes the difficult and hazardous task of contrasting him with
                    his <pb n="319" id="VAA4025-026-4-049"/> powerful <placeName>
                        <country reg="ksu">Kansas</country>
                    </placeName> rival, Charles Robinson. In regard to the two men, the author says with keen insight:
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>In laying the foundations of the new commonwealth his [Lane's name] was inseparably
                            associated with that of Charles Robinson. These two pioneers stood in sharp contrast. Lane
                            was rash, hot-headed, daring, persistent, subtle, provocative, warm-hearted, magnetic.
                            Robinson was cool, cautious, calculative, judicious, logical, shrewd, business-like. In
                            method one was the antipode of the other, "for where Robinson would throw on cold
                            water, Lane would apply the firebrand." Lane was an extremist, a radical,
                            revolutionary spirit, the motive power of the free-state movement. Robinson was a
                            conservative, the brake and balance wheel, the ballast which gave the movement equilibrium.
                            Each possessed an insatiable ambition, and each recognized in the other a political rival.
                            It would be useless to speculate upon the relative contributions of the two men. Indeed it
                            was fortunate for the free-state cause that the party contained diversity of leadership.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <byline>W.O.L.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-026-4-a07">
            <p>The <hi rend="i">Annual Report</hi> of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Mount Vernon</settlement>
                    </placeName> Ladies" Association of the Union for 1930 is a pamphlet of sixty-eight pages.
                    For a copy of this report we are indebted to Mrs. Benjamin D. Walcott of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Muncie</settlement>
                    </placeName>, who is the Vice Regent for Indiana. The Association has a noble purpose: "Its
                    object shall be to perpetuate the sacred memory of ‘The Father of His Country’
                    and, with loving hands, to guard and protect the hallowed spot where rest his mortal remains; to
                    forever hold, manage and preserve the estate, properties and relics at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Mount Vernon</settlement>
                    </placeName>, belonging to the Association, and under proper regulations, open the same to the
                    inspection of all who love the cause of Liberty, and revere the name of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName>."</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">The Archaeology of the <geogName>Whitewater Valley</geogName>
               </hi> is the title of a
                    study of nearly two hundred pages by Frank M. Setzler. This monograph comprises the whole of <hi rend="i">Indiana History Bulletin,</hi> Volume VII, Number 12, issued in September, 1930, by the
                    Indiana Historical Bureau. The study includes a short account of the early history of the
                        <geogName>Whitewater Valley</geogName>, and devotes three pages to its geology and geography.
                    The greater part of the monograph consists of archaeological surveys of <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Franklin</settlement>, <region type="county">Fayette</region>
               </placeName>, Union
                    and <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wayne Counties</region>
                    </placeName>, each treated by townships. A survey of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> township in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Randolph county</region>
                    </placeName> is also included. The text is illustrated by maps, and numerous drawings. Many fine
                    photographs of mounds, relics, skeletons and other objects of interest to students of <pb n="320" id="VAA4025-026-4-050"/> archaeology make up the last thirty-five pages of the study. Mr.
                    Setzler has done an excellent piece of work which will receive high commendation from those who
                    study it with sufficient care.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Lucius B. Swift: A Biography</hi> has just come from the press. This life of the late
                    Mr. Swift of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> is a result of the labors of his friend and militant co-worker of many years, William
                    Dudley Foulke. The biography runs to one hundred twenty-three pages, with four appendices, and an
                    adequate index. Characters with whom Mr. Swift had to deal from Lew Shank up to Colonel Theodore
                    Roosevelt are brought into the narrative in an intimate and interesting fashion. Students of Civil
                    Service Reform and all who are interested in the party history with which the independent reformer,
                    Lucius B. Swift, was connected, will wish to read this latest product from the pen of Mr. Foulke.
                    The biography constitutes Volume IX of <hi rend="i">Indiana Historical Society Publications.</hi> It
                    was brought out for the Society by The Bobbs Merrill Company of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Paper-bound copies may be purchased from the Society or the publishers at
                    $1.50 per copy, or cloth-bound copies at $2.00 each. This biography will be
                    reviewed in our March issue.</p>
            <p>The fourth and last volume of William Watts Folwell's comprehensive <hi rend="i">History of <placeName>
                            <country reg="mnu">Minnesota</country>
                        </placeName>
               </hi> was recently published by the <placeName>
                        <country reg="mnu">Minnesota</country>
                    </placeName> Historical Society. It is a well-written, well-printed, handsomely bound volume, with a
                    brief "Introduction" by Dr. Solon J. Buck, Secretary of the Society. A review of
                    this volume will appear in our next number.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="[321]" id="VAA4025-026-4-051"/>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-026-4-a08">
            <head>Indiana Historical Society</head>
            <byline>Christopher B. Coleman, Secretary</byline>
            <p rend="center">THE STATE SCHOOL FOR THE BLIND</p>
            <p>The Indiana Historical Society has begun a program for the preservation of plans and data of all
                    sorts for important buildings in the State which are changed or torn down. Before the destruction of
                    the building occupied by the State School for the Blind at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> was begun, careful measurements were made of all parts of it by O. E. Williamson, an <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> architect. Drawings will be made by Mr. Williamson from these measurements, and these,
                    together with a collection of old and new photographs, will be placed in the William Henry Smith
                    Memorial Library of the Society which will be located in the main building of the World War
                    Memorial.</p>
            <p>Built in the early fifties, the School for the Blind was one of the most notable historic pieces of
                    architecture in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>. The original plans for the buildings were made by John Elder, under the direction of
                    William H. Churchman, a blind man, and the leader of the movement for the education of blind
                    children in Indiana. He had visited many of the blind schools in other States and was able to
                    incorporate the best features of many of these in the plans. Before the building was begun, however,
                    these plans were altered by Francis Costigan, an architect then living at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indiana. His alterations changed the external appearance of the building but not the
                    inside plans. The cost for the construction of the building was $68,000. Several
                    additions have been made to the original structure.</p>
            <p>Efforts have been made at various times to remove or destroy the building, but always the feeling or
                    sentiment for this old landmark helped to preserve it a few years longer. The completion of the
                    grounds included in the World War Memorial made it necessary for the building to be destroyed. Many
                    suggestions and plans were advanced for the preservation of the original building. These included
                    removing it to another site, or erecting another public building such as the proposed library and
                    historical building as a replica of it, but the World War Memorial Commission found these
                    impracticable.</p>
            <pb n="322" id="VAA4025-026-4-052"/>
            <p>The officers of the Society considered the construction of a miniature in plaster or cement, but
                    finally decided for the present to preserve detailed measurements, drawings, and photographs. At
                    some future time then it will be possible to erect such a model.</p>
            <p rend="center">MEMBERSHIP AND ACTIVITIES</p>
            <p>The Indiana Historical Society reaches the end of its centennial year with a membership approximating
                    1,200. This is the largest in its history but still leaves much to be desired.</p>
            <p>About one-third of this number are new members who have never belonged to the Society prior to 1930.
                    Many of these new memberships were gained through the efforts of the all-state membership committee
                    appointed early in 1930. It consisted of one and sometimes two members from each county in the
                    state. Moses Epstein of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clinton County</region>
                    </placeName> secured the largest number of new members, and George W. Finley of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clay County</region>
                    </placeName>, the second largest number. Members of the committee from other counties also did
                    splendid work and it is hoped that their interest in gaining new members will not cease even though
                    the centennial year is past.</p>
            <p>The publications received by the members during 1930 have been many and varied. The four issues of
                    the <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of History</hi> have included articles on many phases of State
                    history. The April number of the <hi rend="i">Indiana History Bulletin</hi> was devoted to the
                    proceedings of the 1929 history conference, and the September number dealt with recent
                    archaeological surveys and excavations made in this State. Indiana has been considerably behind her
                    neighboring States of <placeName>
                        <country reg="ohu">Ohio</country>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <country reg="ilu">Illinois</country>
                    </placeName> in archaeological work, but during the last three years much progress has been made.
                    The Indiana Historical Society has been the leader in promoting and supporting this work.</p>
            <p>Two <hi rend="i">Publications</hi> of the Society have been printed in 1930, a biography of Lucius B.
                    Swift, by William Dudley Foulke, and the <hi rend="i">Centennial Handbook.</hi> Mr. Foulke was an
                    intimate friend of Mr. Swift, and a fellow worker in the field of civil service reform. No one is
                    better qualified to write the biography of this Indiana leader in the movement for civil service
                    reform than Mr. Foulke</p>
            <p>The history of the Indiana Historical Society, written by the president, Dr. James A. Woodburn, forms
                    the main part <pb n="323" id="VAA4025-026-4-053"/> of the <hi rend="i">Centennial Handbook.</hi> It
                    is the story of an organization that has weathered many storms and has succeeded in spite of them.
                    The prospect for the next one hundred years is much brighter than that faced by the founders in
                    1930.</p>
            <p>The publications of the Society for 1931 will consist of many interesting studies, including some of
                    the following: a collection of Jonathan Jennings' letters; biographies of Jesse D. Bright,
                    John W. Davis, and Isaac Blackford; the history of the Pokagons; and a collection of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New Harmony</settlement>
                    </placeName> letters. The editor of the <hi rend="i">Magazine</hi> also has many interesting
                    articles in store.</p>
            <p>Do not fail to send in your membership for 1931 at once, so that you will not miss any of these
                    publications. Your membership will indicate your interest in and support of the efforts being made
                    to collect and preserve the materials for our State history.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="[324]" id="VAA4025-026-4-054"/>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-026-4-a09">
            <head>Comment and News</head>
            <p>Last January, Kin Hubbard, in the character of Abe Martin, expressed himself with his usual
                    cleverness in regard to the extensive output in the field of biography: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>"Sorry I can't stop as I'm writin' a biography
                            o' Simon Kenton, a great historical character, and I'm afraid somebuddy
                            '11 beat me to it," said Hon. Ex-Editor Cale Fluhart, as he rushed out
                            o' the Emporium with a bottle o' ink today. Biography writin' is
                            one o' the big present-day industries that shows no signs o'
                            lettin' down. Ther'd be fer more unemployment than ther is if it
                            muz'n fer biography writin'. I expect <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Lincoln</settlement>
                            </placeName> is furnishhair. About her a silken shawl she in' almost as much
                            employment as the railroads…. I expect to see a daily ‘Life
                            o' <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Lincoln</settlement>
                            </placeName>’ before the year is out….<hi rend="sup">1</hi>
                  </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>A new issue of the <hi rend="i">
                  <placeName>
                            <country reg="tnu">Tennessee</country>
                        </placeName> Historical Magazine,</hi> which has been in a state of suspension for some time,
                    appeared recently. The last number of the <hi rend="i">Magazine</hi> came out in October, 1928,
                    being No. 4 of Volume IX, the issue for January, 1926. The current number of the quarterly bears the
                    date October, 1930, and is designated as No. 1, Volume 1, Series II. <placeName>
                        <country reg="tnu">Tennessee</country>
                    </placeName> is rich in political and economic history, and the revived <hi rend="i">Magazine</hi>
                    will receive a cordial reception everywhere. It is hoped that the quarterly will be well supported
                    and that its issues will appear without interruption for a long period of years.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">The <placeName>
                            <country reg="alu">Alabama</country>
                        </placeName> Historical Quarterly</hi> is a new magazine in the field of State History. The
                    third or "Fall Issue" of volume one has appeared. The <hi rend="i">Quarterly</hi>
                    is published by the State Department of Archives and History at <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Montgomery</region>
                    </placeName>. The editor is (Mrs.) Marie Bankhead Owen, the capable Director of the Department. The
                    three issues of this new historical magazine have carried matter of great variety. The illustrations
                    are numerous and very attractive. From the Summer Issue of 1930, we quote a poem "The Sea
                    is a Senorita" by Martha Layman Shillito. This real gem is dedicated "To Mobile
                    Bay by Moonlight". A remarkable picture of the bay is shown on the page opposite the poem
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="i">The sea is a Senorita fair With a comb of shell in her swirl of hair About her
                                a silken shawl she flings</hi>
                            <list type="footnotes">
                        <item>
                           <hi rend="sup">1</hi> Abe Martin, "Short Furrows", in <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                                    </placeName> News, January 18, 1930.</item>
                     </list>
                            <pb n="325" id="VAA4025-026-4-055"/>
                            <hi rend="i">That swishes gaily, yet softly clings. Sometimes she flaunts its silver folds,
                                Stamps her foot and shrilly scolds. In fury having spent her strength She swoons upon
                                her couch, full length, Her spangled shawl a shimmering heap Beside her as she falls
                                asleep.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>An interesting interview with Mrs. Catherine Kuhn of North <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Manchester</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indiana, which was reported in the <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Marion</region>
                    </placeName> (Indiana) <hi rend="i">Chronicle</hi> of February 11, 1929, is well worthy of some
                    space here. Mrs. Kuhn was born at <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Gettysburg</settlement>,
                            <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>
               </placeName> on February 13, 1841. She
                    was at home during the great, three-days battle of 1863, when she was twenty-two years old. At the
                    age of eighty-eight, she remembered quite distinctly her exciting experiences during that period of
                    stress and strain. She was a member of the choir and sat on the platform when <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Lincoln</settlement>
                    </placeName> made his famous <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Gettysburg</settlement>
                    </placeName> Address on October 23, 1863. An interesting and carefully prepared volume, <hi rend="i">
                  <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Lincoln</settlement>
                        </placeName> at <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Gettysburg</settlement>
                        </placeName>,</hi> by William E. Barton, has been issued recently by The Bobbs Merrill Company.
                    Mr. Barton did not know of Mrs. Kuhn, but her statements tally closely with his findings. The
                    account by Mrs. Kuhn follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>I do not remember how many there were in the choir that day, but not many. A few of them are
                            living besides myself, I think. The day was nice.<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Governors of all
                            States in the Union came to town for the ceremonies.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> Governor Oliver P.
                            Morton of Indiana was entertained in our home. President Lincoln was entertained at the home
                            of Mr. Wills, a lawyer.</p>
                        <p>The war memorial cemetery was not far from town, situated across the road from the
                            battlefield. The monument which since has been erected there is situated in the center of
                            the cemetery. On the day of the dedication nothing was on the grounds except a little wooden
                            building with a high platform built on one side of it on which the services were held.
                            President Lincoln, the governors and members of the choir sat there.</p>
                        <p>There was a short prayer service at the Presbyterian church before we went out to the
                            cemetery. We walked out there. I remember seeing <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Lincoln</settlement>
                            </placeName> riding to the cemetery on horseback. His head was bare and he did not even
                            bother to put his feet in the stirrups. They almost <list type="footnotes">
                        <item>
                           <hi rend="sup">1</hi> Barton says that "the weather was propitious "<placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Lincoln</settlement>
                                    </placeName> at Gettuysburg. 71.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi rend="sup">2</hi> The Governors present included: Curtin of <placeName>
                                        <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>
                                    </placeName>; Bradford of <placeName>
                                        <region type="state" reg="mdu">Maryland</region>
                                    </placeName>: Morton of Indiana: Scymour of <placeName>
                                        <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                                    </placeName>: Parker of <placeName>
                                        <country reg="nju">New Jersey</country>
                                    </placeName>: Dennison of <placeName>
                                        <country reg="ohu">Ohio</country>
                                    </placeName>; Governor-elect Brough of <placeName>
                                        <country reg="ohu">Ohio</country>
                                    </placeName>; ex-Governor Tcd of <placeName>
                                        <country reg="ohu">Ohio</country>
                                    </placeName>. See ibid., 76. Barton relied on the <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Philadelphia</settlement>
                                    </placeName> Press for the list of Governors and other notables present.</item>
                     </list>
                            <pb n="326" id="VAA4025-026-4-056"/> touched the ground.<hi rend="sup">3</hi> I
                            don't believe that I have ever seen a sadder looking man than Abraham Lincoln.<hi rend="sup">4</hi> When he spoke his voice was sad too. He talked slowly and distinctly,
                            and not for a very long time. A hush fell over the crowd.<hi rend="sup">5</hi> A man before <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Lincoln</settlement>
                            </placeName> had talked for an hour and a half.</p>
                        <p>I remember how big and important I felt sitting up there as a member of the selected choir on
                            the same platform with the President. I can't remember exactly what we sang; some
                            of the good old hymns, I think.<hi rend="sup">6</hi>
                  </p>
                        <p>When I got up on the platform, Governor Morton spoke to me, and that made me feel very happy
                            indeed. After the services, President Lincoln shook hands with all the choir members.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>The Historical Society of Western <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>
                    </placeName> has inaugurated a "vigorous program of research and writing of history of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Pittsburgh</settlement>
                    </placeName> district." The Buhl Foundation and the University of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Pittsburgh</settlement>
                    </placeName> are cooperating in this most laudable enterprise. The research and writing will be done
                    by a staff of six trained men. The labors of the staff are to lead to papers and monographs that
                    will appeal to scholars, but also to narratives of a more popular nature for the general public. In
                    addition, the history of the district is to be written in a form adapted for use in the public
                    schools. Accuracy is to be regarded as of prime importance in each of the three levels of writing,
                    but the hope is entertained by the promoters of the plan that the "full inspirational value
                    of the enterprise as a substantial contribution to a spirit of effective citizenship", will
                    be understood and successfully embodied in whatever the staff of workers may produce. It is much to
                    be desired that the spirit of the movement may spread and prompt similar plans to be launched in a
                    number of other local areas of the country likewise rich in historical experience.</p>
            <p>In the paper on "Colonel John Francis Hamtramck" which was published in our last
                    issue, Zebulon Montgomery Pike was mentioned with a correct list of his greatest exploits. <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">3</hi> Barton says: "The President's horse was too small,
                            and the President did not appear to good advantage". See <hi rend="i">ibid</hi>.,
                            75</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">4</hi> "Colonel Carr, who rode just behind the President stated
                            that when the procession started, the President sat erect on his horse and looked the part
                            of the Commander in Chief of the Army; but as the procession moved on, his body leaned
                            forward, his arms hung limp, and his head was bent. He seemed absorbed in thought"
                            See <hi rend="i">ibid</hi>., 75.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">5</hi> The accounts of other persons who were present agree, generally,
                            with Mrs. Kuhn on this point. See Barton's chapter 21—"Some of
                            Those Who Heard It."</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">6</hi> Just before <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Lincoln</settlement>
                            </placeName>'s brief address, the choir sang a Hymn composed for the occasion by
                            Benjamin B. French. and, after the address, rendered a selected dirge. For the song by
                            French, see Barton, Gkttysburg Addrass, 169-170.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="327" id="VAA4025-026-4-057"/> He was not, however, a soldier in the army of the Northwest in
                    1792, being then but twelve years of age. It was his father, Zebulon Pike who was the captain of a
                    company at that time. The editor of the <hi rend="i">
                  <placeName>
                            <region type="state" reg="miu">Michigan</region>
                        </placeName> Pioneer Collections,</hi> volume XXXIV, is in error both in his footnotes and in
                    the index. He seems not to have known anything about Zebulon Pike, confusing him in every case where
                    he is mentioned with his more illustrious son, Zebulon Montgomery Pike.</p>
            <p>A new department has been added in this issue of the <hi rend="i">Magazine</hi> which will remain a
                    permanent feature. It is headed <hi rend="i">Indiana Historical Society.</hi> The material for its
                    pages is furnished by the Secretary of the Society, Dr. Christopher B. Coleman. This feature is
                    inaugurated on the initative of the <hi rend="i">Editor</hi> who is certain that it will meet with
                    the approval of readers and furnish tangible evidence that a spirit of cooperation exists between
                    the Society and Indiana University.</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="i">General Index</hi> for volumes I-xxv of the <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of
                    History</hi> was prepared by Miss Dorothy Riker, of the Indiana Historical Bureau, who deserves high
                    praise for careful workmanship. Copy was completed before June 1, 1930, and a limited edition of 500
                    was issued from the Indiana University Press in October. The <hi rend="i">Index</hi> has been
                    offered at one dollar, though the cost, aside from the labor of preparing the volume of two hundred
                    pages, has been nearly twice that per copy. It was well understood that sales of the <hi rend="i">Index</hi> would be limited almost entirely to members of the Indiana Historical Society and to
                    libraries possessing files or partial files of the <hi rend="i">Magazine.</hi> Orders have been
                    received from about fifty libraries, but individual members of the Historical Society have supported
                    our venture, certainly a worthy one, to the number of less than twelve. We counted on a sure
                    response from three or four hundred members. Otherwise the publication of an <hi rend="i">Index</hi>
                    would never have been undertaken. Orders will be filled at one dollar per copy, if received within
                    ten days after the mailing of this issue of the <hi rend="i">Magazine,</hi> after which the price
                    will be raised to two dollars. We hope for a quick and generous response</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="[328]" id="VAA4025-026-4-058"/>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-026-4-a11">
            <head>Reprints</head>
            <p>Reprints of any paper published in the <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of History</hi> may be obtained
                    by any contributor. Estimates of the cost will be furnished on request and an order placed for as
                    many reprints of any article as may be desired by the author.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-026-4-a12">
            <head>Wanted</head>
            <p>We are sure that some of our readers can aid us to obtain the desired publications listed below. The
                    Library of Indiana University and other libraries in different parts of the country are in need of
                    copies of the issues mentioned in order to complete files. For older and rarer numbers, prices above
                    the regular rates will be paid. Persons possessing any of the desired magazines or other
                    publications, will confer a great favor by writing to Dr. R. C. Buley, Business Manager of the <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of History.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">The Indianian.</hi> This magazine was published at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> from 1898 to 1906, six volumes in all. Wanted, a complete file. Partial sets will be
                    considered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Indiana, Past and Present</hi>. This little, temporary periodical was published during
                    1914. Wanted, a complete file, and also an extra copy of Number 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">The Open Road</hi>. Wanted copies of this monthly for: March, April, May, June, July,
                    August, September, and November, 1910; March, July, August, and September, 1911; April and May,
                    1912; July, 1913; January, 1914.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Bulletins</hi> of the Indiana Historical Commission. Numbers 16 and 18. These contain
                    the <hi rend="i">Proceedings</hi> of the Southwestern Indiana Historical Society for 1922 and 1923.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Commencement Programs</hi> of Indiana University. Wanted to complete the file of the
                    University Library, the following, but duplicates of those listed and of any programs prior to 1900
                    will be accepted and valued: programs of 1st to 10th Commencements, 1828-1830; 22nd to 24th,
                    1851-1853; 39th to <pb n="329" id="VAA4025-026-4-059"/> 41st, 1868-1870; 49th and 50th, 1878-1879;
                    66th and 67th, 1895-1896.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Indiana School Journal.</hi> Wanted vol. 37, numbers 7-8 (1892); vol. 38, numbers 6, 9,
                    10, 11, 12 (1893); vol. 40, numbers 4, 9, 10, 11 (1895).</p>
            <p>National Educational Association, <hi rend="i">Proceedings.</hi> Wanted for 1860, 1864, 1872, 1884,
                    and 1885.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of History.</hi> We have had a generous response to our appeals for
                    back numbers, especially for those dated later than 1914. We have a serious need for copies of
                    issues from 1905 to 1912. We very much desire to locate the four numbers of volume IV (1908); number
                    one of volume VI (1910); the four numbers of volume VII (1911); the four numbers of vol. VIII
                    (1912). We will buy further copies of the following issues: Dec., 1921; Mar., 1922; double-number
                    June-Sept., 1925.</p>
            <p>Full sets of the <hi rend="i">Magazine</hi> can be supplied to libraries or individuals who may
                    desire to purchase only with great difficulty. A complete file from 1920 forward can be supplied at
                    fifty-cents a copy or two dollars per volume, unbound; from 1914 to 1919, the price is one dollar
                    per copy, or four dollars per volume; a file from 1905-1913, when it can be supplied at all, must be
                    priced at a much higher figure.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <pb n="[330]" id="VAA4025-026-4-060"/>
         <pb n="[331]" id="VAA4025-026-4-061"/>
         <pb n="332" id="VAA4025-026-4-062"/>
         <pb n="333" id="VAA4025-026-4-063"/>
         <pb n="334" id="VAA4025-026-4-064"/>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI.2>