<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "imh_issue.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="VAA4025-072-1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Indiana Magazine of History</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoded by</resp>
               <name>Aptara Inc.</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <date>2007</date>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>Copyright 2007 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
               <p>Indiana University provides the information contained in this file for non-commercial,
        personal, or research use only. All other use, including but not limited to commercial or
        scholarly reproductions, redistribution, publication or transmission, whether by electronic
        means or otherwise, without prior written permission of the copyright holder is strictly
        prohibited.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Indiana Magazine of History</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title>Indiana Magazine of History</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Indiana University Department of History in cooperation with the Indiana
                                Historical Society</publisher>
                     <date>1976</date>
                     <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="volume">72</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="pages">1-94</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10-11</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Annette D. Richmond</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Corrected list and pagebreak formatting.</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n="[]" id="VAA4025-072-1-001"/>
         <pb n="[]" id="VAA4025-072-1-002"/>
         <pb n="[]" id="VAA4025-072-1-003"/>
         <pb n="[]" id="VAA4025-072-1-004"/>
         <pb n="[]" id="VAA4025-072-1-005"/>
         <pb n="[]" id="VAA4025-072-1-006"/>
      </front>
      <body>
         <pb n="[1]" id="VAA4025-072-1-007"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-072-1-a01">
            <head>George Rogers Clark and the American Revolution in the West</head>
            <byline>George M. Waller∗</byline>
            <p>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Brave Lewis our colonel an officer bold,</p>
                        <p>At the mouth of Kanhawa did the Shawnees behold.</p>
                        <p>On the tenth of October, at the rising sun</p>
                        <p>The armies did meet and the battle begun.<hi rend="sup">1</hi>
                  </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            <p>In song and story the heritage of men and battles is often preserved. The quoted couplets are the
                    beginning of an epic verse found in several variations celebrating the battle between forces under
                    Colonel Andrew Lewis and the Shawnee at Point Pleasant, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName>, in the fall of 1774. It was the first outbreak of open Indian war in the West since
                    the end of the French and Indian War and Pontiac's Rebellion in the early 1760s. The Battle
                    of Point Pleasant was the only pitched battle of the brief Lord Dunmore's War against the
                    Shawnee. It signaled the reopening of the Indians' struggle <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">∗</hi> Professor George M. Waller is chairman of the Department
                            of History, Political Science, and Geography at <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Butler</settlement>
                            </placeName> University, <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                            </placeName>, Indiana. The following address was presented to the Indiana University
                            Conference on Historic Preservation in <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Bloomington</settlement>
                            </placeName> on September 13, 1974, as a part of the continuing Cornelius O'Brien
                            Lecture Series on Historic Preservation. A few minor changes have been made in the text of
                            the original speech to adapt it to the printed medium; otherwise, the address is printed
                            here as it was given by Professor Waller. Footnotes have been included only to pinpoint
                            specific quotations or to guide readers to additional sources. Professor Waller, a colonial
                            historian, is the author of <hi rend="i">The American Revolution in the West,</hi> published
                            by Nelson-Hall Company (<placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                            </placeName>, 1976). His address is printed in the <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of
                            History</hi> as part of the American Revolution Bicentennial observance.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">1</hi> Printed in Reuben Gold Thwaites and Louise Phelps Kellogg, eds., <hi rend="i">Documentary History of Dunmore's War, 1774</hi> (<placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                            </placeName>, 1905), 433. The Colonel Lewis referred to was Charles Lewis, a brother of
                            Andrew Lewis who was in overall command at the Battle of Point Pleasant during Lord
                            Dunmore's War in 1774.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="2" id="VAA4025-072-1-008"/> against white advance that was to continue during the years of
                    the American Revolution.<hi rend="sup">2</hi>
            </p>
            <p>George Rogers Clark was a twenty-two year old militia captain in this little "war,"
                    holding a commission from the royal governor of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName>, Lord Dunmore. He marched with a small force that attacked Indian villages on the
                    Muskingum River in southeastern <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> before joining Dunmore. Clark was not at the Battle of Point Pleasant but joined
                    Dunmore's forces to move against the Shawnee town of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Chillicothe</settlement>
                    </placeName> on the <geogName>Scioto River</geogName> where the Indians in 1774 accepted a
                    preliminary agreement, the "treaty" of Camp Charlotte.</p>
            <p>Clark was to become one of the leading figures in the American Revolution, fighting against the
                    British with whom he had so recently marched. I think it is appropriate in considering historic
                    preservation to consider the problems of preserving the history of a war and the knowledge of a hero
                    in that war. George Rogers Clark and the Revolution in the West are a kind of historic structure.
                    Like other more material structures they need to be identified and preserved. Like historic
                    buildings they have been altered, added to, and reshaped in the passage of time, in ways irrelevant
                    to their original reality and historic meanings. These changes need to be stripped
                    off—like the porticos added to ancient buildings —the original integrity
                    reestablished, and their meaning for their time and for later times recognized.</p>
            <p>Unlike historic buildings, heroes, wars, and original topography cannot be preserved or restored in a
                    literal sense. They may only be recreated in words, maps, pictures, statues, or imaginative
                    pictorializations as in films, slides, or tapes. <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">2</hi> Printed sources upon which this account is based can be found in the
                            Draper Collection (State Historical Society of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="wiu">Wisconsin</region>, <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                     </placeName>) and
                            in the following volumes edited by Reuben Gold Thwaites and Louise Phelps Kellogg: <hi rend="i">Documentary History of Dunmore's War, 1771–; Revolution on
                                the <placeName>
                                    <region type="state">Upper Ohio</region>
                                </placeName>, 1775–1777</hi> (<placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                            </placeName>, 1908); <hi rend="i">Frontier Defense on the <placeName>
                                    <region type="state">Upper Ohio</region>
                                </placeName>, 1777–1778</hi> (<placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                            </placeName>, 1912). Additional sources are included in Louise Phelps Kellogg, ed., <hi rend="i">Frontier Advance on the <placeName>
                                    <region type="state">Upper Ohio</region>
                                </placeName>, 1778–1779</hi> (<placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                            </placeName>, 1916); <hi rend="i">ibid., Frontier Retreat on the <placeName>
                                    <region type="state">Upper Ohio</region>
                                </placeName>, 1779–1781</hi> (<placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>
                            </placeName>, 1917); James Alton James, ed., <hi rend="i">George Rogers Clark Papers,
                                1771–1781 (Collections of the <placeName>
                                    <region type="state" reg="ilu">Illinois</region>
                                </placeName> State Historical Library,</hi> Vol. VIII; <placeName>
                                <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                            </placeName> Series, Vol. Ill; <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Springfield</settlement>
                            </placeName>, 1912); <hi rend="i">ibid., George Rogers Clark Papers, 1781–1784
                                (Collections of the <placeName>
                                    <region type="state" reg="ilu">Illinois</region>
                                </placeName> State Historical Library,</hi> Vol. XIX; <placeName>
                                <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                            </placeName> Series, Vol. IV; <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Springfield</settlement>
                            </placeName>, 1926). Jack M. Sosin, <hi rend="i">The Revolutionary Frontier,
                                1763–2783</hi> (<placeName>
                                <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                            </placeName>, 1967) provides a brief secondary account with an excellent bibliography. The
                            most reliable biography of Clark is James A. James, <hi rend="i">The Life of George Rogers
                                Clark</hi> (<placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                            </placeName>, 1928), supplemented by John D. Barnhart, ed., <hi rend="i">Henry Hamilton and
                                George Rogers Clark in the American Revolution</hi> (<placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Crawfordsville</settlement>
                            </placeName>, Ind., 1951).</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="3" id="VAA4025-072-1-009"/> The originals rarely exist. Only a few slabs remain of an
                    original French house at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName>. The Buffalo Trace across southern Indiana from Clarksville to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> is now hardly traceable, even though topography still demonstrates the logic of its
                    course, and one probable buffalo wallow is still clearly visible, although one suspects that it is
                    kept wallowable by more modern kine. The barracks of Fort Patrick Henry, <hi rend="i">nee</hi> Fort
                    Sackville, at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> were being torn down and carried off board by board even before the end of the
                    Revolutionary War, and now it is proving difficult to locate the exact position of the fort itself.
                    At the important Indian trading post of Ouiatenon it has taken strenuous archaeological research to
                    establish where it was on the <geogName>Wabash River</geogName> below <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Lafayette</settlement>
                    </placeName>. <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kaskaskia</settlement>
                    </placeName> and its "elegant stone fort"<hi rend="sup">3</hi> have vanished under
                    the changing currents of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName>. Dams and reservoirs have changed the landscape and the contours of rivers.
                    Clark's little base for his attack on <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kaskaskia</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Corn Island in the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Louisville</settlement>
                    </placeName>, was gradually eroded by the river and finally chewed up entirely in the hoppers of the
                    cement plants nearby. The list could be multiplied.</p>
            <p>This address will concentrate on only a few of the problems in recreating a more accurate and
                    meaningful understanding of Clark's part in the War for American Independence. The answers,
                    as far as they are available, are in the original documents, but it is no easy task to dig them out
                    or assess their meaning. One hopes that the craft of the historian may correct some of the many
                    misconceptions foisted on us by those who depended too much on the accounts of aging contemporaries
                    or family tradition, by those whose verbosity or lack of clarity clouded the story, or by writers
                    who have been carried away by romanticizing and their own literary flourishes. The celebration of
                    the bicentennial of the Revolution over the next few years may forward the job. Indiana and its
                    surrounding states deserve to know what happened in this area during the Revolution and what the
                    area's meaning was for the larger struggle.</p>
            <p>A major problem has been that most of us lack a grasp of the order of events, perhaps because the
                    Revolutionary struggle was the longest war we have ever fought, with the <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">3</hi> George Rogers Clark probably to Governor Patrick Henry of <placeName>
                                <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                            </placeName>, summer or fall, 1777, in James, <hi rend="i">George Rogers Clark Papers,
                                1771–2781,</hi> VIII, 30.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="4" id="VAA4025-072-1-010"/>
                    <figure>
                  <p>Courtesy George M. Waller.</p>
               </figure>
                    <pb n="5" id="VAA4025-072-1-011"/> exception of the recent affair in <placeName>
                        <country reg="-vm">Vietnam</country>
                    </placeName>. It went on for eight tedious, desperate years. Happenings have been confused with
                    other happenings, time sequences have been ignored, misconceptions abound. You are in good company
                    if George Rogers Clark means nothing at all to you. Many people confuse Clark with his youngest
                    brother, William, the Clark in the Lewis and Clark Expedition that explored the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="lau">Louisiana</region>
                    </placeName> Purchase area in 1804–1806. Almost everybody who knows something of the
                    Clark story knows mainly of the famous march on <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> in early 1779, an epic of endurance and daring. For the rest of the war in the West and
                    Clark's part in it even many historians are confused. To start with, a very brief sketch of
                    the order of events may help.</p>
            <p>In late 1776 Indians began to attack across the <geogName>Ohio River</geogName> into <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName>. Clark was instrumental in convincing the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> government, which claimed the area, to organize <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> as a county, and he became commander of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> militia with the rank of major. When the British officially unleashed the Indians
                    against Americans on the frontier in 1777, Clark directed the defense of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> stations from the little fort at Harrodsburg.</p>
            <p>Early in 1778 Clark went to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Williamsburg</settlement>
                    </placeName>, the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> capital, where he received secret instructions from Governor Patrick Henry and the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> Council to carry out his plans for an offensive against the British posts beyond the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName>. His primary objective was <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kaskaskia</settlement>
                    </placeName> on the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName>, though he was also dreaming of an attack on the major British western post, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Detroit</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Then just twenty-five years old, he was promoted to lieutenant colonel. He secured the
                    surrender of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kaskaskia</settlement>
                    </placeName> and other French inhabited villages on the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName>, and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> on the <geogName>Wabash River</geogName>, by the end of 1778.</p>
            <p>
               <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName>—also primarily inhabited by French settlers— had acceded to the
                    Americans readily when called upon by a visiting delegation of Frenchmen sent by Clark from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kaskaskia</settlement>
                    </placeName>. But Henry Hamilton, lieutenant governor of the District of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Detroit</settlement>
                    </placeName> and the British commander in the West, had marched to retake <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> when he heard of Clark's exploits in the <placeName>
                        <country>Illinois Country</country>
                    </placeName>. <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Hamilton</settlement>
                    </placeName> succeeded in regaining control of the post late in 1778. In February, 1779, Clark
                    recaptured <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> after his legendary march <pb n="[6]" id="VAA4025-072-1-012"/>
                    <figure>
                  <p>T<hi rend="sc">HOMAS</hi> H<hi rend="sc">UTCHINS</hi>' S<hi rend="sc">KETCH OF
                            THE</hi> F<hi rend="sc">ALLS OF THE</hi> O<hi rend="sc">HIO</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Corn Island, where George Rogers Clark established his base before advancing to the <placeName>
                                <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                            </placeName>, is the island in the lower center right, near the southern shore of the
                                <geogName>Ohio River</geogName>.</p>
                  <p rend="right">Reproduced from Thomas Hutchins, <hi rend="i">A Topographical Description of
                                        <placeName>
                           <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>, <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>, <region type="state" reg="mdu">Maryland</region>
                        </placeName>, and <placeName>
                                    <country reg="ncu">North Carolina</country>
                                </placeName>
                     </hi> (<placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">London</settlement>
                            </placeName>, 1778).</p>
               </figure>
                    <pb n="[7]" id="VAA4025-072-1-013"/>
                    <figure>
                  <p>T<hi rend="sc">HOMAS</hi> H<hi rend="sc">UTCHINS</hi>' P<hi rend="sc">LAN OF
                            THE</hi> F<hi rend="sc">RENCH</hi> V<hi rend="sc">ILLAGES ALONG THE</hi> M<hi rend="sc">ISSISSIPPI</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The "old fort" on the bluffs east of the village of <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Kaskaskia</settlement>
                            </placeName> was not used during the American Revolution. The fort Clark captured in <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Kaskaskia</settlement>
                            </placeName> was in the southeast corner of the village.</p>
                  <p rend="right">Reproduced from Thomas Hutching, <hi rend="i">A Topographical Description of
                                        <placeName>
                           <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>, <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>, <region type="state" reg="mdu">Maryland</region>
                        </placeName>, and <placeName>
                                    <country reg="ncu">North Carolina</country>
                                </placeName>,</hi> (<placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">London</settlement>
                            </placeName>, 1778),</p>
               </figure>
                    <pb n="8" id="VAA4025-072-1-014"/> through flooded country between the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName> and the <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wabash</region>
                    </placeName>, catching the British commander before <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Hamilton</settlement>
                    </placeName> could mass his forces for a spring attack on Clark. Clark's capture of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Hamilton</settlement>
                    </placeName> dealt a massive though temporary blow to the British-Indian alliances. It should be
                    noted that Clark remained at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> only a month, returning for another month in July when he tried unsuccessfully to
                    organize a follow, up expedition against <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Detroit</settlement>
                    </placeName>. He did not return to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> again until some years after the end of the war, although the town, along with the
                    other French towns in the <placeName>
                        <country>Illinois Country</country>
                    </placeName>, remained nominally under American control though much neglected for the rest of the
                    war.</p>
            <p>After 1779 American hopes for an early end to the war faded. The war in the West was stalemated. In
                    1780 Clark supervised the building of a new fort, Fort Jefferson, at the mouth of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName>. During the summer he rushed north from Fort Jefferson to assist in the defense of
                    Cahokia, attacked— along with <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">St. Louis</settlement>
                    </placeName>—by a motley group of Indians and British traders from Mackinac. Barely back
                    at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Fort Jefferson</settlement>
                    </placeName>, he again hurried north, overland with two companions, in time to divert a massive
                    attack in June, 1780, led by Captain Henry Bird from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Detroit</settlement>
                    </placeName> against his post at the Falls of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> but too late to save the defenseless <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> stations, Martin's and Ruddle's on the Licking River. In retaliation
                    he led an expedition against the Shawnee in the Miami River valley where he commanded American
                    forces in one of the few pitched battles with the Indians during the war, the Battle of Piqua,
                    killing many Indians, burning their towns and crops.</p>
            <p>In early 1781 Clark started to prepare a major expedition against <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Detroit</settlement>
                    </placeName> authorized by Governor Thomas Jefferson of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName>. In view of the British invasion of eastern <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> it seems a visionary plan. In fact, Clark himself was temporarily pressed into service
                    with the regular army in the fighting around <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName> where he gave a good account of himself. Traveling back to recruit his forces for the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Detroit</settlement>
                    </placeName> attack, Clark carried a new commission from <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> as brigadier general in order to make him senior to the Continental commander, Colonel
                    Daniel Brodhead, at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Fort Pitt</settlement>
                    </placeName>, a man intensely jealous of Clark. The expedition failed. Brodhead's thinly
                    veiled opposition and a high rate of desertion among Clark's troops culminated in the
                    overwhelming <pb n="9" id="VAA4025-072-1-015"/> defeat of Colonel Archibald Lochry, a <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>
                    </placeName> militia commander who was bringing a detachment down the <geogName>Ohio
                    River</geogName> to join Clark. Indians massing to attack Clark fell upon Lochry's small
                    force in southeastern Indiana near the mouth of the Miami River with devastating effect.</p>
            <p>Clark remained at the newly completed Fort Nelson at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Louisville</settlement>
                    </placeName> until the fall of 1782 when he led a last foray against the Shawnee towns across the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> but found no Indians to fight. With the war ending, he returned to
                            <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
               </placeName>, and accepted retirement in the spring of 1783.</p>
            <p>This short sketch omits any mention of the ongoing defense of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> stations, of the futile efforts of successive commanders at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Fort Pitt</settlement>
                    </placeName> to take the offensive against the Indians west and north of the upper <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName>, of allied French and Spanish forces in thrusts against <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Fort St. Joseph</region>
                    </placeName> east of the lower end of <geogName>Lake Michigan</geogName> and Miamistown at the head
                    of the Maumee, and of many other movements in the war in the West. But moving in for a closer look,
                    one finds many problems.</p>
            <p>For instance, what was Clark like? He was tall and well built. He was acknowledged to be a superb
                    leader. Contemporaries are lavish in praising his qualities, but we find no references to his
                    personality and character except what we can infer from his writing or his actions. No contemporary
                    portrait of him exists. One painted from life in his later years shows an embittered old man, his
                    face twisted perhaps in pain. His wartime exertions had a telling effect on his health, his
                    disappointments and lack of rewards on his mind. His excessive drinking right after the war
                    occasioned troubled comment from even his good friends, Thomas Jefferson and James Madison. It had
                    probably set in during the tedious months spent in enforced idleness at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Fort Nelson</settlement>
                    </placeName> toward the end of the war when severe shortages of supplies, money, and men prevented
                    further campaigning. It doubtless further hurt his health.</p>
            <p>Some say Clark was redheaded. No real evidence exists. Do we visualize him with long hair or short?
                    Did he wear a wig? Did he fight in buckskin or in uniform? Did he wear a tricorne or a broadbrimmed
                    hat? Someone even asked recently if he needed dentures, like George Washington. Portraits dating
                    from after Clark's death obviously idealize his image and portray a dignified, retired
                    officer, respected <pb n="[10]" id="VAA4025-072-1-016"/>
                    <figure>
                  <p>Thomas Hutchins, <hi rend="i">A New Map of the Western Parts of <placeName>
                           <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>, <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>, <region type="state" reg="mdu">Maryland</region>
                        </placeName>, and <placeName>
                                    <country reg="ncu">North Carolina</country>
                                </placeName>
                     </hi> … (<placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">London</settlement>
                            </placeName>, 1778).</p>
               </figure>
                    <pb n="[11]" id="VAA4025-072-1-017"/>
                    <figure>
                  <p rend="right">Reproduced from Thomas Hutchins, <hi rend="i">A Topographical Description of
                                        <placeName>
                           <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>, <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>, <region type="state" reg="mdu">Maryland</region>
                        </placeName>, and <placeName>
                                    <country reg="ncu">North Carolina</country>
                                </placeName>
                     </hi> (<placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">London</settlement>
                            </placeName>, 1778)</p>
               </figure>
                    <pb n="12" id="VAA4025-072-1-018"/> as he actually was after the controversies that swirled around
                    him in the immediate postwar period died down.</p>
            <p>A more important question, which I have never found discussed, is how did he find his way in the
                    West? Where did his knowledge of its geography, its people, its Indians, its distances come from?
                    How did he come by the information that enabled him to assess the value of his targets? Some things
                    we know. In the years before the Revolution, Clark worked with a number of other surveyors, ranging
                    widely through <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> and well down the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName>, familiarizing himself with the eastern and southern side of the river from the age of
                    nineteen. In the spring of 1777 before his march on <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kaskaskia</settlement>
                    </placeName> he had sent Benjamin Linn and Samuel Moore to spy on the place but what led him to do
                    that? In marching overland from near the mouth of the <geogName>Tennessee River</geogName> to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kaskaskia</settlement>
                    </placeName> he availed himself of a guide, John Saunders, an American hunter who had been there.
                    Further, as a surveyor, Clark knew how to lay out a straight line of march from one point to
                    another.</p>
            <p>But to know where the distant point toward which he marched was suggests the use of maps. Here, a
                    figure enters the picture who has not previously been associated with the story of George Rogers
                    Clark. His possible connection would appear to be a matter of interest. He is Thomas Hutchins, born
                    in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="nju">New Jersey</region>
                    </placeName> in 1730, twenty-two years Clark's senior. Holding a commission as a British
                    army engineer, Hutchins fought in the French and Indian War and helped suppress Pontiac's
                    Rebellion. He was stationed at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Fort Pitt</settlement>
                    </placeName>, indeed probably helped to design the fort. He traveled widely in the Great Lakes
                    region and down the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName>, mapping and sketching the area. He served in the garrisons at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Fort Chartres</settlement>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kaskaskia</settlement>
                    </placeName> until 1772 when he was sent down the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName> to help with the building of British defenses in <placeName>
                        <region type="state">West Florida</region>
                    </placeName>.<hi rend="sup">4</hi>
            </p>
            <list type="footnotes">
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">4</hi> Biographical material about Hutchins may be found in Dumas Malone, ed.,
                            <hi rend="i">Dictionary of American Biography</hi> (20 vols., <placeName>
                            <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                        </placeName>, 1943), IX, 435–36; Thomas Hutchins, <hi rend="i">A Topographical
                            Description of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>, <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>, <region type="state" reg="mdu">Maryland</region>
                     </placeName>, and <placeName>
                                <country reg="ncu">North Carolina</country>
                            </placeName>,</hi> reprinted from 1778 edition, ed. and intro. by Frederick Charles Hicks (<placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Cleveland</settlement>
                        </placeName>, 1904); Thomas Hutchins, <hi rend="i">The Courses of the <geogName>Ohio
                            River</geogName>
                  </hi> …, ed. Beverly W. Bond, Jr. (<hi rend="i">Publications of
                            the Historical and Philosophical Society of <placeName>
                                <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                            </placeName>,</hi> 1942; <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                        </placeName>, 1942). Hutchins' manuscript is located in the <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Huntington</settlement>
                        </placeName> Library, <placeName>
                     <country reg="sm">San Marino</country>, <region type="state" reg="cau">California</region>
                  </placeName>; the map is in the Library of Congress, <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                        </placeName>, D. C.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="13" id="VAA4025-072-1-019"/>
            <p>It may be that Hutchins should be called Mapmaker of the American Revolution in the West. His
                    masterpiece, however, was published in 1778 and was thus not available to Clark when the campaign in
                    the <placeName>
                        <country>Illinois Country</country>
                    </placeName> took place.<hi rend="sup">5</hi> Hutchins had gone to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">London</settlement>
                    </placeName> to discuss plans for fortifications in <placeName>
                        <region type="state">West Florida</region>
                    </placeName> as well as to arrange for publication of his book and accompanying map providing a
                    "Topographical Description" of the West. He refused to return to fight against the
                    Americans, was imprisoned in <placeName>
                        <country reg="enk">England</country>
                    </placeName>, and after his release returned to America with assistance from Benjamin Franklin in <placeName>
                        <country reg="fr">France</country>
                    </placeName>. He became geographer for the Continental southern army under General Nathanael Greene
                    and then, after the war, geographer of the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>, a title never since conferred on anyone.</p>
            <p>Hutchins supervised the survey extending the Mason and Dixon Line, established the boundary between <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mau">Massachusetts</region>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                    </placeName>, and, finally, undertook the great work of laying out ranges, base lines, and other
                    surveys west of the <geogName>Ohio River</geogName> in accordance with the Land Ordinance of 1785.
                    While engaged in this work he died in 1789. He had been a man "of good character, of polite
                    manners, of great integrity, who made a regular profession of religion,"<hi rend="sup">6</hi> and of him his eulogist said: "He has measured much earth, but a small space now
                    contains him."<hi rend="sup">7</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hutchins' maps are remarkable for their period. He drew on prior French knowledge of the
                    country, and he had been associated with another British army engineer, then Lieutenant Philip
                    Pittman, while in service at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Fort Chartres</settlement>
                    </placeName> near <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kaskaskia</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Pittman had traveled from <placeName>
                        <region type="state">West Florida</region>
                    </placeName> to the <placeName>
                        <country>Illinois Country</country>
                    </placeName> charting the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName> as he went.<hi rend="sup">8</hi> Hutchins had worked with Captain Harry Gordon, whose
                    elaborate map of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> from Fort Pitt to the mouth of the river was probably based on Hutchins'
                    surveys and sketches.<hi rend="sup">9</hi>
            </p>
            <list type="footnotes">
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">5</hi> Hutchins, <hi rend="i">Topographical Description.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">6</hi> Hazard to Jeremy Belknap, July 13, 1789, quoted in Hicks'
                        introduction to 1904 edition of Hutchins' <hi rend="i">Topographical Description,</hi>
                        7.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">7</hi> Quoted in <hi rend="i">ibid.,</hi> 49.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">8</hi> Captain Philip Pittman, <hi rend="i">The Present State of the European
                            Settlements on the Missisippi [sic]</hi> …, reprinted from 1770 edition, ed.
                        Frank Heywood Hodder (<placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Cleveland</settlement>
                        </placeName>, 1906); Max Savelle, <hi rend="i">George Morgan, Colony Builder</hi> (<placeName>
                            <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                        </placeName>, 1932).</item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">9</hi> Gordon's map is located in the Library of Congress</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="[14]" id="VAA4025-072-1-020"/>
            <figure>
               <p>T<hi rend="sc">HOMAS</hi> H<hi rend="sc">UTCHINS</hi>' M<hi rend="sc">AP</hi> OF
                        "A T<hi rend="sc">OUR</hi> F<hi rend="sc">ROM</hi> F<hi rend="sc">ORT</hi> C<hi rend="sc">UMBERLAN</hi>D …"</p>
            </figure>
            <pb n="[15]" id="VAA4025-072-1-021"/>
            <figure>
               <p rend="right">Courtesy <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Huntington</settlement>
                        </placeName> Library, <placeName>
                     <country reg="sm">San Marino</country>, <region type="state" reg="cau">California</region>
                  </placeName>.</p>
            </figure>
            <pb n="16" id="VAA4025-072-1-022"/>
            <p>The connection with George Rogers Clark, it may be speculated, was through George Morgan. Hutchins
                    had become a close friend of Morgan when both were active at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Fort Chartres</settlement>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kaskaskia</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Morgan, a partner in the prestigio–s <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Philadelphia</settlement>
                    </placeName> trading firm of Baynton, Wharton, and Morgan, supervised a massive trading operation on
                    the <geogName>Mississippi</geogName> and <geogName>Wabash rivers</geogName>, at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kaskaskia</settlement>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName>, in the years before the Revolution. He had traveled west with Hutchins, and their
                    association continued lifelong.<hi rend="sup">10</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When Clark was in the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Pittsburgh</settlement>
                    </placeName> area gathering supplies for his campaign to the <placeName>
                        <country>Illinois Country</country>
                    </placeName>, Morgan was prominent there as agent for the Indian Commission of the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> Congress, engaged in prolonged negotiations with the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="deu">Delaware</region>
                    </placeName> and other tribes in an attempt to keep them from forming an attachment to the British.
                    Hutchins may well have left a great many sketches and drawings with Morgan when he went to <placeName>
                        <country reg="enk">England</country>
                    </placeName>. In addition, Morgan as well as Hutchins had extensive knowledge of the country from
                    former association with the old trader, George Croghan, who knew the area and the Indians better
                    than any man.</p>
            <p>It may be objected that Clark's project, closely tied to <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName>'s hope to claim the regions of the West in the future, would not recommend
                    itself to Morgan, who represented rival <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>
                    </placeName> interests. Therefore Morgan might not be inclined to share his knowledge with Clark.
                    But in 1778, in the early stages of the war in the West, the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName>-<placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>
                    </placeName> rivalry which frustrated so many plans for offensives later in the war was still
                    subordinated to the overriding concern of both factions to hold the West against the British.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, additional connections exist between <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kaskaskia</settlement>
                    </placeName> traders, Americans in the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Pittsburgh</settlement>
                    </placeName> area, and Clark. Two men who remained in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kaskaskia</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Thomas Bentley and Daniel Murray, held strong leanings toward the Americans and had
                    many friends in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Pittsburgh</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Lieutenant William Linn received help from these <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kaskaskia</settlement>
                    </placeName> men when he brought a supply of powder up from <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New Orleans</settlement>
                    </placeName> for the American armies, the powder later provided for Clark's expedition.
                    Linn's brother, Benjamin, had been one of Clark's spies sent to reconnoiter <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kaskaskia</settlement>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName>, probably because <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">10</hi> Savelle, <hi rend="i">George Morgan.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="17" id="VAA4025-072-1-023"/> he had been there before. It was a mission very likely suggested
                    to Clark by Bentley, through friends. Both Linns served under Clark subsequently. Two of
                    Clark's other officers, Joseph Bowman and William Harrod, frequented the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Pittsburgh</settlement>
                    </placeName> area and had extensive contacts there. A friend of Hutchins at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kaskaskia</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Patrick Kennedy, became Clark's commissary on the famous march to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> and remained there as quartermaster for Clark's garrison.</p>
            <p>Within this complex of personal connections the exchange of information seems most likely,
                    information that may have enabled Clark to confirm and pin down more definitely his own vast
                    knowledge acquired in years on the frontier. Hutchins' map becomes a kind of historic
                    landmark, with its many comments on the nature of the country written across areas portrayed, his
                    precise marking of streams, mountains, prairies, and trails. Its preserves the features of the
                    country known to Clark and other armies that campaigned there, features now lost through natural and
                    manmade changes.</p>
            <p>Notice should be drawn to other problems that arise in attempting to understand this small scale but
                    complex western struggle. Though a dominant figure in this theater of the war, Clark was not the
                    only important American leader, nor were the valiant men who followed him the only ones to fight. In
                    the area between the Great Lakes, the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName>, and the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName>, America was fighting on four frontiers.</p>
            <p>On the upper <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> an impoverished garrison of regulars at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Fort Pitt</settlement>
                    </placeName> was commanded by a succession of officers appointed by General Washington at the
                    direction of Congress. From this post control was extended to garrisons at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Fort Henry</settlement>
                    </placeName> (<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Wheeling</settlement>
                    </placeName>), <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Fort Randolph</settlement>
                    </placeName> (at the mouth of the Kanawha River), Fort McIntosh (at the mouth of Beaver Creek), and
                    Fort Laurens (on the Tuscaroras River), as well as small forts north of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Pittsburgh</settlement>
                    </placeName> on the Allegheny.</p>
            <p>A second, inner frontier at the western edge of the Appalachians stretched along the upper Kanawha,
                    the Greenbrier, and the New rivers. The settlements on the Holston, Watauga, Nolichucky, and upper
                        <geogName>Tennessee rivers</geogName> made up a third frontier in the southwestern corner of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> and western <placeName>
                        <country reg="ncu">North Carolina</country>
                    </placeName>, which extended west in 1780 to the Cumberland settlements around what is now
                            <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Nashville</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="tnu">Tennessee</region>
               </placeName>. Clark was prominent in defending the fourth frontier, the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> stations and their western prolongations <pb n="18" id="VAA4025-072-1-024"/> at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Fort Jefferson</settlement>
                    </placeName> just below the mouth of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> and in the <placeName>
                        <country>Illinois Country</country>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName>.</p>
            <p>In this area the war was mainly an Indian war. Well before the Revolution the Indians were resisting
                    the aggressive, land hungry frontiersmen. Indians had learned to live with the fur traders, indeed
                    coveted trade, first with the French and then with the British. But the arrival of pioneers who
                    felled the forests, planted trees, and built cabins alarmed them and provoked resistance. During the
                    war the struggle merely took on added seriousness insofar as the Indians were supplied and often led
                    by the British.</p>
            <p>On the upper <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="deu">Delaware</region>
                    </placeName> remained peacefully inclined for several years, influenced by Moravian missionaries and
                    the diplomatic skills of George Morgan at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Fort Pitt</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Attacks across the upper <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> and against the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> stations even through the Year of the Three Sevens—the Bloody Year of
                    1777—came mainly from small, roving bands of Mingo (western Seneca), Munsee, and a few
                    renegade <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="deu">Delaware</region>
                    </placeName> and Shawnee. The Shawnee became the principal scourge of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> only in 1778. By the spring of 1777 the Cherokee had been subdued along the Holston
                    frontier. Except for occasional trouble from the irreconcilable Chickamauga offshoot under Chief
                    Dragging Canoe, this tribe made little more trouble. Clark fought no Indians in his <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ilu">Illinois</region>
                    </placeName> campaign and encountered Indians willing to fight only in the first of his two raids
                    into Shawnee country in 1780. On the <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wabash</region>
                    </placeName> and Maumee rivers, the Miami, Wea, Piankeshaw, and Kickapoo wavered between the British
                    and the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> throughout the war, did little fighting, and were cowed by Clark most of the time. One
                    Piankeshaw chief, indeed, professed enduring support of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> Big Knives. Remnants of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ilu">Illinois</region>
                    </placeName> tribe, few, lazy, and debauched, the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kaskaskia</settlement>
                    </placeName> and Michigami Indians, did not fight.</p>
            <p>Large numbers of the British Indians in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="miu">Michigan</region>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <country reg="-cn">Canada</country>
                    </placeName>—<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Ottawa</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Chippewa, Wyandot, Potawatomi, and Huron—joined in attacks on the upper <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> and in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> only in relatively small bands. A few hundred were the most who took part in any siege
                    or battle out of the thousands presumably controlled by the British. It may be said that offensively
                    the Indians were no real asset to the British, although, paradoxically, it would have been fatal to
                    the <pb n="19" id="VAA4025-072-1-025"/> British cause in the West if the Indians had not given as
                    much help as they did. Under guerrilla leaders like William Caldwell; Alexander McKee; the Girty
                    brothers, Simon, James, and George; and Captain Henry Bird of the regular British army, along with
                    occasional French Canadian officers, the warriors would attack undefended cabins and weakly held
                    forts. They were too restless to maintain a long siege. The nine days' siege of
                    Boonesborough was the longest. They never attacked a position where Clark was known to be present
                    and rarely risked a pitched battle. The leaders were too few to control them, and renegades like
                    Simon Girty had no inclination to do so. Cruel treatment of their victims, especially the old, the
                    wounded, and women and children was typical.</p>
            <p>Yet in negotiations with Clark and his officers, or with Morgan at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Fort Pitt</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indian leaders were reasonable, often good humored, and indicated a fair appreciation
                    of America's side of the war. It may be suggested that even fewer would have fought for the
                    British if frontiersmen had not frequently descended to their level and perpetrated equally
                    monstrous atrocities on them. The wanton murders of the friendly Shawnee, Chief Cornstalk, and of
                    White Eyes, who had labored earnestly to keep his <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="deu">Delaware</region>
                    </placeName> friendly, are only two instances.</p>
            <p>The British and their Indian allies were not the only enemies of the American frontiersmen. The men
                    of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> were fighting in the West against rival <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>
                    </placeName> interests for future possession of the land. Clark's march to the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName> and the visionary scheme of a massive <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> mounted attack on <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Detroit</settlement>
                    </placeName> in 1781 may have originated as much with leading <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> land speculators as with Clark. Firm evidence is lacking, but Clark's
                    preliminary discussions with Governor Patrick Henry in 1776 may have led the young westerner to
                    conceive his plan. Historians have questioned his choice of targets. They make sense if he was
                    acting to forestall <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>
                    </placeName> more than to counter the British, though his proposals would effectively serve both
                    purposes. It is clear, too, that personal interest in western lands as well as official concern for <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName>'s claims were combined in the persons of Patrick Henry, George Mason, George
                    Washington, and many other less prominent individuals, and seem to have preoccupied an inordinate
                    amount of their thinking despite their heavy official duties.</p>
            <pb n="20" id="VAA4025-072-1-026"/>
            <p>The militia of states like <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>
                    </placeName> were also constantly pitted against the regular army establishment in the western
                    theater of the war. The long time commander at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Fort Pitt</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Colonel Daniel Brodhead, proved a bitter and frustrated enemy of Clark. Opponents of
                    both the regulars and the dedicated frontier militiamen were an increasing population on the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName>, in the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> stations, and in older parts of the back country. Such opponents included unpatriotic
                    land seekers, growing numbers of Tories fleeing from eastern hostility, and an influential body of
                    separate state men who denied the claims of any eastern state to the area. Opposition arose, too,
                    between those who favored a defensive war and those, like Clark, who wanted to take the war to the
                    enemy.</p>
            <p>Personal rivalry to Clark became evident in the disagreement raised by beleaguered <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> defenders facing Indian attack from across the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> at a point midway between the last fort on the upper <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> and Clark's forces concentrated at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Louisville</settlement>
                    </placeName>. The Warriors' Path crossed near the mouth of the Licking River, a crossing
                    too far from Clark at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Fort Nelson</settlement>
                    </placeName> to be detected.</p>
            <p>Preoccupation with these and many other problems doomed any chance for consistent military effort.
                    The war became a wearying, irresolute seesaw of guerrilla tactics. The Indians were masters of such
                    tactics. Clark was successful when he was able to move swiftly with small forces against
                    unsuspecting targets, when—not by choice but necessity—he had to emulate the
                    Indians and gained their same advantages. Large scale campaigns, whether mounted by the British, the
                    regulars from Fort Pitt, or attempted by Clark, always failed. Major offensives were a logistical
                    impossibility. Equipping, feeding, and transporting large numbers of men, with supplies or
                    artillery, over long distances through difficult terrain proved beyond the means of either side.</p>
            <p>Yet in a long war when unity of purpose characterized none of the thirteen states, western Americans
                    at least held their ground, pinned down large numbers of the British and their Indians so that they
                    could not be used against the eastern areas, and gave the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> a claim on the West that American negotiators could fight for at the peace table.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="[21]" id="VAA4025-072-1-027"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-072-1-a02">
            <head>"Down in the Hills o' <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Brown County</region>
                    </placeName>": Photographs by Frank M. Hohenberger</head>
            <byline>Lorna Lutes Sylvester<hi rend="sup">∗</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>It was cold and snowy in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Brown County</region>
                    </placeName>, Indiana, during the winter of 1917–1918. The temperature was frequently
                    below zero,<hi rend="sup">1</hi> and on his field trips through the county photographer Frank M.
                    Hohenberger sometimes struggled with eighteen inches of snow under a heavy crust. "Walking
                    was an arduous task," he wrote in his diary. "Crust not tough enough to support my
                    weight and every step I had to nearly pull out one foot before I could progress with the
                    other." He added enigmatically: "Crust as strong as that on the pies mother used
                    to make."<hi rend="sup">2</hi> Another photographic expedition Hohenberger described both
                    graphically and philosophically: "Walking on the snow was an illustration of one's
                    uncertainty in this world. You would strike a nice patch and walk on top —first thing you
                    knew, down into it. Out again, one or two steps, down. Get discouraged but just then another fine
                    territory. If anyone saw me they'd have thought I was crazy, but these pictures are not
                    with us every day."<hi rend="sup">3</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hohenberger was a newcomer to <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Brown County</region>
                    </placeName> in 1917, so it must have been the native residents who told him that <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">∗</hi> Lorna Lutes Sylvester, associate editor of the <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of History,</hi> was born in <placeName>
                                <region type="county">Brown County</region>
                            </placeName>, Indiana, and has since resided in it or neighboring counties. Especial thanks
                            are extended to the staffs of the Lilly Library and Indiana University Publications, Indiana
                            University, <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Bloomington</settlement>
                            </placeName>, and to Miss Pamela J. Bennett, Indiana Historical Bureau, for their help in
                            the preparation of this article, which is the second in a series about Frank M. Hohenberger
                            and his photographs. For the preceding article see Lorna Lutes Sylvester,
                            "‘Down in the Hills o' <placeName>
                                <region type="county">Brown County</region>
                            </placeName>’: Photographs by Frank M. Hohenberger," <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of History,</hi> LXXI (September, 1975), 205–44.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">1</hi> Frank M. Hohenberger diary, [18], [20], Hohenberger Collection
                            (Lilly Library, Indiana University, <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Bloomington</settlement>
                            </placeName>).</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">2</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid.,</hi> [17].</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">3</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid.,</hi> [18].</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="22" id="VAA4025-072-1-028"/> this was the first winter of its kind in many years in the
                    county. He stayed on into the spring to see the snow melt "like hot rolls with Jersey cream
                        butter,"<hi rend="sup">4</hi> and for most of the next forty-five years he photographed
                    the southern Indiana hills during all seasons and in all kinds of weather. "Truly weatherly
                    speaking," he wrote, "one who can live in Indiana can exist anywhere. Variety the
                    spice of life. Now the sunshine brightens your hopes, then it is shielded by a cloud and the
                    hurrying bits of clouds parade before you and you forget about the mud around you."<hi rend="sup">5</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Trained from youth in the printer's trade, Hohenberger had worked in many print shops
                    throughout the Midwest before he came to <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Brown County</region>
                    </placeName>. When he lost his job as a makeup man on an <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> newspaper around 1916, he began a new career as manager of a camera shop in the Hoosier
                    capital. From there, snapshots which someone had taken in the rustic southern Indiana county lured
                    him to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Nashville</settlement>
                    </placeName>, the <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Brown county</region>
                    </placeName> seat.<hi rend="sup">6</hi> It proved a propitious move. He photographed his new
                    neighbors, trying to get the "character which stood out in the faces of these people
                    … onto a photographic plate,"<hi rend="sup">7</hi> and he began to record on
                    film the rusticity and beauty of his new home. He snapped birds, trees, clouds, creeks, roads, snow
                    scenes, spring blossoms, autumn leaves—everything from the "majesty" of
                    panoramic views to the "seemingly insignificant objects" which he found
                    "so attractive."<hi rend="sup">8</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In 1933 Hohenberger told a reporter that he had sold his first photographs to tourists who saw them
                    displayed in a <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Nashville</settlement>
                    </placeName> shop window. A short time later the rotogravure editor of an <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> newspaper purchased a "batch" of prints, and Hohenberger, as the
                    reporter put it, "was started."<hi rend="sup">9</hi> By 1920 some of his pictures
                    were selling for as much as twenty-five dollars each, and he was mailing them throughout <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">4</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid.,</hi> [20], [21].</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">5</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid.,</hi> [24].</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">6</hi> Webb Waldron, "He Quit His Job; Took a
                            Train—," <hi rend="i">American Magazine,</hi> CXVI (October, 1933), 104;
                            Hohenberger diary, [66], Hohenberger Collection; <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                            </placeName>
                            <hi rend="i">Star,</hi> January 6, 1957, sect. 2, p. 1; <hi rend="i">ibid.,</hi> November
                            16, 1963, p. 1.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">7</hi> Waldron, "He Quit His Job; Took a Train," 104.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">8</hi> Hohenberger diary, [22], Hohenberger Collection.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">9</hi> Waldron, "He Quit His Job; Took a Train,"
                            104–105.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="23" id="VAA4025-072-1-029"/>
                    <figure>
                  <p>F<hi rend="sc">RANK</hi> M. H<hi rend="sc">OHENBERGER</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
                    <pb n="24" id="VAA4025-072-1-030"/> the world.<hi rend="sup">10</hi> By the time of the Great
                    Depression Hohenberger was sometimes making as much as five thousand dollars a year, most of which
                    he plowed back into photographic equipment and materials. According to the reporter, his financial
                    security lay in the thousands of negatives which he had accumulated and which could be used again
                    and again. They were "as steady a source of income as money put out at
                        interest."<hi rend="sup">11</hi> Hohenberger's photographs appeared in <hi rend="i">Good Housekeeping, Farm and Fireside, Farm Journal,</hi> the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Star.</hi> Authors used them to illustrate their books, they served as guides for
                    artists in their painting, and people frequently sent the "picture man" bits of
                    verse which they hoped he could match with a photograph. He almost always could.<hi rend="sup">12</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Photography, however, was not Hohenberger's only interest. He only took it up in the first
                    place, he said, "for the reason that it took me outdoors." Later he saw its
                    possibilities and "gladly entertained the muse,"<hi rend="sup">13</hi> but he was
                    an avid naturalist and a concerned environmentalist many years before these became popular
                    avocations. As early as 1919 he exhorted groups and individuals to preserve the natural beauties of
                    southern Indiana. "Farmers cutting down the trees here quite rapidly," he
                    observed. "They look at the large area of shade that falls upon their crops, early in the
                    morning, or late in the evening, of course, and then began to figure how much grain could be raised
                    in that spot, and down goes the tree…. We are campaigning through the local papers to
                    stop this destruction. Also how to save the trees when a road is put in, culverts made,
                        etc."<hi rend="sup">14</hi> And in his less tolerant moments the photographer sometimes
                    quoted an artist friend who had stated that a great many of the trees in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Brown County</region>
                    </placeName> were "worth more than the owners themselves to the county."<hi rend="sup">15</hi>
            </p>
            <list type="footnotes">
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">10</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">Ibid.,</hi> 105; Hohenberger diary, [179], Hohenberger Collection. Acknowledging
                        receipt of a photograph of a sycamore that Hohenberger had sent him on order, a professor at <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Cambridge</settlement>
                        </placeName> University, <placeName>
                            <country reg="enk">England</country>
                        </placeName>, wrote: "It is the most magnificent picture of a tree I have ever
                        seen." Quoted in Waldron, "He Quit His Job; Took a Train,"
                        105–106.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">11</hi> Waldron, "He Quit His Job; Took a Train," 106.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">12</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">Ibid.,</hi> 106; Hohenberger diary, [98], [99], [103], [110], [131], [243],
                        Hohenberger Collection.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">13</hi> Hohenberger diary, [47], Hohenberger Collection.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">14</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">Ibid.,</hi> [117].</item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">15</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">Ibid.,</hi> [12].</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="25" id="VAA4025-072-1-031"/>
            <p>Other kinds of progress, too, Hohenberger realized, could ruin the rustic beauty of the <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Brown County</region>
                    </placeName> he photographed. "When the telephone line and improved roadways encroach upon
                    a man's property, in a great many cases he is going to begin to polish up," he
                    reflected, "and away go the vine-covered rail fences and flowered by-paths. The clapboard
                    roof he has grown ashamed of and he covers the log cabin with an outer wall of native grown
                        timber."<hi rend="sup">16</hi> Hohenberger's pictures lured many people to
                    southern Indiana; progress came with them. In a sense, then, the photographer—through the
                    very excellence of his work—helped to destroy as well as to preserve the peaceful, old
                    fashioned flavor which so intrigued him in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Brown County</region>
                    </placeName>.</p>
            <p>Hohenberger's pictures were not always successes, of course, but "I never show my
                    failures," he wrote. "I make as many and possibly a great deal more errors than
                    other folks as I am continually at work with photography," he admitted. "When
                    disappointment looms up I just go at it again."<hi rend="sup">17</hi> Perhaps as much to
                    prevent future mistakes on his part as to provide suggestions for other photographers, Hohenberger
                    filled his diary with instructions for improving photographic technique. These hints ranged from
                    technical descriptions of which film, lens, filter, and camera were best under various conditions to
                    statements that vertical prints were "suitable for pictures intended to convey the sense of
                    life, vigor, gauntness …." Horizontal ones were "preferable for those
                    depicting spaciousness, peace, decay …,"<hi rend="sup">18</hi> In photography,
                    Hohenberger told one interviewer, "you've got to do everything
                    yourself—pressing the bulb, developing, printing. And you've got to put your
                    whole mind on it at every stage."<hi rend="sup">19</hi> He followed his own instructions
                    and proudly claimed that what he knew about photography had "been gained almost entirely
                    through experience. Not bookology."<hi rend="sup">20</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hohenberger also expressed very definite ideas concerning the proper method of viewing a photograph.
                    "Some folks' idea of examining a pictorial print is to figure out where the scene
                    is laid," he sighed.<hi rend="sup">21</hi> This he considered unimportant <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">16</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid.,</hi> [121].</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">17</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid.,</hi> [47].</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">18</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid.,</hi> [182]; see also <hi rend="i">ibid.,</hi> [148], [152], [174],
                            [190].</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">19</hi> Waldron, "He Quit His Job; Took a Train," 104.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">20</hi> Hohenberger diary, [117], Hohenberger Collection.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">21</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Ibid.,</hi> [147].</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="26" id="VAA4025-072-1-032"/> and as great a drawback as observing a picture from such close
                    range that "any opportunity for the work of art to breathe its poetry" was
                        prevented.<hi rend="sup">22</hi> And he recorded in his diary the philosophy with which any
                    collection of his work must be approached:</p>
            <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>In viewing a photograph the first thing some folks do is to search for detail, instead of viewing
                        the picture as a whole. And so we are with the problems of life; instead of picking here and
                        there, why not weigh the matter as a whole. This is giving fair play to the weaker parts. The
                        larger the print the farther away the observer should be. I'll admit that the greater
                        the distance between some of my work and your eyes the more satisfactory is the view. It rests
                        one's eyes to gaze into space.<hi rend="sup">23</hi>
               </p>
                </quote>
            <list type="footnotes">
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">22</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">Ibid.,</hi> [122].</item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">23</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">Ibid.,</hi> [116]. All photographs which have been used in this article are located
                        in the Hohenberger Collection in the Lilly Library, Indiana University, <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Bloomington</settlement>
                        </placeName>. No attempt was made to identify the exact scenes which Hohenberger pictured. All
                        quotations used with the photographs were selected from the Hohenberger diary because of their
                        interest or seeming relevance not because the location specified in the quotation described any
                        particular picture. None of Hohenberger's suggested captions have been used. Entries
                        from the Hohenberger diary have been standardized and typographical errors therein corrected in
                        order to make them more readable.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="[27]" id="VAA4025-072-1-033"/>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="28" id="VAA4025-072-1-034"/>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="29" id="VAA4025-072-1-035"/>
            <p>"It had been a sultry, sticky, threatening for rain day, and clouds tried to gather all
                    around for rain" [40].</p>
            <p>"About four o'clock this afternoon I slipped away from the Studio to get some cloud
                    studies for my spring negatives. Don't know what results I got, but as I only have to
                    journey about 1 1/2 squares to get more clouds it never worries me about what is on the
                    plates" [73].</p>
            <p>"The clouds are rapidly overlapping each other to form an almost opaque canopy. The western
                    sky assumes a blue-lead color. The old hen under the apple tree, now bearing tints of deep red, has
                    gathered her chicks. The light becomes so dim that I light my candle to finish washing
                    dishes" [79].</p>
            <p>"We are told that after the trials in life come the joys. When we view the beautiful cloud
                    formations after the storms we are reminded how true this is in art" [90].</p>
            <pb n="[30]" id="VAA4025-072-1-036"/>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="31" id="VAA4025-072-1-037"/>
            <figure/>
            <p>"About the only thing one thinks of when winter is mentioned is snow and very blizzardy
                    weather. Thousands of things to see that will drive away these shivering thoughts" [32].</p>
            <pb n="32" id="VAA4025-072-1-038"/>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="33" id="VAA4025-072-1-039"/>
            <figure/>
            <p>"Little ditches covered with lids of ice" [26].</p>
            <pb n="[34]" id="VAA4025-072-1-040"/>
            <figure/>
            <p>"<hi rend="i">BIRDS IN WINTER</hi>—After you pass out from the village a little
                    ways you see the nice, clean varieties. Seems like the scuffy sparrows form such a contrast. When
                    crust is on the snow the birds just jump from spot to spot. Some places their tracks look like they
                    had coasted. Saw blue jay Jan. 8/20 in snow at foot of Hopper apple tree. Couldn't tell
                    whether it was getting a ‘drink’ or picking for roots. Many redbirds and
                    flickers noticeable, also an occasional blackbird. Juncos indeed very tame" [14].</p>
            <pb n="[35]" id="VAA4025-072-1-041"/>
            <p>Of a field trip through the snow, Hohenberger wrote: "I wore the following: Winter underwear
                    and flannel shirt, khaki trousers, long woollen socks knitted by Mrs. Berry, also other pair of
                    cotton socks, rubber boots—Jersey Co., 6.7 U.S.A. on heel, and 7W in big red letters near
                    beginning of heel on sole.—pair of woollen gloves from Nelly, also my fleece-lined
                    mittens, Woollen cap, also woollen sweater…. I didn't think the trip was a cold
                    one" [142].</p>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="36" id="VAA4025-072-1-042"/>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="37" id="VAA4025-072-1-043"/>
            <figure/>
            <p>Above: "I had been wishing for a good old <placeName>
                        <country>New England</country>
                    </placeName> snow and here it is. When I arose this morning and raised the window shade the
                    sensation that ran over me is indescribable. Couldn't hardly believe my eyes. Everything
                    bearing a mantle of white …" [141].</p>
            <p>Left: "Bridge at Bessire's recalls with sadness how rapidly rustic things are
                    vanishing" [21].</p>
            <pb n="[38]" id="VAA4025-072-1-044"/>
            <figure/>
            <p>Was glad to see the snow come, and regretted to think of its going until I was all worn out. Then I
                    was glad to see the pictorial end. Nothing more exasperating can happen to you than to get your
                    boots full of water, which happened to me on Salt while trying to break the ice and move it on, so
                    that I might have a solid place for the tripod. While making the little place that had the rushiest
                    little stream near the big trees at McLary's ford, the leaping, laughing waters seemed to
                    say, ‘Hurry, it's getting late’ " [144].</p>
            <pb n="39" id="VAA4025-072-1-045"/>
            <p>"Everything planned nicely—flowers for us along the highways all the
                    time—one comes and the other goes" [46].</p>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="40" id="VAA4025-072-1-046"/>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="41" id="VAA4025-072-1-047"/>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="[42]" id="VAA4025-072-1-048"/>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="43" id="VAA4025-072-1-049"/>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="[44]" id="VAA4025-072-1-050"/>
            <figure/>
            <p>"I would suggest that where your Club sees a tree that is liable to be cut down that you
                    find out what the owner wishes for it, tell him your mission, and if he still is bent on destroying
                    it, offer him a price, own it and then put your name on it" [117].</p>
            <pb n="[45]" id="VAA4025-072-1-051"/>
            <figure/>
            <p>"Old tree with hollow center well elevated looked like one of those big German
                    guns" [29]. Dated March 2, 1918.</p>
            <pb n="46" id="VAA4025-072-1-052"/>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="47" id="VAA4025-072-1-053"/>
            <figure/>
            <p>‘Yes, it's quiet in the country, but if you don't like bird songs you
                    will change your mind. It's the bob white in the early hours and whippoorwill in the
                    earlier hours. Chipping sparrow gives a plaintive chirp and sounds very melancholy, yet I failed to
                    be convinced Sunday morning that I ought to get up’ [39].</p>
            <pb n="[48]" id="VAA4025-072-1-054"/>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="[49]" id="VAA4025-072-1-055"/>
            <figure/>
            <p>"A bird nest an interesting study—day after day intense interest
                    accrues" [46].</p>
            <pb n="50" id="VAA4025-072-1-056"/>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="51" id="VAA4025-072-1-057"/>
            <figure/>
            <p>"A regular paradise for birds. A fine place to meditate. Everything so quiet. The heat of
                    the day kept the cattle from lowing and not even a dog's voice to be heard" [108].</p>
            <pb n="52" id="VAA4025-072-1-058"/>
            <figure/>
            <p>"A lady from <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="flu">Florida</region>
                    </placeName> who has spent some time in <placeName>
                        <country reg="-cn">Canada</country>
                    </placeName> where they have perfectly straight roads remarked that a snake would break its back
                    traveling over our winding thoroughfares. I told her that if we straightened them out we
                    wouldn't have room for all of them" [268].</p>
            <pb n="53" id="VAA4025-072-1-059"/>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="[54]" id="VAA4025-072-1-060"/>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="55" id="VAA4025-072-1-061"/>
            <p>"Speak of the autumn colorings—sassafras, shumac, golden rod, purple aster, small
                    field daisy—white. The golden yellow of the hickories, blended shades of the maple, new
                    clover in in the fields, and the burnt grass along the roadsides. And over it all a blue sky that is
                    lovely to see, and picture" [119].</p>
            <p>"I loved to stand and watch the leaves as they fell into the water—watching their
                    reflections until they touched the water and sailed away like a masted vessel" [128].</p>
            <p>"Every trip to same spot reveals something prettier. And so it should be, else God would
                    have failed in His divine plan to have all things lovable at all times. Our eyes will do the work if
                    our mind is in accord" [25].</p>
            <p>"When making photographs afield I could imagine after I had finally wrestled the best there
                    was from my camera that I could hear Bobwhite sing ‘All right.’ And you can
                    rest assured I would be glad if he was correct in his conclusions" [46].</p>
            <p>"Left at 1 p.m., for trip up Salt creek, returning via Taggart settlement and Clay Lick. Was
                    a fine day, sometimes cloudy—bright, and not too hot. Elderberries ripe, and dragonflies
                    in great numbers here and there, flying over the fields. Touch-me-nots when taken away from their
                    regular surroundings remind us of human nature—die for want of pleasant and profitable
                    surroundings. Like to be where they can do what they most like to do. The creek at Weddle's
                    can be crossed on foot-stones. Locust and elm tree on the little brook near Taggart settlement.
                    James Neff hill, made at 5:50. Bitter sweet not yet ripe, but I brought home green berries. Large
                    jack-in-pulpit seed here and there. This was August 26th, 1919" [108].</p>
            <pb n="56" id="VAA4025-072-1-062"/>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="[57]" id="VAA4025-072-1-063"/>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="58" id="VAA4025-072-1-064"/>
            <figure/>
            <p>"So many small things to command your attention. Have you ever noticed that the tiny bits
                    are so attractive. And so it must be else we would not pause" [22].</p>
            <p>"Not the large things alone that count in Nature. We marvel at the majesty of some things
                    but how much more intimate do we become with the seemingly insignificant objects" [22].</p>
            <pb n="[59]" id="VAA4025-072-1-065"/>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="60" id="VAA4025-072-1-066"/>
            <figure/>
            <p>"<hi rend="i">RATTLESNAKES</hi>—July 28/19 in court house yard. Ned Pedro tells
                    of his brother killing a large one near the Hobbs place. Another evidence that they are numerous on
                    Weed Patch hill [<placeName>
                        <region type="county">Brown County</region>
                    </placeName> State Park]. He also said that there are many tracks of snakes crossing and recrossing
                    roads in search of water—the prophecy is that it will rain soon" [103].</p>
            <pb n="61" id="VAA4025-072-1-067"/>
            <p>"June 3/18. Heavy fog forming the night before as we had a fine rain Sunday. Early Monday
                    the mist was quite heavy and when I went to get a bucket of water was attracted by the spider tents
                    all over the yard. I made several snaps, and while doing so was impressed with the fact that we
                    could learn a lesson from the little spider who makes use of what they have around them to do their
                    work. We could economize also" [38].</p>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="62" id="VAA4025-072-1-068"/>
            <figure>
               <p>P<hi rend="sc">OKEBERRIES AND</hi> P<hi rend="sc">AWPAWS</hi>
               </p>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <pb n="[63]" id="VAA4025-072-1-069"/>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-072-1-a03">
            <head>
                    <hi rend="i">Proclamation</hi>
                </head>
            <p>TO A<hi rend="sc">LL</hi> TO W<hi rend="sc">HOM</hi> T<hi rend="sc">HESE</hi> P<hi rend="sc">RESENTS</hi> M<hi rend="sc">AY</hi> C<hi rend="sc">OME</hi>, G<hi rend="sc">REETING</hi>:</p>
            <table>
               <row>
                  <cell>WHEREAS,</cell>
                  <cell>The American Revolution Bicentennial Observance will be in progress throughout the <placeName>
                                <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                            </placeName> during 1976; and</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>WHEREAS,</cell>
                  <cell>The Old Northwest from which Indiana and other states were established, had an important
                            role in the American Revolution and a key part in the creation of the American Union
                            resulting therefrom; and</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>WHEREAS,</cell>
                  <cell>the Indiana American Revolution Bicentennial Commission and numerous local groups and
                            organizations throughout Indiana have made plans for a variety of programs and observances
                            appropriate to the American Revolution Bicentennial; and</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>WHEREAS,</cell>
                  <cell>the Indiana General Assembly in 1967 enacted a resolution calling upon the Governor to
                            annually declare April to be "Hoosier History and Heritage Month;"</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>NOW, THEREFORE,</cell>
                  <cell>I, Otis R. Bowen, Governor of the State of Indiana, do hereby proclaim the month of April,
                            1976, as</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p rend="center">HOOSIER HISTORY AND HERITAGE MONTH</p>
            <p>and urge that, especially during this month, Hoosiers sponsor tours, films, lectures, exhibits,
                    ceremonies, and other educational programs which will increase both student and citizen
                    understanding of, and appreciation for, our heritage as a state and as a nation.</p>
            <p>[SEAL]</p>
            <p rend="center">IN TESTIMONY WHEREOF, I have hereunto set my hand and caused to be affixed, the great
                    seal of the State of Indiana, at the Capitol, in the city of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, this 20th day of January, 1976.</p>
            <p rend="right">[Signed] Otis R. Bowen, M.D.</p>
            <p rend="right">Governor of Indiana</p>
            <p>[Signed] Larry A. Conrad</p>
            <p>Secretary of State</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="[64]" id="VAA4025-072-1-070"/>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-072-1-a04">
            <head>Awards of Merit and Certificates of Commendation from American Association for State and Local
                    History</head>
            <p>All nominations must be made on the "Awards Nomination Form" and <hi rend="i">postmarked by not later than May 21, 1976.</hi> Each nominator must include a supporting letter
                    which is explicit in indicating why the award or certificate seems merited. Each nominator is also
                    responsible for making certain that at least two or three other persons send similar statements <hi rend="i">directly to the state chairman.</hi> Finally, each nominator should send relevant
                    supporting material such as pamphlets, newspaper clippings, programs, scripts, and books. The views
                    and evaluations of various persons will be considered regarding each nomination.</p>
            <p>1. <hi rend="i">Certificate of Commendation.</hi> The Certificate of Commendation is given for
                    outstanding achievement by an individual or an organization in the field of state, provincial, and
                    local history, but with that achievement judged in the light of local limiting circumstances rather
                    than on a basis of overall excellence in the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <country reg="-cn">Canada</country>
                    </placeName> as a whole. This is an award of encouragement and commendation to a person or group
                    which by great effort has accomplished something that is really outstanding within its own area. The
                    certificate is a pat on the back and says to the individual or organization that receives it:
                    "We think you are doing a wonderful job in your area, and we want to recognize you for
                    it."</p>
            <p>2. <hi rend="i">The Award of Merit.</hi> This was the original award of the American Association for
                    State and Local History and is still the backbone of its competition. It is given for excellence of
                    accomplishment or program in the field of state, provincial, and local history and is in no way
                    judged relative to local limiting circumstances. The giving of the Award of Merit is the same as
                    saying to everyone: "This is public acknowledgment by the American Association for State
                    and Local History that this accomplishment or this program, in comparison with all similar
                    accomplishments and programs in North America, deserves the adjective excellent."</p>
            <p>Nomination forms are available from Gayle Thornbrough, executive secretary, Indiana Historical
                    Society, 140 North Senate Avenue, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indiana 46204. Miss Thornbrough is chairman for nominations from Indiana for 1976.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="[65]" id="VAA4025-072-1-071"/>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-072-1-a05">
            <head>Book Reviews</head>
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">A Documentary History of the Indiana Decade of the Harmony Society,
                        1814–1824.</hi> Volume I, <hi rend="i">1814–1819.</hi> Compiled and edited
                    by Karl J. R. Arndt. (<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>: Indiana Historical Society, 1975. Pp. xxiii, 837. Notes, illustrations, index.
                    Clothbound, $17.50; paperbound, $8.00.)</head>
            <p>
               <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New Harmony</settlement>
                    </placeName> is one of the most fascinating towns in Indiana. Historically, interest focuses on the
                    village's origins in the communal societies of George Rapp and Robert Owen and upon its
                    later importance as a center of science, education, and the arts. Currently, attention is attracted
                    to the historic restoration and revitalization of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New Harmony</settlement>
                    </placeName> being carried out amid a renaissance of its religious and cultural heritage.</p>
            <p>Arndt's <hi rend="i">Documentary History</hi> contributes a new dimension to the
                    understanding of this town. Through sources first printed in this book it is revealed that the
                    Harmonists laid out and constructed the town according to a symmetrical design prepared in advance
                    by Frederick Rapp, the society's business manager and the adopted son of spiritual leader
                    George Rapp. Such information already has proven invaluable for the development of the comprehensive
                    plan by which the historic district of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New Harmony</settlement>
                    </placeName> now is being physically restored to its nineteenth century appearance.</p>
            <p>This first of two proposed volumes is drawn from decades of Arndt's research and supplements
                    the publications that have made this professor of German the principal scholar of the Harmony
                    Society. The book presents carefully selected and minimally edited letters, many translated from the
                    difficult Swabian dialect, describing the German Separatist Rappites between 1814 and 1819 when they
                    moved from Harmony, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>
                    </placeName>, to build their <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New Harmony</settlement>
                    </placeName> in the Indiana Territory. Most of these source materials are in the Harmony Society
                    Archives at Old Economy, Ambridge, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="pau">Pennsylvania</region>
                    </placeName>, where their processing continues. Harmonist correspondence in other repositories, such
                    as the Western Reserve Historical Society Shaker collection in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cleveland</settlement>
                    </placeName>, remains to be researched.</p>
            <p>With its informative introduction, exhaustive annotation, extensive index, and adequate illustration,
                    Arndt's volume is a fine reference work. It is also much more. The book's
                    chronologically arranged letters, interspersed with appropriate public documents, make it an
                    intimate narrative of <pb n="66" id="VAA4025-072-1-072"/> the interaction between a major religious
                    communal group and the economy, politics, and many of the outstanding people of the early Middle
                    West. The reader is transported to the era of twenty-five cent per pound sugar and one dollar per
                    gallon whiskey. There he witnesses the rapid growth of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New Harmony</settlement>
                    </placeName> from Father Rapp's first optimistic appraisal of the frontier site on the <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wabash</region>
                    </placeName> in 1814 to an English traveler's assessment of its thriving appearance in
                    1819. By then, eight hundred Harmonists had cleared and cultivated about 1,400 acres, planted
                    orchards and vineyards, and built a three story brick church, a school, a store, and an inn. They
                    had become virtually self sufficient while establishing an interstate commerce from their
                    distillery, brewery, mills, and woolen and cotton factories.</p>
            <p>Although no new interpretation of the Harmony Society is likely to emerge from this first volume of
                    Arndt's <hi rend="i">Documentary History,</hi> it includes welcome details of Harmonist
                    history, more of which might be anticipated in the second volume. Of particular interest are the
                    Harmonists' persistent refusal to perform military service despite local opposition and
                    state fines, their cultural and religious orientations as indicated by their book and painting
                    orders, their benevolence and skepticism toward other communitarians evident in their correspondence
                    with Shakers and Zoarites, their neighborliness as shown in their cooperation with the English
                    pioneers at Albion, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ilu">Illinois</region>
                    </placeName>, and their political influence as illustrated by Frederick Rapp's membership
                    in the Indiana Constitutional Convention of 1816.</p>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="i">Indiana State University, <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Evansville</settlement>
                        </placeName>
               </hi> Donald E. Pitzer</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-072-1-a06">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">Indiana Historical Society Lectures, 1973–1974: Human and Cultural
                        Development.</hi> By J. T. Robinson, Melvin L. Fowler, and Brian M. Fagan. (<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>: Indiana Historical Society, 1974. Pp. 65. Notes. Paperbound, $1.50.)</head>
            <p>Today scholars are used to reading of fresh archaeological discoveries shedding light on
                    man's past. Only infrequently, however, is there an opportunity to read clearly written
                    assessments of the state of knowledge of man and his prehistory. This volume, which includes three
                    essays <pb n="67" id="VAA4025-072-1-073"/> dealing with where man stands among the organisms and
                    with the origins and early history of civilizations and urban societies, helps fill this gap.</p>
            <p>The first essay by J. T. Robinson, "Man, Evolution and Society," is devoted to
                    explaining the differences between the forces behind man's cultural evolution and evolution
                    among other organisms. Robinson emphasizes that man is really a "primitive example of a
                    wholly new class of organism" (p. 3) since he has evolved as a culture bearer. Hence he is
                    essentially governed by rules of consciousness in contrast to the competitive forces of natural
                    selection operating among higher plants and animals through genetic rules. The unique benefits
                    conferred upon the human organism through the cultural adaption are amply outlined in this essay.
                    However, Robinson strays from an otherwise secure position to argue that the processes of selection
                    are no longer important in modern civilization. He cites the current uncontrolled growth of
                    population as a case in point without considering that the technological attainment of increased
                    capacity to extract energy from the environment has shifted the selective forces from individuals to
                    social, technological, and ideological systems. Man has not escaped selection; in the present
                    society it operates more effectively upon cultural systems than upon biology.</p>
            <p>Some of the ways in which selective forces operate on cultures are revealed in the remaining two
                    essays, which focus on the ancient transformation from simple food producers to more complex
                    societies centered around urban centers or governed by state level polities. The middle essay,
                    "Prehistoric Urban Evolution in North America," by Melvin L. Fowler accurately
                    summarizes the known history of New World urban development that began about 2,000 B.C. and
                    culminated as an independent achievement with the Aztec capital discovered by Cortez. Fowler
                    elaborates a five stage sequence of development that is applicable to both central Mexico, which is
                    his primary case, and to a lesser known case in the eastern <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>. The reader will find the parallels between Mexico and the Southeast provocative. The
                    Old World is a different matter since Americans are used to seeking the roots to their own
                    civilization in the Near East.</p>
            <p>The history of thought concerning the origins of civilization there is ably treated by Brian M. Fagan
                    in the last <pb n="68" id="VAA4025-072-1-074"/> essay, "The Country Life is to be
                    Preferred: A Brief Review of Theories on the Origins of Civilization in the Old World." He
                    traces thought from older ideas of naive evolutionism to current and more comprehensive theories
                    that attribute the grandeur and sophistication of civilization as consequent upon attainment of the
                    state level of political development. Both of these essays by archaeologists are effective in
                    portraying a fine sense of the generality of principles that can emerge from specific regionally
                    focused studies.</p>
            <p>Although some important reservations about aspects of Robinson's essay have been indicated
                    in this review, this collection has the stuff to stimulate the active mind and is an important
                    addition to one's library.</p>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="i">Northwestern University, <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Evanston</settlement>
                        </placeName>
               </hi> James A. Brown</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-072-1-a07">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">Growth of the American Revolution, 1766–1775.</hi> By Bernhard
                    Knollenberg. (<placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                    </placeName>: The Free Press, 1975. Pp. xxii, 551. Appendixes, notes, bibliography, index.
                    $15.00.)</head>
            <p>This extensively documented volume comprised of 197 pages of text, 72 of appendixes, and 264 of
                    footnotes continues Knollenberg's study of the events leading to the outbreak of war in
                    1775 between Great Britain and her thirteen North American colonies. His first volume, published in
                    1960, concentrated on those events between 1759 and 1766 which brought the colonists to the brink of
                    actual rebellion with their reaction to the Stamp Tax in 1766. The present volume, seen through the
                    press by John R. Alden but "virtually completed" before the author's
                    death in 1973, picks up the narrative with the repeal of the Stamp Act and the passage of the
                    Declaratory Act and relates in succinct, almost outline form, those British actions and colonial
                    reactions that led inevitably to military hostilities at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Lexington</settlement>
                    </placeName> and Concord. As the author does not wish to digress from his relentless build up to the
                    climax of war, he delegates to appendixes more lengthy explanations and elaborations of data which
                    he merely mentions in the body of the book.</p>
            <p>In the introduction Knollenberg outlines his purpose, which is to show the development by 1775 of a
                    spirit for revolution in the "Minds and Hearts of a Majority of the People of the Thirteen
                    Colonies" (opposite title page) and also to describe both British conduct and colonial
                    reaction which brought about this spirit. Once the reader masters <pb n="69" id="VAA4025-072-1-075"/> the arrangement of the book it is difficult to avoid acceptance of Knollenberg's case
                    for inevitable conflict. Only at one point does there seem to be a solution short of war. The author
                    speculates that if General Thomas Gage in 1775 had been able to seize the leading <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mau">Massachusetts</region>
                    </placeName> rebels, as Lord Dartmouth suggested, the Whigs throughout the thirteen colonies would
                    have retaliated by holding crown officials as a more effective bargaining force for redress of
                    grievances than economic boycott. This did not happen, of course, and war came.</p>
            <p>Knollenberg admits that his sympathies lie with the colonial Whigs, defined as those colonists who
                    not only denied the right of Parliament to impose taxes, but when petitions failed to bring repeal,
                    advocated commercial pressure. He does not use the term "loyalist" because all
                    colonists were loyal in this period, but he defines as "Tories," as did their
                    contemporaries, those who favored limiting protest to petition and those who did not protest at all.</p>
            <p>British conviction by 1774 of the colonial desire for complete independence, fortified by pride and
                    bad advice that the Americans could be subdued easily by force because of cowardice and inability to
                    fight, made compromise impossible. Although opposing parliamentary taxation, the American Whigs
                    maintained their loyalty and their submission to the prerogative of the crown as late as their 1774
                    petition to the king from the First Continental Congress. Their image of responsible leadership,
                    carefully planned by the Whigs, objecting to British policy in a controlled manner was a major
                    influence in uniting the other colonies behind beleaguered <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mau">Massachusetts</region>
                    </placeName>.</p>
            <p>This book and its predecessor will stand as monuments to the author's excellent scholarship
                    and mastery of the sources.</p>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="i">Ball State University, <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Muncie</settlement>
                        </placeName>
               </hi> Althea L. Stoeckel</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-072-1-a08">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">Thomas L. McKenney: Architect of America's Early Indian Policy,
                        1816–1830.</hi> By Herman J. Viola. (<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                    </placeName>: The Swallow Press, Inc., 1974. Pp. xii, 365. Maps, illustrations, appendix, notes,
                    bibliography, index. $15.00.)</head>
            <p>Since it is generally assumed that <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName>'s bureaucrats, past and present, have not been part of the policy making
                    process, they are not often subjects of book length biographies. <pb n="70" id="VAA4025-072-1-076"/>
                    Some of course have been more than mere functionaries. Herman J. Viola makes such a case for Thomas
                    L. McKenney, the first superintendent of Indian Affairs. He argues that McKenney was in fact the
                    architect of America's early Indian policy.</p>
            <p>Rescued from the life of a <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mdu">Maryland</region>
                    </placeName> merchant, McKenney became the superintendent of Indian trade in 1816, a position he
                    held until 1822. The fur trade was essentially a lucrative business, but the government sponsored
                    factories steadily lost money. Congress was not prepared to support the factories adequately in the
                    face of growing competition from entrepreneurs such as John Jacob Astor. The system was destined to
                    failure, and McKenney received the blame.</p>
            <p>While in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName>, McKenney curried the favor of the political and social elite. He started a short lived
                    newspaper which in 1824 vigorously supported the presidential aspirations of John C. Calhoun. This
                    won him the lasting enmity of Andrew Jackson's supporters, but more immediately it got him
                    back on the government payroll. Secretary of War Calhoun, without congressional approval, appointed
                    McKenney a senior clerk in his department, responsible for Indian affairs. From such a small
                    beginning evolved the Bureau of Indian Affairs. McKenney assumed the title of superintendent of
                    Indian Affairs.</p>
            <p>There was a grandiose side to McKenney's character. To keep up pretensions of class he
                    attempted to maintain a large estate called Weston on a senior clerk's salary. It
                    bankrupted him. His visions of grandeur were further reflected in the public spectacles he arranged
                    for Indian chiefs who visited the capital. When he and other commissioners traveled to the Indian
                    lands, they sometimes arrived at treaty signing ceremonies in a canopied canoe.</p>
            <p>The election of Jackson to the presidency in 1828 precluded a lengthy stay for McKenney in the
                    bureau. He was dismissed in 1830. Thereafter he made repeated attempts to regain his position, but
                    even the Whigs ignored him when they came to power in 1840. A more useful activity, and perhaps
                    McKenney's most lasting monument, was the publication of a three volume folio edition of
                    his <hi rend="i">History of the Indian Tribes of North America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Thomas L. McKenney</hi> is a well written and thoroughly researched book. Viola includes
                    an enormous amount of detail. This does help make <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> politics of the 1820s <pb n="71" id="VAA4025-072-1-077"/> come alive and problems of
                    the Bureau of Indian Affairs seem immediate. But much of the detail borders on the antiquarian.
                    Perhaps it is useful to know something about the bookkeeping practices of the bureau or the number
                    of letters each overworked clerk transcribed. For some there may be a certain fascination in knowing
                    precisely how Indian medals were struck or how books were bound, but does it matter?</p>
            <p>Viola is generally sympathetic toward his subject, although at one perceptive moment he refers to
                    McKenney as a blend of blarney and sincerity. He insists that McKenney was a great humanitarian.
                    This does not quite come off. Other than that McKenney grew up in a <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Quaker</settlement>
                    </placeName> family, there is not a satisfactory explanation of the wellspring of his
                    humanitarianism. But more importantly, the McKenney of this book seems not to have a deep insight
                    into the needs of Indians and the overwhelming problems they faced. Viola sets out to correct what
                    he calls a faulty image of McKenney as a vacillating and self seeking opportunist. The picture that
                    does come through is that of a socially ambitious, impractical dreamer who could not keep his own
                    financial house in order and who did not do much better with the affairs of the Indians.</p>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="i">University of <placeName>
                            <region type="state" reg="mbc">Manitoba</region>
                        </placeName>, <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Winnipeg</settlement>
                        </placeName>, <placeName>
                     <region type="state" reg="mbc">Manitoba</region>, <country reg="-cn">Canada</country>
                  </placeName>
               </hi> George A. Schultz</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-072-1-a09">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">The Mind of America, 1820–1860.</hi> By Rush Welter. (<placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                    </placeName>: <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Columbia</settlement>
                    </placeName> University Press, 1975. Pp. xvi, 603. Appendixes, notes, bibliography, index.
                    $14.95.)</head>
            <p>Rush Welter, whose previous writings have displayed a talent for the American Studies approach to
                    scholarship, is a professor of American history at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Bennington</settlement>
                    </placeName> College. This latest impressive work pursues the same interdisciplinary avenue to
                    understanding an age often called the Middle Period. Welter's emphasis here is more of an
                    exploration of the "inarticulate premises" of a generation (p. vii) than of the
                    formal intellectual trends of the day; therefore, predictable personalities rarely appear except as
                    spokesmen for commonly shared beliefs.</p>
            <p>In order to reveal the views of this traditionally silent majority, Welter draws from patriotic
                    Fourth of July orations, <pb n="72" id="VAA4025-072-1-078"/> state constitutional conventions,
                    pamphlets, periodicals, and, surprisingly, very few contemporary newspapers. The result of this
                    research is an instructive and often entertaining compendium of quotations which validates the
                    author's major theses. A multitude of supposedly inarticulate unknowns speaks forthrightly
                    on the American mission, equality, religion, education, politics, and other topics. The general
                    reader will find the arguments and prose easy to follow and will not be led on any exotic academic
                    excursions. For the more venturesome reader there are two hundred pages of notes, bibliography, and
                    index. In addition to the standard footnotes for source citations, Welter includes a separate set of
                    notes for digressions into historiographical comparisons and sometimes querulous debates with other
                    scholars and definitions.</p>
            <p>Welter skillfully channels the many facets of the Middle Period mind into a number of underlying
                    themes. One of these is the manner in which democrats and conservatives replaced their initial
                    differences with mutual accommodations on many issues. For example, the frontier West became a
                    social leveler for classes and regions because it "made room for their disparate
                    hopes" (p. 320). Another theme, nicely developed in the final chapter, is the inevitability
                    of the Civil War, which resulted, in part, from the contemporary generation's strongly held
                    convictions on morality, constitutions, and individual liberties.</p>
            <p>Any book of this scope and ambition naturally invites as much criticism for what it is not as for
                    what it is. An analysis of popular literature would be appropriate and welcome here, as would a
                    discussion of William McGuffey in either of the sections on morality or education. Welter's
                    omission of proslavery arguments despite generous anti-slavery ones is a curious departure from his
                    usual balanced treatment of issues. And closer editing would have prevented the rhythmic
                    "on the one hand … on the other hand" which appears with metronomic
                    frequency.</p>
            <p>Its minor flaws included, this is a commendable addition to the field of intellectual history. With
                    Russel Nye's <hi rend="i">Society and Culture in America,</hi> a recent look at the same
                    generation from a slightly different vantage point, historians are now better equipped to understand
                    and appreciate the mind of America before the Civil War.</p>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="i">Indiana University <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">East, Richmond</settlement>
                        </placeName>
               </hi> George T. Blakey</byline>
         </div>
         <pb n="73" id="VAA4025-072-1-079"/>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-072-1-a10">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">
                  <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Philadelphia</settlement>
                        </placeName>'s Philosopher Mechanics: A History of the <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Franklin</settlement>
                        </placeName> Institute, 1824–1865.</hi> By Bruce Sinclair. (<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Baltimore</settlement>
                    </placeName>: The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1974. Pp. xi, 353. Notes, illustrations,
                    bibliography, index. $15.00.)</head>
            <p>The <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Franklin</settlement>
                    </placeName> Institute was one of the most successful of several mechanics' institutes
                    founded in urban and manufacturing centers in the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> in the early part of the nineteenth century. Among the valuable contributions of the
                    book are the first two chapters which deal with the significance of mechanics' institutes
                    and similar voluntary organizations both in the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> and in <placeName>
                        <country reg="enk">England</country>
                    </placeName>. Such information is scattered and slight in most published sources.</p>
            <p>The <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Franklin</settlement>
                    </placeName> Institute, founded in 1824, had as one of its purposes the improvement of educational
                    opportunities for workingmen so that they would not only become leaders in a democratic society but
                    would also be in positions to advance better, more efficient fabrications of products from the
                    abundant natural resources of the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>. The institute was never a self help institution; rather, it was led and financed by
                    employers with the cooperation of scientists and teachers. In a day when colleges and schools still
                    maintained basically classical curricula, the institute provided technical and scientific
                    educational opportunities by setting up schools of mathematics and drawing and by offering lecture
                    series on such subjects as chemistry, geology, and mechanics. Associated with this educational
                    endeavor were annual exhibitions of machinery, industrial processes, and products so that
                    manufacturers and their workers could see what the competition was doing. In this connection the
                    institute also reviewed new patents to discover their usefulness. Finally a permanent museum and
                    library was established. These projects and programs were publicized by the <hi rend="i">
                  <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Franklin</settlement>
                        </placeName> Journal and American Mechanic's Magazine</hi> (published under variant
                    titles). The journal included notices of domestic and foreign scientific and technological
                    developments, the evaluations of patents, and much other practical information.</p>
            <p>The leaders thought that the institute should also be a research agency dealing with national
                    problems of industry and commerce. The most important investigations were of water as a power
                    source, the causes of steamboat boiler explosions, <pb n="74" id="VAA4025-072-1-080"/> and the
                    causes and effects of the weather, all of great significance in the early nineteenth century. The
                    experience of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Franklin</settlement>
                    </placeName> Institute in its research was instrumental in eventually bringing science within the
                    scope of government through the National Academy of Science.</p>
            <p>In addition to dealing with larger themes of more than local significance, Sinclair is concerned with
                    the internal history of the institute and its financial and programmatic problems. He also discusses
                    the men in the institute, their businesses, their interests, and their associations with the other
                    scientific and intellectual organizations of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Philadelphia</settlement>
                    </placeName>, principally the American Philosophical Society and the Academy of Natural Sciences.
                    Much important biographical information about a number of technological and scientific leaders of
                    the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> is here presented.</p>
            <p>Sinclair has written an important book in its field. It adds another chapter to an understanding of
                    the American past in science and technology, both of which have been the subjects of scholarly
                    research in the last quarter century. The book deals with the history of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Franklin</settlement>
                    </placeName> Institute for only the period 1824–1865. It was originally a doctoral
                    dissertation and so had to be cut to a manageable length. The period chosen is a viable unit, but
                    this reviewer is left with a feeling of dissatisfaction because he does not know what has happened
                    to the institute in the last 110 years. Maybe Sinclair will fill in this gap by writing a second
                    volume.</p>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="i">MacMurray College, <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Jacksonville</settlement>
                        </placeName>, Ill.</hi> Walter B. Hendrickson</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-072-1-a11">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">The Federal Machine: Beginnings of Bureaucracy in Jacksonian America.</hi> By Matthew
                    A. Crenson. (<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Baltimore</settlement>
                    </placeName>: The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1975. Pp. xii, 186. Notes, tables, figures,
                    bibliography, index. $10.00.)</head>
            <p>Matthew Crenson is a political scientist writing history, and as such he brings both the weakness and
                    strength of that interdisciplinary situation to this study. The author grasps better than most
                    historians writing in the period the significance inherent in the dynamic expansion of the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> federal civil establishment as it grew to meet the equally dynamic expansion of the
                    nation. But Crenson's <pb n="75" id="VAA4025-072-1-081"/> knowledge of what has been
                    written recently about the Age of Jackson is limited only to some very visible political
                    contributions and lacks depth; his knowledge of the earlier formative period in American politics is
                    also very shaky.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless, by concentrating on the General Land Office and the Post Office, the two components of
                    the Jacksonian civil service most affected by the physical growth of the nation in the years
                    1820–1850, and by viewing these from the novel perspective of their roles in the
                    establishment of an American government machine (read bureaucracy), Crenson makes an important
                    contribution. He goes beyond Malcolm Rohrbough's fine study, <hi rend="i">The Land Office
                        Business,</hi> by viewing the land office in clinical terms that capture its mechanistic
                    influence on western expansion. So very little has been written about the early Post Office that any
                    exposure of its social and political role is welcome knowledge.</p>
            <p>A good part of the administrative change that occurred in the Age of Jackson Crenson attributes to
                    "the ascent to power of men of lowly origins" (p. 8), a development to which
                    historians are now returning in an effort to explain anew the dynamic qualities of the Jackson
                    epoch. Under the impact of industrialization there occurred an "apparent deterioration of
                    moral restraints" (p. 44) that infected all of American life, the federal civil service
                    included. "Attorneys and businessmen who went to work for the government could not be
                    expected to possess the same habits of moral uprightness as their predecessors" (p. 46).
                    Jackson consciously attempted to fight this alleged tendency, according to Crenson, so that
                    government, at least, would be freed of acts "injurious to the morals of the
                    country" (p. 173). This explains, then, Old Hickory's effort to place new men in
                    government service and his adherence to the principles of rotation in office.</p>
            <p>This reviewer questions many of the author's basic premises, notably that a decline in
                    public morality had occurred between the end of the era of the founding fathers and 1830. In spite
                    of these facile ideological overtones, the author is still able to reveal a great deal that is new
                    and interesting about the Post Office and the General Land Office.</p>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="i">
                  <placeName>
                            <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                        </placeName> University, <placeName>
                            <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                        </placeName>
               </hi> Carl E. Prince</byline>
         </div>
         <pb n="76" id="VAA4025-072-1-082"/>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-072-1-a12">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">The Presidency of James Buchanan.</hi> By Elbert B. Smith. (Lawrence: The University
                    Press of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ksu">Kansas</region>
                    </placeName>, 1975. Pp. xiii, 225. Frontispiece, notes, bibliographical essay, index.
                    $12.00.)</head>
            <p>The editors of the <hi rend="i">American Presidency Series</hi> expect much of their authors,
                    demanding interesting, scholarly, interpretive, comprehensive, synthetic, and original accounts.
                    Doubly difficult is Smith's task in this volume, for his subject has attracted such
                    outstanding middle period scholars as Allan Nevins, Pulitzer Prize winner Roy Nichols, and Philip
                    Klein. The author's task is to provide both a fresh synthesis of their writings and
                    original interpretations of his subject.</p>
            <p>The synthesis has been provided. Nichols is the chief source for the picture of a Cabinet formed of
                    strong southerners and weak northerners. Nevins is used to depict a president ignoring the
                    separation of powers principle to influence the Dred Scott decision. Nevins is also followed in
                    sketching a president almost brutally indifferent to his party's fate in the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ksu">Kansas</region>
                    </placeName> statehood struggle. Klein's evidence has been used to show an aggressive but
                    unsuccessful imperialist in foreign affairs, and the account of the near identity of
                    Buchanan's and Abraham Lincoln's Fort Sumter policies also faithfully adheres to
                    Klein. While this synthesis is so exacting as to border on plagiarism at times, it is unsatisfactory
                    for two reasons. Nevins and Klein are poles apart in their attitudes, and to combine
                    Nevins' account of Buchanan's weak kneed impotence in the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ksu">Kansas</region>
                    </placeName> crisis with Klein's account of the president's sturdy assertiveness
                    in foreign affairs produces a character too schizoid to be believable. Secondly, the synthesis is
                    highly selective. Works cited in the bibliography as "best" studies fail to appear
                    either in the footnotes or the narrative. Ignored are such works as Norman F. Furniss'
                    account of the Mormon conflict, Ronald T. Takaki's study of efforts to reopen the African
                    slave trade, Robert E. May's depiction of southern hopes for a Caribbean empire, and Tom W.
                    Henderson's analysis of administration policies toward slave smuggling and the slave <hi rend="i">Wanderer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For original interpretations the author's impressive credentials in scholarship and in
                    practical contemporary politics demand a respectful hearing for his assertion that
                    Lincoln's election "was made certain by vigorous political policies that <pb n="77" id="VAA4025-072-1-083"/> stemmed directly from the White House," and, therefore,
                    "that James Buchanan might have prevented … [this] key event that triggered the
                    southern secession" (p. x). In Smith's view these "vigorous political
                    policies" involved the disruptive power of the federal patronage. Yet the contention that
                    "any incumbent president … was … empowered by his control of jobs and
                    favors to play a major role in choosing his party's candidate for the succession"
                    (p. 101) probably reflects the 1960s more than the 1850s, as is indicated by the failure of both
                    Millard Fillmore and Franklin Pierce to secure either their own renominations or determine their
                    party's nominees. Stephen A. Douglas' <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Charleston</settlement>
                    </placeName> support by officeholders like George Sanders (p. 109) suggests that officeholder unity
                    for Douglas' defeat is a myth. Once the campaign commenced, Buchanan, as his published
                    correspondence shows, left most influential Douglasites in federal office undisturbed. And, as the
                    author himself admits, if party unity were necessary to stave off defeat, the "first
                    overture should have come from Douglas" (p. 102).</p>
            <p>This volume stops short of the admittedly difficult objectives of this series. The author summarizes
                    the writings of some major figures of middle period scholarship in the 1940s and 1950s. But those
                    who seek a synthesis of later scholarship or original contributions must continue their quest.</p>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="i">State University of <placeName>
                            <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                        </placeName>, Fredonia</hi> David E. Meerse</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-072-1-a13">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">The Papers of Jefferson Davis.</hi> Volume 2, June 1841-July 1846. Edited by James T.
                    Mclntosh. (<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Baton Rouge</settlement>
                    </placeName>: <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="lau">Louisiana</region>
                    </placeName> State University Press, 1974. Pp. xxxix, 806. Maps, illustrations, tables, notes,
                    appendixes, list of sources, index. $20.00.)</head>
            <p>Jefferson Davis, despite his unique position in American history as president of the Confederate
                    States of America, is still somewhat a man of mystery. In writing his introduction to volume one of
                        <hi rend="i">The Papers of Jefferson Davis</hi> four years ago, Bruce Catton informed readers
                    that "as a man progresses from youth to manhood, and on through manhood to death, he leaves
                    tracks on paper" which should be collected and published if that man has sufficient stature
                    in <pb n="78" id="VAA4025-072-1-084"/> American history. As a congressman, secretary of war, and
                    presider over the lost Grand Cause, Davis certainly merits attention.</p>
            <p>During the 1830s the young Davis resigned his commission in the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> Army, lost his bride of just three months to malaria, then turned his interests toward
                    agriculture in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName>. During the early 1840s—the contents of this volume extend from June, 1841,
                    to July, 1846—Davis gained experience in local and state Democratic party politics which
                    led to his being elected to the House of Representatives in November, 1845. While the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName> planter served in Congress, talk of war circulated because of territorial disputes with
                    Great Britain over the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="oru">Oregon</region>
                    </placeName> boundary and with Mexico over the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="txu">Texas</region>
                    </placeName> boundary. Amply endowed with patriotic and military ardor, Davis welcomed a military
                    commission to serve against Mexico when war was declared against that country in May, 1846. Despite
                    his second wife Varina's anguished objections, Davis wasted no time accepting command of
                    the First <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName> Regiment of volunteers. The last numbered item in volume two is a letter from Davis,
                    dated July 8, 1846, written on a steamboat in the <geogName>Ohio River</geogName> as he and Mrs.
                    Davis journeyed to Vicksburg in order that he could take command of his troops.</p>
            <p>The contents of this volume are disappointing to this reviewer. Of the 715 pages of text, comprising
                    some 255 items, most relate to the political speeches or public documents of Davis. These are
                    certainly of importance, but it is unfortunate that readers of the volume will not gain a closer
                    view of the private side of the man. Of the first 100 pages of the volume there are just three
                    personal letters. The text of all three total just more than one page. If Davis corresponded as much
                    as Frank E. Vandiver maintained in volume one, the correspondence is either destroyed or unknown.
                    Instead, one reads in the volume a steady stream of speeches made by Davis as reported in
                    newspapers. One document, an extract of the proceedings of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName> State Democratic Convention of January, 1844, is about nine pages in length, but there
                    are 139 citations constituting 42 pages of text. Every person mentioned in the text of the document
                    appears to have a lengthy biographical sketch.</p>
            <p>According to the index, Editor Mclntosh and his staff have provided over 430 sketches of persons.
                    Much of the <pb n="79" id="VAA4025-072-1-085"/> documentation contained in these
                    sketches—many are 150 to 200 words in length—could have been omitted without
                    detracting from the Davis material. It is not simply the amount of text taken up by the sketches,
                    but rather the time and effort taken by the editorial staff in gathering and verifying this
                    information. This observation focuses on editorial policy and in no way detracts from the
                    contribution this volume makes to students of Jefferson Davis and <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName> history and genealogy. It also does not detract from the excellent selection of
                    illustrations, the Davis chronology, and the extensive list of sources included in the volume.</p>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="i">National Archives, <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                        </placeName>, <placeName>
                            <region type="state">D.C.</region>
                        </placeName>
               </hi> George C. Chalou</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-072-1-a14">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">Whereby We Thrive: A History of American Farming, 1607–1972.</hi> By John
                    T. Schlebecker. (Ames: The <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="iau">Iowa</region>
                    </placeName> State University Press, 1975. Pp. x, 342. Illustrations, tables, bibliography, index.
                    $12.95.)</head>
            <p>This book is a history of American farming without the farmer. Though the author says his work
                    "becomes basically social history," it is far from the kind of social history
                    written by such outstanding practitioners as Everett Dick and Merle Curti. Nowhere does the farmer
                    appear except as influenced by government, science, politics, and education. The author who is
                    curator of agriculture and mining in the Smithsonian Institution has drawn upon his work at the
                    Smithsonian on the development of agricultural machines and the use of science in agriculture to
                    good effect. He has given us a history of the development of agricultural machinery, of the
                    marketing of farm commodities, and of the application of science to agriculture. Chapters on tools
                    and machines, on transportation and methods of food processing, on biochemistry and genetics are all
                    done with skill and understanding. For this part of his task he was admirably prepared and has done
                    very well. Though the entire book is apparently written for the general reader rather than for
                    specialists, these chapters make clear much that is important for the student of American
                    agricultural history.</p>
            <p>Schlebecker's treatment of government policy, despite some perceptive observations, is
                    disappointing. It has too many errors, misunderstandings, and erroneous information. In places it
                    reminds one of Frederic L. Paxson's <hi rend="i">History of</hi>
                    <pb n="80" id="VAA4025-072-1-086"/>
                    <hi rend="i">the American Frontier</hi> and Benjamin H. Hibbard, History of Public Land Policies,
                    both published in 1924. Though these works are generally displaced, had the author used their data
                    more carefully he might have avoided some of his worst errors. Also, in neglecting many more recent
                    works such as those of Malcolm J. Rohrbough, Hiram M. Drache, Robert R. Dykstra, Robert P.
                    Swierenga, Yasuo Okada, Richard S. Kirkendall, Thomas LeDuc, and the reviewer and older works of
                    David M. Ellis, James B. Hedges, and Everett Dick, he cut himself off from the best treatments of
                    government land policy. Instead, he lists eleven textbooks.</p>
            <p>To list all the errors would take far more space than is justified, but a few will be mentioned.
                    Schlebecker quite misunderstands the many varieties of land paper issued by the government (p. 62).
                    Warrants and scrip did not enable purchasers of government land to avoid the usual public auction;
                    that was accomplished by the preemption laws. The warrants had no advantage over cash. The <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> never abandoned "the concept of money making off the land sales" (p.
                    62). True, free lands as embodied in the homestead laws were a step in that direction; but
                    preemption entries, commutted homestead entries, desert land entries ($1.25 an acre, not
                    $.25 an acre), mineral land entries, and timber and stone entries all called for money
                    payments. In the twentieth century income from royalties, leasing, power site development, and off
                    shore oil drilling have been in a single year far larger than the entire income from public land
                    sales in the nineteenth century. The Agricultural College Act of 1862 was not intended to provide
                    land for farmers, for congressional leaders were aware that the land being granted would mostly pass
                    to speculators. The Corn Laws of <placeName>
                        <country reg="enk">England</country>
                    </placeName> were not responsible for the South's concentration upon cotton rather than
                    wheat (pp. 74–75). The South did not entirely halt cotton planting during the Civil War,
                    but the extreme scarcity of food forced a sharp reduction in the acreage in cotton (p. 155). Much of
                    the cotton raised during the Civil War was burned to prevent its falling into the hands of the Union
                    army. The author missed the significance of the Timber Culture Act which allowed settlers to hold
                    land for as much as a decade until the demand for it enabled them to sell relinquishments at
                    substantial profits (p. 144). The data on homesteading on pages 139 and 208 are seriously wrong, <pb n="81" id="VAA4025-072-1-087"/> and the figure on land sales is too large by 100 per cent.
                    Except in the periods from 1816–1819 and 1834–1837 it was only in rare cases
                    that the government received more than the minimum price for its land. The creation of the forest
                    reserves did not take "place only under the presidency of Theodore Roosevelt."
                    Withdrawals under Harrison were 13,053,440 acres, not "some 13,000 acres" (p.
                    146), and other extensive withdrawals were made by Presidents Grover Cleveland and William McKinley.
                    Neither land purchased for national forests under the Weeks Act nor land "put into national
                    parks" was generally "taken out of agriculture" (p. 219). It is hardly
                    correct to say in this more sophisticated day that "under consumption" and the low
                    wage levels of workers were responsible for low farm commodity prices from 1920 to 1933. The land
                    grants for the transcontinental railroads are given as double what they actually were. Schlebecker
                    misnames the Stock Raising Homestead Act and surely is wrong in calling it the "most
                    popular homestead law" (p. 208).</p>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="i">Cornell University, <placeName>
                     <settlement type="city">Ithaca</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                  </placeName>
               </hi> Paul W. Gates</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-072-1-a15">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">Rich Harvest: A History of the Grange, 1867–1900.</hi> By D. Sven Nordin,
                    (Jackson: University Press of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName>, 1974. Pp. ix, 273. Notes, tables, bibliography, index. $12.00.)</head>
            <p>More than sixty years ago Solon J. Buck published the traditional, interpretive study, The <hi rend="i">Granger Movement,</hi> on the post-Civil War wave of agrarian discontent. Since that
                    time Buck's assumptions and conclusions have been challenged by other historians including
                    George E. Miller and Gabriel Kolko. Disagreeing with Buck, Miller and Kolko argue convincingly that
                    farmers contributed little to the state and federal regulation of <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> railroads. Miller asserts that in most states regulation of railroads was sponsored by
                    local businessmen who were being threatened by discriminatory railroad rates. Kolko shows that
                    federal regulation was preferred by railroads over state laws to remedy injurious competition or
                    arbitrary regulation by states. D. Sven Nordin accepts Miller's and Kolko's
                    conclusions and advances the thesis that the Patrons of Husbandry, or the Grange, "was
                    primarily a social and educational fraternity for farmers and their families rather than a medium
                    for political and economic activities" (p. viii).</p>
            <pb n="82" id="VAA4025-072-1-088"/>
            <p>Nordin distinguishes between the first and second granger movements. The first movement dates from
                    1867 to 1880 with the peak membership reaching 761,273 in 1875 when <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mou">Missouri</region>
                    </placeName>, Indiana, <placeName>
                  <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>, <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
               </placeName>, and <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="iau">Iowa</region>
                    </placeName> possessed the greatest number of members. The second movement extends after 1880 with
                    far fewer members but with greater relative strength in the eastern region of the nation. Regardless
                    of when farmers joined the organization, they expected, "economic, social, and educational
                    improvements to result from their membership in the Grange" (p. 42). Organized in 1867 by
                    Oliver Hudson Kelley, William Saunders, and others, the Patrons of Husbandry was based upon
                    elaborate secret rituals. Kelley and his cofounders, however, quickly realized that it would take
                    more than ritualism to attract agrarians to their organization and dedicated themselves to dealing
                    with the problems of rural America which was being challenged by industrialism and urbanism.</p>
            <p>More intensively than Buck, Nordin devotes his study to the grangers' nonpolitical
                    activities. He finds that state and local granges involved themselves in bringing better education
                    to the rural population. Vocational agriculture, compulsory school attendance laws, longer school
                    terms, rural high schools, and curricula more compatible with farmers' needs were
                    advocated. The Grange also "played a powerful, positive role in the development of
                    land-grant" universities (p. 83). While the patrons admitted that there were economic
                    advantages derived from the buying and selling of goods through granger operated cooperatives, the
                    Grange, nevertheless, was primarily a social institution which promoted a sense of unity and
                    fellowship among its members. Politics, especially partisan politics, were eschewed by Grange
                    leaders who tried to eliminate partisanship from their programs, denouncing "almost every
                    dissident move aimed at forwarding either parties or would-be office seekers" (p. 183).
                    Nordin, therefore, devotes only one chapter to the relationship of the Grange to the enactment of
                    state and federal regulation of communications and railroads.</p>
            <p>Research for this volume is remarkably complete. The author has examined the wide range of personal
                    and organizational manuscripts, public and private primary documents, and pertinent contemporary
                    scholarship. He took the time, for example, to read eighty-four granger newspapers and <pb n="83" id="VAA4025-072-1-089"/> magazines from which he acquired much information about the activities
                    of state and local grangers. Nordin's book supplements other studies and presents the
                    "full program" of the Grange from 1867 to 1900.</p>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="i">Purdue University, <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">West Lafayette</settlement>
                        </placeName>
               </hi> Donald J. Berthrong</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-072-1-a16">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">A Most Unique Machine: The <placeName>
                            <region type="state" reg="miu">Michigan</region>
                        </placeName> Origins of the American Automobile Industry.</hi> By George S. May. ([Grand
                    Rapids]: William B. Eerdmans Publishing Company, 1975. Pp. 408. Illustrations, bibliographical
                    essay, notes, index. $9.95.)</head>
            <p>This volume is a most welcome addition to the growing literature about the earliest years of the
                    American automobile industry. Professor May is an authority on <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="miu">Michigan</region>
                    </placeName> as well as on automotive history, and he offers here the first monographic results of
                    his thorough research into the murky, often muddied waters of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="miu">Michigan</region>
                    </placeName>'s pre-Model T, pre-General Motors automobile history. Writing with an
                    assurance born of intimate association with the primary and secondary sources, both the well known
                    and the obscure, May challenges many of the conventional interpretations about the industry and its
                    leading figures. He offers instead a demythologized account of the complex origins of automobile
                    manufacturing in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="miu">Michigan</region>
                    </placeName> from the mid-1890s to approximately 1910.</p>
            <p>Despite the fact that biographies for many of the automotive pioneers in and around the Motor City
                    have been published, the story of the industry's true origins has remained unclear and
                    incomplete. May has performed a valuable service in reexamining the record and synthesizing
                    previously untapped original sources with the standard secondary works, thereby presenting a fresh,
                    broad ranging narrative. He carefully picks his way along a path strewn with the wreckages of many
                    unsuccessful manufacturing ventures, adding to the information available on such diverse topics as
                    America's first automobile race (in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                    </placeName>, 1895), the Selden patent and lawsuit, and the formation of the Association of Licensed
                    Automobile Manufacturers, while developing the main themes of his story concerning Ransom E. Olds,
                    Henry Ford, and William C. Durant (founder of General Motors). May has a talent for biographical
                    vignettes and supplies corrective <pb n="84" id="VAA4025-072-1-090"/> details and valuable insights
                    into the characters of even the best known of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="miu">Michigan</region>
                    </placeName> pioneers. The result is a fine collective biography of these men and other lesser known
                    figures such as Charles B. King, Claude Sintz, David D. Buick, Henry Leland, the Dodge brothers,
                    Jonathan D. Maxwell (an Indiana transplant), and dozens more, as well as a perceptive analysis of
                    the factors which led to individual success or failure. Indeed, May gives an unusual amount of
                    attention to those in the latter category—e.g., the Baushkes, William Worth, John
                    Dolson—his information ferreted out from long neglected incorporation and bankruptcy
                    records.</p>
            <p>The book concludes with an attempt to explain why the automobile industry flourished in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="miu">Michigan</region>
                    </placeName>, with May again challenging the conventional wisdom and avoiding easy answers. Rather
                    than Great Lakes transportation, a thriving carriage industry, or available capital—these
                    things existed elsewhere, too—May finds the explanation in the economic transition
                    underway in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="miu">Michigan</region>
                    </placeName> at the turn of the century, the search for new investment opportunities, the supportive
                    role of the state's banking community, and such factors as the existence of a strong gas
                    engine (rather than carriage) industry, which led quite early to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Detroit</settlement>
                    </placeName>'s choice of the eventually dominant power source. Once the basis was laid,
                    moreover, other manufacturers and parts suppliers were drawn to the state, where an open shop
                    reputation and lower labor costs were also attractive. It should be emphasized, too, that <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="miu">Michigan</region>
                    </placeName>'s domination of the industry was not nearly as firmly established in 1909 as
                    it became later. A report of that date lists <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="miu">Michigan</region>
                    </placeName> as having forty-five and Indiana forty-four automobile manufacturing plants; of course,
                    the value of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="miu">Michigan</region>
                    </placeName> product greatly exceeded that of its neighbor. This last point nevertheless underscores
                    the need for a similar study of the industry in Indiana; as May has demonstrated, both through
                    example and impressively full documentation, the sources, scattered though they be, do exist for
                    such a work.</p>
            <p>It is disappointing that a book potentially so good and significant as this one was not subjected to
                    more rigorous editorial supervision. The author frequently is in danger of losing his point if not
                    his readers through long digressions, aside comments, and an often confusing organization. Still <pb n="85" id="VAA4025-072-1-091"/> the book, engagingly written for the most part, is a veritable
                    mine of information and doubtlessly will become the standard source on the automobile's
                    birth and adolescence in the state that is now its primary home.</p>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="i">Indiana University - Purdue, University, <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                        </placeName>
               </hi> Ralph D. Gray</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-072-1-a17">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">Black Migration: Movement North, 1900–1920.</hi> By Florette Henri. (<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Garden City</settlement>
                    </placeName>, N. Y.: Anchor Press/Double-day, 1975. Pp. xi, 419. Notes, bibliography, index.
                    $9.95.)</head>
            <p>The first two decades of the twentieth century were years of ever increasing movement of black people
                    out of the South into northern urban areas. Indeed, during the years 1916–1918 this
                    northward migration reached almost flood proportions as black populations in cities of the East and
                    Midwest increased manifold. This huge exodus from the South, representing "simply the
                    movement of one group of citizens trying to improve their conditions in their own country,"
                    as Robert Abbott of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Defender</hi> put it, greatly affected political, social, and economic developments in
                    cities ranging in size from small ones like <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">East St.
                        Louis</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="ilu">Illinois</region>
               </placeName> to metropolitan
                    areas like <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New York City</settlement>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                    </placeName>. The migration even affected national policy as Congress and federal departments
                    studied its effect upon both the North and the South.</p>
            <p>This is the well known story which Florette Henri retells in <hi rend="i">Black Migration.</hi> Based
                    almost entirely on published secondary sources, <hi rend="i">Black Migration</hi> adds little to an
                    understanding of why blacks left the South or the kinds of conditions they faced in their new homes.
                    Moreover, large sections of the book seem to have little to do with the author's avowed
                    purpose of depicting black people as actors on their own behalf. For example, Henri devotes much
                    space to discussion of the development of racist thought among intellectuals and academics during
                    the period of the Great Migration, but she presents little evidence that this thought came about as
                    a result of the northern movement of blacks. Likewise, her discussion of the period of <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> involvement in World War I speaks largely of the racist attitudes of the American
                    military toward Afro-Americans—an important point, but one that hardly developed because
                    blacks had left the South. <pb n="86" id="VAA4025-072-1-092"/> Surely southern black soldiers fared
                    no better in the military than did northern blacks. Indeed, she writes at length about the response
                    of southern whites to the presence of black troops in their midst, but there is little comment about
                    the attitude of northern whites toward black soldiers.</p>
            <p>Though scholars familiar with the period will find little new in this volume, it does serve a purpose
                    for general readers by bringing together in one place the findings of various individuals who have
                    written on black urbanization. Nonexperts can find in <hi rend="i">Black Migration</hi> a more
                    generalized development of the subject than the specialized studies of Allan H. Spear, Gilbert
                    Osofsky, and others. But even general readers and young students should consult books other than
                    Black Migration on the subject of northward movement of blacks during the first twenty years of the
                    current century.</p>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="i">Indiana University, <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Bloomington</settlement>
                        </placeName>
               </hi> William H. Harris</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-072-1-a18">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">Efficiency and Expansion: Foreign Trade Organization in the Wilson Administration,
                        1913–1921.</hi> By Burton I. Kaufman. (<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Westport</settlement>
                    </placeName>, <placeName>
                        <region type="state">Conn.</region>
                    </placeName>: Greenwood Press, 1974. Pp. xviii, 300. Notes, tables, bibliography, index.
                    $12.50.)</head>
            <p>This aptly titled volume focuses on the efforts of the Wilson administration and businessmen to
                    develop foreign markets. More precisely, Burton I. Kaufman is interested in foreign trade
                    organizations and the effect they had on administration programs and policies. Of particular
                    interest in the prewar years were the extensive activities of the first secretary of commerce,
                    William C. Redfield (a former president of the American Manufacturers' Export Association),
                    and the establishment of the National Foreign Trade Council as spokesman for the entire business
                    community. Efforts to expand American markets continued during the war, as was evidenced by the work
                    of the War Trade Board and the Shipping Board. Their actions, along with those of the Federal
                    Reserve Board, Federal Board for Vocational Education, and the Departments of the Treasury,
                    Agriculture, and Navy represented "something of a milestone in terms of government foreign
                    trade activity" (p. 191). In addition Congress <pb n="87" id="VAA4025-072-1-093"/> passed
                    the Webb-Pomerene Act which exempted export combinations from antitrust legislation. This was
                    followed by the Edge Act which was an acknowledgment on the part of the administration that
                    "future world economic development would be predicated on a business-government
                    relationship" (p. 234). In sum, the Wilson administration saw "the establishment
                    of the modern machinery and business-government relations for the promotion of foreign
                    trade" (p. 260).</p>
            <p>Appropriately, Kaufman gives attention to the kind of relationship that developed between businessmen
                    and the government. While acknowledging that conflict and tension existed, he maintains that
                    historians have emphasized these to the extent of underestimating "the coherence of
                    purpose, the breadth of accomplishment, and, indeed, the historical uniqueness that characterized
                    business-government efforts at foreign trade organization during the Wilson years" (p.
                    xvi).</p>
            <p>The impetus behind these organizational activities was twofold. Like their contemporaries, advocates
                    of trade were greatly influenced by the "gospel of efficiency"; equally
                    significant was the influence of Europe on their thinking. It furnished the model they wished to
                    emulate (<placeName>
                        <country reg="gw">Germany</country>
                    </placeName>) and the foe they feared (Great Britain). With regard to this latter point Kaufman
                    correctly reminds one of the extensive Anglo-American friction that occurred over Latin American
                    markets.</p>
            <p>One striking feature of the work is the great interest expansionists had in Latin America and their
                    relative lack of interest in East Asia. While trading statistics bear this out, one nevertheless
                    wonders if the interest in developing Asian markets was that slight. Kaufman quotes Willard Straight
                    on a number of occasions, but he fails to indicate that Straight was primarily interested in Asian
                    markets and was vice president of the American International Corporation in charge of Chinese
                    affairs. The author might also have given more attention to the interest in trade with Russia which
                    prior to the Bolshevik Revolution "had been widely regarded as an important future market
                    for the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>" (p. 200n). Still, there is much in this work to recommend. It is well
                    organized and clearly written.</p>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="i">
                  <placeName>
                            <region type="state">Western Illinois</region>
                        </placeName> University, Macomb</hi> Michael Horacek</byline>
         </div>
         <pb n="88" id="VAA4025-072-1-094"/>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-072-1-a19">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">The World between the Wars, 1919–39: An Economist's View.</hi> By
                    Joseph S. Davis. (<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Baltimore</settlement>
                    </placeName>: The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1975. Pp. viii, 436. Notes, tables, index.
                    $16.00.)</head>
            <p>An economist of reputation and one time professor at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Harvard</settlement>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Stanford</settlement>
                    </placeName> whose professional career dates to 1919, the first year of the period treated in the
                    present study, Joseph S. Davis has written a disappointing book. The title indicates that he has
                    considered "the world" in the years between the two world wars. As the work
                    unfolds, however, it is clear that he was interested only in the industrialized areas of the world,
                    i.e., the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>, Europe, and <placeName>
                        <country reg="ja">Japan</country>
                    </placeName>. The title also indicates that the book abounds with the views of a distinguished
                    economist. Alas, the piece is largely a textbook like survey of events from 1919 to 1939 overlaid
                    with sections detailing economic happenings in the period. Apart from occasional observations that
                    some of the assumptions of John Maynard Keynes in the early 1920s were mistaken and that Herbert
                    Hoover's wisdom regarding the Great Depression was superior to Franklin
                    Roosevelt's, the views of the author are kept in the background until the final seventy
                    pages of the book. And in those concluding pages the author offers few thoughts which seem
                    particularly profound. He enumerates, for example, some of the oft noted weaknesses which afflicted
                    the American economy in the 1920s and observes that national leaders failed to treat those
                    weaknesses with sufficient seriousness, points out that there was a great deal of corruption in the
                    high echelons of American business in the period, and asserts that "economic and political
                    intelligence" before and during the Great Depression was inadequate.</p>
            <p>Still, Davis has surveyed a substantial range of source materials for the economic sections of his
                    book, particularly contemporary articles in scholarly and business journals. (There is little
                    evidence that he himself analyzed much raw data on economic developments during the period, although
                    as an active economist at that time he must have done some of that sort of thing.) And therein lies
                    the principal virtue of the book: it offers an extensive sampling of the contemporary opinions of
                    presumed experts on economic conditions and happenings in the period between the wars, especially
                        <pb n="89" id="VAA4025-072-1-095"/> down to the time of Roosevelt's inauguration as
                    president. (The book is surprisingly thin in its treatment of the economic effects of
                    Roosevelt's New Deal.)</p>
            <p>In summary, then, this book is not one that many readers will want to plow through from beginning to
                    end—if for no other reason than the fact that the author's prose style is so
                    painfully uninspired. But should an individual be interested in what the optimists in America were
                    saying about the economy in the years before the stock market collapse of 1929 or what people were
                    saying about economic prospects in the aftermath of said collapse, he (or she) might find the Davis
                    book useful.</p>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="i">Indiana University, <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Bloomington</settlement>
                        </placeName>
               </hi> John Edward Wiltz</byline>
         </div>
         <pb n="[90]" id="VAA4025-072-1-096"/>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-072-1-a20">
            <head>Review Notices<hi rend="sup">∗</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">The Old Northwest: A Journal of Regional Life and Letters.</hi> Edited by Dwight L.
                    Smith and David L. Frazier. Vol. I, Nos. 1, 2, 3. (<placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Oxford</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
               </placeName>: Miami
                    University, March, June, September, 1975. Magazine.) The editor has received copies of the three
                    initial issues of <hi rend="i">The Old Northwest,</hi> published by Miami University,
                            <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Oxford</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
               </placeName>. This new quarterly, coedited by Dwight L. Smith and David L.
                    Frazier, is "devoted to study of the culture, early to recent, of the area included in the
                    old Northwest Territory." The content of these early issues conforms to this statement.
                    There has long been a need for a scholarly quarterly of this kind. <hi rend="i">The Old
                    Northwest</hi> will hopefully merit and continue to receive a generous response from the general
                    public as well as from scholars, libraries, and historical societies. (Subscriptions are:
                    $5.00 annually within the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>; $5.50 in <placeName>
                        <country reg="-cn">Canada</country>
                    </placeName>; and $6.00 in other countries. All correspondence should be directed to <hi rend="i">The Old Northwest,</hi> Miami University, 244 Upham Hall, Box 165,
                            <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Oxford</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
               </placeName> 45056.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Masonic Historical Markers in Indiana.</hi> ([<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Franklin</settlement>
                    </placeName>]: Grand Lodge Historical Commission, Grand Lodge F. &amp; A. M. of Indiana, 1975.
                    Pp. 28. Illustrations. Pamphlet, free in limited quantities.) Describing and illustrating about two
                    dozen historical markers regarding Masonry in Indiana, this brief publication indicates quite a bit
                    about Indiana's beginnings in the pioneer era as well as items of significance regarding
                    the genesis of Masonry among Hoosiers. (The pamphlet may be ordered from Dwight L. Smith, Grand
                    Lodge F. &amp; A. M. of Indiana, 525 N. <placeName>
                  <region type="state" reg="ilu">Illinois</region>, <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
               </placeName>, Indiana
                    46204.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Keepers of the Council Fire: A Brief History of the Wyandot Indians.</hi> By Robert E.
                    Smith. (Joplin, Mo.: Social Science Department, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mou">Missouri</region>
                    </placeName> Southern State College, 1974. Pp. 13. Selected bibliography. Pamphlet,
                    $.50.) As the subtitle indicates, this booklet is a brief history of the Wyandot Indians.
                    It touches on highlights of tribal events and wanderings from the Saint Lawrence Valley in the 1500s
                    to the Wyandot's present scattered locations in the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>
                    <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">∗</hi> All review notices were written by Donald F. Carmony who
                            retired as editor of the <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of History</hi> effective January 1,
                            1976.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="91" id="VAA4025-072-1-097"/> and <placeName>
                        <country reg="-cn">Canada</country>
                    </placeName>. (This pamphlet can be purchased by writing Robert W. Smith, Box 107, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mou">Missouri</region>
                    </placeName> Southern State College, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Joplin</settlement>
                    </placeName>, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mou">Missouri</region>
                    </placeName> 64801.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Forty Years Among the Indians: A Descriptive History of the Long and Busy Life of
                        Jeremiah Hubbard.</hi> [By Jeremiah Hubbard.] Reprint. (<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Knightstown</settlement>
                    </placeName>, <placeName>
                        <region type="state">Ind.</region>
                    </placeName>: The Bookmark and <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Back Creek</settlement>
                    </placeName> Monthly Meeting of Friends, 1975. Pp. 211. Illustrations, index. Clothbound,
                    $12.50; paperbound, $8.50, plus $.50 for mail orders.) Jeremiah
                    Hubbard, 1837–1915, taught a number of schools in Indiana from the late 1850s to the
                    early 1870s, then spent the remainder of his life as a missionary among the Indians of the West and
                    Southwest. This book is a republication of Hubbard's reminiscences which originally
                    appeared about 1913, plus a forward and an index by Ralph D. Kirkpatrick, but whether it is a
                    photocopy of the original or a new setting of type is not clear. Hubbard offers worthwhile comments
                    about education and perhaps even more significant comments about his conversion to the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Quaker</settlement>
                    </placeName> faith and his role in introducing preaching, singing, the mourners' bench, and
                    other revivalistic practices among the Quakers of Indiana. Most of the book, however, concerns
                    Hubbard's missionary efforts among the Indians, efforts motivated by his belief
                    "that the only way to civilize the Indian is to christianize him" (p. 31). (Orders
                    for the book should be sent to The Bookmark, P. O. Box 74, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Knightstown</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indiana 46148.)</p>
            <p>"American Independence, 1776, and the Bicentennial, 1976." <hi rend="i">Indiana
                        Social Studies Quarterly.</hi> Edited by Richard Wires. Vol. XXVIII, No. 1. (<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Muncie</settlement>
                    </placeName>: Ball State University, Spring, 1975. Pp. 77. Magazine, $2.00.) Though
                    giving some information about the role of George Washington, George Rogers Clark, and women in the
                    American Revolution, most of this publication suggests sources of aid and ways for observing the
                    American Revolution Bicentennial in elementary and secondary schools. Sources are indicated for
                    films and related media aids, ideas are presented for use by teachers, comment is given about
                    historic places in Indiana which might be visited, and a "George Rogers Clark Simulation
                    Game" is included for teachers and students who would like to try to understand better
                    Clark's western campaign of 1778–1779 by playing a game based on his heroic
                    effort.</p>
            <pb n="92" id="VAA4025-072-1-098"/>
            <p>"The American Revolution." <hi rend="i">Indiana Social Studies Quarterly.</hi>
                    Edited by Richard Wires. Vol. XXVII, No. 3. (<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Muncie</settlement>
                    </placeName>: Ball State University, Winter, 1974–75. Pp. 103. Magazine,
                    $2.00.) Here is a potpourri of items offering a variety of views about the events and
                    influences leading to the American Revolution. Attention is also given to various personalities,
                    aspects, and results of the Revolution. Guest edited by Althea L. Stoeckel of the Ball State
                    University History Department, this publication is a timely contribution to the American Revolution
                    Bicentennial.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">
                  <geogName>Mississippi</geogName> And <geogName>Ohio Rivers</geogName>, Southern and
                        Western Inland Steam Vessels.</hi> Drawings by Samuel Ward Stanton. [Edited by Elizabeth Stanton
                    Anderson.] ([Upper Montclair, N. J.: H. Kneeland Whiting], 1974. Pp. 40. Illustrations. Paperbound,
                    $3.50.) This selection of drawings of steamboats which plied the
                    <geogName>Ohio</geogName> and <geogName>Mississippi</geogName> river systems between the Civil War
                    era and the end of the nineteenth century provides a sampling of noteworthy drawings from the hand
                    of Samuel Ward Stanton. (The booklet can be ordered from H. Kneeland Whiting, 63 Beverly Road, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Upper Montclair</settlement>
                    </placeName>, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="nju">New Jersey</region>
                    </placeName> 07043.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Letters From the Promised Land: Swedes in America, 1840–1914.</hi> By H.
                    Arnold Barton. (<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Minneapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>: University of <placeName>
                        <country reg="mnu">Minnesota</country>
                    </placeName> Press, for the Swedish Pioneer Historical Society, 1975. Pp. vi, 344. Illustrations,
                    map, appendix, notes, select bibliography, sources and credits, index. $16.50.) Barton
                    describes and explains the conditions which produced considerable Swedish immigration to the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>, 1840–1914. The author gives the historical context for this exodus of
                    Swedes, but in the main the immigrants tell their own story in contemporary letters and related
                    documents.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">The Booker T. Washington Papers.</hi> Volume 4, <hi rend="i">1894–98.</hi>
                    Edited by Louis R. Harlan; assistant editors, Stuart B. Kaufman, Barbara S. Kraft, and Raymond W.
                    Smock. (<placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Urbana</settlement>
                    </placeName>: University of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ilu">Illinois</region>
                    </placeName> Press, 1975. Pp. xxx, 593. Notes, bibliography, index. $17.50.) This volume
                    covers a key period in the life of Booker T. Washington. By 1895 <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> had achieved national prominence among whites and blacks alike. According to the
                    editor, many whites, both <pb n="93" id="VAA4025-072-1-099"/> northern and southern, believed
                    "that he had conceded to white supremacy more than he had. Blacks, on the other hand, in
                    many cases believed that he had conceded more than he should" (p. xxi). <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName>'s comments on the Plessy <hi rend="i">v.</hi> Ferguson landmark case in 1896,
                    which established the "separate but equal" principle for public accomodations and
                    education as well as for transportation, however, indicate the atmosphere of the day and explain the
                    very restricted and extremely biased context in which he espoused his views (pp.
                186–87).</p>
         </div>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-072-1-a21">
            <head>Back Issues of <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of History</hi> Desired</head>
            <p>Michael L. Cook, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Evansville</settlement>
                    </placeName>, in order to complete his personal files, is seeking the following back issues of the
                        <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of History</hi> in the original bindings: all issues
                    1904–1907, 1910–1915, and 1921. He does not want reprint editions.
                    Correspondence concerning these issues should be sent to Michael L. Cook, 3318 Wimberg Avenue, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Evansville</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indiana 47712.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <pb n="94" id="VAA4025-072-1-100"/>
         <pb n="[]" id="VAA4025-072-1-101"/>
         <pb n="[]" id="VAA4025-072-1-102"/>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI.2>