<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "imh_issue.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="VAA4025-027-1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Indiana Magazine of History</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoded by</resp>
               <name>Aptara Inc.</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <date>2007</date>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>Copyright 2007 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
               <p>Indiana University provides the information contained in this file for non-commercial,
        personal, or research use only. All other use, including but not limited to commercial or
        scholarly reproductions, redistribution, publication or transmission, whether by electronic
        means or otherwise, without prior written permission of the copyright holder is strictly
        prohibited.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Indiana Magazine of History</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title>Indiana Magazine of History</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Indiana University Department of History in cooperation with the Indiana
                                Historical Society</publisher>
                     <date>1931</date>
                     <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="volume">27</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="pages">1-81</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07-23</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Annette D. Richmond</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Split VAA4025-027-1-a05 into three pieces; the first was left as type scholarlyArticle; the second
                    was created as type scholarlyArticle with id VAA4025-027-1-a15; the third was created as type
                    scholarlyArticle with id VAA4025-027-1-a16. Independent headers were created. Changed
                    VAA4025-027-1-a13 from scholarlyArticle to editorialMaterial. Corrected footnote, blockquote, and
                    table formatting. Encoded letter.</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n="[]" id="VAA4025-027-1-001"/>
         <pb n="[]" id="VAA4025-027-1-002"/>
         <pb n="[]" id="VAA4025-027-1-003"/>
         <pb n="[]" id="VAA4025-027-1-004"/>
      </front>
      <body>
         <pb n="[1]" id="VAA4025-027-1-005"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-027-1-a01">
            <head>Kin Hubbard</head>
            <byline>J. H<hi rend="sc">ARLEY</hi> N<hi rend="sc">ICHOLS</hi>
            </byline>
            <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>"You ought to join the Colonial Bridge Club," said Mrs. Leghorn Tharp, when
                        Tell Binkley complained that the newspapers wuzn' printin' any jokes about a
                        certain little car that's on the market. "I heard a shot an' a scream
                        in the hall, but I wuz just listenin' to Amos an' Andy an' thought no
                        more of it," testified Mrs. Tilford Moots's brother, questioned in regard to
                        the murder of his wife.</p>
                </quote>
            <p>With these words the earthly existence of Abe Martin and his troop of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Brown county</region>
                    </placeName> neighbors, friends, and relatives, many of whom lived at a distance from the scenes of
                    their native haunts! came to an end. More than a quarter of a century had elapsed since Abe, with
                    his head full of homely wisdom and his trousers tucked in his high-topped boots, had sprung
                    full-grown from the fertile brain of his creator. During this time, many had doubtless come to
                    regard him as a permanent feature of the universe, had smiled and chuckled and at times laughed
                    uproariously as they saw life reflected in the quaint sayings and subtle observations of the <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Brown county</region>
                    </placeName> philosopher.</p>
            <p>Frank McKinney (Kin) Hubbard, the creator of Abe Martin, was born in Bellefontaine, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName>, in 1868. He came of a family of newspaper men (and women), his father Thomas Hubbard,
                    being the owner and publisher of the Bellefontaine <hi rend="i">Examiner.</hi> This is a weekly
                    journal which has belonged to the Hubbard family since 1830, and is now published by a brother and
                    sister of the late humorist. Receiving a public school education <pb n="2" id="VAA4025-027-1-006"/>
                    in his native town, young Hubbard found employment in his father's newspaper office, and
                    became, as he himself says, a fair printer.<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Later, when his father was
                    appointed postmaster in the first <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cleveland</settlement>
                    </placeName> Administration, he took his station at the general delivery window, and remained at
                    this employment for five years with such respites from a not too arduous task as would enable hirq
                    to satisfy an occasional wanderlust or to exercise a talent for amateur acting, a form of
                    entertainment of which he was inordinately fond.</p>
            <p>While more or less regularly employed in this way, he missed no opportunity, we may be sure, to meet
                    and observe people at close range, and to become familiar with human eccentricities, a knowledge of
                    which formed the basis of his humor. His drawing, too, was not wholly neglected. For this form of
                    expression he had a natural talent which he first used with telling effect in the campaign of 1884.
                    His artistic ability was, however, uncultivated, and it was for this purpose that he entered the
                    Jefferson Art School in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Detroit</settlement>
                    </placeName>.</p>
            <p>It is the old story. The desire to become an artist was present, but perseverance and the steady
                    grind necessary for the mastery of an elaborate technique were conspicuously absent. "I
                    attended three forenoons and became discouraged. It was too tame," Kin explains, when
                    referring to his experience at the art school. He did not return home at once, however. "I
                    bought a nifty suit of clothes," he relates, "a loud plaid cape overcoat, a close
                    reefed brown derby, and a massive buckhorn cane (I already had a large diamond brooch of shallow
                    straw-colored stones) and I remained in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Detroit</settlement>
                    </placeName> some months stalling around and dividing my time with an English artist named Hugh
                    Capper, on the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Detroit</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Journal</hi>, and the theaters. My hair was dark and long and unmanageable, and if I
                    had been ten years older I would have readily passed for an actor of rare ability." And
                    "that was the idea," he informs us.</p>
            <p>Returning to his home in the spring (why, we may imagine) our would-be actor resumed his position at
                    the general delivery window, and sought recreation and diversion in amateur theatricals which won
                    for him no inconsiderable reputation as a black-face comedian. A letter written to a friend in <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">1</hi> The facts for the brief biographical sketch here presented have,
                            unless otherwise indicated, been taken from the short autobiography printed in the <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                            </placeName>
                            <hi rend="i">News</hi>, January 26, 1930.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="3" id="VAA4025-027-1-007"/>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, describing one of these amateur engagements, and embellished with water-color
                    sketches, secured for him a position on the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">News.</hi> Referring to his qualifications for even this modest position, he says:
                    "I was as well qualified for a place on the editorial staff or in the circulation
                    department so far as ability was concerned. But I was taken on at a salary of twelve dollars per
                    week, the editor and owner remarking as we closed the deal, ‘I reckon you've got
                    to live.’"</p>
            <p>This was in the year 1891. He remained with the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">News</hi> during the next three years, but the work of this period left his reputation
                    as a newspaper man very little enhanced. "I was not getting anywhere as a newspaper artist,
                    but I was storing up a vast amount of theatrical knowledge, and incidently accumulating a fine
                    assortment of canes and overgaiters," he writes with reference to his life during these
                    years.</p>
            <p>Severing his connection with the <hi rend="i">News</hi> in 1894, it was not until 1901 that he was
                    again identified with that paper. In the meantime we find him in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Chattanooga</settlement>
                    </placeName> driving a mule team hitched tandem to a baking wagon, copying reprint for the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Tribune</hi>, keeping gate for a summer amusement park at a salary of eleven dollars
                    per week, and at work on the Mansfield (<placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName>) <hi rend="i">News.</hi> He remained in this last position "quite a
                    while," but there were grave. objections to it. There was no chance to dress like an actor
                    in Mansfield and, worse yet, the manager did not accept theater passes. Accordingly, Hubbard gave up
                    the position and returned to Bellefontaine where he once more engaged in amateur theatricals.</p>
            <p>There was naturally a feeling among his immediate relatives that a young man rapidly nearing thirty
                    should have some visible and permanent means of support. Significant insinuations to this effect
                    seem to have been, on occasion, uttered audibly. Kin quotes his brother as saying to him once when
                    he was dressed in minstrel attire: "There you are all blacked up with your uniform and
                    tambourine, but you can't do a thing. You can't dance and you can't sing
                    and you're not funny." We are by no means certain that this criticism was just,
                    for William Herschell, referring to an association with him at a somewhat later period, says:
                    "A group of newspaper comrades at that time had a habit of meeting nightly in the northeast
                    corner of the Dennison House. We called it the <pb n="4" id="VAA4025-027-1-008"/> ‘Amen
                    Corner,’ for few amens ever were said there because those fellows were jovial souls and
                    none merrier than Kin Hubbard. His wit and his ability to imitate national figures, such as actors
                    and politicians, kept us all in a roar."<hi rend="sup">2</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The criticism of the more practical brother, nevertheless, must have had the desired effect, for we
                    find Kin accepting a position with the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Sun</hi>, and remaining with this paper until he became re-identified with the <hi rend="i">News</hi> in 1901. "The salary was small," he explains, "but
                    the theater passes were frequent, and I really made more progress as an artist during my two years
                    on the <hi rend="i">Sun</hi> than I had in all the years before."</p>
            <p>Three years after his return to the <hi rend="i">News</hi>, fortune began to smile upon him. How much
                    of this was due to the woman in the case, we are unable to say, but we know that he was married to
                    Josephine Jackson in 1905. The immediate occasion for his change of fortune was the presidential
                    campaign of 1904. During this contest he accompanied the special trains of William Jennings Bryan
                    and Charles W. Fairbanks on extended tours through Indiana. Concerning these trips and their
                    immediate consequences he writes: "At the close of each day during those trips I made
                    pictures of scenes and incidents and statesmen encountered on the tour and mailed them to the <hi rend="i">News.</hi> At the end of the campaign I had a surplus of material. My system was still
                    full of things I had seen and heard, and I asked to be allowed to work off some of them after the
                    election. I drew a character which I called Abe Martin, and for several days I wrote two connected
                    but unrelated sentences bearing on politics and things in general, and published them beneath the
                    picture. This caused some favorable comment, and it was decided to continue it." From time
                    to time, new characters were introduced to say things that Abe was not likely to think about, and
                    thus in due time appeared Tilford Moots, Lafe Bud, Constable Newt Plum, Gran'ma Pash, Tel
                    Binkley, Fawn Lippincut, Dr. Mopps, Stew Nugent, Pinky Kerr, Tawney Apple, Ex-Editur Cale Fluhart,
                    and a host of others—"veritable figures snatched bodily from the rural
                    landscape," as Meredith Nicholson characterized them.</p>
            <p>Success was spontaneous and immediate. "As the <hi rend="i">News</hi> readers got on to
                    Abe," the humorist writes, "he grew in popularity, <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">2</hi>
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                            </placeName>
                            <hi rend="i">News</hi>, January 26, 1930.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="5" id="VAA4025-027-1-009"/> and after a few months I could not have stopped him if I had
                    wanted to." Some time later Hubbard introduced a new feature which he called
                    "Short Furrows." This feature appeared weekly in the Saturday issues of the <hi rend="i">News</hi>, and in it the characters discussed "questions of deep and grave
                    import" in a more extended and connected fashion than they were wont to do in the daily
                    contributions of "Abe Martin." As his writing increased in popularity, it was
                    syndicated to other journals until the time of his death, which occurred on December 26, 1930, it
                    was appearing in more than three hundred newspapers and magazines. All this, together with books
                    which he published annually containing the sayings of "Abe Martin," brought fame
                    and fortune to the author.</p>
            <p>Strangely enough, however, Hubbard was not known widely by his own name. So retiring and shy of
                    publicity was he that millions to whom "Abe Martin" was a household word never
                    knew the name of his creator. All this the humorist bore like the true philosopher that he was, and
                    when asked whether he had not at some time been tempted to go to one of the big <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                    </placeName> newspapers, replied: "Oh, I've had some flirtations occasionally. But
                    I think I'm like a friend of mine whose uncle wanted him to go to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Denver</settlement>
                    </placeName> to take charge of a drug store. He said. ‘I'd rather stay here
                    where I'm known and can get in the band.’" In regard to being known, he
                    is quoted as saying: "Even here in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> I often meet old acquaintances who ask me what I‘m doing now, and scarcely a
                    day passes that I'm not introduced to somebody who never heard of me. But I don't
                    care," he added, "The world is full of people who don't even know who
                    Tony Pastor was."<hi rend="sup">3</hi>
            </p>
            <p>"A kind of comical mixture of hoss-sense and no sense at all," was the manner in
                    which Riley characterized Hubbard's humor. He observed society with an eye for
                    incongruities, and made his sage observations through the medium of "Abe Martin"
                    or through others of the numerous characters associated with the rural philosopher. He kept abreast
                    of the times and remarked about things people were most likely to be thinking about at the
                    particular moment. Politics, prohibition, the crime wave, farm problems, business depressions,
                    prosperity, were subjects for numerous keen and penetrating remarks. Domestic relations, society,
                    fashions, education, and similar <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">3</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">American Magazine</hi>, April, 1924. Reprinted in the <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                            </placeName>
                            <hi rend="i">News</hi>, January 26, 1980.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="6" id="VAA4025-027-1-010"/> human interests were also objects of attention. At other times,
                    he was content to make observations apropos of little or nothing in particular.</p>
            <p>"Fawn Lippincut, loveliest of June brides, is home on a parole," he could announce
                    innocently but significantly; or "Mrs. Art Purviance is vistin' her husband
                    an' babies." Or again, "Artie Small has quit goin' with
                    th' girls till he kin save enough t' marry one." And so on <hi rend="i">ad infiniturn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>"Farming," he wrote, "is good exercise, an' when that's
                    said, all's said." "A farmer," he declared, "is at the
                    mercy of the elements, droughts, late springs, wet summers, early falls, hail, lightnin',
                    frost, not to mention slumps." "At no time is he safe. Even when
                    ever'thing is breakin' fine, the danger o' bein' gored by an
                    angry bull is allus imminent." At another time, he remarked that "when we do see a
                    nice, well-kept, pros-perous-lookin' farm we find that it's the plaything
                    o' some town phtocrat." This tendency; in fact, he saw manifested among the
                    farmers themselves. As an example, he cited the case of Farmer Jake Bentley who had
                    "accepted the janitor-ship o' Apple Grove Schoolhouse, an' will make
                    agriculture a plaything." So great an encumbrance did the possession of land become that
                    Abe found and repeated this bit of news: "Lile Tharp, whose father left him two farms, has
                    petitioned t'have th' will set aside, declarin' his father must have been
                    crazy." Approaching the problem from another point of view, he made this sly thrust:
                    "Friends don't get you nothin'. Look at the farmer." All this is
                    viewed as part and parcel of a more comprehensive situation. "About th' only thing
                    we have left," he says, "that actually discriminates in favor o'
                    th' plain people is th' stork."</p>
            <p>"It's all right t' aspire to office, but when a feller begins t'
                    perspire fer one it's time t' watch out." This choice piece of humor
                    probably represented the author's own conviction in the field of politics. Although a
                    partisan he did not desire office and rarely did he participate actively in a political contest.<hi rend="sup">4</hi> He was always interested, however, and in this connection we arerfavored with
                    some of his best bits of humor. Attempting to explain the election of 1928, he called attention to
                    what was the trouble, saying: "that indescribable somethin' or <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">4</hi>
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                            </placeName>
                            <hi rend="i">News</hi>, January 26, 1930. In the last years of his life he departed from his
                            usual custom and served on the election board. In 1928 he managed the congressional campaign
                            of Louis Ludlow.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="7" id="VAA4025-027-1-011"/> other that us Democrats allus rely on to swing the election
                    failed to show up." It was a mistake, moreover, to have gone after the farmer vote.
                    "Farmers are Republicans fer th' same reason they're farmers."
                    The trouble with them is "they don't stay mad long enough to scare either
                    political party." And then there was gran'maw Bentley who died recently at the
                    ripe age of 104. "She'd never seen a wheel chair until Al Smith ran fer the
                    presidency." Nor was the election due to a lack of wets: "Ther's enough
                    wets in this country t' elect three presidents, but; ther's no party resourceful
                    enough t' huddle ‘em." And besides "why are only Democrats
                    ever asked how wet they are?" In view of all this, President Hoover surely undertook a
                    man's job in his attempt to make the country dry and the farmers happy at the same time.</p>
            <p>In the realm of domestic matters the humor of Hubbard is irresistible: "The Kite divorce
                    case was settled out o' court, Mrs. Kite agreein' to let Mr. Kite have all the
                    children if he'd pay fer new brake linin's fer her car." Likewise the
                    Larks are divorced but apparently on somewhat different grounds. "I never dreamed the
                    marriage would stick," a woman remarked, "He's a good enough feller, but
                    he doesn't know a thing about cookin."' Beyond a doubt things may go to
                    the other extreme: "I can allus tell a feller who has married a good housekeeper by the way
                    he brightens up when I speak kindly to him." And again there is another possibility:
                    "I knowed they lived comfortably but I didn't know he wuz rich," said
                    Lafe Bud when he heard that Mrs. Tilford Moot's nephew was tired of his wife. On the other
                    hand, Squire Marsh Mallow was of the opinion that "two-thirds o' th'
                    couples who git a divorce still love one another, but hain't got the price t' put
                    it over."</p>
            <p>As to the relative deadliness of the two sexes he says: "When a husband gits tired of a wife
                    he deserts her, but when a wife gits tired of a husband she murders him." He offers proof
                    to corroborate this statement from a woman, who confided: "Oh, she'd have been rid
                    o' him long ago, but he's got insomnia an' she can't ketch him
                    asleep." It was a knowledge of this feminine trait that led the humoroist to conclude that
                    "it's better to change your attitude an' pay heart balm than to be dug up
                    later an' be analyzed."</p>
            <p>Speaking of women's fashions, he says: "Figures don't <pb n="8" id="VAA4025-027-1-012"/> lie, but there's a lot of them on th' streets that
                    look a little too open and above board." This, to be sure, has its advantage: "I
                    used to think women wuz all alike, but now I can see ther's quite a difference in
                    ‘em." Elsewhere he speaks more specifically: "If you wanted a wife with
                    lots of backbone, the past summer wuz th' time to pick her out." There was still
                    another advantage: "A feller kin tell across the street whether he loves a girl or not,
                    an' ther's no occasion or excuse fer long-dram-out engagements. There she is, you
                    kin see what you're gittin', take her or leave her alone." It's
                    a poor rule, however, that won't work both ways. "You can't have a
                    divorce, fer you could see what you wuz gittin' when you married her," roared
                    Judge Pusey from the bench.</p>
            <p>Nor is fashion confined to the clothes. Miss Tawney Apple has several positions in view if she can
                    make the dimensions, and Mrs. Em Moots, having discarded black, offers to remodel to suit the right
                    party. This is a condition, however, for which women are not wholly; responsible: "Women
                    never git th' benefit o' th' doubt. If they don't look good,
                    they might as well be bad." The experience of Miss Lummie Kite is unique in this respect
                    since "she's th' first stubby stout that's caught on here in
                    three years."</p>
            <p>The prohibition question Abe viewed dispassionately but with considerable amusement. He saw it,
                    moreover, in all its ramifications. That there is such a thing as temperance is certain. Mrs. Joe
                    Kite's brother is our authority. "In all th' years I've been in
                    Washin'ton," he testifies, "I've never seen any lit up Siamese
                    Twins." Striking at the heart of the enforcement question, the philosopher declares that
                    "no community is dryer than its officials, an' that's rarely very
                    dry." Nor is it particularly disconcerting to the bootlegger that only total abstainers are
                    to be used in enforcing the law. "Jest because a feller don't drink is no sign he
                    won't listen to reason." The trouble with the Volstead Act has generally been
                    attributed to the teeth. Just the same "while they're X-rayin'
                    th' teeth it won't hurt to examine th' eyes." "Ez
                    Pash," to take an example, "has winked at th' dry law so long he looks
                    like he was paralyzed on th' left side." Nor is the Hoover commission likely to
                    help. "All that I kin git out o' the Wickersham position," Abe declared,
                    near the end, "is that the distinguished <pb n="9" id="VAA4025-027-1-013"/> jurist seems
                    t' feel that if we'd let ‘em have it the problem o'
                    keepin' ‘em from gittin' it would be greatly simplified."</p>
            <p>"Few things make us feel finer than havin' our judgment vindicated," is a
                    fine example of scores of droll remarks that show the humorists' insight into human nature.
                    He was especially adept in discovering manifestations of human vanities and he took delight in
                    exposing them. Parodying Shakespeare, he soberly reflected that "some folks are born great,
                    others achieve greatness, an' still others wear a wide braid on ther nose
                    glasses." "The average important person" he saw as "just an
                    ordinary human bein' reined up," and quoted Dr. Mopps as observing that
                    "barely seven per cent o' people wearing large fierce lookin' shell
                    rimmed glasses are really indispensable." Elsewhere he declared that "after many
                    years o' th' closest observation, I'm more convinced than ever that
                    th' louder a feller laughs at nothin' th' more pop'lar he
                    is." He saw a real inconvenience, moreover, in over-reaching oneself, for
                    "nothin' makes a feller round-shouldered quicker'n gittin' out
                    of his class an' tryin' t' hold up his end." Frankness he liked:
                    "AS between th' feller that gits back at me an' th' feller that
                    closes up like a clam, I'll take the former." Again he makes this revealing
                    comment: "I like little children ‘cause they tear out as soon as they git what
                    they want."</p>
            <p>And thus Frank McKinney Hubbard lived and made us laugh and see the truth. "The funniest guy
                    in America", Will Rogers called him, and "as quaint and droll as Josh Billings and
                    Artemus Ward ever dared to be" wrote George Ade with reference to the character,
                    "Abe Martin."<hi rend="sup">5</hi> But Hubbard was more than funny. "He
                    was a true humorist," says the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">News</hi> editorially, "and being a true humorist, was, as he must have been,
                    a profound philosopher." As has been said of Mark Twain, he was different. Whether his
                    sayings will provoke laughter in an age unfamiliar with the things he observed and wrote about, time
                    only can tell. This much is certain. He understood his own age, and had the genius to mirror it in
                    quaint phrasing, which not only amused the generation of which he was a part, but deeply instructed
                    those keen enough to get his meaning. What more could be asked of a man?</p>
            <list type="footnotes">
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">5</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">American Magazine</hi>, May, 1910.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <pb n="[10]" id="VAA4025-027-1-014"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-027-1-a02">
            <head>Indiana and Her History<hi rend="sup">∗</hi>
            </head>
            <byline>J<hi rend="sc">AMES</hi> A<hi rend="sc">LBERT</hi> W<hi rend="sc">OODBURN</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>Our country's history has witnessed a conflict of loyalties. When the Civil War began, in
                    1861, General Winfield T. Scott and General George H. Thomas, two distinguished Virginians, retained
                    their loyalty to the Union of the States, to a unified Republic. General Robert E. Lee and General
                    "Stonewall" Jackson, deeming it impossible to draw their swords against their
                    native state, maintained their state allegiance and cast their lots with the Southern Confederacy.</p>
            <p>John C. Breckinridge of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName>, Vice-President of the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> up to the outbreak of the war, denying his allegiance both to his state and the nation,
                    went into the Confederate army. He went the way his sympathies led him toward a slave-holding
                    Confederacy. Kentuckians were pretty evenly divided in their army enlistments.</p>
            <p>The Union men in forty counties in Western <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> seeded from the "Old Dominion," created a new commonwealth, and
                    although old <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> could not fairly be said to have been divided by her own consent, the new state was
                    admitted, as a war measure, into, the Union. Those were days of conflicting loyalties in which men
                    had to choose, as they may never have to choose again.</p>
            <p>Behind this old state loyalty, there was a natural and historical background. For two hundred years <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> had been either a self-governing colony of the British Empire or a commonwealth of the
                    American Union. In her colonial days she was as independent of the other colonies on the Atlantic
                    seaboard as she was of <placeName>
                        <country reg="-cn">Canada</country>
                    </placeName> or <placeName>
                        <country reg="bb">Barbados</country>
                    </placeName>. She had been built up by common sacrifices of her citizens, through common trials and
                    tribulations. She had a history in which her people had come to have great satisfaction and pride.
                    "When I speak of my country" said John Randolph of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Roanoke</settlement>
                    </placeName>, "I mean the Commonwealth of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName>." Whenever that patriotic Virginian signed a hotel registry in Europe, it was
                    always as "John Randolph of <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Roanoke</settlement>,
                            <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
               </placeName>." The <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> never came into his affections, hardly into his vision or recognition, certainly not
                    into his first political allegiance. To the South <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">∗</hi> This Paper was read at the Centennial Meeting of the
                            Indiana Historical Society, December 12, 1930, Claypool Hotel, <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                            </placeName>.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="11" id="VAA4025-027-1-015"/> of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName>, Calhoun and Hayne were Carolinians before they were Americans.</p>
            <p>It was the same with <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mau">Massachusetts</region>
                    </placeName>. "<placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mau">Massachusetts</region>
                    </placeName>, There She Stands"—a slogan well worthy of a noble state
                    loyalty—recalls Webster's proud reply to Hayne: "I shall enter upon no
                    encomium upon <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mau">Massachusetts</region>
                    </placeName>. She needs none. There she stands. Behold her and judge for yourselves. There is <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Lexington</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Concord, and <geogName>Bunker Hill</geogName>, and there they will remain
                    forever." In a period of two hundred years, a tie had arisen binding her people together.
                    It was the possession of a common history, a common past, a common tradition. There were memories of
                    sufferings endured and victories achieved. Personalities and names had arisen which expressed the
                    character and ideals of the state, and there were sacred places, where the memories of the state
                    were enshrined.</p>
            <p>
               <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="cau">California</region>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="txu">Texas</region>
                    </placeName> had origins and experiences peculiar to themselves, like most of the original thirteen
                    states. They were children of adventure, of original enterprise in the founding of commonwealths. In
                    a sense they were self-originated, and there is reason why their history should excite special state
                    patriotism.</p>
            <p>Can such a loyalty be induced among a people toward one of the new states in the Old Northwest, let
                    us say, like Indiana, which had, more or less, an artificial origin? She was carved out of what has
                    been called the national domain. The western states having a national origin naturally developed a
                    national loyalty. They were beneficiaries of the Federal Government. That Government created them as
                    states, or granted them power to become states. On the other hand the original states created the
                    Federal Government. As far as governing their people was concerned, that Government was to the old
                    thirteen a subordinate affair, a mere adjunct in their political lives. They had a long way to go
                    before there was much attachment to it or affection for it. To them, at first, the Federal
                    Government was but a convenience to provide for a few common interests—to care for
                    foreign affairs, Indian affairs and inter-state affairs; to provide a common money and a possible
                    common defense against some common enemy. But the new states in the West looked to the Federal
                    Government as their mainstay. From it they received benefits and largesses—grants of
                    land, internal improvements, defense against the <pb n="12" id="VAA4025-027-1-016"/> Indians. They
                    looked to the Union and to the states whence they came as the source of their lives. It was these
                    experiences and benefits that kept the states of the Northwest faithful to the Union in the days of
                    1861. They had more interest in and knowledge of the national government than they had in their
                    local state government.</p>
            <p>Yet after the lapse of a hundred years, we find Indiana inspiring a loyalty of the old kind. She has
                    a <hi rend="i">land</hi> worthy of the love of her native sons; she now realizes that she has a <hi rend="i">history</hi> worthy of regard and preservation; she has a <hi rend="i">people</hi> of
                    common interests, trials, and achievements, with marked characteristics that observing visitors have
                    noticed and praised; she has a <hi rend="i">spirit</hi> that has brought these people into a unity
                    of life; and she has a <hi rend="i">name</hi> that has been growing in favor among the sisterhood of
                    states as our state has grown in wealth, prosperity, and accomplishments. Here are the elements of
                    statehood, the factors that inspire patriotism.</p>
            <p>Indiana has promoted education, has encouraged religion, has advanced the arts and sciences, has
                    developed her natural resources, and has always borne her fair share in meeting all national burdens
                    and emergencies. Why should loyalty to such a state not be encouraged and emulated?</p>
            <p>Loyalty to the smaller groups in our lives is always commendable. There are no inconsistencies in
                    these loyalties, no antagonism of one against another. Loyalty to a local group need not lead one
                    into provincialism or narrowness. Local loyalty is a fine asset to the commonwealth and to the
                    nation; the more wedded one is to his own, the more useful he is likely to be to the larger
                    loyalties of his life. One may rightly love himself, but he should love his family more than
                    himself, and he should strive his best to build a happy and prosperous home. If by any fault of his
                    own, he allows the home to be disrupted and broken up, such a citizen cannot be so good a patriot in
                    the service of his country.</p>
            <p>One should be loyal to his neighborhood, his local community, and he should strive to make it orderly
                    and progressive—a community in which he would desire to bring up his children or other
                    people's children.</p>
            <p>One should be loyal to his city and strive to make it a "City Beautiful," clean,
                    orderly, law-abiding. He should strive to have in it a good educational system, a good health
                    system, <pb n="13" id="VAA4025-027-1-017"/> a good recreational system, a good street system, a just
                    system of taxation, a good administration for the protection of life and property. He should be
                    always looking toward progressive improvement. I need not say how such local loyalties and such
                    achievements will re-act on his state and nation. On such local patriotism and sense of duty the
                    nation depends.</p>
            <p>Then, of course, a man should be loyal to his state. Here is where he is governed. In all affairs
                    that touch his civic life the state is more important to the citizen than the nation. Mr. James
                    Bryce, a generation ago, called attention to the fact that an American "may through a long
                    life never be reminded of the Federal Government except when he votes at presidential or
                    congressional elections, buys a package of tobacco bearing the Government stamp, lodges a complaint
                    against the post office, or opens his trunk for a customs house officer on a pier in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                    </placeName> when he returns from a tour in Europe," and I may add, for these later days,
                    when he pays his income tax. Millions of Americans, the great majority, are not concerned in these
                    things, except in the act of voting.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, the citizen finds that the state, or a local authority constituted by the state,
                    registers a child's birth, appoints his guardian, pays for his schooling, safeguards his
                    inheritance, licenses him for a trade, marries him, divorces him, collects his gasoline tax and
                    builds his highways, and may declare him a bankrupt, convict him of crime, or hang him for murder.
                    The police that guard his house, local authorities that look after the poor, impose water rates,
                    enforce health laws, and manage schools—all these derive their legal powers from the
                    State alone.</p>
            <p>Certainly there are enough political and civil reasons for loyalty to the state. These call for civic
                    devotion and interest that will demand good management and good government. Everything in the life
                    of the citizen seems at stake in the conduct of the state.</p>
            <p>Above his loyalty to his state, or accompanying it, comes a man's loyalty to the nation. He
                    will strive for the integrity of his nation, that it may be one and indivisible—an
                    indivisible union of indestructible states; that the nation may be saved from internal strife or
                    foreign wars; that it may be truly great—an effective instrument for the service of
                    mankind, great in <pb n="14" id="VAA4025-027-1-018"/> its leadership among the nations for the
                    prevention of war and the promotion of peace among men.</p>
            <p>Even above loyalty to the nation one may be called upon to recognize an allegiance to all mankind.
                    "Above all nations, humanity." "My country is the world, my countrymen
                    are all mankind." If we are to obey God rather than man, this test of loyalty may come to
                    the citizen of any country.</p>
            <p>All these loyalties may abide together. True faithfulness to one of them helps all the others. So
                    long as one does not stop with his local loyalty, its cultivation and nourishment promotes his
                    deeper and broader patriotism, and his devotion to humanity will do nothing to lessen his devotion
                    to those aspects of his life which he especially calls his own.</p>
            <p>My special plea is for the good state of Indiana and her history. I call for a willingness in Indiana
                    to support that history, to save it and promote it, to have it written, placed on record, and its
                    sources made available. When we come to reveal the history of Indiana we need no vain boasting, nor
                    concealment, nor false pride, nor jingoistic patriotism, nor pretence that the story of the past is
                    better than it is. The story has its blotches, but if helpful lessons are to be learned from our
                    shortcomings, or our errors and our wrongs, then we should be ready to face the whole truth and set
                    forth "a plain, unvarnished tale." I am sure we shall find much more for
                    gratification than regret in the story of Indiana.</p>
            <p>There are innumerable topics in our state history worthy of attention. Many of them have already been
                    considered, and very worthy studies have been made upon them, published in newspapers, essays,
                    magazines, as separate volumes, or in the publications of the Indiana Historical Society. A few
                    fields may be cited for further study.</p>
            <p>The field of state biography is inviting. We need biographical sketches of prominent men and women,
                    not only of our Senators, Governors, Presidents and Vice-presidents, but sketches of our educational
                    leaders, merchants, manufacturers, men of affairs, leaders at the bar, in medicine, and in the
                    church, inventors, explorers, and pioneers in various lines of endeavor. There are many names worthy
                    of recognition and record.</p>
            <p>We need more of the educational history of the state, accounts of the outstanding educational
                    leaders, the pioneer <pb n="15" id="VAA4025-027-1-019"/> teachers and torch-bearers of learning, the
                    origin and growth of our common school system, the history of our colleges and universities, the
                    story of their endowments, their faculties, changes in their curricula, and the eminent names and
                    achievements of their graduates. What has been done in this line by Professor Richard G. Boone and
                    others may well be enlarged upon. Such papers, or volumes, may need a subsidy or subvention, but,
                    only those names should be considered whose merits and achievements make them worthy of insertion,
                    without money, and without price.</p>
            <p>The literary history of the State is an attractive field. It has been neglected, though at times it
                    has been over-drawn and acclaimed without due knowledge. There have been many men and women of
                    Indiana whose work and worth should be still further recorded, evaluated, and made known. I need not
                    attempt here even a tentative list of these writers. This is a field in which literary taste and
                    discriminating criticism are needed.</p>
            <p>State publications, or official reports, are very naturally looked upon as the most valuable source
                    of our state history. They should be collected, arranged, published in order, indexed, and made
                    accessible to students and writers on Indiana history. Here is a field for valuable editing and
                    support by the Indiana Legislature.</p>
            <p>The civil and constitutional history of the state should be further pursued. Topics such as the
                    following should be covered: the constitutional convention of 1816 and its leading men; the
                    convention of 1851, its problems and its leaders; further constitution-making in Indiana; the
                    efforts to amend our present constitution and why it is inadequate to present conditions. The
                    monumental work of Dr. Charles Kettleborough in this direction is recognised. He has supplied the
                    material for much further study and writing.</p>
            <p>The tax problem in Indiana should be historically considered, and other phases of the economic life
                    of the state need treatment.</p>
            <p>The religious life of the state should be studied and made known, the church organizations, their
                    origins, their progress, and their activities. H. A. Edson's <hi rend="i">Presbyterian
                        Church in Indiana</hi>, published a generation ago, and Rev. Commodore Cauble's <hi rend="i">History of the Church of the Disciples in Indiana</hi> are <pb n="16" id="VAA4025-027-1-020"/> fine illustrations in point. Prof. William W. Sweet's work in
                    this field is notable.</p>
            <p>The industrial history of the state, its transportation systems, its railways, its soil, its
                    products, its stone industry, its automobile industry, the improvement of its highways, its markets,
                    the growth of its cities, its agriculture, its industrial and agriculutral exhibits—all
                    these are valuable fields for the historical student and his projects in historical writing. I need
                    not impose upon your time and patience by mentioning others.</p>
            <p>I wish, however, to emphasize especially the social history of the State. Where did the people of
                    Indiana come from? Who were the first comers and what prompted them to come ? What variety of
                    settlements were there; what kind of people were they; how did they trade and ship their surplus
                    products; what kind of homes had they and how did they live; how did they bring up their children,
                    what kind of schooling did they have, and what kind of religious leaders and religious teachers?
                    What did they do for amusement? In short what was the <hi rend="i">life</hi> of the people and what
                    manner of men and women were they? Here is a fertile field for the further study of Indiana history.</p>
            <p>A few years ago I had occasion to speak of the social character of the early population of southern
                    Indiana. A false, or partial, impression of these people has been gathered from a consideration of
                    such books as Edward Eggleston's <hi rend="i">Hoosier Schoolmaster</hi>, Baynard R.
                    Hall's <hi rend="i">New Purchase</hi> and the late Albert J. Beveridge's
                    representation of the conditions surrounding Lincoln's life in southern Indiana. From these
                    and similar sources, the impression became widespread that southern Indiana in pioneer days was
                    settled by an inferior people, an outlandish folk, steeped in ignorance, illiteracy, boorish-ness,
                    immorality, degradation, and crime. Nothing could be farther from the truth. Such a conclusion could
                    result only from taking one aspect of life for the whole of it.</p>
            <p>We need not care to deny that social conditions, raw and crude, were actually here in early days. We
                    have seen them ourselves, or survivals of them, poor specimens of humanity that were like the
                    left-overs of a fading past. Here were found the depravity, the grog-shops, the drinking, the
                    swearing, the tobacco chewing and spitting, the carousels, the rowdyism, the brawls, the fighting,
                    the rip-roaring drunkenness of <pb n="17" id="VAA4025-027-1-021"/> the countrymen as they galloped
                    out of town on Saturday afternoons. We know that within the memory of men still living, even
                    children of recent memory, Indiana has suffered the disgrace of lynchings and mobs, of White Caps
                    and Ku Klux Klans. But who would take these as representing the whole life, or the real life of
                    Indiana, or, as even being typical of that life?</p>
            <p>Intelligent persons will understand that these accounts of crude conditions in earlier times only
                    tell a part of the story; they reveal only one phase of Indiana life. No one who cares for a
                    balanced historical judgment will take such things as a revelation of the whole truth, or the whole
                    life of the people. The early writers and travelers were not describing all of what they saw, but
                    only the odd, the unusual, the exceptional aspects of life. These were the topics that would attract
                    attention and give raciness to their narratives.</p>
            <p>The truth is that there were at least two distinct skeins, or kinds, in the population of Indiana in
                    pioneer days. They lived side by side in their various communities, yet were easily distinguishable.
                    One composed the backwash in the tide of migration, the inert, the do-less, the
                    ne'er-do-wells, the "onery", the illiterate, the moronic type, the
                    immoral and the unmoral. These were not all incapable of improvement, and some of them have
                    improved, others have only perpetuated their kind, while others have died out and been forgotten.
                    Some of these may have been the survivals of the pauper and jail-bird types that were shipped to
                    America in colonial times, and through <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> and the Carolinas later came to the West.</p>
            <p>Yet, seemingly, out of this very element, out of conditions in the backwoods as poor and bare as one
                    could anywhere find, possibilities of growth were found in the progeny of these people, Poverty and
                    hard conditions had submerged them, and their immediate environment gave them but little chance to
                    rise in the social scale. The common schools reached their neighborhoods in time. Some good teacher,
                    or some good influence excited in some of their youths a thirst for knowledge, aroused their
                    aspirations and stirred their ambition. There was some character or some quality there to which
                    appeal could be made.</p>
            <p>President William Lowe Bryan, in <hi rend="i">The Spirit of Indiana</hi>, tells how from one of these
                    families in the backwoods came a <pb n="18" id="VAA4025-027-1-022"/> boy to the University. He
                    worked his way through college. After graduation and more teaching, he was able to study abroad for
                    two years. Returning as a trained scientist, he was called to one of the great universities of the
                    West. He became associated with the leading scientists of the country, and, at his untimely death,
                    he had demonstrated the possible services to society that could be rendered by this backwoods boy
                    who had been born, and bred in such untoward circumstances.</p>
            <p>His life revealed the other skein, or stock in this population, living in the same hard conditions,
                    struggling, not against pauperism to which they never submitted, but against self-respecting
                    poverty, and toward a betterment and uplift for their children. Here was a people made up, as a
                    rule, of as sturdy and worthy a body of pioneer settlers as ever founded a state. They came from
                    different sources. They were not all alike; they were of different creeds and stocks. Few of them
                    were affluent; more often they were poor. Many of them were unlearned, but they were not illiterate,
                    nor worthless, nor degraded, nor criminal. They were the kind that brought civilization into the
                    Indiana wilderness, there establishing freedom, manhood and homes. They had their professional
                    classes and their capable leaders, graduates of universities, able lawyers at the bar, like John Law
                    and Isaac Black-ford, James Scott and Charles Dewey, who were among the founders of this Society.
                    Their teachers and preachers, like James G. May and John I. Morrison, Andrew Wylie and Baynard R.
                    Hall, Isaac Reed and Samuel T. Scott and William W. Martin, Caleb Mills and Francis Asbury and
                    Matthew Simpson, were constantly spreading the influence of light and learning. My own father and
                    grandfather were pioneer country teachers in southern Indiana, and, though poor in this
                    world's goods, they never condoned, nor compromised with, nor ceased to combat, the
                    ignorance and evils in their community.</p>
            <p>These worthy folks were living alongside the criminals and the toughs, the
                    "hill-billies" and the "roughnecks," who were often drinking and
                    gambling by day and jayhawking by night. The worthy ones constituted the mass of the better people
                    who were going about their business, earning an honest living, establishing their homes, raising
                    their families, cultivating good <pb n="19" id="VAA4025-027-1-023"/> neighborliness, building up
                    their churches and their schools, fearing God and obeying the law. Theirs was the common, every day
                    life, furnishing no news nor themes for journalistic writers of fiction.</p>
            <p>This population was varied. There were French-Swiss settlements at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vevay</settlement>
                    </placeName>, English settlements near <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Evansville</settlement>
                    </placeName>, the Owen settlement at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New Harmony</settlement>
                    </placeName>, German Moravians at Hope, <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Bartholomew county</region>
                    </placeName>—all of enterprising, enlightened, progressive people. There were Scotch and
                    Scotch-Irish settlements at <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Bloomington</settlement>, <settlement type="city">Princeton</settlement>, <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>,
                            <settlement type="city">Hanover</settlement>, <settlement type="city">Crawfordsville</settlement>, <settlement type="city">Greensburg</settlement>
               </placeName>,
                    Richland, Rush county, and Kingston, <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Decatur county</region>
                    </placeName> as well as in other parts of the state. In the middle of the century, Germans and Irish
                    came, settling in various parts of Indiana, exiles from famine and oppression as much as ever were
                    the Puritans of New <placeName>
                        <country reg="enk">England</country>
                    </placeName>, and they added strength to the common stock.</p>
            <p>Two years ago in one of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> newspapers, I called attention to a few of the later descendants of these early Indiana
                    pioneers, as children who had given a good account of themselves in the world. I confined myself,
                    for the most part, to those south of the National Road. I beg to repeat some personal citations here
                    as concrete examples of what this Indiana stock was responsible for—for the sake of a
                    more permanent and a more accessible record.</p>
            <p>William Lowe Bryan, the president of our University, and his brother, Enoch Albert Bryan, long time
                    president of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> State College, were born and brought up in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Monroe county</region>
                    </placeName>, sons of a United Presbyterian minister. Ernest O. Holland, now president of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> State College, hails from pioneer stock in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Switzerland county</region>
                    </placeName>. Ernest H. Lindley, Chancellor of the University of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ksu">Kansas</region>
                    </placeName>, with <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Quaker</settlement>
                    </placeName> blood in his veins, is a product of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Orange county</region>
                    </placeName>, as are also ex-president Millis of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Hanover</settlement>
                    </placeName> College, and his distinguished brother, Professor Millis, the economist of the
                    University of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                    </placeName>. President Robert J. Aley, of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Butler</settlement>
                    </placeName>, came out of Owen county, as did the eminent artist, Theodore C. Steele.</p>
            <p>Lotus Coffman, president of the University of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mnu">Minnesota</region>
                    </placeName>, was born and reared in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Washington county</region>
                    </placeName>, as was also Jesse Newlin, now of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Columbia</settlement>
                    </placeName> University, lately president of the National Educational Association. In that county,
                    too, was born John Hay, the eminent author, diplomat, and Secretary of <pb n="20" id="VAA4025-027-1-024"/> State, and there lived also John I. Morrison, the DePauws, the Mays,
                    the Mitchells, the Tuckers, and there Dr. Martin ministered for many years at Lavonia, and from
                    there came Dr. W. A. P. Martin, President of the Imperial University of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Pekin</settlement>
                    </placeName>, and for fifty years one of the builders of modern <placeName>
                        <country reg="cc">China</country>
                    </placeName>. There lived and now lie buried in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Salem</settlement>
                    </placeName>, two of the worthy founders of this Society, Benjamin Parke and John Hay Farnham.</p>
            <p>Frank Aydelotte, president of Swarthmore College, came out of Sullivan county. Robert C. Brooks, the
                    well known political scientist of Swarthmore, came from <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wayne county</region>
                    </placeName>, a scion of early Indiana, as did Clark Wissler, of the American Museum of Natural
                    History and Professor in Yale University. Professor Jesse S. Reeves, of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="miu">Michigan</region>
                    </placeName> University with a national reputation in international law, is by birth a Hoosier of
                    pioneer stock from <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wayne county</region>
                    </placeName>. William P. Rogers, formerly professor of law in Indiana University, afterwards Dean of
                    the University of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName> Law School came out of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Brown county</region>
                    </placeName>; and the present Dean of the Indiana University law school, recently national commander
                    of the American Legion, Paul C. McNutt, is a product of Johnson and Morgan counties. Judge David
                    Demaree Banta, Dean of the Indiana University Law School, had his upbringing and early years in
                    Johnson county. Banta was one of our best local historians and he produced what is generally
                    regarded as the best County History in the state. (A History of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Johnson County</region>
                    </placeName>.)</p>
            <p>Henry Lester Smith, dean of our school of education, is a product of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Monroe county</region>
                    </placeName>, of pioneer Scotch-Irish stock. The two Coulters, John Merle and Stanley, both
                    distinguished in science, may be ascribed to Jefferson county, and in this same county, in early
                    days, lived the well known Cravens family, the Hollidays, the Wileys (two of the boys distinguished
                    in law and science, born back in the forties). Here also lived the early Hendricks and Dunn
                    families. All of these families have served the state in important ways.</p>
            <p>Judge Walter Q. Gresham came out of Harrison county. Daniel Wait Howe and Jacob P. Dunn, Indiana
                    historians, whose names will always be remembered in the state, were born in southeastern Indiana,
                    the one in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Switzerland county</region>
                    </placeName> and the other in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Dearborn</region>
                    </placeName>. Two other Howes, Tom and Will, <pb n="21" id="VAA4025-027-1-025"/> both well known and
                    successful in the field of business and education, came out of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clark county</region>
                    </placeName>.</p>
            <p>Amos W. Butler, whose name is known wherever charities, penology, defectives, and mental hygiene are
                    studied, came from <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Franklin county</region>
                    </placeName>; and there is the whole cultural beehive of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Brookville</settlement>
                    </placeName> settlement, most worthy of honor. From there, also, (or, if not, from <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wayne county</region>
                    </placeName> not far away) came the Tarkingtons, the Merediths (if not the Nicholsons), the
                    Claypools, the Julians, and the Hoovers, the last kin of our worthy President.</p>
            <p>Professor Frederick A. Ogg, of the University of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="wiu">Wisconsin</region>
                    </placeName>, one of the distinguished political scientists of America, and his uncle Robert A. Ogg,
                    the well known veteran teacher and agriculturist of Indiana, came from Solsberry, Green county, or
                    the family did. James B. Eads, the great engineer, famed for the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                    </placeName> jetties, was born in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Lawrenceburg</settlement>
                    </placeName>.</p>
            <p>What shall I say more? Time would fail me to tell of the Hatfields, the Feslers, the Wheelers, the
                    Ingles, the Flowers, the Boltons, the Cochrans, the Hardings, the Fletchers, the Hornbrooks, the
                    Hillyards, the Heltons, the Ketchams, the Parrets, the Welborns, the Penningtons, the Pfrimmers, the
                    Hoveys, the Englishes, the News, the Stewarts, the Moffets, the Hickams, the Stouts, the Wylies, the
                    Craigs, the Swans, the Harbisons, the Houghtons, the Givens, the McCurdys, the Sanders, the Blairs,
                    the Malotts, the Orchards, the, Niblacks, the Maxwells, the Lanes, the O'Bannons, the
                    Wilsons, the Lanniers, the Scribners, the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Simpsons</settlement>
                    </placeName>, the Sims, the Lockwoods, the Fretageots, the Donalds, the McFaddens, the Hutchinsons,
                    the Lynns, the Wamplers, the Deckards, the Stormonts, the Chapmans, the Morgans, the Clarks, the
                    Polks, the Sewards, the Fosters, the McCallas, and scores of other families that had a worthy place
                    in our southern Indiana pioneer life. They were a highly respectable people, of character and
                    standing. These names are taken from impromptu memory of some of the people I have known without the
                    use of our Pioneer Society's list or without consulting any catalogue of family names. I am
                    well aware that the number of worthy names omitted is far in excess of the number that I have
                    included.</p>
            <p>Did these men and women come from a people that were steeped in ignorance, boorishness, immorality
                    and crime? They did not. These children are the progeny of their own <pb n="22" id="VAA4025-027-1-026"/> kind and of their ancestral soil. A number of them have won some fame,
                    but these are not different from the common run of their kin. Every son of them is ready to
                    acknowledge his lineage. "Like father like sons." Their children have advantages
                    the fathers did not know, but in the fundamental virtues of life they can hardly establish a claim
                    to superiority over their pioneer forbears. The virtues and qualities were there of old.</p>
            <p>These pioneer ancestors were children of the crucible, in the sense that they underwent trial and
                    hardship, tribulation and deprivation, while they were making their homes, building the State, and
                    establishing law and order in this wilderness world. It took a hardy and virtuous people to do that,
                    and such a people were the rank and file of Indiana pioneers.</p>
            <p>Faith, we are told, is the substance of things hoped for, the conviction of things unseen. These men
                    of early Indiana must have had some faith in themselves and their progeny. We shall do well to
                    nourish the conviction that they were worthy of our honor and emulation.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="[23]" id="VAA4025-027-1-027"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-027-1-a03">
            <head>A History of the Indiana State Board of Education</head>
            <byline>President L<hi rend="sc">INNAEUS</hi> N. H<hi rend="sc">INES</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>The State Board of Education has enjoyed a long, continuous, and honorable record in connection with
                    its service to the people of Indiana. In order to arrive at a completely accurate conception of what
                    this board has done to promote education in our commonwealth, it has been necessary to read almost
                    eighty years of minutes of the transactions of this body. The minute-books of this organization are
                    intact and, everything considered, are in complete form. Anyone who has the necessary patience and
                    curiosity may read, from the beginning down to the present, a record of everything that the Board
                    has done. The purpose of this paper is to give something of a picture of the service the State Board
                    has rendered.</p>
            <p>There are few historians of the State Board of Education. Charles A. Greathouse, State Superintendent
                    of Public Instruction from 1910 to 1917, in his report for 1915-16, devoted a chapter to the State
                    Board. He brought out some of the high-lights connected with that organization during the period
                    covered, which was from 1862 to 1916. Mr. Greathouse for the first time wrote into the state reports
                    a considerable account of the organization whose history we are considering.</p>
            <p>Another historian of the State Board of Education was Dr. Richard G. Boone, professor of pedogogics
                    in Indiana University in the eighties and nineties. In 1892 he published his <hi rend="i">History of
                        Education in Indiana</hi>, a standard work in every particular. Although this book has been
                    almost forty, years off the press, it is still used as a book of reference because of its accuracy
                    and because of its scholarly quality. It is a pleasure to refer to Professor Boone's
                    history as it touches the Board of Education. He tells us that a suggestion for a State Board of
                    Education was proposed to a convention of educators and members of the General Assembly held at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> as early as 1847. The idea early grew in this state that there should be some sort of
                    centralized authority in educational matters if our educational system was ever to get anywhere.
                    Four years later Governor Joseph A. Wright issued one of the important state papers in connections
                    with the development of education and admonished the people in regard to their responsibilities <pb n="24" id="VAA4025-027-1-028"/> as to education under the new constitution. The
                    Governor's paper furnished the background for the sixth annual address on popular education
                    by Caleb Mills who was one of the outstanding figures in the history of our state, taken from any
                    viewpoint. Mills emphasized the necessity for a complete organization to supervise the public
                    schools of the state. He recommended the creation of a State Board of Education.</p>
            <p>Professor Boone reminds us that the constitution of 1852 provided for the office of Superintendent of
                    Public Instruction. Proper legislation was soon passed to make this section of the constitution
                    function. The Legislature went still further and created the State Board of Education, making the
                    State Superintendent, ex officio, president of the State Board. In one of his chapters, Professor
                    Boone goes somewhat into detail in regard to the organization of the State Board of Education, its
                    membership, and its work, furnishing facts that will be further developed in the course of this
                    paper.</p>
            <p>Under date of June 14, 1852, the law creating the Indiana State Board of Education first went into
                    effect. The original Board consisted of the Governor of the state, the State Superintendent, the
                    Secretary of State, the state Treasurer and the state Auditor. This was strictly a lay board with
                    the exception of the State Superintendent. The Board was directed to meet annually for the purpose
                    of promoting education through conferences, interchange of views, introduction of uniform
                    schoolbooks, establishing township libraries and determining questions that might arise in
                    connection with the public schools. That first charter of duties to be performed fits rather well a
                    statement of duties of the State Board of Education today with the exception that the old township
                    libraries have disappeared and that all library activities are now supervised by other
                    organizations. The membership of the Board remained as originally organized until March, 1855, when
                    the law added the Attorney-General of the state to the list.</p>
            <p>There was no further change until ten years later when a decided revision of the law was made. Now
                    the State Board was made a professional organization in place of a lay organization. The new
                    membership was the same in so far as the Governor and the State Superintendent were concerned, but,
                    in place of the other members, the new Board included the President of the State University, the
                    President of the State Normal <pb n="25" id="VAA4025-027-1-029"/> School (when the same should be
                    established), and the superintendents of schools of the cities ranking first, second and third in
                    the number of school children enumerated. The State Superintendent of Public Instruction was to be
                    the president, and the Board was to elect one of its members to be secretary and another to be
                    treasurer. The Board was still directed to take cognizance of such questions as might arise in the
                    practical administration of the school system as were not otherwise provided for, and was duly to
                    consider, discuss, and determine the same. The Board was to determine qualification for life state
                    certificates and to attend to routine matters. The pay and mileage of the members were to be the
                    same as those of the members of the General Assembly. The membership of the Board as now constituted
                    remained unchanged for another period of ten years when, on the establishment of Purdue University,
                    the President of that institution was added to the list of members.</p>
            <p>It will be noted that so far, the membership of the State Board has been entirely ex officio. Every
                    member held his place because he had been selected for some other important office in the
                    commonwealth. In 1899, however, the old arrangement of having the entire Board ex officio, was
                    changed by a law that required the addition of "three citizens of prominence actively
                    engaged in educational work in the State, appointed by the Governor, at least one of whom shall be a
                    county superintendent, none of whom shall be appointed from any county in which any other member of
                    the State Board of Education resides."</p>
            <p>This modified plan of organization prevailed until 1913 when the law inaugurating vocational
                    education in the state was originally passed. This particular act left the members of the State
                    Board of Education as they had been before with one omission and with three additions. The Governor
                    of the state was omitted from the list of members. The following from the law indicates how the
                    Board was expanded: "and three persons actively interested in, and of known sympathy with,
                    vocational education, one of whom shall be a representative of employes and one of
                    employers." The length of term for these new appointive members was fixed at four years,
                    whereas three years had been the period for such members before. <pb n="26" id="VAA4025-027-1-030"/>
                    The plan of organization of the Board has remained the same from 1913 to the present.</p>
            <p>Governors sat on the Board from 1852 to 1913. Some of the Governors were very active in the
                    proceedings of the Board. These men considered the problems of public education as a part of the
                    many duties they were called on to perform. The first meeting of the State Board of Education was on
                    June 7, 1853. Those present were Governor Wright, State Superintendent, W. C. Larrabee, John P.
                    Dunn, state Auditor, Nehemiah Hayden, Secretary of State, Elijah Newland, state Treasurer. The
                    Governor was present at all the sessions. His name appears in the minutes of the Board a number of
                    times. Apparently he was active and interested in the problems that came before the members. The
                    next meeting of the Board was on November 14, 1853. The record reveals that on motion of Governor
                    Wright it was resolved that <hi rend="i">The Buckeye Abroad</hi>, a volume written by S. F. Cox, be
                    recommended as a suitable book for township libraries for the State of Indiana. In the meeting of
                    the next year, Governor Wright moved that H. F. West be appointed agent of the Board to distribute
                    township libraries and copies of the second annual report of the State Superintendent. A record of
                    1859 shows the presence of "His Excellency, Ashbel P. Willard," and another record
                    in the same year shows that the State Board of Education, on motion of Governor Willard, adopted the
                    Goodrich readers. It is interesting further to note that in the record of this meeting (June 22,
                    1859), it was directed that the old books in the schools be used till finished and that the new
                    books should then be purchased. This arrangement is still a feature in the procedure of the State
                    Board of Education in that children are not required to buy new books until the old ones have been
                    completed. On December 12, 1860, we find that Governor Abram A. Hammond sat with the Board of
                    Education.</p>
            <p>An interesting part of the State Board minutes is that section of them given to the Civil War period.
                    Governor Oliver P. Morton was a member of the Board and took as active an interest in its work as
                    the troubled times would permit. The Board met irregularly during the years of the great conflict.
                    Governor Morton continued to serve with the Board until 1867, when he became a member of the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>
                    <pb n="27" id="VAA4025-027-1-031"/> Senate. From 1865 to 1867, he served with a Board of
                    professional educators, since the law substituting college presidents and superintendents of schools
                    for state officials had gone into effect.</p>
            <p>The names of other governors appear in the minutes of the Board from time to time. Perhaps no man in
                    the whole list of chief executives was more active or more interested than Governor Thomas R.
                    Marshall, who served from 1909 to 1913. Governor Marshall was present at many meetings of the Board.
                    In the meeting of May 6, 1909, he introduced four resolutions having to do mainly with the adoption
                    of textbooks. The most notable of these resolutions required that votes on the adoption of texts
                    should be by signed ballots, later to be open to the inspection of the public.</p>
            <p>One of the well known incidents in the history of the State Board of Education was the controversy
                    that arose in 1909 over the adoption of a set of geographies. Governor Marshall believed that a
                    certain publishing house which had furnished the state adopted geographies for five years should
                    continue to furnish the books for the next period of five years at the same price as before. The
                    publishers in question had when making new bids placed the price of their books at a higher figure.
                    An attempt was made to hold the prices down to the old level. The company contended that it was
                    under no obligation to furnish books at the same price as cost of labor and material had gone up and
                    argued they could not continue to abide by a contract that had expired. On the other hand, members
                    of the State Board of Education believed that the Board had the right to extend this contract if it
                    saw fit. The controversy raged for months, the Attorney-General's office was drawn into the
                    controvery, and it was finally decided that the state of Indiana could not sue the company since it
                    was not the aggrieved party, and that members of the State Board could not sue but that suit must be
                    brought in the name of some child who was being deprived of his geography at a contract price. The
                    Attorney-General explained that such a suit would last many months and that in the mean time the
                    children would have no geographies at all. It was finally decided to drop the case and the Board
                    later adopted geography texts on a new basis.</p>
            <p>Governor Marshall was the last governor to serve his full <pb n="28" id="VAA4025-027-1-032"/> term of
                    four years on the State Board of Education. He retired from office in January, 1913, and was
                    followed by Samuel L. Ralston who was a member of the State Board until February 22, 1913, when the
                    new vocational law went into effect, at which time the Governor was dropped from the list of
                    members.</p>
            <p>The State Superintendent of Public Instruction has, of course, been a member of the Board from the
                    beginning, and, because of his office and because of the fact that he acts as president of the
                    Board, has had an important part in the development of education in Indiana. The office of State
                    Superintendent was created by the Constitution of 1851. The Legislature, in accordance with the
                    constitution, provided for the election of a Superintendent of Public Instruction at the general
                    election held every two years. He was directed by statute to deliver an address before the State
                    Board on taking office, spend ten days annually on each judicial circuit, examine the schools, act
                    as president of the State Board Education, submit for the inspection of the State Board lists of
                    textbooks for the schools, submit a catalog of suitable works for libraries and superintend the
                    purchase of township libraries. This official still acts as president of the State Board of
                    Education but he does not any more deliver addresses to the State Board when he takes office nor
                    does he spend ten days annually on each judicial circuit. It so happens that, due to the number of
                    judicial circuits in these days, spending ten days annually on each circuit in every year would be a
                    mathematical impossibility. His township library duties have faded out, but he still has a hand in
                    the adoption of textbooks and devotes his time to a multitude of duties that were undreamed of
                    eighty years ago.</p>
            <p>There was an official predecessor in Indiana of the State Superintendent. That official was known as
                    the Superintendent of Common Schools. He functioned from 1843 to 1852. The duties of the office were
                    largely fiscal and consisted in making reports, distributing funds, and performing other similar
                    duties. It was during this period of about ten years that the state Treasurer as required by law
                    acted as Superintendent of Common Schools. The men that filled this office were: George H. Dunn,
                    1843-1844; Royal Mayhew, 1844-1847; Samuel Hannah, 1847-1850; James P. Drake, 1850-1852. There <pb n="29" id="VAA4025-027-1-033"/> was not very much progress in the Indiana schools during this
                    period nor during the preceding period from the adoption of the first Constitution to 1843.</p>
            <p>A curious thing about the law that provided for the state Treasurer to act as Superintendent of
                    Common Schools in Indiana was the fact that this statute was to apply to all counties except Clark
                    and Scott. The State Superintendent of Common Schools was not to have any jurisdiction in those two
                    counties. This was an unusual departure in the enactment of school laws. When the office of State
                    Superintendent of Public Instruction was created, there were no exceptions as to counties or other
                    units. This official was to administer schools in all parts of the state.</p>
            <p>The list of State Superintendents for the entire period from 1852 to the present follows: William C.
                    Larrabee, 1852-1854; Caleb Mills, 1854-1857; William C. Larrabee, 1857-1859; Samuel L. Rugg,
                    1859-1861; Miles J. Fletcher, 1861-1862; Samuel K. Hoshour, 1862-1862; Samuel L. Rugg, 1862-1865;
                    George W. Hose, 1865-1868; Barnabas C. Hobbs, 1868-1871; Milton B. Hopkins, 1871-1874; Alexander C.
                    Hopkins, 1874-1875; James H. Smart, 1875-1881; John M. Bloss, 1881-1883; John W. Holcomb, 1883-1887;
                    Harvey M. LaFollette, 1887-1891; Hervey D. Vories, 1891-1895; David M. Geeting, 1895-1899; Frank L.
                    Jones, 1899-1903; Fassett A. Cotton, 1903-1909; Robert J. Aley, 1909-1910; Charles A. Greathouse,
                    1910-1917; Horace Ellis, 1917-1919; Linnaeus N. Hines, 1919-1921; Benjamin J. Burris, 1921-1924;
                    Henry N. Sherwood, 1924-1927; Charles F. Miller, 1927-1927; Roy P. Wisehart, 1927-1931. County
                    Superintendent George C. Cole of Lawrence-burg was elected State Superintendent in November, 1930,
                    to succeed to the office on March 15, 1931.</p>
            <p>The early duties of the State Board of Education seemed largely to run to three things: the
                    recommendation of texts for the schools; the selection of books for the township libraries; and the
                    election of trustees of Indiana University. The use of books selected by the State Board for the
                    schools in the early days was not compulsory in the sense that such is by law the case now. Local
                    school officers adopted books from 1824 to 1852. The State Board of Education
                    "recommended" texts from 1852 to 1865. County Boards of Education selected texts
                    for several years after 1873. A modern state-wide <pb n="30" id="VAA4025-027-1-034"/> system of book
                    selection by the State Board of Education began in 1889 when the first state textbook law in the
                    modern sense was passed. The law went into great detail, naming the subjects for which texts were to
                    be selected, for the elementary school set forth detailed directions for advertising for bids, for
                    receiving bids, for opening bids and for letting contracts. There were amendments to the law in
                    1891, in 1893 and in 1901. In 1913, under the administration of Superintendent Charles A.
                    Greathouse, state-wide adoption was extended to high schools. Every regular textbook in the twelve
                    grades of the public school system is now used because of its having been adopted by the State Board
                    of Education.</p>
            <p>The work of the early Boards in regard to township libraries was very important. The legislators
                    believed in township libraries as a means of spreading culture. To the State Board of Education was
                    given the task of selecting the books for these libraries and also that of distributing them. The
                    Board did not have any authority or functions after the books had been placed in charge of the
                    township trustees. This duty in regard to township libraries lasted for many years.</p>
            <p>The fact that there were many changes in the membership of the Board of Trustees of Indiana
                    University appears in the minutes of the State Board throughout the years. Sometimes controversies
                    over these appointments reached the Board but every difficulty apparently was smoothed out
                    eventually and the members of the State Board as well as the University survived the rivalry and
                    squabbles that sometimes appeared.</p>
            <p>Another group of members of the State Board of Education has been made up of superintendents of
                    schools in the three Indiana cities having the largest enumeration of school children. <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, of course, has led in this list of three members because <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> has had more school children than any other city in the state since the creation of the
                    State Board. The capital city, therefore, has had representation on the State Board of Education
                    ever since it became a professional Board in 1865. <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> superintendents of schools have been members as follows: A. C. Shortridge, 1865-1872;
                    George P. Brown, 1872-1878; H. S. Tarbell, 1878-1887; Lewis H. Jones, 1887-1895; D. K. Goss,
                    1895-1900; C. N. Kendall, 1900-1911; G. A. Mirick, 1911-1912 (acting supt.); J. G. Collicott,
                    1912-1917; H. S. Gruver, 1917 (acting-supt.); E. U. Graff, 1917- <pb n="31" id="VAA4025-027-1-035"/>
                    1927; J. F. Thornton, 1927 (acting-supt.); Charles F. Miller, 1927-1930; Daniel Weir, 1930
                    (acting-supt.); Paul Stetson, 1930-.</p>
            <p>The city of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Evansville</settlement>
                    </placeName> for many years held the second place as to the number of school children enumerated
                    annually. John O. Chewning, the present <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Evansville</settlement>
                    </placeName> superintendent of schools, was a member of the Board until 1925, when he was succeeded
                    by the superintendent of schools of Fort <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wayne</region>
                    </placeName>, Mr. Louis C. Ward. That city which had before been represented, temporarily won again
                    a place on the Board because of an increase in its enumeration. <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Evansville</settlement>
                    </placeName> is not now represented on the State Board of Education. The list of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Evansville</settlement>
                    </placeName> superintendents who served is as follows: E. J. Rice, 1865-1866; Charles H.
                    Butterfield, 1866-1867; A. &amp;I. Gow, 1867-1875; John M. Bloss, 1875-1881; John Cooper,
                    1881-1887; J. W. Layne, 1887-1894; W. A. Hester, 1894-1902; F. W. Cooley, 1902-1910; J. H. Tomlin,
                    1910-1916; L. P. Benezet, 1916-1924; John O. Chewning, 1924-1925.</p>
            <p>Ft. <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wayne</region>
                    </placeName> long had a member on the Board. This representation was unbroken from 1865 to 1886,
                    when <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Terre Haute</settlement>
                    </placeName> forged ahead to retain a place until 1894. At this time, the latter city was again
                    outdistanced by the former. Ft. <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wayne</region>
                    </placeName> now kept a representation on the Board until 1923, in which year South Wend came to the
                    front. In 1924-1925, Ft. <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wayne</region>
                    </placeName> replaced <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Evansville</settlement>
                    </placeName>, but the growing city of Gary soon passed Ft. <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wayne</region>
                    </placeName> which once more (1925) lost its representation. W. H. Wiley was superintendent of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Terre Haute</settlement>
                    </placeName> schools when that city had a member on the Board. The list of Ft. <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wayne</region>
                    </placeName> superintendents who have been members is as follows: James H. Smart, 1865-1875; John S.
                    Irwin, 1875-1886 and 1894-1896; Justin N. Study, 1896-1917; R. W. Himelick, 1917-1920; L. C. Ward,
                    1920-1923 and 1924-1925.</p>
            <p>
               <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">South Bend</settlement>
                    </placeName> was first represented on the State Board of Education in 1923 when its present
                    superintendent, Mr. W. W. Borden, became a member of the Board. Gary has been represented on the
                    State Board since 1925, when superintendent William A. Wirt came on the Board because of an increase
                    in the Gary enumeration. It will thus be seen that in recent years <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">South Bend</settlement>
                    </placeName> and Gary have both outdistanced <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Evansville</settlement>
                    </placeName> and Ft. <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wayne</region>
                    </placeName>. Whether this arrangement will be permanent or not remains to be seen as these four
                    cities are all growing.</p>
            <pb n="32" id="VAA4025-027-1-036"/>
            <p>Another group of ex officio members has been composed of men who have served as presidents of Indiana
                    University, Purdue University, and the Indiana State Normal School, now the Indiana State Teachers
                    College. The presidents of Indiana University during the period covered, 1865 to 1930, have been:
                    Cyrus Nutt, 1860-1875; Lemuel Moss, 1875-1884; David Starr <placeName>
                        <country reg="jo">Jordan</country>
                    </placeName>, 1884-1891; John M. Coulter, 1891-1893; Joseph Swain, 1893-1902; William Lowe Bryan,
                    1902-.</p>
            <p>The following list of presidents of the Indiana State Normal School and its successor the Indiana
                    State Teachers College have been members of the Board: William A. Jones, 1869-1897; George P. Brown,
                    1879-1885; William Wood Parsons, 1885-1921; Linnaeus N. Hines, 1921-.</p>
            <p>Purdue, as before mentioned, was first represented on the State Board in 1875. This came about
                    through action of the Legislature. The list of Purdue presidents has been as follows: A. C.
                    Shortridge, 1874-1876; Emerson E. White, 1876-1883; James H. Smart, 1883-1900; Winthrop E. Stone,
                    1900-1921; Henry W. Marshall, 1921-1922; Edward C. Elliott, 1922-.</p>
            <p>The entire group of Board members during a period of nearly thirty-five years, 1865-1899, was made up
                    of ex officio members. In the latter year, as has been noted before, the membership of the Board was
                    enlarged so as to include three prominent citizens engaged in educational work at least one of whom
                    was to be a county superintendent. These three persons were to be appointed by the governor.</p>
            <p>We note in the minutes of the summer of 1899 that the names of Mr. E. G. Machan, of LaGrange,
                    President W. T. Stott of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Franklin</settlement>
                    </placeName> College; and President Mills of Earlham College appear in the Board record. Mr. Machan
                    was the county superintendent of LaGrange County and represented the county superintendent group as
                    required by law. In 1901 county superintendent George Worley of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Warsaw</settlement>
                    </placeName> was appointed in place of Mr. Machan. Governor Durbin appointed John M. B~OSS, of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="deu">Delaware county</region>
                    </placeName>, to membership on the Board in 1903. Mr. Bloss had been State Superintendent from 1881
                    to 1883 and previous to that time had served as superintendent of schools in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Evansville</settlement>
                    </placeName>. He had lived in the West for a time after leaving school work in Indiana, but had
                    returned to the state. His ability as a school man was soon thereafter <pb n="33" id="VAA4025-027-1-037"/> recognized by this appointment to the State Board. County
                    Superintendent E. E. Robey, of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Howard County</region>
                    </placeName>, was appointed in 1904 to fill out the unexpired term of George W. Worley, who retired.</p>
            <p>The minutes of September 27, 1904, show the passage of a resolution relative to the then recent death
                    of David K. Goss at Strasburg, <placeName>
                        <country reg="gw">Germany</country>
                    </placeName>. Mr. Goss had left the superintend-ency in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> in 1900 after which he had established a school in Strasburg, where he died. President
                    W. T. Stott, of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Franklin</settlement>
                    </placeName>, resigned at the December meeting in 1904. Governor Durbin immediately appointed
                    President Edwin H. Hughes, of DePauw University, to fill the vacancy. John M. Bloss also died during
                    his membership on the Board and President R. L. Kelley of Earlham College was soon thereafter
                    appointed by Governor J. Frank Hanley to the vacant place. President R. L. Kelley was re-appointed
                    to succeed himself on May 1, 1908. President Elmer B. Bryan, of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Franklin</settlement>
                    </placeName> College, became a member of the State Board in January, 1909. He was appointed by
                    Governor Hanley. Professor George H. Tapy, of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wabash</region>
                    </placeName> College, was appointed by Governor Thomas R. Marshall to succeed E. B. Bryan, when the
                    latter resigned. County superintendent J. C. Webb of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Johnson County</region>
                    </placeName> was appointed by Governor Marshall to succeed E. E. Robey on May 1, 1910</p>
            <p>Mr. George A. Mirick, who served as acting-superintendent of schools in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> for a time following the resignation of Calvin N. Kendall, was temporarily a member of
                    the Board for a few months beginning with the meeting of September 21, 1911. He was succeeded by J.
                    C. Collicott, who became superintendent of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> schools in 1912.</p>
            <p>The year 1913 was marked by the appointment of the first high school inspector. This place was first
                    filled by A. O. Neal, who had been superintendent at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kokomo</settlement>
                    </placeName>. The place had been created by action of the 1913 session of the Legislature.</p>
            <p>County superintendent M. F. Livengood, of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Fountain County</region>
                    </placeName>, was appointed in May, 1913, by Governor Ralston to the State Board in place of Mr.
                    Webb of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Johnson County</region>
                    </placeName>. Superintendent H. G. Brown of <placeName>
                        <country reg="le">Lebanon</country>
                    </placeName>, also received an appointment as member of the State Board from Governor Ralston. P. A.
                    Reid of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName> was appointed by the Governor in the summer of 1913 as the representative of employers
                    under the <pb n="34" id="VAA4025-027-1-038"/> new vocational law. William Dobson was appointed at
                    about the same time as a representative of employes under this same law. President George R. Grose
                    of DePauw University, was appointed a member of the State Board in May, 1914. He took the place of
                    President R. L. Kelley of Earlham. On May 6, 1915, we have the record of the appointment by Governor
                    Ralston of County superintendent Samuel L. Scott of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clark County</region>
                    </placeName> to succeed Professor George H. Tapy of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wabash</region>
                    </placeName> College, and of Frank Duffy of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> to succeed William Dobson.</p>
            <p>County superintendent Charles O. Williams of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wayne County</region>
                    </placeName>, took membership on the State Board in May, 1917, by appointment of Governor Goodrich.
                    He succeeded County superintendent Livengood. Archibald M. Hall of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, was appointed a member of the Board in June, 1917, to succeed P. A. Reid of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName>, as a representative of employers under the state vocational law. County superintendent
                    Clifford Fundenburg of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Huntington county</region>
                    </placeName>, accepted appointment to the State Board by Governor Goodrich after the resignation of
                    H. G. Brown of <placeName>
                        <country reg="le">Lebanon</country>
                    </placeName>, in 1919 to accept employment with a publishing house. In this year, Mrs. E. E. Olcott
                    of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">North Vernon</settlement>
                    </placeName>, succeeded Superintendent S. L. Scott of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Clark County</region>
                    </placeName>, and Harry L. Fidlar of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, succeeded Frank W. Duffy as the employes' member of the State Board. The late <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Elwood</settlement>
                    </placeName> Haynes of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Kokomo</settlement>
                    </placeName>, pioneer inventor and manufacturer of automobiles, came to membership on the Board in
                    1921 as did County superintendent Frank Heighwav of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Lake County</region>
                    </placeName>. Superintendent Heighway died some months later and Mrs. Richard Edwards of Peru, was
                    appointed to the State Board.</p>
            <p>A number of women have had appointments to the State Board of Education. This list includes Mrs. E.
                    E. Olcott of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">North Vernon</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Mrs. Nellie C. Warren of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Mrs. Richard Edwards of Peru, Miss Etelka Rockenback of New <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Albany</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Mrs. Beryl S. Holland of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Bloomington</settlement>
                    </placeName>, and Miss Martha Whitacre of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName>.</p>
            <p>Other persons appointed to membership are President Benjamin J. Burris of the Ball State Teachers
                    College, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Muncie</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Vice-President Henry B. Longden of DePauw University, County Superintendent A. S.
                    Thomas of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Miami County</region>
                    </placeName>, Frank Reynolds of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cambridge City</settlement>
                    </placeName>, William D. Moss of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Marion</region>
                    </placeName>, President L. A. Pittenger of the Ball State Teachers College, and County
                    superintendent George H. Reitzel of Hendricks <pb n="35" id="VAA4025-027-1-039"/> County. It will be
                    seen from the foregoing record of appointments that while the State Board of Education is commonly
                    thought of as rather permanent in its membership there has been a constant changing in the names of
                    those who serve the state in this capacity.</p>
            <p>The State Board of Education is often thought of as having considerable power. It is well to
                    remember, however, that this body has no authority to levy any tax rates or revise any tax rates,
                    school or other. It fixes no salaries of any teachers or of any other group of school employes
                    except some three or four persons who directly or indirectly serve the State Board in the office of
                    the State Superintendent of Public Instruction. No appointments of teachers come from the action of
                    the State Board, which organization serves in an advisory capacity to the state educational system.
                    It fixes the conditions for obtaining teachers certificates under the law. It adopts textbooks for
                    contract periods of five years under the exact wording of the statute.</p>
            <p>It is sometimes charged that the State Board of Education is constantly changing textbooks. Those who
                    give little thought to this situation may readily make this charge, but it is well to remember that
                    the times of the adoptions are fixed by law and the State Board of Education can not change them.
                    The adoptions in high school texts are all considered every five years; the readers, arithmetics and
                    copy books are adopted for five year periods ending at a different time, and the remainder of the
                    grade adoptions are made at still other five year intervals.</p>
            <p>The first high school adoption was made in 1913, according to the act of the Legislature of that
                    year. Adoptions were regularly made in 1918, in 1923, and in 1928, according to the statute.</p>
            <p>This year, 1931, there is to be a consideration of adoptions of texts for grade schools other than
                    those of the three R's, etc., as explained above. It would be a splendid thing if all
                    adoptions were coiisidered in the same year. This wduld help clear up public thinking on this
                    subject. It is strictly illegal for the State Board to consider a contract for a text in any given
                    subject oftener than five years. The Board obeys the law exactly. The difficulty comes in that these
                    several adoptions are made in three different years.</p>
            <pb n="36" id="VAA4025-027-1-040"/>
            <p>The State Board of Education has served in various capacities during its long life. First and always,
                    it has been the State Board of Education. For many years it served as a State Library Board, in
                    cases of vacancies appointing State Librarians, that is, it acted as a Library Board whenever the
                    assembled members gave time to that duty.</p>
            <p>The State Board of Education under the vocational law was made a state board of vocational education
                    and it still serves in that capacity though under the title of the State Board of Education, It has
                    been and is a state teachers training board, a state board of textbook commissioners, and a state
                    board of attendance.</p>
            <p>Perhaps some of the most strenuous times connected with the work of the Board had to do with the
                    state textbook adoptions. These adoptions began in their modern form in 1889. The contract for any
                    given text has always been a period of five years but the contract may be extended for one or more
                    additional five year periods if a given text is satisfactory. The contracts are important and there
                    is great rivalry between the companies for this business. Sometimes the Board has been blamed for
                    adopting some text at a higher price than seemed reasonable. The Board has never been given
                    authority to control bidders' figures. The law directs that the Board receive sealed bids
                    on every contract and further directs the Board to make the best selection possible from the bids
                    received. Thus in 1921, the Board was greatly criticized because those bidders who had held
                    contracts in texts from 1916 to 1921 raised their prices on the proposed new contracts. The critics
                    did not stop to recall that the country had been through the World War, that the prices of material
                    and labor had gone up and that nobody could be found to bid on these books at the prices that had
                    prevailed in 1916. The Board obeyed the law exactly but it did not escape a world of abuse because
                    it did so. The story of state adoptions is a long one and the work involved is a thankless task.</p>
            <p>The State Board of Education is called on sooner or later to consider almost every social and
                    educational question. Many of these topics belong rightly to the Board but some of them come from
                    attempts to impose on the members and get their influence to back propositions the responsibility
                    for which clearly belongs somewhere else. The period following <pb n="37" id="VAA4025-027-1-041"/>
                    the World War was particularly prolific in requests to help out various enterprises. In looking over
                    the minutes of a few months in 1920 we find that the following topics were before the Board:
                    Mayflower descendants, intelligence tests for high school seniors, shortage of teachers, Indiana
                    Tuberculosis Association, the child welfare movement, local history, private and parochial schools,
                    standard equipment for rural schools, committee to approve rural school equipment, inspection of
                    colleges, State Library, vocational education, vocational rehabilitation, selection of school
                    architects, educational work in state institutions, Knights of Pythias' support of the use
                    of the Bible in the schools, Rotary clubs and Americanism, Roosevelt Americanization and Scholarship
                    Fund, America's gift to <placeName>
                        <country reg="fr">France</country>
                    </placeName>, Bible study, length of the school day, credit in school for outside music work,
                    advertisements in textbooks, German in the schools, American Legion and Americanization, state money
                    for private normals, inspection of grade and high schools, the censorship of moving pictures, et
                    cetera.</p>
            <p>As said above, many of these questions rightly belong to the State Board of Education, but there has
                    seldom been any complaint on the part of the members even when extraneous matters have been dragged
                    into the sessions. In fact, the matters for consideration by the State Board have been almost as
                    varied as the subjects for legislation by the Indiana Legislature under the old Constitution when
                    laws were passed all the way from the granting of divorces to the protection of cranberries.</p>
            <p>The proposed censorship of moving pictures, for example, as it was carried to the State Board aroused
                    the almost united opposition of the members. Committees from the Board were to sit and watch films
                    as they were shown the first time and were to decide which pictures were to be given to the public
                    and which were to be discarded. The proposition was an impossible one and finally died for want of
                    support.</p>
            <p>One man, some years ago, came to the office of the State Superintendent in an effort to line up that
                    official and the members of the State Board in favor of an organization built on the lines of a
                    labor union that would include everybody in the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>. The annual membership fee was to be one dollar for each person. In return, American
                    humanity was to have the privilege of trading at stores organized for their benefit, <pb n="38" id="VAA4025-027-1-042"/> the people were to be provided with jobs and everything from then on
                    was to be perfectly lovely. This proposition was not far removed from that of a Hoosier who showed
                    up at the State House many years prior to that date, and who tried to get educational support for
                    his scheme for squaring the circle and then tried to get the Indiana Legislature to recognize by a
                    statute his plan for performing that impossible mathematical feat. The minutes of the State Board,
                    however, do not show any trace of either one of the above questions because the members of the
                    Board, in so far as they were approached, refused to have anything to do with the measures and their
                    backers. These cases are mentioned as extreme instances of attempts to get the State Board of
                    Education behind questionable or impossible propositions.</p>
            <p>Among other questions that came before the Board during the last thirty years were the fight against
                    cigarettes, the appointment of school inspectors, the educational exhibit, the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">St. Louis</settlement>
                    </placeName> Exposition, the consolidation of schools, the publication of textbooks at the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Jeffersonville</settlement>
                    </placeName> reformatory, high schools of the same quality for colored pupils as for white pupils,
                    importance of county institutes, state aid for poverty stricken schools, length of school term,
                    revision of the grade course of study, improvement in the county superintendency, improved sanitary
                    conditions in schools, nominations of teachers by city and county superintendents, the teaching of
                    manual training and agriculture, music and art in the schools, a state depository in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> for adopted textbooks, better school-houses, domestic science, higher standards for
                    teaching, additional revenue for the schools, higher salaries, the classification of teacher
                    training institutions, industrial education, distribution of school funds on the basis of
                    enrollment, a minimum charge for the entire list of grade textbooks, a correct version of the Star
                    Spangled Banner, a retirement law for teachers, medical inspection for pupils, expense allowances
                    for county superintendents, pay for teachers while visiting other schools or attending
                    teachers' meetings, child labor, codification of the school laws, high school librarians,
                    pre-vocational education, Bible study, trade schools, military training in high schools, textbook
                    shortage, teacher shortage, Armistice Day celebrations, and cooperation with improvements of
                    highways. Along with the consideration of all these questions, of course, <pb n="39" id="VAA4025-027-1-043"/> has run constantly the routine business of the Board, the licensing of
                    teachers, adoption of textbooks and other such regular matters.</p>
            <p>In conclusion, it may be mentioned that the State Board of Education is the oldest of several state
                    boards that have a part in the government of Indiana. The record of this earliest created board is a
                    long and honorable one. The State Board of Education, like all other boards later created, is doing
                    its best to serve the people of Indiana.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="[40]" id="VAA4025-027-1-044"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-027-1-a04">
            <head>Harrison's Councils with Tecumseh</head>
            <byline>R<hi rend="sc">OSE</hi> S<hi rend="sc">CHULTHEIS</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>Indiana Territory, which included the present states of Indiana, <placeName>
                  <region type="state" reg="ilu">Illinois</region>, <region type="state" reg="wiu">Wisconsin</region>
               </placeName>
                    and parts of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="miu">Michigan</region>
                    </placeName> and <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mnu">Minnesota</region>
                    </placeName>, began its existence on July 4, 1800. William Henry Harrison, then a young man of
                    twenty-seven was appointed Governor. He was born in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> and was educated at Hamp-den-Sydney College. He took up the study of medicine, but
                    abandoned that profession when his father, Benjamin Harrison, a signer of the Declaration of
                    Independence, died.</p>
            <p>Reports of Indian wars in the western country stirred young Harrison to action and at the age of
                    eighteen, General <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> granted him a commission as Ensign in the First <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> Regiment (the very first unit of our Regular Army) and stationed him at Fort <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName>, north of the present city of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Serving as Aide-de-camp to General Anthony <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wayne</region>
                    </placeName> from 1792 to 1794, he merited a promotion to the rank of Lieutenant. In 1796 he was
                    placed in command of Fort <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName>, a post of importance and responsibility, at the age of twenty-three.</p>
            <p>On November 22, 1795, this young soldier was married to Anna Symmes, daughter of John Cleves Symmes,
                    one of the judges of the Northwest Territory. Three years later Capt. Harrison was appointed
                    secretary of the Northwest Territory, under Governor Arthur St. Clair, whereupon he resigned his
                    commission in the army serving in the new capacity until October 3, 1799. Then he was chosen first
                    Territorial Delegate to Congress from the Northwest Territory by the territorial legislature.</p>
            <p>Harrison's interest in the development of the western country was evinced by his untiring
                    efforts in Congress to set off Indiana Territory from the Northwest Territory. Success ultimately
                    came to the earnest Delegate from the far-off West. Appreciating his interest and sincerity in
                    promoting plans for the new area, President Adams appointed Harrison first Governor of Indiana
                    Territory.</p>
            <p>The power granted with his appointment was far greater in his domain than the authority of the
                    President over the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>. With three Judges, who also were appointed <pb n="41" id="VAA4025-027-1-045"/> by the
                    President, his duty was to make the laws for the Territory, to make all civil appointments and
                    commission military officers below the rank of General. He had authority to pardon all offences and
                    treat with the Indians on all subjects with unlimited power.</p>
            <p>
               <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> was made the capital of Indiana Territory and at this place Governor Harrison built a
                    remarkable home, the Harrison Mansion, which he called "Grouseland." Here he and
                    his family lived from the summer of 1803, when the house was sufficiently advanced toward completion
                    for occupancy, until the latter part of June, 1812. When the Governor was placed in command of <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> troops in the War of 1812, he found it necessary to be far from home for a long period,
                    and, fearing for the safety of his family, took them to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Cincinnati</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Records do not show that Mrs. Harrison was ever in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> again as the Governor resigned his office in May, 1813, upon his appointment as a
                    Major-General in the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> Army.</p>
            <p>The land on which the Harrison Mansion stands was a part of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName> cession of 1784. Governor Harrison received title to it from the Government of the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>. In 1812, the house and part of the estate of "Grouseland" was
                    transferred by General Harrison to his eldest son, John Cleves Symmes Harrison. It remained in the
                    family until 1843. During the seventy-five years that followed this date, the house gradually
                    declined, finally, early in the twentieth century, reaching "the lowest ebb of its
                    fortunes. Beasts were stabled in its rooms. Grain was kept in storage and the house was fast
                    tumbling into a ruin."</p>
            <p>In 1909, Francis Vigo Chapter, Daughters of the American Revolution, began to beg the custody of the
                    old Mansion and for years used every means to interest someone, everyone (legislators, officials and
                    philanthropists) in its preservation. The little group of women failed! At that time the great wave
                    of interest in antiques and historic houses had not surged over the country, as it has today.
                    However, the failure meant ultimate success. In 1917, the owners of the Harrison Mansion decided to
                    raze the building. Frantic, but determined to save this treasure, Francis Vigo Chapter collected in
                    a few days from the citizens of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> a fund for its actual purchase, and so became the owner of the Mansion.</p>
            <pb n="42" id="VAA4025-027-1-046"/>
            <p>Very slowly but very surely the historic building is being restored. The process has necessarily been
                    slow for Francis Vigo Chapter has had very little assistance. Mere preservation and imperative
                    repairs have absorbed a greater part of the door receipts.</p>
            <p>The constant vision of the Chapter has been to restore the house to its original state, but, since
                    through the years of private ownership, each individual owner tried to change a perfect piece of
                    Georgian architecture into a residence (or sometimes into a hotel or stable or storehouse),
                    according to the notions of the period of his occupancy, the business of restoration is truly a long
                    task. The original furnishings, personal belongings and relics of the Harrisons are being collected
                    and placed in their original setting, where many thousands of visitors view them annually.</p>
            <p>The old walnut grove has long since been cleared away, and factories have crowded in, several being
                    located close at hand. Nevertheless, nearby the same old river flows steadily on and the hospitable
                    doorway extends a cordial invitation to enter, just as in the days of yore. Within, as the ancient
                    lock clicks behind one, can almost be heard the scampering tread of little feet upon the stair and
                    suppressed giggles of happy children in the upper rooms, as the dignified beauty of the hall and
                    stairway become a reality in the dim light. To the left, one steps into the great Council Chamber
                    where Harrison of times held conferences with Indian Chiefs and warriors. Here, on one occasion, to
                    settle a controversy with the Indians, the Governor marked out a map of a land tract on the floor
                    with a piece of charcoal obtained from the fireplace.</p>
            <p>Here came all the civil celebrities and military authorities who visited Post <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> during those years. Here "met two future Presidents of the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> [Harrison and Zachary Taylor], French Baron, dashing officers of old <placeName>
                        <country reg="sp">Spain</country>
                    </placeName>, native chieftains, Francis Vigo, Aaron Burr, Father Rivet. These walls witnessed
                    American history in the making."</p>
            <p>Across the hall, the living room with its two comfortable fireplaces, brings one to the family life
                    of William H. Harrison and his lovely wife Anna. Everywhere one turns throughout the house [of
                    thirteen rooms] and basement [of eight rooms] one meets the Harrisons and the nine children in their
                    everyday busy, happy life. When peeping into the childrens' bedrooms <pb n="43" id="VAA4025-027-1-047"/> one thinks of peacefully sleeping babies, or sadly, of the long nights
                    of a mother's anxiety with croup or measles, or ague.</p>
            <p>The kitchen with its deep fireplace, hung with old crane and black pots of various sizes, with a
                    long-handled waffle iron standing near, brings visions of bounteous, temptingly prepared provisions
                    and numerous colored servants. One wonders if the mistress of the Governor's home had much
                    concern about the servant problem. One lingers in the dim and stately hall, loath to depart from the
                    enchantment of bygone days.</p>
            <p>While Governor Harrison lived in this remarkable western home, he had many Indian problems to solve.
                    As early as the beginning of 1802, controversies with the Indians over the boundaries of different
                    tracts was occupying the Governor's attention to a considerable degree and a year later his
                    correspondence with the Secretary of War relates that the Miamis and Pottawatomies objected to a
                    sale of lands made to the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> by the Piankeshaws and Delawares, on the contention that the latter tribes had no right
                    to dispose of any lands without the sanction of the more powerful nations.</p>
            <p>This feeling grew among many of the stronger tribes, and, about 1805, a Shawnee warrior named
                    Tenskwatawa, began preaching a sort of religion among the tribes around Greenville. He was called
                    the Prophet, and soon had established an inter-tribal reputation as a leader and adviser. He
                    enlisted many followers among the Indians living beyond Lake Superior, as well as the Osages,
                    Delawares, Miamis, and practically all other tribes living within a radius of a hundred miles or
                    more.</p>
            <p>About this same time a group of religious enthusiasts from <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> founded a settlement called Shakertown, north of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName>. It was a co-operative community, holding property in common and forbidding marriage.
                    Harrison at one time wrote: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>I have also sent for the leading member of the Shaker Society (a religious sect of very
                            extraordinary principles which you may have heard of) who resides about 20 miles from this
                            place, with the intention of prevailing on him to take a speech to the Prophet. This
                            scoundrel (the Prophet) affects to follow the Shaker principles in everything but the vow of
                            celebacy [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>], and the above mentioned leader has assured me that he
                            believes the Prophet to be under the same divine inspiration that he himself is (a
                            circumstance by no means improbable) but that for <pb n="44" id="VAA4025-027-1-048"/>
                            reasons growing out of his situation as a savage he was still permitted, with his immediate
                            followers, to cohabit with women.<hi rend="sup">1</hi>
                  </p>
                    </quote>
            </p>
            <p>A passage in the very first letter addressed to the Secretary of War by the young Governor of Indiana
                    territory reads: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The British have been unremitted in their exertions to preserve their influence over the
                            Indians resident within our Territory.</p>
                        <p>last year they delivered a greater quantity of goods to their Indians than they have ever
                            been known to do—and I have been lately informed that talks are now circulating
                            amongst them, which are intended to lesten [sic] the small influence we have over the
                            Indians—I cannot vouch for the truth of this report—but I think it
                            very probable that the British will redouble their efforts to keep the Indians in their
                            interest as a means of assisting them in any designs they may form against <placeName>
                                <region type="state" reg="lau">Louisiana</region>
                            </placeName> which it is said will shortly be delivered up to the French.<hi rend="sup">2</hi>
                  </p>
                    </quote>
            </p>
            <p>The influence of the English agents was always evident, particularly among the tribes in the northern
                    part of the territory, and half hidden beneath the advice and religion of the Prophet was the
                    British intention to incite the Indians against the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> Government. The Governor wrote his superior in 1808 that the Prophet's
                    followers were "constantly engaged in what they term religious duties," but that
                    their prayers were "always succeeded by or intermixed with warlike sports, shooting with
                    the bow, throwing the tomahawk or wielding the war club." Harrison believed that,
                    "this combination of religious and warlike exercise and the choice of weapons of their own
                    manufacture" sufficiently indicated "the designs of their author."</p>
            <p>Many times during his term as Governor of Indiana Territory, Harrison's correspondence
                    includes reports of interference in Indian affairs by the English agents. Although no admission
                    appears from the Prophet himself, there are a number of instances where friendly Indians, as well as
                    settlers, traders and interpreters warned the Governor of the insidious work of the British through
                    the Shawnee preacher. At one time, Harrison wrote to the Secretary of War: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The Prophet contrives to have every Indian put to death who attempts to open the eyes of
                            their unfortunate countrymen, and I am told that his vengeance is particularly directed
                            against those whom he suspects of <list type="footnotes">
                        <item>
                           <hi rend="sup">1</hi> Governor Harrison to the Hon. William Eustis, Secretary of
                                    War, <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                                    </placeName>. May 15, 1810, in <hi rend="i">Messages and Letters of William Henry
                                        Harrison</hi>, edited by Logan Esarey (<placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                                    </placeName>, 1922). I, 421-422.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi rend="sup">2</hi> Harrison to the Secretary of War [Henry Dearborn] July 16,
                                    1801, in <hi rend="i">ibid.</hi>, 27.</item>
                     </list>
                            <pb n="45" id="VAA4025-027-1-049"/> an attachment to the <placeName>
                                <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                            </placeName>. Five <placeName>
                                <region type="state" reg="deu">Delaware</region>
                            </placeName> Chiefs of this description have been lately sent far from them under guard. I
                            have serious apprehensions for their safety. I have received information which cannot be
                            doubted that war belts have been passing through all the tribes from the gulf of <placeName>
                                <region type="state" reg="flu">Florida</region>
                            </placeName> to the Lakes. The Shawnees were the bearers of these belts and they have never
                            been our friends. The traders who are attached to our government are unanimously alarmed and
                            agree on the opinion that a general combination of Indians for a war against the <placeName>
                                <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                            </placeName> is the object of all these messages and councils. My own opinion is that this
                            is certainly the object but I hope and believe that it will not be accomplished. The several
                            branches of the Miami Tribe are immovable in our interest. The influential chiefs of the
                            Delawares are equally so but if the machinations of the Prophet should be successful in
                            getting these removed, I cannot answer for the fidelity of the rest of the
                                tribe…<hi rend="sup">3</hi>
                  </p>
                    </quote>
            </p>
            <p>A little later, Harrison wrote that the "agency of a foreign power is producing the
                    discontents among the Indians cannot be questioned," and "It is my opinion that
                    the British are at the bottom of all this business, and depend on it that if we have war with them
                    many of the Indiana tribes will take an active part against us." Again, he asserted:
                    "I am confident however, that the ultimate object of the British (which no doubt is that of
                    forming a general confederacy against US) has not yet been communicated either to the Miamis, Weas,
                    Delawares or even the Kickapoos." A month later he declared: "I do believe that
                    the Chippeways, Ottawas and part of the Pottawatamies only wait the signal from the British agents
                    to attack us."</p>
            <p>In a speech "to the chiefs and head men of the Shawanese tribe of Indians,"
                    Harrison said: "You have called in a number of men from the most distant tribes to listen
                    to a fool [the Prophet], who speaks not the words of the Great Spirit but those of the devil, and of
                    the British Agents." The next year, 1808, the following was written: "The result
                    of all my inquires on the subject is that the late combination was produced by British intrigue and
                    influence in anticipation of war between them and the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>."</p>
            <p>The record of the British Agent shows a "requisition for an extra quantity of goods to
                    supply his Majesty's Indian stores with presents in case of war with the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> for 1809", including</p>
            <list type="footnotes">
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">3</hi> Harrison to Hon. Henry Dearborn, Secretary of War, <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                        </placeName>, July 11, 1807, in <hi rend="i">ibid.</hi>, 224.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="46" id="VAA4025-027-1-050"/>
            <table>
               <row>
                  <cell>Gunpowder</cell>
                  <cell>180,000 lbs.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Flints</cell>
                  <cell>24,000</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Lead Bars</cell>
                  <cell>1,000 lbs.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>On June 26, 1810, Harrison asserted his belief, "that the scheme originated with the
                    British" and that the Prophet was "inspired by the Superintendent of Indian
                    affairs of Upper <placeName>
                        <country reg="-cn">Canada</country>
                    </placeName>, rather than the Great Spirit", from who he pretended to derive his
                        authority.<hi rend="sup">5</hi> A little later, we read: "A Miami Chief who has just
                    returned from his annual visit to Malden, after having received the accustomed donation of goods,
                    was thus addressed by Elliot the British Agent—'My son keep your eyes fixed on
                    me—my tomahawk is now up—be you ready—but do not strike until I
                    give the signal.'"<hi rend="sup">6</hi>
            </p>
            <p>While the Red Prophet was preaching Shaker doctrines to the Indians, his twin brother, Tecumseh, the
                    war leader of the Shawnees, was making plans for a vast confederacy of all tribes of the
                        <geogName>Mississippi valley</geogName>, including, too, those north of the Great Lakes and
                    tribes of the South. For years he had paid visits to the many nations. He had rebuked those who had
                    disposed of lands by treaties with the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>, and told them all that no single tribe or group of tribes had a right to transfer
                    lands, for all the land "upon the continent was the common property of all the tribes and
                    that no sale to any part of it could be valid without the consent of all."</p>
            <p>Following the Treaty of Ft. <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wayne</region>
                    </placeName> of September 30, 1809, Tecumseh renewed his activities against the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName> by threatening to kill all the chiefs who participated and drive the white people back
                    across the Alleghenies, if the lands ceded in that treaty were not returned. So bold was his
                    preparation for war and so insolent was he toward the peaceful advances of the Governor that
                    Harrison finally, in July, 1810, sent a' speech of chastisement to the Prophet and
                    Tecumseh. In regard to this, Governor Harrison reported: "No particular answer was returned
                    by Mr. Barron [the interpreter]. It is to be brought by the brother of the Prophet who will be here
                    in a few days. This brother is really the efficient man—the Moses of the family. I have
                    not seen him since the Treaty of Greenville and should not know him. He is described by all <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">4</hi> See <hi rend="i">ibid.</hi>, 418, footnote.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">5</hi> Harrison to the Secretary of War, [William Eustis] <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                            </placeName>, June 26, 1810, in <hi rend="i">ibid.</hi>, 435.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">6</hi> Harrison to the Secretary of War, <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                            </placeName>, July 8, 1810, in <hi rend="i">ibid.</hi>, 447.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="47" id="VAA4025-027-1-051"/> as a bold, active, sensible man, daring in the extreme and
                    capable of any undertaking".<hi rend="sup">7</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Harrison also included the following in his letter to the Secretary of War: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The Prophet's brother [Tecumseh] told Mr. Barron that he would bring with him about
                            thirty of his principal men and as he knew that the young men were fond of attending on such
                            occasions, that there would probably be one hundred in all; but the Prophet said that he
                            might expect to see a great many more. Besides the expense which will be incurred by
                            supporting such a number 10 or 15 days, it will not be very pleasant to have them here, from
                            other considerations; I therefore immediately dispatch'd an Indian with a message
                            to request that the chiefs only would come down, attended by a few of their young men. This
                            day I have dispatched [Michael] Brouillette [an interpreter] by water to in-force the
                            necessity of their compliance.<hi rend="sup">8</hi>
                  </p>
                    </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Nearly a week later, on August 12, Tecumseh arrived at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName>. The number of visitors in his party is uncertain, but in a Post Script to his official
                    report of the council, the Governor says: "I have had nearly the whole Wea and Piankeshaw
                    tribes with me since the 12th. inst, besides the Prophet's party, a number of stragglers
                    and well affected Pottawatomies under Winemac, and I was unable to get rid of them until today
                    [August 281 when their annuities were delivered."<hi rend="sup">9</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Council of August, 1810, was held in the walnut grove which lay to the south of the Harrisdn
                    Mansion. Thither the Indians came to confer with their Great Father. "This personage, who
                    is called Tecumseh, arrived here on the 12th Inst, and excepting the intervening Sunday and one bad
                    day I have been constantly engaged with him until the last evening", the Governor wrote on
                    August 22, 1810. "His speeches the first two days were sufficiently insolent and his
                    pretentions arrogant." Threats of violence, made by the warriors were so alarming that when
                    a number of Indians sprang up and stood in a threatening attitude General Gibson, the
                    Governor's Secretary, who understood the Shawnee language, ordered the militia officer at
                    hand to bring up a guard. After this demonstration, Governor Harrison put out the Council Fire and
                    refused to hear them further. They returned to their camp peacefully and the next morning, after
                    profuse apologies by Tecumseh, negotiations were continued for more than a week. <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">7</hi> Harrison to the Secretary of War, <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                            </placeName>, August 6, 1810, in <hi rend="i">ibid.</hi>, 466.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">8</hi> See <hi rend="i">ibs.</hi>, 467-468.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">9</hi> Harrison to the Secretary of War, <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                            </placeName>, Augwt 28, 1810, in <hi rend="i">ibid.</hi>, 472.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="48" id="VAA4025-027-1-052"/> But when the Council Fire was finally extinguished, nothing had
                    been accomplished toward a permanent peace.<hi rend="sup">10</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the months that followed the white people of the territory were constantly harrassed by the
                    Indians. Horse stealing was perhaps the commonest offense, but no depredation was beyond achievement
                    by the hostile Indians. The murder of men and the stealing of women and children was not uncommon.
                    The Governor was deeply aroused by the increasing reports of preparations for war with the
                    assistance of the British, coming from friendly Indians, traders and frightened settlers far from
                    the forts and stations. To the Secretary of War, Harrison wrote in April, 1811: "I have
                    pursued the President's directions with regard to the use of pacific and concilatory
                    measures with the Indians", but, in spite of this, Tecumseh and the Prophet, encouraged by
                    the British agents at Malden, continued to enlarge their following. "Nothing but the great
                    talents of Tecumseh could keep together this heterogeneous mass which compose the Prophet's
                    force", declared Harrison which shows his opinion of the war chief of the Shawnees.</p>
            <p>In June, 1811, a pirogue laden with salt to be delivered to the tribes farther up the river, was
                    seized by the Prophet and his men. As soon as the boatmen returned to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> and reported the theft to the Governor, he sent Captain Walter Wilson to Prophetstown,
                    at the mouth of the <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Tippecanoe</region>
                    </placeName>, with a speech to the offender. In his reply dated July 4, 1811, Tecumseh stated
                    several times that he would be with Harrison in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> in eighteen days. He made the assertion that, "when I come to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> to see you, all will be settled in peace and happiness."<hi rend="sup">11</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The merciless sun of a mid-July day was setting in the West—far across the Prairies of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ilu">Illinois</region>
                    </placeName> country—a glowing ball. Birds twittered their evening messages to their
                    mates and the humming song of the katydid was beginning somewhere in the gloomy coolness of the
                    forest. The placid <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wabash</region>
                    </placeName> flowed quietly between its banks lined with willows now softly astir with the slight
                    breeze that seemed to come from the silent movement of the water at sunset.</p>
            <p>Around the bend to the north of old <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> appeared a canoe filled with Indians. Soon another canoe, and yet another, <list type="footnotes">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">10</hi> Harrison to the Secretary of War, <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                            </placeName>, August 22, 1810, in <hi rend="i">ibid.</hi>, 460-461.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="sup">11</hi> Tecumseh to Harrison, July 4, 1811, in <hi rend="i">ibid</hi>,
                        629.</item>
               </list>
                    <pb n="49" id="VAA4025-027-1-053"/> approaching with the swift paddling of the redmen. Soon a whole
                    fleet, numbering sixty or more in all, rounded the bend and drew in to the stone landing on the east
                    side, known as Ft. <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Knox</region>
                    </placeName>. Three hundred Indian warriors with their Chiefs, followed by a few women and children,
                    swarmed up the rocky hillside to the woods above. Camp was made a little above the village of Post <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Preparations for feeding the company were simple enough—a handful or two of
                    parched corn was considered a day's marching rations for each hardy redskin. The great
                    Tecumseh had promised Captain Wilson that he would bring only a few men, but fearing this a ruse to
                    cover the long threatened attack on <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName>, the Governor ordered guards of two companies of militia infantry and a detachment of
                    fifteen dragoons to a position on the borders of the town, and warned the whole neighboring militia
                    to be on the alert.</p>
            <p>The Indians did not arrive until July 27th. Captain Wilson met Tecumseh up the river with a message
                    expressing the Governor's astonishment that he should be accompanied by so large a force,
                    in the face of the fact that he had been requested to bring a few only. Tecumseh declared that but
                    twenty-four men had come because of his order and that all the rest had come of their own accord.</p>
            <p>July 27th fell on Saturday. On the following Tuesday, Governor Harrison and Tecumseh met in council.
                    About one hunded eighty Indians attended and a body of dismounted dragoons served as a guard for
                    Harrison. It was not possible to make definite terms with Tecumseh, who declared that after an
                    extended tour, to visit the Creeks, Choctaws and Osages, he would return and then go to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> to see the President. The conference broke up on Wednesday, July 31. Harrison was not
                    able to get the bulk of the Indians away until Saturday. Tecumseh did not leave until August 5th,
                    when he set off down the <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wabash</region>
                    </placeName> with twenty men on his visit to the South. Harrison believed that Tecumseh had meant to
                    attack, and that he had only changed his plans because of the size of the force which he saw it
                    possible for the Governor to muster on short notice.<hi rend="sup">12</hi> After the break-up of
                    this council of the summer, 1811, an Indian war in the Northwest seemed very probable. Before
                    Tecumseh's return, came the Battle of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Tippecanoe</region>
                    </placeName>, a prelude to the War of 1812 in the West.</p>
            <list type="footnotes">
               <item>
                  <hi rend="sup">12</hi> Harrison to Secretary of War, <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                        </placeName>, August 6, 1811, in <hi rend="i">ibid.</hi>, 542-546.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <pb n="[50]" id="VAA4025-027-1-054"/>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-027-1-a05">
            <head>Documents</head>
            <head>A NEW HARMONY LETTER OF 1851</head>
            <p>The writer of the letter printed below, Robert Dale Owen, is well known to students of Indiana
                    history, as is the recipient, Mrs. Sarah T. Bolton, wife of Nathaniel Bolton an <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> editor. Mrs. Bolton was a notable woman in her day, the author of many poems. Almost
                    anything from Robert Dale Owen is worthy of publication, but the letter here published for the first
                    time has an especial charm. In a most natural manner, the writer reveals his appreciation of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">New Harmony</settlement>
                    </placeName> and his admiration of some of the characters who lived in the village. The original
                    copy of the letter is in the possession of Mr. Benj. D. Hiltz of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>. For the use of a photo-static copy, the <hi rend="i">Magazine</hi> is indebted to Miss
                    Esther U. Mc-Nitt of the Indiana State Library.</p>
            <p rend="center">[ROBERT DALE OWEN TO MRS. SARAH T. BOLTON]</p>
            <p>
                    <text>
                  <body>
                     <div type="letter">
                        <dateline rend="right">
                                    <address>
                              <addrLine>
                                 <placeName>
                                    <settlement type="city">New Harmony</settlement>
                                 </placeName> Inda</addrLine>
                           </address>
                                    <date>July 6, 1851</date>
                                </dateline>
                        <p>The "Home Journal", which you were good enough to send me, and
                                    which I had not recd when I last wrote you has come to hand. Nothing <hi rend="i">cd</hi> be more flattering than the notice it contains. I send you by this post a <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                                    </placeName> paper, containing my address entire, with an editorial notice. Have you
                                    yet received the pamphlets from <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Kent</settlement>
                                    </placeName>? I am glad you liked the [word blurred] style in which they were got
                                    up.</p>
                        <p>It must be confessed, that the whole affair has been eminently successful and
                                    promises to leave behind it important results. To whom the credit is due of
                                    effecting this, I at least, know, if the public does not. I think it will always be
                                    a pleasant reflection to you, that, by dint of perseverance through many obstacles,
                                    you have so efficiently contributed to the good cause of the property rights of your
                                    sex.</p>
                        <p>We have had quite a spirited Fourth of July celebration; an oration, which I was
                                    called to deliver; then a picnic in the woods, got up in a most creditable
                                    style—upwards of 300 persons being seated to a handsomely laid out
                                    dinner; &amp; in the evening a ball, at which upwards of 150 were present.
                                    Nothing could have passed off more harmoniously or decorously or pleasantly than the
                                    entire proceedings. We are truly a social people in our little village, &amp;
                                    never let slip an opportunity of social reunions on easy &amp; pleasant terms;
                                    &amp; as we have few who are rich among us, &amp; [two words missing]
                                    ostentatious display has reached us yet. We get up such celebrations simply
                                    &amp; economically. On this occasion, ball, supper &amp; all, it did not
                                    cost each of US over a dollar; I mean the gentlemen; <pb n="51" id="VAA4025-027-1-055"/> for it is a rule with us never to charge the ladies. In
                                    this way, we can afford to have frequent amusements; &amp; we don't
                                    enjoy them the less, because of their small cost. It is customary for many of our
                                    neighbors, from <placeName>
                              <settlement type="city">Mount Vernon</settlement>,
                                            <settlement type="city">Evansville</settlement>, <settlement type="city">Princeton</settlement>
                           </placeName> &amp; the neighborhood, to attend
                                    our celebrations; &amp; they all admit, that nowhere do they find as pleasant
                                    social gatherings as at Harmony.</p>
                        <p>I have a mind, by way of offering you additional inducement to come and see
                                    us—&amp; also that when you do make out that promised visit, you may
                                    not feel as if you were coming among strangers—to send you a few sketches
                                    of the more notable personages, who make up the society of our little village. I am
                                    bent, you may see, upon securing that visit, if I can.</p>
                        <p>Let me begin with the Flowers, who keep the principal tavern in the place; &amp;
                                    a most comfortable, tidy, <hi rend="i">home-atmospheve</hi> sort of house it is.
                                    They migrated from <placeName>
                                        <country reg="enk">England</country>
                                    </placeName>, some thirty years ago; wealthy farmers on a large scale. Mr. Flowers
                                    having won, for several successive years, the highest prizes for the best Merino
                                    flock of sheep in <placeName>
                                        <country reg="enk">England</country>
                                    </placeName>; prizes which still appear, on his tavern table, in the shape of
                                    handsome pieces of plate. He brought with him the ideas of an improved system of
                                    agriculture inconsistent with the then state of the country; run <hi rend="i">[sic]</hi> through much of his property in unsuccessful attempts to introduce
                                    expensive impYovements; lost many thousand dollars by going security for an idle,
                                    worthless, dissipated son-in-law; and finally the family, having thirty thousand
                                    dollars invested in Bank stock, lost the whole by the failure of that institution.
                                    Throughout all these reverses George Flowers never lost the open-hearted, generous
                                    spirit of a hospitable English gentleman. He kept almost open house long after he
                                    could ill afford it. And, for a long term of years, there was not a stranger
                                    visiting Albion (the name of the settlement he made, in <placeName>
                                        <region type="state" reg="ilu">Illinois</region>
                                    </placeName>, about 25 miles west of this) who was not invited to make his
                                    house—beautifully situated on the edge of a lovely prairie—his
                                    home, so long as he saw fit to stay. Chiefly to pay his security debts, one piece of
                                    property after another went, at a runious sacrifice. And at last, after a long
                                    struggle to save it, the favorite homestead, too, went with the rest. The sole
                                    remaining consolation was that, by such sacrifices, he paid up every debt he owed in
                                    the world, and stood, at last, a free though a landless man. I ought not <hi rend="i">to</hi> say the <hi rend="i">only</hi> consolation, for he had one
                                    which might well support a man under worse reverses than these; the unwaning love of
                                    a high-minded, warm-hearted, spirited woman. Mrs Flowers is quite a character. Even
                                    now, at sixty, or near it, the mother of six or seven children, all of adult age,
                                    after a life of continued labor &amp; renewed disappointment, she retains the
                                    vivacity, &amp; almost the cheerfulness, of early youth. To the remains of great
                                    beauty, she still joins a raciness of wit &amp; a sprightliness of fancy, which
                                    make the life of any society in which she happens to be. I am sure she will amuse
                                    and interest you. You must expect to see an extraordinary looking person; a somewhat
                                    short figure, inclining to em bon point, not bent with age, though the hair is
                                    silvered; an aquiline nose &amp; Eastern looking face; the head often surmounted
                                    by a most voluminous &amp; uncommon looking turban, with lace depending from its
                                    folds; altogether a figure &amp; character, anything but <pb n="52" id="VAA4025-027-1-056"/> commonplace. She took to the toils of tavern-keeping
                                    for a living—&amp; you know what they are in a country like
                                    this—, without a murmur. It was not a great deal more labor or trouble,
                                    she said to me one day, than to keep open house at "Park-place",
                                    as she had been used to do: the only difference which grated on her feelings was,
                                    the making out these odius bills, &amp; demanding so many dollars &amp;
                                    cents from each guest, before they departed. Amid all the cares of the tavern, which
                                    sometimes fall on her without any help whatever, she preserves her spirit unbroken,
                                    &amp; still finds time for a thousand touching little attentions to her husband,
                                    helpless rather from habit than age, &amp; in part from a degree of deafness
                                    which renders an ear-trumpet indispensible. She has usually with her her youngest
                                    daughter, Mary Flower, with a face as pretty as her name, &amp; a disposition
                                    corresponding to both. Mary, with her bright eyes &amp; her real auburn hair
                                    &amp; her nineteen or twenty years, is an excellent, true-hearted girl, without
                                    much literary cultivation, but devoted to her father &amp; mother, inheriting a
                                    spark of her mother's spirit, but unluckily not her mother's
                                    bodily strength; or she could more effectually assist her, in her household cares. A
                                    married son, good like the rest of the family, but somewhat rough in his exterior,
                                    with a pleasant girl for a wife, has lately been added to the household. They have a
                                    large commodious dwelling, rent free, &amp; I believe they are making an humble
                                    but comfortable living. The family have maintained their honor and integrity
                                    unblemished, through all reverses, &amp; are, in consequence, treated with every
                                    respect, and in their fallen fortunes I often spend an agreeable evening with them.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi rend="i">July</hi> 7. My Fourth of July oration, it seems, had great success;
                                    every one, I am told speaks well of it. It is more than I expected; for I had not
                                    even began <hi rend="i">[sic]</hi> to think about what I had to say, until the
                                    afternoon of the third. Until then I had been very busy—you cannot, I am
                                    sure, guess at what. In this village of ours, we have to learn all kinds of trades;
                                    &amp; I had been spending a couple of days, with a young man who did not know a
                                    great deal more about it than I, in papering our entrance hall &amp; staircase.
                                    I think, when all trades fail, I can now set up for paper-hanger. I have been
                                    repairing, renovating &amp; enlarging this old, rambling house of ours;
                                    &amp; though nothing can ever make it handsome, it is now very comfortable. Your
                                    room has been newly painted and I hope you will find it fresh t pleasant.</p>
                        <p>What have you been writing lately? I have not seen a line of yours for an age. Cannot
                                    you spare me a duplicate now &amp; then?—so as to give me some idea
                                    of what you are thinking &amp; feeling. I am very sure, that nothing but such a
                                    quiet st[e]ady life, as you are now leading, is necessary, to make every
                                    year's productions more true &amp; effective and artistical than those
                                    of the preceding. Nothing pleases me more in you, than the consciousness you have so
                                    often expressed to me, that you have powers yet undeveloped, &amp; can write
                                    better than you have yet done. There is no true genius without the continued
                                    striving after excellence. I always sympathize with those who are imbued with it,
                                    even in the everyday business of life; far more, in the higher departments of art.
                                    In truth, what would the world be without it? But I am sure I must have said all
                                    this to you, many times already.</p>
                        <pb n="53" id="VAA4025-027-1-057"/>
                        <p>Have you heard from good Professor Larrabee? I am ashamed to say I have not written
                                    to him yet, but shall do [so] in a day or two. He ought to have a least 20 or 30
                                    copies of the pamphlet, when it comes out. Do you think he has ever repented
                                    accepting a position, which exposed him to bigotry, as a mark to be shat at? He
                                    ought not to repent. He has aided in a successful effort to advance a great and good
                                    cause.</p>
                        <p>I send you a number of an English paper which my father occasionally sends
                                    us—the "Leader"—ably edited. You will find
                                    (p. 494) an address to my father; and, at pp. 490 and 494 (2d column), articles
                                    worth reading. Believe me, ever, My dear Mrs Bolton</p>
                        <closer>
                                    <salute rend="right">faithfully yr friend</salute>
                                    <signed rend="right">Robert Dale Owen</signed>
                                </closer>
                        <trailer>Mrs Sarah T. Bolton</trailer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </text>
                </p>
         </div>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-027-1-a15">
            <p rend="center">THE FIRST STEAMBOAT ON WHITE RIVER</p>
            <p>Some time between 1870 and 1880, John Scott Elder wrote an account of his experiences as a river
                    pilot. Born in <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Lexington</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
               </placeName>, in 1802, this colorful character had many
                    adventures as he guided steamboats up and down mid-western rivers. In 1906, Emma Carleton
                    contributed a portion of the old pilot's story, that relating to a trip on White river, to
                    the <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of History</hi> (11, 95-96), which is reproduced below.</p>
            <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>In 1829, I continued on the steamboat "Victory", running up and down the
                            <geogName>Ohio river</geogName> until near the last of August; then the
                        "Victory" laid up to repair. I then went aboard of the steamboat
                        "Traveler," William Sanders, master, bound for <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">New Orleans</settlement>
                        </placeName>. Yellow fever was raging in <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">New Orleans</settlement>
                        </placeName> at this time. After our safe return from <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">New Orleans</settlement>
                        </placeName>, I asked Captain Sanders for my discharge: he would not hear of it, and went up to
                        Louisvill—mur boat was lying at Shippingsport. When he returned he said: "I
                        have got a full load to go up White river to <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Spencer</settlement>
                        </placeName>." White river empties into the <geogName>Wabash river</geogName> near <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Mt. Carmel</settlement>
                        </placeName>, though on the opposite side of the river; <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Spencer</settlement>
                        </placeName> is in Indiana. So we loaded the boat with salt, and went on our way. Henry
                        Christopher was still my pardner, and neither of us was ever up White river, but we went on our
                        way up the <placeName>
                            <region type="county">Wabash</region>
                        </placeName> to <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Mt. Carmel</settlement>
                        </placeName>, then up the <geogName>White River</geogName>. White river is a small stream and
                        very crooked; we went over mill-dams, though the water was high, and we finally arrived at <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Spencer</settlement>
                        </placeName>. The steamboat "Traveler" was the first steamboat that ever
                        turned a wheel on White river; William Sanders, master.</p>
                    <p>The water commenced falling so we had to hurry out our load of salt, and go out of the river as
                        soon as possible. Saptain Sanders, said we would run down the river about thirty miles, land
                        some passengers, and stay there all night, as we had told him we could not run in the night. It
                        was Christopher's first watch. We went on down White river and landed the passengers,
                        some time in the fore part of the night. The <pb n="54" id="VAA4025-027-1-058"/> Captain then
                        said, "We will go on to-night. Christopher said nothing", and away we went, I
                        told Christopher if he could stand it, I could. So my pardner stood watch until twelve
                        o'clock and then called me up. When I took hold of the wheel I do not think I was ever
                        in such a bad fix in my life, for a man that is a pilot can generally see the river all the way
                        ahead of him. However, I told my pardner that I would go it blind, if there was ever any one
                        time in my life when I longed for the light of day that was the time. So we continued on down
                        and I heard the chickens crow, then I knew it was not long until daylight. The first thing I
                        knew we went into the <geogName>Wabash river</geogName>, then I was all right. The <placeName>
                            <region type="county">Wabash</region>
                        </placeName>, after White river, appeared to be as wide as the <placeName>
                            <region type="state" reg="msu">Mississippi</region>
                        </placeName> and we went on our way repoicing to <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Louisville</settlement>
                        </placeName>, without accident.</p>
                </quote>
         </div>
         <div type="scholarlyArticle" id="VAA4025-027-1-a16">
            <p rend="center">GRAHAM, FROMAN AND HARRISON FAMILIES</p>
            <p rend="center">By A<hi rend="sc">NNIE</hi> L<hi rend="sc">EE</hi> S<hi rend="sc">AMUEL</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The following data on the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> branches of these prominent families may be of value to descendants who are interested
                    in genealogical work. Many of these descendants moved farther on and settled in Indiana, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mou">Missouri</region>
                    </placeName> and other new states.</p>
            <table>
               <head>Revolutionary Soldiers of <placeName>
                            <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                        </placeName>.</head>
               <row>
                  <cell>(Soldiers of the American Revolution Year Book, <placeName>
                                <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                            </placeName> Society, 1896.)</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Amos Graham—<placeName>
                        <region type="county">Washington County</region>,
                                    <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                     </placeName>.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Pensioner under the Act of June 7, 1832.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Began March 4, 1831.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Amos Graham, private, <placeName>
                                <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                            </placeName> militia, Feb. 28, 1833: $40, age 74.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Thomas Graham—Mercer County, <placeName>
                                <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                            </placeName>.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Pensioner under the Act of June 7, 1832.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Began March 4, 1831.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Thomas Graham, private and sergeant—<placeName>
                                <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                            </placeName> militia.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>May 30, 1833: $87, age 75.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <table>
               <head>Marriage Licenses, 1792-1825, <placeName>
                     <region type="county">Washington County</region>,
                                <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                  </placeName>.</head>
               <row>
                  <cell>Date of License</cell>
                  <cell>Names of Parties</cell>
                  <cell>Parent or Guardian.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>March 14, 1797</cell>
                  <cell>William Graham and Susannah Caskey</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Oct. 18, 1797</cell>
                  <cell>John Jackson and Nancy Graham</cell>
                  <cell>Mary A. Graham</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Sept. 24, 1806</cell>
                  <cell>John Graham and Catherine Jones</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>July 11, 1810</cell>
                  <cell>John Graham and Polly Lowe</cell>
                  <cell>Samuel Lowe</cell>
               </row>
               <pb n="55" id="VAA4025-027-1-059"/>
               <row>
                  <cell>July 11, 1810</cell>
                  <cell>John Lowe and Patcy Graham</cell>
                  <cell>Amos Graham</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Aug. 8, 1810</cell>
                  <cell>Thomas Wright and Mary Graham</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Oct. 31, 1811</cell>
                  <cell>Major Farris and Salley Graham</cell>
                  <cell>Amos Graham</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Sept. 1, 1812</cell>
                  <cell>George Houts and Jane GrahamJacob Houts</cell>
                  <cell>Jacob Houts<lb/>Marcus Graham</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Jan. 8, 1812</cell>
                  <cell>David Dickey and Nancy Graham</cell>
                  <cell>Francis Graham</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Jan. 26, 1814</cell>
                  <cell>Andrew Davison and Sally Graham</cell>
                  <cell>Francis Graham</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>May 3, 1815</cell>
                  <cell>Moses Swinney and Dicy Frowman</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Apr. 6, 1815</cell>
                  <cell>Isaac Graham and Rachel Fowler</cell>
                  <cell>Thomas Fowler</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Sept. 9, 1816</cell>
                  <cell>Matthew Byrne and Nancy Graham</cell>
                  <cell>Catherine Graham</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Jan. 10, 1816</cell>
                  <cell>James C. Martin and Janey Graham</cell>
                  <cell>David Graham</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Nov. 17, 1817</cell>
                  <cell>John Graham and Sarah Frowman</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Dec. 26, 1817</cell>
                  <cell>Thomas Lowe and Jane Graham</cell>
                  <cell>Samuel Lowe, Sr.<lb/>Amos Graham</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Dec. 7, 1819</cell>
                  <cell>John A. Fogle and Mary Graham</cell>
                  <cell>Catherine Graham</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>July 11, 1820</cell>
                  <cell>James Graham and Peggy Graham</cell>
                  <cell>David Graham</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>May 28, 1821</cell>
                  <cell>William Graham and Harriett Frowman</cell>
                  <cell>Jacob Frowman</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Jan. 27, 1824</cell>
                  <cell>James Mercer and Ann Graham</cell>
                  <cell>Jane Graham</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Jan. 13, 1824</cell>
                  <cell>David Graham and Mariah Stayton</cell>
                  <cell>Peter Stayton</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Feb. 14, 1824</cell>
                  <cell>James Graham and Mary Newton</cell>
                  <cell>John Newton</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>May 25, 1817</cell>
                  <cell>Erasmus Northcraft and Sally Graham</cell>
                  <cell>Catherine Graham</cell>
               </row>
               <pb n="56" id="VAA4025-027-1-060"/>
               <row>
                  <cell>Nov. 28, 1804</cell>
                  <cell>Samuel Harrison and Ann Scott</cell>
                  <cell>George Scott</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <table>
               <head>Marriages, Nelson County, <placeName>
                            <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                        </placeName>.</head>
               <row>
                  <cell>Date</cell>
                  <cell>Groom</cell>
                  <cell>Bride</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>1790</cell>
                  <cell>Cuthbert Harrison</cell>
                  <cell>Ann Tannyhill</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>1798</cell>
                  <cell>Burr Harrison</cell>
                  <cell>Elizabeth Hynes</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>1799</cell>
                  <cell>Wm. Harrison</cell>
                  <cell>Letty Green</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>1801</cell>
                  <cell>John Harrison</cell>
                  <cell>Agnes Green</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>1809</cell>
                  <cell>Gore Harrison</cell>
                  <cell>Judy Snook</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>1816</cell>
                  <cell>Grove Harrison</cell>
                  <cell>Elizabeth White</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <table>
               <head>Marriages, Logan County, <placeName>
                            <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                        </placeName>.</head>
               <row>
                  <cell>Date</cell>
                  <cell>Groom</cell>
                  <cell>Bride</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Oct. 29, 1836</cell>
                  <cell>James Graham</cell>
                  <cell>Mary Robinson</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Aug. 10, 1837</cell>
                  <cell>Henry D. Hardy</cell>
                  <cell>Mary Grayham</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>1839</cell>
                  <cell>Thos. B. Graham</cell>
                  <cell>Jane E. Sudduth</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Sept. 29, 1842</cell>
                  <cell>Seth J. T. Graham</cell>
                  <cell>Mary Julian McWhirter</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Dec. 12, 1842</cell>
                  <cell>Hugh H. McMillin</cell>
                  <cell>Lucy F. Graham</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Apr. 10, 1844</cell>
                  <cell>Christopher Hardy</cell>
                  <cell>Amanda Graham</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Feb. 22, 1847</cell>
                  <cell>Lewis F. Graham</cell>
                  <cell>Mary M. Coffman</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Sept. 28, 1847</cell>
                  <cell>Robt. L. Graham</cell>
                  <cell>Caroline R. Stokes</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Jan. 23, 1855</cell>
                  <cell>John A. Humphrey (Res. Nelson Co., Ky., age 22, single, b. Nelson Co., Ky.)</cell>
                  <cell>Mary A. Graham (Res. Nelson Co., Ky. age 18, single, b. Nelson Co., Ky.)</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p rend="center">Births</p>
            <p>June 15, 1859, Jesse Crum, male, alive, b. Nelson Co., Ky. Father, Harrison Crum, Mother's
                    maiden name, Julia Ann Graham. Res. of parents, Beechfork.</p>
            <p>March 9, 1859, Matthias <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Benton</region>
                    </placeName>, Male, b. Nelson Co., Ky. Mother's maiden name, Julia P. Graham, white, b.
                    Nelson Co., Ky. Res. of parents Nelson Co., Ky.</p>
            <p rend="center">Marriages</p>
            <p>Oct. 18, 1854, Jas. A. McMillen, (age 22, single, Res. Logan Co., Ky.) and M. J. Graham, (Res. Logan
                    Co., Ky., single, age 21.)</p>
            <p>Nov. 22, 1854, James A. McMillen, (Res. Logan Co., Ky., age 27, <pb n="57" id="VAA4025-027-1-061"/>
                    single, b. Logan Co., Ky.) and Martha A. Graham, (Res. Logan CO., Ky., age 21, singLe, b. Logan Co.,
                    Ky.)</p>
            <p>[Note: Evidently there is a mistake here. Both of the foregoing marriages appear in the original
                    Vital Statistics of Logan County, <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName>, and were copied from them.]</p>
            <p rend="center">Births</p>
            <p>S. E. Graham, maiden name of mother, Logan Co., Ky. A Orndoff, father. Res. of parents Logan Co., Ky.
                    Born a daughter, Oct. 1855, Logan Co., Ky.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="[58]" id="VAA4025-027-1-062"/>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-027-1-a06">
            <head>Reviews and Notices</head>
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">A History of <placeName>
                            <region type="state" reg="mnu">Minnesota</region>
                        </placeName>.</hi> By William Watts Folwell. Four volumes. <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mnu">Minnesota</region>
                    </placeName> Historical Society, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">St. Paul</settlement>
                    </placeName>, 1921-1930. Pp. xvii+515, xviii+477, xiii+605, xviii+ 575.</head>
            <p>The volumes of this work have been greeted as they appeared from time to time during the last ten
                    years with expressions of appreciation and praise by those interested in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mnu">Minnesota</region>
                    </placeName> history. The commendations of the reviewers have been tempered with some criticism, but
                    the impression gained from the work and from the judgment of critics is that of a substantial,
                    comprehensive, scholarly treatise on the political history of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mnu">Minnesota</region>
                    </placeName>. It is a monument to the author whose long and useful life came to a close so quickly
                    after the writing was finished. It is also an excellent example of the type of publication which an
                    adequately financed and managed state historical society can produce.</p>
            <p>The activities of the French, English, and Americans in the pre-territorial period, the acquisition
                    by the <placeName>
                        <country reg="-us">United States</country>
                    </placeName>, the coming of the settlers, and the years of territorial government are the main
                    topics described in the first volume. The admission of the new state (1857-1858), economic
                    flounder-ings in railroad building and banking, the Sioux Outbreak in 1862, and the state in the
                    "slaveholders' rebellion" constitute the story of the second volume. The
                    third takes up the narrative at the close of the Civil War and carries it through to 1925, two of
                    the better chapters are concerned with the "Grangers," and the
                    "Grasshopper Invasion." The years from 1876 to 1909, except for the
                    Spanish-American War, are organized according to gubernatorial administrations. A final chapter
                    chronicles the events of more recent years. Because of the difficulties of presenting in a single
                    narrative the various tangled threads of life in a modern commonwealth, the author reserved for the
                    final volume certain important topics in economic and social history; the development of the iron
                    mines, educational progress, Indian problems, changing electoral procedure, and the contributions of
                    twelve leading citizens to the evolution of the state and its institutions. In each volume important
                    material has been placed in numerous appendices, <pb n="59" id="VAA4025-027-1-063"/> and excellent
                    illustrations and maps have been inter. spersed <hi rend="i">throughout the text.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although no distinction has been noted in the character of the work, previous to the year 1869, it is
                    that of an historian treating events with which he did not have personal contact. In that year the
                    author became President of the University of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mnu">Minnesota</region>
                    </placeName>, and a participant in the events he described. During the later years of his life he
                    was active in collecting material which he used in these volumes. He also employed the sources in
                    the manuscript and newspaper collections of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mnu">Minnesota</region>
                    </placeName> Historical Society, especially the Sibley, Ramsey, and Donnelly papers. It is to be
                    regretted that some important papers of the period since the Civil War have not been available,
                    though the effect is not seen by the reader. It is difficult to understand the motives of
                    descendants who withhold from the Historical Society or the University Library such material. Mr.
                    Folwell's own experience may have made these papers somewhat less essential.</p>
            <p>The author possessed many of the qualifications for his task. It is obvious that he was a skilled
                    investigator, and an industrious collector of evidence. The presentation of his conclusions is
                    scholarly. With a few exceptions he maintained a detachment and lack of bias that is unusual. Quite
                    marked is the ability to summarize. The style is adequate, and in most respects admirable, though it
                    cannot rightly be called brilliant. It is simple, clear, and spirited. The narrative does not lag,
                    although it possesses little romance or stimulus to the imagination.</p>
            <p>The shortcomings of this work can be traced very largely to Mr. Folwell's lack of an
                    historical training and to the times in which he lived. To the latter may be attributed his emphasis
                    upon the political and military, which is in harmony with the conception of history during much of
                    his life. Training under one of the better historians might have enabled him to have associated the
                    history of his state more closely with the progress of the nation. Western historians will look in
                    vain for an account of the racial or sectional contributions to the commonwealth, or the routes by
                    which the settlers came, or the factors which induced them to migrate. There is little evidence that
                    he grasped the significance of geographic or economic forces. In contrast with these shortcomings,
                    it is <pb n="60" id="VAA4025-027-1-064"/> interesting to note that he was aware of the social
                    concept of history and made efforts to embody it in his writing, particularly in the final volume.
                    His success in this endeavor will probably be considered limited by the members of this school of
                    thought. The chronological proportion of the work is not that of the present generation. The fourth
                    volume, composed of various essays not entirely confined to the period since the Civil War, does not
                    overcome the lack of balance occasioned by condensing the narrative of the years since 1865 into the
                    third volume, after the first two had been devoted to the affairs of the small community which
                    existed prior to that date. Folwell was true to the generation that passed through the Civil War
                    when he took the entire second volume for the years 1857 to 1865. If the discussion of Indian
                    affairs received too much space throughout the publication, it is easily forgiven because the
                    thoroughness with which it is done makes it one of the most valuable phases of the work.</p>
            <p>The labor of others, in addition to the author, is involved in this history. The experience and
                    training of the excellent staff of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mnu">Minnesota</region>
                    </placeName> Historical Society has been drawn upon to transform the manuscript into a finished
                    product. The able editor, Solon J. Buck, with the assistance of Theodore C. Blegen, <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Warren</region>
                    </placeName> Upham, Mary E. Wheelhouse, and others, has accomplished a thoroughly creditable piece
                    of editing and publishing. Very few flaws can be found. The table of contents, footnotes,
                    illustrations, maps, and indices are excellent. The appearance of the volumes is neat and dignified.
                    The most serious omission in this part of the work is the lack of a formal bibliography which was
                    promised in the introduction to the first volume. The editor may be quoted in his own defense,
                    "in view of the inclusion of complete bibliographical information with the first reference
                    in each volume to each work cited, it seemed that the principal object of such a bibliography would
                    be achieved by listing the works in the consolidated index."</p>
            <p>Since the fourth volume has recently appeared, it may be briefly considered apart from the others.
                    The chapters are quite different in character and are only loosely associated, The development of
                    the iron mines and the problems of the Chippewa Indians are delineated in a complete and thorough
                    manner. The discussion of the University of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mnu">Minnesota</region>
                    </placeName> is <pb n="61" id="VAA4025-027-1-065"/> supplemental to other published accounts. The
                    chapter entitled "Public Education" is more general but not exhaustive. The final
                    chapter with its biblical title, "The Acts of the Apostles" is a combination of
                    institutional history and biography. It may be suggested that the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mnu">Minnesota</region>
                    </placeName> History Bulletin would have been a more suitable medium of publication for these essays
                    than a separate volume of the history.</p>
            <p>What may be said about the importance of this work? It is chiefly significant to the people of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="mnu">Minnesota</region>
                    </placeName> for whom it was written. It stands out as superior to most of the histories of its
                    type. Since national history is in part a mosaic of that of the states it has a place of wide
                    importance, though its author has failed to take full advantage of this opportunity. It should be
                    useful in assembling special histories of mining and of the Indians. Should one need to be
                    disillusioned about the benevolence of mankind or the enlightened Indian policy of recent years, a
                    reading of the chapter "Chippewa Indian Problems" will be found useful. It has
                    numerous other values. Unquestionably it is a contribution to knowledge.</p>
            <byline>J<hi rend="sc">OHN</hi> D<hi rend="sc">ONALD</hi> B<hi rend="sc">ARNHART</hi>
            </byline>
         </div>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-027-1-a07">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">Lucius B. Swift, a Biography.</hi> By William Dudley Foulke. Indiana Historical
                    Society (<hi rend="i">Publications</hi>, IX), <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, 1930. Pp. vi+153.</head>
            <p>This biography of Lucius B. Swift is a modest and loyal attempt to portray the life of a close friend
                    of nearly half a century. Owing to the intimate friendship between Mr. Foulke and Mr. Swift and
                    between these men and Theodore Roosevelt, the study is uncritical. The book deals prominently with
                    Mr. Swift, Mr. Roosevelt and Civil Service Reform. It is primarily a memorial to Mr. Swift, but
                    secondarily a tribute to Mr. Roosevelt. Although Mr. Foulke was a more influential civil service
                    reformer than Mr. Swift and a more consistent one than Mr. Roosevelt, yet he leaves himself almost
                    entirely out of the story. The book must be read as the tribute of one friend to another.</p>
            <p>Mr. Swift was born on a farm in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="nyu">New York</region>
                    </placeName> in 1844. He entered the Civil War as a private in 1861 and was mustered out as a
                    sergeant in June, 1863. Later he entered <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="miu">Michigan</region>
                    </placeName> University from which institution he was graduated in 1870. To pay his college debt, he
                    entered the teaching profession at <pb n="62" id="VAA4025-027-1-066"/>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">La Porte</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Indiana, and soon was elected Superintendent of the city schools. He moved to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> in 1879 where he set up in the practice of law and where he lived until his death in
                    July, 1929. It is the story of a man who rose from meagre circumstances and made his own career. It
                    was not a spectacular career but it was honest and substantial and devoted to the political
                    betterment of his fellow-men.</p>
            <p>The book is divided into four parts and each part deals with a number of sub-topics. There are four
                    appendices which add to the value of the book. A picture of Mr. Swift as a boy is presented opposite
                    page two, and another as an old man opposite page ninety-eight. Owing to the method of binding, the
                    book is difficult to handle and much of the print is so small that it is tedious reading, but the
                    printing is neatly and accurately done. The table of contents is detailed and the index is adequate.
                    There is no bibliography but the few footnotes and the references cited in the text perhaps
                    sufficiently offset this omission. Approximately half of the book is composed of quotations from
                    various documentary sources, thereby making it of greater value to the student.</p>
            <p>So many sub-headings, however, scattered throughout the book mar the symmetry of the page, and
                    combined with numerous and frequently long quotations, interrupt the continuity of the story. Mr.
                    Foulke is a man of marked literary ability. His style is clear and simple and his remarks between
                    quotations are always to the point, but they are so broken up that the charm is largely destroyed.
                    The narrative would be more readable had the quotations from the documents been better correlated
                    with the narrative, but Mr. Foulke states in his preface that it was his aim "to let Mr.
                    Swift tell his own story in his own words."</p>
            <p>Mr. Swift's chief life interest was civil service reform. Eighty-five of the one hundred and
                    forty-one pages of the biography are devoted to that phase of his life. But he had other interests.
                    Mr. Foulke catalogues some of these (p. 66) but gives little or nothing about them in detail. What
                    of his law practice, his vocation in life? One of his interesting cases was the prosecution of an <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> newspaper on behalf of Julia Marlowe, but Mr. Foulke mentions it only incidentally in a
                    part of a sentence toward the end of the book (p. 124). Further, since Mr. Roosevelt is given half
                    as much space in <pb n="63" id="VAA4025-027-1-067"/> the biography as far as the index is concerned
                    as is Mr. Swift himself, it might have been well to have devoted more space to Mr. Swift's
                    part in the Progressive campaign of 1912. It is only in a couple of pages and then under the title
                    "Taft and the Civil Service," that the Progressive Party is noticed.</p>
            <p>Several of Mr. Roosevelt's letters are quoted at considerable length in reply to letters
                    from Mr. Swift that are only mentioned (pp. 70-71). From page sixty-five on, for several pages, it
                    is difficult to tell whether the story is a biography of Mr. Swift or of Mr. Roosevelt. A letter is
                    quoted (p. 66 note) asking Mr. Swift to help organize the division which Colonel Roosevelt offered
                    to raise for the World War. It would be interesting to know Mr. Swift's reaction to that
                    request.</p>
            <p>Although Mr. Foulke does not mention it, apparently the worst charge ever made against Mr. Swift was
                    that he meddled in affairs that did not concern him. This refers to his persistent and consistent
                    attempts to eradicate the spoils system from state and national governments. But Mr. Swift acted
                    upon the correct conviction "that the public business is every citizen's
                    concern." As a tribute to a friend who is allowed to tell his own story little is wanting,
                    but the student of history would like to know further what Indiana thought of its great citizen.
                    What were the favorable and adverse newspaper comments throughout the years?</p>
            <p>Mr. Foulke states (p. 16) that "…Andrew Jackson supplanted the custom of earlier
                    Presidents to appoint only meritorious persons and not to discharge employees for political
                    reasons." This does not conform with the findings of other students of the spoils
                    system."</p>
            <p>"Mr. Taft", says Mr. Foulke (p. 86), "was personally a sincere friend of
                    civil service reform and during his administration he made further extensions of the classified
                    service. Indeed it then reached a higher percentage of all office holders and employees of the
                    Government than at any other time before or since, but his administration of the law was far less
                    vigorous and effective than Roosevelt's." The last clause of this statement is
                    perhaps too broad and dogmatic. In fact Mr. Foulke is less positive on the same point in his
                    "Fighting the Spoilsmen." Here he says (p. 218), "… it may be
                    doubted whether the service (during Taft's administration) <pb n="64" id="VAA4025-027-1-068"/> was as efficient or as free from political influence as during the
                    administration of President Roosevelt." After an investigation of candidates (Wilson,
                    Roosevelt and Taft) and of platforms during the campaign of 1912, the friends of civil service
                    reform were able to say, "As to candidates the election of 1912 presents no issue for the
                    friends of civil service reform" <hi rend="i">(Good Government</hi>, vol. XXIX, pp. 26,
                    144).</p>
            <p>Mr. Foulke states as a characteristic of Mr. Swift that "he took great care to be sure of
                    his facts" in speech and correspondence. But he was not infallible. He is quoted as saying:
                    "Taft had abandoned Roosevelt's policies and had gone completely over to the ways
                    of Aldrich and Cannon (p. 88), and in regard to the Pinchot-Ballinger controversy that
                    "Taft blundered from the beginning to the end." (p. 82). When Mr, Foulke says (p.
                    82) that "Gifford Pinchot who had been at the head of the Forestry Bureau but had been
                    dismissed by Taft", he might have added on behalf of the latter, "for
                    insubordination." At least, he should have recognized that the controvery had two sides.</p>
            <p>Mr. Swift fought for his country in the Civil War; he fought for it in the eighteen eighties and
                    nineties in the line of civil service reform; he fought for it during the World War by speaking and
                    writing against the German threat and by serving as chairman of the District Conscription Board at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>: and after the war he struggled to educate his fellow citizens in the fundamentals of
                    their constitutional background. It is a splendid record of service and sacrifice. All this the
                    reader gets from Mr. Foulke's biography. Compared with the glories and victories of these
                    struggles any criticisms of the warrior and his good biographer, who was his comrade in most of
                    them, are petty indeed. The biography is a valuable addition to the Indiana Historical
                    Society's <hi rend="i">Publications.</hi>
            </p>
            <byline>F<hi rend="sc">RED</hi> E. B<hi rend="sc">RENGLE</hi>
            </byline>
         </div>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-027-1-a08">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">The Archaeology of the <geogName>Whitewater Valley</geogName>.</hi> By Frank M.
                    Setzler. Indiana Historical Bureau (Indiana History Bulletin, Vol. VII, No. 12), <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, 1930. Pp. 196 (353-549).</head>
            <p>This bulletin is a report of an archaeological surrey of the <geogName>Whitewater Valley</geogName>,
                    Indiana, made by Frank M. Setzler in the summers of 1928 and 1929. The counties covered by this
                    survey <pb n="65" id="VAA4025-027-1-069"/> are <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Franklin</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Union, <placeName>
                  <region type="county">Fayette</region>, <region type="county">Wayne</region>
               </placeName>, and the southern part of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Randolph</settlement>
                    </placeName>.</p>
            <p>The following is the list of prehistoric remains studied by Mr. Setzler in the <geogName>Whitewater
                        Valley</geogName>: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>
                     <placeName>
                                <region type="county">Franklin county</region>
                            </placeName>,—50 earth mounds, 29 of which had been destroyed, and 13 stone
                            mounds.</p>
                        <p>
                     <placeName>
                                <region type="county">Fayette County</region>
                            </placeName>,—5 earth mounds, 2 earth mounds which had been destroyed, and 14
                            camp sites.</p>
                        <p>Union County,—14 earth mounds and a large village site.</p>
                        <p>
                     <placeName>
                                <region type="county">Wayne County</region>
                            </placeName>,—20 earth mounds, 7 destroyed mounds, 3 earthworks, and a gravel
                            bank from which, by report, 30 skeletons had been removed several years ago.</p>
                        <p>
                     <placeName>
                                <region type="county">Randolph County</region>
                            </placeName> (<placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                            </placeName> Township.),—3 large earth mounds.</p>
                    </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Six mounds of the Whitewater group, three earth mounds and three stone mounds, were carefully
                    excavated. All six are in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Franklin county</region>
                    </placeName>. "Mound Camp" was the first to be excavated. It is on the east side
                    of the Whitewater about three miles below <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Brookville</settlement>
                    </placeName>. It is situated on a second terrace about 75 feet above the river. River cutting and
                    highway construction had removed over half this mound and the remnant was the part excavated for
                    archaeological purposes. The human bones were so completely disarticulated that it was concluded
                    that they represent reburials. Many broken artifacts indicate ceremonial breaking, a feature common
                    in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Hopewell</settlement>
                    </placeName> mounds of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName>.</p>
            <p>The second excavation was that of the Stoops Mound. It is located on a high ridge 1 1/2 miles west of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Brookville</settlement>
                    </placeName>. Beneath the center a burnt clay floor was found. No skeletal materials were found and
                    but few artifacts. These consisted of slate gorgets, projectile point, slate Celts, and a
                    "laurel leaf" chalcedony blade. These finds furnish little basis for the
                    identification of culture.</p>
            <p>The other earth mound excavated was the Whitehead Mound near the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName>-Indiana line, and in the drainage basin of the Great Miami River. Excavations of the
                    mound yielded a group of three undisturbed skeletons, a group of two undisturbed skeletons, a
                    reburial of three skeletons, one slate gorget, <pb n="66" id="VAA4025-027-1-070"/> a celt blade, a
                    broken gorget drilled, and many pieces of broken pottery. Setzler deems the evidence too scanty to
                    indicate the culture of this mound. However, Shetrone in his recently published book, "The
                    Mound-Builders," places this mound in the Adena culture of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> area.</p>
            <p>In the Precht stone mound a few bone fragments and no artifacts were discovered. In the Pierson stone
                    mound a bundle reburial of a child was found. Several skulls and other bones all badly broken were
                    discovered. These indicated re-burials. Among these broken bones were many artifacts consisting of
                    flint spawls, bone implements, arrowheads, and pieces of pottery. In the C. B. Martin stone mound,
                    small fragments of bones were found and two crude slate Celts. The scant archaeological evidences in
                    these three stone mounds make it impossible to draw any conclusions.</p>
            <p>Setzler believes that the archeological remains of the <geogName>Whitewater Valley</geogName>
                    indicate the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Hopewell</settlement>
                    </placeName>, Adena, and Fort Ancient cultures of the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> area, but, he is careful to make no definite conclusions until further studies can be
                    made.</p>
            <p>One of the many strong features of this report is the full detailed description of the methods of
                    excavation. In the years since the first excavations in Indiana, hundreds of mounds have been opened
                    by amateur archaeologists and collectors; and the careless work in large measure destroyed the
                    scientific value of the excavations. If all the mounds opened by the amateurs had been carefully
                    excavated and the skeletons and other finds properly preserved, what a wealth of archaeological
                    material we would have in Indiana!</p>
            <p>Excellent illustrations enhance, the value of this bulletin.</p>
            <byline>F<hi rend="sc">RED</hi> J. B<hi rend="sc">REEZE</hi>
            </byline>
         </div>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-027-1-a09">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">Excavation of Albee Mound, 1926-1927.</hi> By J. A<hi rend="sc">RTHUR</hi> M<hi rend="sc">CLEAN</hi>. Indiana Historical Bureau (Indiana History Bulletin, Vol. VIII, No. 4), <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, 1931. Pp. 85 (91-176).</head>
            <p>This bulletin is the report of the thorough and scientific excavation of a large mound known as the
                    Albee Mound, near Fairbanks in <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Sullivan County</region>
                    </placeName>, Indiana. Its exact location is the southeast corner of Section 6, T. 9 N., R. 10 W. It
                    lies on the edge of the upland and overlooks the broad valley of the <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wabash</region>
                    </placeName> to the west.</p>
            <pb n="67" id="VAA4025-027-1-071"/>
            <p>The work was begun in the summer of 1926 and was completed in the summer of 1927. The magnitude of
                    the excavation is indicated by the fact that during the second summer twenty shovelers, and four
                    double-horse scoops with drivers were engaged in the removal of the earth, under the direction of
                    Mr. McLean and his assistants.</p>
            <p>Forty-one burials were found, each containing a skeleton or parts of a skeleton, together with
                    various artifacts. These were carefully preserved and catalogued. The artifacts found are
                    arrowpoints, stone scrapers, hammerstones, stone axes, stone pendants, copper beads, bone scrapers,
                    bone needles, bone awls, shell beads, copper beads, and carapaces of turtles. Two of the most
                    interesting artifacts are a bone needle and a string of shell beads. The needle, which is nearly
                    nine inches long, was found ten feet below the surface. One end is pointed, and near the other end
                    is a small hole for the insertion of thread. It has a high polish from use and is beautiful in form
                    and workmanship. The string of beads was found near the skeleton of a child. Near the beads was a
                    copper <hi rend="i">gorget</hi> which had been worn on the breast of the child; and the blue copper
                    oxide, formed by the weathering of the metallic copper, had preserved the thread so perfectly that
                    the beads were still strung intact. The preservation of this fibrous thread although protected by
                    the copper oxide indicates comparative recency of burial.</p>
            <p>The author of this bulletin assigns the culture represented by these artifacts to a period later than
                    that of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Hopewell</settlement>
                    </placeName> stage of prehistoric cultures.</p>
            <p>One of the outstanding features of this report is the description of the methods of excavation. This
                    work can serve as a model for future excavations in Indiana.</p>
            <p>Many excellent illustrations add greatly to the value of this publication.</p>
            <p>Appendix I of this bulletin is a classification of the stone artifacts on the basis of their
                    lithologic character. This was done by Dr. W. N. Logan, State Geologist of Indiana. Appendix Il is a
                    report by E. Y. Guernsey of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Bedford</settlement>
                    </placeName> of an examination of the skeletal materials taken from the mound. It emphasizes the
                    fine state of preservation of all skeletons and parts of skeletons. Appendix III is a useful and
                    much-needed bibliography on Indiana archaeology.</p>
            <byline>F<hi rend="sc">RED</hi> J. B<hi rend="sc">REEZE</hi>
            </byline>
         </div>
         <pb n="68" id="VAA4025-027-1-072"/>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-027-1-a10">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">La Salle.</hi> By R<hi rend="sc">OSS</hi> F. L<hi rend="sc">OCKRIDGE</hi>. The World
                    Book Company, Yonkers-on-Hudson, 1931. Pp. xv+312, illustrated.</head>
            <p>I have read very many of the histories relating to La Salle and his explorations—my
                    library shelves are filled with books about New <placeName>
                        <country reg="fr">France</country>
                    </placeName> and the Great Lakes country and the fascinating story of the intrepid men who planted
                    the cross of the church and the arms of Louis XIV throughout the central west, and if I had not had
                    access to this mass of literature and wanted simply to know about Ren6 Robert Cavelier, sieur da la
                    Salle, and his exploits in behalf of his country and his king, I would get it all from Ross F.
                    Lockridge's latest book, <hi rend="i">La Salle</hi>, just off the press—which I
                    trust will be on, every book counter, in every library and in every school in the country. I have
                    read it carefully and checked it up mentally with Parkman, Sparks, Winsor, Margry, Abbott, <hi rend="i">et al</hi> and it "clicks" beautifully. The careful reader of this
                    modest book will get more out of it than he will by reading through all the rest, which statement
                    must not be taken as a reflection on them.</p>
            <p>What particularly pleased me and which makes for ready understanding, is the insertion in the text as
                    the story proceeds, of much original matter taken verbatim from the <hi rend="i">Jesuit
                    Relations</hi>, contemporary letters and extracts from diaries, all of which having hen written
                    while the drama was on the stage, gives undoubted authenticity to the narrative thus avoiding the
                    coloring and the embroidery that many historians delight to hang on their stories. Here are
                    down-right facts backed by authority. Lockridge, instead of using foot notes referring to the books
                    from which he gleans, and practically asking the reader to look it up for himself, avoids that
                    custom, and inserts in the proper places in his narrative the actual language used at the moment of
                    the episode he is describing.</p>
            <p>His description of La Salle's conference with the Miamis under the Council Oak on the <placeName>
                        <region type="county">St. Joseph</region>
                    </placeName>-Kankakee portage in May, 1681, together with the masterly oration of La Salle and the
                    dramatic reply of the Miami chief assenting to the confederacy with the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ilu">Illinois</region>
                    </placeName>, is only one of the fine passages in this fine book.</p>
            <p>I will mention here the fact that under the tree identified as the old Council Oak to which reference
                    is made above, there has been placed a huge boulder bearing a bronze tablet memorializing <pb n="69" id="VAA4025-027-1-073"/> the conference, which, as Lockridge says, united the Miamis and the <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ilu">Illinois</region>
                    </placeName> to resist the aggressions of the Iro-quois. I will also add that the grand old tree is
                    an object of the greatest solicitude and its life will, by constant expert attention be prolonged to
                    the very limit, to the end that future generations will have the pleasure of standing under its wide
                    spreading branches and realizing the part it played in the picturesque and dramatic episode there
                    enacted in May 1681.</p>
            <p>My friendship with and admiration for the author as a man and as a historian whom I hold in high
                    esteem, do not in the slightest degree color my judgment of his <hi rend="i">La Salle.</hi> If he
                    were an utter stranger to me, my estimate of the book would be the same as I have expressed. I am
                    proud to place it on my shelves along with his <hi rend="i">4. Lincoln</hi> and his <hi rend="i">George Rogers Clark</hi> and all the rest. It is a lovely tale beautifully told and it should
                    have wide reading and, as we are now, this year, observing the Quarto-millennia1 of La
                    Salle's greatest achievement which took place on the soil of this state, the book under
                    review is particularly timely and I trust its reading will awaken a new interest in our first
                    Hoosier.</p>
            <byline>O<hi rend="sc">TTO</hi> M. K<hi rend="sc">NOBLOCK</hi>
            </byline>
         </div>
         <div type="bookReview" id="VAA4025-027-1-a11">
            <head>
               <hi rend="i">Johnny Appleseed and His Time, an Historical Romance.</hi> By H<hi rend="sc">ENRY</hi> A. P<hi rend="sc">ERSHING</hi>. Shenandoah Publishing House, Strasburg (<placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="vau">Virginia</region>
                    </placeName>), 1930. Pp. xx+379, illustrated.</head>
            <p>This is the first complete biography ever written of John Chapman, who was known to the settlers of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> and Indiana as Johnny Appleseed. It was the purpose of the author to weave the facts
                    and legends about Johnny Appleseed into an historical romance. The author had no intention of
                    writing a book that would stand successfully the test of historical criticism, but one that would
                    enlighten the general reader as to the real contribution of Johnny Appleseed to the middle west. The
                    author writes in an entertaining manner, and his survey of the life of this interesting character is
                    as comprehensive as could be expected in this type of work.</p>
            <p>The career of Johnny Appleseed is one of the most interesting and unique in the history of the middle
                    west. He has been called the "patron saint of the American orchard." This
                    picturesque man, who for forty-six years planted appleseeds in the middle west, appeals to the
                    imagination. He first appeared <pb n="70" id="VAA4025-027-1-074"/> in <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> about 1801. He kept ahead of the settlers and each year planted his seeds farther west.
                    In this way he covered most of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> and came far into Indiana. He died near Fort <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wayne</region>
                    </placeName> in 1847. It was due to the untiring efforts of Johnny Appleseed that many people
                    settling in Indiana and <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> during the first quarter of the 19th century found orchards waiting for them. Johnny
                    Appleseed led a busy life planting nurseries, teaching farmers apple culture, assisting them in
                    caring for their orchards, and preaching the Swedenborgian religion at the same time. This strange
                    character did a great deal toward making the lives of the settlers of Indiana and <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="ohu">Ohio</region>
                    </placeName> pleasant and endurable. The people of both states owe him a debt of gratitude.</p>
            <p>Mr. Pershing has not been unduly careful in his handling of chronology, to say the least. In his zeal
                    to do his character justice he has committed several errors. His account of Johnny
                    Appleseed's experiences with Daniel <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Boone</region>
                    </placeName> will hardly stand rigid investigation. He relates that Johnny witnessed the capture of <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Boone</region>
                    </placeName> by the Shawnees and tells of their effort to make him a member of the tribe. It is true
                    that <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Boone</region>
                    </placeName> did undergo such an experience, but it was in 1778 when John Chapman was a mere boy in
                    his New <placeName>
                        <country reg="enk">England</country>
                    </placeName> home. It is also very doubtful whether Johnny Appleseed covered as much territory and
                    was a participant in so many of the great events of the day as Mr. Pershing gives him credit for in
                    his narrative. There is no mention of Johnny Appleseed in the papers of William Henry Harrison
                    although the author assigns him an important role in the battle of Tippecanw. These are examples of
                    what the reader must be on his guard against when reading the book.</p>
            <p>Mr. Pershing, however, has done a useful and laudable work. His purpose in writing the biography was
                    to instill in the hearts of the people of the nation a real appreciation of the life and work of
                    Johnny Appleseed. The book, it can confidently be expected, will do this.</p>
            <byline>P<hi rend="sc">OWELL</hi> M<hi rend="sc">OORE</hi>
            </byline>
         </div>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-027-1-a12">
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">A Centennial Handbook</hi> covering the first one hundred years (1830-1930) of the
                    Indiana Historical Society appeared late in 1930. This very useful and interesting pamphlet (Indiana
                        <pb n="71" id="VAA4025-027-1-075"/> Historical Society, <hi rend="i">Publications</hi>, Vol. X,
                    No. 1) is edited by Dr. Christopher B. Coleman. It includes a roster of officers of the Society from
                    the beginning to the present, the Legislative Charter granted by the General Assembly in 1831, the
                    Constitution of the Society, the roster of the officers and members (November 15, 1930), and a
                    complete list of the <hi rend="i">Publications</hi> of the Society.</p>
            <p>Thirty-eight pages out of a total of seventy-nine are devoted to "The Indiana Historical
                    Society: A Hundred Years" by Dr. James A. Woodburn, President of the Society from 1923 to
                    1930, and now President Emeritus. This summary of the history of the Society has been welcomed with
                    great interest by the older members, while young members have found in it useful information and an
                    inspiration to carry on the activities of the Society without faltering or lowering of standards.
                    Brief biographical statements relating to outstanding personages who contributed to the success of
                    the Society in the past are included. Especially valuable are the passages in which the writings of
                    those, who, like John B. Dillon, William H. English, Jacob P. Dunn, and Logan Esarey, have written
                    extensively on Indiana and the Old Northwest, are evaluated.</p>
            <p>The closing paragraph of the paper is worthy of reproduction. In this Doctor Woodburn says: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>But after all, the success of this Society has depended, not on the few, not on a handful of
                            managers, but on the rank and file of its membership. Their interest and faithfulness have
                            made possible the work that has been accomplished. We still hope that our membership may
                            reach into the thousands, and that the people of Indiana in the hundred years to come may
                            find more and more interest and pride in their history and become even more constant in
                            their support of the agencies that are seeking to preserve this history and to make it known
                            to future ages.</p>
                    </quote>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">National and State Banks</hi>, by Leonard C. Helderman, associate professor of History, <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Washington</settlement>
                    </placeName> and Lee University, has recently been issued by the Houghton Mifflin Company. This
                    monograph, a Hart, Schaffner &amp; Marx Prize Essay of one hundred seventy-eight pages, includes
                    a chapter relating to banking in the Old Northwest. The volume will be reviewed in our next
                issue.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="[72]" id="VAA4025-027-1-076"/>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-027-1-a13">
            <head>Indiana Historical Society</head>
            <byline>B<hi rend="sc">Y</hi> C<hi rend="sc">HRISTOPHER</hi> B. C<hi rend="sc">OLEMAN</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>The Indiana Historical Society last December celebrated the centennial of its organization which
                    occurred at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName>, December 11, 1830. The first hundred years of the society's existence has
                    been checkered. It has the honor of being one of the earliest state historical societies now in
                    existence, but as Professor Evarts B. Greene, president of the American Historical Association in
                    his address on the occasion of the centennial remarked, part of the time the Indiana Historical
                    Society has been like Lost River, flowing underground without any manifestation of its existence. No
                    publications of the society were put in permanent from until 1897. The membership of the society
                    remained very small, usually less than a hundred, even during the years of its revived activity,
                    until within the last ten years.</p>
            <p>The problem now before the society is the enlargement of its activities and the production of more
                    important results in the next hundred years of its existence. The centennial year brought the total
                    membership of the society up to 1204. This membership should be greatly increased. If the state is
                    to become historically minded, four or five thousand is the least number which would seem to
                    represent adequately the element of our population which has an interest in the preservation of the
                    past and in an intelligent view of the present, based upon knowledge of the past. The executive
                    committee is developing an organization, which it is hoped, will produce considerable results. An
                    All-State Membership Committee, organized last year, is to be continued with as many changes of
                    personnel as possible so as to reach new people. Special attention is to be paid to the teachers of
                    the state who have not hitherto been represented in the society in as large numbers as they ought to
                    be. Edgar T. Forsyth, of Shortridge High School, has been appointed chairman of the committee on
                    high schools and their relation to the society. Professor Albert L. Kohlmeier, of Indiana
                    University, has been appointed chairman of a similar college and university section. A circular has
                    been printed, describing the work of the society and the privileges of membership. The secretary of
                    the society will be glad to have the readers of the <hi rend="i">Magazine</hi> aid in the
                    distribution of this circular <pb n="73" id="VAA4025-027-1-077"/> and will, upon request, send any
                    number of them from his office, 334 State House. There are a large number of people in the state who
                    would be glad to join in the work of the society if they were personally given an invitation to do
                    so. Some confusion still exists as to the requirements of membership. There is no requirement of
                    ancestral residence in the state, as in the case of the Society of Indiana Pioneers. All persons of
                    good character interested in history are cordially invited to become members.</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of History</hi> is vitally interested in the increase of the
                    membership in the Indiana Historical Society. Under an agreement between the Magazine and the
                    society, the <hi rend="i">Magazine</hi> is sent to all members of the society in return for the
                    payment of a reduced subscription for each member by the Society. The larger part of the circulation
                    of the <hi rend="i">Magazine</hi> comes th!rough this channel. The circulation, however, is as yet
                    not sufficiently large to secure such economical printing and management as to pay the costs
                    involved. Consequently, Indiana University is annually called upon to pay a more or less
                    considerable deficit. While the <hi rend="i">Magazine</hi> is one of the important educational
                    agencies of the University and entitled to its financial support, there are so many demands upon the
                    resources of the University for work which cannot possibly bring in compensating returns, that the
                        <hi rend="i">Magazine</hi> should be put upon as nearly a self Supporting basis as possible. A
                    membership of four or five thousand in the Indiana Historical Society will not only make the <hi rend="i">Magazine</hi> self supporting but will make possible an increase in its size and in the
                    scope of its articles.</p>
            <p>The Executive Committee of the Society is planning to make the work which it did in preserving data
                    about the building of the School for the Blind, a permanent feature of its program. A committee npon
                    the preservation of data, photographs and other material of important buildings threatened with
                    destruction, is to be appointed. Interest, at the Indiana History Conference last December, in the
                    discussion of old covered bridges has led to the appointment of a committee up. on bridges; or, as
                    one of the ladies present humorously remarked, a "Bridge Committee." Instead of
                    giving bridge parties, however, it is to gather information about the oldest and most important
                    wooden bridges about the state and to <pb n="74" id="VAA4025-027-1-078"/> promote the preservation
                    of such bridges as can and should be allowed to remain in place, either as part of our highway
                    system or as historical monuments no longer used by traffic.</p>
            <p>Another feature to be developed is the historical museum. Quarters in the main building of the
                    Indiana World War Memorial have been assigned to the Indiana Historical Society. This will be an
                    ideal place for the preservation and exhibition of historical material. A general museum would
                    seemingly be inappropriate in a building devoted to the memory of the state's participation
                    in the World War; but material illustrating the history of the state, especially material connected
                    with the World War, would be a most desirable feature in the World War Memorial. The historical
                    society can do a great service by beginning and promoting this development.</p>
            <p>The; established activities of the Society are to be COIItinued. Besides cooperation in the
                    distribution of the <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of History</hi>, it will secure for its members
                    the <hi rend="i">Irtdiana History Bulletin</hi>, published monthly by the Indiana Historical Bureau.
                    Out of nearly a dozen manuscripts on hand or promised for publication, at least two or three will be
                    issued this year. The midyear historical tour and meeting is being planned by a committee recently
                    appointed by the Executive Committee. The Society will cooperate with the Society of Indiana
                    Pioneers—these two organizations have hitherto paid all the expenses
                    involved—in the annual Indiana History Conference which is held in December of each year.</p>
            <p>The thanks and good wishes, not only of the members of the Society but of the whole state, are
                    extended to two of the officers of the historical society who have resigned after long and honorable
                    service. Professor James A. Woodburn throughout his long career at Indiana University was an active
                    member and supporter of the Society and vice-president from 1910 to 1923. He served as president
                    from 1923 to the end of 1930. As president emeritus, his interest in the Society and the interest of
                    the Society in him continue unabated. Charles E. Coffin, treasurer of the Society since 1894, a
                    period of thirty-six years, has felt that the burden of this work should be passed on to younger
                    hands, and early in January insisted upon the acceptance of his resignation.</p>
            <p>The present officers of the society are: James A. Wood-burn, President Emeritus; Evans Wollen,
                    President; Richard <pb n="75" id="VAA4025-027-1-079"/> B. Wetherill, First Vice-president; Mrs.
                    Harvey Morris, Second Vice-president; Arthur G. Mitten, Third Vice-president; John G. Rauch,
                    Treasurer; Christopher B. Coleman, Secretary.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="[76]" id="VAA4025-027-1-080"/>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-027-1-a14">
            <head>Comment and News</head>
            <p>The sudden death of Kin Hubbard ("Abe Martin") on December 26, 1930, was a calamity. The American
                    people, including hard-headed business men, politicians, educators, lawyers, the medical fraternity,
                    gentlemen of the cloth, the "four-hundred" of every city, as well as just folks,
                    needed and needed badly the tonic of Kin's deep, homely wisdom. He had a true sense of
                    humor, the meaning of which is that he could penetrate to the inwardness of things and recognize the
                    incongruities present. Present day America needs statesmen, economists, educators, historians,
                    scientists, but above all, kindly, keen critics like "Abe Martin." Kin Hubbard has
                    gone and a great unfilled space remains. When shall his like appear again?</p>
            <p>Taxation is a theme that engages the attention of everyone, especially in periods of business
                    depression. Citizens of every walk of life desire to contribute less to the public revenues, but
                    almost every element is in reality opposed to smaller appropriations for public purposes. Changing
                    economic processes have thrown the old taxation system out of adjustment. There is a great need that
                    owners of certain newer forms of property shall be required to pay in proportion to what is exacted
                    of the possessers of older, easily recognized forms of property. Changes in'this direction
                    have been too long delayed. They should have come gradually keeping pace with a changing business
                    rbgime. To transform the existing system of taxation into one that will bear justly on all economic
                    classes, requires a struggle with powerful interests that are wedded to the existing modes of
                    raising public revenues. Reforms will undoubtedly be brought about, but will necessarily come
                    slowly.</p>
            <p>Aside from the inequalities and injustices of the archaic system of taxation in use, there is another
                    phase of the problem that should more often be made a matter of inquiry by the taxpayer. He is sure
                    to show concern about the size of his tax-bill, but he should always ask, "What do I get in
                    return for my checks that go for taxes?" Few try to find the answer to this question. In
                    most instances, it would be impossible to <pb n="77" id="VAA4025-027-1-081"/> obtain equal benefits
                    for the same outlay, if privately obtained. Some things that everyone must have can only be secured
                    through cooperation with the general body of citizens. Other things can be purchased in better
                    quality, in greater abundance and at the same time more cheaply by the taxation route than by any
                    other. Thousands of citizens would do well to compare and contrast what comes to them as a result of
                    taxes paid with what they acquire through the private expenditure of equal sums.</p>
            <p>Indiana has many public libraries and many high schools. Is it possible that any library or any high
                    school in the state can afford to be without the <hi rend="i">Bulletins</hi> and <hi rend="i">Publications</hi> of the Indiana Historical Society and the <hi rend="i">Ipzdiana Magazine of
                        Histors</hi>? There are very many libraries in Indiana that do not supply their readers with
                    this important material which is constantly coming out in the field of Indiana history. There are
                    numbers of high school students who do not have access to the current writings pertaining to the
                    history of the state. The funds at the disposal of many local Iibraries and high schools are very
                    limited, but when so limited that $3.00 can not be appropriated for membership in the
                    Indiana Historical Society, there are no doubt in every community so situated public-spirited
                    citizens who will come to the rescue.</p>
            <p>A short time after this issue reaches our readers, the annual meeting of the <geogName>Mississippi
                        valley</geogName> Historical Association will be held at <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Lexington</settlement>, <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
               </placeName>. The
                    sessions will begin on Thursday, April 30, and continue through Friday and Saturday, May 1 and 2.
                    The program will be varied and interesting, dealing with several different phases and periods of
                        <geogName>Mississippi valley</geogName> history. A trip to the metropolis of the famous Blue
                    Grass region of <placeName>
                        <region type="state" reg="kyu">Kentucky</region>
                    </placeName> in spring time by anyone from Indiana, whatever the route taken or the mode of travel,
                    should prove highly enjoyable. There are several excellent reasons why many Hoosiers interested in
                    history should attend the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Lexington</settlement>
                    </placeName> meeting.</p>
            <p>The <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Richmond</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Palladium</hi>, which was established in 1831, has rounded out a century of worthy
                    existence. In an unusually fine edition of January 1, 1931, this newspaper celebrated <pb n="78" id="VAA4025-027-1-082"/> its hundredth anniversary. The magazine of sixty-two pages, the notable
                    part of this special edition, is filled with extremely interesting matter largely culled from the
                    files of the <hi rend="i">PalMiurn.</hi> The magazine includes a history of the newspaper by Luther
                    M. Feeger. It is accompanied by a <hi rend="i">fac-simile</hi> reproduction of the four-page issue
                    of January 8, 1831, the second issue of the <hi rend="i">Palladium.</hi> The magazine carries
                    numerous illustrations which lend much to its interest. Only one newspaper in Indiana, the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="i">Sun</hi>, is older than the <hi rend="i">Palladium.</hi> Each has exerted a great
                    influence in the history of the state. May both continue to live, becoming with the passing years
                    more vigorous, more fearless, more liberal and more progressive.</p>
            <p>The reproduction in this issue of the <hi rend="i">Magazine</hi> of a brief portion of a narrative of
                    his experiences by an old river pilot, John Scott Elder, raises the question of the whereabouts of
                    the entire manuscript. The interesting account of the steamboat trip up the White river to <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Spencer</settlement>
                    </placeName> and back to the <placeName>
                        <region type="county">Wabash</region>
                    </placeName>, in 1829, was contributed to the <hi rend="i">Magazine</hi> in June, 1906, by Emma
                    Carleton. Any information concerning the original document written by Mr. Elder will be gladly
                    received.</p>
            <p>Dean Frank Smith Bogardus, since September, 1904, a member of the faculty of the Indiana State
                    Teachers College of <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Terre Haute</settlement>
                    </placeName>, died on March 18, at the age of fifty-six. From 1904 until his death Mr. Bogardus! was
                    professor of European history. As a thorough and much respected teacher of history and head of the
                    department, he left a deep impress on the lives of many young men and women of Indiana. As an active
                    and courageous member of the faculty and dean, he was a very real force in the life of the
                    institution which he served. He was a member of the Indiana Historical Society, at the last
                    conference of which, he read a paper on Daniel W. Voorhees. We are glad to announce that this sketch
                    will appear in our June issue.</p>
            <p>The Harrison Mansion at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> is one of the oldest and most interesting buildings in Indiana. The <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> Chapter, Daughters of the American Revolution, owns and most unselfishly cares for this
                    old home which William Henry <pb n="79" id="VAA4025-027-1-083"/> Harrison built and occupied while
                    Governor of Indiana Territory. This Chapter has prepared a beautiful souvenir plate to be disposed
                    of in the interest of the old Harrison House. A picture of this plate we are privileged to use on
                    the first cover page of the <hi rend="i">Mugazine</hi> during the present year. The article which we
                    carry in this issue, "Harrison's Councils with Te-cumseh," was written by
                    a member of the <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Vincennes</settlement>
                    </placeName> Chapter of the D. A. R. at our request.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="80" id="VAA4025-027-1-084"/>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-027-1-a17">
            <head>Reprints</head>
            <p>Reprints of any paper published in the <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of History</hi> may be obtained
                    by any contributor. Estimates of the cost will be furnished on request and an order placed for as
                    many reprints of any article as may be desired by the author.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="editorialMaterial" id="VAA4025-027-1-a18">
            <head>Wanted</head>
            <p>We are sure that some of our readers can aid us to obtain the desired publications listed below. The
                    Library of Indiana University and other libraries in different parts of the country are in need of
                    copies of the issues mentioned in order to complete files. For older and rarer numbers, prices above
                    the regular rates will be paid. Persons possessing any of the desired magazines or other
                    publications, will confer a great favor by writing to Dr. R. C. Buley, Business Manager of the <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of History.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">The Indianian.</hi> This magazine was published at <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Indianapolis</settlement>
                    </placeName> from 1896 to 1904 or 1906, six volumes in all. Wanted, a complete file. Partial sets
                    will be considered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Indiana, Past and Present.</hi> This little, temporary periodical was published during
                    1914. Wanted, a complete file, and also an extra copy of Number 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">The Open Road.</hi> Wanted copies of this monthly for: March, April, May, June, July,
                    August, September, and November, 1910; March, July, August, and September, 1911; April and May,
                    1912; July, 1913; January, 1914.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Bulletins</hi> of the Indiana Historical Commission. Numbers 16 and 18. These contain
                    the <hi rend="i">Proceedings</hi> of the Southwestern Indiana Historical Society for 1922 and 1923.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Commencement Programs</hi> of Indiana University. Wanted to complete the file of the
                    University Library the following, <pb n="81" id="VAA4025-027-1-085"/> but duplicates of those listed
                    and of any programs prior to 1900 will be accepted and valued: Programs of 1st to 19th
                    commencements, 1828-1848; 22nd to 24th, 1851-1853; 26th to 28th, 1855-1857; 30th and 31st,
                    1859-1860; 33rd to 43rd, 1862-1872; 44th and 45th, 1873-1874; 47th, 1876 50th and 51st, 1879-1880;
                    53rd, 1882; 55th and 56th, 1884-1885; 59th and 60th, 1887-1888; 52nd, 1891; 64th, 1893-1897.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Indiana School Journal.</hi> Wanted vol. 37, numbers, 7-8 (1892); vol. 38, numbers 6, 9,
                    10, 11, 12 (1893); vol. 40, numbers 4, 9, 10, 11 (1895). Surely some veteran educator can furnish
                    the missing numbers of this <hi rend="i">Journal</hi>, which are much desired.</p>
            <p>National Educational Association, <hi rend="i">Proceedings.</hi> Wanted for 1860, 1864, 1872, 1884,
                    and 1885.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">Indiana Magazine of History.</hi> We have had a generous response to our appeals for
                    back numbers, especially for those dated later than 1914. We have a serious need for copies of
                    issues from 1905 to 1913. We very much desire to locate the four numbers of volume IV (1908); number
                    one of volume VI (1910); the four numbers of volume VII (1911); the four numbers of vol. VIII
                    (1912). We will buy further copies of the following issues: Dec., 1921; Mar., 1922; double-number
                    June-Sept., 1925.</p>
            <p>Full sets of the <hi rend="i">Magazine</hi> can not be supplied to libraries or individuals who may
                    desire to purchase. A complete file from 1920 forward can be supplied at fifty-cents a copy or two
                    dollars per volume, unbound; from 1914 to 1919, the price is one dollar per copy, or four dollars
                    per volume; single copies from 1905-1913, when they can be supplied at all, must be priced at a much
                    higher figure.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <pb n="[]" id="VAA4025-027-1-086"/>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI.2>