<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//IA Books//DTD TEI for Indiana Authors Books//EN" "teixlite.dtd" [
<!NOTATION JPG SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY VAA2347-1 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-1.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-2 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-2.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-3 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-3.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-4 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-4.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-5 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-5.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-6 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-6.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-7 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-7.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-8 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-8.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-9 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-9.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-10 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-10.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-11 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-11.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-12 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-12.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-13 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-13.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-14 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-14.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-15 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-15.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-16 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-16.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-17 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-17.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-18 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-18.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-19 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-19.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-20 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-20.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-21 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-21.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-22 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-22.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-23 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-23.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-24 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-24.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2347-25 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2347-25.jpg" NDATA JPG>
]>
<TEI.2 id="VAA2347">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Abe Martin of Brown County, Indiana: electronic edition</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
                </address>
                <idno>VAA2347</idno>
                <availability status="unknown">
                    <p>Copyright 2008 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
                    <p>Indiana University provides the information contained on this web site for non-commercial,
                        personal, or research use only. All other use, including but not limited to commercial or
                        scholarly reproductions, redistribution, publication or transmission, whether by electronic
                        means or otherwise, without prior written permission of the copyright holder is strictly
                        prohibited.</p>
                </availability>
                <date>2007</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull><titleStmt>
                    <title type="main">Abe Martin of Brown County, Indiana</title>
                    <author id="ina-v1-entry-0440">Hubbard, Kin, 1868-1930</author></titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Press of Levey Bros. &amp; Co</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Indianapolis</pubPlace>
                        <date>1906</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Digital Library Program was awarded a Library Services and Technology Act (LSTA)
                    grant in 2005 to make available online the three-volume, reference work, <title>Indiana Authors 
                        and Their Books</title> along with selected monographs by Indiana authors.
                </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3">
                <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoded and edited using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines following the TEI Lite standard. Digital page images are
                    linked to the text file.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <tagUsage gi="div1">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language>English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-02-22</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Annette D. Richmond</name>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Corrected teiHeader, pb tags, front matter.</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <pb id="VAA2347-001" n="[]"/>
            <div1 type="cover">
                <figure entity="VAA2347-1"/>
                <p/>
            </div1>
            <pb id="VAA2347-002" n="[]"/>
            <div1 type="halftitle">
                <head>ABE MARTIN</head>
                <p/>
            </div1>
            <pb id="VAA2347-003" n="[]"/>
            <div1 type="dedication">
                <head>To My Wife</head>
                <p/>
            </div1>
            <pb id="VAA2347-004" n="[]"/>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">ABE MARTIN OF<lb/> B<hi rend="sc">ROWN</hi> C<hi rend="sc">OUNTY,</hi> I<hi
                            rend="sc">NDIANA</hi></titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <byline>By <docAuthor>KIN HUBBARD</docAuthor></byline>
                <docEdition>Third Edition</docEdition>
                <docImprint>Compiled from<lb/>
                    <publisher>THE INDIANAPOLIS NEWS</publisher>
                    <docDate>1906</docDate>
                </docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <pb id="VAA2347-005" n="[]"/>
            <div1 type="verso">
                <p rend="center">Copyright, 1906<lb/> By<lb/> F. K. HUBBARD</p>
                <p>PRESS OF <lb/> LEVEY BROS. &amp; CO<lb/> INDPLS.</p>
            </div1>
            <pb id="VAA2347-006" n="[]"/>
            <div1 type="preface">
                <head>INTRODUCTORY</head>
                <p>Persons who have tried all known patent medicines without relief will do well to try these Abe Martin
                    dandelion and sassafras cocktails before turning their faces to the wall. Abe is now an established
                    institution and no supper table is complete without him. The clods are softer under the weary hoof
                    and the plow-handles easier to manage after a moment&apos;s communion with Abe. He is Plato on a
                    cracker barrel; or radiant Socrates after Xanthippe&apos;s departure to visit her own folks in
                    Tecumseh Township.</p>
                <p>A cartoon and two sentences are sufficient for Mr. Hubbard&apos;s purposes, and no one since
                    &quot;A. Ward&quot; has shown the same genius for mirth-provoking epigram. Abe&apos;s
                    friends are as classic as Abe&apos;s whiskers, and those of us who have stayed all night at the
                    &quot;grand hotel&quot; of some budding town that hopes to have a street fair and a
                    ten-wagon circus next yeardelectable and permanent hope!know that Constable Newt Plum, Tipton Bud,
                    Niles Turner, Pinky Kerr, Tilford Moots, the Misses Fawn Lippincut and Tawney Apple are veritable
                    figures snatched <pb id="VAA2347-007" n="[]"/> bodily from the rural landscape. Mr. Hubbard is a
                    direct descendant of the well-known Hubbard family whose dog got no bone from the historic cupboard.
                    Toothpicks from this cupboard are now sold at two dollars apiece at the Museum of Fine Arts in
                    Chillicothe, Ohio.</p>
                <p>In fifteen years&apos; acquaintance I have never known Mr. Hubbard to be serious but once, and
                    that was when he described Bellefontaine as a place that the expectant pilgrim could always identify
                    by the two sparrows on the south end of the water tank near the Big Four station. I have passed that
                    tank twenty-seven times since and have found Mr. Hubbard&apos;s statement accurate in every
                    particular.</p>
                <p>It is, therefore, with a clear conscience that I give this symphony in gingham my hearty endorsement;
                    and if the author of it should be arrested for arson or safe-blowing at any time when I myself am at
                    large, I solemnly promise to be one of ten thousand men to put up a dime apiece to bail him out.</p>
                <p rend="right">MEREDITH NICHOLSON.</p>
                <p>Indianapolis, November 7, 1906.</p>
            </div1>
        </front>
        <body>
            <pb id="VAA2347-008" n="[]"/>
            <div1 type="book">
                <head>ABE MARTIN</head>
                <pb id="VAA2347-009" n="[]"/>
                <div2 type="chapter">
                    <head>RILEY&apos;S TRIBUTE</head>
                    <p>To Kin Hubbard<lb/> the Father of His Countryman.<lb/> Abe Martin:</p>
                    <lg>
                        <l n="1">ABE MARTIN!dad-burn his old picture!</l>
                        <l n="2">P&apos;tends he&apos;s a Brown county fixture</l>
                        <l n="3">A kind of comical mixture</l>
                        <l n="4" rend="ti-1">Of hoss-sense and no sense at all!</l>
                        <l n="5">His mouth, like his pipe, &apos;s allus goin&apos;,</l>
                        <l n="6">And his thoughts, like his whiskers, is flowin&apos;</l>
                        <l n="7">And what he don&apos;t know ain&apos;t worth knowin&apos;</l>
                        <l n="8" rend="ti-1">From Genesis clean to baseball!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg>
                        <l n="1">The artist, Kin Hubbard, &apos;s so keerless</l>
                        <l n="2">He draws Abe &apos;most eyeless and earless;</l>
                        <l n="3">But he&apos;s never yit pictured him cheerless</l>
                        <l n="4" rend="ti-1">Er with fun &apos;at he tries to conceal</l>
                        <l n="5">Whuther onto the fence er clean over</l>
                        <l n="6">A-rootin&apos; up ragweed er clover,</l>
                        <l n="7">Skeert stiff at some &quot;Rambler&quot; er &quot;Rover&quot;</l>
                        <l n="8" rend="ti-1">Er new fangled automobeel.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg>
                        <l n="1">It&apos;s a purty steep climate old Brown&apos;s in;</l>
                        <l n="2">And the rains there his ducks nearly drowns in</l>
                        <l n="3">The old man hisse&apos;f wades his rounds in</l>
                        <l n="4" rend="ti-1">As ca&apos;m and serene, mighty nigh,</l>
                        <l n="5">As the old handsaw hawg, er the mottled</l>
                        <l n="6">Milch-cow, er the old rooster wattled</l>
                        <l n="7">Like the mumps had him &apos;most so well throttled</l>
                        <l n="8" rend="ti-1">That it wuz a pleasure to die.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg>
                        <l n="1">But best of &apos;em all&apos;s the fool-breaks &apos;at</l>
                        <l n="2">Abe don&apos;t see &apos;at all, and yit makes, &apos;at</l>
                        <l n="3">Both me and you lays back and shakes at</l>
                        <l n="4" rend="ti-1">His comic, miraculous cracks,</l>
                        <l n="5">Which makes himclean back of the power</l>
                        <l n="6">Of genius itsse&apos;f in its flower</l>
                        <l n="7">This Notable Man of the Hour,</l>
                        <l n="8" rend="ti-1">Abe Martin, the Joker on Facts.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <p>Very truly your old Hoosier friend,<lb/> JAMES WHITCOMB RILEY<lb/> Indianapolis, May 1, 1906.</p>
                </div2>
                <pb id="VAA2347-010" n="[]"/>
                <div2 type="chapter">
                    <p>Did you ever go int&apos; one o&apos; them tonslitis parlors an&apos; hev a
                        bald-headed barber talk fer an&apos; hour t&apos; git you t&apos; try some hair
                        restorer? A gal will stand in front o&apos; th&apos; lookin&apos; glass an&apos;
                        power her nose fer twenty minutes an&apos; then fly int&apos; a tantrum if anybuddy
                        tells her it shows.</p>
                    <p>A feller down et Seymour hez got a half dollar o&apos; th&apos; date o&apos; 1849. By
                        ginger, he must be a tight wad. Th&apos; saddest, most pathetic o&apos; all sorry
                        spectacles is a red nose an&apos; a dyed mustache.</p>
                    <p>I&apos;ll be blamed if it dun&apos;t seem like th&apos; fellers thet er so crazy
                        &apos;bout wearin&apos; unyforms never hev any shoulders. I asked Uncle Ez Pash how he
                        accounted for his longevity, an&apos; he says, &quot;I never shaved, an&apos; jist
                        let &apos;em grow.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Mr. Alex Tansey is puttin&apos; th&apos; finishin&apos; touches on his new
                        meller-drammer, &quot;The Slaves o&apos; Catarrh.&quot; Pinky Kerr hez bought a pair
                        o&apos; $2.00 patent leathers fer Easter an&apos; he hed t&apos; break a couple
                        o&apos; raw eggs in &apos;em before he could git &apos;em on.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-011" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Some folks seem t&apos; think thet th&apos; only time they ort&apos; t&apos; look
                        pleasant is when ther in a photergraf gallery. Pinky Kerr says thet th&apos; difference
                        between a trained seal an&apos; a regular actor is thet yer hev t&apos; feed
                        th&apos; seal.</p>
                    <p>Seems like folks what take little trips once a year spend all ther time an&apos; money on
                        souvenir pustal cards. My wife&apos;s niece et Cumberland says thet th&apos; corn i so
                        high ther thet th&apos; sun hez t&apos; back in on th&apos; old National road.</p>
                    <p>Ez Pash wuz lookin&apos; in a cistern over et Nashville Saturday an&apos; fell in with
                        some folks from Bloomington. A country preacher allus dresses like a corpse.</p>
                    <p>By ginger, I reckon Bryan will git back from hez European trip in time t&apos; split up
                        th&apos; Dimmycratic party fer 1908. Union City is famous fer its quiet Sundays an&apos;
                        leaf terbacker.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-012" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Gettysburg Johnson says he paid $175,000 in Confederate money fer a ham durin&apos;
                        th&apos; civil war an&apos; wuz glad t&apos; git it et thet price. Newt Plum told Ez
                        Pash thet th&apos; Czar hed resigned an&apos; Ez replied: &quot;I hope Roosyfel
                        dun&apos;t appoint a mugwump in his place.&quot;</p>
                    <p>By ginger, one blamed good thing &apos;bout bein&apos; poor is thet you&apos;ll never
                        git killed in a ortermobile smashup. Miss Fawn Lippincut took a drink o&apos; patent
                        medicine yisterday with suicidal intent.</p>
                    <p>Madam Neuralgi, a pammist, is stoppin&apos; et th&apos; Palace hut-tel. Pinky Kerr says
                        thet th&apos; trouble with roller skatin&apos; is thet th&apos; moon never goes
                        behind a cloud an&apos; th&apos; girls&apos; hands dunt git cold.</p>
                    <p>Ther&apos;s some talk o&apos; sendin&apos; Evansville t&apos; th&apos;
                        laundry. By ginger, it haint allus th&apos; doctor thet drives th&apos; most horses
                        t&apos; death thet hez th&apos; most practice.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-013" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Th&apos; country boy thet plows all day hez got th&apos; feller thet dun&apos;t know
                        what t&apos; do with himself beat a mile. Th&apos; fust thing thet a fool does when he
                        gits in a railroad car is t&apos; open a window.</p>
                    <p>Did you ever go t&apos; th&apos; the-ater with th&apos; feller that jabs you in
                        th&apos; ribs every time th&apos; comedian says somethin&apos; funny? Young Lafe Bud
                        is travelin&apos; fer a washin&apos; machine an&apos; makes all th&apos; tall
                        grass towns an&apos; carries a sickle.</p>
                    <p>You can&apos;t fool all th&apos; people all th&apos; time, but you kin fool enough
                        o&apos; them all th&apos; time t&apos; huld your head up in society. What hez become
                        o&apos; th&apos; ole feller thet used t&apos; light his pipe with a coal o&apos;
                        fire?</p>
                    <p>It looks now like Hiram Meadows would git th&apos; pustoffice. He&apos;s allus been purty
                        prominentconstable durin&apos; th&apos; week o&apos; th&apos; fair last fall
                        an&apos; a pallbearer a year er so ago. Even an English sparrow knows enough t&apos;
                        build a home before he gits married.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-014" n="[]"/>
                    <p>I read wher th&apos; LeClair Twin Sisters in &quot;Little Goldie&quot; packed
                        th&apos; Grand Army Hall et Roundhead, Ohio, fer two nights this week. I wish something good
                        would come here. I&apos;ll bet them ther ole three-legged delivery wagon hosses up et
                        Indynoplus wishes thet men did all th&apos; shoppin&apos;. Jist think o&apos;
                        gallopin&apos; three miles with a bunch o&apos; parsley.</p>
                    <p>Pinky Kerr kin hardly talk &apos;bove a whisper t&apos;day. He says he wuz out with some
                        Anderson pollerticians yisterday an&apos; hurt his voice sayin&apos; &quot;gimme
                        th&apos; same.&quot; A feller kin be a knocker an&apos; still not &quot;keer a
                        rap&quot; &apos;bout things in general.</p>
                    <p>It&apos;s cheaper t&apos; move than t&apos; stand fer 3-cent wall paper. No feller
                        ever thinks thet any man is good enough fer his sister.</p>
                    <p>Some fellers er jist naturally intelligent an&apos; others hev long, flowin&apos;
                        whiskers. You never kin tell how many folks go t&apos; th&apos; the-ater till you try
                        t&apos; spring somethin&apos; eriginal.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-015" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Th&apos; katydids will soon be gone, but th&apos; Indianny Legislature will meet before a
                        great while. Some fellers er so close thet they stay on a street car t&apos; th&apos;
                        end o&apos; th&apos; line, no matter where they wunt t&apos; go.</p>
                    <p>Women must be awful glad t&apos; git home an&apos; git ther shoes off. You dun&apos;t
                        hev t&apos; put &quot;excuse spellin&apos;&quot; on your letters any more.</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; lid is on et th&apos; pustoffis. You kin git stamps but no licker. I&apos;d
                        jist ez leave eat a padlock ez one o&apos; them hand-me-down doughnuts.</p>
                    <p>A feller kin fail at everthing else an&apos; still be a good pool player. Seems like
                        th&apos; feller thet wins two er three dollars playin&apos; cards never wunts
                        t&apos; work fer a salary agin.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-016" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Between sharps an&apos; flats it costs like blazes t&apos; live in a city.
                        Returnin&apos; t&apos; th&apos; chorus girl home project, young Lafe Bud, who hez
                        been up t&apos; Indynoplus fer weeks et a time durin&apos; th&apos; winter, says
                        th&apos; undertakin&apos; would percipitate th&apos; question o&apos; a canteen.</p>
                    <p>Young Lafe Bud went up t&apos; Indynoplus Wednesday t&apos; git a fall suit an&apos;
                        come home with a red vest. He says everything is a blank after he stepped int&apos;
                        th&apos; store. When it comes t&apos; knowledge, th&apos; feller thet builds a house
                        finds out things a Harvard graduate never heerd of. .</p>
                    <p>It seems like a person is disqualified fer all future usefullness after they once make a hit on
                        th&apos; amateur stage. Mr. Alex Tansey, our school teacher, says thet a pipe should never
                        be brought int&apos; th&apos; house after it hez once been smoked.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-017" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Ole Ez Pash says it must a been hard pickin&apos; t&apos; run a newspaper in th&apos;
                        stone age. Jist think a writin&apos; four perch o&apos; society news with a chissel
                        an&apos; deliverin&apos; th&apos; papers t&apos; th&apos; subscribers in a
                        hod. You can&apos;t tell much &apos;bout a girl jist &apos;cause she cries et
                        &quot;East Lynne.&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-018" n="[]"/>
                    <figure entity="VAA2347-2"/>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-019" n="[]"/>
                    <p>There&apos;s jist one chance fer an ugly girl--amiability. This is th&apos; week
                        o&apos; th&apos; Johnson county fair et Franklin. Tight shoes an&apos; starch.</p>
                    <p>Ole Ez Pash&apos;s mem&apos;ry goes back t&apos; th&apos; time o&apos; Queen
                        Anne. He says he kin remember when termatoes wuz poison. I wuz over t&apos; Stop 5
                        yisterday. It&apos;s quite a town an hez a trolley pole, seven English sparrows an&apos;
                        a rain shed.</p>
                    <p>Ther seems t&apos; be a blamed sight o&apos; &quot;Conn&quot; mixed up in these
                        travelin&apos; bands. In lookin&apos; over th&apos; devorce docket up et Indynoplus
                        I noticed a number o&apos; &quot;flat failures.&quot;</p>
                    <p>A Indynoplus drummer asked ole Ez Pash if he got t&apos; see th&apos; St. Louis fair
                        &apos;an Ez says, &quot;yes, I went on Thursday.&quot;</p>
                    <p>I wonder if women spoil ortomobiles jist like they do horses? Tabitha Plum run her peek-a-boo
                        waist through th&apos; pi-an-oley last week an&apos;, by ginger, it played a medley.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-020" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Talk &apos;bout devotion. A woman up et Columbia City hed a valuable horse die fer her. Ez
                        Pash an&apos; Niles Turner hev made arrangements t&apos; receive Bryan&apos;s New
                        York speech by rounds et th&apos; blacksmith shop t&apos;night.</p>
                    <p>I take notice thet these fellers thet hev successfully worked out th&apos; problem
                        o&apos; ariel navigation allus ride on th&apos; cars when they wunt t&apos; go
                        anywheres. Our school teacher, Mr. Alex Tansey, denounces Roosyfel&apos;s pneumatic
                        spellin&apos; in unmistakable terms.</p>
                    <p>Elgin Tyler is th&apos; oddest feller. He&apos;ll take a drink o&apos; liquor
                        an&apos; mebby he wunt take another fer ten er fifteen minutes. Th&apos; burlesque
                        the-aters er open up et Indynoplus fer th&apos; benefit o&apos; those thet
                        didn&apos;t git t&apos; go t&apos; Atlantic City.</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; grove wuz man&apos;s fust temple, but thet wuz long before we got ont&apos;
                        to issuin&apos; bonds. A woman excels et blamed nigh everthing but ironin&apos;
                        th&apos; neckband o&apos; a shirt.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-021" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Th&apos; feller thet hez &quot;loved an&apos; lost&quot; ought t&apos; hev
                        lots o&apos; money saved up. Lem Crevison is travelin&apos; with a circus out in
                        Missoury an&apos; Niles Turner says he hain&apos;t a blamed bit surprised, ez Lem used
                        t&apos; jump over ever gate he come t&apos; an&apos; would steal anything.</p>
                    <p>After thet new &quot;flat iron&quot; buildin&apos; up et Indynoplus gits full
                        o&apos; tailors th&apos; dudes ort t&apos; git ther clothes pressed purty cheap. A
                        druggist is allus tickled t&apos; death t&apos; see th&apos; feller thet buys ten
                        cents worth o&apos; stamps jist t&apos; use th&apos; phone.</p>
                    <p>If a feller kin git up on th&apos; Soldiers&apos; Monument et Indynoplus an&apos;
                        take a pair o&apos; strong glasses an&apos; see Cambridge City, what could he see with a
                        quart? Elgin Tyler hez been monkeyin&apos; with correspondence schools fer two er three
                        years, an&apos; now when he wunts money he jist writes home fer it.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-022" n="[]"/>
                    <p>While th&apos; price o&apos; everthing you eat these days is fluctuating like Uncle Ez
                        Pash&apos;s Adam&apos;s apple, th&apos; ole reliable prune remains one price
                        t&apos; all. I&apos;m gittin&apos; pretty well up in years, but, by ginger, I
                        can&apos;t remember o&apos; ever hearin&apos; a good word fer th&apos; United
                        States Senate.</p>
                    <p>A blamed fool dentist &apos;ll fill your mouth full o&apos; rubber an&apos; strings
                        an&apos; things an&apos; then perceed t&apos; ask you a thousan&apos; questions.
                        Elsie Plank asked young Lafe Bud if he an&apos; his wife kept a hired girl an&apos; Lafe
                        said, &quot;No, you can&apos;t keep &apos;em.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Ez Pash, th&apos; blamed ole dunce, says he hez a brother thet&apos;s half Indian. By
                        ginger, whenever you see a dude with a double watch chain you kin bet thet ther&apos;s a
                        lookin&apos; glass on one end o&apos; it.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-023" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Some well dressed stranger was in th&apos; neighborhood yisterday gittin&apos; signers
                        fer th&apos; San Jose scale. Th&apos; feller thet throws a good straw hat away
                        th&apos; fust o&apos; September an&apos; puts on a stiff hat thet hez been worn fer
                        three yearsbut no matter.</p>
                    <p>Tipton Bud says he spent seven hours &quot;between trains&quot; et Evansville Friday.
                        O&apos; course he took a big chance o&apos; gittin&apos; killed by th&apos;
                        cars, but he didn&apos;t miss much by not goin&apos; up town. You can&apos;t lay off
                        Labor Day unless you&apos;re a workin&apos; man.</p>
                    <p>Food fer thought seems t&apos; be th&apos; only cheap commodity on th&apos; market.
                        Mr. Alex Tansey is et work on a new bill t&apos; be presented t&apos; th&apos; next
                        Legislature makin&apos; it a misnomer t&apos; attend a the-ater wearin&apos; goat
                        furs an&apos; musk.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-024" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Pinky Kerr is writin&apos; some caliope music an&apos; th&apos; notes er ez big ez
                        walnuts. Th&apos; blessings o&apos; this life er purty evenly divided. In th&apos;
                        winter th&apos; rich folks git t&apos; go t&apos; all th&apos; the-aters
                        an&apos; in th&apos; summer th&apos; poor folks git t&apos; see all th&apos;
                        circus perades.</p>
                    <p>Tilford Moots hits th&apos; nail purty fairly on th&apos; head when he says thet
                        th&apos; Democratic party hed better cut out its educational features an&apos; git down
                        t&apos; business. A &quot;boy&quot; pianist never puts on long pants till
                        he&apos;s forty years old.</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; trouble with chewin&apos; terbacker is thet you&apos;ve got t&apos; keep
                        your mouth shut lots o&apos; times under exasperatin&apos; circumstances. O&apos;
                        all th&apos; unbearable nuisances th&apos; ignoramus thet hez traveled is th&apos;
                        wust.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-025" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Even if th&apos; feller thet gits talked int&apos; buyin&apos; some minin&apos;
                        stock should lose everything, his dreams an&apos; enthusiasm fer th&apos; fust few weeks
                        er well worth th&apos; cost. Ther hain&apos;t no advantage in bein&apos; dressed
                        up-t&apos;-date if you&apos;ve got t&apos; keep on th&apos; back streets.</p>
                    <p>Ole Ez Pash says thet th&apos; feller thet kin make enough money on th&apos; lecture
                        platform in a few years t&apos; buy all th&apos; railroads wouldn&apos;t suit him
                        fer President. Miss Fawn Lippincut hez th&apos; emotional insanity an&apos; Alex Tansey
                        is talkin&apos; &apos;bout starrin&apos; her in &quot;East Lynne.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Tilford Moots wuz over t&apos; th&apos; Henryville poor farm th&apos; other day
                        t&apos; see an ole friend o&apos; his thet used t&apos; publish a newspaper thet
                        pleased everbuddy. Poor ole Ez Pash walked all th&apos; way t&apos; th&apos;
                        Franklin fair th&apos; day o&apos; th&apos; &quot;free-fer-all&quot; pace
                        cuz he thought he&apos;d git in fer nothin&apos;.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-026" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Th&apos; average young man makes his fust spurt et economy by smokin&apos; stogies fer
                        eight er ten days after his marriage. This is th&apos; fust time I&apos;ve hed this plug
                        hat on since I thought Tilden wuz elected.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-027" n="[]"/>
                    <figure entity="VAA2347-3"/>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-028" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Th&apos; store keepers hev got you sized up. If yer know jist what you wunt you&apos;re a
                        crank, an&apos; if you dun&apos;t know jist what you wunt wou&apos;re an easy mark.
                        Seems like a woman would rather pay 89 cents fur somethin&apos; than 75.</p>
                    <p>Pinky Kerr says thet young Lafe Bud is &quot;on th&apos; hummer&quot; up et
                        Indynoplus. I dun&apos;t know whether thet&apos;s some newspaper er what it is. No-buddy
                        ever becomes so intelligent thet he can&apos;t be scared by a fake doctor.</p>
                    <p>Newt Plum traded fer a organ yisterday. He says thet his dorter, Pet, shall hev all th&apos;
                        advantages o&apos; a city gal. Th&apos; Uncle Tom&apos;s troupe thet wuz in
                        Rushville last week hez &quot;gone t&apos; th&apos; dogs.&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-029" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Ike Soles, who hez been janitor o&apos; th&apos; Roundhead (O.) Gazette-Bugle-Herald,
                        robbed th&apos; office waste basket last week an&apos; started another paper. A feller
                        will flare up in a minute when he&apos;s accused o&apos; doin&apos;
                        somethin&apos; he didn&apos;t do an&apos; smile from ear t&apos; ear when
                        praised fer somethin&apos; he couldn&apos;t do.</p>
                    <p>Newt. Plum&apos;s married dorter up et Indynoplus is savin&apos; up t&apos; get a
                        spring chicken. Friday wuz Tipton Bud&apos;s birthday annyversity an&apos; his wife gave
                        him a straight-handled umbrella so he wouldn&apos;t leave it hangin&apos; on some bar.</p>
                    <p>Pinky Kerr says thet th&apos; reason he dun&apos;t git married is becuz he dun&apos;t
                        want t&apos; be worried t&apos; death by life insurance agents. Some folks think thet
                        they&apos;re blase jist ez soon ez they see Niaggary Falls.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-030" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Newt Plum&apos;s son-in-law lives in one o&apos; them Indynoplus flats an he says thet
                        his settin&apos; room is so blamed little thet ever time he crosses his legs he kicks his
                        wife. Elcine Budd&apos;s husband hez gone back t&apos; his parents.</p>
                    <p>By ginger, they&apos;ve finally got th&apos; lid on up et Kokomo, but Tapley Bray says it
                        looks like a minnow bucket lid. It very often happens thet some folks give even themselves away
                        Christmas.</p>
                    <p>You git a hack with ever shave down et Lon Meadow&apos;s shop. Ther&apos;s some prospects
                        o&apos; a new opery hall up et Indynoplus with all th&apos; seats on th&apos; end
                        o&apos; th&apos; sixth row.</p>
                    <p>I allus did maintain thet yer could&apos;nt git over three good se-gars fer five cents.
                        I&apos;ll be gosh dinged if Roosyfel hain&apos;t a wonder. Ez Pash says thet if he ever
                        hez &apos;nother chance he&apos;ll clip his whiskers an&apos; vote fer him.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-031" n="[]"/>
                    <p>A feller never ort t&apos; git married till he&apos;s absolutely sure he kin break away
                        from th&apos; bunch et&apos; th&apos; segar store. Nobuddy is ever ready fer
                        company.</p>
                    <p>Miss Fawn Lippincut recited Grays Anatomy on a Country Church Yard et Melodeon Hall Wednesday
                        evenin&apos;. Tipton Bud says you could cut a street through with a drink o&apos; thet
                        &quot;third rail&quot; whisky thet they sell up et Martinsville.</p>
                    <p>Opportunity only knocks once, an&apos; then we&apos;re generally in th&apos; back
                        part o&apos; th&apos; house. Newt Plum&apos;s son-in-law up et Indynoplus says
                        he&apos;s jist about &quot;flat&quot; broke.</p>
                    <p>Ever time I cross a street et Indynoplus I take my pipe in one hand an&apos; my life in
                        &apos;tother. I&apos;ve met all o&apos; th&apos; Lieber boys &apos;cept Ach.</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; feller thet says &quot;free gratis&quot; generally wears suspenders with his
                        belt. Th&apos; ole proverb, &quot;beggars should not be chewers,&quot; is almost
                        absolete.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-032" n="[]"/>
                    <p>A stuckup city gal is too blamed nice t&apos; carry a spool o&apos; thread but
                        she&apos;ll tote a bundle o&apos; golf clubs fer miles.
                        &quot;Eat-a-wheat-a&quot; hez bills up t&apos; be et Columbus an&apos; a right
                        smart o&apos; people o&apos; this place expects t&apos; take it in.</p>
                    <p>A Terry Hut policeman kin wear any size helmet. Th&apos; man thet practices on th&apos;
                        clarinet kin never git any recognition in his home town.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Early t&apos; bed an&apos; early t&apos; rise makes folks healthy, wealthy
                        an&apos; wise,&quot; an&apos; if you dun&apos;t believe it jist look et your
                        milk man. Pinky Kerr hed a &quot;knock down&quot; t&apos; Jimmy Britt up et
                        Indynoplus last week.</p>
                    <p>Did you ever notice your butcher weight his hand an&apos; say &quot;thirty-eight
                        cents?&quot; Buffalo Bill wunts a devorce. Famous people er &apos;bout all alike, no
                        matter whether they got th&apos; fame breakin&apos; glass balls er in polytics.</p>
                    <p>Dave Angel&apos;s dorter, Angie, is almost ugly enough t&apos; make a good stenographer.
                        Admiral Nogi added a few more vessels t&apos; Rushy&apos;s &quot;submarine
                        navy&quot; yisterday.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-033" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Alonzo Moon, who hez been readin&apos; law in &apos;Squire Snoot&apos;s office at
                        Shoals is goin&apos; t&apos; practice economy et Seymour this win<hi rend="i">t</hi>er.
                        By ginger, they&apos;ve got twins over et Hale Turner&apos;s house, an&apos; Hale is
                        layin&apos; off et th&apos; saw mill, an&apos; doin&apos; a day an&apos;
                        night shift et hum.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-034" n="[]"/>
                    <figure entity="VAA2347-4"/>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-035" n="[]"/>
                    <p>I dunt see where Alex Tansey gits his insperation. He dunt drink. When a father says,
                        &quot;Well, I guess I&apos;ll make a lawyer out o&apos; Jimmy,&quot; he probably
                        means all right.</p>
                    <p>I dun&apos;t see why hut-tels an&apos; resturints want t&apos; mix cement with
                        anything ez cheap ez buckwheat is. Ther never used t&apos; be near so many women on
                        th&apos; street before they hed French plate show windows.</p>
                    <p>Ez Pash is the durndest meanest ole cuss; Alex Tansey wuz complainin&apos; o&apos; them
                        medical examinations up et th&apos; State House an&apos; Ez says, &quot;They ort
                        t&apos; make &apos;em so hard they&apos;d be prohibitive.&quot; It&apos;s
                        cheaper t&apos; pay rent than move unless you&apos;ve got rubber furniture.</p>
                    <p>Pinky Kerr says thet th&apos; way t&apos; beat them Indynoplus street cars is t&apos;
                        git on th&apos; hind end o&apos; one thet&apos;s crowded an&apos; then
                        dun&apos;t change your expression. Ewin&apos; Grimes wuz circulatin&apos;
                        &apos;mongst his ole friends here yisterday an&apos; th&apos; clothes he got married
                        in look ez good ez they did nine years ago.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-036" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Th&apos; feller what&apos;s allus spoken of ez bein&apos; &quot;fond o&apos;
                        horses&quot; ez th&apos; very one thet pulls ther heads &apos;way up in th&apos;
                        air an&apos; drives ther tails off. This is fine corn weather, an&apos; ez old Milt
                        Whitehill would say, &quot;corn makes whisky, an&apos; whisky makes Dimmycrats
                        an&apos; Dimmycrats make parrymount issues.&quot;</p>
                    <p>By ginger, I never knowed a good fisherman thet &apos;mounted t&apos; anything. Dave
                        Angel says Bill Bryan would rather be wrong than President.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Pinky Kerr wuz tellin&apos; Ez Pash thet John R. Walsh started out years ago a poor boy,
                        an&apos; Uncle Ez said: &quot;Who&apos;n th&apos; dickens ever heerd o&apos;
                        anybuddy ez old ez Walsh thet started out rich.&quot; Kris Kingle is &apos;bout
                        th&apos; only feller in this country thet kin clean up on a &quot;one-night
                        stand.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; most exactin&apos; an&apos; critical lover in th&apos; world is
                        th&apos; ugly feller. He expects his girl t&apos; be endowed with all th&apos; grace
                        an&apos; lovliness known t&apos; her sex. When a feller can&apos;t spell he allus
                        puts &quot;dictated&quot; on his letters.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-037" n="[]"/>
                    <p>I seen a Chineeman in Columbus &apos;tother day with human bein&apos; clothes on. No
                        matter how hard up er how homely th&apos; average feller is, he&apos;ll allus subscribe
                        liberally t&apos; any scheme t&apos; git his picture in a volume o&apos;
                        &quot;Prominent Men o&apos; Indianny.&quot;</p>
                    <p>When a feller comes around you complainin&apos; thet th&apos; banks an&apos;
                        pustoffis er closed put your hands in your pockets. The Republican party is goin&apos;
                        t&apos; give us a purty good termater crop after all.</p>
                    <p>Our pustoffice stays open till 8 p. m. now since Miss Germ Williams is takin&apos;
                        &quot;Journalism&quot; by mail. Ther&apos;s a great display o&apos; buggies
                        an&apos; sausage et th&apos; State Fair.</p>
                    <p>I seen a big feller with a whisky nose drinkin&apos; sody water with a couple o&apos;
                        girls over et Morgantown yisterday. I dun&apos;t know which one he wuz tryin&apos;
                        t&apos; please, but he seemed t&apos; be makin&apos; an awful sacrifice. Ole Niles
                        Turner allus borrows a newspaper &quot;jist t&apos; read.&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-038" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Ther&apos;s a constable named Gourd-seed livin&apos; in Orange county an&apos; yet
                        some people say meller-drammers er overdrawn. Next t&apos; a rich country editur
                        th&apos; most unusual thing in th&apos; world is a German tramp.</p>
                    <p>Newt Plum&apos;s oldest girl is with a opery troupe an&apos; plays a pheasant. She gits
                        $10 a week, rides in a day coach an&apos; hez changed her name t&apos; Fanchon Gazelle.
                        Elder Berry an&apos; wife hev gone to Wapakoneta, Ohio, t&apos; live with ther son,
                        Stephen. Aunty Berry will be greatly missed ez we hev no newspaper here.</p>
                    <p>I guess from what I hear thet most o&apos; th&apos; Indianny school teachers git
                        &apos;bout three months&apos; vacation ever year so thet they kin earn some clothes
                        t&apos; wear while they teach. Them blamed &quot;silence an fun&quot; matches hev
                        jist struck this localitee. They smell like a combernation o&apos; th&apos; ole sulphur
                        match an a hoss burnin&apos; up.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-039" n="[]"/>
                    <p>All I ever got out o&apos; pollytics wuz a package o&apos; punkin seeds thet
                        didn&apos;t come up. Uncle Ez Pash says he&apos;s got a niece et Bloom Center, Ohio,
                        thet&apos;s so blamed good lookin&apos; thet th&apos; resturints stay open till
                        midnight.</p>
                    <p>When it comes t&apos; a divorce ther&apos;s allus three sides t&apos; th&apos;
                        storyth&apos; husband&apos;s, his wife&apos;s an&apos; her mother&apos;s.
                        You kin allus bet thet th&apos; feller thet cuts down expenses by stoppin&apos; his
                        newspaper smokes an&apos; chews.</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; average legislater will &quot;beat th&apos; trucks&quot; afore
                        he&apos;ll pay railroad fare. Old ladies must hev a fine timeknit.</p>
                    <p>A jack knife an&apos; a pug o&apos; terbacker would make a good design fer a seal
                        o&apos; Indianny. Bob Meadows hez written t&apos; his father sayin&apos; thet he is
                        with a circus playin&apos; alto in th&apos; band. He says he&apos;s havin&apos;
                        a fine time an&apos; gits six dollars a month an&apos; gits t&apos; see th&apos;
                        show twice a day fer nothin&apos;.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-040" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Elmer Pate, o&apos; Michigan City, is here an&apos; hez orgernized a dancin&apos;
                        class an&apos; teaches th&apos; lock step. Th&apos; Angola capitalists who were
                        t&apos; perduce Mr. Alex Tansey&apos;s drammer, &quot;Th&apos;
                        Butcher&apos;s Bride,&quot; hev abandoned th&apos; project an&apos; Mr. Tansey
                        is puttin&apos; all his energy int&apos; a new problem play called
                        &quot;Th&apos; Runaway Hearse.&quot;</p>
                    <p>El Jones, o&apos; Rushville, hez written t&apos; Consul-General Gowdy tellin&apos;
                        him t&apos; fetch him a can o&apos; Paris green when he comes home. When you see your
                        boy startin&apos; off t&apos; school with his books in one hand an&apos; a cigaroot
                        in th&apos; &apos;tother you kin jist quit makin&apos; plans fer his future.</p>
                    <p>By ginger, if we git elastic currency it&apos;ll be a great thing fer rubber necks. I wuz
                        just wonderin&apos; yisterday what becomes o&apos; all th&apos; people thet sell out
                        ever year an&apos; go int&apos; th&apos; chicken raisin&apos; business.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-041" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Republican office holders, office hunters an&apos; perlitical spear carriers of th&apos;
                        State er all meetin&apos; up et Indynoplus t&apos; day fer a love feast. Some wunt
                        t&apos; huld on, some wunt t&apos; git on an&apos; some wunt t&apos;
                        &quot;be in on.&quot; Some fellers er born unlucky an&apos; others live with ther
                        wive&apos;s folks.</p>
                    <p>It must be awful lonesome in Peru these long winter evenin&apos;s unless you like t&apos;
                        go t&apos; church er shake dice. Waldo Blayney, who hurt hisself makin&apos; a high dive
                        in Bean Blossom crick this summer, hed his skull terrapined yisterday.</p>
                    <p>Ther&apos;s too much blamed tomfoolery &apos;bout how t&apos; eat nowerdays.
                        I&apos;d jist ez leave tek chances on splittin my tongue with a knife es punchin&apos;
                        my eye out with a fork. No feller ever ort t&apos; git too great t&apos; register from
                        th&apos; little town where he lives.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-042" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Th&apos; fust thing they do t&apos; you after you git in Bloomington is t&apos; take
                        your attention off th&apos; public square. Constable Newt Plum&apos;s dorter thet lives
                        up et Indynoplus is so blamed skeered about porch climbers thet she made her husband move
                        int&apos; a one-story cottage.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-043" n="[]"/>
                    <figure entity="VAA2347-5"/>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-044" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Some fellers er pokey an&apos; some er on th&apos; dot, but we rarely find one thet is
                        pokey dot. It&apos;s purty hard t&apos; save anything these days openly an&apos;
                        above &quot;board.&quot;</p>
                    <p>With peaches sellin&apos; et th&apos; prices they are a woman must hev a lot t&apos;
                        put up with. All is not gold thet glitters an&apos; some red noses er caused by indigestion.</p>
                    <p>Tipton Bud&apos;s niece died from a successful operation yisterday &quot;Peck&apos;s
                        Bad Boy&quot; delighted two large houses et Logansport th&apos; other day an&apos;
                        yet we say thet th&apos; world is gittin&apos; better.</p>
                    <p>Ther wuz a great discussion up et th&apos; pustoffice this mornin&apos; about who wuz
                        Secretary o&apos; State under George Washington. Ole Ez Pash said it wuz Tony Pastor
                        an&apos; Newt Plum swore up an&apos; down it wuz Alexander Hamilton. One good thing
                        about magazine pictures is thet they kin be used fer most any story.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-045" n="[]"/>
                    <p>This is th&apos; open season fer hunters, barbed-wire fences an&apos; funerals. Newt
                        Plum&apos;s married dorter up et Indynoplus hez gone blind lookin&apos; fer soap sales
                        in th&apos; newspapers.</p>
                    <p>Congressman Fred Landis is a makin&apos; his canvas up in th&apos; &quot;felt boot
                        district&quot; this week. Landlord Newt Slicer o&apos; Pickreltown, Ohio, knows ez much
                        &apos;bout th&apos; show business ez a reglar perfessional. He hez t&apos; travel
                        two er three days with ever troupe thet stops et his hut-tel.</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; trouble with bein&apos; diagnosed by mail an&apos; dosed by express is thet
                        a railroad strike would emperil your life. A Uncle Tom&apos;s Cabin troupe with two Ohio
                        rivers will be et th&apos; Melodeon Hall Saturday night.</p>
                    <p>Tilford Moots hez a niece thet poses in a art school in New York an&apos; jist makes a bare
                        livin&apos;. A feller thet orders scrambled eggs would take chances on anything.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-046" n="[]"/>
                    <p>A number o&apos; good men hev come from Boonville an&apos; you can&apos;t blame
                        &apos;em if you&apos;ve seen Boonville. Some o&apos; th&apos; young folks went
                        over t&apos; Franklin t&apos; day t&apos; see th&apos; sights an&apos; git
                        th&apos; provincialism rubbed off.</p>
                    <p>Ez Pash says thet when you hear some smart alex blowin&apos; off &apos;bout his
                        &quot;ideal home life&quot; you kin bet your boots thet he travels er belongs
                        t&apos; all th&apos; lodges. Th&apos; newspapers thet print &quot;What
                        t&apos; git fer Christmas&quot; ort t&apos; print how t&apos; git it.</p>
                    <p>By ginger, did you ever notice how two women with babies o&apos; th&apos; same age hobnob
                        t&apos;gither. It beats all who some people will work fer. Tapley Bray is cleanin&apos;
                        brick for a home wrecker up et Indynoplus.</p>
                    <p>This is George Washington&apos;s birthday. Th&apos; ole feller wouldn&apos;t be in it
                        t&apos;-day. Tryin&apos; t&apos; scrape up relationship with some one
                        thet&apos;s rich er prominent is one o&apos; th&apos; fifty-seven varieties of
                        showin&apos; inferiority.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-047" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Th&apos; only time a woman ever tells her right age is when she fust starts t&apos;
                        school. Pinky Kerr says th&apos; &quot;Watch on Rhein&quot; must a been German
                        silver.</p>
                    <p>Ther er still two or three hut-tels in Indianny thet put toothpicks on th&apos; dinner table.
                        Arson Smith is runnin&apos; th&apos; traction engine fer Tilford Moots durin&apos;
                        th&apos; threshin&apos; season. He carries a dollar watch an&apos; knows all
                        &apos;bout machinery.</p>
                    <p>Waldo Blayney says ther&apos;s many a feller owns a steamer trunk thet never seen
                        th&apos; Wabash. Th&apos; blame fool sheriff et Bloomcenter, Ohio, let all th&apos;
                        prisners out o&apos; jail t&apos; see a circus last Monday an&apos; told
                        &apos;em if they wasn&apos;t back by ten o&apos;clock they&apos;d hev
                        t&apos; sleep on th&apos; jail steps.</p>
                    <p>Figures dunt lie but you kin group &apos;em so they&apos;ll answer th&apos; same
                        purpose. The Civic Pride Club o&apos; Carmel, Indianny, is after th&apos; citizens thet
                        eat olives with nut crackers.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-048" n="[]"/>
                    <p>A full-front photer-graf o&apos; a feller allus makes him look like he&apos;d murdered a
                        whole family an&apos; then burned th&apos; house. Th&apos; only thing o&apos;
                        real deep seated interest thet ever happens in Jonesville is when some one drops along
                        an&apos; covers th&apos; livery stable with circus bills.</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; county commissioners er hevin&apos; a conference with th&apos; American
                        Painless Bridge Company t&apos;day. Miss Tawney Apple an&apos; Miss Fawn Lippincut
                        bought some &quot;lissly&quot; stockin&apos;s up et Indynoplus Saturday.</p>
                    <p>Tipton Bud asked Ole Niles Turner if a watch would run jist ez well hangin&apos; up ez it
                        would in your pocket, an&apos; Ole Niles said, &quot;Thet depends on whether your Uncle
                        winds it er not.&quot; Th&apos; trouble with this Christian Science business is thet
                        you&apos;ve got t&apos; keep whistlin&apos; all th&apos; time.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-049" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Dr. Hiram Tate is a goin t&apos; be married in September. Hiram says thet ther&apos; wunt
                        be no invitations, so I guess he&apos;s t&apos; furnish his own home. Ther&apos;s
                        allus somethin&apos; brewin&apos; in Milwaukee t&apos; stagger humanity.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-050" n="[]"/>
                    <figure entity="VAA2347-6"/>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-051" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Owin&apos; t&apos; th&apos; increased cost o&apos; livin&apos;
                        they&apos;ve changed th&apos; rates down et th&apos; taverna quarter et th&apos;
                        plain table an&apos; thirty-five cents et th&apos; table with th&apos; jelly role
                        on. Some drummer from Indynoplus wuz here yisterday, an&apos; he says thet they&apos;re
                        goin&apos; t&apos; change th&apos; name o&apos; Illinoy street t&apos;
                        Clairvoyant avenue.</p>
                    <p>Aunt Tilda Myers&apos;s funeral wuz pustponed two times last week on account o&apos;
                        interferin&apos; with card clubs. Who ever seen a &quot;large an&apos;
                        intelligent&quot; audience?</p>
                    <p>Some feller wuz down here yisterday tryin&apos; t&apos; start some sort o&apos; a new
                        insurance lodge. When you die you git a brass band o&apos; eight pieces, two wreathes, a
                        concrete tomb stone an&apos; fifty dollars, an&apos; when you&apos;re sick
                        th&apos; lodge members shake th&apos; box t&apos; see who nurses you. Th&apos;
                        Uncle Tom&apos;s Cabin troupe thet wuz here Monday wuz th&apos; best dog an&apos;
                        pony show thet hez been long this way in years.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-052" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Seems like ever feller thet makes a success o&apos; anything never knowed nuthin&apos;
                        when he went t&apos; school. I reckon ole Ez Pash will stick t&apos; his winter
                        underwear agin this summer.</p>
                    <p>I walked &apos;round th&apos; State House up et Indynoplus &apos;tother day
                        an&apos; I jist thought thet Govnor Hanly must go broke payin&apos; his dog tax. Pinky
                        Kerr sez thet a feller will git talked int&apos; buyin&apos; a suit o&apos; clothes
                        made o&apos; cotton an&apos; wood fibre an&apos; then turn his nose up et hypnotism.</p>
                    <p>Ole Ez Pash is th&apos; blamedest feller t&apos; be a blowin&apos; off all
                        th&apos; time &apos;bout his army record. By ginger, he played a yaller clarynet in
                        th&apos; band et Johnson&apos;s Island, Lake Erie, durin&apos; th&apos; war
                        an&apos; wuz never south o&apos; th&apos; Smith an&apos; Wesson line. I seen
                        Elwell Miller smokin&apos; a reglar five-cent se-gar Saturday night. Well, he makes his
                        money easyplowin&apos;.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-053" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Dock Osler, o&apos; Hopkin&apos;s University, kicked up a hornets&apos; nest among
                        th&apos; &quot;old scouts&quot; when he said a feller ort ter be clorformed et
                        th&apos; age o&apos; forty. Ther wuz a circus in Laffy&apos;et &apos;tother day
                        an&apos; so blamed many perlice an&apos; marshals went in on ther badges thet
                        th&apos; manager wuz jist &apos;bout t&apos; put in more seats when th&apos;
                        perlice department run out o&apos; tin.</p>
                    <p>By ginger, when a feller reads th&apos; newspapers these days he can&apos;t help
                        wonderin&apos; how th&apos; early settlers ever existed without patent medicines. Newt
                        Plum&apos;s brother, Ignatus, who lives in th&apos; East, is a visitin&apos; him.
                        He&apos;s ez polished an&apos; fascinatin&apos; ez a bigamist.</p>
                    <p>There goes old Ez Pash. By ginger, he&apos;s a old timer. He kin remember when it wuz all
                        right t&apos; be a Dimmycrat. Th&apos; best fire escape fer a theatre is a bum show.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-054" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Our school teacher, Mister Alex Tansey, says he wurshes winter would &quot;take his grippe
                        an&apos; leave.&quot; Alex is purty comic fer a teacher. Th&apos; magazines is full
                        o&apos; Pope Toledo these days. By ginger, he&apos;s a new one on me.</p>
                    <p>Furniture is blamed cheap up et Indynoplus. I wuz standin&apos; on th&apos; corner up
                        there &apos;tother night an&apos; a feller asked me if I wouldn&apos;t give him a
                        dime fer a bed. Link Gage says Richmond&apos;s new pustoffice looks like a dollar&apos;s
                        worth o&apos; white chips.</p>
                    <p>By ginger, next t&apos; bein&apos; ez good ez yer wife&apos;s folks th&apos;
                        hardest thing in th&apos; world t&apos; do is pick up a three-cent piece with a
                        boxin&apos; glove on. Dave Angel asked old uncle Ez Pash if he ever seen any o&apos;
                        th&apos; Pilgrim fathers, an&apos; Uncle Ez said: &quot;Nup, I wuz livin&apos;
                        near Union City in those days.&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-055" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Newt Plum&apos;s married dorter up et Indynoplus says thet ther is a hot water famine in her
                        flat et th&apos; end o&apos; each month when th&apos; renters begin t&apos;
                        bathe. Tipton Bud wuz up t&apos; Indynoplus yisterday an&apos; put up et
                        Claypool&apos;s hut-tel. He told th&apos; clerk if he wuzn&apos;t back in time fer
                        supper not t&apos; wait fer him.</p>
                    <p>Young Lafe Bud is jist like a rattlesnake. He wears rubber heels an&apos; th&apos; only
                        warnin&apos; you git o&apos; his bein&apos; around is th&apos; rattle
                        o&apos; his celluloid cuffs. Th&apos; feller thet drinks et home hain&apos;t
                        foolin&apos; no one but hisself.</p>
                    <p>I meet old-time Dimmycrats ever once in a while, but I&apos;ll be blamed if I ever meet any
                        new ones. Niles Turner&apos;s big lazy hunk o&apos; a boy, Lucien, is t&apos; proud
                        an&apos; stuck up t&apos; stay on th&apos; farm, so they&apos;ve sent him
                        t&apos; agger-cultural college.</p>
                    <p>Ther promises t&apos; be only a fair crop o&apos; &quot;genuine Vermont maple
                        sirup&quot; in Indianny this year. When a feller&apos;s overcoat sleeve linings begin
                        t&apos; wear out, good-bye New Year&apos;s reselutions.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-056" n="[]"/>
                    <p>I reckon they&apos;ll adulterate cotton seed oil next. Mr. Alex Tansey is a bright fellow. He
                        understands a life insurance policy.</p>
                    <p>Speakin&apos; o&apos; th&apos; weather, ole Ez Pash says thet ther is an&apos;
                        ole sayin&apos; thet if a village sport stands out in front o&apos; a
                        &quot;fifteen-ball pool&quot; room durin&apos; February he&apos;ll set by a fire
                        in March. Tilford Moots hez got th&apos; hippo. He thinks he can&apos;t work.</p>
                    <p>Poor ole hen pecked Milt White-hill died o&apos; lard on th&apos; heart up et Mulberry
                        Junction Tuesday. I asked Al Johnson what his last words wuz, an&apos; he said, &quot;He
                        didn&apos;t hev none, his wife wuz with him.&quot; Married men work longer than single
                        men.</p>
                    <p>Money is purty tight hereabouts an&apos; folks wun&apos;t spend much o&apos; anything
                        durin&apos; th&apos; hollerday season but Christmas. My wife haint got no dish mop
                        an&apos; no rubber gloves, but she gits thar jist th&apos; same.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-057" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Niles Turner hez sent t&apos; Warshin&apos;ton fer a patent fer his new shovel thet
                        he&apos;s gittin&apos; up. It hez a clock in th&apos; handle. Folks what eat liver
                        &quot;make no bones&quot; &apos;bout it.</p>
                    <p>Owin&apos; t&apos; th&apos; &quot;long glove famine&quot; quite a number
                        o&apos; our girls&apos; elbows er gittin&apos; t&apos; look like goat&apos;s
                        knees. There&apos;s a good deal o&apos; speculation down here ez t&apos; whether
                        Taft is a goin&apos; t&apos; run er set down.</p>
                    <p>Ez fast ez th&apos; world gits better some one designs a dress t&apos; spoil it. Nobuddy
                        kin talk ez hard agin excessive rates ez th&apos; feller thet spends fifteen cents a minute
                        fer his enthusiasm.</p>
                    <p>Miss Angie Moots, Tilford Moot&apos;s oldest dorter, is t&apos; be married th&apos;
                        fust o&apos; May an&apos; ther gittin&apos; ready t&apos; send out
                        &apos;bout 350 duns. You kin git a purty fair idear o&apos; a woman&apos;s
                        dispersition from th&apos; way she scrapes out a pan.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-058" n="[]"/>
                    <p>While Pinky Kerr wuz watchin&apos; th&apos; circus perade up et Indynoplus, Monday, some
                        one hooked his watch an&apos; run through th&apos; crowd. Pinky says he called
                        t&apos; him but th&apos; band wuz playin&apos; an&apos; th&apos; feller
                        didn&apos;t hear him. Ole Niles Turner swears thet he seen an adult drinkin&apos; sody
                        water down et Bloomington Saturday.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-059" n="[]"/>
                    <figure entity="VAA2347-7"/>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-060" n="[]"/>
                    <p>It&apos;ll soon be time fer &quot;mushyroom experts&quot; t&apos; begin
                        turnin&apos; up ther toes. Yisterday quite a few o&apos; th&apos; folks went over
                        t&apos; see th&apos; steam cars et Trevlac an&apos; when they all got huddled
                        &apos;bout th&apos; injine th&apos; injineer hollered, &quot;look out,
                        I&apos;m goin&apos; t&apos; turn around,&quot; an you should o&apos; saw
                        th&apos; scramblin&apos; t&apos; git away.</p>
                    <p>From all I kin understand, &apos;bout th&apos; hardest thing t&apos; do next
                        t&apos; standin&apos; on your ear is t&apos; publish a Dimmycratic paper in a
                        Republican town. Speakin&apos; o&apos; th&apos; &quot;beef trust,&quot; jist
                        think o&apos; th&apos; trust you place in th&apos; feller thet sells you
                        &quot;real&quot; calf&apos;s liver.</p>
                    <p>When a young feller can&apos;t think o&apos; nothin&apos; but ham an&apos; eggs
                        when he goes t&apos; a resturint it&apos;s time he wuz gittin&apos; married. I
                        wonder who&apos;ll be th&apos; next lucky private banker t&apos; git off with a few
                        months.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-061" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Th&apos; Embryo Dramatic Troupe, o&apos; Bedford, Indianny, played &quot;Richard
                        th&apos; Third&quot; et Mitchell last week, an&apos; killed Richard in th&apos;
                        fust act so thet they could git a early train out o&apos; town. They expect t&apos; open
                        th&apos; new grain elevator et Shoals next Saturday. Tipton Bud missed his car up et
                        Indynoplus last Saturday. He thought it left thirty minutes before th&apos; hour, instead
                        o&apos; thirty minutes after th&apos; hour.</p>
                    <p>I reckon thet blamed anti-rebate bill is mighty unpopular with th&apos; fishermen.
                        Ever&apos; time a feller speaks o&apos; his salary he adds five or ten t&apos; it.</p>
                    <p>Young Lafe Bud, who travels fer a &quot;crayon portrait hold up,&quot; says
                        &apos;bout th&apos; only difference he sees in Indianny hut-tels is in th&apos;
                        color o&apos; th&apos; ice cream. I&apos;ll be gash dinged if it wouldn&apos;t
                        look funny t&apos; see some feller o&apos; ordinary means runnin&apos; fer State
                        Treasurer.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-062" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Somehow you never hear much &apos;bout th&apos; sons o&apos; clubwomen. I
                        dun&apos;t believe I ever seen one. &quot;How much does a ton o&apos; coal
                        weigh?&quot; wuz th&apos; question thet almost caused a lively rumpus over et
                        th&apos; grocery this mornin&apos;.</p>
                    <p>Uncle Ez Pash says thet ther wuz quite a racket over et Columbus Saturday night &apos;bout a
                        game o&apos; poll an&apos; thet when Mert Sanders went t&apos; look fer th&apos;
                        constable, Pinky Kerr wuz shot in th&apos; interim. By ginger, I dun&apos;t see how he
                        kin git well. Th&apos; pustoffis smells like a wet hen on rainy days.</p>
                    <p>Onions keep off th&apos; gripo&apos; your friends. Nice overhead t&apos;day but no
                        ones goin&apos; thet way.</p>
                    <p>Did yer ever hev a feller thet hed never been out o&apos; town tell you thet you&apos;d
                        &quot;missed th&apos; treat o&apos; your life&quot; cuz you stayed away from a
                        ten cent lecture? Th&apos; feller thet &quot;kin quote anything&quot;
                        hezn&apos;t necessarily got any more sense than a parrot.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-063" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Th&apos; cost o&apos; livin&apos; haint so much et fifty cents a bottle if you jist
                        foller th&apos; directions. Many a feller gits credit fer bein&apos; eccentric when he
                        ort t&apos; be in a padded cell.</p>
                    <p>There&apos;s one good thing &apos;bout them blamed four-room flats an&apos; thet is
                        your relatives can&apos;t &quot;remain over.&quot; Some girls er born with big feet
                        an&apos; others wear white shoes.</p>
                    <p>A prize-fighter kin &quot;know th&apos; ropes&quot; an&apos; still git his head
                        knocked off. Marion Wilder went up t&apos; Indynoplus Sunday an&apos; got his tongue
                        fastened in a beer bottle on Pearl street.</p>
                    <p>Hiram Turner wuz round Friday showin&apos; th&apos; boys a artificial fifty cent piece
                        thet he got ketched on up et Indynoplus. It looks like th&apos; ortomobile wuz
                        goin&apos; t&apos; go way with hoss sense ez well ez th&apos; hoss.</p>
                    <p>Tipton Bud says thet if ther&apos;s one thing&apos; more&apos;n another thet ort
                        t&apos; cause a public official t&apos; do his duty it&apos;s th&apos;
                        inducements offered by th&apos; lecture platform. Yaller journalism is bad enough, but a
                        yaller cucumber is th&apos; limit.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-064" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Th&apos; New Plush Ultra Comedy Company played &quot;Fogs Ferry&quot; here last
                        night, an&apos; No. 28 got th&apos; barrel o&apos; flour. Anybuddy kin tell Aunt
                        Maria Pash hez seen better days by th&apos; evidences o&apos; refinement an&apos;
                        gentle blood &apos;bout her home premises. She hez a geranium in a tomato can.</p>
                    <p>I often wonder what kind o&apos; lookin&apos; people pick out th&apos; pictures thet
                        hang in hut-tel rooms. Country editurs go a merry &quot;clip.&quot;</p>
                    <p>I wonder if Christmus segars make so many folks swear off smokin&apos; on New Year&apos;s
                        day? Ther er three kind o&apos; Christmusseswhite, green an&apos; blue.</p>
                    <p>Miss Fawn Lippincut recited in Melodeon Hall last night fer the benefit o&apos; Clem
                        Harner&apos;s band an&apos; notwithstanding th&apos; infrequency o&apos;
                        th&apos; weather ther wuz many people in th&apos; audience who were not there.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-065" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Alex Tansey thinks somethin&apos; o&apos; goin&apos; with a troupe. His uncle wuz
                        quite a actor an&apos; tore paper fer th&apos; snow scene in th&apos; &quot;Two
                        Orphans&quot; when it wuz played in th&apos; old Metropolitan livery stable et Urbana,
                        O., back in fifty-one.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-066" n="[]"/>
                    <figure entity="VAA2347-8"/>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-067" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Tipton Bud&apos;s wife is so dash blamed stingy thet she peels pertaters with a safety razor.
                        If a young lawyer kin jist evade his rent an&apos; stick t&apos; a prune diet fer three
                        er four years he may git on a payin&apos; basis.</p>
                    <p>Senitur Beveridge hez sent us a package each o&apos; salpiglossis, calliopsis, gaillardia
                        an&apos; aquilegia. My wife hez taken part o&apos; one package an&apos; she feels
                        like a two-year-old. Speakin&apos; o&apos; th&apos; foreign invasion, you
                        kin&apos; hardly git along th&apos; resident streets o&apos; Indynoplus fer poles.</p>
                    <p>By ginger, talk about a huldup. If you wunt t&apos; go on th&apos; sojers&apos;
                        monument et Indynoplus you&apos;ve got t&apos; buy a roundtrip ticket. Pinky Kerr is
                        raisin&apos; a set o&apos; whiskers fer th&apos; winter, an&apos; his chin looks
                        like thcylinder in a music box.</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; feller thet worries along in a four-room flat is not always a four-flusher. By
                        ginger, ther&apos;s a big perlitical fight goin&apos; on et Bloom Center, O. All
                        th&apos; business men er tryin&apos; t&apos; keep out o&apos; th&apos; city
                        council.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-068" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Ole Niles Turner says thet he dun&apos;t keer whether a feller hez been married ten, twenty
                        er fifty years, some new phase o&apos; his wife&apos;s character will pop out every day.</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; old-fashioned &quot;dollar excursionist&quot; thet used t&apos; pull his
                        boots off an&apos; let his feet dangle over th&apos; arm o&apos; th&apos; seat
                        seems t&apos; hev dropped out altogether. Ez long ez th&apos;
                        &quot;findings&quot; fer a woman&apos;s dress cost ten times ez much ez th&apos;
                        dress, times will allus be a little skimpish in this country.</p>
                    <p>Some of those blamed Indynoplus grocery keepers ort t&apos; go t&apos; a ball game
                        an&apos; learn somethin&apos; &apos;bout quick delivery. I guess it&apos;ll be
                        purty hard t&apos; revive wrestling an&apos; croquet in this country.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-069" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Some folks think thet th&apos; only time they ever hev t&apos; pologize is when you ketch
                        &apos;em et th&apos; circus. It&apos;s gittin&apos; so nobuddy but printers and
                        telegraph operators chaw terbacker.</p>
                    <p>Constable Newt Plum got off one t&apos;-day in his perculiar quiet style o&apos;
                        pitchin&apos; thet hed more truth &apos;n poetree in it. He said thet when times git so
                        blamed good in this country thet a feller can&apos;t put a new roof on his kitchen
                        it&apos;s time fer a panic.</p>
                    <p>Miss Fawn Lippincut says thet th&apos; Indianny University Aluminum is th&apos; next
                        thing on th&apos; tapestry fer her. Tailors dunt care much fer promisin&apos; young men.</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; Decluration o&apos; Inderpendence, th&apos; burnin&apos; o&apos;
                        th&apos; fire department et St. Marys, Ohio, th&apos; Emancerpation Proclermation
                        an&apos; th&apos; long sleeve glove famine o&apos; 1906, will always be memorable
                        epicures in American history.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-070" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Too many womens&apos; clubs spoil th&apos; broth. Tipton Bud is diggin&apos; a well.
                        Tip is fond o&apos; waterafterwards.</p>
                    <p>No matter how blamed careful a feller is o&apos; his pusonal appearance he can&apos;t
                        keep egg off his chin. Some fellers git credit fer bein&apos; affable an&apos; generous
                        when they&apos;ve only been drinkin&apos;.</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; must exactin&apos; critic thet goes t&apos; th&apos; the-ater is
                        th&apos; feller thet gits in on a billboard ticket an&apos; chews terbaccer on
                        th&apos; lower floor. Th&apos; child thet&apos;s preached t&apos; all week long
                        an&apos; then sent t&apos; Sunday-school with a punched nickle soon gits wise.</p>
                    <p>Did you ever notice thet th&apos; girl thet says &quot;don&apos;t you&quot;
                        instead o&apos; &quot;don&apos;t chew&quot; says et fer eat. Most o&apos;
                        th&apos; articles you read in th&apos; newspapers signed by &quot;constant
                        reader&quot; sound like th&apos; writer didn&apos;t know enough t&apos; read.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-071" n="[]"/>
                    <p>There hain&apos;t been no quorum down et th&apos; grocery since they put th&apos;
                        cheese in a wire cage. It&apos;s been a blamed long while a-comin&apos;, but et last we
                        hev a &quot;Y&quot; in Ellyn.</p>
                    <p>While he may laugh best, there is jist a bare possibility thet th&apos; feller who laughs
                        last is slow &apos;bout ketchin&apos; on. We never hear nuthin&apos; &apos;bout
                        a &quot;eight-hour day&quot; fer mother.</p>
                    <p>They&apos;ve got everything in them ther big department stores up et Indynoplus but a place
                        t&apos; sleep while your waitin&apos; t&apos; be waited on. Th&apos;
                        Rushin&apos; news is still bomb.</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; Reglar Army an&apos; th&apos; street car companies er gittin&apos; most
                        o&apos; th&apos; boys in this country. Clem Harner says thet if it wuzn&apos;t fer
                        th&apos; colleges ther wouldn&apos;t be a soul t&apos; drive delivery wagons
                        an&apos; solicit insurance. By ginger, Speak Taylor is a slangy feller. He says thet he got
                        so blamed tired huskin&apos; corn thet he went home an&apos; &quot;threw two singles
                        fer th&apos; mat&quot; an&apos; never waked up till 9 th&apos; next day.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-072" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Th&apos; feller thet&apos;s allus tellin&apos; what a wonderful woman his wife is
                        generally hez t&apos; smoke in th&apos; kitchen. Nobuddy ever elopes but once.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Alex Tansey hez got a new graffyphun. It sounds like th&apos; raspin&apos;
                        o&apos; a new pair o&apos; overalls. Tilden Moon is travelin&apos; with a troupe ez
                        juggler. He comes by it honestly. His father used t&apos; eat peas with a knife.</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; folks down et Madison er goin&apos; crazy over th&apos; new State insane
                        asylum. Th&apos; &quot;Denver Dames Beauty Show&quot; burlesque troupe passed
                        thro&apos; Columbus yisterday. Th&apos; show looked ez though it might o&apos; been
                        organized under a lamp pust et Sidney, O.</p>
                    <p>By ginger, I&apos;ll never fergit th&apos; time I carried th&apos; bass drum through
                        two foot o&apos; snow fer ole Dupree an&apos; Bennydick&apos;s minstrel troupe. Ever
                        time th&apos; feller soaked th&apos; drum it knocked my hat off.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-073" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Poor ole Turpin Pusey hez hed a peck o&apos; trouble. His wife wuz struck by
                        lightnin&apos; while she wuz plowin&apos;, three sons takin&apos; th&apos; gold
                        cure an&apos; a dorter thet recites. I dun&apos;t know which is th&apos; biggest
                        rubeth&apos; countryman walkin&apos; about with a conductor&apos;s check in his hat
                        er th&apos; tadpole with his suit case covered with labels.</p>
                    <p>I&apos;ll bet thet th&apos; editurs thet hev been flyin&apos; over th&apos;
                        country fer years on railroad passes wish they&apos;d paid more attention t&apos;
                        th&apos; scenery while they hed a chance. Newt Plum&apos;s son Decatur is goin&apos;
                        t&apos; th&apos; Rose Pyrotechnic Instytute et Terry Hut. He&apos;s
                        learnin&apos; t&apos; make sky rockets.</p>
                    <p>&apos;Bout ever so often pollyticians git t&apos; talkin&apos; o&apos; gittin
                        &quot;close to th&apos; plain people,&quot; yet th&apos; plain people never seem
                        t&apos; git &quot;next&quot; t&apos; th&apos; pollyticians. It takes jist
                        &apos;bout two good compliments t&apos; disquollerfy th&apos; ordinary feller.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-074" n="[]"/>
                    <p>This is the sort o&apos; weather I allus think o&apos; th&apos; campaign orator what
                        buzzes &apos;bout th&apos; glorious independent life o&apos; th&apos; farmer.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-075" n="[]"/>
                    <figure entity="VAA2347-9"/>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-076" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Clem Harner says a &quot;pervaricator&quot; is a tailor. Who ever heard o&apos; a
                        bank cashier thet could hit anything with a pistol.</p>
                    <p>I seen a sign up et Indynoplus &apos;tother day thet said, &quot;supper 5 to 7.&quot;
                        Thet&apos;s a good deal t&apos; pay fer meals. Pinky Kerr says you can&apos;t shoot
                        quails till November 10. I wondered why I had been missin&apos; so many.</p>
                    <p>Ashby Perkins says it&apos;s no use t&apos; try t&apos; carry out a color scheme in a
                        flat thet wunt stand fer anything better than three-cent wall paper. I asked Ez Pash who
                        th&apos; fust pioneer around Nashville wuz, an&apos; he says: &quot;I dun&apos;t
                        know who th&apos; fust pioneer wuz, but Plum&apos;s folks hed th&apos; fust organ.</p>
                    <p>Some folks seem t&apos; think thet jist cuz a feller is a &quot;travelin&apos;
                        man&quot; he knows it all. I used t&apos; know a chap named Jimmy Prince over in Ohio
                        thet hed been all over th&apos; world three times an&apos; all I ever heerd him tell wuz
                        thet he couldn&apos;t find no plug terbaccer in London.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-077" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Th&apos; peaches on top o&apos; th&apos; baskets er unusually large an&apos; fine
                        this season. By ginger, you kin drive a man t&apos; drink but you can&apos;t make him
                        take a se-gar.</p>
                    <p>There&apos;s many a man gits int&apos; trouble thet&apos;s allus been good
                        t&apos; his wife. By ginger, a night school fer sign painters would be a crackin&apos;
                        good thing.</p>
                    <p>When a feller subscribes $10 t&apos; some worthy cause he stays in a ugly humor fer two years
                        after-wards. High priced flats seem t&apos; be drivin&apos; married people out
                        o&apos; business up et Indynoplus. Th&apos; devorce court shows thet th&apos; old
                        ketch, &quot;two livin&apos; cheaper&apos;n one,&quot; hain&apos;t
                        makin&apos; a hit fer some reason.</p>
                    <p>Tiry Buff dun&apos;t take hez wife no where now since they&apos;re married. He says
                        fellers dun&apos;t run after street cars after they&apos;ve caught &apos;em. Dr.
                        Elliott Nod, a imminent writer o&apos; Bucyrus, Ohio, sez we&apos;re ridin&apos;
                        faster&apos;n we live.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-078" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Th&apos; good thing &apos;bout th&apos; old-fashioned paper collar wuz thet folks put
                        on a clean one once in awhile. Th&apos; next General Assembly ort t&apos; be held on
                        th&apos; cottage plan.</p>
                    <p>I claim thet ther haint no good excuse fer marryin&apos; a penniless, ugly
                        girl&apos;specially if yer goin&apos; t&apos; be home much. You kin generally tell a
                        feller thet likes a &quot;wide open&quot; town by his stomach an&apos; watch chain.</p>
                    <p>I guess pickin&apos; out wall paper hez caused &apos;bout ez many tragedies ez liquor.
                        Dave Angel says thet it gits a hundred in th&apos; shade down here in th&apos; summer
                        time. By ginger, I dun&apos;t keer. I dun&apos;t hev t&apos; stay in th&apos;
                        shade all th&apos; time.</p>
                    <p>A nephew of a feller named Teeters livin&apos; et Hagerstown, Indianny, hez given a top
                        t&apos; one o&apos; th&apos; Roosyfel children an&apos; th&apos; eyes
                        o&apos; th&apos; nation are once agin on Indianny. It hez been a good many years since
                        only fellers thet amounted t&apos; somethin&apos; wore plug hats.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-079" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Niles Turner hez a niece, Miss Fawn Lippincut, thet&apos;s a comer in th&apos; literary
                        world if she jist keeps her health. Here&apos;s a little thing she wrote yisterday in less
                        than a hour: Oh, th&apos; purty little birds!</p>
                    <p>How I love t&apos; hear them sing, Ez they flit from tree t&apos; treeLet me count them,
                        one, two, three! Some er red an&apos; some er blue, But th&apos; red er very few.</p>
                    <p>A farmer allus gits off a street car a block too soon.</p>
                    <p>Aunt Tildy McGoogle died yisterday et Evansville, aged 105, an&apos; she hed smoked all her
                        life. By ginger, if she&apos;d lived another year she&apos;d a hed enough coupons
                        t&apos; git a pasteboard suitcase. Waldo Blayney &quot;bet his life&quot; on Britt,
                        an&apos; wuz in a percarious condition Saturday night. This mornin&apos; he wuz able
                        t&apos; worry down a soft egg.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-080" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Th&apos; good old days hev gone by when yer could give a editur a sack o&apos; cornmeal
                        an&apos; git a puff in th&apos; paper. Ther haint much economy in stogies fer a feller
                        allus breaks two out o&apos; possible three.</p>
                    <p>A feller may git jist ez tired o&apos; a wife ez he does a boardin&apos; house but it
                        wunt be ez easy t&apos; change. Ole Ez Pash says, &quot;in makin&apos; apple butter
                        use only th&apos; largest turnips.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Muncie is a great city. I wuz there &apos;bout fifteen minutes tother day an&apos; I
                        didn&apos;t git t&apos; see much more&apos;n half o&apos; what there wuz
                        t&apos; be seen. Th&apos; smoke must be purty bad up et Indynoplus. Th&apos; papers
                        is advertisin&apos; smokin&apos; jackets.</p>
                    <p>This is jist &apos;bout th&apos; time o&apos; year th&apos; average farmer moves
                        hez fences &apos;bout two feet neerder th&apos; railroad tracks. By ginger, some dude
                        gimme a cigaroot while I wuz up t&apos; Indynoplus an&apos; th&apos; blamed thing
                        smells like a G string burnin&apos; up.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-081" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Miss Pearline Smith wuz voted th&apos; queen o&apos; th&apos; carnival at Round-head,
                        Ohio, an&apos; her picture wuz in one o&apos; th&apos; Sunday papers. If her nose
                        keeps on a growin&apos; it will hit her on th&apos; back. Life&apos;s t&apos;
                        short t&apos; monkey with uncut magazines.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-082" n="[]"/>
                    <figure entity="VAA2347-10"/>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-083" n="[]"/>
                    <p>I heerd there wuz goin&apos; ter be a new magazine printed et Indynoplus called th&apos;
                        &quot;Sky Scraper.&quot; Twenty-two stories. I&apos;ll be gosh dinged ef I ever
                        heard o&apos; a feller gitting a devorce from a women thet wuz a good cook.</p>
                    <p>What would become o&apos; this Government if all th&apos; Landis boys would make up ther
                        minds t&apos; git out o&apos; pollyticks an&apos; go t&apos; work? Tipton Bud
                        sez th&apos; only thing new &apos;bout th&apos; Barnum circus wuz thet they
                        didn&apos;t hev no trained seals.</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; feller thet got hez coat tails shot off at Loogootee last night is able t&apos;
                        be &quot;roundabout.&quot; It must be awful t&apos; hev t&apos; live in
                        Indynoplus durin&apos; one o&apos; them campaigns fer a &quot;business
                        administration.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Uncle Ez Pash says his new hired man is so dinggasted lazy thet he hed t&apos; sharpen all
                        th&apos; stumps on th&apos; farm t&apos; keep him from settin&apos; down. Your
                        husband wunt kiss th&apos; cook if you do your own cookin&apos;.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-084" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Ole Niles Turner hez took forty-two kinds o&apos; patent medicine an&apos; hez hed his
                        picture in all th&apos; county newspapers. He says thet th&apos; publicity keeps him
                        alive. They still hitch horses around th&apos; court-house et Marion, Indianny.</p>
                    <p>I wuz up t&apos; Anderson yisterday an you can&apos;t tell it from some parts o&apos;
                        Lincoln City. William Henry Harrison and Gov&apos;ner Hanly er th&apos; only two men
                        thet ever enforced th&apos; law et Vincennes.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Shirk&quot; Johnson sez his family is all well an&apos; happy &apos;cept
                        Myrtle&apos; an&apos; she&apos;s in Urbana, Ohio. Who in th&apos; thunder ever
                        heerd o&apos; any other kind o&apos; a girl but a strikin&apos;ly beautiful one
                        committin&apos; sueycide?</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-085" n="[]"/>
                    <p>A feller kin be a model husband without surrenderin&apos; his right t&apos; select his
                        own socks. Th&apos; mere mention o&apos; Bryan&apos;s name still continues
                        t&apos; cause uproarious applause down our way.</p>
                    <p>A feller in ordinary circumstances died o&apos; &apos;pendicitus et Shoals
                        &apos;tother day. Th&apos; ole sayin&apos; &quot;th&apos; selection
                        o&apos; wall paper makes strange bed fellows&quot; is put nigh right.</p>
                    <p>Tipton Bud hez received a pustal card from his wife sayin&apos; thet she hed arrived in
                        Urbana, Ohio, safe an&apos; sane. Miss Tawney Apple, one o&apos; Alex Tansey&apos;s
                        scholars et school, wrote this an&apos; she&apos;s only 19 years old</p>
                    <p>Oh! Oh! th&apos; snow, th&apos; snow,</p>
                    <p>After all o&apos; this delayin&apos;</p>
                    <p>The ground is covered with you now An&apos; we&apos;ll go a sleighin&apos;.</p>
                    <p>She is finishin&apos; up another batch t&apos; be called &quot;When th&apos;
                        Spout is Filled with Ice.&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-086" n="[]"/>
                    <p>I guess th&apos; poolrooms hev opened up agin up et Indynoplus fer Pinky Kerr seen a sign on
                        a buildin&apos; sayin&apos; &quot;Aristoka Flat1 to 4.&quot; By ginger,
                        it&apos;s fer better t&apos; give than receivea Christmus necktie.</p>
                    <p>Lots o&apos; seemin&apos;ly intelligent folks keep on sayin&apos;
                        &quot;butatoes&quot; fer pertaters. I kin remember when they used t&apos; line
                        pantaloons.</p>
                    <p>Ole Ez Pash says thet he guesses th&apos; reason Oklahoma editurs look so happy an&apos;
                        prosperous is becuz they raise two crops o&apos; turnips a year out there.</p>
                    <p>Ther&apos;s gittin&apos; t&apos; be too many blamed schemes in this country
                        t&apos; &quot;make people save thet wouldn&apos;t otherwise
                        save&quot;an&apos; lose thet wouldn&apos;t otherwise lose. Th&apos; society
                        column in a newspaper is a good directory fer a porch climber.</p>
                    <p>Strawberry boxes er so blamed little this year thet they bruise th&apos; berries. Tipton Budd
                        will be seventy-three years old t&apos;morrow. He says he&apos;d be seventy-five, but he
                        wuz in Urbana, Ohio, two years.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-087" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Some blamed troupe is a playin&apos; &quot;Repertoire&quot; agin&apos; over et
                        Columbus. I&apos;d think thet they&apos;d git tired o&apos; thet play some time er
                        nother. Anna Laurie must a bin a wonderful woman. Th&apos; poet says thet her voice wuz
                        &quot;low an&apos; sweet.&quot;</p>
                    <p>A good, shiny book agent kin sniff &quot;a dollar per&quot; hut-tel farther than any man
                        thet travels. Th&apos; feller thet dun&apos;t read th&apos; daily newspapers hez a
                        hard time lookin&apos; wise while his friends discuss th&apos; affairs o&apos;
                        th&apos; country.</p>
                    <p>Ther seems t&apos; be some considerable sediment agin Gov&apos;nor Hanly&apos;s
                        two-cent fare policy. Folks thet patternize th&apos; interurban lines er claimin&apos;
                        thet they wunt be able t&apos; save ez much. Jim Collins, up et Indynoplus, sez thet
                        th&apos; &quot;round robin&quot; fust started et Circleville, Ohio.</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; feller thet looks funny with his hat off is allus th&apos; busiest individual et
                        a convention er meetin&apos; o&apos; any sort. Al Clemens an&apos; his wife hev
                        split up. His wife took all th&apos; furniture an&apos; th&apos; five children
                        an&apos; Al took th&apos; blame.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-088" n="[]"/>
                    <p>I wuz tellin&apos; Pinky Kerr thet you could go from Indynoplus t&apos; Bloomington with
                        out change now an&apos; he said he didn&apos;t believe itthet he hed traveled with too
                        many Uncle Toms not t&apos; know how fur you kin go without change. Young Arson Smith died
                        in perfect agony yisterday. He didn&apos;t smoke cigaroots, so th&apos; doctors
                        didn&apos;t know what ailed him.</p>
                    <p>What good house painters those ther porch climbers would make if they&apos;d only settle
                        down. Miss Fawn Lippincut says thet th&apos; time t&apos; eat onions is et midnight.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-089" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Tilford Moots thinks some o&apos; runnin&apos; fer offis, but he hates t&apos;
                        mortgage his home. A couple o&apos; strangers wuz here this week talkin&apos; up a
                        cannin&apos; factory. One wuz dressed like a Dimmycrat an&apos; th&apos;
                        &apos;tother looked like he wuz in ordinary circumstances too.</p>
                    <p>I notice by th&apos; papers thet ther is quite a &quot;Hearst feelin&apos;&quot;
                        in New York. Must be yeller janders. Tipton Budd says thet he went &apos;round t&apos;
                        th&apos; hut-tel yisterday an&apos; ther wuz a sign on th&apos; door sayin&apos;
                        &quot;gone t&apos; dinner.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Professor Runyan&apos;s troupe o&apos; smilin&apos; cows from Bluffton will be seen
                        et one o&apos; th&apos; Indynoplus parks this season. Seems like complercations er
                        &apos;bout ez successful ez operations these days.</p>
                    <p>Tad Clemens, who hez been a livin&apos; et Indynoplus fer two er three years, jist
                        can&apos;t git weaned away from th&apos; good ole times down here. He buys a
                        nickle&apos;s worth o&apos; cherries an&apos; climbs up in a tree t&apos; eat
                        &apos;em. Fine nights t&apos; sleepif you&apos;ve got a nice, light pink conscience.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-090" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Th&apos; bad thing &apos;bout Roosyfel&apos;s perposed uniform devorce law is thet it
                        would be hard on folks thet wunt devorces an&apos; hain&apos;t able t&apos; buy
                        uniforms. Prof. Alex Tansey hez arranged his trip t&apos; Niagry Falls so he&apos;ll go
                        through Greensburg in th&apos; daytime. He dun&apos;t wunt t&apos; miss anything.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-091" n="[]"/>
                    <figure entity="VAA2347-11"/>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-092" n="[]"/>
                    <p>After everbuddy else gits paid in full, th&apos; family doctor gits a dollar on account. It
                        now develops thet th&apos; West Liberty (O.) boy thet shot his father an&apos; cut his
                        mother&apos;s nose off, an&apos; burned th&apos; house, hed been readin&apos; a
                        Sunday newspaper.</p>
                    <p>Ther hain&apos;t nothin&apos; in Ringling&apos;s circus ez rare ez Colonel Stegg,
                        o&apos; Limesdale. He&apos;s th&apos; only livin&apos; Dimmycratic pust-master
                        in th&apos; world an&apos; probably th&apos; last. Constable Newt Plum sez thet
                        folks thet live in &quot;glass houses&quot; throw no boquetsunless you pay fer them.</p>
                    <p>When a woman gits a dress made th&apos; tailor allus measures her husband fust. Ole Niles
                        Turner says thet he wuz in th&apos; poorhouse three years under Cleveland. He hez come out
                        flat-footed fer Bryan.</p>
                    <p>Miss Fawn Lippincut&apos;s uncle took her over t&apos; Morgantown this mornin&apos;
                        in his new ten-candlepower ortomobile an&apos; she bought one o&apos; them new style
                        lingerin&apos; waists. Laugh an&apos; th&apos; world laughs with you, weep
                        an&apos; it&apos;ll buy your papers.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-093" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Mr. Alex Tansey hez a theory thet I&apos;m rather inclined t&apos; take a good deal
                        o&apos; stock in. He says thet th&apos; thinnin&apos; out o&apos; th&apos;
                        great forests in th&apos; Northwest an&apos; fillin&apos; Indianny with telephone
                        an&apos; interurban poles is undoubtedly changin&apos; th&apos; course o&apos;
                        th&apos; gulf stream. Some &quot;peroxide blonde&quot; is a gittin&apos; ready
                        t&apos; hev a millinery openin&apos; in a room next t&apos; th&apos; livery
                        stable.</p>
                    <p>Constable Newt Plum raided a card club yisterday an&apos; got a pair o&apos; green lisle
                        hose, a hand-painted plate an&apos; a shirtwaist pattern. A feller thet buys three er four
                        15-cent drinks on his way t&apos; a 10-cent dinner generally sends money loose in
                        th&apos; mails.</p>
                    <p>Ther&apos;s lots o&apos; worse things than eatin&apos; with your knifebut not much.
                        When a spring cannydate comes whinin&apos; &apos;round you an&apos; tells you thet
                        he &quot;allus voted th&apos; party ticket,&quot; ask him what else he kin do.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-094" n="[]"/>
                    <p>In these high-fa-lootin&apos; days you never see th&apos; old wood-box covered with wall
                        paper. O&apos; all th&apos; woman&apos;s clubs th&apos; rollin&apos; pin is
                        th&apos; wust.</p>
                    <p>I seen a well-dressed stranger chewin&apos; terbaccer Sunday, so I guess we&apos;re all
                        purty much human after all. Ez Pash says thet after he gits through readin&apos; some
                        o&apos; th&apos; stories in th&apos; Sunday papers he&apos;s afeerd t&apos;
                        go t&apos; bed.</p>
                    <p>Old Niles Turner says thet th&apos; feelin&apos; o&apos; security thet comes with
                        th&apos; &apos;cumilation o&apos; a few thousand dollars must be a wonderful
                        sensation. It&apos;s almost impossible t&apos; git a huld o&apos; a non-onion segar
                        these days.</p>
                    <p>When ther&apos;s &quot;no use talkin&apos;&quot; &apos;bout a thing a woman
                        wunt hev nothin&apos; t&apos; do with it. Jist ez soon ez th&apos; new culbert
                        across th&apos; crick east of Moot&apos;s place is done, Miss Fawn Lippincut is a
                        goin&apos; t&apos; give a &quot;bridge party.&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-095" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Pinky Kerr says thet people who live in glass houses should stone no cherries. Th&apos;
                        feller with th&apos; celluloid collar an&apos; his friend er soon parted.</p>
                    <p>Newt Plum&apos;s son-in-law says thet he never saved a blamed cent until after his wife hed
                        quarreled with ever&apos; dressmaker in town. My idea o&apos; an&apos; old-fashioned
                        Dimmycrat is one thet never goes no place where he can&apos;t wear a plaid sack suit.</p>
                    <p>A good deal o&apos; anxiety is felt fer Alex Tansey&apos;s safety. Yisterday
                        evenin&apos; he started t&apos; visit his aunt up et Angola, an&apos; up t&apos;
                        noon t&apos;day not one single souvenir pustal card hez been received from him. By ginger,
                        yer never see no wax flowers with a glass globe over &apos;em settin&apos; on
                        th&apos; &quot;what-not&quot; like yer used t&apos; years ago.</p>
                    <p>Tipton Bud lost three fingers yisterday. A feller asked him t&apos; hev a drink, but his wife
                        wuz with him. It&apos;s purty hard t&apos; &quot;keep up t&apos; th&apos;
                        Standard&quot; these days.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-096" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Th&apos; most familiar o&apos; all th&apos; ole masters is Simon Legree. Th&apos;
                        frequent changes in Roosyfel&apos;s official family must make th&apos; cabinet
                        photergraf business good down et Washington, D. C.</p>
                    <p>Pinky Kerr wuz down t&apos; Vincennes yisterday t&apos; hear Bryan an&apos; he says
                        he looks fine. Well, what&apos;s t&apos; prevent? When a feller gits too fat t&apos;
                        eat in a dinin&apos; car he ort t&apos; walk.</p>
                    <p>After thet anty-pass law goes int&apos; effect you&apos;ll allus find th&apos; editur
                        in. Ther haint enough Dimmycrats up et Winchester t&apos; move a pi-anner.</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; principal trouble &apos;bout marryin&apos; a girl with money is thet her
                        father is liable t&apos; worry himself t&apos; death wonderin&apos; how you er
                        goin&apos; t&apos; spend it. A bird on th&apos; hat is worth ten in th&apos;
                        pocket.</p>
                    <p>William Jennings Bryan an&apos; Mrs. Nicholas Longworth hev closed ther Indianny tours
                        an&apos; ole General Apathy wuz able t&apos; potter down town this mornin&apos; fer
                        th&apos; fust time in a week. Do you remember how grand you used t&apos; think it would
                        be t&apos; chaw terbacker.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-097" n="[]"/>
                    <p>It&apos;s all right t&apos; be close mouthed an&apos; cool headed if you kin be thet
                        way without lookin&apos; stupid. Miss Fawn Lippincut says thet th&apos; trouble with
                        most wives is thet when they&apos;re not hungry they dun&apos;t think no one else is
                        ither.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-098" n="[]"/>
                    <figure entity="VAA2347-12"/>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-099" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Eatin&apos; et swell calfs after th&apos; theater is gittin&apos; t&apos; be
                        quite a fad with th&apos; young folks up et Indynoplusbefore ther married. I never knowed
                        till t&apos;-day thet Alex Tansey&apos;s brother wuz a intestine et a hospital over et
                        Cincinnatty.</p>
                    <p>Newt Plum&apos;s married dorter up et Indynoplus, thet bit her tongue off tryin&apos;
                        t&apos; climb in one o&apos; them new summer cars, is gittin&apos; along fine,
                        an&apos; Thursday she wuz able t&apos; walk downtown an&apos; exchange a canteloupe.
                        Ferdinand, Dubios county, Indianny, is a picturesque place, th&apos; inhabitants
                        bein&apos; all Dimmycrats.</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; reason so many people come home &quot;flat&quot; is because travel broadens.
                        Th&apos; newspapers hev been so full o&apos; th&apos; Thaw murder case th&apos;
                        past few weeks thet it&apos;ll be purty hard t&apos; git a juryunless they find it et
                        Evansville.</p>
                    <p>Ther haint no fun in goin&apos; out o&apos; town on a vacation trip if you&apos;ve
                        got t&apos; keep figurin&apos; all th&apos; time. Miss Fawn Lippincut says thet when
                        she&apos;s invited t&apos; a party she allus gits ther fust so thet th&apos; other
                        guests can&apos;t talk &apos;bout her.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-100" n="[]"/>
                    <p>One good thing &apos;bout bein&apos; a Dimmycrat in Indianny is thet you dun&apos;t
                        hev t&apos; mortgage your home t&apos; git a perlitical nomination. A story wuz in
                        circulation here Monday thet a stranger, claimin&apos; t&apos; be a well-t&apos;-do
                        sewin&apos; machine agent o&apos; Mansfield, Ohio, found a good canteloupe up et
                        Indynoplus.</p>
                    <p>A farmer never seems t&apos; be satisfied. Jist ez soon ez he harvests his wheat he commences
                        t&apos; plow fer more. Even handle bars are higher these days along with ever&apos;thing
                        else.</p>
                    <p>No matter what it isa reception, a hat, a funeral er a glass o&apos; sodya girl allus calls
                        et &quot;swell.&quot; We&apos;d hev longer summers if th&apos; blamed Park
                        The-ater up et Indynoplus didn&apos;t open so early.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-101" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Tipton Bud&apos;s wife hez been kickin&apos; all her life fer a new summer kitchen,
                        an&apos; Tip told her yisterday thet he&apos;d build her one when Bryan got elected,
                        an&apos; she said: &quot;You&apos;ll not git out o&apos; buildin&apos; it
                        thet way.&quot; These people thet go t&apos; th&apos; circus &quot;jist
                        t&apos; take th&apos; children&quot; never wunt t&apos; pay fer them when they
                        git up t&apos; th&apos; door.</p>
                    <p>Tilford Moot&apos;s wife is a smart critter. She punched th&apos; bottom o&apos;
                        th&apos; coffee pot full o&apos; holes so it wouldn&apos;t rust. Constable Newt
                        Plum&apos;s son-in-law up et Indynoplus is goin&apos; t&apos; move out o&apos; a
                        flat int&apos; a ten-room house so he&apos;ll hev room t&apos; take a Sunday paper.</p>
                    <p>Tipton Bud says thet if everbuddy thet listened t&apos; Bryan up et Plymouth Wednesday would
                        vote fer him he could be elected without New York an&apos; all th&apos; States
                        o&apos; th&apos; middle West. Standin&apos; on ther dignity makes some people look
                        still shorter.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-102" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Th&apos; woman who spends her whole life et home an&apos; raises a flock o&apos;
                        ungrateful children is called a &quot;homebuddy,&quot; an&apos; when she dies she
                        gits good press notices. People who flock t&apos;gether er busy these days layin&apos;
                        in ther winter supply o&apos; feather boas.</p>
                    <p>After all, a Dimmycrat with a trade is not so bad off these days. Th&apos; feller thet shaves
                        himself is a close shaver.</p>
                    <p>Seems like ther&apos;s twice ez many marriages nowerdays when th&apos; newspapers print
                        half tone pictures so well. Germans an&apos; ostriches seem t&apos; be able t&apos;
                        digest anything.</p>
                    <p>Tipton Budd says his idea o&apos; a ideal wife is one thet says she&apos;d like
                        t&apos; hev this er thet but hates t&apos; ask her husband fer it. Th&apos; Jungle
                        will soon be drammertized an&apos; on th&apos; road &quot;packin&apos;
                        houses.&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-103" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Some o&apos; th&apos; girls up et Indynoplus hev such small waists thet they must live on
                        spig-gety. Never let your children know thet you were young once yourself.</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; carpenters an&apos; joiners out t&apos; San Francisco er gittin&apos;
                        along fine. Th&apos; carpenters hev all th&apos; work they kin do an&apos;
                        th&apos; lodges look after th&apos; joiners. Young Lafe Bud tried t&apos; git on a
                        trunk line et Mitchell yisterday with a suit case an&apos; a brakeman put him off.</p>
                    <p>Some new-married couple hez moved next t&apos; Tapley Bray&apos;s home. Tap says his wife
                        is a goin&apos; t&apos; call on &apos;em jist ez soon ez she sees &apos;em go
                        out. Th&apos; feller thet wears eyeglasses kin booze around all night an&apos; look like
                        he&apos;d wrote a history o&apos; th&apos; world th&apos; next mornin&apos;.</p>
                    <p>Pinky Kerr wuz remarkin&apos; et th&apos; pustoffis yisterday thet th&apos; feller
                        with a red nose an&apos; dyed mustache allus wears a light hat. Some fellers hustle along
                        an&apos; manage t&apos; make both ends meet an&apos; others wear emblurmatic pins
                        an&apos; watch charms.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-104" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Ther&apos;s lots o&apos; simple girls in smart gowns. I understand many non-union
                        laborers er leavin&apos; th&apos; cities an&apos; goin&apos; on farms where they
                        kin work twice ez many hours fer half th&apos; money.</p>
                    <p>Miss Tawney Apple started out t&apos; a kitchen shower this afternoon with an umbrella. All
                        this talk &apos;bout a home fer chorus girls is blamed nonsense. They stay on th&apos;
                        stage till ther a hundred years ole.</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; way t&apos; stop wars between nations is t&apos; stop lendin&apos;
                        &apos;em money. I know a feller et Mulberry Junction what quit drinkin&apos; thet way.
                        Ther&apos;s some talk &apos;mongst th&apos; women folks down here o&apos;
                        tryin&apos; t&apos; git a tainted library.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-105" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Dave Angel&apos;s boy is gittin&apos; &apos;bout big enough t&apos; run off.
                        He&apos;ll probably be a motorman er go with th&apos; reglar army. I dun&apos;t look
                        fer much good t&apos; come o&apos; municipal ownership in this country ez long ez we hev
                        Dimmycrats an&apos; Republicans.</p>
                    <p>Ther&apos;s a unusually big crop o&apos; girls with bulging foreheads an&apos;
                        retreatin&apos; chins wearin&apos; turbans this fall. Th&apos; streets er so wide et
                        Crawfordsville th&apos; neighbors hev t&apos; use opery glasses t&apos; keep a line
                        on one &apos;nother.</p>
                    <p>Newt Plum says he seen a two hundred dollar bill yisterday, an&apos; it wuz ez big ez
                        th&apos; South Bend Tribune. I heerd some blamed Indynoplus dude ask fer
                        &quot;country-fied&quot; pertaters et a resturint in Columbus Saturday.</p>
                    <p>Talk &apos;bout humidity, by ginger, Newt Plum says they served butter in a dipper over
                        t&apos; th&apos; New Palace Hut-tel t&apos;day. Some folks hev hired girls
                        &apos;round th&apos; house jist t&apos; git th&apos; news.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-106" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Its almost suicide fer a pug nosed girl t&apos; put spectacles on. A resturint waiter allus
                        lays your check on th&apos; table upside down so you won&apos;t choak t&apos; death.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-107" n="[]"/>
                    <figure entity="VAA2347-13"/>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-108" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Our new school teacher is a funny lookin&apos; chap. He&apos;s got sideburns like one
                        o&apos; them students thet hangs paper in th&apos; summer time an&apos; goes
                        t&apos; medical college in th&apos; winter. By ginger, this is th&apos; kind
                        o&apos; weather thet is only found in th&apos; mountains er et th&apos;
                        seashoreaccordin&apos; t&apos; th&apos; railroad folders.</p>
                    <p>Some o&apos; th&apos; &apos;rithmetic problems thet spoiled yer childhood bother yer
                        a durned sight more after you er married an&apos; try t&apos; git by on eight or nine
                        dollars a week. By ginger, it&apos;s no wonder we&apos;re hevin&apos; so many
                        sueycides with th&apos; cost o&apos; livin&apos; up where it is.</p>
                    <p>A barber never begins t&apos; sharpen his razor er tighten his shears till somebuddy gits in
                        his chair thet wunts t&apos; be shaved in a hurry. Ole Ez Pash, who spent his early manhood
                        with th&apos; Mac-o-chee injuns et Pickreltown, Ohio, says thet nothin&apos; so
                        completely infuriates a injun chief ez t&apos; hit him in th&apos; eye with a fried egg.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-109" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Pinky Kerr says thet there is fellers thet kin tell you all about th&apos; baseball games et
                        Chicago thet dun&apos;t know who Garfield wuz. If I went int&apos; Roosyfel&apos;s
                        Cabinet I&apos;d hev to hev a contract.</p>
                    <p>Them ther souvenir cards er great things fer folks thet dun&apos;t know how t&apos; write
                        what they see. I got a letter from Rushville sayin&apos; thet ther wuz a Tom&apos;s
                        cabin troupe up ther last week an&apos; thet th&apos; dogs were good, but thet they hed
                        poor support.</p>
                    <p>Talkin&apos; &apos;bout spotted pups an&apos; red wagons hev you saw th&apos;
                        girls in th&apos; ticket offices along th&apos; interurban between Indynoplus
                        an&apos; Logansport? Miss Germ Williams sez thet th&apos; odor o&apos; Niles
                        Turner&apos;s ole pipe is ez th&apos; perfume o&apos; Araby compared t&apos; one
                        o&apos; them blamed camel hair cigaroots.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-110" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Miss Germ Williams hez returned from a two years&apos; trip &quot;abroad.&quot; She
                        says she wuz greatly taken by Windsor, Canada, an&apos; Covington, Kentucky. Ther wuz quite
                        a lively local option meetin&apos; et th&apos; school house Sunday night. Uncle Ez Pash
                        declared thet what th&apos; community needed worst o&apos; all wuz nine er ten good
                        saloons thet would&apos;n sell t&apos; no one what drinks.</p>
                    <p>When a feller hez t&apos; pay fer a spring suit thet he ordered in December he allus says
                        he&apos;ll never git another one. Miss Tawney Apple entertained a few o&apos; her young
                        friends last night an&apos; th&apos; evenin&apos; wuz happily spent playin&apos;
                        &quot;dimple.&quot; Thet&apos;s a new game where you discard everthing but
                        th&apos; queen.</p>
                    <p>Alex Tansey lost his Phi-Delta-Phila-ma-delphia class pin some wheres between the schoolhouse
                        an&apos; th&apos; pustoffis Monday. Tipton Budd&apos;s boy, Francis, is one
                        o&apos; them peaked-headed chaps thet&apos;s allus takin&apos; ther hat off.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-111" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Th&apos; depression o&apos; business an&apos; felt boots make it so quiet up et Mill
                        Grove, Indianny, thet you can hear th&apos; rustle o&apos; a pair o&apos; overalls
                        two miles away. Quite a number o&apos; the boys went over t&apos; Columbus last night
                        t&apos; see &quot;A Life&apos;s Mistake.&quot; Pinky Kerr said thet th&apos;
                        plot wuz th&apos; thickest he ever seen.</p>
                    <p>Niles Turner is a blamed ole ignomus. Durin&apos; th&apos; Cuby war Jack Gregg used
                        t&apos; read th&apos; war news t&apos; him. One day Jack told him thet
                        Severy&apos;s fleet hed busted &apos;way from Santy Ague harbor an&apos; wuz
                        steamin&apos; up White river towards Indynoplus. Ole Niles jumped higher&apos;n a kite
                        an&apos; sez: &quot;B&apos;gosh, I&apos;ve got a married dorter livin&apos;
                        up there.&quot; A green persimmon broke up th&apos; band practice last night.</p>
                    <p>Some fellers belong t&apos; s&apos; many blamed secret orders thet they hev t&apos;
                        die before ther wives kin git a new dress. Farming looks nicefrom a car window.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-112" n="[]"/>
                    <p>After a feller gits though with a marriage license clerk an&apos; his applercation fer life
                        insurance he&apos;s told &apos;bout all he knowed an&apos; more too. &apos;Cause
                        ther haint no place like home is th&apos; reason so many girls work in th&apos; stores
                        an&apos; offices.</p>
                    <p>Pinky Kerr is th&apos; only feller I ever seen thet played th&apos; accordion without
                        th&apos; tin-cup attachment. Th&apos; feller thet&apos;s goin&apos; t&apos;
                        lecture here t&apos;night on &quot;Germs o&apos; Verse&quot; asked Newt Plum
                        &apos;bout th&apos; acoustic properties o&apos; th&apos; hall an&apos; Newt
                        said: &quot;All we do is t&apos; furnish th&apos; lamps.&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-113" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Newt Plum&apos;s married dorter up et Indynoplus says she bought a spring chicken et
                        &quot;catch weights&quot; Monday. You never heerd much complainin&apos;
                        &apos;bout eyesight in th&apos; ole days when a feller paid a quarter fer a pair
                        o&apos; steel-rimmed spectacles an&apos; picked &apos;em out himself.</p>
                    <p>It takes an experienced grocer three er four minutes t&apos; weigh a pound o&apos;
                        somethin&apos;, but somehow a butcher seems t&apos; hit th&apos; right weight
                        th&apos; fust time. It must go purty hard fer a feller thet&apos;s been drawin&apos;
                        &quot;twenty-five per&quot; t&apos; throw his crutches away.</p>
                    <p>Pinky Kerr seys he dun&apos;t see how th&apos; girls in th&apos; big department
                        stores up et Indyn-plus kin work from mornin&apos; till night in them basements without
                        chewin&apos; er smokin&apos;. These fellers thet er allus askin&apos; fer a
                        &quot;flat&quot; rate must hev money.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-114" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Ther&apos;s one thing you&apos;ll never be able t&apos; git in a city with all its
                        blamed advantages, an&apos; thet is &quot;a good, ole country dinner.&quot; Jist
                        &apos;bout th&apos; time they begun t&apos; impale a jury fer Al Thomas th&apos;
                        jedge granted him a change o&apos; menu.</p>
                    <p>By ginger, its a funny thing how some fellers write &apos;bout things they dun&apos;t
                        know nuthin&apos; &apos;bout. Uncle Ez Pash says thet ther used to be a feller et
                        Evansville what wrote th&apos; best articles you ever read &apos;bout clean cities.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-115" n="[]"/>
                    <p>Some folks er so blamed up-t&apos;-date thet they allus take a late train. Ther&apos;s a
                        new clothin&apos; store up et IndynoplusSol, o&apos; Tarsus.</p>
                    <p>Tilford Moots boy, Elmer, threw a fit in th&apos; court-house yard yisterday an&apos;
                        when he come to he passed his hat &apos;mongst th&apos; crowd thet stood
                        watchin&apos; him. It&apos;s all right t&apos; hev a wife thet&apos;s a good
                        manager, but it goes purty hard t&apos; hev t&apos; wear th&apos; same overcoat
                        seven winters.</p>
                    <p>Th&apos; funny thing about a new trimmer comin&apos; t&apos; town is thet
                        th&apos; commotion is allus mongst th&apos; boys. when a feller thet hez hed
                        th&apos; advantages o&apos; travel can&apos;t tell you about anything but
                        th&apos; &quot;best huttels&quot; it hain&apos;t done him much good.</p>
                    <p>Tilford Moots says you kin allus tell when one o&apos; them campaign specials gits down near
                        Evansville, fer some feller with a broad-rimmed hat an&apos; a bottle o&apos; whisky
                        gits on th&apos; train. Most o&apos; th&apos; Indianny hut-tels hev two ratestwo
                        dollars a day er three dollars a week.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-116" n="[]"/>
                    <p>A cannydate fer office needs somethin&apos; else besides a long memory an&apos; a box
                        o&apos; 5-cent se-gars these days. Ther numberin&apos; th&apos; houses over et
                        Seymour so poor people kin find a home.</p>
                    <p>Farmers go t&apos; th&apos; &quot;hay&quot; purty early. You kin allus tell a
                        feller thet&apos;s satisfied with hisself by th&apos; way he passes th&apos; show
                        windows.</p>
                </div2>
                <pb id="VAA2347-117" n="[]"/>
                <div2 type="chapter">
                    <head type="main">ABE MARTIN</head>
                    <head type="subtitle">HIS NEIGHBORS</head>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-118" n="[]"/>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <figure entity="VAA2347-14"/> Tawney Apple.</head>
                        <p>Miss Tawney Apple, still in school, makes her home with the family of elgin Tyler, her father
                            and mother having been killed by a corn shredder two years ago. She is remarkably bright for
                            her years, nineteen summers, and can bound Indiana and write verse of a high order, as
                            witness:</p>
                        <lg>
                            <l n="1">Hear the school bell, hear it ring.</l>
                            <l n="2">I trip along and laugh and sing.</l>
                            <l n="3">I love to go to school each day</l>
                            <l n="4">And when there&apos;s work I never play.</l>
                        </lg>
                    </div3>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-119" n="[]"/>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <figure entity="VAA2347-15"/> Miss Fawn Lippincut</head>
                        <p>Miss Fawn Lippincut is the niece of Tilden Moon, and is in her seventeenth year. She
                            commenced to attract attention in Brown county as early as 1895 by her remarkable talent as
                            a recitationist. One member of the Moon family recently remarked that she had probably
                            recited &quot;Twinkle, Twinkle, Little Star&quot; 500 timesalways with much success.
                            She comes of a dramatic family. Her mother kept a theatrical boarding-house at Crestline,
                            O., and her father was a trap drummer and traveled many years with well-to-do comedy
                            troupes. It is the desire of the Moons to some day develop her and put her on the road to
                            fame.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-120" n="[]"/>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <figure entity="VAA2347-16"/> Newt Plum.</head>
                        <p>Constable Newt Plum is a sample of what a cool, calculating, upright gentleman of steady
                            habits, a strong right arm and a disposition &quot;to do&quot; can accomplish in a
                            small community offering few advantages. His sterling integrity and respect for the views of
                            others brought to him the highest office within the gift of his neighborsthe important and
                            highly essential office of constable. mr. Plum has filled the office for thirty-two years
                            with wonderful credit to himself, his married daughter and his legion of friends. In
                            settling the disputes over great national problems that arise at the blacksmith shop and the
                            postoffice, Mr. Plum is seen at his highthis clear, thunderous voice never failing to bring
                            calm and good feeling.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-121" n="[]"/>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <figure entity="VAA2347-17"/> Alex Tansey.</head>
                        <p>Professor Alexander Tansey was entering his second year in the Angola (Ind.) high school when
                            he quit and accepted a position as a teacher in Brown county. During vacation time Mr.
                            Tansey hangs paper and canvasses for a &quot;work&quot; called &quot;Gems of
                            Verse and Prose.&quot; He reads a little medicine, too, at night.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-122" n="[]"/>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <figure entity="VAA2347-18"/> Young Lafe Bud.</head>
                        <p>Young Lafe Bud is the only son of Tipton Bud and cares little or nothing for agriculture. He
                            yearns for the commercial life and solicits for a Chicago firm that makes life-sized,
                            realistic crayon portraits from written description or old battered up wartime photos. He
                            makes the small towns and registers from Philadelphia, and is a favorite with interurban
                            conductors and dining-room girls. He appears at his best in a crowded hotel office after the
                            business worries of the day, when his merry quips cause roars of laughter among the
                        guests.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-123" n="[]"/>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <figure entity="VAA2347-19"/> Tilford Moots.</head>
                        <p>Tilford Moots is a native of Champaign county, Ohio, and comes from a famous pioneer family
                            that was identified in a large degree with the early history of the Democratic party and
                            other hardships. He can remember when Urbana, O., was a field of yellow grain. Mr. Moots has
                            resided in Brown county for thirty-three years and is prominent in the hoop pole industry.
                            He is widely read and greatly interested in the conduct of the Panama canal project, the
                            election of united States Senators by direct vote of the people, and has written a number of
                            stinging articles on the silver crime of &apos;73.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-124" n="[]"/>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <figure entity="VAA2347-20"/> Ez Pash.</head>
                        <p>Uncle Ezra Braddock Pash is a direct descendant of a family of Norse pirates, and was born at
                            Cat Creek, Pa., many years ago. He has a marvelous memory and little or no regard for the
                            truth. He remembers distinctly seeing General Marquis de lafayette change cars at Union
                            City, Ind., for Greenville, O. Mr. Pash has lived in Brown county forty years and has two
                            sons, one at Michigan City and one at Jeffersonville.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-125" n="[]"/>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <figure entity="VAA2347-21"/> &quot;Pinky&quot; Kerr.</head>
                        <p>&quot;Pinky&quot; Kerr is a slip-horn player of rare ability and when he is not
                            traveling with some troupe he makes his home with his sister, Mrs. Bunker Hooper. He relates
                            many interesting stories of his travels, of famous managers who have skinned him, of narrow
                            hotel escapes, long walks and of once being poisoned on canned corn at Hurley, Wis., while
                            traveling with old Dupre and Benedict.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-126" n="[]"/>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <figure entity="VAA2347-22"/> Clem Harner.</head>
                        <p>One very rarely finds a musician possessing the rare ability, both cultivated and native, of
                            Prof. Clem Harner, stowed away in an isolated hamlet. Mr. Harner has made his home in Brown
                            county for fifteen years, and practically nothing is known of his previous life. Since his
                            sweet, silver notes on the cornet first charmed the community, the gossips stopped their
                            speculating and immediately commenced to pay homage to the genius in their midst. Professor
                            Harner has organized a silver cornet band that plays on the slightest provocation, and his
                            concerts always create widespread interest. He has played for two political meetings where
                            Bryan has spoken, and talks most interestingly of once shaking hands with the peerless
                            Nebraskan.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-127" n="[]"/>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <figure entity="VAA2347-23"/> Tipton Bud.</head>
                        <p>Tipton Lucien Bud was born at Seelyville, Ind., in 1850, and settled in Brown county in
                            &apos;72. He is a gentleman of strong convictions and has been a prominent mule breeder
                            for some years, not caring to mix in politics. His wife had money.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-128" n="[]"/>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <figure entity="VAA2347-24"/> Niles Turner.</head>
                        <p>Niles Thurston Turner was born at Roundhead, Ohio, in 1818, and came West with the Blue
                            Jacket Indians to Indianapolis, in 1840. Later he took up his residence with his daughter,
                            Mrs. Clement Mopps, in Brown county. After a perfectly rounded out career Mr. Turner
                            delights to while away the evening of his life telling the most outrageous and preposterous
                            Indian stories, and scaring little children. He also makes ax handles.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <pb id="VAA2347-129" n="[]"/>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <figure entity="VAA2347-25"/> Germ Williams.</head>
                        <p>Miss Germ Williams is just out of her teens and already has quite a reputation as a trimmer
                            and organist. Her needle has won her many a prize at fairs of different kinds. She expects
                            to accept a position with one of the largest millinery establishments in Indianapolis at no
                            distant date.</p>
                    </div3>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>