<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//IA Books//DTD TEI for Indiana Authors Books//EN" "teixlite.dtd" [
<!NOTATION JPG SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY VAA2432-1 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2432-1.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2432-2 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2432-2.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2432-3 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2432-3.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2432-4 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2432-4.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2432-5 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2432-5.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2432-6 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2432-6.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2432-7 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2432-7.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2432-8 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2432-8.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2432-9 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2432-9.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2432-10 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2432-10.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2432-11 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2432-11.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2432-12 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2432-12.jpg" NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY VAA2432-13 SYSTEM "figures/VAA2432-13.jpg" NDATA JPG>
]>
<TEI.2 id="VAA2432">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Social Secretary: electronic edition</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
                <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            	<idno>VAA2432</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright 2008 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
                    <p>Indiana University provides the information contained on this web site for
                        non-commercial, personal, or research use only. All other use, including but
                        not limited to commercial or scholarly reproductions, redistribution,
                        publication or transmission, whether by electronic means or otherwise,
                        without prior written permission of the copyright holder is strictly
                        prohibited.</p>
                </availability>
                <date>2007</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull><titleStmt>
                    <title type="main">The Social Secretary</title>
                    <author id="ina-v1-entry-0678">Phillips, David Graham, 1867-1911</author></titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>The Bobbs-Merrill Company</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Indianapolis</pubPlace>
                        <date>1905</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Digital Library Program was awarded a Library Services and Technology Act (LSTA)
                    grant in 2005 to make available online the three-volume, reference work, <title>Indiana Authors 
                        and Their Books</title> along with selected monographs by Indiana authors.
                </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3">
                <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoded and edited using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines following the TEI Lite standard. Digital page images are
                    linked to the text file.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <tagUsage gi="div1">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language>English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-06-25</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Annette D. Smith</name>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Corrected teiHeader, pb tags, front matter.</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <pb id="VAA2432-001" n="[]"/>
            <figure entity="VAA2432-1"/>
            <pb id="VAA2432-002" n="[]"/>
            <div1>
                <head>The Social Secretary</head>
                <p/>
            </div1>
            <pb id="VAA2432-003" n="[]"/>
            <div1 type="frontispiece">
                <figure entity="VAA2432-2"/>
                <p/>
            </div1>
            <pb id="VAA2432-004" n="[]"/>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">THE SOCIAL<lb/> SECRETARY</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <byline>by<lb/>
                    <docAuthor>DAVID GRAHAM PHILLIPS</docAuthor><lb/> Author of The Plum Tree<lb/>
                    The Cost etc. etc.</byline>
                <byline>WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY<lb/> CLARENCE F. UNDERWOOD<lb/> Decorations by<lb/>
                    Ralph Fletcher Seymour</byline>
                <docImprint>
                    <pubPlace>Indianapolis</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>The Bobbbs-Merrill Company<lb/> Publishers</publisher>
                </docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <pb id="VAA2432-005" n="[]"/>
            <div1 type="verso">
                <p rend="center">C<hi rend="sc">OPYRIGHT</hi> 1905<lb/> T<hi rend="sc">HE</hi> B<hi
                        rend="sc">OBBS</hi>-M<hi rend="sc">ERRILL</hi> C<hi rend="sc">OMPANY</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O<hi rend="sc">CTOBER</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRESS OF<lb/> BRAUNWORTH &amp; CO.<lb/> BOOKBINDERS AND PRINTERS<lb/>
                    BROOKLYN, N. Y.</p>
            </div1>
            <pb id="VAA2432-006" n="[]"/>
            <div1 type="figures">
                <head>ILLUSTRATIONS</head>
                <list type="simple">
                    <item>&quot;I beg your pardon, Miss Talltowers, for what I said&quot;<hi
                            rend="i">Frontispiece</hi>
                        <ptr targType="pb" target="VAA2432-003"/></item>
                    <item>Jim stood behind me, staring over my shoulder <hi rend="right">2</hi>
                        <ptr targType="pb" target="VAA2432-010"/></item>
                    <item>In her embarrassment she had forgotten my name <hi rend="right">18</hi>
                        <ptr targType="pb" target="VAA2432-027"/></item>
                    <item>I was glad when she hurried away <hi rend="right">36</hi>
                        <ptr targType="pb" target="VAA2432-046"/></item>
                    <item>I consult with Cleopatra every day <hi rend="right">68</hi>
                        <ptr targType="pb" target="VAA2432-079"/></item>
                    <item>Nadeshda <hi rend="right">78</hi>
                        <ptr targType="pb" target="VAA2432-090"/></item>
                    <item>As I had expected, she didn&apos;t stand very long <hi rend="right"
                            >82</hi>
                        <ptr targType="pb" target="VAA2432-095"/></item>
                    <item>I was breakfasting alone in my sitting-room <hi rend="right">108</hi>
                        <ptr targType="pb" target="VAA2432-122"/></item>
                    <item>&quot;Well, Gus, has that wild man told you?&quot; <hi
                            rend="right">112</hi>
                        <ptr targType="pb" target="VAA2432-127"/></item>
                    <item>&quot;Anyhow, I don&apos;t care to undertake the job&quot; <hi
                            rend="right">152</hi>
                        <ptr targType="pb" target="VAA2432-168"/></item>
                    <item>He had both my hands now, and was looking at me at arm&apos;s length
                            <hi rend="right">196</hi>
                        <ptr targType="pb" target="VAA2432-213"/></item>
                </list>
            </div1>
            <pb id="VAA2432-007" n="[]"/>
            <div1>
                <head>The Social Secretary</head>
                <p/>
            </div1>
        </front>
        <body>
            <pb id="VAA2432-008" n="1"/>
            <div1 type="book">
                <head>The Social Secretary</head>
                <div2 type="chapter">
                    <head>I</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="b">N</hi>OVEMBER 29. At half-past one to-dayhalf-past one exactlyI
                        began my &quot;career.&quot; Mrs. Carteret said she would call for
                        me at five minutes to one. But it was ten minutes after when she appeared,
                        away down at the corner of I Street. Jim was walking up and down the
                        drawing-room; I was at the window, watching that corner of I Street.
                        &quot;There she blows!&quot; I cried, my voice brave, but my heart
                        like a big lump of something soggy and sad.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-009" n="2"/>
                    <p>Jim hurried up and stood behind me, staring glumly over my shoulder. He has
                        proposed to me in so many words more than twenty times in the last three
                        years, and has looked it every time we&apos;ve metwe meet almost every
                        day. I could feel that he was getting ready to propose again, but I
                        hadn&apos;t the slightest fear that he&apos;d touch me.
                        He&apos;s in the army, and his &quot;pull&quot; has kept him
                        snug and safe at Washington and has promoted him steadily until now
                        he&apos;s a Colonel at thirty-five. But he was brought up in a formal,
                        old-fashioned way, and he&apos;d think it a deadly insult to a woman he
                        respected enough to ask her to be his wife if he should touch her without
                        her permission. I admire Jim&apos;s self-restraint, butI
                        couldn&apos;t bear being married to a man who worshiped me, even if I
                        only liked him. If I <pb id="VAA2432-010" n="[]"/>
                        <figure entity="VAA2432-3"/>
                        <pb id="VAA2432-011" n="3"/> loved him, I&apos;d be utterly miserable.
                        I&apos;ve been trying hard to love Jim for the past four months, or ever
                        since I&apos;ve really realized how desperate my affairs are. But I
                        can&apos;t. And the most exasperating part of my obstinacy is that I
                        can&apos;t find a good reason or excuse for it.</p>
                    <p>As I was sayingor, rather, writingJim stood behind me and said in a husky
                        sort of voice: &quot;You ain&apos;t goin&apos; to do it, are
                        you, Gus?&quot;</p>
                    <p>I didn&apos;t answer. If I had said anything, it would have been a
                        feeble, miserable &quot;No&quot;which would have meant that I was
                        accepting the alternativehim. All my courage had gone and I felt
                        contemptibly feminine and dependent.</p>
                    <p>I looked at himI did like the expression of his eyes and the strength and
                        manliness of him from head to foot. <pb id="VAA2432-012" n="4"/> What a fine
                        sort of man a &quot;pull&quot; and a private income have spoiled in
                        Jim Lafollette! He went on: &quot;Surely, I&apos;m not more
                        repellent to you thanthan what that auto is coming to take you away
                        to.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Shame on you, Jim Lafollette?&quot; I said angrilymost of the
                        anger so that he wouldn&apos;t understand and take advantage of the
                        tears in my eyes and voice. &quot;But how like you! How <hi rend="i"
                            >brave!&quot;</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>He reddened at thatpartly because he felt guilty toward me, partly because he
                        is ashamed of the laziness that has made him shirk for thirteen years.
                        &quot;I don&apos;t care a hang whether it&apos;s brave or not,
                        or <hi rend="i">what</hi> it is,&quot; he said sullenly. &quot;I
                        want <hi rend="i">you</hi>. And it seems to me I&apos;ve got to do
                        somethinguse force, if necessaryto keep you from<hi rend="i">from that.</hi>
                        You ain&apos;t fit for it, Gusnot in any way.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-013" n="5"/>
                    <p>Why, it&apos;s worse than being a servant. And youbrought up as
                        you&apos;ve been&quot;</p>
                    <p>I laugheda pretty successful effort. &quot;I&apos;ve been educating
                        for it all my life, without knowing it. And it&apos;s honest and
                        independent. If you had the right sort of ideas of self-respect,
                        you&apos;d be ashamed of me if you thought I&apos;d be low enough to
                        marry a man I couldn&apos;t give my heart tofor a living.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Don&apos;t talk rubbish,&quot; he retorted.
                        &quot;Thousands of women do it. Besides, if I don&apos;t mind, why
                        should you? God knows you&apos;ve made it plain enough that you
                        don&apos;t love me. Gus, why can&apos;t you marry me and let me save
                        you from this just as a brother might save a sister?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Because I may love somebody some day, Jim,&quot; said I. I
                        wanted to hurt himfor his own sake, and also because I didn&apos;t want
                        him to tempt me.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-014" n="6"/>
                    <p>The auto was at the curb. He didn&apos;t move until I was almost at the
                        drawing-room door. Then he rushed at me and his look frightened me a little.
                        He caught me by the arm. &quot;It&apos;s the last chance,
                        Augusta!&quot; he exclaimed. &quot;Won&apos;t you?&quot;</p>
                    <p>I drew away and hurried out. &quot;Then you don&apos;t intend to have
                        anything to do with me after I&apos;ve crossed the line and become a
                        toiler?&quot; I called back over my shoulder. I couldn&apos;t resist
                        the temptation to be thoroughly feminine and leave the matter open by
                        putting him in the wrong with my &quot;woman&apos;s last
                        word.&quot; I was so low in my mind that I reasoned that my adventure
                        might be as appalling as I feared, in which case it would be well to have an
                        alternative. I wonder if the awful thoughts we sometimes have are our real
                        selves <pb id="VAA2432-015" n="7"/> or if they just give us the chance to
                        measure the gap between what we might be as shown by them and what we are as
                        shown by our acts. I hope the latter, for surely I can&apos;t be as poor
                        a creature as I so often have impulses to make myself.</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Carteret was waiting for the servant to open the door. I hurried her
                        back toward the auto, being a little afraid that Jim would be desperate
                        enough to come out and beg her to help himand I knew she would do it if she
                        were asked. In the first place, Jessie always does what she&apos;s asked
                        to doif it helps her to spend time and breath. In the second place,
                        she&apos;d never let up on me if she thought I had so good a chance to
                        marry. For she knows that Washington is the hardest place in the world for a
                        woman to find a husband <pb id="VAA2432-016" n="8"/> unless she&apos;s
                        got something that appeals to the ambition of men. Besides, she thinks, as
                        do many of my friends, that I am indifferent to men and discourage them. As
                        if any woman was indifferent to men! The only point is that women&apos;s
                        ideas of what constitutes a man differ, and my six years in this cosmopolis
                        have made me somewhat discriminating.</p>
                    <p>But to return to Jessie, she was full of apologies for being late.
                        &quot;I&apos;ve thought of nothing but you, dear, for two days and
                        nights. And I thought that for once in my life I&apos;d be on time. Yet
                        here I am, fifteen minutes late, unless that clock&apos;s
                        wrong.&quot; She was looking at the beautiful little clock set in the
                        dashboard of the auto.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Only fifteen minutes!&quot; I said. &quot;And you never
                        before were known to be less <pb id="VAA2432-017" n="9"/> than half an hour
                        late. You even kept the President waiting twenty minutes.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Isn&apos;t it stupid, this fussing about being on
                        time?&quot; she replied. &quot;I don&apos;t believe any but dull
                        people and those who want to get something from one are ever on time. For
                        those who really live, life is so full that punctuality is impossible. But I
                        should have been on time, if I hadn&apos;t been down seeing the
                        Secretary of War about Willie Catesbypoor Willie! He has been <hi rend="i"
                            >so</hi> handicapped by nature!&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Did you get it for him?&quot; I asked.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I think sothird secretary at St. Petersburg. The secretary said:
                        &apos;But Willie is almost an imbecile, Mrs. Carteret. If we
                        don&apos;t send him abroad, his family&apos;ll have to put him
                        away.&apos; And I said: &apos;That&apos;s true, Mr. Secretary.
                        But if we don&apos;t send that sort of people to <pb id="VAA2432-018"
                            n="10"/> foreign courts, how are we to repay the insults they send us in
                        the form of imbecile attachs?&apos; And then I handed him six letters
                        from senatorsevery one of them a man whose vote he needs for his fight on
                        that nomination. They were <hi rend="i">real</hi> letters. So presently he
                        said, &apos;Very well, Mrs. Carteret, I&apos;ll do what I can to
                        resent the Czar&apos;s last insult by exporting Willie to
                        him.&quot;</p>
                    <p>I waited a moment, then burst out with what I was full of. &quot;You
                        think she&apos;ll take me?&quot; I said.</p>
                    <p>Jessie reproached me with tragedy in her always intensely serious gray eyes.
                        &quot;Take <hi rend="i">you?&quot;</hi> she exclaimed.
                        &quot;Take a Talltowers when there&apos;s a chance to get one? Why,
                        as soon as I explained who you were, she fairly quivered with
                        eagerness.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;You had to <hi rend="i">explain</hi> who a Talltowers <pb
                            id="VAA2432-019" n="11"/> is?&quot; I said with mock amazement.
                        It&apos;s delightful to poke fun at Jessie; she always appreciates a
                        jest by taking it more seriously than an ordinary statement of fact.</p>
                    <p>&quot;But, dear, you mustn&apos;t be offended. You know Mrs. Burke is
                        very common and ignorant. She doesn&apos;t know the first thing about
                        the world. She said to me the other day that she had often heard there were
                        such things as class distinctions, but had never believed it until she came
                        to Washingtonshe had thought it was like the fairy stories. She never was
                        farther east than Chicago until this fall. She went there to the Fair. You
                        must get her to tell you how she and three other women who belong to the
                        same Chautauqua Circle went on together and slept in the same room and
                        walked from dawn <pb id="VAA2432-020" n="12"/> till dark every day,
                        catalogue in hand, for eleven days. It&apos;s too pathetic. She said,
                        &apos;My! but my feet were sore. I thought I was a cripple for
                        life.&apos;&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;That sounds nice and friendly,&quot; said I, suspicious that
                        Jessie&apos;s quaint sense of humor had not permitted her to appreciate
                        Mrs. Burke. &quot;I&apos;m so dreadfully afraid I&apos;ll fall
                        into the clutches of people that&apos;ll try toto humiliate
                        me.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Tears sprang to Jessie&apos;s eyes. &quot;Please don&apos;t,
                        Gus!&quot; she pleaded. &quot;They&apos;ll be only to
                        deferential. And you must keep them so. I suspect that Mrs. Burke chums with
                        her servants.&quot;</p>
                    <p>We were stopping before the housethe big, splendid Ralston Castle, as they
                        call it; one of the very finest of the houses that have been building since
                        rich men began to buy into the Senate and Cabinet and aspire for diplomatic
                        places, <pb id="VAA2432-021" n="13"/> and so have attracted other rich
                        families to Washington. What a changed Washington it is, and what a fight
                        the old simplicity is making against the new ostentation! The sight of the
                        Ralston Castle in my present circumstances depressed me horribly. I went to
                        my second ball there, and it was given for me by Mrs. Ralston. And only a
                        little more than a year ago I danced in the quadrille of honor with the
                        French Ambassadorand the next week the Ralstons went smash and hurried
                        abroad to hide, all except the old man who is hanging round Wall Street,
                        they say, trying to get on his feet with the aid of his friends. Friends!
                        How that word must burn into him every time he thinks of it. When he got
                        into a tight place his &quot;friends&quot; took advantage of their
                        knowledge of his affairs to grab his best securities, they <pb
                            id="VAA2432-022" n="14"/> say. No doubt he was disagreeable in a way,
                        but still those who turned on him the most savagely had been intimate with
                        him and had accepted his hospitality.</p>
                    <p>&quot;You&apos;ll be mistress here,&quot; Jessie was saying. She
                        had put on her prophetic look and poseshe really believes she has second
                        sight at certain times. &quot;And you&apos;ll marry the son, if you
                        manage it right. I counted him in when I was going over the advantages and
                        disadvantages of the place before proposing it to you. He looks like a mild,
                        nice young manthough I must say I don&apos;t fancy cowlicks right in the
                        part of the hair. I saw only his picture.&quot;</p>
                    <p>A tall footman with an insolent face opened the door and ushered us into the
                        small drawing-room to the left: &quot;Mrs. Carteret! Miss
                        Talltowers!&quot; he shoutedfar louder than is customary or courteous.
                            <pb id="VAA2432-023" n="15"/> I saw the impudent grin in his eyesno
                        proper man-servant ever permits any one to see his eyes. And he almost
                        dropped the curtain in our faces, in such haste was he to get back to his
                        lunging-place below stairs.</p>
                    <p>His roar had lifted to her feet an elderly woman with her hair so badly dyed
                        that it made her features look haggard and harsh and even dissipated. She
                        made a nervous bow. She was of the figure called stout by the charitable and
                        sumptuous by the crude. She was richly-dressed, over-dressed,
                        dressed-upshiny figured satin with a great deal of beads and lace that added
                        to her width and subtracted from her height. She stood miserable, jammed and
                        crammed into a tight corset. Her handsvery nice hands, I noticedwere folded
                        upon her stomach. As soon as I got used to that <pb id="VAA2432-024" n="16"
                        /> revolting hair-dye, I saw that she had in fact a large-featured, sweet
                        face with fine brown eyes. Even with the dye she was the kind of looking
                        woman that it sounds perfectly natural to hear her husband call
                        &quot;mother.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Jessie went up to her as she stood wretched in her pitiful attempt at youth
                        and her grandeur of clothes and surroundings. Mrs. Burke looked down kindly,
                        with a sudden quizzical smile that reminded me of my suspicions as to the
                        Chicago Fair story. Jessie was looking up like a plump, pretty, tame robin,
                        head on one side. <hi rend="i">&quot;Dear</hi> Mrs. Burke,&quot; she
                        said. &quot;This is Miss Talltowers, and I&apos;m sure
                        you&apos;ll love each other.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Burke looked at meI thought, with a determined attempt to be suspicious
                        and cautious. I&apos;m afraid Jessie&apos;s <pb id="VAA2432-025"
                            n="17"/> reputation for tireless effort to do something for everybody
                        has finally &quot;queered&quot; her recommendations. However,
                        whatever warning Mrs. Burke had received went for nothing. She was no match
                        for JessieJessie from whom his Majesty at the White House hides when he
                        knows she&apos;s coming for an impossible favorshe was no match for
                        Jessie and she knew it. She wiped the sweat from her face and stammered:
                        &quot;I hope we&apos;ll suit each other, Miss&quot; In her
                        embarrassment she had forgotten my name.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Talltowers,&quot; whispered Jessie with a side-splitting look
                        of tragic apology to me. Just then the clock in the corner struck out the
                        half-hour from its cathedral bellthe sound echoed and rechoed through me,
                        for it marked the beginning of my &quot;career.&quot; Jessie went on
                        more <pb id="VAA2432-026" n="18"/> loudly: &quot;And now that our <hi
                            rend="i">business</hi> is settled, can&apos;t we have some lunch,
                        Mrs. Burke? I&apos;m starved.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Burke brightened. &quot;The Senator won&apos;t be here
                        to-day,&quot; she drawled, in a tone which always suggests to me that,
                        after all, life is a smooth, leisurely mater with plenty of time for
                        everything except work. &quot;As he was leaving for the Capitol this
                        morning, he says to me, says he: &apos;You women had better fight it out
                        alone.&apos;&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;The <hi rend="i">dear</hi> Senator!&quot; said Jessie.
                        &quot;He&apos;s <hi rend="i">so</hi> clever?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Yes, he <hi rend="i">is</hi> mighty clever with those he
                        likes,&quot; replied Mrs. BurkeJessie looking at me to make sure I would
                        note Mrs. Burke&apos;s &quot;provincial&quot; way of using the
                        word clever.</p>
                    <p>Jessie saved the luncheonor, at least, thought she was saving it. Mrs. Burke
                            <pb id="VAA2432-027" n="[]"/>
                        <figure entity="VAA2432-4"/>
                        <pb id="VAA2432-028" n="19"/> and I had only to listen and eat. I caught her
                        looking at me several times, and then I saw shrewdness in her
                        eyesgood-natured, but none the less penetrating for that. And I knew I
                        should like her, and should get on with her. At last our eyes met and we
                        both smiled. After that she somehow seemed less crowded and foreign in her
                        tight, fine clothes. I saw she was impatient for Jessie to go the moment
                        luncheon was over, but it was nearly three o&apos;clock before we were
                        left alone together. There fell an embarrassed silencefor both of us were
                        painfully conscious that nothing had really been settled.</p>
                    <p>&quot;When do you wish me to comeif you do wish it at all?&quot; I
                        asked, by way of making a beginning.</p>
                    <p>&quot;When do you think you could come?&quot; she inquired
                        nervously.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-029" n="20"/>
                    <p>&quot;Then you do wish to give me a trial? I hope you won&apos;t feel
                        that Mrs. Carteret&apos;s precipitate way binds you.&quot;</p>
                    <p>She gave me a shrewd, good-natured look. &quot;I want you to
                        come,&quot; she said. &quot;I wanted it from what I&apos;d heard
                        of youI and Mr. Burke. I want it more than ever, now that I&apos;ve seen
                        you. When can you come?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;To-morrowto-morrow morning?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Come as early as you like. The salary isis
                        satisfactory?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Mrs. Carteret saidbut I&apos;m sureyou can judge
                        betterwhatever&quot; I stuttered, red as fire.</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Burke laughed. &quot;I can see you ain&apos;t a great hand at
                        business. The salary is two thousand a year, with a three months&apos;
                        vacation in the time we&apos;re not at Washington. Always have a plain
                        understanding <pb id="VAA2432-030" n="21"/> in money mattersit saves a lot
                        of mean feelings and quarrels.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Very wellwhatever you think. I don&apos;t believe I&apos;m
                        worth much of anything until I&apos;ve had a chance to show what I can
                        do.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Well, TomMr. Burkesaid two thousand would be about right at the
                        set-off,&quot; she drawled in her calming tone. &quot;So
                        we&apos;ll consider that settled.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Yes,&quot; I gasped, with a big sigh of relief. &quot;I
                        suppose you wish me to take charge of your social mattersrelieve you of the
                        burdensome part of entertaining?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;I just wish you could,&quot; she said, with a great deal of
                        humor in her slow voice. &quot;But I&apos;ve got to keep
                        thatit&apos;s the trying to make people have a good time and not look
                        and act as if they were wondering why they&apos;d come.&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-031" n="22"/>
                    <p>&quot;That&apos;ll soon wear off,&quot; said I. &quot;Most of
                        the stiffness is strangeness on both sides, don&apos;t you
                        think?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;I don&apos;t know. As nearly as I can make out, they never had
                        a real, natural good time in their lives. They wear the Sunday,
                        go-to-meeting clothes and manners the whole seven days. I&apos;ll never
                        get used to it. I can&apos;t talk that kind of talk. And if I was just
                        plain and natural, they&apos;d think I was stark crazy.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Did you ever try?&quot;</p>
                    <p>She lifted her hands in mock-horror. &quot;Mercy, no! TomMr. Burkewarned
                        me.&quot;</p>
                    <p>I laughed. &quot;Men don&apos;t know much about that sort of
                        thing,&quot; said I. &quot;A woman might as well let a man tell her
                        how to dress as how to act.&quot;</p>
                    <p>She colored. &quot;He does,&quot; she said, her eyes twinkling.
                        &quot;He was here two wintersthis <pb id="VAA2432-032" n="23"/> is my
                        first. I&apos;ve a kind of feeling that he really don&apos;t know,
                        but he&apos;s positive andI&apos;ve had nobody else to talk about it
                        with. I&apos;m a stranger herenot a friend except people whowell, I can
                        guess pretty close to what they say behind my back.&quot; She laugheda
                        great shaking of as much of her as was not held rigid by that tight corset.
                        &quot;Not that I careI like a joke myself, and I&apos;m a good deal
                        of a joke among these grand folks. Only, I do want to help Tom, and not be a
                        drag.&quot; She gave me a sudden, sharp look. &quot;I don&apos;t
                        know why I trust you, I&apos;m sure.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Because I&apos;m your confidential adviser,&quot; said I,
                        &quot;and it&apos;s always well to keep nothing from a confidential
                        adviser.&quot; The longer I looked and listened, the larger
                        possibilities I saw in her. My enthusiasm was rising.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-033" n="24"/>
                    <p>She rose and came to me and kissed me. There were tears in her eyes.
                        &quot;I&apos;ve been <hi rend="i">so</hi> lonesome,&quot; she
                        said. &quot;Even Tom don&apos;t seem natural any more, away off here
                        in the East. Sometimes I get so homesick that I just can&apos;t eat or
                        anything.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;We&apos;re going to have a lot of fun,&quot; said I
                        encouraginglyas if she were twenty-four and I fifty, instead of it being the
                        other way. &quot;You&apos;ll soon learn the ropes.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;I&apos;m so glad you use slang,&quot; she drawled, back in
                        her chair and comfortably settled. &quot;My, but Tom&apos;ll be
                        scandalized. He&apos;s made inquiries about you and has made up his mind
                        that whatever you say is right. And I almost believed he knew the trials. I
                        might &apos;a&apos; known! He&apos;s a man, you see, and always
                        was stiff with the ladies. You ought to &apos;a&apos; <pb
                            id="VAA2432-034" n="25"/> seen the letter he wrote proposing to me. You
                        see, I&apos;m kind of fat and always was. Mother used to tease me
                        because I hadn&apos;t any beaux except Tom, who wouldn&apos;t come
                        to the point. She said: &apos;Lizzie, you&apos;ll never have a man
                        make real love to you.&apos; And she was right. When Tom proposed he
                        wrote very formal-likenot a sentimental world. And when we were married and
                        got better acquainted, I teased him about it, and tried to get him to make
                        love, real book kind of love. But not a word! But he&apos;s fond of mewe
                        always have got on fine, and his being no good at love-talk is just one of
                        our jokes.&quot;</p>
                    <p>It was fine to hear her drawl it outI knew that she was sure to make a hit,
                        if only I could get her under way, could convince her that it&apos;s
                        nice to be natural if you&apos;re naturally nice.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-035" n="26"/>
                    <p>&quot;Tom&quot; came in from the Senate and I soon saw that, though
                        she was a &quot;really&quot; lady, of the only kind that is realthe
                        kind that&apos;s born right, he was a made gentleman, and not a very
                        successful job. He was small and thin and dressed with the same absured
                        stiff care with which he had made her dress. He had a pointed reddish beard
                        and reddish curls, and he used a kind of scent that smelt cheap though it
                        probably wasn&apos;t. He was very precise and distant with mehow
                        &quot;Lizzie&apos;s&quot; eyes did twinkle as she watched him. I
                        saw that she was &quot;on to&quot; Tom with the quickness with which
                        a shrewd woman always finds out, once she gets the clue.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Have you had Miss Talltowers shown her rooms, Mrs. Burke?&quot;
                        he soon inquired.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Why, no, pa,&quot; replied Mrs. Burke. <pb id="VAA2432-036"
                            n="27"/> &quot;I forgot it clear.&quot; As she said
                        &quot;pa&quot; he winced and her eyes danced with fun. She went on
                        to me: &quot;You don&apos;t mind our calling each other pa and ma
                        before you, do you, Miss Talltowers? We&apos;re so used to doing it
                        that, if you minded it and we had to stop, we&apos;d feel as if we had
                        company in the house all the time.&quot;</p>
                    <p>I didn&apos;t dare answer, I was so full of laughter. For
                        &quot;pa&quot; looked as if he were about to sink through the floor.
                        She led me up to my roomsa beautiful suite on the third floor. &quot;We
                        took the house furnished,&quot; she explained as we went, &quot;and
                        I feel as if I was living in a hotelexcept that the servants ain&apos;t
                        nearly so nice. I do hope you&apos;ll help me with them. Tom wanted me
                        to take a housekeeper, but those that applied were such grand ladies that
                        I&apos;d <pb id="VAA2432-037" n="28"/> rather &apos;a&apos; done
                        all my own work than &apos;a&apos; had any one of them about.
                        Perhaps we could get one now, and you could kind of keep her in
                        check.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;I think it&apos;d be better to have some one,&quot; I
                        replied. &quot;I&apos;ve had some experience in managing a
                        house.&quot; I couldn&apos;t help saying it unsteadilynot because I
                        miss our house; no, I&apos;m sure it wasn&apos;t that. But I
                        suddenly saw the old library and my father looking up from his book to smile
                        lovingly at me as I struggled with the household accounts. Anyhow, deep down
                        I&apos;m glad he did know so little about business and so much about
                        everything that&apos;s fine. I&apos;d rather have my memories of him
                        than any money he could have left me by being less of a father and friend
                        and more of a &quot;practical&quot; man.</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Burke looked at me sympatheticallyI <pb id="VAA2432-038" n="29"/> could
                        see that she longed to say something about my changed fortunes, but
                        refrained through fear of not saying the right thing. I must teach her never
                        to be afraid of thata born lady with a good heart could never be really
                        tactless. She went to the front door with me, opening it for me herself to
                        the contemptuous amusement of the tall footman. We shook hands and kissedI
                        usually can&apos;t bear to have a woman kiss me, but I&apos;d have
                        felt badly if &quot;ma&quot; Burke hadn&apos;t done it.</p>
                    <p>When I got back to Rachel&apos;s and burst into the drawing-room with a
                        radiant face, I heard a grunt like a groan. It was from Jim in the twilight
                        near Rachel at the tea-table. &quot;I&apos;m going out to service
                        to-morrow,&quot; said I to Rachel. &quot;So you&apos;re to be
                        rid of your visitor at last.&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-039" n="30"/>
                    <p>&quot;Oh, Gus!&quot; exclaimed Rachel between anger and tears. And
                        Jim looked black and sullen. But I was happyand am to-night. Happy for the
                        first time in two years. I&apos;m going to <hi rend="i">do</hi>
                        somethingand it is something that interests me. I&apos;m going to launch
                        a fine stately ship, a full-rigged four-master in this big-little sea of
                        Washington society. What a sensation I can make with it among the pretty
                        holiday boats!</p>
                </div2>
                <pb id="VAA2432-040" n="31"/>
                <div2 type="chapter">
                    <head>II</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="b">D</hi>ECEMBER 6. Last Monday morning young Mr. BurkeCyrus, the
                        son and heirarrived, just from Germany. The first glimpse I had of him was
                        as he entered the house between his father and his mother, who had gone to
                        the station to meet him. I got myself out of the way and didn&apos;t
                        come down until &quot;ma&quot; Burke sent for me. I liked the way
                        she was sitting there beamingbut then, I like almost everything she does;
                        she&apos;s such a large, natural person. She never stands, <pb
                            id="VAA2432-041" n="32"/> except on her way to sit just as soon as ever
                        she can. &quot;I never was a great hand for using my feet,&quot; she
                        said to me on my second day, &quot;and I don&apos;t know but about
                        as much seems to &apos;a&apos; come to find me as most people catch
                        up with by running their legs off.&quot; I liked the way her son was
                        hovering about her. And I liked the way &quot;pa&quot; Burke hovered
                        round them both, nervous and pulling at his whiskers and trying to think of
                        things to sayif he only wouldn&apos;t use brilliantine, or whatever it
                        is, on his whiskers!</p>
                    <p>&quot;Cyrus, this is my friend, Miss Talltowers,&quot; said Mrs.
                        Burke. I smiled and he clapped his heels together with a click and doubled
                        up as if he had a sudden pain in his middle, just like all the northern
                        Continental diplomats. When he straightened back to the normal I <pb
                            id="VAA2432-042" n="33"/> took a good look at himand he at me. I
                        don&apos;t knowor, rather, didn&apos;t then knowwhat <hi rend="i"
                            >he</hi> thought. But I thought himwell, &quot;common.&quot; He
                        has a great big body that&apos;s strong and well-proportioned; but his
                        features are so insignificanta small mouth, a small nose, small ears, eyes,
                        forehead, small head. And there, in the very worst placejust where the part
                        ought to bewas the cowlick I&apos;d noticed in his photograph. When he
                        began to speak I liked him still less. He&apos;s been at Berlin three
                        years, but still has his Harvard accent. I wonder why they teach men at
                        Harvard to use their lips in making words as a Miss Nancy sort of man uses
                        his fingers in doing fancy work?</p>
                    <p>Neither of us said anything memorable, and presently he went away to his
                        room, his mother going up with him. <pb id="VAA2432-043" n="34"/> His father
                        followed to the foot of the stairs, then drifted away to his study where he
                        could lie in wait for Cyrus on his way down. Pretty soon his mother came
                        into the &quot;office&quot; they&apos;ve given meit&apos;s
                        just off the drawing-room so that I can be summoned to it the instant any
                        one comes to see Mrs. Burke.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I&apos;ve let his pa have him for a while,&quot; she
                        explained, as she came in. I saw that she was full of her boy, so I turned
                        away from my books. She rambled on about him for an hour, not knowing what
                        she was saying, but just pouring out whatever came into her head.
                        &quot;His pa has always said I&apos;d spoil him,&quot; was one
                        of the things I remember, &quot;but I don&apos;t think love ever
                        spoiled anybody.&quot; Also she told me that his real name
                        wasn&apos;t Cyrus but Bucyrus, the town his father originally came
                        fromit&apos;s some-where <pb id="VAA2432-044" n="35"/> in Ohio, I think
                        she said. &quot;And,&quot; said she, &quot;whenever I want to
                        cut his comb I just give him his name. He tames right down.&quot; Also
                        that he has used all sorts of things on the cowlick without success.
                        &quot;There it is, still,&quot; said she, &quot;as cross-grained
                        as ever. I like it about the best of anything, except maybe his long legs.
                        I&apos;m a duck-leg myself, and his pawell, <hi rend="i">his</hi> legs
                        &apos;just about reach the ground,&apos; as Lincoln said, and after
                        that the less said the sooner forgot. But Cyrus has <hi rend="i">legs</hi>.
                        And his cowlick matches a cowlick in his dispositiona kind of gnarly knot
                        that you can&apos;t cut nor saw through nor get round no way.
                        It&apos;s been the saving of him, he&apos;s so good-natured and easy
                        otherwise.&quot; And she went on to tell how generous he is,
                        &quot;the only generous small-eared person I&apos;ve ever known, <pb
                            id="VAA2432-045" n="36"/> though I must say I have my doubts about ears
                        as a sign. There was Bill Slayback in our town, with ears like a
                        jack-rabbit, and whenever he had a poor man do a job of work about his place
                        he used to pay him with a ninety-day note and then shave the
                        note.&quot;</p>
                    <p>I was glad when she hurried away at the sound of Cyrus in the hall. For a
                        huge lot of work there&apos;ll be for me to do until I get things in
                        some sort of order. I&apos;ve opened a regular set of books to keep the
                        social accounts in. Of course, nobody who goes in for society, on the scale
                        we&apos;re going into it, could get along without social bookkeeping as
                        big as a bank&apos;s. I pity the official women in the high places who
                        can&apos;t afford secretaries; they must spend hours every night posting
                        and fussing with their account-books when they ought to be in bed
                        asleep.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-046" n="[]"/>
                    <figure entity="VAA2432-5"/>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-047" n="37"/>
                    <p>On my second day here &quot;pa&quot; Burke explained what his plans
                        were. &quot;We wish to make our house,&quot; said he, &quot;the
                        most distinguished social center in Washington, next to the White Houseand
                        very democratic. Above all, Miss Talltowers, democratic.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;He don&apos;t mean that he wants us to do our own work and send
                        out the wash,&quot; drawled &quot;ma&quot; Burke, who was
                        sitting by. &quot;But democratic, with fourteen servants in
                        livery.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;I understand,&quot; said I. &quot;You wish simplicity, and
                        people to feel at ease, Mr. Burke.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Exactly,&quot; he replied in a dubious tone. &quot;But I
                        wish to maintain thethe dignities, as it were.&quot;</p>
                    <p>I saw he was afraid I might get the idea he wanted something like those
                        rough-and-tumble public maulings of <pb id="VAA2432-048" n="38"/> the
                        President that they have at the White House. I hastened to reassure him;
                        then I explained my plan. I had drawn up a system somewhat like those the
                        President&apos;s wife and the Cabinet women and the other big
                        entertainers have. I&apos;m glad the Burkes haven&apos;t any
                        daughters. If they had I&apos;d certainly need an assistant. As it is,
                        I&apos;m afraid I&apos;ll worry myself hollow-eyed over my
                        books.</p>
                    <p>First, there&apos;s the Ledgera real, big, thick office ledger with
                        almost four hundred accounts in it, each one indexed. Of course, there
                        aren&apos;t any entries as yet. But there soon will bewhat we owe
                        various people in the way of entertainment, what they&apos;ve paid, and
                        what they owe us.</p>
                    <p>Second, there&apos;s my Day-Book. It contains each day&apos;s
                        engagements so that I can find out at a glance just what we&apos;ve <pb
                            id="VAA2432-049" n="39"/> got to do, and can make out each night before
                        going to bed or early each morning the schedule for Mrs. Burke for the day,
                        and for Senator Burke and the son, I suppose, for the late afternoon and the
                        evening.</p>
                    <p>Third, there&apos;s the Calling-Book. Already I&apos;ve got down more
                        than a thousand names. The obscurer the women arethe back-district
                        congressmen&apos;s wives and the likethe greater the necessity for
                        keeping the calling account straight. I wonder how many public men have had
                        their careers injured or ruined just because their wives didn&apos;t
                        keep the calling account straight. They say that <hi rend="i">men</hi>
                        forgive slights, and, when it&apos;s to their interest, forget them. But
                        I know the <hi rend="i">women</hi> never do. They keep the knife sharp and
                        wait for a chance to stick it in, for years and years. Of <pb
                            id="VAA2432-050" n="40"/> course, if the Burkes weren&apos;t going
                        into this business in a way that makes me think the Senator&apos;s
                        looking for the nomination for president I shouldn&apos;t be so
                        elaborate. We&apos;d pick out our set and stick to it and ignore the
                        other sets. As it is, I&apos;m going to do this thing thoroughly, as it
                        hasn&apos;t been done before.</p>
                    <p>Fourth, there&apos;s our Ball-and-Big-Dinner Book. That&apos;s got a
                        list of all the young men and another of all the young women. And
                        I&apos;m making notes against the names of those I don&apos;t know
                        very well or don&apos;t know at allnotes about their personal
                        appearance, eligibility, capacities for dancing, conversation, and so forth
                        and so on. If you&apos;re going to make an entertainment a success
                        you&apos;ve got to know something more or less definite about the people
                        that are coming, whom to ask to certain things <pb id="VAA2432-051" n="41"/>
                        and whom not to ask. Take a man like Phil Harkness, or a girl like Nell
                        Witton, for example. Either of them would ruin a dinner, but Phil shines at
                        a ball, where silence and good steady dancing are what the girls want. As
                        for Nell, she&apos;s possible at a ball only if you can be sure John
                        Rush or somebody like him is comingsomebody to sit with her and help her
                        blink at the dancers and be bored. Then there&apos;s the Sam Tremenger
                        sort of mana good talker, but something ruinous when he turns loose in a
                        ball-room and begins to batter the women&apos;s toilets to bits.
                        He&apos;s a dinner man, but you can&apos;t ask him when politics may
                        be discussedhe gets so violent that he not only talks all the time, but
                        makes a deafening clamor and uses swear wordsand we still have quiet people
                        who get gooseflesh for damn.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-052" n="42"/>
                    <p>Then there&apos;slet mesee, what numberoh, yesfifth, there&apos;s my
                        Acceptance-and-Refusal Book. It&apos;s most necessary, both as a direct
                        help and as an indirect check on other books. Then, too, I want it to be
                        impossible to send the Burkes to places they&apos;ve said they
                        wouldn&apos;t go, or for them to be out when they&apos;ve asked
                        people to come here. Those things usually happen when you&apos;ve asked
                        some of those dreadful people that everybody always forgets, yet that are
                        sure to be important at some critical time.</p>
                    <p>Sixth, there&apos;s my Book of Home Entertainmentsa small book but most
                        necessary, as arranging entertainments in the packed days of the Washington
                        season isn&apos;t easy.</p>
                    <p>Seventh, there&apos;s the little book with the list of entertainments
                        other people <pb id="VAA2432-053" n="43"/> are going to give. We have to
                        have that so that we can know how to make our plans. And in it I&apos;m
                        going to keep all the information I can get about the engagements of the
                        people we particularly want to ask. If I&apos;m not sharp-eyed about
                        that I&apos;ll fail in one of my principal duties, which is getting the
                        right sort of people under this roof often enough during the seasons to give
                        us &quot;distinction.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Eighth, there&apos;s my Distinguished-Stranger Book. I&apos;m going
                        to make that a specialty. I want to try to know whenever anybody who is
                        anybody is here on a visit, so that we can get hold of him if possible. The
                        White House can get all that sort of information easily because the
                        distinguished stranger always gives the President a chance to get at him.
                            <hi rend="i">We</hi> shall have to make an effort, but I think
                        we&apos;ll succeed.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-054" n="44"/>
                    <p>Ninththat&apos;s my book for press notices. It&apos;s empty now, but
                        I think &quot;pa&quot; Burke will be satisfied long before the
                        season is over.</p>
                    <p>Quite a library isn&apos;t it? How simple it must be to live in a city
                        like New York or Boston where one bothers only with the people of one set
                        and has practically no bookkeeping beyond a calling list. And here
                        it&apos;s getting worse and worse each season.</p>
                    <p>Let me see, how many sets are there? There&apos;s the set that can say
                        must to usthe White House and the Cabinet and the embassies. Then
                        there&apos;s the set we can say must toa huge, big set and, in a way,
                        important, but there&apos;s nobody really important in it. Then
                        there&apos;s the still wider lower official setsuch people as the
                        under-secretaries of departments, the attachs of embassies, small
                        congressmen <pb id="VAA2432-055" n="45"/> and the like. Then
                        there&apos;s the old Washington aristocracymy particular crowd. It
                        doesn&apos;t amount to &quot;shucks,&quot; as Mrs. Burke would
                        say, but everybody tries to be on good terms with it, Lord knows why.
                        Finally, there&apos;s the set of unofficial peoplethe rich or otherwise
                        distinguished who live in Washington and must be cultivated. And
                        we&apos;re going to gather in all of them, so as not to miss a
                        trick.</p>
                    <p>The first one of the Burkes to whom I showed my books and explained myself in
                        full was &quot;ma&quot; Burke. She looked as if she had been taken
                        with a &quot;misery,&quot; as she calls it. &quot;Lord!
                        Lord!&quot; she groaned. &quot;Whatever have I got my fool self
                        into?&quot;</p>
                    <p>I laughed and assured her that it was nothing at all. &quot;I&apos;m
                        only showing you <hi rend="i">my</hi> work. All you&apos;ve got to do is
                        to <pb id="VAA2432-056" n="46"/> carry out each day&apos;s work.
                        I&apos;ll see to it that you won&apos;t even have to bother about
                        what clothes to wear, unless you want to. You&apos;ll be perfectly free
                        to enjoy yourself.&quot;</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">&quot;Enjoy</hi> myself?&quot; said she. &quot;Why,
                        I&apos;ll be on the jump from morning till night.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;From morning till morning again,&quot; I corrected.
                        &quot;The men sleep in Washington. But the women with social duties have
                        no time for sleeponly for naps.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;I reckon it&apos;ll hardly be worth while to undress for
                        bed,&quot; she said grimly. &quot;I&apos;m going to have the bed
                        taken out of my room. It&apos;d drive me crazy to look at it. Such a
                        good bed, too. I always was a great hand for a good bed. I&apos;ve often
                        said to pa that you can&apos;t put too much value into a bedand by bed
                            <pb id="VAA2432-057" n="47"/> I don&apos;t mean headboard and
                        footboard, nor canopy nor any other fixings. What do you think of my
                        hair?&quot;</p>
                    <p>I was a bit startled by her sudden change of subject. I waited.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Don&apos;t mind mespeak right out,&quot; she said with her
                        good-natured twinkle. &quot;You might think it wasn&apos;t my hair,
                        but it is. The color&apos;s not, though, as you may be surprised to
                        hear.&quot; The &quot;surprised&quot; was broadly satirical.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I prefer natural hair,&quot; said I, &quot;and gray hair is
                        most becoming. It makes a woman look younger, not older.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;That&apos;s sensible,&quot; said she. &quot;I never did
                        care for bottled hair. I think it looks bad from the set-off, and gets
                        worse. The widow Pfizer in our town got so that hers was bright green after
                        she bottled it for two years, trying to catch old man Coakley. And after she
                            <pb id="VAA2432-058" n="48"/> caught him she bottled his, and it turned
                        out green, too, after a while.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Why run such a risk?&quot; said I. &quot;I&apos;m sure
                        your own hair done as your maid can do it would be far more
                        becoming.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Burke was delighted. &quot;I might have known better,&quot; she
                        observed, &quot;but I found Mr. Burke bottling his beard, and he wanted
                        me to; and it seemed to me that somehow bottled hair just fitted right in
                        with all the rest of this foolishness here. How they would rear round at
                        home if they knew what kind of a place Washington is! Why, I hear that up at
                        the White House, when the President leaves the table for a while during
                        meals, all the ladieswomen, I meanhis wife and all of them, have to rise and
                        stand till he comes back.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Yes,&quot; I replied. &quot;He&apos;s started that
                        custom. I like ceremony, don&apos;t you?&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-059" n="49"/>
                    <p>&quot;No, I can&apos;t say that I do,&quot; she drawled.
                        &quot;Out home all the drones and pokes and nobodies are just crazy
                        about getting out in feathers and red plush aprons and clanking and pawing
                        round, trying to make out they&apos;re somebody. And I&apos;ve
                        always noticed that whenever anybody that is a somebody hankers after that
                        sort of thing it&apos;s because he&apos;s got a streak of nobody in
                        him. No, I don&apos;t like it in Cal Walters out home, and I
                        don&apos;t like it in the President.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;We&apos;ve got to do as the other capitals do,&quot; said
                        I. &quot;Naturally, as we get more and more ambassadors, and a bigger
                        army, and the President more powerful, we become like the European courts.
                        And the President is simply making a change abruptly that&apos;d have to
                        come gradually anyhow.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Her eyes began to twinkle. &quot;First <pb id="VAA2432-060" n="50"/>
                        thing you know, the country&apos;ll turn loose a herd of steers from the
                        prairies in this town, and But, long as it&apos;s here, I suppose
                        I&apos;ve got to abide by it. So I&apos;ll do whatever you say.
                        It&apos;ll be a poor do, without my trying to find fault.&quot;</p>
                    <p>And she&apos;s being as good as her word. She makes me tell her exactly
                        what to do. She is so beautifully simple and ladylike in her frank
                        confessions of her ignorancejust as the Queen of England would be if she
                        were to land on the planet Mars and have to learn the waysthe surface ways,
                        I mean. I&apos;ve no doubt that outside of a few frills which silly
                        people make a great fuss about, a lady is a lady from one end of the
                        universe to the other.</p>
                    <p>I&apos;m making the rounds of my friends with Mrs. Burke in this period
                        of waiting for the season to begin. And she <pb id="VAA2432-061" n="51"/>
                        sits mum and keeps her eyes moving. She&apos;s rapidly picking up the
                        right way to say thingsthat is, the self-assurance to say things in her own
                        way. I took her among my friends first because I wanted her to realize that
                        I was absolutely right in urging her to naturalness. There are so many in
                        the different sets she&apos;ll be brought into contact with who are
                        ludicrously self-conscious. Certainly, there&apos;s much truth in what
                        she says about the new order. We Americans don&apos;t do the European
                        sort of thing well, and, while the old way wasn&apos;t pretty to look at
                        it, it wasit was our own. However, I&apos;m merely a social secretary,
                        dealing with what is, and not bothering my head about what ought to be. And
                        as for the Burkes, they&apos;re here to take advantage of what is, not
                        to revolutionize things.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-062" n="52"/>
                    <p>Mr. Burke himself was the next member of the family at whom I got a chance
                        with my great plans. When he had got it all out of me he began to pace up
                        and down the floor, pulling at his whiskers, and evidently thinking. Finally
                        he looked at me in a kindly, sharp way, and, in a voice I recognized at once
                        as the voice of the Thomas Burke who had been able to pile up a fortune and
                        buy into the Senate, said:</p>
                    <p>&quot;I double your salary, Miss Talltowers. And I hope you understand
                        that expense isn&apos;t to be considered in carrying out your program. I
                        want you to act just as if this were all for yourself. And if we succeed I
                        think you&apos;ll find I&apos;m not ungenerous.&quot; And before
                        I could try to thank him he was gone.</p>
                    <p>The last member was &quot;Bucyrus.&quot; As I knew his parents wished
                        to be alone <pb id="VAA2432-063" n="53"/> with him at first I kept out of
                        the way, breakfasting in my rooms, lunching and dining out a great deal.
                        What little I saw of him I didn&apos;t like. He ignored me most of the
                        timeand I, for one woman, don&apos;t like to be ignored by any man. When
                        he did speak to me it was as they speak to the governess in families where
                        they haven&apos;t been used to very much for very long. Perhaps this
                        piqued me a little, but it certainly amused me, and I spoke to him in an
                        humble, deferential way that seemed somehow to make him uneasy.</p>
                    <p>It was day before yesterday that he came into my office about an hour after
                        luncheon. He tried to look very dignified and superior.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Miss Talltowers,&quot; he said, &quot;I must request you to
                        refrain from calling me sir whenever you address me.&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-064" n="54"/>
                    <p>&quot;I beg your pardon, sir,&quot; I replied meekly, &quot;but I
                        have never addressed you. I hope I know my place and my duty better than
                        that. Oh, no, sir, I have always waited to be spoken to.&quot;</p>
                    <p>He blazed a furious red. &quot;I must request you,&quot; he said,
                        with his speech at its most fancy-work like, &quot;not to continue your
                        present manner toward me. Why, the very servants are laughing at
                        me.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Oh, sir,&quot; I said earnestly, &quot;I&apos;m sure
                        that&apos;s not my fault.&quot; And I didn&apos;t spoil it by
                        putting accent on the &quot;that&quot; and the
                        &quot;my.&quot;</p>
                    <p>He got as pale as he had been red. &quot;Are you trying to make it
                        impossible for us to remain under the same roof?&quot; he demanded. What
                        a spoiled stupid!</p>
                    <p>&quot;I&apos;m sure, sir,&quot; said I, and I think my eyes must
                        have shown what an unpleasant <pb id="VAA2432-065" n="55"/> mood his hinted
                        threat had put me in, &quot;that I&apos;m not even succeeding in
                        making it impossible for us to remain in my private office at the same time.
                        Do you understand me, or do you wish me to make my meaning&quot;</p>
                    <p>He had given a sort of snort and had rushed from the room.</p>
                    <p>I suppose I ought to be more charitable toward him. A small person, brought
                        up to regard himself as a sort of god, and able to buy flattery, and
                        permitted to act precisely as his humors might suggestwhat is to be expected
                        of such a man? No, not a man but boy, for he&apos;s only twenty-six. <hi
                            rend="i">Only</hi> twenty-six! One would think I was forty to hear me
                        talking in that way of twenty-six. But women always seem older than men who
                        are even many years older than they. And how having to earn <pb
                            id="VAA2432-066" n="56"/> my own bread has aged me inside! I think
                        Jessie was right when she said in that solemn way of here, &quot;And
                        although, dear Augusta, they may think you haven&apos;t brains enough, I
                        assure you you&apos;ll develop them.&quot; Poor, dear Jessie! How
                        she would amuse herself if she could be as she is, and also have a sense of
                        humor!</p>
                    <p>At any rate, Mr. Bucyrus came striding back after half an hour, and, rather
                        surlily but with a certain grudging manliness, said: &quot;I beg your
                        pardon, Miss Talltowers, for what I said. I am ashamed of my having
                        forgotten myself and made that tyrannical speech to you.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Thank you, sir,&quot; said I, without raising my eyes.
                        &quot;You are most gracious.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;And I hope,&quot; he went on, &quot;that you will try to
                        treat me as an equal.&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-067" n="57"/>
                    <p>&quot;It&apos;ll be very hard to do that, sir,&quot; said I. And
                        I lifted my eyes and let him see that I was laughing at him.</p>
                    <p>He shifted uneasily, red and white by turns. &quot;I think you understand
                        me,&quot; he muttered.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Perfectly,&quot; said I.</p>
                    <p>He waved his arm impatiently. &quot;Please don&apos;t!&quot; he
                        exclaimed rather imperiously. &quot;I could have got my mother
                        to&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;I hope you won&apos;t complain of me to your mother,&quot;
                        I pleaded.</p>
                    <p>He flushed and snorted, like a horse that is being teased by a fly it can
                        reach with neither teeth, hoofs nor tail. &quot;You know I
                        didn&apos;t mean that. I&apos;m not an utter cadnow, don&apos;t
                        say, &apos;Aren&apos;t you, sir?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;I had no intention of doing so,&quot; said I. &quot;In fact
                        I&apos;ve been trying to <pb id="VAA2432-068" n="58"/> make allowances
                        for youfor your mother&apos;s sake. I appreciate that you&apos;ve
                        been away from civilization for a long time. And I&apos;m sure we shall
                        get on comfortably, once you&apos;ve got your bearings
                        again.&quot;</p>
                    <p>He was silent, stood biting his lips and looking out of the window.
                        Presently, when I had resumed my work, he said in an endurable tone and
                        manner: &quot;I hope you will be kind enought to include me in that
                        admirable social scheme of yours. Are those your books?&quot;</p>
                    <p>I explained them to him as briefly as I could. I had no intention of making
                        myself obnoxious, but on the other hand I did not, and do not purpose to go
                        out of my way to be courteous to this silly of an overgrown, spoiled baby.
                        He tried to be nice in praise of my <pb id="VAA2432-069" n="59"/> system,
                        but I got rid of him as soon as I had explained all that my obligations as
                        social secretary to the family required. He thanked me as he was leaving and
                        said, in his most gracious tone, &quot;I shall see that my father raises
                        your salary.&quot;</p>
                    <p>I fairly gasped at the impudence of this, but before I could collect myself
                        properly to deal with him he was gone. Perhaps it was just as well. I must
                        be careful not to be &quot;sensitive&quot;that would make me as
                        ridiculous as he is.</p>
                    <p>And that&apos;s the man Jim Lafollette is fairly smoking with jealously
                        of! He was dining at Rachel&apos;s last night, and Rachel put him next
                        me. He couldn&apos;t keep of the subject of &quot;that young
                        Burke.&quot; Jessie overheard him after a while and leaned round and
                        said to me, &quot;How do you and young Mr. Burke get on?&quot; in
                        her &quot;strictly private&quot; mannerJessie&apos;s <pb
                            id="VAA2432-070" n="60"/> strictly private manner is about as private as
                        the Monument.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Not badly,&quot; I replied, to punish Jim.
                        &quot;We&apos;re gradually getting acquainted.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Jim sneered under his mustache. &quot;It&apos;s the most shameful
                        scheme two women ever put up,&quot; he said, as if he were joking.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Oh, has Jessie told you?&quot; I exclaimed, pretending to be
                        concealing my vexation.</p>
                    <p>&quot;It&apos;s the talk of the town,&quot; he answered, showing
                        his teeth in a grin that was all fury and no fun.</p>
                    <p>There may be women idiots enough to marry a man who warns them in advance
                        that he&apos;s rabidly jealous, but I&apos;m not one of them. Better
                        a crust in quietness.</p>
                </div2>
                <pb id="VAA2432-071" n="61"/>
                <div2 type="chapter">
                    <head>III</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="b">D</hi>ECEMBER 27. Three weeks simply boiling with business
                        since I wrote hereand it seems not more than so many days. And all by way of
                        preparation, for the actual season is still five days away.</p>
                    <p>I can hardly realize that Mrs. Burke is the same person I looked at so
                        dubiously two days less than a month ago. Truly, the right sort of us
                        Americans are wonderful people. To begin with her appearance: her hair
                        isn&apos;t &quot;bottled,&quot; as she called it, any more.
                        It&apos;s beautiful <pb id="VAA2432-072" n="62"/> iron-gray, and softens
                        her features and permits all the placid kindliness and humor of her face to
                        show. Then there&apos;s her dressgracious, how tight-looking she was!
                            <hi rend="i">A thin</hi> woman can, and should, wear <hi rend="i"
                            >close</hi> things. But no woman who wishes to look like a lady must
                        ever wear anything <hi rend="i">tight.</hi> To be tight in one&apos;s
                        clothes is to be tight in one&apos;s talk, manner, thoughtand that
                        meanswell, common. What an expressive word &quot;common&quot; is,
                        yet I&apos;m sure I couldn&apos;t define it.</p>
                    <p>For a fat woman to be tight isrevolting! My idea of misery is a fat woman in
                        a tight waist and tight shoes. Yet fat women have a mania for wearing tight
                        things, just as gaunt women yearn for stripes and short women for flounces.
                        My first move in getting Mrs. Burke into shapeafter doing away <pb
                            id="VAA2432-073" n="63"/> with that dreadful &quot;bottled&quot;
                        hairwas to put her into comfortable clothes. The first time I got her into
                        an evening dress of the right sort I was rewarded for all my trouble by her
                        expression. She kissed me with tears in her eyes. &quot;My
                        dear,&quot; said she, &quot;never before did I have a best dress
                        that I wasn&apos;t afraid to breathe in for fear I&apos;d bust out,
                        back or front.&quot; Then I made her sit down before her long glass and
                        look at herself carefully. She had the prettiest kind of color in her cheeks
                        as she smiled at me and said: &quot;If I&apos;d
                        &apos;a&apos; looked like this when I was young I reckon Mr. Burke
                        wouldn&apos;t &apos;a&apos; been so easy in his mind when he
                        went away from home, nor &apos;a&apos; stayed so long. I always did
                        sympathize with pretty women when they capered round, but now I wonder they
                        ever do sober down. If I weighed a hundred <pb id="VAA2432-074" n="64"/>
                        pounds or so less I do believe I&apos;d try to frisk yet.&quot;</p>
                    <p>And I do believe she could; for she&apos;s really a handsome woman. Why
                        is it that the women who have the most to them don&apos;t give it a
                        chance to show through, but get themselves up so that anybody who glances at
                        them tries never to look again?</p>
                    <p>It is the change in her appearance even more than all she&apos;s learned
                        that has given her self-confidence. She feels at easeand that puts her at
                        ease, and puts everybody else at ease, too. It has reacted upon Mr. Burke.
                        He has dropped brilliantineperhaps &quot;ma&quot; gave him a quiet
                        hintand he has taken some lessons in dress from &quot;Cyrus,&quot;
                        who really gets himself up very well, considering that he has lived in
                        Germany for three years. I should have hopes <pb id="VAA2432-075" n="65"/>
                        that &quot;pa&quot; would blossom out into something very attractive
                        socially if he hadn&apos;t a deep-seated notion that he is a great
                        joker. A naturally serious man who tries to be funny is about the most
                        painful object in civilization. Still, Washington is full of statesmen and
                        scholars who try to unbend and be &quot;light,&quot; especially with
                        &quot;the ladies.&quot; Nothing makes meor any other woman, I
                        supposeso angry as for a man to show that he takes me for a fool by making a
                        grinning galoot of himself whenever he talks to me. Bucyrus is much that
                        kind of ass. He alternates between solemnity and silliness.</p>
                    <p>I said rather pointedly to him the other night: &quot;You men with your
                        great, deep minds make a mistake in changing your manner when you talk with
                        the women and the children. Nothing <pb id="VAA2432-076" n="66"/> pleases us
                        so much as to be take seriously.&quot; But it didn&apos;t touch him.
                        However, he&apos;s hardly to blame. He&apos;s spent a great many
                        years round institutions of learning, and in those places, I&apos;ve
                        noticed, every one has a musty, fusty sense of humor. Probably it comes from
                        cackling at classical jokes that have laughted themselves as dry as a
                        mummy.</p>
                    <p>We&apos;ve been giving a few entertainmentsinformal and not large, but
                        highly important. I had two objects in mind: In the first place, to get Mr.
                        and Mrs. Burke accustomed to the style of hospitality they&apos;ve got
                        to give if they&apos;re going to win out. In the second place, to get
                        certain of the kind of people who are necessary to us in the habit of coming
                        to this houseand those people are not so very hard to get hold of now; later
                        they&apos;ll be engaged day and night.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-077" n="67"/>
                    <p>For two weeks now I&apos;ve had my two especial features going. One of
                        them is for the men, the other for the women. And I can see already that
                        they alone would carry us through triumphantly; for they&apos;ve caught
                        on.</p>
                    <p>My men&apos;s feature is a breakfast. I engaged a particularly good
                        cookthe best old-fashioned Southern cook in Washington. Rachel had her, and
                        I persuaded Mr. Derby to consent to giving her up to us, just for this
                        season. Cleopatrathat&apos;s her namehas nothing to do but get together
                        every morning by nine o&apos;clock the grandest kind of an old-fashioned
                        American breakfast. And I explained to Senator Burke that he was to invite
                        some of his colleagues, as many as he liked, and tell them to come any
                        morning, or every morning if they wished, and bring their friends.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-078" n="68"/>
                    <p>I consult with Cleopatra every day as to what she&apos;s to have the next
                        morning; and I think dear old father taught me what kind of breakfast men
                        like. I don&apos;t give them too much, or they&apos;d be afraid to
                        come and risk indigestion a second time. I see to it that everything is
                        perfectly cookedand it&apos;s pretty hard for any man to get
                        indigestion, even from corned beef hash and hot cornbread and buckwheat
                        cakes with maple syrup, if it&apos;s perfectly cooked and is eaten in a
                        cheerful frame of mind. No women are permitted at these breakfastsjust men,
                        with everything free and easy, plenty to smoke, separate tables, but each
                        large enough so that there&apos;s always room at any one of them for one
                        more who might otherwise be uncomfortable. Even now we have from fifteen to
                        twenty menamong them <pb id="VAA2432-079" n="[]"/>
                        <figure entity="VAA2432-6"/>
                        <pb id="VAA2432-080" n="69"/> the very best in Washington. In the season
                        we&apos;ll have thirty and forty, and our house will be a regular club
                        from nine to eleven for just the right men.</p>
                    <p>My other big feature is an informal dance every Wednesday night.
                        It&apos;s already as great a success in its way as the breakfasts are in
                        theirs. I&apos;ve been rather careful about whom I let Mrs. Burke invite
                        to come in one Wednesdays whenever they like. The result is that everybody
                        is pleased; the affairs seem to be &quot;exclusive,&quot; yet are
                        not. I know it will do the Burkes a world of good politically, because a
                        certain kind of people who are important politically but have had no chance
                        socially are coming to us on Wednesdays, and that&apos;s just the kind
                        of people who are frantically flattered by the idea that they are
                        &quot;in the push.&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-081" n="70"/>
                    <p>Speaking of being &quot;in the push,&quot; there are two ways of
                        getting there if one isn&apos;t there. One is to worm your way in; the
                        other is to make yourself the head and front of &quot;the
                        push.&quot; That&apos;s the way for those who have money and know
                        how. And that&apos;s the way the Burkes are getting ingetting in at the
                        front instead of at the rear.</p>
                    <p>It&apos;s most gratifying to see how Mr. Burke treats me. He always has
                        been deferential, but he now shows that he thinks I have real brains. And
                        since his breakfasts have become the talk of the town and are
                        &quot;patronized&quot; by the men he&apos;s so eager to get hold
                        of, he is even consulting me about his business. I am criticizing for him
                        now a speech he&apos;s going to make on the canal question next montha
                        dreadfully dull speech, and I don&apos;t feel competent to tell him <pb
                            id="VAA2432-082" n="71"/> what to do with it. I think I&apos;ll
                        advise him not to make it, tell him his forte is diplomacywinning men round
                        by personal dealing with themwhich is the truth.</p>
                    <p>Young Mr. Burkeafter a period of unbendingis now shyer than ever. I wondered
                        why, until it happened to occur to me one day as I was talking with Jessie.
                        I suddenly said to her: &quot;Jessie, did you ever tell Nadeshda that
                        you had planned to marry me to Cyrus Burke?&quot;</p>
                    <p>She hopped about in her chair a bit, as uneasy as a bird on a swaying perch.
                        Then she confessed that she &quot;might have suggested before Nadeshda
                        what a delightfully satisfactory thing it would be.&quot;</p>
                    <p>I laughed to relieve her mindalso because it amused me to see through
                        Nadeshda.</p>
                    <p>Of course, one of the women I needed <pb id="VAA2432-083" n="72"/> most in
                        this Burke campaign was Nadeshda. And I happened to know that she is bent on
                        marrying a rich Americanindeed, that&apos;s the only reason why the
                        wilds of America are favored with the presence of the beautiful, joy-loving,
                        courted and adored Baroness Nadeshda Daragane. The yarn about her sister,
                        the ambassadress, being an invalid and shrinking from the heavy social
                        responsibilities of the embassy is just so much trash. So, as soon as
                        &quot;Cyrus&quot; came I went over to see her, and, as
                        diplomatically as I knew how, displayed before her dazzled eyes the
                        substantial advantages of the sole heir of the great Western
                        multi-millionaire.</p>
                    <p>As I went on to tell how generous the Senator is, and how certain he would be
                        to lavish wealth upon his daughter-in-law, I could see her mind at work. <pb
                            id="VAA2432-084" n="73"/> A fascinating, naughty, treacherous little
                        mind it islike a small Swiss watch of the rarest workmanship and full of
                        wheels within wheels. And she&apos;s a beautiful little creature, as
                        warm as a tropical sun to look at, and about as cold as the Arctic regions
                        to deal with. No, I haven&apos;t begun to describe her. I&apos;d not
                        be surprised to hear that she had eloped with her brother-in-law&apos;s
                        coachman; nor should I be surprised to hear that she had married the most
                        hideous, revolting man in the world for his money, and was suspected of
                        being engaged in trying to hasten him off to the grave. She&apos;s of
                        the queer sort that would kiss or kill with equal enthusiasm, capable of
                        almost any virtue or viceon impulse. If there&apos;s any part of her
                        beneath the impulsive part it&apos;s solid ice in a frame of steel.
                        Butis there? She&apos;s talked <pb id="VAA2432-085" n="74"/> about a
                        good dealnot a tenth enough to satisfy her craving for notoriety, and, I may
                        add, not a tenth part so much as she deserves to be, and would be if we
                        studied character on this side of the water instead of being too busy with
                        ourselves to look beyond anybody else&apos;s surface.</p>
                    <p>Well, the Baroness Nadeshda has been wild about the Burkes ever since we had
                        our talk. And she has Mr. Cyrus thoroughly tangled in her nets, and the
                        Senator, too. And, naturally, she lost no time in trying to
                        &quot;do&quot; me. She has told Bucyrus what a designing creature I
                        amno doubt has warned him that if I seem distant to him I&apos;m at my
                        deadliest, and to look out for mines. He certainly is looking out for them,
                        for, whenever I speak to him, he acts as if he were stepping round on a
                        volcano. <pb id="VAA2432-086" n="75"/> I&apos;m having a good deal of
                        fun with him. I wish I had the time; I&apos;d try to teach him a very
                        valuable lesson. Really, it&apos;s a shame to let a man go through life
                        imagining that he&apos;s an all-conqueror, when in reality the woman who
                        marries him will feel that she&apos;s swallowing about as bitter a dose
                        as Fate ever presented to feminine lips in a gold spoon.</p>
                    <p>Dear old &quot;ma&quot; Burke hasn&apos;t yet yielded to
                        Nadeshda&apos;s blandishments. We went to the embassy to call yesterday
                        afternoon at tea-time, and I saw her watching Nadeshda in that smiling,
                        simple way of hers that conceals about as keen a brain as I
                        shouldn&apos;t care to have tearing me to pieces for inspection.</p>
                    <p>The embassy at tea-time is always wild. For then Sophie comes in with her
                        monkey and Nadeshda&apos;s seven dogs are racing about. And the Count
                        always <pb id="VAA2432-087" n="76"/> laughs loudly, usually at nothing at
                        all. And each time he laughs the dogs bark until the monkey in a great
                        fright dashes up the curtains or flings himself at Sophie and almost
                        strangles her with his paws or arms, or whatever they are, round her neck. I
                        don&apos;t think I&apos;ve ever been there that something
                        hasn&apos;t been spilt for a huge mess; often the whole tea-table
                        topples over. Mrs. Burke loves to go, for afterward she laughs a dozen times
                        a day until her sides ache.</p>
                    <p>As we came away yesterday I said to her: &quot;What a fascinating,
                        beautiful creature Nadeshda is!&quot;</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Burke smiled. &quot;When I was a girl,&quot; she said,
                        &quot;I had a catamount for a peta cub, and they had cut his claws. He
                        was beautiful and mighty fascinatingyou never did know when he was going to
                        fawn on you and when <pb id="VAA2432-088" n="77"/> he was going to fasten
                        his teeth in you. The baroness puts me in mind of my old pet, and how I
                        didn&apos;t know which was harderto keep him or to give him
                        up.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;She certainly has a strange nature,&quot; said I.</p>
                    <p>After a pause Mrs. Burke went on: &quot;She&apos;s the queerest
                        animal in this menagerie here, so far as I&apos;ve seen. And I
                        don&apos;t think I&apos;m wrong in suspecting she&apos;s sitting
                        up to Cyrus.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;I don&apos;t wonder he finds her interesting,&quot; said
                        I.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Cyrus is just like his pa,&quot; said she, &quot;a mighty
                        poor judge of women. It was lucky for his pa that he married and settled
                        down before he had much glitter to catch the eyes of the women. Otherwise,
                        he&apos;d &apos;a&apos; made a ridiculous fool of himself. But I
                        like a man the <pb id="VAA2432-089" n="78"/> women can fool easy. That shows
                        he&apos;s hones. These fellows who are so sharp at getting on to the
                        tricks of the women ain&apos;t, as a rule, good for much else. But Cyrus
                        has got <hi rend="i">me</hi> to look after him.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;He might do much worse than marry Nadeshda,&quot; said I.</p>
                    <p>&quot;That&apos;s what his pa says,&quot; she replied.
                        &quot;But I ain&apos;t got round to these new-fashioned notions of
                        marriage. I want to see my Cyrus married to the sort of woman his
                        ma&apos;d like and be proud to have for the mother of her
                        grand-children. And I ain&apos;t altogether sure we need the kind of
                        tone in our blood that a catamount&apos;d bring. Though I must say a
                        year or so of living with a catamount might do Cyrus a world of
                        good.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Which shows that even love can&apos;t altogether blind
                        &quot;ma&quot; Burke.</p>
                    <p>January 3. I had to do a little scheming <pb id="VAA2432-090" n="[]"/>
                        <figure entity="VAA2432-7"/>
                        <pb id="VAA2432-091" n="79"/> to get Mrs. Burke an invitation to assist at
                        the New Year&apos;s reception. It&apos;s always the first event of
                        the season, and, though it would have been no great matter if I
                        hadn&apos;t been able to get her in among those who stand near the
                        President&apos;s wife and the Cabinet women, still I felt that I
                        couldn&apos;t get my &quot;pulls&quot; into working order any
                        too soon. Ever since the second week in my &quot;job&quot;
                        I&apos;ve realized that nothing could be easier than to put the Burkes
                        well to the front, but my ambition to make them first calls for the exertion
                        of every energy.</p>
                    <p>So, in the third week of December I set Rachel at Mrs. Senator Lumley and
                        Mrs. Admiral Bixbytwo women who can get almost anything in reason out of the
                        President&apos;s wife. Rachel is about the most important woman in the
                        old Washington aristocracy, and the Lumleys <pb id="VAA2432-092" n="80"/>
                        and the Bixbys are in the nature of fixtures here, not at all like an
                        evanescent President or Cabinet person. So Rachel&apos;s request set the
                        two women to work. And although the President&apos;s wife said
                        she&apos;d asked all she intended to ask, far too many, and
                        didn&apos;t see why on earth she should be beset for a new-comer who had
                        been reported to her as fat and impossible, still she finally yielded.</p>
                    <p>I hadn&apos;t hoped to get an invitation for them for the Cabinet dinner,
                        and I was astounded when it came. We had arranged to give a rather large
                        informal dinner that night and had to call it off, as an invitation from the
                        White House, even from the obscurest member of the President&apos;s
                        family for any old function whatever, is a command that may not be
                        disobeyed. Well, as I was saying, the <pb id="VAA2432-093" n="81"/>
                        invitation to the Cabinet dinner came unsought. It seems that the Burke
                        breakfasts are making a great stir politically; so great a stir that they
                        have made the President a little uneasy. Of course, the best way to get rid
                        of an opponent is to conciliate him. Hence the royal command to Senator and
                        Mrs. Burke to appear at his Majesty&apos;s dinner to his
                        Majesty&apos;s ministers.</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Burke is tremendously proud of her first two communications from the
                        White House. As for the Senator, he looks at them half a dozen times a
                        day.</p>
                    <p>I went down to the New Year&apos;s reception to see how
                        &quot;ma&quot; was getting on. As I had expected, she
                        didn&apos;t stand very long. She cast about for a chair, and, seeing
                        one, planted herself. Soon the Baroness joined her, and young Prince
                        Krepousky joined Nadeshda, and <pb id="VAA2432-094" n="82"/> then General
                        Martin, who loves Mrs. Burke for the feeds she gives. The group grew, and
                        Mrs. Burke began to talk in her drawling, humorous way, and Nadeshda
                        laughed, which made the others laughfor it&apos;s impossible to resist
                        Nadeshda. When I arrived Mrs. Burke was &quot;right in it.&quot;</p>
                    <p>And after a while the President came and said: &quot;Is this your
                        reception, madam, or is it mine?&quot; At which there was more laughing,
                        he raising a great guffaw and slapping his hip with his powerful hand. Then
                        they all went up to have something to eat, and the President spent most of
                        the time with her.</p>
                    <p>She doesn&apos;t need any more coaching. Of course, she&apos;s
                        flattered by her success. But instead of having her head turned, as most
                        women do who get the least bit of especial attention from the conspicuous
                            <pb id="VAA2432-095" n="[]"/>
                        <figure entity="VAA2432-8"/>
                        <pb id="VAA2432-096" n="83"/> men here, she takes it all very placidly.
                        &quot;They don&apos;t care shucks for me,&quot; she says,
                        &quot;and I know it. We&apos;re all in business together, and
                        I&apos;m mighty glad it can be carried on so cheerful-like.&quot; At
                        the Cabinet dinner, to-morrow night, she&apos;ll have to sit well down
                        toward the foot of the table. But she won&apos;t mind that. Indeed, if I
                        hadn&apos;t been giving her lessons in precedence she wouldn&apos;t
                        have an idea that everything here is arranged by rank.</p>
                    <p>Jessieso she tells mehad a half-hour&apos;s session with
                        &quot;Cyrus&quot; the other day and gave him a very exalted idea of
                        my social position and influence. No doubt, what she said confirmed his
                        suspicion that I and my friends are conspiring against him; but I observe a
                        distinct change in his manner toward me. He&apos;s even humble. I
                        suppose he <pb id="VAA2432-097" n="84"/> thought I was some miserable
                        creature whom his mother had taken on, half out of charity. I&apos;m
                        afraid I have a sort of family pride that&apos;s a little ridiculousbut
                        I can&apos;t help it. Still, I am American enough to despise people who
                        are courteous or otherwise, according as they look up to or look down on the
                        particular person&apos;s family and position. I guess young Mr. Burke is
                        his father in an aggravated form. Yet Jessie, and Rachel, too, pretend to
                        like him. And probably they really doit&apos;s not hard to like any one
                        who is not asking favors and is in a position to grant them, and
                        isn&apos;t so near to one that his quills stick into one.</p>
                    <p>The Countess of Wend came in to see me this afternoon and told me all about
                        the row over at the legation. It seems that the new minister is a plebeian,
                        and in their country people of his sort <pb id="VAA2432-098" n="85"/>
                        aren&apos;t noticed by the upper classes unless an upper-class man
                        happens to need something to wipe his boots on and one of them is convenient
                        for use. Well, every attache is in a fury, and none of them will speak to
                        the minister except in the most formal way and only when it&apos;s
                        absolutely necessary. As for the minister&apos;s wife, the other
                        womenbut what&apos;s the use of describing it; we all know how nasty
                        women can be about matters of rank. The Count is talking seriously of
                        resigning. I&apos;d be dreadfully sorry, as Eugenie is a dear, more like
                        an American than a foreigner; and I believe she really likes us, where most
                        of them privately despise us as a lot of low-born upstarts. I know they
                        laugh all day long at the President&apos;s queer manners and
                        mannerismsbut then, so do we, for that matter. And it&apos;s quite <pb
                            id="VAA2432-099" n="86"/> unusual for Washington, where each President
                        is bowed down to and praised everywhere and flattered till he thinks
                        he&apos;s a sort of godand forgotten as soon as his term is ended. I
                        suppose there&apos;s nothing deader on this earth than an ex-President,
                        with no offices to distribute and no hopes for a further political
                        career.</p>
                    <p>January 9. We had a beautiful dinner here last nightvery brilliant too, as we
                        all were going to a ball at the Russian embassy afterward. All the diplomats
                        and army men were in uniformand one or two of the army men were really
                        brilliant. But none of the diplomats. They say that no nation sends us its
                        best or even its second best. It seems that diplomats don&apos;t amount
                        to much in this day of cables. Those who have any intelligence naturally go
                            <pb id="VAA2432-100" n="87"/> to courts, where the atmosphere is
                        congenial and where there are chances for decorations. So we get only the
                        stiffs and stuffswith a few exceptions. If it weren&apos;t for their
                        women</p>
                    <p>But, to return to our dinnerMrs. Burke went in with the German ambassador,
                        and I saw that they were getting on famously. He is a very clever man in a
                        small way, and has almost an American sense of humor. As soon as he saw that
                        she intended what she said to be laughed at he gave himself up to it.
                        &quot;Your Mrs. Burke is charming, Miss Talltowers,&quot; said he to
                        me after dinner. &quot;She ranks with Bret Harte and Mark Twain.
                        It&apos;s only in America that you find old women who make you forget to
                        wish you were with young and pretty women.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Jim Lafollette took me inthe first <pb id="VAA2432-101" n="88"/> time
                        I&apos;ve had him here. I must say he behaved very well and was the
                        hand-somest man in the room. But he never has much to say that is worth
                        hearing. Though conversation at Washington in society isn&apos;t on any
                        too high a plane, as a rulehow could conversation in a mixed society
                        anywhere be very high?still it isn&apos;t the wishy-washy chatter and
                        gossip that Jim Lafollette delights in. Of course, army officers almost
                        always go in for gossipthat comes from sitting round with their women at
                        lonely posts where nothing occurs. And they, as a rule, either gossip or
                        simply drivel when they talk to women, because all the women that ever liked
                        them liked them for their brass buttons, and all the women they ever liked
                        they liked for their pretty faces and empty heads. So, usually, to get an
                        army officer <pb id="VAA2432-102" n="89"/> at dinner is to sit with a bowl
                        of soft taffy held to your lips and a huge spoonful of it thrust into your
                        mouth every time you stop talking. That&apos;s true of many of the
                        statesmen, too, especially the heavyweights. I suppose I&apos;m wrong,
                        but I can&apos;t help suspecting a man without a sense of humor of being
                        a solemn fraud.</p>
                    <p>You&apos;d think American women, at the capital, at least, would be
                        interested in politics. But they&apos;re not. They say it&apos;s the
                        vulgarity of the intriguing and of most of the best intriguers that makes
                        them dislike politics, even here. I suspect there&apos;s another reason.
                        We women are so petted by the men that we don&apos;t have to know
                        anything to make ourselves agreeable. If we&apos;re pretty and listen
                        well that&apos;s all that&apos;s necessary. So, why get headaches
                        learning things?</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-103" n="90"/>
                    <p>Of course, there are exceptions. Take Maggie Shotwell. Her husband is a
                        wag-eared ass. Yet in eleven years she has advanced him from second
                        secretary to minister to a second-class power just by showing up here at
                        intervals and playing the game intelligently. And there are scores of army
                        women who do as well in a smaller way, and a few of the diplomats&apos;
                        wives are most adroit, intriguing well both here and at their homes in a
                        nice, clean way, as intrigue goes.</p>
                    <p>But most of the women are like &quot;ma&quot; Burke, who&apos;d
                        as soon think of entering for a foot-race as of interfering in her
                        husband&apos;s political affairs in any way, beyond giving him some
                        sound advice about the men that can be trusted and the men that
                        can&apos;t. I suppose if there were real careers in public life in <pb
                            id="VAA2432-104" n="91"/> this country, not dependent upon elections,
                        the Washington women wouldn&apos;t be so lazy and indifferent, but would
                        wake up and intrigue their brothers and sons and other male relatives into
                        all sorts of things. Then, too, a man has to vote with his
                        &quot;party&quot; on everything that&apos;s important, and his
                        &quot;party&quot; is a small group of old men who are beyond social
                        blandishments and go to bed early every night and associate only with men in
                        the daytime.</p>
                    <p>No, we women don&apos;t amount to much <hi rend="i">directly</hi> at
                        Washington. If Jim Lafollette had kept away from the women and society he
                        might have amounted to something. It&apos;s become a proverb that
                        whenever a young man comes here and goes in for the social end of it he is
                        doomed soon to disappear and be heard of no more. The President is trying
                            <pb id="VAA2432-105" n="92"/> to make society amount to something, but
                        he won&apos;t succeed. Whatever benefit there may be in it will go, not
                        to him, but to men like Senator Burke. He doesn&apos;t go any more than
                        he can help, except to his own breakfasts. But he sends his wife, and so,
                        without wasting any of his time, he makes himself prominent in a very short
                        space of time and gets all the big social indirect influencethe influence of
                        the women on their husbands.</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Burke&apos;s younger brother, Robert Gunton, arrived last night. He
                        reminds me of her, but he&apos;s slender and very activea shabby sort of
                        person, clean but careless, and he looks as if he had so many other things
                        to think about that he hadn&apos;t time to think about himself. He looks
                        younger and talks older than his years. He&apos;s here to get some sort
                            <pb id="VAA2432-106" n="93"/> of patent through; he won&apos;t
                        permit his brother-in-law to assist him; he refuses to go anywherein
                        society, I mean. We rode up to the Capitol together in a street-car this
                        morning, and I liked him.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Why do you ride in a street-car?&quot; he asked.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Because it&apos;s not considered good form to use carriages too
                        much,&quot; I replied. &quot;It might rouse the envy of those who
                        can&apos;t afford carriages.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Then it isn&apos;t because you don&apos;t want to, but
                        because you don&apos;t dare to?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Yes,&quot; said I. &quot;But things are changing rapidly.
                        The rich people who live here but care nothing for politics are gradually
                        introducing class distinctions.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;You mean, poor people who like to fawn upon and hate the rich are
                        introducing class distinctions,&quot; he corrected.</p>
                    <p>He is thirty-two years old; he treats <pb id="VAA2432-107" n="94"/> a woman
                        as if she were a man, and he treats a man as if he himself were one. It
                        isn&apos;t possible not to like that sort of human being.</p>
                    <p>Invitations are beginning to come in floodsinvitations for the big, formal
                        things for which people are asked weeks in advance. And we are getting a
                        splendid percentage of acceptances for our big affairs, thanks to my taking
                        the trouble to find out the freest dates in the season. If all goes well,
                        before another month, as soon as it gets round that we are going to give
                        something big in a short time, lots of pretty good people will be holding
                        off from accepting other things in the hope that they&apos;re on our
                        list.</p>
                    <p>Certainly, there&apos;s a good deal in going about anything in a
                        systematic wayeven a social launching.</p>
                </div2>
                <pb id="VAA2432-108" n="95"/>
                <div2 type="chapter">
                    <head>IV</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="b">J</hi>ANUARY 12. We are all sleeping so badly. Even the
                        Senator, whom nothing has ever before kept from his &quot;proper
                        rest,&quot; is complaining of wakefulness. Suppers every night either
                        here or elsewhere, the house never quiet until two or three in the morning,
                        all of us up at eight Cyrus often at seven because he rides a good deal, and
                        the early morning is the only time when any one in Washington in the season
                        can find time to ride. &quot;It&apos;s worse than the Wilderness
                        campaign,&quot; said Mr. <pb id="VAA2432-109" n="96"/> Burke, who was a
                        lieutenant in the war. &quot;For now and then, between battles and
                        skirmishes, we did get plenty of sleep. This is a continuous battle day and
                        night, week in and week out, with no let-up for Sundays.&quot; And Mrs.
                        Burkepoor &quot;ma!&quot; How hollow-eyed and sagged-cheeked she is
                        getting with the real season less than two weeks old! She says: &quot;I
                        wouldn&apos;t treat a dog as I treat myself. I no sooner get to sleep
                        than they wake me. I think the servants just delight to wake me, and I
                        don&apos;t blame them, for they&apos;re worse off than we are,
                        though I do try to be as easy on them as possible.&quot; She
                        doesn&apos;t know how many long naps they take while she&apos;s
                        dragging herself from place to place.</p>
                    <p>On our way to the White House to a musicale she fell asleep. As we rolled up
                        to the entrance I had to wake her. <pb id="VAA2432-110" n="97"/> She came to
                        with a sort of groan and gave a ludicrously pitiful glance at the attendant
                        who was impatiently waiting. &quot;Oh, Lord!&quot; she muttered.
                        &quot;I was dreaming I was in bed, and it ain&apos;t so. Instead,
                        I&apos;ve got to enjoy myself.&quot; And then she gave a dreary
                        laugh.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Ma&quot; Burke dozed through the musicale with a pleasant smile
                        on her large face and her head keeping time to the music. When we spoke to
                        the President and he said he hoped she&apos;d &quot;enjoyed
                        herself,&quot; she drawled: &quot;I did that, Mr. President! I only
                        wish it had been longerI&apos;m &apos;way behind on sleep.&quot;
                        He laughed uproariously. It&apos;s the fashion to laugh at everything
                        &quot;ma&quot; says now, because the German ambassador tells every
                        one what a wit she is. And who&apos;d fail to laugh at wit admired by an
                        ambassador?</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-111" n="98"/>
                    <p>Writing about sleep has driven off my fit of wakefulness. I&apos;ll only
                        add that Lu Frayne&apos;s in town, working day and night to get her
                        husband transferred from San Francisco to the War Department here. I think
                        she&apos;ll win out, as she&apos;s got two Senators who&apos;ve
                        been frightening the President by acting queerly lately. It&apos;s too
                        funny! When the new Administration came every one was scared because the
                        rumor got round that he was going to give us a repetition of the Cleveland
                        nightmare. But there was nothing in it; the only &quot;pulls&quot;
                        that have failed to work are those that were strong with the last
                        Administration, and there&apos;s a whole crop of new pulls. Well, at
                        least, the right sort of people, those who have family and position, are
                        getting their rights to preference as they never did before. We&apos;ve
                            <pb id="VAA2432-112" n="99"/> not had many Presidents who knew the right
                        sort of people even when they&apos;ve been willing to please them, if
                        they could pick them out.</p>
                    <p>What a changed Washington it is: so many formalities; so many rich people; so
                        many rich men, and men of family and position in office; so many big, fine
                        houses and English and French servants. &quot;Such a
                        stylishness!&quot;</p>
                    <p>January 14. Our first big dance last nightI mean, formal dance to show our
                        strength. Everybody was here, and the dinner beforehand and the supper
                        afterward and all the mechanical arrangements, so to speak, were perfect.
                        The ball-room was a sighteven &quot;ma&quot; Burke, tired to death,
                        perked up. Almost all the diplomats, except those nobody asks, were here.
                        And I don&apos;t think more than thirty people we hadn&apos;t
                        invited <pb id="VAA2432-113" n="100"/> ventured to come. We were all so
                        excited that, after the last people had gone, we sat round for nearly an
                        hour. &quot;Ma&quot; Burke took me in her arms and kissed me.
                        &quot;It was your ball,&quot; said she. &quot;But then,
                        everything we get credit for is all yours; ain&apos;t it,
                        pa?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Miss Talltowers has certainly done wonderfully,&quot; said
                        &quot;pa&quot; in his cautious, judicial way. Then he seemed ashamed
                        of himself, as if he had been ungenerous, and shook hands with me and added:
                        &quot;Thank you, thank you, Miss Augustaif you&apos;ll permit me the
                        liberty of calling you so.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;I never expected to see as pretty a girl as you bothering to have
                        brains,&quot; Mrs. Burke went on to say. And for the first time in weeks
                        and weeks it occurred to me that I did have a personal existence apart from
                        my workthe <pb id="VAA2432-114" n="101"/> books and bookkeeping, the
                        servants and the housekeeper, who is only one more to fuss with, the
                        tradespeople, and musicians, and singers, and florists, andit makes my head
                        whirl to try to recall the awful list.</p>
                    <p>&quot;She won&apos;t be pretty very long,&quot; said
                        Cyrushe&apos;s taking lessons of his mother and is dropping his
                        fancy-work speech and his &quot;made-in-Germany&quot;
                        manners&quot;if she don&apos;t stop working day <hi rend="i"
                            >and</hi> night.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Oh, I&apos;m amusing myself,&quot; replied I; but I was
                        reminded how weary I felt, and went away to bed. I neglected to close my
                        sitting-room door, and as I was getting ready for bed in my dressing-room I
                        couldn&apos;t help overhearing a scrap of talk between Cyrus and Mr.
                        Gunton as they went along the hall on the way to their apartments.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-115" n="102"/>
                    <p>&quot;The Tevises were disgustingthey showed their envy so
                        plainly,&quot; Cyrus said. The Tevises are trying hard to do what
                        we&apos;re doing in a social way, and thought they must have even more
                        money than the Burkes, they&apos;re failing at it.</p>
                    <p>&quot;They&apos;ll never get anywhere,&quot; Mr. Gunton replied.
                        &quot;You can&apos;t collect much of a crowd of nice people just to
                        watch you spend money. You&apos;ve got to give them a real show.
                        There&apos;s where Miss Talltowers comes in.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;She has wonderful taste and originality,&quot; said Cyrus.
                        Cyrus!</p>
                    <p>Mr. Gunton sat out most of the evening with Nadeshda. I suppose she was
                        trying to make Cyrus jealous and also to create trouble between him and his
                        uncle. I&apos;ve not seen a franker flirtation even in Washington.
                        Whenever I <pb id="VAA2432-116" n="103"/> chanced to look at them, Mr.
                        Gunton was talking earnestly, and she seemed to be hanging to his words like
                        a thirsty bird to a water-pan. And her queer, subtle face waswell, it was
                        beautiful, and gave me that sense of the wild and fierce and uncanny which
                        makes her both fascinating and terrible. I think Mr. Gunton was
                        infatuatedindeed, I know it. For when I spoke of her to him this morning his
                        eyes seemed to blaze. He drew a long breath. &quot;A
                        wonder-woman!&quot; he said. &quot;I never saw anything like herin
                        the flesh.&quot; Then he looked a little sheepish, and added:
                        &quot;I mean it, but I laugh at myself, too. There are fools that
                        don&apos;t know they&apos;re fools; then, there are fools that do
                        know it and laugh at themselves as they plan fresh folliesit takes a pretty
                        clever man, Miss Talltowers, <pb id="VAA2432-117" n="104"/> to make a grand,
                        supreme, rip-roaring ass of himself, doesn&apos;t it? At least, I hope
                        so.&quot; And with that somewhat mysterious observation he left me
                        abruptly.</p>
                    <p>When I saw him and Nadeshda together so much at the ball I looked out for
                        Cyrus. He seemed bored, and devoted himself to wallflowers, but on the whole
                        was surprisingly unconcerned, apparently. I had him in sight almost the
                        whole evening. Jim Lafollette, who stuck to my train like a Japanese poodleI
                        told him so, but he didn&apos;t take the hintsaid that &quot;the
                        gawk,&quot; meaning Cyrus, was hanging round me. &quot;He&apos;s
                        moon-struck,&quot; said Jim. &quot;So your little put-up job with
                        Jessie seems to be doing nicely, thank you.&quot; I wonder why a man
                        assumes that the fact that he loves a woman gives him the <pb
                            id="VAA2432-118" n="105"/> right to insult her and makes it his duty to
                        do it. And I wonder why we women assent to that sort of impudence.
                        There&apos;s another conventionality that ought to be stamped out.</p>
                    <p>I find I was hasty in my judgment of Cyrus. He&apos;s a lot more of a man
                        than he led me to suppose at first. I think he might be licked into shape.
                        He ought to hunt up some widow or married woman older than himself and go to
                        school for a few seasons. But perhaps Nadeshda will do as well.</p>
                    <p>January 17. There were thirty-two at Senator Burke&apos;s
                        &quot;little informal breakfast&quot; yesterday morning, including
                        four of the leading Senators, two members of the Cabinet, an ambassador and
                        three ministers, several generals, half a dozen distinguished strangers,
                        four or five big financial men from New York who are <pb id="VAA2432-119"
                            n="106"/> here on &quot;private business&quot; with Congress,
                        and not a man who doesn&apos;t count for something except that wretched
                        little Framstern, who never misses anything free. And our regular weekly
                        informal dance was an equal success in its way. Senator Ritchie told me it
                        was amazing how Burke had forged to the front in influence and in
                        popularity. &quot;And now that the newspapers have begun to take him up
                        he&apos;ll soon be standing out before the whole country.&quot; So
                        my little suggestion about the wives and families of correspondents of the
                        big papers, which the Burkes adopted, is bearing fruit. And Mrs. Burke is so
                        genuinely friendly and hospitable that really I&apos;ve only to suggest
                        her being nice to somebody to set her to work. If she were the least bit of
                        a fraud I&apos;d not dareshe&apos;d only get into trouble.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-120" n="107"/>
                    <p>January 18. I was breakfasting alone in my sitting-room this morningI always
                        do an hour or so of work before I touch anything to eatwhen Mr. Gunton sent,
                        asking if he might join me. I was glad to have him. His direct way is
                        attractive, and he never talks without saying at least a few things I
                        haven&apos;t heard time and again. He was in riding clothes, and as soon
                        as I looked at him I saw he had something on his mind.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Good ride?&quot; I asked.</p>
                    <p>He made an impatient gesturewhenever he has anything to say and
                        doesn&apos;t know how to begin, the way to start him off is to make some
                        commonplace remark. It acts like a blow that knocks in the head of a full
                        barrel. &quot;I was out with the Baroness Daragane,&quot; he said,
                        &quot;with Nadeshda.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;And Cyrus?&quot; said I.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-121" n="108"/>
                    <p>He looked at me in astonishment, then laughed queerly. &quot;Oh,
                        bother!&quot; he exclaimed. &quot;Cyrus doesn&apos;t disturb
                        himself about <hi rend="i">her,</hi> or she about himand you know it. Miss
                        Talltowers, I love herand she loves me.&quot;</p>
                    <p>His tone was convincing. But, after the first shock, I couldn&apos;t
                        believe anything so preposterous. And I felt sorry for himan honest,
                        straight man, inexperienced with women, a fine mixture of gentleness and
                        roughness, at once too much and too little of a gentleman for Nadeshda. If I
                        had dared I should have tried to undeceive him. But I&apos;m not so
                        stupid as ever to try to make a person in love see the truth about the
                        person he or she&apos;s in love with. So I simply said: &quot;She is
                        a most fascinating woman.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;You think I&apos;m a fool,&quot; he went on, <pb
                            id="VAA2432-122" n="[]"/>
                        <figure entity="VAA2432-9"/>
                        <pb id="VAA2432-123" n="109"/> as if I hadn&apos;t spoken, &quot;and
                        I am aa blankety-blank fool. Did you see her night before last in that dress
                        of silver spangles like the wonderful skin of some amazing serpent? Did you
                        see her eyesher hairthe way her arms lookedas if they could wind themselves
                        round a man&apos;s neck and choke him to death while her eyes were
                        fooling him into thinking that such a death was greater happiness than to
                        live?&quot; He rolled this all out, then burst into a queer, crazy
                        laugh. &quot;You see, I&apos;m a lunatic!&quot; he said.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Yes, I see it,&quot; I replied cheerfully. &quot;But why do
                        you rave to me?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Because Iwehave got to tell somebody, and you&apos;re the only
                        person in Washington that I know that&apos;s both sensible and
                        experienced, wise enough to understand, beautiful enough to sympathize, <pb
                            id="VAA2432-124" n="110"/> and young enough to encourage.&quot;</p>
                    <p>That was rather good for a man who had had less than a month&apos;s real
                        experience with women, wasn&apos;t it? I recognized Nadeshda&apos;s
                        handiwork, and admired.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Miss Talltowers,&quot; he went on, &quot;I am going to make
                        a fool of myself, and she&apos;s going to help me.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;In what particular sort of folly are you about to embark?&quot;
                        said I.</p>
                    <p>&quot;We&apos;re going to marry,&quot; he replied.
                        &quot;We&apos;ve <hi rend="i">got</hi> to marry. I&apos;m afraid
                        of her and she&apos;s afraid of me, and we&apos;ll either have
                        Heaven or the other place when we do marryperhaps big doses of each
                        alternately. But we&apos;ve got to do it.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;You know it&apos;s impossible,&quot; said I.
                        &quot;Under the laws of her country she mayn&apos;t marry without
                        the consent of her parents. And they&apos;d never consent.&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-125" n="111"/>
                    <p>&quot;Certainly they won&apos;t,&quot; said he, &quot;unless
                        you can suggest some way of getting the ambassador and his wife round. We
                        want to give her people a chance.&quot; This with perfect coolness. I
                        began to believe that there must be something in it.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Does Nadeshda know you aren&apos;t rich?&quot; I asked.</p>
                    <p>&quot;She knows I have practically nothing. In fact I told her I had less
                        than I have.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;And you&apos;re sure she wishes to marry you?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Ask her.&quot;</p>
                    <p>He was quiet a while, then raved about her for ten minutes, begged me to do
                        my best thinking, and left me. I felt dazed. I simply couldn&apos;t
                        believe it. And the longer I thought, the more certain I was that she was
                        making some sort of grand play in coquetry, which <pb id="VAA2432-126"
                            n="112"/> seemed ridiculous enough when I considered what small game Mr.
                        Gunton is from the standpoint of a woman like Nadeshda.</p>
                    <p>In the afternoon I was in a flower store in Pennsylvania Avenue, and Nadeshda
                        joined me. Her surface was, if anything, cooler and subtler and more cynical
                        than usual. &quot;Send away your cab,&quot; said she, &quot;and
                        let me take you in my autowherever you wish.&quot;</p>
                    <p>As I was full of curiosity, I accepted instantly. When we were under way she
                        gave me a strange smilea slow parting of the lips, a slow half-closing and
                        elongation of those Eastern eyes which she inherits from a Russian
                        grandmother, I believe.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Well, Gus,&quot; she said, &quot;has that wild man told
                        you?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Yes, and you ought to be ashamed <pb id="VAA2432-127" n="[]"/>
                        <figure entity="VAA2432-10"/>
                        <pb id="VAA2432-128" n="113"/> of yourself,&quot; said I, a little
                        indignantly. &quot;It ain&apos;t fair to coax an innocent into <hi
                            rend="i">your</hi> sort of game and fleece him of his little
                        all.&quot;</p>
                    <p>She laughedbeautiful white teeth, cruel like her red lips.
                        &quot;It&apos;s all trueall he told you,&quot; she replied.
                        &quot;All true, on my honor.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Every season Washington&apos;s strange mixture of classes and conditions
                        and nations furnishes at least one sensation of some kind or other. But,
                        used as I am to surprises until they have ceased to surprise, this took me
                        quite aback. &quot;Do you love him, Nadeshdareally?&quot;</p>
                    <p>She quite closed her eyes and said in a strange, slow undertone:
                        &quot;He&apos;s my master. The blood in my veins flowed straight
                        from the savage wilderness. And he comes from there, and I don&apos;t
                        dare disobey him. I&apos;d do anything he said. <pb id="VAA2432-129"
                            n="114"/> And when we&apos;re married I&apos;ll never glance at
                        another manif he saw me he&apos;d kill me. Ah, you don&apos;t
                        understandyou&apos;re tootoo civilized. Now, I think I should love him
                        better if he&apos;d beat me.&quot;</p>
                    <p>I laughedit was too ridiculous, especially as she was plainly in earnest. She
                        laughed, too, and added: &quot;I think some day I&apos;ll try to
                        make him do it. He&apos;s afraid of me, too. And he may well be, for
                        Iwell, he belongs to <hi rend="i">me,</hi> you see, and I <hi rend="i"
                            >will</hi> have what&apos;s mine!&quot;</p>
                    <p>Yes, she wouldI believe her absolutely. And I must say I like her at last,
                        for all her extremely uncanny way of loving and of liking to be loved. I
                        suppose she&apos;s only a primeval womanI believe the primeval woman
                        fancied the lover who lay in wait and brought her down with a club. I begin
                        to understand <pb id="VAA2432-130" n="115"/> Robert Gunton, toothat is, the
                        side of his nature she&apos;s roused.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Do you believe us?&quot; she asked.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Yes, I do,&quot; said I, &quot;and I apologize to you.
                        I&apos;ve been thinking of you all along asfascinating, of course,
                        butmercenary.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Ah, but so I am!&quot; she exclaimed. &quot;It breaks my
                        heart to marry this poor manand of such a vulgar familyeven among you funny
                        Americans. But&quot;she threw up her arms and her shoulders and let them
                        drop in a gesture of tragicomic helplessness&quot;I must have him; I
                        must be his slave.&quot;</p>
                    <p>I can&apos;t imagine how it&apos;s going to end, as her people will
                        never let her marry him. Possibly, if &quot;ma&quot; Burke were to
                        persuade the Senator to settle a large sum on herbut that&apos;s wild,
                        even if Gunton would consent. I can imagine <pb id="VAA2432-131" n="116"/>
                        what a roar he&apos;d give if such a thing were proposed. He&apos;ll
                        insist on having her on his own terms. As if his insisting would do any
                        good!</p>
                    <p>The last thing she said to me was: &quot;Do you know when we became
                        engaged? Listen! It was the first time we metafter three hours. After one
                        hour he made me insult the men who came up to claim dances. After two hours
                        he made me say, &apos;I love you.&apos; After three hoursit was on
                        the way down to my carriagehe asked me to come into the little
                        reception-room by the entrance. And he closed the door and caught me in his
                        arms and kissed me. &apos;That makes you my wife,&apos; he said in a
                            <hi rend="i">dreadful</hi> voiceoh, it was<hi rend="i"
                        >magnifique!</hi>and he said, &apos;Do you understand?&apos;
                        And&quot;she smiled ravishingly and nodded her head &quot;I
                        understood.&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-132" n="117"/>
                    <p>I shan&apos;t sleep a wink to-night.</p>
                    <p>January 20. I wish they hadn&apos;t told me. If ever a man loves me and
                        wants to win me he must bewell, perhaps not exactly <hi rend="i">that,</hi>
                        but certainly not tame. I&apos;m not a bit like Nadeshda, but I do hate
                        the tame sort. I know what&apos;s the matter with me now. Yes, I wish
                        they hadn&apos;t told me.</p>
                    <p>January 21. Robert and Nadeshda have told &quot;ma&quot; Burke. She
                            is<hi rend="i">delighted!</hi> &quot;I never heard of the like, she
                        said to me all in a quiver. &quot;I wish I&apos;d known there were
                        such things. I reckon I&apos;d &apos;a&apos; made my Tom cut a
                        few capers before he got <hi rend="i">me.&quot;</hi> And then she
                        laughed until she cried. It certainly was droll to picture
                        &quot;pa&quot; capering in the Robert-Nadeshda fashion.</p>
                    <p>She went to the embassy and told Nadeshda&apos;s sister, Madame
                        l&apos;Ambassadrice. <pb id="VAA2432-133" n="118"/> &quot;She let on
                        as if she was just tickled to death,&quot; she reported to me a few
                        minutes after she returned. &quot;And when I told her that weTom and
                        Iwould do handsomely by Nadeshda as soon as they were married she had tears
                        in her eyes. But I don&apos;t trust hernor any other
                        foreigner.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Not even Nadeshda?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Ma&quot; nodded knowingly. &quot;I reckon Bob&apos;ll
                        keep her on the chalk,&quot; she replied. &quot;He&apos;s
                        started right, and in marriage, as in everything else, it&apos;s all in
                        the start.&quot;</p>
                    <p>January 22. Nadeshda asked Mrs. Burke to give a big costume ball, but I sat
                        on it hard. &quot;I don&apos;t think you want to do that, Mrs.
                        Burke,&quot; said I, when she proposed it to me. &quot;If this were
                        New York it wouldn&apos;t matter so much, though I don&apos;t think
                        really nice <pb id="VAA2432-134" n="119"/> people with means do that sort of
                        thing there. Here I&apos;m afraid it&apos;d make you very
                        unpopular.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Do you think so?&quot; said she. &quot;Now, I&apos;d
                        &apos;a&apos; said it was just the sort of foolishness these
                        people&apos;d like.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Those who have money would,&quot; I replied. &quot;But how
                        about those who haven&apos;t? Don&apos;t you think that people of
                        large means ought to make it a rule never to cause any expense whatever to
                        those of their friends and acquaintances who haven&apos;t
                        means?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Don&apos;t say another word!&quot; she exclaimed, seeing my
                        point instantly. &quot;Why, it&apos;d be the worst thing in the
                        world. Out home I&apos;ve always been careful about those kind of
                        things, but on here I don&apos;t know the people and am liable to forget
                        how they&apos;re circumstanced. They all seem so prosperous <pb
                            id="VAA2432-135" n="120"/> on the surface. I reckon there&apos;s a
                        lot of miserable pinching and squinching when the blinds are
                        down.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Cyrus happened to come in just then, and she told him all about it. He looked
                        at me and grew red and evidently tried to say somethingprobably something
                        that would have shown how poorly he thought of my cheating them all out of
                        the fun. But he restrained himself and said nothing.</p>
                    <p>Presently he went out and must have gone straight to his father probably to
                        remonstrate, though I may wrong himfor, after a few minutes, the Senator
                        came.</p>
                    <p>&quot;My son has just been telling me,&quot; he said to me,
                        &quot;and I agree with you entirely. It would be ruinous politically. As
                        it is, if it hadn&apos;t been for you we&apos;d never have been able
                        to keep both the <pb id="VAA2432-136" n="121"/> official and the fashionable
                        sets in a good humor with us.&quot; I never saw him so
                        &quot;flustered&quot; before.</p>
                    <p>&quot;What are you talking about, pa?&quot; inquired Mrs. Burke.</p>
                    <p>&quot;About the costume ball you were thinking of giving.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Burke smiled. &quot;You&apos;d better go back to your
                        cage,&quot; said she. &quot;That&apos;s settled and done for
                        long ago.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Pa&quot; looked more uneasy than his good-natured tone seemed
                        to justify but, no doubt, he knows when he has put his foot into it. He
                        &quot;faded&quot; from the room. When she heard his study door close
                        &quot;ma&quot; said to me in a complacent voice&quot;
                        &quot;There&apos;s nothing like keeping a man always to his side of
                        the fence. When &apos;pa&apos; began to get rich I saw trouble
                        ahead, for he was showing signs that he was thinking himself right <pb
                            id="VAA2432-137" n="122"/> smart better than the common run, and that he
                        was including his wife in the common run. I took Mr. Smartie Burke right in
                        hand. And so, with him it&apos;s never been &apos;I&apos; in
                        this family, but &apos;we.&apos; And keeping it that way has made
                        Tom lots happier than he would &apos;a&apos; been lording it over me
                        and having no control on his foolishness anywhere.&quot;</p>
                    <p>What a dear, sensible woman she is! He&apos;s got good brains, but if he
                        had as good brains as she has he&apos;d get what he&apos;s after and
                        doesn&apos;t stand a show for.</p>
                    <p>January 24. The whole town is in a tumult over Robert and Nadeshda. People
                        think she&apos;s crazy. When Cyrus said this to me I said: &quot;And
                        I think they areat least, delirious.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;A divine delirium, though,&quot; he replied, much to my
                        astonishment. For he&apos;s never shown before that he had so <pb
                            id="VAA2432-138" n="123"/> much as a spot of that sort of thing in him.
                        But then, I&apos;m beginning to revise my judgment of him in some ways.
                        He is much nearer what his mother said he was than what I thought him. But
                        he&apos;s young and crude. I find that he likesand really appreciatesthe
                        same composers and poets and novelists that I do. I can forgive much to any
                        one who realizes what a poet Browning waswhen he did write poetry, not when
                        he wrote the stuff for the Browning clubs to fuddle with.</p>
                    <p>Nadeshda is in the depthsexcept when Robert is by to hypnotize her.
                        &quot;I was so strong,&quot; she said pathetically to me to-day,
                        &quot;or I thought I was. And now I&apos;m all weakness.&quot;
                        She went on to tell me how horribly they are talking to her at the
                        embassyfor they are determined she shan&apos;t marry &quot;that <pb
                            id="VAA2432-139" n="124"/> nobody with nothing.&quot; I always knew
                        her brother-in-law was a snob of the cheapest and narrowest kindthe
                        well-born, well-bred kind. But I had no idea he was a coward. He threatens
                        to have the Emperor make her come home and go into a convent if she
                        doesn&apos;t break off the engagement within a week.</p>
                    <p>We are tremendously popular. Everybody is cultivating us, hoping to find out
                        the real inside of this incredible engagement. And the ambassador has to
                        pretend publicly that he&apos;s personally wild with delight and hopes
                        Nadeshda&apos;s parents will consent. He knows how unpopular it would
                        make him and his country with America if his opposition and his reason for
                        it were to be known.</p>
                    <p>January 30. Nadeshda has disappeared. They give out at the embassy that she
                        has left for home to consult <pb id="VAA2432-140" n="125"/> with her
                        parents. Robert looks like a man who had gone stark mad and was fighting to
                        keep himself from showing it.</p>
                    <p>We were all at the ball at the French embassy, Mr. and Mrs. Burke dining
                        there. I dined at the White Housea literary affair. The conversation was
                        what you might expect when a lot of people get together to show one another
                        how brilliant they are. The President talked a great deal. He has very
                        positive opinions on literature in all its branches. I was the only person
                        at the table who wasn&apos;t familiar with his books. Fortunately, I
                        wasn&apos;t cornered. Cyrus came to the ball from Mrs.
                        Dorringer&apos;s, where he took in the Duchess d&apos;Emarre.
                        &quot;She has a beautiful face in repose,&quot; he said to me as he
                        paused for a moment, &quot;and it&apos;s not at all pretty when she
                        talks. So she listened well.&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-141" n="126"/>
                    <p>I was too tired to dance, as were the others. We went home together, all
                        depressed. &quot;It&apos;s too ridiculous, this kind of
                        life,&quot; said &quot;ma&quot; Burke, &quot;and the most
                        ridiculous part of it is that, now we&apos;re hauled into it and set
                        a-going, we&apos;ll never get out and be sensible again. It just shows
                        you can get used to anything in this worldexcept doing as you please. I
                        don&apos;t believe anybody was ever satisfied to do that. Did you ever
                        wear a Mother Hubbard? <hi rend="i">There&apos;s</hi>
                        comfort!&quot;</p>
                    <p>I can think of nothing but Robert and Nadeshda. Have they some sort of
                        understanding? NoI&apos;m afraid not.</p>
                    <p>I forgot to put down that Robert made the Senator go to the Secretary of
                        State about Nadeshda&apos;s disappearance. The Secretary was
                        sympathetic, but he refused to interfere in any way. What else could he
                        do?</p>
                </div2>
                <pb id="VAA2432-142" n="127"/>
                <div2 type="chapter">
                    <head>V</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="b">F</hi>EBRUARY I. Last night Robert started for Europe. He is
                        going to see Nadeshda&apos;s father and mother. I begin to suspect that
                        Nadeshda has really gone abroad and that she has let him know. He is
                        certainly in a very different frame of mind from what he was at first. But
                        he says nothing, hints nothing. Rachel, who has a huge sentimental streak in
                        her, has given Robert a letter to her sister Ellenshe&apos;s married to
                        one of the biggest nobles in the empire, Prince Glckstein. Also, <pb
                            id="VAA2432-143" n="128"/> she has written Ellen a long, long letter,
                        telling her all about Robert, and what a great catch he is. And he <hi
                            rend="i">is</hi> a great catch now, for Senator Burke has organized a
                        company to take over his patents and pay him a big sum for
                        themit&apos;ll sound fabulously big to such people as the Daraganes. For
                        even where these foreigners are very rich and have miles on miles of land
                        and large incomes from it, they&apos;re not used to the kind of fortunes
                        we havethe sums in cash, or in property that&apos;s easily sold. And the
                        Daraganes have only rank; their estates are quite insignificant, Von
                        Slovatsky says.</p>
                    <p>&quot;They might as well consent first as last,&quot; said Mrs. Burke
                        to me just after Robert left; &quot;for Bob always gets what he wants.
                        He never lets go. Cyrus is the same wayhe spent eleven months <pb
                            id="VAA2432-144" n="129"/> in the mountains once, and like to
                        &apos;a&apos; starved and froze and died of fever, just because
                        he&apos;d made up his mind not to come back without a grizzly.
                        That&apos;s why the President took to him.&quot;</p>
                    <p>And then she told me that it was Cyrus who thought out the scheme for making
                        Robert financially eligible and put it in such form that Robert consented.
                        That convicted me of injustice again, for I had been suspecting him of being
                        secretly pleased at Robert&apos;s setbackhe certainly hasn&apos;t
                        looked in the least sorry for him. But it may be that Robert has told him
                        more than he&apos;s told us. He certainly couldn&apos;t have found a
                        closer-mouthed person. As his mother says, &quot;The grave&apos;s a
                        blabmouth beside him when it comes to keeping secrets. And most men are <hi
                            rend="i">such</hi> gossips.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Fortescue came in to tea this <pb id="VAA2432-145" n="130"/> afternoon.
                        Mrs. Burke was out calling, and I received heror, rather, she caught me, for
                        I detest her. Just as she was going Cyrus popped in, and she nailed him
                        before he could pop out. She thought it was a good chance to put in a few
                        strong strokes for her daughter. &quot;Of course, it&apos;s very
                        pretty and romantic about Nadeshda,&quot; she said, &quot;and in
                        this case I&apos;m sure no one with a spark of heart could object.
                        Still, the principle is bad. I don&apos;t think young girls who are
                        properly brought up are so impulsive and imprudent. I often say to my
                        husband that I think it&apos;s perfectly frightful the way girlsyoung
                        girlsgo about in Washington. They&apos;re out before they should be even
                        thinking of leaving the nursery, and go round practically unchaperoned.
                        It&apos;s so demoralizing.&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-146" n="131"/>
                    <p>&quot;But how are they to compete with the young married women if they
                        don&apos;t?&quot; said Cyrus, because he was evidently expected to
                        say something.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I don&apos;t think a mana <hi rend="i">sensible</hi> manlooking
                        for a wife for his home and a mother for his children would want a girl
                        who&apos;d been &apos;competing&apos; in Washington
                        society,&quot; she answered. &quot;I don&apos;t at all approve
                        the way American girls are brought up, anywayit&apos;s entirely too free
                        and destructive of the innocence that is a woman&apos;s chief charm. And
                        as for turning the young girls loose in Washington!&quot; Mrs. Fortescue
                        threw up her hands. &quot;It&apos;s simply madness. Most of the men
                        are foreigners, accustomed to meet only married women in society. They
                        don&apos;t know how to take a young girl, and they don&apos;t
                        understand this American freedom. The wonder to me <pb id="VAA2432-147"
                            n="132"/> is that we don&apos;t have a regular cataclysm every
                        season. Now, I never permit Mildred to go <hi rend="i">anywhere</hi> without
                        me or some other <hi rend="i">real</hi> chaperon. And I know that her mind
                        is like a fresh rose-leaf.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Cyrus and I exchanged a covert glance of amusement. Mildred Fortescue is a
                        very nice, sweet girl, butwell, she does fool her mother scandalously.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I should think a man would positively be <hi rend="i">afraid</hi>
                        to marry the ordinary Washington society girl who knows everything that she
                        shouldn&apos;t and nothing that she should.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Perhaps that&apos;s what makes them so irresistible,&quot;
                        said Cyrus.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Irresistible to flirt with and to <hi rend="i">flaner</hi> about
                        with,&quot; said Mrs. Fortescue reproachfully. &quot;But
                        I&apos;m sure you wouldn&apos;t marry one of them, Mr.
                        Burke.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Oh, I don&apos;t know,&quot; he answered. <pb
                            id="VAA2432-148" n="133"/> &quot;No doubt it does spoil a good many,
                        being so free and associating with experienced men who&apos;ve been
                        brought up in a very different way. But&quot;he hesitated and blushed
                        uncomfortably&quot;it seems to me that those who do come through all
                        right are about the best anywhere. If a girl has any really bad qualities
                        anywhere in her they come out here. And if a Washington girl does marry a
                        manfor himselfand I rather think they make marriages of the heart more than
                        most girls in the same sort of society in other citiesdon&apos;t you,
                        Miss Talltowers?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;It may be so,&quot; I replied. &quot;But probably
                        they&apos;re much like girlsand meneverywhere. They make marriages of
                        the heart if they get the chance. And if nobody happens along in the
                        marrying mood who is able to appeal to their <pb id="VAA2432-149" n="134"/>
                        hearts, they select the most eligible among the agreeable ones they can get.
                        I think many a girl has been branded as mercenary when in reality the rich
                        man she chose was neither more nor less agreeable than the poor man she
                        rejected, and she only had choice among men she didn&apos;t especially
                        care about.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Fortescue looked disgusted. Cyrus showed that he agreed with me.
                        &quot;What I was going to say,&quot; he went on, &quot;was, that
                        if a Washington girl does choose a man, after she has known lots of men and
                        has come to prefer him, she&apos;s not likelyat least, not <hi rend="i"
                            >so</hi> likelyto repent her bargain. And,&quot; he said, getting
                        quite warmed up by his subject, &quot;if a man looks forward to his
                        wife&apos;s going about in society, as he must if he lives in a certain
                        way, I think he&apos;s wise to select some one who has learned <pb
                            id="VAA2432-150" n="135"/> something of the worldhow to conduct herself,
                        how to control herself, how to fill the rle Fate has assigned
                        her.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Oh, of course, a girl should be well-bred,&quot; said Mrs.
                        Fortescue, as sourly as her sort of woman can speak to a bachelor with
                        prospects.</p>
                    <p>Cyrus said no more, and soon she was off. He stood at the window watching her
                        carriage drive away. He turned abruptlyI was at the little desk, writing a
                        note.</p>
                    <p>&quot;You can&apos;t imagine,&quot; he said with quick energy,
                        &quot;how I loathe the average girl brought up in conventional,
                        exclusive society in America.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Really?&quot; said I, not stopping my writingthough I
                        don&apos;t mind confessing that I was more interested in his views than
                        I cared to let him see.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-151" n="136"/>
                    <p>&quot;Yes, really,&quot; he replied ironically. Then he went on in
                        his former tone: &quot;Poor things, they can&apos;t help having
                        silly mothers with the idea of aping the European upper classes, and with
                        hardly a notion of those upper classes beyondwell, such notions as are got
                        in novels written by snobs for snobs. And these unfortunate girls are afraid
                        of a genuine emotionby Jove, I doubt if they even have the germs of genuine
                        emotion. All that sort of thing has been weeded out of them. Little dry
                        minds, little dry heartsso &apos;proper,&apos;
                        sovulgar!&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Not in Washington,&quot; said I.</p>
                    <p>&quot;No, not so many in Washington; though more and more all the time.
                        Miss Talltowers, will you marry me?&quot;</p>
                    <p>It was just like thatno warning, not a touch of sentiment toward me. I almost
                        dropped my pen. But I managed <pb id="VAA2432-152" n="137"/> to hide myself
                        pretty well. I simply went on with my note, finished it, sealed and
                        addressed it, and rang for a servant. Then I went and stood by the fire. The
                        servant came; I gave him the note and went into my office. I had been in
                        there perhaps ten minutes when he came, looking shy and sheepish. He
                        stumbled over a low chair and had a ridiculous time saving himself from
                        falling. When he finally had himself straightened up and shaken together he
                        stood with his hands behind him, and his face red, and his eyes down, and
                        with his mouth fixed in that foolish little way as if he were about to speak
                        with his fancy-work way of handling his words.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Do you wish something?&quot; I asked.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Onlyonly my answer,&quot; said he humbly.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-153" n="138"/>
                    <p>Would you believe it, I actually hesitated.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I want a woman that doesn&apos;t like me for my money, and that
                        at the same time would know how to act and would bebe sensible.
                        I&apos;ve had you in mind ever since you explained your system
                        forfor&quot;he smiled faintly&quot;exploiting mother and father. And
                        mother has been talking in the same way of late. She says we can&apos;t
                        afford to let you get out of the family. That&apos;s all, I guessall
                        you&apos;d have patience to hear.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Then you were making me a serious business proposition?&quot;
                        said I.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Well, you might call it that,&quot; he admitted, as if he
                        weren&apos;t altogether satisfied with my way of summing it up.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I&apos;m much obliged, but it doesn&apos;t attract
                        me,&quot; I said.</p>
                    <p>He gave a kind of hopeless gesture. <pb id="VAA2432-154" n="139"/>
                        &quot;I&apos;ve put it all wrong,&quot; said he. &quot;I
                        always <hi rend="i">say</hi> things wrong. ButII believe I <hi rend="i"
                            >do</hi> things better.&quot; And he gave me a look that I liked. It
                        was such a quaint mingling of such a nice man with such a nice boy.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I understand perfectly,&quot; said I, and I can&apos;t tell
                        how much I hated to hurt himhe did so remind me of dear old
                        &quot;ma&quot; Burke. &quot;Butplease don&apos;t discuss it.
                        I couldn&apos;t consider the matterpossibly.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;You won&apos;t leave!&quot; he exclaimed. &quot;I
                        assure you I&apos;ll not annoy you. You must admit, Miss Talltowers,
                        that I haven&apos;t tried to thrustmyself on you in the past. Andreally,
                        mother and father couldn&apos;t get on at all without you.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Certainly, I shan&apos;t leavewhy should I?&quot; said I.
                        &quot;I&apos;m very well satisfied with my position.&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-155" n="140"/>
                    <p>&quot;Thank you,&quot; he said with an awkward bow, and he left me
                        alone.</p>
                    <p>Of course, I couldn&apos;t possibly marry him. But I suppose a
                        woman&apos;s vanity compels her to take a more favorable view of any man
                        after she&apos;s found out that he wishes to marry her. Anyhow, I find I
                        don&apos;t dislike him at all as I thought I did. I couldn&apos;t
                        help being amused at myself the next day. I was driving with Jessie, and she
                        was giving me her usual sermon on the advantages of the Burke allianceif I
                        could by chance scheme it through. &quot;You&apos;re very pretty,
                        Gus,&quot; she said. &quot;In fact you&apos;re beautiful at
                        times. Men do like height when it goes with your sort of aa willowy figure.
                        Your eyes aloneif you would only <hi rend="i">use</hi> themwould catch him.
                        And the Burkes would bewell, they might object a little at first <pb
                            id="VAA2432-156" n="141"/> because you&apos;ve given them a position
                        that has no doubt swollen their headsbut they&apos;d yield gracefully.
                        And although you are very attractive and are always having men in love with
                        you, you&apos;ve simply got to make up your mind soon. Look how many
                        such nice, good-looking girls have been crowded aside by the young ones. Men
                        are crazy about freshness, no matter what they pretend. Yes, you must
                        decide, dear. AndI couldn&apos;t <hi rend="i">endure</hi> poor Carteret
                        when I married him.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Carteret is a miserable specimen, and Jessie&apos;s ways keep him in a
                        dazed statelike an old hen sitting on a limb and turning her head round and
                        round to keep watch on a fox that&apos;s racing in a circle underneath.
                        Fox doesn&apos;t seem exactly to fit Jessie, but sometimes I
                        suspecthowever</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-157" n="142"/>
                    <p>&quot;But,&quot; Jessie was going on, &quot;I knew mama was my
                        best friend. And when she said, &apos;Six months after marriage
                        you&apos;ll be quite used to him and won&apos;t in the least mind,
                        and you&apos;ll be so glad you married somebody who was quiet and
                        good,&apos; I married him. And I love him dearly, Gus, and we make each
                        other <hi rend="i">so</hi> happy!&quot;</p>
                    <p>I laughedJessie doesn&apos;t mind; she don&apos;t understand what
                        laughter means in most people. I was thinking of what Rachel told me the
                        other day. She said to Carteret, &quot;It must be great fun wondering
                        what Jessie will do next.&quot; And he looked at her in his dumb way and
                        said: &quot;What she&apos;ll do <hi rend="i">next?</hi> Lord, I
                        ain&apos;t caught up with <hi rend="i">that.</hi> I&apos;m just
                        about six weeks behind on her record all the time.&quot;</p>
                    <p>But to go back to Jessie&apos;s talk to me, <pb id="VAA2432-158" n="143"
                        /> she went on: &quot;And Mr. Burke&apos;s not so dreadfully
                        unattractive, dear. Of course, he&apos;s far from handsome, andwell,
                        he&apos;s the son of Mr. and Mrs. Burkebut though they&apos;re quite
                        common and all that&quot;</p>
                    <p>I found myself furiously angry. &quot;I don&apos;t think
                        he&apos;s at all bad-looking,&quot; I said, pretending to be
                        judicial. &quot;He&apos;s big and strong and sensible; and what more
                        does a woman usually ask for? And I don&apos;t at all agree with you
                        about his father and mother, eitherespecially his mother. No, Jessie, dear,
                        my objections aren&apos;t yours at all. I&apos;m sure you
                        wouldn&apos;t understand them, so let&apos;s not talk about
                        it.&quot;</p>
                    <p>February 3. Yesterday Mrs. Tevis sent for me. That was a good deal of an
                        impertinence, but I&apos;m getting very sensible about impertinences.
                        She lives <pb id="VAA2432-159" n="144"/> in grand style in a big, new house
                        in K Streetit, like everything about her, is &quot;regardless of
                        expense.&quot; The Tevises have been making the most desperate efforts
                        to &quot;break in&quot; last season and this, and as Washington is,
                        up to a certain point, very easy for strangers with money, they&apos;ve
                        gone pretty far. I suppose Washington&apos;s like every other capitalthe
                        people are so used to all sorts of queer strangers and everything is so
                        restless and changeful that no one minds adding to his list of acquaintances
                        any person who offers entertainment and isn&apos;t too appalling. And
                        the Tevises have been spending money like water.</p>
                    <p>It&apos;s queer how people can go every-where that anybody goes and can
                        seem to be &quot;right in it,&quot; yet not be in it at all.
                        That&apos;s the way it is with the Tevises. They are at every big affair
                        in town <pb id="VAA2432-160" n="145"/> White House, embassies, private
                        houses. But they&apos;re never invited to the smaller, more or less
                        informal things. And when they do appear at a ball or anywhere
                        they&apos;re treated with formal politeness. They know there&apos;s
                        something wrong, but they can&apos;t for the life of them see what it
                        is. And that&apos;s not strange, for who can see the line
                        that&apos;s instinctively drawn between social sheep and social goats in
                        the flock that&apos;s apparently all mixed up? Everybody knows the sheep
                        on sight; everybody knows the goats. And all act accordingly without
                        anything being said.</p>
                    <p>Well, Mr. and Mrs. Tevis are goats. Why? Anybody could see it after talking
                        to either of them for five minutes; yet who could say why? It isn&apos;t
                        because they&apos;re snobslots of sheep are nauseating snobs. It
                        isn&apos;t because they&apos;re very <pb id="VAA2432-161" n="146"/>
                        badly self-madeI defy anybody to produce a goat that can touch Willie
                        Catesby or Rennie Tucker, yet each of them has ancestors by the score. It
                        isn&apos;t because they&apos;re newthe Burkes are new, yet Mrs.
                        Burke has at least a dozen intimate acquaintances of the right sort. It
                        isn&apos;t because they&apos;re ostentatious and boastful about
                        wealth and pricesthere are scores of sheep who make the same sort of absurd
                        exhibition of vulgarity. I can&apos;t place it. They&apos;re just
                        goats, and they know it, and they feel it; and when you go to their house
                        they suggest a restaurant keeper welcoming his customers; and when they come
                        to your house they suggest Cook&apos;s tourists roaming in the private
                        apartments of a palace, smiling apologetically at every one and wondering
                        whether they&apos;re not about to be told to &quot;step
                        lively.&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-162" n="147"/>
                    <p>Mrs. Tevis received me very grandly and graciously, though dreadfully nervous
                        withal, lest I should be seeing that she was &quot;throwing a
                        bluff&quot; and should put her in her place.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I&apos;ve requested you to come, my dear Miss
                        Talltowers,&quot; she began, after she had bunglingly served tea from
                        the newest and costliest and most elaborate tea-set I ever saw,
                        &quot;because I had a little matter of business to talk over with you
                        and felt that we could talk more freely here.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;I must be back at half-past five,&quot; said I, by way of
                        urging her on to the point.</p>
                    <p>&quot;That will be quite time enough,&quot; said she. &quot;We
                        can have our little conversation quite nicely, and you will be in ample time
                        for your duties.&quot;</p>
                    <p>I wonder what sort of dialect she <pb id="VAA2432-163" n="148"/>
                        <hi rend="i">thinks</hi> in. It certainly can&apos;t be more irritating
                        than the one she translates her thoughts into before speaking them. The
                        dialect she inflicts on people sounds as if it were from a Complete
                        Conversationalist, got up by an old maid who had been teaching school for
                        forty years.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I have decided to take a secretary for next season,&quot; she
                        went on. &quot;Not that I need any such direction as the Burkes.
                        Fortunately, Mr. Tevis and I have had a large social experience on both
                        sides of the Atlantic and have always moved with the best people. But just a
                        secretaryto attend to my onerous correspondence and arrangements for
                        entertaining. The duties would be light, but we should be willing to pay a
                        larger salary than the position would really justifythat is, we should be
                        willing <pb id="VAA2432-164" n="149"/> to pay it, you know, to a <hi
                            rend="i">lady</hi> such as you are.&quot;</p>
                    <p>I bowed.</p>
                    <p>&quot;We should treat you with all delicacy and appreciation of the fact
                        that your misfortunes have compelled you to take
                        aapositionwhichwhich&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;You are very kind, Mrs. Tevis,&quot; said I.</p>
                    <p>&quot;And we realized that in all probability the Burkes would have no
                        further use for your services at the end of this season, as you have been
                        most successful with them.&quot;</p>
                    <p>I winced. For the first time the &quot;practical&quot; view of what
                        I&apos;ve been doing for the Burkes stared me in the facethat is, the
                        view which such people as the Tevises, perhaps many of my friends, took of
                        it. So I was being regarded, spoken of, discussed, as a person <pb
                            id="VAA2432-165" n="150"/> who had been bought by the Burkes to get them
                        in with certain people. And it was assumed that, having got what they
                        wanted, they would dismiss me and so cut off a superfluous expense! I was
                        somewhat astonished at myself for not having seen my position in this light
                        before.</p>
                    <p>And I suddenly realized why I hadn&apos;tbecause the Burkes were really
                        nice people, because I hadn&apos;t been their employee but their friend.
                        What if I had started my career as a dependent of Mrs. Tevis&apos;! I
                        shivered. And when the Burkes should need me no longerwhy, the probabilities
                        were that I should have to seek employment from just such dreadful people as
                        theseupstarts eager to jam themselves in, vulgarians whom icy manners and
                        forbidding looks only influence to fiercer efforts to associate with those
                            <pb id="VAA2432-166" n="151"/> who don&apos;t wish to associate with
                        them.</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Tevis interrupted my dismal thoughts with a cough, intended to be
                        polite. &quot;Whatwhatcompensation would you expect, may I
                        ask?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;What do such positions pay?&quot; I said, and my voice sounded
                        harsh to me. I wished to know what value was usually put upon such
                        services.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Wouldsaytwenty-five dollars a week bemeet with your
                        views?&quot; she asked, and her tone was that of a person performing an
                        act of astounding generosity.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Oh, dear me, no,&quot; said I, with the kind of sweetness that
                        coats a pill of gall. &quot;I couldn&apos;t think of trying to get
                        you in for any such sum as that.&quot;</p>
                    <p>I saw that the gall had bit through the sugar-coat.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Would you object to giving me some <pb id="VAA2432-167" n="152"/>
                        idea of what the Burkes pay?&quot; she asked, with the taste puckering
                        her mouth.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I should,&quot; I replied, rising. &quot;Anyhow, I
                        don&apos;t care to undertake the job. Thank you so much for your
                        generosity and kindness, Mrs. Tevis.&quot; I noddedI&apos;m afraid
                        it was a nod intended to &quot;put her in her place.&quot;
                        &quot;Good-by.&quot; And I smiled and got myself out of the room
                        before she recovered.</p>
                    <p>I <hi rend="i">wish</hi> I hadn&apos;t seen her. I hate the
                        truthit&apos;s always unpleasant.</p>
                    <p>February 5. Mrs. Burke had thirty-one invitations to-day, eleven of them for
                        her and Mr. Burke. Seven were invitations to little affairs which Mrs. Tevis
                        would givewell, perhaps five dollars apieceto get to. How ridiculous for her
                        to economize in the one way in which liberality is most necessary. Here they
                        are spending probably <pb id="VAA2432-168" n="[]"/>
                        <figure entity="VAA2432-11"/>
                        <pb id="VAA2432-169" n="153"/> a hundred thousand dollars a season in
                        hopeless attempts to do that which they would hesitate to pay me six hundred
                        dollars for doing. And this when they think I could accomplish it. But could
                        I? I guess not. To win out as I have with the Burkes you&apos;ve got to
                        have the right sort of material to work on, and it must be workable. Vulgar
                        people would be ashamed to put themselves in any one&apos;s hands as
                        completely as Mrs. Burke put herself in my hands.</p>
                    <p>Oh, I&apos;m sicksick, sick of it! I&apos;m ashamed to look
                        &quot;ma&quot; Burke in the face, because I think such mean things
                        about them all when I&apos;m in bed and blue.</p>
                    <p>February 6. I decline all the invitations that come for me personally. I sit
                        in my &quot;office&quot; and pretend to be fussing with my booksthey
                        give me the horrors! And I was so proud of them and <pb id="VAA2432-170"
                            n="154"/> of my plans to make my little enterprise a success.</p>
                    <p>February 7. Mrs. Burke came in this afternoon and came round my desk and
                        kissed me. &quot;What is it, dear? What&apos;s the matter?&quot;
                        she said. &quot;Won&apos;t you tell <hi rend="i">me?</hi> Why, I
                        feel as if you were my daughter. I did have a daughter. She came first. Tom
                        was so disappointed. But I was glad. A son belongs to both his parents, and,
                        when he&apos;s grown up, to his wife. But a daughtershe would
                        &apos;a&apos; belonged to me always. And she had to up and die just
                        when she was about to make up her mind to talk.&quot;</p>
                    <p>I put my face down in my arms on the desk.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Tired, dear?&quot; said &quot;ma&quot;she&apos;s a
                        born &quot;ma.&quot; &quot;Of course, that&apos;s it.
                        You&apos;re clean pegged out, working and worrying. <pb id="VAA2432-171"
                            n="155"/> You must put it all away and rest.&quot; And she sat down
                        by me.</p>
                    <p>All of a suddenI couldn&apos;t help itI put my head on her great, big
                        bosom and burst out crying. &quot;Oh, I&apos;m so <hi rend="i"
                            >bad!&quot;</hi> I said. &quot;And you&apos;re so <hi
                            rend="i">good!&quot;</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>She patted me and kissed me on top of my head. &quot;What pretty, soft
                        hair you have, dear,&quot; she said, &quot;and what a lot of it! My!
                        My! I don&apos;t see how anybody that looks like you do could ever be
                        unhappy a minute. You don&apos;t know what it means to be born homely
                        and fat and to have to work hard just to make people not object to having
                        you about.&quot; And she went on talking in that way until I was
                        presently laughing, still against that great, big bosom with the great, big
                        heart beating under it. When I felt that it would be a downright imposition
                        to stay there any longer <pb id="VAA2432-172" n="156"/> I straightened up. I
                        felt quite cheerful.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Was there something worrying you?&quot; she asked.</p>
                    <p>I blushed and hung my head. &quot;Yes, but I can&apos;t tell
                        you,&quot; said I. And I couldn&apos;tcould I? Besides, there
                        somehow doesn&apos;t seem to be much of anything in all my brooding.
                        What a nasty beast that Mrs. Tevis is!</p>
                    <p>February 12. Mrs. Burke and I went to a reception at the Secretary of
                        State&apos;s this afternoon. We saw Nadeshda&apos;s sister in the
                        distancethat&apos;s where we&apos;ve always seen her and the
                        ambassador and the whole embassy staff ever since the
                        &quot;bust-up,&quot; except funny little De Pleyev. He, being of a
                        mediatized family, does not need to disturb himself about ambassadorial
                        frowns or smiles. It&apos;s curious what a strong resemblance there is
                        between a foreigner of royal blood and <pb id="VAA2432-173" n="157"/> a
                        straightaway American gentleman. But, as I was about to write, this
                        afternoon the distance between us and Madame l&apos;Ambassadrice slowly
                        lessened, and when she was quite close to us she gave us a dazzling smile
                        apiece and said to Mrs. Burke: &quot;My dear Madame Burke, you are
                        looking most charming. You must come to us to tea. To-morrow? Do say
                        yeswe&apos;ve missed you so. My poor backit almost shuts me out of the
                        world.&quot; And she passed onprobably didn&apos;t wish to risk the
                        chance that &quot;ma&apos;s&quot; puzzled look might give place
                        to an expression of some kind of anger and that she might make one of those
                        frank speeches she&apos;s famous for.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Well, did you <hi rend="i">ever!&quot;</hi> exclaimed
                        &quot;ma&quot; when the Countess was out of earshot.</p>
                    <p>I said warningly: &quot;Everybody&apos;s seen <pb id="VAA2432-174"
                            n="158"/> it and is watching you.&quot; And it was true. The whole
                        crowd in those perfume-steeped rooms was gaping, and the news had spread so
                        quickly that a throng was pushing in from the tea-room, some of them still
                        chewing.</p>
                    <p>Afterward we discussed it, and could come to but one conclusionthat the
                        Robert-Nadeshda crisis had passed. Butdo the Daraganes think that Nadeshda
                        is safe from Robert, or have they decided to take him in? Certainly, <hi
                            rend="i">something</hi> decisive has happened. And if Robert had
                        anything to do with it it must have been stirring enough to make the
                        Daraganes use the cablehow else could Nadeshda&apos;s sister have got
                        her cue so soon?</p>
                    <p>February 15. No news whatever of Robert and Nadeshda. Yesterday the
                        ambassadress came here to tea and said <pb id="VAA2432-175" n="159"/> to
                        Mrs. Burke that she had had a letter from Nadeshda in which she sent us all
                        her love&quot;especially your dear, splendid, big Monsieur
                        Cyrus.&quot; Mr. and Mrs. Burke are to dine at the embassy five weeks
                        from to-nightthe ambassadress insisted on Mrs. Burke&apos;s giving her
                        first free evening to her, and that was it.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I reckon we&apos;ll have to go,&quot; said
                        &quot;ma&quot; after her departure, and while the odor of her
                        frightfully-powerful heliotrope scent was still heavy in the room,
                        &quot;though I doubt if I&apos;ll be alive by then. Sometimes it
                        seems to me I&apos;ve just got to knock off and take a clean week in
                        bed. I thought I&apos;d never think of drugs to keep me going, as so
                        many women advise. But I see I&apos;m getting round to it. And
                        I&apos;m getting <hi rend="i">that</hi> fat in the body and <hi rend="i"
                            >that</hi> lean in the face! Did you ever <pb id="VAA2432-176" n="160"/>
                        see that like? I must &apos;a&apos; lost three pounds off my face.
                        And the skin&apos;s hanging there waiting for it to come back, instead
                        of shrinking. I&apos;m glad my Tom never looks at me. I know to a
                        certainty he ain&apos;t looked at me in twenty years. Husbands and wives
                        don&apos;t waste much time looking at each other, and I guess
                        it&apos;s a good, safe plan.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Burke does look badly. I must take better care of her. Cyrus looks
                        badly, too. I haven&apos;t seen him to talk to since he made his
                        &quot;strictly business&quot; proposition. I suppose he wants me to
                        realize that he isn&apos;t one of the pestering kind. I&apos;m sorry
                        he takes it that way, as I&apos;d have liked to be friends with him. He
                        quarreled so beautifully when we didn&apos;t agree. It&apos;s a
                        great satisfaction to have some one at hand who both agrees and quarrels in
                        a satisfactory way. But <pb id="VAA2432-177" n="161"/> I don&apos;t dare
                        make any advances to him. He might misunderstand.</p>
                    <p>I&apos;ve just been laughingat his cowlick. It <hi rend="i">is</hi> such
                        an obstinate little swirl. And when he looks serious it looks so funnily
                        frisky, and when he smiles it looks so fiercely serious and disapproving.
                        Yesterday I hurried suddenly into the little room just off the ball-room,
                        thinking it was empty. But Cyrus and his mother were there, and he was
                        tickling her, and he looked so fond of her, and she looked so delighted. I
                        slipped away without their seeing me.</p>
                    <p>February 16. We gave our second big ball last night with a dinner for sixty
                        before. It was just half-past five this morning when the last couple came
                        sneaking out from the alcove off the little room beyond the conservatory
                        and, we pretending not to see them, scuttled <pb id="VAA2432-178" n="162"/>
                        away without saying good night. Major-General Cutler danced with Mrs. Burke
                        in the opening quadrille, and Mr. Burke danced with the British
                        ambassadressthe ambassador is ill. I had Jim on my hands most of the
                        eveningthough I was flirting desperately with little D&apos;Estourelle,
                        he hung to me with a maddening husbandish air of proprietorship. I
                        don&apos;t see how I ever endured him, much less thought of marrying
                        him. Cyrus Burke is a king beside him. Excuse me from men who think the fact
                        that they&apos;ve done a woman the honor of loving her gives them a
                        property right to her. Mrs. Burke was the belle of the ball. She had a crowd
                        of men round her chair all evening, laughing at everything she said.</p>
                    <p>February 17. A cable from Robert Gunton at Hamburg this morning <pb
                            id="VAA2432-179" n="163"/> just &quot;Arrive Washington about March
                        3.&quot; That was allworse than nothing. It is Lent, but
                        there&apos;s no let up for us. We only get rid of the kind of
                        entertainments that cost us the least trouble to plan and give, and we have
                        to arrange more of the kind that have to be done carefully. Anybody can give
                        a dance, but it takes skill to give a successful dinner.</p>
                    <p>February 19. Nadeshda&apos;s sister said to-day, quite casually, to
                        Jessie: &quot;Deshda&apos;s coming back, and we&apos;re so glad.
                        The trip has done her <hi rend="i">so</hi> much goodin every way.&quot;
                        Now, whatever did <hi rend="i">that</hi> mean?</p>
                </div2>
                <pb id="VAA2432-180" n="164"/>
                <div2 type="chapter">
                    <head>VI</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="b">F</hi>EBRUARY 26. No news of Robert and Nadeshda. Have been
                        glancing through this diary. How conceited I am, taking credit to myself for
                        everything. I wonder if I am vainer than most people, or does everybody make
                        the same ridiculous discovery about himself when he takes himself off his
                        guard? What an imperfect record this is of our launching. But then, if I had
                        made it perfect I should have had to go into so many wearisome details, not
                        to speak of my having so <pb id="VAA2432-181" n="165"/> little time. Still,
                        it would have been interesting to read some day, when I shall have forgotten
                        the little stepsfor although we&apos;ve had in all only a month before
                        the season and five weeks between New Year&apos;s and Ash Wednesday, so
                        much has been crowded into that time. It&apos;s amazing what one can
                        accomplish if one uses every moment to a single purpose. And I&apos;ve
                        not only used my own time, but Robert&apos;s and Jessie&apos;s and
                        the time of their and my friends, and that of Nadeshda and a dozen other
                        people. They and I all worked together to make my enterprise a successand
                        Jim and the Senator, and &quot;ma&quot; Burke was a great help after
                        the first few weeks. Yes, and I mustn&apos;t forget Cyrus. He has made
                        himself astonishingly popular. I see now that he showed a better side to
                        every one than he did to me. <pb id="VAA2432-182" n="166"/> Perhaps I can
                        guess why. I wonder if he really cares or did carefor me, or was it just
                        &quot;ma&quot; trying to get me into the family, and he willing to
                        do anything she asked of him?</p>
                    <p>But to go back to my vanityI see that Jessie, Rachel and Cyrus were the real
                        cause of my success. Jessie and Rachel alone could make anybody, who
                        wasn&apos;t positively awful, a go. Then Nadeshda, bent on marrying
                        Cyrus at first, was a big helpand every mama with a marriageable daughter
                        was hot on Cyrus&apos; trail. So it&apos;s easy to make an
                        infallible recipe for getting into society: First, wealth; second,
                        willingness to act on competent advice; third, get a
                        &quot;secretary&quot; who knows society and has intimate friends in
                        its most exclusive set, and who also knows how to arrange entertainments;
                        fourth, have a <pb id="VAA2432-183" n="167"/> marriageable son, if possible,
                        or, failing that, a daughter, or, failing that, a near relative who will be
                        well dowered; fifth, organize the campaign thoroughly and pay particular
                        attention to getting yourself liked by the few people who really count. You
                        can&apos;t bribe them; you can&apos;t drive them; you must <hi
                            rend="i">amuse</hi> them. The more leisure people have the harder it is
                        to amuse them.</p>
                    <p>Looking back, I can see that &quot;ma&quot; Burke passed her social
                        crisis when, on January 5, Mrs. Gaether asked her to assist at her
                        reception. For Mrs. Gaether was the first social power who took
                        &quot;ma&quot; up simply and solely because she liked her.</p>
                    <p>We have spent a great deal of money, but not half what the Tevises have
                        spent. But our money counted because it was incidental. Mere money
                        won&apos;t carry any <pb id="VAA2432-184" n="168"/> one very far in
                        WashingtonI don&apos;t believe it will anywhere, except, perhaps, in New
                        York.</p>
                    <p>I ought to have kept some sort of record of what we&apos;ve done from day
                        to dayI mean, more detailed than my books. However, I&apos;ll just put
                        in our last full day before Lent, as far as I can recall it. No,
                        I&apos;ll only write out what Mrs. Burke alone did that day:</p>
                    <p>7:30 to 10. She and I, in her room, went over the arrangements for the ball
                        we were giving in the evening.</p>
                    <p>10 to 12:30. She went to see half a dozen people about various social
                        matters, besides doing a great of deal shopping.</p>
                    <p>12:30 to 1:45. More worrying consultation with me, then dressing for
                        luncheon.</p>
                    <p>1:45 to 3:45. A long and tiresome luncheon at one of the embassies.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-185" n="169"/>
                    <p>3:45 to 6:30. More than twenty calls and teasa succession of exhausting
                        rushes and struggles.</p>
                    <p>6:30 to 7:15. In the drawing-room here, with a lot of people coming and
                        going.</p>
                    <p>7:15 to 8. Dressing for dinnera frightful rush.</p>
                    <p>8 to 8:30. Receiving the dinner guests.</p>
                    <p>8:30 to 10:45. The dinner.</p>
                    <p>10:45 to midnight. Receiving the guests for the danceon her feet all the
                        time.</p>
                    <p>Midnight to 6 in the morning. Sitting, but incessantly busy.</p>
                    <p>6 to 9. In bed.</p>
                    <p>9. A new and crowded day.</p>
                    <p>This has been a short season, but I don&apos;t think it was the
                        shortness, crowding much into a few days, that made <pb id="VAA2432-186"
                            n="170"/> the pressure so great. It&apos;s simply that year by year
                        Washington becomes socially worse and worse. As I looked round at that last
                        ball of ours I pitied the people who were nerving themselves up to trying to
                        enjoy themselves.</p>
                    <p>Almost every one was, and looked, worn out. Here and there the unnatural
                        brightness of eyes or cheeks showed that somebodyusually a young personhad
                        been driven to some sort of stimulant to enable him or her to hold the pace.
                        Quick to laugh; quick to frown and bite the lips in almost uncontrollable
                        anger. Nerves on edge, flesh quivering.</p>
                    <p>Yet, what is one to do? To be &quot;in it&quot; one must go all the
                        time; not to go all the time, not to accept all the principal invitations,
                        is to make enemies right and left. Besides, who that gets <pb
                            id="VAA2432-187" n="171"/> into the hysterical state which the
                        Washington season induces can be content to sit quietly at home when on
                        every side there are alluring opportunities to enjoy?</p>
                    <p>No wonder we see less and less of the men of importance. No wonder the
                        &quot;sons of somebodies&quot; and the young men of the embassies
                        and legations and departments, most of them amiable enough, but all just
                        about as near nothing as you would naturally expect, are the best the women
                        can get to their houses.</p>
                    <p>It is foolish; it is frightful. But it is somehow fascinating, and it gives
                        us women the chance to go the same reckless American gait that the men go in
                        their business and professions.</p>
                    <p>I am utterly worn out. I might be asleep at this moment. Yet I&apos;m
                        sitting here alone, too feverish for hope of rest. <pb id="VAA2432-188"
                            n="172"/> And I can see lights in Cyrus&apos; apartment and in
                        Senator Burke&apos;s sitting-room, and I don&apos;t doubt poor
                        &quot;ma&quot; is tossing miserably in a vain attempt to get the
                        sleep that used to come unasked and stay until it was fought off.</p>
                    <p>It is Lent, and the season is supposed to be over. But the rush is still on,
                        and other things which crowd and jam in more than fill up the vacant space
                        left by big, formal parties. It seems to me that there is even as much
                        dancing as there was two weeks ago. The only difference is that it
                        isn&apos;t formally arranged for beforehand.</p>
                    <p>I&apos;d like to &quot;shut off steam&quot;indeed, it seems to me
                        that I must if &quot;ma&quot; Burke is not to be sacrificed. But how
                        can we? People expect us to entertain, and we must go out to their affairs
                        also. The only escape would be to fly, and <pb id="VAA2432-189" n="173"/> we
                        can&apos;t do that so long as Congress is sitting.</p>
                    <p>February 27. Robert and Nadeshda are both in town, he with us, she at the
                        embassy. They are to be married the twelfth of April. The engagement is to
                        be announced to-morrow. I&apos;ve never seen any one more demure than
                        Nadeshda, or happier. I suspect she&apos;s going to settle down into the
                        most domestic of women. Indeed, I know itfor, as she says, she&apos;s
                        afraid of him, obeys him as a dog its master, and the domestic side of her
                        is the only one he&apos;ll tolerate. I&apos;ve always heard that her
                        sort of woman is the tamest, once it&apos;s under control. She has will
                        but no continuity. He has a stronger will and his purposes are unalterable.
                        So he&apos;ll continue to dominate her.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Ma&quot; Burke asked him, &quot;How did you make out with
                        her folks?&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-190" n="174"/>
                    <p>He smiled, then laughed.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I don&apos;t knowexactly,&quot; he said. &quot;They
                        couldn&apos;t talk my language nor I theirs. So it was all done through
                        an interpreter. And he was Mrs. Dean&apos;s brother-in-law, Prince
                        Glckstein, and a regular trump. He saw them half a dozen times before I did.
                        When I saw them everything was lovely. They left me alone with her after
                        twenty minutes. Finally it was agreed that we should come back on the same
                        steamer, her brother accompanying her.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;But why on earth didn&apos;t you cable us?&quot; she
                        demanded.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I did,&quot; he replied.</p>
                    <p>&quot;But you didn&apos;t tell us anything,&quot; she
                        returned.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I told you all there was to tell,&quot; he replied.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-191" n="175"/>
                    <p>&quot;You only said you were coming,&quot; she objected.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Well,&quot; he answered, looking somewhat surprised,
                        &quot;I knew you&apos;d know I wouldn&apos;t come without
                        her.&quot;</p>
                    <p>I&apos;m glad he didn&apos;t get it into his head to &quot;take
                        after&quot; me. A woman stands no more chance with a man like that than
                        a rabbit with a greyhound.</p>
                    <p>February 29. &quot;Ma&quot; Burke is dreadfully illhas been for two
                        days. The doctors have got several large Latin names for it, but the plain
                        truth is that she has broken down under the strain she seemed to be bearing
                        so placidly. She didn&apos;t give up until she was absolutely unable to
                        lift herself out of bed. &quot;I knew it was coming,&quot; she said,
                        &quot;but I thought I had spirit enough to put it off till I had more
                        time.&quot;</p>
                    <p>It wasn&apos;t until she did give up that <pb id="VAA2432-192" n="176"/>
                        her face really showed how badly off she was. I was sitting by her bed when
                        &quot;pa&quot; Burke and Cyrus came in. I couldn&apos;t bear to
                        look at them, yet I couldn&apos;t keep my eyes off their faces. Both got
                        deadly white at sight of her, and &quot;pa&quot; rushed from the
                        room after a moment or two. The doctor had cautioned him against alarming
                        her by showing any signs of grief. But &quot;pa&quot;
                        couldn&apos;t stand it. He went to his study, and the housekeeper told
                        me he cried like a baby. Cyrus stayed, and I couldn&apos;t help admiring
                        the way he put on cheerfulness.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I&apos;ll be all right in a few days,&quot; said
                        &quot;ma.&quot; &quot;It wasn&apos;t what I did; it was what
                        I et. I&apos;m such a fool that I can&apos;t let things that look
                        good go by. And I went from house to house, munching away, cake here, candy
                        there, chocolate <pb id="VAA2432-193" n="177"/> yonder, besides lunches and
                        dinners and suppers. I et in and I et out. Now, I reckon I&apos;ve got
                        to settle the bill. Thank the Lord I don&apos;t have to do it standing
                        up.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Cyrus and I went away from her room together. &quot;If she
                        wasn&apos;t so good,&quot; said he, more to himself than to me,
                        &quot;I&apos;d not be soso uncertain.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;I feel that I&apos;m to blame,&quot; said I bitterly.
                        &quot;It was I that gave her all those things to do.&quot;</p>
                    <p>He was silent, and his silence frightened me. I had felt that I was partly to
                        blame. His silence made me feel that I was wholly to blame, and that he
                        thought so.</p>
                    <p>&quot;If I could only undo it,&quot; I said, in what little voice I
                        could muster.</p>
                    <p>&quot;If you only could,&quot; he muttered.</p>
                    <p>I was utterly crushed. Every bit of <pb id="VAA2432-194" n="178"/> my courage
                        fled, andbut what&apos;s the use of trying to describe it? It was as if
                        I had tried to murder her and had come to my senses and was realizing what
                        I&apos;d done.</p>
                    <p>I suppose I must have shown what was in my mind, for, all of a sudden, with a
                        sort of sob or groan, he put his arms round mesuch a strong yet such a
                        gentle clasp! &quot;Don&apos;t look like that, dear!&quot; he
                        pleaded. &quot;Forgive meit was cowardly, what I saidand not true.
                        We&apos;re all to blameyou the least. Haven&apos;t I seen, day after
                        day, how you&apos;ve done everything you could to spare herhow
                        you&apos;ve worn yourself out?&quot;</p>
                    <p>He let me go as suddenly as he had seized me.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I&apos;m not fit to be called a man!&quot; he exclaimed.
                        &quot;Just because I loved you, and was always thinking of you, and <pb
                            id="VAA2432-195" n="179"/> watching you, and worrying about you, I
                        neglected to think of mother. If I&apos;d given her a single thought
                        I&apos;d have known long ago that she was ill.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Just then Mrs. Burke&apos;s maid called meshe was only a few yards away,
                        and must have seen everything. I hurried back to the room we had quitted a
                        few minutes before. &quot;You must cheer up those two big, foolish men,
                        child,&quot; she said. &quot;You all think I&apos;m going to
                        pass over, but I&apos;m not. You won&apos;t get rid of me for many a
                        year. And I rely on you to prevent them from going all to
                        pieces.&quot;</p>
                    <p>She paused and looked at me wistfully, as if she longed to say something but
                        was afraid she had no right to. I said: &quot;What is
                        itma?&quot;</p>
                    <p>Her face brightened. &quot;Come, kiss me,&quot; she murmured.
                        &quot;Thank you for <pb id="VAA2432-196" n="180"/> saying that.
                        We&apos;re very different in lots of ways, being raised so different.
                        But hearts have a way of finding each other, haven&apos;t
                        they?&quot;</p>
                    <p>I nodded.</p>
                    <p>&quot;What I wanted to say was aboutCyrus,&quot; she went on.
                        &quot;My Cyrus told me that he don&apos;t see how he could get along
                        without you, no way, and I advised him to talk to you about it, because I
                        knew it&apos;d relieve his mind and because it&apos;d set you to
                        looking at him in a different way. Anyhow, it&apos;s always a good plan
                        to ask for what you want. And he didand he told me you wouldn&apos;t
                        hear to him. Don&apos;t think I&apos;m trying to persuade you. All I
                        meant to say is that&quot;</p>
                    <p>She stopped and smiled, a bright shadow of that old, broad, beaming smile of
                        hers.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-197" n="181"/>
                    <p>&quot;I&apos;d do anything for you!&quot; I exclaimed, on
                        impulse.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I&apos;m afraid that wouldn&apos;t suit Cyrus,&quot;
                        she drawled, good humoredly. &quot;He&apos;d be mad as the Old
                        Scratch if he knew what I was up to now. Welldo the best you can. But
                        don&apos;t do anything unless it&apos;s for his sake. Onlyjust look
                        him over again. There&apos;s a lot to Cyrus besides his cowlick. And
                        he&apos;s been so dead in love with you ever since he first saw you that
                        he&apos;s been making a perfect fool of himself every time he looked at
                        you or spoke to you. Sometimes, when I&apos;ve seen the way
                        he&apos;s acted up, like a farmhand waltzing in cowhides, I&apos;ve
                        felt like taking him over my knees and laying it on good and
                        hard.&quot;</p>
                    <p>I was laughing so that I couldn&apos;t answerthe reaction from the fear
                        that she might be very, very ill had made me <pb id="VAA2432-198" n="182"/>
                        hysterical. I could still see that she was sick, extremely sick, but I
                        realized that our love for her had just put us into a panic.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Do the best you can, dear,&quot; she ended. &quot;And
                        everythingall the entertaining here and the going outmust be kept up just
                        the same as if I was being dragged about down stairs instead of lying up
                        here resting.&quot;</p>
                    <p>She insisted on this, and would not be content until she had my promise.
                        &quot;And don&apos;t forget to cheer pa and Cyrus up. I never was
                        sick beforenot a day. That&apos;s why they take on so.&quot;</p>
                    <p>I think I have been succeeding in cheering them up. And everything is going
                        forward as beforeexcept, of course, that we&apos;ve cut out every
                        engagement we possibly could.</p>
                    <p>It&apos;s amazing how many friends &quot;ma&quot; <pb
                            id="VAA2432-199" n="183"/> Burke has made in such a short time. Ever
                        since the news of her illness got out, the front door has been opening and
                        shutting all day long. And those of the callers that I&apos;ve seen have
                        shown a real interest. This has made me have a better opinion of human
                        nature than I had thought I could have. I suppose half the seeming
                        heartlessness in this world is suspicion and a sort of miserly dread lest
                        one should give kindly feeling without getting any of it in return. But
                        &quot;ma&quot; Burke, who never bothers her head for an instant
                        about whether people like her, and gets all her pleasure out of liking them,
                        makes friends by the score.</p>
                    <p>I&apos;m in a queer state of mind about Cyrus.</p>
                    <p>March 3. &quot;Ma&quot; Burke was brought down to the drawing-room
                        for tea <pb id="VAA2432-200" n="184"/> to-day. She held a regular levee.
                        Those that came early spread it round, and by six o&apos;clock they were
                        pouring in. She looked extremely well, and gloriously happy. All she had
                        needed was complete rest and sleepand less to eat. &quot;After
                        this,&quot; she said, &quot;I&apos;m not going to eat more than
                        four or five meals a day. At my age a woman can&apos;t stand the strain
                        of ten and twelvemy record was sixteencounting two teas as one
                        meal.&quot; For an hour there was hilarious chattering in English,
                        French, German, Italian, Russian, and mixtures of all five. I think the
                        thing that most fascinates Mrs. Burke about Washington is the many languages
                        spoken. She looks at me in an awed way when I trot out my three in quick
                        succession. And she regards the women as superhuman who speak so many
                        languages so fluently that <pb id="VAA2432-201" n="185"/> they drift from
                        one to the other without being quite sure what they&apos;re speaking.
                        There certainly were enough going on at once to-day, and a good many of the
                        women smoked.</p>
                    <p>But to return to Mrs. Burke. When only a few of those we know best were left
                        this afternoon, and Nadeshda was smoking, Jessie, who is always so tactful,
                        said to Robert: &quot;I&apos;m glad to see that you don&apos;t
                        object to Nadeshda&apos;s smoking.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Burke laughed. &quot;Why should he?&quot; said she.
                        &quot;Why, when we were children ma and pa used to sit on opposite sides
                        of the chimney, smoking their pipes. And ma dipped, too, when it
                        wasn&apos;t convenient for her to have her pipe.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Do <hi rend="i">you</hi> smoke, Mrs. Burke?&quot; asked Jessie,
                        with wide, serious eyes. &quot;I never saw you.&quot;</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-202" n="186"/>
                    <p>&quot;No, I don&apos;t,&quot; she confessed. &quot;Tom used
                        to hate the smell of it, so I never got into the habit.&quot;</p>
                    <p>Nadeshda was tremendously amused by what Mrs. Burke had said about pipes.
                        &quot;I didn&apos;t know it was considered nice for a lady to smoke
                        in America until recently,&quot; said she. &quot;And pipes! How
                        eccentric! Mama smokes cigarsone after dinner, but I never heard of a lady
                        smoking a pipe.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Ma wasn&apos;t a ladywhat <hi rend="i">you&apos;d</hi> call
                        a lady,&quot; replied Mrs. Burke. &quot;She was just a plain woman.
                        She didn&apos;t smoke because she thought it was fashionable, but
                        because she thought it was comfortable. As soon as we children got a little
                        older we used to be terribly ashamed of itbut <hi rend="i">she</hi> kept
                        right on. And now it&apos;s come in style.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Not <hi rend="i">pipes,&quot;</hi> said Jessie.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-203" n="187"/>
                    <p>&quot;Not <hi rend="i">yet,&quot;</hi> said &quot;ma,&quot;
                        with a smile. When I thought they had all gone, and I was writing in my
                        &quot;office&quot; for a few minutes before going up to dress,
                        Nadeshda came in to me. &quot;Ma&quot; Burke used often to say that
                        Nadeshda&apos;s eyes were &quot;full of the Old Scratch,&quot;
                        but certainly they were not at that moment. She was giving me a glimpse of
                        that side which, as Browning, I think, says, even the meanest creature has
                        and shows only to the person he or she loves. Not that Nadeshda loves me,
                        but she has that side turned outermost nowadays whenever she hasn&apos;t
                        the veil drawn completely over her real self.</p>
                    <p>&quot;My dear,&quot; she said in French, &quot;what is it? Why
                        these little smiles all afternoon whenever you forgot where you
                        were?&quot;</p>
                    <p>I couldn&apos;t help blushing. &quot;I don&apos;t <pb
                            id="VAA2432-204" n="188"/> quite know, myself,&quot; I repliedand it
                        was so.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Oh, you cold, cold, <hi rend="i">cold</hi> Americans!&quot;then
                        she paused and gave me one of her strange smiles, with her eyes elongated
                        and her lips just parted&quot;I mean, you American women.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Cold, because we don&apos;t set ourselves on fire?&quot; I
                        inquired.</p>
                    <p>&quot;But yes,&quot; she answered, &quot;yourselves, and the men,
                        too. Never mind. I shall not peep into your little secret.&quot; She
                        laughed. &quot;It always chills me to grope round in one of your cold
                        American women&apos;s hearts.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;I wish you could tell me what my secret isand that&apos;s the
                        plain truth,&quot; said I.</p>
                    <p>She laughed again, shrugged her shoulders, pinched my cheek, nodded her head
                        until her big plumed hat was <pb id="VAA2432-205" n="189"/> all in a quiver
                        and was shaking out volumes of the strong, heavy perfume she uses. And
                        without saying anything more she went away.</p>
                    <p>March 4. Cyrus and I sat next each other at dinner at the Secretary of
                        War&apos;s to-night. It has happened several times this winter, as the
                        precedence is often very difficult to arrange at small dinners. Old Alex
                        Bartlett took me in, and as he&apos;s stone deaf and a monstrous eater I
                        was free.</p>
                    <p>Cyrus had taken in a silent little girl who has just come out. She had
                        exhausted her little line of prearranged conversation before the fish was
                        taken away. So Cyrus talked to me.</p>
                    <p>&quot;She&apos;s grateful for my letting her alone,&quot; said he
                        when I tried to turn him back to his duty. &quot;Besides, if I
                        didn&apos;t meet you out once in a while <pb id="VAA2432-206" n="190"/>
                        you&apos;d forget me entirely. And I don&apos;t want that, if I can
                        avoid it.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Thank you,&quot; said I, for lack of anything else to say, and
                        with not the remotest intention of irritating him. But he flushed scarlet,
                        and frowned.</p>
                    <p>&quot;You always and deliberately misconstrue everything I say,&quot;
                        said he bitterly. &quot;I know I&apos;m unfortunate in trying to
                        express myself to you, but why do you never attribute to me anything but the
                        worst intentions?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;And why should you assume that every careless reply I make is a
                        carefully thought out attack on you?&quot; I retorted.
                        &quot;Don&apos;t you think your vanity makes you
                        morbid?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;You know perfectly well that it isn&apos;t vanity that makes me
                        think you especially dislike me,&quot; said he.</p>
                    <p>&quot;But I don&apos;t,&quot; I answered. &quot;I confess <pb
                            id="VAA2432-207" n="191"/> I did at first, but not since I&apos;ve
                        come to know you better.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Why did you dislike me at first?&quot; he asked. &quot;You
                        began on me with almost the first moment of our acquaintance.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;That&apos;s trueI did,&quot; I admitted. &quot;I had a
                        reason for itdidn&apos;t Nadeshda tell you what it was?&quot;</p>
                    <p>He looked frightened.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Be frank, if you want me to be frank,&quot; said I.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I never for an instant believed what she said,&quot; he replied
                        abjectly. Then after a warning look from me, he added<hi rend="i"
                            >&quot;Really</hi> believed it, I mean.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;And what was it that you didn&apos;t really believe?&quot;
                        I demanded.</p>
                    <p>He looked at me boldly. &quot;Nadeshda and one or two others told me that
                        you and your friends had arranged it for me <pb id="VAA2432-208" n="192"/>
                        to marry you. But, of course, I knew it wasn&apos;t so.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;But it was so,&quot; I replied. &quot;You were one of the
                        considerations that determined my friends in trying to get me my
                        place.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Welland why didn&apos;t you take me when I finally fell into
                        the trap?&quot;</p>
                    <p>I let him see I was laughing at him. He scowledhis cowlick did look so funny
                        that I longed to pull it. &quot;Simply couldn&apos;t stand menot
                        even for the sake of what I brought,&quot; he said. And then he gave me
                        a straight, searching look. &quot;I wonder why I don&apos;t hate
                        you,&quot; he went on. &quot;I wonder why I am such an ass as to
                        care for you. Yeseven if I knew you didn&apos;t care for me, still
                        I&apos;d want you. Can a man make a more degrading confession than
                        that?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;But why?&quot; said I, very careful not <pb id="VAA2432-209"
                            n="193"/> to let him see how eagerly I longed to hear him say <hi
                            rend="i">the</hi> words again. &quot;Why should you
                        wantme?&quot;</p>
                    <p>He gave a very unpleasant laugh. &quot;If you think I&apos;m going to
                        sit here and exhibit my feelings for your amusement you&apos;re going to
                        be disappointed. It&apos;s none of your business <hi rend="i">why.</hi>
                        Certainly not because I find anything sweet or amiable or even kind in
                        you.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;That&apos;s rude,&quot; said I.</p>
                    <p>&quot;It was intended to be,&quot; said he.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Pleaselet&apos;s not quarrel now,&quot; said I coldly.
                        &quot;It gives me the headache to quarrel during dinner.&quot;</p>
                    <p>And he answered between his set teeth, &quot;To quarrel with
                        youanywheregives methe heartache, Gus.&quot;</p>
                    <p>I had no answer for that, nor should I have had the voice to utter it if I
                        had had it. And then Mr. Bartlett began <pb id="VAA2432-210" n="194"/>
                        prosing to me about the Greeley-Grant campaign. And when the men came to
                        join the women after dinner Cyrus went away almost immediately.</p>
                    <p>I am <hi rend="i">so</hi> happy to-night.</p>
                    <p>March 5. Cyrus came to me in my office to-dayas I had expected. But instead
                        of looking woebegone and abject, he was radiant. He shut the door behind
                        him. <hi rend="i">&quot;You</hi>guilty of cowardice,&quot; he began.
                        &quot;It isn&apos;t strange that I never suspected it.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;What do you mean?&quot; I asked, not putting down my pen.</p>
                    <p>He came over and took it out of my fingers, then he took my fingers and
                        kissed them, one by one. I was so astoundedand something elsethat I made not
                        the slightest resistance. &quot;It&apos;s useless for you to cry
                        out,&quot; he said, &quot;for I&apos;ve got the outer door well
                        guarded.&quot; <pb id="VAA2432-211" n="195"/> I started up aflame with
                        indignation. &quot;Whowhom&quot; I began.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Ma,&quot; he replied.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Oh!&quot; I exclaimed, looking round with a wild idea of making
                        a dart for liberty.</p>
                    <p>&quot;Ma,&quot; he repeated, &quot;and it&apos;s not of the
                        slightest use for you to try to side-step. You&apos;re
                        cornered.&quot; He had both my hands now and was looking at me at
                        arm&apos;s length. &quot;So you are afraid to marry me for fear
                        peopleyour friendswill say thatI walked right into the trap?&quot;</p>
                    <p>I hung my head and couldn&apos;t keep from trembling, I was so
                        ashamed.</p>
                    <p>&quot;And if it wasn&apos;t for that you&apos;d accept my
                        &apos;proposition&apos;nowwouldn&apos;t you?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;I would not,&quot; I replied, wrenching myself away with an
                        effort that put my <pb id="VAA2432-212" n="196"/> hair topsy-turvyit always
                        does try to come down if I make a sudden movement, and I washed it only
                        yesterday.</p>
                    <p>&quot;What gorgeous hair you have!&quot; he said. &quot;Sometimes
                        I&apos;ve caught a glimpse of it just as I was entering a roomand
                        I&apos;ve had to retreat and compose myself to make a fresh
                        try.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;You&apos;ve been talking to your mother!&quot; I
                        exclaimedI&apos;d been casting about for an explanation of all this
                        sudden shrewdness of his in ways feminine.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I have,&quot; said he. &quot;It&apos;s as important to
                        her as to me that you don&apos;t escape.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;And she told you that I was in love with <hi rend="i"
                            >you!&quot;</hi> I tried to put a littlenot too muchscorn into the
                        &quot;you.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;She did,&quot; he answered. &quot;Do you deny that
                        it&apos;s true?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;I have told you I would never accept your
                        &apos;proposition,&apos;&quot; was my answer.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-213" n="[]"/>
                    <figure entity="VAA2432-12"/>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-214" n="197"/>
                    <p>&quot;So you did,&quot; said he. &quot;Then you mean that
                        you&apos;re going to sacrifice my mother&apos;s happiness and mine,
                        simply because you&apos;re afraid of being accused of mercenary
                        motives?&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;I shall never accept your
                        &apos;proposition,&apos;&quot; I repeated, with a faint smile
                        that was a plain hint.</p>
                    <p>He came very close to me and looked down into my face. &quot;What do you
                        mean by that?&quot; he demanded. And then he must have remembered what
                        his proposition wasa strictly business arrangement on both sides. For, with
                        a sort of gasp of relief, he took me in his arms. I do love the combination
                        of strength and tenderness in a man. He had looked and talked and been so
                        strong up to that instant. Then he was <hi rend="i">so</hi> tenderI could
                        hardly keep back the tears.</p>
                    <pb id="VAA2432-215" n="[198]"/>
                    <p>&quot;Wouldn&apos;t you like me to tell mother?&quot; he asked.
                        &quot;She&apos;s just in the next roomand&quot;</p>
                    <p>I nodded and said, &quot;I never should have caught you if it
                        hadn&apos;t been for her.&quot;</p>
                    <p>&quot;Nor I you,&quot; said he. And he put me in a chair and opened
                        the door. I somehow couldn&apos;t look up, though I knew she was
                        there.</p>
                    <p>&quot;I don&apos;t know whether to laugh or cry,&quot; said
                        &quot;ma&quot; Burke. &quot;So I guess I&apos;ll just do
                        both.&quot; And then she seated herself and was as good as her word.</p>
                    <figure entity="VAA2432-13"/>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>