<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//IA Books//DTD TEI for Indiana Authors Books//EN"
                       "teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="VAB1822">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Down our way</title>
                <title type="subtitle">stories of southern and western character</title>
                <author>Judah, Mary Jameson, 1851-1930.</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded By</resp>
                    <!--Update the value of the element below with your name in
                                direct order.-->
                    <name>Peter Kaczmarczyk</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
                </address>
                <idno>VAB1822</idno>
                <availability status="unknown">
                    <p>Copyright 2009 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
                    <p>Indiana University provides the information contained on this web site
                                for non-commercial, personal, or research use only. All other use,
                                including but not limited to commercial or scholarly reproductions,
                                redistribution, publication or transmission, whether by electronic means
                                or otherwise, without prior written permission of the copyright holder
                                is strictly prohibited.</p>
                </availability>
                <!--Update the value of the date element with the year the document
                        is being encoded.-->
                <date>2009</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title type="main">Down our way</title>
                        <title type="subtitle">stories of southern and western character</title>
                        <author>Judah, Mary Jameson, 1851-1930.</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>5 p. β., 9-266 p., 1 β. 18 cm.</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Way &amp; Williams</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                        <date>1897</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Digital Library Program was awarded a Library Services and Technology
                            Act (LSTA) grant in 2005 to make available online the three-volume,
                            reference work, <title>Indiana Authors and Their Books</title> along
                            with selected monographs by Indiana authors.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3">
                <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition
                            (OCR), and has been encoded and edited using the recommendations for
                            Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines following the TEI Lite
                            standard. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <tagUsage gi="div1">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language>English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <!--The revision description tracks significant changes made to the file
                    after completion. This information will remain commented out unless someone has
                    conducted quality assessment of the texts and have made changes to the file as a
                    result.-->
        <!-- <revisionDesc> <change>
                    <date>$Date</date> <respStmt>
                    <name>$Name</name>
                    <resp>$Responsibility</resp>
                    </respStmt> <item>$Changes</item>
                    </change> </revisionDesc> -->
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
        
                           <pb id="VAB1822-001"
                    n="[]"/>


    <div1 type="halftitle"><head type="supplied">Halftitle</head><p rend="center">D<hi rend="sc">OWN</hi> O<hi rend="sc">UR</hi> W<hi rend="sc">AY</hi></p></div1>







<pb
                    id="VAB1822-002" n="[]"/>
                <pb id="VAB1822-003"
                    n="[1]"/>
<titlePage><docTitle><titlePart type="main">DOWN OUR
    WAY</titlePart>
<titlePart type="subtitle">Stories of Southern and Western
   character</titlePart></docTitle>
      <byline>by
<docAuthor>Mary Jameson
    Judah</docAuthor></byline>


    <docImprint><pubPlace>CHICACO</pubPlace>
<publisher>WAY &amp; WILLIAMS</publisher></docImprint></titlePage>



<pb
                    id="VAB1822-004"
                    n="[2]"/>












          <div1 type="verso"><head type="supplied">Verso</head><p>COPYRIGHT<lb/>
      BY WAY &amp; WILLIAMS<lb/>
          MDCCCXCVII</p></div1>



















 


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-005"
                    n="[3]"/>













    <div1><head type="supplied">Forward</head><p>Two of these stories have been published before:
"A Gentlewoman," under another title in the Arena,
1893, and "An Adventure of a Lady of Quality," in
Harper's Magazine for January, 1895--more than a
year before the announcement of a book with a similar
title.</p></div1>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-006" n="[4]"/>



<pb id="VAB1822-007"
                    n="[5]"/>












        	<div1 type="contents"><head><hi rend="center">CONTENTS</hi></head>
          <list type="simple">
                                            <item rend="right">PAGE</item>
<item><hi rend="left">A VISIBLE SIGN</hi> <hi rend="right">9</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAB1822-009"/></item>
            <item><hi rend="left">THE END OF SOCIETY</hi> <hi rend="right">21</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAB1822-021"/></item>
<item><hi rend="left">AN ADVENTURE OF A LADY OF QUALITY</hi> <hi rend="right">39</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAB1822-039"/></item>
<item><hi rend="left">A PART OF THE NEW SOUTH</hi> <hi rend="right">51</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAB1822-051"/></item>
<item><hi rend="left">A CONFLICT OF RIGHTS</hi> <hi rend="right">77</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAB1822-077"/></item>
<item><hi rend="left">THE MORNINGSTAR ELOPEMENT</hi> <hi rend="right">159</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAB1822-159"/></item>
<item><hi rend="left">THE WIFE OF A CARPENTER</hi> <hi rend="right">193</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAB1822-193"/></item>
<item><hi rend="left">A GENTLEWOMAN</hi> <hi rend="right">215</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAB1822-215"/></item>
<item><hi rend="left">THE BLUE BLAZERS</hi> <hi rend="right">247</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAB1822-247"/></item></list>

</div1>
<pb
                    id="VAB1822-008"
                    n="[6]"/>












        </front><body><div1 type="book"><head type="supplied">Down our way</head>
<pb
                    id="VAB1822-009" n="[7]"/>






          <div2 type="chapter"><head rend="center">A VISIBLE SIGN</head>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-010"
                    n="[8]"/>









<pb
                    id="VAB1822-011"
                    n="9"/>



          <head rend="center">A VISIBLE SIGN</head>


<p><hi rend="b">I</hi>T was at first a matter of indifference to
   Captain Lee that in the dismemberment
of the Confederacy the records of his regiment
had been destroyed. The memories
so overwhelmingly present with him must,
he thought, be part of the universal knowledge, 
not to be lost. Later it seemed to
him that all the world but himself had forgotten. 
He tried to find his old commander,
to get some accredited statement of his
services; but the Colonel was dead, and the
other officers were scattered beyond finding.</p>
    <p>The letters that the Captain had written
to his wife had been lost in moving to town
from the plantation, and his body servant
who went up to Richmond with him when
he enlisted had died in the first yellow fever
year. It came at last to this,--that there
was not one record, not one scrap of paper,


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-012"
                    n="10"/>



no person or document by which his devotion 
and service to the Confederacy might
be proved,--nothing but his old uniform.</p>
   <p>A person who did not know him well
would not have guessed how deeply he felt
on this subject. He was a most reserved
man, and it was a part of his reserve that
he could not speak of the time of the Confederacy.
He said to himself that he feared
to make the subject commonplace or even
tedious by talking of it to his children; he
had seen that happen in families of his acquaintance.
But the real reason was not
that he did not want to speak--he could not.</p>
  <p>The uniform, at first almost unconsidered,
then a saddening relic, came to be very
precious. Sometimes in the reverent silences
of the church, or in the watches of a wakeful 
night, he found himself thinking: "I
shall leave no inheritance to my grandsons
so priceless as that old uniform will be.
Looking at it, our cause will seem real to
them, and because of me they will study the
story of our struggle."</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-013"
                    n="11"/>



  <p>The Captain's wife and daughters regarded
him as a being set apart, a person too high
and fine for the affairs of this world. There
was even in the family an appearance of
making up to him for something lacking,
although he himself would have resented
such an idea. The ladies understood him
partly, and their affection carried them the
rest of the way in their loving and gentle
family life. They were never so busy that
he was not the one to be considered first.
All the little social news was told in his
presence. It was not addressed to him directly,
but was intended to divert him.</p>
   <p>He liked to hear of the historical societies
and of the organizations of women formed
to perpetuate the memory of the heroic
past. His daughters brought him many
stories from the meetings of such associations.</p>
   <p>"Mrs. Conway's great-great-grandfather
was one of the signers!" said Patty.</p>
   <p>"Yes; but she can't prove that he was
<hi rend="i">her</hi> great-great-grandfather!" exclaimed

          
<pb
                    id="VAB1822-014"
                    n="12"/>


Fairfax. "Now Mrs. Pinckney has the
actual letter that her ancestor wrote from
Valley Forge."</p>
   <p>"But didn't that letter fade away into
insignificance when Mrs. Fauquier brought
out <hi rend="i">her</hi> relic?"</p>
   <p>"And what was that?" inquired the Captain,
with much interest.</p>
   <p>"Only think, father, she had the <hi rend="i">hat</hi>, the
actual <hi rend="i">hat</hi>--cockade and all--that her ancestor
wore through the North Carolina
campaign!"</p>
   <p>"Yes," said Patty, "we walked up to
look at it without a word. It seemed so
wonderful to see it after all these years. It
almost made me tremble,--it was so near
and real."</p>
  <p>The Captain did not speak; it made his
heart beat to think of his own sacred gray,
and of a past that it would some day revivify.</p>
  <p>In the earlier years the Captain had often
looked at his uniform. Of late he had not
cared to take it out; it was like going to


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-015"
                    n="13"/>




the cemetery,-he came away unsatisfied.
It pleased him to think of it as safe in the
little trunk in the attic, but he did not wish
to see it. That night he remembered that
it had been a long time since he had looked
at it. He troubled himself about the chance
of moths and resolved to examine it the
first thing in the morning.</p>
  <p>But in the morning his desire was gone.
Indeed, it was only when the trunk was to
be emptied that he might put in it the things
for a little journey, that he spoke of the
uniform.</p>
  <p>Then he went to the foot of the stairs
and called to Patty, who was getting together
what he was to take with him.</p>
   <p>"Daughter, bring down my old uniform
when you empty the little trunk."</p>
  <p>He heard her sweet, clear voice: "Yes,
father!" He heard her light step as she
walked about the bare floor of the attic.
Then she came hurriedly to the upper balustrade.</p>
   <p>"Father, it isn't here! There's nothing


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-016"
                    n="14"/>




in the trunk but a roll of silk pieces and an
old white vest. And I've looked everywhere 
else!"</p>
  <p>Mrs. Lee appeared at the door of her
room. She thought that her husband had
replaced the uniform in the trunk after it
was out the last time. He supposed that
she had done so. Patty was called from
her little studio.</p>
   <p>"Patty, come here! Do you know anything 
about father's old uniform?"</p>
  <p>Patty came, rosy and graceful. She stuck
her brushes in her hair and pondered.</p>
   <p>"I have not seen it since father took the
trunk to Tennessee six months ago. Then
I hung it in the attic just over the place
where the little trunk always stands. I
knew father always liked to fold it himself."</p>
  <p>"Has anything been given away lately?"
asked Mrs. Lee.</p>
  <p>Fairfax overheard her mother's question.
Her face turned blood red; she put her
hand to her head.</p>
   <p>"Oh, wait a minute till I think!" she
said. "I met a tramp at the door one day


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-017"
                    n="15"/>




last fall--I was just going to a card party;:
I called to that light-colored Tilly we had
then to give him any old thing that might
be lying around the attic."</p>
  <p>Her father turned away with the stooping
gesture of a man who has had a heavy
blow. The side of his face that they could
see was gray and sunken.</p>
  <p>His daughter rushed to him; she clung to
him wildly; she spoke as a little child might
speak. "Oh, papa, papa, <hi rend="i">don't!</hi> Indeed
I didn't know! Oh, please forgive me,
<hi rend="i">papa!</hi>"</p>
  <p>The Captain could not speak at first; his
old throat made queer choking noises, but
he patted the girl's shoulder reassuringly.</p>
   <p>"Do not blame yourself, my daughter.
It is a misfortune; we must learn to bear
misfortunes."</p>
   <p>The Captain's business had not been
pressing for many years, and shortly after
the loss of the uniform he gave up active
connection with the firm of cotton-factors
of which he had been a member. His


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-018"
                    n="16"/>



health had never been very strong, and he
spent many hours at home with the ladies.
On fine afternoons he walked out to attend
the meeting of some board of directors or
to spend a little while in the office of his
old firm. Once or twice when he came in
he spoke of the dust, and how it showed on
his dark clothing.</p>
   <p>"I wonder, Mrs. Lee," he said, "if it
would be out of the way for me to get a
suit of light-colored clothes, such as the
young gentlemen wear--one of those tans,
or, maybe, a nice gray?"</p>
  <p>He spoke of it again: "'Of course a man
of my age wouldn't want one of those bobtailed 
coats--if I <hi rend="i">should</hi> get a light suit."</p>
  <p>The suit came home; the color was a clear
gray; there was a long frock coat. The
Captain buttoned it around his neat figure
with grave satisfaction.</p>
   <p>"Father may not know much about the
styles," said Fairfax, "but he's awfully
distinguished."</p>
  <p>He wore his gray suit so constantly that


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-019"
                    n="17"/>




the ladies laughingly, spoke of it as. his
"uniform." This was only to one another;
when they were in his presence there was
no. recognition of the fact that there was
anything to be remarked about his clothing.
It was felt that any comment would hurt
him. Later the coat was sent out for some
repair. When it came home, Patty said, in
some surprise, "Why, father, the tailor has
put brass buttons on it!"</p>
  <p> "So he has!" exclaimed the Captain; but
the buttons were not removed.</p>
  <p>The Captain had always liked a slouch
hat. Now he wore one constantly. He let
his beautiful smooth hair grow long and
parted it far down over one ear. "What
picture is it that father looks like?" asked
Fairfax. "He looks like one of those old
daguerreotypes taken during the war that
grandmother used to show us on Sunday
afternoons when we were little," answered
her sister.</p>
  <p>As he sat in a shady corner of the veranda 
in the long mornings, the Captain
      


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-020"
                    n="18"/>


sometimes looked tenderly at the sleeve of
his 'gay coat, as though he loved to see
the color near him. And in the evenings
he might be seen pacing back and forth for
hours on the gallery in front of his house,
silent, stern, wrapped in contemplation of
a lost time, clad in the insignia of an un-
forgotten past.</p>
</div2>
          
<pb
                    id="VAB1822-021"
                    n="[19]"/>



          




          <div2 type="chapter"><head rend="center">THE END OF SOCIETY</head>

          
<pb
                    id="VAB1822-022"
                    n="[20]"/>



<pb
                    id="VAB1822-023"
                    n="21"/>





<head rend="center">THE END OF SOCIETY</head>


            <epigraph><p>("The end of society is the individual."--</p><bibl><hi rend="i">Law maxim</hi>.)</bibl></epigraph>

<p><hi rend="b">T</hi>HE cabin had but one room; at one end
    of that was a bedstead high piuffed
with a feather bed, though the month was
August; at the other was the stove on which
Alfaretta was cooking the supper. A child
of two hung on her skirt, and a six-months-
old baby was tied in a high chair.</p>
  <p>Occasionally she looked out over the
swampy prairie toward the direction from
which her husband, Sol, might come.</p>
  <p>Nine months before, on their way to
Dakota, they had halted their wagon here
when Sol had hired out to clear the swamp,
and Alfaretta, with her tow-headed child in
her arms, had climbed out of the back of
the wagon, and set up the stove, and put
the bed together.</p>
  <p>Sol's partner and employer, Asaph, lived


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-024"
                    n="22"/>




in a cabin three miles west. He had undertaken
to clear two hundred acres of land
for a company in La Fayette. He kept an
account of the work done by himself and
Sol and settled once a month.</p>
   <p>This was settlement day and Alfaretta
knew Sol would be later than usual; nevertheless
she kept looking out for his approach 
with a sort of formless anxiety.
Asaph could read and write, Sol could not.
Sol thought Asaph had cheated him the last
two times. Alfaretta did not doubt that
this had been the case, although her experience
of life had not been extended enough
to give her much reason for thinking one
thing or another. She had married at fifteen,
and her life before that had been
passed partly in the mountains of Tennessee,
and partly on the little clay-soiled farm
in Southwestern Indiana where her father
had "squatted." The three years since her
marriage she had spent for the most part in
the wagon. Sol had been anxious to better
himself. This determination and the fact


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-025"
                    n="23"/>



that he possessed a wagon and team were
evidences that he was, although only twentyone
years old, a man of some capacity.</p>
   <p>At sunset Alfaretta saw him coming across
the clearing. He was over six feet high,
and blond in hair and beard. Though he
carried an ax over his shoulder he walked
with the easy swing of symmetrical strength.
Alfaretta perceived this with an appreciation
for which she had no medium of expression.</p>
  <p>When he came in without addressing her
she did not wonder. He was silent by nature,
and at any time had but little to say.
Besides this the months the two had passed
in almost entire, isolation had developed
between them an understanding independent
of speech. She knew his thoughts as a
dog knows the moods of his master. The
child toddled toward him; he took it in his
arms and sat silent while Alfaretta spread a
newspaper on the top of a box and put on
it the skillet of fried pork, some corn pone,
and two tin cups of coffee.</p>
     


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-026"
                    n="24"/>




<p>When Sol had eaten his supper his wife
asked, "Wha'd he give you this time?"</p>
   <p>"Fifty cents for a month's work."</p>
   <p>"He's give us some meat and meal."</p>
   <p>Sol made no response, but after a quarter
of an hour he spoke again.</p>
   <p>"He says I owed him ten dollars last
time. He says that was in the paper I
signed."</p>
  <p>Alfaretta did not ask if this was true; she
knew it was not. But she did not know
that she had any right to be specially indignant.
That they should be forever
cheated and betrayed was only a part of the
order of things.</p>
  <p>Sol went outside of the door and sat there
with the child in his arms while he smoked
his pipe. Malarial mists rose heavily and
almost obscured the dull after-glow of the
sunset. The child went to sleep, and he
brought it in, and unclasping its little arms
took its apron off and put it on the back of
the bed.</p>
  <p>The baby was fretful; Alfaretta soothed


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-027"
                    n="25"/>




it to sleep again and again, only to have it
waken with the peevish wail of a teething
child whenever she tried to put it down.
Mosquitos and gnats came in swarms and
clouded the light of the dingy little lamp,
in the oil of which floated a red rag--put
there with decorative intent. Sol sat on
the bed for another half hour in deep
thought. Then he rose and went toward
the door.</p>
   <p>"Where you going?"</p>
   <p>"I'm going to try to make Asaph square
up."</p>
   <p>"Well, he won't."</p>
   <p>He had taken his gun up as she spoke.
Now, he answered, "Well, if he don't I'll
kill him."</p>
  <p>Such a threat gave Alfaretta no particular
concern at the moment. She had heard
such threats all of her life; they were the
recourse of the injured, the argument of the
angry. She had seen men who had killed
others; she had even witnessed a shooting
or two in which no one was hurt. But no


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-028"
                    n="26"/>




sooner was Sol gone than she became
troubled. She tried with all the intensity
of which she was capable to make the baby
sleep, to force him to stay asleep. When
she had succeeded she came out, shutting
the cabin door softly behind her. She stood
for an instant as if in doubt; then with her
arm held before her to shield her face from
the low-growing bushes, she ran at full
speed across the marsh toward the cabin of
Asaph.</p>
  <p>As she came near she heard the sound of
loud talking. The men seemed to come
out of the door together. Their tones grew
fiercer. There were two shots, a shriek, an
oath, and then silence.</p>
  <p>As Sol strode through the slashes Alfaretta
slipped to his side and touched his arm. He
clutched her (he shook from head to foot)
and dragged her out into the moonlight and
looked at her. She was crying aloud.</p>
   <p>"Damn you, be still!" he said, and drove
her before him along the way home.</p>
  <p>In the morning Sol put on his other shirt


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-029"
                    n="27"/>





from the box under the bed. He lingered
awhile, as if waiting for something. At
about seven, however, he took his ax and
went to work.</p>
  <p>The shirt he left on the floor was 
bloodstained--his left arm had been grazed by a
bullet. When he got home Alfaretta had
washed the garment and it hung drying on
a stump near the door. He looked at it and
then, sharply, at his wife.</p>
  <p>At first Alfaretta had no thought but simple 
horror at the deed. She had been so
far away from everything that she had no
constant realization that there was anyone
in the world but themselves. By the second
morning she began to fear. She knew that
it was wrong to kill and the possibility of
some human vengeance occurred to her
mind. In her sleep she had visions of the
streets in Indianapolis through which they
had passed, on their way. There were
crowds there, always moving, and moving.</p>
  <p>She had moments of that strange physical
apprehension of danger that some women


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-030"
                    n="28"/>




call nervousness. She was frightened into
speechless trembling when at the end of the
third day Sol, speaking for the first time,
said, "(If you blab you ought to be killed,
too."</p>
   <p>By this time he did not eat or sleep, but
sat in one position all day long. As Alfaretta 
had looked about for a place to lay
the little baby, Sol had held out his hands.
After that he had cared for it altogether,
except when he gave it to the mother to
be fed.</p>
  <p>One day he put his head forward as if to
listen. Then he laid the child down gently
and walked to the door. Alfaretta heard
him give a long sigh. In a moment three
men on horseback came in view--the sheriff
and two deputies. Sol went with them
without resistance.</p>
  <p>While Sol was in jail he was approached
by a shystering lawyer who had heard from
a turnkey of his wounded arm. "Give me
twenty-five dollars," he said, "and I'll get
you off. It was self-defense." Sol listened


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-031"
                    n="29"/>





to what the other had to propose and then
said simply, " I 'low it wasn't self-defense,
I reckon I wasn't afred of Asaph's killing
me." When the lawyer lowered his price
to five dollars Sol would not even give him
so much out of the money for which his
team had been sold, and as soon as he could
he gave every cent to the sheriff to be kept
for Alfaretta.</p>
  <p>At the opening of the trial the judge,
finding no lawyer acting for the prisoner,
asked an attorney who was in the courtroom
to take charge of the case. It was the same
man who had approached Sol in jaiL "Your
honor," said he, "I have consulted with the
prisoner already, and I can only advise him
to plead guilty."</p>
  <p>The trial was soon over. When Sol was
asked if he was guilty or not he looked up
as if bewildered at so superfluous a question. 
"Yes," he said, "I done it."</p>
  <p>The Land Company in La Fayette had
sent a skillful lawyer to represent them in
the prosecution. There had been deeds of


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-032"
                    n="30"/>





violence among their men before and they
were sensitive.  He was able to show that
the murder had been wanton and cold
blooded. The newspapers were saying,
"There has been too much monkeying with
life sentences, and getting pardoned out in
a few years. What this county needs is a
little hanging." Because the community
had felt themselves outraged by recent failures
of justice, Sol's plea of guilty did not
serve, as it ordinarily would have done, to
mitigate the sentence that was to be passed
on him.</p>
  <p>Alfaretta was not at the trial. The county
seat was far away and she had no one with
whom to leave the children. Some of the
neighbors were able to go and drove four
miles out of their way on their return to tell
her that Sol had been sentenced to be
hanged. She got one short letter from her
husband; it was written by a fellow-prisoner
whose lack of facility in writing had made
him  abbreviate the sentences out of all
meaning. A few days before the time set


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-033"
                    n="31"/>





for the hanging she walked, carrying both
children, to a farm five miles away and got
the woman of the house to engage to take
charge of the older child on the day of the
execution. In preparation she had already
made for the six months baby who was to
go with her a little dress of pink calico and
a sun-bonnet of the same.</p>
  <p>The day appointed was late in October,
and, although clear, very chilly. Alfaretta
left home early in the morning and took her
way across great fields of soft black prairie
earth newly plowed for the planting of
winter wheat, or sometimes she jumped from
one little grassy pyramid to another across
the frost-stiffened swamp.</p>
  <p>The nearest railroad was five miles from
her cabin, and there were four miles more
for her to walk to the county seat after she
left the cars. She was admitted at once to
the inclosure at the Courthouse when she
made herself known.  Someone asked her
if she would like to see the prisoner, but
while she dumbly hesitated a deputy said it


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-034"
                    n="32"/>



was pretty late already and he reckoned Sol
oughtn't to be bothered.</p>
   <p>As she sat there in front of the scaffold
the silence grew deeper and deeper. The
crowd around her changed into a thousand
presences, near and oppressive. The officers 
moved back and forth with grave and
automatic directness. Everything began to
swing over her in rhythmic risings and fallings.
Then the silence, the multitude, the
swaying of the universe, seemed to her
sense to unite in the cadences of some awful
force hitherto unknown.</p>
   <p rend="i">"It is over, life is over, hope is over.
You two have never been alone, never-not
even in the woods. A multitude has watched
you.   They all have watchedyou-and now
they have taken him, and now they are going
to kill him!--to kill him "</p>
  <p>She saw them lead out the condemned
man. He had on new black clothes. His
eyes were glassy, his mouth hung open, his
head wabbled from side to side. He had
been filled with morphine and brandy. Men


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-035"
                    n="33"/>



held him up on either side. The sheriff,
pale as ashes, turned to test the ropes for
the last time.</p>
  <p>Alfaretta got to her feet. She made an
effort like the terrible struggle of nightmare,
but no voice came. An agony clutched her
whole slender little frame. She screamed,
she shrieked.</p>
   <p>"He never knowed! You're doing just
what he done! It ain't right! It ain't
right!"</p>
  <p>She was pulled down into her seat. The
baby began to wail. She opened her dress
and put it to her flat young breast.
  She still sat there as the crowd-dispersed.
The young reporters passed near her. One
said, "Oh, there's the widow!" and taking
out his note book turned toward her. The
other drew him away. "Oh, hell! Ain't
you sick enough already?"</p>
  <p>A deputy came to inquire if she wanted
the "remains." She made some sort of
affirmative sign, and when Sol's body was
put in the coffin she came and sat down
     


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-036"
                    n="34"/>




beside it with her arm over the box. The
sheriff said he would ask some of the folks
that were going that way to carry the body
as far as the train. Later he came back
and said in something like apology that the
Balzer boys were the only ones he could
get.</p>
  <p>The sheriff's wife left her hospitable
kitchen--she had a lot of company to dinner
that day--and came across to where Alfaretta
sat in front of the jail and begged her
to come in and get a comfortable dinner
with the folks. Alfaretta looked at her in
silence as she continued with kindly insistence.
"Oh, come right on, Miz Hopper;
you know you'd ought to eat to keep up
your strength." Later a bareheaded little
girl ran over, bringing a plate on which was
a large piece of custard pie and some sweet
pickles, and a cup of coffee over-sugared
and creamed. Alfaretta gave the baby a
little of the coffee.</p>
  <p>At five o'clock the Balzers came by.
They had been drinking, but were quiet. "I


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-037"
                    n="35"/>





reckon they'll have sense enough not to
talk any blaggard talk while she's along,"
the sheriff said, anxiously, as they passed
out of sight.</p>
  <p>The first mile they were silent. Then
they stopped and drank from a jug which
lay at their feet. Alfaretta sat in the rear
end of the wagon on some straw. Before
they had gone another half mile they were
singing and yelling. From then on they
were drinking constantly, at one minute
making frightful threats to anything and
everything, at another uttering horrible
blasphemies. Later it occurred to them to
ask the dead man to drink. They turned
in the seat and poured whisky on the head
of the coffin.</p>
  <p>It was dark when they reached the station. 
The Balzers had grown sullen and
quarrelsome. The agent came out and
helped them to put the coffin on the platform 
which made the station--it was only
a place where the train took water. Then
after the wagon was gone the agent told


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-038"
                    n="36"/>




Alfaretta that he'd got to go to his supper,
but he'd come back in time to flag the eight
o'clock train. She saw his lantern fade
and go out down the road.</p>
  <p>As she sat there the night grew cold.
Heavy mists rose from the earth. She took
off her shawl to put around the baby, and
then her sun-bonnet to wrap around its
little feet.</p>
  <p>And as she waited alone with her dead
husband she knew not of any mercy in the
hollow swinging earth beneath her, nor in
the empty heavens above.</p>
</div2>
                           
<pb
                    id="VAB1822-039"
                    n="[37]"/>






          


<div2 type="chapter"><head rend="center">AN ADVENTURE OF A LADY OF
        QUALITY</head>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-040"
                    n="[38]"/>




<pb
                    id="VAB1822-041"
                    n="39"/>






<head rend="center">AN ADVENTURE OF A LADY
            OF QUALITY</head>

<p><hi rend="b">T</hi>HE regular Saturday afternoon meeting
    of the Woman's Club was over. It had
been a delightful occasion; the club members 
standing about the room in little groups
said to each other that it had been a "beautiful" 
meeting. They were prosperous-
looking women. Some of them were pretty,
some far from it, but they all had the look
of belonging to that class which subordinates
the physical, and gives the intellectual part
of their natures at least a fair chance.</p>
  <p>Many of them lingered to speak to the
President of the club. She had read the
paper of the day. Her theme had been
"The Divinity of Man." Everybody was
charmed.</p>
  <p>"I don't want to be an angel!" said one
                   


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-042"
                    n="40"/>




lady. " Now that I've heard you, I'd rather
be a human being!"</p>
   <p>"I seemed to recognize it as my own
subconscious  thinking,"  said  another.
"'Humanity shares in the holiness of the
universe!'"</p>
  <p>"Oh!" cried a third, "I <hi rend="i">did</hi> like it when
you said that we are all of the same essence
-'Call no man common or unclean; he is
in God, as we are in God!'"</p>
  <p>Mrs. Owen stood smiling and flushed in
the middle of the eager group. Her breath
was still coming fast from the emotion of
her subject. She gave both hands to those
near her. "Thank you, dear." "Oh, how
kind you are!" "Yes," to another, "when
one gets possession of the thought it clears
away everything. All that is wrong rights
itself."</p>
  <p>Some young girls stood at the edge of the
circle, waiting for a chance to approach her.
"Isn't Mrs. Owen <hi rend="i">lovely?</hi>" said one. " She
herself makes everything she says seem so
exquisite!"</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-043"
                    n="41"/>



  <p>"I'm not sure we have a right to feel that,"
  answered her friend. "The truth ought to
  go by its own strength, without any charming 
  woman to fire it off. For myself, I try
  to listen to everything I hear as if it were
  uttered by a young man with big feet, no
  chin, and a prominent Adam's apple!"
  "Well, that doesn't make Mrs. Owen
  any less lovely, does it?" asked the first.
  "Oh, no!--and <hi rend="i">she</hi> believes all she
says!"</p>
  <p>The club members passed out. Mrs.
Owen remained to speak to the custodian
of the rooms. As she waited she was conscious 
of a sort of exaltation. She reveled
in the thought of her own happiness. Everything 
pleased her. From the first she had had
great faith in the woman's club idea. Her
society had prospered beyond all expectation. 
She looked about her; the beautiful
building in which she was had been built by
the members of the club, and consecrated
to the uses of women and children. In the
rooms nearest was an art school for working-


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-044"
                    n="42"/>




girls; upstairs a Delsarte teacher was in-
structing fifty children.</p>
   <p>Every day brought to her fresh signs of
the intellectual activity of the town. And,
she thought, spiritually everything was better 
than it had been--there was surely less
gossip, less malicious criticism! It seemed
to her that she might count the time near
when men would be true and wise, and
women free and strong.</p>
  <p>She went smiling down the stairway, a
crowd of children from the upper floor trooping 
after her. From the club she was to
go for her husband and take him with her
to a reception; it was because of this reception 
that she was dressed more showily than
she would otherwise have been. The four-
o'clock whistle of a factory around the corner 
had just sounded. At the foot of the
steps she looked ahead of her quickly, and
then turned to the children above her. " Go
back!" she cried; "Go back instantly!"</p>
  <p>As she reached the street she had come
between two men. One had. run past her,


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-045"
                    n="43"/>




bareheaded and in his shirt sleeves. There
was fury in his face, and shame too. He
stopped suddenly, his hand at his hip, and
turned on the man who pursued him.
"Don't you touch me!" he shouted; "I've
got a gun!"</p>
  <p>As he spoke his pursuer closed with him;
they went to the earth together in fierce
writhings. Mrs. Owen threw out her hands
and looked about for help. The people
who a moment before crowded the street
had moved back into a ring. She was in
the middle of it, the two struggling men at
her feet. She said to those nearest her:
"<hi rend="i">Can't</hi> you stop it? This is awful!" The
spectators grinned sheepishly. One nudged
his neighbor with his elbow, and said, in a
low voice, but with a distinct imitation of
her tone, "<hi rend="i">Can't</hi> you stop this, Jim?" Mrs.
Owen tried to look away, but she could not.
Either the horror of the thing had deadened
her senses so she could not feel it, or it was
not horrible. At any rate, she looked; more
than that, she knew she <hi rend="i">wanted</hi> to look.


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-046"
                    n="44"/>




She scrutinized the two men; they were
shabby, undersized, ill fed. She heard the
blows, and even wondered: "I did not
know that flesh striking flesh would make
a sound like that!" She saw, too, another
thing that surprised her--a blow did not
bring blood at once; first the flesh was
white, then the blood oozed to the surface.</p>
   <p>They rolled and tossed from edge to edge
of the sidewalk. One bit the other's ear,
and chewed at it furiously. The other
heaved and tossed in fierce effort to get at
his opponent's throat. As they fought they
uttered sharp little cries. It seemed that
the pursuer was getting the best of it; the
other man for a moment made no resistance,
Immediately the reason was evident; he was
trying to get his pistol out of his pocket.
Another half-turn and he would have it.
"Let me up!" he shouted, as the other
ground his elbow into his chest; "I don't
want to kill you!" The other gave no heed;
his face was full of inhuman fury. It seemed
as if nothing could reach him. The first


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-047"
                    n="45"/>



man got his hand on his pistol--in a breath
there would be murder!</p>
  <p>Mrs. Owen sprang at the two. .She
clutched the upper man by the arms. "Get
up this minute!" she said. "<hi rend="i">Drop</hi> him!"</p>
  <p>He looked around stupidly. A lady, pale
and beautiful, held him by the shoulders.
A slow surprise came over his distorted fea-
tures. His hands fell. He let her drag
him to his feet. She held him tightly by
the wrists as they stood.</p>
  <p>The other one sat up and looked blankly
at the bloody pavement. "Go!" she cried.
He staggered to an upright position, his
pistol in his hand. As he turned, the man
she held began to cry. He looked hideous
--like an ugly baby. "Lady," he said, "I
never gave her a hard word since we was
married!"</p>
  <p>The pursued man had reeled a few feet
down the street; he turned, and without a
word of warning shot full into the crowd
once--and again.</p>
  <p>By some chance no one was hit, but on


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-048"
                    n="46"/>



the instant the silent street broke into motion. 
Men shouted and pushed forward and
back, and, as if they had sprung from the
earth, two policemen appeared, swinging
their clubs as they ran.  One seized the
man with the pistol, who looked at him
with a silly, bewildered smile on his bloody
face. The other bore down on the whimpering 
wretch that Mrs. Owen still held.
He laid hold of him with that ferocity that
makes manifest the majesty of the law.
Then he turned.</p>
   <p>"Lady in the scrap?" he asked, indicating 
Mrs. Owen with a fat thumb.
  The crowd surged down the street, leaving 
  Mrs. Owen almost alone. Some street
boys, torn with vain regrets, rushed by her
in hot chase. The janitress of the building
hurried down the stair.</p>
  <p>"Won't you come up and wait for your
carriage?" she asked.</p>
  <p>'No," said Mrs. Owen; "I'll wait here."
But it seemed to her that she must move.


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-049"
                    n="47"/>

  

  "Tell the coachman to come to Mr. Owen's
  office for me."</p>
  <p>As she started she had a mechanical sort
  of perception that her beautiful garments
  were not suited to the street. Then she
  knew that she was saying to herself, "That
is what I <hi rend="i">might</hi> think; really I don't care
in the least about it--or about anything!"
She loathed herself; she had a sickening
consciousness that she was part of it all,
and that those brutes were part of her.
  Suddenly she thought, "Oh, how sleepy
I am!" Then, with the woman's club habit
of analysis, "How strange that I should be
sleepy!" She was in front of a wholesale
hardware shop. She leaned for a moment
on a convenient keg of nails, to the admiration 
of a banana peddler.</p>
  <p>A little later she walked into her hus-
band's office, past a boy who was screwing
down a copying-press and a young man who
talked a denunciatory letter into a phonograph.  
She opened a door marked <hi rend="i">Mr.
Owen</hi>. Her husband sat at a desk writing;


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-050"
                    n="48"/>



he smiled, but-did not raise his eyes above
the border of her skirt.</p>
   <p>"That you, Amy? Sit down; I'll be done
in a minute."</p>
  <p>She put her hand against the casing of
the door. It seemed to her that she could
go no farther. At the end of the line her
husband looked up. "What is it, Amy?"
he cried, hastening toward her. "What
makes you so pale?"</p>
  <p>She smiled at him mistily. "I guess,
Richard," said she, "I guess <hi rend="i">you'd</hi> be pale,
too, if you'd just been in a scrap!"</p>
</div2>
          
<pb
                    id="VAB1822-051"
                    n="[49]"/>







<div2 type="chapter"><head rend="center">A PART OF THE NEW SOUTH</head>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-052"
                    n="[50]"/>




<pb
                    id="VAB1822-053"
                    n="51"/>





<head rend="center">A PART OF THE NEW SOUTH</head>

<p><hi rend="b">A</hi>T the time of Lee's surrender the Cap-
    tain was in Virginia; it was six weeks
later when he reached his plantation. The
driver of the wagon hired to bring him from
Natchez put him down with some pretense
of apology at the big gate a half mile
from the house. Weak and ill though he
was, he did not object, for he wanted to be
alone a few moments before he reached
home. He had been stunned by defeat and
disaster, and thus far had not been able to
think clearly of the future.</p>
  <p>As he went up the leaf-strewn avenue he
saw the whole situation plainly. The fight
was over, the old hopes were dead, he must
bury them out of sight and take up with
single mind the life that lay ahead. He
had served through the entire war, his health                   


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-054"
                    n="52"/>




was broken, his fortune was gone; but he
was not dismayed.</p>
   <p>"A man's spirit is his own," he thought.
 "Defeat cannot crush it, nor, unless he
 consent, can any misfortune take it from
 him." And then he saw his wife's white
 dress float across the gallery as she came
 to meet him.</p>
   <p>It was evident almost at once that Captain
     Lee must give up the plantation to his
creditors. Before he went into the army
he had been admitted to the bar, but they
had nothing to live on while he should wait
for a practice. He took the first employment
he could get--a situation as clerk in
a cotton house--and went to work as earnestly
and simply as if he had never meant
to do anything else.</p>
  <p>The new way of living upon which the
Lees entered was very different from anything
which they had known before, but
Mrs. Lee went into its hardships as unrepiningly
as did her husband, and gayly too.
She found a score of new interests. She borrrowed

<pb
                    id="VAB1822-055"
                    n="53"/>



recipes and learned to be a frugal
housekeeper; she practiced her economies
with the air of a princess. She went much
into society, wearing her old finery so convincingly
that other women thought they
had been misinformed about the fashions.</p>
  <p>The Captain's salary was soon increased,
and before many years a partnership was
offered to him. He and his wife had meant
that as soon as their affairs grew a little
brighter he should take up the practice of
law, but, when the time came to decide, he
at once gave up all idea of following the
profession which he loved. His own preferences
and, stronger still, the traditions of
his race were set aside for the chance of
more speedily securing ease for those dependent
on him.</p>
  <p>They went North for a few weeks every
summer, and it sometimes happened that
the Captain was asked if he were related to
the great General whose name was the
same as his own. He answered in the negative
as briefly as was possible in so courteous


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-056"
                    n="54"/>




a man, nor did he ever follow the
lead thus given and talk of the time of the
Confederacy.</p>
   <p>"I wonder," said Mrs. Lee to him one
day at Mackinac, "that you did not respond
more cordially to that gentleman. He
showed such a nice spirit. I should think
you would be interested in talking the subject
over with an intelligent person on the
other side."</p>
  <p>The Captain looked at her with his fine,
gentle face drawn with feeling. "Oh, Mrs.
Lee, don't you know that I cannot talk it
over? It is too near--it hurts too much."</p>
  <p>But after that, he might have been seen
trying to make special amends in the way
of courtesy to the Northern gentleman. He
played whist with him for a partner, and
watched him lead from a short suit with
unflinching politeness; and he listened with
interest to all that the other had to say of
the surpassing attractions the state of Iowa
presented as a place of residence.</p>
  <p>To his wife only did the Captain speak


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-057"
                    n="55"/>





of the past. She listened always with tender
interest, but one day she said: "Those
times must always be sacred and precious
to you and me, but is it wise to dwell much
on what is over? Should we not fill our
minds as much as possible with other interests?"
He thanked her for her candor.
"You are right, dear; we must think of the
present."</p>
  <p>The Captain's two little daughters were
born after the circumstances of the family
had grown brighter-they were a part of
the new and prosperous life. In their childhood
he spent much time with them, and he
invariably treated them with the courtesy
he would have shown to young ladies. The
thought of reproving them, or finding fault
with them, would have given him pain.
He listened to the talk of his associates on
the fertile theme of how to bring up children
as if he had no share in such cares.
"No doubt a boy may need at times to be
disciplined, but a little <hi rend="i">girl!</hi>--I have not


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-058"
                    n="56"/>





known any instance where a little girl did
anything that you could call wrong."</p>
  <p>The Captain's daughters grew up into
beautiful, capable young women.  They
were sent North to school and came home
with an amount of Latin and science that
startled their father. Their natural charm
still further heightened by cultivation and by
conscious endeavor, they soon were recog-
nized belles. Their fondness for dancing
and finery and all kinds of social gayety was,
in their father's opinion, only natural. But
they united with these seasonable instincts
others that were less easy of comprehen-
sion. Miss Fairfax hastened to join the
Woman's Club, and studied, and, it was
said, mastered the Previous Question. Miss
Patty worked in the Art League. The
Captain in his heart did not quite see the
use of all this, but he stood by his daughters
loyally.</p>
   <p>"There's a lot of foolishness going on!"
said an old gentleman to him as they walked
down the magnolia-shaded street one morn-


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-059"
                    n="57"/>



ing. "These clubs are no place for a
woman. A woman ought to stay at home
and attend to her house and her children."</p>
  <p>The Captain saw that his friend had forgotten 
that he was speaking to a man whose
wife and daughters were active in the very
work that he condemned. He had a moment's 
embarrassment; he would not mortify
the gentleman by reminding him of it,
but he could not even seem to acquiesce in
what might be a criticism of the ladies of
his family.</p>
   <p>"I have looked into the matter rather
closely," he hastened to say, "and I do
not find any ground for the misgiving that
you entertain. The ladies meet as ladies,
to discuss in a modest and thoughtful manner 
themes of an elevating nature. And,"
he continued, warming up to his subject,
"it is my conviction that anything a lady
does is right. The hand of woman, sir,
glorifies and  blesses whatever it rests
upon."</p>
  <p>He came indeed to take pleasure in the


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-060"
                    n="58"/>




doings of the societies. When Fairfax was
appointed to write a paper on the Poets of
the Elizabethan Age, he was more interested 
in the subject than was the young
woman herself. He sent away for books
and went over the half-forgotten volumes
that had come to him from his father's
library; and when her paper was completed
he read it with much pleasure.</p>
   <p>"I certainly, was surprised at its excellence,"
he said to Mrs. Lee. "The essay
not only evinces study, but also manifests a
very considerable degree of taste and sensibility, 
and a not unfeminine perception of
humor. The style might be thought a little
abrupt, and the language in some places inclined
to colloquialism; but those are faults
that may be cured by observation and application.
I shall recommend her to the
careful reading of Addison for a month or
two, with something of Washington Irving
to-give her expression the modern cast."</p>
  <p>In the infancy of the little girls the Captain
had said to his wife, " Our children are


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-061"
                    n="59"/>





our dearest possession and we want to keep
them near us. Let us always respect their
individuality and ever encourage them to approach
us with perfect freedom." In this
there was no doubt that he succeeded; the
young ladies were free to utter their thoughts
on any subject that might come up.  As
they sat at the table one evening Miss Fairfax 
mused deeply. Suddenly she spoke:</p>
   <p>"The whole theory of this government,"
said she, "is wrong and impracticable!
The answer for our difficulty lies, I have no
doubt, in some form of socialism!"</p>
  <p>The Captain almost jumped out of his
chair in horror and indignation.  "Good
heavens, child, what are you talking about?
Socialism means atheism--the destruction
of private rights--anarchy--everything else
that is bad!"</p>
   <p>"Oh, that's not argument, father," she
responded calmly, "that's just violence.
We will talk the matter over, and I am
almost sure I can convince you."</p>
  <p>The Captain looked for an instant at the


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-062"
                    n="60"/>




pretty and fashionable young person who
had gravely made this suggestion, and then
(a most unusual thing for him) he broke
into a laugh. "Well, my dear," he said,
"I wonder what <hi rend="i">my</hi> father would have
done if I had made such a speech as that to
him."</p>
   <p>But it was plain that he had something
on his mind all the evening, and before they
separated for the night he spoke to Fairfax
seriously.</p>
   <p>"Daughter," he said, "I can hardly believe
that you were in earnest in your talk
about the theory of our national existence.
A republic like ours is the best form of government 
on which the sun ever shone; the
principles on which it is founded are the
noblest ever conceived by human intellect.
An American should be proud to lay down
his life in the defense of these principles,
and he should feel, with reverent gratitude,
that they have had the special blessing of
the Almighty as well as the applause of the
world."</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-063"
                    n="61"/>





   <p>"I was right much worried to see that
you took Fairfax's nonsense so seriously,"
said Mrs. Lee, when they were alone.
"You mustn't mind it,-it's just her way of
talking."</p>
  <p>The Captain was not to be reassured.
"I feel," said he, "that I have neglected
one of the most sacred duties of a parent.
I have not, as I should have done, day by
day instilled into the minds of my children
that patriotism which is one of the highest
qualities of any soul, and without which a
nation, like an uprooted plant, will surely
perish. And the natural outgrowth of my
carelessness is the alarming view held by
my own daughter."</p>
   <p>"Oh, I guess you're feeling it too much,"
his wife answered. "We're just like other
parents. Nobody talks much to their chil-
dren about that sort of thing nowadays. I
<hi rend="i">know</hi> they don't in the North. Perhaps the
way you and I were brought up is a little
out of style now," she added, laughingly.</p>
   <p>"My love, this is hardly a matter of


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-064"
                    n="62"/>





fashion," said the Captain, with dignity.
"It is a question, is it not, of what is true?"</p>
  <p>Shortly after this, in his gentle way, he
asked his daughters to read the Declaration
of Independence, and spoke more than once
of Washington and LaFayette. "They
belong to us as much as they did to our
forefathers," he said, "and we may well
profit by the study of their lives and motives."</p>
  <p>One beautiful evening in April the Captain 
stood on the gallery and looked down
across the lawn. The magnolia trees were
in full bloom and there were roses everywhere. 
The air was deliciously sweet, and
there was something peaceful and reminiscent 
in the scene. It brought back to him
the time when all the year was glowing and
tender as an April afternoon.</p>
  <p>As he stood, he heard the sound of a
horn, then merry shouts and laughing and
the noise of wheels. He saw the coach
coming on which his daughters had gone to
the races that afternoon. In his dignified


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-065"
                    n="63"/>




way he started down the long drive to meet
the young ladies, but before he had gone
ten steps some young men sprang to the
earth and held outstretched arms to the
girls. The Captain saw his daughters jump
from what seemed to him dizzy heights, he
saw them light like bubbles in a swirl of
lace and silken flounces. The coach drove
away, good-byes were shouted and waved,
the horn sounded out merrily as the great
vehicle swung along under the trees.</p>
  <p>As the Captain looked at the scene,
memories came to him. He thought of his
gentle mother, dead in his youth; how
softly she moved, how frail and fine she
seemed. And then he remembered his wife
when he was courting her--"the lily of
Tupelo County," they called her. He saw
her again, stepping from her father's carriage; 
the tip of one tiny satin shoe peeped
from the folds of her rich robe, and she
lightly touched with the ends of her gloved
fingers the arm of the gentleman who, hat


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-066"
                    n="64"/>




in hand, eyes on the ground, had the honor
of assisting her to alight!</p>
  <p>The young women saw him coming toward 
them. They noticed his fine military
bearing and his clear-cut, high-bred features.
"Doesn't he look awfully swell?"
said Fairfax. "Doesn't he look awfully
<hi rend="i">sweet?</hi>" answered her sister.</p>
  <p>They quickened their steps into a run.
"Bless your heart!" cried Fairfax, "how
solemn he looks, doesn't he, Patty?"</p>
   <p>"I should say so," Patty answered, putting 
her arm around his slim old waist. "He
looks as if he'd lost something and couldn't
find it."</p>
   <p>"I guess he thought he'd lost his supper,"
declared Fairfax. "He'll feel better when
he's had a 'square meal'--as mother would
say," she added, roguishly.</p>
  <p>The Captain looked at her with reluctant
disapprobation. He stopped as they were
entering the dining-room door. "My dear,"
said he, "I do not <hi rend="i">think</hi> I ever heard your
mother make use of that expression."</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-067"
                    n="65"/>



  <p>The sisters smiled at each other. "Oh,
father, you are hopeless," said one of them.
"I don't believe you'd know a joke if you
met it coming up the big road."</p>
   <p>"Then that's a good reason why you all
shouldn't tease him," said Mrs. Lee.</p>
  <p>At the table the two paid their father
every pretty attention. They told him, as
they knew he liked to be' told, fully and in
detail, about the races and everything that
had happened. They were very bright in
their talk, and he was, as he would have
said, much "diverted" by it. He admired
their wit, their grace, and their shrewd
common sense. But their point of view
was not his; he had felt this vaguely before,
now he saw it clearly. There was a difference; 
his wife could come to a subject in
the way that they did; but he felt himself
an alien.</p>
  <p>And yet, even as he perceived this, it
seemed to him that he saw a forgotten self
reflected in his daughters. The spirit of
his college days came to him like a faint
     


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-068"
                    n="66"/>




echo through their gay discourse; he almost
heard his own voice as they spoke.</p>
  <p>"Something dreadful must have happened
to me!" he thought--"something <hi rend="i">awful</hi>
--or I should have kept on being quick and
free-minded, just the way that they are."</p>
  <p>He was disturbed and bewildered. The
pressure of a situation he could not understand 
was on him. When the young ladies
were gone he turned to his wife. He recognized 
fondly as he did so that through
everything she was the same. He thought
that she looked as young as her daughters,
and her face, with its colorless olive skin
and its soft, dark eyes, had an effect of distinction 
that was lacking in the blooming
beauty of the girls. But he could not find
words in which to express his question, and
he hardly knew what he wished to ask.</p>
   <p>"Well," he said, "our daughters are
certainly very pretty."</p>
  <p>His wife looked at him with candid, laughipg 
eyes. "Is that all you can say, Mr.


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-069"
                    n="67"/>





Lee? Now, I think they are the nicest girls
in the world."</p>
   <p>"Oh, so do I," he hastened to declare.
 "But are they like other girls?"</p>
   <p>"Certainly they are," she answered, "ex-
cept that they are brighter than most girls."</p>
   <p>"But, my dear," he urged, "they are
not as <hi rend="i">you</hi> used to be!"</p>
   <p>"No," she sighed. "I <hi rend="i">try</hi> not to be envious 
when I see how much better a chance
my daughters have than I ever had."</p>
   <p>"Of course," said the Captain, "I know
the times are changed, but do you think
that with this modern spirit there is reverence 
for the old ways--respect for the things
that stand for them?" He hesitated. "'Do
you suppose that Fairfax or my little Patty
would care for those ideas that have been
dearer than life to me?"</p>
  <p>His wife answered easily, "Oh, Mr. Lee,
the girls are young; we mustn't expect much
of them yet."</p>
  <p>The Captain turned his head and saw
Patty coming toward him. She had been


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-070"
                    n="68"/>




in the next room and had heard his questions. 
There were tears in her eyes.</p>
   <p>"Father," said she, "we are <hi rend="i">not</hi> fine,
like you and mother." Then she smiled.
"But you must remember that we hadn't
the same advantages in our youth."</p>
  <p>He put his arm around her fondly. "You
two are father's dear treasures."</p>
  <p>Shortly after this Miss Patty went to visit
a friend whose husband, an officer in the
regular army, was stationed at the Post at
San Antonio. In her first letters she often
mentioned Lieutenant Walters. It was he
who sent the flowers and arranged the riding 
parties. Then she wrote no more about
him. Later she said, " They all talk a lot
about what a good family Mr. Walters belongs 
to. Ask father if he ever heard of
a Colonel Horatio Walters who was in the
Federal army."</p>
  <p>"Patty is too absurd!" exclaimed Fairfax.
"She thinks as we did when we were little,
that father knows everything and everybody
in the round world."</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-071"
                    n="69"/>




   <p>"Her instinct, if it be instinct, is not
 misplaced this time," said the Captain; "I
 have known of Horatio Walters for forty
 years!"</p>
   <p>"Well, I always <hi rend="i">did</hi> say that you were
the most remarkable man alive! How did
you ever happen to know him?"</p>
   <p>"It was when we were both young.
Every spring for many years my father
carried .us all to Newport. The Walters
family had a place there. 'Raish' and I
were together every day and all day long
through many summers."</p>
  <p>He mused smilingly for a few minutes,
then he said:</p>
   <p>"He was a mighty nice boy. It certainly
is curious-I never have seen him since we
were eighteen-never but once; and yet
positively I think of him oftener than I do
of men whom I've been meeting every day
for years."</p>
  <p>"You <hi rend="i">have</hi> seen him once since you were
grown, did you say, father?"</p>
  <p>"Yes, once when I was about twenty-


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-072"
                    n="70"/>




five," he answered. But he did not seem
inclined to say more.</p>
  <p>When they were alone Mrs. Lee said to
her daughter, "I think I can tell you when
your father met Colonel Walters again."</p>
   <p>"I thought you could," answered her
daughter; "that's why I didn't tease him."</p>
   <p>"Of course I wouldn't tell you if I thought
he would object," said Mrs. Lee; "but he
just doesn't care to speak of those things
himself. He told me long ago that one
day in Virginia at the time when it began to
be plain that the Confederate forces could
not hold out, he found that an old friend of
his was in command of the Federal regi-
ment just in front of him. He was wild to
see him, so he took a glass and went to an
elevation inside the lines. By some chance
the other man was looking for him and they
saw each other at the same instant. He
said he saw his friend throw down his glass,
swing his cap around his head, and he heard
him give the long shrill whistle--'<hi rend="i">Oo-ee-
ee!</hi>'--by which they summoned each other


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-073"
                    n="71"/>





as boys. And to his surprise he found himself 
doing the same thing."</p>
   <p>"Dear me!" said the girl, "I wonder if
 that was really a pleasant experience?"</p>
   <p>"It was to him. He said that all day
 he kept thinking of his friend's gay affectionate 
 face, and of how handsome he looked
 in his fine uniform."</p>
   <p>"It would have made <hi rend="i">me</hi> awfully <hi rend="i">mad!</hi>"
 said Fairfax.</p>
   <p>Miss Patty was absent for three months.
 When she came home her mother and sister
 thought her a trifle absent-minded, and she
 was no less so on the Saturday after her
 arrival. On that day the Captain came
 from his office with great news. Mr. Walters 
 had been with him for some time that
 afternoon. He had been courting Patty all
 winter and now asked her father's permission 
 to address her. The young man had
 behaved with great propriety and candor.
 The Captain could not but be satisfied with
 what he learned of his character and prospects. 
 He had only stipulated for a longer


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-074"
                    n="72"/>




acquaintance before an engagement should
be entered into, in case Patty should feel
inclined to accept his addresses. Concerning 
this the young man had shown a degree
of doubt that was most becoming, but when
Patty was called from her room where she
had locked herself it became evident that
the two understood each other pretty well.
As the family sat together some hours later
the Captain suddenly broke a silence by
saying, "He looks just as his father did
that day!"</p>
   <p>"Oh, father," said Fairfax, "you <hi rend="i">don't</hi>
expect us to believe that you <hi rend="i">can</hi> remember
how anybody looked thirty years ago?"</p>
  <p>But Patty rose at once and came to her
father's side. "Thank you, father," she
said; *I think that means that you like
him."</p>
  <p>The Captain had early acquired a competence, 
and by the time his daughters were
grown he was a wealthy man. Having leisure 
and means, .and a genuine interest in all
that was for the good of the community, he


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-075"
                    n="73"/>




was constantly, in spite of his reserve and
modesty, called on to fill places of prominence. 
His absolute integrity, his wide and
temperate judgment were valued most highly.
In many of the ceremonials of the region, such
as the opening of the great bridge, or the
dedication of the monument, he made, with
his distinguished bearing and his pale, sad
face, a most impressive figure. One day
as he sat reading, while Mrs. Lee by his
side worked at her embroidery, he put down
his newspaper with a sad smile. He had
been reading an announcement of his
daughter's engagement, which included a
tribute to himself as a successful man and a
public-spirited citizen. It closed with these
words: "Captain Lee is a part, and a characteristic 
part, of the New South." His
eyes took the look of one who recalls with
undying love a dead and buried past.</p>
  <p>His wife rose and put her hand on his
shoulder. She had it in her mind to catch
his thought and then to lead him out of it.
"I wonder," said she, "if you are remem.


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-076"
                    n="74"/>



bering that this week is the anniversary of
the fall of Richmond?"</p>
  <p>He looked at her with startled, bewildered
eyes. She made the quick effort of a wife
to bring him to a happier mood.</p>
  <p>'We have lived a great deal since then,
have we not?"</p>
  <p>He put his hand to his brow; the look of
distress flamed up into angry pain.</p>
  <p>"No, no!" he said. "It seems to me
that I have been dead ever since then."</p></div2>

          
<pb
                    id="VAB1822-077"
                    n="[75]"/>




<div2 type="chapter"><head rend="center">A CONFLICT OF RIGHTS</head>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-078" n="[76]"/>


<pb id="VAB1822-079"
                    n="77"/>





    <head rend="center">A CONFLICT OF RIGHTS</head>

                   <div3 type="part"><head rend="center">I</head>
<p><hi rend="b">A</hi>T six o'clock in the morning a train
     slackened and stopped at the little station. 
It was summer still, and the atmosphere 
had in it the memory of a hot day
just passed, and the promise of one to come.
The freight agent came out of his little
office and stood by the baggage car. He
was pale and sleepy-looking, but he smiled
with the good humor of a man who finds
something rather amusing in his own over-
worked condition. The blinds were down
in the Pullman car and only one passenger
appeared at the end where the white-coated
porter had placed his step. He put her bags
into her hands and sprang back on to the
car.</p>
  <p>The young lady looked up and down the
cindery platform, and across the little grassplat
                    


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-080"
                    n="78"/>




and its gay beds of foliage plants, as if
in expectation of someone to meet her.
Then she walked to the baggageman, who
had put her trunk on a hand truck and was
about to wheel it into the depot.</p>
   <p>"Do you know Mr. Amos Peabody?" she
 asked. "Has he been here this morning?"</p>
   <p>"Oh, yes," he said. I have known Mr.
Peabody and Miss Dezzie ever since I was
a little boy. But they ain't been here this
morning. They went up to Chicago yesterday 
afternoon. They laid off to do some
trading, I guess."</p>
  <p>The girl for an instant seemed dismayed.
  "When will they return?" she asked.</p>
  <p>'I don't exactly know, but I heard her
telling somebody she must get right back,
--some of her folks was coming. Now, I
reckon--"</p>
  <p>The young lady did not prolong the conversation. 
"Thank you," said she; "I will
send for the trunk."</p>
  <p>The man followed her respectfully to the
edge of the platform.  "The house is


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-081"
                    n="79"/>



straight down the street.   It's the old-
fashioned red brick with a big orchard in
front. It's been here since the Indians,
'most. Row of mill hands' cottages built
up pretty close to the far side of the lot."</p>
  <p>As the young girl walked down the dewy
street the station agent looked after her
with interest. He knew all about her; he
knew that Mr. Peabody and his maiden
sister, Miss Dezzie, had several years before
adopted a little orphan niece, and that they
had kept her at school in Vermont, where
every year they spent the summer, and that
now, having been graduated, she was coming 
to Indiana to live with them.</p>
   <p>"I don't wonder the old folks are so soft
about her," he said. "She's a hummer for
looks."</p>
  <p>The town through which Elinor Fletcher
walked was just beginning to awaken. It
was a pretty, ready-made town grouped
around the works that made the heart of it.
The same architect had planned it all.
Whether one looked at the great mills themselves


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-082"
                    n="80"/>




or at the long rows of operatives'
houses, or at the library or the theater or
the showy residences of the proprietors, half
hidden in trees, with stretches of lawn, the
same features were evident; the same red
brick, the same deep set windows, the same
olive shingles, the same green grass, close-
cut and water-drenched, and the same beds
of red geraniums all in full bloom. The
town looked as if it had been put down all
at once. Only here and there, through its
spick and span woof, there protruded a
house of an older time, a residence like the
Peabody's, which held in its aspect a memory 
of the period before the great factories
had been dreamed of,--a time, still to be
boasted of, when Greenfield had a Presbyterian 
and a Methodist and a Campbellite
church while Chicago was only a swamp.</p>
  <p>The girl walked up the long path, between
rows of blooming perennial phlox and clusters 
of gladioli, to the door of her uncle's
house. At the foot of the steps she stopped.
The front porch was dusty, and some wind-


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-083"
                    n="81"/>




blown leaves and twigs lay about it.   In
the door-recess were two newspapers, rolled
and still keeping the boomerang shape in
which they had been thrown. Under the
door was tucked a yellow envelope which
the girl recognized as possibly containing
the telegram she had sent in notification.
She looked at the closed door in thoughtful
consideration of what was to be done.</p>
  <p>Across the garden at one side was the last
of the row of cottages. Evidently its inmates 
were stirring, for smoke rose from
the chimney. Some children, who had apparently 
with one bound left their beds and
the house, stood around the back door.
They stared awhile and then ran into the
house. A woman came back with them;
she also stared, adjusted the neck of her
gown and came to the dividing fence. Elinor
went toward her with an inquiry.</p>
  <p>"Their hired girl was over here night before 
last," the woman responded, "and she
said they didn't look for you till to-morrow;
     


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-084"
                    n="82"/>




and so when they went off she was going out
to see her folks in the country."</p>
   <p>"It is quite my fault," said Miss Elinor.
 "I found I could get through sooner. Have
 you any idea when they will come home?"</p>
   <p>"Law, yes! They're going to get here tonight 
sure. The train gets in about nine--
 that is, if it ain't late. You know," said
 she, with a certain air, "that this is Labor
 Day."</p>
   <p>"Is there any hotel near?" asked the
young woman.</p>
   <p>"They ain't none in town, none nearer
than New Greenfield-that's three miles up
the road."</p>
  <p>Miss Elinor turned with a smile. " Well,
then, Mrs.-oh, Mrs. Montague, thank you!
I guess I'll have to ask you to give me some
of your coffee and let me spend the day
with you."</p>
  <p>Mrs. Montague flushed with pleasure.
"That's right. I'll take good care of you.
Montague's gone off already to get the


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-085"
                    n="83"/>




transparencies for the procession, and you
and me'll have breakfast right away."</p>
   <p>The two went into the kitchen. It was
a dreary, disorderly place. A few large
goods boxes stood about; they had not been
unpacked, but part of their contents had
been dragged out, and the rest were spilling 
over the top. "We have been here
four months," said Mrs. Montague, "but I
don't feel really settled so as to have any
ambition to get out my things. We come
here from Pullman, and he's wanting to go
on to Alton, to the wagon-works there. If
we can sell our things and get the money I
reckon we'll get off this week."</p>
  <p>The woman looked tired. Her figure was
flat and bent. She spoke in a sharp, querulous 
voice, not because she was bad tempered, 
but because that tone might claim
attention when a milder one would not
avail.</p>
  <p>The young lady took her cup of coffee
and slice of bread in her hands and sat down
on the steps behind the kitchen door. She


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-086"
                    n="84"/>



talked pleasantly with Mrs. Montague and
tried to make friends with the children.
When her breakfast was done she coaxed
them to let her wash their faces, and bribed
the little one to have her hair curled.</p>
  <p>Within Mrs. Montague was packing up
the basket of dinner that was to be taken
to the Labor-Day picnic. She explained
the program as she worked; all the unions
were to march through town in a big
procession- two bands- at the grounds
there were to be speeches, everybody was
going, and, best of all, there would be
grand fireworks.</p>
  <p>The whole suggestion of Mrs. Montague's
talk was quite new to Elinor and most interesting. 
The things of which she spoke and
her easy confidence in her own claim to be
as good as anybody were, the girl thought,
a manifestation of the free Western life,
the real American life, something quite different 
from anything possible in New England--which, 
after all, was still England
and no longer "New." Before many minutes


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-087"
                    n="85"/>



had passed, Mrs. Montague, with the
appearance of regarding the picnic as an
entertainment of her own, asked Elinor to
accompany her, and pressed the invitation
with hospitable importunity. After a little
hesitancy the young lady consented. As
they went on their way she had an amused
consciousness of the emotion the Bennington 
Institute would experience at the sight
of her on her way to a public picnic, leading
two white-haired children and chaperoned
by Mrs. Montague with her basket of lunch.</p>
  <p>At the grounds they were joined, when
the procession disbanded, by Montague,
who looked at Miss Fletcher with some
timidity and then ignored her altogether.
The crowd grew larger every minute; families 
greeted each other and pushed on.
Babies cried; women called. Little groups
formed around peddlers and venders, and
those who were anxious to get near these
attractions no sooner got within hearing
than they were equally anxious to get away.
At intervals great wagons loaded with beer


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-088"
                    n="86"/>




kegs pushed through the crowd. "Here,
Mag! Here, Miss!" cried Montague, "let's
get up to the speaking place."</p>
   <p>They held close together; Montague first,
 then his wife, basket-laden, hot and breathless, 
 then Elinor with the two babies.
 Aided by the man's elbows they got to the
 center of the space where some boards put
 across trestles made rude seats.</p>
   <p>By the time they found their places the
girl was very uncomfortable; the crowding
offended her, the noise was bewildering.
But as they sat in the comparative ease of
their position she recovered her spirits.
She said to herself that a little inconvenience 
was nothing, and anyway it would be
over in a few hours.</p>
  <p>She looked about her with renewed interest 
at the audience that was assembling.
There were family parties like the Montagues 
and herself who pushed about look-
ing in vain for seats near the front. But
there were others who were more significant; 
these were the older workingmen who


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-089"
                    n="87"/>




had come early to pre-empt good places,
and now waited in patient silence for the
speaking to begin. She saw their bent
backs, and their nervous, tired, honest faces.
She compared their hard mutilated hands
with her own, sensitive and daintily kept.
There is no entailment of crushed fingers
and swollen joints. At birth the hands of
all children are alike. Did God mean that
later they should come to such difference?</p>
   <p>The air cooled as they waited; little
breezes played about. The crowd found
places on benches, and beyond their limit
on the grass. The people grew quiet, the
faces of the younger men, which had seemed
coarse or silly when in action, now relaxed
into apathy or into a look, of timid hope
that was more pitiful than despair.</p>
  <p>The Chairman and the chief officers of
the Union took their places on a stand made
of rough lumber decorated with flags and
green branches. Elinor had heard of labor
agitators, of "loud-mouthed, beer-drinking
demagogues." She looked at the men on


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-090"
                    n="88"/>




the stand; they were pale, thin and sickly.
One of them had the deep-set, rapt aspect
of a fanatic, and the eyes of another shifted
nervously from side to side; but they were
all sad. The girl who sat in the midst of
this perceived that she had never before
thought of a great concourse which, whether
it rejoiced, protested or denounced, had
not a hope and courage that their gather-
ing seemed to lack.</p>
  <p>The meeting was opened; some reports
were read. There was trouble in New Jersey, 
and a lockout at St. Louis; in local
affairs there was nothing better, nor was
there anything new to be complained of.
There was nothing in these reports to en-
courage and nothing to stimulate. The
meeting sat apathetic and dumb.</p>
  <p>By and by a whisper passed about, "Dick
Morgan comes next." As Elinor listened
to the Chairman's last statement she got,
in Mrs, Montague's hoarse undertones, some
information about him. "He's great! He
belongs around here and they all think


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-091"
                    n="89"/>




they's nobody like him; grew up in the
shops, but he's a delegate now." A young
man came forward and began to speak
quietly. The older men settled themselves
to listen, a woman near Elinor lifted her
painted face from the shoulder of the man
who sat beside her, and fixed her eyes on
the speaker with the same absorbing atten-
tion that showed in the face of her lover.</p>
  <p>At first Elinor resented the man's appearance, 
his clear skin, his strong, easy youth.
"Of course <hi rend="i">they</hi> like him, poor things!
They think (and no doubt he agrees with
them) that it's very fine for them to have a
representative who looks like that." She
thought that he was out of place, an intrusion. 
If the cause of the laboring man had
any force, it lay in austerity, in simplicity.
This man's good looks made it, so she
thought, theatrical.  What influence he
had he had got in the cheapest and poorest
way.</p>
  <p>But as the speaker proceeded his manner
grew more forcible. He looked older and


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-092"
                    n="90"/>




sterner. Whatever beauty of feature she
might have observed passed from notice
when his face was worked upon by the
earnestness of his thought. His aspect,
growing less personal, seemed to her more
and more the expression of uncolored intellect, 
as if he were turning on the state of
things the light of an unbiased intelligence.
Each sentence was plain and direct, meaning 
apparently no more nor less than its
words; but as Elinor came under his influence 
she felt that his thought went ahead
of his word-the suggestiveness of his
presence so outran his utterance that he left
with the hearer a sense of his moderation
rather than his violence. His language had
been commonplace, and his sentences even
halting; now the words poured out of his
mouth with what seemed to the girl an in.
comparable felicity, originality, exactness
"Great heavens," she thought, "the things
I have studied are dead; this is alive."</p>
  <p>The audience at first clapped and shouted
in approval, but as Morgan proceeded they


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-093"
                    n="91"/>



kept still as if for fear of losing something.
He spoke of their hardships, but more of
the wrongs of others; he spoke of faith, of
love, of manly truth and womanly courage.
And then he spoke of their rights. "Let
no man deceive himself," he said. "There
are more rights than yours or mine. We
must try to see farther than ourselves, to
be as afraid of being wrong as we are of
being cowardly. It is easy to curse the order
of things. It <hi rend="i">is</hi> wrong, but it went wrong
centuries ago. We must try to get back to
the loving, the beautiful order of nature,
the orderthat is free from fear, from tyranny,
from selfishness. God's creatures never were
meant to hate each other. They would not,
if they had half a chance at any other way.
But as it is, a man <hi rend="i">must</hi> be greedy; he
must fight for his life. If he turns aside to
help another, he and those he loves go
to the wall. Have we been endowed with
a hundred faculties, a hundred aspirations
for what is beautiful and gentle, to give
them all up, to spend ourselves eternally


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-094"
                    n="92"/>




in belittling strife? We are all of the same
flesh-if it were only class against class,
that would be easier. If it were Right
against Wrong, that would be easier. But
it is not Right against Wrong. It is right
against right; and because we have known
poverty and misery, it is to us, rather than
to the rich and fortunate, that God will
give the wisdom and courage to work for
a better day--a millenium of peace and 
love."</p>
   <p>His spirit seemed to surge through the
crowd as he continued. The men's faces
grew pale and flushed under the eyes.
Elinor's last critical feeling melted away.
She yielded to the emotion of the moment.
There seemed to her no possible life so
glorious as the one given to the help of
humanity; nothing, she thought, could be
so sweet, so satisfying, as to put aside every
thought of self as a joyous sacrifice to this
one purpose. "Oh, my friends," said the
speaker, "do not doubt that you are equal
to whatever may come. There is a strength


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-095"
                    n="93"/>




in the heart of every man of which he has
never dreamed. There is a force on which
he has never drawn. There is a will which
rises strong and refreshed at the chance of
loss and danger. We are in a losing fight--
what of that? The struggle is almost hopeless--
does that scare any man? I tell you
there is that in you that will welcome sacrifice, 
poverty, pain and defeat, as a man
puts out his arms to his sweetheart, graceful 
and beloved. To know this-and it's
true--to feel it, if only once, lifts a man
forever, and lets him say through all time
and eternity: I was poor, I was humble, I
was despised. But in my hour I chose--
and chose greatly--and now I stand above
all that any wealth or power can give, with
those who for love and for right counted all
else as nothing. It is a chance for which
we thank God."</p>
  <p>"This," thought Elinor, "is the glorious
ministry; this is the spirit of the saints and
martyrs. With such inspiration I could
dare anything, give up everything."</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-096"
                    n="94"/>




  <p>When the speaking was over the audience 
scattered aimlessly about. There was
nothing to do. Everybody had been anticipating 
a very delightful time, and was
so abstracted in looking for it that no one
could settle down to talk with everyday
friends.</p>
  <p>Only a few had brought luncheon with
them. The others purchased thick sandwiches 
and balls of popcorn wrapped in gay
colored paper. Everybody was thirsty;
but there was no water to be had, and men
clustered about beer stands, or went back
from them to their friends with a half-dozen
mugs of beer strung on the fingers of one
hand. As Elinor moved away with her
companions, Dick Morgan's voice was ringing 
in her ears. When she saw him through
the crowd the blood came to her face. She
wanted to speak to him, she wanted to tell
him that she knew--that she understood.</p>
  <p>She could not eat the luncheon, nor drink
the mawkish lemonade that Montague
brought them. The crowd had grown


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-097"
                    n="95"/>






noisier. Gayly dressed women drove up in
shabby open carriages, and, alighting,
walked in twos and threes through the
grounds. Sometimes a man rougher and
more nearly drunk than the others joined
such a one and bought beer and candy for
her with noisy extravagance. Elinor tried
to amuse the children; she told them little
stories, and made a doll out of her hand-
kerchief; but she was conscious that she
was stared at, although her modesty kept
her from guessing what a marked object she
was with her delicate face and the fashionable 
plainness of her traveling dress.</p>
  <p>Over her shoulder she heard Morgan's
voice addressed to Mrs. Montague. She
looked up and the two were introduced, but
he continued to talk to the older woman.
The latter began to fidget-she had left her
umbrella at one of the stands. Morgan
offered to go for it, but she could not
describe the place. Elinor rose at once
and proposed that they should go together,
but Mrs. Montague objected, "No, I don't


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-098"
                    n="96"/>




want to lose this place; it'll be right in the
middle when the dancing begins. You and
Mr. Morgan stay and keep it for me. I'll
come right back."</p>
  <p>The two were left alone. Elinor spoke
first: "I heard your speech." "I know it,"
he answered; "I saw you. At first I was
afraid I could not please you; later--"</p>
   <p>"Later you saw that I was pleased,"
she said.</p>
  <p>He laughed a boyish, half embarrassed
laugh; then he grew serious. "Later I did
not care--No, I don't mean that; I forgot
whether I cared or not."</p>
   <p>"I understand; you must not care."</p>
   <p>"Oh, I might care, but I would know that
that was not the thing for me to think of."</p>
  <p>"I wanted to tell you something," she
said, hesitatingly. "I felt what you said
very deeply--I had not thought of those
things before."</p>
  <p>He looked at her. "Do you really care?"</p>
  <p>She blushed a little. "Indeed I do. You
must believe that!"</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-099"
                    n="97"/>




  <p>"I shall be glad to believe it," he answered.</p>
  <p>Suddenly the two became conscious that
there was noise and movement all around
them. Some musicians were playing near
by. "Partners for the Matrimonial Quadrille!" 
someone had shouted. They saw
that a set had formed of which they were
the last couple. The girl looked about;
Mrs. Montague was not to be seen. Everywhere 
were coarse, suspicious-looking faces.
Men and women were calling on them to
get up and dance. She turned to Morgan
with a frightened appeal. "Oh, I can't.
Let me get away from here!"</p>
  <p>A woman's sneering voice rang out. She
was a dark and glowing creature with hate
in her black eyes, and wickedness on her
painted lips. "Oh, she won't dance--she's
too good for us. Dick wouldn't let her
dance with us."</p>
  <p>Morgan gave one quick glance at the
three men who, with their partners, waited.
"It's the McCoy gang!" be groaned. He
     


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-100"
                    n="98"/>




spoke to the girl gently. "I'd like to break
the heads of some of these fellows, but a
fight would only draw a crowd around you.
Could you go through this?"</p>
   <p>She looked at him and then at the others;
her color came back and her eyes flashed.
"Certainly I can," she said.</p>
   <p>She went through the dance as coolly as if
it had been a calisthenic exercise in a school
gymnasium. The men showed some signs
of growing respect, but the women looked
at her with only more cruelty as they observed 
the change in the demeanor of their
companions.</p>
  <p>They were in the last figure, and Elinor
found herself at Morgan's side in a line of
couples who were moving toward a man
standing on a table. She heard the guffaws 
of the men, and the shrill forced
laughter of women over-merry at a coarse
joke.   Then she saw that each couple
paused a moment before the man on the
table, who went through some mummery to
which they responded, and  then broke


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-101"
                    n="99"/>




away to join the crowd. Morgan saw it
also; his face grew black. "Oh, what is
this?" asked Elinor. "It's the infernal
nonsense they call the matrimonial quadrille. 
Don't look, don't speak; it can't last
but a minute longer, and then I'll get you
out of this crowd at once."</p>
  <p>The next moment they stood before the
mock minister. She heard his drunken
voice saying, "I pronounce you man and
wife."   Then she felt herself hurried
through the crowd.  Mrs. Montague appeared 
from blurred space, and Morgan
spoke to her. "Please keep close by Miss
Fletcher--you'd better take her home!"</p>
  <p>The woman was tired and peevish. "I
don't see what Morgan's jawing <hi rend="i">me</hi> about,"
she said to his retreating back. "I've lost
my umbrella, and <hi rend="i">he's</hi> run off, goodness
knows where, and the young ones are acting 
like the Old Scratch, and I ain't had a
bit of pleasure yet, and it's most night
now."</p>
  <p>The children dragged at their mother's


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-102"
                    n="100"/>







skirts. "Let me take them home, Mrs.
Montague," begged Elinor. "I am sure I
can find the way. We are all so tired."</p>
   <p>Mrs. Montague finally agreed to this.
 "The truth is," said she, "I never seen
 any fireworks figure pieces, and somehow I
 just can't bear to leave 'em.  I reckon the
 children 'll go to sleep and your aunt 'll be
 there before long, anyhow."</p>
   <p>"Oh, yes; indeed it's quite right," urged
the girl. She got out of the grounds and
stood waiting for a car. She held in her
arms the two-year-old baby, and the four-
year-old child began to cry to be carried,
too. She was trying to soothe it when
Dick Morgan took the little one from her,
and lifted the other one to his arm.</p>
  <p>In the five-mile ride they hardly spoke;
and they walked in the bright moonlight
down the street to the house with the staid
manner of old people. " Give me the key,
please," he said. "I never once thought
of that!" she gasped.</p>
  <p>They looked at each other blankly; each


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-103"
                    n="101"/>






saw what the other felt. "I can sit here
on the steps till my aunt comes," she said.</p>
   <p>"Well, I'll go."  But as he spoke a
wagon went by full of men singing and
swearing. "I'll not leave you here alone,"
he said.</p>
  <p>They sat together on the little porch in
front of the house. Elinor held the baby
in her arms; the older child leaned against
Morgan's shoulder. The moonlight showed
them each other as plainly as daylight could
have done, but it added to the unreality of
the situation. The girl felt as if she had
been picked up out of her New England life
and dropped down on another planet, and
that on it were but two persons, herself and
Morgan. She found herself talking more
freely than she had ever done of what
seemed to her the true ideals of life. He
responded with instant comprehension of
the things she tried to say. All they said
was abstract (or they believed it to be so),
and full of the high purity of intense youth.
If there came to him a momentary consciousness


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-104"
                    n="102"/>

102





of her beauty and sympathy it
was not a feeling that he looked for or encouraged.</p>
  <p>The train was late, and, as the time went
on, their conversation grew less impersonal.
The young man spoke of his childhood: "I
was very happy," he said, "although my
mother was dead, and my father, who
worked in the shops, was not always kind.
I had a friend, a boy of my own age, with
whom I spent much of my time. We knew
every foot of the country for miles around
here, and, except the months when we went
to the village school, we lived out of doors.
It was a happy time. Then, of course, when
I was old enough I went into the shops.
Since then it seems to me I have always
been alone."</p>
  <p>"But what has become of your friend?"</p>
  <p>The young man answered shortly, "Oh,
I don't see him often now; we have not
much in common." He added, "I suppose
a man really has nothing but himself in the
whole universe."</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-105"
                    n="103"/>







   <p>"Yes," she said, "himself, and the hope
of getting what he is working for--if he
knows what that is."</p>
  <p>The young man looked past her at the
sapphire sky.</p>
   <p>"I don't hope for success; I don't expect
anything of the sort. But there is one
thing I do want--that is, to believe in myself--
to believe that I mean to give my life
to my own people. If I can only feel that
I'm true to that--"</p>
  <p>"<hi rend="i">I</hi> believe in you," she said; "in your
goodness and your faithfulness;--yes, and
in the end there must be success. The
down-trodden shall be raised up. God will
not forget his creatures."</p>
  <p>She was intense and exalted; the young
man thought that as she sat there with the
baby in her arms she was like the Blessed
Virgin, the worship of whom was his inheritance.
All hope and sorrow were in her
eyes.</p>
  <p>The baby shivered. Morgan rose, took
off his coat and, leaning over the two,


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-106"
                    n="104"/>

104





wrapped it around the little one. It was
eleven o'clock. Far down the street the
lights showed that the train was in.</p>
  <p>"Your uncle and aunt will be here in a
few minutes," he said. "I will stay with
the babies."</p>
  <p>They both rose. "I am going away in
the morning and I may not come back for a
long time," he said, after a pause. She
spoke with sudden impulse:</p>
   <p>"Will you always believe that I am
the same-your friend, as long as I live?"
  A man and woman walking by stopped
and looked in curiously. It was the McCoy
woman. She raised her voice:</p>
  <p> "Oh, it's Dick Morgan and his girl, hiding 
in the dark."</p>
  <p>The two scarcely heard. In a moment
the train omnibus came rumbling up the
street. There was an instantaneous change
in the relation of the shadows on the porch
and then Elinor Fletcher was flying through
the yard to the door of her uncle's house.</p></div3>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-107"
                    n="105"/>


  


                   <div3 type="part"><head rend="center">II</head>

  <p>It was' natural that Elinor should sleep
late next morning, and equally natural that
her elders should wake early to enjoy the
consciousness that they at last had her
under their own roof. Miss Dezzie herself
prepared the breakfast, and she and Amos
tiptoed around the kitchen and talked in
whispers lest they should awaken the tired
girl.</p>
   <p>"Poor child," sighed Miss Dezzie, "she
just looked all used up last night. Now,
brother Amos, when she <hi rend="i">does</hi> come down,
<hi rend="i">don't</hi> go to bothering her asking her about
her trip--there's nothing more exhausting
to a person than that sort of talk."</p>
   <p>"I don't want to!" cried Uncle Amos
with warmth, "I feel bad enough already
to think of her getting in on the six o'clock
train, four hours before us--as she must 'a
done, and nobody to meet her. You noticed,
sister Dezzie, I shut you up pretty sharp
last night when you began asking her about


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-108"
                    n="106"/>







it. You could see that she could hardly
speak."</p>
   <p>"Well, well," sighed Miss Dezzie, "I
 only hope she ain't sick. She doesn't look
 like she did last summer, Amos.  She's
 real peaked and thin."</p>
   <p>"Now, Dezzie, do hush," cried Amos.
 "If you had your own way you'd worry
 that child into the grave by forever thinking
 she's sick. She's just as well and strong
 as a young pine tree, and you know it. As
 to her being thin--well, I never fancied
 fat girls much."</p>
   <p>"You never fancied any girl," said Miss
Dezzie, with piercing sarcasm.  "You
think whatever Elinor is is all right just
because it's she--and that reminds me,
Amos; I don't want you should be so foolish 
about her looks. Folks will laugh at
you. Of course she's a nice-looking girl,
but other folks may, for-all we know,
think their girls are just as pretty."</p>
  <p>"It ain't likely," said Amos. Miss Dezzie 
mused for a while.  "Her mother began


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-109"
                    n="107"/>







to get thin at just her age," she said,
anxiously.</p>
  <p>Amos vanished from the breakfast table.
In a few minutes he came back.  "I don't
want to scare you, sister, but I've been listening 
at her door, and I can't hear breathing,"
he faltered.</p>
   <p>"Of course you couldn't hear her
breathe," said Miss Dezzie.  "She never
was one to snore." She gave him a kindly
push into his chair. "Now you finish your
breakfast."</p>
  <p>The breakfast being over, Miss Dezzie
washed the breakfast things while Amos attended
to the canary birds. Then the two
repaired to the sitting-room (a pleasant,
sunny room filled with a blending of Vermont 
comfort and Indiana liberality), where
Amos read aloud a chapter from the Bible.</p>
   <p>"Did you notice Elinor had on one of
those new-style cut skirts last night?" asked
Miss Dezzie, as she settled herself to her knitting.  
"It's the first I've seen except that
Chicago girl's who was at the Gilroys'--


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-110"
                    n="108"/>







and that didn't look anything more like Elinor's!"</p>
   <p>"I don't know that I noticed it specially,"
said Amos. "But it seemed to become her
real well."</p>
  <p>The hired girl appeared. She was late.
"I stopped to see them Montagues," she
said, "but they've gone; left this morning
--poor tramps."</p>
   <p>"Of course," said Amos, "Elinor will
want to stay mostly with us for a year or
two till she gets to feeling real well 
acquainted, but we must remember that we're
old, and young folks like company. Have
you thought of that, sister?"</p>
  <p>"A year or two," sniffed Miss Dezzie.
"Why, brother, I calculate she'll know the
most of the young folks 'round here in a
couple of months. We are all asked down
to Martha Gilroy's to tea, Sunday."</p>
  <p>"That's good! It's just like Martha not
to wait. They're good friends year in and
out. It ain't Chauncey Gilroy's fault if he
started a factory and got rich while I was


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-111"
                    n="109"/>







satisfied to live along on my little property."</p>
   <p>"Certainly not," said Miss Dezzie. "It's
to his credit. Not that I should 'a wanted
you to 'a done different, Amos. Chauncey's
fortune's brought him care and trouble. The
men don't act like they did thirty years
ago."</p>
   <p>"Well, I d' know as I blame the men."</p>
   <p>"Well, <hi rend="i">I</hi> d' know as I blame Chauncey
Gilroy," said Miss Dezzie. "But I'm glad
John is such a nice young man, and beginning 
to take the load off his father's shoulders."</p>
  <p>They heard a light step in the hall.
"Here she is," said one of them. Elinor
entered. She was fresh as the morning.</p>
  <p>"Yes, here she is!" she said, "and she's
glad she's here, and she's going to stay here
forever!"</p>

  <p>When Chauncey Gilroy and Amos Peabody 
had come West to make their fortunes
forty years before, Gilroy had firmly intended, 
as soon as he should be able, to go


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-112"
                    n="110"/>








back to Vermont for a wife. But while be
was yet a poor young man he married Martha 
Simcox--a bright, sweet-tempered, sensible 
Indiana girl, and in the years of his
happy married life he grew to be, as his
Vermont friends said, "more Hoosier than
Martha herself." His wife worked and
saved and helped him to lay the foundation
of his fortune. In the early days she knew
the families of the workmen, and they were
all good friends together. If now, when
the men were numbered by hundreds instead 
of tens, she could not come near to
them, it was surely not a thing for which
she was to be blamed.</p>
  <p>The Gilroys spent their money without
conscious ostentation. Gilroy liked what
was substantial; his wife enjoyed pretty
things; so their house was handsome and
pleasing. They knew a few very rich people 
away from home, but the society they
prized was that of their plainer friends in
Greenfield. The wife's chief cares were to
save her husband from bother, to try to make


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-113"
                    n="111"/>







a good man of her son Jack, and to help all
the young people around to have a good
time.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Gilroy met Elinor during the week.
She saw for herself that the girl was not only
pretty, but well-bred and lively. In short,
she was what Mrs. Gilroy called "nice."
When the time approached for her guests to
arrive on Sunday evening, she bethought
herself of her wish that the girl should be
received with special cordiality. She began,
in what she considered a wily way, to gossip 
about the Peabodys.</p>
   <p>"I have always thought that their tenderness 
for that little orphan was beautiful;
such people as they are the salt of the
earth."</p>
  <p>"Yes, indeed," responded John. He knew
what was coming.</p>
  <p>"Of course anyone would fear that the
girl would be spoiled by their fondness--I
own I <hi rend="i">was</hi> a little afraid of it myself."</p>
  <p>"Dear me! were you?" asked her son.</p>
  <p>"You know I am not one to form hasty


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-114"
                    n="112"/>






opinions, or to take sudden fancies," she
said. John contemplated his cigarette with
solemn interest, while the father smiled at
him over Mrs. Gilroy's head.</p>
   <p>"And I really am very particular about
 girls, but I must say I was pleased with
 Elinor Fletcher. She is so gay, so helpful,
 so exactly what a daughter should be. I
 really think you'll take great pleasure in
 knowing her."</p>
   <p>"I am glad to hear that she is what you
say," said Jack, "but as I am at present
not conscious of needing the gayety and
helpfulness of a daughter--"</p>
   <p>"Now, John, don't begin that way," cried
the lady; "I only mean for you to be nice
to her."</p>
   <p>"Mrs. Gilroy, please inform me if I am
not always nice to your guests?"</p>
   <p>"Oh yes--you'll be <hi rend="i">nice</hi> enough, I 
suppose; but do try to make her like you."</p>
   <p>"Mother, I assure you I don't dare to try.
My effort must always be in the other direction 
when I'm with the female sex. Mine


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-115"
                    n="113"/>







is the fatal gift to fascinate in spite of myself."</p>
  <p>"Oh, Chauncey, make him behave!"</p>
  <p>As the Peabodys and Elinor walked up
to the house through the well-kept grounds,
Miss Dezzie talked of John. "He was the
nicest, boy, but always in mischief. He
was in my Sunday-school class, he and
Dick Morgan." ("Poor Dick," said Amos).
"They used to come by our house for 
gingerbread every Sat'day.   You wouldn't
dream, seeing John so elegant in church
this morning, how dirty he used to get,"
Miss Dezzie added, to Elinor.</p>
  <p>"What a good time those two boys had!"
said Amos. "Martha Gilroy was always
a sensible woman.   She knew John got
no harm from Dick. They grew up like
brothers."</p>
  <p>Elinor listened politely, although she had
her own opinion. She had thought when
she saw John Gilroy in church that he
looked stiff and priggish. He on his part
vanished when he saw her approaching the
     


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-116"
                    n="114"/>







house. "Mother probably knows less about
girls than anybody living. But of course
I'll go back when tea is ready, and try to
be agreeable."</p>
  <p>He came into the dining-room after they
were seated. His slight look of surprise
when he first saw Elinor would not have
been recognized by anyone who did not
know him well. The Peabodys evidently
understood the languid manner with which
their niece was at first displeased. "He
must be nice," the girl thought, "or Uncle
Amos wouldn't be on such good terms with
him."</p>
  <p>The meal was quite informal. A tidy
maid servant waited on the guests, but in
her absence Mrs. Gilroy sent her son to the
sideboard. The old people talked about the
morning's sermon. The ladies agreed that
the preacher had been narrow. "He talked
as if there was nothing right but Presbyterianism," 
said Miss Dezzie. "Now I think
there's something good in every church."</p>
  <p>"Of course there is," declared Mrs. Gilroy.


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-117"
                    n="115"/>




"Some of the best people I ever knew
were Catholics."</p>
  <p>The young man rose and gathered his
plate in one hand and his teacup in the
other.</p>
  <p>"This conversation is getting entirely too
lax for me.  I have never realized until
now the danger the community is in from
the loose views of advanced and radical
women like mother and Miss Dezzie. If I
cannot stem the tide I can at least, as I go
down, make my weak protest against such
destructive views. I shall sit by these persons 
no longer."   He moved down the
table, stopped a moment at Uncle Amos'
side, then doubtfully shook his head and
moved on. He stood before Elinor and
looked at her sternly. "'Miss Fletcher, ere
I let myself sit down by you answer me one
thing. Are you entirely sound on the
Thirty-nine Articles?"</p>
  <p>"I am," said she.  "Pray be seated,
and you and I in the middle of a degenerate


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-118"
                    n="116"/>








age will together uphold the banner of
truth."</p>
   <p>The old people laughed. "It's a little
queer, Jack, considering how strict your
views are," said Mr. Gilroy, "that your
mother has such a hard time getting you to
church."</p>
   <p>"I am misunderstood in that as well as
in other matters," answered John. "The
fact is, I can't get my conscience reconciled 
to instrumental music."</p>
   <p>"Your situation is painful, truly," said
Elinor. "No doubt, too, you disapprove
of promiscuous sittings."</p>
   <p>"I do indeed," he answered, "and I am
glad to feel that the young sister agrees
with me."</p>
  <p>The conversation became divided after
tea. John and Elinor went to one corner
of the drawing-room to see a new picture,
and remained there. Mrs. Gilroy beamed
approvingly when she saw that her son was
really exerting himself to entertain the
young woman. She had no doubt that any


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-119"
                    n="117"/>




girl would like John if he would be but half
way pleasant.</p>
  <p>As the guests were about to leave, the
young man addressed his mother:</p>
   <p>"I asked Miss Fletcher, as you told me
to, if she played tennis, and she's accepted
your invitation for to-morrow afternoon."</p>
   <p>"Oh, I'm <hi rend="i">so</hi> glad," gushed the good lady,
who had never heard of the matter till that
minute.</p>
  <p>When they were gone, Mrs. Gilroy, full
of the pleasure of the occasion, turned to
her son:</p>
  <p>"Well, it wasn't so <hi rend="i">very</hi> hard, was it?"</p>
  <p>"Mother," he said pensively, "I'd go
through even more than that to please you!"</p>
  <p>"Really, Jack," said the father, "your
devotion to your mother's wishes this evening 
brought tears to my eyes."</p>
  <p>From that time on there was a great deal
of tennis played on the Gilroy's court, and
John Gilroy seemed to think it only common 
courtesy to stroll home with Elinor
after the game was over. Other girls were


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-120"
                    n="118"/>







there, too. He knew them much better
than he knew Elinor, and she thought it
very nice of him to pay so much attention
to her. Mrs. Gilroy was always sending
over to suggest a picnic supper down the
river or out on the Indian mound.</p>
  <p>A rainy week came. John Gilroy was
out of town. Elinor wrote long accounts
of the picnics and tennis games to her
school friends, but the days seemed a little
dull. Late one afternoon she saw the
young man's knowing mail-phaeton dash up
the road. It stopped at her uncle's gate.
The groom sprang to the ground, touched
his hat and caught the reins with the same
motion as his master passed him.</p>
  <p>The young man, faultlessly dressed,
walked deliberately up the path. When he
rang, Elinor opened the door (such was the
friendly custom of the house). "Good
evening," he said; "is there any gingerbread 
about the place?"</p>
  <p>"I think so," she answered. "Will you


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-121"
                    n="119"/>








wait while I find out?" She came back
smiling: "Yes, there's lots."</p>
  <p>"Very well," he said, taking off his hat;
"if Mr. Peabody and Miss Dezzie are willing 
I'd like to stay to supper."</p>
  <p>He often came to supper, and in the
evening the two young people sat on the
porch, and at intervals one of them played
on mandolin or guitar. The elders, perfectly 
happy, sat inside, Miss Dezzie knitting 
and Mr. Peabody reading the paper.</p>
  <p>One night Mr. Peabody lowered his voice
and said to his sister: "Do you know,
Dezzie, I <hi rend="i">think</hi> there's a little sparking
going on out there!"</p>
  <p>Miss Dezzie flamed up in virginal indignation.</p>
   <p>"Ain't you ashamed of yourself, Amos,
to have such thoughts? If you put such a
notion as that in their heads I'll never forgive 
you!"</p>
  <p>The old man grinned sheepishly, and said
no more.</p>
  <p>But only a night or two later the young


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-122"
                    n="120"/>





people came in together through the open
window. The young man's eyes shone and
he laughed for happiness.</p>
   <p>"I have asked Elinor to marry me," he
 said, "and she says she will if you two will
 consent."</p>
   <p>"Come let me give you a good hug," said
 Miss Dezzie. "This is just what I've been
 expecting."</p>
   <p>The personal impression which Dick Morgan 
had made on Elinor's mind soon faded
away, but her determination to try to help
the distressed and down-trodden remained
almost as definite as it was at first. Early
in her engagement she thought with pleasure 
that she would now be in a position to
do more than she could have otherwise done.
The Labor-Day picnic she had never spoken
of to her aunt and uncle. At first she refrained 
because they were already so distressed 
at having been absent when she
arrived; and then, with the Montagues gone,
and many new interests coming to her, the
whole thing seemed far away and irrelevant.


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-123"
                    n="121"/>





Nevertheless, she was anxious to tell her
lover. She hoped indeed that she might
bring him to think pleasantly of Morgan.
It was evident that there was some coolness
between the two. She was the more desirous 
of doing this because suddenly trouble
threatened in the shops. The unions held
meetings every night with closed doors.
Strange-looking men appeared in town.
Some of the best hands stopped work and
moved away. The two Gilroys were busy
and careworn. "To-night I will tell John
all about my acquaintance with Morgan,"
resolved Elinor, in an access of conscientiousness.</p>
  <p>He came earlier than usual that evening
and sat on the porch with her aunt while
she finished a letter which she was writing.</p>
  <p>"You look tired, John," she heard her
aunt say.</p>
  <p>"I <hi rend="i">am</hi> tired; I'm awfully worried. Things
are pretty bad at the shops. Nothing is
certain from one hour to the next."</p>
  <p>"What do the men want?"</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-124"
                    n="122"/>




   <p>"We don't know, and I don't believe
that they know. It seems pretty rough
when we've always tried to treat them
fairly," he added. "However, I'm not going
to complain. What disturbs me most is
the fear that we may have to postpone our
marriage."</p>
   <p>"Where is Dick Morgan?" asked Miss
Dezzie, after a pause.</p>
   <p>"I don't know," replied John. "I would
rather not think of him, not hear of him,"
he went on, in a voice vibrant with a protesting 
indignation. He felt that the man
who had been for so much of his life his
dearest friend had now, without offense on
his own part, chosen to regard him as an
enemy. That man was now absent, through
such a troublous time as this--and working 
against him from a distance, probably.
Far less prompt and clear-sighted than
Morgan in detecting the inevitable ending
of the perfect equality of their boyhood,
Gilroy was hurt and angered by his friend's
defection, and in the other's concern for


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-125"
                    n="123"/>





"his own people" he even scented the presence 
of hypocrisy. "You know what that
man was to me, Miss Dezzie," he said, as if
the words were forced out of him. "Well,
he has gone back on me."</p>
  <p>"Oh, maybe he hasn't," she said, comfortingly.</p>
   <p>"I'd give anything to think that he hasn't,
but I can't see anything in it except that.
What I want to do is to forget all about
him. He's gone, and I hope he won't come
back."</p>
  <p>After a pause he spoke more calmly:
"You don't know what a comfort it is to
me that Elinor doesn't know anything about
all this. There isn't a soul about here but
her who doesn't know all the ins and outs
of the relations of the shops and the men.
It's such a relief to get away from it once
in a while."</p>
  <p>"Oh, I <hi rend="i">can't</hi> tell him to-night," said
Elinor to herself.</p>
  <p>The troubles blew over and the young
people were married about six months from


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-126"
                    n="124"/>





the time when they first met. They went to
live in a beautiful house that Mr. Gilroy had
built for them in one corner of his grounds.
With every month Elinor loved her husband
better. She admired his manliness, his integrity, 
his generosity; and she delighted in
his responsive mind and fastidious taste.
She was very happy. At times she thought
of Morgan and his speech with a stinging
fear that she had been disloyal to what she
had promised herself to do. But she dispelled 
her uneasiness with the thought that
the men were contented and Morgan might
never come back; if he did she would tell
her husband of the friendship she had promised 
to him and to his cause.</p>
  <p>One afternoon several months after her
marriage, she drove to the works. She sent
the carriage away and started to walk home
with her husband. Some workmen came
out of a shop entrance and stood aside to
let the two pass. Elinor glanced up and saw
Morgan. A look of recognition came over
her face. He turned scarlet, and so did


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-127"
                    n="125"/>




she. But in a breath she was past him.
The next moment she and her husband
were joined by a young woman of their
acquaintance.</p>
   <p>"Oh, why did I not speak to him?" Elinor
kept thinking. "But it was so sudden. I
did not know that he was back here again,
and now I can't make John understand."</p>
  <p>She thought of it all night. To seem to
have forgotten in her luxury and ease the
promises she had made to one less fortunate
was unspeakably shameful. "If I could
see him just one moment," she said, "and
tell him I was surprised out of my senses!"
She even mentally composed notes to him.</p>
  <p>The next day she went again for her husband. 
He was not quite ready to go, and
as she waited for him she paced up and
down the asphalt walk that ran past the
offices and along the side of the high iron
fence that shut the works from the street.</p>
  <p>John Gilroy, standing near a window as
he gave some last orders, saw Dick Morgan
come out of the gate. He saw his wife advance,


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-128"
                    n="126"/>




and the severity of Morgan's face
lighten as she spoke. And then the two
parted as quietly as they had met. John
was bewildered. "In heaven's name, what
does that mean?" he said. And then he
bethought himself: "She probably took him
for the gardener and asked him about the
beds of foliage plants on the grass-plat."
But he did not forget the occurrence.</p>
  <p>The setting up of a new household had
stimulated the social life of the neighborhood. 
The wealthier families of the adjacent 
manufacturing towns plied the young
people with invitations and visits. Guests
were constantly in the house. Their way
of living became much more luxurious than
that of the older Gilroys. There were more
servants, more carriages; there was more
display of every sort. This was not because
either John or Elinor wished to make a show
of wealth, but because it was easy and
pleasant to adopt the habits of their associates.</p>
   <p>In this manner the gulf between the houses


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-129"
                    n="127"/>








of employer and employed grew wider every
month. John was conscious of this, and
sometimes painfully so, when he saw Dick
Morgan's pale face and shabby coat.</p>
   <p>"But why should I make myself unhappy
about <hi rend="i">that?</hi>" he said, grimly; "it's Dick's
own doing--not mine."</p>
  <p>These thoughts grew frequent, and the old
yearning for Dick's friendship came back.
One day he stepped to the door of his office:
"Send to the East shop for Dick Morgan,"
he said; "I want to see him."</p>
  <p>A moment later he added to himself,
"And what I'll say to him when he comes
I don't know."</p>
  <p>Morgan came in, erect and grave. He
looked straight at Gilroy. "Well, what do
you want?"</p>
  <p>"Sit down, Dick," said Gilroy, but Morgan 
remained standing. Gilroy rose, his
feeling varying between hurt pride and the
old friendship.</p>
  <p>"Dick," he said at last, "can't we make
up somehow?"</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-130"
                    n="128"/>





   <p>"I don't see how we can," answered Morgan, 
simply. The two stood and looked at
 each other.  All conventionalities were
 stripped off.</p>
   <p>"I don't see why I bother about it since
you are so plaguey cool," said Gilroy, hotly;
then he burst out, "Dick, don't you see
this is pretty rough on me sometimes?"</p>
   <p>"It's pretty rough on me <hi rend="i">all</hi> the time,
Jack," said Morgan.</p>
   <p>"Well, isn't it your own fault?" said Gilroy. 
"You know I'd make you foreman of
one of the shops or take you here in the
office or do anything else just to have your
friendship--to believe in it as I used to."</p>
  <p>"I don't want your jobs, friendship or no
friendship. I only came back because the
Union sent me. I earn every cent I get
and you know it."</p>
   <p>"And you slap me in the face when I try
to show you I'm in earnest!"</p>
  <p>"I suppose it seems that way, but I can't
take favors and I won't," said Dick.</p>
  <p>"Good heavens, it isn't a favor! We


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-131"
                    n="129"/>




grew up together like brothers.  Do you
remember how you used to climb up the
lightning rod and sleep with me when your
old daddy came home drunk at night?"
In a momentary cessation of antagonism
the two smiled at each other like boys.</p>
   <p>"Yes, and it was pretty often," said Morgan. 
"And do you remember the time we
camped out?" he added, softening still further.</p>
   <p>"Yes," said Gilroy, "and the time when
we read the 'Three Musketeers' in the old
apple tree? And you got so excited you fell
out of the tree into the cider vat?" They
laughed and then were silent. Their faces
grew stern again. Gilroy spoke first: "How
did things get this way?"</p>
  <p>"Oh, I don't know," said Morgan. "Jack,
what's the use? It just hurts, and we can't
change it!"</p>
  <p>"But maybe we could change it," persisted 
Gilroy. "When did it begin? I've
asked myself a thousand times, and I can't
think."</p>
    


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-132"
                    n="130"/>





  <p>Morgan reflected. "I think it began
when you first came back from school," he
said, as calmly and candidly as if he were
recalling an historical date.</p>
  <p>Gilroy flushed up. "Dick, I may have
been a fool then--I was a silly boy--but
before Heaven I didn't mean to brag. I
didn't brag half as much as you did the time
you ran away and went to the State Fair
at Indianapolis. It was all of a piece with
that!"</p>
  <p>"You were kind of offish," said Morgan.</p>
  <p>"Offish! well I should smile! I came
home expecting to have a good time with
you, and you'd cut off with any fellow under
the sun rather than me! You know, Dick
Morgan, that you left me to go fishing
alone--" He stopped with the impatience
of a man who feels a petty thing and is
ashamed of it.</p>
  <p>Dick stared. Could it be that Jack had
actually been jealous? No, it was too absurd.</p>
  <p>Gilroy continued; "And then when I


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-133"
                    n="131"/>




coaxed my father into saying he'd send you
to college with me you wouldn't go--Oh,
you were mighty fond of me!"</p>
   <p>"I couldn't go then--I was too proud by
then."</p>
  <p>"Too proud! Isn't anybody else proud
but you? Dick, I'd have shared your last
dollar then if I'd needed it, and you know it!"
  For the first time Dick broke out in a
rage: "For mercy's sake, man, be still!
Are you an idiot? Can't you see that I'd
have shared your last dollar (as God knows
I would now), but the cursed thing about it
was that it <hi rend="i">wasn't</hi> your last dollar!" Then
he spoke more quietly: "It's no use. I
told you so in the beginning;" he put his
hand on the door knob as he spoke.</p>
  <p>"Well, if you've determined we can't be
friends I am sure I won't beg you," said
Gilroy, coldly.</p>
  <p>"No, we can't be friends." Morgan was
about to go when a sudden impulse struck
Gilroy.</p>
  <p>"Look here," he said; "tell me the


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-134"
                    n="132"/>




truth, anyhow. Is there any other reason
why we can't be friends?"</p>
   <p>Morgan turned and looked at him.</p>
  <p>"There is," he said.</p></div3>

 
 <div3 type="part"><head rend="center">III</head>
   <p>A hard winter set in early. The Chauncey 
Gilroy Company had a heavy load to
-carry. Other mill owners closed their doors
to wait for better times, and advised the
Gilroys to do the same. The old man refused 
to think of it. "The Gilroy mills
have not lost a day in thirty years, and we're
not going to close up now just because we're
not making much." Fewer and fewer orders
came in at anything like reasonable prices.
There was really not enough work to go
around. The Gilroys and their superintendents 
spent hours in consultation. Young
Gilroy and the others agreed that the thing
to do was to put all hands on half work.
But his father objected: "I don't like that,
and the men won't. It looks crooked. If
we've got to do something we will keep all


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-135"
                    n="133"/>







the married men at the present rates--
they've got their wives and young ones--
and lay off the single men."</p>
  <p>The single men did not move on in search
of other work, as had been expected. All
day they clustered in idle, discontented
groups around the station and near the gates,
and at night they filled the saloons with
brawling, hungry drunkards. What else
could they do, they asked? The old man
knew when he discharged them that there
wasn't a job in two hundred miles.</p>
  <p>At Lunderville, ten miles away, the situation 
was worse. The Lunders had kept
their factories open and had taken contract
after contract at low prices. Then they
made heavy cuts in the wages, claiming
in a statement to the men that they were
obliged to reduce wages forty per cent all
round to work out the contracts, but declaring 
that they wanted to do the fair thing
and to keep the men if it were possible.
The men agreed, and worked for weeks on
starvation wages. Many a good steady man


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-136"
                    n="134"/>




with a family could only make a dollar a
day. Suddenly a discovery was made. The
cuts were out of all proportion. Even at
the low prices of the contracted work the
Lunders were piling up immense profits
while their men starved and froze. A strike
was ordered, and two thousand men were
adrift without money or employment.</p>
   <p>It was hoped by the union that the prospect 
of heavy damages on unfilled contracts
would bring the Lunders to terms, but the
head of the firm bragged privately to the
Gilroys that they couldn't be bullied worth
a cent. The largest of the contracts were
only begun, prices had gone down so that
some of the big firms East would like well
enough to take the whole thing off their
hands.   He showed the Gilroys letters,
which he afterward left with them, from
Ohio and Pennsylvania manufacturers containing 
definite offers. He said he was just
itching to get the whole thing lifted off to
another part of the country; it would teach
the men not to monkey with the buzz-saw.</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-137"
                    n="135"/>




  <p>The matter of the strike made great excitement 
at Greenfield. Nothing else was
talked of, and resolutions were passed denouncing 
the Lunders and expressing sympathy 
for the strikers. As for the Lunder
brothers, they took their families and went
off to the Mediterranean.</p>
  <p>The indignation of the Gilroys, father and
son, although not expressed publicly, was
not less than that of the men.</p>
  <p>"The Lunders lack common humanity,"
said John; "they are lost in greed and tyranny."</p>
  <p>"They are dirty dogs!" roared the father.
"I don't want any money made that way.
I'd just like to show 'em the way an honest
man treats his hands."</p>
  <p>This thought took possession of him, and
it was not long until he conceived of a plan
which he hastened to put forth.</p>
  <p>"Jack," said he, "the thing for us to
do is to enlarge our plant and take the Lunders' 
unfulfilled contracts, and set things
humming in this neck of the woods."</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-138"
                    n="136"/>




   <p>The young man held out against it for
several days. "I don't like it, father," he
said.   ' It's like letting out sail in a storm.
On one side there are awful risks, and on
the other there is no margin of profit at
the contract prices unless we cut wages
too."</p>
   <p>"Who wants a profit?" shouted the old
man.   "Even if we lose a little we can
stand it. What we want is to help the men
through this winter."</p>
   <p>"But you must remember that if we take
the contracts this late in the day we sha'n't
have a chance to avoid the penalty if we
don't get the work done in time. Just let
the men get it into their heads to strike
and we're hung up with fires out, engines
rusting, and a hundred thousand dollars
damages to pay."</p>
   <p>"What in thunder could the men strike
about? I'm not going to cut wages--not one
cent. It's cold business; the men can't
strike. It's to their interest to stay--and


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-139"
                    n="137"/>





even if it wasn't I verily believe they
wouldn't leave the old firm in the lurch."</p>
   <p>A force of masons and machinists were
set to work, and in a short time the Gilroy
factory started in with increased capacity
and on full time. All of the former Gilroy
men were taken back and work was found
for some of the Lunder men. There was
great rejoicing among the town-people.
The old man stood in the door of the office
and rubbed his hands with pleasure at the
sight of the men's cheerful faces.</p>
   <p>"Fine fellows! I want 'em to know that
no man ever worked for Chauncey Gilroy
and was the worse for it."</p>
  <p>But although as many of the Lunderville
men were given work as was possible, there
was dissatisfaction  almost immediately
among the strikers at that place. What
right had Gilroy to take the Lunders' contracts 
off their hands? By so doing the
men declared he had cut them out of their
one chance of redress. Meetings were held
for two or three nights, and finally resolutions


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-140"
                    n="138"/>





were adopted calling on the Greenfield
men to support the strikers in their fight
against Lunder and Gilroy.</p>
   <p>The next morning the Greenfield men
 went to work as usual, but anxious women
 stood in doorways and looked down the
 street for news, and some little groups lingered 
 on the street near the gates.</p>
   <p>At three o'clock the message came from
the Central Committee. At five minutes
past three a delegate walked into each shop
and threw up his arms. Without a word
the men put down their tools and silently
marched out. At ten minutes past three
the shops were empty, fifteen hundred work-
men were assembled on the common, and
the sympathetic strike was on.</p>
  <p>The men held meetings every day and
night. Windy orators thronged in from
outside and called on the men to stand for
their rights--never to give up--the country
was with them. A blizzard came, and a
woman froze to death. Scarlet fever broke
out among the children. Chauncey Gilroy


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-141"
                    n="139"/>





worked himself into an illness in his rage at
the men's ingratitude and folly. "Let
them starve," he shouted; "maybe it'll
teach 'em a little sense." John Gilroy sat
in his empty office all day and walked the
floor the most of the night. Elinor lay
awake thinking of the sick babies who begged
their mothers for a little more milk, and of
that woman in childbirth who had had the
bed taken from under her and split up into
fuel to keep her alive.</p>
  <p>One cold afternoon Elinor and her husband 
came out of the Postoffice. A crowd
stood around the entrance and did not move
to let them pass. John Gilroy pushed a
man or two aside rather roughly.</p>
  <p>A woman thinly wrapped and coughing
frightfully hung on to Gilroy's arm and
begged for money. He shook her off. She
grew more noisy; he called to a policeman,
"Take this woman in charge." The woman
began to scream. She looked at Elinor,
who recognized her as the McCoy woman
whom she had seen at the picnic.  The


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-142"
                    n="140"/>




policeman seized her, but she writhed away
from him like a wounded snake and spit her
fury out on Gilroy. "Oh, you've got a
sweet-scented wife, haven't you? She was
with Dick Morgan before you ever saw her."</p>
  <p>After this Elinor was more wretched than
ever. Her sense of justice forced her to
see that the McCoy woman was not to be
blamed, and yet-she could not (or at any
rate she thought she could not) burden her
husband with a fresh trouble at such a time
as this.</p>
   <p>"Elinor," said he, the next day, "I am
glad to be able to tell you that that woman
is sentenced to hard labor for sixty days."
  She shook from head to foot. "Oh,
John!--that is <hi rend="i">too</hi> hard--the woman was
just drunk!"</p>
  <p>"That's all right," he answered sternly.
"I used all the influence I have to get some
floating sentences for former misdemeanors
raked up against her, and I guess she won't
be drunk again soon."</p>
  <p>A rumor got about among the strikers


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-143"
                    n="141"/>




that really the Gilroys were not so much to
be blamed. Some one had heard a superintendent 
of the Lunderville shops say that
Chauncey Gilroy had stepped in and kept
the work from going to Pittsburg. If this
was true the Committee wanted to know
it, but they did not want to make an open
inquiry. They therefore asked for a meeting 
with the Gilroys, their purpose being
to ask for confidential information about
that and other matters. Old Mr. Gilroy
rolled over in his sick bed when he got the
message and asked if the men wanted to
come back. "We think not," answered a
clerk. "We think they want to look at the
books."</p>
   <p>"Tell them I'll see them when they say
they want to come back; tell them they
can go to hell for all I care."</p>
  <p>This message was softened a little, but it
nevertheless hurt the men a good deal to
have the old man treat them like that.
They made another less formal attempt to
get a hearing. This was addressed to John


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-144"
                    n="142"/>





Gilroy personally. An unofficial Committee 
of which Morgan was the head asked
for the privilege of meeting him at any
time he might appoint. The young man
was in the office when the request for this
conference came to him. He received very
civilly the men who brought the message
and took from them the list of names of the
proposed Committee. After reading it he
looked up and spoke coldly: "I absolutely 
refuse to receive, now or at any other
time, any committee or delegation of which
Mr. Morgan is a member."</p>
  <p>This was an insult which even the most
peaceable of the men felt must be resented.
The elder Gilroy fumed when he heard of
it. "Jack, I believe you're crazy. Dick's
a crank, but he means to keep the men
straight and he's done it time and again. I
feel like sending for them and telling them
you made a fool of yourself--though I don't
suppose they had anything to say of any
importance."</p>
  <p>Things grew worse every day. The Gilroys


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-145"
                    n="143"/>





tried to bring in men from outside,
but they, poor wretches, were frightened
away by the awful cry of "Scab!" which
the working man fears more than God or
devil.  The police force was doubled.
There were threats of burning the shops.</p>
  <p>A coarsely-printed anonymous little sheet
began to be circulated on the streets. Elinor 
found a copy under the door. It was
addressed to her. She tried to put it into
the fire--she knew it would contain abuse
of her husband--but in spite of herself she
read the article, which was marked to attract 
notice. It was as follows: "There
has been a decision in a New York case
lately that a man and woman who take
each other as man and wife before witnesses 
even as a joke are really married in
the eyes of the law. The Indiana law is
probably the same as the New York law.
This may prove interesting to the participants 
in a certain picnic two years ago, and
particularly to the alleged wife of a millionaire 
who is living in luxury on the money


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-146"
                    n="144"/>



wrung from his starving employes.  One
thing that makes the matter still more interesting 
is that Jim Martin, who performed
the ceremony, is a justice of the peace and
authorized to perform marriages."</p>
   <p>Elinor's heart stood still and the earth
seemed to fall from beneath her feet. She
looked again at the coarse head-lines in big
letters: "Is She a Bigamist or Merely a
Flirt?"</p>
  <p>She threw the paper into the fire, and
tried to get her scattered senses together.
She was frightfully ill, but at least she
could try to keep down every sign of the
physical pain that accompanied her shame
and misery. Jack when he came home
must not be worried over her.</p>
  <p>As she moved about the library that evening 
she was full of blind resentment at a
Providence that let her suffer so much. "I
did not deserve this," she said. "I did
nothing wrong; I yielded to no temptation."
At other times she was overwhelmed with
remorse, "I have hurt everybody. What


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-147"
                    n="145"/>





will all these people think of me?--that I'm
false, vain, wicked. It is I who should be
in prison, and not that poor woman." She
felt that because she had a secret on her
conscience she had not dared to take the
part of the men to her husband and his
father. It was the consequence of her sin
that her mouth had been closed. "If only
I could atone," she thought, "could in some
way help to bring about a better time, and
then vanish forever!"</p>
  <p>This longing to make some sort of atonement 
took a disproportionate place in her
racked fancy. She was conscious of her
own voice speaking to her husband. She
asked him about the strike--the beginning,
the claims of the men, and all the questions
that thus far she had avoided. For the first
time he talked to her freely; he seemed to
find some unexpected relief in the discussion. 
He did not suppose, did not believe,
that she understood, but nevertheless he
went into the details. He even showed her
the Lunders' letters from the other people


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-148"
                    n="146"/>




who had wanted to take the contracts.
His wife could see that he had gone over
and over the thing in his own mind till his
courage and his nerve were almost lost.</p>
  <p> "Why do you not give up to the men?"
she asked.</p>
   <p>"There is nothing to give up but the
contracts, and when we give them up there
will be no work for the men to do.
We could not open at all if we were to do
what they are demanding."</p>
   <p>"If the strike is lasting and the works
remain closed for a long time it will ruin
you, will it not?"</p>
   <p>"We are ruined, anyway, unless the men
come back before Saturday. That's the
limit; a week later and we cannot by any
earthly possibility finish the contracted
work in time."</p>
  <p>"But can't you talk with the men? Can't
you explain to them that you were really
helping them?" she persisted.</p>
  <p>"They ought to know without being told,
and I won't go to begging them. I am not


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-149"
                    n="147"/>




afraid of poverty; mother is fixed, and I can
take care of you. The thing that breaks
me up is to have to go before the world as
a failure, as a man who couldn't hold his
own. That just takes the life out of me--
when we had meant so well by the men,
too. And they are hurting themselves; if
we go under, and I suppose we are bound
to, Greenfield bursts like a bubble. Hundreds 
of the men own their houses and we'll
go down together."</p>
   <p>"Do you think the men want to come
back?" she asked.</p>
   <p>"I know they do, if the Central Union
would let them; but those fellows think that
by ruining us they can help the Lunderville
men."</p>
  <p>All that night Elinor sat by her window;
her head ached and she could not sleep.
The next morning she telephoned to Lunderville, 
where the Union had its office: "I
want to speak to Mr. Morgan." (Morgan
was Secretary of the Union).  When he
came to the telephone, she said: "This is


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-150"
                    n="148"/>





Mrs. John Gilroy. I want to see you. I
want to see you privately."</p>
  <p>Whatever hesitation he felt was shown
in the silence that preceded his answer.
"Very well-shall I go to your house?"</p>
  <p>"No; come to the west gate at eight this
evening."</p>
  <p>There was another silence before he answered. 
 "All right."</p>
  <p>That evening she left her husband writing
in the library and walked out bareheaded
and unwrapped across the firm snow under
the great trees. She unlocked the gate and
stood in the moonlight face to face with
Morgan.</p>
  <p>She poured out the story of the suffering
of the hungry children, and the sick women
--of her husband's goodness and anxiety,
and her own distress. She grew more excited 
every moment; the misery of weeks
culminated in a storm of tears. She begged
him to help--to tell her what to do. He
tried gently to quiet her, and asked a few
questions about Gilroy's affairs--the contracts


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-151"
                    n="149"/>



and so forth. She understood neither
questions nor answers, but she knew word
for word what her husband had told her.
As she proceeded the charm of Morgan's
presence came over her as strongly as before. 
It warmed her into something like
peace.   But she recognized, distracted
though she was, that he had forgotten about
her; it was her husband of whom he was
thinking.</p>
  <p>"Oh, why couldn't Jack have told me
this?" he said.</p>
 <p> "And you can do something with the
men?"</p>
  <p>"No, but I think I can do something with
the Central Committee. At any rate, I'll
try. Please go back into the house, Mrs.
Gilroy."</p>
  <p>"And when shall I hear?" she persisted.
"Oh, hurry, or I shall die!"</p>
  <p>"If I have anything to tell you I'll come
here to-morrow night at this time."</p>
  <p>"And when you do," she said, excitedly,


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-152"
                    n="150"/>



"put your hand up on the high ledge there,
and you'll find the gate key."</p>
  <p> The next day she roamed about like one
distracted. She insisted on hearing every
particular of the suffering in town.  She
asked her husband again and again if they
would really be absolutely penniless. And
at each answer she laughed to herself. "It
will be an atonement--an expiation."</p>
  <p>As the great clock at the works struck
eight she stood on the snow with Morgan.
"Oh, tell me!" she said.</p>
   <p>"It's done. Orders will be sent to-night
to the men to go back to work. A concession 
about piece work will be asked, but
it's trifling."</p>
  <p>She seized both his hands. "Oh, thank
God!" she said. "And <hi rend="i">now</hi> they all may
forgive me!"</p>
  <p>But at the instant the alarm of fire rang
out, clamorous, fierce. A light rose in the
sky.</p>
  <p>"It is the east shop!" said Morgan, and
he rushed away.</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-153"
                    n="151"/>



   <p>The fire was stopped before much harm
was done. The order came. In the morning 
long lines of men walked in single file
into each shop, giving their names as they
passed to the busy timekeeper, while on
the streets the women cried and laughed
and kissed each other.</p>
   <p>Gilroy came home late. "I must go
right over to see father," he said. "I am
sorry to say," he added, "that Morgan is
suspected of setting the shops on fire last
night and that steps are being taken to arrest 
him. The watchman swears he saw
him come out of the shop as the clock struck
eight."</p>
  <p>Elinor sprang to her feet.</p>
  <p>"Oh, John, he didn't--he <hi rend="i">didn't!</hi>"  Her
husband looked at her curiously. "My
dear, you will make yourself ill. I am
sorry I can't stay with you, but I must run
now."</p>
  <p>She hung on his arm. "John, don't let
him be arrested; he wasn't there--indeed
he wasn't!" But her husband was gone.


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-154"
                    n="152"/>




She ran out into the grounds.  She was
almost frantic. Suddenly she heard a pistol 
shot; then shouts, the gate was unlocked
and Dick Morgan turned into the grounds.</p>
  <p>He staggered away from her. "I did not
mean to see you," he said--" I ran in to
get away from that gang. That scab policeman 
tried to arrest me--he had no warrant. 
He struck me, he shot through my
arm. I knocked him down--I guess I killed
him. I'll get no justice. If I can't get
away, I shall be locked up for years."</p>
  <p>"You are wounded," she said--"bleeding.
Go into that room--that one there on the
veranda, and I'll lock the gate." As he
passed through the door, a policeman tried
the gate, others following him.  They
pounded and shouted.</p>
  <p>A crowd of frightened servants came.
The police demanded entrance and the right
to go through the house. Mrs. Gilroy advanced. 
"No one has come in, " she said.
"I've been here for an hour."</p>
  <p>Then she heard her husband's voice.


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-155"
                    n="153"/>




"No," he said. "Get on, men--I've been
here with my wife. No one has come in."</p>
  <p> The crowd rushed off. Elinor seized her
husband's hand. "Oh, come, <hi rend="i">come!</hi>" She
led him into the room where Morgan lay
senseless. As Gilroy bent over to lift him
he opened his eyes and smiled. "Jack,"
he said, "I'm tired-roll over and let me
get into bed."</p>
   <p>Gilroy sprang to the door. "Telephone
for a doctor to come here instantly," he
cried to a passing servant.</p>
  <p>The doctor came. Elinor, clinging to her
husband, left the room. "Oh, let me tell
you, Jack!" she said. "Not now," he answered, 
gently.</p>
   <p>"Yes, <hi rend="i">now!</hi>"</p>
   <p>She told him with sobs--then with 
defiance--then with entreaties and wild self-
reproaches. She told him all--of the 
picnic--the McCoy woman--the newspaper.
He listened with as calm a face as though
he sat in church on a summer morning. At
the end he rose and walked to the fire, where


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-156"
                    n="154"/>



he stood in silence. She could not guess
of what he was thinking. She was past
caring. "Well, my dear," he said, "you've
paid pretty fully for whatever you may have
done that was wrong. I'm afraid all this
will make you ill. Try to forget as soon as
possible."</p>
  <p>The doctor appeared at the door. Gilroy
turned toward him with a question. " He's
been shot through an artery in the arm,"
the doctor responded. "I'm afraid he will
hardly recover."</p>
  <p>The young man spoke to his wife hastily:
"Ring for somebody to help you to bed,
my dear. I must stay with Dick."</p>
  <p>Outside of the door the doctor asked who
was to blame for Morgan's wound.</p>
  <p>"I don't know," said the young man; "I
don't know who's to blame for that or for
anything!"</p>
  <p>Elinor looked after her husband with bewildered 
eyes. She was no longer crushed
and repentant. She suddenly saw the truth
which, later, was often absent from her


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-157"
                    n="155"/>

     

mind, but never quite forgotten: that no
two human beings can ever be absolutely
clear to each other.</p></div3></div2>

      
<pb
                    id="VAB1822-158" n="156"/>
                <pb id="VAB1822-159"
                    n="[157]"/>




            




<div2 type="chapter"><head rend="center">THE MORNINGSTAR ELOPEMENT</head>


<pb                    id="VAB1822-160" n="[158]"/>


<pb id="VAB1822-161"
                    n="159"/>







  <head rend="center">THE MORNINGSTAR ELOPEMENT</head>
<p><hi rend="b">T</hi>HE sky was so brilliant, and the lake at
    the foot of the hill such a glowing mass
of copper and violet, that it seemed for the
moment strange that the men who were
coming up the road should show in the twilight 
only as dark shapes. From the kitchen
windows the lights shone down with cheerful 
promise of supper. The air was chilly,
but the dusty path gave out a sort of sweet-
smelling warmth. There was a coziness
about the close shut scene; the fishermen,
laughing and singing, evidently felt something 
of it.</p>
  <p>The owner of the house came ahead of
the others; he carried a great basket of fish.
As he strode toward the door Lon Bunker,
the hired man, stopped him.</p>
                  


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-162"
                    n="160"/>





   <p>"Better not go in there, Abe," he said.
 "She's on her ear again."</p>
   <p>"What in thunder's the matter with her?"
shouted Abe. He spoke with the anticipatory 
violence of a man who is trying to work
himself into a defensive rage.</p>
   <p>"She's jawin' about them town fellers
bein' late for supper, and I reckon she's mad
about your goin' fishin' with 'em all day,"
said Lon.</p>
   <p>"Well I 'low to run this house myself,"
said Abe, with an emphasis intended to
penetrate the door. "The women round
here got to do the way <hi rend="i">I</hi> say-or I'll make
'em!"</p>
  <p>The door was suddenly opened; Mrs.
Morningstar threw herself out with a fury
that made even Lon quail. " Say that again,
will you! Just say that again! You <hi rend="i">dassent</hi>, 
you know you dassent! <hi rend="i">You</hi> are going
to run this house, are you? Well, you can
just do it! I got to do what you want, have
I? You just better try it! I tell you I've
worked as long as I'm going to for <hi rend="i">you</hi>. I


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-163"
                    n="161"/>



 ain't going to work for no more tramps <hi rend="i">like</hi>
 you! You can get your own supper, or go
 without. I'm tired. I've been up since
 four o'clock this morning, working like a
 dog, and I'm going to stop. And you dassent 
 say a word--and you know it--Abe
 Morningstar!"</p>
 <p>The fishermen filed around the house to
 wash their hands before supper. They
 were a party of estimable gentlemen from a
 neighboring city, who, when twice a year
 they came to the lake to fish, lodged at
 the Morningstars'. Mrs. Morningstar had
 known them all for several years; all but
 one man, who had only joined them to-day.
 She found them profitable guests, and would
 have been sorry to lose them. Nevertheless 
 she scolded, and they kept out of her
 way, and pitied Abe.</p>
 <p>They came into supper hungry and noisy.
 They did not notice her at all. She was
 wretchedly tired; she knew what the meal
 would be-a conversation full of references
to things which she knew nothing of, and


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-164"
                    n="162"/>





of jokes that she could not understand.
She felt with a sort of dumb bitterness that
the gentlemen were cruel to her. She knew
that she could in some circumstances have
claimed their respect, have held their interest, 
but they never gave her a chance.
They paid her no more attention than if
she had been a block of wood. The very
supper to which they were seating themselves, 
poor as it seemed to these men, was,
with its two kinds of cake and its napkins
folded in the glasses, the result of tremendous 
effort on her part. But they did not
even recognize that she had taken great
pains; to pay their bill and get out of her
way was apparently all they thought necessary.</p>
  <p>To-night the new man, Mr. Vawter, was
the center of the group. Mrs. Morningstar
knew all about him. He was the one who was
always desired. Half a dozen times she
had seen everybody elated at the prospect
of his joining them, and depressed when
word arrived that he could not come. She


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-165"
                    n="163"/>




 hated them all, but she hated him the most
 of all, because they seemed so fond of him.
 She looked sidewise at him. " Mighty sick-
 looking chap to make all that fuss over!"
 she said to herself. Indeed his appearance
 was not impressive. He was slight and
 would have seemed undersized but for his
 erect military carriage. His hair was thin,
 he had a funny little beard, a sallow skin,
 and very bright twinkling blue eyes. She
 knew that he was what she called "rich,"
 and she was surprised at the plainness of
 his dress and manner. He had been brought
 up on a farm, and fell easily into the kind
 of speech with which she was most familiar;
 this made him seem less important than the
 others, with their crisp citified pronunciation. 
 She wondered at the consideration
 in which they held him.</p>
 <p>They seated themselves. Vawter looked
 about him with concern. "See here!" he
 cried out cheerfully; "where's Miz Morningstar 
 going to sit? I got her place."</p>
  <p>There was no answer. Lon Bunker tittered,


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-166"
                    n="164"/>




 Tilly, the girl who had come in to
help, tossed her head.  "<hi rend="i">I</hi> can't fry the
victuals and hand 'em, too!"</p>
   <p>"Of course you can't! Of <hi rend="i">course</hi>!" said
Vawter, with ready sympathy.  "George!"
he said, addressing the Morningstars' son,
a hulking boy of fifteen, who had been rowing Vawter's 
boat that day--" George, you
suffering lamb you, you just hustle those
cakes along quick's Tilly gets 'em fried--
d'ye hear, son? Miz Morningstar, you sit
right down by Abe. I'm used to having
ladies at the table. I guess this crowd's
pretty rough," he added, pensively.</p>
  <p>Mrs. Morningstar's face lost some of its
grimness. She seated herself with a little
offishness; she was pretty cross still.</p>
  <p>The talk was not addressed to her, but
she could understand the most of it. When
a reference was made to something that had
happened in town, or on the last fishing
journey, Vawter demanded an explanation
with cheerful persistence. They all seemed
pleasanter than before.</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-167"
                    n="165"/>



  <p>The old man of the party, General Harbison, 
 told in his hoarse, wheezy voice a
story of Vawter in which he took much delight, 
and which evidently he had often told
before. "That youngster was the pet of
the whole brigade," he said, affectionately.
Mrs. Morningstar looked at the stranger
with quickened interest. She had been to
Laporte in her youth, to see a company
start off to the War. The memory of it
came back to her. It was a day of music,
and banners, and gay uniforms, and tender
partings. It was the one heroic recollection 
of her life.</p>
  <p>They spoke of the soldiers' reunions and
campfires at which some of the company
had recently been present. "Tell you
what, Vawter," said one of the men, "when
you got onto the tie between old comrades
the other night it was just great. I pretty
near broke down!"</p>
  <p>Vawter looked embarrassed at the talk
about himself. 'You know Barney Sheehan?" 
he said. "Well, some of us went


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-168"
                    n="166"/>



up the other night to hear him address the
United Irishmen. I saw him as we came
out--he was pretty full. 'Mr. Vawter,' he
said, 'I'm not wishful to be egotistical, but I
will say, sorry, that whin I spake on the subject 
of brotherly love I find myself spaking
wid great aise!' I guess I'm like Barney."</p>
   <p>There was much boyish fun-making. In
his deprecating sweet voice Vawter rebuked
the company for their disorderly mirth.
Mrs. Morningstar brightened up and supported 
him. He declared himself flattered
by her concurrence, and put on, in addressing 
her, a ceremonious manner brought, 
perhaps, from a residence of some years in
Georgia.</p>
   <p>"Miz Morningstar, Madam! Nothing
could give me mo' playsu' then to pa'take
of some pie--pa'ticuly such elegunt and
temptin' pie as the pie I see befo' me. But
I am sho', madam, that the enjoyment I
would thereby confer upon myself would be
annulled by the thought of the pain which
so tende' hahted a lady would experience at


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-169"
                    n="167"/>



the spectacle of my subsequent and uncontrollable 
anguish!"</p>
   <p>"Sir," she responded with much show of
dignity, "my pie is less important than
your well-being."</p>
  <p>Tilly giggled at the cooking-stove. George,
on his way with the batter cakes, laughed so
that once he had to sit down plate in hand.</p>
  <p>Vawter looked at him pensively.
"George, you put me in mind of a steamboat 
I once met with up on the Miss'sippi.
When she was going she couldn't toot--and
when she was tooting she couldn't go!" He
went on gloomily: "She afterward bust!"</p>
  <p>The meal was over and the men began to
move toward the front porch. "Have a
cigar, Vawter?" "Yes, thank you," he answered, 
"but let's stay here and red up.
When I'm camping out I don't cut off the
very first night, and leave the cook to wash
the dishes. Give me a napern, please!"</p>
  <p>Abe bestirred himself and hunted the
broom. "I'll brush up the crumbs. I've got
some style about me, too!"</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-170"
                    n="168"/>



   <p>The work was soon done; they drew their
 chairs around the stove-the night was
 frosty. The little Morningstar girl had
 watched Vawter with fascinated eyes. She
 came to his side and put her hand on his
 arm. Vawter drew her to him. " George,
 honey," he said, looking over his shoulder
 at Mrs. Morningstar, who was fidgeting
 about in the background, ' give your mother
 that chair and come sit on my other knee!"</p>
   <p>Little Myrtie whispered something, and
then said it out in her shrill little voice:
"Mammy's got a fiddle on top shelf!"</p>
  <p>Abe explained, "Loretty's had it since
she was a girl. Bought it with egg money
and learned herself. She ain't played much
late years!"</p>
   <p>"I guess I'd have more time to play if
you had less!" she said. But nobody noticed
her pettishness. They all begged; the fiddle 
was brought out; Abe looked anxiously
at the guests to see how they were taking it.
*I reckon they'll all make fun of your playing," 
he said, not unkindly.</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-171"
                    n="169"/>




   <p>She played better than they had expected,
 and they praised her perhaps more than she
 deserved. As she began to feel at ease her
 black eyes shone, she threw her head back,
 and swung to and fro in accord with the
 music, smiling brightly. Abe, looking at
 her, remembered one Sunday afternoon
 when he was courting her, and met her coming 
 through the meadow. He had thought
 she looked like a quail, bright-eyed and
 graceful. After she had played a while they
 all sang together:-" The Sweet Bye and
 Bye," and "We're Tenting To-night on the
 Old Camp Ground," and "Lorena."</p>
 <p>They sang, they told conundrums, they
 even danced. The General Manager of the
 Lake Side System instructed George in the
 two-step. Price, the handsome and cynical
 editor and dramatic critic, gallantly led Abe
 down the center in the Virginia reel.</p>
 <p>It was a time of kindness, and wit, and
 happy laughter. The humor of Vawter was
 not only keen and diverting--it was, as Abe
thought, "friendly."  Everything about


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-172"
                    n="170"/>





him was warm and alive. He had the actor's 
art, the orator's charm.</p>
  <p>Mrs. Morningstar, looking at him now,
wondered that she could have thought him
plain. She noticed the neat freshness of
his rough surfaced clothes-they seemed
different from other men's garments; and on
one of his slender hands he wore a splendid
dazzling ring.</p>
  <p>She was lifted out of herself, she walked
on air. The music, the wit, the courtesy,
were like some grand dream. It was theater, 
society, literature, opera, all in one.</p>
  <p>They did not separate till midnight. As
the men were going to bed upstairs Wemys
said, "Who would have thought that that
woman could be so nice? I took her for a
regular wildcat."</p>
  <p>Vawter sat on the edge of his cot, contemplating 
the sole of his shoe. "Well,"
he said, "you know my wife?--no, she
could not be anything but an angel in any
circumstances; but if <hi rend="i">I</hi> had to milk eight
cows, and cook for the hands, and keep


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-173"
                    n="171"/>




boarders, I'd be something of a wildcat myself!"</p>
  <p>The next afternoon there was a clatter
of preparation.  They were departing.
Loretta Morningstar helped everybody; she
watched the packing of the bass in big boxes
of ice; she hunted for the lost rubber boot.
Her calico dress was fresh and starchy; over
her head a red shawl was tied, not unbecomingly. 
Her sullenness had vanished;
they were all good friends. Vawter bade
her good-bye with simple courtesy, hat in
hand. "Mrs. Morningstar, I thank you for
your kindness to all of us. I hope you will
be well and happy till we see you again."</p>
  <p>As he was about to step into the wagon
he looked back at her standing in the door
alone. Something about her moved his
heart. He hurried back. " Mrs. Morningstar--I 
wish I could do something for you--I 
don't suppose I ever can, but if I can I
will. Remember that!"</p>
  <p>The wagon vanished over the top of the
bill. She turned into the house. She was


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-174"
                    n="172"/>





not lonely, she hardly missed them--there
was so much for her to think of.</p>
  <p>It was late in October when the fishermen 
  went home. Only a few weeks after
that the Morningstar family woke one morning 
to find the earth covered with snow and
the pump frozen. It was an early winter
and a cold one. The road was obliterated
by snow drifts; not a neighbor came in for
weeks. Abe slouched his way a mile and
a half up the hill to the store every day,
and came home only at dark. He had no
news to tell; if he had had any he could
not have told it.</p>
  <p>Loretta looked about the room sometimes
with a feeling that everything was unreal.
Here, on this very seam of the carpet, Vawter's 
chair had stood. Over there was the
braided rug that Price rolled up when they
began to dance. It was the same, but lifeless; 
it was revolting, like a dead thing.</p>
  <p>Behind the house a little path had been
made to the barn. She hurried along it
half a dozen times a day on her way to milk,


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-175"
                    n="173"/>


or to feed the chickens. Around the kitchen
door were untidy heaps of frozen ashes;
here and there the white surface was defiled 
by coffee grounds and egg shells. The
strata of potato peelings and the like that
kind nature had covered from time to time
with fresh snow cropped out in some places
with sickening insistence. Loretta had no
time to look beyond at the sleeping fields,
the tender curves of down-swathed hills,
the glittering amethyst of the frozen lake.</p>
  <p>The steps that led from the kitchen door
into the back yard were slippery with ice;
besides that they were broken. Abe had
promised months before to nail them into
place. His wife sometimes at night reminded 
him bitterly of his neglect. "I'm
sorry I didn't do it before," he thought,
"but I won't do it now till she stops her
jawin'."</p>
  <p>Late one afternoon as Loretta put her
foot on the icy step the board slipped from
its insecure fastening.  She had a milk
bucket in each hand and could not save


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-176"
                    n="174"/>






herself. As she lay on the frozen ground
she thought her ankle was broken. She
could not move; she had moments of unconsciousness 
and periods of agonizing pain.
She did not cry, she did not pray. Her
whole being was swept with a torrent of
rage and despair. As she lay there evening 
came on; the sky showed lavish glory,
splendor piled itself on splendor, the snow-
covered earth reflected the tints above, the
stars throbbed in burning blue. Abe, coming 
around the corner of the house, found
his wife at the foot of the steps unconscious
and half frozen.</p>
  <p>Her ankle was not broken, but badly
sprained; she was quite helpless. For weeks
she lay watching, with dark inscrutable
eyes, Abe's clumsy attempts at cleaning and
cooking. At first he was afraid of her, but
she said nothing. She was, as she would
have said, "studying." As she grew better
she seemed to have come to a conclusion--
or to have reached an end in her deliberation.
She was calmer than before. Abe could


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-177"
                    n="175"/>


not understand. He made piteous efforts
to entertain her. He would have been glad
even to see her angry.</p>
  <p>One night as she was beginning to move
about he spoke to her; he could keep silence
no longer. "Loretty," he said, but he
could not find words for his thought--"Loretty, 
don't take on so!" She heard him as
one listens absently to a child.</p>
  <p>The next day he went to the store--he
felt the need of counsel. Old Van Horn
had had three wives and might be deemed
an authority. Abe turned on him his honest
blue eyes, heavy with trouble.</p>
  <p>"If a sick person's extry quiet and patient 
do you 'low it's a sign they ain't goin'
to get well?"</p>
  <p>"Man or woman?" asked old Van Horn.</p>
  <p>"Woman," answered Abe.</p>
  <p>Old Van Horn spoke with rustic candor.
"Well, Abe, if it's your Loretty, and she
ain't talking, she'll die certain."</p>
  <p>But Mrs. Morningstar was almost well
the next week when the huckster stopped


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-178"
                    n="176"/>



to trade with her for butter and eggs. She
gave him privately a letter to mail for her
in Laporte.</p>

   <p>Mr. and Mrs. Vawter were at a dinner
 party one evening in January. Price, the
 editor, was there, and Wemys and General
 Harbison's son Richard, and others of the
 fishing party. Young Harbison sat next to
 Mrs. Vawter. In a pause her husband
 heard the young man say, "I wonder if Mr.
 Vawter confessed to you the flirtation he
 had up at the lake with Mrs. Morningstar?"
 She answered him lightly; he persisted,
 "Oh ask any of them. They'll all tell
 you!"</p>
 <p>She smiled indulgently. The young man's
 face flushed; it came to him, he could not
 tell how, that she thought him a little rude.
 Yet she was kinder than ever; Vawter,
 watching her, thought as he had thought
 before, " She is the best bred woman in the
world, as she is the sweetest."</p>
  <p>He looked at her as a stranger might


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-179"
                    n="177"/>



have looked; he saw her radiant face, her
round throat encircled with diamonds, the
low bodice of her white gown sable-edged
and jewel-pinned. He recalled the woman
up in the country-her sharp tongue, her
wistful eyes, her poor little red shawl. "I
wish Judith understood!" he thought. But
he knew that she would never understand;
he knew another thing too-that, although
she was the most sympathetic of wives, she
sometimes felt that he made himself a little
common.</p>
  <p>The next morning Vawter sat in his private 
office. A clerk brought to him his
personal mail. As he read his letters he
uttered an exclamation that made his secretary 
turn to him. "You may go into the
other room, Mr. Holliday," he said. "When
I want you I'll ring."</p>
  <p>Left alone he read again the letter he
held in his hand:</p>
  <p>"<hi rend="i">Mr. Vawter, respected friend:</hi> I write
this to let you know that I have got so
that I can't live here any longer, and I
    


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-180"
                    n="178"/>



have made up my mind that I have got to
leave, and remembering your promise, I
write to say that I am going to leave Abe
for good. He will be in Laporte a week
from Monday, and I can get away and will
go to your town, so please meet me at the
train and tell me what to do. So no more
at present from yours truly,</p>
                <p>L<hi rend="sc">ORETTA</hi> M<hi rend="sc">ORNINGSTAR</hi>.</p>
  <p>The situation was bad enough at first, but
it seemed worse the more he thought about
it. He stepped to the door. "Telephone
for my horse; I'm going to drive."</p>
  <p>Out on the deserted boulevard he tried to
get a clearer view of the case, but all that
he could think of was that a married woman,
utterly ignorant of the ways of the world,
was about to leave her husband, and that,
perhaps, as the result of something like a
suggestion of his own. The wind in his
face was icy, but he broke into a perspiration 
as he thought of the obvious and inevitable 
criticism to which his own thoughtless 
impulsiveness would expose him. He
did not dare to name his wife even in his


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-181"
                    n="179"/>



thoughts, but he could feel the way in which
any woman might say, "Were you not a little
rash? Why need <hi rend="i">you</hi> have taken on yourself 
the responsibility of a declared sympathy?"</p>
   <p>"It's no use going over and over it by
myself," he said, at last. "I have got to
ask somebody!"</p>
   <p>Of the men of the fishing party to whom
he might go for advice, there was General
Harbison, whose age and high character
might be supposed particularly to qualify
him; and there was Wemys, who, perhaps,
was Vawter's closest friend.</p>
   <p>"Harbison's all <hi rend="i">right</hi>, he'd talk it over
fully and wisely-but he'd continue talking
it over fully and wisely for the next twenty
years.</p>
   <p>"And Wemys--well, <hi rend="i">he'd</hi> be all right
after he once got down to it, but he'd want
to philosophize round and round creation
before he started in on the subject--like a
writing-master when he's going to make a
scroll eagle. And Price-he's out of the


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-182"
                    n="180"/>




question, I suppose. For one thing, he's
too young; and for another, from what the
boys say, he's had a little too much experience 
already. I reckon I got to tell
Wemys."</p>
  <p>He stopped in front of a tall building
which was almost in the center of a whirlpool 
of commercial activity. In the elevator 
with him as he went up were a printer,
carrying long strips of proof in his hands,
and some young men who had that look of
sodden cleanliness that belongs to going to
bed at four in the morning, and bath and
breakfast at noon.</p>
  <p>"Tell Mr. Price that Mr. Vawter wants to
see him." As he waited he said to himself,
"I knew all along it was Price I was coming 
to, and yet I made up reasons against
Wemys and poor old Harbison. I've got to
watch out-that kind of thing isn't just
straight."</p>
  <p>In his own room, and surrounded by
the signs of his work, there was a force
about Price that was not so evident elsewhere.


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-183"
                    n="181"/>



There was something comforting,
too, in the quick perception that made him
say at once to someone outside of the door,
"Don't let anybody in."</p>
  <p>He listened gravely with a kind and concentrated 
    interest that had the appearance
of being an interest diverted for the time
from his own affairs. Vawter gave him
Loretta's letter. It hurt him to do it; there
was a sort of violation of confidence in the
act. A fear took him that Price might
laugh. But Price read it through slowly,
looking back at the date, with a face as unchanging 
as if he had been considering a
poker hand.</p>
   <p>"Poor woman, I suppose it's been pretty
hard on her this winter," he said, after a
moment or two. "Yes," said Vawter,
"and that's one of the things that breaks
me all up. You see I know all about it.
Our folks were pretty well off, as farmers go,
in Indiana, but all the same I know the life
is awful for the women."</p>
  <p>"She'd be nervous and cross, and then


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-184"
                    n="182"/>




Abe would get grumpy," suggested the
other.</p>
   <p>"Yes, I reckon he'd act like a brute,"
 Vawter answered-" and yet Abe's a mighty
 good-humored fellow by nature."</p>
   <p>"He is, by nature; but the good humor
that's going to redeem a man he's got to
work for."</p>
   <p>"Well, I don't know as I exactly understand 
what you mean by that, but anyhow
Abe's a good man according to his lights,
and hardly deserves that his home should
be broken up! You feel that?"</p>
  <p>Price responded absently, looking out of
the window as he spoke. Vawter proceeded
with some heat:</p>
   <p>"Don't we <hi rend="i">both</hi> know that? Of course
she can't come--."</p>
  <p>"Certainly not."</p>
  <p>"But what kind of a man am <hi rend="i">I?</hi> Here
I am plotting to get out of keeping my
promise to her. I never in my life before
went back on a creature that trusted me.
It's awful rough!"</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-185"
                    n="183"/>



   <p>"That's so," said Price. "There's sometimes 
some comfort in finding out how far you're 
to blame, and taking it out on yourself, 
but there is nothing of that in this, to
my mind."</p>
   <p>"No, I can't see how I am to blame. I
was sorry for her, awfully sorry, as I am
for any human being who is in a hard place.
I said so, and I don't take it back either."</p>
  <p>"Of course the idea that you would be
her friend made her think it possible to
leave Abe."</p>
   <p>"I reckon so--I'm not going to blame a
woman for believing what I tell her, am I?"</p>
   <p>"The result is pretty embarrassing," said
Price, with a smile.</p>
   <p>"I suppose it is, but you don't think I
mind about myself, do you? It's her I'm
thinking of-how she'll be hurt, and lose
confidence, and maybe get more bitter. It's
like slapping a child that holds out its hands
to you."</p>
  <p>"I see that," said Price. "I mean I can
see how it would worry you." After a moment's


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-186"
                    n="184"/>




silence he asked, "Can't you write
to her?"</p>
  <p>"Write to her? Good land, no! Anybody 
who chose would open the letter, and
if it got out that she had ever planned to
run away from Abe she'd never hear the
last of it. You don't know the coarse jokes,
the silly repetitions-Say! Maybe I could
go up there and talk her out of it!"</p>
  <p>"I guess not,"said Price. 'A man doesn't
travel to the end of creation in the dead of
winter, and then go fourteen miles by wagon,
just to make an afternoon call."</p>
  <p>Vawter rose. "Well, it's something to
get the situation clear in your mind. She
mustn't come, that's one thing; and the
other is, that nobody but you and me must
ever know that she wanted to come. That's
as far as I can go. You can't help me beyond 
that-nobody can. I've got to hope
for a leading."</p>
  <p>"Yes, and I guess you'll get it. And,
Vawter--please remember that you don't
have to tell me what you may decide to do."</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-187"
                    n="185"/>



   <p>At the door Vawter stopped. "I'd like
to say that I think you've been pretty nice
about a thing some men would have treated
as a joke."</p>
   <p>"Don't mention it," said Price. "I don't
know when I've enjoyed anything so much
as seeing the way I took it. It gave me
some hope for myself."</p>
  <p>Later at his office Vawter said to himself
with a sigh, "Well, if there isn't any possible 
way out of a thing, I reckon all I can
do is to get out in an impossible way." He
called for his secretary to come and take
down a letter. "On plain paper, please,
Mr. Holliday."</p>
  <p>The letter set forth that it had come to
the knowledge of the writer that the property 
of Abraham Morningstar was in danger,
that great harm might come to him should
he be absent for a day, that he ought to remain 
closely at home for some months, and
that he must not tell anyone he had received
such a warning. "And, Mr. Holliday, you
may bring it to me to sign." As he put it


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-188"
                    n="186"/>


into an envelope he turned pale with his
horror of it. "Great Caesar! Have <hi rend="i">I</hi> gone
into the White Cap business? Am I the
sort of man that sends anonymous letters?"</p>
   <p>That night his little daughter clung to
him. "Oh, father, how good you are!"
"Well, honey," he answered with grim
amusement at his own distress, "maybe
I'm good, but <hi rend="i">maybe</hi> I'm one of the lowest
creatures known to society."</p>

  <p>Before the next summer the fishermen
built a pretty clubhouse of their own on the
shore of the lake. Vawter went later than
the others and was welcomed at the landing
with joyous acclamations. At the door a
spry mulatto hurried forward to take his
bag and overcoat. "You Cunnel Vawter,
suh?" He looked about at the gentlemen
in expectation of the guffaw that he thought
would follow his next words. "Woman up
on the hill where we-all gets our aigs mighty
keen to see you, suh!"</p>
  <p>Vawter's steel-colored eyes rested on the


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-189"
                    n="187"/>



 negro for an instant. Then he spoke even
 more gently than was usual with him. "You
 mean Mrs. Morningstar? As soon as the
 steward can spare you, you may go up there
 and tell her that Mr. Vawter will do himself
 the honor of calling on her to-morrow
 morning."</p>
   <p>As they passed on into the house young
Harbison lingered in the hall.  "Look
here," he said to the steward, "that nigger
of yours is just a little too fresh!"</p>
  <p>In the radiant morning Vawter, trim and
soldierlike, walked toward the Morningstar
house. Flocks of little yellow butterflies
flowered the road along which he went.
Beyond the fields the lake lay blue and
sparkling. At intervals the song of a
meadow lark rang out. He felt the beauty
of it all, but he was greatly disturbed. He
could not guess what Mrs. Morningstar's
situation might be. Had Abe suspected
the truth? Had Loretta in some desperate
moment confessed it? She might be more
wretched than ever; she might meet him


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-190"
                    n="188"/>




with reproaches. He could bear her anger,
but to seem to be false to one who had
trusted him, was a thought that stung him.
He went over it all again with a sickening
feeling that he in some way was at the bottom 
of the trouble.</p>
   <p>"I have meant to do only what is right.
 I have tried to walk uprightly before God
 and man, and I guess I have blundered along
 like one of these wobbly-legged calves!"</p>
   <p>Loretta saw him approaching; she came
hurriedly out of the door-the house was
only a few feet from the roadside. She
took no time for greeting. " Some of the
folks are in the kitchen. Go up to the edge
of the cornfield and wait for me."</p>
  <p>She vanished before he could speak. He
walked on bewildered. As he got his breath
he addressed himself: "Henry Vawter,
have you gone crazy? Are you waiting at
the edge of the cornfield for Abe Morningstar's 
wife?"</p>
  <p>She appeared almost immediately; her
pink sunbonnet was perched on the top of
her head; she looked very pretty.</p>

<pb
                    id="VAB1822-191"
                    n="189"/>



   <p>"I've wanted to see you awful bad--"
 she hesitated. Vawter's heart sank.</p>
   <p>"I've been so-so afraid you thought
 hard of my not coming last winter. What's
 the matter?" she asked, as the man drew a
 quick breath.</p>
   <p>"Oh, nothing. I ought not to go out in
the sun without my smelling salts and parasol."</p>
   <p>She laughed and went on, "You see it
was this way; I really did lay off to go, but
I couldn't seem to get away nohow. After
I began to pick up, Abe got a notion he
was poorly, and he took to settin' round the
house, and after he was converted he helped
me lots, and George he went up to Valparaisy 
to clerk in his uncle's store, and Lon
Bunker got married, and there wasn't no
one but Abe and me and Myrtie, and I
got real reconciled. Fact is," she added,
with a flash of youthful gayety, "time I
could go I was plum out of notion of goin'!"</p>
   <p>"Well, that's a heap better, ain't it?"
said Vawter.</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-192"
                    n="190"/>



   <p>"Yes, I can see that plenty well now--
 for one thing, I expect I'd 'a' had a hard time
 earning my living teaching music." She
 continued, with simple confidence in his
 friendly interest: "I get a good deal more
 time to play now than I did, and Abe and
 me's joined the Christian Endeavors at our
 church, and we're going to attend the entertainments 
the Campbellites are gettin' up.
 Looky here! You won't ever let on to Abe
 that I had a notion of leavin' him?"</p>
   <p>"No, indeed; I don't even let it on to
myself."</p>
  <p>That evening Wemys said, "They say
Abe got converted at the big revival this
spring. Vawter, when you were up there
this morning did you see anything of the
family altar that exhorters counsel the
brother who has found the light to set up?"</p>
  <p>"Yes," answered Vawter whimsically,
"I saw it; I helped shove it round into
place. It's just a plain, ordinary, homemade, 
medium-sized altar."</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-193"
                    n="[191]"/>
</div2>

            



<div2 type="chapter"><head rend="center">THE WIFE OF A CARPENTER</head>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-194"
                    n="[192]"/>




<pb
                    id="VAB1822-195"
                    n="193"/>





<head rend="center">THE WIFE OF A CARPENTER</head>

<p><hi rend="b">W</hi>HEN at dinner Dr. Harmon 
      mentioned a sick woman whom he had
seen that day he was not departing from his
habit of professional reticence; it was not
of her illness that he spoke. Her name,
Moore, was that of Mrs. Harmon's kinspeople 
in Whitcomb County. She and her
husband were from that part of the State--
there might be some connection.</p>
  <p>"I guess they are poor, and they seem to
have no acquaintances. It might be a kind
thing for you to go to see her," he said, regarding 
Mrs. Harmon with the lack of confidence 
in his own good impulses that overcomes 
a man in the presence of his wife.</p>
  <p>It turned out there was no relationship;
but when Mrs. Harmon went to see the
sick woman she was so much pleased with
her that she soon went again, and took
   


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-196"
                    n="194"/>





some pains to make the acquaintance of
the husband.</p>
  <p>"Mr. Moore and his wife are as timid and
shy as two gentle animals," said Mrs. Harmon, 
at home. "I do not see how they can
get on in the city."</p>
  <p>"As to that," said the doctor, "they
came here because they could not get on in
the country. Moore is a carpenter, and at
present there are not many lordly mansions
in process of erection on the farms of Whitcomb 
County."</p>
  <p>"He ought to be a farmer--that's what
<hi rend="i">I'm</hi> going to be," said little Tom--"anyhow 
in maple sugar time."</p>
   <p>"Maybe he hadn't enough money to buy
a farm, Tom," said Miss Amy. "<hi rend="i">I'm</hi> going
to have plenty of money," answered the
boy.</p>
  <p>The doctor continued: "I spoke to Moore's
boss about him. He says that the man
will always be able to earn his bread and
butter--he's competent and industrious--
but that he'll never get on much. He hasn't


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-197"
                    n="195"/>





enough cheek to look out for little contracts
or to ask for higher wages."</p>
  <p>Mrs. Harmon's well-filled satin bodice
creaked as she sighed, "Well, it's something 
for a man to be able to earn his bread
and butter."</p>
   <p>"My dear," said the doctor, "you are,
as usual, distinctly right."</p>
  <p>As soon as Mrs. Moore was well she let
the doctor's wife see that she wanted to earn
a little money herself, and Mrs. Harmon
often carried to her small bits of sewing--a
lace flounce to be pieced, some frills to be
hemstitched for Amy's night gowns. The
children, Tom, Nelly and the two-year-old
baby, were sometimes in the carriage with
their mother.  " It was the strangest thing
to see the little woman brighten up at the
sight of the babies," said Mrs. Harmon.
'She forgot all about <hi rend="i">me</hi>. I left them with
her for a while. When I went back for
them they wailed and she looked so wistful
that it was positively touching."</p>
  <p>It was the desire to see the children that


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-198"
                    n="196"/>




first drew Mrs. Moore, in spite of her shyness,
to the Harmons' house. Later she came
often and sat busy at her sewing in the wide
upper hall. The children hung round her
and climbed over her, but she never seemed
to tire of them. She was such a gentle,
ladylike little creature, that all the family
grew fond of her and came to call her, as
the children did, "Cousin Mary." She had
beautiful red hair, a thin skin, and mild,
protuberant blue eyes. Her husband was
enough like her to be her brother. When the
doctor and his wife went off on short trips,
Mrs. Moore was asked to stay at the house
with Miss Amy and the little ones. At such
times her husband, William, came to dinner
with them. He sat up at the table, shiningly 
clean and very well-behaved, looking
like a little boy who has been asked out to
tea. When one of the children said anything 
bright (and the Harmon children were
generally free to speak their minds), William 
and his wife would look at each other
in silent delight and admiration.</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-199"
                    n="197"/>




   <p>"I wonder how they manage to exist,"
said Amy (she was one of the girls who are
putting into the work of improving their
minds the same sort of energy and devotion 
that their grandmothers gave to the
business of saving their souls). "They seem
never to have anything to talk about, even
to each other, but some baby that they
know."</p>
  <p>"Oh," said Mrs. Harmon, " they have a
great deal to interest them. They read the
Bible to each other every night, and they
always go to church."</p>
  <p>They not only went to church on Sundays, 
but to prayer-meeting on Thursday
nights. They were as regular in attendance 
at these meetings and as little noticed
as the negro janitor, who slept quietly in
one of the dusky corners that surrounded
the illuminated center where a few old men
and women and one fashionably dressed sister, 
whose husband was not a "professor,"
asked each other once a week why the
young people would not attend prayer-


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-200"
                    n="198"/>




meeting. The Moores enjoyed it all greatly.</p>
  <p>Once William made a joke. His wife
complained of the rain. "Don't you remember, 
Mary," he said, "that Brother
Taylor said that if there was one thing that
more than another was sent for our personal 
reproof and correction, it was the
weather? I guess you've been doing something 
naughty."</p>
  <p>When this jeu d'esprit was reported by
Cousin Mary (who had a modest pride in it),
Amy fairly turned pale.</p>
  <p>"Oh, what barrenness!" she- said to her
mother, later. "Have they <hi rend="i">no</hi> intellectual
life?"</p>
  <p>"I never have observed," responded Mrs.
Harmon, with dignity, "that intellectual
people have any better time than others who
make less pretensions. Cousin Mary certainly 
seems as happy as the rest of you."</p>
  <p>Miss Amy could admit a truth even if she
did not approve of the conclusion to be
drawn from it. She saw that Cousin Mary
was happy; she saw, indeed, that she was


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-201"
                    n="199"/>





not only happy, but in a sort of exaltation.
Her color was brighter than it had been;
she laughed aloud as she played with the
children; sometimes when she thought no
one could hear her she sang aloud as she
sat at her sewing. William, also, was
changed. Formerly he hardly dared answer
when Mrs. Harmon addressed him; now
when his wife came in the morning he
escorted her to the front door, rang the bell
bold as a lion, and told Mrs. Harmon not
to let Mary get tired.</p>
  <p>In the autumn and winter she did not
come often to the Harmons'. The children
were taken to her house and came back
noisy and happy, bearing little homemade
toys that she and William had contrived for
them.</p>
  <p>In March Cousin Mary gave birth to a
child which died immediately. From the
first she was out of her senses, and an alarming 
mania developed. She was violently ill
for weeks. During this time her husband
worked night and day taking care of her.


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-202"
                    n="200"/>




His toil was incredible; he went through
more than it would have been thought could
be endured by the stoutest frame. But it
could not be permitted. An awful day
came for the poor little man. In a close
carriage with Mrs. Harmon and the doctor
he took his wife, tied hand and foot, to the
insane asylum. As they drew near the
place he made pitiful attempts to smooth
her gown, to adjust her hat, though she
struck at him. "Mary is always so tidy and
particular about her looks," he said.</p>
  <p>That night as Amy Harmon in her ballroom 
finery sat with her parents in the
library waiting for the carriage that was to
take her to a dance, they spoke of the distress 
of the day.</p>
  <p>"Why has it happened?" the girl asked
of her father. "What have Cousin Mary and
her husband ever done to deserve this awful
thing?" She spoke with the bewildered bitterness 
of one who for the first time finds
her question cannot be answered.</p>
  <p>"We must trust in a Providence that is


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-203"
                    n="201"/>




wiser than we are," said the mother, comfortably. 
The girl still looked at her father.</p>
  <p>"Well, Amy, one woman in so many
hundreds goes crazy. Poor Cousin Mary
drew the marked ballot. That is all. You
all take your chance."</p>
  <p>"Oh, I don't know what 'chance' is!"
she exclaimed.</p>
  <p>"Neither do I," he replied. "But I <hi rend="i">think</hi>
it is a segment of some great circle of the
law."</p>
  <p>After this the Harmons saw nothing of
Cousin Mary's husband. He crept away
like some wounded animal to suffer alone.
Mrs. Harmon looked for him at church, but
he was seen there no more. She drove to
the little house and found it locked. A
woman stretched her neck over the next
fence and then addressed her:</p>
  <p>"You ain't acquainted with them folks,
are you?"</p>
  <p>"Oh, yes," Mrs. Harmon responded; "I
know them very well."</p>
  <p>The neighbor brightened ip with the


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-204"
                    n="202"/>


pleasure of one who has something of interest 
to communicate. "Well, you won't
find her at home; she's gone crazy."</p>
   <p>"I didn't expect to see Mrs. Moore. I
 wanted to find out something about Mr.
 Moore. Do you know if he is well?"</p>
   <p>"Oh, he's all right, I reckon, far's <hi rend="i">that</hi>
 goes.  But he acts mighty curious.  He
 just cooks and works for himself, and never
 speaks to a soul. Minute his work's done
 he puts out his lamp. But if he don't want
 to be friendly, it's no difference to <hi rend="i">us!</hi>" Her
 tone indicated advances not responded to.</p>
   <p>The resident physicians at the asylum
 sometimes communicated with Dr. Harmon
 about Mrs. Moore's condition, and occasion ally, 
 when William's day's work was done,
 he came to the house to ask for news. In
 the long summer evenings, as Miss Amy
 sat with her friends on the wide veranda,
 in the scent of the lilies that came up from
 the lawn below, she often saw William's
 slight, boyish figure in the shadow of the
 trees that edged the sidewalk-sometimes


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-205"
                    n="203"/>




when the doctor was delayed he stood there
for two or three hours. And when the doctor 
alighted she saw the face of the young
man in the light of the street lamps as he
came forward. It was wild and haggard
and unshaven. But sometimes, after long
waiting, when William heard the carriage
wheels coming, he stole away without a
word.</p>
  <p>"I wonder what Mr. Moore does with
himself on Sundays?" said Mrs. Harmon.
"I've sent to his house several times, but
he's never at home."</p>
  <p>"I think I saw him one Sunday," said the
doctor. "I was driving past the grounds of
the asylum--six miles from town, you know;
--the rain was coming down in sheets. A
man that looked like him was lying on the
grass huddled close against the palings that
inclosed the grounds. But if it was he,
he hid his face so that I might not recognize
him."</p>
  <p>The day came in August when the doctor
had good news. Cousin Mary was improving.


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-206"
                    n="204"/>



Then word came that William might
see her for a few minutes. He took hope
immediately and was ready to talk to Mrs.
Harmon about what he might cook to carry
to his wife. He came to ask advice about
a flannel dressing gown. He began to make
a store of jelly for winter consumption, and
he even tried to coax a few late flowers to
bloom in the little yard.</p>
   <p>In the autumn Mary was discharged.
Mrs. Harmon sent flowers to the house to
welcome her home, and they all made every
show of kindly feeling. But they spoke of
it gravely to one another.</p>
   <p>"How much better it would have been if
she had died," said Amy. "How horrible
for her to drag through life, knowing she
has been insane!"</p>
   <p>"Does it seem so to you?" asked the
doctor.</p>
  <p>"How could it seem otherwise?--to distrust 
one's judgment--to watch each whim
with trembling horror--to have the doubt


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-207"
                    n="205"/>





always hanging over you. It would drive
me mad a second time!"</p>
   <p>"Probably it would," responded her
father; "but then you have had the advantage 
of a higher education. You, I
doubt not, know much about alienism and
have studied something of diseases of the
mind and will. Cousin Mary has not had
your opportunities. She is no more ashamed
than she would be of having had the grip.
It was bad, it is over, and that is the end
of it."</p>
   <p>"But her husband! won't <hi rend="i">he</hi> be ashamed?
Won't he trust her less?"</p>
  <p>"Oh, I never said William was a gentleman. 
I dare say he'll be just as fond of
her as ever."</p>
   <p>"He is not a gentleman, of course," said
Mrs. Harmon, severely. "But he is an
earnest, sincere Christian, and I don't see
why <hi rend="i">you</hi> should run him down--and you
always talking the way you do--"</p>
  <p>The reunited pair took up their life just
where they had left it. They were at church


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-208"
                    n="206"/>




the next Sunday perhaps a little paler than
formerly, but looking very happy. Cousin
Mary came to the Harmons' as often as before. 
They tried to be very considerate;
Mrs. Harmon and Amy often sat with her
while she sewed, and at such times one of
them would read aloud from some book that
Cousin Mary might find diverting. Amy
talked gayly about the little things that were
happening, taking the greatest pains to be
as gentle and simple in her talk as might be.
They learned afterward that Cousin Mary
regarded these hours as times of great intellectual 
stimulus. As she gained confidence
the mother and daughter used the tact for
which they were distinguished in a wide circle 
to induce her to talk freely to them.
One day she told them of her experiences
in the hospital. She spoke quite simply,
with no show of feeling or self-pity, or the
least perception that there might be anything 
in the situation that called for special
sympathy. She said that when she came
to herself she felt that her mind was 


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-209"
                    n="207"/>





disturbed, and was glad to be in a place where
she might be helped to get well.</p>
   <p>"I have wondered if you were not
 troubled about the baby," said Mrs. Harmon.</p>
   <p>Cousin Mary's mild face flushed. "Before 
I knew anything else I knew that it
 was dead. I never asked; sometimes in the
 night I cried."</p>
   <p>"Did you begin to think about your home
and William long before you spoke?"</p>
   <p>"Oh, yes; I wanted to ask about William 
for weeks, but somehow I could not.
One day I could say the words, and I asked
the attendant--" Here she hesitated. "I
remember her," said Mrs. Harmon; "that
big, strong Irish woman. What did she tell
you?"</p>
  <p>"She said, 'Don't bother about him--
he's got another wife long ago!' Of course
I knew it was not true," said Cousin Mary,
meekly, "but it grieved me a little."</p>
  <p>Amy made some gesture of indignant pro-
test, but Cousin Mary, busy at her sewing,


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-210"
                    n="208"/>





did not see it. She went on calmly, saying
that perhaps she had delayed her own recovery. 
She had found in the pocket of one
of her dresses a scrap of the lace that she
had sewn around the neck of one of the
baby's slips. She liked to touch it, and to
hold it against her face. One day the nurse
suddenly pointed her out to a passing doctor. 
"She's pretty crazy yet, you see!" "I
did not know that it was wrong," said Cousin 
Mary, "or I should not have done it."</p>
   <p>"How horrible!" cried Amy; "that woman 
ought to be killed!"</p>
   <p>"Oh, you <hi rend="i">mustn't</hi> think that," begged
Cousin Mary; "I am sure she never meant
to be unkind, and she was very faithful and
industrious."</p>
  <p>The next autumn Cousin Mary seemed
frailer than before. Sometimes the doctor
stopped her in the hall with kindly inquiries
about her health. "Is there any danger
of Cousin Mary's mania returning?" asked
Amy.</p>
  <p>"They say not," answered her mother.


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-211"
                    n="209"/>




"It was not constitutional; it was an accident, 
as a fever might have been."</p>
  <p>In her heart Amy thought them all a little
dull. Certainly, Cousin Mary was not well.
She came no more to the house, but in the
evening William often stopped for a tonic
or a sleeping powder on his way home from
work. He did not, however, seem any
more distressed than did the others.</p>
  <p>It was the last season before Amy Harmon's 
marriage. She was going out constantly. 
The night before Christmas she
danced till three o'clock. "Don't try to
get up to breakfast, dear," said her mother.</p>
   <p>"Not get up on Christmas morning?
Why, I'd get up then if I had to stay in bed
a month to pay for it."</p>
  <p>The Christmas tree was shown just after
breakfast.  The children screamed and
shouted.  Everybody was happy.  The
drawing-room floor was covered with tinsel
cords and ribbons and wrapping paper;
neighbor children ran in and out; uncles
   


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-212"
                    n="210"/>





came bearing gifts; the telephone rang itself
into spasms.</p>
  <p>On Christmas evening the Harmons
always went to the house of the grandfather.
There was a supper at which everybody,
big and little, was seated, and in the evening 
dancing and games. Amy and her little
sister Nelly went first; they were to send
the carriage back for the others. As they
were starting Mrs. Harmon gave them a
basket full of little gifts for Cousin Mary to
be left at her house on the way.</p>
   <p>"Go in quietly without knocking," she
said.  "Your father says she is doing well,
but she may be asleep."</p>
  <p>The house was one of a row of workingmen's 
cottages that stretched out in the
shadow of a great factory. The factory
was still and dark; the street lay hushed in
the silence of a late Christmas afternoon.
There was no light in the house except one
that shone through a side window. The
coachman carried the basket to the door,
and Amy, gathering her finery over her arm


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-213"
                    n="211"/>






and followed by her little sister, ran through
snow drifts as high as her shoulder along
the little path from the gate to the house.</p>
   <p>She opened the door softly and they
entered. She viewed the little place--its
braided rugs, its tidy poverty. There was
no sound except that of the voice of a man
reading in the inner room. Amy floated
across the outer one; her bright mantle
slipped from her shoulders and lay at her
feet, a pool of shimmering gold and azure.
As she stood poised in her white gown in the
square of light that came through the open
doorway little Nelly saw her with sudden
awe. '"I think," she whispered to herself,
"that sister looks like an angel!" Then she
stole to Amy's side and looked into the
further room. There, white as a lily, her
bright hair spread out like an aureole over
her pillow, lay Cousin Mary. The light of
happiness and life and love was in her blue
eyes. On her arm was a baby. As they
stood there they heard William read the
scripture for the day:</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-214"
                    n="212"/>




   <p>"And this shall be a sign unto you; Ye
shall find the babe wrapped in swaddling
clothes, lying in a manger.</p>
  <p>"And suddenly there was with the angel
a multitude of the heavenly host praising
God, and saying,</p>
  <p>"'Glory to God in the highest, and on
earth peace, good will toward men.'"</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-215" n="[213]"/>
</div2>
          





<div2 type="chapter"><head rend="center">A GENTLEWOMAN</head>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-216"
                    n="[214]"/>



<pb
                    id="VAB1822-217"
                    n="215"/>






<head rend="center">A GENTLEWOMAN</head>


<p><hi rend="b">O</hi>NE winter afternoon three friends sat
     together sewing. It was the week before 
Christmas, and they were busy preparing 
for that season. Some packages, beribboned 
and addressed, lay on the table in
the middle of the drawing-room in the
shadow of a cluster of long-stemmed red
roses. Other parcels, almost ready to be
put with them, filled a chair near one of
the ladies.</p>
  <p>As they pursued their pretty work, they
talked together with playful candor. But
although their conversation was intelligent
and free, there was a sort of repression
about it which stands among American women 
as a sign of high breeding. The same
thing was to be noticed in the composure
of their attitudes and even in the simple elegance 
of their attire. It was an easy guess


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-218"
                    n="216"/>



that any one of them would regard a manifestation 
of mental or moral vehemence as
evidence of a lack of culture.</p>
   <p>They had been speaking of a woman
 whom they all knew. Then as the sun
 sank behind the snow-capped turrets of
 the house opposite, they dropped their work
 and talked of womankind.</p>
   <p>"I wonder if it is true that all women are
 at heart pretty much alike?" asked Theodora.</p>
   <p>"For my part," said Fanny, "I see no
more reason for believing that women's
hearts are alike than that their minds are,
which is absurd."</p>
   <p>"I think we are all alike," said Amy.
 "There are the same depths and shallows
 in every woman's nature. What fills the
 depth--love, or religion, or jealousy--is of
 course decided by circumstances or education."</p>
 <p>Fanny objected: " It is easy to say that,
 but you cannot prove it. There are a very
few instinctive passions, such, for instance,


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-219"
                    n="217"/>



as maternal affection (which even Theodora
must admit she has in common with the
lower animals), that we all may feel; but
I think it probable that the highly developed 
sensibility which alone can engender
complex and delicate emotion is the result
of culture, either personal or inherited."</p>
   <p>"I don't like to agree with you," said
Theodora. "For one thing, such an idea
seems irreligious."</p>
   <p>"Yes; that's a fine reason," laughed
Fanny.</p>
  <p>"I have known many women intimately,"
said Amy, "and I am sure that no class
monopolizes the capacity for high and intense 
feeling."</p>
  <p>"I like the way you two talk!" exclaimed
Fanny. "Whom did either of you ever
know outside of your relatives and visiting
lists?"</p>
  <p>Theodora ventured to respond that she
had gone among the poor a great deal.</p>
  <p>"No doubt," commented Fanny, "the


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-220"
                    n="218"/>




<hi rend="i">worthy</hi> poor!--that is to say; the poor made
in your image."</p>
   <p>"And I," asserted Amy, "may have
learned something from books. You know
I read <hi rend="i">anything</hi> that tells of humanity."</p>
   <p>"Yes, I know," said Fanny, "you pride
yourself on your love for your kind, and you
lie on the sofa all day reading stories about
French and Russian women. I don't say
the stories are not true, but how do you
know they are?"</p>
   <p>"How does one know anything?" asked
Theodora. "One sees by one's imagination; 
one tests what is seen by one's reason."</p>
   <p>"That sounds very grand; it's a pity
there's no sense in it!" said Fanny. "For
my part, I wish I could know for myself."
She paused, laughed, and then, with a look
of defiance on her pretty face, began to
speak more earnestly than before. "The
truth is, I just long to know something outside 
of ourselves. I am lonely on our little
desert island of culture. I want to shake


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-221"
                    n="219"/>




hands with the howling savages on shore.
Maybe I wouldn't like it, but I wish I could
get a chance."</p>
  <p>Amy began to speak, and then hesitated.
"I do not know that it would interest you
--last summer I met,-but perhaps it's too
long a story."</p>
  <p>"Pray tell it," said Theodora, politely.</p>
  <p>"Yes," said Fanny, "pray tell it. But
I don't believe you ever met anybody who
was not introduced to you by your mother
or your sister-in-law."</p>
  <p>Amy blushed a little as she began.
"Eighteen months ago I had to go to Chicago 
alone. It was necessary that I should
change from one train to another on the
way, and I was to wait in Plymouth from
noon until six in the afternoon. There was
nothing alarming about this, for Plymouth
is as quiet an old place as one could wish
to find."</p>
  <p>"I know it," interrupted Fanny. "The
cleanest little town! There are sandy
streets densely shaded by beautiful maple


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-222"
                    n="220"/>





trees, and here and there a mountain ash
bright with clusters of scarlet berries."</p>
   <p>"My husband had told me just what to
do," continued Amy. "I was to go from
the station to the La Fayette House, and
stay there until time for the next train.
This house is an old place which is highly
thought of by the few travelers--mostly
lawyers--who have occasion to stop in the
little town. It is more like an English inn
than one would think possible, with not one
modern improvement, and yet much homely
comfort.</p>
   <p>"I walked from the station to the hotel.
The day was beautiful. At the door the
landlord met me with hospitable warmth. I
was late for their regular dinner, but his
daughter, a comely old maid, took me into
the dining-room, seated me by a vine-
shaded window, and served me with simple
dainties-red raspberries fresh from the garden 
just outside, a pitcher of yellow cream,
and later a little cake hot from the oven--


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-223"
                    n="221"/>



the 'try-cake,' she said, of one she was
'making for tea.'</p>
   <p>"When my luncheon was finished, I went
 across the hall to the parlor and looked
 about me before I settled myself for the
 afternoon with a novel. I delighted in the
 room;-the striped paper on the walls; the
 pictures high-hung and tilted forward; the
 clean Nottingham curtains that shook in the
 sweet air."</p>
   <p>"You don't say anything about the tin
plaque with a one-legged stork on it," said
Fanny.</p>
   <p>"No; because I didn't see it. But there
was an old glass fruit dish full of mignonette
on the center table. The room seemed like
the rest of the house-sweet and peaceful,
as if it were the index of simple, undisturbed
lives.</p>
  <p>"In a far corner, with her back to me,
sat a lady busy with some needlework.
She had the appearance of being at home.
Her work-basket was beside her. I did not
look at her twice, but opened my book and


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-224"
                    n="222"/>





read for awhile, forgetting there was anyone
present but myself. A half hour, perhaps,
had passed, when the lady rose and walked
across the room. As she moved, I looked
after her, at first listlessly, then astounded.
I could not see her face, but her dress, her
figure, above all, her carriage, fairly took
my breath away. I never have seen anything 
like the grace of her moving. I know
now that the most beautiful dancing in the
world is not so beautiful as--is not to be
compared with--the rhythmical grace possible 
in the human walk. When she seated
herself, I felt a sort of pang, as if music had
ceased. Then I noticed her costume. You
may smile, Fanny, but I have seldom seen
a woman so charmingly dressed.  My own
little bravery seemed tawdry and common
beside the fashion of her attire. I almost
thought I was dreaming."</p>
  <p>"And were you not?" asked Fanny. "You
know I've been in Plymouth myself!"</p>
  <p>"Who was she?" inquired Theodora.</p>
  <p>"That was what I tried to think. I concluded


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-225"
                    n="223"/>





that she must belong to one of the
wealthy Sevier County families, and was
perhaps waiting here after a summer's absence 
for her house to be opened. But I
wondered that in that case I had not heard
of her. She was sewing on some fancy-
work, a strip of pink velvet cut in deep
points along one edge, which she embroidered 
with silver thread and jewel-like beads.
She dropped her thimble and rose to look
for it. I saw it in a corner. Then we fell
into conversation. Soon I was seated at
her side, counting the beads for her as she
used them. I know I can <hi rend="i">never</hi> make you
understand the simple elegance of that woman's 
manner--her grace, her dignity!"</p>
  <p>"First," said Fanny, "I'd like to understand 
something about <hi rend="i">your</hi> manner and its
dignity. Are you in the habit of sitting
down to sew with every woman you meet
in a hotel parlor?"</p>
  <p>"You know very well that I am not. It
was her fineness which made it possible. It
seemed just the natural thing to do. There


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-226"
                    n="224"/>




was no possibility of making one's self common 
in her society."</p>
   <p>"Oh, well," said Fanny, "I suppose it
was not so very bad. I know who she was
--that young Mrs. Ridley, whose husband
is minister to China."</p>
   <p>"No, my dear," answered Amy, "she was
<hi rend="i">not</hi> Mrs. Ridley. Of course I myself was
wondering who she was, though the instant
charm of her presence kept me from thinking 
definitely about it. By and by I carelessly 
asked her what her work (the strip of
velvet) was for. What do you think she
said--you, Fanny, who know everything?"</p>
   <p>"For the mantelpiece in her own little
sitting-room, of course," said Fanny.</p>
  <p>"Not at all! Without haste or hesitation, 
as simply as possible, she said, 'For
my husband's costume.'"</p>
   <p>"Well," said Fanny, "I suppose they
were going to have some private theatricals."</p>
  <p>"I said something implying that. She
looked at me with mild surprise.  'Ah,'


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-227"
                    n="225"/>




said she, 'I fancy Raymond would find
that very tiresome.' Then we went back to
what we had been talking about. She told me
of a winter journey in Russia; how her husband 
piled furs over her till she thought she
should smother; of the palaces and their
conservatories; of a certain princess' gowns;
of market scenes and fetes on the ice--all
this, and more, with such gaiety and wit,
with such pretty accompaniment of gesture
and changing color and light mimicry, that
nothing could have been more charming."</p>
  <p>Fanny mused: "The Reed-Dudleys live
somewhere up there; they are often abroad."</p>
  <p>"She was <hi rend="i">not</hi> one of the Reed-Dudleys,"
answered Amy.</p>
  <p>"Well, then," said Fanny, "you deserved
no such luck; and how it ever happened in
Plymouth, and in summer, is past me--but
she was an actress or a singer."</p>
  <p>"She was neither; a thought of that sort
did occur to me for a minute, but I rejected
it, even before I found out positively that it
was not true. One look at her face would
      


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-228"
                    n="226"/>




have convinced you that never since she was
born had that rose-petal skin ever been
touched by paint and powder. Have I told
you what she was like?"</p>
   <p>"No," said Fanny. "I thought you
spared us purposely."</p>
   <p>"I suppose she was very pretty!" said
Theodora.</p>
   <p>"I do not know whether she was or not,
but she was a revelation of what a woman
may be at the high mark of physical perfection. 
She had in her appearance a quality
that transcends any beauty of feature."</p>
   <p>"Oh, yes," said Fanny, "goodness--I
used to hear that sort of talk when I was a
little girl. I thought it was out of date
now."</p>
  <p>"I do not mean goodness; though for
that matter, her face did show that. It was
a quality that is as much a material attribute 
as beauty is. She was the incarnation
of physical well-being-the climax of perfect 
health. She fairly glowed with it; an
atmosphere of it seemed to surround her,


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-229"
                    n="227"/>




Even to be near her was to feel a health-
giving influence. Looking at her, one would
say that from head to foot there was not a
muscle, not a nerve, not a drop of blood,
but was working in absolute order as God
meant it to work. I never thought until I
saw her what physical perfection might be
--not physical beauty, which beside it is a
poor, scrappy affair, but strong, flawless
vitality. I tell you this fair creature made
other women show beside her as deformities
--cripples."</p>
  <p>"How you must love to contemplate Mr.
Corbett!" said Fanny.</p>
  <p>"Nonsense!" answered Amy. "A man
of that kind is the owner of certain abnormally 
developed muscles-to a degree the result 
of special training. This young woman
seemed to have blossomed into perfection
as a flower does.</p>
  <p>"But I was telling you of our conversation. 
She mentioned her husband again,
and said he had gone to some small town
near by on professional business. She had


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-230"
                    n="228"/>



stayed in Plymouth a while the year before,
when he was on a similar journey; he felt
it safe to leave her there because the people
in the house were such good, kindly folks."</p>
   <p>"And <hi rend="i">then</hi>," said Fanny, "I suppose
you asked this United States Senator's wife
what her husband's line of trade was?"</p>
   <p>"Not quite that, but something like it,
I'm afraid. She answered me at once."</p>
   <p>"She answered you as you deserved, I
hope," said Fanny.</p>
   <p>"Fanny, are you not ashamed of yourself?" 
exclaimed Theodora. "You know you
would have asked her flatly in the first five
minutes!"</p>
   <p>"She looked up at me with a smile,"
continued Amy," and she said, 'Will it seem
vain for me to say, what our agent has
printed on all his letterheads, that my husband, 
Raymond Mersac, and I are the leading 
cannon-ball artists in the world?'"</p>
  <p>"And what," said Theodora, "is a cannon-ball 
artist?"</p>
  <p>"I'll tell you,",cried Fanny. "A 


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-231"
                    n="229"/>



cannon-ball artist--oh, why was I not in Ply-
mouth that day?--a cannon-ball artist is a
lady, clad in tights, who is shot out of an
imitation cannon-Amy, you never deserved
this; <hi rend="i">you</hi> could not appreciate it--shot out
of an imitation cannon with a spring, high
into the air, where she catches the hands of
a gentleman who is at the moment suspended 
by the knees, head down, from a
trapeze--that is a little swing fastened on
a tight rope! Amy, it has been the dream
of my life to meet, to actually know, one of
these circus people. And now it has happened 
to <hi rend="i">you!</hi> It is too much!"</p>
  <p>"I can understand," said Theodora, "that
one might be curious, not about the individuals, 
but about their habits. I confess
that I cannot see how a person living such
a life as that from childhood (and I believe
that only long training makes such feats
possible) could have any of the womanly
charm that Amy says belonged to her Madame 
Mersac."</p>
  <p>"I do not ask you to understand it," said


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-232"
                    n="230"/>




Amy, "and I do not know that her life had
anything to do with her personality, though
probably it had preserved for her the transcendent 
physical endowment with which
she must have been born."</p>
   <p>"Well, I hope you asked her a thousand
 questions!" exclaimed Fanny.</p>
   <p>"No doubt I should have expected myself 
to, but in her presence one was not
 tempted to the impertinence of questioning.
That would have been impossible. However, 
I was with her for several hours. I
saw that she was drawn to me as I was to
her. It seemed just the natural thing to
talk freely, and by and by we gave ourselves
to confidences, as children do, or as young
girls will in the first abandonments of intimacy.</p>
   <p>"What she told me of herself was in
 substance this: Her parents died when she
 was three years old. They had been acrobats.  
 Her father was English, her mother
 French. They had no relatives. At their
 death the little Leonie was taken in charge


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-233"
                    n="231"/>



by an old Frenchman and his wife, who had
some little employment at a zoological garden 
near London, and who kept a sort of
training school for acrobats. They must
have been a very gentle, kindly old pair.
They gave her the best training their knowledge 
could secure. Her exercise, her food,
her hours of rest, were carefully (and she
said lovingly) arranged for her from her
earliest recollection. Except the hours when
she was being taught, she spent almost all
her time out of doors. She had no playmates; 
she said she never wanted any. The
other students at the training school were
all older than she while she was a child; and
after she was ten, she was so much more
proficient in the feats of her profession than
the others, that she had her lessons alone.</p>
   <p>"I asked her if masters were not at times
cruel, and if, when she was a child, she was
not frightened at the danger of the exercises. 
She said she supposed trainers were
unkind sometimes, but she fancied not
often, even if they were by nature bad-


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-234"
                    n="232"/>




tempered. 'A master,' said she, 'wants,
more than anything else, that his pupils
should do him   credit.  Everyone knows
that nothing is done well under compulsion.
When there is one trace of fear in the heart,
one can't think; one can't act; one can do
nothing really very good.   For my own
part,' said she, 'I was never set to do a special 
feat for which I was not already so well
prepared that it was easy. It was a delightful 
pastime, the reward often of months of
work. This routine work was never hard,
and only tiresome because it lasted so long;
but one came to do it as one might dance--
without thinking much about it.'"</p>
   <p>"I suppose," said Theodora, "that those
nets that are hung under the performers
give them confidence when they are poised
high in the air."</p>
   <p>"I said that.  She was very engaging
and sweet in her desire that I should not
guess what a primary sort of question I had
asked, but her answer was clear. The net
gave no confidence, because one never could


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-235"
                    n="233"/>




walk on a tight rope at all until one had
forgotten all about the elevation of the rope.
The first thing to learn was to feel that the
rope was not a rope stretched in mid-air,
but a line drawn flat on the surface of the
earth. Consequently, the net made no difference 
one way or the other. With it she
merely exercised on a line that rested on a
surface covered with netting. As she was
saying this, she stopped suddenly with a
radiant smile. Then she said, ' I should
tell you that Raymond does not agree with
me about this.'</p>
   <p>"'He prefers a netting under him?' said I.</p>
   <p>"'Oh, no,' she laughingly answered;
 'but he not only prefers, he insists on one
 under me. He sees to it himself at every
 performance. The canvas men, I am sure,
 hate him. The whole company laughs.
 Sometimes, when the netting has been mislaid, 
 he will not let me appear, and has in
 consequence stormy interviews with the
 manager. I thought it a little babyish of
him at first--he is so brave for himself, and


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-236"
                    n="234"/>




he knows so well my strength and confidence. 
I said so to him.' Here she
stopped.</p>
   <p>"'And what did he say, my dear?' I asked,
with courage born of our intimacy.</p>
   <p>"She spoke gravely, ' He said: "Should
I see you in great danger, Leonie, it might
not kill me, but I think it would."'"</p>
   <p>"She had lived so quietly with the old
French couple," said Theodora, "where
did she get her husband?"</p> 
   <p>"This is what she told me," continued
Amy: 'I have been married four years, and
I can hardly remember when I did not know
that I was to marry Raymond. This always
made me very happy when I thought of it,
and I tried hard to be good, so that he might
be pleased with me. He is ten years older
than I, and was a relative of my dear master. 
When he had a vacation he came to
see us. Sometimes, not often, he brought
me a gift; and he always talked to me so
sensibly, and yet so entertainingly, that it
seemed to me no company could be so 


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-237"
                    n="235"/>



delightful as his. And then he makes one feel
when he is gone that one must try to be
kinder and more unselfish, so as to be like
him. I thought there was no wiser or wittier 
man in the world, and no finer gentleman. 
I think so still,' she added, simply."</p>
   <p>"What did she know about gentlemen?"
asked Fanny.</p>
   <p>"Nothing, except what she had learned
from books. She had met a good many
men of the world, she said, but she had the
idea that they were rude and silly. She suggested 
an ingenious explanation-that such
people, not being forced to be constantly together, 
as those are who work, are not
obliged to learn to control themselves and
be polite for their mutual comfort; so they
should be excused for little rudenesses."</p>
  <p>"This is important, if true," said Fanny;
"I must think of it!"</p>
  <p>Amy continued: "As we talked, I came
to see that there was a very tender union
between Madame Mersac and her husband.
It was a rare chance that had united two


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-238"
                    n="236"/>




people so untouched by what we call the
realities of life. They seemed to be as alone
as Adam and Eve in Paradise. She told me
that they had never had an intimate friend;
their whole life was in each other. No doubt
there are many people who are capable of
such a passion, but I don't think they often
marry each other."</p>
   <p>"Well, it is saddening," said Fanny, "to
think that wedded love in its highest, purest 
form can only exist between a gentleman 
and a lady who are shot out of a cannon 
at each other, and who enjoy hanging
by their toes from tight ropes."</p>
  <p>Amy continued: "I do not say anything
so absurd as that the calling of these two
made them what they were. I do believe
that a healthful existence, away from the
intellectual strife in which the most of us
take some part, might nourish a simple and
faithful spirit, but I cannot think of Madame
Mersac as belonging to one order or another.
She was nature's own."</p>
  <p>"You said she was witty and vivacious,"


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-239"
                    n="237"/>




said Theodora, "but had she any education?"</p>
   <p>"As we count education she probably had
almost none; and yet, as results go, she was
not behind some highly educated women.
She knew French perfectly-not lady's maid
French, nor governess French, but that
beautiful, elegant, elastic tongue that never
was taught in a finishing school. I suppose
she had a natural aptitude for language, for
her English was charming.  Apparently
her words were chosen with regard to their
finest meaning, and not, as ours sometimes
are, in conformity to a.passing fashion. She
had read a great many books, but she knew
nothing of magazines or newspapers. Apart
from what she said, her manner of speaking
was that of a highly cultivated person. Her
master had a friend, an old dramatic teacher,
who had instructed some of the greatest of
English and French actors. This man had
given her lessons in pronouncing and enunciation.  
Every sentence came from her
lips with a high-bred accuracy that gave it


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-240"
                    n="238"/>




a charm quite independent of its meaning.
But everything about her was fine and delicate; 
her accent was only part of it!"</p>
  <p>"Did she have any curiosity about your
life, such as you felt about hers?" asked
Theodora.</p>
  <p>"Yes; but I do not think her interest was
as--morbid, shall I say? She did ask me
many questions, but I fancy they were
prompted more by her liking for me than
by any curiosity. It was a startling experience. 
You do not know what an embarrassing 
thing it is to hold such a life as ours
up to the inspection- of a sensible person
from another world. She wanted to know
something of the pursuits of a person who
had no special work. She had thought it
might be very pleasant, she said, but that
one would have to decide on ways in which
to spend the time profitably. She asked
me what <hi rend="i">I</hi> did.</p>
   <p>"'Oh, I keep house,' I said.</p>
   <p>"'Surely,' she answered; 'I might have
known that; and it must take thought and


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-241"
                    n="239"/>



much time. Raymond is a very good cook.
He has taught me how to prepare several
dainties. When we have a chance I cook
something and we have a fete. It must be
very pleasant to have one's husband and
children come to the table every day to compliment 
one's successes.'</p>
   <p>"'Oh, I don't cook,' said I.</p>
   <p>"She looked a little surprised for an instant.  
'I see, I was thinking of a simpler
life than yours. Of course there is no reason 
why a woman should cook when she can
afford to hire the services of someone who
can do it equally well. I can fancy there
are many things one might better save one's
time for--sewing, teaching the children,
visiting the poor, going to church, and the
like.'</p>
  <p>"I was getting desperate. 'My dear,'
I said, 'I neither sew, nor teach the children, 
nor visit the poor, nor go to church
on week days, and yet I think I am always
busy.'</p>
  <p>"'What <hi rend="i">do</hi> you do?' she had to ask.</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-242"
                    n="240"/>




   <p>"'Well, I make visits and receive them--'
 'Ah, but you have many friends, no doubt,'
 she smilingly interrupted--'and,' continued 
 I, 'I go out and buy things.'"</p>
   <p>"Did you tell her that you improved your
 mind?" asked Fanny; "because, if you did,
 she might have thought you were chaffing
 her."</p>
   <p>Amy gave her an indulgent smile as she
 continued: "We talked all that long, quiet
 afternoon of more subjects than I can recount. 
 We talked as women do who feel
 perfectly at ease and happy with each other;
 of large questions, and of trifles, and with
 every sentence I felt that this was the friend
 I had dreamed of--a woman who was utterly 
 congenial and yet inspiringly different.</p>
   <p>"The time came for me to go to the station. 
She put on her hat and walked with
me. I shall never forget how she looked in
the low afternoon sunlight.  Her flesh
seemed of half crystalline texture, like a
perfect fruit or flower. Other women give
you the impression of being clothes all the


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-243"
                    n="241"/>





way through, like a rag doll. Leonie moved
like a living, glowing statue draped in soft
fabrics that covered her, but were no more a
part of her than are the clouds part of the
moon that they veil. Once I slipped on
the board walk. She put her arm around
me for an instant. Her touch was magnetic
--life-giving.</p>
   <p>"The train came in; we stood in silence;
she held my hands tightly; she looked
straight into my eyes, and then we parted.
Oh, how <hi rend="i">sweet</hi> she was!"</p>
  <p>"What became of her?" asked Theodora,
biting off a thread.</p>
  <p>"That is not the way to put it," said
Fanny; "the question is, what happened
to her? Amy, I think it is something you
do not want to tell us. May we try to
guess?"</p>
  <p>"Yes."</p>
  <p>"Did she fall from a trapeze or anything
of that sort?"</p>
  <p>"Oh, no."</p>
  <p>"Before we begin guessing," said Theodora,
  


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-244"
                    n="242"/>





"I want to say that you probably got
an entirely wrong idea of your circus woman.
It was your own artlessness and delicacy
that brought her up into consideration, not
hers. You took for granted her possession
of qualities to which she had no claim, and
from your notion of her environment and
your thought of yourself or some other nice
person in such a place, you built up a false
conception of her character. You may as
well be sensible; a woman could not live
that life and be what you fancy her to be."</p>
  <p>Amy responded with more feeling than
her friends had ever seen her manifest. I
might have known you'd say that--it has
kept me silent all these months when I've
been thinking of her all the time. She was
the sweetest human being, and the purest--
not to be a child--that I have ever seen.
On the way to the station that day we
crossed a little stream. As I stood by her
side for a moment or two looking down into
the water, I had a sense of her spotless


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-245"
                    n="243"/>




sweetness that was like a rapture--it was
like what a mother may feel for a baby."</p>
   <p>She stopped abruptly. She was greatly
 embarrassed. Fanny began to talk quickly
 to relieve the tension of the moment.</p>
   <p>"I thought I should like to guess, but I
shall not try if what happened was one of
the things that in newspapers is headed
'Stranger Than Fiction.' I decline to let
my imagination wander in such inartistic
ways. I shall not lower myself by pursuing
anything less than the inevitable. Was the
end that?"</p>
   <p>"Yes, I suppose it was inevitable--but I
had not expected it."</p>
   <p>"They will retire from the circus business," 
said Theodora, "and go to live in
some little French town. Monsieur will
wax his mustache and walk out often with
Madame. They will have a little dog of
whom they will make a great pet."</p>
  <p>"Oh, how cheap! You think, I suppose,
that that sounds quite like Coppée and
Maupassant."</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-246"
                    n="244"/>





  <p>Amy had risen and was standing looking
out of the window. Fanny went to her
side. "Madame Mersac is dead, is she
not?" she asked, gently.</p>
   <p>"Yes, she is dead."</p>
   <p>"I fancy there is something about it that
pains you; I do not know what that is, of
course, still I am sorry. But, Amy, a woman 
like that must die or change. There
is no place for her."</p>
   <p>"I have said that to myself a hundred
times, but the loss is the same," responded
Amy.</p>
  <p>As the two stood by the window the winter 
sunset grew each moment more brilliant.
The snow-covered lawn shone with a pinkish 
glow, and on the white-capped stone
pillars of the gates gleamed a faint copper
luster. Nature was deep in winter.</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-247"
                    n="[245]"/>

</div2>

          



<div2 type="chapter"><head rend="center">THE BLUE BLAZERS</head>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-248" n="[246]"/>
                <pb id="VAB1822-249"
                    n="247"/>






<head rend="center">THE BLUE BLAZERS</head>


<p><hi rend="b">T</hi>HE  great Triennial Convention of
    United Women had lasted three days
and Mrs. Lodge and her friend, Fanny Wilson, 
admitted to each other that they were
beginning to be tired. It was their first experience 
at such a meeting, and when Mrs.
Lodge was chosen as a delegate by her own
club, she at first said she couldn't think of
going--it would just scare her to death. Of
course she was very much interested and all
that, and it was perfectly lovely to have the
ability and the courage to take part in such
things, but to go away off from home all by
herself, and to have to appear before those
awfully clever women! Oh, she just couldn't
--it wouldn't be fair to the club to have
such a delegate.</p>
  <p>But Sarah Lee Wills, Mrs. Lodge's dear
friend and the well-known speaker on the
                  


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-250"
                    n="248"/>




subject of Equal Suffrage, said to her that
it was most important that this Convention
should be marked by the presence of women
who were both earnest and conservative,
and Auntie Montgomery told her plainly that
it was her duty to go--to come out, as it
were, and take her stand for the right.
Auntie Montgomery was a blessed old woman 
who had been persecuted all her life
for temperance's sake, and Mrs. Lodge would
have wanted to please her even if the idea
of going to the Convention had been less
attractive to her than it was. Therefore she
decided to go in the company of these two
standard-bearers. But she invited Fanny
Wilson to go with her (Fanny was a clever
girl who was always ready for anything) so
that they two might keep together and not
be too much of a charge on Sarah Lee Wills
and Mrs. Montgomery.</p>
  <p>Mr. Lodge from the first approved of his
wife's going and he was pleased at her decision.
"You'll have a good time," he said,


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-251"
                    n="249"/>




"and when you tell me all about it I'll enjoy
it probably even more than you have done."</p>
  <p>She told him that he was sweet as he
always was--that if he were like some women's 
husbands she just didn't know what
she should do. He admitted the justice of
her opinion, but confessed to a lurking doubt
in the matter. It was about her, and it gave
him some uneasiness on this occasion. Was
she really an earnest woman? At times--
rarely, to be sure--he had feared that she
was at heart a butterfly.</p>
  <p>She responded with dignity that while she
did not claim to be a reformer, she greatly
admired a woman who was, and that if there
was anything which she had deeply at heart
it was the advancement of women, and
from that the elevation of humanity, and
he still smiled and said, "Oh, that's all
right."</p>
  <p>The meetings of the Convention were
more impressive than even the most sanguine 
had dared to hope for. The papers
were of the highest quality, the discussions


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-252"
                    n="250"/>





  following the papers were, so all agreed,
  simply inspiring. A session for the revision
  of the Constitution was so ably conducted
  that a newspaper that had headed the report 
  of a former meeting with the statement
  that "The Woman Who Deliberates is
  Lost " now apologized all of its own accord!
  And as the committee reports were received,
  and adopted, and amended, and reamended,
  -no one could help feeling that the occasion
  was epoch-making. But three meetings a
  day for three days had brought Mrs. Lodge
  to the end of her strength, and when
  Fanny Wilson declared that she was not
  going to the night session, she agreed to
  stay at home with her. Mrs. Lodge asked
Sthe older ladies if they also would not like
to rest that evening, but they were sustained
by inward grace, and the bare thought of
another meeting was a trumpet call to them.
Auntie Montgomery's face was as rosy as
ever under her white hair, as they joyously
started off, and Sarah Lee Wills held her
slim figure with the alertness of one who


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-253"
                    n="251"/>




may be called on at any moment to battle
for the truth.</p>
   <p>Nearly all of the United Women were
billeted out on resident club members, but
the distinguished speakers, Mrs. Montgomery
and Sarah Lee Wills, agreed with Mrs. Lodge
and Fanny in preferring to stay at a hotel.
The one which they chose, because some of
the meetings were to be held there, was an
immense be-mirrored place through the
doors of which conventions flowed all year
long. At this time it was so crowded that
the ladies could get only two rooms for the
four, and because one of the rooms was
much larger than the other the older ladies
took it with the understanding that Mrs.
Lodge and Fanny were to spend as much
time in it as they chose. It was to this
room that they turned after they had seen
their friends disappear down the hall.</p>
   <p>"And <hi rend="i">now</hi>, Margaret," said Fanny, throwing 
up her arms excitedly, "here's our
chance. Nobody knows when we'll ever


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-254"
                    n="252"/>



again be away from home all alone. Let's
do something interesting for once!"</p>
   <p>"Oh, if we just could! But what?"</p>
   <p>"We might go to a theater."</p>
   <p>"Not by ourselves."</p>
   <p>"We might send for a carriage and go
out for a drive."</p>
   <p>"My goodness, no!"</p>
   <p>"Let's go to a restaurant and have something 
to eat. I'm half starved."</p>
   <p>"Certainly not."</p>
   <p>Fanny sulked; then she broke out, "Well,
it's perfectly awful. What's the use of <hi rend="i">being</hi> 
emancipated if you can't do anything or
have any fun!"</p>
  <p>Sadly they looked out of the window.
They saw crowds on the sidewalks far below,
and carriages rolled by, no doubt carrying
beautiful ladies to balls and operas.</p>
   <p>"Here we are locked up like tenement
house babies!" wailed Fanny. "I wish we
had some candy, anyhow!"</p>
   <p>"There is one thing that Tom does sometimes."


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-255"
                    n="253"/>




said Mrs. Lodge. "We might ring
and order something to drink."</p>
   <p>"Oh, that's splendid!--something sort of
desperate and wicked!"</p>
   <p>A bell-boy clinked along the hall bearing
the presumably always desired ice water.
"I'll talk to him," said Mrs. Lodge, "and
maybe he'll think that Tom is here with me."
She stepped to the door; she was tall and
slim and elegant.</p>
   <p>"Please bring me from the bar a list of
the fancy and mixed drinks."   When the
boy stared and said, "Ma'am!" she repeated
the order. Looking back into the room she
added (so quickly is the sense of right and
wrong blunted by evil behavior), "That is
what you want, Thomas, is it not?"</p>
  <p>They feverishly studied the list he brought.
"'Manhattan Cocktail,' 'Martini Cocktail,'
'Vermouth Cocktail,'--Cocktails are not
nice, they have an awfully funny taste.
'Soul Reviver,'--that sounds nice. 'Mint
Julep,'--they're historic, you know."</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-256"
                    n="254"/>




   <p>"Well, what I want is something contemporaneous," 
said Fanny.</p>
   <p>"'Gin Sling,' 'Gin Fizz.' Once I tasted
something with gin in it; it was pretty good."</p>
  <p> "That settles it; we're not going to have
anything you ever had in the seclusion of
private life. Oh, <hi rend="i">here's</hi> the thing!" She
pointed rapturously to a line toward the end
of the list:</p>
   <p>"Blue Blazer, forty cents."</p>
   <p>"It ought to be good--it costs more than
some of the others," said Mrs. Lodge.</p>
   <p>"And it sounds so lovely and abandoned!"
cried Fanny.</p>
  <p>Fanny Wilson gave the order; she was
short and brisk, and got to the door before
Mrs. Lodge had started. "Two Blue Blazers, 
please!" Then they remembered that
the boy would know that Tom wasn't there,
and they giggled a great deal about it.</p>
  <p>On the tray that the boy brought were
four glasses. Two were filled with water,
the other two had in them some strange
mixture to which, in clumsy carrying out of


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-257"
                    n="255"/>




directions, he touched a lighted match.
The stuff flamed up and spilt over; into the
flames he threw a powder which flared up in
blue and lurid fires. The fumes rose and
spread heavily through the room. They
were almost sulphurous. The two women
left alone clutched their skirts to be ready to
jump. "What can we do with it," asked
Fanny; "we can't drink that ghastly stuff!"</p>
   <p>"Let's try to blow it out!"</p>
   <p>"Or ring the fire alarm!"</p>
   <p>They blew with all their, might; a newspaper 
or two caught fire, but they finally extinguished 
the flames. The odor, however,
was not extinguished. It curled itself round
and clung to the atmosphere. It was like
paregoric and alcohol-barrels and burnt
leather.</p>
  <p>Mrs. Lodge rushed across the room and
rang the bell. "It isn't paid for, and it's
nearly ten o'clock! Won't that boy ever
come?"</p>
  <p>Another boy--with ice water--answered
the bell. He was commanded, implored, to


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-258"
                    n="256"/>



find the first boy, to bring him instantly,
and to bring also the bill from the bar.
While they waited they discussed the question 
of getting rid of the stuff in the glasses.
It could not be allowed to stay in the room
--anybody would smell it. To pour it out
of the window was the thing. They hysterically 
watched the slim liquid trickle out
of the glasses and fall toward the glittering
street. Mrs. Lodge feared it might get into
someone's eyes, but Fanny, stretching herself
out over the sill, said, "No, but it may eat
a hole in the awning."</p>
  <p>They rang the bell frantically again and
again. The original boy came at length--
incidentally carrying ice water. He was
told to bring the bill-and to <hi rend="i">hurry!</hi></p>
  <p>Word came that the bill was not to be
had.  The drinks had been charged--
charged to the room--and the room was the
room of Sarah Lee Wills and Mrs. Eliza
P. Montgomery!</p>
   <p>"Go instantly," commanded Mrs. Lodge.
"Bring the barkeeper <hi rend="i">himself!</hi>"</p>
             


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-259"
                    n="257"/>




   <p>A young man appeared; two interested
 bell boys on their way with ice water stopped 
 to listen. He stared with an ugly grin
 on his coarse face. The two drinks were
 eighty cents, serving them in the room was
 twenty-five cents more. Would he take a
 dollar and five cents-no, a dollar and a
 half-and be <hi rend="i">sure</hi> the charge was taken off
 the bill? The bell boys had moved on; he
 looked about him and took the money.</p>
   <p>"Oh, why didn't we make him carry
away the glasses?" they exclaimed. Stories
heard long before of shoes changed in tavern
halls came to their minds. With the tray
in their hands they peeped up and down,
waiting till the hall should be clear so that
they could slip out and deposit their load at
the door of some innocent commercial traveler. 
Finally not a person was to be seen,
except indeed a man who lingered in the
diminishing distance, but he did not seem to
be looking at them, and anyhow he just
wouldn't go. They scurried fifty feet down
the hall, the man looking calmly on, put
     


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-260"
                    n="258"/>




down their glasses and ran back breathless
with excitement and laughing. Mrs. Lodge
said that it wasn't really wrong, you know,
and it was funny. Fanny thought that the
ways of vice were all right, but the drinks
were awful. "Oh, how I wish I had some
lemonade!" she sighed. A little later the
others came in and told them they had
missed <hi rend="i">such</hi> a treat.</p>
  <p>Mrs. Lodge and Fanny went home the
next morning, leaving the two leaders to
take part in inner councils and committee
meetings. Mrs. Lodge had recurring pangs
of anxiety. What if somehow or other it
should get out about the Blue Blazers? At
home she told the story at once to her husband, 
who tried to sympathize, and, she
thought, laughed more than there was any
call for. "Now," she said, "have I done
right? Should I have told Mrs. Wills and
Auntie Montgomery all about it?"</p>
  <p>"Oh, I guess not; you've paid for your
drinks; you've been honest.  You never


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-261"
                    n="259"/>




professed any rabid temperance principles
yourself."</p>
   <p>"But-suppose they should hear it talked
 about in the hotel? Of course we had a
 right to order what we chose, but maybe it
 was a little inconsiderate when we were in
 the same party."</p>
   <p>He tried not to smile. "Well, if they, as
 you say, hear it spoken of they can just say
 that they are not responsible for you." He
 went on: "Really I wouldn't distress myself 
 about it, and I'd never mention it again.
 It was an accident, your being in their room,
 and to try to explain will only make it
 worse."</p>
 <p>The morning that Sarah Lee Wills and
 Mrs. Montgomery were to leave the hotel
 Alice Van Blaricum came to see them off.
 She, as everybody knows, is a lawyer, and
 also the strongest of the Eastern workers
 in the temperance cause. Her majestic appearance 
 and fiery eloquence have turned
thousands from the path of error. She
perched on the bed and watched the others


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-262"
                    n="260"/>




pack, meanwhile talking with animation of
the work and its prospects.</p>
   <p>"Now," said Sarah Lee Wills, as she
locked her trunk, "I'll run down and pay
the bill, and then we'll have a few peaceful
minutes."</p>
  <p>She came back almost immediately. In
her hand was the bill; her face showed the
wildest agitation. " Come! Come!" she
cried to the others. "Something of the
greatest importance has happened!"</p>
  <p>She hurried them into the great marble-
floored rotunda, and up to a pale young
clerk.</p>
  <p>"<hi rend="i">Now</hi>," she said, "will you in the pres-
ence of these women say what is in that
bill?"</p>
  <p>"Certainly, ma'am," he replied, and in
a firm voice he read aloud these words:</p>
  <p>"Mrs. Sarah Lee Wills and Mrs. Montomery, 
for drinks sent from bar to room
105."</p>
  <p>Mrs. Montgomery stepped forward; her
sweet, round old face was flushed; her clear


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-263"
                    n="261"/>





voice penetrated to the far limits of the 
rotunda:</p>
   <p>"I call upon you to explain that bill!"</p>
   <p>The place was full of men. The River
 and Levees Commission was in session; the
 Cotton Planters' Association met that day.
 Other clerks left their books. "Ladies,"
 said the young man, nervously, "come into
 the private office. This is too public a place
 for a discussion."</p>
   <p>"Sir," said Sarah Lee Wills, "we will not
be hustled off into <hi rend="i">any</hi> private office! <hi rend="i">We</hi>
are not afraid of the public! We <hi rend="i">want</hi> the
public to hear our denial of your infamous
charge!"</p>
   <p>"All right," said the clerk, desperately;
 "have it your own way. Madam," turning
 to Mrs. Montgomery, "do you deny that
 you made this order?"</p>
 <p>Mrs. Montgomery's short plump figure expanded 
with emotion; her eyes flashed, she
waved her arm majestically for silence, and
addressed the crowd.</p>
   <p>"Gentlemen, for twenty-five years I was


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-264"
                    n="262"/>




an honored wife, for twenty-five years I have
been a widow. I have raised eleven children 
to worthy manhood and womanhood.
For a lifetime I have worked for and with
the outcast and lowly, but never until this
hour was such an insult put upon me! never
until now has my character been attacked!"</p>
  <p>The young man trembled, but was obstinate; 
a running bell-boy brought the proprietor. 
The crowd parted to let the great man
pass through. * What's this?" he said, and
then, to the clerk, "Sure this charge is
right?"</p>
   <p>"There isn't any doubt of it, sir. I can
prove it by half a dozen boys."</p>
  <p>Alice Van Blaricum now stepped forward.
"Here is my card! I undertake the charge
of this case. First, I wish to examine in
private the person who claims to have received 
this order."</p>
  <p>She came from the interview with rage
in her eye.  "It is a conspiracy; he describes 
you perfectly--one short and rosy,


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-265"
                    n="263"/>




one tall and thin with black eyes!" (which
indeed was perfectly true).</p>
   <p>"Bring that boy here!" called Sarah Lee
Wills. "'Let <hi rend="i">me</hi> talk to him!"</p>
   <p>"Now," she said, transfixing him with
stern outstretched finger, "<hi rend="i">Look me in the
face, and tell me if I gave you that order!</hi>"</p>
  <p>The boy's countenance changed as he
looked at her. "No'm," he whimpered, "I
guess not!"</p>
  <p>The bookkeeper addressed the proprietor,
"They ordered the stuff of this boy, and
tried to make him think it was for a man
inside. The watchman saw them for a half
hour trying to get rid of the glasses. The
chambermaid found the tray in front of a
linen-closet door. The barkeeper was taken
there by another boy, and they tried to get
him to accept the money and remove the
charge from the bill, but he refused."</p>
  <p>The proprietor looked at the excited women 
and at the irreverent crowd. "All
right, ladies," he said; "little dispute about


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-266"
                    n="264"/>





the bill. You needn't pay it." The three
all answered him at once:</p>
   <p>"What do we care for the money!"</p>
   <p>"We have been insulted, and you offer us
no apology!"</p>
   <p>"You need not think to get out of it that
way!"</p>
  <p>He ran his hand wildly through his hair,
"Ladies," he said, desperately, "we apologize
--we're sorry--we'll take the charge off
--we'll do <hi rend="i">anything!</hi>"</p>
  <p>A look of consultation passed between the
three. "We can do no more <hi rend="i">now</hi>," they
said.</p>
  <p>As they turned to go Alice Van Blaricum
addressed the audience, and particularly the
proprietor: "To be abused and slandered
is no new thing for those who oppose the
terrific power of the liquor interest, but this
attack surpasses in virulence and infamy
anything that has thus far been attempted.
But do not think that we do not know the
secret spring that controls your action. You,


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-267"
                    n="265"/>




sir, and your whole establishment are bought
and sold by the gold of the rumseller!"</p>
   <p>They went out and the proprietor passed:
on into his private office, making wearily a
significant motion to a bell-boy. As the
ladies parted at the station they said darkly
to each other that they were not done with
this yet; this was only the beginning, and
it would be in every newspaper in America
to-morrow morning.</p>
  <p>The next day Sarah Lee Wills telephoned
for Mrs. Lodge to come to her house. " Oh,
Tom," she said, "I <hi rend="i">can't!</hi> I just know!"</p>
   <p>"Nonsense," said he, " go on; remember
that in any case you will embarrass her more
than yourself if you go into explanations."</p>
  <p>Sarah Lee Wills met her with open arms.
"Oh, my <hi rend="i">dear!</hi>" she cried, "I am so glad
that you were here safe. You could not
have borne it, you've always been so sheltered 
from the knowledge of this evil world.
The awfulest thing happened--"</p>
  <p>Mrs. Lodge tottered to a chair. " First I
must tell <hi rend="i">you!</hi>" she said, but before she got


<pb
                    id="VAB1822-268"
                    n="266"/>




her thoughts together it was too late. Her
hesitation had bound her. She gasped out
miserable monosyllables as Sarah Lee's eloquent 
flood poured forth.</p>
   <p>"Oh I don't wonder that you are speechless 
with horror!" said she. "If it had been
<hi rend="i">anything</hi> else!--but can you imagine even
the vilest of women doing what they charged
us with-?-sending to a <hi rend="i">bar!</hi> and the degradation 
of sending for a thing with such a
name!--'Blue Devils.' "</p>
  <p>A little later she said, "The one thing
that hurt me most was that that poor little
bell-boy should be mixed up in such horrors,
and he had a <hi rend="i">good</hi> face!"  "So he had!"
moaned Mrs. Lodge.</p>
   <p>"And at the last, when it was over and
we were going, I turned back to take one
more look at those men. I <hi rend="i">saw</hi> that proprietor 
look at those clerks, and--oh, it was
too <hi rend="i">hideous</hi>--I saw him <hi rend="i">wink!</hi>"</p>


<p>THE END.</p>
</div2>
        </div1>
        </body>


          
















      <back><pb
        id="VAB1822-269" n="[267]"/><div1 type="colophon"><p rend="cemter">THIS BOOK HAS BEEN PRINTED<lb/>
DURING OCTOBER, 1897, BY THE<lb/>
BLAKELY PRINTING COMPANY.<lb/>
CHICAGO, FOR WAY &amp; WILLIAMS.</p></div1></back>
          
            </text>
            </TEI.2>