<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//IA Books//DTD TEI for Indiana Authors Books//EN"
                       "teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="VAB1847">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The seven joys of reading</title>
                <author>Plummer, Mary Wright, 1856-1916.</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded By</resp>
                    <!--Update the value of the element below with your name in
                                direct order.-->
                    <name>Jane Torres</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
                </address>
                <idno>VAB1847</idno>
                <availability status="unknown">
                    <p>Copyright 2009 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
                    <p>Indiana University provides the information contained on this web site for
                        non-commercial, personal, or research use only. All other use, including but
                        not limited to commercial or scholarly reproductions, redistribution,
                        publication or transmission, whether by electronic means or otherwise,
                        without prior written permission of the copyright holder is strictly
                        prohibited.</p>
                </availability>
                <!--Update the value of the date element with the year the document
                        is being encoded.-->
                <date>2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title type="main">The seven joys of reading</title>
                        <author id="ina-v1-entry-0684">Plummer, Mary Wright, 1856-1916.</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>20 p. ; 21 cm.</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>H.W. Wilson</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date>1915</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note>Reprinted from the Sewanee review, October 1910.</note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Digital Library Program was awarded a Library Services and Technology Act
                    (LSTA) grant in 2005 to make available online the three-volume, reference work,
                        <title>Indiana Authors and Their Books</title> along with selected
                    monographs by Indiana authors.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3">
                <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoded and edited using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines following the TEI Lite standard. Digital page images are
                    linked to the text file.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <tagUsage gi="div1">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language>English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Books and reading.</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <!--The revision description tracks significant changes made to the file
                    after completion. This information will remain commented out unless someone has
                    conducted quality assessment of the texts and have made changes to the file as a
                    result.-->
        <!-- <revisionDesc> <change>
                    <date>$Date</date> <respStmt>
                    <name>$Name</name>
                    <resp>$Responsibility</resp>
                    </respStmt> <item>$Changes</item>
                    </change> </revisionDesc> -->
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <front>
            <div1 type="halftitle">

                <pb id="VAB1847-001" n="[]"/>

                <head rend="center">The Seven Joys of Reading</head>

                <p rend="center">Mary Wright Plummer</p>

                <p> This booklet is sent with best wishes for the New Year and with the hope that
                    its reading will bring you pleasure. The H. W. Wilson Company</p>

                <p>Christmas, 1916 </p>
            </div1>

            <pb id="VAB1847-002" n="[]"/>
            <pb id="VAB1847-003" n="[1]"/>

            <titlePage>

                <docTitle rend="center">
                    <titlePart type="main">The Seven Joys of Reading</titlePart>
                </docTitle>

                <byline rend="center">
                    <docAuthor>Mary Wright Plummer</docAuthor>
                </byline>

                <docImprint rend="center">
                    <publisher>The H. W. Wilson Company</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>White Plains, New York</pubPlace>
                    <docDate>1916</docDate>
                </docImprint>
            </titlePage>

            <pb id="VAB1847-004" n="[2]"/>

            <div1 type="verso">
                <p rend="center">Reprinted from the Sewanee Review, October, 1910.</p>
            </div1>

        </front>

        <body>

            <div1 type="book">

                <pb id="VAB1847-005" n="3"/>

                <head rend="b center">The Seven Joys of Reading</head>


                <p><hi rend="b">W</hi>E must all have noticed a certain change of late in the
                    attitude of the librarian and the library assistant toward books. Whereas, the
                    time was when books were regarded as things to be entered, catalogued,
                    classified, shelflisted, and then given out in as great numbers as possible to a
                    more or less willing public, and the numbers reported with pride to the
                    professional journals, it seems now to have occurred to the majority, as it had
                    never failed to present itself to the minority, that books are also to be read,
                    that, in fact, that is what they are for.</p>
                <p>In the days when the slogan of the librarian was the glib cry, "The librarian who
                    reads is lost," and to stop classifying or cataloguing a book or even to want to
                    stop for a dip into its pages, was a positive crime, the librarians in this
                    country were being led astray by a misquotation, or rather a garbled quotation,
                    for Mark Pattison's words were these, in speaking of Casaubon, the great
                    classical scholar who was made librarian to Henry IV of France: "The use which
                    he made of the library was one which no librarian ought to make-it was to read
                    the books . . . he did nothing for arranging or cataloguing, hardly anything for
                    publishing new texts . . . he never made any thorough or complete investigation
                    of what was there-much less a catalogue. The librarian who reads is lost,"
                    which, as you see, is quite a different thing from the banner under which we
                    went marching so long.</p>



                <pb id="VAB1847-006" n="4"/>
                <p>There were many protestants in our procession, murmuring, from time to time:
                    "This isn't the main track," or crying, "We're lost, we're lost!" and pointing
                    in another direction, miles away where a much larger procession--that of the
                    public we had been serving--was going gaily along with flags and music and
                    banners and all the signs of enjoyment, every one with a book--and often two, as
                    many as we had been able to get him to carry, in fact.</p>
                <p>Not much attention was paid to these protests, however, until nearly all the
                    questions about cataloguing and classification and records and methods had been
                    settled or had almost settled those who discussed them, and in the lull many
                    voices were heard saying: "Well, what shall we do next with the books ?" Then
                    some long-suffering scholar-librarian with his pet edition of Horace or Virgil
                    in his pocket suggested grimly, "Suppose we read them." It was a brilliant idea
                    and the first manifestation of its popularity has come in the form of the book
                    symposium, a delightful occasion for every one who likes or prizes a book to
                    give his reasons or, if he pleases, just stand up and "enthuse" about it.
                    Everybody who is fond of a book is only too glad to listen, for some day his
                    turn will come and his pet book will have its innings. And what a jolly
                    procession the book symposium is making of us! "I'm so glad you talked about
                    these essays--I'm so fond of them," or, "I never read that biography you spoke
                    of but I'm going to get it the very first time it is in," etc., etc. Where
                    questions of cataloguing and accessioning led to puckered brows and worried
                    faces, a comparison of favorite authors seems to wake every one up and set every
                    one smiling. We are finding that many of us have always loved books, by stealth,
                    as it were, not wishing to be considered <hi rend="i">lost</hi> by Mark Pattison
                    or any of his misquoters. It is as if a new charter of liberties had been put
                    into our hands. We are free to read and read openly and need no longer pretend
                    that we read everything long <pb id="VAB1847-007" n="5"/> ago, before we became
                    librarians and found something more important to think of. And whereas it was
                    once the fashion to smile in a superior way over the young person who thought
                    herself qualified to enter a library school because she loved books and had read
                    a great many good ones, we are really beginning to admit that that is a
                    qualification, after all.</p>
                <p>One of the city libraries of New England for some years past has actually spent
                    money in printing in its bulletin the personal opinions of some of the staff
                    about the new books and new editions added, which shows, when you come to think
                    of it, that they must have read the books more or less. In a way, this could be
                    justified, even to those who think the reading of books too frivolous for a
                    serious librarian, for this acquaintance with the books enables the editor of
                    the bulletin to say such charming things about them as to make the <hi rend="i"
                        >public</hi> want to take them out--and that, of course, is justification
                    enough. A second library is following the bulletin-model of this one, and any
                    day we may see a third or a fourth, though good example is not so "catching" as
                    bad, it is said. Lately this same New England library has gone so far as to
                    publish a list of its modern poetry, and under the leading names to quote such
                    admirably chosen stanzas as to make of the list a fascinating little anthology
                    of the editor's special favorites, let us say.</p>
                <p>And so, although the new fashion is, as yet, on trial, I am emboldened to say a
                    word or two on what I shall call "The Seven Joys of Reading." Of course there
                    may be more--there may be seventy times seven--I could think of more myself,
                    probably--but I <hi rend="i">know</hi> there are seven. Some of these come when
                    we are children, long before we do much thinking about our reading and when it
                    is still a purely sensuous enjoyment, and the first is the <hi rend="i">joy of
                        familiarity</hi>. Who that has watched the story-telling of today, has not
                    seen the little bits of children smile all over <pb id="VAB1847-008" n="6"/>
                    their faces and begin to hug themselves, as the story teller began, "Once upon a
                    time there were a king and a queen." And so in <hi rend="i">reading</hi> the
                    story. You knew that story and you knew it was good, and as you went on and came
                    to this turn in the plot and that ever-to-be-remembered speech, you could have
                    squeezed the very type for pleasure. It was the joy of familiarity that made you
                    like to read about "Little Susy" in one after another of six small volumes and
                    about "Little Prudy" and then about all her family, one by one. You did not have
                    that chill in opening a new one of a series that you felt when you first opened
                    an entirely new book and had to move to a new town and meet a lot of strange
                    people. After you had read such a book, you came back to the old ones and felt.
                    warm and comfortable again, and screwed yourself all up into a knot in the
                    corner by the fire and read them all over for the fourth or fifth time.</p>
                <p>We are but children of a larger growth, and to this day there are some of us who
                    periodically take down "David Copperfield" or "The Mill on the Floss" or "Henry
                    Esmond" or "Emma" or "Barchester Towers," and refresh our memories of old
                    friends, yes, and of old foes; who at Christmas time think we must read the
                    "Christmas Carol" for old sake's sake, who turn away from the modern songster
                    chirping in every magazine and go back to "Thanatopsis" or "In Memoriam" or
                    "Snowbound"--to hear the familiar lines rolling in like waves, one after
                    another, in their well-known cadence. Of course, there are some books that are
                    "born old," such as "Joseph Vance," for instance. As we read that there came
                    gradually upon us such a haunting sense of familiarity that we were convinced it
                    had been known to us and loved by us in some previous state of existence--there
                    was none of the chill of the untried, the discomfort of adjustment to a new
                    writer, a new theme, a new way of seeing things.</p>



                <pb id="VAB1847-009" n="7"/>

                <p>The joy of familiarity comes not alone from novels and poems. You can turn at the
                    right moment--and there are mental as well as physical settings for such
                    enjoyments--to many an essay the pages of which show that that is where the book
                    has been opened most often. Don't say that you have not, more times than one, on
                    a cold winter Sunday when dinner is later than usual, used "The Dissertation on
                    Roast Pig" as an appetizer. Or that you have not found satisfaction for an
                    oft-recurring mood of wanting you know not what--in some perfect piece of
                    writing such as Pater's 'Child in the House." Or that, feeling limp and languid,
                    you have not, time and again, breathed in Emerson's "Self-reliance" like a
                    draught of salt sea air.</p>
                <p>One knows where to go for the remedies needed by one's constitution--one does not
                    try new prescriptions when the old ones have always answered; and in one's
                    mental and emotional medicine-chest, the old specifics hold their own, this for
                    homesickness, that when you need bracing, the other to make you gay, and the
                    fourth to give you a sense of comfort and cosiness and rest you for your next
                    sally into the cold world.</p>

                <p>The second joy is the <hi rend="i">joy of surprise</hi>. And this, too, belongs
                    in a measure to childhood when everything is new and the trick of weaving plots
                    is unsuspected. Do you remember when the wandering prince or princess, tired and
                    hungry and cold, lost in the dark wood at nightfall, appealed to you as in so
                    dreadful a case that you didn't see how it was ever to be mended? And
                    then--suddenly came the life-saving solution--"He saw a light !" Oh, that light
                    that twinkles in the pages of fairy tales! What a big sigh of relief it affords
                    one! How clever it was of the old storytellers to save it for the last
                    emergency! It meant shelter and warmth and food and probably friends--though we
                    did <pb id="VAB1847-010" n="8"/> find sometimes that even bands of robbers
                    flourished deceptive lights that lured to danger.</p>
                <p>The joy of surprise for us older ones lies not in new books, not in the
                    discoveries and inventions and new theories that fill the modern page, to all
                    these we are hardened, proof --nothing of that kind can surprise us; it lurks
                    instead in the old book. We pick up a volume and hear Pliny talking about
                    lecturers in old Rome:</p>
                <p>"We approach the hall," he says, "as if compelled by main force; many of us sit
                    outside the door and try to overcome the ennui by discussing the gossip of the
                    town. Messengers are surreptitiously sent in to inquire whether the lecturer has
                    really made his appearance, whether he has finished his prologue, or how many
                    sheets are still left to be read. Then, when we hear that the moment of deliver-
                    ance is not very far off, we come in slowly, sit on the edge of our chairs, and
                    do not even wait for the end of the discourse to slip, or steal quietly away."
                    The lecture-ridden reader of today at once feels a surprised kinship with the
                    old Roman that nothing can weaken.</p>
                <p>We take up "Job" and hear him say to his comforters, "Oh, yes, you know it all,
                    of course," only, as Job put it, it was "No doubt but ye are the people and
                    wisdom shall die with you." We find with Emerson's farmer that Plato has got
                    "some o' my idees." And in Chaucer we find literally a bit of modern slang,
                    "Come off," used in much the same sense, while Shakespeare says, "And my good
                    angel fire my bad one out."</p>
                <p>The surprise of finding human nature always human nature, ever since there is any
                    record of humanity, of finding that truths that we think modern have been
                    apprehended or glimpsed by the ancients, and sometimes grasped fully and
                    examined on all sides, of learning that love and friendship and compassion are
                    as old as the hills, is one of the rewards that await him who reads old books.
                    He feels that <pb id="VAB1847-011" n="9"/> he could take issue with Aeschylus,
                    split hairs with Plato, quarrel with Lord Bacon, be instructed by Leonardo, and
                    smoke with Raleigh, if only he had them here, with such common meeting-ground as
                    he has found in their written words. And his respect for Solomon grows apace,
                    who knew and said that there was nothing new under the sun.</p>
                <p>The social reformer in particular must have this joy of surprise when he looks
                    over an old book. From the days of the bricks without straw to Piers Ploughman
                    and the Cry of the Children, literature is full of the oppression and injustice
                    and unfairness that he is so prone to consider the especial sin of his own
                    generation. Whether the surprise one might experience on discovering that these
                    were all ages-old and world-wide could be called a joy, is perhaps doubtful, but
                    it makes one feel a little less guilty personally.</p>
                <p>When the epidemic of influenza first reached this country and was characterized
                    as a mysterious new malady, I came across a description of it in a letter of
                    Campbell the poet, written in 1803, with a surprise that was relief, if not
                    exactly joy. It <hi rend="i">had</hi> happened before, then, and people were not
                    frightened to death and the world had survived, after all!</p>
                <p>A few years ago a strange figure appeared in my office, a little man, a
                    foreigner, of Hebrew race, I judged, who offered for sale very simply a volume
                    of philosophy of his own writing, printed by some third-rate printer, cheaply
                    bound and in no way attractive. The author told me he was a cobbler, if I
                    remember aright, but he had thought out this book and by great economy had
                    managed to get it printed. Ordinarily a librarian makes short shrift of book
                    peddlers; but there was something in this case that made me buy the book without
                    any reference to its merits--something in the man himself that forbade me to
                    disappoint him. I watched for notices of it, not being myself a judge of
                    philosophical writings. A long review of it appeared after a time. Imagine the
                    astonishment, astonishment that must <pb id="VAB1847-012" n="10"/> have been a
                    joy, of the reviewer when he found as he read that this uneducated cobbler who
                    had never read and probably never heard of Spinoza, had worked out a similar
                    philosophy, was as original a thinker, in fact, as Spinoza! Had he been first,
                    he would have been as famous.</p>
                <p>This very rare surprise of finding something unusual where one expects the
                    average and the ordinary, belongs to new books with reputations as yet unmade,
                    and the joy of surprise is mingled with the joy of discovery, and the joy of
                    proprietorship that comes by right of discovery. There is nothing at such times
                    that one wants to do so much as to get upon a fence or a stone and crow!</p>

                <p>The third joy is that of <hi rend="i">sympathy</hi>. There are all kinds of
                    sympathy, including that of a perfectly good tooth with one that aches. It is
                    not only of this kind that one feels like using Mark Twain's anathema, "Darn
                    such sympathy !" For there is the author who won't let us off without a few
                    pages of pathos, who deliberately works us up to the weeping-point (we can see
                    the memorandum in his notebook, "Make 'em cry in this chapter"), and who makes
                    it absolutely impossible to the tender-hearted to read certain passages aloud.
                    One dislikes very much to sit in a subway train and sob, or to have one's voice
                    give way when one is reading aloud to one's family, yet these are the
                    humiliations that this kind of sympathy puts upon one. In childhood, it was a
                    different thing. Then we loved to cry and deliberately read over again the
                    chapter that excited our lachrymal glands. We are not so easily worked upon now
                    as in the days of Little Eva and Beth March and Louie's Last Term at St. Mary's;
                    though some of our childhood's favorites have the power of wringing a few tears
                    from us still if they catch us in an impressionable moment. But we no longer
                    find this kind of sympathy a joy.</p>

                <pb id="VAB1847-013" n="11"/>

                <p>The power of fiction is perhaps at no time better demonstrated than when we take
                    sides with the character against the author, accusing him of cruelty,
                    unfairness, and lack of sympathy with one or another of his creations. Some one
                    complained to George Eliot that she had been cruel to poor Hetty in "Adam Bede."
                    "If I had not made her pitiful, you could not have pitied her," was the reply.
                    Many times as I have read "Martin Chuzzlewit," I find myself still scanning
                    every line referring to the detestable Jonas for some redeeming trait, hoping
                    against hope that he may prove less black this time than previous readings have
                    shown him to be. The feeling is akin to that I had as a child in rereading a
                    book with a tragic ending, that perhaps <hi rend="i">now</hi> it would turn out
                    differently. However, neither is this the kind of sympathy that is a joy--it is
                    indeed rather an anxiety. The joy lies in finding in a writer one who would
                    evidently be congenial to us if we knew him, who sees with us, who does not rub
                    us the wrong way, who does not explode fireworks at our ear nor lay traps for
                    our feet, but goes along at the pace we like best, turning aside just where we
                    would turn aside if left to ourselves, and coming neck and neck with us to a
                    common conclusion. This sympathy goes out chiefly to the essayists, though
                    occasionally a biography or an autobiography is so happily written that one
                    feels one has met a real personality and found a friend. Dr. Johnson and Charles
                    Lamb are the two examples that come at once to one's mind as authors arousing
                    this peculiar personal sympathy, and every librarian must have the same feeling
                    on reading Prothero's "Life of Henry Bradshaw."</p>
                <p>It is literally true that there is companionship in books when one finds the
                    author who is <hi rend="i">simpatico</hi>, as the Italians say. And I can
                    imagine a deaf person or one cut off in some other way from congenial human
                    society actually finding <pb id="VAB1847-014" n="12"/> his friends between the
                    pages of his books. Even in life the best friendships are based not so much on
                    propinquity and contact as on the touching of minds and spirits, and this is
                    almost completely obtainable in a book. Not quite, because there can be no
                    dialogue, one must be simply a listener, so that talk really is best; but
                    failing the ability to talk together because of a few thousand miles of distance
                    or a few hundred years of time, the next best thing is to have a friend to whom
                    one can listen and whose spiritual portrait, at least, one can discern.</p>

                <p>The fourth joy is the <hi rend="i">joy of appreciation</hi>, one that belongs to
                    our maturer years, and concerns itself chiefly with the way of saying things.
                    There are refrains that seize us powerfully with some haunting quality and sing
                    themselves in our ears all day, quick turns of speech that bring a responsive
                    smile, the use of an old word in a new and exactly fitting sense that gives an
                    unaccountable thrill of pleasure, a dainty exactness of definition or
                    description that is wholly satisfying, word-pictures that have all the color and
                    vividness of those on canvas, and we linger over the lines, tasting and
                    retasting, and wondering why we cannot say things so since we so enjoy them when
                    others say them. The subtly funny things that you do not see until you have
                    passed them (like violet-hunting in the spring, some one says), and that keep
                    you smiling and turning back and that you <hi rend="i">must</hi> read aloud to
                    some one, the pathetic aspect of things shown by a mere word or two, that
                    catches you unaware and makes a clutch at your throat, the world-old truth that
                    strikes you anew because of its perfect and vital expression--it is chiefly when
                    one reads for this joy and finds it that one realizes the time wasted on
                    commonplace stuff. It has become the fashion in some quarters to decry Stevenson
                    and Pater as affected and far-fetched and unreal, and there may be reason for
                    the charge, but on the whole <pb id="VAB1847-015" n="13"/> they do a good work
                    for us in reminding us that there is magic in the <hi rend="i">how</hi> things
                    are said. What if Stevenson did consciously write one page in the style of the
                    eighteenth century and another in that of the time of James I, and write in
                    Lamb's manner as well as Lamb himself! In so doing he preached the importance of
                    skill and deftness in handling one's tools, a doctrine somewhat needed in a gen-
                    eration whose vocabulary and construction grow more and more careless and show
                    less and less pains.</p>

                <p>The fifth joy is that of <hi rend="i">expansion</hi>. To be caught out of our
                    daily rut and be taken up where we get the birdseye view, to see the kingdoms of
                    the earth and their relation to us, to make friends in every land, of every
                    tongue, and of every age, to escape from the steam-heated air of conventional
                    respectability and soar among the great realities, to see as by sudden intuition
                    the true proportions of things and never to quite forget the lesson afterward,
                    even to wallow for a bit with primitive beasts in their mire, just as an
                    experience and to help one understand--these things make one rise from a book a
                    changed being, with wider horizons, broader sympathies, deeper comprehension,
                    and no less firm a grip on the essentials because the non-essentials have been
                    classified as such at last.</p>
                <p>The epoch-making books in science, the philosophy of history, great tragedies
                    greatly written, novels that are faithful portrayals of other lands and other
                    ideals--all of these open doors to a wider and sometimes a higher world.</p>
                <p>The people who like only one kind of book, and won't even try any other kind, who
                    read only to confirm their own opinions and prejudices, forever miss this
                    exhilarating joy. Exploring, even in imagination, with one's feet on the
                    hearthstone and a fair certainty that eventually one's mind also will come home,
                    has its adventures and even its dangers, and one is bigger and better for having
                    passed through <pb id="VAB1847-016" n="14"/> them. As I read of the courage and
                    perseverance and pluck of Isabella Bird, of Mrs. Rowan, the flower-hunter, of
                    Mary Kingsley, and other women-travelers and explorers, I find out what is
                    wanting in my own make-up and have a better idea of comparative values, and
                    though <hi rend="i">that</hi> may not be a joy the admiration of my betters is
                    decidedly one. As one reads "Julius Caesar," and "King Lear" and "Hamlet," one
                    has the joy of knowing that if one has not the mind of Shakespeare, at least one
                    has enough to follow its thoughts and appreciate the wonder of it--and that is
                    something, as Hans Andersen says.</p>
                <p>But I must get on with my joys or they will be turned into mourning.</p>

                <p>The sixth joy is the opposite of the joy of sympathy, for it is the <hi rend="i"
                        >joy of shock</hi>. To most of us it is an acquired taste --and it takes
                    time to make shock into a joy, just as it does to make oneself willing to take
                    hold of the handles of an electric battery after one experience. The paradoxical
                    people that give shocks are likely to get on our nerves, and if we aren't of the
                    minority who love we are of the majority who hate, for there is no half-way
                    attitude for most of us toward these electric authors. We either take them very
                    seriously or we turn up our noses at them as charlatans. They are not
                    charlatans, but perhaps we may call them jugglers--they twist and turn the truth
                    so that it has faces we never saw before, and either we think we have never seen
                    truth at all until now or because of its newness we refuse to recognize this one
                    aspect of it. Their work is purely intellectual, so there is really nothing to
                    get mad about any more than there is about the juggler's trick that we can't see
                    through. They have done something we couldn't do, they have shown us something,
                    or pretended to show us something, we never saw before, and the thing for us to
                    do is to take it for what it is worth as an exhibition and rejoice <pb
                        id="VAB1847-017" n="15"/> in the cleverness of it. And if we do make a joy
                    of the shock we get, our mental circulation is quickened and we feel so
                    wideawake that the first thing we know we are incurring again the risk of
                    contact with the battery. These writers are particularly good for the people who
                    constitutionally dislike them--by the time one has reached the point of finding
                    joy in repeated shocks, the cure is pretty well effected and one needs them no
                    longer--one is now thoroughly stirred up, with the blood circulating to every
                    finger-end and one can do some tricks oneself.</p>
                <p>The serious shocker who speaks his mind, like Ibsen, gets a readier hearing
                    because people believe he is in earnest--they are not afraid that if they agree
                    with him he will suddenly say, "over the left" and deny all he has just been
                    converting them to. Besides, he can generally produce a lot of evidence and
                    doesn't ask you to take a new truth or a new view of truth on his unsupported
                    word. The paradox maker is an irritant, and the serious shocker is a stimulant,
                    and they are both good for a sluggish circulation. To people who are already
                    sufficiently excitable they are an intoxicant, and we have all seen people who
                    have imbibed Bernard Shaw almost to the verge of <hi rend="i">d. t.</hi> Time
                    was when I would no more have taken a shock voluntarily than I would have walked
                    up to a strange cow; but one or two experiences of the gasp and the tingling
                    sensation proved that it "didn't hurt," as the children say, and so I have come
                    to put the shock among the joys of reading--a fearful joy, to be sure, but none
                    the less a joy.</p>

                <p>The last of the seven is the <hi rend="i">joy of revelation</hi>. Of course, this
                    does not belong to reading alone. Music, pictures, sculpture, architecture,
                    drama--all contain the possibilities of revelation. Perhaps science in these
                    days may be counted the great revealer. Between the sober, well-supported
                    pillars that have become its foundation, one catches glimpses of <pb
                        id="VAB1847-018" n="16"/> visions, of dazzling hypotheses, of broken arcs of
                    the perfect circle of law, and one hears strains of music that seem to belong to
                    other strains heard before and to indicate a great harmony somewhere if our ears
                    were only attuned to hear it. Through some sentence of apparently secondary im-
                    portance, we catch sight of possibilities so great, so revolutionary, that we
                    are a trifle dizzy--in fact, it is only in snatches that we can bear such
                    revelations, and they are gone before we can register them or know truly just
                    what we have seen. But we realize that for one fleeting instant, we have been
                    rapt out of the body, that we have seen with something other than the bodily eye
                    or the eye of the mind, that the little intuitions we experience occasionally
                    are to these great revelations as <hi rend="i">twice two is four is to the
                        calculus</hi>. Whether the writer knew when he penned his sentence that it
                    would be an <hi rend="i">open sesame</hi> to those who read, is doubtful. Is it
                    not Emerson who says that there is inspired reading as well as inspired writing?
                    One reads the same words at another time and they produce no vision; one tries
                    to analyze them to see where--through what opening--one had one's glimpse, and
                    they are solidly welded together; but no number of failures and disappointments
                    can ever convince one that there was no revelation--the experience was too keen
                    and the effect too overwhelming to be either denied or forgotten. As a rule, we
                    look for revelation of this kind, if anywhere, in religious books, but we find
                    it, or rather it finds us, for we seem to have nothing to do with it, through
                    the pages of almost any book written in seriousness. Great as is the joy when it
                    arrives, it is so rare that I almost feel I am wrong in placing among the joys
                    of reading one that <hi rend="i">may</hi> come but once in a lifetime.</p>


            </div1>
        </body>

    </text>
</TEI.2>
