<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//IA Books//DTD TEI for Indiana Authors Books//EN"
                       "teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="VAB1852">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Asa Holmes</title>
				<title type="subtitle">or, At the cross-roads</title>
				<author>Johnston, Annie F. (Annie Fellows), 1863-1931.</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded By</resp>
					<!--Update the value of the element below with your name in
                                                                                                                        direct order.-->
					<name>Janice Lorenz</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
				<address>
                                                                                                    <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
                                                                                                    <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
                                                                                </address>
				<idno>VAB1852</idno>
				<availability status="unknown">
					<p>Copyright 2009 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
					<p>Indiana University provides the information contained on this web site for
						non-commercial, personal, or research use only. All other use, including but not limited
						to commercial or scholarly reproductions, redistribution, publication or transmission,
						whether by electronic means or otherwise, without prior written permission of the
						copyright holder is strictly prohibited.</p>
				</availability>
				<!--Update the value of the date element with the year the document
                                                                                                    is being encoded.-->
				<date>2009</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblFull>
					<titleStmt>
						<title type="main">Asa Holmes</title>
						<title type="subtitle">or, At the cross-roads</title>
						<author id="ina-v1-entry-0462">Johnston, Annie F. (Annie Fellows), 1863-1931.</author>
					</titleStmt>
					<extent>215 p. illus. 19 cm.</extent>
					<publicationStmt>
						<publisher>L. C. Page</publisher>
						<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
						<date>1902</date>
					</publicationStmt>
				</biblFull>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>The Digital Library Program was awarded a Library Services and Technology Act (LSTA)
					grant in 2005 to make available online the three-volume, reference work, <title>Indiana
						Authors and Their Books</title> along with selected monographs by Indiana authors.</p>
			</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl n="3">
				<p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and has
					been encoded and edited using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
					Guidelines following the TEI Lite standard. Digital page images are linked to the text
					file.</p>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<tagUsage gi="div1">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy id="lcsh">
					<bibl>
						<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language>English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<!--The revision description tracks significant changes made to the file
                                                            after completion. This information will remain commented out unless someone has
                                                            conducted quality assessment of the texts and have made changes to the file as a
                                                            result.-->
		<!-- <revisionDesc> <change>
                                                            <date>$Date</date> <respStmt>
                                                            <name>$Name</name>
                                                            <resp>$Responsibility</resp>
                                                            </respStmt> <item>$Changes</item>
                                                            </change> </revisionDesc> -->
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>

			<pb id="VAB1852-001" n="[1]"/>



			<div1 type="halftitle">
				<head rend="center">Asa Holmes<lb/> or<lb/> At the Cross-roads</head>
				<p/>
			</div1>

			<pb id="VAB1852-002" n="[2]"/>




			<div1 type="advertisement">

				<head rend="center">Works of<lb/> Annie Fellows Johnston</head>
				<list type="simple">
					<head rend="center">THE LITTLE COLONEL SERIES</head>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">The Little Colonel</hi>
						<hi rend="right">$ .50</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">The Giant Scissors</hi>
						<hi rend="right">.50</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">Two Little Knights of Kentucky</hi>
						<hi rend="right">.50</hi>
					</item>
					<item>(The three stories above are also published in one volume, entitled The Little
						Colonel Stories, $1.50.) </item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">The Little Colonel's House Party</hi>
						<hi rend="right">1.00</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">The Little Colonel's Holidays</hi>
						<hi rend="right">1.50</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">The Little Colonel's Hero</hi>
						<hi rend="right"><hi rend="i">net,</hi>1.20</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">The Little Colonel at Boarding-School</hi>
						<hi rend="right"><hi rend="i">net,</hi>1.20</hi>
					</item>
				</list>
				<list type="simple">
					<head rend="center">OTHER BOOKS</head>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">Big Brother</hi>
						<hi rend="right">.50</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">Ole Mammy's Torment</hi>
						<hi rend="right">.50</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">The Story of Dago</hi>
						<hi rend="right">.50</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">Cicely</hi>
						<hi rend="center"><hi rend="i">net,</hi> .40</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">Aunt 'Liza's Hero</hi>
						<hi rend="left"><hi rend="i">net,</hi> .40</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">Asa Holmes</hi>
						<hi rend="right">1.00</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">Flip's "Islands of Providence"</hi>
						<hi rend="right">1.00</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">Songs Ysame</hi>
						<hi rend="right">1.00</hi>
					</item>
				</list>

				<p rend="center">L. C. PAGE AND COMPANY<lb/> 200 Summer Street, Boston, Mass.</p>
			</div1>


			<pb id="VAB1852-003" n="[3]"/>

			<pb id="VAB1852-004" n="[4]"/>

			<div1 type="frontispiece">
				<head type="supplied">Frontispiece</head>
				<p>
					<figure>
						<p rend="center"> ASA HOLMES</p>
					</figure>
				</p>
			</div1>



			<pb id="VAB1852-005" n="[5]"/>

			<titlePage>
				<docTitle rend="center">
					<titlePart type="main">Asa Holmes</titlePart>
					<lb/>
					<titlePart type="subtitle">or<lb/> At the cross-roads</titlePart>
				</docTitle>

				<byline rend="center">By<lb/>
					<docAuthor>Annie Fellows Johnston</docAuthor><lb/> Author of "The Little Colonel," "Two
					Little Knights of Kentucky," etc.</byline>

				<byline rend="center">With a frontispiece by Ernest Fosberg</byline>

				<docImprint rend="center">
					<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
					<lb/>
					<publisher>L. C. Page &amp; Company</publisher>
					<lb/>
					<docDate>Mdccccii</docDate>
				</docImprint>
			</titlePage>





			<pb id="VAB1852-006" n="[6]"/>




			<div1 type="verso">
<head type="supplied">Verso</head>





				<p rend="center i">Copyright, 1900, 1901</p>
				<p rend="center">BY E. S. BARNETT</p>

				<p rend="center i">Copyright, 1902</p>
				<p rend="center">By L. C. PAGE AND COMPANY</p>
				<p rend="center sc">(INCORPORATED)</p>

				<p rend="center i">All rights reserved</p>










				<p rend="center b">Colonial Press</p>
				<p rend="center">Electrotyped and Printed by C. H. Simonds &amp; Co.</p>
				<p rend="center">Boston, Mass., U. S. A.</p>

			</div1>



			<pb id="VAB1852-007" n="[7]"/>









			<div1 type="dedication">
				<head type="supplied">Dedication</head>
				<p rend="center b">TO<lb/> A Dear Old Philosopher</p>
				<p rend="center sc">WHOSE CHEERFUL OPTIMISM AND SUNNY FAITH HAVE<lb/> SWEETENED LIFE FOR ALL
					WHO KNOW HIM</p>

			</div1>




			<pb id="VAB1852-008" n="[8]"/>
		</front>

		<body>

			<pb id="VAB1852-009" n="9"/>


			<div1 type="book">
				<head type="supplied">Asa Holmes, or, At the cross-roads</head>
				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">Chapter I</head>

					<p><hi rend="b">T</hi>HERE is no place where men learn each other's little peculiarities
						more thoroughly than in the group usually to be found around the stove in a country
						store. Such acquaintance may be of slow growth, like the oak's, but it is just as sure.
						Each year is bound to add another ring to one's knowledge of his neighbours if he
						lounges with them, as man and boy, through the Saturday afternoons of a score of
						winters.</p>
					<p>A boy learns more there than he can be taught in schools. It may be he is only a
						tow-headed, freckle-faced little fellow of eight when he rides <pb id="VAB1852-010"
							n="10"/> over to the cross-roads store for the first time by himself. Too timid to
						push into the circle around the fire, he stands shivering on the outskirts, looking
						about him with the alertness of a scared rabbit, until the storekeeper fills his
						kerosene can and thrusts the weekly mail into his red mittens. Then some man covers him
						with confusion by informing the crowd that "that little chap is Perkins's oldest," and
						he scurries away out of the embarrassing focus of the public eye.</p>
					<p>But the next time he is sent on the family errands he stays longer and carries away
						more. Perched on the counter, with his heels dangling over a nail keg, while he waits
						for the belated mail train, he hears for the first time how the government ought to be
						run, why it is that the country is going to the dogs, and what will make <pb
							id="VAB1852-011" n="11"/> hens lay in cold weather. Added to this general information,
						he slowly gathers the belief that these men know everything in the world worth knowing,
						and that their decisions on any subject settle the matter for all time.</p>
					<p>He may have cause to change his opinion later on, when his sapling acquaintance has
						gained larger girth; when he has loafed with them, smoked with them, swapped lies and
						spun yarns, argued through a decade of stormy election times, and talked threadbare
						every subject under the sun. But now, in his callow judgment, he is listening to the wit
						and wisdom of the nation. Now, as he looks around the overflowing room, where butter
						firkins crowd the calicoes and crockery, and where hams and saddles swing sociably from
						the same rafter, as far as <pb id="VAB1852-012" n="12"/> his knowledge goes, this is the
						only store in the universe.</p>
					<p>Some wonder rises in his childish brain as he counts the boxes of axle-grease and the
						rows of shining new pitchforks, as to where all the people live who are to use so many
						things. He has yet to learn that this one little store that is such a marvel to him is
						only a drop in the bucket, and that he may travel the width of the continent, meeting at
						nearly every mile-post that familiar mixture of odours --coal oil, mackerel, roasted
						coffee, and pickle brine. And a familiar group of men, discussing the same old subjects
						in the same old way, will greet him at every such booth he passes on his pilgrimage
						through Vanity Fair.</p>
					<p>Probably in after years Perkins's oldest will never realise how much of his early
						education has been acquired <pb id="VAB1852-013" n="13"/> at that Saturday afternoon
						loafing-place, but he will often find himself looking at things with the same squint
						with which he learned to view them through 'Squire Dobbs's short-sighted spectacles.
						Many a time he will find that he has been unconsciously warped by the prejudices he
						heard expressed there, and that his opinions of life in general and men in particular
						are the outgrowth of those early conversations which gave him the creed of his
						boyhood.</p>
					<p>"Them blamed Yankees!" exclaims one of these neighbourhood orators, tilting his chair
						back against the counter, and taking a vicious bite at his plug of tobacco. "They don't
						know no better than to eat cold bread the year 'round!" And the boy, accepting the
						statement unquestioningly, stores away in his memory not only <pb id="VAB1852-014"
							n="14"/> the remark, but all the weighty emphasis of disgust which accompanied the
						remark in the spitting of a mouthful of tobacco juice. Henceforth his idea of the menu
						north of the Mason and Dixon line is that it resembles the bill of fare of a
						penitentiary, and he feels that there is something cold-blooded and peculiar about a
						people not brought up on a piping hot diet of hoe-cake and beaten biscuit.</p>
					<p>In the same way the lad whose opinions are being moulded in some little corner grocery
						of a New England village, or out where the roads cross on the Western prairie, receives
						his prejudices. It may be years before he finds out for himself that the land of Boone
						is not fenced with whiskey jugs and feuds, and that the cap-sheaf on every shock of
						wheat in its domain is not a Winchester rifle.</p>



					<pb id="VAB1852-015" n="15"/>


					<p>But these prejudices, popular at local cross-roads, are only the side lines of which
						every section carries its own specialty. When it comes to staple articles, dear to the
						American heart and essential to its liberty and progress, their standard of value is the
						same the country over.</p>
					<p>One useful lesson the youthful lounger may learn here, if he can learn it anywhere, and
						that is to be a shrewd reader of men and motives. Since staple characteristics in human
						nature are repeated everywhere, like staple dry goods and groceries, a thorough
						knowledge of the group around the stove will be a useful guide to Perkins's oldest in
						forming acquaintances later in life.</p>
					<p>Long after he has left the little hamlet and grown gray with the experiences of the
						metropolis, he will <pb id="VAB1852-016" n="16"/> run across some queer Dick whose
						familiar personality puzzles him. As he muses over his evening pipe, suddenly out of the
						smoke wreaths will spring the face of some old codger who aired his wisdom in the
						village store, and he will recognise the likeness between the two as quickly as he would
						between two cans of leaf lard bearing the same brand.</p>
					<p>But Perkins's oldest is only in the primer of his cross-roads curriculum now, and these
						are some of the lessons he is learning as he edges up to the group around the fire. On
						the day before Thanksgiving, for instance, he was curled up on a box of soap behind the
						chair of old Asa Holmes --Miller Holmes everybody calls him, because for nearly half a
						century his water-mill ground out the grist of all that section of country. He is
						retired now; gave <pb id="VAB1852-017" n="17"/> up his business to his grandsons. They
						carry it on in another place with steam and modern machinery, and he is laid on the
						shelf. But he isn't a back number, even if his old deserted mill is. It is his boast
						that now he has nothing else to do, he not only keeps up with the times, but ahead of
						them.</p>
					<p>Everybody goes to him for advice; everybody looks up to him as they do to a hardy old
						forest tree that's lived through all sorts of hurricanes, but has stood to the last,
						sturdy of limb, and sound to the core. He is as sweet and mellow as a winter apple,
						ripened in the sun, and that's why everybody likes to have him around. You don't see
						many old men like that. Their troubles sour them.</p>
					<p>Well, this day before Thanksgiving the old miller was in his usual place at the store,
						and as usual it was he who <pb id="VAB1852-018" n="18"/> was giving the cheerful turn to
						the conversation. Some of the men were feeling sore over the recent election; some had
						not prospered as they had hoped with their crops, and were experiencing the pinch of
						hard times and sickness in their homes. Still there was a holiday feeling in the
						atmosphere. Frequent calls for nutmeg, and sage, and cinnamon, left the air spicy with
						prophecies of the morrow's dinner.</p>
					<p>The farmers had settled down for a friendly talk, with the comfortable sense that the
						crops were harvested, the wood piled away for the winter, and a snug, warm shelter
						provided for the cattle. It was good to see the hard lines relax in the weather-beaten
						faces, in the warmth of that genial comradeship. Even the gruffest were beginning to
						thaw a little, when the door opened, 18 <pb id="VAB1852-019" n="19"/> and Bud Hines
						slouched in. The spirits of the crowd went down ten degrees.</p>
					<p>Not that he said anything; only gave a gloomy nod by way of greeting as he dropped into
						a chair. But his whole appearance said it for him; spoke in the droop of his shoulders,
						and the droop of his hat brim, and the droop of his mouth at the corners. He looked as
						if he might have sat for the picture of the man in the "Biglow Papers," when he said:
						
						<q rend="blockquote">
							<lg>
								<l>"Sometimes my innard vane pints east for weeks together,</l>
								<l>My natur' gits all goose-flesh, an' my sins</l>
								<l>Come drizzlin' on my conscience sharp ez pins."</l>
							</lg>
						</q></p>

					<p>The miller greeted him with the twinkle in his eye that eighty years and more have
						never been able to dim; and Perkins's oldest had his first meeting with the man who
						always finds a <pb id="VAB1852-020" n="20"/> screw loose in everything. Nothing was
						right with Bud Hines. One of his horses had gone lame, and his best heifer had
						foundered, and there was rust in his wheat. He didn't have any heart to keep
						Thanksgiving, and he didn't see how anybody else could, with the bottom dropped clean
						out of the markets and the new road tax so high. For his part he thought that everything
						was on its last legs, and it wouldn't be long till all the Powers were at war, and
						prices would go up till a poor man simply couldn't live.</p>
					<p>It was impossible not to be affected more or less by his gloomy forebodings, and the
						old miller, looking around on the listening faces, saw them settling back in their old
						discouraged lines. Clasping his hands more firmly over the top of his cane, he
						exclaimed: "Now look here, Bud Hines, I'm <pb id="VAB1852-021" n="21"/> going to give
						you a proverb that was made on purpose for such a poor, weak-kneed Mr. Ready-to-halt as
						you are: 'Never be discouraged, and never be a discourager!' If you can't live up to the
						first part, you certainly can to the second. No matter how hard things go with you,
						you've no right to run around throwing cold water on other people. What if your horse
						has gone lame? You've got a span of mules that can outpull my yoke of oxen any day. One
						heifer oughtn't to send a man into mourning the rest of his days, and it would be more
						fitting to be thankful over your good tobacco crop than to groan over the failure of
						your wheat. More fitting to the season. As for the rest of the things you're worrying
						over, why, man, they haven't happened yet, and maybe never will. My old grandad used to
						say to <pb id="VAB1852-022" n="22"/> me when I was a lad, 'Never cross your bridge till
						you come to it, Asa,' and I've proved the wisdom of that saying many a time. Suppose'n
						you put that in your pipe and smoke it."</p>
					<p>If Perkins's oldest learns no other lesson this year than to put those two proverbs
						into practice, he will have had a valuable education. How many Thanksgivings they will
						help to make for him! How many problems and perplexities they will solve!</p>
					<p>"Never be discouraged; never be a discourager! Don't cross your bridge until you come
						to it!" It is a philosophy that will do away with half the ills which flesh imagines it
						is heir to.</p>
					<p>Thanksgiving Day! How much more it means to the old miller than to the little fellow
						beside him on the soap box! To the child it is only a feast day; to the old man it is a
						festival <pb id="VAB1852-023" n="23"/> that links him to a lifetime of sacred
						memories.</p>
					<p>"Five and eighty years," he says, musingly, resting his chin on the wrinkled hands that
						clasp the head of his cane. A silence falls on the group around the stove, and through
						the cracked door the red firelight shines out on thoughtful faces.</p>
					<p>"It's a long time; five and eighty years," he repeats, "and every one of them crowned
						with a Thanksgiving. Boys," lifting his head and looking around him, "you've got a good
						bit of pike to travel over yet before you get as far as I've gone, and some of you are
						already half fagged out and beginning to wonder if it's all worth while --Bud, here, for
						instance. I'd like to give you all a word of encouragement.</p>
					<p>"Looking back, I can see that I've had as many ups and downs as any of <pb
							id="VAB1852-024" n="24"/> you, and more than your share of work and trouble, for I've
						lived longer, and nearly all the years are marked with graves. Seems to me that lately
						I've had to leave a new grave behind me at every mile-stone, till now I'm jogging on all
						alone. Family gone, old neighbours gone, old friends --I'm the last of the old set. But,
						still, when all is said and done, I haven't lost heart, for 'I've lived, seen God's hand
						through a lifetime, and all was for best.'</p>
					<p>"When I was milling down there on Bear Creek you'd 'a' thought I was a fool if I hadn't
						taken my rightful toll out of every bushel of grist that ran through my hopper, and
						sometimes I think that the Almighty must feel that way about us when we go on grinding
						and grinding, and never stopping to count up our share of the profit and pleasure and be
						thankful over it. I believe that <pb id="VAB1852-025" n="25"/> no matter what life pours
						into our hopper, we are to grind some toll of good out of it for ourselves, and as long
						as a man does his part toward producing something for the world's good, some kind of
						bread for its various needs, he will never go hungry himself.</p>
					<p>"And I believe more than that. You've heard people compare old age to a harvest field,
						and talk about the autumn of life with its ripened corn waiting for the reaper Death,
						and all that, and speak about the 'harvest home,' as if it were the glorious end of
						everything. But it never did strike me that way, boys. The best comes after the
						harvesting, when the wheat is turned into flour and the flour into bread, and the full,
						wholesome loaves go to make up blood and muscle and brain. That's giving it a sort of
						immortality, you might say, raising it into a higher <pb id="VAB1852-026" n="26"/> order
						of life. And it's the same with a man. His old age is just a ripening for something
						better a little further on. All that we go through with here isn't for nothing, and at
						eighty-five, when it looks as if a man had come to the stepping-off place, I've come to
						believe that 'the best is yet to be.'"</p>
					<p>There is a stir around the door, and the old miller looks around inquiringly. The mail
						has come in, and he rises slowly to get his weekly paper. Perkins's oldest, waiting his
						turn in front of the little case of pigeonholes, eyes the old man with wondering side
						glances. He has not understood more than half of what he has heard, but he is vaguely
						conscious that something is speaking to him now, as he looks into the tranquil old face.
						It is the miller's past that is calling to him; all those honest, hard-working years
						that show <pb id="VAB1852-027" n="27"/> themselves in the bent form and wrinkled hands;
						the serene peacefulness that bespeaks a clear conscience; the big, sunny nature that
						looks out of those aged eyes; and above all the great hopefulness that makes his days a
						perpetual Thanksgiving.</p>
					<p>The mute eloquence of an unspoken invitation thrills the child's heart, he knows not
						why: 
						
						<q rend="blockquote">
							<lg rend="center">
								<l>"Grow old along with me</l>
								<l>The best is yet to be!"</l>
							</lg>
						</q></p>

					<p>It is the greatest lesson that Perkins's oldest can ever learn.</p>

				</div2>

				<pb id="VAB1852-028" n="28"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">Chapter II</head>

					<p><hi rend="b">O</hi>NE would have known that it was the day before Christmas at the
						Cross-Roads store, even if the big life insurance calendar over the desk had not
						proclaimed the fact in bold red figures. An unwonted bustle pervaded the place. Rows of
						plump, dressed turkeys hung outside the door, and on the end of the counter where the
						pyramid of canned tomatoes was usually stacked, a little evergreen tree stood in a brave
						array of tinsel and tiny Christmas tapers.</p>
					<p>It was only an advertisement. No one might hope to be the proud possessor of the Noah's
						ark lodged in its branches, or of the cheap toys and candy rings dangling from every
						limb, unless he had the necessary pennies. <pb id="VAB1852-029" n="29"/> Still, every
						child who passed it eyed it with such wistful glances that the little rubber Santa Claus
						at the base must have felt his elastic heart stretch almost to bursting.</p>
					<p>Above the familiar odour of coal-oil and mackerel, new leather, roasted coffee and
						pickle brine, rose the holiday fragrance of cedar and oranges.</p>
					<p>"Makes me think of when I was a kid," said a drummer who had been joking with the men
						around the stove, trying to kill time while he waited for the train that was to take him
						home for Christmas. "There's nothing like that smell of cedar and oranges to resurrect
						the boy in a man. It puts me straight back into knickerbockers again, among a whole
						grove of early Christmas trees. I'll never forget the way I felt when I picked my first
						pair of skates off one of them. A house and <pb id="VAB1852-030" n="30"/> lot wouldn't
						give me such a thrill now."</p>
					<p>"Aw, I don't believe Christmas is at all what it's cracked up to be," said a voice from
						behind the stove, in such a gloomy tone that a knowing smile passed around the
						circle.</p>
					<p>"Bet on you, Bud Hines, for findin' trouble, every time," laughed the storekeeper.
						"Why, Bud, there ain't no screw loose in Christmas, is there?"</p>
					<p>"Well, there just is!" snapped the man, resenting the laugh. "It comes too often for
						one thing. I just wish it had happened on leap-year, the twenty-ninth of February. It
						would be a heap less expensive having it just once in four years. Seems to me we're
						always treading on its heels. My old woman hardly gets done knitting tidies for one
						Christmas till she's hard at it for another.</p>


					<pb id="VAB1852-031" n="31"/>



					<p>"Anyhow, Christmas never measures up to what you think it's a-going to --not by a
						jug-full. Sure as you get your heart set on a patent nail- puller or a pair of fur
						gloves --something that'll do <hi rend="i">you</hi> some good --your wife gives you a
						carpet sweeper, or an alarm-clock that rattles you out an hour too early every
						morning."</p>
					<p>The drummer led the uproarious laughter that followed. They were ready to laugh at
						anything in this season of good cheer, and the drummer's vociferous merriment was
						irresistible. He slapped the speaker on the back, adding jokingly, "That's one thing Job
						never had to put up, did he, partner! He nearly lost his reputation for politeness over
						the misfit advice he didn't want. But there's no telling what he'd have done with misfit
						Christmas gifts. It would take a star actor <pb id="VAB1852-032" n="32"/> to play the
						grateful for some of the things people find in their stockings. For instance, to have a
						fond female relative give you a shaving outfit, when you wear a full beard."</p>
					<p>"You bet your life," answered the store-keeper feelingly. "Now, if Santa Claus wasn't a
						fake --"</p>
					<p>"Hist!" said the drummer, with a significant glance toward a small boy, perched on a
						soap-box in their midst, listening open-mouthed to every word. "I've children myself,
						and I'd punch anybody's head who would shake their faith in Santy. It's one of the rosy
						backgrounds of childhood, in my opinion, and I've got a heap of happiness out of it
						since I was a kid, too, looking back and recollecting."</p>
					<p>It was very little happiness that the boy on the soap-box was getting out of anything,
						that gray December afternoon. <pb id="VAB1852-033" n="33"/> He was weighed down with a
						feeling of age and responsibility that bore heavily on his eight-year-old shoulders. He
						had long felt the strain of his position, as pattern to the house of Perkins, being the
						oldest of five. Now there was another one, and to be counted as the oldest of six pushed
						him almost to the verge of gray hairs.</p>
					<p>There was another reason for his tear-stained face. He had been disillusioned. Only
						that noon, his own mother had done that for which the drummer would have punched any
						one's head, had it been done to his children. "We're too poor, Sammy. There can't be any
						Christmas at our house this year," she had said, fretfully, as she stopped the noisy
						driving of nails into the chimney, on which he contemplated hanging the fraternal
						stockings. To his astonished "Why?" <pb id="VAB1852-034" n="34"/> she had replied with a
						few blunt truths that sent him out from her presence, shorn of all his childish
						hopefulness as completely as Samson was shorn of his strength.</p>
					<p>There had been a sorry half-hour in the hay-mow, where he snuffled over his shattered
						faith alone, and from whence he went out, a hardened little skeptic, to readjust himself
						to a cold and Santa Clausless world. The only glimmer of comfort he had had since was
						when the drummer, with a friendly wink, slipped a nickel into his hand. But even that
						added to his weight of responsibility. He dropped it back and forth from one little red
						mitten to another, with two impulses strong upon him. The first was to spend it for six
						striped sticks of peppermint candy, one for each stocking, and thus compel Christmas to
						come to the house of <pb id="VAB1852-035" n="35"/> Perkins. The other was to buy one
						orange and go off in a corner and suck it all by himself. He felt that fate owed him
						that much of a reparation for his disappointment. He was in the midst of this inward
						debate when a new voice joined the discussion around the stove. It came from Cy
						Akers.</p>
					<p>"Well, <hi rend="i">I</hi> think it's downright sinful to stuff a child with such
						notions. You may call 'em fairy-tales all you like, but it's nothing more or less than a
						pack of lies. The idea of a Christian payrent sitting up and telling his im- mortal
						child that a big fat man in furs will drive through the air to-night in a reindeer
						sleigh right over the roofs and squeeze himself down a lot of sooty chimneys, with a bag
						of gimcracks on his back --it's all fol-de-rol! I never could see how any <pb
							id="VAB1852-036" n="36"/> intelligent young one could believe it. I never did. But
						that's one thing about me, as the poet says, 'If I've one pecooliar feature it's a nose
						that won't be led.' I never could be made to take stock in any such nonsense, even as a
						boy. I'll leave it to Mr. Asa Holmes, here, if it isn't wrong to be putting such ideas
						into the youth of our land."</p>
					<p>The old miller ran his fingers through his short white hair and looked around. His
						smile was wholesome as it was genial. He was used to being called in judgment on these
						neighbourhood discussions, and he spoke with the air of one who felt that his words
						carried weight:</p>
					<p>"You're putting it pretty strong, Cy," he said, with a laugh, and then a tender,
						reminiscent light gleamed in his old eyes.</p>
					<p>"You see it's this way with me, <pb id="VAB1852-037" n="37"/> boys. We never heard any
						of these things when I was a lad. It's plain facts in a pioneer cabin, you know. Father
						taught us about Christmas in the plain words that he found set down in the Gospels, and
						I told it the same way to my boys. When my first little grandson came back to the old
						house to spend Christmas, I thought it was almost heathenish for his mother to have him
						send letters up the chimney and talk as if Santa Claus was some real person. I told her
						so one day, and asked what was going to happen when the little fellow outgrew such
						beliefs.</p>
					<p>"'Why, Father Holmes,' said she, --I can hear her now, words and tones, for it set me
						to thinking,-- 'don't you see that he is all the time growing into a broader belief?
						It's this way.' She picked up a big apple from the table. <pb id="VAB1852-038" n="38"/>
						'Once this apple was only a tiny seed-pod in the heart of a pink blossom. The beauty of
						the blossom was all that the world saw, at first, but gradually, as the fruit swelled
						and developed, the pink petals fell off, naturally and easily, and the growing fruit was
						left. My little son's idea of Christmas is in the blossom time now. This rosy glamour of
						old customs and traditions that makes it so beautiful to him is taking the part of the
						pink petals. They will fall away by and by, of their own accord, for underneath a
						beautiful truth is beginning to swell to fruitage. Santa Claus is the Spirit of
						Christmas love and giving, personified. It is because I want to make it real and vital,
						something that my baby's mind can grasp and enjoy, that I incarnate it in the form of
						the good old Saint Nicholas, but I never let him lose sight of the <pb id="VAB1852-039"
							n="39"/> Star. It was the Spirit of Christmas that started the wise men on their
						search, and they followed the Star and they found the Child, and laid gifts at his feet.
						And when the Child was grown, he, too, went out in the world and followed the Star and
						scattered his gifts of love and healing for all the children of men. And so it has gone
						on ever since, that Spirit of Christmas, impelling us to follow and to find and to give,
						wherever there is a need for our gold and frankincense and myrrh. That is the larger
						belief my boy is growing into, from the smaller.'</p>
					<p>"And she is right," said the old man, after an impressive pause. "She raised that boy
						to be an own brother to Santa Claus, as far as good-will to men goes. It's Christmas all
						the year round wherever <hi rend="i">he</hi> is. And now when he brings his boys back to
						the old <pb id="VAB1852-040" n="40"/> home and hangs their stockings up by the fire, I
						never say a word. Some- times when the little chaps are hunt- ing for the marks of the
						reindeer hoofs in the ashes, I kneel down on the old hearthstone and hunt, too.</p>

					<p>"A brother to Santa Claus!" The phrase still echoed in the heart of Perkins's oldest
						when the group around the stove dispersed. It was that which decided the fate of the
						nickel, and filled the little red mittens with sticks of striped delight for six,
						instead of the lone orange for one. Out of a conversation but dimly understood he had
						gathered a vague comfort. It made less difference that his patron saint was a myth,
						since he had learned there might be brothers in the Claus family for him to fall back
						upon. Then his fingers closed over the paper bag of <pb id="VAB1852-041" n="41"/>
						peppermints, and, suddenly, with a little thrill, he felt that in some queer way he
						belonged to that same brotherhood.</p>
					<p>As he fumbled at the latch, the old miller, who always saw his own boyhood rise before
						him in that small tow-headed figure, and who somehow had divined the cause of the
						tear-streaks on the dirty little face, called him. "Here, sonny!" It was a pair of
						shining new skates that dangled from the miller's hands into his.</p>
					<p>One look of rapturous delight, and two little feet were flying homeward down the frozen
						pike, beating time to a joy that only the overflowing heart of a child can know, when
						its troubles are all healed, and faith in mankind restored. And the old man, going home
						in the frosty twilight of the Christmas eve, saw before him all the way the light of a
						shining star.</p>
				</div2>

				<pb id="VAB1852-042" n="42"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">Chapter III</head>

					<p><hi rend="b">I</hi>T was an hour past the usual time for closing the Cross-Roads store,
						but no one made a move to go. Listening in the comfortable glow of the red-hot stove, to
						the wind whistling down the long pipe, was far pleasanter than facing its icy blasts on
						the way home. Besides, it was the last night of the old year, and hints of forthcoming
						cider had been dropped by Jim Bowser, the storekeeper. Also an odour of frying doughnuts
						came in from the kitchen, whenever Mrs. Bowser opened the door into the entry.</p>
					<p>Added to the usual group of loungers was the drummer who had spent Christmas eve with
						them. He had come in on an accommodation train, <pb id="VAB1852-043" n="43"/> and was
						waiting for the midnight express. He had had the floor for some time with his stories,
						when suddenly in the midst of the laughter which followed one of his jokes, Bud Hines
						made himself heard.</p>
					<p>"I say, Jim," he exclaimed, turning to the storekeeper, "why don't you tear off the
						last leaf of that calendar? We've come to the end of everything now; end of the day, end
						of the year, end of the century! Something none of <hi rend="i">us</hi> will ever
						experience again. It's always a mighty solemn thought to me that I'm doing a thing for
						the la-ast time!"</p>
					<p>Jim laughed cheerfully, tilting his chair back against the counter, and thrusting his
						thumbs into the armholes of his vest.</p>
					<p>"I don't know as I feel any call to mourn over takin' down an old <pb id="VAB1852-044"
							n="44"/> calendar when I have a prettier one to put in its place, and it's the same
						way with the century. There'll be a better one to begin on in the morning."</p>
					<p>"That's so," asserted Cy Akers. "But some people come bang up against a New Year as if
						it was a stone wall, and down they set and count up their sins, and turn over new
						leaves, and load 'emselves down with so many good resolutions that they stick in the mud
						by the end of the first week. Now I hold that if it wasn't for the almanacs, steppin'
						from one year to another, or from one century to another, wouldn't jar you no more than
						steppin' over the equator. They're only imaginary lines, and nobody would ever know
						where he was at, either in months or meridians, if he didn't have almanacs and the like
						to keep him posted. Fourth of July is just as good <pb id="VAB1852-045" n="45"/> a time
						to take stock and turn over a new leaf as the first of January."</p>
					<p>"Maybe you take stock like a man I used to sell to down in Henderson County," said the
						drummer. "He never kept any books, so he never knew exactly where he was 'at,' as you
						say. Once a year he'd walk around the store with his hands in his pockets, and size up
						things in a general sort of way. 'Bill,' he'd say to his clerk, cocking his eyes up at
						the shelves, 'we've got a right smart chance of canned goods left over. I reckon there's
						a half shelf full more than we had left last year. I know there's more bottles of
						ketchup.' Then he'd take another turn around the room. ' Bill, I disremember how many
						pitchforks we had in this rack. There's only two left now. Nearly all the calico is
						sold, and (thumping the <pb id="VAB1852-046" n="46"/> molasses barrel), this here bar'l
						sounds like it's purty nigh empty. Take it all around, Bill, we've done first-rate this
						year, so I don't know as it's worth while botherin' about weighin' and measurin' what's
						left over, so long as we're satisfied.' And maybe that's why Cy makes so little of New
						Year," added the drummer, with a sly wink at the others. "He thinks it's not worth while
						to weigh and measure his shortcomings when he can take stock of himself in a general
						sort of a way, and always be perfectly satisfied with himself."</p>
					<p>There was a laugh at Cy's expense, and Bud Hines began again.</p>
					<p>"What worries me is, what's been prophesied about the new century. One would think
						we've had enough famines and plagues and wars and rumours of wars in this here old one
						to <pb id="VAB1852-047" n="47"/> do for awhile, but from what folks say, it ain't goin'
						to hold a candle to the trouble we'll see in the next one."</p>
					<p>"Troubles is seasonin'. ''Simmons ain't good till they are frostbit,'" quoted Cy.</p>
					<p>"Then accordin' to Bud's tell, he ought to be the best seasoned persimmon on the
						bough," chuckled the storekeeper.</p>
					<p>"No, that fellow that was here this afternoon goes ahead of Bud," insisted Cy, turning
						to the drummer. "I wish you could have heard him, pardner. He came in to get a postal
						order for some money he wanted to send in a letter, and he nearly wiped up the earth
						with poor old Bowser, because there was a two-cent war tax to pay on it.</p>
					<p>"'Whose war?' says he. ''Tain't none of my makin',' says he, 'and I'll be switched if
						I'll pay taxes on a thing <pb id="VAB1852-048" n="48"/> I've been dead set against from
						the start. It's highway robbery,' says he, 'to load the country down with a war debt in
						times like these. It's kill yourself to keep yourself these days, and as my Uncle Josh
						used to say after the Mexican war, "it's tough luck when people are savin' and scrimpin'
						at the spigot for the government to be drawin' off at the bung."'</p>
					<p>"Bowser here just looked him over as if he'd been a freak at a side-show, and said
						Bowser, in a dry sort of way, he guessed, 'when it came to the pinch, the spigot
						wouldn't feel that a two-cent stamp was a killin' big leakage.'</p>
					<p>"The fellow at that threw the coppers down on the counter, mad as a hornet. 'It's the
						principle of the thing,' says he. 'Uncle Sam had no business to bite off more'n he could
						chew and then call on me to help. <pb id="VAB1852-049" n="49"/> What's the war done for
						this country, anyhow?'</p>
					<p>"He was swinging his arms like a stump speaker at a barbecue, by this time. 'What's it
						done?' says he. 'Why it's sent the soldiers back from Cuba with an itch as bad as the
						smallpox, and as ketchin' to them citizens that wanted peace, as to them that clamoured
						for war. I know what I'm talkin' about, for my hired man like to 'uv died with it, and
						he hadn't favoured the war any more than a spring lamb. And what's it doin' for us,
						now?' says he. 'Sendin' the poor fellows back from the Philippines by the ship-load,
						crazy as June-bugs. I know what I'm talkin' about. That happened to one of my wife's
						cousins. What was it ever begun for,' says he, 'tell me that!'</p>
					<p>"Peck here, behind the stove, sung <pb id="VAB1852-050" n="50"/> out like a fog-horn,
							<hi rend="i">'Remember the Maine!'</hi> Peck knew what a blow the fellow had made at
						an indignation meeting when the news first came. No tellin' what would have happened
						then if a little darky hadn't put his head in at the door and yelled, 'Say, mistah, yo'
						mules is done backed yo' wagon in de ditch!' He tore out to tend to them, or we might
						have had another Spanish war right here among Bowser's goods and chattels."</p>
					<p>"No danger," said Peck, dryly, "he isn't the kind of a fellow to fight for principle.
						It's only when his pocketbook is touched he wants to lick somebody. He's the stingiest
						man I ever knew, and I've known some mighty mean men in my time."</p>
					<p>"What's the matter with you all tonight?" said the drummer. "You're the most
						pessimistic crowd I've struck <pb id="VAB1852-051" n="51"/> in an age. This is the tune
						you've been giving me from the minute I lifted the latch." And beating time with foot
						and hands in old plantation style, the drummer began forthwith to sing in a deep bass
						voice that wakened the little Bowsers above:
						
						<q rend="blockquote">
							<lg rend="center">
								<l>"Ole Satan is loose an' a-bummin'!</l>
								<l>De wheels er distruckshin is a-hummin.'</l>
								<l>Oh, come 'long, sinner, ef you comin'!"</l>
							</lg>
						</q></p>

					<p>The door into the entry opened a crack and Mrs. Bowser's forefinger beckoned.</p>
					<p>"Here's good-bye to the old and good luck to the new," cried Jim, jumping up to take
						the big pitcher of cider that she passed through the opening.</p>
					<p>"And here's to Mrs. Bowser," cried the drummer, taking the new tin cup filled for him
						with the sparkling cider, <pb id="VAB1852-052" n="52"/> and helping himself to a hot
						doughnut from the huge panful which she brought in. "It's a pretty good sort of world,
						after all, that gives you cakes as crisp and sugary as these. 'Speak well of the bridge
						that carries you over' is my motto, so don't let another fellow cheep to-night, unless
						he can say something good of the poor old century or the men who've lived in it!"</p>
					<p>"Mr. Holmes! Mr. Asa Holmes!" cried several voices.</p>
					<p>The old miller, who had been silent all evening, straightened himself up in his chair
						and drew his hand over his eyes.</p>
					<p>"I feel as if I were parting with an old comrade, to-night," he said. "The century had
						only fifteen years the start of me, and it's a long way we've travelled together. I've
						been sitting here, <pb id="VAB1852-053" n="53"/> thinking how much we've lived through.
						Listen, boys."</p>
					<p>It was a brief series of pictures he drew for them, against the background of his early
						pioneer days. They saw him, a little lad, trudging more than a mile on a winter morning
						to borrow a kettle of hot coals, because the fire had gone out on his own hearthstone,
						and it was before the days of matches. They saw him huddled with the other little ones
						around his mother's knee when the wolves howled in the night outside the door, and only
						the light of a tallow-dip flickered through the darkness of the little cabin. They saw
						the struggle of a strong life against the limitations of the wilderness, and realised
						what the battle must have been oftentimes, against sudden disease and accident and
						death, with the nearest doctor a three days' journey distant, and <pb id="VAB1852-054"
							n="54"/> no smoke from any neighbour's chim- ney rising anywhere on all the wide
						horizon.</p>
					<p>While he talked, a heavy freight train rumbled by outside; the wind whistled through
						the telegraph wires. The jingle of a telephone bell interrupted his reminiscences. The
						old man looked up with a smile. "See what we have come to," he said, "from such a past
						to a time when I can say 'hello,' across a continent. Cables and cross-ties and
						telegraph poles have annihilated distance. The century and I came in on an ox-cart; we
						are going out on a streak of lightning.</p>
					<p>"But that's not the greatest thing," he said, pausing, while the listening faces grew
						still more thoughtful. "Think of the hospitals! The homes! The universities! The social
						settlements! The free libraries! The humane <pb id="VAB1852-055" n="55"/> efforts
						everywhere to give humanity an uplift! When I think of all this century has
						accomplished, of the heroic lives it has produced, I haven't a word to say about its
						mistakes and failures. After all, how do we know that the things we cry out against <hi
							rend="i">are</hi> mistakes?</p>
					<p>"This war may be a Samson's riddle that we are not wise enough to read. Those who shall
						come after us may be able to say <hi rend="i">'Out of the eater came forth meat, and out
							of the strong came forth sweetness!'"</hi></p>
					<p>Somewhere in an upper room a clock struck twelve, and deep silence fell on the little
						company as they waited for the solemn passing of the century. It was no going out as of
						some decrepit Lear tottering from his throne. Per- haps no man there could have put it
						in words, but each one felt that its majes- tic leave-taking was like the hoary old <pb
							id="VAB1852-056" n="56"/> apostle's: "I have fought a good fight, I have finished my
						course, I have kept the faith."</p>
				</div2>


				<pb id="VAB1852-057" n="57"/>
				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">Chapter IV</head>
					<p><hi rend="b">F</hi>OR some occult reason, the successful merchant in small towns and
						villages is the confidant, if not father-confessor, of a large number of his
						patronesses. It may be that his flattering air of personal interest, assumed for purely
						business purposes, loosens not only the purse-strings but the spring that works the
						panorama of private affairs. Or it may be an idiosyncrasy of some classes of the mind
						feminine, to make no distinction between a bargain counter and a confessional. Whatever
						the cause, many an honest merchant can testify that it is no uncommon thing for a woman
						to air her domestic troubles while she buys a skirt braid, or to drag out her family
						skeleton with the <pb id="VAB1852-058" n="58"/> sample of sewing silk she wishes to
						match.</p>
					<p>The Cross-Roads had had its share of confidences, although as a rule the women who
						disposed of their butter and eggs in trade to Bowser were of the patient sort, grown
						silent under the repressing influence of secluded farm life. Still, Bowser, quick to see
						and keen to judge, had gained a remarkable insight into neighbourhood affairs in fifteen
						years' dealings with his public. "All things come to him who waits" if he wears an air
						of habitual interest and has a sympathetic way of saying "Ah! indeed!"</p>
					<p>It was with almost the certainty of foreknowledge that Bowser counted his probable
						patrons as he spread out his valentines on the morning of the fourteenth of February. He
						had selected his comic ones with a view to the <pb id="VAB1852-059" n="59"/> feud that
						existed between the Hillock and Bond families, well knowing that a heavy cross-fire of
						ugly carica- tures and insulting rhymes would be kept up all day by the younger members
						of those warring households. It was with professional satisfaction he smiled over the
						picture of a fat man with a donkey's head, which he was as sure would be sent by Pete
						Hillock to old man Bond, as if he had heard Pete's penny dropping into the
						cashdrawer.</p>
					<p>"Nothing like supplying the demand," he chuckled.</p>
					<p>It was with more than professional interest that he arranged the lace-paper valentines
						in the show-case, for the little embossed Cupids had a strong ally in this rustic
						haberdasher, whose match-making propensities had helped many a little romance to a happy
						issue. <pb id="VAB1852-060" n="60"/> Drawing on his fund of private information,
						acquired in his role of confidant to the neighbourhood gossips, he set out his stock of
						plump red hearts, forget-me-nots, and doves; and with each addition to the festal array
						he nodded his head knowingly over the particular courtship it was designed to speed, or
						the lovers' quarrel that he hoped might be ended thereby.</p>

					<p>There had been two weeks of "February thaw." Melting snow had made the mud hub-deep in
						places. There was a velvety balminess in the touch of the warm wind, and faint, elusive
						odours, prophetic of spring, rose from the moist earth and sap-quickened trees.</p>
					<p>The door of the Cross-Road store stood open, and behind it, at the post-office desk,
						sat Marion Holmes, the old miller's granddaughter. Just out <pb id="VAB1852-061" n="61"
						/> of college and just into society, she had come to spend Lent in the old place that
						had welcomed her every summer during her childhood. The group around the stove stared
						covertly at the pretty girl in the tailor-made gown, failing to recognise in the tall,
						stylish figure any trace of the miller's "little Polly," who used to dangle her feet
						from the counter and munch peppermint drops, while she lisped nursery rhymes for their
						edification.</p>
					<p>She had come for the letters herself, she told Bowser, because she was expecting a
						whole bag full, and her grandfather's rheumatism kept him at home. Installed in the
						post-office chair, behind the railing that enclosed the sanctum of pigeon-holes, she
						amused herself by watching the customers while she waited for the mail-train.</p>
					<p>"It's like looking into a kaleidoscope," <pb id="VAB1852-062" n="62"/> she told Bowser
						in one of the pauses of trade. "Every one who comes in gives me a different point of
						view and combination of opinions. Now, those valentines! I was thinking what
						old-fashioned things those little lace-paper affairs are, and wondering how anybody
						could possibly get up any thrills over them, when in walked Miss Anastasia Dill. Prim
						and gentle as ever, isn't she? Still getting her styles from <hi rend="i">Godey's Lady's
							Books</hi> of the early sixties; she must draw on their antiquated love stories for
						her sentiment, too, for she seemed lost in admiration of those hearts and darts. What
							<hi rend="i">do</hi> you suppose is Miss Anastasia's idea of a lover?"</p>
					<p>Marion rattled on with all of a debutante's reckless enthusiasm for any subject under
						discussion. "Wouldn't he be as odd and old-fashioned as the <pb id="VAB1852-063" n="63"
						/> lace valentines themselves? She'd call him a <hi rend="i">suitor</hi>, wouldn't she?
						I wonder if she ever had one."</p>
					<p>Then Bowser, piecing together the fragmentary gossip of fifteen years, told Marion all
						he knew of Miss Anastasia's gentle romance; and Marion, idly clasping and unclasping the
						little Yale pin on her jacket, gained another peep into the kaleidoscope of human
						experiences.</p>
					<p>"I have read of such devotion to a memory," she said when the story was done, "but I
						never met it in the flesh. What a pity he died while he was on such a high pedestal in
						her imagination. If he had lived she would have discovered that there are no such
						paragons, and all the other sons of Adam needn't have suffered by comparison. So she's
						an old maid simply because she put her ideal of a lover so high in <pb id="VAB1852-064"
							n="64"/> the clouds nobody could live up to it! Dear old Miss Anastasia!"</p>
					<p>Bowser pulled his beard. "Such couples make me think of these here lamps with double
						wicks," he said. "They hardly ever burn along together evenly. One wick is sure to flare
						up higher than the other; you either have to keep turning it down and get along with a
						half light or let it smoke the chimney --maybe crack it-- and make things generally
						uncomfortable. But here comes somebody, Miss Marion, who's burned along pretty steady,
						and that through three administrations. It's her brag that she's had three husbands and
						treated them just alike, even to the matter of tombstones. 'Not a pound difference in
						the weight nor a dollar in the price,' she always says."</p>
					<p>The newcomer was a fat, wheezy woman, spattered with mud from the <pb id="VAB1852-065"
							n="65"/> hem of her skirt to the crown of her big crape bonnet, which had tipped on
						one side with the jolting of the wagon.</p>
					<p>"Well, Jim Bowser!" she exclaimed, catching sight of the valentines. "Ef you ain't got
						out them silly, sentimental fol-de-rols again! My nephew, Jason Potter, --that's my
						second husband's sister's son, you know, -- spent seventy-five cents last year to buy
						one of them silly things to send to his girl; and I says to him, 'Jason,' says I, 'ef
							<hi rend="i">I'd</hi> been Lib Meadows, that would 'uv cooked your goose with <hi
							rend="i">me!</hi> Any man simple enough to waste his substance so, wouldn't make a
						good provider.' I ought to know --I've been a wife three times."</p>
					<p>This, like all other of Mrs. Power's conversational roads, led back to the three
						tombstones, and started a flow <pb id="VAB1852-066" n="66"/> of good-natured badinage on
						the subject of matrimony, which continued long after she had taken her noisy departure.
						"Well!" exclaimed Bud Hines, as the big crape bonnet went jolting down the road, "I
						guess there's three good men gone that could tell why heaven is heaven."</p>
					<p>"Why?" asked Cy Akers.</p>
					<p>"Because there's no marryin' or givin' in marriage there."</p>
					<p>"Bud speaks feelingly!" said Cy, winking at the others. "He'd better get a job on a
						newspaper to write Side Talks with Henpecked Husbands."</p>
					<p>"Shouldn't think <hi rend="i">you'd</hi> want to hear any extrys or supplements,"
						retorted Bud. "You get enough in your own daily editions."</p>

					<p>"St. Valentine has been generous with my little Polly," said the old miller, <pb
							id="VAB1852-067" n="67"/> looking up fondly at the tall, graceful girl, coming into
						his room, her face aglow and her arms full of packages.</p>
					<p>"But what's the good of it all, grandfather?" answered Marion. "I've been looking into
						Cupid's kaleidoscope through other people's eyes this afternoon, and nothing is
						rose-coloured as I thought. Everything is horrid. 'Marriage is a failure,' and sentiment
						is a silly thing that people make flippant jokes about, or else break their hearts with,
						like Mr. Bowser's double-wick lamps, that flare up and crack their chimneys. I've come
						to the conclusion that St. Valentine has outlived his generation."</p>
					<p>She broke the string which bound one of the boxes that she had dropped on the table,
						and took out a great dewy bunch of sweet violets. As their fragrance filled the room,
						the old man <pb id="VAB1852-068" n="68"/>Bea lolmes looked around as if half expecting
						to see some familiar presence; then dropped his white head with a sigh, and gazed into
						the embers on the hearth, lost in a tender reverie.</p>
					<p>Presently he said, "I wish you would hand me that box on my wardrobe shelf, little
						girl." As Marion opened the wardrobe door, something hanging there made her give a
						little start of surprise. It was an old familiar gray dress, with the creases still in
						the bent sleeves just as they had been left when the tired arms last slipped out of
						them. That was ten years ago; and Marion, standing there with a mist gathering in her
						eyes, recalled the day her grandfather had refused to let any one fold it away. It had
						hung there all those years, the tangible reminder of the strong, sweet presence that had
						left its imprint on every part of the household.</p>



					<pb id="VAB1852-069" n="69"/>
					<p>"It is like my life since she slipped out of it," the old man had whispered, smoothing
						the empty sleeve with his stiff old fingers. "Like my heart --set to her ways at every
						turn, and left just as she rounded it out --but now-- so empty!"</p>
					<p>He lifted an old dog-eared schoolbook from the box that Marion brought him, a queer
						little "Geography and Atlas of the Heavens," in use over fifty years ago. Inside was a
						tiny slip of paper, time-yellowed and worn. The ink was faded, until the words written
						in an unformed girlish hand were barely legible:
						
						<q rend="blockquote">
							<lg rend="center">
								<l>"True as grapes grow on a vine,</l>
								<l>I will be your Valentine."</l>
							</lg>
						</q></p>

					<p>"I had put a letter into her Murray's grammar," he explained, holding up another little
						book. "Here is the <pb id="VAB1852-070" n="70"/> page, just at the conjugation of the
						verb 'to love.' You see I was a big, shy, overgrown boy that lost my tongue whenever I
						looked at her, although she wasn't fifteen then, and only reached my shoulder. This
						valentine was the answer that she slipped into my atlas of the heavens. I thought the
						sky itself had never held such a star. We walked home across the woodland together that
						day, never saying a word. It was the last of the February thaw, and the birds were
						twittering as if it were really spring. Just such a day as this. All of a sudden, right
						at my feet, I saw something smiling up at me, blue as the blue of my Polly's eyes. I
						stooped and brushed away the leaves, and there were two little violets.</p>
					<p>"As I gave them to her I wanted to say, 'There will always be violets in my heart for
						you, my Polly,' but I <pb id="VAB1852-071" n="71"/> couldn't speak a word. I know she
						understood, for long years after --when she was dead-- I found them here. She had pinned
						them on the page where my letter had lain, here on the conjugation that says, 'we love,'
						and she had added the word <hi rend="i">'for ever.'"</hi></p>
					<p>A tear dropped on the dead violets as the old man reverently closed the book, and sat
						gazing again into the dying embers. There was a tremulous smile on his face. Was it
						backward over the hills of their youth he was wandering, or ahead to those heights of
						Hope, where love shall "put on immortality?"</p>
					<p>Marion laid her warm cheek against her violets, still fragrant with the sweetness of
						their fresh, unfaded youth. Then taking a cluster from the great dewy bunch, she
						fastened it at her throat with the little Yale pin.</p>
				</div2>



				<pb id="VAB1852-072" n="72"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">Chapter V</head>
					<p><hi rend="b">T</hi>RADE was dull at the Cross-Roads. Jim Bowser, his hands thrust into
						his pockets and his lips puckered to a whistle, stood looking through the dingy glass of
						his front door. March was coming in with a snow-storm, and all he could see in any
						direction was a blinding fall of white flakes. There were only three men behind the
						stove that afternoon, and one of them was absorbed in a newspaper. Conversation flagged,
						and from time to time Bud Hines yawned audibly.</p>
					<p>"This is getting to be mighty monotonous," remarked the storekeeper, glancing from the
						falling snow to the silent group by the stove.</p>
					<p>"March always is," answered Bud <pb id="VAB1852-073" n="73"/> Hines. " The other months
						have some holiday in 'em; something to brighten 'em up, if it's no more than a family
						birthday. But to me, March is as dull and uninteresting as a mud road."</p>
					<p>"There's the inauguration this year," suggested Cy Akers, looking up from his
						newspaper. "That's a big event. This paper is full of it."</p>
					<p>"Well, now you've hit it!" exclaimed Bud, with withering scorn, as he bit off another
						chew of tobacco. "That is exciting! Just about as interesting as watching a man take his
						second helping of pie. I wouldn't go across the road to see it. Now in a monarchy, where
						death makes the changes, it can't get to be a cut and dried affair that takes place
						every four years. They make a grand occasion of it, too, with their pomp and ceremony
							<pb id="VAB1852-074" n="74"/> Look at what England's just seen. It's the sight of a
						lifetime to bury a queen and crown a king. But what do we see when we change Presidents?
						One man sliding into a chair and another sliding out, same as when the barber calls
						'Next!' Humph!"</p>
					<p>Cy Akers rubbed his chin. "Fuss and feathers! That's all it amounts to," he exclaimed.
						"I'm down on monopolies, and in my opinion it's the worst kind of monopoly to let one
						family crowd out everybody else in the king business. I like a country where every man
						in it has a show. Not that I'd be President, if they offered me double the salary, but
						it is worth a whole lot to me to feel that in case I did want the office, I've as good a
						right to it as any man living. And talk about sights --I say it's the sight of a
						lifetime to see a man step out from his <pb id="VAB1852-075" n="75"/> place among the
						people, anywhere he happens to be when they call his name, take his turn at ruling as if
						he'd been born to it, and then step back as if nothing had happened."</p>
					<p>Bud smiled derisively. "You only see that on paper, my boy. Men don't step quietly into
						offices in this country. They run for 'em till they are red in the face, and it's the
						best runner that gets there, not the best man. Monopoly in the king business keeps out
						the rabble, any how, and it gives a country a good deal more dignity to be ruled by a
						dynasty than by Tom, Dick, and Harry."</p>
					<p>"Well, there's no strings tied to you," said Cy, testily, taking up his newspaper
						again. "When people don't like the way things are run on this side of the water, there's
						nothing to hinder emigration."</p>


					<pb id="VAB1852-076" n="76"/>
					<p>There was a stamping of snowy feet outside the door, and a big, burly fellow blustered
						in, whom they hailed as Henry Bicking. He was not popular at the Cross-Roads, having the
						unenviable reputation of being a "born tease," but any diversion was welcome on such a
						dull day.</p>
					<p>In the catalogue of queer characters which every neighbourhood possesses, the Autocrat,
						Bore, and Crank may take precedence of all others alphabetically, but the one that heads
						the list in disagreeableness is that infliction on society known as the "born tease."
						One can forgive the teasing propensity universally found in boys, as he would condone
						the playful destructiveness of puppyhood; something requiring only temporary
						forbearance. But when that trait refuses to be put away with childish things it makes of
						the man it dominates <pb id="VAB1852-077" n="77"/> a sort of human mosquito. He regards
						every one in reach his lawful prey, from babies to octogenarians, and while he does not
						always sting, the persistency of his annoying attacks becomes exasperating beyond
						endurance.</p>
					<p>The same motive that made Henry Bicking pull cats' whiskers out by the roots when he
						was a boy, led him to keep his children in a turmoil, and his sensitive little wife in
						tears half the time. He had scarcely seated himself by the stove when he was afforded
						opportunity for his usual pastime by the entrance of half a dozen children, who came
						tumbling in on their way home from school to warm.</p>
					<p>He began with a series of those inane questions by which grown people have made
						themselves largely responsi- ble for the pertness of the younger generation. If children
						of this day <pb id="VAB1852-078" n="78"/> have departed from that delectable state
						wherein they were seen and not heard, the fault is due far more to their elders than to
						them. Often they have been made self-conscious, and forced into saucy self-assertion by
						the teasing questions that are asked merely to provoke amusing replies.</p>
					<p>Henry Bicking's quizzing had an element of cruelty in it. His was the kind that pinches
						his victims' ears, that tickles to the verge of agony, that threatens all sorts of
						disagreeable things, for the sake of seeing little faces blanch with fright, or eyes
						fill with tears of pain.</p>
					<p>"Come here, Woodpecker," he began, reaching for a child whose red hair was the grief of
						his existence. But the boy deftly eluded him, and the little fellow standing next in
						line, drying his snowball-soaked mittens, <pb id="VAB1852-079" n="79"/> became the
						victim. He was dragged unwillingly to his tormentor's knee.</p>
					<p>"What are you going to be when you're a man?" was demanded, when the first questions
						had elicited the fact that the child's name was Sammy Perkins, and that he was eight
						years old. But Perkins's oldest, having no knowledge of the grammar of life beyond its
						present tense indicative, hung his head and held his tongue at mention of its future
						potential.</p>
					<p>"If you don't tell me you sha'n't have your mittens!" Bicking dangled them
						tantalisingly out of reach, until, after an agonising and unsuccessful scramble, the
						child was forced into a tearful reply.</p>
					<p>Then he began again: "Which are you for, Democrats or Republicans?"</p>
					<p>"Ain't for neither."</p>
					<p>"Well, you're the littlest mugwump <pb id="VAB1852-080" n="80"/>Ela lRolmes I ever did
						see. Mugwumps ain't got any right to wear mittens. I've a notion to pitch 'em in the
						stove."</p>
					<p>"Oh, <hi rend="i">don't!"</hi> begged the child. <hi rend="i">"Please,</hi> mister! I'm
						not a mugwump!"</p>
					<p>The tragic earnestness of the child as he disclaimed all right to the term of reproach
						which he could not understand, yet repudiated because of its obnoxious sound, amused the
						man hugely. He threw back his head and laughed.</p>
					<p>"Tell me who you holler for!" he continued, catching him up and holding him head
						downward a moment. Then goaded by more teasing questions and a threatenin swing of his
						red mittens toward the stove door, Perkins's oldest was at last led to take a bold stand
						on his party platform, and publicly declare his political preference. <pb
							id="VAB1852-081" n="81"/> But it was in a shaking voice and between frightened
						sobs.</p>
					<p>"M-ma, she's for McKinley, an' p-pap, he's for B-Bryan, so I jus' holler for Uncle
						Sam!"</p>
					<p>"Good enough for you, sonny," laughed the storekeeper. "That's true blue Americanism.
						Stick to Uncle Sam and never mind the parties. They've had new blades put on their old
						handles, and new handles put on those old blades again, till none of 'em are what we
						started out with. We keep on calling them 'genuine Bar- lows,' but it's precious little
						of the original Barlows we're hanging on to nowadays."</p>
					
					<p>It was a woman's voice that interrupted the conversation. Mrs. Teddy Mahone had come
						in for some tea.</p>
					<p>"Arrah, Misther Bicking! Give the <pb id="VAB1852-082" n="82"/> bye his mitts! You're
						worrse than a cat with a mouse."</p>
					<p>The loud voice with its rich Irish brogue drew Cy Akers's attention from his newspaper.
						"By the way, Bud," he exclaimed, raising his voice so that Mrs. Mahone could not fail to
						hear, "you were complaining about March being so dull and commonplace without any
						holidays. You've forgotten St. Patrick's Day."</p>
					<p>"No, I haven't. St. Patrick is nothing to me. There's no reason I should take any
						interest in him."</p>
					<p>"And did you hear that, Mrs. Ma- hone," asked Henry Bicking, anxious to start a war of
						words.</p>
					<p>"Oh, Oi heard it, indade Oi did!" she answered with a solemn shake of the head. "It
						grieves the hearrt of me to hear such ingratichude. There's niver a sowl in all Ameriky
						but has <pb id="VAB1852-083" n="83"/> cause to be grateful for what he's done for this
						counthry."</p>
					<p>"What's he ever done?" asked Bud, skeptically. There was a twinkle in Mrs. Mahone's
						eyes as she answered:</p>
					<p>"It was this way. A gude while back whin it was at the beginnin' iv things, Ameriky
						said to herself wan day,' It's a graand pudding Oi'll be afther makin' meself, by a new
						resait Oi've just thought iv.' So she dips into this counthry for wan set iv immy-
						grants, an' into another counthry for another batch, and after a bit a foine mess she
						had iv 'em. Dutch an' Frinch an' Eyetalian, Rooshian, Spaniards an' haythen Chinee, all
						stirred up in wan an' the same pudding-bag.</p>
					<p>"'Somethin's lackin',' siz she, afther awhile, makin' a wry face.</p>
					<p>"'It's the spice,' siz St. Pathrick, 'ye lift out iv it, an' the leaven. Ye'll <pb
							id="VAB1852-084" n="84"/> have to make parsinal application to meself for it, for Oi'm
						the only wan knowin' the saicret of where it's to be found.'</p>
					<p>"'Then give me some,'siz she, an' St. Pathrick, not loikin' to lave a leddy in trouble,
						reached out from the auld sod and handed her a fair shprinklin' of them as would act as
						both spice an' leaven.</p>
					<p>"'They'll saison the whole lot,'siz he, 'an' there's light-heartedness enough among
						them to raise the entoire heavy mass in your whole united pudding-bag.'</p>
					<p>"'Thanks,' siz she, stirrin' us in. 'It's the makin' of the dish, sorr, and Oi'm
						etarnally obliged to ye, sorr. Oi'll be afther puttin' the name of St. Pathrick in me
						own family calendar, and ivery year on that day, it's the pick iv the land that'll take
						pride in addin' <pb id="VAB1852-085" n="85"/> to me own shtars an' shtripes the wearin'
						o' the green.'</p>
					<p>"Ye see, Misther Hines, ye may think ye're under no parsinal obligation to him, but
						down-hearted as ye are by nature, what wud ye have been had ye niver coom in conthact
						with the leaven of St. Pathrick at all, sorr? Oi ask ye that."</p>

					<p>Late that night Bowser pushed his ledger aside with a yawn, and got down from his high
						stool to close the store. As he counted the meagre contents of the cash drawer, he
						reviewed the day, whose minutes had been as monotonous in passing as the falling of the
						snowflakes outside. It had left nothing behind it to distinguish it from a hundred other
						days. The same old faces! The same kind of jokes! The same round of commonplace duties!
						A <pb id="VAB1852-086" n="86"/> spirit of unrest seized him, that made him chafe against
						such dreary monotony.</p>
					<p>When he went to the door to put up the shutters, the beauty of the night held him a
						moment, and he stood looking across the wide fields, lying white in moonlight and snow.
						Far down the road a lamp gleamed from the window of an upper room in the old miller's
						house, where anxious vigil had been kept beside him for hours. The crisis was passed
						now. Only a little while before, the doctor had stopped by to say that their old friend
						would live. Down the track a gleaming switch-light marked the place where a wreck had
						been narrowly averted that morning.</p>
					<p>"And no telling how many other misfortunes we've escaped to-day," mused Bowser. "Maybe
						if a light <pb id="VAB1852-087" n="87"/> could be swung out for each one, folks would
						see that the dull gray days when nothing happens are the ones to be most thankful for,
						after all."</p>
				</div2>


				<pb id="VAB1852-088" n="88"/>
				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">Chapter VI</head>
					<p><hi rend="b">A</hi>PRIL sunshine of mid-afternoon poured in through the open door of
						the Cross-Roads. The usual group of loungers had gathered around the rusty stove. There
						was no fire in it; the day was too warm for that, but force of habit made them draw
						their chairs about it in a circle, as if this common centre were the hub, from which
						radiated the spokes of all neighbourly intercourse.</p>
					<p>The little schoolmistress was under discussion. Her short reign in District No. 3 had
						furnished a topic of conversation as inexhaustible as the weather, for her regime was
						attended by startling changes. Luckily for her, the young ideas enjoyed being taught to
						shoot at wide variance from the targets set up <pb id="VAB1852-089" n="89"/> by parental
						practice and tradition, else the tales told out of school might have aroused more
						adverse criticism than they did.</p>
					<p>"You can't take much stock in her new-fangled notions," was the unanimous opinion at
						the Cross-Roads. She had "put the cart before the horse" when she laid the time-honoured
						alphabet on the shelf, and gave the primer class a whole word at a mouthful, before it
						had cut a single orthographic tooth on such primeval syllables as a-b ab.</p>
					<p>"Look at my Willie," exclaimed one of the district fathers. "Beating around the bush
						with talk about a picture cow, and a real cow, and a word cow, and not knowing whether B
						comes after W or X. At his age I could say the alphabet forwards or backwards as fast as
						tongue could go without a slip."</p>



					<pb id="VAB1852-090" n="90"/>
					<p>"She's done <hi rend="i">one</hi> sensible thing," admitted Cy Akers. "They tell me
						she's put her foot down on the scholars playing April fool tricks this year."</p>
					<p>"I don't see why," said Henry Bicking. "It has been one of the customs in this district
						since the schoolhouse was built. What's the harm if the children do take one day in the
						year for a little foolishness? Let them have their fun, I say."</p>
					<p>"But they've carried it too far," was the answer. "It's scandalous they should be
						allowed to abuse people's rights and feelings and property as they have done the last
						few years. First of April doesn't justify such cutting up any more than the first of
						August."</p>
					<p>"She's got Scripture on her side," said Squire Dobbs. "You know Solomon says, 'As a mad
						man who casteth 90 <pb id="VAB1852-091" n="91"/> firebrands, arrows, and death, so is
						the man that deceiveth his neighbour and saith, am I not in sport?'"</p>
					<p>"She can't stamp out such a deep-rooted custom in one day," protested Bicking.</p>
					<p>"You can bet on the little school-ma'am every time," laughed Bowser. "My daughter Milly
						says they didn't have regular lessons yesterday afternoon. She had them put their books
						in their desks.</p>
					<p>"Said they'd been studying about wise men all their lives, now they'd study about fools
						awhile; the fools of Proverbs and the fools of history.</p>
					<p>"She read some stories, too, about a cruel disappointment and the troubles brought
						about by some thoughtless jokes on the first of April. Mighty interesting stories, Milly
						said. You could have heard a pin drop, and some <pb id="VAB1852-092" n="92"/> of the
						girls cried. Then she drew a picture on the blackboard of a court jester, in cap and
						bells, and asked if they wouldn't like a change this year. Instead of everybody acting
						the fool and doing silly things they'd all be ashamed of if they'd only stop to think,
						wouldn't they rather she'd appoint just one scholar to play the fool for all of them, as
						the old kings used to do.</p>
					<p>"They agreed to that, quick enough, thinking what fun they'd have teasing the one
						chosen to be it. Then she said she'd appoint the first one this morning who showed
						himself most deserving of the office. Milly says from the way she smiled when she said
						it, they're all sure she means to choose the first one who plays an April Fool joke.
						She'd put it so strong to 'em how silly it was, that there ain't a child in school you
						could hire to run <pb id="VAB1852-093" n="93"/> the risk of being appointed fool for the
						day. So I think she's coming out ahead as usual."</p>
					<p>"After all," said Bud Hines, "there's some lessons to be got out of those old tricks we
						used to play. For instance, the pocketbook tied to a string. Seems to me that everything
						in life worth having has a string tied to it, and just as I am about to pick it up, Fate
						snatches it out of my hands."</p>
					<p>"Don't you believe it, Buddy," said Bowser, cheerfully; "you take notice those
						pocketbooks on strings are always empty ones, and they don't belong to us, so we have no
						business grabbing for them or feeling disappointed because we can't get something for
						nothing."</p>
					<p>But Bud waved aside the interruption mechanically.</p>
					<p>"Then there's the <hi rend="i">gifts</hi> with strings <pb id="VAB1852-094" n="94"/>
						tied to 'em," he continued. "My wife has a rich aunt who is always sending her presents,
						and writing, 'Understand this is for <hi rend="i">you</hi>, Louisy. You're too generous,
						and I don't want anybody but your own deserving self to wear this.' Now out in the
						country here, my wife doesn't have occasion to wear handsome clothes like them once a
						year, while they'd be the very thing for Clara May, off at Normal School. But not a
						feather or a ribbon can the child touch because her great-aunt bought them expressly for
						her ma. Goodness knows she'd have a thousand times more pleasure in seeing Clara May
						enjoy them, than knowing they were lying away in bureau drawers doing nobody any good.
						When she takes 'em out at house-cleaning times I say, 'Ma,' says I, 'deliver me from
						gifts with strings tied to 'em. I'd rather <pb id="VAB1852-095" n="95"/> have a ten-cent
						bandanna, all mine, to have and to hold or to give away as pleased me most, than the
						finest things your Aunt Honigford's money could buy, if I had to account to her every
						time I turned around in them.'</p>
					<p>"When I give anything I <hi rend="i">give</hi> it, and don't expect to come back,
						spying around ten years afterward to see if it's worn out, or cracked, or faded, or
						broken. That's my doctrine."</p>

					<p>Marion Holmes, driving along the country road in the old miller's antiquated chaise,
						drew rein in front of a low picket gate, overhung by mammoth snowball bushes. Down the
						path, between the rows of budding lilacs and japonicas, came an old gentleman in a
						quaintly cut, long-tailed coat. He was stepping along nimbly, although he leaned hard on
						his gold-headed cane.</p>



					<pb id="VAB1852-096" n="96"/>
					<p>"'A man he was to all the country dear,'" quoted Marion softly to herself as the
						minister's benign face smiled a greeting through his big square-bowed spectacles. "I
						know he must have been Goldsmith's friend, and I wish I dared ask him how long he lived
						in the Deserted Village." But all she called out to him as he stopped with a courtly
						bow, under the snowball bushes, was a cheery good morning and an invitation to take a
						seat beside her if he wanted to drive to the Cross-Roads store.</p>
					<p>"Thank you, Miss Polly," he answered, "that is my destination. I am on my way there for
						a text."</p>
					<p>"For a what?" exclaimed Marion in surprise, turning the wheel for him to step in beside
						her.</p>
					<p>"For a text for my Easter sermon," he explained as they drove on in the <pb
							id="VAB1852-097" n="97"/> warm April sunshine. "Ah, I see, Miss Polly, you have not
						discovered the school of philosophers that centres around the Cross-Roads store. Well,
						it's not to be wondered at; few people do. I spent a winter in Rome, when I was younger,
						and one of my favourite walks was up on the Pincian Hill. The band plays in the
						afternoons, you know, and tourists flock to see the queen drive by. There is a charming
						view from the summit --the dome of St. Peters against the blue Italian sky, the old
						yellow Tiber crawling along under its bridges from ruin to ruin, and the immortal city
						itself, climbing up its historic hills. And on the Pincio one meets everybody,
						--soldiers and courtiers, flower girls and friars, monks in robes of every order, and
						pilgrims from all parts of the world.</p>
					<p>"The first time I was on the hill, <pb id="VAB1852-098" n="98"/> as I wandered among
						the shrubbery and flowers, I noticed a row of moss-grown pedestals set along each side
						of the drive for quite a distance. Each ped- estal bore the weather-beaten bust of some
						old sage or philosopher or hero.</p>
					<p>"They made no more impression on my mind then, than so many fence-posts, but later I
						found a workman repairing the statuary one day. He had put a new nose on the mutilated
						face of an old philosopher, and that fresh white nasal appendage, standing out jauntily
						in the middle of the ancient gray visage, was so ludicrous I could not help smiling
						whenever I passed it. I began to feel acquainted with the old fellow, as day after day
						that nose forced my attention. Sometimes, coming upon him suddenly, the only familiar
						face in a city full of strangers, I felt that he was an old <pb id="VAB1852-099" n="99"
						/> friend to whom I should take off my hat. Then it became so that I rarely passed him
						without recalling some of his wise sayings that I had read at college. Many a time he
						and his row of stony-eyed companions were an inspiration to me in that way.</p>
					<p>"It was so that I met these men at the Cross-Roads. They scarcely claimed my attention
						at first. Then one day I heard one of them give utterance to a time-worn truth in such
						an original way that I stopped to talk to him.</p>
					<p>"Trite as it was, he had hewn it himself out of the actual experiences of his own life.
						It was the result of his own keen observation of human nature. Set as it was in his
						homely, uncouth dialect, it impressed me with startling force. Then I listened to his
						companions, and found that they, too, were sometimes worthy of pedestals. <pb
							id="VAB1852-100" n="100"/> Unconsciously to themselves they have often given me
						suggestions for my sermons. Ah, it's a pity that the backwoods has no Pincio on which to
						give its philosophers to posterity!"</p>

					<p>Half an hour later as they drove homeward, Marion glanced at her companion. "No text
						this time," she laughed, breaking the reverie into which the old minister had fallen.
						"Your sages said nothing but 'good morning, sir,' and there wasn't a single suggestion
						of Easter in the whole store, except the packages of egg dyes, and some impossible
						little chocolate rabbits. Oh, yes, --those two little boys playing on the doorstep.
						Tommy Bowser had evidently taken time by the forelock and sampled his father's dyes, for
						he had a whole hatful of coloured eggs, and was teaching that little Perkins <pb
							id="VAB1852-101" n="101"/> boy how to play 'bust.' He was an apt scholar, for while I
						watched he won five of Tommy's eggs and never cracked his own. You should have seen
						them."</p>
					<p>"Oh, I saw them," said the minister, with a smile. "It was those same little lads who
						suggested the text for my Easter sermon."</p>
					<p>Marion gave a gasp of astonishment. "Would you mind telling me <hi rend="i">how?"</hi>
						she exclaimed.</p>
					<p>"It came about very naturally. There they stood with their hands full of the Easter
						eggs, with never a thought of what they symbolised --the breaking shell-- the rising of
						this little embryo earth-existence to the free full-winged life of the Resurrection.
						They were too intent on their little game, on their small winnings and losings, to have
						a thought for higher things. As I <pb id="VAB1852-102" n="102"/> watched them it
						occurred to me how typical it was of all the children of men, and instantly that text
						from Luke flashed into my mind: <hi rend="i">'Their eyes were holden.'</hi> Do you
						remember? It was when the two disciples went down to Emmaus. I often picture it," mused
						the old man after a little pause. "The green of the olive groves, the red and white of
						the blossoming almond-trees, the late afternoon sunshine, and those two discouraged
						fishermen trudging along the dusty road. They were turning away from a lost cause and a
						buried hope, too absorbed in their overwhelming grief to see that it was the risen Lord
						Himself who walked beside them. Not till the end of their journey did they know why it
						was that their hearts had burned within them as He talked with them by the way. Their
						eyes were holden.</p>



					<pb id="VAB1852-103" n="103"/>
					<p>"How typical that is, too, Miss Polly. Sometimes we go on to the end of life, missing
						the comfort and help that we might have had at every step, because we look up at our
						Lord only through eyes of clay, and hold communion with him as with a stranger. Yes, I
						shall certainly make that the subject of my Easter sermon, Miss Polly. Thank you for
						helping me discover it."</p>
					<p>That next Sunday as Marion sat in church beside the old miller, her gaze wandered from
						the lilies in the chancel to the faces of the waiting congregation. Bud Hines was there
						and Bowser, Cy Akers, and even Perkins's oldest, whose game of "bust" had suggested the
						helpful sermon of the morning. Marion studied the serious, weather-beaten faces with new
						interest. "It is not in spiritual things alone <pb id="VAB1852-104" n="104"/> that our
						eyes are holden," she said to herself. "I have been looking at only the commonplace
						exterior of these people. It takes a man like the old minister to recognise
						unpedestalled virtues and to set them on the Pincio they deserve."</p>
				</div2>





				<pb id="VAB1852-105" n="105"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">Chapter VII</head>

					<p><hi rend="b">T</hi>HE old saying that "there are always two sides to a story" has worn
						a deep rut into the popular mind. It has been handed down to us so often with an air of
						virtuous rebuke, that we have come to regard the individual who insists on his two-sided
						theory as the acme of all that is broad-minded and tolerant. But in point of fact, if
						two sides is all he sees, he is only one remove from the bigot whose mental myopia
						limits him to a single narrow facet.</p>
					<p>Even such a thing as a May-day picnic is polyhedral. The little school-mistress, who
						was the chief promoter of the one at the Cross-Roads, would have called it a
						parallelopiped, if she had been there that morning, to have <pb id="VAB1852-106" n="106"
						/> seen the different expressions portrayed on the faces of six people who were
						interested in it.</p>
					<p>The business side of the picnic appealed to Bowser.As he bustled around, dusting off
						cases of tinned goods that he had long doubted his ability to dispose of, and climbed to
						the top shelves for last summer's shop-worn cans of sardines and salmon, as he sliced
						cheese, and counted out the little leathery lemons that time had shrivelled, his smile
						was as bland as the May morning itself. One could plainly see that he regarded this
						picnic as a special dispensation of Providence, to help him work off his old stock.</p>
					<p>There were no loungers in the store. Field and garden claimed even the idlest, and only
						the old miller, who had long ago earned his holiday, sat in the sun on the porch
						outside, with his chair <pb id="VAB1852-107" n="107"/> tipped back against the wall. At
						intervals a warm breath from the apple orchard, in bloom across the road, touched his
						white hair in passing, and stirred his memory until he sat oblivious of his
						surroundings. He was wholly unmindful of the gala stir about him, save when Polly
						recalled his wandering thoughts. She, keenly alive to every sensation of the present,
						stood beside him with her hand on his shoulder, while she waited for her picnic basket
						to be filled.</p>
					<p>"Isn't it an ideal May-day, grandfather?" she exclaimed. "It gives me a real Englishy
						feeling of skylarks and cuckoos and cowslips, of primroses and village greens. I think
						it is dear of the little school-ma'am to resurrect the old May-pole dance, and give the
						children some idea of 'Merrie old England' other than the dates and dust of its ancient
						history." <pb id="VAB1852-108" n="108"/> Unconsciously beating time with light
						fingertips on the old man's shoulder, she began to hum half under her breath:
						
						<q rend="blockquote">
							<lg rend="center">
								<l>"'And then my heart with rapture thrills,</l>
								<l>And dances with the daffodills-o-dills--</l>
								<l>And dances with the daffodils!'"</l>
							</lg>
						</q></p>
					
					<p>Suddenly she broke off with a girlish giggle of enjoyment. "Listen, grandfather.
						There's little Cora Bowser upstairs, rehearsing her speech while she dresses. Isn't it
						delicious to be behind the scenes!"</p>
					<p>Through an open bedroom window, a high-pitched, affected little voice came shrilly down
						to them: "'If you're <hi rend="i">wa-</hi>king, call me <hi rend="i">early!</hi> Call me
							<hi rend="i">early,</hi> mother dear!'"</p>
					<p>"Now, Cora," interrupted the maternal critic, "you went and forgot to make your bow;
						and how many times have I told you about turning <pb id="VAB1852-109" n="109"/>att the
						Crosezroas your toes out? You'll have to begin all over again." Then followed several
						beginnings, each brought to a stop by other impatient criticisms. There were so many
						pauses in the rehearsal and reminders to pay attention to manners, commas, and
						refractory ribbons, that when Cora was finally allowed to proceed, it was in a tearful
						voice punctuated with sobs, that she declared, "'To-morrow will be the ha-happiest day
						of all the g-glad new year.'"</p>
					<p>"'Uneasy lies the head that wears the crown,'" quoted the old miller with a smile, as
						Mrs. Bowser's parting injunction reached their ears.</p>
					<p>"Now, Cora, for goodness' sake, don't you forget for one minute this whole enduring
						day, that them daisies on your crown came off your teacher's best hat, and have to be
						put back on. <pb id="VAB1852-110" n="110"/> If you move around much to the picnic you
						might lose some of 'em. Best keep pretty quiet anyway, or your sash will come unpinned,
						and the crimp will all get out of your hair. Wish I'd thought to iron them plaits before
						I unbraided 'em. They'd have been lots frizzier."</p>
					<p>It was a very stiffly starched, precise little Queen o' the May who came down the steep
						back stairs into the store. She stepped like a careful peacock, fearing to ruffle a
						feather of her unrivalled splendour. Her straight flaxen hair, usually as limp as a
						string, stood out in much crimped profusion from under her gilt paper crown. Polly could
						not decide whether the pucker on the little forehead came from anxiety concerning the
						borrowed daisies which starred her crown, or the fact that it was too tightly <pb
							id="VAB1852-111" n="111"/> skewered to the royal head by a relentless hat-pin.</p>
					<p>One of the picnic wagons was waiting at the door, and as Bowser lifted her in among her
						envious and admiring schoolmates, Polly saw with sympathetic insight which of its many
						sides the picnic parallelopiped was presenting to the child in that proud moment. The
						feeling of supreme importance that it bestowed is a joy not permitted to all, and rarely
						does it come to any mortal more than once in a lifetime.</p>
					<p>But for every Haman, no matter how resplendent, sits an unmoved Mordecai in the king's
						gate. So to this little Sheba of the Cross-Roads there was one who bowed not down.
						Perkins's oldest, on the front seat beside the driver, had no eyes for her. He scarcely
						looked in her direction. His <pb id="VAB1852-112" n="112"/> glances were all centred on
						the baskets which Bowser was packing in around his feet. He smelled pickles and pies and
						ham sandwiches. He knew of sundry tarts and dressed eggs in his own basket, and wild
						rumours had reached his ears that Miss Polly intended to stand treat to the extent of
						Bowser's entire stock of bananas and candy. Aside from hopes of a surreptitious swim in
						the creek and a wild day in the woods, his ideas of a picnic were purely prandial.</p>
					<p>Across the road, Miss Anastasia Dill, peeping through the blinds, watched the wagon
						rattle off with its merry load. Long after the laughing voices had passed beyond her
						hearing, she still stood there, one slender hand holding back the curtain, and the other
						shading her faded blue eyes, as she gazed absently after them. It was the sunshine of
							<pb id="VAB1852-113" n="113"/> another May-day she was looking into. Presently with a
						little start she realised that she was not out in the cool green woods with a May-basket
						in her hands, brimming over with anemones. She was all alone in her stuffy little
						parlour, with its hair-cloth furniture and depressing crayon portraits. And the canary.
						was chirping loudly for water, and the breakfast cups were still unwashed. But for once,
						heedless of her duties, even unmindful of the fact that she had left the shutters open,
						and the hot sun was streaming across her cherished store carpet, she drew a chair up to
						the marble-topped centre table, and deliberately sat down. There was a pile of
						old-fashioned daguerreotypes in front of her. She opened them one by one, and then took
						up another that lay by itself on a blue beaded mat. So the face it dimly pictured held a
							<pb id="VAB1852-114" n="114"/> sacred place, apart, in her memory. When her eyes had
						grown misty with long gazing, she lifted a book from its place beside the family Bible.
						It was bound in red leather, and it had a quaint wreath of embossed roses around the
						gilt letters of its title, "The Album of the Heart." It was an autograph album, and as
						she slowly turned the pages she remembered that every hand that had traced a sentiment
						or a signature therein had once upon a time gathered anemones with her in some one of
						those other May-days.</p>
					<p>Then she turned through the pages again. Of all that circle of early friends not one
						was left to give her a hand-clasp. She had friends in plenty, but the old ones --the
						early ones-- the roots of whose growth had twined with hers in the intimacy known only
						to childhood, were all gone. The <pb id="VAB1852-115" n="115"/> May-day picnic brought
						only a throb of pain to gentle Miss Anastasia, for to her it was but the lonely echo of
						a "voice that was still."</p>
					<p>Bud Hines watched the wagon drive away with far different emotions. He had happened to
						come into the store for a new hoe, as the gay party started. "It's all foolishness," he
						grumbled to the miller, "to lose a whole day's schooling while they go gallivanting
						around the country for nothing. They'll ride ten miles to find a place to eat their
						dinner in, and pass by twenty on the way nicer than the one they finally pick out.
						They'd better be doing sums in school, or grubbing weeds out of the garden, instead of
						playing 'frog in the meadow' around a fool British May-pole."</p>
					<p>He looked around inquiringly as if he expected his practical listener to <pb
							id="VAB1852-116" n="116"/> agree with him. But all the sympathy he got from the old
						miller was one of the innumerable proverbs he seemed to keep continually on tap. "'All
						work and no play makes Jack a dull boy,' Bud. Life is apt to be little but sums and
						grubbing for the youngsters by and by, so let them make the most of their May-days
						now."</p>
					
					<p>The sequels of picnics are also polyhedral. Miss Anastasia, lingering at her front gate
						in the early twilight, that she might enjoy to the last moment the orchard odours that
						filled all the balcony outdoors, heard the rattle of returning wheels. She had had a
						pleasant day, despite the tearful retrospection of the morning, for she had attended the
						great social function of the neighbourhood, the monthly missionary tea. It had brought
							<pb id="VAB1852-117" n="117"/> immeasurable cheer, and now she was returning with a
						comfortable conviction that she was to be envied far above any of her neighbours. The
						consciousness of having on her best gown, of being the mistress of the trim little home
						to which she was going, of freedom from a hundred harassing cares that she had heard
						discussed that afternoon, all combined to make her supremely contented with her lot.</p>
					<p>"Poor children," she sighed, as the tired, dirty little picnickers were lifted from the
						wagon across the road. "They look as if the game hadn't been worth the candle. I'm glad
						that I've outgrown such things."</p>
					<p>Perkins's oldest, having soaked long in the cold creek, and sampled every dinner-basket
						with reckless abandon till he could sample no more, sat doubled up in the straw of the
						wagonbed. <pb id="VAB1852-118" n="118"/> He was white about the mouth, and had he been
						called upon to debate the time-worn question, "Resolved, that there is more pleasure in
						pursuit than in possession," the tarts and sandwiches of that day's picnic would have
						furnished several dozen indisputable arguments for the affirmative.</p>
					<p>The dishevelled little queen sat beside him, tired out by her day's wild frolic, with
						starch and frizzes all gone.</p>
					<p>As she was lifted over the wheel, and put down on the doorstep, a limp little bunch of
						woe, Miss Anastasia heard her bewailing her fate. She had lost the stars from her crown,
						the borrowed daisies that must be reckoned for on the morrow. The amused listener smiled
						to herself under cover of the twilight, as she heard Bowser's awkward attempts at
						consolation, for all the comfort that he could muster was <pb id="VAB1852-119" n="119"/>
						an old saw learned from the miller: "Never mind, Cora, pa's mighty sorry for his little
						girl. But you know: 
						
						<q rend="blockquote">
							<lg rend="center">
								<l>"'When a man buys meat he buys bone,</l>
								<l>And when he buys land he buys stone.</l>
								<l>You must take the bad with the good.'"</l>
							</lg>
						</q>
					</p>
				</div2>




				<pb id="VAB1852-120" n="120"/>
				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">Chapter VIII</head>

					<p><hi rend="b">T</hi>HERE is something in the air of June that stirs even insentient
						things with a longing to blossom. Staid old universities blaze out with the gala colours
						of commencement week, when the month of roses is ushered in, and on every college campus
						the social life of the student year comes to flower in the crowning exercises of
						class-day.</p>
					<p>One wonders sometimes if the roots, burrowing underground in order to fill the bush
						overhead with myriads of roses, have any share in the thrill of success at having
						produced such a wealth of sweetness and beauty. But there need be no surmise about
						college florescence. Faculties may beam with complacency on their yearly cluster of <pb
							id="VAB1852-121" n="121"/> full-blown graduates, the very walls of the gray old
						universities may thrill as they echo the applause of admiring audiences, but the
						greatest pride is not felt within the college town itself where the student life
						centres. It is back in the roots that have made college life possible. Back in some
						parental existence that daily sinks itself farther into the commonplace in order that
						some son or daughter may blossom into the culture of arts and belles-lettres. The
						Jacqueminot that flaunts its glory over the garden wall may not sweeten life for the
						fibres that lift it, but the valedictorian who flaunts his diploma and degree in the
						classic halls of some sea-board college may be glorifying the air of some little
						backwoods village a thousand miles inland. Even the Cross-Roads are bound with a network
						of such far-reaching roots <pb id="VAB1852-122" n="122"/> to the commencements of
						Harvard and Yale.</p>
					<p>It was Cy Akers's boy who came home this June, a little lifted up, perhaps, by the
						honours he had won; thoroughly impressed with the magnitude of his own knowledge and the
						meagreness of other peoples', but honestly glad at first to get back to the old home and
						neighbours.</p>
					<p>The family pride in him was colossal. Old Cy encouraged his visits to the Cross-Roads
						store, inventing excuses for going which he considered the acme of subtle diplomacy. But
						his motives were as transparent as a child's. Illiterate himself, he wanted his
						neighbours to see what college had done for his boy in the way of raising him head and
						shoulders above them all. And the boy was good-naturedly compliant. He was as willing to
						show off <pb id="VAB1852-123" n="123"/> mentally as he had been to lend a hand in the
						wheat harvest, and demonstrate what football training had done for him in the way of
						developing muscle.</p>
					<p>Like Perkins's oldest, his education had begun with the primer of the Cross-Roads. He
						could remember the time when he, too, had ignorantly believed this to be the only store
						in the universe, and wondered if there were enough people living to consume all its
						contents. Now he smiled to himself when he looked around the stuffy little room and saw
						the same old butter firkins crowding the --apparently --same old calico and crockery,
						and looked up at the half-dozen hams still swinging sociably from the low rafters.</p>
					<p>Time had been, too, when he thought the men who gossiped around its rusty stove on
						Saturday afternoons knew <pb id="VAB1852-124" n="124"/> everything. Like Perkins's
						oldest, he had unquestioningly formulated the creed of his boyhood from their
						conversations, and he smiled again when he recalled how he had been warped in those
						early days by their prejudices and short-sighted opinions.</p>
					<p>The smile extended outwardly when he walked into their midst to find them repeating the
						same old saws about the weather, and the way the country was going to the dogs. Yet in
						his salad days these time-honoured prognostications had seemed to him the wisdom of
						seers and sages.</p>
					<p>Probably it was the thought that he had travelled far beyond the narrow confines of the
						Cross-Roads that gave his conversation a patronising tone. But the Cross-Roads refused
						to be patronised. He learned that on the day of his arrival. It was the first <pb
							id="VAB1852-125" n="125"/> lesson of a valuable post-graduate course. That a man away
						from home may be Mister Robert Harrison Hamilton Akers, with all the A. B.'s and LL.
						D.'s after his name that an educational institution can bestow; but as soon as he sets
						foot again on his native heath, where he has gone through the vicissitudes of boyhood,
						he is shorn of titles and degrees as completely as Samson was shorn of his locks, and
						his strength straightway falls from him. He is nobody but Bobby Akers, and everybody
						remembers when he robbed birds' nests, and stole grapes, and played hooky, and was a
						little freckle-faced, snub-nosed neighbourhood terror. A man cannot maintain his
						importance long in the face of such reminiscences. No amount of university culture is
						going to lay the ghost of youthful indiscretions, and he might as well put <pb
							id="VAB1852-126" n="126"/> his patronising proclivities in his pocket. They will not
							be tolerated by those who have patted him on the head when he wore roundabouts.</p>
					
					<p>It was Saturday afternoon, but it was also the and of the wheat-harvest, and the men
						were afield who usually gathered on the Cross-Roads porch to round up the week over
						their pipes and plugs of chewing tobacco. Only three chairs were tilted back against the
						wall, and on these, with their heels caught over the front rungs, sat Bowser, the old
						miller, and Robert Akers.</p>
					<p>The whirr of reaping machines came faintly up from the fields and near by, where
						several acres of waving yellow grain still stood uncut, a bob-white whistled cheerily.
						No one was talking. "Knee-deep in June" would have voiced the thoughts of the trio, for
							<pb id="VAB1852-127" n="127"/> they were "Jes' a sort o' lazein' there," with their
						hats pulled over their eyes, enjoying to the utmost the perfect afternoon. Every breeze
						was redolent with red clover and wild honeysuckle, and vibrant with soothing country
						sounds.</p>
					<p>"Who is that coming up the road?" asked the miller, as a team and wagon appeared over
						the brow of the hill.</p>
					<p>"They wabble along like Duncan Smith's horses," answered the storekeeper, squinting his
						eyes for a better view. "Yes, that's who it is. That's Dunk on the top of the load.
						Moving again, bless Pete!"</p>
					<p>As the wagon creaked slowly nearer, a feather bed came into view, surmounting a motley
						collection of household goods, and perched upon it, high above the jangle of her jolting
						tins and crockery, sat Mrs. Duncan Smith. A <pb id="VAB1852-128" n="128"/> clock and a
						looking-glass lay in her lap, and, like a wise virgin, in her hands she carefully bore
						the family lamp. From frequent and anxious turnings of her black sunbonnet, it was
						evident that she was keeping her weather eye upon the chicken-coop, which was bound to
						the tail-board of the wagon by an ancient clothes-line.</p>
					<p>A flop-eared dog trotted along under the wagon. Squeezed in between a bureau and the
						feather bed, two shock-headed children sat on a flour barrel, clutching each other at
						every lurch of the crowded van to keep from losing their balance.</p>
					<p>"Howdy, Dunk!" called the storekeeper, as the dusty pilgrims halted in front of the
						porch. "Where are you bound now?"</p>
					<p>"Over to the old Neal place," answered the man, handing the reins to <pb
							id="VAB1852-129" n="129"/> his wife, and climbing stiffly down over the wheel. Going
						around to the back of the wagon, he unstrapped a kerosene can which swung from the pole
						underneath.</p>
					<p>"Gimme a gallon of coal-ile, Jim," he said. "I don't want to be left in the dark the
						first night, anyway. It takes awhile to git your bearings in a strange place, and it's
						mighty confusing to butt agin a half-open door where you've always been used to a plain
						wall, and it hurts like fire to bark your shins on a rocking-chair when you're steering
						straight for bed, and hain't no idee it's in the road. This time it'll be a little more
						so than usual," he added, handing over the can. "The house backs up agin a graveyard,
						you know. Sort o' spooky till you git used to it."</p>
					<p>"What on earth did you move there <pb id="VAB1852-130" n="130"/> for?" asked Bowser.
						"They say the place is ha'nted."</p>
					<p>"To my mind the dead make better neighbours than the living," came the tart reply from
						the depths of the black sunbonnet. "At any rate, they mind their own business."</p>
					<p>"Oh, come now, Mrs. Smith," began Bowser, good-naturedly. "Maybe you've been
						unfortunate in your choice of neighbours."</p>
					<p>"I've had a dozen different kinds," came the emphatic answer. '"This'll make the
						twelfth move in eight years, so you can't say that I'm speaking from hearsay."</p>
					<p>"Twelve moves in eight years!" exclaimed Bowser, as the wagon went lurching and
						creaking on through the dust. "There's gipsy blood in that Dunk Smith, sure as you live.
						Seems like that family can't be satisfied anywhere; <pb id="VAB1852-131" n="131"/>
						always thinking they can better themselves by changing, and always getting out of the
						frying-pan into the fire. There wa'n't no well in the place where they settled when they
						was first married, and they had to carry water from a spring. The muscle put into
						packing that water up-hill those six months would have dug a cistern, but they were too
						short-sighted to see that. They jest played Jack and Jill as long as they could stand
						it, and then moved to a place where there was a cistern already dug. But there wa'n't
						any fruit on that place. If they'd have set out trees right away they'd have been eating
						from orchards of their own planting by this time. But they thought it was easier to move
						to where one was already set out.</p>
					<p>"Then when they got to a place where they had both fruit and water, <pb
							id="VAB1852-132" n="132"/> it was low, and needed draining. The water settled around
						the house, and they all had typhoid that summer. Oh, they've spent enough energy packing
						up and moving on and settling down again in new places to have fixed the first one up to
						a queen's taste. They seem to be running a perpetual Homeseeker's Excursion. Well, such
						a life might suit some people, but it would never do for me."</p>
					<p>'"But such a life has some things in its favour," put in Rob Akers, always ready to
						debate any question that offered, for the mere pleasure of arguing. "It keeps a man from
						getting into a rut, and develops his ability to adapt himself to any circumstance. A man
						who hangs his hat on the same peg for fifty or sixty years gets to be so dependent on
						that peg that he would be uncomfortable if it were suddenly denied him. <pb
							id="VAB1852-133" n="133"/> Now Dunk Smith can never become such a slave to habit.
						Then, too, moving tends to leave a man more unhampered. He gradually gets rid of
						everything in his possessions but the essentials. He hasn't a garret full of old
						claptraps, as most people have who never move from under their ancestral roof-trees. You
						saw for yourself, one wagon holds all his household goods and gods.</p>
					<p>"It is the same way with a man mentally. If he stays in the spot where his forefathers
						lived, in the same social conditions, he is apt to let his upper story accumulate a lot
						of worn-out theories that he has no earthly use for; all their old dusty dogmas and
						cobwebbed beliefs. He will hang on to them as on to the old furniture, because he
						happened to inherit them. If he would move once in awhile, keep <pb id="VAB1852-134"
							n="134"/> up with the times, you know, he'd get rid of a lot of rubbish. It is
						especially true in regard to his religion. All those old superstitions, for instance,
						about Jonah and the whale, and Noah's ark and the like.</p>
					<p>"He hangs on to them, not because he cares for them himself, but because they were his
						father's beliefs, and he doesn't like to throw out anything the old man had a sentiment
						for. Now, as I say, if he'd move once in awhile --do some scientific thinking and
						investigating on his own account-- he'd throw out over half of what he holds on to now.
						He'd cut the most of Genesis out of his Bible, and let Job slide as a myth. One of the
						finest bits of literature, to be sure, that can be found anywhere, but undoubtedly
						fiction. The sooner a man moves on untrammelled, I say, by those old heirlooms <pb
							id="VAB1852-135" n="135"/> of opinion, the better progress he will make."</p>
					<p>"Toward what?" asked the old miller, laconically. "Dunk's moving next door to the
						graveyard." There was a twinkle in his eye, and the young collegian, who flattered
						himself that his speech was making a profound impression, paused with the embarrassing
						consciousness that he was affording amusement instead.</p>
					<p>"The last time I went East to visit my grandson," said the old man, meditatively, "his
						wife showed me a mahogany table in her dining-room which she said was making all her
						friends break the tenth commandment. It was a handsome piece of furniture, worth a small
						fortune. It was polished till you could see your face in it, and I thought it was the
						newest thing out in tables till she told me she'd <pb id="VAB1852-136" n="136"/>
						rummaged it out of her great-grandmother's attic, and had it 'done over' as she called
						it. It had been hidden away in the dust and cobwebs for a lifetime because it had been
						pronounced too time-worn and battered and scratched for longer use; yet there it stood,
						just as beautiful and useful for this generation to spread its feasts on as it was the
						day it was made. Every whit as substantial, and aside from any question of sentiment, a
						thousand times more valuable than the one that Dunk Smith drove past with just now. His
						table is modern, to be sure, but it's of cheap pine, too rickety to serve even Dunk
						through his one short lifetime of movings.</p>
					<p>"I heard several lectures while I was there, too. One was by a man who has made a name
						for himself on both sides of the water as a scientist and a liberal thinker. He took up
							<pb id="VAB1852-137" n="137"/> Genesis, all scratched and battered as it is by
						critics, and showed us how it had been misunderstood and misconstrued. And by the time
						he'd polished up the meaning here and there, so that we could see the original grain of
						the wood, what it was first intended to be, it seemed like a new book, and fitted in
						with all the modern scientific ideas as if it had been made only yesterday.</p>
					<p>"There it stood, like the mahogany table that had been restored after people thought
						they had stowed it away in the attic to stay. Just as firm on its legs, and as
						substantial for this generation to put its faith on, as it was in the days of the
						Judges.</p>
					<p>"Take an old man's word for it, Robert, who has lived a long time and seen many a
						restless Dunk Smith fling out his father's old heirlooms, in his <pb id="VAB1852-138"
							n="138"/> fever to move on to something new. Solid mahogany, with all its dust and
						scratches, is better than the modern flimsy stuff, either in faith or furniture, that he
						is apt to pick up in its stead."</p>
				</div2>


				<pb id="VAB1852-139" n="139"/>
				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">Chapter IX</head>
					<p><hi rend="b">T</hi>HE booming of distant cannon had been sounding at intervals since
						midnight, ushering in the Fourth, but Bowser, although disturbed in his slumbers by each
						reverberation, did not rouse himself to any personal demonstration until dawn. Then his
						patriotism manifested itself in a noisy tattoo with a hammer, as he made the front of
						his store gay with bunting, and nailed the word <hi rend="i">Welcome</hi> over the door,
						in gigantic letters of red, white, and blue.</p>
					<p>When he was done, each window wore a bristling eyebrow of stiff little flags, that gave
						the store an air of mild surprise. The effect was wholly unintentional on Bowser's part,
						and, unconscious of the likeness to human <pb id="VAB1852-140" n="140"/> eyes he had
						given his windows, he gazed at his work with deep satisfaction.</p>
					<p>But the expression was an appropriate one, considering all the astonishing sights the
						old store was to look upon that day. In the woodland across the railroad track, just
						beyond Miss Anastasia Dill's little cottage, preparations were already begun for a grand
						barbecue. Even before Bowser had finished tacking up his flags, the digging of the
						trench had begun across the way, and the erection of a platform for the speakers. In one
						corner of the woodland a primitive merry-go-round had already been set in place, and the
						first passenger train from the city deposited an enterprising hoky-poky man, a peanut
						and pop-corn vender, and a lank black-bearded man with an outfit for, taking
						tin-types.</p>



					<pb id="VAB1852-141" n="141"/>
					<p>By ten o'clock the wood-lot fence was a hitching-place for all varieties of vehicles,
						from narrow sulkies to cavernous old carryalls. A haze of thick yellow dust, extending
						along the pike as far as one could see, was a constant accompaniment of fresh arrivals.
						Each newcomer emerged from it, his Sunday hat and coat powdered as thickly as the
						wayside weeds. Smart side-bar buggies dashed up, their shining new tops completely
						covered with it. There was a great shaking of skirts as the girls alighted, and a great
						flapping of highly perfumed handkerchiefs, as the young country beaux made themselves
						presentable, before joining the other picnickers.</p>
					<p>Slow-going farm wagons rattled along, the occupants of their jolting chairs often
						representing several generations, for the drawing power of a <pb id="VAB1852-142"
							n="142"/> Fourth of July barbecue reaches from the cradle to the grave.</p>
					<p>The unusual sight of such a crowd, scattered through the grove in gala attire, was
						enough of itself to produce a holiday thrill, and added to this was the smell of
						gunpowder from occasional outbursts of firecrackers, the chant of the hoky-poky man, and
						the hysterical laughter of the couples patronising the merry-go-round, as they clung
						giddily to the necks of the wooden ostriches and camels in the first delights of its
						dizzy whirl.</p>
					<p>"Good as a circus, isn't it?" exclaimed Robert Akers, pausing beside the bench where
						the old miller and the minister sat watching the gay scene. "I'm having my fun walking
						around and taking notes. It is amusing to see how differently the affair impresses
						people, and what seems to <pb id="VAB1852-143" n="143"/> make each fellow happiest.
						Little Tommy Bowser, for instance, is in the seventh heaven following the hoky-poky man.
						He gets all that people leave in their dishes for helping to drum up a crowd of patrons.
						Perkins's boy sticks by the merry-go-round. He has spent every cent of his own money,
						and had so many treats that he's spun around till he's so dizzy he's cross-eyed. One old
						fellow I saw back there is simply sitting on the fence grinning at everything that goes
						by. He's getting his enjoyment in job lots."</p>
					<p>"Sit down," said the minister, sociably moving along the bench to make room beside him
						for the young man. "Mr. Holmes and I are finding our amusement in the same way, only we
						are not going around in search of it. We are catching at it as it drifts by."</p>



					<pb id="VAB1852-144" n="144"/>
					<p>"What has happened to Mrs. Teddy Mahone?" exclaimed Rob, as a red-faced woman with an
						important self-conscious air hurried by. "She seems ubiquitous this morning, and as
						proud as a peacock over something. One would think she were the mistress of ceremonies
						from her manner."</p>
					<p>"Or hostess, rather," said the miller. "She met me down by the fence on my arrival, and
						held out her hand as graciously as if she were a duchess in her own drawing-room, and I
						an invited guest.</p>
					<p>"'Gude marnin' to yez, Mr. Holmes,' she said. 'I hope ye'll be afther enjyin' yerself
						the day. If anything intherferes wid yer comfort ye've but to shpake to Mahone about it.
						He's been appinted <hi rend="i">constable</hi> for the occasion, ye understhand. If I do
						say it as oughtn't, he can carry the title wid the best av <pb id="VAB1852-145" n="145"
						/> 'im; him six fut two in his stockin's, an' the shtar shinin' on his wes'cut loike
						he'd been barn to the job.'</p>
					<p>"Then she turned to greet some strangers from Morristown, and I heard her introducing
						herself as Mrs. <hi rend="i">Constable</hi> Mahone, and repeating the same instructions
						she had given me, to report to her husband, in case everything was not to their
						liking."</p>
					<p>Both listeners laughed at the miller's imitation of her brogue, and the minister
						quoted, with an amused smile:
						
						<q rend="blockquote">
							<lg rend="center">
								<l>"'For never title yet so mean could prove,</l>
								<l>But there was eke a mind, which did that title love.'</l>
							</lg>
						</q>
						
						It is a pity we cannot dress more of them in 'a little brief authority.' It seems
						to be a means of grace to a certain class of Hibernians. It has Americanised the
						Mahones, for instance. <pb id="VAB1852-146" n="146"/> You'll find no patriots on the
						ground to-day more enthusiastic than Mr. and Mrs. Constable Mahone. Fourth of July will
						be an honoured feast-day henceforth in their calendar. It is often surprising how
						quickly a policeman's buttons and billy will make a good citizen out of the wildest
						bog-trotter that ever brandished a shillalah."</p>
					
					<p>Later, in subsequent wanderings around the grounds, the young collegian spied the
						little schoolmistress helping to keep guard over the cake-table. He immediately crossed
						over and joined her. She was looking unusually pretty, and there was an amused gleam in
						her eyes as she watched the crowds, which made him feel that she was viewing the scene
						from his standpoint; that he had found a kindred spirit.</p>
					<p>"What incentive to patriotism do <pb id="VAB1852-147" n="147"/> you see in all this,
						Miss Helen?" he asked, when he had induced her to turn over her guardianship of the
						cake-table to some one else, and join him in his tour among the boisterous
						picnickers.</p>
					<p>"None at all --yet," she answered. "I suppose that will come by and by with the songs
						and speeches. But all this foolishness seems a legitimate part of the celebration to me.
						You remember Lowell says, 'If I put on the cap and bells, and made myself one of the
						court fools of King Demos, it was less to make his Majesty laugh than to win a passage
						to his royal ears for certain serious things which I had deeply at heart.' It takes a
						barbecue and its attendant attractions to draw a crowd like this. See what a hotch-potch
						it is of all nationalities. Now that Schneidmacher family never would have driven ten
						miles in this heat <pb id="VAB1852-148" n="148"/> and dust simply to hear the band play
						'Hail, Columbia,' and Judge Jackson make one of his spread-eagle speeches on the Duty of
						the American Citizen. Neither would the O'Gradys or any of the others who represent the
						foreign element in the neighbourhood. Even Young America himself, the type we see here,
						is more willing to come and bring his best girl on account of the diversions
						offered."</p>
					<p>"Well, that may be so," was the reluctant assent, "but if this is a sample of the
						Fourth of July observances all over the country I can't help feeling sorry for Uncle
						Sam. Patriotism has sadly degenerated from the pace that Patrick Henry set for it."</p>
					<p>"The old miller says not," answered the little schoolmistress. "I made that same
						complaint last Washington's Birth- day, when I was trying to work my <pb
							id="VAB1852-149" n="149"/> school up to proper enthusiasm for the occasion. He
						recalled the drouth of the summer before when nearly every well and creek and pond in
						the township went dry. Cattle died of thirst, gardens dried up like brick-kilns, and
						people around here were almost justified in thinking that the universe would soon be
						entirely devoid of water. The skies were like brass, and there was no indication of rain
						for weeks. But one day there was a terrific earthquake shock. It started all the old
						springs, and opened new ones all over this part of the country, and the water gushed out
						of the earth where it had been pent up all the time, only waiting for some such touch to
						call it forth. 'And you're afraid that patriotism is going dry in this generation,' he
						said to me. 'But it only takes some shock like the sinking of the <hi rend="i"
							>Maine</hi>, or some sudden <pb id="VAB1852-150" n="150"/> menace to the public
						safety, to start a spring that will gush from Plymouth Rock to the Golden Gate. There is
						a deep underground vein in the American heart that no drouth can ever dry. Maybe it does
						not come to the surface often, but it can always be depended on in time of need.'"</p>
					<p>The speakers for the day began to arrive, and Rob, seeing the crowds gravitating toward
						the grand stand, took the little schoolmistress to the bench where the miller had
						stationed himself.</p>
					<p>"Watch that old Scotchman just in front of us," whispered the girl, "Mr. Sandy
						McPherson. Last Thanksgiving there was a union service in the schoolhouse. After the
						sermon 'America' was sung, and that old heathen stood up and roared out through it all,
						at the top of his voice, every word of 'God <pb id="VAB1852-151" n="151"/> Save the
						Queen!' Wasn't that flaunting the thistle in our faces with a vengeance? I am sure that
						he will repeat the performance to-day. Think of the dogged persistence that refuses to
						succumb to the fact that we have thrown off the British yoke! The very day we are
						celebrating that event, he'll dare to mix up our national hymn with 'God Save the
						King.'"</p>
					<p>It was as she had predicted. As the band started with a great clash of brazen
						instruments, and the whole company rose to the notes of "Amer- ica," Sandy McPherson's
						big voice, with its broad Scotch burr, rolled out like a bass drum:
						
						<q rend="blockquote">
							<lg rend="center">
								<l>"'Thy choicest gifts in store,</l>
								<l>On <hi rend="i">him</hi> be pleased to pour.</l>
								<l>Long may <hi rend="i">he</hi> reign.'"</l>
							</lg>
						</q>
					</p>
					
					<p>It drowned out every voice around him. "He ought to be choked," exclaimed <pb
							id="VAB1852-152" n="152"/> Rob, in righteous indignation, as they resumed their seats.
						"To-day of all days! The old Tory has been living in this country for forty-five years,
						and a good living he's gotten out of it, too, for himself and family. Nobody cares what
						he sings on his own premises, but he might have the decency to keep his mouth shut on
						occasions of this kind, if he can't join with us."</p>
					<p>There was a gleam of laughter in the little schoolmistress's eyes as she replied: "If
						the truth were known I have no doubt but that this Fourth of July celebration is very
						like the pie in Mother Goose's song of sixpence, when her four and twenty blackbirds
						were baked in a pie. If this pie could be opened, and the birds begin to sing according
						to their sentiments, there would be a wonderful diversity of <pb id="VAB1852-153"
							n="153"/> tunes. One would be twittering the 'Marseillaise,' and another 'Die Wacht am
						Rhein,' and another echoing old Sandy's tune. America was in too big a hurry to serve
						her national pie, I am afraid. Consequently she put it in half prepared, and turned it
						out half baked. The blackbirds should have had their voices tuned to the same key before
						they were allowed to become vital ingredients of such an important dish."</p>
					<p>"In other words," laughed Rob, "you'd reconstruct the enfranchisement laws. Make the
						term of probationary citizenship so long that the blackbird would have time to change
						his vocal chords, or even the leopard his anarchistic spots, before he would be
						considered fit to be incorporated in the national dish. By the way, Miss Helen, have you
						heard Mrs. Mahone's <pb id="VAB1852-154" n="154"/> allegory of the United Pudding bag?
						You and she ought to collaborate. Get the storekeeper to repeat it to you sometime."</p>
					<p>"You needn't laugh," responded the little schoolmistress, a trifle tartly. "You know
						yourself that scores of emigrants are given the ballot before they can distinguish
						'Yankee Doodle' from 'Dixie,' and that is only typical of their ignorance in all matters
						regarding governmental affairs. Too many people's idea of good citizenship is like the
						man's 'who kept his private pan just where 'twould catch most public drippings.' There
						is another mistaken idea loose in the land," she continued, after a moment. "That is,
						that a great hero must be a man who has a reputation as a great soldier. I wish I had
						the rewriting of all the school histories. They are better now than <pb id="VAB1852-155"
							n="155"/> when I studied them, but there is still vast room for improvement. I had to
						learn page after page of wars. Really, war and history were synonyms then as it was
						taught in the schools. Every chapter was gory, and we were required to memorise the
						numbers killed, wounded, and captured in every battle, from the French and Indian
						massacres, down to the last cannon-shot of the sixties. That is all right for government
						records and reference libraries, but when we give a text-book to the rising generation,
						the accounts of battles and the glorifying thereof would be better relegated to the
						foot-notes. It is loyal statesmanship that ought to be exalted in our school histories.
						We ought to make our heroes out of the legislators who cannot be bribed and public men
						who cannot be bought, and the honest private citizen who <pb id="VAB1852-156" n="156"/>
						<hi rend="i">lives</hi> for his country instead of dying for it."</p>
					<p>The old miller beside her applauded softly, leaning over to say, as the overture by the
						band came to a close with a grand clash, "If ever the blackbirds are tuned to one key,
						Miss Helen, America will know whom to thank. Not the legislators, but the patriotic
						little schoolma'ams all over their land who are serving their country in a way her
						greatest generals cannot do."</p>
					
					<p>All day the Cross-Roads store raised its bristling eyebrows of little flags, till the
						celebration came to a close. Savoury whiffs of the barbecued meats floated across to it,
						vigorous hand-clapping and hearty cheers rang out to it between the impassioned words of
						excited orators. Later there were the fireworks, and more rag-time music by <pb
							id="VAB1852-157" n="157"/> the band, and renewed callings of the hoky-poky man. But
						before the moon came up there was a great backing of teams and scraping of turning
						wheels, and a gathering together of picnic-baskets and stray children.</p>
					<p>"Well, it's over for another year," said Bowser, welcoming the old miller, who had
						crossed the road and taken a chair on the porch to wait until the crowds were out of the
						way.</p>
					<p>"Those were fine speeches we had this afternoon, but seemed to me as if they were plumb
						wasted on the majority of that crowd. They applauded them while they were going off,
						same as they did the rockets, but they forget in the next breath." As Bowser spoke, a
						rocket whizzed up through the tree tops, and the old miller, looking up to watch the
						shining trail fade out, saw that the sky was full of stars.</p>



					<pb id="VAB1852-158" n="158"/>
					<p>"That's the good of those speeches, Bowser," he said. "'<hi rend="i">To leave a wake,
							men's hearts and faces skyward turning.'</hi> I hadn't noticed that the stars were out
						till that rocket made me look up. The speeches may be forgotten, but they will leave a
						memory in their wake that give men an uplook anyhow."</p>
				</div2>





				<pb id="VAB1852-159" n="159"/>
				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">Chapter X</head>

					<p>"<hi rend="b">G</hi>UESS who's come to board at the Widder Powers's for the month of
						August?" It was Bowser who asked the question, and who immediately answered it himself,
						as every man on the porch looked up expectantly.</p>
					<p>"Nobody more nor less than a <hi rend="i">multimillionaire!</hi> The big boot and shoe
						man, William A. Maxwell. Mrs. Powers bought a bill of goods this morning as long as your
						arm. It's a windfall for <hi rend="i">her</hi>. He offered to pay regular
						summer-resort-hotel prices, because she's living on the old farm where he was born and
						raised, and he fancied getting back to it for a spell."</p>
					<p>"Family coming with him?" queried Cy Akers, after a moment's meditation <pb
							id="VAB1852-160" n="160"/> over the surprising fact that a millionaire with the world
						before him should elect such a place as the Cross-Roads in which to spend his
						vacation.</p>
					<p>"No, you can bet your bottom dollar they're not. And they're all abroad this summer or
							<hi rend="i">he'd</hi> never got here. They'd had him dragged off to some fashionable
						watering-place with them. But when the cat's away the mice'll play, you know. Mrs.
						Powers says it is his first visit here since his mother's funeral twenty years ago, and
						he seems as tickled as a boy to get back.</p>
					<p>"Yesterday evening he followed the man all around the place while she was getting
						supper. She left him setting up in the parlour, but when she went in to ask him out to
						the table, he was nowhere to be seen. Pretty soon he came walking around the corner of
						the <pb id="VAB1852-161" n="161"/> house with a pail of milk in each hand, sloshing it
						all over his store clothes. He'd done the milking himself, and seemed mightily set up
						over it."</p>
					<p>"Lawzee! Billy Maxwell! Don't I remember him?" exclaimed Bud Hines. "Seems like 'twas
						only yesterday we used to sit on the same bench at school doin' our sums out of the same
						old book. The year old man Prosser taught, we got into so much devilment that it got to
						be a regular thing for him to say, regular as clockwork, almost, 'I'll whip Bud Hines
						and Billy Maxwell after the first arithmetic class this morning.' I don't s'pose he ever
						thinks of those old times since he's got to be one of the Four Hundred. Somehow I can
						hardly sense it, his bein' so rich. He never seemed any smarter than the rest of us.
						That's the way of the world, though, <pb id="VAB1852-162" n="162"/> seesaw, one up and
						the other down. Of course it's my luck to be the one that's down. Luck always was
						against me."</p>
					<p>"There he is now," exclaimed the storekeeper, and every head turned to see the stranger
						stepping briskly along the platform in front of the depot, on his way to the telegraph
						office.</p>
					<p>He had the alertness of glance and motion that comes from daily contact with city
						corners. If there was a slight stoop in his broad shoulders, and if his closely cut hair
						and beard were iron gray, that seemed more the result of bearing heavy responsibilities
						than the token of advancing years. His immaculate linen, polished low-cut shoes, and
						light gray business suit would have passed unnoticed in the metropolis, but in this
						place, where coats and collars were in evidence only on Sunday, they <pb
							id="VAB1852-163" n="163"/> gave him the appearance of being on dress parade.</p>
					<p>Perkins's oldest eyed him as he would a zebra or a giraffe, or some equally interesting
						curiosity escaped from a Zoo. He had heard that his pockets were lined with gold, and
						that he had been known to pay as much as five dollars for a single lunch. Five dollars
						would board a man two weeks at the Cross-Roads.</p>
					<p>With his mouth agape, the boy stood watching the stranger, who presently came over to
						the group on the porch with smiling face and cordial outstretched hand. Despite his gray
						hair there was something almost boyish in the eagerness with which he recognised old
						faces and claimed old friendships. Bowser's store had been built since his departure
						from the neighbourhood, so few of the congenial <pb id="VAB1852-164" n="164"/> spirits
						accustomed to gather there were familiar to him. But Bud Hines and Cy Akers were old
						schoolfellows. When he would have gone up to them with old-time familiarity, he found a
						certain restraint in their greeting which checked his advances.</p>
					<p>If he thought he was coming back to them the same freckle-faced, unconventional country
						lad they had known as Billy Maxwell, he was mistaken. He might feel that he was the same
						at heart; but they looked on the outward appearance. They saw the successful man of the
						world who had outstripped them in the race and passed out of their lives long ago. They
						could not conceive of such a change as had metamorphosed the boy they remembered into
						the man who stood before them, without feeling that a corresponding change must have <pb
							id="VAB1852-165" n="165"/> taken place in his attitude toward them.</p>
					<p>They were not conscious that this feeling was expressed in their reception of him. They
						laughed at his jokes, and indulged in some reminiscences, but he felt, in a dim
						subconscious way, that there was a barrier between them, and he could never get back to
						the old familiar footing.</p>
					<p>He turned away, vaguely disappointed. Had he dared to dream that he would find his lost
						youth just as he had left it? The fields and hills were unchanged. The very trees were
						the same, except that they had added a few more rings to their girth, and threw a larger
						circling shade. But the old chums he had counted on finding had not followed the same
						law of growth as the trees. The shade of their sympathies had narrowed, not expanded,
							<pb id="VAB1852-166" n="166"/> with the passing years, and left him outside their
						contracted circle.</p>
					<p>Perkins's oldest, awed by reports of his fabulous wealth, could hardly find his tongue
						when the distinguished visitor laid a friendly hand on his embarrassed tow head, and
						inquired about the old swimming-hole, and the mill-dam where he used to fish. But the
						boy's interest grew stronger every minute as he watched him turning over the limited
						assortment of fishing tackle. The men he knew had outlived such frivolous sports. It was
						a sight to justify one's gazing open-mouthed, --a grown man deliberately preparing for a
						month's idleness.</p>
					<p>If the boy could have seen the jointed rods, the reels, the flies, all the expensive
						angler's outfit left behind in the Maxwell mansion; if he could have known of the tarpon
						this man <pb id="VAB1852-167" n="167"/> had caught in Florida bays, and the fishing he
						had enjoyed in northern waters, he would have wondered still more; wondered how a man
						could be considered in his right mind who deliberately renounced such privileges to come
						and drop a common hook, on a pole of his own cutting, into the shallow pools of the
						Cross-Roads creek.</p>
					<p>After his purchases no one saw him at the store for several days, but the boy, dodging
						across lots, encountered him often, --a solitary figure wandering by the mill stream, or
						crashing through the woods with long eager strides; lying on the orchard grass sometimes
						with his hat pulled over his eyes; leaning over the pasture bars in the twilight, and
						following with wistful glance the little foot-path stretching white across the meadows.
						A pathetic sight to eyes wise enough to <pb id="VAB1852-168" n="168"/> see the pathos,
						--a world-weary, middle-aged man in vain quest of his lost boyhood.</p>
					<p>On Sunday, Polly, looking across the church from her place in the miller's pew,
						recognised the stranger in their midst, and straightway lost the thread of the sermon in
						wondering at his presence. She had gone to school with his daughter, Maud Maxwell. She
						had danced many a german with his son Claude. They lived on the same avenue, and passed
						each other daily; but this was the first time she had seen him away from the shadow of
						the family presence, that seemed to blot out his individuality.</p>
					<p>She had thought of him only as Maud's father, a simple, good-natured nonentity in his
						own household. A good business man, but one who could talk nothing but leather, and
						whose <pb id="VAB1852-169" n="169"/> only part in the family affairs was to furnish the
						funds for his wife and children to shine socially.</p>
					<p>"Oh, your father's opinion doesn't count," she had heard Mrs. Maxwell say on more than
						one occasion, and the children had grown up, unconsciously copying her patronising
						attitude toward him. As Polly studied his face now in the light of other surroundings,
						she saw that it was a strong, kindly one; that it was not weakness which made him yield
						habitually, until he had become a mere figurehead in his own establishment. It was only
						that his peace-loving nature hated domestic scenes, and his generosity amounted to
						complete self-effacement when the happiness of his family was concerned.</p>
					<p>His eyes were fixed on the chancel with a wistful reminiscent gaze, and <pb
							id="VAB1852-170" n="170"/> Polly read something in the careworn face that touched her
						sympathy. "Grandfather," she said, at the close of the service, "let's be neighbourly
						and ask Mr. Maxwell home to dinner with us. He looks lonesome."</p>
					<p>She was glad afterward that she had suggested it, when she recalled his evident
						pleasure in the old man's company. There were chairs out under the great oak-trees in
						the yard, and the two sat talking all afternoon of old times, until the evening shadows
						began to grow long across the grass. Then Polly joined them again, and sat with them
						till the tinkle of home-going cowbells broke on the restful stillness of the country
						Sabbath.</p>
					<p>"All the orchestras in all the operas in the world can't make music that sounds as
						sweet to me as that does," said Mr. Maxwell, raising his head from <pb id="VAB1852-171"
							n="171"/> the big armchair to listen. Then he dropped it again with a sigh.</p>
					<p>"It rests me so after the racket of the city. If Julia would only consent, I'd sell out
						and come back to-morrow. But she's lost all interest in the old place. I'm country to
						the core, but she never was. She took to city ways like a duck to water, just as soon as
						she got away from the farm, and she laughs at me for preferring katydids to the whirr of
						electric cars."</p>
					<p>A vision rose before the old miller of a little country girl in a pink cotton gown, who
						long ago used to wait, bright-eyed and blushing, at the pasture bars, for Billy to drive
						home the cows. Many a time he had passed them at their trysting-place. Then he recalled
						the superficial, ambitious woman he had met years afterward when he visited his son. He
						shook <pb id="VAB1852-172" n="172"/> his head when he thought of her renouncing her
						social position for the simple pastoral life her husband longed to find the way back to.
						Presently he broke the silence of their several reveries by turning to Polly.</p>
					<p>"What's that piece you recited to me the other night, little girl, about old times? Say
						it for Mr. Maxwell." And Polly, clasping her hands in her lap, and looking away across
						the August meadows, purple with the royal pennons of the ironweed, began the musical old
						poem:
						
						<q rend="blockquote">
							<lg rend="center">
								<l>"'Ko-ling, ko-lang, ko-linglelingle,</l>
								<l>Way down the darkening dingle</l>
								<l rend="ti-1">The cows come slowly home.</l>
								<l>(And old-time friends and twilight plays</l>
								<l>And starry nights and sunny days</l>
								<l>Come trooping up the misty ways,</l>
								<l rend="ti-1">When the cows come home.)</l>
							</lg>
							<lg rend="center">
								<l>"'And over there on Merlin Hill</l>
								<l>Hear the plaintive cry of the whippoorwill.</l>



								<pb id="VAB1852-173" n="173"/>
								<l>And the dewdrops lie on the tangled vines,</l>
								<l>And over the poplars Venus shines,</l>
								<l>And over the silent mill.</l>
							</lg>
							<lg rend="center">
								<l>"'Ko-ling, ko-lang, ko-linglelingle,</l>
								<l>With ting-aling and jingle</l>
								<l rend="ti-1">The cows come slowly home.</l>
								<l>(Let down the bars, let in the train</l>
								<l>Of long-gone songs and flowers and rain,</l>
								<l>For dear old times come back again,</l>
								<l rend="ti-1">When the cows come home.)'"</l>
							</lg>
						</q>
					</p>
					
					<p>>Once as Polly went on, she saw the tears spring to his eyes at the line "and
						mother-songs of long-gone years," and she knew that the
						
						<q rend="blockquote">
							<lg rend="center">
								<l>"same sweet sound of wordless psalm,</l>
								<l>The same sweet smell of buds and balm,"</l>
							</lg>
						</q>
						
						that had been his delight in the past, were his again as he listened. But, much to
						her surprise, as she finished, he rose abruptly, and began a hurried leave-taking. She
						understood his <pb id="VAB1852-174" n="174"/> manner, however, when his mood was
						revealed to her a little later.</p>
					<p>At her grandfather's suggestion she walked down to the gate with him, to point out a
						short cut across the fields to Mrs. Powers's. Outside the gate he paused, hat in
						hand.</p>
					<p>"Miss Polly," he began, as if unconsciously taking her into his confidence, "old times
						never come back again. Seems as if the bottom had dropped out of everything. I've done
						my best to resurrect them, but I can't do it. I thought if I could once get back to the
						old place I could rest as I've not been able to rest for twenty years --that I'd have a
						month of perfect enjoyment. But something's the matter.</p>
					<p>"Many a time when I've been off at some fashionable resort I've thought I'd give a
						fortune to be able to drop <pb id="VAB1852-175" n="175"/>aIt the dross-roas my hook in
						your grandfather's millstream, and feel the old thrill that I used to feel when I was a
						boy. I tried it the day I came --caught a little speckled trout, the kind that used to
						make me tingle to my finger ends, but somehow it didn't bring back the old sensation. I
						just looked at it a minute and put it back in the water, and threw my pole away.</p>
					<p>"Even the swimming-hole down by the mill didn't measure up to the way I had remembered
						it. I've fairly ached for a dip into it sometimes, in the years I've been gone. Seemed
						as if I could just get into it once, I could wash myself clear of all the cares and
						worries of business that pester a man so. That was a disappointment, too. The change is
						in me, I guess, but nothing seems the same."</p>
					<p>Polly knew the reason. He had <pb id="VAB1852-176" n="176"/>Esa Rolmes tried so long to
						mould his habits to fit his wife's exacting tastes, that he had succeeded better than he
						realised. He could not analyse his feelings enough to know that it was the absence of
						long accustomed comforts that made him vaguely dissatisfied with his surroundings; his
						luxuriously appointed bathroom, for instance; the perfect service of his carefully
						trained footmen. Mrs. Powers's noisy table, where with great clatter she urged every one
						"to fall to and help himself," jarred on him, although he was unconscious of what caused
						the irritation. As for the rank tobacco Bowser furnished him when he had exhausted his
						own special brand of cigars with which he had stocked his satchel, it was more than
						flesh and blood could endure. That is, flesh and blood that had acquired the pampered
						taste of a millionaire whose wife <pb id="VAB1852-177" n="177"/> is fastidous, and only
						allows first-class aromas in the way of the weed.</p>
					<p>But Polly knew another reason that his vacation had been a failure. She divined it as
						the little Yale pin, stuck jauntily into the front of her white dress, met the touch of
						her caressing fingers. The girl in the pink cotton gown was long dead, and the woman who
						had grown up in her stead had no part in the old scenes that he still fondly clung to,
						with a sentiment she ridiculed because she could not understand. <hi rend="i">>There
							must always be two when you turn back searching for your lost Eldorado, and even the
							two cannot find it, unless they go hand in hand.</hi></p>
					
					<p>Next day Bowser had another piece of news to impart. "Mr. Maxwell went home this
						morning. He told Mrs. Powers it was like taking a vacation <pb id="VAB1852-178" n="178"
						/> in a graveyard, and he'd had enough. He'd have to get back to work again. So he paid
						her for the full month, and took the first train back to the city."</p>
					<p>"Well, I'll be switched!" was Bud Hines's comment. "If I had as much money as he's got,
						I'd never bother my head about work. I'd sit down and take it easy all the rest of my
						born days."</p>
					<p>"I don't know," answered Bowser, meditatively. "I reckon a man who's worked the way Mr.
						Maxwell has, gets such a big momentum on to himself that he can't stop, no matter how
						bad he wants a vacation."</p>
					<p>"He's a fool for coming back here for it," said Bud Hines, looking out across the
						fields that stretched away on every side in unbroken monotony.</p>
					<p>But miles away, in his city office, the busy millionaire was still haunted <pb
							id="VAB1852-179" n="179"/> by an unsatisfied longing for those same level meadows.
						Glimpses of the old mill-stream and the willows still rose before him in tantalising
						freshness, and whenever he closed his tired eyes, down twilight paths, where tinkling
						cowbells called, there came again the glimmer of a little pink gown, to wait for him as
						it had waited through all the years, beside the pasture bars.</p>
				</div2>




				<pb id="VAB1852-180" n="180"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">Chapter XI></head>

					<p><hi rend="b">T</hi>HE seat was an empty starch-box on the Cross-Roads porch, its
						occupant a barefoot boy with a torn straw hat pulled far down over his eyes. To the
						casual observer one of the most ordinary of sights, but to one possessed of sympathetic
						powers of penetration into a boy's inner consciousness there was a suggestion of the
						tragic. Perkins's oldest had that afternoon in school been told to write a composition
						on September. It was to be handed in next morning. It was the hopelessness of
						accomplishing the fact even in ons, not to mention the limited time of a dozen short
						hours, that had bound him, a little Prometheus, to the starch-box, with the vulture of
						absolute despair tearing at his vitals.</p>



					<pb id="VAB1852-181" n="181"/>
					<p>Two other boys had been assigned the same subject, and the three had kicked the dust up
						wrathfully all the way from the schoolhouse, echoing an old cry that had gone up ages
						before from the sons of Jacob, under the lash of the Egyptian, "How can we make bricks
						without straw?"</p>
					<p>"Ain't nothin' to say 'bout September," declared Riley Hines, gloomily, "and I'll be
						dogged if I say it. I'm goin' to get my sister to write mine fer me. She'll do it ef I
						tease long enough, and give her something to boot."</p>
					<p>"I'll ask paw what to say," declared Tommy Bowser. "He won't write it for me, but he'll
						sort o' boost me along. Then if it ain't what she wants, <hi rend="i">I</hi> won't be to
						blame. I'll tell her paw said 'twas all right."</p>
					<p>This shifting of responsibility to <pb id="VAB1852-182" n="182"/> paternal shoulders
						restored the habitual expression of cheerfulness to Tommy's smudgy face, but there was
						no corresponding smile on Sammy's. There was no help to be had in the household of
						Perkins.</p>
					<p>That was why he was waiting on the starch-box while Tommy was sent on an errand. It was
						in the vain hope that Tommy would return and apply for his "boost" and share it with him
						before darkness fell. He was a practical child, not given to whimsical reflections, but
						as he sat there in desperate silence, he began wondering what the different customers
						would have to say if they were suddenly called upon, as he had been that afternoon, to
						write about September.</p>
					<p>Mrs. Powers, for instance, in her big crape bonnet, with its long wispy veil trailing
						down her back. He was <pb id="VAB1852-183" n="183"/> almost startled, when, as if in
						answer to his thought, she uttered the word that was at the bottom of his present
						trouble, the subject assigned him for composition.</p>
					<p>"Yes, Mr. Bowser, September is a month that I'm never sorry to say goodbye to. What
						with the onion pickle and peach preserves and the house-cleaning to tend to, I'm nearly
						broke down when it's over. There's so many odds and ends to see to on a farm this time
						of year, first in doors and then out. I tell Jane it's like piecing a crazy quilt. You
						can't never count on what a day's going to bring forth in September. You may get a
						carpet up and beat, and have your stove settin' out waiting to be put up, and your
						furniture in a heap in the yard, and the hired man will have to go off and leave it all
						while he takes the cider-mill to <pb id="VAB1852-184" n="184"/> be mended. And you in a
						stew all day long for fear it'll rain before he gets things under shelter.</p>
					<p>"Then it's a sad time to me, too," she exclaimed with a mournful shake of the head in
						the black bonnet. "It was in September I lost my first and third husbands, two of the
						best that ever had tombstones raised to their memory, if I do say it as oughtn't. One
						died on the sixteenth, and his funeral was preached on the eighteenth, and the other
						died fifteen years later on the twenty-third, and we kept him three days, on account of
						waiting till his brother could get here from Missouri. So you see that makes nearly a
						week altogether of mournful anniversaries for me every September."</p>
					<p>Another breath and she had reached the three tombstones, and talking volubly on her
						favourite subject, she <pb id="VAB1852-185" n="185"/> completed her purchases and went
						out. But her conversation had not lightened the woes of the little Prometheus on the
						starch-box. Despair still gnawed on. House-cleaning worries and onion pickle, and
						reminiscences of two out of three departed husbands, might furnish material for Mrs.
						Powers's composition, should the fates compel her to write one, but there was no straw
						of a suggestion for Sammy Perkins, and again he cried out inwardly as bitterly as the
						oppressed of old had cried out against Pharaoh.</p>
					<p>A man in a long, sagging linen duster was the next comer. He squeaked back and forth in
						front of the counter in new high-heeled boots, and talked incessantly while he made his
						purchases, with a clumsy attempt at facetiousness.</p>
					<p>"Put in a cake of shaving-soap, too, Jim," he called, passing his hand over <pb
							id="VAB1852-186" n="186"/> the black stubble on his chin. "County court begins
						to-morrer. Reckon the lawyers will shave everything in sight when it comes to their
						bills, but I want to be as slick as them. I'll be settin' on the jury all week. Did you
						ever think of it, Jim, that's a mighty interesting way to earn your salt? Jest set back
						and be entertained with the history of all the old feuds and fusses in the county, and
						collect your two bucks a day without ever turning your hand over. Good as a show, and
						dead easy.</p>
					<p>"Only one thing, it sort o' spiles your faith in human nature. The court stenographer
						said last year that in the shorthand he writes, the same mark that stands for lawyer
						stands for liar, too. He! he! he! isn't that a good one? You can only tell which one is
						meant by what comes before it, and this fellow said he'd come to <pb id="VAB1852-187"
							n="187"/> believe that one always fit in the sentence as good as the other. Either
						word was generally appropriate. You miss a lot of fun, Jim, by not getting on the jury.
						I always look forrard to fall on that account."</p>
					<p>No help for Perkins's oldest in <hi rend="i">that</hi> conversation. He waited awhile
						longer. Presently an old gentleman in a long-tailed, quaintly cut black coat, stepped up
						on the porch. He had a gold-headed cane under his arm, and the eyes behind the
						square-bowed spectacles beamed kindly on the little fellow. He stopped beside the
						starch-box a moment with a friendly question about school and the health of the Perkins
						household. The boy's heart gave a jump up into his throat. The old minister knew
						everything. The minister could even tell him what to write in his composition if he
						dared <pb id="VAB1852-188" n="188"/> but ask him. He opened his mouth to form the
						question, but his tongue seemed glued in its place, and the head under the torn hat
						drooped lower in embarrassed silence. His troubled face flushed to the roots of his tow
						hair, and he let the Angel of Opportunity pass him by unchallenged.</p>
					<p>"Will you kindly give me one of those advertising almanacs, Mr. Bowser?" inquired the
						parson, when his packages of tea and sugar had been secured. "I've misplaced mine, and I
						want to ascertain at what hour tomorrow the moon changes."</p>
					<p>"Certainly, certainly!" responded the storekeeper with obliging alacrity, rubbing his
						hands together, and stepping up on a chair to reach the pile on a shelf overhead. "Help
						yourself, sir. I must answer the telephone."</p>
					<p>The parson, slowly studying the <pb id="VAB1852-189" n="189"/> moon's phases as he
						stepped out of the store, did not notice that he had taken two almanacs until one fell
						at his feet. The boy sprang up to return it, but he waved it aside with a courtly sweep
						of his hand.</p>
					<p>"No, my son, I intended to take but one. Keep it. They are for general distribution.
						You will find it full of useful information. Have you ever learned anything about the
						signs of the Zodiac? Here is Leo. I always take an especial interest in this sign,
						because I happened to be born under it. I'm the seventh son of a seventh son, born in
						the seventh month, and I always take it as a good omen, seven being the perfect number.
						You know the ancients believed a man's star largely affected his destiny. You will find
						some interesting historical events enumerated under each month. A good <pb
							id="VAB1852-190" n="190"/> almanac is almost as interesting to study as a good
						dictionary, my boy. I would advise you to form a habit of referring to both of them
						frequently."</p>
					<p>With one of his rare, childlike smiles the good man passed on, and Perkins's oldest was
						left with the almanac in his hands. For awhile he studied the signs of the Zodiac, in
						puzzled awe, trying to establish a relationship between them and the man they
						surrounded, whose vital organs were obligingly laid open to public inspection,
						regardless of any personal inconvenience the display might cause him.</p>
					<p>Then he turned to the historical events. There was one for each day in the month. On
						Sunday, the first, eighteen hundred and ninety-nine, had occurred the Japanese typhoon.
						Friday, the sixth, sixteen hundred and <pb id="VAB1852-191" n="191"/> twenty, the <hi
							rend="i">Mayflower</hi> had sailed. Mahomet's birth had set apart the eleventh in five
						hundred and seventy. The founding of Mormonism, Washington's Farewell, and the battle of
						Marathon were further down the list, but it was all Greek to Perkins's oldest. Any one
						of these items would have been straw for the parson. Out of the <hi rend="i"
							>Mayflower</hi>, Mahomet, Mormonism, or Marathon, each one of them the outgrowth of
						some September, he could have pressed enough literary brick to build a fair sky-scraping
						structure that would have been the wonder of all who gazed upon it. This time the boy
						looked his Angel of Opportunity in the face and did not recognise it as such.</p>
					<p>The gate clicked across the road and he turned his head. Miss Anastasia Dill was going
						up the path, her arms <pb id="VAB1852-192" n="192"/> full of goldenrod and white and
						purple asters. September was a poem to Miss Anastasia, but the boy looked upon goldenrod
						and the starry asters simply as meadow weeds. The armful of bloom brought no suggestion
						to him. On the morrow Riley Hines would hand in two pages of allusions to them,
						beginning with a quotation from Whittier's "Autumn Thoughts," and ending with a couplet
						from Pope, carefully copied by Maria Hines from the "Exercises for Parsing" in the back
						of her grammar.</p>
					<p>Somebody's supper-horn blew in the distance, and, grown desperate by Tommy's long
						absence and the lateness of the hour, he took his little cracked slate from the strap of
						books on the floor beside him, and laid it across his knees. Then with a stubby pencil
						that squeaked dismally in its <pb id="VAB1852-193" n="193"/> passage across the slate,
						he began copying bodily from the almanac the list of historical events enumerated
						therein, just as they stood, beginning with the Japanese typhoon on the first, and
						ending "<hi rend="i">Volunteer</hi> beat <hi rend="i">Thistle</hi>" on the thirtieth,
						eighteen hundred and eighty-seven.</p>
					<p>Then he began to copy a few agricultural notes, inserted as side remarks for those who
						relied on their almanacs as guide-posts to gardening. "Gather winter squashes now. They
						keep better when stored in a warm dry place. Harvest sugar beets when the leaves turn
						yellowish green, etc."</p>
					<p>He was bending painfully over this task when a shadow fell across his slate, and,
						looking up, he saw the old miller looking over his shoulder.</p>
					<p>"Doing your sums?" he asked, with a friendly smile. "Let's see if you do <pb
							id="VAB1852-194" n="194"/> them the way I was taught when I was a lad." He held out
						his hand for the slate. There had been a bond of sympathy between the two ever since
						Christmas eve, when a certain pair of skates had changed owners, and now, although the
						boy's voice trembled almost out of his control, he managed to stammer out the reply that
						he was trying to write a composition.</p>
					<p>The old man looked from the straggling lines on the slate, then at the open almanac,
						then down at the boy's troubled face, and understood. Drawing a chair across the porch
						he sat down beside him, and, catching the furtive, scared side-glance cast in his
						direction, he plunged at once into a story.</p>
					<p>It was about a shepherd boy who went out to fight a giant, and the king insisted on
						lending him his armour. <pb id="VAB1852-195" n="195"/> But he couldn't fight in the heavy
						helmet and the coat of mail. The shield was in his way, and the spear more than he could
						lift. So he threw it aside, and going down to a little brook, chose five small pebbles,
						worn smooth by the running water. And with these in his hand, and only the simple sling
						he was accustomed to use every day, he went out against the Philistine giant, and slew
						him in the first round.</p>
					<p>Perkins's oldest wondered what the story had to do with his composition. He wasn't
						looking for a personal application. He had not been brought up at Sunday schools and
						kindergartens. But all of a sudden he realised that the miller meant him; that his
						depending on Tommy, or the customers, or the almanac, to furnish him ideas, was like
						going out in Saul's armour, and that he could only come to failure in that, <pb
							id="VAB1852-196" n="196"/> because it wouldn't fit him; that he could hit the mark the
						little schoolmistress had in mind for him, only with the familiar sling-shot of his own
						common every-day personal experiences.</p>
					<p>Maybe the old miller recognised that it was a crisis in the little fellow's life, for
						he stayed beside him with helpful hints and questions, until the slate was full. When he
						carried it home in the gloaming it no longer bore the items from the almanac. There were
						other remarks straggling across it, not so well expressed, perhaps, but plainly
						original. They were to the effect that September is the month you've got to go back to
						school when you don't want to, 'cos it's the nicest time of all to stay out-doors,
						neither too hot nor too cold. There's lots of apples then, and it's the minister's
						birthday. He's the seventh son of <pb id="VAB1852-197" n="197"/> a seventh son, and Dick
						Wiggins says if you're that you can pick Wahoo berries in the dark of the moon and make
						med'cine out of them, that will cure the bone-break fever every time, when nothing else
						in the world will. Then followed several items of information that he had discovered for
						himself, in his prowls through the September woods, about snakes and tree-toads, as to
						their habits at that season of the year. It closed with a suggestive allusion to the
						delights of sucking cider from the bung of a barrel through a straw.</p>
					<p>Next day the little schoolmistress shook her head over the composition that Riley Hines
						handed in, and laid it aside with a hopeless sigh. She recognised too plainly the hand
						of Maria in its construction. The sentiments expressed therein were as foreign <pb
							id="VAB1852-198" n="198"/> to Riley's nature as they would have been to a woodchuck's.
						She took up Tommy Bowser's. Alas, four-syllabled words were not in Tommy's daily
						vocabulary, nor were the elegant sentences under his name within the power of his
						composition. Plainly it was the work of a plagiarist.</p>
					<p>She went through the pile slowly, and then wrote on the blackboard as she had promised,
						the names of the ten whose work was the best and most original. It was then that
						Perkins's oldest had the surprise of his life, for lo! his name, like Abou-ben-Adhem's,
						"led all the rest."</p>
					<p>Again the Cross-Roads had taught him more than the school, --to depend on the resources
						to which nature had adapted him, and never again to attempt to sally forth in borrowed
						armour, even though it be a king's.</p>
				</div2>


				<pb id="VAB1852-199" n="199"/>
				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">Chapter XII</head>

					<p><hi rend="b">I</hi>T was Cy Akers who carried the news to the schoolhouse, galloping
						his old sorrel up to the open door just before the bell tapped for afternoon dismissal.
						He did not dismount, but drawing rein, leaned forward in his saddle, waiting for the
						little school-mistress to step down from the desk to the doorstep. The rows of waiting
						children craned their necks anxiously, but only those nearest the door heard his
						message.</p>
					<p>"Mr. Asa Holmes died this morning," he said. "The funeral is set for to-morrow
						afternoon at four, and you can announce to the children that there won't be any school.
						The trustees thought it would be only proper to close out of respect for him, as he was
							<pb id="VAB1852-200" n="200"/> on the school board over thirty years, and has done so
						much for the community. He's one of the old landmarks, you might say, about the last of
						the old pioneers, and everybody will want to go."</p>
					<p>Before she could recover from the suddenness of the announcement the rider was gone,
						and she was left looking out across the October fields with a lonely sense of personal
						loss, although her acquaintance with the old miller had extended over only two short
						school terms.</p>
					<p>A few minutes later the measured tramp of feet over the worn door-sill began, and forty
						children passed out into the mellow sunshine of the late autumn afternoon. They went
						quietly at first, awed by the tender, reverent words in which the little schoolmistress
						had given them the message to carry <pb id="VAB1852-201" n="201"/> home. But once
						outside, the pent-up enthusiasm over their unexpected holiday, and the mere joy of being
						alive and free on such a day sent them rushing down the road pell-mell, shouting and
						swinging their dinner-pails as they ran.</p>
					<p>A shade of annoyance crossed the teacher's face as she stood watching from the
						doorstep. She wished she had cautioned them not to be so noisy, for she knew that their
						shouts could be plainly heard in the old house whose gables she could see through a
						clump of cedars, farther down the road. It was standing with closed blinds now, and she
						had a feeling that the laughing voices floating across to it must strike harshly across
						its profound silence.</p>
					<p>But presently her face brightened as she watched the children running on <pb
							id="VAB1852-202" n="202"/> in the sunshine, in the joy of their emancipation. Part of
						a poem she had read that morning came to her. She had thought when she read it that it
						was a beautiful way to look upon death, and now it bore a new significance, and she
						whispered it to herself:
						
						<q rend="blockquote">
							<lg rend="center">
								<l>"'Why should it be a wrench to leave this wooden bench?</l>
								<l>Why not with happy shout, run home when school is out?'</l>
							</lg>
						</q>
					</p>
					
					<p>"That's the way the old miller has gone," she said, softly. "His lessons all learned
						and his tasks all done --so well done, too, that he has nothing to regret. I'm glad that
						I didn't stop the children. I am sure that's the way he would want them to go. Dear old
						man! He was always a boy at heart."</p>
					<p>She turned the key in the door behind her presently, and started down <pb
							id="VAB1852-203" n="203"/> the road to Mrs. Powers's, where she boarded. In every
						fence corner the sumachs flamed blood-red, and across the fields, where purple shadows
						trailed their royal lengths behind every shock of corn, the autumn woodlands massed
						their gold and crimson against the sunset sky. She walked slowly, loath to reach the
						place where she must go indoors.</p>
					<p>The Perkins home lay in her way, and as she passed, Mrs. Perkins with a baby on her
						hip, and a child clinging to her skirts, leaned over the gate to speak to her.</p>
					<p>"Isn't it sad," the woman exclaimed, grasping eagerly at this chance to discuss every
						incident of the death and illness, with that love for detail always to be found in
						country districts where happenings are few and interests are strong.</p>



					<pb id="VAB1852-204" n="204"/>
					<p>"They sent for the family Tuesday when he had the stroke, but he couldn't speak to them
						when they got here. They said he seemed to recognise Miss Polly, and smiled when she
						took his hand. She seemed to be his favourite, and they say she's taking it mighty hard
						--harder than any of the rest. It's a pity he couldn't have left 'em all some last
						message. I think it's always a comfort to remember one's dying words when as good a
						person as Mr. Holmes goes. And it's always so nice when they happen to be appropriate,
						so's they can be put on the tombstone afterward. I remember my Aunt Maria worked my
						grandfather's last words into a sampler, with an urn and weeping-willow-tree. She had it
						framed in black and hung in the parlour, and everybody who came to the house admired it.
						It's a pity that the miller <pb id="VAB1852-205" n="205"/> couldn't have left some last
						word to each of 'em."</p>
					<p>"I don't think it was necessary," said the girl, turning away with a choke in her
						voice, as the eloquent face of the old man seemed to rise up before her. "His whole life
						speaks for him."</p>
					<p>Mrs. Perkins looked after the retreating figure regretfully, as the jaunty sailor hat
						disappeared behind a tall hedge. "I wish she hadn't been in such a hurry," she sighed,
						shifting the baby to the other hip. "I would have liked to ask her if she's heard who
						the pall-bearers are to be."</p>
					<p>At the turn in the road the little schoolmistress looked up to see Miss Anastasia Dill
						leaning over her gate. She had just heard the news, and there were tears in her pale
						blue eyes.</p>
					<p>"And Polly's wedding cards were <pb id="VAB1852-206" n="206"/> to have been sent out
						this next week!" she exclaimed after their first words of greeting. "The poor child told
						me so herself when she was here in August on a visit. 'Miss Anastasia,' she said to
						me,'I'm not going abroad for my honeymoon, as all my family want me to do. I'm going to
						bring Jack back here to the old homestead where grandfather's married life began. Some-
						how it was so ideal, so nearly perfect, that I have a feeling that maybe the mantle of
						that old romance will fall on our shoulders. Besides, Jack has never seen grandfather,
						and I tell him it's as much of an education to know such a grand old man as it is to go
						through Yale. So we're coming in October. The woods will have on all their gala colours
						then, and I'll be the happiest bride the sun ever shone on, unless it was my grandmother
						Polly.' And now <pb id="VAB1852-207" n="207"/> to think," added Miss Anastasia,
						tearfully, "none of those plans can come to pass. It's bad luck to put off a wedding.
						Oh, I feel so sorry for her!"</p>
					
					<p>There is an undefined note of pathos in a country funeral that is never reached in any
						other. The little schoolmistress felt it as she walked up the path to the old house
						behind the cedars. The front porch was full of men, who, dressed in their unaccustomed
						best, had the uneasy appearance of having come upon a Sunday in the middle of the week.
						Their heavy boots tiptoed clumsily through the hall, with a painful effort to go
						silently, as one by one the neighbours passed into the old sitting-room and out again.
						The room across the hall had been filled with rows of chairs, and the women who <pb
							id="VAB1852-208" n="208"/> came first were sitting there in a deep silence, broken
						only by a cough now and then, a hoarse whisper or a rustle, as some one moved to make
						room for a newcomer.</p>
					<p>It was a sombre assembly, for every one wore whatever black her wardrobe afforded, and
						many funeral occasions had left an accumulation of mourning millinery in every house in
						the neighbourhood. But the limp crape veils and black gloves and pall-like cashmere
						shawls were all congregated in the dimly lighted parlour. In the old sitting-room it was
						as cheerful and homelike as ever, save for the still form in the centre.</p>
					<p>Through an open window the western sun streamed into the big, hospitable room, across
						the bright home-made rag carpet. The old clock in the corner ticked with the placid,
						steady <pb id="VAB1852-209" n="209"/> stroke that had never failed or faltered, in any
						vicissitude of the generations for which it had marked the changes. No fire blazed on
						the old hearthstone that had warmed the hearts as well as the hands of the whole
						countryside on many a cheerful occasion. But a great bough of dogwood, laid across the
						shining andirons, filled the space with coral berries that glowed like live embers as
						the sun stole athwart them.</p>
					<p>"Oh, if the old room could only speak!" thought Miss Anastasia, when her turn came to
						pass reverently in for a last look at the peaceful face. "There would be no need of
						man's eulogy."</p>
					<p>But man's eulogy was added presently, when the old minister came in and took his place
						beside the coffin of his lifelong friend and neighbour. The men outside the porch closed
						in around the windows to listen. The <pb id="VAB1852-210" n="210"/> women in the back
						rows of chairs in the adjoining room leaned forward eagerly. Those farthest away caught
						only a faltering sentence now and then.</p>
					<p>"A hospitality as warm as his own hearthstone, as wide as his broad acres. ... No man
						can point to him and say he ever knowingly hurt or hindered a fellow creature. ... He
						never measured out to any man a scant bushel. Be it grain or good-will, it was ever an
						overflowing measure. ..." But those who could not hear all that was said could make the
						silent places eloquent with their own recollections, for he had taken a father's
						interest in them all, and manifested it by a score of kindly deeds, too kindly to ever
						be forgotten.</p>
					<p>It was a perfect autumn day, sunny and golden and still, save for the patter <pb
							id="VAB1852-211" n="211"/> of dropping nuts and the dry rustle of fallen leaves. A
						purple haze rested on the distant horizon like the bloom on a ripened grape. Down
						through the orchard, when the simple service was over, they carried their old friend to
						the family burying-ground, and, although voices had choked, and eyes overflowed before,
						there was neither sob nor tear, when the light of the sunset struck across the low
						mound, heaped with its covering of glowing autumn leaves. For if grief has no part in
						the sunset glory that ends the day, or in the perfect fulness of the autumn time, then
						it must indeed stand hushed, when a life comes both to its sunset and its harvest, in
						such royal fashion.</p>
					
					<p>That evening at the Cross-Roads, Bowser lighted the first fire of the season in the
						rusty old stove, for the night <pb id="VAB1852-212" n="212"/> was chilly. One by one the
						men accustomed to gather around it dropped in and took their usual places. The event of
						the day was all that was spoken of.</p>
					<p>"Do you remember what he said last Thanksgiving, nearly a year ago?" asked Bowser. "It
						came back to me as I stood and looked at him to-day, and if I'd never believed in
						immortality before, I'd 'a' had to have believed in it then. The words seemed to fairly
						shine out of his face. He said '<hi rend="i">The best comes after the harvest, when the
							wheat goes to make up blood and muscle and brain; when it's raised to a higher order
							of life in man. And it's the same with me. At eighty-five, when it looks as if I'd
							about reached the end, I've come to believe that "the best is yet to be."'"</hi></p>
					<p>There was a long pause, and Cy Akers said, slowly, "Somehow I can't <pb
							id="VAB1852-213" n="213"/> feel that he is dead. Seems as if he'd just gone away a
						while. But Lord! how we're going to miss him here at the store."</p>
					<p>"No, don't say that!" exclaimed Bud Hines, with more emotion than he had ever been
						known to show before. "Say, how we're going to feel him! I can't get him out of my mind.
						Every time I turn around, most, seems to me I can hear him laugh, and say, 'Don't cross
						your bridge till you come to it, Bud.' That saying of his rings in my ears every time I
						get in the dumps. Seems like he could set the calendar straight for us, all the year
						around. The winters wasn't so cold or the summers so hard to pull through, looking at
						life through his eyes."</p>
					<p>Perkins's oldest crept up unnoticed. He added no word, but deep in his <pb
							id="VAB1852-214" n="214"/> heart lay an impression that all the years to come could
						never erase; the remembrance of a kindly old man who had given him a new gospel, in that
						one phrase, "A brother to Santa Claus;" who had taught him to go out against his
						Philistines with simple directness of aim and whatever lay at hand; who had left behind
						him the philosophy of a cheerful optimist, and the example of a sweet simple life,
						unswerving in its loyalty to duty and to truth.</p>
					
					<p>Over in the old homestead, Polly, standing in the firelight, fair and slender in her
						black gown, looked up at the tall young fellow beside her, and placed two little books
						in his hands. The old house was not her only heritage. The little atlas of the heavens
						was hers also. Standing there in the room <pb id="VAB1852-215" n="215"/> where the
						beloved presence seemed to have left its benediction, Polly told the story of the love
						that had outlived Death. Then across the yellowed page of the old grammar where the
						faded violets lay, two hands met in the same sure clasp that had joined the souls of
						those older lovers, who somewhere beyond the stars were still repeating the old
						conjugation-- "we love --<hi rend="i">for ever!"</hi></p>

					<p rend="center sc">THE END.</p>

				</div2>
			</div1>
		
		</body> 
<back>			
<pb id="VAB1852-216" n="[216]"/>
                 
                                
                <pb id="VAB1852-217" n="[1]"/>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<head rend="left b">L. C. Page and Company's<lb/>
Announcement List<lb/>
of New Fiction</head>

<p>	
<hi rend="b">The Mystery of Murray Davenport.</hi> By
R<hi rend="sc">OBERT</hi> N<hi rend="sc">EILSON</hi> S<hi rend="sc">TEPHENS</hi>, author of "An Enemy to
the King," "Philip Winwood," etc.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth, with six full-page illustrations by H. C.
Edwards . . . . . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>In his latest novel, Mr. Stephens has made a radical
departure from the themes of his previous successes. Turning
from past days and distant scenes, he has taken up American
life of to-day as his new field, therein proving himself equally
capable. Original in its conception, striking in its psychologic
interest, and with a most perplexing love problem, "The
Mystery of Murray Davenport" is the most vital and
absorbing of all Mr. Stephens's novels, and will add not a little to
his reputation.</p>
	
<p>
"This is easily the best thing that Mr. Stephens has yet done.
Those familiar with his other novels can best judge the measure of
this praise, which is generous."--<bibl rend="i">Buffalo News.</bibl>
</p>

<p>
"Mr. Stephens won a host of friends through his earlier volumes,
but we think he will do still better work in his new field if the
present volume is a criterion."--<bibl rend="i">N. Y. Com. Advertiser.</bibl>
</p>

<p>	
<hi rend="b">The Daughter of the Dawn.</hi> By R. H<hi rend="sc">ODDER</hi>.
</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
With 12 full-page illustrations by Harold Piffard.
Library 12mo, cloth, decorative cover . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
<p>	
This is a powerful story of adventure and mystery, its scene
New Zealand. In sustained interest and novel plot, it recalls
Rider Haggard's "King Solomon's Mines," and "She," but
the reader will find an added interest due to the apparent
reality with which the author succeeds in investing the 
sensational incidents of his plot.</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1852-218"
                    n="2"/>
<p>
<hi rend="b">The Spoilsmen.</hi>By E<hi rend="sc">LLIOTT</hi> F<hi rend="sc">LOWER</hi>, author of
"Policeman Flynn," etc.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth . . . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>This is a story of municipal politics, depicting conditions
common to practically all large cities. The political methods
employed, however, are in most instances taken from the
actual experiences of men who have served the public in some
capacity or other, and the stories told of some of the 
characters are literally true. The love interest centres around a girl
of high ideals, who inspires a wealthy young man to enter the
local campaign.</p>
	
<p>"The best one may hear of 'The Spoilsmen' will be none too
good. As a wide-awake, snappy, brilliant political story it has few
equals, its title-page being stamped with that elusive mark, 'suc-
cess.' One should not miss a word of a book like this at a time
like this and in a world of politics like this."--<bibl rend="i">Boston Transcript.</bibl>
</p>
	
<p>"...It ought to do good. The world of municipal politics is
put before the reader in a striking and truthful manner; and the
sources of evil that afflict the government of our cities are laid bare
in a manner that should arrest the attention of every honest man
who wishes to purge and cleanse our local governments. It 
illustrates, too, very forcibly, how difficult a work it is to accomplish
such municipal reform, and how useless it is to attempt it without
united and persistent effort on the part of those who should be
most interested."--<bibl rend="i">Grover Cleveland.</bibl>
</p>
	
<p>
<hi rend="b">A Daughter of Thespis.</hi> By J<hi rend="sc">OHN</hi> D. B<hi rend="sc">ARRY</hi>,
author of "The Intriguers," "Mademoiselle Blanche," etc.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth . . . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>The author's experiences as a dramatic critic have enabled
him to write with authority on the ever fascinating theme of
stage life. From "the front," in the wings, and on the boards
--from all these varying points of view, is told this latest
story of player folk --an absorbing tale.</p>
	
<p>"This story of the experiences of Evelyn Johnson, actress, may
be praised just because it is so true and so wholly free from melodrama
and the claptrap which we have come to think inseparable
from any narrative which has to do with theatrical experiences."--<bibl rend="i">Professor
Harry Thurston Peck, of Columbia University.</bibl>
</p>	


<pb
                    id="VAB1852-219"
                    n="3"/>

<p>
<hi rend="b">Prince Hagen.</hi> By U<hi rend="sc">PTON</hi> S<hi rend="sc">INCLAIR</hi>, author of
"King Midas," etc.</p>
	
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth. . . . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>In this book, Mr. Sinclair has written a satire of the first
order --one worthy to be compared with Swift's biting tirades
against the follies and abuses of mankind.</p>
	
<p>
The scheme of the book is as delightful as it is original --Prince
Hagen, son of that Hagen who killed Siegfried, grandson
of Alberich, King of the Nibelungs, comes to this earth
from Nibelheim, for a completion of his education, and it is
the effect of our modern morality on a brilliant and 
unscrupulous mind which forms the basis of Mr. Sinclair's story.
Prince Hagen's first exploits are at school; then in the thick
of New York's corrupt politics as a boss. Later, after he has
inherited the untold wealth of the Nibelungs, he tastes the
society life of the metropolis.</p>
	
<p>
As a story simply, the book is thoroughly entertaining, with
a climax of surprising power; but, as a satire, it will live.</p>

<p>
<hi rend="b">Earth's Enigmas.</hi> By C<hi rend="sc">HARLES</hi> G. D. R<hi rend="sc">OBERTS</hi>,
author of "The Kindred of the Wild," "The Heart of the
Ancient Wood," etc. A new edition, with the addition of
three new stories, and ten illustrations by Charles Livingston
Bull.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth, uncut edges. . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>"It will rank high among collections of short stories. ... His
prose art, too, has reached a high degree of perfection. ... In
'Earth's Enigmas' is a wider range of subject than in the 'Kindred
of the Wild.'" --<bibl rend="i">Review from advance sheets of the illustrated edition
by Tiffany Blake in the Chicago Evening Post.</bibl>
</p>
	
<p>"Throughout the volume runs that subtle questioning of the
cruel, predatory side of nature which suggests the general title of
the book. In certain cases it is the picture of savage nature 
ravening for food --for death to preserve life; in others it is the secret
symbolism of woods and waters prophesying of evils and 
misadventures to come. All this does not mean, however, that Mr. Roberts
is either pessimistic or morbid --it is nature in his books after all,
wholesome in her cruel moods as in her tender."--<bibl rend="i">The New York
Independent.</bibl>
</p>	


<pb
                    id="VAB1852-220"
                    n="4"/>
	
<p>	
<hi rend="b">The Silent Maid.</hi> By F<hi rend="sc">REDERIC</hi> W. P<hi rend="sc">ANGBORN</hi>.
</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>		
Large 16mo, cloth, with a frontispiece by Frank T. 
Merrill  . . . . . . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.00</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>A dainty and delicate legend of the brave days of old, of
sprites and pixies, of trolls and gnomes, of ruthless barons and
noble knights. "The Silent Maid" herself, with her strange
bewitchment and wondrous song, is equalled only by Undine
in charm and mystery. The tale is told in that quaint diction
which chronicles "The Forest Lovers," and in which Mr.
Pangborn, although a new and hitherto undiscovered writer, is
no less an artist than Mr. Hewlett.</p>
	
<p>
<hi rend="b">The Golden Kingdom.</hi>  By A<hi rend="sc">NDREW</hi> B<hi rend="sc">ALFOUR</hi>,
author of "Vengeance is Mine," "To Arms!" etc.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Cloth, 12mo, decorative cover  . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>This is a story of adventure on land and sea, beginning in
England, and ending in South Africa, in the last days of the
seventeenth century. The scheme of the tale at once puts the
reader in mind of Stevenson's "Treasure Island," and with
that augury of a good story, he at once continues from the
mysterious advent of Corkran the Coxswain into the quiet
English village, through scenes of riot, slave-trading, ship-
wreck, and savages to the end of all in the "Golden 
Kingdom" with its strange denizens. The character of Jacob the
Blacksmith, big of body and bigger of heart, ever ready in
time of peril, will alone hold his attention with a strong grip.</p>
	 	
<p>
<hi rend="b">The Promotion of the Admiral.</hi> By M<hi rend="sc">ORLEY</hi>
R<hi rend="sc">OBERTS</hi>, author of "The Colossus," "The Fugitives,"
"Sons of Empire," etc.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth decorative, illustrated  . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>We consider ourselves fortunate in being able to announce
this latest novel by Mr. Morley Roberts, who has such a wide
circle of readers and admirers. This volume contains half a
dozen stories of sea life, --fresh, racy, and bracing, --some
humorous, some thrilling, all laid in America, --a new field for
Mr. Roberts, --and introduces a unique creation, "Shanghai
Smith," of "'Frisco," kidnapper of seamen, whose calling and
adventures have already interested and amused all readers of
<hi rend="i">The Philadelphia Saturday Evening Post.</hi>
</p>	

 	
<pb
                    id="VAB1852-221"
                    n="5"/>
<p>	
<hi rend="b">The Schemers.</hi> A T<hi rend="sc">ALE OF</hi> M<hi rend="sc">ODERN</hi> L<hi rend="sc">IFE</hi>. By
E<hi rend="sc">DWARD</hi> F. H<hi rend="sc">ARKINS</hi>, author of "Little Pilgrimages
Among the Men Who Have Written Famous Books," etc.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth, with a frontispiece by Ernest
Fosbery  . . . . . . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>A story of a new and real phase of social life in Boston,
skilfully and daringly handled. There is plenty of life and
color abounding, and a diversity of characters --shop-girls,
society belles, men about town, city politicians, and others.
The various schemers and their schemes will be followed with
interest --and there will be some discerning readers who may
claim to recognize in certain points of the story certain recent
happenings in the shopping and the society circles of the Hub.</p>

<p>
<hi rend="b">The Captain's Wife.</hi>  By W. C<hi rend="sc">LARK</hi> R<hi rend="sc">USSELL</hi>,
author of "The Wreck of the Grosvenor," "The Mate of
the Good Ship York," etc.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth, with a frontispiece by  W. H.
Dunton   . . . . . . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>The customary epithets applied to nautical fiction are quite
incommensurate with the excellence of Mr. Clark Russell's 
narrative powers, and these are thoroughly at their best in "The
Captain's Wife." "The Captain's Wife" is the story of a
voyage, and its romantic interest hinges on the stratagem of
the captain's newly wedded wife in order to accompany him
on his expedition for the salvage of a valuable wreck. The plot
thickens so gradually that a less competent novelist would be
in danger of letting the reader's attention slip. But the climax
of Benson's conspiracy to remove the captain, and carry off
the wife, to whom his lawless passion aspires, is invested with
the keenest excitement.</p>

<p>
<hi rend="b">The Story of the Foss River Ranch.</hi> By
R<hi rend="sc">IDGWELL</hi> C<hi rend="sc">ULLOM</hi>.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth decorative  . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>	
The scene of this story is laid in Canada, not in one of the
great cities, but in that undeveloped section of the great 
Northwest where to-day scenes are being enacted similar to those
enacted fifty years ago during the settlement of the great 
American West. The story is intense, with a sustained and 
well-developed plot, and will thus appeal to the reading public.</p>



 
<pb
                    id="VAB1852-222"
                    n="6"/>
<p>	
<hi rend="b">The Interference of Patricia.</hi> By  L<hi rend="sc">ILIAN</hi>
B<hi rend="sc">ELL</hi>, author of "Hope Loring," "Abroad with the 
Jimmies," etc. With a frontispiece from drawing by Frank T
Merrill.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Cloth, 12mo, decorative cover . . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.00</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>This story adds not a little to the author's reputation as a
teller of clever tales. It is of the social life of to-day in Denver
--that city of gold and ozone-- and deals of that burg's 
peculiarities with a keen and flashing satire. The character of the
heroine, Patricia, will hold the reader by its power and 
brilliancy. Impetuous, capricious, and wayward, with a 
dominating personality and spirit, she is at first a careless girl, then
develops into a loyal and loving woman, whose interference
saves the honor of both her father and lover. The love theme
is in the author's best vein, the character sketches of the 
magnates of Denver are amusing and trenchant, and the episodes
of the plot are convincing, sincere, and impressive.</p>
	
<p>	
<hi rend="b">A  Book of Girls.</hi> By L<hi rend="sc">ILIAN</hi> B<hi rend="sc">ELL</hi>, author of "Hope
Loring," "Abroad with the Jimmies," etc. With a 
frontispiece.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Cloth, 12mo, decorative cover . . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.00</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>It is quite universally recognized that Lilian Bell has done
for the American girl in fiction what Gibson has done for her
in art --that Lilian Bell has crystallized into a distinct type all
the peculiar qualities that have made the American girl unique
among the women of the world. Consequently, a book with a
Bell heroine is sure of a hearty welcome. What, therefore,
can be said of this book, which contains no less than four
types of witching and buoyant femininity? There are four
stories of power and dash in this volume: "The Last Straw,"
"The Surrender of Lapwing," "The Penance of Hedwig,"
and "Garret Owen's Little Countess."  Each one of these
tells a tale full of verve and thrill, each one has a heroine of
fibre and spirit.</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1852-223"
                    n="7"/>

<p>
<hi rend="b">Count Zarka.</hi> By S<hi rend="sc">IR</hi> W<hi rend="sc">ILLIAM</hi> M<hi rend="sc">AGNAY</hi>, author of
"The Red Chancellor."</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
One volume, library 12mo, cloth, decorative cover, with a
striking frontispiece.  . . . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>"The Red Chancellor" was considered by critics, as well as
by the reading public, one of the most dramatic novels of last
year. In his new book, Sir William Magnay has continued in
the field in which he has been so successful. "Count Zarka"
is a strong, quick-moving romance of adventure and political
intrigue, the scene being laid in a fictitious kingdom of central
Europe, under which thin disguise may be recognized one of
the Balkan states. The story in its action and complications
reminds one strongly of "The Prisoner of Zenda," while the
manoeuvring of Russia for the control in the East strongly 
suggests the contemporary history of European politics. The
character of the mysterious Count Zarka, hero and villain, is
strongly developed, and one new in fiction.</p>
	
<p>	
<hi rend="b">The Golden Dwarf.</hi>       By R. N<hi rend="sc">ORMAN</hi> S<hi rend="sc">ILVER</hi>,
author of "A Daughter of Mystery," etc.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth, illustrated  . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>Mr. Silver needs no introduction to the American public.
His "A Daughter of Mystery" was one of the most realistic
stories of modern London life that has recently appeared.
"The Golden Dwarf" is such another story, intense and 
almost sensational. Mr. Silver reveals the mysterious and 
gruesome beneath the commonplace in an absorbing manner. The
"Golden Dwarf" himself, his strange German physician, and
the secret of the Wyresdale Tower are characters and 
happenings which will hold the reader from cover to cover.</p>
	
<p>	
<hi rend="b">Alain Tanger's Wife.</hi>  By J. H. Y<hi rend="sc">OXALL</hi>, author
of "The Rommany Stone," etc.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth, decorative cover .  .  . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>A spirited story of political intrigue in France. The various
dissensions of the parties claiming political supremacy, and
"the wheels within wheels" that move them to their schemes
are caustically and trenchantly revealed. A well known figure
in the military history of France plays a prominent part in the
plot --but the central figure is that of the American heroine
--loyal, intense, piquant, and compelling.</p>


<pb
                    id="VAB1852-224"
                    n="8"/>
<p>	
<hi rend="b">The Diary of a Year.</hi> P<hi rend="cs">ASSAGES IN THE</hi> L<hi rend="sc">IFE OF
A</hi> W<hi rend="sc">OMAN OF THE</hi> W<hi rend="sc">ORLD</hi>. Edited by Mrs. C<hi rend="sc">HARLES</hi>
H. E. B<hi rend="sc">ROOKFIELD</hi>.
</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth, decorative cover . . . <hi rend="right">$1.25</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>The writer of this absorbing study of emotions and events is
gifted with charming imagination and an elegant style. The
book abounds in brilliant wit, amiable philosophy, and 
interesting characterizations. The "woman of the world" reveals
herself as a fascinating, if somewhat reckless, creature, who
justly holds the sympathies of the reader.</p>

<p>
<hi rend="b">The Red Triangle.</hi> Being some further chronicles of
Martin Hewitt, investigator.  By A<hi rend="sc">RTHUR</hi> M<hi rend="sc">ORRISON</hi>,
author of "The Hole in the Wall," "Tales of Mean
Streets," etc.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth  . . . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>This is a genuine, straightforward detective story of the kind
that keeps the reader on the <hi rend="i">qui vive</hi>. Martin Hewitt, 
investigator, might well have studied his methods from Sherlock
Holmes, so searching and successful are they. His adventures
take him at times to the slums of London, amid scenes which
recall Mr. Morrison's already noted "The Hole in the Wall."
As a combination of criminal and character studies, this book
is very successful.</p>
</div1>	

		
<div1 type="advertisement">
<head rend="center b">COMMONWEALTH SERIES</head>
<p>	
<hi rend="b">No. 7. The Philadelphians:</hi> A<hi rend="sc">S</hi> S<hi rend="sc">EEN BY A</hi>
N<hi rend="sc">EW</hi> Y<hi rend="sc">ORK</hi> W<hi rend="sc">OMAN</hi>. By K<hi rend="sc">ATHARINE</hi> B<hi rend="sc">INGHAM</hi>. (Pseud.)
</p>	
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Large 12mo, cloth, gilt top, with illustrations by Alice 
Barbour Stephens and George Gibbs.    . . . <hi rend="right">$1.25</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>A bright and breezy tale of a charming New York woman,
whose wedded lot is twice cast in Philadelphia. The family of
her first husband committed the unpardonable sin of living
north of Market Street; that of her second husband resided
south of that line of demarcation. She is thus enabled to
speak whereof she knows concerning the conventions, and
draws the characteristics of life in the Quaker city, as well as
the foibles of the " first families" with a keen and caustic,
though not unkindly, pen.</p>
</div1>	


<pb
                    id="VAB1852-225"
                    n="[1]"/>
	
<div1 type="advertisement">
	
<head rend="left"><hi rend="b">Selections from<lb/>
L. C. Page and Company's<lb/>
List of Fiction
	
<hi rend="center">WORKS OF<lb/>
ROBERT NEILSON STEPHENS</hi></hi></head>
<p>	
<hi rend="b">Captain Ravenshaw;</hi> O<hi rend="sc">R</hi>, T<hi rend="sc">HE</hi> M<hi rend="sc">AID OF</hi>
C<hi rend="sc">HEAPSIDE</hi>. (35th thousand.) A romance of Elizabethan
London. Illustrations by Howard Pyle and other artists.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth . . . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>Not since the absorbing adventures of D'Artagnan have we
had anything so good in the blended vein of romance and
comedy. The beggar student, the rich goldsmith, the roisterer
and the rake, the fop and the maid, are all here: foremost
among them, Captain Ravenshaw himself, soldier of fortune
and adventurer, who, after escapades of binding interest,
finally wins a way to fame and to matrimony. The rescue of
a maid from the designs of an unscrupulous father and rakish
lord forms the principal and underlying theme, around which
incidents group themselves with sufficient rapidity to hold one's
attention spellbound.</p>
	
<p>	
<hi rend="b">Philip Winwood.</hi> (70th thousand.) A Sketch of
the Domestic History of an American Captain in the War of
Independence, embracing events that occurred between and
during the years 1763 and 1785 in New York and London.
Written by his Enemy in War, Herbert Russell, Lieutenant
in the Loyalist Forces.  Presented anew by R<hi rend="sc">OBERT</hi> 
N<hi rend="sc">EILSON</hi> S<hi rend="sc">TEPHENS</hi>. Illustrated by E. W. D. Hamilton.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth    . . . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>"One of the most stirring and remarkable romances that have
been published in a long while, and its episodes, incidents, and
actions are as interesting and agreeable as they are vivid and
dramatic." --<bibl rend="i">Boston Times.</bibl>
</p>	


<pb
                    id="VAB1852-226"
                    n="2"/>
<p>	
<hi rend="b">An Enemy to the King.</hi> (40th thousand.) From
the "Recently Discovered Memoirs of the Sieur de la
Tournoire." Illustrated by H. De M. Young.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth  . . . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>An historical romance of the sixteenth century, describing
the adventures of a young French nobleman at the Court of
Henry III., and on the field with Henry of Navarre.</p>
<p>"A stirring tale." --<bibl rend="i">Detroit Free Press.</bibl></p>
<p>"A royally strong piece of fiction."--<bibl rend="i">Boston Ideas.</bibl></p>
<p>"Interesting from the first to the last page." --<bibl rend="i">Brooklyn Eagle.</bibl></p>
<p>"Brilliant as a play; it is equally brilliant as a romantic novel." --
	<bibl rend="i">Philadelphia Press.</bibl></p>

<p>
<hi rend="b">The Continental Dragoon:</hi> A R<hi rend="sc">OMANCE OF</hi>
P<hi rend="sc">HILIPSE</hi> M<hi rend="sc">ANOR</hi> H<hi rend="sc">OUSE IN</hi> 1778. (42d thousand.) 
Illustrated by H. C. Edwards.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth    . . . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>A stirring romance of the Revolution, the scene being laid
in and around the old Philipse Manor House, near Yonkers,
which at the time of the story was the central point of the 
so-called "neutral territory" between the two armies.</p>
	
<p>	
<hi rend="b">The Road to Paris:</hi> A S<hi rend="sc">TORY OF</hi> A<hi rend="sc">DVENTURE.</hi>
(23d thousand.) Illustrated by H. C. Edwards.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth    . . . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>An historical romance of the 18th century, being an account
of the life of an American gentleman adventurer of Jacobite
ancestry, whose family early settled in the colony of 
Pennsylvania.</p>
	
<p>	
<hi rend="b">A Gentleman Player:</hi> H<hi rend="sc">is</hi> A<hi rend="sc">DVENTURES ON A</hi>
S<hi rend="sc">ECRET</hi> M<hi rend="sc">ISSION FOR</hi> Q<hi rend="sc">UEEN</hi> E<hi rend="sc">LIZABETH.</hi> (35th 
thousand.) Illustrated by Frank T. Merrill.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth   . . . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>"A Gentleman Player" is a romance of the Elizabethan
period. It relates the story of a young gentleman who, in the
reign of Elizabeth, falls so low in his fortune that he joins
Shakespeare's company of players, and becomes a friend and
protg of the great poet.</p>
</div1>	

 
<pb
                    id="VAB1852-227"
                    n="3"/>

<div1 type="advertisement">
<head rend="center b">WORKS OF<lb/>
CHARLES G. D. ROBERTS</head>
<p>	
<hi rend="b">Barbara Ladd.</hi> With four illustrations by Frank
Verbeck.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, gilt top     . . . . . .  <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>"From the opening chapter to the final page Mr. Roberts lures
us on by his rapt devotion to the changing aspects of Nature and
by his keen and sympathetic analysis of human character." --<bibl rend="i">Boston
Transcript.</bibl></p>
	
<p>	
<hi rend="b">The Kindred of the Wild.</hi> A B<hi rend="sc">OOK OF</hi> A<hi rend="sc">NIMAL</hi>
L<hi rend="sc">IFE</hi>. With fifty-one full-page plates and many decorations
from drawings by Charles Livingston Bull.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Small quarto, decorative cover. . . . . <hi rend="right">$2.00</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>"Professor Roberts has caught wonderfully the elusive 
individualities of which he writes. His animal stories are marvels of 
sympathetic science and literary exactness. Bound with the superb
illustrations by Charles Livingston Bull, they make a volume which
charms, entertains, and informs." --<bibl rend="i">New York World.</bibl></p>
<p>"... Is in many ways the most brilliant collection of animal
stories that has appeared ... well named and well done." --<bibl rend="i">John
Burroughs.</bibl></p>
	
<p>	
<hi rend="b">The Forge in the Forest.</hi> Being the Narrative of
the Acadian Ranger, Jean de Mer, Seigneur de Briart, and
how he crossed the Black Abb, and of his Adventures in a
Strange Fellowship. Illustrated by Henry Sandham, R. C. A.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth, gilt top  . . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>A romance of the convulsive period of the struggle between
the French and English for the possession of North America.
The story is one of pure love and heroic adventure, and
deals with that fiery fringe of conflict that waved between
Nova Scotia and New England. The Expulsion of the Acadians
is foreshadowed in these brilliant pages, and the part of
the "Black Abb's" intrigues in precipitating that catastrophe
is shown.</p>


<pb
id="VAB1852-228" n="4"/>

<p>
<hi rend="b">The Heart of the Ancient Wood.</hi> With six
illustrations by James L. Weston.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, decorative cover  . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>"One of the most fascinating novels of recent days." --<bibl rend="i">Boston
Journal.</bibl></p>
<p>"A classic twentieth century romance." --<bibl rend="i">New York Commercial
Advertiser.</bibl></p>
	
<p>	
<hi rend="b">A Sister to Evangeline.</hi> Being the Story of
Yvonne de Lamourie, and how she went into Exile with the
Villagers of Grand Pr.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth gilt top, illustrated  . . . <hi rend="right">$1.50</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>This is a romance of the great expulsion of the Acadians
which Longfellow first immortalized in "Evangeline." Swift
action, fresh atmosphere, wholesome purity, deep passion,
searching analysis, characterize this strong novel; and the
tragic theme of the exile is relieved by the charm of the wilful
demoiselle and the spirit of the courtly seigneur, who bring the
manners of old France to the Acadian woods.</p>

<p>
<hi rend="b">By the Marshes of Minas.</hi></p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Library 12mo, cloth, gilt top, illustrated . . . <hi rend="right">$1.25</hi>
</item>
</list>

<p>This is a volume of romance of love and adventure in that
picturesque period when Nova Scotia was passing from the
French to the English rgime of which Professor Roberts is
the acknowledged celebrant. Each tale is independent of the
others, but the scenes are similar, and in several of them the
evil "Black Abb," well-known from the author's previous
novels, again appears with his savages at his heels --but to be
thwarted always by woman's wit or soldier's courage. Most of
these romances are in the author's lighter and more playful
vein; each is a unit of absorbing interest and exquisite work-
manship.</p>

<p>
<hi rend="b">Asa Holmes;</hi> <hi rend="sc">OR</hi>, A<hi rend="sc">T THE</hi> C<hi rend="sc">ROSS</hi>-R<hi rend="sc">OADS</hi>. A sketch
of Country Life and Country Humor. By A<hi rend="sc">NNIE</hi> F<hi rend="sc">ELLOWS</hi>
J<hi rend="sc">OHNSTON</hi>. With a frontispiece by Ernest Fosbery.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>	
Large 16mo, cloth, gilt top  . . . . . <hi rend="right">$1.00</hi>
</item>
</list>
	
<p>"Asa Holmes; or, At the Cross-Roads" is the most delightful,
most sympathetic and wholesome book that has been published in a
long while. The lovable, cheerful, touching incidents, the 
descriptions of persons and things are wonderfully true to nature." 
--<bibl rend="i">Boston Times.</bibl></p>
	
</div1>


		
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
