<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//IA Books//DTD TEI for Indiana Authors Books//EN"
                       "teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="VAB1854">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">A little shepherd of Provence</title>
				<author>Stein, Evaleen, 1863-1923.</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded By</resp>
					<!--Update the value of the element below with your name in
                                direct order.-->
					<name>Brenda Beaman</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
				<address>
                    <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
                </address>
				<idno>VAB1854</idno>
				<availability status="unknown">
					<p>Copyright 2009 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
					<p>Indiana University provides the information contained on this web site for
						non-commercial, personal, or research use only. All other use, including but not limited
						to commercial or scholarly reproductions, redistribution, publication or transmission,
						whether by electronic means or otherwise, without prior written permission of the
						copyright holder is strictly prohibited.</p>
				</availability>
				<!--Update the value of the date element with the year the document
                        is being encoded.-->
				<date>2009</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblFull>
					<titleStmt>
						<title type="main">A little shepherd of Provence</title>
						<author id="ina-v1-entry-0815">Stein, Evaleen, 1863-1923.</author>
					</titleStmt>
					<extent>5 p. β., 210 p. 6 col. pl. (incl. front.) 20 cm.</extent>
					<publicationStmt>
						<publisher>L.C. Page &amp; Company</publisher>
						<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
						<date>1910</date>
					</publicationStmt>
					<notesStmt>
						<note>Title within green ornamental border.</note>
					</notesStmt>
				</biblFull>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>The Digital Library Program was awarded a Library Services and Technology Act (LSTA)
					grant in 2005 to make available online the three-volume, reference work, <title>Indiana
						Authors and Their Books</title> along with selected monographs by Indiana authors.</p>
			</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl n="3">
				<p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and has
					been encoded and edited using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
					Guidelines following the TEI Lite standard. Digital page images are linked to the text
					file.</p>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<tagUsage gi="div1">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy id="lcsh">
					<bibl>
						<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language>English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<!--The revision description tracks significant changes made to the file
                    after completion. This information will remain commented out unless someone has
                    conducted quality assessment of the texts and have made changes to the file as a
                    result.-->
		<!-- <revisionDesc> <change>
                    <date>$Date</date> <respStmt>
                    <name>$Name</name>
                    <resp>$Responsibility</resp>
                    </respStmt> <item>$Changes</item>
                    </change> </revisionDesc> -->
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>


			<pb id="VAB1854-001" n="[]"/>
			<pb id="VAB1854-002" n="[]"/>

			<div1 type="halftitle">
				<p rend="center">A LITTLE SHEPHERD OF PROVENCE</p>
			</div1>

			<pb id="VAB1854-003" n="[]"/>

			<div1 type="advertisement">
				<head rend="center">STORIES BY<lb/> EVALEEN STEIN</head>

				<list type="simple">
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">The Circus Dwarf Stories</hi>
						<hi rend="right">$1.65</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">Children's Stories</hi>
						<hi rend="right">1.65</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">Troubadour Tales</hi>
						<hi rend="right">1.65</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">Pepin: A Tale of Twelfth Night</hi>
						<hi rend="right">1.65</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">When Fairies Were Friendly</hi>
						<hi rend="right">1.65</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">Gabriel and the Hour Book</hi>
						<hi rend="right">1.65</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">The Christmas Porringer</hi>
						<hi rend="right">1.65</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">A Little Shepherd of Provence</hi>
						<hi rend="right">1.65</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">The Little Count of Normandy</hi>
						<hi rend="right">1.65</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">Our Little Celtic Cousin of Long Ago</hi>
						<hi rend="right">1.00</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">Our Little Crusader Cousin of Long Ago</hi>
						<hi rend="right">1.00</hi>
					</item>

					<item>
						<hi rend="left">Our Little Frankish Cousin of Long Ago</hi>
						<hi rend="right">1.00</hi>
					</item>
					<item>
						<hi rend="left">Our Little Norman Cousin of Long Ago</hi>
						<hi rend="right">1.00</hi>
					</item>

				</list>

				<p rend="center">L. C. PAGE &amp; COMPANY (Inc.)<lb/> 53 Beacon Street, Boston, Mass.</p>




			</div1>


			<pb id="VAB1854-004" n="[]"/>


			<pb id="VAB1854-005" n="[]"/>

			<div1 type="frontispiece">
				<p>
					<figure>
						<p> "<hi rend="b">L</hi>ITTLE JEAN FAVETTE WAS<lb/> IN A BROWN STUDY"<lb/>
							<hi rend="i center">(See page 1)</hi></p>
					</figure>
				</p>
			</div1>

			<pb id="VAB1854-006" n="[]"/>

			<titlePage>
				<docTitle>
					<titlePart type="main" rend="center">A Little Shepherd<lb/> of Provence</titlePart>

				</docTitle>

				<byline rend="center">BY<lb/>
					<docAuthor>Evaleen Stein </docAuthor></byline>

				<byline>
					<docAuthor rend="i center">Author of "Gabriel and the Hour Book"</docAuthor>
				</byline>

				<byline>
					<docAuthor rend="i center">ILLUSTRATED BY<lb/> Diantha Horne Marlowe</docAuthor>
				</byline>

				<docImprint>
					<publisher rend="center">L. C. Page &amp; Company</publisher>
					<pubPlace rend="left">Boston</pubPlace> Publishers </docImprint>
			</titlePage>

			<pb id="VAB1854-007" n="[]"/>
			<div1 type="verso">

				<p rend="center">Copyright, 1910, by<lb/> L. C. PAGE &amp; COMPANY<lb/>
					<hi rend=" i center">(Incorporated)</hi></p>

				<milestone unit="typography" n="-----" rend="center"/>

				<p rend="i center">All rights reserved</p>

				<p>Eighth Impression, May, 1926</p>
				<p>Ninth Impression, March, 1928</p>
				<p>Tenth Impression, January, 1933</p>
				<p>Eleventh Impression, December, 1937</p>

				<p rend="center">Made in U. S. A.</p>
			</div1>

			<pb id="VAB1854-008" n="[]"/>


			<div1 type="dedication">
				<p rend="center">TO MY FRIEND<lb/></p>

				<p rend="center">Anna Nicholas</p>
			</div1>


			<pb id="VAB1854-009" n="[]"/>
			<pb id="VAB1854-010" n="[]"/>

			<div1 type="contents">
				<head rend="center">CONTENTS</head>

				<list type="ordered" rend="upper-roman">
					<item>The Golden Goat<hi rend="right">1</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAB1854-010"
						/></item>
					<item>The Surprise in the Cottage<hi rend="right">22</hi><ptr targType="pb"
							target="VAB1854-037"/></item>
					<item>Jean's Idea<hi rend="right">31</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAB1854-046"/></item>
					<item>The Coming of Christmas<hi rend="right">44</hi><ptr targType="pb"
							target="VAB1854-059"/></item>
					<item>Christmas Eve<hi rend="right">54</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAB1854-069"
						/></item>
					<item>In the Sheepfold<hi rend="right">70</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAB1854-085"
						/></item>
					<item>Perplexing Questions<hi rend="right">93</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAB1854-110"
						/></item>
					<item>VIII Helping the Fugitive<hi rend="right">111</hi><ptr targType="pb"
							target="VAB1854-128"/></item>
					<item>Sieur Raimond's Wallet<hi rend="right">127</hi><ptr targType="pb"
							target="VAB1854-144"/></item>
					<item>Jean's Garden<hi rend="right">139</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAB1854-158"
						/></item>
					<item> Pare Favette goes to the Castle<hi rend="right">151</hi><ptr targType="pb"
							target="VAB1854-170"/></item>
					<item>Lady Azalais<hi rend="right">168</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAB1854-189"
						/></item>
					<item>The Birthday Fête<hi rend="right">178</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAB1854-199"
						/></item>
					<item>Damask Roses<hi rend="right">198</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAB1854-221"
						/></item>

				</list>
			</div1>

			<pb id="VAB1854-011" n="[]"/>
			<pb id="VAB1854-012" n="[]"/>

			<div1 type="figures">
				<head rend="center">ILLUSTRATIONS</head>
				<list type="simple">
					<item>"Little Jean Favette was in a brown study"<hi rend="i right">(See page 1)
							Frontispiece</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAB1854-005"/></item>
					<item>"The flock loitered along in the soft June twilight"<hi rend="right">16</hi><ptr
							targType="pb" target="VAB1854-030"/></item>
					<item>"Lifting up the lantern, took a step toward the corner"<hi rend="right">72</hi><ptr
							targType="pb" target="VAB1854-088"/></item>
					<item>"Coming across the field he saw a strange man"<hi rend="right">130</hi><ptr
							targType="pb" target="VAB1854-148"/></item>
					<item>"In the great hall they met the Lady Azalais"<hi rend="right">164</hi><ptr
							targType="pb" target="VAB1854-184"/></item>
					<item>"All the while they kept climbing up and up"<hi rend="right">182</hi><ptr
							targType="pb" target="VAB1854-204"/></item>
					<pb id="VAB1854-013" n="[]"/>

				</list>
			</div1>
		</front>
		<body>

			<pb id="VAB1854-014" n="1"/>
			<div1 type="book">

				<head rend="center">A LITTLE SHEPHERD OF PROVENCE</head>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER I</head>

					<head rend="center sc">THE GOLDEN GOAT</head>

					<p>
						<hi rend="b">L</hi>ITTLE Jean Favette was in a brown study. He was sitting under a
						mulberry tree at the edge of a grassy meadow; overhead, between the green leaves,
						twinkled the bright blue sky of Provence, and through all the fields the June poppies
						flickered and tossed like myriads of tiny scarlet flames.</p>
					<p>Now and then, shaken by some fitful breeze, the ripe purple mulberries <pb
							id="VAB1854-015" n="2"/> pattered down, fairly pelting him as they fell; but so
						absorbed was he in his thoughts that he paid no heed.</p>
					<p>His hands were clasped around his knees, and his brown bare feet half buried in tufts
						of clover, as he gazed steadily at the meadow pasture in front of him. In it, busily
						nibbling the tender green grass, was the little flock that Jean shepherded; four sheep,
						a small lamb with shining fleece and long pink ears, and two gray goats.</p>
					<p>No, there were <hi rend="i">three</hi> goats! And it was this third one that was
						causing Jean such perplexity.</p>
					<p>The day before, made drowsy by the June sunshine, he had lain down on the green turf
						and slept for a little while, and when he <pb id="VAB1854-016" n="3"/> awakened he saw
						that a strange goat had joined his flock. He did not know from what direction it had
						come, and by and by, later on in the day, before he knew it, it had strayed away as
						unexpectedly as it had come. And now again to-day it had suddenly appeared beside his
						sheep; there it was, browsing away as quietly and contentedly as if it had always
						belonged with them. </p>
					<p>But where did it come from?</p>
					<p>Now for two years it had been Jean's task to tend the family flock. The peasant folk
						were permitted by the lords of the land to pasture their few animals along the
						road-sides, or in such unused fields or meadows as they could find. And as day by day
						Jean had <pb id="VAB1854-017" n="4"/> driven his charges to pasture in company with
						other shepherds, some of them boys and girls as young as himself, he had come to know
						all the sheep and goats for miles about.</p>
					<p>The valley where he lived was shut in almost completely by a steep, craggy chain of
						mountains, the Alpilles, while along its western edge flowed the great river Rhone, and
						beyond these Jean had never been. But all the valley he knew very well; and he knew,
						too, that this strange goat feeding with his flock was different from any he had ever
						seen.</p>
					<p>It had long silky hair, and except for its feet and forehead, which were silvery white,
						its colour was a peculiarly bright, tawny brown, <pb id="VAB1854-018" n="5"/> that shone
						like gold in the sunlight.</p>
					<p>As Jean sat watching it, trying to understand whence it had come, all at once an idea
						occurred to him that made him draw in his breath with a long "Oh!" while his dark eyes
						grew very big and round with wonder.</p>
					<p>"Oh!" he repeated to himself, "perhaps,--perhaps it is the Golden Goat!"</p>
					<p>In the excitement of this idea he rose to his feet to go and look more closely at the
						newcomer. And then it was one might see that poor little Jean was lame; for he picked up
						a small crutch that had lain in the long grass at his side, and with the help of this
						started off toward the pasture.</p>
					<pb id="VAB1854-019" n="6"/>
					<p>When scarcely more than a baby the lad had strayed off to the mountains, one day, and a
						cruel fall from one of the steep rocks had left him with lameness. Through the warm
						summer months when he could go barefooted it was not so hard to get about with his
						crutch; but in the winter time, when obliged to wear his wooden shoes, he would be very,
						very tired by the end of his day's work.</p>
					<p>But while we have left Jean eagerly hurrying out to the pasture, as fast as his poor
						little lame legs would take him, let us see why it was that he was so eager to learn
						whether or not the newcomer to his flock was really the Golden Goat.</p>
					<pb id="VAB1854-020" n="7"/>
					<p>Now, in Jean's time, almost six hundred years ago, the valley in which he lived, and
						indeed all the villages thereabout, were owned and ruled over by Count Guillaume, the
						Lord of Baux, a powerful nobleman whose castle was in the strong stone-built town of Les
						Baux, perched on top of the highest crag of the Alpilles and over-looking all the
						region.</p>
					<p>A strange town it was. Its narrow crooked streets were cut in the solid rock of the
						mountain; many of the dwellings, too, and a part of the great castle were hewn from this
						same living rock. At one edge of the highest cliff skirting the town, there rose a
						curious stone tower, which, to this day, may still be seen standing forlorn <pb
							id="VAB1854-021" n="8"/> and weatherbeaten among the gray ruins of Les Baux.</p>
					<p>This tower was called "The Saracen's Tower," because folk said it had been built, no
						one knew how long before, by a race of people who had come from Africa and had held the
						crags of the Alpilles until driven out by the Lords of Baux. It was further declared
						that the Saracens had hidden a great treasure of gold and precious stones in some cavern
						of the Alpilles near this tower and had set a Golden Goat to guard it; but when they
						took flight from the mountain they were so hard pressed that they had no time to seek
						this treasure and take it with them.</p>
					<p>So, from that day to this, the people of Provence have firmly <pb id="VAB1854-022"
							n="9"/> believed that hidden somewhere in the Alpilles is this hoard of wealth guarded
						by the Golden Goat; though no one has ever been able to find the hiding place. Really,
						not to know of the Golden Goat, when one lives in Provence, is to be very ignorant
						indeed.</p>
					<p>But Jean, being only a little boy twelve years old, had somehow not happened to hear of
						it until the summer before, when it had chanced that Grandpère Chartier had come along
						the road, and, being tired, had stopped to rest beside Jean who was sitting by a
						hawthorn hedge watching his flock; and the two had fallen to talking. Presently down the
						steep ioad from Les Baux a richly dressed nobleman had come pricking <pb
							id="VAB1854-023" n="10"/> along on a tall horse with a scarlet bridle; and seeing him,
						Jean, leaning on his crutch, had exclaimed, "O, Grandpère, I wish I might have a velvet
						doublet and ride on horseback!"</p>
					<p>And then Grandpère had laughed in his high, cracked voice and said, "Ah, little one, if
						only thou couldst find the Golden Goat what a fine thing it would be!"</p>
					<p>At this Jean had looked so very blank that Grandpère had exclaimed in surprise, "Bless
						me, child! Is it possible thou dost not know of the Golden Goat?"</p>
					<p>At once he went on to tell Jean the old tale, assuring him that he had no doubt that it
						was true. "For," said Grandpère, "everybody knows that the witch Taven lives <pb
							id="VAB1854-024" n="11"/> in a cavern in the heart of yonder mountain, and the good
						fairy Esterelle in the range just beyond; so why not a Golden Goat with hoards of
						riches?"</p>
					<p>Jean, who had listened in open-mouthed wonder, quite agreed with Grandpère; and after
						the latter had hobbled off, he thought a great deal about the tale he had heard.</p>
					<p>Perhaps it was because Jean was lame, and could not run about and work and play as did
						the other peasant children, that he had become much more thoughtful than they. As he
						sat, day after day, watching his sheep, many things came into his mind, and after this
						story that Grandpère had told him he wished oftentimes that he could find the Golden
						Goat and its hidden <pb id="VAB1854-025" n="12"/> treasure, for his family was very
						poor.</p>
					<p>Yet, as month after month passed, and he heard no more about it, he had almost ceased
						to remember it, for every day brought so many other things for him to do and think
						of.</p>
					<p>But now, on this June morning, when the strange goat suddenly appeared in the meadow
						with his little flock, it was no wonder that he was all excitement in his idea that it
						might be the marvelous goat set by the Saracens to guard their hidden gold.</p>
					<p>For, by this time, Jean had finished examining it, and though except for its beautiful
						and unusual colour it seemed quite like the other goats, he none the less felt entirely
							<pb id="VAB1854-026" n="13"/> sure that it was the very one of which Grandpère had
						told him. Of course it was long, long ago that the Saracens had gone, but then if the
						goat was enchanted, that would make no difference. He was not quite clear as to why it
						was called Golden, whether because of the treasure it guarded or because it was itself
						in some manner made of gold. But this strange goat, with its glossy coat of tawny brown,
						shone exactly like gold; and, well, at any rate, Jean decided that there could be no
						possible doubt in the matter.</p>
					<p>"She has grown tired," he said to himself, "staying all these hundreds of years in some
						gloomy cavern, and so she has come down <pb id="VAB1854-027" n="14"/> the mountain to
						enjoy herself like other goats."</p>
					<p>Jean's active imagination at once began to weave all sorts of dreams; but he determined
						to tell no one his thoughts, but to carefully watch the Golden Goat, and some day surely
						it would lead him to its home and the hidden riches.</p>
					<p>Indeed, he was so taken up with the idea that the morning passed, and the flock in the
						pasture began to seek shady places under the great, overhanging rocks at the edge of the
						mountain before Jean remembered that he was hungry; for he had been in the fields since
						dawn.</p>
					<p>So drawing from the pocket of his blouse a piece of hard bread and a bit of cheese he
						made his breakfast; for French folk call their noon <pb id="VAB1854-028" n="15"/> meal
						breakfast. The bit of food they have early in the morning is only the "little
						breakfast." And Jean's had been little enough; only hard bread without even cheese. But
						he was very well satisfied, and really felt that at this noon breakfast he fared quite
						finely, for he finished off with some of the sweet juicy mulberries that had fallen from
						the tree above him.</p>
					<p>The afternoon he passed in a dream, every now and then looking to be sure the Golden
						Goat was still there.</p>
					<p>When it drew toward dusk and time to take the little flock to the fold, he was fairly
						trembling with anxiety for fear the newcomer might disappear. He felt that it was no use
						trying to drive an enchanted <pb id="VAB1854-029" n="16"/> goat as he did the others; he
						could only hope that she would decide to stay with his flock.</p>
					<p>And sure enough, when he started the others homeward, along came the beautiful new goat
						as placidly as if she had always followed the way to the Favette fold.</p>
					<p>It was not far they had to go; only past the bend in the road and beyond the row of
						tall cypress trees, behind which was Jean's home. The flock loitered along in the soft
						June twilight, the goats now and then stopping to snatch a branch of bramble berries, or
						the sheep to nibble a bit of clover. The lamb with the long, pink ears had a little
						tinkling bell fastened about its neck, so that it might not stray away too far; and Jean
						coming <pb id="VAB1854-030" n="[]"/>
						<figure>
							<p> "<hi rend="b">T</hi>HE FLOCK LOITERED ALONG IN<lb/> THE SOFT JUNE TWILIGHT" </p>
						</figure>
						<pb id="VAB1854-031" n="[]"/>
						<pb id="VAB1854-032" n="17"/> behind them all--and it was surprising how fast he could
						get along despite his crutch--kept the flock in the road, now and then flicking one or
						the other of them, except the Golden Goat, he would not presume to touch <hi rend="i"
							>that</hi>, with a small willow branch which he carried. Sometimes the lamb, tossing
						its head and wagging its fat woolly tail, would scamper off in an absurdly awkward
						frolic; but it always tinkled back again, and presently they all turned into the path
						beyond the cypress trees and toward the open door of the fold.</p>

					<p>This was a small enclosure rudely built of rough stones, which were most plentiful at
						the foot of the mountains; it had a wooden door and was roofed with thatch. <pb
							id="VAB1854-033" n="18"/> For it was well to have one's flock safely housed at night,
						not only to keep it from straying, but also to guard against the possible visit of
						greedy wolves, which had sometimes been known to prowl down from the rocky crags
						above.</p>

					<p>As Jean was about to fasten the door of the fold, his father, Père Favette, chanced to
						come along, and, glancing in, saw the strange goat. He blinked with surprise, rubbed his
						eyes, looked again, and then stopped stock-still with amazement. He turned sternly to
						Jean for explanation.</p>

					<p>"What means this, lad?" he said, "whose goat hast thou brought home with ours?"</p>

					<p>"Nay, father," answered Jean, "I have taken her from no one! <pb id="VAB1854-034"
							n="19"/> Yesterday she came and fed with our flock, and again to-day; and truly she
						has followed them here of her own will. I said naught to coax her, and I have no idea
						where she came from; but, father, I am sure she does not belong to any farm in this
						valley."</p>

					<p>At this Père Favette was very much perplexed. He was an honest soul, and he knew Jean
						had always been a truth-telling child. He believed what the boy said, but he did not
						like the idea of harbouring this fine strange goat from no one knew where. He was afraid
						the peasant folk might think he had stolen her. Yet surely it would be a shame to turn
						her out now; perhaps to stray up into the mountains and be eaten by wolves.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-035" n="20"/>

					<p>He thought a while, and then at last he said, " Well, child, I suppose we can but let
						her stay to-night, seeing we know not who her owner may be. To-morrow I will tell Father
						Antoine, and ask him what to do."</p>

					<p>Now Father Antoine was the parish priest, who knew every one in the valley and was very
						wise besides; so Père Favette felt that his advice would be quite worth while.</p>

					<p>Jean devoutly hoped that the priest would not make him give up the goat, but he did not
						think he would. He said to himself, "Father Antoine surely would not keep her, and who
						else is there to take her away?" For down in his heart he was certain that she was
						enchanted, and belonged to no one <pb id="VAB1854-036" n="21"/> but the far away
						Saracens. And as everybody knew that the Saracens were wicked heathens whom the armies
						of Christendom at that very time were crusading against in the Holy Land, Jean felt that
						it was perfectly right for him to keep their Golden Goat and the treasure too, when he
						found it as he was sure he would. So he contentedly fastened the door of the fold and
						followed his father toward the cottage.</p>
				</div2>

				<pb id="VAB1854-037" n="22"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER II</head>
					<head rend="center sc">THE SURPRISE IN THE COTTAGE</head>

					<p>
						<hi rend="b">L</hi>IKE most of the farmhouses of the valley, the Favette home was small
						and very old. Its walls were covered with stucco, and its few windows protected by
						wooden shutters that had once upon a time been painted a light grass green; but the hot
						summer sun of Provence had long ago faded them to a soft indefinite colour, just as it
						had turned the tiles of the roof pale buff and brown instead of the brave red with which
						they had started out.</p>

					<p>A gourd vine hung with striped yellow and white fruit clambered <pb id="VAB1854-038"
							n="23"/> over the cottage walls and a great fig tree quite over-shadowed it. The bit
						of ground about it was enclosed by a frail leaning fence made of the slender gray stalks
						of wild cane bound together with withes of osiers. Stretching off back of the house was
						a small turnip field, another of barley, a little vegetable garden, two or three olive
						and fig trees and a few grapevines, though the soil was too stony for anything to
						flourish well.</p>

					<p>The cottage within had just two rooms, one good sized and one very tiny. In the larger
						one all the real life of the family went on. The floor was paved with coarse tiles, and
						overhead, from the brown rafters, hung strings of dried herbs, a few pieces of bacon and
						some <pb id="VAB1854-039" n="24"/> wicker baskets, in one of them a long loaf of bread.
						At one end of the room was the fireplace where the mother cooked, and at each side of it
						stood a high bed and a little stool to help climb into it. Then there was a table in the
						middle of the room and wooden benches for the children to sit on while they ate their
						meals, a clothes press, a tall clock, a churn, a dresser for the few earthen dishes and
						pots and kettles, some jars for olives, a little hutch in which were some baby rabbits;
						indeed almost everything that belonged to the Favette family was to be found there.</p>

					<p>And whatever there was no place for in the living room was tucked into the little room
						beyond, that had only an earthen floor and a queer <pb id="VAB1854-040" n="25"/> bed
						built into the wall like a cupboard.</p>

					<p>Like all the other peasant folk in the region, Père Favette had to pay rent for the
						little cottage and farm to the Lord of Baux who owned all the land. That is to say, the
						peasants had to send the castle folk a large part of the little they were able to raise
						on the small farms allotted to them; they seldom saw any money, and were thus obliged to
						pay the lord of the country with meat and vegetables, butter and cheese, grapes and
						olives and whatever nice things they could manage to wring from the stony soil, though
						it left almost nothing for themselves. It was not a fertile valley, and those who, like
						Père Favette, lived nearest the mountains, where the land <pb id="VAB1854-041" n="26"/>
						was poorest of all, had to toil early and late to get a bare living.</p>

					<p>In the Favette home besides the father and mother and Jean, who was the eldest of the
						children, there were also little Pierre and Annette and baby Henri, who could just
						toddle about. It was hard work to clothe and feed them all, to be sure; and yet the
						summers were long and warm, and melons and figs ripened easily, so they could get along
						much better than if they had lived in a less kindly land. And then, too, all the
						children were gay and happy hearted, which went a very long way.</p>

					<p>When Père Favette and Jean entered the cottage they found their supper ready and
						waiting. Mere Favette sat at one end of the long <pb id="VAB1854-042" n="27"/> brown
						table that stood in the middle of the living room, and the children sat on the wooden
						benches at either side, while a chair stood at the head for the father. In the center of
						the table was an earthen bowl of potato soup, and then there was bread and some little
						melons, for this was the chief meal of the day.</p>

					<p>"Come, Jean," said Annette, making room for him on the bench beside her.</p>
					<p>"Yes," said the mother, "the soup is getting cold. Thou wast long in penning up the
						flock to-night."</p>
					<p>At this Jean looked at his father, and the father, still perplexed, said, "We were
						looking at the strange goat that came home with Jean."</p>
					<p>"Strange goat?" said the mother in an amazed tone.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-043" n="28"/>

					<p>"Strange goat?" repeated the children, dropping their wooden spoons full of soup,
						spilling it over the mother's freshly scoured table. And then in true Provencal fashion
						they were all excitement, and jumping up from their benches, nothing would do but they
						must run out to the sheepfold and see for themselves.</p>

					<p>When the father and mother and Jean reached the fold, the other children, who had raced
						on ahead, were already peering through the chinks between the stones, and when Jean
						opened the door, in they rushed.</p>

					<p>"O," said Pierre, "what nice long hair!"</p>

					<p>"What a pretty yellow colour!" cried Annette.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-044" n="29"/>

					<p>Baby Henri all the while chattered loudly, though no one paid any heed to him, and the
						father and mother discussed it together, While, "Where did it come from, Jean?" "Jean,
						Jean, is it ours?" and a thousand other questions burst from the nimble tongues of
						Pierre and Annette.</p>
					<p>When Jean had at last satisfied their curiosity as best he could, and they had all
						inspected the strange goat which good-naturedly allowed them to walk about and pat her
						admiringly, they once more trooped back to the cottage and finished the soup, which by
						this time had grown quite cold; but no one minded that.</p>

					<p>And then, by and by, the mother tucked the two younger children into one of the high
						old-fashioned <pb id="VAB1854-045" n="30"/> beds that stood on either side the fireplace
						in the cottage living room, and Jean and Pierre went off to the queer cupboard bed in
						the wall of the little room beyond.</p>

					<p>Before long every one in the cottage was fast asleep but Jean. He had breathed no word
						to any one, not even to his little bed-fellow Pierre, as to what he thought about the
						new-comer in the sheepfold. He called her always the Golden Goat, but that was only to
						himself, and he happily pictured over and over the surprise and delight of the family
						when he found the hidden treasure and brought it home to them. At last, though still
						with his head full of dreams, he, too, fell asleep.</p>
				</div2>

				<pb id="VAB1854-046" n="31"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER III</head>
					<head rend="center sc">JEAN'S IDEA</head>

					<p>
						<hi rend="b">T</hi>HE next day Père Favette sought out Father Antoine, as he had said,
						and telling him of the unknown goat, asked his advice as to what he should do with
						it.</p>

					<p>Father Antoine, after thinking it over a few minutes, told the Père that he thought
						Jean was right, and that the goat did not belong to any one in their valley, but that
						perhaps she had strayed from some wealthy owner of uncommon varieties somewhere on the
						other side of the mountains. "But," he added, "I will remember about her, and when I go
							<pb id="VAB1854-047" n="32"/> through the parish will ask if any one has lost such a
						goat. Meanwhile you may as well keep her with your little flock."</p>

					<p>So the goat stayed in the Favette fold, and day by day Jean took the flock to pasture;
						and as he watched them through the long, bright hours he dreamed many, many dreams.</p>

					<p>He used to look at his crutch and sigh, and wonder what he could do when he grew to be
						a man. He knew he never could become a soldier--as Pierre wished to be--because of his
						lameness. Sometimes he wondered if priests were ever lame and if he could be one like
						Father Antoine; but then he would remember that he would have to be very wise to be a
						priest, <pb id="VAB1854-048" n="33"/> and poor little Jean not only had no books, but
						could not have read them if he had. For in those days, except the priests and
						brotherhoods of men who lived in monasteries, very few people could read or write. Then
						Jean would think that he did not wish to tend a few sheep all his life, and he knew he
						could not do much of the hard work about the farm as he was not strong and it was hard
						for a lame boy to get about. So he did not quite see how he could get his own living and
						help the family, unless he could find the treasure hidden in the mountains.</p>

					<p>The Golden Goat he petted and tended most carefully. Often he would gather flowers and
						weave little garlands which he would hang <pb id="VAB1854-049" n="34"/> around her neck;
						though he soon found that he must make these not too long, for if he did, the goat would
						very likely nibble the blossoms, which somehow he did not expect an enchanted animal to
						do.</p>

					<p>Yet even though the petted one ate them up, Jean delighted to make these garlands; for
						he was passionately fond of flowers, and one of his greatest pleasures was to limp about
						through the fields and woods hunting the different kinds. And there were so many
						varieties! Poppies and lilies in the fields; white candy-tuft, drifted over the bare
						ground of the olive orchards and shining like snow in April; along the roadsides the
						scarlet flowers of wild pomegranates, little thistles with round sky-blue balls of <pb
							id="VAB1854-050" n="35"/> bloom, thyme with its gray-green leaves and dainty starry
						flowers of rosy purple, and everywhere the tall feathery sprays of wild lavender
						overhung by honey-bees. It bordered all the paths with a soft misty colour and clambered
						up the rocky slopes of the Alpilles, all the while scenting the air with its delicate
						aromatic fragrance.</p>

					<p>Jean loved to gather great handfuls of flowers and then he would sit for hours
						examining each one with the greatest care, till soon he knew how each grew, what soil it
						loved best, whether field or meadow or woodland, and the season of its blossoming.</p>

					<p>He had carried home many of his favourites from time to time and planted them around
						the cottage; <pb id="VAB1854-051" n="36"/> and Jean seemed to be one of those fortunate
						folk under whose fingers every growing thing flourishes. No matter how tiny the root or
						how withered seemed the plant that he brought home, it always took heart and grew when
						he tended it.</p>

					<p>And as Jean thus busied himself studying the flowers and weaving collars of wild
						lavender and poppies to deck out the Golden Goat, he did not forget to keep close watch
						on the movements of the latter. He was always expecting her to wander back to her
						enchanted cavern. But day after day, she browsed quietly with the others.</p>

					<p>Sometimes, it is true, she clambered up the rocky slopes of the mountains, and then
						Jean would <pb id="VAB1854-052" n="37"/> eagerly take up his little crutch and try to
						follow her. But always the rocks became so steep and rough that the poor little boy was
						quite unable to climb them; and then he would stand shading his eyes with his hand and
						look, oh, so hard! in his effort to watch the path of the goat. But she would go
						frisking along, jumping from rock to rock, hidden now and then by thickets of underwood,
						till he would have to give it up as hopeless.</p>

					<p>So the summer wore away and the autumn drew on; though the hot sun had parched the
						meadows so that Jean was obliged to wander far to find pasture for his flock, in the
						less rocky parts of the valley the olives and grapes were ripening. Day by day they grew
						plumper <pb id="VAB1854-053" n="38"/> and rounder, and soon through the groves and
						vineyards of the better farms the peasant folk began to gather the harvest.</p>

					<p>It was a busy time, and every day along the roads and byways went quaint two-wheeled
						carts of bright blue drawn by horses wearing high pointed collars tipped with scarlet
						pompons, or little jingling bells. Some of these carts carried the olives to
						old-fashioned mills where the oil was pressed out, but most of them bore brown wicker
						baskets of grapes going to the village wine-press.</p>

					<p>Such a pretty sight it was, these carts laden with pale green and rosy purple! And as
						the olives and grapes must be harvested quickly when once ripe, every one who <pb
							id="VAB1854-054" n="39"/> possibly could went out to help gather them. And so it was
						that during this busy time little Jean had extra work too; for he had the care of
						another and larger flock of sheep. These belonged to a peasant who lived on a better
						piece of land than the Favettes and who needed the help of his shepherd at the grape
						harvest. So it kept Jean and his crutch busy all day long to see that none of his charge
						strayed away.</p>

					<p>By and by, into the mellow autumn sunshine there began to creep a hint of the Provencal
						winter. The vintage season was over, and the Christmas time drew on.</p>

					<p>All the while the Golden Goat stayed with the Favette flock, or <pb id="VAB1854-055"
							n="40"/> else rambled in such steep rocky places that poor little Jean could not keep
						pace with her. He had, at last, begun to despair of ever finding out where to seek the
						hidden treasure.</p>

					<p>But one day, as he was driving the sheep and goats homeward, and thinking of the
						Christmas time now near at hand, suddenly something occurred to him that sent a happy
						smile over his face. He remembered that Father Antoine had many times told the children
						of the parish the story of the Christ Child's coming on earth; and had he not said that
						on the Holy Night, when the heavenly Babe was born, all the animals in the stable about
						him, the ox and the ass, the cows and sheep and <pb id="VAB1854-056" n="41"/> goats,
						were gifted with a miraculous power to speak, so they might greet the blessed Child? And
						Father Antoine had also said that ever since then, at midnight of the holy Christmas
						Eve, all such animals could speak as at the time of the Christ Child's birth.</p>

					<p>"And so," thought Jean, "if I can be in the sheepfold at midnight Christmas Eve,
						perhaps, if I ask the Golden Goat, she will tell me how to find the treasure! Surely the
						Christ Child would be glad for me to find it, for we are so poor.</p>

					<p>And straightway the little boy's head was again filled with all sorts of happy dreams.
						When he would bring the gold and jewels home <pb id="VAB1854-057" n="42"/> they would
						build a beautiful castle like the castle of Baux, his father and mother would not have
						to work so hard any more, nor worry about bread enough for all of them. And then, too,
						Jean himself could study hard and grow wise, and learn all about the wonderful trees and
						flowers that grew in all of the world. And he would have a great garden, the most
						beautiful ever seen, and the children should play in it all day long, and never have to
						weed the turnip field in the hot summer sun, nor, in winter, carry heavy bundles of
						fagots down the stony mountain paths.</p>

					<p>Oh, yes, there were so many nice and pleasant things one could do with the treasure;
						for Jean was a generous-hearted boy, and he <pb id="VAB1854-058" n="43"/> longed for the
						gold far more because of the beautiful things he could do with it for those he loved
						than for anything it might bring to himself.</p>
				</div2>

				<pb id="VAB1854-059" n="44"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER IV</head>
					<head rend="center sc">THE COMING OF CHRISTMAS</head>

					<p>
						<hi rend="b">A</hi>S the Christmas time drew on, though many of the noble lords and
						their followers were off warring in the Holy Land, the peasant folk at home began to
						make preparations to keep the blessed time as it had always been kept for many, many
						centuries.</p>

					<p>In the valley where Jean lived, the children were busy a week ahead of the great day.
						They clambered up the lower slopes of the mountains and gathered green laurel boughs and
						branches of scarlet haw berries, which they called "the little apples of St. <pb
							id="VAB1854-060" n="45"/> John"; for in Provence it does not grow very cold and many
						things are green all the year. Then they made the pretty things they had found into
						wreaths and festoons, which they hung about all the old stone crosses and shrines that
						stood here and there along the waysides, so that travelers might stop and remember the
						good God with a little prayer.</p>


					<p>These shrines soon looked very gay and bright. Nor did the little ones forget their
						feathered friends; for these, they bound together tiny sheaves of wheat, and presently
						in the courtyards of all the larger farms these small sheaves might be seen, each
						fastened to the tip of a tall pole, a Christmas offering to the birds.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-061" n="46"/>

					<p>And then there were the Yule logs to be cut by the peasant fathers and brought home for
						the Christmas fires; and the special supper of Christmas eve and the feast of the great
						day itself,--these must be made ready by all the busy peasant mothers.</p>

					<p>The Favette farm was so poor and stony that Jean's father had been able to provide but
						little with which to keep the holiday time, but they did the best they could with the
						little they had.</p>

					<p>For the Yule log it was the custom to cut a fruit tree where one had plenty; but this
						was not to be thought of by Père Favette, for their few olive and fig trees were too
						much needed; they would feed the Yule fire with a small <pb id="VAB1854-062" n="47"/>
						branch from one of these, and that would do quite as well. For the log itself on the
						morning of the day before Christmas they made a little procession up one of the slopes
						of the Alpilles. The father, with baby Henri toddling behind him, led the way, and the
						mother, Annette, Pierre, and Jean with his crutch, came behind.</p>

					<p>Now, all the region belonged to the Lord of Baux, and the poor peasants could not cut
						down the forest trees without permission, though they might gather for firewood such
						fagots and fallen trees as they could find. So Père Favette looked about, and at last
						decided upon a spruce tree that had blown down the year before, <pb id="VAB1854-063"
							n="48"/> and from which he saw that he could cut a good-sized log.</p>

					<p>All the children and the mother watched him with great interest as he chopped off the
						little branches and shaped the log for the fireplace; for the Christmas fire was no
						ordinary affair, but everything connected with its building was in some way a quaint
						ceremony.</p>


					<p>When at last the father had the log ready, he fastened a stout rope about it, which he
						had brought, so that he might drag it down the mountain, and along the road home. As he
						took the rope in his strong hands, the mother put the dangling end of it in the chubby
						palms of baby Henri; for the pretty, old custom was that the <pb id="VAB1854-064" n="49"
						/> home-bringing of the Yule log must be by the oldest and youngest in the family. So
						little Henri felt quite important as he toddled along in his small wooden shoes, and
						thought he was helping to pull the heavy load, that trailed along behind, quite as much
						as the father.</p>

					<p>When they reached the cottage the father, carrying the log in his sturdy arms, brought
						it in and laid it in the fireplace. Afterward Jean and Annette and Pierre made a wreath
						of holly, which they fastened around it, and it was ready for the evening, when they
						would place it on the fire.</p>

					<p>And then while Annette was busy tidying up the house, and the mother doing a little
						extra cooking <pb id="VAB1854-065" n="50"/> at the fireplace, and baby Henri pattering
						about taking a hand in everything, Jean went out to lead the sheep and goats along the
						road to feed. The grass was brown, and there had been some frosts, but still they could
						nibble enough to keep them.</p>

					<p>As the little boy limped along the road behind the flock, he kept thinking all the
						while "To-night will be Christmas eve, and at midnight perhaps the Golden Goat will tell
						me about the treasure!" And then his generous little soul, touched and swayed by the
						gracious spirit of the Christmas time, saw lovely visions of all the beautiful things he
						meant to do with the hidden riches.</p>

					<p>Presently he passed a poor old <pb id="VAB1854-066" n="51"/> beggar hobbling along with
						a staff, and his heart swelled with pity. "Oh," he breathed to himself, "when I find the
						Saracens' gold there will not be any more beggars in our valley. I will help them all!"
						And thinking how happy he was going to make every one, he limped slower and slower, and
						the flock loitered along as it pleased, and the tinkling bell of the lamb, which by this
						time had grown into quite a sheep, fell unheeded upon his ears.</p>

					<p>Here and there along the road the wind stirred the gay garlands on some wayside shrine,
						and in the distance, up on the gray crags, where rose the town of Les Baux, over the
						castle fluttered a blood-red banner on which shone a single <pb id="VAB1854-067" n="52"
						/> white star. For the lords of Baux claimed to have sprung from no humbler source than
						royal Balthazar, one of the Three Wise Kings who had come out of the East to seek the
						blessed Christ Child as he lay in the manger of Bethlehem. And so, whatever was going on
						with the castle folk, whether peace or war, always at Christmas time this red banner was
						unfurled from the castle parapets, and the white star, in memory of the wonderful star
						that had led the Three Kings, glittered and shone and fluttered from the mountain top
						and seemed to fill the valley with a sweet peace.</p>

					<p>Little Jean, with his heart full of kindly thoughts, caught its influence too, and felt
						that in some <pb id="VAB1854-068" n="53"/> mysterious way the spirit of King Balthazar
						brooded over the valley, and that the dear Christ Child whom he had worshipped was very
						near and real.</p>

				</div2>
				<pb id="VAB1854-069" n="54"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER V</head>
					<head rend="center sc">CHRISTMAS EVE</head>

					<p>
						<hi rend="b">J</hi>EAN was still seeing happy visions when the time came to guide the
						flock back to the fold. He took them home earlier than usual, for the December days had
						grown shorter. And then, too, he wanted to go to the Ranier farm before supper time, and
						it took him long to reach it with his limping steps. It was the sheep from this farm
						that he had tended through the vintage season.</p>

					<p>Mère Ranier had told Jean to be sure and come to her sometime on this day before
						Christmas, for one of the good old customs of <pb id="VAB1854-070" n="55"/> the Provence
						peasants who were better off, was that every one who had worked for them through the
						year should receive a gift of sweetmeats in honour of the Christ Child's birthday. It
						was usual to give each a fougasse, which was a kind of nice large doughnut, always very
						marvelously made in fanciful shapes, of crispy brown; and each labourer received also a
						handful of nuts and figs, and a stick of almond nougat.</p>

					<p>As Mère Ranier had particularly reminded him not to forget his Christmas visit, as soon
						as the flock had been safely penned up in the fold, Jean limped along the road to the
						Ranier farm.</p>

					<p>"A merry, merry Christmas, Jean!" cried Mère Ranier, as she <pb id="VAB1854-071" n="56"
						/> caught sight of him from the dooryard of the farm-house, where she was distributing
						her gifts to a number of peasant labourers.</p>

					<p>"Come here, child, I have a special fougasse for thee." And with this, kind-hearted
						Mère Ranier, who was fond of Jean and pitied him because of his lameness, gave him a
						little wicker basket in which was a wonderful fougasse made like a braid of dough and
						sprinkled with sugar, a double handful each of figs and almonds, a piece of nougat, and
						besides these the basket contained six little honey cakes, which had been baked on the
						hearth and were an especial treat he had never before had.</p>

					<p>Jean was delighted with all <pb id="VAB1854-072" n="57"/> these nice things. The Mère
						Ranier had given him much the same the year before, and he knew how good they were and
						how they had all enjoyed them; for of course he had shared everything, as he meant to do
						this time, with the folks at home. After thanking Mère Ranier and wishing her a happy
						Christmas, he hung the basket over one arm, and taking his crutch set off for home.</p>

					<p>When he came near the cottage, Annette and Pierre were watching for him, and running
						down the road, they met him with "O Jean, look! the Mere has braided the fougasse this
						time!" And then, sniffing it rapturously, "How good it smells!"</p>

					<p>Jean laughed, and said, "You <pb id="VAB1854-073" n="58"/> shall do more than smell it
						by and by." For he was very proud and pleased that he was thus able to bring home a
						little holiday treat, as sweetmeats were seldom seen in the homes of the poorer peasant
						children.</p>

					<p>When he reached the cottage Jean placed the basket with the precious fougasse and the
						other things on a shelf by the fireplace; that is, all but the honey cakes, these he had
						put in his blouse pocket, for he wanted to surprise the children with them the next
						day.</p>

					<p>Indeed, unless one had a great plenty, which few peasants ever did, it was not the
						custom to eat any of such sweetmeats until the great day itself. The supper of <pb
							id="VAB1854-074" n="59"/> Christmas eve was held to be not the true feast time but a
						vigil awaiting the birthday of the Christ Child. So, from time immemorial, the folks of
						Provence had settled upon certain things that it was considered proper to have at this
						supper. No one thought of eating meat then; but instead, there were fish and fruits,
						nuts and bread and wine, and, if one lived in a castle where such things were to be had,
						many sweets were added.</p>

					<p>The castle people, too, spread their tables with three linen cloths, one above another,
						and lighted them with seven wax candles in silver candlesticks and observed much
						ceremony in the making of the supper. The poorer people did the best they could to
						honour <pb id="VAB1854-075" n="60"/> the old customs, though in a far humbler way.</p>

					<p>In Jean's home they had no linen cloths or silver candlesticks, but the mother had
						scoured the bare table until it fairly shone. In the center, stuck in a pewter holder,
						was a homemade candle of tallow, and beneath it was a coarse earthenware saucer in
						which, growing in a little earth and water, was a tiny crop of fine green blades of
						wheat. This was called St. Barbara's grain, and at this supper, in every peasant family,
						such a plate was to be seen on the table; the seeds were always planted long enough
						before so that they might have time to sprout, and every one watched these little dishes
						very anxiously, because they believed that if the wheat sprang <pb id="VAB1854-076"
							n="61"/> up green and sturdy, so would be their harvest for the coming year, but if it
						grew pale and scanty they might look for poor crops to come.</p>

					<p>Jean had planted and tended their little saucer of seeds, and he was very pleased to
						see that the green blades stood straight and sturdy.</p>

					<p>"Ah, Jean," said the father, "'tis a pity thou canst not plant all the seeds in the
						fields, for thou knowest how to please the good St. Barbara!"</p>

					<p>As Jean looked at his lame foot and sighed, the mother hastened to say, "Never mind,
						child, thou art the best little shepherd in all the valley! And no one can find such
						nice snails as thou! See, <pb id="VAB1854-077" n="62"/> Jean, I have them cooked as thou
						likest them best." And she pointed to a bowl filled with small steaming hot shells in
						which were the snails that Provence folks think so fine a dish.</p>

					<p>They had no plates for the table, but at each place was a long thorn from an acacia
						tree that grew in the dooryard, and with these the snails were to be taken out of their
						shells. Then, besides the snails, there was a fish which the father had caught in a
						stream down in the valley; there were also a few dried figs, and at one corner of the
						table a large round loaf of bread. This Christmas loaf was always a special one baked on
						the hearth with great care. On its top the mother had cut a deep cross before <pb
							id="VAB1854-078" n="63"/> baking it, so that it still plainly showed in the brown
						crust through which was stuck a sprig of holly; for this loaf was especially dedicated
						to the Christ Child.</p>

					<p>All was now ready, but the Yule log must be lighted before they sat down to eat, so
						they gathered in front of the fireplace while the father lifted the log with its wreath
						of holly and laid it on the fire. Then, before it had time to blaze up, he took a cup of
						wine from the little supply carefully kept from year to year for this purpose, and,
						pouring it on the Yule log, made a little prayer to the good God that He would bless and
						keep them during the coming year.</p>

					<p>When this pretty, old ceremony was finished, they all sat down to <pb id="VAB1854-079"
							n="64"/> supper, and first of all the father divided the Christmas loaf into a piece
						for each one there, taking care to leave a large extra piece. This he placed in the
						middle of the table by itself; for every one knew that this part of the loaf was what
						the peasant folk called " God's Share," and was considered the right of the first beggar
						that came to the door. And in those troubled times of the crusading wars, the country in
						many places was neglected and untilled, and there was much poverty and many begging
						their bread. But the peasant people tried always to help one another, and the family was
						poor indeed that did not set aside a "God's Share" of the Christmas loaf.</p>

					<p>When at last they began to eat, <pb id="VAB1854-080" n="65"/> every one was so hungry,
						and it seemed such a feast to them, and they laughed and talked so happily that they
						thought the Christmas eve supper was really gayer than the great day itself. And such a
						merry time, too, as the children had getting the snails out of their curly shells; more
						than once they broke their acacia thorns in their eager efforts, but there were more
						thorns on the tree, and they would scamper out for fresh ones.</p>

					<p>When they had finished, and the mother with Annette's help had straightened the table,
						they began to talk of the midnight mass in the village church of St. Remy.</p>


					<p>Now every one wanted to go to this Christmas eve service, which <pb id="VAB1854-081"
							n="66"/> was always very beautiful with its music of singing voices and the golden
						candle light of the altar, and the wonderful "crèche" made to look like the manger in
						Bethlehem, and the Christmas garlands and green boughs everywhere.</p>

					<p>Some of the peasants of the valley climbed up the mountains to Les Baux and heard mass
						in the ancient stone church in the midst of the town, and this service was finer still.
						But the Favette cottage being a little nearer the village of St. Remy, they always went
						thither, as it was hard work for the little children to climb up the steep mountain
						roads, and especially poor Jean with his crutch. Indeed to go to St. Remy on foot was
						more than he <pb id="VAB1854-082" n="67"/> could do without growing painfully tired. And
						so for two years past a neighbor peasant, who had a donkey and two-wheeled cart, used to
						take Jean to the village. But this time the cart was broken from going over a sharp rock
						and was not yet mended; so there seemed no way for the little boy to go unless he limped
						along on his crutch.</p>

					<p>The mother could not bear to get the other children ready and leave Jean behind, for
						because of his lameness her heart was especially tender toward him.</p>

					<p>But Jean, who really loved to go to the wonderful midnight mass, was secretly very glad
						that this time there was no way to take him. He did not wish to miss being in <pb
							id="VAB1854-083" n="68"/> the sheepfold at midnight, when he felt sure he might learn
						important things from the Golden Goat. Indeed, he had wondered much how he would manage
						to be at home at this time, and so he was delighted that things had come about as they
						did.</p>

					<p>The children were so excited getting ready for the walk that they did not notice him,
						though the mother wondered that he showed no disappointment at being left behind. It
						quite consoled her, though, as she kissed him goodbye and told him not to be lonesome,
						but to go to bed when he grew sleepy, and they would soon be home again.</p>

					<p>And so they all trooped off, the father carrying baby Henri, who <pb id="VAB1854-084"
							n="69"/> was expected to walk part of the way, however, and the others following after
						and singing as they went.</p>

					<p>Jean, who watched them out of sight in the star-lit dark, could now and then hear
						groups of other peasants caroling their quaint old Christmas songs, or Noels, as they
						trudged along the valley roads toward St. Remy; or the sweet strains floating down from
						the mountain paths, as more adventurous ones took the way to Les Baux.</p>

				</div2>

				<pb id="VAB1854-085" n="70"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER VI</head>
					<head rend="center sc">IN THE SHEEPFOLD</head>

					<p>
						<hi rend="b">W</hi>HEN left alone Jean was fairly trembling with excitement, and
						determined to go to the sheepfold very soon, as they had no clock and he was afraid he
						might miss the time; for he knew that it was only for a few minutes on the stroke of
						midnight that the miracle happened and the animals could speak. He was sure he would
						know the moment by the peal of bells that always echoed through the valley from the
						distant church at St. Remy and shaken down from the towers of Les Baux.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-086" n="71"/>

					<p>He sat and dreamed by the blaze of the Yule log for a little while, and then, taking
						down a small lantern that hung in the chimney-place, he lighted it and made his way out
						to the fold. It was quite dark, but the Christmas stars twinkled brightly through the
						frosty air.</p>

					<p>When he reached the fold and unbuttoned the door, he held the lantern very carefully as
						he stepped over the threshold with his crutch. Once inside, the light he carried seemed
						very faint in the velvety darkness. He looked around, and when his eyes grew accustomed
						to the dusk, he saw that the sheep were dozing with their toes doubled up under their
						thick fleece, while the two gray goats and the Golden <pb id="VAB1854-087" n="72"/>
						Goat, still wearing the collar of holly sprigs that Jean had made for her that day, were
						sleeping standing up, huddled together, for the night was chill.</p>

					<p>They all blinked in sleepy amazement at Jean with his lantern, and one or two of the
						sheep gave faint "baas!"</p>

					<p>Jean patted them gently, and then, as he put down his lantern and made a little pile of
						straw so that he might sit down by the Golden Goat, suddenly happening to glance toward
						a corner of the fold, where a ray of light fell, he started with surprise.
						For--yes!--surely, it looked as if some one was there hiding in the shadows!</p>

					<p>He got to his feet as soon as he could and, lifting up the lantern, <pb
							id="VAB1854-088" n="[]"/>
						<figure>
							<p>"<hi rend="b">L</hi>IFTING UP THE LANTERN, TOOK<lb/> A STEP TOWARD THE CORNER"</p>
						</figure>
						<pb id="VAB1854-089" n="[]"/>
						<pb id="VAB1854-090" n="73"/> took a step toward the corner, and there, sure enough, the
						light shone full upon the face and figure of a man crouching against the stone wall.</p>

					<p>For perhaps a full minute neither one moved; Jean standing quite still, staring at the
						stranger, who, on his part, looked at Jean with equal intentness. Jean saw that the man
						was not young, that his hair was gray, and his sunken cheeks looked very wan and
						haggard. His eyes shone with an almost feverish brightness, and his thin hands nervously
						plucked at a torn cloak half wrapped about him.</p>

					<p>In spite of his pitiful appearance he had the air of one gently bred, and presently he
						said to Jean,--<pb id="VAB1854-091" n="74"/>and his voice was very faint and
						weak,--"Have no fear, little one. I am no robber, nor am I here to do harm to you or
						your flock."</p>

					<p>Jean was silent a moment, and then answered, "Nay, Sir, I am not afraid. I do not
						believe you are a robber; and even if you were, Father Antoine says no one need fear
						robbers or witches or bad fairies at the blessed Christmas time, for they can do no
						harm."</p>

					<p>"Very true," said the stranger. "And yet, child, you might do harm to me!"</p>

					<p>"I!" said Jean, opening his eyes still wider with surprise, "How, sir?"</p>

					<p>Indeed, to look at the two, the little lame boy and the pale, feeble-looking man, it
						would have seemed <pb id="VAB1854-092" n="75"/> that neither one could do much hurt to
						any one.</p>

					<p>But the stranger went on, "If you were to tell anybody that I am here it might cost me
						my life."</p>

					<p>At this Jean looked greatly perplexed, and after studying his honest, thoughtful little
						face for a few moments, the man went on, in a whisper, "Lad, since you have found me so
						unexpectedly, I will tell you how I happen to be here. You have seen the great castle of
						Les Baux, up on the mountain top?"</p>

					<p>"Yes," whispered Jean, "I have seen it from here in the valley."</p>

					<p>"Well," said the other, "perhaps you have heard of its dungeons hewn out of the rock."
						The stranger shivered as he went on.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-093" n="76"/>

					<p>"I have been imprisoned in one of those for more than a year, and last night, with the
						help of one of the jailers, who pitied me, I made my escape.</p>

					<p>"In coming down the mountain yonder, in the darkness, I fell from one of the rocks. I
						swooned, I think, and by and by, when I came to myself, it was daylight. I dragged
						myself to a thicket of bushes and lay hidden till it grew dark again. And then, at last,
						I made my way down into the valley, and I saw this sheepfold and opened the door and
						crept in here for a while for shelter and warmth; for there are wolves in the forest up
						there, and I was very cold. Do you understand now, little one?"</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-094" n="77"/>

					<p>Jean, who was breathlessly listening, nodded, as the tears streamed down his cheeks;
						for the stranger's distress had so melted his heart that he could not speak.</p>

					<p>"Now," continued the other, "if the Lord of Baux finds me, he will kill me; for he will
						be very angry because I have escaped from his dungeon. So you must tell no one that you
						have seen me here, and if I can gather strength, I will try and move on before daybreak;
						though I had hoped I might hide here for a day or two while they will be searching for
						me."</p>

					<p>With this, the stranger fell back so weak and exhausted, that Jean was frightened.</p>

					<p>"Oh, sir," he said, "would you not like a sip of wine?"</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-095" n="78"/>

					<p>But the man was too weak to speak. So Jean, turning around, hurried back to the cottage
						as fast as he could and made his way into the living-room. By the light of the Yule-log,
						for he had left his lantern in the fold, he found the bottle and cup from which the
						father had poured the wine for the Christmas fire, and hastily snatching them up, again
						started for the fold.</p>

					<p>When he entered this he found the man as he had left him, crouching on the ground and
						half leaning against the wall. His eyes were closed and he looked very wan and
						frail.</p>

					<p>Jean knelt by him holding the wine to his lips, and presently he swallowed a little,
						and then opened <pb id="VAB1854-096" n="79"/> his eyes and seemed to grow somewhat
						stronger.</p>

					<p>All at once, as Jean watched him, it occurred to him that the stranger might be hungry.
						"Yes," he thought to himself, "I think he must be hungry; he looks so white and thin,
						and if he has been so long in the dungeon perhaps he has not had enough to eat!" Which
						was quite true; for people in those days were in many ways very cruel.</p>

					<p>Every castle had its terrible underground dungeons, just as much a matter of course as
						its towers or banquet hall. And in these dark, dismal places noble lords often kept
						captive other nobles whose only offence was that they had been captured, perhaps in <pb
							id="VAB1854-097" n="80"/> some one of the many unjust private wars of those lawless
						and turbulent times.</p>

					<p>Such indeed was the case with the stranger in the Favette sheepfold, of whom I will
						tell you more by and by. He had escaped from his prison more dead than alive, and during
						the time he had wandered on the mountain had had nothing to eat. So it was small wonder
						that when at last he crept in with Jean's sheep, he was almost too exhausted to
						speak.</p>

					<p>As Jean, full of his kindly desire to find some food for his unexpected guest, made a
						sudden movement to rise, the stranger said in alarm, "O, child, is any one coming? Does
						the rest of your family know that I am here?"</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-098" n="81"/>

					<p>"Do not be afraid, sir," answered Jean, "they have all gone to the church at St. Remy.
						No one is home but me, and I am going to the house for something, but will be back
						directly and will watch the road as I come."</p>

					<p>At this the fugitive breathed a sigh of relief, and Jean, leaving the fold, found his
						way once more to the living-room of the cottage. As he looked about in the uncertain
						light of the fire, which, by this time, was burning low, the first thing that caught his
						eye was the shelf close by the fireplace and on it the little supply of goodies that
						Mère Ranier had given him. Glad in feeling that these were his own to bestow as he
						pleased, he eagerly lifted down the wicker <pb id="VAB1854-099" n="82"/> basket of nuts
						and figs and the wonderful fougasse. His heart misgave him, though, as he looked at that
						tempting braid of sugary dough and thought of the other children's disappointment. To be
						sure, he argued, they had not been shut up in a dungeon for a whole year without enough
						to eat; they did not need the fougasse, but then he had promised to share it with them,
						so to settle the matter he quickly broke it in two and left a part for them and also the
						stick of nougat which he considered only fair, as they would get none of the nuts and
						figs which quite filled up the basket and made it look very nice.</p>

					<p>He was glad, too, in his generous little heart, when he remembered <pb id="VAB1854-100"
							n="83"/> the honey cakes that were still in his blouse pocket. It was lucky, he
						thought, that he had said nothing about those, so the children would not expect any, and
						he could add them all to the things for the stranger. He could think of nothing else to
						take; but on passing the table on his way to the door he noticed the "God's Share" of
						the Christmas loaf, which was still where the Père had placed it at supper time, as no
						beggar had yet chanced to come. Jean caught up the bread thankfully, for he felt that
						from the family's none too plentiful store of food, this, at least, he was free to
						dispose of.</p>

					<p>But all at once, just as he was placing "God's Share" in the basket, he paused in
						dismay, as <pb id="VAB1854-101" n="84"/> for the first time he realized that a faint,
						sweet sound had begun to steal through the air.</p>

					<p>He listened breathlessly, for the sound was very far away; but yes, unmistakably it was
						the pealing of bells, the joyous midnight chimes of St. Remy and Les Baux!</p>

					<p>Poor Jean! The tears sprang to his eyes from disappointment; for in the excitement of
						finding and helping the stranger in the fold, he had quite forgotten that the time had
						been slipping away and the longed-for magic hour was so near! And now here he was, in
						the cottage instead of in the sheepfold, as he had so long planned to be! And he knew
						that with his lame steps he could not possibly get back in time, for Father <pb
							id="VAB1854-102" n="85"/> Antoine had said that it was only for a few moments at the
						stroke of midnight, that the miracle happened and the animals could speak.</p>

					<p>And now, alas, he had lost his opportunity of asking the Golden Goat, for that year
						anyway. And to wait another year seemed such a long, long time before he could find the
						treasure and do all the beautiful things he had dreamed of.</p>

					<p>The little boy was indeed deeply, bitterly disappointed. But remembering his errand to
						the cottage, and that the aid he wished to give to the fugitive must be done quickly,
						before the family returned from St. Remy, he tried bravely to make the best of his <pb
							id="VAB1854-103" n="86"/> disappointment, and hanging the basket of food over his arm,
						he once more limped back to the fold.</p>

					<p>The stranger was sitting still, with a dreamy look in his eyes, as Jean approached him
						and said timidly, "I thought you might be hungry, sir; so I have brought you something
						to eat."</p>

					<p>The other, touched by the lad's act, smiled faintly and said very gently, "Thank you,
						little one, for your good heart! Perhaps I <hi rend="i"/>am hungry. I have eaten nothing
						since yesterday; and not too much for a year," he added, "for dungeon keepers do not
						greatly trouble themselves as to how their captives fare." And then he broke and ate a
						bit of the bread, though it <pb id="VAB1854-104" n="87"/> was very little, for he was
						more feverish and exhausted than he himself realized.</p>

					<p>Meantime, Jean, who had gone at once to the Golden Goat and whispered in its ear, was
						intently listening in the forlorn hope that the miracle might not yet be past. But no
						reply came save a surprised bleat from the goat. Yes, he thought in despair, he knew it
						was too late! Oh, if he had only been there in time!</p>

					<p>Then, turning to the stranger who had been watching him curiously, he said, "Did you
						hear them speak, sir?"</p>

					<p>At this the man opened his eyes in perplexity. "Who?" he asked.</p>

					<p>"Why, the sheep and goats," said Jean. "Father Antoine says <pb id="VAB1854-105" n="88"
						/> they can talk at the stroke of midnight on Christmas eve, and I missed it, for I was
						in the cottage when the bells rang a few minutes ago.</p>

					<p>"Oh," said the stranger, a light breaking upon him, "so that is why you came to the
						fold to-night? to hear the animals speak? I wondered much when I saw you come in with
						the lantern and sit down by yonder goat."</p>

					<p>"Yes," replied Jean shyly, "there was something I wanted greatly to ask her."</p>

					<p>The stranger listened gravely, and then he said, "I am very sorry, child, that it was
						because of me that you missed this. If you had not gone back for the food, you would
						have been here! Yes, <pb id="VAB1854-106" n="89"/> I am very, very sorry! And if I had
						only known, I would have listened to what they said, so I could have told you. But I am
						afraid I must have dropped into a doze for that few minutes at midnight, for I had such
						a beautiful dream."</p>

					<p>"Did you, sir?" said Jean, who liked to dream himself.</p>

					<p>"Yes," said the other, "I dreamed that the Christ Child was here in this sheepfold; and
						do you know, little one, he looked so like you!"</p>

					<p>"Oh!" exclaimed Jean in surprise, "how could that be? For you know the Christ Child
						always has a lovely golden light shining from his hair; and then, he was never lame."
						Jean added, with a sigh.</p>

					<p>"Nevertheless," answered the <pb id="VAB1854-107" n="90"/> stranger, "the Christ Child
						I saw was lame, yes, and wore wooden shoes and a little blue blouse just like a peasant
						boy--was it not strange?"</p>

					<p>But then presently the man's face grew anxious, and "Child," he said, "will they not
						soon be coming home from the church? Had you not better take the lantern and go back to
						the cottage? I dare not have them find us here!"</p>

					<p>"Yes," said Jean, "I will go now. But, sir, why can you not stay here till you can
						travel? We can make a place for you to hide here in the sheepfold, and no one need know.
						Father leaves me to tend the flock, and the children hardly ever come about in winter,
						for when they are not working and <pb id="VAB1854-108" n="91"/> have time to play they
						stay in the cottage where we have a fire; for it is chilly here."</p>

					<p>"And see," he added eagerly, for he, too, was growing anxious for fear the family
						should come home before he got back to the cottage, "here are some old boards and straw
						and we can make a place where you can hide."</p>

					<p>And soon between them they arranged the boards and a bundle of reeds left over from the
						last year's fence mending, and with these made a little shelter under which a man might
						lie concealed. There was some straw in one corner of the fold, and they placed this on
						the earthen floor to make it warmer, and then Jean put inside the hiding place the food
							<pb id="VAB1854-109" n="92"/> which he had brought, for the stranger had eaten but
						little.</p>

					<p>"There," he said in a whisper, "you can stay here, and each day I will bring you water
						and something to eat. I must go now. Good-night, sir."</p>

					<p>The stranger's eyes swam with tears as he watched the lad, carrying his lantern, limp
						through the door of the fold. The light he held before him shed a misty radiance about
						Jean's figure, and presently over the stranger's face, as he watched him, came a look of
						great awe; and bowing his head, he murmured to himself, "Surely it is true! the very
						Christ Child himself is abroad this night!"</p>

				</div2>

				<pb id="VAB1854-110" n="93"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER VII</head>
					<head rend="center sc">PERPLEXING QUESTIONS</head>

					<p>
						<hi rend="b">J</hi>EAN nervously hurried along the path to the cottage, for already in
						the distance he could hear the faint echoes of the Noels the peasants were singing on
						their homeward way from the village mass.</p>

					<p>He knew, though, that the father and mother and the children would be apt to lag
						behind, as it was a long way for little ones, and baby Henri was heavy to carry.</p>

					<p>And sure enough, Jean had time to reach the cottage and creep into the cupboard bed,
						before he heard the shrill sleepy voices of Annette <pb id="VAB1854-111" n="94"/> and
						Pierre as they trudged along the road. In another moment they all came trooping in, very
						tired from the long walk and the excitement of the midnight service; for except this one
						night in the year, the peasant folks were used to being in their beds at dark.</p>

					<p>Jean could hear Annette stirring the fire as she called in to him, "O, Jean, such
						wonderful candles on the altar, and a manger, larger than ours, with red berries stuck
						in the hay and the Christ Child in a new silken robe of blue, with gold stars about his
						head!"</p>

					<p>Jean said nothing, but wondered how the Christ Child would look as the stranger had
						dreamed him, with wooden shoes and a little peasant blouse. Of course the <pb
							id="VAB1854-112" n="95"/> silken robe and the gold stars must be very splendid, but
						somehow Jean felt he could love him best as the stranger had described him.</p>

					<p>Here Pierre burst into the room with "See, Jean! Father Antoine gave each of us
						children a honey cake and he sent one to thee!"</p>

					<p>Jean's heart smote him as he remembered the honey cakes he had meant to give to them.
						Pierre was still talking about all the wonders of the evening, when the mother, who was
						taking off baby Henri's hood and coat while he was whimpering sleepily, called in, "So,
						Jean, thou hadst a beggar whilst we were gone. When did he come?"</p>

					<p>"Oh, no," said Jean innocently, "there was no beggar here."</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-113" n="96"/>

					<p>"Why, then," said the mother, with a puzzled face, "what has become of God's Share of
						the loaf I left on the table?" For her quick eyes had already noticed that it was
						gone.</p>

					<p>At this Jean pricked up his ears in alarm. He had not thought of this! When he said
						there had been no beggar there, he was perfectly honest, for the man in the sheepfold
						did not for a moment seem like a beggar to him. Beggars were people who came to one's
						door asking for numbers of things, and often angry if one could not give to them; for
						Jean had seen many from year to year. But the man in the sheepfold was so different that
						the lad felt instinctively that he was of gentle birth, and then <pb id="VAB1854-114"
							n="97"/> he had asked for nothing; no, he was no beggar. But how now could he account
						for the missing God's Share? He was quite at a loss, and did not know what to say. He
						determined, however, not to tell of the stranger, if he could possibly help it; for he
						had a feeling that the father, who had rather stern ideas about some things, would not
						wish to have an escaped prisoner of his master, the Lord of Baux, hiding in his
						sheepfold, and of course it would never do for the children to find it out.</p>

					<p>Jean was quite unused to deceit of any kind, and so in his predicament, he presently
						stammered out, "I don't know--I--I must have taken it!"</p>
					<p>"What, child!" exclaimed the <pb id="VAB1854-115" n="98"/> mother in amazement, "didst
							<hi rend="i">thou</hi> eat God's Share? Why, Jean, have I not told thee that 'tis the
						right of beggars, and a sin to eat it if one is not really in need? Perhaps thou didst
						not go to bed early, but, Jean, if thou wast hungry thou shouldst have eaten from the
						other loaf on yonder shelf." And the mother looked very serious and surprised that he
						had done so wicked and unheard-of a thing as to eat God's Share, seeing he was not in
						real want of bread.</p>

					<p>Annette and Pierre who had been almost too tired and sleepy to notice anything, now
						hearing this talk about God's Share, began to look around, and all at once they
						discovered that part of the fougasse was gone and set up a cross wail.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-116" n="99"/>

					<p>"O see!" they cried, "he has eaten the fougasse, too! And the nuts and figs besides!"
						For they quite forgot that the gifts of Mere Ranier were really Jean's, though he had
						always given to them far the greater part.</p>

					<p>Poor Jean was quite overpowered by the turn things had taken! He could not bear to have
						them all suppose he had greedily feasted by himself on the Christmas sweets; but then,
						if he said anything, he might betray the stranger, so he decided that he would have to
						stand it, and let them think what they would. He was only thankful they did not know
						about the honey cakes, but there was still the stick of nougat, he thought; they might
						have all of <pb id="VAB1854-117" n="100"/> that if it would satisfy them. Indeed, the
						poor little boy was having a very disappointing Christmas. Things had not turned out at
						all as he had hoped. He had missed hearing anything of the treasure from the Golden
						Goat, as he had set his heart upon, and now all the family looked at him reproachfully
						because they thought he had eaten the holiday sweetmeats all by himself, and, almost
						worse still, the beggar's portion of the Christmas loaf.</p>

					<p>But then when he thought of the strange man in the sheepfold and how much he must have
						suffered up there in the dungeon at Les Baux, he was glad to feel that he had been able
						to do something for him, and he made up his mind <pb id="VAB1854-118" n="101"/> that he
						would keep on helping him till he could get away. For everyone, even the children, in
						those days knew what a terrible thing it was to be imprisoned in the castle of a great
						nobleman; and the Lord of Baux was a passionate man and cruel to those in his power. He
						was often so harsh and exacting with the peasant folk, that they had little love for
						him.</p>

					<p>So in spite of his own troubles, Jean was unselfishly glad that the poor fugitive at
						least had been made more comfortable; for he had been singularly drawn to the
						gentle-mannered stranger. He wondered greatly as to who he was, till at last, tired out
						by the excitement of the night, he fell asleep; though not till long after <pb
							id="VAB1854-119" n="102"/> Pierre who had crept in beside him.</p>

					<p>The next morning, instead of rising before daybreak as usual, they all slept till the
						sun was well over the mountains, for this was Christmas day, and so they felt they might
						indulge themselves in a little extra rest after the long midnight walk of the night
						before. Still, they were up hours before the folks in the castle were stirring, for the
						peasants always had plenty of work to do, even if the day was Christmas.</p>

					<p>Though at first Jean felt himself somewhat in disgrace, for the children still looked
						at him reproachfully, yet their light hearts soon got the better of their resentment for
						the loss of the fougasse, <pb id="VAB1854-120" n="103"/> and they chattered continually
						of the glories of the village church and the midnight mass, as they ate their "little
						breakfast" of hard bread, and a bit of cheese, because it was Christmas.</p>

					<p>Then, when they had finished, every one set about some sort of work. The mother and
						Annette had the dinner to make ready; the grand dish was to be a hare, which the father
						had snared in the fields the day before. For at Christmastime the peasants were thus
						allowed to capture such small game as they could, though the rest of the year they were
						forbidden to do so.</p>

					<p>While the hare was being prepared, the father and little Pierre went off up the slopes
						of the <pb id="VAB1854-121" n="104"/> mountains to gather faggots for the fireplace; and
						meanwhile Henri toddled about, busily watching everything going on.</p>

					<p>As the day was chilly and seemed to threaten rain, the father had told Jean that he
						need not take the flock out to pasture, but to give them some turnips in the fold.</p>

					<p>This just suited Jean, for he was most anxious to see how the stranger fared. So he got
						a basket and putting the turnips in it, started toward the fold. As he passed the old
						stone well on the way he remembered that the man might be thirsty. It was hard work for
						a little lame boy to turn the heavy old-fashioned windlass that drew up the water, but
						he <pb id="VAB1854-122" n="105"/> managed it somehow, and filling one of several empty
						gourds that stood on the curb, he steadied it among the turnips so the water would not
						spill and went on to the sheepfold.</p>

					<p>As he stepped inside the first thing he did was to hurry over to the corner where they
						had made the little hiding place, and peep in. The strange man was lying on the straw,
						his cloak over him; he seemed to be asleep, but opened his eyes at Jean, and smiled and
						in a low voice wished him a happy Christmas. And then he asked anxiously, "Is all well,
						little one?"</p>

					<p>"Yes, sir," whispered Jean, "but keep hidden, and I will try and watch that no one
						comes here. Have you enough to eat, Sir? I <pb id="VAB1854-123" n="106"/> have brought
						you some water," and he pointed to the gourd which he had set on the straw beside the
						food put there the night before and which was still untouched.</p>

					<p>The stranger turned eagerly toward the water, and with Jean's help raised it to his
						lips and drank feverishly, for the hardships through which he had passed had told sadly
						upon him and broken his strength.</p>

					<p>"If I can but rest here a few days," he said, "I will try to make my way to Marseilles,
						where I have friends."</p>

					<p>And then he told Jean how he wanted to reach Marseilles, which is a very ancient city
						on the shores of the Mediterranean Sea. There his friends would provide him with <pb
							id="VAB1854-124" n="107"/> means to take ship for the Holy Land. "For," he explained,
						"I made a vow that if the good God let me escape from the dungeon in Les Baux, I would
						go again to Palestine and help fight for the tomb of the blessed Christ. Or," he added,
						"if I cannot fight as I did before when I went thither a younger man, at least I can
						make the pilgrimage again."</p>

					<p>In those days for one to make a pilgrimage to the Holy Land was considered a thing
						pleasing to God, and so people in distress often made such a vow.</p>

					<p>Jean listened breathlessly, for he had never before talked to any one who had gone to
						the crusading wars, and he asked many questions. They had to talk in <pb
							id="VAB1854-125" n="108"/> whispers though, and Jean did not dare to stay long as he
						was afraid they might wonder what he was doing. So presently he rose to attend to his
						flock and go back to the cottage.</p>

					<p>Before they parted, the stranger asked Jean his name and told the lad that he might
						call him Sieur Raimond. That was only one of his titles though, for the fugitive in the
						sheepfold was really a nobleman of France, and like all such he had a number of other
						names; but he did not wish to tell any one who he was until he reached a place of
						safety.</p>

					<p>It will do no harm, however, for us to know that Sieur Raimond was really Count Edouard
						Raimond Castellane D'Aulnay, and <pb id="VAB1854-126" n="109"/> that he was the last of
						his family. He was a brave and good man, and several years before, leaving his castle
						near Aix, as had so many others of the best of the land, had joined the crusading army
						and journeyed to Palestine.</p>

					<p>There he had fought long and gallantly, though the crusaders, worn out by the continued
						struggle with the Saracens who greatly out-numbered them, were at last obliged to return
						home to gather strength for fresh effort.</p>

					<p>When the Sieur Raimond (for we will call him by the name Jean knew) came back to
						Provence his health was broken and his castle had begun to fall into decay. And when,
						soon after, he had been wantonly attacked by the cruel and <pb id="VAB1854-127" n="110"
						/> quarrelsome Lord of Baux, he had not enough followers left nor was his castle strong
						enough to resist for long; and to crown his misfortunes, his only son had been killed in
						the struggle, and he himself taken prisoner.</p>

					<p>He told Jean these snatches of his history, for somehow he seemed to feel that he could
						trust the boy. And then, when the latter had finished feeding his little flock, the
						Sieur begged him to bring some water again if he could possibly manage it, for he was
						parching with fever. Jean succeeded once more in filling the gourd from the well,
						without any one seeing him; and, fetching it back to his sick friend, he left him,
						promising to return whenever he could.</p>

				</div2>

				<pb id="VAB1854-128" n="111"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER VIII</head>
					<head rend="center sc">HELPING THE FUGITIVE</head>

					<p>
						<hi rend="b">W</hi>HEN Jean reached the cottage again, he found that Pierre and his
						father had come back with their faggots; the hare was boiling briskly in the pot over
						the open fire, and everybody was happy and light-hearted with the spirit of the
						Christmas. The children sang pretty, old-time Noels and played games, and it did not
						seem long till it was time for dinner.</p>

					<p>They had scarcely sat down to this when Pierre, who was facing the window that looked
						toward the road, exclaimed, "See, father! <pb id="VAB1854-129" n="112"/> there is a man
						on horseback stopping here!"</p>

					<p>At this the father arose and went to the cottage door and, sure enough, there was a
						strange man just tying his horse to a wayside tree. That he was a guardsman from Les
						Baux they all knew from his uniform.</p>

					<p>He came up the path and greeting the father, said, "I am sent by Count Guillaume, the
						Lord of Baux, to inquire through this valley if any have seen a man who has escaped from
						the castle dungeon."</p>

					<p>"What?" said the father in surprise. "Who is he? What does he look like?"</p>

					<p>"As for who he is," said the guardsman," I do not rightly know, save that he is a noble
						lord whom <pb id="VAB1854-130" n="113"/> Count Guillaume captured last year when he
						attacked a castle near Aix. He is tall, and thin, his age something past fifty years,
						and his hair, I think, is gray. We do not know how he is clad, for we know not how he
						managed to escape nor whether or not he wears disguise. Hast thou seen any such stranger
						about this neighborhood?"</p>

					<p>"Nay, nay!" the father hastened to reply, "that I have not!"</p>

					<p>"Well," said the guardsman, "I am afraid he is well away by this time, for he has had
						two days' start of us. Count Guillaume has only just learned of his escape; for the
						jailer who kept him, and who probably aided him, is gone too, and the other dungeon
						keepers were afraid to tell our master of Baux. <pb id="VAB1854-131" n="114"/> Thou
						knowest he has a fierce temper. Indeed, 'twill fare ill with folk in this valley if he
						finds they have given shelter to his prisoner."</p>

					<p>And with this the guardsman wished them all a merry Christmas, and took his leave, to
						search elsewhere for the escaped captive. He really felt sorry for the latter, and was
						not anxious to find him, but was obliged to carry out the orders of the Lord of
						Baux.</p>

					<p>While the guardsman had been talking to the father, the rest of the family had listened
						in breathless silence; but as soon as he was gone, they all burst forth in excited
						chattering.</p>

					<p>"O," said Annette, who had a tender heart, "I do hope they will never find him."</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-132" n="115"/>

					<p>"Nevertheless," said the father, "if thou seest such a one about here, thou must tell
						me at once, or Count Guillaume will punish me cruelly; perhaps put me in the empty
						dungeon!"</p>

					<p>Here Jean, who had said nothing but had not missed a word of all that had gone on,
						opened his eyes in alarm and turned very pale. Of course he did not wish any harm to
						befall his father, neither was he used to disobeying the commands of the latter; indeed,
						he felt himself again in a very perplexing position. For a moment or two he thought very
						hard. Then quickly he argued to himself that even if they were to find the man in the
						sheepfold, which he did not think at all likely, as his hiding <pb id="VAB1854-133"
							n="116"/> place was so well concealed, but even if they did, surely Count Guillaume,
						cruel though he was, when he understood the matter--and he would explain it to
						him--would not punish the father who had known nothing about it. No, he thought, if
						anybody had to go to a dungeon it would be himself, for he was the one who had helped to
						hide the stranger.</p>

					<p>To be sure Jean was no whit more anxious to be put in a dungeon than any one else; and
						to own the truth, the mere thought of such a thing made him shiver to his finger-tips!
						But as to betraying to death the fugitive who trusted him, <hi rend="i">that</hi> he
						could not and would not do. And he determined, too, that nothing should prevent his
						continuing <pb id="VAB1854-134" n="117"/> to help Sieur Raimond until the latter could
						make good his escape.</p>

					<p>For though frail in body and timid in manner, little Jean had none the less an
						exceedingly brave spirit and his heart was kind; and perhaps, also, a decided dash of
						stubbornness in his nature did not come amiss, when he was convinced that he was doing
						the right thing.</p>

					<p>But though his mind was thus firmly made up, the rest of the day passed very
						uncomfortably for the poor lad. He thought they would never get done talking about the
						escaped prisoner from the castle of Les Baux! They all wondered what he was like, who he
						might be, and whither he had gone, till Jean was glad when night fell and every <pb
							id="VAB1854-135" n="118"/> one crept into bed and sleep silenced their busy tongues.
						He hoped that by morning they would forget about it, and, sure enough, the next day they
						had lost interest in the subject.</p>

					<p>The father declared that the man, whoever he was, must be far away by this time; and
						there was so much else to be thought of in the daily work to be done, that nobody had
						much time to wonder about Count Guillaume's prisoner.</p>

					<p>Jean was to take the flock to pasture along the roadside, and the mother gave him, as
						usual, a little luncheon of bread and cheese, which he stowed away in the pocket of his
						blouse. But when he went to the fold to get the flock, he slipped over to the corner
						where <pb id="VAB1854-136" n="119"/> his stranger guest was hidden and placed the bread
						and cheese inside the shelter. Sieur Raimond was asleep and so Jean did not disturb him.
						He noticed that the other food was still untouched, "But then," he thought, "he will
						need it when he starts off, if he cannot eat it before."</p>

					<p>Indeed, the poor stranger had been so exhausted that had he not received the friendly
						shelter of the sheepfold and Jean's kindly aid, he must surely have died or been again
						taken captive. But as he could quietly rest in the little hiding place, he was able
						gradually to get back his strength.</p>

					<p>For three days he was too feverish to want anything but the water which Jean contrived
						to bring to <pb id="VAB1854-137" n="120"/> him from time to time. But after that he grew
						better and ate some of the food; though Sieur Raimond had no idea that in order to
						supply him this, the little boy had been obliged to go hungry himself.</p>

					<p>Always, too, when Jean returned with his flock in the evening, he brought to his new
						friend some pretty bit of greenery from along the wayside; a cluster of glossy laurel
						leaves, or perhaps a tiny field flower which he had discovered in some sheltered spot,
						for it never grew so cold in the valley but that now and then one might find a hardy
						blossom or two. These little offerings of Jean's always greatly pleased Sieur Raimond,
						who loved flowers almost as dearly <pb id="VAB1854-138" n="121"/> as Jean himself, and
						who knew so much about them.</p>

					<p>The two found no end of interesting things to talk about, though Jean never dared stay
						long at a time, and they always had to be very careful to speak low and be on the alert
						that no one overheard them or took them by surprise.</p>

					<p>The little boy had never before had a friend anything like Sieur Raimond, or one who
						could tell him so many wonderful things about the great world beyond the valley. And
						this friendship was so new and delightful to him, that his heart sank, when on the fifth
						morning the Sieur told the lad that, thanks to his care and watchfulness, he felt strong
						enough to travel again, and that he meant <pb id="VAB1854-139" n="122"/> that night to
						push on toward Marseilles.</p>

					<p>He looked very white and weak, but was anxious to go on to a place of safety, among his
						friends; though he declared to Jean that nowhere in all the world had he found a truer
						or dearer friend than he, and that he could never forget that he owed his life to the
						little boy who had found him in the sheepfold that Christmas eve.</p>

					<p>Poor Jean, on his part, was quite heart-broken when he heard the Sieur was really going
						that night. Of course he was glad that he felt stronger, but he hated to have him leave.
						All day he was unhappy thinking of it, and yet he knew it was best for the Sieur to go
						as soon as he could, for every <pb id="VAB1854-140" n="123"/> day in spite of Jean's
						watchfulness there was danger of the other children or the father discovering the hiding
						place; and if the Lord of Baux should find out about it, he did not dare to think what
						terrible things would happen! Yes, he knew it was better for the Sieur to go, but he
						would miss dreadfully the interesting friend who had opened up such a new world to
						him.</p>

					<p>Late that afternoon, when Jean took the flock back to the fold, he brought to the Sieur
						a little sprig of basil that he had found in a sunny spot by the roadside, for, among
						the peasant folk, to give another a bit of basil meant all manner of good wishes. Jean
						brought also a few fig leaves and in these <pb id="VAB1854-141" n="124"/> he and the
						Sieur wrapped the little stock of provisions that the lad had brought from day to day,
						and the Sieur placed the package inside his doublet to serve him on his journey.</p>

					<p>Then they talked of how the Sieur was to reach Marseilles; though the little boy who
						had never been more than a few miles from home knew nothing about the roads beyond the
						valley, yet he could direct him how to reach the highway that went toward the river
						Rhone which was what the Sieur particularly wanted to know; for if he could once reach
						the Rhone he knew he could make his way to Marseilles.</p>
					<p>When all was settled, and Jean was obliged to leave, there were <pb id="VAB1854-142"
							n="125"/> tears in the eyes of both of them as they said good-bye.</p>

					<p>The Sieur rose to his feet, and stooping over, kissed the little boy on the forehead,
						thanking him with all his heart for what he had done.</p>

					<p>Jean, as he turned to go, saw the Golden Goat looking at them so gravely that he felt
						sure she understood all about it and sympathized with his grief at parting from his dear
						friend, the Sieur; so he patted her gently as he passed by, and for days after the
						hiding place in the sheepfold was empty and the Sieur gone, he talked it all over with
						the Golden Goat, who would always seem to listen with an attentive interest that was
						very consoling to <pb id="VAB1854-143" n="126"/> the little boy, who dared not tell any
						one else how much he missed the stranger he had befriended.</p>

				</div2>

				<pb id="VAB1854-144" n="127"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER IX</head>
					<head rend="center sc">SIEUR RAIMOND'S WALLET</head>

					<p>
						<hi rend="b">I</hi>T was more than a year after the night when, with the sprig of basil
						and little store of provisions from Jean, Sieur Raimond had left the sheepfold and taken
						his way toward Marseilles. Jean had never breathed a word about him to any one but the
						Golden Goat; but he had often wondered what had become of his unknown friend, and
						whether he had reached Marseilles in safety. How eagerly he hoped he had! For the lad
						still cherished a strong affection for the stranger, and wished many times that he had
						some way of hearing from him.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-145" n="128"/>

					<p>Meanwhile he still tended the little flock as before, though to his great sorrow the
						Golden Goat had one day wandered off to the mountains and had never come back again. The
						Père and Father Antoine had said that probably she had strayed back to her home
						somewhere on the other side of the Alpilles. But Jean was sure that she had gone once
						more to the enchanted cavern to guard the hidden treasure, and he was quite heart-broken
						that he had never been able to follow her wanderings. Sometimes he was sorry he had not
						told Annette or Pierre, so that perhaps they might have followed her; but he had not
						thought of her going away, and then, too, she was not used to the other children <pb
							id="VAB1854-146" n="129"/> and always seemed frightened, and hurried off when they
						came near; so he decided that after all, they could probably never have found the
						treasure.</p>


					<p>It had been very hard, though, to give up the golden dreams from which he had hoped so
						much.</p>

					<p>But Jean now had a new employment as he sat in the fields and meadows guarding the
						flock. He had learned to weave baskets from the willow osiers that grew on the margin of
						a little stream that ran through the valley. One of the peasant folk had taught him
						through the winter, and he had already sold a few in Les Baux, where the Père had
						carried them on market days.</p>

					<p>And so, on this January morning, <pb id="VAB1854-147" n="130"/> sheltered in a sunny
						corner of a hedgerow, he was busy weaving a round turnip basket, when presently
						something made him raise his eyes and there, coming across the field he saw a strange
						man.</p>

					<p>The stranger wore a cloak and hat such as he had seen pilgrims wear; but there was
						something about the man that made Jean's heart leap, and in another moment, when the
						pilgrim came in front of him, he started to rise to his feet with a glad cry of "Oh,
						Sieur Raimond!"</p>

					<p>"There, Jean," said the Sieur, for it was really he. "Do not get up; I will sit here
						beside thee. Father Antoine told me I would likely find thee in this field, so I came
						hither." And with that he <pb id="VAB1854-148" n="[]"/>
						<figure>
							<p>"<hi rend="b">C</hi>OMING ACROSS THE FIELD<lb/> HE SAW A STRANGE MAN"</p>
						</figure>
						<pb id="VAB1854-149" n="[]"/>
						<pb id="VAB1854-150" n="131"/> seated himself in the sunny spot beside Jean.</p>

					<p>And then, looking at the little boy, he said, "Thou surely art grown taller, child.
						Yes, but I could wish thy cheeks less pale. How has it fared with thee, little one, this
						whole year?"</p>

					<p>"We have kept well, sir," answered Jean. "And I am still tending the flock, though the
						Golden Goat is gone," he added sadly. "But," he continued eagerly, "where did you come
						from, Sieur Raimond? And did you get safely to Marseilles, and go to the Holy Land?"</p>

					<p>"Yes," said the Sieur, "thanks to thy help, child, I was able to reach Marseilles. I
						traveled only at night, and passed the days hiding <pb id="VAB1854-151" n="132"/> as
						best I could; and thanks to thy little supply of food, I did not need to let myself be
						seen till I found my friends." Here he looked affectionately at Jean, and stroked his
						brown hand.</p>

					<p>Then with a weary sigh, the Sieur went on, "Yes, I have been again to the Holy Land as
						I had vowed; and, better than I had hoped, I had strength to join the army and strike a
						few more blows for the cause."</p>

					<p>Indeed, though the Sieur did not boast of what he had done in the crusade he had given
						gallant aid, and it was through his wisdom and bravery more than any other of the
						leaders, that the army of France had been able to force the Saracens to promise a ten
						years' peace.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-152" n="133"/>
					<p>"And then," he continued, "after the heathen had agreed to a truce of ten years, I
						joined my friend Count Thibaut of Champagne and journeyed with him as far as Damascus;
						for I had not traveled thither when in Syria before. Count Thibaut is a maker of
						beautiful songs and, like all such, loves beautiful things. The city of Damascus, child,
						is famed through all those eastern lands for its splendor and especially for its
						glorious gardens."</p>

					<p>"Oh!" breathed Jean longingly; picturing the gardens in eager fancy.</p>

					<p>"Now," the Sieur went on, "I cannot make songs myself, but as thou knowest, Jean, I,
						too, love beautiful flowers above all things; <pb id="VAB1854-153" n="134"/> and so
						Count Thibaut easily persuaded me to be his traveling companion.</p>

					<p>"Damascus we found to be indeed a wonderful city, and such gardens, little one, as thou
						hast not even dreamed of! I would thou couldst have seen them! Gardens there were all of
						roses; roses such as I never before knew, and lovelier than I had any idea of. And,
						Jean, I thought of thee and thy love of flowers; I had no gold to bring back to thee as
						I longed to do, for I am an old man and my strength and fortune are gone, but see,
						little one, I have brought thee these!"</p>

					<p>And here Sieur Raimond opened a large wallet which he carried hung by a leather strap
						from one shoulder.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-154" n="135"/>

					<p>As Jean peered curiously in, he saw a small tin box in which were a number of little
						brown twigs carefully embedded in sand and partly covered by layers of moss. These, the
						Sieur explained, were cuttings and in a small package also in the wallet were seeds from
						the wonderful roses of Damascus.</p>

					<p>"Count Thibaut, too," he said, "carried some home for his castle gardens in Champagne.
						But, Jean, I am certain that in all our country of Provence there is nothing
						likethem."</p>

					<p>"And yet, child," he added sadly, "had it not been for thee, I would have had but
						little heart to bear them over seas to France, for I have naught else left in life to
						draw me hither; unless it be to die in my own land.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-155" n="136"/>

					<p>"But," he continued, with a defiant smile, "I do not mean to die till I have helped
						thee coax to light the hoard of blossoms hidden in this little package!"</p>

					<p>"Oh," said Jean delightedly, "am I to have some of them, sir?"</p>

					<p>"Why, child," said Sieur Raimond, "I have brought them all for thee! Indeed, to see
						thee, and to deliver into thy hands this bit of Damascus' rose garden, are the sole
						reasons why I have come back to this valley." And he shuddered as he glanced toward the
						distant towers of Les Baux up on the rocky crag of the Alpilles.</p>

					<p>Jean noticed his look, and hastened to say, "But, sir, Count Guillaume who imprisoned
						you, is dead, and the new Lord of Baux <pb id="VAB1854-156" n="137"/> is not cruel; his
						name is Count Franҫois."</p>

					<p>"Yes," said Sieur Raimond, "I know I am safe now in being seen here, and I mean to stay
						a while."</p>

					<p>And then he told Jean how he had discovered an old friend in Father Antoine, to whom,
						years before, he had once done a great favor. Father Antoine had been overjoyed to see
						the Sieur and had begged the latter to stay with him as long as he would. So he told
						Jean that he had decided to accept his friend's invitation; at least he would stay until
						Jean had a rose garden such as he hoped to see.</p>

					<p>Then they fell to talking over where they would plant the roses the Sieur had brought
						so far.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-157" n="138"/>

					<p>"Perhaps," said Jean, "my father will let me have the cottage dooryard." This was a
						little plot of ground between the cottage and the road; and there the Père had made a
						bench where they used to sit through summer evenings. The Sieur thought awhile, and then
						decided that it would be a good place, warm and sunny.</p>

					<p>"And," he said, "we must begin right away to get it ready for planting; for I have
						carried these slips and seeds longer now than I had thought to do."</p>

					<p>So the Sieur went off at once to hunt up Père Favette, as Jean, though all eagerness,
						could not leave his flock.</p>

				</div2>

				<pb id="VAB1854-158" n="139"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER X</head>
					<head rend="center sc">JEAN'S GARDEN</head>

					<p>
						<hi rend="b">P</hi>ÈRE Favette was greatly astonished when Sieur Raimond found him and
						told him what he wanted. At first he was rather suspicious of the Sieur who, of course,
						was an entire stranger to him. But when the latter told him that Jean had once been kind
						to him, had given him food when he was hungry (he did not think it necessary to tell him
						everything about the sheepfold), and that he wanted to do something in return, Père
						Favette relented, and really became quite friendly when he learned that the Sieur was
						staying as a guest of <pb id="VAB1854-159" n="140"/> Father Antoine whose old friend he
						was; for all the peasant folks looked up to good Father Antoine with great
						reverence.</p>

					<p>And so the rose garden was all planned out. The Sieur came back to the field where Jean
						was anxiously waiting, and told him that he had arranged with Père Favette that Pierre,
						who was now getting quite old enough to help tend the little flock, should every day
						take charge of it, at least part of the time, so Jean and the Sieur could see to the
						roses.</p>

					<p>Jean's delight was unbounded; and from that day on, he and the Sieur devoted their best
						energies to the little brown twigs and seeds from Damascus. And ah, how hard they worked
						all summer! <pb id="VAB1854-160" n="141"/> The Sieur, who was a great lover of flowers
						himself and who knew so much about them, took great pains to teach Jean how best to care
						for them.</p>

					<p>First of all he got Père Favette to dig up the ground, and then he obtained permission
						for him to fill it in with soil from Father Antoine's meadow which was much richer and
						more fertile land. Indeed, Father Antoine even loaned his donkey and two-wheeled cart in
						which to carry this soil to Jean's garden, which was a long way from the meadow.</p>

					<p>Then when the ground was ready, Père Favette enclosed it with a fence of tall reeds so
						that no stray animals could disturb it. And after that Sieur Raimond and <pb
							id="VAB1854-161" n="142"/> Jean carefully set out the precious little cuttings that
						had journeyed so far; and they also, in another part of the bed, sowed the seeds. There
						were twenty-four of the cuttings, and Sieur Raimond said they must be planted well apart
						so they might grow into large beautiful trees.</p>

					<p>They looked very tiny and fragile at first to expect so much from. But by and by,
						through Jean's constant and careful tending under the guidance of his friend, they took
						root and flourished and grew in green, leafy luxuriance.</p>

					<p>And such good times, too, as the little boy had with the Sieur, who used to come to the
						Favette cottage every few days to see his <pb id="VAB1854-162" n="143"/> little friend
						and to inspect the rose garden. He taught Jean how to weed and prune, and how to
						cultivate the soil so the sun and moisture might best nourish the delicate roots of the
						young rose plants. And as he and Jean worked together, they had so many long talks about
						such numbers of interesting things, that the lad sometimes wondered how he had ever
						gotten along without knowing Sieur Raimond!</p>

					<p>And so the spring and summer slipped away with their warm golden sunshine, and again
						the autumn came with its vintage of purple grapes and its dreamy days.</p>

					<p>And all the while the rose-garden had continued to grow and flourish, and the little
						cuttings and the seeds <pb id="VAB1854-163" n="144"/> had become tall green plants. When
						some of the strongest ones began to show signs of flowering, the Sieur said to Jean,
						"Nay, pluck off the little buds; they must grow now and gather strength of root and
						bough. Another summer will be time enough for bloom."</p>

					<p>Jean always did just as the Sieur told him; and with his own natural instinct for
						tending growing things, under his care the rose-plants developed perfectly and much to
						the satisfaction of both himself and Sieur Raimond.</p>

					<p>When the winter came on, though never very long or cold in sunny Provence, the garden
						rested for a while. And then early in the following spring, the little rose-trees began
						sending forth <pb id="VAB1854-164" n="145"/> new leaves and, by and by, a wealth of tiny
						buds. Every day Jean discovered new ones.</p>

					<p>Sieur Raimond, who was all the time growing weaker and more frail looking, could not
						find strength to come so often as before. But when he did, he smiled and nodded his head
						and said, "Yes, child, all goes well. 'Twill not be long now till thou wilt see what
						splendid things were hidden in those little twigs I carried oversea."</p>

					<p>And sure enough, when the Maytime came, all at once the rose-garden burst forth in a
						glory of flowering!</p>

					<p>One morning when Jean came out at daybreak, dozens of buds which for two days had been
							<pb id="VAB1854-165" n="146"/> trembling on the verge of breaking, softly opened
						beneath the touch of the sun. Jean, giving a little cry of delight, hurried along the
						path through the midst of the garden; and then he stood still, his lips parted and his
						eyes glistening.</p>

					<p>Now at the time when Jean lived, Provence had not yet earned the sweet title of "Land
						of Roses," as it is called to-day. For though there were many beautiful gardens, the
						varieties of roses were very few, scarcely more than four or five; and even these were
						all single flowers.</p>

					<p>Nowhere in that valley, or indeed in all Provence, had any one before seen such
						splendidly lovely blossoms as those that covered the <pb id="VAB1854-166" n="147"/>
						rose-trees that Jean had tended. Two kinds there were, white and crimson, and in each
						flower were a hundred leaves of dewy sweetness. Their soft, velvety petals glowed in the
						sunlight, and the air was laden with their rich fragrance; and as the little boy gazed
						around at the dazzling glory of bloom, he wondered if all that loveliness could possibly
						have come from the tiny twigs that Sieur Raimond had carried so far in his brown
						wallet.</p>

					<p>As he was still standing spellbound by the beauty of the garden, Sieur Raimond came
						along the road and called to him.</p>

					<p>"Truly, Jean," he said, "'tis like a glimpse of Damascus itself! And now," he added
						briskly, "we <pb id="VAB1854-167" n="148"/> must lose no time. Some one must carry a
						cluster of these to Les Baux. Who can take them the soonest?"</p>

					<p>"O," called a shrill voice at his elbow, "let me take them, sir!"</p>

					<p>It was Annette who had run out of the cottage to see Jean's wonderful roses; and in a
						little while all the rest of the family were standing around the rose plot exclaiming
						with admiration.</p>

					<p>On talking it over, though, it was at last decided that Père Favette should take the
						flowers. Annette was much disappointed, but it was several miles and a steep climb to
						Les Baux, and as Père Favette knew the place much better, he seemed the best one to
						go.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-168" n="149"/>

					<p>"But where shall he take them, sir?" said Jean to Sieur Raimond, "to the
						market-place?"</p>

					<p>These first roses were so lovely that he really hated to gather them at once. He had
						worked so long for them, that he could not help but sigh at the thought of selling them,
						for he supposed that was what the Sieur meant.</p>

					<p>"Nay," answered the Sieur, "Père Favette must carry them to the castle and see that
						they are given to none but its mistress, the Lady Azalais."</p>

					<p>At this, they all wondered what the Sieur had in mind; but as his advice had always
						been so good, they did not dream of doing otherwise than he said.</p>

					<p>Jean, when he found his roses <pb id="VAB1854-169" n="150"/> were to go to the Lady of
						Baux, was full of enthusiasm. He went to the little shed where he kept his weaving
						things, and came back with a basket of green osiers, which he had made not long
						before.</p>

					<p>"Good!" said the Sieur, as he looked at it, "twill be just the thing to set off these
						white and crimson flowers."</p>

					<p>He then helped Jean gather a beautiful cluster of the finest roses, and these they
						arranged in the basket, and over them they placed some wet fig leaves, so as to keep the
						flowers cool and unfaded on the way to Les Baux; and all being ready the Père set out at
						once, for the Sieur said the Lady Azalais must receive the roses as fresh as
						possible.</p>

				</div2>
				<pb id="VAB1854-170" n="151"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER XI</head>
					<head rend="center sc">PÈRE FAVETTE GOES TO THE CASTLE</head>
					<p>
						<hi rend="b">I</hi>T was a long climb up the Alpilles to Les Baux. But nothing could be
						lovelier than springtime in Provence, and even Père Favette, who was generally too busy
						to look much about him, could not help but feel the beauty of things as he trudged
						along.</p>

					<p>Everywhere was a soft veil of tender green, and here and there the rosy flush of an
						almond tree in flower. Along the roadside the hawthorn hedges were drifted over with
						snowy bloom, and beneath them innumerable pretty field-flowers nodded in the wind; <pb
							id="VAB1854-171" n="152"/> while up the steep slopes of the mountains the wild thyme
						was radiant with pink, starry blossoming.</p>

					<p>As he drew near the old town the great rocks towered above and the road grew steeper
						and steeper, zigzagging up the mountain crags and worn in stony furrows from the passing
						of many feet; for Les Baux was very, very old.</p>

					<p>As Père Favette entered the narrow, arched gateway of the strong wall surrounding the
						town, he soon found himself in a motley throng of people. There were shop-keepers
						arranging their wares in curious cavern-like places hewn out of the solid rock; there
						were women, with dark skirts kilted back and pretty white kerchiefs about <pb
							id="VAB1854-172" n="153"/> their shoulders, who sold sweetmeats from great trays which
						they carried about; there were sabot venders, and water-carriers and sellers of rosaries
						and holy images; indeed all manner of busy folk passing to and fro.</p>

					<p>At the end of one of the narrow streets, so narrow that the queer gargoyles on the
						stone houses and the waterspouts, carved like impossible animals' heads, almost touched
						noses across it, was a little open space where the market people were gathered. Some had
						tiny donkey carts filled with peas and lettuce and such early vegetables as the peasants
						raised on their little farms. Some had cheeses of goats' milk to sell and a few had
						strings of fish, which <pb id="VAB1854-173" n="154"/> they had caught in the river Rhone
						at the edge of the valley.</p>

					<p>Many of the dwelling houses were beautifully carved; but for all that, the town looked
						somber and old, for everything was built of the gray stone of which the mountain was
						made.</p>

					<p>Towering over it all, on the very highest part of the crag, rose the great castle of
						Les Baux. It stood on the very edge of the mountaintop and on the brow of a great
						precipice, over which it was the custom of the Lords of Baux sometimes to fling such of
						their prisoners or enemies as they wished to get rid of, for the castle dungeons were
						hewn from the rock conveniently near; (indeed it was small wonder that Sieur Raimond <pb
							id="VAB1854-174" n="155"/> had risked his life to escape from so terrible a
						place!).</p>

					<p>And yet, despite its cruel dungeons hidden underground, the castle was very splendid,
						and the view it commanded was one of the finest in Provence. On all sides the mountains
						and valleys spread away for miles and miles beneath it, and, on clear days, far off on
						the southern horizon one might even glimpse the gleaming blue waters of the
						Mediterranean Sea, though the city of Marseilles, where Sieur Raimond had found his
						friends, was hidden beyond a mountain spur in the farther distance.</p>

					<p>As Père Favette climbed the steep street leading to this castle, he saw many men
						dressed in gay costumes and carrying lutes or <pb id="VAB1854-175" n="156"/> viols or
						other musical instruments which hung from their shoulders by bright green or scarlet
						ribbons. Some of the richer of these men were followed by little pages, who bore their
						instruments for them. These were all wandering poets, of whom, at that time, there were
						very many in Provence, where they strolled about from castle to castle singing their
						songs to the music of their lutes and viols.</p>

					<p>Les Baux was a famous gathering place for these poets, and they were always sure of a
						welcome at the great castle; for more than one of the Lords of Baux had composed and
						sung songs of his own, and, strangely enough, even the most cruel of them was always
						interested in poetry.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-176" n="157"/>
					<p>Following a group of the poets, Père Favette made his way to the drawbridge over the
						moat, which guarded that part of the castle which did not face the precipice. On
						crossing this bridge and going through several stone gateways in high walls, at last he
						found himself in the inner courtyard.</p>

					<p>Here he looked about in a be wildered way, for he had never before been within the
						castle walls. Presently he made bold to go to a young page he saw idling in front of one
						of the doorways. The youth was dressed in a suit of blue silk with pointed shoes of
						velvet and a crimson cap, and altogether looked so grand that Père Favette, pausing in
						front of him, stood timidly for a moment before <pb id="VAB1854-177" n="158"/> he asked,
						"Sir, will you tell me the way to the Lady Azalais?"</p>

					<p>At this the page, who was not used to being called "Sir," insolently staring at Père
						Favette's peasant blouse and wooden shoes, dusty from his long walk up the mountain, and
						his basket covered with fig leaves, burst into laughter; for he was a very ill-mannered
						youth.</p>

					<p>"Ho," he said, when he had finished laughing. "Thou stupid! Dost thou suppose the Lady
						Azalais deigns to look at every peasant yokel who trudges hither with turnips and
						cabbages?"</p>

					<p>"Nay," answered Père Favette sharply, "'tis neither turnips nor cabbages I bring! But
						something to make even thy silly tongue wag <pb id="VAB1854-178" n="159"/> with wonder,
						if I were a mind to show thee."</p>

					<p>As he said this with some spirit, the page stopped laughing and grew a trifle more
						civil, and especially so as just at that moment there came along a man who was one of
						the seneschals of the castle and who, hearing the cause of dispute between them, turned
						to the page with a short "Master Insolence, wilt thou never learn a proper behaviour?"
						and commanded him straightway to carry to the Lady Azalais the basket which Père Favette
						still held in his hand. Then to the latter he said kindly, "Thou canst rest on yonder
						bench; 'tis a hard climb to this rock-built town."</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-179" n="160"/>

					<p>Père Favette looked at him gratefully as he went to the bench and sat down; for he had
						no intention of going away at once, as Sieur Raimond had particularly told him to wait
						until the Lady Azalais received the roses.</p>

					<p>Meantime the disdainful page, taking the green osier basket as he had been bidden, went
						into the castle, and climbing up a winding stone staircase reached a tower chamber where
						the Lady Azalais sat with some silken embroidery on a frame in front of her. She was
						very beautiful, with dark hair and soft black eyes and a delicate pink colour in her
						cheeks. Indeed, many of the poets of the land had made songs about the loveliness of
						this Lady of Baux, and some of <pb id="VAB1854-180" n="161"/> these songs were so pretty
						that to this day they are still sung by the people of Provence.</p>

					<p>As the Lady Azalais looked up from her embroidery, when the page knocked at the heavy
						oaken door, she bade him enter, and he came over to her and, bowing low, set the basket
						down at her feet. She looked in surprise at it, still covered as it was with the damp
						fig leaves.</p>

					<p>"Well, Ferdinand," she said, "what is this thou bringest?"</p>

					<p>"'Tis something a peasant yokel carried to town, and he would not be satisfied till I
						brought it to your ladyship," answered Ferdinand with a curl of his lip." I daresay,
						'tis a new cheese or a cabbage," he added scornfully.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-181" n="162"/>

					<p>"Ferdinand," said the lady, "if thou wishest to serve me thou wilt have to mend thy
						manners, and teach thy tongue to be somewhat less pert. Uncover this basket!"</p>

					<p>Ferdinand, flushing under her words, bent down and lifted up the thick covering of
						leaves, and there, underneath, nestled the great cluster of roses, as fresh and dewy and
						deliciously fragrant as when Jean had first placed them there.</p>

					<p>As the Lady Azalais looked at them her eyes opened wide with surprise and delight; and
						then quickly lifting the cluster in her arms she buried her face in the rich, velvety
						petals.</p>

					<p>"O!" she said, drawing a long breath of their exquisite perfume, "O Ferdinand, <hi
							rend="i">where</hi> did they <pb id="VAB1854-182" n="163"/> come from? I never saw
						anything half so lovely! White and crimson, too!" she murmured." The very colours of the
						House of Baux!" And in truth the roses were the exact hues of the white starred banner
						of the Lords of Baux. Then in another moment "Ferdinand!" she exclaimed, "go quickly;
						see if the peasant who brought them is still here, and bring him to me! I must know
						whence these came, if I have to search all the valleys round about."</p>

					<p>Thereupon Ferdinand scampered down the stone stairs as fast as he could, and hurried
						out to the courtyard where he soon spied Père Favette still quietly seated on the
						bench.</p>

					<p>"Come," said the page, still somewhat <pb id="VAB1854-183" n="164"/> haughtily, though
						he was obliged to be civil, "the Lady Azalais wishes to see thee."</p>

					<p>Père Favette rose at this and followed Ferdinand into the castle, his wooden shoes
						clattering over the stone floors as he went. In the great hall they met the Lady Azalais
						still hugging the bunch of roses; for in her eagerness she had come down to see for
						herself whether the peasant had gone. As Ferdinand led him to her, Père Favette taking
						off his cap, stood awkwardly in front of her.</p>

					<p>"Art thou the man who brought these wonderful flowers?" she asked, looking curiously at
						Père Favette.</p>

					<p>"Yes, my lady," he stammered, for the peasant folks were quite <pb id="VAB1854-184"
							n="[]"/>
						<figure>
							<p>"<hi rend="b">I</hi>N THE GREAT HALL THEY<lb/> MET THE LADY AZALAIS"</p>
						</figure>
						<pb id="VAB1854-185" n="[]"/>
						<pb id="VAB1854-186" n="165"/> unused to talking to noble ladies. "My little boy tended
						them in his garden, but he is lame and could not climb the mountain, and so I brought
						them for him. They are a present to you."</p>

					<p>"But where," continued Lady Azalais, "where did he get the seeds? Never has the like of
						these roses been seen in this valley, nor, I believe, in Provence!"</p>

					<p>Here Père Favette hardly knew how to answer. But presently, gathering his wits
						together, he said, "A stranger, my lady, brought them oversea from Palestine and gave
						them to my little boy, Jean, who, he said, had once been kind to him, though in truth I
						know not what he did," and the Père looked very perplexed.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-187" n="166"/>

					<p>"That is a strange story," said the lady, looking thoughtfully at her roses, "but yet I
						have heard it said that in the far east are marvelous gardens."</p>

					<p>Then she asked particularly where he lived, and told him she would come herself, the
						next day, and see Jean's garden. And then charging him to return her warmest thanks to
						his little boy, for his beautiful gift, she dismissed him with a kind smile.</p>

					<p>Père Favette, still somewhat dazed from the interview with the lady and the wonderful
						things he had seen within the castle walls, trudged out of the courtyard and back into
						the old town, and by and by took his way down the mountain and reached home at
						nightfall.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-188" n="167"/>

					<p>Of course no one in the cottage went to bed until they had heard everything he had done
						from the moment he had started to Les Baux.</p>
				</div2>

				<pb id="VAB1854-189" n="168"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER XII</head>
					<head rend="center sc">LADY AZALAIS</head>

					<p>
						<hi rend="b">T</hi>HE next morning all was excitement at the Favette cottage. Every one
						was up long before daybreak, for the Lady Azalais was coming.</p>

					<p>The children, who had never been to Les Baux and had only seen and dreamed about the
						castle from afar, were so full of the wonderful, expected visit that they could scarcely
						eat the bits of bread the mother gave them for breakfast.</p>

					<p>Their faces had been washed till they fairly shone; baby Henri had on a clean little
						pinafore, and <pb id="VAB1854-190" n="169"/> Annette her fête-day dress of coarse blue
						home-spun with a pink kerchief, and Pierre and Jean had brushed their blouses till not a
						speck of dust was to be seen. The mother, too, when the cottage was in order, put a
						fresh white kerchief about her shoulders, and on her hair the pretty head-dress of
						Provence, a tiny white cap fastened on with a bit of stiff black ribbon.</p>

					<p>As for Jean, he had been so excited all night that he had scarcely slept a wink. But
						none the less he was up bright and early with the others; and though his thin little
						face looked pale, his eyes shone like stars as he limped through the rose garden,
						plucking off a withered leaf here and <pb id="VAB1854-191" n="170"/> there, or fastening
						up a fallen branch.</p>

					<p>The garden was a dream of loveliness that sunny May morning. Fresh roses had blossomed
						so thickly that you could scarcely tell where the great cluster had been cut the day
						before. A honeysweet fragrance hovered over them, and the dew still trembled in the
						shadowy hollows of their soft petals.</p>

					<p>Jean had scarcely finished inspecting his posies, when all at once Annette, whose sharp
						eyes had been on the alert watching the road from Les Baux, cried out, "See! see! the
						Lady Azalais is coming!"</p>

					<p>And sure enough, winding down the mountain road came two figures on horseback, the Lady
						Azalais and a single groom attending <pb id="VAB1854-192" n="171"/> her. She came thus
						by herself, as she did not wish any one else to see the new roses until she chose to
						display them. As the two riders drew near, Lady Azalais was seen to be mounted on a
						white palfrey; she wore a gown of soft blue with a silver embroidery and a dark velvet
						hat with a curling feather of white; and as she rode, the little silver chains that
						bridled her palfrey made a pretty, tinkling sound.</p>

					<p>Presently she reached the Favette cottage, and after the groom had helped her to
						dismount, she bade him await her in the road without. Then entering the wicket gate, she
						courteously greeted the father and mother who were bowing and smiling in their most
						polite <pb id="VAB1854-193" n="172"/> manner, while the children, overawed by the noble
						visitor, had scampered off behind the fence of reeds that hid the rose garden and from
						its shelter peered curiously out.</p>

					<p>Lady Azalais asked at once for Jean to show her his garden, and when the father brought
						him to her, she bent down and taking both his little brown hands in her own white ones
						smiled kindly into his eyes and said, "Child, art thou the lad that sent me such lovely
						roses from thy garden? Come, show it to me! I long to see it!"</p>

					<p>Poor Jean was so embarrassed he did not know what to say, and could only shyly stammer
						out, "I am glad they pleased you." And <pb id="VAB1854-194" n="173"/> then, turning
						about, he led the way to his garden.</p>

					<p>As Lady Azalais first caught sight of its beauty, she exclaimed with delight. And then,
						just as Jean had done the morning before, she walked into the midst of the roses and
						stood still, drinking in their loveliness. Jean, gazing at her, thought that she looked
						exactly like some wonderful fairy princess. And in truth she did look very lovely among
						the roses, her eyes shining and the bright colour coming and going in her cheeks.</p>

					<p>When presently she turned around and saw Jean about to gather some of the flowers for
						her, she stopped him quickly, saying, "Nay, child, do not break those <pb
							id="VAB1854-195" n="174"/> budded sprays, for soon I shall want all thou canst
						spare!"</p>

					<p>Then she told him that three days off she was to give a birthday fête; and at that time
						she would send down from the castle and wished him to have ready as many roses as his
						garden would supply; and that he was to come, too, with the messenger, for she wanted
						him to see the fête which she had planned to take place out of doors in the middle of
						the day.</p>

					<p>Then, after admiring the roses to her heart's content, and leaving with Jean a package
						of bonbons which she had brought for him, she went back to the road, and mounting her
						white palfrey rode off toward Les Baux, her groom following close behind.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-196" n="175"/>

					<p>When they had made a turn up the steep road that hid them from sight, Sieur Raimond
						came walking slowly across the fields. He was smiling to himself, and as Jean hurried
						out to meet him and tell him of their wonderful visitor, he listened in a pleased way,
						though he did not seem surprised.</p>

					<p>"Yes, child," he said, "I have known somewhat of the Lady Azalais, and I know that she
						loves flowers even as thou and I. And I was sure, too, that she had but to see thy
						cluster of roses yesterday to bring her hither this morning. And," he added
						thoughtfully, "I am most glad, Jean, for it will go well with thee hereafter."</p>

					<p>And then when Jean told him of the coming fête of Lady Azalais <pb id="VAB1854-197"
							n="176"/> and of her order for roses and how he himself was to see it all, Sieur
						Raimond was very pleased indeed. " Truly, child," he exclaimed, "the lucky stars are
						working things out for thee as happily as I had dreamed! And how fares the garden
						to-day? Thou must tend it well, Jean, especially as some of it is to go to so fine a
						thing as one of the birthday fêtes of Lady Azalais!"</p>

					<p>But when he went with Jean to look over the garden, it had been so well cared for that
						not a single yellow leaf was to be seen anywhere; while as for a weed, no sooner did one
						dare to show its head than Jean whisked it out at once.</p>

					<p>And now as he and the Sieur <pb id="VAB1854-198" n="177"/> stood looking at the result
						of the hard work of the last year, they were both very, very happy. The May air brought
						them the perfume of the roses and the warm southern sun stirred their blood, till they
						would both surely have fallen to dancing like Annette, who was whirling about to work
						off her excitement, had not the Sieur been too weak and Jean too lame. As it was, the
						Sieur, patting Jean's hair, walked with him to a shady spot beneath a fig tree, and
						there they both sat down and laughed and talked for a whole hour, about all the nicest
						things they could think of.</p>

				</div2>

				<pb id="VAB1854-199" n="178"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER XIII</head>
					<head rend="center sc">THE BIRTHDAY FÊTE</head>

					<p>
						<hi rend="b">T</hi>WO days had passed since the Lady Azalais had come to the garden, and
						the third morning dawned bright and sunny. Jean was up with the birds, which meant very
						early indeed. He ardently wished for a fête-day suit with brass buttons, as had some of
						the little boys of the better off peasant folk, but he had to be content with his old
						blue blouse and his faded cap. But then, when he went out to gather the roses he was to
						bring, everything was so bright and beautiful that he quite forgot about his
						clothes.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-200" n="179"/>

					<p>He filled the largest basket he could find with the fragrant blossoms, and was all
						ready long before the serving-man from the castle came for him. When the latter arrived,
						riding a brown horse, the first thing he did on dismounting was to hand Jean a parcel,
						which he said Lady Azalais had sent to him with her best birthday compliments.</p>

					<p>For the Lady Azalais was used not only to receiving on her birthday the gifts of her
						noble friends, but she also loved herself to send presents on that day to the poorer
						peasant folks round about. But as she had not lived long in Les Baux, and as the former
						mistress of the castle had been proud and haughty and did little for the poor, the <pb
							id="VAB1854-201" n="180"/> peasants of the valley had not yet grown used to the
						gracious ways of Lady Azalais.</p>

					<p>So Jean was almost too surprised to speak when he received the parcel and on opening it
						found within a little fête-day suit of soft brown cloth with brass buttons, and a cap
						with a band of gilt braid; all just the very things he had longed for, only prettier
						than any he had ever seen! As he stood rapt in admiration the serving-man reminded him
						that the Lady Azalais hoped that he would wear the new suit in honour of her birthday.
						At this Jean caught up the things, and, hurrying into the house as fast as he could, had
						dressed himself and was out again beaming with delight, before the <pb id="VAB1854-202"
							n="181"/> rest of the family had even begun to get over their astonishment.</p>

					<p>The man now lifted Jean, basket, crutch, and all, up in front of him, and off they
						started, the father and mother and the children waving excited good-byes till they were
						out of sight. Indeed, you would have thought Jean was going away for a whole year
						instead of a single day.</p>

					<p>As they rode slowly along up the steep road, Jean's companion asked him many questions
						which the lad answered as best he could, all except who had first given him the rose
						plants. To this question he merely replied, as Sieur Raimond had told him, that a friend
						who had been on the crusade had brought them to him.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-203" n="182"/>

					<p>All the while they kept climbing up and up, till by and by they crossed a spur of one
						of the mountains that shut in Jean's valley, and looked down into a smaller one beyond.
						Above them, close at hand, towered the stone walls of Les Baux; but it was not there
						they were going, but to a meadow below, where the birthday fête was to be held, and
						where a flutter of gay banners already marked the spot. To be sure, the Lady Azalais was
						to give a great feast in the evening, up in the banquetting hall of the castle, but the
						greater part of the day was to be spent out of doors.</p>

					<p>Now, in those days, the lords and ladies of the land had many odd ways of amusing
						themselves. <pb id="VAB1854-204" n="[]"/>
						<figure>
							<p>"<hi rend="b">A</hi>LL THE WHILE THEY KEPT<lb/> CLIMBING UP AND UP"</p>
						</figure>
						<pb id="VAB1854-205" n="[]"/>
						<pb id="VAB1854-206" n="183"/> Sometimes they held great tournaments, where, for their
						entertainment, noble knights in armour fought each other on horseback in a sort of mimic
						warfare. But in Provence, where every one loved poetry, they liked best of all to
						entertain themselves by listening to contests of song.</p>

					<p>Oftentimes these contests were held in the courtyard of some castle, where, beneath a
						pretty pavilion built of green boughs, or perhaps more elaborately of stone, the
						mistress of the castle and a chosen few of her high-born ladies would hold a little
						court. It was always the great ladies who presided over these, and before them the
						different poets would sing their songs (for in those days poets always <pb
							id="VAB1854-207" n="184"/> sang their poems to music), and the one who sang the best
						song received a prize, usually a flower or garland of roses; and it was thought a great
						honour for any one to win this prize.</p>

					<p>Sometimes, if the castle courtyard was not large enough for these contests, they were
						held in some grassy meadow land near by. And so it was at Les Baux; in the great castle
						there, built as it was on the edge of the rocky crag, there was not a great deal of room
						for the courtyard. There was a broad, level place in the small valley not far below the
						town, and so it was there that the ladies of Baux always held their courts for the song
						contests, such as Lady Azalais had planned for her birthday fête.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-208" n="185"/>

					<p>When Jean and his companion reached the bottom of this valley, they stopped in front of
						a wall of buff stone that enclosed an open field. The serving-man lifted Jean to the
						ground, and then gave the basket of roses to a page who was waiting for them and who at
						once whisked them away out of sight.</p>

					<p>The serving-man then led Jean through an arched opening in the stone wall and into the
						field beyond, where he found a shady place under a tree for him to sit, as Lady Azalais
						had directed, and there he left him in the care of a young page who was very civil to
						Jean, though the latter was so shy and so taken up with watching the scene about them
						that he spoke but little.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-209" n="186"/>

					<p>The field was large and carpeted with grass and sweet-clover through which shone golden
						buttercups and starry white narcissus flowers. Here and there a group of olive or almond
						trees cast a pleasant shade, and overhead the sky was very bright and blue. Laughing and
						talking and strolling about beneath the trees were many noble ladies in trailing silken
						gowns and gentlemen in velvets and ruffles. While sitting apart beneath the trees,
						fingering their lutes and viols and humming their songs, were a number of poets. The
						page pointed them out to Jean, though the latter would have known them from the
						description the Père had given of those he had seen going to the castle of Les Baux.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-210" n="187"/>

					<p>Count Franҫois and Lady Azalais were seated under a gay canopy in the center of the
						field, and courteously greeted the guests who, from time to time, continued to come
						through the arched gateway.</p>

					<p>Presently, when all the company had gathered, every one began moving toward a corner of
						the enclosure where the pavilion was built; and the page and Jean, going a little nearer
						also, found a sheltered seat beside a pomegranate bush, where they could see all that
						went on.</p>

					<p>The pavilion itself though very tiny, no larger than a small summer-house, was very
						beautiful. It was six-sided in shape and made of the same kind of buff stone that
						enclosed the field; within, three <pb id="VAB1854-211" n="188"/> little seats were built
						into the wall at the back, while in front were three open arches with slender fluted
						pillars between. The roof of stone was like a great flower turned upside down, and was
						delicately carved to resemble overlapping petals.</p>

					<p>Indeed, to this day, though the rock-built city and once strong castle of Les Baux are
						only forlorn gray ruins, and though the grassy field in the valley below is quite
						deserted, and the olive and almond trees old and gnarled, yet, strangely enough, the
						little stone pavilion is still standing, as perfect and beautiful as when Jean saw it on
						that fête day so long ago. There is no one now to trim it with garlands, but on the
						birthday <pb id="VAB1854-212" n="189"/> of Lady Azalais it was hung with festoons of
						flowers, and a silken flag, red with a single white star, the emblem of the House of
						Baux, fluttered from its pinnacle.</p>

					<p>In a few minutes Lady Azalais, looking like a flower herself in a soft rose-coloured
						robe, took her place on the central seat of the pavilion and on either side sat a high
						born dame of her choosing; for these three were to judge the songs of the poets.</p>

					<p>One by one, standing before the open arches, playing on their lutes or viols the while,
						the poets took their turns in singing. There were seven of them, and when the last had
						finished and the applause died away, Jean whispered to the page at his side that he was
						very glad <pb id="VAB1854-213" n="190"/> he did not have to judge them, for all the
						songs were so beautiful that he could never in the world decide which was the best!</p>

					<p>The Lady Azalais, however, was a very good judge, and could herself make up songs quite
						as well as anybody; so her opinion was thought by the poets to be really worth
						while.</p>

					<p>By and by, after she had consulted with the ladies beside her, a herald blew a silver
						bugle and announced that her choice was made. Then from the group of poets, who had
						meantime retired a little distance, the three fortunate ones were summoned back to the
						pavilion; and there, kneeling on the steps in front of the arches, they received their
						prizes.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-214" n="191"/>

					<p>The reward of honour was bestowed by Lady Azalais herself, who hung a garland of
						crimson roses over the shoulders of the kneeling poet-singer. Each of the others
						received theirs from the hands of her companions, the second prize being a cluster of
						roses, red and white, and the third, one superb white rose with long stem and glossy
						green leaves.</p>

					<p>Now the roses that had always before been given as prizes at these song contests were
						of the much less beautiful varieties, with few petals, that were the only ones then
						known in Provence.</p>

					<p>But these roses from the Lady Azalais were of a kind no one there had ever before seen.
						And Jean's cheeks flushed and his heart <pb id="VAB1854-215" n="192"/> swelled with
						pride as he recognized the flowers of his own tending and heard the general murmur of
						surprise and admiration that they excited. Their size, their shape, their pure and
						glowing colour and great masses of velvety petals, were eagerly admired and wondered at
						by every one who saw them.</p>

					<p>Lady Azalais, who quite enjoyed the sensation her prizes had made, was beseiged by
						questions as to where these splendid new roses had come from. At first she had almost a
						mind to send for Jean and have him satisfy the general curiosity. But then she
						remembered his shyness and felt sure that he would be so embarrassed as to be very
						uncomfortable <pb id="VAB1854-216" n="193"/> if obliged to face so many people; so she
						contented herself by simply saying that all she knew was that the rose plants had been
						brought from the far east by a crusader returning from the Holy Land, and that they had
						been tended by a little peasant boy in a valley near St. Remy, and that the next year
						she meant that he should have a much larger garden, and that, after a while, perhaps he
						could grow enough roses to satisfy them all.</p>

					<p>Meantime, while every one was still talking of the new roses, in another part of the
						field the castle cooks were busy unpacking great baskets of dainties and spreading the
						feast, picnic fashion, on long tables, which they set among the <pb id="VAB1854-217"
							n="194"/> buttercups and narcissus flowers in the soft green grass.</p>

					<p>Before the noble folks sat down on the benches provided for them, Lady Azalais sought
						out Jean and spoke kindly to him and told him how pleased she was with the roses he had
						brought. And then, before she left, she directed the page to fetch a basket which she
						had ordered to be specially prepared for them so that they might have a little picnic of
						their own.</p>

					<p>And such a grand picnic as it was! For by this time Jean and the page had become very
						good friends, and when the latter brought the basket and spread on the grass a small
						square of linen for tablecloth, they had the merriest time imaginable setting out the
							<pb id="VAB1854-218" n="195"/> things. White bread and meat, patties and almond cakes,
						fruits and sweetmeats, in bewildering variety; never before had Jean seen or tasted such
						wonderful food.</p>

					<p>When the feast was over, the great folks lingered for a while making merry beneath the
						trees; and later on, when the afternoon began to wane, they took their leave in order to
						rest a little before the gayeties of the evening that were to take place in the
						castle.</p>

					<p>After all were gone, the serving-man again took Jean on the brown horse, over the
						mountain road and back to the Favette cottage. Over one arm the man carried the basket
						in which they had taken the roses in the morning; and when he had brought it into the
						house for Jean <pb id="VAB1854-219" n="196"/> and said good-bye to them all, on raising
						the cover they found it to be packed with dainties from the picnic feast, and down in
						the very bottom were some bright gold pieces for the little rose gardener.</p>

					<p>It was a long while before any of the cottage folks went to bed that night, for Jean
						had to tell them over and over every smallest particular of the day's happenings, from
						the moment the brown horse had trotted away in the morning until they heard the patter
						of his hoofs on the homeward way.</p>

					<p>But at last all grew too sleepy to listen longer, even to the wonderful tale of Lady
						Azalais' birthday. The children's eyes that had been very round and wide with wonder, by
						and by began blinking drowsily; <pb id="VAB1854-220" n="197"/> and when all was quiet
						for the night, and Jean himself fell asleep, he was so happy that he dreamed that his
						hard little cupboard bed was all made of roses large and sweet, and softer than velvet,
						that fairyland was all around him, and that Lady Azalais was its queen.</p>

				</div2>

				<pb id="VAB1854-221" n="198"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER XIV</head>
					<head rend="center sc">DAMASK ROSES</head>

					<p>
						<hi rend="b">T</hi>T would take quite too long to tell you all the rest of Jean's life
						after the wonderful birthday fête when the new roses first became known; but it would
						never do for you not to hear something of the good fortune that they brought him.</p>

					<p>Lady Azalais continued to interest herself in Jean and his garden, and, true to her
						word, the next year she saw to it that he had a larger piece of ground and some one to
						help him with his work.</p>

					<p>The castle folks bought all the roses he could grow, and in a few <pb id="VAB1854-222"
							n="199"/> years, through the kindness of Count Franҫois and Lady Azalais, the Favette
						cottage was exchanged for one close to St. Remy where there was more and better ground
						for the garden.</p>

					<p>This change in their home was a special favour, for in those days the peasants were
						nowhere allowed to move about without permission--which was rarely given--from whatever
						lord happened to rule them and own their land. But not only was Jean thus given more
						space for his rose growing, but also he was permitted to sell both plants and roses to
						other noble folks, many of whom sent long distances to get some of the beautiful new
						varieties for their own castle gardens. And gradually the whole family, <pb
							id="VAB1854-223" n="200"/> the father and mother (when she had time) and Annette and
						even baby Henri, when they grew older, all but Pierre--who still insisted on being a
						soldier--became helpers in the care of the garden; though always under the direction of
						Jean. And they all thought it vastly pleasanter to earn their living with rose leaves
						instead of turnips and cabbages.</p>

					<p>Meantime the roses, as they grew more used to their adopted country, constantly
						increased in beauty and luxuriance. And by and by, when Jean was quite grown up, his
						gardens had extended more and more until the fame of his flowers spread far beyond many
						valleys. His roses were considered the best, too, from <pb id="VAB1854-224" n="201"/>
						which to make the rose-water that the people who lived in castles were so fond of using;
						and many of the fragrant petals from Jean's garden went to distill this sweet
						perfume.</p>

					<p>The roses, having been brought in the first place from Damascus, came naturally to be
						called Damascus roses, and in time this was shortened to Damask; and by this name they
						are still everywhere known. Though the cuttings which Count Thibaut, the friend of Sieur
						Raimond, had brought to his castle in Champagne, grew and flourished and spread over the
						more northern parts of France, yet nowhere did the Damask roses attain such perfection
						as in Jean's gardens. And to this very day the roses of St. Remy are declared to be the
						most <pb id="VAB1854-225" n="202"/> beautiful in all Provence; and they are no doubt
						descended from the same tiny cuttings that Jean and Sieur Raimond first planted in the
						door-yard of the Favette cottage.</p>

					<p>And to this day, too, though many splendid varieties of roses are now known that were
						unheard of in Jean's time, still no one's garden is thought to be quite complete without
						at least several bushes of the sweet old-fashioned Damask roses of Provence, with their
						hundred leaves and honeyed fragrance, and which, surely, you all know and love.</p>

					<p>But we have not quite finished with Jean's history; nor must we forget Sieur Raimond,
						whose gratitude to the little boy who had befriended him that night in the <pb
							id="VAB1854-226" n="203"/> sheepfold was the first means of all the good fortune that
						befell him in after years.</p>

					<p>Sieur Raimond, whose health had always been frail, had only through sheer force of will
						kept up his strength long enough to teach Jean how to care for the roses he had brought,
						and to see him well started toward success.</p>

					<p>After Lady Azalais' fete, and seeing the interest that she took in Jean, the Sieur knew
						that he need no longer have any anxiety for the lad's future. So feeling himself growing
						weaker, he retired to spend his last days in the Abbey of Mont Major.</p>

					<p>This was a great and powerful monastery built on a hill-top not far from Les Baux; the
						Abbot who <pb id="VAB1854-227" n="204"/> ruled it was a noble lord, and both he and the
						brotherhood of monks who dwelt in the Abbey warmly welcomed Sieur Raimond, who was known
						for his honourable life and his bravery in the wars in Palestine. And they treated him
						with the greatest kindness and courtesy throughout the rest of his life, which was not
						long.</p>

					<p>But though he did not live to know all the success that came to Jean, his last days
						were cheered by feeling that he had been able to help his little friend. And as for
						Jean, all his life long he cherished the memory of Sieur Raimond, and a tender affection
						for him and gratitude for all that the Sieur had done to bring happiness to his
						life.</p>

					<p>For Jean was very, very happy <pb id="VAB1854-228" n="205"/> in his work. And beside
						the fame and fortune which we have seen his garden brought him as he grew older, there
						was yet another piece of good luck that came to him, through his flowers, when he had
						grown to manhood.</p>

					<p>Now at that time there was a very ancient and beautiful custom every year observed in
						the Parliament of Paris where the nobles of France met to make the laws of the land. On
						certain days during the spring and early summer, one of the great dukes of the realm,
						who was specially appointed for the purpose, used to conduct a ceremony called the
						"Presentation of Roses." At such times it was his duty to see that the chambers of
						Parliament were strewn with flowers, and <pb id="VAB1854-229" n="206"/> especially
						roses. On the morning of the day of the ceremony, he was required to entertain all the
						nobles at a costly breakfast; and after that, taking with him a page bearing a a large
						silver basin in which were as many bouquets and crowns of roses as members of
						Parliament, the duke made the rounds presenting his gifts of flowers.</p>

					<p>It was a quaint and lovely old custom, and for many years the office of this master of
						ceremonies was highly esteemed and eagerly sought for by the greatest peers of France.
						And of course to make the bouquets and crowns thus presented it was very important to
						have the finest roses it was possible to get. And so as long as the observance of the
						ceremony lasted, <pb id="VAB1854-230" n="207"/> which was several centuries, it was
						customary to keep a plot of ground near Paris especially for growing the flowers of
						Parliament; and the head gardener of these flowers was called the "Rosier de la Cour,"
						which means "Rose-gardener of the Court."</p>

					<p>And now we come to Jean's piece of good luck when he grew to manhood; for it was no
						less than an appointment to the office of Rosier de la Cour, that came to him because of
						the fame of the rose gardens of St. Remy.</p>

					<p>Jean was delighted with the honour of this office; yet in growing the roses for the
						peers to make their presents to the French Parliament, he did not entirely forsake his
						home. Every year he journeyed <pb id="VAB1854-231" n="208"/> up to Paris where he spent
						a few months directing the care of the garden there, and then the rest of his time he
						stayed among the roses of his own dear Provence. And no one in all the valley was more
						beloved than he, because of his kindness and generosity to all about him.</p>

					<p>There was one thing, however, that his better fortunes could not do for him, and that
						was to cure his lameness. He always limped; but the crutch he carried was much lighter
						and easier, and the shoes he wore less wearisome than the heavy sabots of his childhood,
						and altogether it was surprising how nimbly he could get about and how deftly he could
						work among his flowers.</p>

					<pb id="VAB1854-232" n="209"/>
					<p>And then, too, it was not many years till he had a horse of his own to ride; yes, and a
						velvet doublet just as he had wished to have when as a little boy he had sat by the
						roadside with Grandpère Chartier and sighed as the nobleman had ridden down the road
						from Les Baux.</p>

					<p>Indeed, Jean could never ride down that same road himself, and pass the hawthorn hedge,
						without thinking of Grandpère Chartier and how he had first told him of the Golden Goat.
						And remembering it all, and poor old Grandpère and his cracked voice as he repeated the
						wonderful tale, oftentimes, between a smile and a tear, Jean would say to himself that
						though he had not found the Saracen's <pb id="VAB1854-233" n="210"/> hidden riches of
						gold and jewels, nevertheless he was far happier and more fortunate than he had ever
						dreamed of being, and that, truly enough, the very beginning of it all had come directly
						from the Golden Goat that he had tended when a little shepherd lad.</p>

					<p rend="center">THE END</p>
				</div2>
			</div1>
		</body>


		<back>
			<pb id="VAB1854-234" n="[A-1]"/>

			<div1 type="advertisement">

				<head type="center">Selections from<lb/> L. C. Page &amp; Company's<lb/> Books for
					Girls</head>

				<milestone unit="typography" n="-----" rend="center"/>

				<head>THE BLUE BONNET SERIES</head>
				<list type="simple">
					<item><hi rend="i">Each large 12mo, cloth decorative, illustrated, per volume <hi
								rend="right"> $2.00</hi></hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="i">The seven volumes, boxed as a set <hi rend="right"
						>14.00</hi></hi></item>
				</list>

				<p>A TEXAS BLUE BONNET<lb/> B<hi rend="sc">Y</hi> C<hi rend="sc">AROLINE</hi> E. J<hi
						rend="sc">ACOBS.</hi></p>

				<p>BLUE BONNET'S RANCH PARTY<lb/> B<hi rend="sc">Y</hi> C<hi rend="sc">AROLINE</hi> E. J<hi
						rend="sc">ACOBS</hi> AND E<hi rend="sc">DYTH</hi> E<hi rend="sc">LLERBECK</hi> R<hi
						rend="sc">EAD.</hi></p>

				<p>BLUE BONNET IN BOSTON<lb/> B<hi rend="sc">Y</hi> C<hi rend="sc">AROLINE</hi> E. J<hi
						rend="sc">ACOBS</hi> AND L<hi rend="sc">ELA</hi> H<hi rend="sc">ORN</hi> R<hi rend="sc"
						>ICHARDS.</hi></p>

				<p>BLUE BONNET KEEPS HOUSE<lb/> B<hi rend="sc">Y</hi> C<hi rend="sc">AROLINE</hi> E. J<hi
						rend="sc">ACOBS</hi> AND L<hi rend="sc">ELA</hi> H<hi rend="sc">ORN</hi> R<hi rend="sc"
						>ICHARDS.</hi></p>

				<p>BLUE BONNET--DÉBUTANTE<lb/> B<hi rend="sc">Y</hi> L<hi rend="sc">ELA</hi> H<hi rend="sc"
						>ORN</hi> R<hi rend="sc">ICHARDS.</hi></p>

				<p>BLUE BONNET OF THE SEVEN STARS<lb/> B<hi rend="sc">Y</hi> L<hi rend="sc">ELA</hi> H<hi
						rend="sc">ORN</hi> R<hi rend="sc">ICHARDS.</hi></p>

				<p>BLUE BONNET'S FAMILY<lb/> B<hi rend="sc">Y</hi> L<hi rend="sc">ELA</hi> H<hi rend="sc"
						>ORN</hi> R<hi rend="sc">ICHARDS.</hi></p>

				<p>"Blue Bonnet has the very finest kind of wholesome, honest, lively girlishness and cannot
					but make friends with everyone who meets her through these books about her."--<bibl
						rend="i">Chicago Inter-Ocean.</bibl></p>

				<p>"Blue Bonnet and her companions are real girls, the kind that one would like to have in
					one's home."--<bibl rend="i">New York Sun.</bibl></p>

			</div1>

			<pb id="VAB1854-235" n="A-2"/>

			<div1 type="advertisement">

				<head>
					<hi rend="center">THE LITTLE COLONEL BOOKS</hi>
				</head>

				<p>
					<hi rend="center">(Trade Mark)</hi>
					<lb/>
					<hi rend="center">B<hi rend="sc">Y</hi> A<hi rend="sc">NNIE</hi> F<hi rend="sc"
							>ELLOWS</hi> J<hi rend="sc">OHNSTON</hi></hi>
				</p>

				<list type="simple">
					<item><hi rend="i">Each large 12mo, cloth, illustrated, per volume <hi rend="right"
								>$2.00</hi></hi></item>
				</list>
			</div1>

			<div1 type="advertisement">
				<head>THE LITTLE COLONEL STORIES</head>

				<p>
					<hi rend="center">(Trade Mark)</hi>
					<lb/>
				</p>

				<p>Being three "Little Colonel" stories in the Cosy Corner Series, "The Little Colonel,"
					"Two Little Knights of Kentucky," and "The Giant Scissors," in a single volume.</p>
			</div1>

			<div1 type="advertisement">

				<head>THE LITTLE COLONEL STORIES:</head>
				<p>Second Series <hi rend="center">(Trade Mark)</hi>
				</p>

				<p>Tales about characters that appear in the Little Colonel Series.--"Ole Mammy's Torment,"
					"The Three Tremonts," and "The Little Colonel in Switzerland."</p>

				<p>THE LITTLE COLONEL'S HOUSE PARTY<lb/>
					<hi rend="center">(Trade Mark)</hi>
				</p>

				<p>THE LITTLE COLONEL'S HOLIDAYS<lb/>
					<hi rend="center">(Trade Mark)</hi>
				</p>

				<p>THE LITTLE COLONEL'S HERO<lb/>
					<hi rend="center">(Trade Mark)</hi>
				</p>

				<p>THE LITTLE COLONEL AT BOARDING SCHOOL<lb/>
					<hi rend="center">(Trade Mark)</hi>
				</p>

				<p>THE LITTLE COLONEL IN ARIZONA<lb/>
					<hi rend="center">(Trade Mark)</hi>
				</p>

				<p>THE LITTLE COLONEL'S CHRISTMAS VACATION<lb/>
					<hi rend="center">(Trade Mark)</hi>
				</p>

				<p>THE LITTLE COLONEL, MAID OF HONOR<lb/>
					<hi rend="center">(Trade Mark)</hi>
				</p>

				<p>THE LITTLE COLONEL'S KNIGHT COMES RIDING<lb/>
					<hi rend="center">(Trade Mark)</hi>
				</p>

				<p>THE LITTLE COLONEL'S CHUM, MARY WARE<lb/>
					<hi rend="center">(Trade Mark)</hi>
				</p>

				<p>MARY WARE IN TEXAS</p>

				<p>MARY WARE'S PROMISED LAND</p>

				<list type="simple">
					<item><hi rend="i">These thirteen volumes, boxed as a set, $26.00</hi></item>
				</list>

			</div1>

			<pb id="VAB1854-236" n="A-3"/>


			<div1 type="advertisement">
				<p>FOR PIERRE'S SAKE AND OTHER STORIES</p>
				<list type="simple">
					<item><hi rend="i">Cloth, 12mo, illustrated by Billie Chapman <hi rend="right"
							>$1.75</hi></hi></item>
				</list>

				<p>"'For Pierres Sake,' who works so hard to scrape together the pennies necessary for a
					wreath for his brother's grave, 'The Rain Maker,' who tries to bring rain to the drought
					stricken fields--these and many others will take their places in The Children's Hall of
					Fame, which exists in the heart of childhood."--<bibl rend="i">Portsmouth (N. H.)
						Herald.</bibl></p>

			</div1>

			<div1 type="advertisement">
				<p>THE ROAD OF THE LOVING HEART</p>
				<list type="simple">
					<item><hi rend="i">Cloth decorated, with special designs and illustrations <hi
								rend="right">$1.25</hi></hi></item>
				</list>

				<p>This story of a little princess and her faithful pet bear, who finally <hi rend="i"
						>do</hi> discover "The Road of the Loving Heart," is a masterpiece of sympathy and
					understanding and beautiful thought.</p>

			</div1>

			<div1 type="advertisement">

				<head>
					<hi rend="center">THE JOHNSTON JEWEL SERIES</hi>
				</head>
				<list type="simple">
					<item><hi rend="i">Each small 16mo, decorative boards, per volume <hi rend="right"
								>$0.75</hi></hi></item>
				</list>

				<p>IN THE DESERT OF WAITING:<lb/> T<hi rend="sc">HE</hi> L<hi rend="sc">EGEND</hi> OF C<hi
						rend="sc">AMELBACK</hi> M<hi rend="sc">OUNTAIN.</hi></p>

				<p>THE THREE WEAVERS:<lb/> A F<hi rend="sc">AIRY</hi> T<hi rend="sc">ALE</hi> FOR F<hi
						rend="sc">ATHERS</hi> AND M<hi rend="sc">OTHERS</hi> AS W<hi rend="sc">ELL</hi> AS FOR
						T<hi rend="sc">HEIR</hi> D<hi rend="sc">AUGHTERS.</hi></p>

				<p>KEEPING TRYST:<lb/> A T<hi rend="sc">ALE</hi> OF K<hi rend="sc">ING</hi> A<hi rend="sc"
						>RTHUR'S</hi> T<hi rend="sc">IME.</hi></p>

				<p>THE LEGEND OF THE BLEEDING HEART</p>

				<p>THE RESCUE OF PRINCESS WINSOME:<lb/> A F<hi rend="sc">AIRY</hi> P<hi rend="sc">LAY</hi>
					FOR O<hi rend="sc">LD</hi> AND Y<hi rend="sc">OUNG.</hi></p>

				<p>THE JESTER'S SWORD</p>

			</div1>

			<milestone unit="typography" n="-----" rend="center"/>

			<div1 type="advertisement">

				<p>THE LITTLE COLONEL'S GOOD TIMES BOOK</p>

				<list type="simple">

					<item><hi rend="i">Uniform in size with the Little Colonel Series <hi rend="right"
								>$2.50</hi></hi></item>

					<item><hi rend="i">Bound in white kid (morocco) and gold <hi rend="right"
						>6.00</hi></hi></item>

				</list>

				<p>Cover design and decorations by Peter Verberg.</p>

				<p>"A mighty attractive volume in which the owner may record the good times she has on
					decorated pages, and under the directions as it were of Annie Fellows Johnston."--<bibl
						rend="i">Buffalo Express.</bibl></p>

			</div1>

			<pb id="VAB1854-237" n="A-4"/>

			<div1 type="advertisement">

				<head rend="center">HILDEGARDE-MARGARET SERIES<lb/></head>

				<p>B<hi rend="sc">Y</hi> L<hi rend="sc"/>AURA E. R<hi rend="sc">ICHARDS</hi></p>

				<list type="simple">

					<item><hi rend="center">Eleven Volumes</hi></item>
				</list>

				<p>The Hildegarde-Margaret Series, beginning with "Queen Hildegarde" and ending with "The
					Merryweathers," make one of the best and most popular series of books for girls ever
					written.</p>

				<list type="simple">

					<item><hi rend="i">Each large 12mo, cloth decorative, illustrated, per volume <hi
								rend="right">$1.75</hi></hi></item>

					<item>The eleven volumes boxed as a set <hi rend="right">$19.25</hi></item>

				</list>

			</div1>

			<div1 type="advertisement">

				<list type="simple">

					<item><hi rend="center">LIST OF TITLES</hi></item>
				</list>

				<p>QUEEN HILDEGARDE</p>

				<p>HILDEGARDE'S HOLIDAY</p>

				<p>HILDEGARDE'S HOME</p>

				<p>HILDEGARDE'S NEIGHBORS</p>

				<p>HILDEGARDE'S HARVEST</p>

				<p>THREE MARGARETS</p>

				<p>MARGARET MONTFORT</p>

				<p>PEGGY</p>

				<p>RITA</p>

				<p>FERNLEY HOUSE</p>

				<p>THE MERRYWEATHERS</p>

			</div1>

		</back>

	</text>

</TEI.2>
