<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//IA Books//DTD TEI for Indiana Authors Books//EN"
                       "teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="VAB8222">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Conservatism, the essential in American character and
                    policy</title>
                <title type="subtitle">address, delivered at the auditorium, at Chicago, on the
                    afternoon of February 22d, 1902</title>
                <author>Beveridge, Albert Jeremiah, 1862-1927.</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded By</resp>
                    <!--Update the value of the element below with your name in
                                direct order.-->
                    <name>Ruth Tucker</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
                </address>
                <idno>VAB8222</idno>
                <availability status="unknown">
                    <p>Copyright 2009 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
                    <p>Indiana University provides the information contained on this web site for
                        non-commercial, personal, or research use only. All other use, including but
                        not limited to commercial or scholarly reproductions, redistribution,
                        publication or transmission, whether by electronic means or otherwise,
                        without prior written permission of the copyright holder is strictly
                        prohibited.</p>
                </availability>
                <!--Update the value of the date element with the year the document
                        is being encoded.-->
                <date>2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title type="main">Conservatism, the essential in American character and
                            policy</title>
                        <title type="subtitle">address, delivered at the auditorium, at Chicago, on
                            the afternoon of February 22d, 1902</title>
                        <author id="ina-v1-entry-0073">Beveridge, Albert Jeremiah,
                            1862-1927.</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>22 p. ; 21 cm.</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>[s.n.]</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>[Chicago]</pubPlace>
                        <date>[1902]</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Digital Library Program was awarded a Library Services and Technology Act
                    (LSTA) grant in 2005 to make available online the three-volume, reference work,
                        <title>Indiana Authors and Their Books</title> along with selected
                    monographs by Indiana authors.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3">
                <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoded and edited using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines following the TEI Lite standard. Digital page images are
                    linked to the text file.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <tagUsage gi="div1">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language>English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Conservatism</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <!--The revision description tracks significant changes made to the file
                    after completion. This information will remain commented out unless someone has
                    conducted quality assessment of the texts and have made changes to the file as a
                    result.-->
        <!-- <revisionDesc> <change>
                    <date>$Date</date> <respStmt>
                    <name>$Name</name>
                    <resp>$Responsibility</resp>
                    </respStmt> <item>$Changes</item>
                    </change> </revisionDesc> -->
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>

            <pb id="VAB8222-001" n="[1]"/>


            <titlePage>
                <docTitle rend="center">
                    <titlePart type="main">CONSERVATISM:</titlePart><lb/>
                    <titlePart type="subtitle"> T<hi rend="sc">HE</hi> E<hi rend="sc">SSENTIAL
                            IN</hi> A<hi rend="sc">MERICAN</hi> C<hi rend="sc">HARACTER <lb/>
                            AND</hi> P<hi rend="sc">OLICY</hi>.</titlePart><lb/>

                    <titlePart type="subtitle">Address, delivered at the Auditorium, at Chicago,
                        on<lb/> the afternoon of February 22d, 1902,</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <byline rend="center">BY<lb/>
                    <docAuthor>S<hi rend="sc">ENATOR</hi> A<hi rend="sc">LBERT</hi> J. B<hi
                            rend="sc">EVERIDGE</hi>.</docAuthor>
                </byline>

            </titlePage>


            <pb id="VAB8222-002" n="[2]"/>
        </front>
        <body>
            <pb id="VAB8222-003" n="3"/>


            <div1 type="book">

                                <head rend="center">CONSERVATISM:<lb/> The Essential in American Character and
                    Policy.</head>

                <milestone unit="typography" n="-------" rend="center"/>

                <div2 type="chapter">
                    <head type="supplied">Chapter</head>
                    
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Ladies and Gentlemen :</hi>
                    </p>

                    <p>The meaning of Washington in American history is discipline. The message of
                        Washington's life to the American people is discipline. The need of American
                        character is the cultivation of discipline.</p>

                    <p> Washington did not give patriotism to the American colonies. The people had
                        that as abundantly as he. He did not give them courage. That quality was and
                        is in the American blood. He did not even give them resource. There were
                        intellects more productive than his. But Washington gave balance and
                        direction to elemental forces. He was the genius cf order. He was poise
                        personified. He was the spirit of discipline. He was the Great Conservative.
                        It was this that made all other elements of the Revolution effective. It was
                        this that organized a nebulous independence into a Nation of liberty. The
                        parts of a machine are useless until assembled and fitted each to its
                        appropriate place. Washington did that. And so it is that we are a
                        people.</p>

                    <p>But we are not yet a perfect people any more than a youth is yet a perfect
                        man. We are yet in the making. It is a glorious circumstance. Youth is the
                        noblest of God's great gifts. The life of a nation is like the life of a
                        man. Read the history of apeople who have done things in their day. Read the
                        life of a man who has done things in his day. They are as imilar as sea and
                        ocean. It is only a question of magnitude.</p>

                    <pb id="VAB8222-004" n="4"/>

                    <p>The American people are young? Yes! Vital? Yes! Powerful? Yes! Masterful?
                        Yes! Disciplined? Not entirely. Reserved? Not yet, but will be. Moderate?
                        Not yet, but growing in that grace. And therefore on this, his day, I bear
                        you the message of Washington-he, whose sanity, orderliness and calm have
                        reached through the century, steadying us when untamed passions of riotous
                        youth had all but reached the climax of chaos.</p>

                    <p>The American people have finally overcome every convulsion? True. The element
                        of sobriety has never failed to master the maddest agitations? True again.
                        But the cost of the struggle in every instance has been measured by the
                        strength of the instinct of discipline at the time. To-day we are calm, and
                        are conscious of no need for self-restraint. Yes! But yesterday we were
                        delirious, and the rumble bf cannon on your streets and the rattle of
                        musketry at your doors was hailed with feelings of security and relief. The
                        necessity for this should never have occurred. And many crises may be
                        recalled by men not yet old; The political convulsion of five years ago is a
                        peaceful example of popular hysteria, overcome by strenuous work that tested
                        the powers of conservatism to the ultimate limit. Popular reserve, the
                        self-restraint of the people, the fireside conference, would have lessened
                        every excited circumstance in our history, and prevented many or most of
                        them. Reason is better than bayonet Sober second thought is better than the
                        destroying violence of a campaign over passion-born propositions.</p>

                    <div3 type="part">
                        <head rend="center sc">THE LABOR AND CAPITAL ARBITRATION COMMITTEE.</head>

                        <p>In the daily press we read of a co-operative council of capitalists,
                            clergy, workers and publicists to settle the conflicts between labor and
                            productive wealth. We applaud it, and we should. But not because it will
                            be effective--for it may not be effective. But we hail it as an evidence
                            that the spirit of forbearance is spreading among the people. It is an
                            expression of the instinct of order which must become the ruling element
                            in American civilization And this it is which, more and more, will
                            settle strikes, and in the end prevent them. This it is</p>

                        <pb id="VAB8222-005" n="5"/>

                        <p>which, more and more, will take wildness out of our politics, until
                            reasonable issues only remain. The remedy for friction between employer
                            and employed is in the breasts of the men themselves and their
                            employers. The saving of the people is in the hands of the people
                            themselves, and nowhere else. Better than councils and commissions and
                            congresses is the self-discipline, the reasoning reserve, the regulated
                            conscience of a free people. And congresses and councils are, effective
                            only as they are expressions of this.</p>

                        <p>Indeed, we have awakened to the fundamental fact that written 1ws are not
                            everything and that the people are everything. Back of our statutes
                            stands our Constitution, and back of our Constitution stands our
                            institutions, and back of our institutions stands our race. Let us
                            remember that the people are the real foundation; not laws, not even
                            constitutions. It is the people from which statutes, constitutions and
                            even institutions spring that give these forms of civil method their
                            meaning. The Constitution of this Republic would be a different
                            instrument as the fundamental law of a Latin nation even though that
                            nation copied it word for word. It would be interpreted by their racial
                            spirit, expounded in the light of their racial institutions. Every day
                            since our Constitution was adopted we have been acting beyond the limits
                            of its written word, but within the limits of its institutional meaning.
                            If we had not done so we would not now be a Nation.</p>
                        
                    </div3>

                    <div3 type="part">
                        <head rend="center sc">WORD OF THE CONSTITUTION INADEQUATE.</head>

                        <p> More and more this will be so. The growth of modern Industry, the
                            gradual change of competition into co-operation, the manifold and
                            infinitely interwoven activities of modern business, the steady knitting
                            together of all the agencies of production, distribution and exchange
                            until the whole nation is ell nigh an industrial unit as it is a
                            political unit, the extenion of this process until international
                            relations are so interlaced at no nation, even by war, can entirely cut
                            the golden cords commerce and culture that bind her to her sisters--the
                            prosses of civilization, in short,--bring into play national necesities
                            and national powers as much greater and more complex those exercised by
                            the Fathers, as the Nation and its </p>

                        <pb id="VAB8222-006" n="6"/>

                        <p>activities to-day are greater and more complex than they were a century
                            ago. We cannot adopt.new constitutions to meet these new conditions.
                            They would be inadequate if we did adopt them; and each decade would
                            make the constitution of the preceding decade obsolete if its letter
                            alone were read. And so we rely on a law more permanent and more
                            vital--the institutional law with its roots springing from the very soul
                            of our race, by whose living meaning our written laws and constitutions
                            are interpreted. Our hope is in ourselves. Our safety is in our racial
                            customs and tendencies. Our salvation and supremacy is in the character
                            of or people.</p>

                        <p>I do not mean that we should bind ourselves to custom. I am only a
                            limited believer in the philosophy of precedent. Precedent becomes
                            paralysis, if observed when customs no longer fit conditions.
                            Conservatism does not mean adherence to existing order merely because it
                            is existing order. Conservatism means the adaptation of means to ends
                            naturally and without violence. Reason is the touch-stone of
                            conservatism. And so it is that we must foster the element of
                            conservatism in American character as we would-fan the spark of life
                            itself, for it is that vital spark. Let the American people write over
                            the fireside of every American home those words of inspired direction:
                            "Prove all things--hold fast to that which is good." Time is the greater
                            reasoner. Patience is the eternal method of accuracy and truth. Time and
                            Patience, Patience and Time--these are the ancient counsellors who never
                            err. These are the sages to consult when perplexing situations seem
                            unsolvable. Beware of instantaneous processes.</p>

                    </div3>

                    <div3 type="part">
                        <head rend="center sc">HOT-HOUSE LAWS INEFFECTIVE.</head>

                        <p>There can be no instantaneous settlement of any large question. To say
                            that there can be, is to say that civilization itself could be completed
                            by piecemeal. But that is not the method of civilization's progress.
                            Society is a growth--not a creation And all social, industrial and
                            political questions are relate as a tree's branches to the common trunk.
                            They are not, therefore, to be determined permanently by cure-all
                            measures and put aside as settled, as you pack articles in a box and put
                            it on the shelf, sealed and labeled. Conditions undergo</p>

                        <pb id="VAB8222-007" n="7"/>

                        <p>ceaseless change, and measures made for those conditions must also
                            undergo ceaseless change. But if the change is wise it must be slow, and
                            not sudden. The wrenching of the vast and delicate machinery of the
                            Nation's business, the straining of the nerves of the whole people in
                            unnecessary campaigns, has been due to impossible propositions to
                            instantly enact felicity. This is not discipline, not sanity. It is not
                            reason, but passion; not reserve, but rashness.</p>

                        <p>On the other hand, measures once enacted are not immortal. No economic
                            statute can be perpetual. To say that it can never be bettered is to say
                            that human conditions can never be bettered. But they can be bettered.
                            Yesterday we lumbered in stages; to-day we fly in palaces. And the
                            change from stage-coach to railway has required a new body of laws,
                            which are themselves perpetually changing. Yesterday both capital and
                            labor were individualized; to-day both are consolidated, systematized,
                            co-operative. But these new conditions grew out of the old conditions --
                            they were not suddenly created. And so we must let the new laws,
                            regulating those new conditions, grow, and not suddenly create them.
                            Quick creations always are ineffective. Conditions make laws, not laws
                            condition. And when this order is reversed both the law-made conditions
                            and the law which makes them are unhealthy, irritating and dangerous.
                            Events are the greatest of law-makers. Deliberation, patience nd the
                            self-regulation of our activities are the surest of safeuards. Put not
                            your faith in written word alone; put your faith in your own steady
                            self-restraint. "The letter killeth ut the spirit giveth life." As in
                            your relations to morals, you 'member the Master and strive to be like
                            Him; so in your lations to the state and your attitude toward all
                            questions at present themselves to you as one of a self-governing
                            people, remember Washington and strive to be like him--reserved,
                            considering, considerate and calm.</p>

                        <p>The national habit of self-control exercised in the current velopments of
                            each day, when times are not hot with friction, ll act without effort in
                            the hour when events flame with itement. If the people will adopt this
                            formula of conserve thought: Everything is not bad because it is new,
                            and</p>

                        <pb id="VAB8222-008" n="8"/>

                        <p>everything is not good because it is old,--and upon that formula base
                            conservative procedure, we shall always end with conservative results.
                            And conservative results are safe results; and safe progress is
                            permanent progress. Let us beware of rebounds.</p>

                    </div3>
                    
                    <div3 type="part">
                        <head rend="center sc">TREATMENT OF TRUSTS OF LABOR AND CAPITAL.</head>

                        <p>We are in a period of growth which is itself a proof of our youth and
                            enlarging vitality. It is inevitable that each year, almost each day,
                            shall behold unheard-of developments in our industrial, commercial,
                            financial methods. Let us be not startled at them. They may be
                            beneficent or they may be malevolent, but denunciation, hasty action,
                            conclusions which are jumped at instead of being thought out, are no
                            proper test. The habit of mind which leads us to bitterly denounce or
                            unreservedly praise, is not the temper which a free people should
                            foster. For be it remembered that a free people must depend upon
                            themselves and not upon some separate power which attempts to solve
                            every problem for them, as is the case in autocracies. We are fond of
                            saying that in a republic each citizen is a king. But saying so does not
                            make it so. Each of us can be a king, and therefore the nation itself
                            clothed with majesty as no people ever were arrayed; but only by each
                            citizen acting as a king should act; thinking as a king should think,
                            steadily, calmly, with balanced judgment and well-considered action.</p>

                        <p>The developments in the combinations of capital call for just such
                            popular treatment; the developments in combinations of labor call for
                            just such treatment. We behold millions of money which yesterday were
                            acting separately, to-day massed in mighty organizations for the
                            production, the transportation, the distribution of national products.
                            Let us not be alarmed at their magnitude. Let us not be paniced at their
                            novelty. It is not helpful to slap on the statute books hasty screeds
                            and call them laws. It will throw no light upon the real question for
                            excited meetings to grow frenzied over excited appeals. No great problem
                            was ever illuminated by the torch of a mob; and between the
                            conflagrations of the Commune and fiery talk of agitators who feel they
                            must carry the next election at any cost, there is little</p>

                        <pb id="VAB8222-009" n="9"/>

                        <p>difference. Both may be useful in revolution; both may be useful in the
                            bloody overthrow of tyranny; but neither are the method of a free
                            people, who hold their own destiny in their own hands.</p>
                        
                    </div3>

                    <div3 type="part">
                        <head rend="center sc">WORK OF THE TRUSTS.</head>

                        <p>It is apparent to the shallowest observer and certain to the profoundest,
                            that the great combinations of capital recently developed are based upon
                            some of the fundamental principles of progress. It is equally apparent
                            and certain that in their development, evils and crudities have attended
                            them. But this is true of everything. It is even true of the development
                            of a child into a boy and of a boy into a man; and constant care is
                            exercised in the draining of the infant mind and character. Maturity is
                            a hard process and slow, but it is a simple process. Let as simple a
                            process be exercised in the new development of our social economy. As
                            violence and hot words and stormy conduct spoil the vision of the
                            parent; so will the same savage methods spoil the vision and make
                            foolish the action of the people in the regulation of the development of
                            capital and labor. he great combinations of capital devoted to the
                            production of steel or flour or meats or oil, systematize the industry,
                            reduce the expense of production, simplify and make easy distribution,
                            invade and conquer foreign markets. The organizations of wealth devoted
                            to the preparation of meats and other food stuffs sell their products
                            abroad as well as here. Their vast resources enable them to put
                            refrigerating ships upon the sea and furnish the breakfast tables of
                            London and Berlin. And to supply that foreign demand the farmers of
                            Illinois, Dakota and Kansas are called upon for cattle at profitable
                            prices which otherwise they could not sell at all. So we see that this
                            golden shuttle of modern enterprise shooting backward and forward, not
                            only through our own land, but across the seas and into Europe and Asia,
                            too, weaves occupation and prosperity for our citizens in its ministry
                            to the wants of our fellow-men abroad.</p>

                        <p>These are a few of the benefits visible to all. On the other hand, the
                            arbitrary raising and lowering of prices, the unjust exaction of unfair
                            profits from our own consumers, are the evils.</p>

                        <pb id="VAB8222-010" n="10"/>

                        <p>But the benefits are fundamental, and the evils incidental. And you
                            cannot shear away the good from the bad by some measure evolved over
                            night from,an excited brain and adopted next day as a party measure to
                            carry an election the day after. The whole field of national and even
                            international industry and trade must be considered. When you reflect
                            that you cannot do the simplest thing without involving every activity
                            of industrial civilization all over the world, you can appreciate how
                            dangerous makeshift measures are. The simplest act of civilized life
                            affects all human industry. Take, for example, your journey home this
                            afternoon in the cab or railway or street-car. It involves the growing
                            and felling of forests. It calls into play the energies of miners
                            searching out the ore from which are made the wheels that carry you. It
                            involves the cattle from whose hides are made the harness of your
                            horses, or the leather. used in cars. It involves the activities, the
                            lives and the livlihood often thousand men immediately at hand ; and
                            broadening from this center of focused activity, it circles out to the
                            remotest confines of the world's industry. If so simple an act as your
                            journey home this afternoon, to which you give no heed, so commonplace
                            has it become, is thus far-reaching, how infinite in consequence are
                            measures controlling these industries, and how vastly greater even is
                            the policy of a people with reference to them. Do I say, therefore, that
                            no measures should be taken; no policy be formed? No, I say the reverse.
                            But I say with greater earnestness, caused by the danger of unthoughtful
                            and undisciplined action, that those measures and that policy should be
                            well considered, cautiously adopted, executed with sanity and
                            judgment.</p>
                    </div3>

                    <div3 type="part">
                        <head rend="center sc">CHANGE IN CHARACTER OF CAPITALISTS.</head>

                        <p>On the other hand, this development is having its beneficial effect upon
                            the capitalists themselves. Responsibility always brings a broader
                            understanding and a gentler consideration of others. And dealing, as the
                            managers of these vast agencies of production and exchange are, with all
                            the people of the nation, and well-nigh with all the world, a new
                            comprehension of those people is forced upon the capitalist, whether he
                            will or no. The financier of the twentieth century</p>

                        <pb id="VAB8222-011" n="11"/>

                        <p>has got to be more than a financier. <hi rend="i">The modern financier
                                must be a statesman.</hi> The day of the local Wall Street
                            capitalist is passed. he hour when the wizard of tricks sat in his
                            office and considred that the world of money was compassed by his
                            eye-sight, was struck yesterday, and that hour is no more forever.
                            To-day the capitalist can no longer indulge in the legerdemain of mere
                            stock speculation. He must build machinery; he must erect mills; he must
                            construct railroads; he must buy steamship lines. Therefore he must
                            understand the people, he must consider the people. The financial
                            rashness of the black Fridays of our history was as much a manifestation
                            of our undisciplined and capricious state of undevelopment as was the
                            burning of railroad properties at Pittsburg in the red days now almost
                            forgotten.</p>
                    </div3>

                    <div3 type="part">
                        <head rend="center sc">CAPITALISTS MUST CONSIDER THE PEOPLE.</head>

                        <p>And so we see capitalists have got to understand that the opinion of the
                            people is as definite a factor in their great plans as the quantity of,
                            coal remaining in the mine or the producing capacity of a mill. As much
                            a factor? Yes, infinitely more of a factor. For, after all, it is the
                            consuming and producing Capacity of the people upon which all industries
                            are built. It is the thought and settled resolve of the people which is
                            the most important element in the mosaic of our national economy. Thus
                            have the constructive capitalists of America come to understand that
                            public opinion must be taken into account as much as the amount of cash
                            on hand or bills receivable. They have been forced to this, let us say,
                            or they have learned it. No matter, they have come to understand it; and
                            so <hi rend="i">we see that voluntarily the greatest corporation of the
                            world has published to all the people a statement of its business
                            and its operations, of its assets and its liabilities, of its
                            products and its sales, of its history and its prospects. That is
                            the thing which the financier of ten years ago would have called
                            chimerical, foolish, the unwise pandering of the theorist to the
                            curiosity of the crowd.</hi> But the financier of the twentieth
                            century no longer calls it so. He knows it is not so. He. knows that it
                            is a necessity of his business -- a thing essential to the popular
                            Support of his enterprise. Another great corporation of Illinois</p>

                        <pb id="VAB8222-012" n="12"/>

                        <p>whose managing mind appears to be a statesman as well as a financier,
                            began some three or four years ago to distribute the stock of his
                            railroad among its employees, and to sell shares at lowest terms to the
                            people living along its line. Ten years ago that would have been called
                            socialism--to-day it is business. It is conservatism. It is the
                            realization of things as they are and the adjustment of the measures of
                            wisdom and humanity to existing conditions, in order that the best of
                            existing conditions may be preserved, and from them still better
                            conditions may be evolved. All this is sanity; all this is calm and
                            gentle and considerate hought; all this is the beginning of that
                            discipline which comes from self-restraint and the respect for the
                            rights and opinions of our fellows.</p>
                        
                    </div3>

                    <div3 type="part">
                        <head rend="center sc">LABOR TRUSTS.</head>

                        <p>Organizations of labor are cognate to the organizations of capital. Each
                            is the outgrowth of that principle of co-operation which is the very
                            spirit of civilized society. The family is cooperation; a partnership is
                            co-operation; the simplest form of a state is co-operation; and as the
                            state grows more perfect, its citizens more and more co-operate each
                            with all and all with each. Neither labor organizations, therefore, nor
                            those of capital are unnatural or harmful. But the tyranny of greed may
                            pervert the one; the tyranny of passion may ruin the other. Considerate
                            moderation is the safety of both, and if each were to adopt it, it would
                            be their glory as well. And if capital will not be reasonable, if labor
                            will not be reasonable; the people will be reasonable for them. There is
                            no place in this country for the absolutist of capital. There is no
                            place in this country for the absolutist of riot. The bully of wealth
                            shaking his clenched fist of gold, is wealth's worst enemy. The bully of
                            labor shouting denunciation, is labor's worst enemy. Let the wiser
                            laborer elbow from his company, him of the Flaming utterance and
                            untruthful tongue. Let the wiser capitalists suppress their would-be
                            Czars. Out wilth the element of unreason in both camps, and the di ided
                            hosts will be one! Out with unreason everywhere in the Republic! Let
                            thspirit of Washington be monarch of the hearts and minds of men
                            everywhere beneath the flag which Washington established.</p>
                        
                    </div3>

                    <pb id="VAB8222-013" n="13"/>

                    <div3 type="part">
                        <head rend="center sc">CHANGE IN CHARACTER OF LABOR LEADERS.</head>

                        <p>As the twentieth century financier must be a statesman, so the twentieth
                            century labor leader must be a statesman, too. He, too, must consider
                            the people's thought. He, too, must measure popular tendencies. He, too,
                            must counsel no act without weighing the effect that act will have
                            throughout the whole complicated machinery of related and interdependent
                            industries. And such statesmanship is being evolved. A man cannot long
                            remain the head of one of the great armies of organized workers without
                            developing conservatism. Necessity teaches him the value of moderation.
                            When he feels his hand upon the lever that directs the movements of a
                            hundred thousand toilers, his awful responsibility instructs him in
                            self-restraint. The events of the last two years have proved that the
                            directing heads of two of the greatest labor trusts are conservative
                            counsellors. Their number will increase. More and more the organizations
                            of labor will insist that their leaders shall be men of thought, slow to
                            wrath, steady in action. More and more, they will come to appreciate
                            that a leader is none the less loyal because he is wise.</p>

                        <p>How majestic is the majesty of moderation!</p>

                    </div3>

                    <div3 type="part">
                        <head rend="center sc"> CONSERVATISM IN TARIFF RE-ADJUSTMENT.</head>

                        <p>These are the aggressive tendencies of the times when the calm of
                            Washington councils prudence, self-restraint, the holding well in hand
                            of the people's thought and action by the people themselves. And there
                            are retrogressive tendencies as well to which the spirit of Washington
                            equally applies. The fanaticism of existing conditions is the reverse of
                            the shield. It is as unreasoning to say that an outgrown law shall not
                            be modified as it is to say that immature statutes shall be enacted. One
                            is the hysteria of precedent; the other is the hysteria of alarm. Men
                            say "Down with the tariff" ! Men say "Maintain the tariff," or "Lift it
                            higher still." Conservatism says, "You both are wrong--adjust the tariff
                            to conditions. Tariff merely ifor protection is no fetish; tariff for
                            mere revenue is no God. No system of taxation is sacred. It is merely a
                            means to an</p>

                        <pb id="VAB8222-014" n="14"/>

                        <p>end or many ends. It is not an end in itself." This is the voice of
                            Conservatism and it is the voice of truth and soberness.</p>

                        <p>Even self-government is not an end in itself. It is a means to an end.
                            With Anglo-Saxon peoples self-government is the means to the end of
                            individual and collective human happiness. And all the laws of
                            self-governing peoples are just that and nothing more. Tariff laws are
                            no exception. If they are wise, they grow out of conditions; and so they
                            become unwise When the conditions out of which such laws have grown,
                            have themselves outgrown the laws. When this becomes true, such laws
                            need re-adjustment, for the very same reason that calls for their
                            original enactment.</p>
                        
                    </div3>

                    <div3 type="part">
                        <head rend="center sc">HOME MARKET; FOREIGN MARKET.</head>

                        <p>We have entered upon an era of production that overwhelms our very
                            understanding. It was not so yesterday. Yesterday we made little we did
                            not want ourselves, and so the "Home Market" was then the word of
                            economic truth; and that word spoke into life a system of protection as
                            perfectly fitted for its purpose as ever the mind of man devised. Mills,
                            factories, railroads, farms, mines--a thousand forms of productive
                            industry developed magically; and over all the busy genius of invention
                            brooded, making one hand do that which thousands toiled to do before,
                            fertilizing fields, abbreviating space, extracting gold from hopeless
                            rocks, discovering wealth and human uses in the very refuse of a cruder
                            day. And so it came to pass that our home market is supplied and the
                            overflowing ,surplus threatens to choke the very machinery that produces
                            it unless we find a place to sell that surplus. And so it is that to-day
                            Progress speaks a new word of economic truth as needful now as was the
                            old word then. As the "Home market" was the word of wisdom in its
                            season, so "Foreign markets" is the word of wisdom now.</p>

                        <p>We have more coal, more iron, more skill in workmanship, More ability and
                            experience in organizing capital for productive uses than any other
                            portion of the globe--almost more than all of the rest of the world
                            combined. And so we sell abroad our girders, beams and plates of steel,
                            and the many forms into which wealth and work and genius have fashioned
                            the useful</p>

                        <pb id="VAB8222-015" n="15"/>

                        <p>metals. We must sell them abroad. Otherwise, idle over his accumulated
                            products, will sit the laborer; lifeless will be the throbbing mill;
                            deserted the producing mine; chained to the rotting docks the ships of
                            export. And this is true of the fabrics of cotton and of wool; true of
                            meats, flour, and all the stuffs that feed and clothe the human race.
                            For other nations have factories, too. Other nations spin and weave, and
                            plant and sow and reap. They will not always permit us to supply their
                            citizens. The words "Home market," which yesterday was our talisman,
                            to-morrow will be theirs, and for the same reason that it was once ours.
                            Conditions have turned the tables; and where yesterday we asked
                            protection from them, to-day they are demanding protection from us. They
                            will erect tariff walls against us as we once " erected tariff walls
                            against them. Where, then, shall we turn with our ships of merchandise?
                            What, then, will be the destination of our weighted trains of freight?
                            Not to ourselves, for we are already supplied, and it is our surplus
                            that fills those ships and burden those countless cars of commerce. We
                            cannot turn entirely to the Orient, for that market is not yet
                            sufficiently understood, although it will be. It is not yet sufficiently
                            exploited, although it will be. And when the Oriental market is opened
                            in its fullness and occupied by us, it will be our commerial and
                            financial salvation. Meanwhile our own consuming capacity will increase.
                            But while it is increasing, our surplus cannot wait. It must be disposed
                            of as it is produced. And, always, there will be a surplus. The
                            productive capacity of a people beyond their own needs is the measure of
                            their increasing wealth. And so, while the increase of our own consuming
                            capacity is important, the development of our foreign markets is
                            indispensable, too. Both are necessary to the consumption of our
                            ever-increasing production. And of foreign markets, the Oriental field
                            is virgin soil and awaits our intelligent cultivation.</p>

                    </div3>

                    <div3 type="part">
                        <head rend="center sc">RECIPROCITY.</head>

                        <p>But that is a question for to-morrow. We must consider the reuirements of
                            to-day. We must turn to t instant need of things." We must make those
                            common sense arrangements</p>


                        <pb id="VAB8222-016" n="16"/>

                        <p>with our neighbors among the nations by which our surplus of American
                            products may be taken across the seas. This is the statesmanship of
                            common sense. The eye of Blaine perceived it in the distance, and too
                            soon announced its principle. The even more prophetic mind of Grant,
                            whose elemental statesmanship will be better appreciated a hundred years
                            from now than it is to-day, perceived it even before Blaine saw it. And,
                            even if both had failed to grasp its meaning, that meaning would be
                            unmistakable at this hour. For, gradually, foreign statesmen are closing
                            their markets to us. They will do it more swiftly in the future than
                            they have done it in the past, or else they will fail in their duties to
                            their peoples. On one hand the miraculous growth of our export trade is
                            lessening; and on the other hand our productiveness waxes until its
                            magnitude to-day makes little its proportions of yesterday, which then
                            were wonderfu. <hi rend="i">Decreasing markets, increasing productions--
                            </hi> this is the situation. It is not a situation that calls for
                            fanaticism in favor of any law; it is not a situation that calls for D
                            fanaticism in favor of the destruction of any law. It is a situation
                            that calls for the patient, intelligent adjustment of means to ends. It
                            is a situation that calls for the councils of conservatism. Out upon the
                            selfish interest that would enrich itself at the expense of the
                            permanent prosperity of the Nation! Out upon the passionate demand for
                            the destruction of all protection! Up with the standard of moderation
                            and let all the forces of American conservatism rally around it! So
                            shall employment continue to wait on labor. So shall investment continue
                            to plead with capital. So shall this marvelous American civilization,
                            whose far meaning even the most prophetic mind cannot grasp to-day,
                            continue to evolve out of the play of our free and unfettered
                            activities.</p>

                    </div3>

                    <div3 type="part">
                        <head rend="center sc">CONSERVATISM AND OUR FOREIGN POSSESSIONS.</head>

                        <p>It was a wisdom higher than our own that drove us into the markets of the
                            world. You may say that it was the wisdom of events. You may say it was
                            the wisdom that springs From the wealth of our resources and the
                            ingenuity of our brains and the skill of our fingers. I prefer to
                            believe and do </p>


                        <pb id="VAB8222-017" n="17"/>

                        <p>believe that it was a loftier wisdom still, the universal wisdom of the
                            Father. And it was His wisdom, too, that placed in our guardianship new
                            peoples and alien races. You may say that it is a blunder that did that.
                            I will not quarrel with you. You may s that it was a conjunction of
                            circumstances. I will not argue the point. Whatever the compelling
                            cause, the fact exists and the duty is ours. Call it circumstance, call
                            it events, call it blunder, or call it the decree of destiny--other
                            peoples are our wards and we will not desert them. Their lands are our
                            trust and we will not betray it. All will admit that if we could succeed
                            in discharging this trust so that these dependent peoples would be
                            happier, our nation better and the civilization of the world thereby
                            advanced, it would be a noble conclusion for which the most doubtful
                            heart might yearn. All this we may accomplish. All this we will
                            accomplish. Let no man doubt our ultimate success, for we will proceed
                            according to the councils of conservatism. Moderation will direct
                            us.</p>
                        
                    </div3>

                    <div3 type="part">
                        <head rend="center sc">THE AMERICAN CHARACTERISTIC.</head>

                        <p>We daily hear dogmatic demands for the independence of our Malay wards,
                            without considering concrete, conditions. Is this .moderation? Is this
                            the "method of calm reason ? Is it not better to fit our acts to
                            whatever the actual facts may be? Adaptability is the American
                            characteristic. We are told that self-government is the American
                            characteristic. We are told that this and that is the American
                            characteristic. We are asked. to frame our action upon this tradition or
                            that, regardless of changed situations, of absolutely different facts.
                            But adaptability is the American characteristic. Adaptability,
                            adaptability, adaptability. The fitting of means to ends, the adjustment
                            of measures to conditions--this is the heart of Americanism. The secret
                            of American success has been that we have looked the facts squarely in
                            the face and then made our measures fit those facts. We have done this
                            regardless of maxims, indiffer- ent to theories and even over the letter
                            of our Constitution Itself when it stood in the way. President Madison
                            thought that the Federal Government had no power to build a na- Stional
                            highway. The power to make internal improvements</p>

                        <pb id="VAB8222-018" n="18"/>

                        <p>was not conferred on Congress by the Constitution, he said. This was the
                            view of the Fathers. Rivers, roads and harbors were matters of local
                            concern, they thought. Their theory of local self-government, of the
                            sovereignty of the State, of the independence of the community, required
                            that the National Government should not better local conditions. If a
                            river was non-navigable at a point within a state through which it ran,
                            it was not the mission of the general government to dredge it. Its care
                            was in the keeping of the people who lived upon its banks. Local
                            self-government, they said, was an end and not a means. But Progress
                            said that the prosperity of the people is the end, and local
                            self-government, general government, or any other kind of government
                            nothing but a means. Progress said, "The logic of strict construction is
                            built on words; I demand logic built on facts." And so into the written
                            Constitution, the necessities of national intercourse read the power of
                            the General Government to make internal improvements. And to-day that
                            power is so much a matter of course that not one man in ten thousand
                            knows that that power was originally denied. Thus it was that the spirit
                            of American adaptability triumphed even over the letter of the
                            Constitution.</p>

                        <p>Business is the great expounder of our fundamental law. Conditions
                            construe our Constitution more completely than alI the lawyers who ever
                            lived. Geography, invention, exploration, are continuous interpreters of
                            that great instrument. Mountains, rivers, plains and lakes, railways,
                            telegraphs, the planting of new communities, the discovery of new
                            resources, the interchange of thought and products--to these great
                            natural and human. facts the spirit of American adaptability has
                            conformed ancient customs, honored traditions, written constitutions.
                            There is no written power in the Constitution for the National
                            Government to charter banks, but a man would be considered mad to-day
                            who denied that power to the National Government. The list of instances
                            where the practical genius of the American people has adapted their
                            Constitution to their needs is the most striking circumstance of our
                            history and the profoundest proof of our vitality. From that saving
                            wisdom of adaptability</p>

                        <pb id="VAB8222-019" n="19"/>

                        <p> we will not now depart. If Phlippine conditions require Filipino
                            self-government, self-government we will give the Filipinos because it
                            is wise. If legislative participation in their government is permitted
                            by Porto Rican conditions, we will give the Porto Ricans that because it
                            is wise. If Cuban conditions require American suzerainty, we will
                            maintain that because it is wise; if annexation, we will accomplish that
                            because it is wise; if utter searation, that shall be done because it is
                            wise. If facts demand that we administer government in our Far-Eastern
                            possessions without the participation of an incompetent people, that
                            government we will, ourselves, administer, because it is wise. We are
                            wedded to no theory; we are chained to no catch-word; our free hand is
                            not fettered by any unchangeable method. If Washington thought that
                            Christmas Day, drunken Hessians and all the elements of surprise
                            existed, he crossed the Delaware and attacked like another Attila. If he
                            thought that overwhelming British forces discouraged American troops and
                            all the elements of weakness in his own ranks required avoidance of
                            conflict, he retreated like another Fabius. That is the American spirit.
                            And so with our new and world-wide duties. If facts demand autonomy for
                            our possessions, autonomy it shall be. If facts demand guardianship at
                            our hands, guardianship it shall be. Over the American mind and heart
                            and directing American action, the genius of the practical still
                            presides. We are no China cursed with custom, drugged and dead with
                            precedent. We are Americans--the people of the appropriate and the
                            adaptable</p>

                    </div3>

                    <div3 type="part">
                        <head rend="center sc">NO ABANDONMENT OF THE PHILIPPINES.</head>

                        <p>The treatment of our dependencies is the world issue now confronting us.
                            Let us then plant ourselves on the fundamental certainties. And the
                            first of these certainties is that not one single foot of soil over
                            which American civil authority is established will be abandoned. "What
                            we have, we hold !"--this is the voice of our race. People of our blood
                            seldom leave land they have occupied. No master people ever yields while
                            they remain a master people. Emerson declares that when the powers of a
                            man decline he draws in his enterprise; he quits business ;</p>

                        <pb id="VAB8222-020" n="20"/>

                        <p>he prepares for the inevitable end. The same is true of a people. But the
                            American people are not on the decline. The American People are not
                            ready to go out of business. The American people are stronger for the
                            world's work now than any people ever were before. And our portion of
                            the world's work, which Destiny has laid upon us in common with the
                            younger and the growing races, is the duty and labor of guardianship. We
                            are the executors of a trust estate in Porto Rico, in Cuba, in the
                            Philippines. That trust we will execute as thoroughly as Americans do
                            everything. And so American government in the Philippines will be
                            permanent. The American Flag in Porto Rico will float there as long as
                            the Republic's goverment itself shall stand. American suzerainty over
                            Cuba will remain until time laces that island more closely to us with
                            more enduring bonds. Events call for the conservatism of adaptability.
                            Conditions demand the moderation of the free hand. The radicalism of
                            ancient methods has no place among new conditions. Remember the parable
                            of the new wine in the old bottles. What would we say if the Ancient
                            Mariner should step from his vessel of wood and sail and spars and ropes
                            onto the bridge of a twentieth century ocean liner, and declare that the
                            steam which drove it, the electricity which lighted it, the steel
                            plates, the copper bottoms and all the method of modern ship-building
                            are sacrilege, because he had not done in that way? This hoary
                            representative of a day that is dead would not be considered
                            conservative. The board of directors that would place him in command of
                            a Deutschland or a Lucania would not be considered conservative.
                            Moderation means the progress of facts--not the daring of dreams on the
                            one hand nor yet the cowardice of reminiscence on the other. And so with
                            the dependencies of the american Republic, american statesmen must deal
                            as practical thought directed to actual conditions demands that they
                            should deal. They must not deal spasmodically. They must not deal
                            retrogressively. They must deal practically, steadily. The free hand
                            must be the steady hand if it is to be the hand of the master, and the
                            free hand can be the steady hand only when its action is governed by
                            actual, and not imaginary conditions.</p>

                    </div3>

                    <pb id="VAB8222-021" n="21"/>

                    <div3 type="part">
                        <head rend="center sc">PATIENCE ESSENTIAL.</head>

                        <p>But in this great problem of our dependencies, more even than in the
                            surprising developments of our internal economy, patience is the word of
                            power and of success. A race cannot be transformed over night. The
                            methods of three Centuries cannot be remedied between sunrise and
                            sunset. The character of a people is not to be altered even by the
                            school-teachers' priceless work in a season or a year. Let us not be in
                            haste. Let us have the serenity of the situation. We are dealing with an
                            elemental problem, a racial problem, world question. We must act,
                            therefore, with a deliberation as large and a patience as steady as the
                            problem is vast and historic. We must employ no magic but time, no
                            legerdemain but that of steady and continuous effort unvarying and
                            undismayed. There must be no spasms of extravagance, no spasms of
                            retrenchment, no panic of retreat, no fury of advance. Let us not pine
                            for the fruit before the seed is planted, or even the ground
                            prepared.</p>

                        <p>So, fellow-citizens, we will go on in the spirit and method of
                            Washington, practically, steadily, calmly, without prejudice and without
                            fear. Whatever the future may hold for the American people in internal
                            development or foreign dominion, that future will be met with that
                            thoughtful moderation which adapts means to ends. If old methods
                            suffice, those old methods we will use because they are approved. If
                            present methods suffice, present methods we will use because they are at
                            hand. If new methods are necessary, new methods we will invent because
                            the case demands them. The fanaticism of the old will not influence the
                            American people. The fanaticism of the new will not influence the
                            American People. The conservatism of adaptability, the calmness of the
                            appropriate, the patience necessary for the doing of the work in hand
                            whatever that work may be-these are the saving influences which will
                            govern American action now and hereafter. The disc line of the day's
                            work, the balanced judgment that accomplishes real things, the Steady
                            sanity essential to the settlement of actual situations--these are the
                            counsellors which now and henceforth the American People will consult.
                            Neither passion nor fear, neither theory nor precedent, neither
                            imagination nor impulse, shall corrupt in</p>

                        <pb id="VAB8222-022" n="22"/>

                        <p>the American character. that orderly adaptability which has been the very
                            soul of American progress. And before these influences of light every
                            cloud that fear discerns on our horizon will dissolve ; every impassable
                            ocean which imagination sees in our pathway will be safely crossed ;
                            ever foe which foresight beholds in the distance will be vanquished, and
                            the flag which Washington unfurled will float over ever-broadening
                            horizons brightening every hour with increasing glories of actual
                            achievement.</p>

                    </div3>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
