<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//IA Books//DTD TEI for Indiana Authors Books//EN"
                       "teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="VAB8214">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Old age</title>
                <title type="subtitle">Two discourses upon this theme; delivered ... in ...
                    Bloomington, Indiana</title>
                <author>Ballantine, Elisha.</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded By</resp>
                    <!--Update the value of the element below with your name in
                                direct order.-->
                    <name>Jane Torres</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
                </address>
                <idno>VAB8214</idno>
                <availability status="unknown">
                    <p>Copyright 2009 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
                    <p>Indiana University provides the information contained on this web site for
                        non-commercial, personal, or research use only. All other use, including but
                        not limited to commercial or scholarly reproductions, redistribution,
                        publication or transmission, whether by electronic means or otherwise,
                        without prior written permission of the copyright holder is strictly
                        prohibited.</p>
                </availability>
                <!--Update the value of the date element with the year the document
                        is being encoded.-->
                <date>2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title type="main">Old age</title>
                        <title type="subtitle">Two discourses upon this theme; delivered ... in ...
                            Bloomington, Indiana</title>
                        <author id="ina-v1-entry-0043">Ballantine, Elisha.</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>22 p.</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Dodds</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Bloomington</pubPlace>
                        <date>1879</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Digital Library Program was awarded a Library Services and Technology Act
                    (LSTA) grant in 2005 to make available online the three-volume, reference work,
                        <title>Indiana Authors and Their Books</title> along with selected
                    monographs by Indiana authors.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3">
                <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoded and edited using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines following the TEI Lite standard. Digital page images are
                    linked to the text file.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <tagUsage gi="div1">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language>English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Old age.</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <!--The revision description tracks significant changes made to the file
                    after completion. This information will remain commented out unless someone has
                    conducted quality assessment of the texts and have made changes to the file as a
                    result.-->
        <!-- <revisionDesc> <change>
                    <date>$Date</date> <respStmt>
                    <name>$Name</name>
                    <resp>$Responsibility</resp>
                    </respStmt> <item>$Changes</item>
                    </change> </revisionDesc> -->
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>

            <pb id="VAB8214-001" n="[]"/>
            <div1 type="halftitle">

                <head rend="center">OLD AGE.</head>

                <milestone unit="typography" n="---" rend="center"/>

                <p>
                    <hi rend="sc">BY</hi><lb/> R<hi rend="sc">EV</hi>. E. BALLANTINE.</p>


                <milestone unit="typography" n="---" rend="center"/>

                <p>
                    <hi rend="sc">BLOOMINGTON, IND.</hi><lb/> S. C. DODDS &amp; CO.<lb/>
                    1879</p>

            </div1>

            <pb id="VAB8214-002" n="[]"/>
            <pb id="VAB8214-003" n="[1]"/>

            <titlePage>
                <docTitle rend="center">
                    <titlePart type="main">OLD AGE.</titlePart>

                    <titlePart type="subtitle"> TWO DISCOURSES UPON THIS THEME;<lb/> DELIVERED<lb/>
                        THE FIRST IN THE CHAPEL OF THE INDIANA UNIVERSITY,<lb/> THE SECOND IN THE
                        PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH,<lb/> BLOOMINGTON, INDIANA. </titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <byline rend="center"> BY <docAuthor>REV. E. BALLANTINE,</docAuthor><lb/>
                    <hi rend="sc">EX-PROFESSOR OF GREEK IN THE UNIVERSITY, AND AUTHOR OF
                        "CHRIST<lb/> HIS OWN WITNESS."</hi>
                </byline>

                <milestone unit="typography" n="---" rend="center"/>

                <epigraph rend="center">
                    <p>"And even to your old age I am He."</p>
                    <bibl>--Isa. xlvi. 4.</bibl>
                </epigraph>
                <milestone unit="typography" n="---" rend="center"/>
                <docImprint rend="center">
                    <pubPlace>BLOMMINGTON, IND.</pubPlace>
                    <lb/>
                    <publisher>S. C. DODDS &amp; CO.</publisher>
                    <lb/>
                    <docDate>1879</docDate>
                </docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <pb id="VAB8214-004" n="[2]"/>
        </front>



        <body>
            <div1 type="book">
                <pb id="VAB8214-005" n="3"/>
                <head rend="center">OLD AGE.</head>
                <div2 type="chapter">
                    

                    <head rend="center">I.--ADDRESSED TO THE YOUNG.</head>

                    <p>A<hi rend="sc">T</hi> the request of one of my late and honored associates,
                        and with the sanction of them all, I am here this afternoon to take part in
                        these services. I have selected for a theme of remark "OLD AGE."</p>

                    <p>To the possible query why the subject of Old Age should be chosen for a
                        lecture designed especially for young persons, an answer may be given in the
                        form of a good wish that all and each of you, my young friends, may live to
                        be old. If you do, this subject will be both a personal and a very practical
                        one.</p>

                    <p>A man who has reached his sixty-fifth year may thenceforward be classed with
                        the old. From that time he is passing the last stage of life, and is at a
                        point from which the views of human existence have a character of their own.
                        And as the Natural Bridge or the Falls of Niagara appear differently viewed
                        from above or from below, as an Alpine scene has elements of beauty looked
                        at from every position, but as seen from one particular stand-point combines
                        more of these than from the rest, so the stand-point, of old age commands,
                        perhaps, more characteristic features of life than any other.</p>

                    <p>It may not be unprofitable, then, for you all to see how, from of old age, a
                        man may look out upon his Past, his Present, and his Future.</p>

                    <p>And first upon his Past.</p>

                    <p>His Past, to the old man, is the greater part of his life, <pb
                            id="VAB8214-006" n="4"/> perhaps the whole of his active part. That, the
                        active part of life, which to the young man is before, is to the old man all
                        behind, and the two parties meeting together may compare their views. The
                        contrast is striking,--there are such differing elements in the two views.
                        The one view is Fiction, the other Fact; the one is Possibility, the other
                        Reality; the one is Imagination, the other History; the one Aspiration, the
                        other Experience. Let me not be understood as disparaging the landscape
                        beheld from the point of view of the young. By no means. Those who are now
                        old once stood there themselves, and were filled and thrilled, perhaps
                        benefited, by the view.</p>

                    <p>What is a young man or woman worth who has no plans, no aspirations? The
                        youth who does not <hi rend="i">look forward</hi> to life cannot be
                        efficiently preparing for it. If his plans and expectations are possible,
                        they may become real. Indeed, the imagined future of the youth is only a
                        mosaic made up of other people's experience. The materials of fiction are
                        facts, and the silvery mist which is spread over the whole future, softening
                        and brightening it to the youthful heart, is calculated to excite it to high
                        exertion effective of great results. Let the young, then, look forward; let
                        them build their castles; but let them do it as sanely as possible.</p>

                    <p>The old, looking <hi rend="i">back</hi>, need no such caution. The views
                        which present themselves of their past lives will, if they see rightly, be
                        found to contain much to sober them, to chasten their self-esteem; yes,
                        probably, much to mortify them, to humble them to the dust, to make them
                        penitent and contrite, perhaps even to subject them to unavailing remorse.
                        History is in this respect terribly different from anticipation. It is far
                        clearer to the view, and it cannot be changed. Alas for the deep gnawings at
                        heart of the old man, who yet cannot refrain from dwelling in thought upon
                        some dark, infamous passage of his history, which he would, but cannot, blot
                        out. There it stands, written plainly on the page. It stares at him; he
                        shuts his eyes; but, as if written in raised letters, it meets his
                        finger-ends, <pb id="VAB8214-007" n="5"/> it touches his forehead, it
                        presses its words and facts upon his cheek and his heart. Nothing but a
                        sweet sense of Divine forgiveness can change his misery to peace. An old age
                        of remorse is the beginning of future perdition. Lay not up for yourselves,
                        young friends, this provision for old age. Do you ask how this may be
                        avoided? By being conscientious now and always; by honesty, and purity, and
                        doing good; and these by means of the love of God and man.</p>

                    <p>But even without causing remorse, can the just and honest view of his past be
                        to the old man otherwise than forbidding? 'Tis quite possible, my
                        friends.</p>

                    <p>That old person has led a miserable life indeed who cannot discern, as he
                        looks back upon it, first, the evidence and marks of a kind. Providence
                        ruling through it all, the proof of a Heavenly Hand which, unseen at the
                        time, was yet all the time ordering, preventing, providing, silently,
                        mightily, graciously, securing for him great and good results; the hand,
                        namely, of a Wise Father superintending the life and life-experiences of his
                        child struggling here on earth.</p>

                    <p>"And he has led a <hi rend="i">poor life</hi>, to say the least, who, being
                        now old, cannot, on looking back, discern a course of useful industry, of
                        energetic activity, directed to and productive of benefits to himself and
                        others, good results immediate, and perhaps lasting for generations</p>

                    <p>Perhaps also, the old man, looking back, is permitted to recognize the coming
                        of <hi rend="i">new element</hi>s into his life's experience, such as <hi
                            rend="i">repentance</hi> and <hi rend="i">love</hi> to God and the
                        Saviour, and these entering not as mere sentiments, but as principles of
                        action, resulting in a <hi rend="i">reformation of life</hi>; and,
                        accompanying these, a <hi rend="i">joy</hi> unknown before, namely, that of
                        a <hi rend="i">loyalty</hi> and a <hi rend="i">service</hi> directed towards
                        his God and Saviour; in short, the beginning to live for eternity. If these
                        elements have existed, as they may, and do exist, in the case of many, as
                        factors in the past of one's life, the views of that life from the
                        standpoint of age connot be altogether forbidding. Nay, suppose <pb
                            id="VAB8214-008" n="6"/> that with these elements there appear upon
                        review also their natural and proper consequences, lines of effort at
                        self-improvement, and at doing good to others, benevolent and religious
                        efforts for their eternal good, and, what many are permitted to see and
                        know, manifest and blessed results of these efforts in the rescue of some,
                        perhaps of many, from a life of godlessness, wickedness, and vice to one of
                        purity and piety, and to companionship with themselves in all these
                        sentiments efforts. I tell you, young friends, if your lookings-forward to
                        life are pleasant, if the pictures which your imaginations and fond hopes
                        draw have their silver fringes, their golden linings, all of them as yet
                        unreal, these lookings-back of the old and their views of their lives--now
                        unchangeable history--have, with all their abatements arising from sin and
                        short-coming, also <hi rend="i">their</hi>, silver and golden linings, the
                        creation, indeed, all of them, of a Divine Hand, but belonging really to the
                        personal picture, and contributing rightfully and richly to the peace and
                        joy of him who can say with the apostle, "By the grace of God I am what I
                        am." May you all in your old age have much of this blessed experience! So
                        much in regard to the Past.</p>

                    <p>We next look at the old man in his situation at the time,-- in his
                        Present.</p>

                    <p>We see upon him the marks of age. And he is more or less affected by its
                        power both in body and mind. Yet he not necessarily wrecked, or even racked.
                        He has probably less <hi rend="i">elasticity</hi> of thought and limb; but
                        with body, mind, heart, and conscience well preserved, he is still a man.
                        For I am not now speaking of the down-broken and imbecile, though such are
                        not uncommon among the aged. Such are found even among the younger,
                        shattered prematurely,--victims of disease, perhaps of vice. The old man,
                        then, who has taken proper care of himself has a net-work of <hi rend="i"
                            >good habits</hi>, which, like the coat of mail of the old knights,
                        protects him measurably from the onsets of bodily and mental disease and
                        prolongs his vital energy. He has, too, a fund of <hi rend="i"
                            >experience</hi> and <hi rend="i">observation</hi> greater <pb
                            id="VAB8214-009" n="7"/> than that of others by the greater number of
                        his years, and all of it now available capital. There is a <hi rend="i"
                            >maturity</hi> both of principles and powers which makes them available
                        to their utmost extent, and enables him to make much of a little time. With
                        a well-stored <hi rend="i">memory</hi> and well-practised <hi rend="i"
                            >judgment</hi>, he is not so liable to be misled; and with <hi rend="i"
                            >objects of thought</hi> and steady effort, approved by time, he
                        certainly need not be as yet either idle or useless.</p>

                    <p>i Yet the aged have the right to withdraw from places of active duty. It is
                        not well that their physical and mental muscle should be subjected to the
                        constant or occasional strain which such places will bring upon them.
                        Destined soon to leave this busy scene, it is appropriate for them to stop a
                        little beforehand and address themselves to their situation. Nay, to the
                        right-minded, the objects of active business, so far as they are merely
                        worldly, <hi rend="i">lose their interest</hi> in great part as eternal
                        things come nearer; and, unless personal or family necessity compel the
                        contrary, the old find it pleasant to retire, and yield to others the places
                        which they have lfeld and their emoluments.</p>

                    <p>But, then, what shall they do? Join the crowd of idlers and busybodies? By no
                        means. The man who has in former life been really active, usefully
                        industrious, will have no inclinations of that kind. Ennui would oppress and
                        crush him at once. It takes hard apprenticeship and long practice to endure
                        idleness. So the man of industry, when old, will be industrious still. "But
                        at what?" said a young man lately to your speaker. With no more more
                        examinations to pass,--the idea was,--no position to gain, no professional
                        reputation to make, what motive for study or effort further? But are these
                        the only objects and ends of study? Is not knowledge valuable for its own
                        sake? Is not truth precious in itself? And are there not stores of golden
                        thoughts laid up in books still unread, the treasures of the ages, lofty
                        imaginings, holy aspirations of human souls with which it will be good to
                        hold communion; and above all, divine revelations, often already read, but
                        still <pb id="VAB8214-010" n="8"/> unfathomed, and yielding to right search
                        most precious pearls of heavenly truth, and bringing their earnest students
                        into communion with the holiest and the best; with angels and with God? Do
                        you ask, then, What shall the old man do? Shall an <hi rend="i"
                            >immortal</hi>, having an undying mind, even before his short life is
                        spent, <hi rend="i">lack something to do</hi>, because, forsooth, he needs
                        no more to obey the bell-tap, write a sermon, or prepare an argument? He has
                        learned but little, practically, who, with a measure of health and eyesight,
                        and leisure, finds his time hangs heavy on his hands.</p>

                    <p>And the old man may yet serve his generation. Now, when worldly motives have
                        less power, Jet him show the power of his moral and religious convictions to
                        keep fresh and strong his past profession and character. Let him be like the
                        well-built arch, which had at first a temporary support, but having received
                        the keystone, and made to depend upon itself, does not settle the fraction
                        of an inch. Let me say that as there is no sight more pitiful than an aged
                        person greedy, discontented, morose, because worldly property and pleasures
                        are slipping from his grasp, so there is no sight more pleasant, or even, if
                        you please, more sublime, than that of him who parts easily with all these,
                        and is yet quiet, cheerful, and kind, because, forsooth, he has other and
                        unfailing resources, fountains of supply, hidden but high, keeping full and
                        overflowing the streams of serene and quiet joy. The well-built ship, now
                        finished but still on the stocks, suffers no disaster and scarcely a shock
                        as the props beneath are falling one by one. Well-braced and strong within
                        itself, it is ready for the moment when, the last stay removed, it shall by
                        easy glide enter the element for which it is prepared. So the aged, ready
                        for death, may await its coming with serene assurance.</p>

                    <p>We consider, thirdly, the old man's Future.</p>

                    <p>He has a Future,--and not the young only. And these two Futures may be
                        compared without disadvantage to that of the aged; especially if the Future
                        of the young is limited, so far <pb id="VAB8214-011" n="9"/> as they look at
                        it, to the present life. If the Present of the old man, who when young chose
                        as his only treasure and joy the things that are now crumbling to dust in
                        his hands, is pitiful and bitter, then the Future of this same man must, as
                        he looks at it, be dark and terrible indeed, with no mitigating element
                        whatever. Such a Future, however, is not necessary for any one: we turn from
                        it with a sigh and look to its brighter alternative.</p>

                    <p>You have all read, in early American history, of the party who, after long
                        marches and many labors, reached at length the summit of the Andes, and
                        beheld, first of Europeans, the boundless western prospect which that
                        position commanded. Nearest to them in the view, and almost beneath their
                        feet, was a narrow strip of territory consisting of ridges, gorges, and
                        torrents, crowded together, all descending rapidly to the near coastline,
                        and then the waters of the Pacific stretching off widely into the invisible.
                        It was a time for cheers, and shouts, and triumph. A crucifix erected on the
                        spot was the appropriate memorial of the hour. Let that rough strip of
                        territory represent, if you please, the piece of life yet remaining to the
                        aged one. Let its surface be jagged, its descent rapid, its torrents boiling
                        and plunging, its only pathways on toppling crests; it is also narrow; it
                        will soon be past; and in the mean time it furnishes from every point a
                        commanding view of the blue, quiet waters beyone. And these are so broad, so
                        level, so peaceful, so near, they make the traveller forget the few rough
                        steps which are still before him. And has he in hand the trusty Alpine staff
                        of Faith in Jesus Christ, by which alone he could have reached and passed in
                        safety that summit now behind him? If so, he can travel the remainder of the
                        descent without danger and fear. "In their hands they shall bear thee up,
                        that thou dash not thy foot against a stone." "And even to your old age I am
                        He, and even to hoar-hairs will I carry you. I have made and I will bear,
                        even I will carry, and I will deliver you." These are words of God.</p>


                    <pb id="VAB8214-012" n="10"/>

                    <p>Are we immortal beings? and has the aged man done his life-work humbly and
                        conscientiously, looking unto Jesus, the Author and Finisher of his faith?
                        Is the Pacific Ocean of Eternity just before him? What is there, then, in
                        death, though it be near, to terrify or even discompose him? He will indeed
                        soon disappear from these material scenes. But watch him as he is making his
                        last descent, as he reaches the shore, as the rippling waters already play
                        with his feet. Or, to drop the figure, look and listen as, on his death-bed,
                        he is gradually sinking. Hear his few broken words, catch the glance of his
                        eye, the expressions of feeling glittering there and playing over his face.
                        You will see that, whatever else may be failing, his personality, his
                        conscious identity, his traits of mental and moral character, his
                        affections, his religious fear and love and trust, <hi rend="i">are all
                            there</hi>, and there, too, in all their undiminished strength, perhaps
                        in more than their youthful vigor. All namely, that constitute the man, all
                        save his crumbling tenement of clay, continues, substantial, compact, and
                        instinct with a life which defies death's greatest power. Shall that man the
                        next moment cease to be? Shall that soul, with all its matured powers and
                        grace, <hi rend="i">go out</hi> as the spent lamp-wick? Be sure that, if you
                        could rend the veil, and be endowed with spiritual light, you would see him
                        still, and more alive than ever. We refrain from following his new, strange,
                        and blessed experiences in that deathless, painless, sinless, perfect
                        world.</p>

                    <p>In conclusion, I will say:</p>

                    <p>First. That Old Age, though it is now far off from you who are young, is
                        continually coming nearer to you. Its onward march is silent, but
                        uninterrupted; it is slow, but never delays. A few days ago you reassembled
                        in this place just as you have done perhaps ten times before. The only, and
                        yet a real difference is, that you are one term farther on in your course.
                        The spring season is now opening just as did the last; 'tis a year farther
                        on in your lives. This morning dawned as did yesterday; but you are a day
                        nearer to death than you were then. <pb id="VAB8214-013" n="11"/> Old Age
                        comes on with every tick of that clock. It moves visibly with that pendulum.
                        You may see it walking with the second hand of your watch. By and by it will
                        reach you--and lay its hand on you--unless, God so ordering, Death shall
                        anticipate it and, with ruder shock, snatch you from its grasp. Look, then,
                        at this certainty, young as you are.</p>

                    <p>Prepare for old age. Provide good habits, a good conscience, love for your
                        kind. Secure the pardon of your sins, and a gospel hope of heaven. Prepare
                        for old age by preparing for the eternity beyond it. Remember that "the
                        sinner being a hundred years old shall be accursed;" while "the path of the
                        just is as the shining light, which shineth more and more unto the perfect
                        day." Take as your counsellor throughout your life the Bible.</p>

                    <p>I have thus tried to show you how, if you are permitted by the Giver and
                        Preserver of life, you may spend a useful, quiet, and happy old age.</p>

                    <p>And with such an old age, by God's grace within your reach, I repeat the wish
                        with which this discourse was begun,--May you all live to be old!</p>

                </div2>

                <pb id="VAB8214-014" n="12"/>
                <div2 type="chapter">
                    <head rend="center">II.-ADDRESSED TO THE OLD.</head>

                    <p>I<hi rend="sc">N</hi> the previous discourse the subject of Old Age was
                        presented in general. We will now pursue a special part of the subject, and
                        illustrate the matter of <hi rend="i">Piety in Old Age</hi>, and endeavor to
                        obtain light upon it from particular cases in the Bible. We take for this
                        purpose those of Zechariah and Elizabeth, Simeon and Anna.</p>

                    <p>Luke is the sacred writer who tells us all that we know of these persons. He
                        speaks of them all in connection with his account of the birth of Jesus
                        Christ. This gives a unity to their several histories and furnishes us a
                        stand-point from which to study them.<ref id="ref_001" rend="super"
                            target="note_001">*</ref></p>

                    <p>As to their time of life, Luke says that Zechariah and Elizabeth "were now
                        well stricken in age," and of Anna, that "she was a widow of about
                        fourscore-and-four years." The advanced age of Simeon is implied in his
                        story. They were all among the oldest people of their day, and therefore
                        deserve the special attention of the aged now. They are "ensamples to us,"
                        and their history is "written for our learning."</p>

                    <p>In endeavoring to learn what we may about the Piety of these aged people, we
                        will study, in order, their Religious Faith or Creed, their Religious
                        Spirit, their Religious Life, and their Religious Blessings and Joys.</p>

                    <p>And, first, their Religious Faith or Creed. It was, in short, that of Jewish
                        Orthodoxy. I will mention its two fundamental points, as comprehending all
                        the rest.</p>

                    <p>The first of these was, <hi rend="i">The Authority of the Herew
                            Scriptures</hi>
                        <note id="note_001"><ref target="ref_001" rend="super">*</ref> Luke i. 5-20,
                            67-79; ii. 25-32, 36-38.</note>
                        <pb id="VAB8214-015" n="13"/> (our present Old Testament), <hi rend="i">as
                            the Word of God, in all matters of religious faith and practice</hi>.
                        Upon this point these people, in common with all their race of that
                        generation, had not the sadow of a doubt. We hear Zechariah saying, "As he
                        (that is God) spake by the mouth of all the holy prophets since the world
                        began. To perform the mercy promised to our fathers, and to remember his
                        holy covenant; the oath which he sware to our father Abraham." These and
                        other words of Zechariah show an implicit faith in the Scriptures as being
                        God's word. Such a faith involves the reception of all the doctrines which
                        the Old Testament plainly teaches, and of all its commands binding on the
                        conscience and the life. All that is related of these four persons shows the
                        same fixed conviction, the same infaltering faith in their holy book. The
                        source of their religious beliefs was not tradition, or superstition, or
                        philosophy, but Divine Revelation. The religious creed of the Jews contained
                        all the great truths with which we, too, are familiar, except those
                        distinctively Christian, and even these also in the germ. For,</p>

                    <p>The second great point of Jewish Orthodoxy to be noticed is the doctrine of
                            <hi rend="i">the Messiah to come</hi>. This may be said to have been the
                        central article of the Jewish faith. From the first promise made to
                        Abraham,--"In thy seed shall all the families of the earch be blessed,"
                        which seed, Paul says, was Christ,-- Jewish faith and piety looked forward
                        to "Him who was to come." The words of Zechariah, already quoted, show this
                        in his case. Elizabeth, his wife, Simeon, and Anna express the same faith
                        and expectation. Others also whom Anna knew "looked for Redemption in
                        Israel." Joseph of Arimathea "waited for the kingdom of God." Of the whole
                        nation Paul say, "To which promise (<hi rend="i">i.e.,</hi> of the Messiah)
                        our twelve tribes, instantly serving God day and night, hope to come." Even
                        the Samaritans, half heathen and half Jewish in their faith and practice,
                        "knew that Messias cometh, and when he is come he will tell us all
                        things."</p>

                    <pb id="VAB8214-016" n="14"/>

                    <p>We rightly, then, sum up the Religious Faith of these four Jewish people in
                        the two points, Belief in the Jewish Scriptures, as God's word, and Belief
                        in a Redeemer to come. It was faith in a Divine Revelation and in a Divine
                        Redeemer,-- the best possible elements of all Religious Belief, and without
                        which it must be utterly inadequate.</p>

                    <p>We see that the religious faith of these persons was very strong. They had
                        imbibed it in childhood; it had grown with them to maturity; they had
                        carried it through the years of their earlier and riper manhood and
                        womanhood; and they had brought it with them, unshattered, unweakened, to
                        their old age. Their faith wore well. It did not grow old with their bodies,
                        but was now young and fresh as ever; and it was a light to their feet, a
                        staff to their hands, a foundation of rock for them to build their house
                        upon, which no floods or winds could shake. The sceptic's horizon is all
                        uncertainty; especially when he is old all is darkness above, around, and
                        before him. But to the aged believer in the Bible and in Jesus Christ there
                        is a light shining "above the brightness of the sun," and "it shineth more
                        and more unto the perfect day."</p>

                    <p>We look, secondly, at the Religious Spirit of these Bible examples of Piety
                        in Old Age.</p>

                    <p>We learn from their story that they had not only the letter but the Spirit of
                        true Faith in God. They not only "received the truth," but "received it in
                        the love thereof." It is very possible to rest in the letter while lacking
                        the spirit altogether. Many Jews were thus deficient in the time of Christ:
                        they "said and did not." Paul speaks of those who "rested in the law," and
                        "made their boast of God," and "knew his will," and yet lived in
                        disobedience. In our day, also, many people, orthodox in faith, have little
                        or none of the spirit of piety. Many aged people, alas, are of this
                        description. There is nothing, my friends, more dead than a dead orthodoxy,
                        or more damaging and dangerous to the soul. Mere orthodoxy is a scaffolding
                        without any edifice being built up by its means; it <pb id="VAB8214-017"
                            n="15"/> is a temple without its altar and its worship; it is a body
                        from which the living spirit is gone, a skeleton which is a sarcasm upon the
                        form, and beauty, and life of real piety. It deceives and pleases neither
                        God nor man,--none except its blinded holder. The faith of the four aged
                        saints whom we are now studying was a living faith and one working by love.
                        Hear their words, look at their acts, and learn the spirit and feeling which
                        breathes in all. Heartiness, earnestness, humility, gratitude to God, praise
                        to God in the highest style of the ancient psalms, and mutual gratulations
                        break out from their full hearts. They can be fired and be all aglow with
                        religious emotion. Evidently they had not before this been strangers to
                        strong and lively religious feelings; these appear too naturally in them to
                        be entirely new. They were familiar with holy joys, and, doubtless, also
                        with deep and sacred sorrows. I infer this from the times and events through
                        which they had lived. These very persons had seen the close of the Maccabean
                        dynasty, with which, sixty years before, the civil independence of the
                        Jewish people ceased forever. Pompey and his legions crushed all opposition
                        beneath their feet; and when that proud Roman, violating the religious
                        feelings of every Jew, walked into the temple, and, drawing aside the sacred
                        veil, pressed sacrilegiously into the Holy of holies, a shriek was heard, I
                        reckon, and a wail, the like of which has not often been heard on earth.
                        Especially the pious ones were afflicted. They could not see --what was,
                        however, true--that these very events were preparing the way for the true
                        Redemption of Israel. Then came the long reign of Herod, who with the
                        profession of a Jew had the heart of a brute and the hand of a savage,
                        desolating by murder even his own house and bed. Deeply tried these good
                        people and others like them must have been! Did God, they asked, "remember
                        his own elect?" Was he not "slack concerning his promise?" And now will
                        they, thus tried, endure, so that "when the Son of man cometh he shall find
                        faith on the earth?" </p>

                    <pb id="VAB8214-018" n="16"/>

                    <p>My friends, the history before us gives the answer. It shows to us these
                        believers in God's promises, now grown gray with waiting, still looking for
                        the promised One. Their whole hearts were bound up in their faith. Oh! a
                        blessed thing that is in human hearts, strong faith in God's work. It
                        enables him who has it to endure the wear and tear of earth's struggles and
                        disappointments. It holds the soul steady, as the strong cable fastened to
                        the well-planted anchor does the ship, enabling it to ride out safely the
                        night of darkness and storm. To such a living faith and piety, and only to
                        such, the morning will surely come at last, if not in this world, then all
                        the more gloriously in the next. Let us learn from these examples that the
                        soul must be <hi rend="i">alive</hi> in its religion, must burn and glow
                        with the spirit and affections proper for the child of God. The body may
                        decay, the intellect may be enfeebled, but the truly pious may, and often
                        do, exhibit, even in extreme old age, an undiminished strength of religious
                        affections; more like to heaven as more near.</p>
                    <p>We will look, thirdly, at the Religious Life of these aged people. And I mean
                        their outer life, as we have already considered their inward spiritual
                        life.</p>
                    <p>The outer is the outflow of the inner. "The good tree brings forth good
                        fruit." We shall find in the present case that old Scripture fulfilled,
                        "They (the pious) shall still bring forth fruit in old age."</p>
                    <p>And let the old note carefully the record; for this is God's way of
                        instructing us in our duty and our privilege.</p>
                    <p>The aged pair, Zechariah and Elizabeth, till now childless, had, by mutual
                        affection and confidence, been everything to each other. Luke tells us that
                        "they were both righteous before God, walking in all the commandments and
                        ordinances of the Lord blameless." They sympathized entirely in their
                        religious feelings and, practice, and they were now spending their old age
                        in united faith and fidelity towards God. Friends, there is a purity, and
                        excellence, and serenity in the life of a <pb id="VAB8214-019" n="17"/>
                        loving, pious, aged couple bordering on the life of the blessed in heaven.
                        Zechariah was a priest. Twice in the year, and for a week each time, his
                        office called him from his country home to the scared duties of the temple.
                        We see him in the story thus engaged. His lot at this time is to burn the
                        incense. Look at him, the aged Aaronic priest, as, just like the long line
                        of his predecessors, with the censer in his hand, he enters the house of the
                        temple, the holy place, "wherein was the golden candlestick" with its seven
                        burning lamps, and "the table" with "the shew-bread," and the golden altar
                        standing immediately before the veil. Upon that altar he places the censer
                        with its smoking incense, the symbol of the prayers of all saints. Doubtless
                        he then prayed himself, standing alone before God; for it was "the hour of
                        prayer," and the people also standing without in the court "were praying at
                        the time of incense." Among them at that very time, probably, were Simeon
                        and Anna; for Luke says that the former was "just and devout," --that is,
                        much in devotion,--and Anna "departed not from the temple, but served God
                        with fastings and prayers night and day." Elizabeth, in her little home in
                        the country village, like Daniel long before at Babylon, joined at the same
                        hour with the devotions of the temple.</p>
                    <p>It is manifest that these aged people made much of the worship of God, both
                        public and private, were faithful in these services as well as in the other
                        duties of religion, spending much time in worship.</p>
                    <p>The words of Luke saying that Zechariah and Elizabeth "were both righteous
                        before God, walking in all the commandments and ordinances of the Lord
                        blameless," not only certify all we have said, but also show that they were
                        conscientious and faithful in their duties to men. They made no selection of
                        duties, but conscientiously performed them all. Such was their Religious
                        Life. What is said of Simeon and Anna, their love and trust, and devotion,
                        and also their being favored with direct communications from God, warrants
                        us to believe <pb id="VAB8214-020" n="18"/> the same also of them. Their
                        Faith and their inner and outer Life were in high harmony.</p>
                    <p>The fourth point to be noticed in the Piety of these old people was its Joy
                        and Blessedness.</p>
                    <p>The history of all the happy religious experiences in their lives is not
                        given us: only that of one inpouring into their cup of joy which made it run
                        over. It was their experience in connection with the birth of Jesus, the
                        coming of the Christ into the world.</p>
                    <p>I have already had occasion to say that the expectation of the Messiah was a
                        prime element in Jewish faith and piety. It was important and precious to
                        each individual in proportion to his spiritual attainments. Jesus says,
                        "Abraham rejoiced to see my day, and he saw it and was glad." And again he
                        said, "Many prophets and righteous men have desired to see the things that
                        ye see and have not seen them, and to hear the things that ye hear and have
                        not heard them." Peter speaks of the old prophets as "Searching what, or
                        what manner of time the Spirit of Christ which was in them did signify, when
                        it testified beforehand the sufferings of Christ, and the glory that should
                        follow. Unto whom," he says, "it was revealed, that not unto themselves, but
                        unto us they did minister the things, which are now reported unto you." Paul
                        also says of the Old Testament saints, that they "died not having received
                        the promise, but were persuaded of them and embraced them. God having
                        provided some better thing for us, that they without us should not be made
                        perfect." Every pious Jew inherited and cherished this hope long deferred,
                        this longing expectation of the Christ. In the hearts of the four aged
                        saints of whom we now speak that desire had long burned, only increasing in
                        intensity with their years. And now at length the fulness of time had come
                        when this expectation was to be realized, when this desire was to be
                        gratified. The great announcement was first made to Zechariah. It was, as we
                        have seen, when he was in the temple alone burning incense in the holy
                        place. The angel Gabriel <pb id="VAB8214-021" n="19"/> --the same one who,
                        more than five hundred years before, had given to Daniel the most distinct
                        revelation of the time of the Messiah's coming--now appeared to Zechariah
                        standing on the right side of the altar where the smoking incense was, and
                        told him that a son should be born to him of his wife Elizabeth who should
                        be the forerunner of the Christ now soon to come.</p>
                    <p>At the expiration of his week of service Zechariah, going home, made known
                        the heavenly news to his wife. About the same time, probably, the aged
                        Simeon, now expecting daily to die, is told be revelation that "he should
                        not see death before he had seen the Lord's Christ." Judge of the thrill of
                        joy which these announcements would cause in the hearts of these aged
                        saints. Within two years the great promises were fulfilled. Elizabeth's
                        words to Mary, who made a visit to her, show the deep joy of her soul. And
                        when her son was born, Zechariah first used his now recovered power of
                        speech in sublime strains of joyful gratitude. When Mary presented her child
                        in the temple, Simeon, informed by the Spirit, recognized in the babe the
                        coming One, and thus found God's promise to him fulfilled. He saw with his
                        eyes the Lord's Christ. There is no such interesting passage in human
                        history outside of the history of Jesus himself. The old Simeon stood there,
                        representing all the believing pious Jews of all the generations before him,
                        all who had looked and longed for the Messiah. The faith and hopes and
                        longings of them all were, concentrated in his own soul. And he now saw the
                        One desired of all. Not doubting in his heart, but exulting in his assured
                        faith, acting for the covenant people, and especially for the pious of all
                        the ages, he took the child in his arms, expressing his faith, his love, and
                        his gratitude. In him the chose people accepted its Messiah. Did ever the
                        rapture of joy rise higher on the earth? And did joy ever have a greater
                        cause, a better occasion? Simeon's highest earthly wish is now fulfilled.
                        There is nothing more to make him wish to live. He is ready to exchange
                        earth for heaven. He "blessed God and said, Lord, now lettest thou thy
                        servant <pb id="VAB8214-022" n="20"/> depart in peace, for mine eyes have
                        seen thy salvation." Such joy the sight of Jesus can give to the believing,
                        pious soul. Just then Anna, the prophetess, also came into the temple, and
                        learning the facts, and sympathizing in the joy and exultation of her
                        friend, she too "gave thanks unto the Lord," and in the fulness of her soul
                        "spake of" the child to all those of sympathizing spirit.</p>
                    <p>These happy experiences of these four aged saints show us, dear friends, that
                        old age may be made very happy, may be as familiar with high and lasting joy
                        as younger years can be. The case of Simeon shows that the joy of the aged
                        saint may even be so near akin to that of heaven as to cause the soul to
                        look with desire and confidence to the heavenly bliss as its sure and only
                        appropriate sequence. The highest and holiest earthly joy passes easily and
                        naturally into the heavenly.</p>
                    <p>We must not fail to note the important fact that the centre and source of
                        this religious joy of these aged persons was Jesus the Christ. It
                        illustrates the great truth that he, Christ, is the true and only source of
                        the highest and enduring happiness of men. He says himself, "He that
                        drinketh of the water that I shall give him shall never thirst," and to his
                        disciples, "Ask, and ye shall receive, that your joy may be full." Nothing
                        else can be substituted for this source of true joy. Men "forsake this
                        fountain of living waters and hew out to themselves cisterns," but they "can
                        hold no water." The time is near to the aged, or has already come, when they
                        must say of earthly enjoyments, "I have no pleasure in them." Then those who
                        are earthly-minded will have no joys left them. They become discontented,
                        unhappy, morose, a burden to themselves and their friends, and a dishonor to
                        religion. But those who believe trust in, and love Jesus the Christ, when
                        old may have their cup of joy running over, and, as Jesus says, "springing
                        up into everlasting life."</p>
                    <p>This joy in Christ and his salvation, let the aged remember, will be in exact
                        proportion to the strength of their faith and <pb id="VAB8214-023" n="21"/>
                        the warmth of their love to him. The cases which we have been studying show
                        this. Without their faith and love they would not have been made happy by
                        the coming Jesus. Herod was not made happy thereby, nor the wicked and
                        worldly-minded Jews, nor the formal, self-righteous Pharisees. Would we,
                        then, be happy in old age, we must live as those saints had
                        done,--believing, loving, obeying, and longing for him who is our Redeemer
                        as well as theirs.</p>
                    <p>Do you say, Jesus can be born but once, and therefore n others can have the
                        same joy as Simeon had and Anna and the rest? Remember the words of the
                        angel to the shepherds of Bethlehem: "Behold, I bring you good tidings of
                        great joy, which shall be to all people. For unto you is born this day a
                        Saviour, which is Christ the Lord." And Simeon said that Jesus was given for
                        "a light to lighten the Gentiles, and the glory of his people Israel." We
                        too, then, may share in the same joy which at that supreme moment filled the
                        hearts of Simeon and the rest.</p>

                    <p>Let us notice as a fact of special interest in the surroundings of the Word
                        made Flesh this circle, this quartette of aged people, thus brought into
                        near relation to Jesus at his birth. It does not seem to us to be an
                        essential part in the programme of events. It might, to human judgment, have
                        been wanting without essential loss; but not so did the matter appear to
                        Divine Grace and Thoughtful Love. God's thoughts of love "are higher" than
                        ours, "as the heavens are higher than the earth." He cares for aged saints,
                        and he has illustrated that care divinely in this arrangement, providing for
                        the old, too, a place and a part in the scenes before, at, and after the
                        birth of Jesus. "And even to your old age I am he." Those venerable four
                        represent almost, to our eyes, the privilege of the aged in blessings
                        procured for men by the Incarnation of Christ.</p>

                    <p>Nor is it unworthy, finally, to notice that of these four representative
                        persons thus brought so near to the person of Jesus two were men and <hi
                            rend="i">two were women</hi>. Is there no significance <pb
                            id="VAB8214-024" n="22"/> here? Let us take it as a prophecy of the
                        elevation of woman by the Gospel. The fact was an earnest of Paul's inspired
                        announcement that "In Christ Jesus there is neither male nor female; for ye
                        are all one." From the birth of Jesus, throughout his life, at his death and
                        resurrection, women acted a prominent part, and obtained gracious
                        recognition and signal favor. Be comforted, then, ye aged Elizabeths and
                        Annas. You may be weak in body, poor in estate, friendless, sick, even
                        bedridden, sinking down to death: Still love and trust, and "rejoice in
                        Christ Jesus;" for you are dear to him. Thus await the time of your
                        departure hence, expecting to go and be with him forever.</p>
                </div2>

            </div1>
        </body>

    </text>
</TEI.2>
