<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//IA Books//DTD TEI for Indiana Authors Books//EN"
                       "teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="VAB9263">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Aes signatum</title>
        <author>Comparette, T. Louis (Thomas Louis), 1868-</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded By</resp>
          <!--Update the value of the element below with your name in
                                direct order.-->
          <name>Pam Cook</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
        <address>
                    <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
                </address>
        <idno>VAB9263</idno>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>Copyright 2009 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
          <p>Indiana University provides the information contained on this web site for
            non-commercial, personal, or research use only. All other use, including but not limited
            to commercial or scholarly reproductions, redistribution, publication or transmission,
            whether by electronic means or otherwise, without prior written permission of the
            copyright holder is strictly prohibited.</p>
        </availability>
        <!--Update the value of the date element with the year the document
                        is being encoded.-->
        <date>2012</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Aes signatum</title>
            <author id="ina-v1-entry-0192">Comparette, T. Louis (Thomas Louis), 1868-</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>61 p. 8 pl.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>American Numismatic Society</publisher>
            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
            <date>1919</date>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Digital Library Program was awarded a Library Services and Technology Act (LSTA)
          grant in 2005 to make available online the three-volume, reference work, <title>Indiana
            Authors and Their Books</title> along with selected monographs by Indiana authors.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="3">
        <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and has
          been encoded and edited using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
          Guidelines following the TEI Lite standard. Digital page images are linked to the text
          file.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <tagUsage gi="div1">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
      </tagsDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language>English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list>
            <item>Coinage</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <!--The revision description tracks significant changes made to the file
                    after completion. This information will remain commented out unless someone has
                    conducted quality assessment of the texts and have made changes to the file as a
                    result.-->
    <!-- <revisionDesc> <change>
                    <date>$Date</date> <respStmt>
                    <name>$Name</name>
                    <resp>$Responsibility</resp>
                    </respStmt> <item>$Changes</item>
                    </change> </revisionDesc> -->
  </teiHeader>
  <text>

    <front>

      <pb id="VAB9263-001" n="[1]"/>


      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">AES SIGNATUM</titlePart>
        </docTitle>

        <byline>B<hi rend="sc">Y</hi><docAuthor> T. LOUIS COMPARETTE</docAuthor></byline>
      </titlePage>

    </front>


    <body>
      <div1 type="book">
        <div2 type="section">
          <head>
            <hi rend="center">I.</hi>
          </head>

          <p>As in almost every other field of human knowledge so in Numismatics there are several
            unsolved problems which have been discussed so often that one feels inclined to make
            some sort of apology to readers of a journal when he essays further discussion of them
            and ventures yet other solutions. But as a defense of one's temerity in asking their
            attention to further consideration of one of these apparently unsolvable problems, one
            may always urge the very common experience that when by general agreement a problem has
            been practically given up as defying solution "in our present state of knowledge"
            somebody promptly puts forth the correct solution, or when something is declared
            impossible to do somebody does it. No hope is entertained for such happy results from
            this paper, which aims at being nothing more than suggestive.</p>
          <p>Among the difficult subjects with which the student of Roman coinage has long struggled
            is the perplexing question of the origin and use of that considerable number of large
            bronze bars that have been found in various parts of Italy and generally known as <hi
              rend="i">aes signatum</hi>, a question which seems to be almost as far from a
            satisfactory answer as it was before a large number of distinguished scholars had made
            it the subject of thorough investigations. And, indeed, no explanation of these bars may
            ever be given that will appear to be so sensible as to merit generally even temporary
            approval, yet it will always be difficult for the student of Roman coinage to pass over
            them without turning serious attention to the problems they give rise to, so
            irresistible is the challenge their great size and the elusive enigma of their
            apparently significant types make to prove or disprove their purely monetary purpose on
            the one hand and the meaning of several of those types, on the other. In the preceding
            decade the question of the <hi rend="i">aes signatum</hi> came prominently to the front
            again after for a number of years scholars had apparently concluded that the principal
            questions of their origin and use had been satisfactorily answered. Few numismatists, if
            any, doubted <pb id="VAB9263-002" n="2"/> the identity of the heavy bars as specimens of
            the first Roman coinage. For Pliny tells us, on the authority of Timaeus, that after the
            Romans had used for an indefinite period amorphous lumps of bronze for money King
            Servius Tullius issued a currency of bronze marked with a type--<hi rend="i">Servius
              primus signavit aes</hi>. Now here was a number of large bronze pieces marked, some of
            them, with very interesting types, and with considerable alacrity numismatists and
            historians came to the conclusion that these bars were specimens of that early coinage.
            Furthermore, amorphous lumps of bronze were found in the territory of ancient Rome and
            Etruria--the <hi rend="i">aes rude</hi> of Pliny or rather of Timaeus! Early tradition
            was seemingly corroborated by extant monuments and in turn the two classes of objects,
            otherwise so puzzling, were as completely identified by statements of ancient writers.
            The reciprocal nature of the evidence made for conviction and if it did not silence
            interrogation it did restrict the field of investigation. Then, too, the great authority
            of several modern savants, among them Prof. Mommsen, was added to increase the already
            general belief that these bars were issued for monetary use, were in fact specimens of
            Rome's earliest coined money, which remained in use for some time after the introduction
            of coins proper by the Decemvirs.</p>
          <p>In later discussions, however, there have accumulated numerous objections, and some of
            them apparently unanswerable, to these earlier explanations of the bars, and the
            objections have gone so far as not only to deny their identity with the <hi rend="i">aes
              signatum</hi> but also to reject the theory that they were of state origin or intended
            for use as money. But these objections have not been followed by more satisfactory
            explanations of the bars, though new theories have not been wanting. Because of the
            doubts thus raised, and probably also because of a certain reluctance on the part of
            many to give up as unrelated to the Roman series pieces long regarded as forming one of
            the most important links in its history, the remarkable theories of Dr. Haeberlin in his
            monograph on <hi rend="i">Die Systematik des ältesten römischen Münzwesens</hi> have
            attracted the greatest attention and in the main have apparently been accepted by many
            numismatists. </p>
          <p>The various theories that have been hitherto advanced to explain these bars may be
            comprehended under two general heads:</p>
          <list type="ordered" rend="upper-latin">
            <item>State issues for monetary purposes. <list type="ordered" rend="decimal">
                <item>Legal coins.</item>
                <item>Bars of legal coin-metal; for <pb id="VAB9263-003" n="3"/>
                  <list type="ordered" rend="lower-latin">
                    <item>various ceremonial and sacred uses;</item>
                    <item>substitutes for legal coins; and</item>
                    <item>use in large transactions.</item>
                  </list></item>
              </list></item>

            <item>Private issues. <list type="ordered" rend="decimal">
                <item>Private coins.</item>
                <item>Bars of bronze for export.</item>
              </list></item>
          </list>

          <p>The explanation of the bars which I shall venture to suggest has grown out of a
            distrust of the authenticity of the literary tradition as well as out of the conviction
            that such pieces were, if not impracticable, yet unnecessary for use as money in Roman
            territory at the time of their issue, while their types, I believe, warrant their
            attribution elsewhere than to a mint. It is with the utmost diffidence that an attempt
            is made to give the grounds for these views.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head>
            <hi rend="center">II.</hi>
          </head>
          <p>The literary tradition in regard to the first issue of money by the Romans has
            unmistakably been a controlling influence over those who have associated these bars with
            the monetary system of Rome, whether they have held them to be examples of the early <hi
              rend="i">aes signatum</hi> or an echo of that enigmatical coinage issued in later
            times. For if we take into consideration how recalcitrant the bars have proved at every
            attempt to account for types and fix the monetary function of those varieties that
            plainly belong to a late period when Rome was issuing coins properly so called, we are
            almost compelled to conclude that without being prejudiced by the literary tradition no
            numismatist would have thought of regarding them as money, much less as coins.</p>
          <p>The authenticity of the literary tradition, therefore, becomes of great moment when one
            would propose a theory of the origin and purpose of the bars. And this question of
            authenticity is a delicate one. For experience has shown that in almost every tradition,
            however absurd it has been made by distortions and foolish additions, there is generally
            a kernel of historic truth. If, therefore, the statements of Varro, Pliny, and Plutarch
            could be shown to be based upon a proper tradition one would hestitate to reject the
            theory that these large quadrilateral bars are examples of the earliest Roman coinage
            they mention, or had some historical relation to that coinage, though the tradition does
            not state that the <hi rend="i">aes signature</hi> was of quadrilateral form and though
            the types of the extant bars do not conform to the meager descriptions given by those
            writers.</p>


          <pb id="VAB9263-004" n="4"/>

          <p>The few statements that have come down to us regarding the beginnings of Roman coinage
            afford but little material for determining whether we have to deal with an actual
            tradition, as the term is generally understood, or, as in the accounts of other Roman
            institutions, with the invention, at a comparatively late period, of some fertile
            imagination. But if, as seems to be the case, Timaeus of Tauromenium, is the earliest
            writer to give an account of that alleged coinage, then there is room for grave doubts,
            owing to his unfavorable reputation as a historian. And while it cannot be established
            beyond dispute that Timaeus was the sole authority upon whom the Roman writers depended
            for their account, yet what evidence we have for the source of the supposed tradition
            points to the Tauromenitan.</p>
          <p>Now Pliny mentions Timaeus as the authority for the story in a well-known passage which
            is one of the chief literary evidences for the Servian coinage: N.H. XXXIII, 3--<hi
              rend="i">Servius rex primus signavit aes; antea rudi usos Romae Timaeus tradit.
              Signatum est nota pecudum unde et pecunia appellata</hi>. While Pliny refers to
            Timaeus as his authority for the account, yet it does not necessarily follow that he
            drew it directly from the writings of Timaeus; it is rather more probable that he found
            the passage in Varro's <hi rend="i">Antiquitates</hi> from which he is known to have
            copied so freely; and that impression is further confirmed when one compares Pliny's
            brief statements about the types of the Servian coinage with allusions to them in extant
            works of Varro and notes the similarity of expression. For example the expressions in
            Varro's <hi rend="i">De Re Rustica, II. 1, 9: . . . quod aes antiquissimum, quod est
              flatum, pecore est notatum;</hi> and <hi rend="i">De Vit. P.R.I.</hi> (Nonius, p. 189)
              <hi rend="i">aut bovem aut ovem aut vervecem habet signum</hi>, probably disclose
            where Pliny got his statement: <hi rend="i">Servius rex ovium boumque effigie primus aes
              signavit (1: Pliny, N.H. XVIII, 12</hi>) as well as the quotation given above. And for
            the same reasons the statements of Plutarch, such as <hi rend="i">Poblicola 11</hi>--
              --<hi rend="i">τϖν νoμιςμάτϖν τoιϛ παλαιoτάτoιϛ βoυv έπϵΧάραττoν ή πρόβατov ή
            δύν</hi>--are likely to have been extracts from Varro's works, from which he also drew
            heavily, though perhaps indirectly, for his material on the early history and life of
            the Romans. Of course, if Pliny did copy his account from Varro there can be little
            doubt that he found the statement there also that Timaeus was the authority for it, and
            that is the commonly accepted view. On the other hand, that Timaeus was the sole
            authority for the story cannot be established, but that he was the chief authority seems
            quite beyond doubt; for in spite of his peculiar methods, or lack of <pb
              id="VAB9263-005" n="5"/> method, in compilation it is unlikely that Pliny would have
            failed to mention a better, particularly some Roman, source for the story had such been
            known to him.</p>
          <p>The name of Timaeus in connection with the tradition casts suspicion upon its
            authenticity and brings up the question whether we have not to deal with a pure
            invention. It seems to be the view of Prof. Pais that Timaeus was romancing on the
            subject of the Servian coinage and that Varro either accepted the fiction or followed
            the example thus set him.<ref id="ref_001" rend="super" target="note_001">¹</ref> And it
            is, moreover, just the sort of historical invention we should expect from Timaeus,
            judging from ancient, and also modern criticism of his works. For instance, it would
            agree with the estimate Polybius gives us of Timaeus in his Twelfth Book, wherein,
            though perhaps inspired to some degree by personal motives, he yet successfully
            impeaches him of lack of conscientious scruple for historical truth, and also of a
            readiness to publish as facts his personal views falsely authenticated by fabricated
            conversations and imaginary monuments. Prominent among the vices Polybius convicts
            Timaeus of is his lack of reliability when dealing with the origin, primitive history,
            and peculiar customs of peoples. Illustrations of this pseudo-antiquarian interest of
            Timaeus are given by Polybius in which he shows that the writer was either unpardonably
            ignorant or deliberately mendacious, with the weight of evidence preponderantly in favor
            of the latter.</p>
          <p>Because of this tendency to write with confidence about what he did not know or to
            misapply the knowledge he had gathered Polybius particularly impugns the value of
            Timaeus's "account of Libya, Sardinia, and, above all, of Italy"--a hint which is of
            special importance in connection with the subject of this investigation. In a word,
            Polybius, one of the most careful historians of antiquity, charges that Timaeus had no
            hesitancy to resort to fiction and deliberate falsehood. Strabo also has several times
            questioned the accuracy of Timaeus's statements on important matters, and likewise
            Diodorus Siculus; while among modern critics his value as a historian is summed up by
            Mommsen who says of him: "He was one of the historians who upon no matters are so well
            informed as upon things unknowable."</p>
          <p>Such was the character of the historian to whom we apparently owe the earliest known
            account of the coinage by Servius, the perplexing <hi rend="i">aes</hi>
            <note id="note_001"><ref target="ref_001" rend="super">¹</ref>Pais <hi rend="i">Storia
                d. R.</hi> I, 2, p. 406, n. 2. Mi limito solo a notare che nulla vieta pensare che
              Timeo abbia favoleggiato sulle monete di Servio e che alla sua volta fosse seguito in
              questo caso da Varrone.</note>
            <pb id="VAB9263-006" n="6"/>
            <hi rend="i">signatum</hi>. And while Timaeus may have gathered his account from current
            tradition, yet he was plainly not incapable of inventing it, and if sufficient motives
            can be found for such a course, I believe that we are warranted in concluding that he
            did invent the story; and for a writer like Timaeus the motives were not wanting.</p>

          <p>The conditions under which he wrote were such as to invite extravagance from a pen
            uncontrolled by severe regard for historic truth. The steady advance of the Romans
            toward the Greek cities of Italy, and especially the defeat of Pyrrhus, had greatly
            impressed the eastern Greeks and created a keen interest in the new power rising in the
            West. But the history of the Romans was but little known to the Greeks; it had never
            been written. Fully conscious of all this Timaeus, probably the first to write a history
            of the Romans,<ref id="ref_002" rend="super" target="note_002">¹</ref> wrote the early
            history of the city of Rome; and the opportunity which a new field and a keenly
            interested reader offered his style, it was Asiatic,<ref id="ref_003" rend="super"
              target="note_003">²</ref> was not lost by one so apparently ready to sacrifice
            historic truth to lively narrative.</p>
          <p>The immediate inspiration for an account of Rome's first attempt at coining money would
            have been readily given by the interest which may well have been aroused by the
            introduction of the first, the well-known heavy bronze, coinage (B. C. 335), and later
            (B. C. 269) of the first silver coinage by the Romans; for both of those coinages were
            introduced in the lifetime of Timaeus.</p>
          <p>Furthermore, the chief motive of the fabrication, if such it was in substance, and the
            sources of some of the material that was woven into it, are perhaps not far to seek. It
            is well known that very much of the early history of Rome, as we find it recorded by
            Livy and other writers, is not authentic, some of it having been invented by early
            annalists to explain existing institutions while much of it was undoubtedly appropriated
            or imitated from the earlier history of other great states, especially of Athens. In
            particular Professor Pais points out how the Hellenic and Roman historians copied their
            accounts of the reign of Servius Tullius from the record of the legislation of
              Solon,<ref id="ref_004" rend="super" target="note_004">³</ref> who was almost his
              <note id="note_002"><ref target="ref_002" rend="super">¹</ref>Dionysius of
              Halicarnassus, I. 6.</note>
            <note id="note_003"><ref target="ref_003" rend="super">²</ref>Cicero, Brutus,
              325.</note>
            <note id="note_004"><ref target="ref_004" rend="super">³</ref>Pais, <hi rend="i">Storia
                di Roma</hi>, I, 2, p. 570:--Nella Storia di Servio Tullio è lecito forse constatare
              anche altre correnti elleniche. Questo re, che sostituisce ordinamenti timocratici
              alla antica costituzione genocratica, che abolisce l'usura, distribuisce le terre ai
              poveri, favorisce gli schiavi, che è autore del censo, della legge agraria, di
              contratti, che pubblica le sue leggi, dal lato storico e cronologico è una copia di
              Solone, che visse verso gli stessi decenni e che fu realmente l'autore della
              "seisachteia," Solone anzi, stando alla storia tradizionale, sarebbe stato l'autore in
              genere di tutti i provvedimenti che vengono pure attribuiti al sesto re romano. Si
              mirava ad attribuire anche a Roma i fatti piu salienti della storia ateniese, della
              cittá principe della Grecia.</note>
            <pb id="VAB9263-007" n="7"/> contemporary. And since one of the important features of
            the legislation of Solon was the reform of the monetary system of Athens, so in the
            parallelism an epoch-making monetary event was needed for the reign of Servius. For that
            purpose the story attributing the first coinage of money by the Romans to that king
            served well indeed.</p>
          <p>The parallelism is further established by the general character of the types attributed
            to the first coinage by the Romans wherein the account follows rather faithfully the
            ancient legend about the first Athenian coin-types. For there was a tradition, mentioned
            by Plutarch and Pollux, that the earliest coin-type of Athens was an ox. The types of
            the supposed <hi rend="i">aes signatum</hi> included the ox, hog, and sheep. The greater
            variety of types assigned to the earliest Roman coinage might well be due to what was
            doubtless a simple fact and well known, that at an early period, perhaps in the regal
            period, and probably for some time thereafter, the wealth of a Roman consisted of
            lands--he was <hi rend="i">locupletes</hi>--and his ready funds, of cattle, sheep, and
            hogs; with the latter, for instance, he paid his fines: <hi rend="i">multaeque dictione
              ovium et bovum, (quod tum erat res in pecore et in locorum possessionibus, ex quo
              pecuniosi et locupletes vocabantur) non vi et suppliciis coercebat. Cic. De Leg. II,
              9;)</hi><ref id="ref_005" rend="super" target="note_005">¹</ref>--and thus to
            represent Rome's first coined money as reproducing in its types the animals that before
            had been used as money would not only parallel the early Athenian tradition but by
            showing an apparent development from earlier Italian conditions would give the bit of
            "history" a desirable plausibility.</p>
          <p>Now if there is some ground to suspect the authenticity of the story preserved by the
            writers because of the character of the earliest known source of their statements, there
            is another fact that must not be left out of consideration and one that cannot but cause
            grave doubt as to the truth of the supposed tradition. This fact is that no specimens of
            Roman bronze coins have come to light that correspond either as to types (with a
            possible single exception) or to period of origin with the <hi rend="i">aes
              signatum</hi> of that tradition. We have one specimen with an ox-type on both sides,
            but it is evident, and so agreed, that the piece is not Roman but Greek in style of art
            nor is it of earlier origin than the first issues of the Roman heavy round coins,
            probably not so early. As is well known, owing to the ancient practice of burying coins
            and other objects of value, no other class of monuments relating to the history of man
            exists in <note id="note_005"><ref target="ref_005" rend="super">¹</ref>See also Varro,
                <hi rend="i">De R. R. II</hi>, 1, 9:--Multa etiam nune ex vetere instituto bubus et
              ovibus dicitur.</note>
            <pb id="VAB9263-008" n="8"/> greater numbers than, or in so nearly unbroken series as,
            coins. Specimens are extant of what was doubtless the very earliest issues of coins in
            western Asia and Europe about 700 B.C., remains of what could hardly have been very
            considerable coinages. And while doubtless specimens of the first and scanty issues of
            certain states are yet wanting, still it is almost impossible to point to an ancient
            coinage that was extensive or long continued of which specimens are not extant and
            sometimes in enormous numbers. If, now, we accept the traditional date for the beginning
            of Rome's first coinage, the so-called <hi rend="i">aes signatum</hi>, or if the first
            issue of that coinage be attributed to the period of the Decemvirs, then for at least a
            century or until the accepted date (B. C. 335) when the prow-series was first issued,
            that rising state issued coins bearing the types of the ox, hog, and sheep; and since,
            we must infer, Rome issued no other bronze coins, we should be compelled to conclude
            that the annual coinage of such money was considerable, while the aggregate volume that
            would naturally accumulate in the course of so long a period would necessarily become
            enormous. Yet no examples of that alleged early coinage, no pieces bearing such types
            and attributable to that period, have ever come to light! And there is no reason why
            specimens of it should not have been found in buried hoards and sacred deposits that
            have been unearthed in Italy. In fact we have many specimens of what numismatists choose
            to call the earlier <hi rend="i">aes rude</hi>, mere amorphous lumps of bronze. And if
            these lumps of bronze do represent the <hi rend="i">aes rude</hi> of the tradition then
            we are in the singular position of having examples of the very earliest and crude Roman
            metallic money, but probably none of the later money bearing a mark (<hi rend="i"
              >signum</hi>). This would certainly be a rather unusual situation!</p>
          <p>This failure of the finds of ancient coins in Italy to corroborate the statements of
            the writers as to the <hi rend="i">aes signature</hi>, while in a way negative evidence,
            yet when considered in connection with other arguments, can hardly fail to prove
            damaging to any theory that in this tradition relating to Rome's first coinage there is
            a kernel of truth.</p>
          <p>So much for the supposed tradition which certain writers have preserved in regard to
            the first issue of money by the Romans. The tentative conclusions reached as to the
            authenticity of that tradition cannot but be in a measure confirmed, or weakened, by
            consideration of some of the arguments by which investigators have sought to establish
            the identity of extant bars with the <hi rend="i">aes signatum</hi> of the writers or at
            least to show that they were somehow historically related thereto, and also by a study
            of those bars themselves.</p>
        </div2>

        <pb id="VAB9263-009" n="9"/>


        <div2 type="section">
          <head>
            <hi rend="center">III.</hi>
          </head>
          <p>The numerous varieties of extant bars do not admit of satisfactory classification on
            the basis of chronology, composition or any other principle on which coins are generally
            classified, except in part by the unsatisfactory geographical distribution, determined,
            not as in the case of coins, by the known or probable places of issue, but merely by the
            general locality in which they have been discovered. Thus Dr. Haeberlin in his
            monumental work on the <hi rend="i">Aes Grave</hi> makes a classification of them that
            represents fairly the consensus of opinion on the subject; his three classes are:</p>
          <list type="ordered">
            <item>The north Etruscan bars, with iron alloy.<lb/> Types: dead branch (<hi rend="i"
                >ramo secco</hi>) or plain.</item>
            <item>The decorated bars of northern Central-Italy.<lb/> Types: fish-skeleton, dolphins,
              twigs with leaves, and crescents.</item>
            <item>The Romano-Campanian bars, of which there are so far known nine varieties.<lb/>
              Types: <list type="ordered">
                <item>Eagle on fulmen.--Pegasus; ROMANOM.</item>
                <item>Shield.--Shield.</item>
                <item>Sword.--Scabbard.</item>
                <item>Barley-ear.--Tripod.</item>
                <item>Anchor.--Tripod.</item>
                <item>Trident.--Caduceus.</item>
                <item>Cocks and stars.--Rostra and dolphins.</item>
                <item>Ox.--Ox.</item>
                <item>Elephant.--Sow.</item>
              </list></item>
          </list>
          <p>This classification has almost no scientific basis and is at most a mere convenience of
            questionable value. For provenience alone is not a safe guide to the actual origin of
            antiquities as has been shown in more than one instance, and strikingly by the error of
            attributing the thousands of Greek vases found in Etruria to local makers. It is
            improbable that the bronze bars found in Etruria and elsewhere in Italy present a case
            parallel to that of the vases, but the mistake made with the latter may well be taken as
            a warning. And such a caution gains some force when it is considered that in the case of
            groups 1 and 2 there is not a single type that can be brought into relation with an
            Etruscan community or legend; while the bars of group 3 have been ascribed to the Roman
            mint at Capua chiefly because the artistic quality of the types forbids their
            attribution to Roman engravers. This attribution Dr. Haeberlin has sought to establish
            on numismatic and historical evidence, but his arguments are hardly convincing.</p>
          <pb id="VAB9263-010" n="10"/>
          <p>In the various discussions of these bars a number of their salient features have been
            brought out and emphasized, more especially those which must be taken into account on
            the theory that the bars are coins or in some way by law or custom connected with the
            Roman monetary system. The mere statement of these facts will not only show why
            explanations of these great bars have been so varied, having run, in fact, the whole
            gamut of possibilities from state-issued coins down to mere bars of bronze produced by
            private enterprize; but it will also present succinctly the chief factors that must be
            taken into consideration in every attempt to arrive at an explanation of them. The more
            important if not all of the facts are:</p>
          <list type="ordered">
            <item>The weights of the bars vary greatly, and they are not adjusted to the standard
              unit of Roman bronze coinage, nor to that of any other Italian community.</item>
            <item>The composition of the bars differs widely, some having large proportions of iron
              and little or no lead, others a large percentage of lead and no iron, while still
              others have varying proportions of tin and lead.</item>
            <item>The artistic style of the types on several examples shows unmistakably the work of
              Greek artists and in no case has anything in common with Roman die engraving.</item>
            <item>Only one of the bars bears an inscription, which is ROMANOM.</item>
            <item>The majority of the bars have been found in a fragmentary state, deliberately
              broken it has been claimed and such is apparently the case--a purely incidental fact
              but one of which much has been made by the advocates of the theory that they were
              meant for use as money.</item>
          </list>
          <p>Certain alleged characteristics of the Servian <hi rend="i">Aes signatum</hi> and the
            necessary qualities of Roman coins, which the bars do not possess, are:</p>
          <list type="ordered">
            <item>Domestic animal types are found exclusively on but one bar.</item>
            <item>Archaic art is not found in any of the types.</item>
            <item>Marks of value do not occur.</item>
            <item>No recognized coin-types of Rome or of any other Italian community are found on
              any of them--but one of the bars bears the same devices as are found on the coins of
              two Greek communities of Italy, the barley-ear and tripod.</item>
          </list>
          <p>The above statements take into consideration all of the bars usually designated <hi
              rend="i">Aes signatum</hi>. And there is no reason why they should not be considered
            as a whole. For with the possible exception of a single series, those with the so-called
              <hi rend="i">ramo secco</hi> types, these bars cannot be <pb id="VAB9263-011" n="11"/>
            classified chronologically into widely separated groups; they are for the most part
            contemporary. Willers places the issue of the <hi rend="i">Fischgräte</hi> bars between
            B. C. 325 and 250, while two other varieties, the one with the crescent-shaped types,
            the other with "marks of value" (Pl. VIII, 1 and 2), he dates to almost the same period,
              <hi rend="i">i. e.</hi>, B. C. 300-250. While I believe there are good reasons to
            doubt that the production of the bars ceased round B. C. 250, it is very probable that
            the <hi rend="i">terminus post quem</hi> given by Willers is approximately correct. And
            it is generally conceded that the bars which bear types in the fine style of Greek art
            belong to about the same period, being assigned by most writers to B. C. 312 to 269. So,
            then, if the bars belong to the same general period and especially if they were state
            issues for any special purpose, we should be justified in expecting them to possess
            common characteristics as do the coins of several cities in the same country and of the
            same period.</p>
          <p>The bars that have received by far the most attention are the so-called
            Romano-Campanian group, evidently because their splendid types seemed to assure for them
            a noble origin and purpose and apparently afforded, in some cases at least, historical
            and other data, while without doubt the un-Roman, plainly Greek, art of their types
            gives rise to special difficulties. It is with these nine bars that Dr. Haeberlin deals
            so ingeniously in his <hi rend="i">Systematik</hi>, where he presents a theory that at
            present overshadows all other explanations of them. Some of the main points of Dr.
            Haeberlin's theory in regard to the origin and use of these particular bars are in
            substance as follows:</p>
          <list type="ordered">
            <item>They date between 312 and 269 B. C.</item>
            <item>They were issued by the State.</item>
            <item>They are to be regarded as successors of earlier and cruder bars--<hi rend="i">als
                die verfeinerten Nachfolger der alten Rohbarren zu denken seien</hi>.</item>
            <item>They were issued from the mint at Capua, which was served by Greek artists.</item>
            <item>Seven of the bars were issued in connection with as many series of coins
              proper.</item>
            <item>They were not coins, but bars of coin-metal, the fineness of which was guaranteed
              by the State's type--<hi rend="i">bestehen die campanischen Barren aus
              Münzmetall</hi>.</item>
            <item>They were intended to serve all the purposes that the earlier <hi rend="i">aes
                rude</hi> and cruder <hi rend="i">aes signatum</hi> had served, such as (a) monetary
              purpose; consisting of coin-metal and issued by the state the bars possessed the
              proper qualities of money--<hi rend="i">sie besitzen demnach die wesentlichen vom <pb
                  id="VAB9263-012" n="12"/> Gelde zu erfordenden Eigenschaften und wenn es neben
                ihnen kein gemünztes Geld gegeben hätte, so waren sie unzweifelhaft geeignet an
                Geldesstatt zu dienen</hi>; (b) ceremonial purposes, in transactions of <hi rend="i"
                >emtiovenditio per aes et libram, mancipatio</hi>, and for <hi rend="i">aera
                stipata</hi>, and possibly the fragments for <hi rend="i">tesserae
              hospitales</hi>.</item>
          </list>
          <p>As to the period when these bars had their origin there will be no dispute, for the
            artistic style of their types bring them well into the fourth century. But on nearly all
            the other points of Dr. Haeberlin's treatise there is room for endless argument. Thus we
            know nothing of the earlier crude bars to which these Campanian examples are supposed to
            have succeeded; and that such bars had ever been issued in southern Italy seems to have
            been inferred from the existence of cruder ones found further north. And yet, while the
            types of the latter are less elaborate and significant, and perhaps less artistic, than
            those of the nine bars in question, it is by no means certain that the northern bars are
            of very much earlier date.</p>
          <p>As to his contention that the bars were issued by the state and from a government
            coinage mint, that is established by the relationship claimed for several of them with
            certain series of alleged Roman silver and bronze coins. This connection is based
            largely upon internal evidence afforded by the types. Both of these questions will come
            up in the discussion of the types of some of the bars and might, therefore, be passed
            over here. But there are one or two general observations bearing upon that question that
            may as well be made now.</p>
          <p>The evidence upon which their state origin is chiefly based is apparently the presence
            of the inscription ROMANOM on one variety of bar, the one with the eagle-pegasus types.
            That inscription has been the real nexus between the literary tradition about an early
              <hi rend="i">aes signatum</hi> and these great quadrilateral bricks. Romano-Campanian
            silver coins of about the same period bear the genitive case form ROMANO and it has been
            generally accepted that the inscription on the bar pointed to the same authority. But
            the presence of that inscription on a single variety of the bars can be used as evidence
            against, as well as for, the view that they were issued by Roman state authority;
            perhaps with even greater force against it. For the presence of the inscription on but
            one variety does not point to an identical authority for the issue of all of them; it
            rather suggests different sources. Had all the nine bars of the "Romano-Campanian" group
            been issued from the Capuan mint and within a very brief period of years (B. C. 312 to
            269), as Dr. Haeberlin <pb id="VAB9263-013" n="13"/> contends, it seems incredible that
            there should not have been greater consistency in the use of inscriptions. This
            objection gains force when it is considered that the inscription ROMANOM is found on the
            only bar that bears what might then have been recognized as a Roman type, the eagle and
            fulmen of Jupiter. Were that inscription found upon one of the bars with apparently
            non-Roman or non-Campanian types the exception could then feebly be explained as having
            been necessary in order to guarantee its Roman origin.</p>
          <p>It is difficult, therefore, to see how this inscription can be regarded as evidence
            that the bar was issued by Roman state authority. Another view of the significance of
            that legend will be given below where the eagle-pegasus bar is discussed. But whether
            the meaning of the eagle-pegasus types and ROMANOM there given be acceptable or not the
            objections to the usual interpretation of the legend as designating the Roman state
            authority are too serious to be overlooked.</p>
          <p>Attention also may be called to the frequent changes in the types of both the coins
            proper and of the bars which the theory of Dr. Haeberlin requires. For according to that
            theory there were six radical changes in the types of the bronze coins issued by Rome
            from the Capuan mint in the short period between B. C. 312 and 269, and one of the
            series was issued in two varieties; while in connection with each series of coins a bar
            of distinct type was issued. This frequent change of types is not only remarkable and
            almost without parallel in any other country, but such a practice is decidedly un-Roman.
            The subsidiary bronze coins of many of the Greek states show great variety of types, but
            it is questionable if in any place the changes followed in such rapid succession as that
            supposed for these heavy bronze coins of much higher value and which, at first
            certainly, were not subsidiary. In the case of the undisputed Roman bronze coinage the
            practice was just the opposite. For the types of the prow-series persisted for
            centuries. Moreover, in the case of the bars, that rapid succession of new types is
            carried still further, for Dr. Haeberlin holds, that in addition to the seven bars
            issued in conjunction with and as a part of as many series of silver and heavy bronze
            coins, two additional bars were issued within the same period with new types
            commemorative of historical events! Such a view of the production of the bars is no less
            discordant than their novel devices with that spirit of Roman conservativeness that, it
            is claimed, would not employ the new bronze coins for ceremonial and religious uses
            because they were an innovation (eine Neuerung).</p>
          <pb id="VAB9263-014" n="14"/>
          <p>Among numismatists the view has generally prevailed that the bars were issued for use
            as money and are either coins, the <hi rend="i">aes signatum</hi>, or at least money in
            the wider sense of the term; and their efforts have chiefly been directed to showing
            just what the status of this money was in the general monetary system of the country.
            For example, it was the opinion of Mommsen that the bars were a sort of coin issued
            under the direction of the Roman government and, with or without legend, circulated in
            about the same manner as the coins proper of later times; while Professor Milani<ref
              id="ref_006" rend="super" target="note_006">¹</ref> went even further and attempted to
            fix the denomination of the bars as Quincussis. Perhaps few persons, if any, would still
            hold to the earlier belief that the bars are coins, but the statements of some writers
            about them are unfortunately so ill-guarded as to lead one to surmise that their real
            convictions do not altogether square with the theories to which the logic of facts has
            driven them. But the notion that the bars are coins has been necessarily given up
            because they lack the requirements of coins proper, especially of Roman coins. Thus
            their weights are not adjusted to the Roman or any other coinage unit,<ref id="ref_007"
              rend="super" target="note_007">²</ref> so that they could not pass by tale at an
            average value guaranteed by the state, which is the chief function of a coin proper; and
            they bear no marks of value, while from the first Roman bronze coins as well as those of
            other Italian states did bear marks of value.</p>
          <p> The theory, therefore, that the bars are coins has given way to the view that they
            were intended for use as money only in the broad meaning <note id="note_006"><ref
                target="ref_006" rend="super">¹</ref>Rivista Italiana di Numismatica, 1890.</note>
            <note id="note_007"><ref target="ref_007" rend="super">²</ref>The weights of 25
              specimens of the Romano-Campanian bars show a wide variation, the discrepancy between
              the lightest and the heaviest reaching several hundred grammes and is over 200 grammes
              above and below the average weight. The following schedule of weights show how they
              vary: <table rows="28" cols="3">
                <row>
                  <cell><hi rend="b">T<hi rend="sc">YPE</hi>.</hi></cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell><hi rend="b">Weight in grammes.</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Eagle--Pegasus</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>1642.00</cell>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell>2</cell>
                  <cell>1542.00</cell>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell>3</cell>
                  <cell>1394.60</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell>4</cell>
                  <cell>1389.63</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Shield--Shield</cell>
                  <cell>5</cell>
                  <cell>1623.30</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell>6</cell>
                  <cell>1580.00</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell>7</cell>
                  <cell>1516.00</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Sword--Scabbord</cell>
                  <cell>8</cell>
                  <cell>1618.00</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell>9</cell>
                  <cell>1593.69</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Tripod--Anchor</cell>
                  <cell>10</cell>
                  <cell>1830.05</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell>11</cell>
                  <cell>1677.20</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell>12</cell>
                  <cell>1543.70</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell>13</cell>
                  <cell>1495.06</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Caduceus--Trident</cell>
                  <cell>14</cell>
                  <cell>1686.35</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell>15</cell>
                  <cell>1679.50</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell>16</cell>
                  <cell>1628.00</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell>17 </cell>
                  <cell>1614.00</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell>18 </cell>
                  <cell>1141.50</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Cocks--Rostra</cell>
                  <cell>19 </cell>
                  <cell>1525.25</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell>20 </cell>
                  <cell>1491.76</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Ox--Ox</cell>
                  <cell>21</cell>
                  <cell>1790.23</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell>22</cell>
                  <cell>1624.50</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell>23</cell>
                  <cell>1389.90</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell>24</cell>
                  <cell>1347.00</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell>25</cell>
                  <cell>1746.49</cell>
                </row>


                <row>
                  <cell>Total weight</cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell>39,109.71</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Average weight,</cell>
                  <cell> </cell>
                  <cell>1564.39 grammes.</cell>
                </row>
              </table>
            </note>
            <pb id="VAB9263-015" n="15"/> of that term. In this wider sense of money Willers<ref
              id="ref_008" rend="super" target="note_008">¹</ref> and Dr. Haeberlin<ref id="ref_009"
              rend="super" target="note_009">²</ref> hold that the bars are of coin-metal and as
            such were guaranteed by the state, so that they could be used to make payments when it
            happened that no coins proper were at hand. Not very materially different from this view
            is the suggestion of Dr. Regling,<ref id="ref_010" rend="super" target="note_010"
              >³</ref> who rejects the Haeberlin explanation that the bars were also intended for
            ceremonial uses, but agrees that they were a convenient form of coin-metal, of a
            fineness guaranteed by the State's type or the inscription ROMANOM, and were intended
            for use as money, evidently in transactions involving the payment of large sums, similar
            in character to the bars of the precious metals issued from the mints of Europe in the
            Middle Ages--a view that is perhaps influenced by the practices of modern international
            commerce wherein large sums in gold bricks are frequently transferred in the settlement
            of trade balances.</p>
          <p>This theory of the bars assumes that the Romans lacked an adequate supply of coined
            money, a condition that must have prevailed also or especially in the newly conquered
            territory; and so recourse was had to issuing of bricks of bullion to eke out the volume
            of currency; Nur grosse und einschneidende politische Umwälzungen konnten eine
            fundamentale Reform dieses durch den Mangel der Münze characterisirten Zustandes
            Mittelitaliens zur Folge haben u.s.w.<ref id="ref_011" rend="super" target="note_011"
              >⁴</ref> And this is the only rational ground upon which the theory can be based; for
            it would be absurd to contend that the people inhabiting those countries insisted upon
            retaining a crude and unwieldy form of currency when the infinitely greater convenience
            of coins proper had been long known to them or that Rome was ready to humor such an
            impracticable whim!</p>
          <p>There is, however, no evidence that the volume of coined money was inadequate either at
            Rome or in the conquered territory. With the knowledge we have of how in antiquity
            comparatively backward communities made use of the coins imported from more advanced
            states it would be a mistake to suppose that Roman domestic trade was served only by her
            own alleged makeshift currency prior to about B. C. 335, <note id="note_008"><ref
                target="ref_008" rend="super">¹</ref> Willers, <hi rend="i">Numismatische
                Zeitschrift</hi>, 1905, p. 13 f.</note>
            <note id="note_009"><ref target="ref_009" rend="super">²</ref> Haeberlin, <hi rend="i"
                >Systematik</hi>, p. 57.</note>
            <note id="note_010"><ref target="ref_010" rend="super">³</ref> Regling, <hi rend="i"
                >Klio</hi>, 1908, p. 501:--Auch der Gesamtsauffassung Haeberlins von den Barren ...
              vermag ich mich nicht anzuschliessen, halte die Barren vielmehr für Rohmaterial, das,
              in handliche Form gebracht und hinsichtlich der Feinheit als Münzmetall vom Staate
              durch das Bild bezw. die Aufschrift ROMANOM garantiert, jederzeit als Geld zugewogen
              werden konnte.</note>
            <note id="note_011"><ref target="ref_011" rend="super">⁴</ref> Willers, <hi rend="i"
                >loc. cit.</hi></note>
            <pb id="VAB9263-016" n="16"/> or thereafter only by her new and proper bronze coinage.
            The states on her narrow confines north and south were at that early period coining
            money, and of the precious metals too; while the aggressive commerce of several great
            Greek and Asiatic states had pushed its way throughout Italy and where that commerce
            went their gold and silver coins went with it. It would certainly be contrary to the
            usual practices everywhere, in both ancient and modern times, had the Romans failed to
            make extensive use of coins struck by other peoples. It is more likely that an abundant
            supply of such currency for her domestic trade was a factor in postponing somewhat the
            introduction of a national coinage or in restricting the national coinage to bronze for
            so long a period of time; for coins imported through the channels of commerce would be
            solely of silver and gold.</p>

          <p>Furthermore, at the very time when it is urged that these bars were being issued by
            Rome necessarily to supplement the volume of coined money, the other States of Italy
            were evidently well supplied with the precious metals. For M. Babelon in discussing the
            abundance of the precious metals in antiquity<ref id="ref_012" rend="super"
              target="note_012">¹</ref>--in the course of which he makes the interesting and
            probably correct statement that the volume of such metals in antiquity was likely as
            great in proportion to the population using money coined of gold and silver as it is
            today, or even greater--in reference to Italy shows that the States of the peninsula
            were not exceptionally poor in these nobler metals. For in B. C. 293 Papirius Cursor
            collected a booty of 1,830 pounds of silver in his campaign among the Samnites, (cf.
            Liv. X 46) a very large sum when one considers that Samnium was an inland agricultural
            country and also that the precious metals would be the first objects which the populace
            would endeavor to protect from the hands of the invader, so that the Roman general
            secured a very small portion of Samnium's supply of silver; and it is certainly a safe
            conjecture that the more powerful Rome was much better supplied with silver and gold
            than was Samnium.</p>
          <p>Even less defensible is the suggestion that these bars were intended to facilitate
            large transactions. For, as Mr. Hill has pointed out, if there had been need of pieces
            of larger value than the heavy bronze coins for the occasional payment of large sums,
            the Roman silver Didrachm would have supplied that need far more conveniently than these
            large unwieldy bricks.<ref id="ref_013" rend="super" target="note_013">²</ref> And it
            must furthermore be noted that, so far as it is <note id="note_012"><ref
                target="ref_012" rend="super">¹</ref> Babelon, <hi rend="i">Les Origines de la
                Monnaie</hi>, p. 250ff.</note>
            <note id="note_013"><ref target="ref_013" rend="super">²</ref> Hill, G. F., <hi rend="i"
                >Historical Roman Coins</hi>, p. 16.</note>
            <pb id="VAB9263-017" n="17"/> implied that the larger pieces of coin-metal would be more
            convenient than the coins, the bars being only four or five times as large as the libral
            bronze <hi rend="i">As</hi> then in circulation offered but slight advantage in that
            respect when considered only in respect of the number of pieces required to make up a
            given sum of money; and far less convenient when the necessity of weighing the bars is
            taken into consideration. And finally since the speed with which a casting mint operated
            depended more upon the melting process than the size of moulds the making of the larger
            bars instead of the libral <hi rend="i">As</hi> could hardly increase the mint's
            production of money.</p>
        </div2>

        <div2 type="section">
          <head>
            <hi rend="center">IV.</hi>
          </head>
          <p>The difficulties in the way of proving that these bars were made for a money use of any
            sort are so numerous that inevitably the doctrine must be abandoned or greatly modified.
            And a modification has now been suggested in the form of a theory that holds the bars to
            be a late continuation or perhaps'revival of the old bar-coinage and issued chiefly for
            certain uses, other than monetary, which had become so deeply rooted in popular usage
            that the conservative spirit of legal and religious practices required their
            continuance. Preeminent among the theories of this character is Dr. Haeberlin's, that
            they were meant to serve those ceremonial uses which the traditional aes signatum had
            probably served, such as the transactions that only could be legally completed by use of
            a piece of bronze (emtio venditio per aes et libram) and also for religious offerings
            (aera stipata). And with this part of his theory the views of Mr. Hill substantially
            agree: "The question of the use of the bricks must, therefore, be left open; we cannot
            disprove the theory that they may have been used in large payments, but the theory that
            they served ceremonial purposes is by far the most plausible that has yet been
              advanced."<ref id="ref_014" rend="super" target="note_014">¹</ref></p>
          <p>This theory of the bars appears to be in no small degree a last resort in despair of
            proving for them a sole monetary function. It is difficult, however, to see why the
            state should find it necessary to issue a special bronze piece for such purposes. There
            is certainly no evidence from literary sources that a piece of bronze of any special
            design, form or size was required for these uses; and as for religious offerings, so far
            as the evidence of what are generally regarded as the finds of sacred deposits gives us
            any hint, that points to the fact that bronze in any form was suitable for such
            purposes. For these deposits are a jumble of many forms and qualities of copper.</p>
          <note id="note_014"><ref target="ref_014" rend="super">¹</ref> Hill, G. F., <hi rend="i"
              >loc. cit</hi>., p. 17.</note>

          <pb id="VAB9263-018" n="18"/>

          <p>On the other hand, so far as the argument is based upon the usual conservativeness of a
            people in customs pertaining to such common matters of their daily life as purchase and
            sale and religious offerings, nine of the bars, the so-called Romano-Campanian examples,
            hardly favor such a contention. For in their outward appearance, the feature which would
            most impress the common people, the bars are not of a conservative character; in fact
            their types are varied and novel and treated in a most advanced artistic style. Besides,
            had the state issued bars with a view even secondarily to their ceremonial use, it is
            almost inconceivable that some among so many examples should not have borne a type
            somehow alluding to such a purpose; but none of these do. Again, had the state issued
            bronze pieces for such uses, the most popular next to a monetary use, it is certainly
            improbable that pieces of such high value would have been issued; for the value of these
            bars runs from four to above five libral Asses, pieces whose purchasing power then was
            the equivalent of several dollars today. Only the prosperous could have afforded to make
            use of such valuable pieces for ceremonial purposes. Had a large number of very small
            bronze pieces come to light in Italy, one should be justified in inferring that they had
            been made for some such popular uses as proposed for these great bars.</p>
          <p>It is true, on the other hand, that the bars are mostly found in fragments; but if it
            be contended that they were reduced to fragments for the use under consideration, the
            fact would only prove that any piece of bronze, however crude it might be, would serve
            the purpose, and that actually pieces much smaller than the extant bars were generally
            employed. And if that had been the case, the fact would have been well known to the
            Roman government, who would certainly not have sanctioned the issue of pieces too large
            and valuable for the convenience of the masses of the people.</p>
          <p>The objections that have been urged against the theory that these bars were issued by
            the State for ceremonial and religious uses may not carry sufficient weight to discredit
            it entirely, yet until that doctrine has been grounded upon some definite proofs it will
            be impossible to believe that the Romans ever incurred the unnecesary expense and went
            to the trouble of issuing a bar that was not needed and in a size that was not
            practicable.</p>
        </div2>

        <div2 type="section">
          <head>
            <hi rend="center">V.</hi>
          </head>
          <p>The theory that these bars were produced by private enterprise and were intended for
            use as coins or for foreign commerce has recently <pb id="VAB9263-019" n="19"/> been put
            forward. Thus in a paper read before the International Congress of Numismatists at Paris
            in 1900 (<hi rend="i">I bronzi quadrilateri della republica e la moneta privata dei
              Romani</hi>) Com. F. Gnecchi advanced the view that these bricks were not issued by
            the state; (1) because their types do not present the head of a divinity, which is a
            characteristic of the bronze coinage of the Romans; and (2) because they are
            quadrilateral in form, while the coins issued by the Roman government, even the large
            Dupondius, Tripondius, and Decussis, were round. These bars are, therefore, to be
            considered private coins, a sort of continuation of the <hi rend="i">aes signatum</hi>
            of an earlier period,<ref id="ref_015" rend="super" target="note_015">¹</ref> which is
            supposed to have been a private issue.</p>
          <p>The assumption that the Romans restricted religious types to official coins and would
            have denied the use of such types to private persons though the latter were allowed to
            issue, or were not molested in the practice of issuing, coins is without foundation;
            while at the same time the writer seems to hold that such religious character was
            conferred only by the use of the effigy of the divinity and to lose sight of the fact
            that many ancient coin-types present only the symbol of a divinity and are yet properly
            regarded as of religious character; and among the types of these bars are a number of
            objects recognized as symbols of divinities. Besides, the cock, hog, elephant, and
            pegasus types are found on the coins of other states of Italy where because of a common
            inheritance of religious and social institutions the types of coins were probably
            regarded much the same as by the Romans. As to Mr. Gnecchi's argument from the
            quadrilateral form of the bricks, he assumes that the more ancient <hi rend="i">aes
              signatum</hi> of questionable tradition was of private origin, a view that contradicts
            a part of the same literary tradition which he accepts as to the existence of that
            coinage, for Pliny expressly states that it was a royal coinage; and also he assumes
            that that <hi rend="i">aes signatum</hi> was of quadrilateral form, which is a
            groundless assumption.</p>
          <p>Least tenable, however, is Gnecchi's conclusion that these bricks were coins produced
            by private enterprise. For nothing could be more inconsistent with the Roman conception
            of the State in the fourth century, and probably much earlier, than to permit the
            individual to compete <note id="note_015"><ref target="ref_015" rend="super">¹</ref>
              Conclusione: questi pezzi, sia pel carattere evidente delle loro impronte, sia per la
              loro forma, non erano moneta ufficiale dello Stato romano. Cosa potevano dunque essere
              se non moneta privata?<lb/> Come tali non dovevano e non potevano portare impronta
              religiosa;--lo Stato non l'avrebbe permesso--e come tali, conservavano la forma
              quadrata, quasi in continuazione degli antichi pezzi di <hi rend="i">Aes signatum</hi>
              i quali indubbiamente costituivano la moneta primitiva e privata dei Romani.</note>
            <pb id="VAB9263-020" n="20"/> with the sovereign power in the exercise of one of its
            chief functions--that of establishing a system of currency and coining money. Thus the
            theory that these bars were privately issued coins or money would but substitute greater
            problems for the ones whose solution has already proved sufficiently difficult.</p>
          <p> Finally, Bahrfeldt <hi rend="i">Eine vorläufige Erörterung der Barrenfrage, Berlin
              1901)</hi> influenced apparently by his recent studies of the large find of bars and a
            great many fragments of bars at Mazin, Croatia, contends that they were not coins,
            either official or private. The objection to regarding them as coins of any sort is
            based upon the absence of marks of value. But the reported<ref id="ref_016" rend="super"
              target="note_016">¹</ref> view of General Bahrfeldt that they were simply ingots of
            bronze, which formed an article of export to the countries that made use of bronze, is,
            I believe, true in part. But there is no reason to believe that they were meant only for
            export; while there are reasons to believe that the ingots of bronze transported in
            foreign commerce were much larger than these bars.<ref id="ref_017" rend="super"
              target="note_017">²</ref></p>
          <p>It appears, therefore, that the various efforts to associate these bars with the Roman
            coinage have served chiefly to emphasize the difficulties in the way of such
            explanations of them and to point out how far their characteristics remove them from a
            monetary use. In the case of the types, it is a noticeable fact that, with exception of
            but one or two varieties (such as the Hog-Elephant bar), whose certainly erroneous
            interpretations have been generally accepted, the very few writers who have attempted to
            solve the riddle of their meaning have found themselves compelled to have recourse to
            broad and general notions, to which the types do not with clearness allude, and seldom
            have found the meaning in facts and events readily symbolized for the masses of the
            people by such devices as occur on these bars; whereas antique coin-types, and also a
            rather wide range of purely artistic representations, generally have for subjects
            religious notions, myths, or events that were well known to the people and therefore
            readily suggested by a simple symbol.</p>
          <p>Any theory of the bars to be worthy of consideration must be free of these fundamental
            grounds of objection.</p>
          <note id="note_016"><ref target="ref_016" rend="super">¹</ref>I have to acknowledge
            regretfully that I have not had Bahrfeldt's paper to read, but have necessarily depended
            upon brief notices of his argument.</note>
          <note id="note_017"><ref target="ref_017" rend="super">²</ref> Many large bronze ingots
            have been found, 19 at Hagia Triada with an average weight of 29231.6 grammes, and 17 in
            the sea near Chalkis whose weights range from 5350 to 17000 grammes; while three
            Sardinian ingots, which were probably imported from Cyprus, are reported as averaging
            31233 grammes in weight. See Evans, <hi rend="i">Corolla Numismatica</hi>, p.
            358ff.</note>

        </div2>
        <pb id="VAB9263-021" n="21"/>

        <div2 type="section">
          <head>
            <hi rend="center">VI.</hi>
          </head>

          <p>On the basis of the artistic character of the types the extant bars may be classified
            into two groups, Greek bars and Italian bars. The former embraces the examples, nine in
            number, with types which are plainly the work of Greek artists; while the latter class
            includes all others, in whatever parts of Central Italy and Etruria they may have been
            produced.</p>
          <p>Now, since the former group are plainly the work of Greek artists there is that one
            good reason for looking to Greek communities for their origin. Moreover, this group is
            distinct from the other bars not only in respect to their utterly un-Roman types but
            also as regards their composition. It seems proper, therefore, that the possibility of
            their having originated in Greek communities should be exhausted before we accept any
            theory of them based upon the assumption of their Roman origin. And, since the bars have
            been found almost exclusively in Italy, it is the Greek cities of Southern Italy that
            claim first attention in the search for events that might explain the types of this
            group. So scanty, however, is our knowledge of the history of those Greek cities and so
            few the remains of them that an effort to connect these bar types with events in their
            history is bound to be attended by many difficulties. But a strong presumption will have
            been created in favor of such an origin for them if in case of even two or three bars it
            can be shown that we have the recognized coin-types or "arms" of some of those cities
            together with an assignable reason for their employment, or if one can find in the
            history of those Greek communities events which may reasonably be regarded as
            commemorated by other of the bar-types. It has, therefore seemed to me that efforts in
            that direction were well worth while, and some of the results of my researches are here
            offered.</p>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="center">TRIDENT-CADUCEUS BAR.<lb/>
              <hi rend="i">The Commercial Greatness of Tarentum.</hi><lb/> Plate I.</head>

            <p>This bar probably originated at Tarentum, but since it refers to no historical event
              datable within narrow limits it is impossible to determine where it belongs
              chronologically in the list of bars to be discussed. It may as well, however, be
              treated here, where for certain reasons it may also belong.</p>
            <p>The few attempts to explain the types of this bar have been so manifestly
              unsuccessful that special mention of any of them might well be <pb id="VAB9263-022"
                n="23"/> omitted; but the views of Dr. Haeberlin deserve notice because of the
              rather forced reasoning by which he endeavors to maintain his general theory of the
              bars and connect this one with a series of alleged Roman coins. For it is certainly a
              curious bit of logic that is employed to show that this bar was issued in conjunction
              with the heavy <hi rend="i">Janus-Mercury series</hi> of coins. In the first place, it
              is not in this instance the types of a silver Didrachm at the head of the series that
              determines the types of the bar, but the type, rather one of the types, of the large
              bronze <hi rend="i">As</hi>. That may not be important, yet elsewhere he seems to
              attach no little importance to the fact that the types of the Didrachm furnished the
              controlling idea for the bar-types. This series of bronze coins Dr. Haeberlin holds
              was issued at Rome. At the same time silver <hi rend="i">Quadrigati</hi> were being
              struck at the Capua mint; and certainly it is very remarkable in view of the
              application of the theory in other cases that the types of this bar issued at Capua
              should be brought into relation with the types of the heavy bronze <hi rend="i"
                >As</hi> issued from the mint at Rome and not with the types of the new silver
              Didrachm brought out at Capua! And even more remarkable is it that while the heavy
              bronze <hi rend="i">As</hi> bears a Janus head and the bar a trident, symbol of
              Neptune, two of the greater divinities, yet it is the lesser Mercury that furnishes
              the dominant idea of the coin and bar.</p>
            <p>Dr. Haeberlin's interpretation of the caduceus symbol of this bar is interesting.
              Mercury was the god of commerce, especially on land (?), and that commerce implied
              established domination of the country in which it was carried on; the caduceus,
              therefore, becomes a symbol of Rome's supremacy on land. <hi rend="i">"Merkurs Walten
                als Gottes des Verkehrs, wird im erster Linie auf den Verkehr des Landes bezogen und
                es symbolizirt daher der Caduceus nach italischer Denkweise die Herrschaft über das
                Land, die im Hinblick auf einen geregelten Verkehr als die befriedete Herrschaft zu
                Lande aufgefasst wird."</hi> The trident of Neptune on the other side of the bar,
              taken as a symbol of the lordship of the sea, supplements the idea expressed by the
              caduceus and rounds out the conception of Rome's lordship on land and sea. <hi
                rend="i">Er</hi> (Trident) <hi rend="i">bildet . . . auch der Idee nach . .. zu dem
                Zeigen Merkurs die ergänzende Parallele. Ausgedrückt sollte werden, dass ein
                dauernder Zustand geschaff en sei, indem Rom in gesamten ihm fortan unterstehenden
                Bereiche zu Land and zu See eine Herrschaft siegreich und zu dauerndem Frieden
                bergründet habe.</hi> Evidently the Romans must have been somewhat obsessed by that
              notion of their <hi rend="i">Herrschaft zur See</hi>, however the notion was
              conceived, <pb id="VAB9263-023" n="23"/> for Dr. Haeberlin finds it expressed again by
              the types of the <hi rend="i">Cocks-Rostra bar</hi>, a remarkable persistence in an
              idea that is, as I shall attempt to show in connection with the latter bar, purely
              mythical, and a very modern myth at that.</p>
            <p>This bar with the types of a trident and a caduceus alludes to the commercial
              greatness of Tarentum; and of Tarentum's proud position in the commerce of the
              Mediterranean there can be no dispute; while on the other hand there can be no doubt
              of the appropriateness of the two symbols on this bar to express the sentiments of the
              Tarentines regarding their prosperous commerce.</p>
            <p>There are a number of references among the ancient writers to the commercial
              greatness of Tarentum. Polybius in the first chapter of his tenth book draws attention
              to the splendid harbor and commanding position of that city as the chief entrepôt for
              the commerce between Greece proper, together with that of the Adriatic, and Italy;<ref
                id="ref_018" rend="super">¹</ref> and of course much of the exports of Italy were
              carried to Greece and to the eastern shores of the Mediterranean in the same bottoms
              that had brought wares to the emporium of Tarentum. Even in his own time the favorable
              position of Tarentum insured her a large commerce although it had been greatly reduced
              by the development of the port of Brundisium. Florus also has preserved the comment of
              probably another writer on the subject, yet it is similar in showing that Tarentum was
              the commercial centre of a vast region extending from the northern Adriatic to
                Africa.<ref id="ref_019" rend="super" target="note_019">²</ref> And the commercial
              position due to these natural advantages was in time strengthened by the course of
              events in other parts of Southern Italy. For soon after the middle of the fourth
              century B. C. the pressure of the native inland peoples upon the Greek colonies of
              Italy resulted in the capture of several cities on the western coast while those on
              the southern coast suffered the loss of valuable territory and being further menaced
              lost also their commerce which in some cases was very considerable. The <note
                id="note_018"><ref target="ref_018" rend="super">¹</ref>Polybius, X, 1: Bρέττιοι γὰρ
                καὶ Λευκανοὶ καὶ τινα μέρη των Δαυνίων, ἔτι δὲ Καλαβροὶ καὶ πλείουϛ ἕτεροι τουτο τὸ
                κλίμα νέμονται της Ἰταλίαϛ· ὀμοίωϛ δὲ καὶ των Ἑλληνίδων πόλεων Ῥήγιον καὶ Καυλωνία
                καὶ Λοκροὶ καὶ Κρότων, ἕτι δὲ Μεταπόντιοι καὶ ϴούριοι ταύτην ἐπέχουσι τὴν παραλίαν,
                ωστε καὶ τοὺϛ ἀπὸ Σικελίαϛ καὶ τοὺϛ ἀπὸ τηϛ Ἑλλάδοϛ ϕερομένουϛ ἐπί τινα τόπον των
                προειρημένων κατ' ἀνάγκην ὁρμέιν ἐν τοιϛ των Ταραντίνων λιμέσι, καὶ τὰϛ ἀμείψειϛ καὶ
                τὰϛ οἰκονομίαϛ πρὸϛ πάνταϛ τοὺϛ κατέχονταϛ ταύτην τὴν πλευρὰν τηϛ Ἰταλίαϛ ἐν ταύτη
                ποιεισθαι τη πόλει.... τέτακται δὲ καὶ πρὸϛ τοὺϛ κατὰ τὸν Ἀδρίαν λιμέναϛ εὐϕυωϛ καὶ
                νυν μέν, ἔτι δὲ μαλλον ᾖν πρὸ του (i. e. before founding of Brundisium), ἀπὸ γὰρ
                ἄκραϛ, Ἰαπυγίαϛ ἕωϛ εἰϛ Σιπουντα παϛ προσϕερόμενοϛ ἐκ των ἀντιπέραϛ καὶ καθορμισθεὶϛ
                πρὸϛ τὴν Ἰταλίαν εἰϛ Ταραντ' ἐποιειτο τὴν ὑπερβολήν, καὶ ταύτῃ συνεχρητο τῃ πόλει
                πρὸϛ τὰϛ ἀλλαγὰϛ καὶ μεταθέσειϛ οιον ἐμπορίῳ.</note>
              <note id="note_019"><ref target="ref_019" rend="super">²</ref> Florus, I, 18:--Cum
                magnitudine et muris portuque nobilis, tum mirabilis situ; quippe in ipsis Adriatici
                maris faucibus posita in omnes terras, Istriam, Illyriam, Epirum, Achaiam, Africam,
                Siciliam vela dimittit.</note>
              <pb id="VAB9263-024" n="24"/> ruin or weakening of these other Greek centers in Italy
              seems to have proved beneficial to the commerce of Tarentum, which at that period
              reached its greatest extent.<ref id="ref_020" rend="super" target="note_020"
              >¹</ref></p>
            <p>While her advantageous position and fine harbor had much to do with the development
              of Tarentum's commerce, yet, as is well known, an important factor was her large
              volume of exportable manufactures and products besides the grain, wine and oil, which
              other Greek communities in Italy and Sicily exported to the motherland and Asia Minor.
              Woolen fabrics from looms supplied by the flocks of Apulia, her world-renowned purple
              dyes, certain manufactures in bronze, her potteries, and the products of her
              fisheries, all combined produced a volume and variety of exports of which very few
              ancient cities could boast. From this extensive commerce the wealth of the city was
              derived, a wealth that had made Tarentum a city of great splendor and made possible a
              too luxurious manner of living.</p>
            <p>Now it was no uncommon practice for the Greeks and other peoples of antiquity to
              celebrate in one way or another the sources of their national wealth, usually with
              monuments or hymns in honor of the patron divinity. Many instances, too, are found of
              coin-types which plainly refer to the local products that formed the basis of the
              state's prosperity, a very notable instance being the sylphium-plant types on the
              coins of Cyrene. So it need occasion no surprise to find evidence that at least
              individual citizens of Tarentum saw in their very large and profitable commerce a just
              ground for pride and something worthy of commemoration. The city itself had done a
              similar thing when it had placed the horseman-types on the silver Staters in
              commemoration of its famous cavalry.</p>
            <p>The types of this bar well suit the idea suggested above. Taras, the son of Poseidon,
              had founded Tarentum and the god of the sea was regarded as the patron divinity of the
              city. This latter fact is officially signalized by a remarkable coin type issued soon
              after the middle of the fourth century B. C. in which the youthful Taras is
              represented as appealing to his father. Poseidon, probably on the eve of some crisis
              in state affairs; while Horace specifically mentions Neptune as the patron <note
                id="note_020"><ref target="ref_020" rend="super">¹</ref> Speck, <hi rend="i"
                  >Handelsgeschichte des Altertums</hi>, II, 467:--Das Griechentum (in Italy) wurde
                auf wenige Plätze eingeschränkt, die auch nur mit Mühe die Angriffe der Barbaren
                abwehrten. Nur Tarent machte eine Ausnahme in dem allgemeinen Verfall. Es erreichte
                im 4. Jahrh. die höchste Stufe seiner Macht. Sein vortrefflicher Hafen, der
                ergiebige Thunfischfang, die Wollweberei, die Purpurfärberei, die Vasenfabrikation
                zeitigten auch seine wirtschaftliche Blülte.</note>
              <pb id="VAB9263-025" n="25"/> divinity of Tarentum.<ref id="ref_021" rend="super"
                target="note_021">¹</ref> The trident of Poseidon, therefore, may quite properly be
              taken as an allusion to that city.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, the caduceus of Mercury, patron of merchants, on the other side of
              the brick almost certainly alludes, as had been before interpreted, to commerce; and
              in conjunction with the other facts recited above there is surely good ground to
              believe that it alludes to the flourishing commerce of Tarentum and not to the
              negligible trade of a subjugated small territory. The commerce of Tarentum was chiefly
              seaborne, with which fact the types of the trident and the caduceus are particularly
              consistent.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi rend="i">lemnisci</hi> or <hi rend="i">taeniae</hi> attached to the
              trident and the caduceus Dr. Haeberlin's confidence that they clinch the argument in
              favor of the view that the devices allude to a victory is hardly well grounded. By far
              the most common use of the <hi rend="i">vittae</hi> or <hi rend="i">lemnisci</hi> was
              to indicate a consecration; and that is not improbably the meaning of the ribbon and
              crown on the Romano-Campanian silver <hi rend="i">didrachm</hi> to which Dr. Haeberlin
              refers; for why should Victory be represented as attaching a symbol of victory to such
              a well-known emblem of victory as the palm-branch! As a sign of consecration the <hi
                rend="i">lemnisci</hi> or <hi rend="i">taeniae</hi> are frequently referred to. In
              this sense Suetonius refers to their use in marking the consecration of Nero's course
              through the city on his return to Rome from his sham artistic triumps in Greece (Nero,
              25); evidently Tacitus alludes to the very same things as we find on the coin referred
              to when he mentions the reconsecration of the ground on which Vespasian was about to
              rebuild the temple of Jupiter (Hist. IV, 53: <hi rend="i">omne spatium . . . evinctum
                vittis coronisque</hi>); while there are numerous allusions to the fact that they
              were worn by priests and priestesses, carried by suppliants, placed on altars and
              statues of deities, and on the thyrsus carried in the Dionysiac procession
              (Baumeister, Denkm. Abb. 1849).</p>
            <p>If the <hi rend="i">taeniae</hi> on this bar are not to be regarded as merely
              ornamental, it is most likely that they were meant as a sign of consecration, serving
              to indicate that the artist was employing the caduceus and trident with their
              appropriate religious and symbolic meaning and not simply as ornaments. Because the
              bricks possessed none of the qualities of coins, whose types were everywhere regarded
              as sacred, the use of such an emblem was the more necessary to give the types
              significance and render the meaning of the combination intelligible.</p>
            <note id="note_021"><ref target="ref_021" rend="super">¹</ref> Horace, <hi rend="i"
                >Od.</hi> I, 28, 29:--<hi rend="i">multaeque merces unde protest tibi deflat aequo
                ab Iove Neptunoque sacri custode Tarenti.</hi></note>


            <pb id="VAB9263-026" n="26"/>
            <milestone unit="typography" n="_____________________" rend="center"/>

            <p>In the case of the next bar as well as of two or three others the proposed
              explanations of the types point to political alliances, real or merely formal. And it
              so happens that Magna Graecia was the most fertile field of antiquity for military
              and, perhaps, monetary alliances;<ref id="ref_022" rend="super" target="note_022"
                >¹</ref> and, what is more important here, many of those alliances were commemorated
              on the coins of the contracting states. The reasons for these alliances are of course
              well known. For it was not long after the establishment of the Greek settlements on
              the South coast of Italy till the danger that for a century and a half threatened them
              from the interior made its appearance. As early as the middle of the sixth century B.
              C. they were driven into some kind of union for mutual help against the Lucanians and
              their other inland neighbors; and when wealth and power had been gained by some of the
              Greek cities, similar alliances were frequently formed by two or more for the
              protection against a more powerful Greek neighbor. Finally, toward the last of their
              careers as independent states, a number of alliances, as threatening to their
              liberties as helpful against the pressing danger, were contracted with foreign
              princes. It is not difficult, therefore, to realize that that feature of the public
              policy in each of these cities which had to do with its defensive alliances was a
              matter of greatest popular concern; for it involved the burning question of their
              welfare and, at a later period, of their liberties, too, as well as the political
              fortunes of individuals, and the historic cleavage between Doric Tarentum and Achaean
              Metapontum, Croton and Sybaris.</p>
            <p>So scanty are the annals which the historians have preserved of those cities that it
              is very unlikely that we have a complete record of the unions they formed; very many
              of their alliances are known, however, from the combined evidence of historians and
              the coins. The subjoined list, though almost certainly incomplete, of some of the
              better attested alliances, because in so many cases corroborated by coins, shows how
              deeply rooted the practice was in their history and gives us a background of
              interesting precedents for the explanations of certain of the Greek bars. For while
              these bars were never issued by the Greeks for use as money and were probably not
              issued by any State, yet the long standing practice of commemorating various sorts of
              international relations on the coins evidently exercised an influence upon the private
              persons who <note id="note_022"><ref target="ref_022" rend="super">¹</ref> Gardner,
                  <hi rend="i">Greek Coin Types</hi>, page 31.</note>
              <pb id="VAB9263-027" n="27"/> did produce the bars; and the result was a number of
              types that reflect important political events of the time. Instances of such
              coin-types are:</p>
            <list type="simple">
              <item>B. C. 550-480. General alliance of all the south Italian Greek cities. Attested
                by their coins with the obverse type repeated incuse on reverse. Within same period,
                and attested by coins of the contracting cities, were the alliances of : Croton and
                Sybaris. Croton and DA (ancle ?) <hi rend="i">i. e.</hi>, Messana. Croton and
                Terina. Poseidonia and Sybaris. Pyxus and Siris.</item>
              <item>B. C. 390-388. League of the Greek cities renewed under the leadership of
                Croton. Alliance coin, infant Heracles strangling two serpents.</item>
              <item>380-360. The League again renewed, under leadership of Archytas of Tarentum.
                Federal coinage, Attic obols with types of Athena and Heracles strangling Nemean
                lion.</item>
              <item>388-384. Archadamus of Sparta goes to Tarentum. Commemorated by stars of the
                Dioscuri as symbols on coins, the Dioscuri referring to Sparta.</item>
              <item>380. Alexander the Molossian, of Epirus, goes to assist the Italian Greeks.
                Macedonian type of Heracles head on gold coins.</item>
              <item>281. Confederation of Italian states in alliance with Pyrrhus. Commemorated by
                elephant symbol on Tarentine Staters.</item>
              <item>272. Greek cities come under Roman domination as <hi rend="i">civitates
                  foederatae</hi>. Commemorated by Locris on a Stater with Fides crowning
                Roma.</item>
            </list>

            <milestone unit="typography" n="_____________________" rend="center"/>
          </div3>


          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="center">THE TRIPOD AND BARLEYHEAD BAR.<lb/>
              <hi rend="i">Alliance Between Croton and Metapontum.</hi><lb/> Plate II.</head>

            <p>Dr. Haeberlin connects this bar with what he calls the Apollo-series of coins which
              the Romans are supposed to have issued from the mint at Capua. The series is composed
              of the silver Didrachm with types of Apollo-head and a horse and a partial series of
              four bronze coins of which the <hi rend="i">As</hi> has an Apollo-head on both sides.
              The tripod of Apollo on the bar furnishes the reason for connecting it with that
              series of coins. The types of the bar, however, seem to have no special meaning, real
              or fanciful, from a Roman point of view. That is specially true of the barley ear, of
              which no explanation has yet been offered. As to the tripod, thanks to the wide-spread
              cult of Apollo a coin-type with that symbol of the god can always be explained
              somehow, wherever it may be found. But, not only from the Roman point of view have the
              types of this bar no significance, the situation is not improved if the bar be
              regarded as Campanian in spirit and for use chiefly in Campania. For there seems to be
              no more warrant for the statement that the Apollo-type was specially favored in
              Campania than the claim elsewhere that the Pegasus-type is to be identified as the
              arms, <hi rend="i">Wappentier</hi>, of that country.</p>


            <pb id="VAB9263-028" n="28"/>

            <p>This bar bears devices that are identical with the long-established and well-known
              coin types of two cities of Magna Graecia. Since the middle of the sixth century the
              tripod had formed with rare exceptions the type of the coins of Croton, while the
              barley-ear had for the same long period appeared on the coins of Metapontum. This
              union of the recognized coin types, a sort of state arms, of those two cities on this
              one bar readily suggests the question as to whether the piece may not have been made
              to commemorate some event of common interest to those two cities. And obviously the
              question would be of an alliance between Croton and Metapontum. Now, a particular
              alliance between those two cities is not, I believe, recorded by ancient historians,
              nor is one with certainty commemorated on their coins. But this lack of such records
              does not prove conclusively that no alliance was ever contracted between them. For not
              all the monetary unions and defensive leagues of those states left numismatic
              monuments, while some that did affect the coinage are not mentioned by the writers.
              Was there, then, a critical period in the affairs of the Greek states on the southern
              coast of Italy when their ancient institution of the defensive league became necessary
              and would concern chiefly these two Achaean cities?</p>
            <p>If there was a situation of that sort, it was most likely toward the very end of the
              fourth century. For soon after the campaign of Alexander the Molossian, B. C. 330-328,
              the political situation in Magna Graecia became substantially as follows. The Greek
              cities of the western coast and inland had been captured by the Lucanians and
              Bruttians, while the cities of the southern coast were being hard pressed by the same
              enemies. Locris had been detached from the rest of the Greek towns and was somewhat
              protected by its relations with Syracuse. The difficulties which Alexander had had
              with the jealous and suspicious Tarentines had induced him to rebuke that city in
              various ways; thus he had made a treaty of alliance with Metapontum--perhaps, too,
              with Croton at the same time; he had removed the synod of the League from Tarentine
              control at Heraclea and had established it in Thurian territory. One of the chief
              results of these measures was that from the intervention of Alexander the Molossian
              until the time of Pyrrhus, Tarentum was not an active member of any union with the
              Achaean cities.</p>
            <p>The check which the Italian campaigns of Alexander had administered to the forward
              movement of the Lucanians and Bruttians was not of long duration, and what respite
              from aggression it did give the Greek cities was felt chiefly by Tarentum. The
              assaults, however, soon became <pb id="VAB9263-029" n="29"/> specially strong at two
              points--against Metapontum and against Croton. This was due directly to the
              geographical position of the former, in a rich territory on the gulf of Tarentum, and
              to the power and dominating position of the latter. F. Lenormant draws a similar
              picture of the position of these two cities in respect to this danger: La Grande
              Grece, I, p. 130--<hi rend="i">"La poussée des Lucaniens contre les villes grecques
                devenait chaque jour plus forte. Avec Thurioi, c'était Metaponte a qui sa position
                geographique en faisait recevoir le premier choc,"</hi> and Vol. II, p. 128--<hi
                rend="i">"Mais la principal objectif de leurs (les Bruttiens) attaques fut toujours
                Crotone, cornmme Héraclée et Thurioi avaient été des Lucaniens. C'était la grande
                ville dont la possession aurait doublé leur puissance et leur aurait permis de se
                créer une marine militaire."</hi></p>
            <p>In 319 B. C. the position of the Crotons, who were besieged by the Bruttians, became
              so desperate that an appeal to Syracuse was made. It is in that period, sometime
              between 330 and 320, when the two chief Achaean cities fronted alone the attacks of
              the Lucanians and Bruttians, that the alliance to which the bar evidently alludes may
              have been made. Nor is this conjecture entirely unsupported by evidence. For on silver
              Staters issued at Croton in the period from 330 to 300 B. C. a barley-ear is found as
              a symbol on the reverse, which M. de Foville<ref id="ref_023" rend="super"
                target="note_023">¹</ref> interprets as probably an allusion to an alliance between
              Croton and Metapontum. And far more suggestive of an alliance between these cities, if
              not convincing proofs of one, are the types of certain coins struck by Metapontum in
              about the same period. One of these is a small silver piece<ref id="ref_024"
                rend="super" target="note_024">²</ref> with reverse type consisting of a barley head
              and a tripod, the latter device being of the same size as the former and not a minor
              type or symbol in the field. Another is a small bronze coin with the barleyhead on the
              obverse and the tripod on the reverse<ref id="ref_025" rend="super" target="note_025"
                >³</ref>. This latter piece has in fact been explained by Minervini as the product
              of such an alliance as is here in question.</p>
            <p>However strong the objections may be to the view that these coin types contain
              allusions to an actual alliance between Croton and Metapontum, it will hardly be
              disputed that they are noteworthy evidence of close political relations between the
              two cities.</p>
            <p>And just such cordial relations established between Croton and Metapontum under
              stress of a common danger, and not necessarily a <note id="note_023"><ref
                  target="ref_023" rend="super">¹</ref>
                <hi rend="i">Revue Numis.</hi> 1908, p. 8 See, however, <hi rend="i">Numismatic
                  Chronicle</hi> 1916, p. 214, where Mr. S. W. Gross gives his reasons for doubting
                that interpretation.</note>
              <note id="note_024"><ref target="ref_024" rend="super">²</ref> Garrucci, <hi rend="i"
                  >Mon. d. Italia ant.</hi>, Tav. CIV, No. 21.</note>
              <note id="note_025"><ref target="ref_025" rend="super">³</ref> Ibid., Tav. CV, No.
                30.</note>
              <pb id="VAB9263-030" n="30"/> political alliance, would be an event of a sort and
              sufficient to explain the association of their respective arms, the tripod and
              barleyhead, on this bar. The absence of inscriptions of any sort is not a serious
              omission. On no other of these bars was an inscription less requisite to explain its
              origin and meaning than on this one; for the devices were well known in Southern Italy
              in relation to Croton and Metapontum, and equally well known was the significance of
              their appearance together on a coin or on such a piece as this bar.</p>
            <p>The question of the place where the bar may have had its origin, whether at Croton or
              Metapontum, can hardly be answered, nor is it of much importance; while the inevitable
              questions relating to its issue, whether by public authority or private enterprise,
              and also to its use, will be discussed below.</p>
          </div3>

          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="center">HOG-ELEPHANT BAR.<lb/>
              <hi rend="i">The Alliance Between the Italian States and Pyrrhus for the War with
                Rome.</hi><lb/> Plate III.</head>

            <p>It is very generally accepted that the types of this brick refer in some way to the
              war between the Romans and the Italian States aided by Pyrrhus. This conviction is due
              chiefly, it seems, to the representation of an elephant on the piece; for the
              elephants brought to Italy by Pyrrhus were, so far as we know, the first with which
              the Romans had to deal in battle, and it is stated specifically that those captured at
              Beneventum and later brought to Rome were the first elephants ever seen by the Roman
              populace. Such capital events certainly justify the conclusion that somehow the
              elephant type alludes to the military force brought to Italy by the king of Epirus and
              possibly to some particular engagement with that force. But however obvious the
              general events to which the types of the brick may allude seem to be, yet the
              particular way in which the elephant and hog are to be interpreted as having reference
              to the war with Pyrrhus has not been shown to be so obvious.</p>
            <p>Without any objection, so far as I know, the types have been explained as alluding to
              a catastrophe at the battle of Asculum. According to a legend<ref id="ref_026"
                rend="super" target="note_026">¹</ref> the Romans took advantage of their thorough
              knowledge of certain idiosyncrasies of the elephant--an animal, as stated before, with
              which hitherto they had had nothing to do, at least in battle--and resorted to the
              strategem of introducing hogs into their battle-front and <note id="note_026"><ref
                  target="ref_026" rend="super">¹</ref> Aelian <hi rend="i">De Nat. Animal.</hi> I,
                38; quoted by Garrucci.</note>
              <pb id="VAB9263-031" n="31"/> the grunting of these hogs caused the elephants to
              stampede and trample down their own lines. The result of this debacle was a brilliant
              victory for the Romans: <hi rend="i">ή νίκη σΰν τoìς Ρωμαíοις λαμπρώς έγένετο</hi>.
                Milani<ref id="ref_027" rend="super" target="note_027">¹</ref> accepts this
              interpretation, but with the interesting addition that the Romans meant to imply a
              hint to the Tarentines of the contempt in which they held the dangerous military
              elephant.</p>
            <p>Now, I do not understand that Garrucci, Haeberlin, nor anybody else who has accepted
              this explanation of the types necessarily regards the tradition of the
              elephant-stampede at Asculum as authentic. Mr. Hill in particular speaks guardedly of
              it, suggesting that the story may have been of later invention "inspired by the types
              of the 'brick' "; but Dr. Haeberlin is certainly less cautious, evidently believing
              that the tradition arose immediately after the battle and confidently states that the
              types allude to the stampede and that the brick was issued in 273 B. C., the date when
              the four elephants captured at Beneventum in 275 were led in triumph at Rome.<ref
                id="ref_028" rend="super" target="note_028">²</ref> Accepting the existence of the
              story at so early a date as B. C. 273, or but seven years after the battle, does not,
              however, imply a belief that there was any basis in fact for the tale. Similarly there
              can be no question about a story of "The Angels of Mons" just after the battle at that
              place (1914), but there is likewise no question that the story was fictitious. More
              than one ancient coin-type represents an artistically wrought out but baseless legend;
              such legends, however, generally belonged to the already remote and somewhat shadowy
              past of the issuing State and there was, at the time the coin-types were engraved, an
              uncritical and quasi-religious faith in the stories.</p>
            <p>But the case in question is very different and one in which the facts back of the
              story cannot be neglected, particularly by those who maintain that the bar was issued
              by the Roman government. For in that case it is implied that the piece was meant
              incidentally to commemorate an action that was immediately or eventually favorable to
              the Romans; and several writers plainly hold that the bar was intended to celebrate
              the final triumph of the Romans over Pyrrhus. In that view the Roman government must
              be supposed to have claimed a victory in the battle of Asculum, or at least to have
              succeeded by means of a clever stratagem in stampeding the elephants in the army of
              Pyrrhus, and the achievement was regarded as worthy not only of record but of
              symbolizing their complete <note id="note_027"><ref target="ref_027" rend="super"
                  >¹</ref><hi rend="i">Rivista Ital.</hi> 1891, p. 81--... i Romani fecero intendere
                sarcasticamente a chi non P'avrebbero voluto sapere ai Tarentini che a cacciare lo
                spauracchio dei magni elefanti asiatici di Pirro, bastava il grugnito della
                leggendaria scrofa di Roma.</note>
              <note id="note_028"><ref target="ref_028" rend="super">²</ref>Haeberlin, <hi rend="i"
                  >Systematik</hi>, p. 54.</note>
              <pb id="VAB9263-032" n="32"/> triumph over the powerful ally of the Italian
              confederation; for otherwise we must conclude that the Roman government sanctioned,
              for no discernible reason, an apocryphal story, and that, too, almost immediately
              following the supposed event. But the fact is that there is no trustworthy evidence
              either of a victory at Asculum or of a debacle in the lines of the allies. For from
              the dependable accounts of that battle, both ancient and modern, with special
              reference to Prof. Mommsen's among the latter, two or three facts stand out
              prominently. These are, that from the Roman point of view it was at best something
              less than a rout, at worst something more than a technical victory for Pyrrhus; for
              the Romans fled from the field to their strongly fortified camp where they evidently
              expected and prepared for an attack, while Pyrrhus remained in full possession of the
              battle ground. And as to the story of the eleplant-stampede, alleged to have been
              occasioned by a clever strategem, it is impossible to believe that, had it occurred or
              been mentioned by an early writer of any trustworthiness whatever, the later annalists
              and historians would have failed to make much of it. That they do not seem to have
              done; and Professor Mommsen evidently found no ground for crediting the tale and does
              not mention it in his account of the battle. In fact he takes an altogether different
              view of the part performed by the elephants in that battle; for he says: "It was not
              till the numerous escort of the elephants had, with arrows and stones hurled from
              slings, dislodged the combatants stationed in the Roman war-chariots and had cut the
              traces of the horses, and the elephants pressed upon the Roman line, that it began to
              waver. The giving way of the guard attached to the Roman chariots formed the signal
              for universal flight, which however, did not involve the sacrifice of many lives, as
              the adjoining camp received the fugitives."</p>
            <p>On the other hand, assuming that, although no such disaster took place within the
              lines of the coalition, yet a story that it did occur was spread about by the Romans
              to conceal the facts of their defeat and that the story was credited, it is still
              impossible to believe that the Roman government would have made use of such an
              unauthentic tale for the subject of types of such a commemorative piece, especially at
              a time when the facts about the battle of Asculum were very fresh in the minds of all
              informed citizens.<ref id="ref_029" rend="super" target="note_029">¹</ref> For these
              reasons it is quite impossible to accept the usual interpretation of the types of this
              brick and retain <note id="note_029"><ref target="ref_029" rend="super">¹</ref>It is
                not unlikely that the dramatic description of an elephant-stampede in battle was one
                of the stock themes of the schools; and Aelian employed the theme for practice in
                writing Greek.</note>
              <pb id="VAB9263-033" n="33"/> one's well-founded respect for the good taste and sane
              judgment of the Romans in the matters respecting a proper pride in their national
              history.</p>
            <p>The interpretation of the types which I venture to suggest, would, if found
              acceptable, remove the brick from any direct connection with Rome, and, of course,
              from all connection with the Roman or any other monetary system. Beginning with what I
              regard as properly the reverse type of the brick, the accepted belief that the
              elephant alludes to the advent of the Epirote king and his army in Italy as an ally of
              the confederation of Italian States against Rome is so well grounded that probably
              none would dispute it. That momentous event was commemorated on at least three issues
              of Tarentine Staters by means of an elephant-symbol in the field, showing that the
              elephant was regarded as the proper symbol of the Epirote army. But it is the sow that
              furnishes the proof for connecting the types of this brick with the alliance between
              Pyrrhus and the Italian coalition.</p>

            <figure>
              <p>Fig. 1.</p>
            </figure>

            <p>A rational and dignified explanation of the hog-type is found in the old Italian
              ceremony of sacrificing a young sow when making a treaty of alliance (foedus). In the
              artistic representation of that ceremony on certain issues of coins, of which the
              denarii with the oath-scene issued during the Social War are specially instructive
              examples, a pig is held by a young man, while representatives of the high contracting
              parties stand with swords pointing toward the animal, probably meant to be resting
              upon the head of the victim, and thus take the solemn oath. It is probably such a
              representation, very likely on a coin, that Cicero had in mind and perhaps before his
              eyes when he wrote the passage in <hi rend="i">De Inventione II, 91: In eo foedere
                quod factum est quondam cum Samnitibus, quidam adulescens nobilis porcum sustinuit
                iussu imperatoris;</hi><ref id="ref_030" rend="super" target="note_030">¹</ref> for
              the institution had apparently become obsolete after the complete conquest of the
              Italic states by Rome. (Fig. 1.)</p>
            <note id="note_030"><ref target="ref_030" rend="super">¹</ref>See also Livy I, 24 and
              Varro De R. R, II, 4.</note>


            <pb id="VAB9263-034" n="34"/>

            <p>The pig which was sacrificed in the religious ceremony that was observed to make a
                <hi rend="i">foedus</hi> binding upon all parties was thus the central object of the
              final act with which the treaty of alliance was consummated and made effective. The
              appropriateness, therefore, of the pig as a symbol of the resulting alliance or of the
              allied powers is hardly open to dispute.</p>
            <p>When the coalition was formed for the great struggle with Rome the power of the
              Italic states predominated and so there is little room to doubt that when the treaty
              of alliance was made that treaty was solemnized by the Italic and not by the Greek
              rite. The pig on this brick is, therefore, to be understood as a symbol of the
              alliance among the Italian states; and in conjunction with the elephant for a reverse
              type the wider alliance between the coalition on the one hand and king Pyrrhus on the
              other is appropriately symbolized.</p>
            <p>An objection to this interpretation will perhaps be made on the ground that the
              animal represented on the bar is a sow, while nearly all writers employ the masculine
              form <hi rend="i">(porcus)</hi> of the word in discussing the old Italian ceremony of
              making treaties of alliance; and especially since Servius states definitely that
              Vergil had made a mistake in calling the pig employed as a victim for this ceremony a
                sow<ref id="ref_031" rend="super" target="note_031">¹</ref>--<hi rend="i">Comment.,
                ad Aen. l. e., falso autem ait "porca"; nam ad hoc genus sacrificii porcus
                adhibatur.</hi> But Vergil's antiquarian knowledge is generally trustworthy, and in
              this case he is corroborated by the representations on coins. For on the <hi rend="i"
                >denarii</hi> struck by the confederates during the Social War where the sex of the
              pig is determinable it is found to be a sow; and Garrucci so describes it:<hi rend="i"
                > una porchetta, Mon. della Italia,</hi> p. 105, and Tav. XCI, 1-3. The masculine
              form porcus, on which alone Servius may have based his criticism, is of common gender,
              and so used for "pig" without any notion of the sex.<ref id="ref_032" rend="super"
                target="note_032">²</ref> Furthermore it was a young pig that was used for the
              ceremony as is certainly shown both from the representation on the Denarius and by
              Vergil's other allusion to the sacrifice in <hi rend="i">Aen.</hi> XII, 170:</p>
            <q rend="blockquote"><hi rend="i right">Sacerdos</hi><lb/>
              <hi rend="i left">Saetegerae foetum suis intonsamque bidentem Attulit.</hi></q>
            <p>And it is a young sow that is represented on this bar, the proportions, <note
                id="note_031"><ref target="ref_031" rend="super">¹</ref><hi rend="i">Aen.</hi> VIII.
                638, . . <hi rend="i">et caesa iungebant foedera porca.</hi></note>
              <note id="note_032"><ref target="ref_032" rend="super">²</ref> Varro, de R. R. II, 4,
                13, <hi rend="i">scrofa alat suos porcus, and in the singular with a qualifying
                  word: Cic. de Leg. II, 22, 57, porco femina piaculum.</hi></note>
              <pb id="VAB9263-035" n="35"/> however, suited to the artistic requirements of a figure
              that should fill the large field of the brick.</p>
            <p>If the above interpretation of the types of this brick be correct, then there can be
              little doubt that the piece had its origin in one of the Greek cities of southern
              Italy, in one of the members of the alliance during the war with Rome when Pyrrhus was
              their ally. It is impossible to state just where it originated, for a brick with such
              types might have appeared in any of the cities that participated in the treaty of
              confederation for the prosecution of the war. But the most probable place of origin is
              Tarentum. Tarentum was the chief State of the Italian allies, it was the Tarentines
              that had taken the lead in securing the aid of Pyrrhus, and it was at that city that
              the king landed his army and established his headquarters.</p>
            <p>The reasons for commemorating the alliance between the Italian coalition and Pyrrhus
              are not so very far to seek. The motive is to be found in the great enthusiasm which
              the arrival of such a powerful army and resourceful general aroused throughout the
              countries that hoped at last to check the rising power of Rome and retain or recover
              their liberties. There was little doubt that the destruction of the Roman domination
              in the conquered states of the South would speedily follow. In these circumstances it
              was natural that poet, painter, and sculptor should be aroused to celebrate in their
              respective ways this promising turn of affairs. And in this brick we have probably but
              one of many examples of commonplace objects which in one way or another reflected the
              enthusiasm of the hour.</p>
          </div3>

          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="center">THE EAGLE-PEGASUS BAR.<lb/>
              <hi rend="i">Offensive and Defensive League Between Rome and Carthage.</hi><lb/> Plate
              IV.</head>
            <p>The types of this brick have proved exceedingly difficult to explain; and the problem
              they present has not been made easier, as might be expected, by the fact that the
              eagle and fulmen type was apparently a distinctive Roman emblem, as it certainly was
              in later times, and also by the presence of the legend ROMANOM which seemed to some
              writers to determine the origin of the piece very definitely and fix it beyond doubt
              as an issue of the Roman government. For the ground given by those plain indications
              at once became insecure when the investigator turned to the other side of the bar and
              attempted to explain the pegasus-type; for the latter no rational explanation has yet
              been found,</p>

            <pb id="VAB9263-036" n="36"/>

            <p>Now the eagle and fulmnen type does indeed seem to have reference to Roman
              sovereignty and so it has been generally accepted, though somewhat cautiously because,
              as Mr. Hill suggests,<ref id="ref_033" rend="super" target="note_033">¹</ref>that
              meaning may be of later origin. As to the pegasus-type, several theories have been
              advanced to explain it and justify its presence on a supposed Roman bar in conjunction
              with the eagle. Thus Professor Milani suggested that it was a sort of type parlant
              alluding to the invincible Roman cavalry: . . . . <hi rend="i">imagine parlante della
                insuperabile rapidità e potenza della cavalleria romana, la quale l'ha infatti
                adottato più tardi per proprio vessillo.</hi><ref id="ref_034" rend="super"
                target="note_034">²</ref> Such a flight of fancy is certainly very interesting and
              worthy of the subject! Yet not much less fanciful is the view of Dr. Haeberlin that
              the pegasus is to be understood as the arms of Campania--"<hi rend="i">das Wappentier
                Campanienis.</hi>"<ref id="ref_035" rend="super" target="note_035">³</ref> He offers
              no reasons for connecting pegasus with Campania in such a manner; whereas, if among
              the monuments of Campania one were to search for what might be considered to have been
              an armorial emblem of that country he would very likely decide upon the well-known
              man-headed bull which occurs so often on coins of Campanian cities; and he certainly
              would be cautious about pronouncing in favor of such an object as pegasus, the myth of
              which was so very widely spread and which appears upon the coins and other monuments
              of so many Greek settlements. It is, indeed, difficult to find any evidence that might
              warrant Dr. Haeberlin's interpretation of this interesting type.</p>
            <p>With that view, however, of the pegasus-type on this bar Dr. Haeberlin proceeds to a
              most ingenious explanation of the bar as a whole. The types of the piece, he holds,
              allude to the final conquest of Campania by Rome, an event definitely consummated and
              best marked by the completion of the military Via Appia in B. C. 312. Commemorative of
              the completion of that highway the <hi rend="i">Wheel-series</hi> of heavy bronze
              coins was issued by Rome from the Capuan mint and in connection therewith this bar
              with the eagle-pegasus types. This bar is, therefore, the first of the nine forming
              his "Romano-Campanian" group. Since this interpretation of the bar depends wholly upon
              the unproved assumption that pegasus was the <hi rend="i">Wappentier</hi> of Campania
              one could not feel very secure about its correctness; and since there is good reason
              to believe that the assumption is utterly wrong, for that reason, if for no others,
              the Haeberlin explanation would have to be rejected. <note id="note_033"><ref
                  target="ref_033" rend="super">¹</ref> Hill, G. F., <hi rend="i">Hist. Roman
                  Coins</hi>, p. 14, ftn. 1.</note>
              <note id="note_034"><ref target="ref_034" rend="super">²</ref><hi rend="i">Rivista
                  Ital.</hi>, 1891, p. 70.</note>
              <note id="note_035"><ref target="ref_035" rend="super">³</ref><hi rend="i"
                  >Systematik</hi>, p. 32.</note></p>


            <pb id="VAB9263-037" n="37"/>

            <p>As to the inscription ROMANOM Dr. Haeberlin accepts, and his general theory of the
              bars naturally reinforces, the view that it is the official ethnic name; and he
              explains the presence of the inscription on the side that bears the alleged arms of
              Campania by saying that thus it was meant to express graphically that Campania had
              become entirely Roman territory.</p>
            <p>The significance and great importance that have generally been attached to this
              inscription have been discussed above and certain objections to the theory stated. A
              reason for its occurrence on the reverse of the bar will be suggested below.</p>
            <p>The explanation of the types of this brick about to be suggested is so utterly at
              variance with the views of the many able writers who have discussed it, writers whose
              great learning and acumen will always be entitled to the highest esteem, that I
              hesitate to advance it, and I should feel even greater diffidence were it not that the
              views which have been given are not supported by substantial proofs and also that
              other scholars of equal authority have been unable to accept them. For the explanation
              here proposed does not find the meaning of the types in the conquest of Campania nor
              in any other Roman conquest, nor in the Roman government the authority that issued the
              bar.</p>
            <p>The eagle-and-fulmen type of the obverse of this bar with much probability refers to
              Rome in some way; and apparently it is an emblem of Roman power and sovereignty, a
              sovereignty that had been extended and was, at the time this bar was made, upheld
              wholly by the Roman armies. It cannot, perhaps, be definitely proved that this was a
              recognized symbol of Roman power in the early part of the third century B. C., the
              period in which I propose to date the bar, but the eagle-and-fulmen occurs as a
              coin-type on bronze coins issued by certain Italian cities under Roman domination
              before the end of the third century, so that it seems very probable, indeed, that it
              had become established as a symbol of Rome at a much earlier date, and very likely as
              early as the beginning of that century, perhaps earlier.</p>
            <p>In the article on <hi rend="i">Pegasus</hi> in Roscher's Lexicon, p. 1743, occurs the
              very important statement that a horse, either with or without wings, was an emblem on
              Punic ships; <hi rend="i">ein einfaches oder geflügeltes Ross ist ja das Zeichen
                punischer Schiffe, doch gehört es als solches wahrscheinlich unter den symbolischen
                Figuren der Phöniker.</hi> The horse emblem in some form--hippocamp, wingless horse
              or pegasus--on Phoenician and Punic ships must have been familiar to seafaring peoples
              throughout the <pb id="VAB9263-038" n="38"/> Mediterranean. Strabo states, for
              instance, that small trading ships from the Phoenician city of Gadira were called <hi
                rend="i">horses (ΐπποı)</hi> because they bore effigies of horses on their
                prows.<ref id="ref_036" rend="super">¹</ref></p>
            <p>The pegasus-type was placed on the reverse of the brick by an Italian Greek as an
              emblem of the Carthaginian sea power. The horse on Punic ships and on the ships of
              other Phoenician colonies may not have been a winged pegasus, but a Greek was quite
              certain to recognize in even the well-known wingless horse of Carthage the same
              mythical animal, the offspring of Poseidon, that he knew as the winged pegasus; and
              they may have been the same, for originally the Greek pegasus was a wingless creature.
              And in the course of the third century, probably, however, as Mr. Head states, in the
              period between the First and Second Punic Wars, a winged horse (pegasus?) was employed
              by the Carthaginians for the type of a large silver Duodekadrachm, while in the same
              period a Dekadrachm was struck with the type of the wingless horse. Evidently,
              therefore, the myth of a winged pegasus was being gradually localized at Carthage in
              the third century.</p>
            <p>This evidence is of unmistakable importance in connection with the types of this
              brick. For if an historical reason can be found for uniting on such a thing as a coin
              or a bar like the one under consideration such devices as the eagle and fulmen,
              symbolical of Roman power, which was mainly a military power, and the pegasus,
              symbolical of the Carthaginian sea-power, a rational and perhaps a correct explanation
              of the types will have been gained. And such a reason clearly exists. For Livy states
              that in B. C. 279 Rome for the fourth time renewed a treaty of alliance with the
                Carthaginians.<ref id="ref_037" rend="super">²</ref> The texts of these four
              treaties are given by Polybius, the fourth<ref id="ref_038" rend="super">³</ref> of
              which has special reference to the struggle with a number of Italic nations and
              western Greeks, then led by Pyrrhus, in which Rome and Carthage had a common interest,
              and felt the menace of a common danger should Pyrrhus succeed in building up a
              powerful Greek empire in the West. Mommsen in his History of Rome (Vol. II, page 28)
              discusses this treaty in extenso: <q rend="blockquote">"The immediate effect, indeed,
                of this union of the Italian and Sicilian Greeks under one control was a closer
                concert also <note id="note_036"><ref target="ref_036" rend="super">¹</ref> Strabo,
                  II, 3, 4: -- Τούτων (Γαδειριτων) γὰρ τοὺϛ μὲν ἐμπόρουϛ μεγάλα στέλλειν πλοια, τοὺϛ
                  δὲ πένηταϛ μικρά, ἄ καλειν ἵππουϛ ἀπὸ των ἐν ταιϛ πρῳραιϛ ἐπισήμων.</note>
                <note id="note_037"><ref target="ref_037" rend="super">²</ref> Livy, <hi rend="i"
                    >Epit</hi>. <hi rend="i">Lib</hi>. XIII. Cum Carthaginiensibus quarto foedus
                  renovatum est.</note>
                <note id="note_038"><ref target="ref_038" rend="super">³</ref>Polybius, III, 25: --
                  ἐὰν συμμαχίαν ποιωνται πρὸϛ ΙΙύῤῥον, ἔγγραπτον ποιείσθωσαν ἀμϕότεροι, ἵνα ἐξῃ
                  βοηθειν ἀλλήλοιϛ ἐν τῃ των πολεμουμένων χώρᾳ · ὁπότεροι δ΄ ἂν χρείαν ἔχωσι τηϛ
                  βοηθείαϛ, τὰ πλοια παρεχέτωσαν Καρχηδόνοι καὶ εἰϛ τὴν ὁδὸν καὶ εἰϛ τὴν ἔϕοδον, τὰ
                  δὲ ὀψώνια τοιϛ αὑτων ἑκάτεροι. Καρχηδόνοι δὲ καὶ κατὰ θάλατταν Ρωμαίοιϛ
                  βοηθείτωσαν, ἄν χρεία ῃ. τὰ δὲ πληρώματα μηδεὶϛ ἀναγκαζέτω ἐκβαίνειν
                  ἀκουσίωϛ.</note>
                <pb id="VAB9263-039" n="39"/> on the part of their antagonists. <hi rend="i"
                  >Carthage and Rome now converted their old commercial treaties into an offensive
                  and defensive league against Pyrrhus</hi>, the tenor of which was that, if Pyrrhus
                invaded Roman or Carthaginian territory, the party which was not attacked should
                furnish that which was assailed with a contingent on its own territory and should
                defray the expense of the auxiliary troops; <hi rend="i">that in such event Carthage
                  should be bound to furnish transports and to assist the Romans also with a war
                  fleet</hi>, but the crews of that fleet should not be obliged to fight for the
                Romans by land; that lastly, both states should pledge themselves not to conclude a
                separate peace with Pyrrhus. The object of the Romans in entering into the treaty
                was to render possible an attack on Tarentum and to cut off Pyrrhus from his own
                country, neither of which ends could be attained without the coöperation of the
                Punic fleet; the object of the Carthaginians was to detain the king in Italy, so
                that they might be able without molestation to carry into effect their designs on
                Syracuse."</q> (The Italics are mine.)</p>

            <p>This treaty went into effect immediately after it was concluded, and concerted action
              between the Carthaginian fleet and the Romans proceeded at once; for Prof. Mommsen
              adds: "A powerful Carthaginian fleet of 120 sail under the admiral Mago proceeded from
              Ostia, whither Mago seems to have gone to conclude the treaty, to the Sicilian
              Straits."</p>
            <p>Here, then, is an event of capital importance involving Rome and Carthage, and
              involving them in such a manner that it might be very appropriately commemorated by
              means of just such a monument as this bar with a Roman eagle on one side and the
              Carthaginian horse or pegasus on the other. The suitability of the types to the event
              is quite beyond question, a fact however that does not definitely settle the question
              of the explanation of the bar; it does justify the suggestion that such might be the
              correct explanation and also the hope that further investigation may produce better
              evidence that the types of the bar do allude to that treaty. This suggestion is
              further supported by the inscription on the brick!</p>
            <p>For if the meaning that has been suggested for the types should prove correct, the
              interpretation of the inscription ROMANOM on the reverse is not far to seek. If a hint
              of how it should be read were necessary, that hint would be given by the inscription
              on a Roman Aureus <pb id="VAB9263-040" n="40"/> struck by the monneyer C. Antestius
              Reginus in B. C. 18, (Bab. Antestia, No. 17). The reverse type of that Aureus alludes
              to the treaty with the Gabini and the inscription reads, <q rend="blockquote">FOEDVS P
                  (<hi rend="i">opuli</hi>). R(<hi rend="i">omami</hi>) QVM GABINIS</q> and if the
              inscription on the bar be expanded, with the help of the meaning expressed by the
              types, according to the form given on the later coin, it would read, <q
                rend="blockquote"><hi rend="sc">FOEDVS</hi> R O M A N 0 M <hi rend="sc">CVM
                  CARTHAGINIENSIBVS</hi>.</q></p>

            <p>It is doubtless unnecessary to repeat that the word ROMANOM is a genitive plural
              form. Whether it is an alternate form of ROMANO found on certain silver coins, that
              is, whether the two forms were in use in the same place and at the same time, is open
              to question.</p>
            <p>Assuming that the above explanation of the bar is correct the question naturally
              arises as to the time and place of its origin. Of course the Haeberlin theory that it
              was made in B. C. 312, or very soon thereafter, would be proved erroneous--in fact the
              whole ingenious <hi rend="i">Systematik</hi> collapses if one or two of those bricks
              should be torn from the structure. The bar was probably made very soon after the
              political events of B. C. 279, which inspired the choice of the types, and very
              likely, though not necessarily, before the relations between the Romans and
              Carthaginians became strained, preceding the outbreak of The First Punic War. This <hi
                rend="i">terminus ante quem</hi> might be considered settled if the brick had been
              issued by the State; but it is not so certain, though probable, if the piece was of
              private origin.</p>
            <p>And certainly the question whether the bar was, as Haeberlin holds, after all issued
              by the Roman government as a sort of commemorative piece must be answered in the
              negative. For although there is much evidence that the practice of commemorating
              events of public and private importance had become established among the Romans long
              before the date suggested for this brick, yet it is improbable that the Romans would
              thus honor an alliance that was dictated by necessity with a nation that was even then
              an object of their contemptuous hatred. For this reason and other considerations which
              I shall state further on it seems probable that the piece was the product of private
              enterprise.</p>
            <p>The place of production cannot be determined with any greater degree of certainty
              than the character of the authority that was responsible for the piece, but I venture
              to suggest that it was at Venusia where a large Roman colony had been established (B.
              C. 292) and which was <pb id="VAB9263-041" n="41"/> within the immediate vicinity of
              the stirring events of the war with Pyrrhus and the coalition. The Roman colonists and
              Greek exiles at Venusia were in a position to be acquainted with the drift of affairs
              at Tarentum, especially to know of the great hopes of victory the coming of the
              Epirote had inspired. It is also by no means impossible that the hog-and-elephant bar,
              which the consummation of the alliance and the arrival of Pyrrhus had brought forth,
              had become known at Venusia and in response to the boast thus implied this bar was
              produced alluding to the more than counterbalancing alliance between Rome and
              Carthage.</p>
          </div3>

          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="center">THE TRIPOD AND ANCHOR BAR.<lb/>
              <hi rend="i"/>Croton's Participation in the First Punic War.<lb/> Plate V.</head>
            <p>This bar is discussed to considerable length by Milani in his paper on the <hi
                rend="i">aes rude</hi> and <hi rend="i">aes signatum</hi> of the important find at
              Bruna. He endeavored to show that the various specimens of this type were produced at
              different periods, basing his argument upon differences of weight and a variation of
              artistic treatment, which he regarded as marking successive degrees of development
              from an archaic style. In the anchor he finds allusions to sea voyages, whose
              destinations, as indicated by the tripod of Apollo, were shrines of that god. He then
              connects the different specimens of the bar, or rather coins according to Prof.
              Milani's view, with various official embassies to Delphi on occasions of pestilence at
              Rome in B. C. 453, 429, and 399.</p>
            <p>There are a good many obstacles to one's taking this explanation very seriously, let
              alone accepting it. Chief among them is the impossibility of accepting the view that
              the artistic treatment of the types, especially of the tripod, on which Milani lays
              most stress, reveals traces of archaism in any of the specimens or any diversity of
              treatment that can be ascribed to different stages of artistic development. Not all of
              the specimens are from the same moulds, some of them are evidently better done than
              others, but the differences are those of careful and careless workmanship. The several
              pieces are certainly contemporaneous. As to the explanation of the anchor-type, Dr.
              Haeberlin has pointed out that it was too widely employed, by inland as well as by
              maritime states, to admit of the specific interpretation Prof. Milani offers.</p>
            <p>The tripod of this bar again recalls the well-known coin-type or <hi rend="i"
                >arms</hi> of Croton, and since no satisfactory explanation has yet been given <pb
                id="VAB9263-042" n="42"/> of the types from a Roman point of view the effort to find
              an explanation of them in the history of Croton is specially justified. And in the
              part which Croton almost certainly played in connection with the First Punic War I
              believe there can be found a rational explanation of the tripod in connection with the
              anchor on this bar. To make clear the motive that inspired the employment of such
              types as well as the event it seems to commemorate it is necessary to recall briefly
              certain facts about the extension of Roman sovereignty over the Greek cities of Italy
              and the manner in which that authority was accepted by the Greeks.</p>

            <p>Rome's conquest of the South Italian states, made complete by the fall of Tarentum
              and of Cosentia, capital of the Bruttii, in the same year of B. C. 272, was followed
              by the exercise of those mild measures Rome had before employed in dealing with
              peoples rightfully proud of a rather long and glorious past. For following a policy
              which had also served so well her own interests, the Greek cities were annexed with
              the peculiar relationship of confederated or allied states <hi rend="i">(civitates
                foederatae)</hi>, a form of incorporation that left in their own hands the
              administration of their local affairs. In return for this favorable status there was
              required of them military aid when needed--of the inland cities, troops and military
              supplies; of the maritime states, contingents of warships for the Roman fleet.</p>
            <p>Now there can be no doubt that the real benefits which accrued to the conquered Greek
              cities were fully as great as the advantages gained by the conqueror, important though
              the latter were. For the advent of Roman power checked at once the recurrent bitter
              wars among the Greek communities themselves, it freed them, also, from the
              centuries-old menace of their rude war-like neighbors, and finally it delivered them
              from the increasing peril of being subjugated by a foreign power, a danger to which
              their later policy of appealing to foreign princes for help and protection had exposed
              them. On the other hand, the terms of submission granted by Rome were so respectful of
              the political feelings of the Greek communities that they not only became reasonably
              contented, but were apparently inspired with considerable enthusiasm for their new
              suzerain.</p>
            <p>Our information in regard to the real sentiment of the Greek population in Italy
              toward Rome is not extensive, but the little we have indicates that with the
              realization that they had been saved from a worse fate than the loss of independence
              there arose among them a genuine <pb id="VAB9263-043" n="43"/> loyalty to the new
              relationship. The most substantial proof of this feeling is the response the various
              maritime cities made to Rome's requirements of warships for the prosecution of the
              First Punic War, for that was prompt and seemingly enthusiastic, while the heavy
              burdens laid upon them during that long struggle were evidently borne without undue
              complaint. Had they desired to be rid of Roman domination, the war offered them the
              opportunity of achieving that end. For had the Greek cities revolted or even been lax
              in the naval service, which must have fallen largely to their lot, the Romans would
              have been paralyzed in not only their naval but also their military operations, so
              dependent were they upon the ships furnished by the Greek cities for transports as
              well as ships of the line, particularly in the earliest part of the struggle.</p>

            <p>But in no way is the spontaneous loyalty of the Greek cities toward Rome better
              attested than by the Didrachm which Locris struck soon after Roman domination had been
              securely established in that city, a form of proof that is particularly interesting in
              view of the suggestion presently to be made in connection with the bar in question. I
              mean that well-known silver Didrachm<ref id="ref_039" rend="super">¹</ref> with the
              reverse type showing <hi rend="i">Fides</hi> standing and in the act of placing a
              crown upon the head of <hi rend="i">Roma</hi> who is seated. To leave no doubt about
              the identity of the two figures and the significance of the type the engraver added
              the names PΩMA and IIIΣTIΣ. In this remarkable way Locris gave expression to her loyal
              acceptance of Roman domination. But not less important than the testimony of this
              interesting monument to their political sentiments was the resort to the traditional
              method of expressing them by means of a coin type; for it is a strong proof that this
              means of commemorating political events, especially those of an international or
              quasi-international character, had become thoroughly established in the course of the
              long practice that has been mentioned above. It will, therefore, hardly appear a
              far-fetched suggestion that in some of the other Greek cities a similar means was
              employed to give expression to a similar sentiment though perhaps by individuals after
              the right to strike coins had been lost or at least limited by law or necessity.</p>
            <p>What part, now, did Croton probably take in the First Punic War that could justify
              the theory that this brick has reference thereto? Ancient historians tell us
              comparatively little of the extent of the services Rome had from her recently
              conquered Greek cities in that war, though sporadic notices prove that they were
              considerable. Especially can there <note id="note_039"><ref target="ref_039"
                  rend="super">¹</ref>Head, <hi rend="i">Historia Numorurm</hi>, p. 88, fig.
                -5).</note>
              <pb id="VAB9263-044" n="44"/> be little doubt that both Mommsen<ref id="ref_040"
                rend="super">¹</ref> and Pais<ref id="ref_041" rend="super">²</ref> are correct in
              assigning to them a very important role in all the naval preparations and operations.
              Suddenly brought face to face with the greatest sea-power of the time Rome found
              herself unequipped to meet such an antagonist; therefore she had to depend upon the
              contingents of warships required of the maritime cities for whatever effective naval
              force she succeeded in mustering at the beginning of the war. But, more important
              still, these cities furnished men trained to the sea, also men skilled in the
              construction of ships, and finally, what was of chief value, in the great forests
              which Rome had exacted from the Bruttii as a condition of peace in B. C. 272 there was
              near these Greek cities a convenient supply of excellent timber. This forest, known as
              the Sila, stretched through what had once been the territory of Croton and other
              cities, but had been taken from them by the Bruttii. The Sila was famous in antiquity
              for the abundance of its timbers which were suitable for every kind of construction
              including shipbuilding.<ref id="ref_042" rend="super">³</ref> From it were built the
              considerable fleets which the coast cities had from time to time for the past two
              centuries sent to sea; and when the Elder Dionysius sent a force of men to Italy to
              cut ship-timber it was undoubtedly from the Sila the timber was procured (Diodorus
              Sic. XIV, 7).</p>

            <p>Now, when the Romans took possession of half of that splendid forest it became a
              public property and was exploited by the State through commissioners who leased the
              rights to use the grazing lands, to produce pitch, and cut timber. This was probably
              the abundant source of timber the Romans had when in the first conflict with Carthage
              they were compelled to make the greatest exertions to create and afterwards to
              maintain a fleet. For if we accept the statements of the careful Polybius the Roman
              fleet of triremes, composed mainly of the contingents levied upon the Greek maritime
              cities, was soon found to be no match for the heavy Carthaginian battleships, so that
              heavier vessels, on the model of a captured quinquereme according to Polybius,<ref
                id="ref_043" rend="super">⁴</ref> had to be built at once after the breaking out of
              hostilities, while successive disastrous naval engagements made it necessary to build
              several large fleets in the <note id="note_040"><ref target="ref_040" rend="super"
                  >¹</ref> Mommsen, <hi rend="i">Staatsrecht</hi>, III, p. 677:--Die Italiken, so
                weit sie Griechen sind, bilden den Kern der römischen Flotten.</note>
              <note id="note_041"><ref target="ref_041" rend="super">²</ref> Pais, <hi rend="i"
                  >Storia di R</hi>, I, 2, p. 645:--Quelli che posero fine alla supremazia punica,
                piú che ai duci romani sono dovuti al genio degli Italici e dei federati delle altre
                regioni maritime della penisola.</note>
              <note id="note_042"><ref target="ref_042" rend="super">³</ref> Dion., Halic XX, <hi
                  rend="i">Frag.</hi> V: -- οἱ βρέττιοι, ἑκόντεϛ ὑποταγέντεϛ Ρωμαίοιϛ, τὴν ἡμίσειαν
                τηϛ ὀρεινηϛ παρέδωκαν αὐτοιϛ, ἥ καλειται μὲν Σίλα, μεστὴ δ' ἐστὶν ὕληϛ εὶϛ οἰκοδομάϛ
                τε καὶ ναυπηγίαϛ καὶ πασαν ἄλλην κατασκευὴν εὐθέτον.</note>
              <note id="note_043"><ref target="ref_043" rend="super">⁴</ref> Polybius, I, 20.</note>
              <pb id="VAB9263-045" n="45"/> course of the long war. These ships were probably built
              in several places, and very likely some of them in the <hi rend="i">navalia</hi> at
              Rome, but it is most probable that the majority of them were constructed on the
              southern coast where excellent timber was at hand in abundance and skilled shipwrights
              could be secured.</p>
            <p>While direct evidence for such a conclusion is not given by the ancient writers, yet
              circumstantial evidence, if evidence be needed, is to be found in the movements of the
              Roman fleet as recorded by the historians. For example, in speaking of the new fleet
              of 220 sail which the Romans built in B. C. 254, following the disaster off Camarina,
              Polybius (I, 38) says: "<hi rend="i">As they passed through the straits</hi> they took
              up from Messana those of the vessels which had been saved from the wreck; and having
              thus arrived with three hundred ships off Panormus . . . they began to besiege it."
              This fleet, then, came from the south, or at least a portion of it apparently did,
              passed through the straits on its way to the north coast of Sicily and on to Panormus.
              Certainly that must be the meaning of the language of Polybius. For had the fleet been
              built at Rome, for instance, and sailed down to Sicily it is improbable that such a
              careful historian and so clear in stating facts, would have mentioned a single passage
              through the straits as an incident of the voyage to Panormus; for a fleet coming down
              from Rome would have passed through the straits twice (at least through the greater
              and more dangerous portion of them) in reaching Messana and then proceeding to
              Panormus. But it is probably a safe assumption and hardly requiring proof that when
              all the resources of the republic were laid under contribution to meet the greatest
              sea-power of the time on something like equal terms the Romans made the fullest
              possible use of the vast shipbuilding facilities available on the southern coast.</p>
            <p>When the exploitation of the State's portion of the Sila was put in charge of a
              commission, the commissioners were stationed at Croton, a fact that would lead one to
              suppose that the portion belonging to Rome stood convenient to that city. And, indeed,
              the best part of the Sila apparently was just back of Croton, where it had long
              afforded protection as well as material advantages to the enemies of the city during
              the protracted period of border warfare. So when in the First Punic War the Romans
              proceeded to utilize that forest for the construction of warships it was almost
              certainly at Croton that the extensive yards were built. This inference rests not
              alone upon the fact of Croton's proximity to the Sila but upon the equally important
              consideration that its harbor was <pb id="VAB9263-046" n="46"/> one of the best on
              that coast between Messana and Tarentum.<ref id="ref_044" rend="super">¹</ref> It was
              not a land-locked harbor, only a roadstead suitable for use in the summer, but
              evidently a better anchorage than Polybius seems to describe if, as he further states,
              the great wealth of Croton was largely due to the superior advantages shipping had
              there over any afforded by the other cities of that coast. Furthermore, Croton had the
              most easily defended citadel<ref id="ref_045" rend="super">²</ref> on the entire south
              Italian coast. Croton was, then, at once the most convenient and the most secure place
              along that coast for the utilization of the public forests for shipbuilding; and there
              is probably very little if any ground to doubt that the principal shipyards were at
              that time located at that place.</p>
            <p>It is to that event, the particular part which Croton played in the prosecution of
              the First Punic War, that the types of the brick have reference. The presence of the
              tripod as the obverse type furnishes of course the principal clew to this attribution,
              but the lead thus given has brought us to an event that also gives a reasonable ground
              for associating the anchor with the Croton tripod.</p>
            <p>It is not claimed of course that the anchor had in antiquity the specific symbolic
              meaning that is apparently here attached to it. In fact it is difficult to determine
              the symbolic meaning of the anchor found on Greek and Roman coins; its significance
              seemingly varies and is applied in several ways to shipping and harbors, but hardly to
              voyages, which the Disocuri were supposed to safeguard. On this brick the anchor is
              employed to indicate in a general way the sort of service, that is, to the fleet,
              which Croton rendered to the Romans during the war.</p>
            <p>If much be still desired to place the attribution of this bar beyond dispute, yet I
              believe that some solid ground has been reached as a basis of future investigations.
              The tripod had for centuries been the principal coin-type of Croton; few Greek cities
              had more consistently adhered to a particular device than it had to that emblem, so
              that in Italy and likely much more widely, the tripod-device must have become so well
              associated with that city as to acquire as much the position of a city-arms of Croton
              as the owl was of Athens, Arethusa and the dolphins were of Syracuse, or Pegasus of
              Corinth. And it is because of this historical association of the tripod with Croton,
              coupled with the fact that there was an important event in the history of the city to
              which the <note id="note_044"><ref target="ref_044" rend="super">¹</ref> Polybius, X,
                1, 6: ἐκεινοι γὰρ θερινοὺϛ ἔχοντεϛ ὅρμουϛ καὶ βραχειάν τινα παντελωϛ προσαγωγήν,
                μεγάλην εὐδαιμονίαν δοκουσι περιποιήσασθαι δι' οὐδὲν ἕτερον ἤ διὰ τὴν των τόπων
                εὐϕυίαν, ἣν οὐδὲ συγκρίνειν ἄξιόν ἐστι τοιϛ Ταραντίνων λιμέσι καὶ τόποιϛ.</note>
              <note id="note_045"><ref target="ref_045" rend="super">²</ref> Lenormant, <hi rend="i"
                  >La Grande Grece</hi>, II, p. 14.</note>
              <pb id="VAB9263-047" n="47"/> anchor type might properly allude, that the explanation
              here given seems justified.</p>
          </div3>

          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="center">TIlE COCKS AND ROSTRA BAR.<lb/>
              <hi rend="i"/>The Guard at the Straits During the First Punic War.<lb/> Plate
              VI.</head>

            <p>There have been several interpretations of the types of this brick, but none of them
              is free from serious objections. The earlier theory was that the types had reference
              to some battle at sea, that being apparently the significance of the "tridents" and of
              the "fighting cocks," but that idea had to be abandoned, chiefly for want of a naval
              engagement to justify it. Then Garrucci showed that the supposed "tridents" were in
              reality the rostra of battleships, a suggestion more fully confirmed by Prof. Milani,
              a fact that should have aided the older explanation. In the two cocks Garrucci saw a
              representation of the augural ceremony of the <hi rend="i">tripudium solistimum</hi>,
              whereby the military or naval commander was warned of the fated issue of an impending
              engagement by the behavior of the sacred chickens: favorable if they should eat
              greedily, unfavorable should they refuse to eat; while the two stars referred to the
              Dioscuri, guardians of the sea-voyage, thus connecting the type with the action of a
              naval commander. One of the serviceable features of this explanation is that its
              generality permits the widest application of its meaning. Thus Prof. Milani suggested
              that the types alluded to the naval victory won by Duilius off Mylae in B. C. 260. Dr.
              Haeberlin objects to this purely on the ground of his own theory that no bars were
              issued after the institution of the denarius coinage in B. C. 268, an objection that
              begs one of the vital questions in his theory. A more serious objection, it seems to
              me, is the fact that the notion of a victory is not indicated by either of the types
              on the bar. And so enthusiastic were the Romans over the victory of Duilius that it is
              inconceivable that the State would issue this bar with types intended to commemorate
              that victory and yet fail utterly to give a plain and intelligible expression to the
              main idea.</p>
            <p>Dr. Haeberlin in turn develops his own interesting views of this bar with much
              fullness. He connects it with the prow-series of bronze coins, of reduced standard,
              issued at Rome; the bar, however, for reasons of style, he holds, was issued, like the
              earlier examples, from the mint at Capua. At the head of this series of coins are a
                <hi rend="i">Decussis</hi> and a <hi rend="i">Tressis</hi>
              <pb id="VAB9263-048" n="48"/> whose types are head of Roma and the well-known prow,
              the Roma-head alluding to the sovereignty of Rome. Now the same general idea had to be
              expressed by the types of the bar issued in connection with that series. And that
              requirement is met by this bar, more or less obviously by the rostra, though one would
              naturally expect the prow here the same as on the coins. Accepting Garrucci's view
              that in the cocks we have a representation of the <hi rend="i">tripudium
                solistimum</hi> which the rostra and dolphins show was meant to have reference to
              the sea, Dr. Haeberlin concludes that the general significance of the types is Rome's
              claim of lordship on the sea--"Herrschaft . . . zur See."</p>
            <p>Against this very ingenious interpretation it can be properly urged that sea-power is
              only won by victories on the sea, and, as we shall see below, Rome did not become a
              sea-power at all until after the First Punic War, nor had the Romans before that war
              built a navy of any considerable power, nor a merchant fleet; on the other hand,
              neither a victory nor sea-power can be appropriately commemorated by the
              representation of a ceremony that was customarily employed to ascertain in advance the
              fated issue of a particular engagement. The ancients had several ways of commemorating
              a victory and also the definite results of a successful war, but none of them was
              quite so far-fetched as would be the portrayal of a <hi rend="i">favorable</hi> issue
              of an engagement by the representation of a mode of prediction employed <hi rend="i"
                >before the beginning</hi> of the action.</p>
            <p>But the chief objection is found in the fact that at the time to which Dr. Haeberlin
              would assign this bar--that is, several years before B. C. 268--Rome was not a
              sea-power. Nothing could be more evident from the very terms of the treaty of alliance
              with Carthage made in B. C, 279, and quoted above. An offensive league with Carthage
              would have been the last measure Rome would have considered had she possessed a fleet
              able to cope with the limited naval resources of Pyrrhus or the experienced men and
              material to build one. And if we refer back to the commercial treaty<ref id="ref_046"
                rend="super">¹</ref> made with Carthage in B. C. 348 we find the facts to be even
              worse respecting Rome's power on the sea. "In that treaty," as set forth by
                Mommsen,<ref id="ref_047" rend="super">²</ref> "the Romans had to come under the
              obligation not to navigate the Libyan coast to the west of the Fair Promontory (Cape
              Bon) excepting in cases of necessity. On the other hand, they obtained the privilege
              of freely trading, like the natives in Sicily, so far as it was Carthaginian; and in
              Africa and Sardinia they obtained at least the <note id="note_046"><ref
                  target="ref_046" rend="super">¹</ref> Polybius, III, 21.</note>
              <note id="note_047"><ref target="ref_047" rend="super">²</ref> Mommsen, <hi rend="i"
                  >History of Rome</hi>,Vol. II, p. 41 f.</note>
              <pb id="VAB9263-049" n="49"/> right to dispose of their merchandise at a price fixed
              with the concurrence of the Carthaginian officials and guaranteed by the Carthaginian
              community. The privilege of free trading seems to have been granted to the
              Carthaginians at least in Rome, perhaps in all Latium; only they bound themselves
              neither to do violence to the subject Latin communities nor, if they should set foot
              as enemies on Latin soil, to take up their quarters for a night on shore--in other
              words, not to extend their piratical inroads into the interior--nor to construct any
              fortresses in the Latin land." And in the very next paragraph Mommsen mentions a
              treaty which Rome entered into with Tarentum and probably at the same period, by which
              "The Romans bound themselves--for what concessions on the part of Tarentum is not
              stated--not to navigate the waters to the east of the Lacinian promontory; a
              stipulation by which they were thus wholly excluded from the eastern basin of the
              Mediterranean." There is not the least evidence that any of the terms of these
              treaties had been changed in the interval up to the end of the war with Pyrrhus; and
              since the treaty of alliance with Carthage in B. C. 279 was made under stress of
              circumstances, it is not improbable that that power even more severely enforced the
              agreements with her possible rival.</p>
            <p>Never did a free country subscribe to more humiliating conditions than did Rome in
              those two treaties. So far as she was concerned the western Mediterranean became
              virtually a Carthaginian lake which Romans might navigate only on sufferance of the
              African naval power or, as the Carthaginian ambassadors bluntly put it, "Against our
              will you (Romans) cannot even wash your hands in the sea," while they dared not dip an
              oar in the eastern waters. The only discernible compensation for such renunciation of
              her natural rights was the promise, of Carthage at least, to impose some restraint
              upon the activities of pirates who sailed from her harbors and especially of those who
              made it a business to plunder the Italian coast.</p>
            <p>It is probable that in B. C. 348, and for long afterward, Roman state policy did not
              contemplate any oversea conquests, but was limited to the subjugation of neighboring
              nations in Italy, in order to secure themselves against future aggressions, and
              probably with a view of ultimately securing the sovereignty of the entire peninsula.
              If Rome had a fleet of warships before the end of the fourth century Roman historians
              seem never to have discovered trace of it. The Board of Fleet-masters (<hi rend="i"
                >duoviri navales</hi>) created in B. C. 311 was more likely charged with the task of
              building and organizing a fleet than of taking over the administration <pb
                id="VAB9263-050" n="50"/> of one already in existence; for the fleet mentioned by
                Livy<ref id="ref_048" rend="super">¹</ref> is the first Roman fleet of which there
              is any record (cf Ihne, <hi rend="i">Hist. of Rome, p. 421</hi>), and that was in the
              year 310. When the First Punic War began the Roman naval power was still
              negligible.</p>

            <p>Any theory, therefore, that this bar may have had reference to Rome's sovereignty on
              the sea is hardly tenable; and likewise is it impossible to associate the bar with a
              naval victory, because Rome had no naval victories to commemorate till late in the
              First Punic War, and probably no naval battles. For there are very good reasons to
              believe that Antium was taken by a land operation and the few (only six) pirate ships
              which harbored there were surrendered in accordance with the terms of the treaty of
              peace; and thus there was no naval victory over the Antiate fleet, which the rostra on
              the tribunal in the forum and on the bronze coins are supposed to commemorate.</p>
            <p>The real significance of the types of this brick will probably be found, if ever, in
              a definite fact or event and not in any general idea. And there is such a definite
              event in the First Punic War to which these types might fitly allude.</p>
            <p>In that war the control of Messana and Rhegium together with the intervening Straits
              was of the utmost strategic importance to the Romans. In fact the immediate cause of
              the first conflict between Rome and Carthage may have been rather the danger Rome saw
              was imminent if the Carthaginians in alliance with Hiero of Syracuse should succeed in
              capturing Messana than the other political and commercial considerations usually
              given. For the Romans realized that the possession of Messana by the Carthaginians was
              a javelin aimed at the vitals of the republic. The city's great harbor could
              accommodate six hundred warships<ref id="ref_049" rend="super">²</ref> and would have
              afforded an excellent base for a great sea-power like Carthage, not only for military
              operations against Rome's newly conquered and yet insecurely held southern provinces,
              but also for plundering the coast towns. Of all these dangerous possibilities,
              Polybius says, the Romans were fully aware--that Messana to the Cathaginians "would be
              like a bridge to enable them to cross over into Italy."<ref id="ref_050" rend="super"
                >³</ref></p>
            <p>But it was after the struggle of the First Punic War had begun that the Straits and
              Messana assumed the greatest strategic importance to the Romans. Realizing the value
              of the city's fine harbor and dominant position, its sudden capture had been their
              first move in the war; there <note id="note_048"><ref target="ref_048" rend="super"
                  >¹</ref> Livy, IX, 38.</note>
              <note id="note_049"><ref target="ref_049" rend="super">²</ref> Diod. Sic., XIV,
                56.</note>
              <note id="note_050"><ref target="ref_050" rend="super">³</ref> See also <hi rend="i"
                  >Zonaras</hi>, VIII, 8: -- καὶ ὲϛ τὴν Ιταλίαν ἐξ αὔτηϛ (Messana)
                διαβήσονται.</note>
              <pb id="VAB9263-051" n="51"/> they had established a naval arsenal, equipped for
              repairing warships and furnished with large quantities of material for supplying the
              fleet. The protection of that arsenal, while important, was, however, only an incident
              in the more vital policy they had to pursue of restricting the operations of the
              Carthaginian fleet and preventing the interruption of their chief line of
              communications with Sicily. Both of these objects could be attained by a secure hold
              on Messana and Rhegium; for it was the judgment of ancient as it is also of modern
                writers<ref id="ref_051" rend="super">¹</ref> that the possession of these two
              cities carried with it the control of the intervening Straits.</p>

            <p>It requires no extended portrayal of the situation to understand how it came about
              that the state of affairs at the Straits was throughout the war of the greatest
              concern. For effective control there meant closing of that narrow channel to
              navigation and thereby greatly hampering if not paralyzing the offensive operations of
              the Punic fleet, so distant for warships of that period were its bases, at the western
              end of the island, from the Italian coast and the chief field of activity; while
              merchantmen creeping along the Italian coast and likewise the coast towns, so often
              plundered in the past, were comparatively free from attack.</p>
            <p>But the greatest calamity that could have befallen the Romans would have been to have
              their communications with Sicily interrupted. And not only was the line of
              communications by way of the Straits the chief one but the loss of that would have
              rendered the others impracticable. It is inconceivable how in that case the war could
              have been continued; for the Roman fleet would have been compelled to base itself on
              Tarentum or Naples, positions too far away to be effective, while it would have been
              impossible to supply or reinforce the army in Sicily. The loss of Messana in fact
              would have brought the war to a speedy conclusion and with complete victory for the
              Carthaginians. It was, therefore, of the utmost importance to Rome that strong
              contingents of warships be kept at Messana and Rhegium in order to close the Straits
              completely to hostile craft and protect their communications with Sicily. Polybius
              states that on one occasion the Roman communications were almost cut off, a sufficient
              hint that they were not preserved without challenge, yet there is no evidence that the
              interruption was of long duration or threatened to become serious. It is evident,
              therefore, that <note id="note_051"><ref target="ref_051" rend="super">¹</ref> Thucyd.
                IV, 24; Siefert, <hi rend="i">Messena und Rhegion</hi>, p. 15. Wer Rhegion und
                Zancle (Messana) habe, auch Herr der wichtigen Meerenge sei.</note>
              <pb id="VAB9263-052" n="52"/> the contingents of the fleet stationed at Rhegium and
              Messana--probably ships furnished by these cities whose sailors were well acquainted
              with those dangerous waters--formed a powerful force and maintained a vigilant
              guardianship unbroken for many years--a very notable achievement!</p>

            <p>It is to that event that I venture to suggest the types of this brick allude. It was
              just the sort of an event that is apt to appeal strongly to the imagination, whether
              regarded merely as an achievement or of vital military and political importance,
              making its appeal, therefore, to all classes of persons. Events of that character are
              the ones most often chosen for medallic and kindred representations. It remains, then,
              to point out that the types of the brick appropriately represent the event.</p>
            <p>On the obverse of the brick are two cocks in an attitude of alertness and vigilance;
              they are not fighting nor eating. They are here the <hi rend="i">vigiles
              nocturni</hi>, as Pliny calls cocks, and with the two stars they symbolize the popular
              notion of the birds' constant vigilance, by night as well as by day: Pliny, N. H. X,
              21, 24 <hi rend="i">Proxume gloriaim sentiunt et hi nostri vigiles nocturni quos
                excitandis in opera mortalibus rumpendoque somno natura genuit. Norunt sidera et
                ternas distingunt horas interdiu cantu.</hi></p>
            <figure>
              <p>Fig. 2. Bronze coin, of Caiatia.</p>
            </figure>


            <p>The cock-and-star type is found on the bronze coins of Aquinum, Caiatia, Cales,
              Suessa, Teanum, and Telesia, where the accepted explanation, as given by Garrucci,<ref
                id="ref_052" rend="super">¹</ref> is, to employ the language of Mr. Head, (<hi
                rend="i">Hist. Num. p. 27</hi>), that "all these towns had probably concluded an
              alliance on favorable terms with Rome, by virtue of which they were permitted to issue
              bronze coins in their own names down to a comparatively <note id="note_052"><ref
                  target="ref_052" rend="super">¹</ref>Garrucci, <hi rend="i">Monete d. Italia
                  Antica</hi>, p. 77, under <hi rend="i">Aquinam</hi> : Aquino. . . . deve
                annoverarsi fra le città che ebbero un trattato di alleanza con Roma, come ii fa
                suppore l'uso che gli Aquinati fanno della lingua latina nella moneta, al pari del
                Teanesi, dei Caiatini, di Calvi e Sessa colonie latine, che battono un simile nummo
                col tipo del gallo (che canta, dietro un astro).</note>
              <pb id="VAB9263-053" n="53"/> late period." Thus the cock of vigilance with the star
              symbolizes the unbroken watchfulness with which these communities engaged to guard
              their pact with Rome. (Fig. 2.)</p>
            <p>In the case of the brick, the two cocks are standing, turned toward each other, in an
              attitude of extreme alertness, ready to spring forward, but not at each other: there
              is not the remotest trace of anger apparent in the drawing of the two birds as is best
              shown by Garrucci's plate No. XVIIII. Their attitude shows that the object of their
              vigilance lies at a point between them. The concrete forces whose watchfulness these
              cocks symbolize and also the object of that watchfulness are suggested by the reverse
              type, where we have two battle-ship rostra turned toward each other and toward a body
              of water that lies between them, the water being symbolized in the usual way by means
              of dolphins. These dolphins are represented swimming from opposite directions in
              between the rostra, positions which might be interpreted to symbolize recurrently
              flowing water and so specially appropriate for the Sicilian Straits. But it is never
              desirable to carry to the uttermost possible detail the interpretation of a symbolic
              group, nor is it here necessary to descend to details where the general meaning
              suggested for the type is so fitly expressed.</p>
            <p>The naval forces to which these rostra allude must, of course, be the warships the
              Romans kept stationed at Messana and Rhegium.</p>
            <p>It will help us to realize the importance of the event to which the types of this
              brick are here thought to allude if a similar event in the present European War is
              taken into consideration. One of the proudest achievements of the British navy has
              been its unbroken success in guarding the line of communication across the English
              Channel. It is perfectly realized how vital this matter is to the English in order
              that they may be able to reinforce and supply the huge armies operating in France; and
              yet it is no more vital to them than it was for the Romans to protect a similar line
              of communication across the Straits with their army and navy operating in and around
              Sicily. As to the suitability of the types to commemmorate such an event there seems
              to be little question. In fact an artist at the present day would find the Cocks of
              Vigilance very suitable symbols of the alert watch the British fleet has kept on the
              Channel and the battleship rostra appropriate emblems of the force that has made it
              secure for the transport service.</p>
            <p>I will not hazard a suggestion as to the place where the brick might have been
              produced, except that it was probably at some Greek town not far from the scene of the
              event that formed the subject of the types. <pb id="VAB9263-054" n="54"/> Certainly I
              should not entertain the view that it was produced by the Roman government.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="center">VII.</head>
            <p>Six of the nine extant specimens of Greek bars have been discussed and explanations
              of their types suggested. This is a far larger number than the object of this paper
              required, for two or three of them would sufficiently illustrate their non-Roman
              origin, provided of course the explanations offered should in some cases at least
              prove to be correct. The remaining examples of <hi rend="i">aes signatum</hi> it is my
              purpose to discuss in a fuller treatise of the whole subject and hopefully in the near
              future.</p>
            <p>The most important bearing of the foregoing explanations is still upon the general
              question of the purpose of the bars; for the whole tendency of the evidence afforded
              by those explanations is to deepen suspicion of all the theories by which it has been
              attempted to connect these large bronze pieces in some way with the traditional <hi
                rend="i">aes signatum</hi> currency of Rome or to show that they were at a later
              time issued by Rome from a government mint for use as money or for some other public
              purpose. For if the above interpretations are correct, hardly one of the six pieces
              discussed bears types that the Romans would have chosen as suitable for a state issue
              of such a bar, whatever its purpose may have been. Nor would this conclusion be
              greatly weakened if it should be shown that some of the suggestions that have been
              ventured are untenable; for if, as stated before, it can be proved that even one of
              the bars because of the meaning of its types is indisputably of other than Roman
              origin and, therefore, could not have been produced at a Roman mint or have had
              anything to do with the Roman or any other currency system, then the wider conclusion
              is almost forced upon us that the Roman government had nothing to do with the
              production of the rest of them. This would certainly be true of the so-called
              Campanian bars; and if this group be thrown out of the account, then the various
              theories that have hitherto been advanced and more or less widely accepted in regard
              to the extant specimens of the <hi rend="i">aes signatum</hi> must be greatly
              modified. For it is upon examples of this small group, the fine specimens in the best
              style of Greek art, such as the <hi rend="i">hog-and-elephant</hi> bar and especially
              the <hi rend="i">eagle-and-pegasus</hi> example with its suggestive inscription
              ROMANOM, that Mommsen, Garrucci, Milani, Haeberlin, as well as other earlier and later
              writers, have principally based their views of the whole subject. They have evidently
              held that in the main whatever could be established with <pb id="VAB9263-055" n="55"/>
              reference to these examples must hold true of the other and cruder specimens. And that
              position is undoubtedly correct; so that vice versa whatever of their theories may be
              disproved with reference to the "Campanian bars" must apply also to all of the
              quadrilateral bronze bricks.</p>
            <p>While that view of an identical purpose for all the extant bars, however much they
              differ in the details of composition and types, seems undoubtedly sound, yet the
              explanations of the types given above, because of their apparent allusion to important
              events, almost inevitably suggest the query whether the Greek bars may not have been
              intended primarily as commemorative plaques with no special utilitarian purpose.
              Indisputably such commemorative plaques, approaching closely to the modern medallic
              plaque, have not hitherto been known to have existed among the Greeks and Romans. But
              from an early date the commemorative coin-type was employed sporadically by the
              Greeks, in fact much more extensively throughout the Greek world, there is reason to
              believe, than has been generally recognized. Commemorative types are particularly
              remarkable in the coinage of the western Greeks of Magna Graecia and Sicily. And it
              was the western Greeks, too, who extended the practice of issuing commemorative coins
              to include, besides local myths and local physiographic features, also the
              commemoration of historical events;<ref id="ref_053" rend="super">¹</ref> or perhaps
              it would be better to say that, while the older Greek communities often celebrated
              important events by striking new coins with types presenting simply a more beautiful
              effigy of the patron deity of the city to whose help their successful issue was
              ascribed, the western Greeks frequently struck coins whose main types or adjuncts more
              particularly alluded to the specific event.</p>
            <p>Now these great bronze plaques are of course far removed from commemorative coins.
              They might be regarded as holding a position somewhere between the medallic coin and
              the fixed bronze commemorative tablet. Moreover, the mere fact that the other Greeks
              are not known to have made use of such monuments as medallic plaques would hardly
              constitute a fatal objection to a suggestion that such was the purpose for which these
              bars were produced by the Italian Greeks; for the independence and originality of the
              Western Greeks were manifested in many ways and notably in certain extraordinary
              features of the coins struck for centuries in Magna Graecia as compared with the coins
              of the rest of the Greek world. Should one hesitate to regard as commemorative plaques
              those examples which were produced while the Greeks yet <note id="note_053"><ref
                  target="ref_053" rend="super">¹</ref> McDonald, <hi rend="i">Coin Types</hi>, pp.
                92, 110; Reinach. <hi rend="i">L'Histoire par les Monnaies</hi>, p. 9 ff.</note>
              <pb id="VAB9263-056" n="56"/> retained their independence, less doubt might
              justifiably attach to those datable in a period subsequent to the conquest and the
              establishment of the Roman domination. For after the conquest those cities suffered
              considerable restriction of the right of coinage in the precious metals if they did
              not lose that right altogether, while the issues of bronze coins apparently ceased at
              some cities and became uncertain at others; and thus deprived of the opportunity of
              striking coins to commemorate an event, or give expression to a political sentiment,
              the cities, or rather private persons, might have had recourse to these plaques; and
              the plaques would the more readily commend themselves as suitable for the purpose
              because they were so unlike the inhibited coin in form and size as to avoid any
              complication with the Roman authorities.</p>
            <p>While the suggestion just made arises naturally from the very character of the
              explanations that have been given of some of the types, yet for reasons already stated
              it is hardly to be entertained seriously; for it would explain the purpose of but a
              part of the extant bars, whereas it is most probable that they were all intended for
              the same use.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="center">VIII.</head>

            <p>Now if the Greek bars have with some degree of probability been shown to have
              originated elsewhere than at a Roman mint and under other than Roman influence, and
              therefore most likely intended for other use than as money, then certainly it becomes
              increasingly difficult to regard the bars attributed to Central and Northern Italy as
              specimens of <hi rend="i">aes signatum</hi> produced by either private persons or by
              communities for use as money. For the alloys of this latter class of bars lend no
              support to the money theory, while their types are without significance and too
              commonplace to connect their issue with any particular places. There are, however,
              certain interesting facts observable in the devices found on some of these bars that
              may be mentioned chiefly because they seem to dispose of a few curious views that have
              been advanced regarding two varieties of them.</p>
            <p>On the grounds of provenience and the evidence of coins found along with certain of
              these bars various conjectures have been made as to the date and place of their
              production. And in the case of one group Dr. Haeberlin holds that the type also
              confirms the evidence of provenience. These are the fragments which bear the character
              A (Pl. VII), interpreted by Haeberlin as a ligature of TA, an abbreviation of Tachna,
                <hi rend="i">i.e.</hi>, Tarquinii, the ancient site in whose vicinity, at Corneto,
              the bars were <pb id="VAB9263-057" n="57"/> found. It is needless to point out that a
              ligature of TA in such form would be very unusual, quite unique, I believe.</p>
            <p>No more acceptable is the view of Garrucci, followed by Willers, that the character
              is the simple Roman letter A, and that we have the mark of value &#8814;||| = <hi
                rend="i">Asses tres</hi>. For that form of the letter A, with the cross-bar
              extending beyond the side-strokes, would also be unique, I believe; at least I have
              been unable to find a parallel to it. Nor does the suggestion of Willers that the
              cross-bar was so extended in order to fill the space about the letter help
              matters.</p>

            <p>In this device and also in that of the two crescents (P1. VIII, 4) we have the
              results of a simplification of earlier forms of the types, the evolution of which can
              be traced rather fully in the case of the latter. There was a tendency toward
              simplification of the so-called fish-skeleton or leaf types,<ref id="ref_054"
                rend="super">¹</ref> by reducing the number of "spines," or leaves, the admittedly
              later specimens having a smaller number in a given length than the earlier ones. No.
              1, Plate VIII, has a much later form of the device with but two pairs of "spines" on
              the stem, heavy in form and approaching the general shape of crescents. Whether the
              entire bar had more of such members than appear on the extant fragment cannot of
              course be determined. No. 2 of the same plate probably had two pairs as there was
              likely another pair at a lower point on the stem and perhaps turned in the opposite
              direction.</p>
            <p>The next change in the device consisted in omitting the stem and to take its place in
              filling the field there was introduced a sort of star, possibly two stars, Pl. VIII,
              No. 3. In the final form there were but two pairs of spines or leaves conventionalized
              into crescent-shaped devices at the ends of the ingots, the intervening field being
              left plain (No. 4).</p>
            <p>It should also be noted that the curved ornament on the reverse of the small brick
              No. 2 is very similar to that on the broad No. 1. The two pieces were apparently
              produced in the same <hi rend="i">officina</hi> and mark a transition from the large
              to a smaller form of ingot.</p>
            <p>A similar evolution of the <hi rend="i">ramo secco</hi> type is shown by Nos. 1, 2,
              and 3, of Pl. VII resulting in the character resembling somewhat the Roman letter A.
              The central stem of the earlier device, whatever it may have been intended to
              represent, has here given way to a series of short lines, a sort of cross-hatching to
              fill up the field. And since the cross-bar of what has been often taken for the letter
              A is of the same length as the <note id="note_054"><ref target="ref_054" rend="super"
                  >¹</ref>More likely, as Garrueci has pointed out (<hi rend="i">Mon. d. Ial.
                  Ant.</hi>, p. 5), the type represents a conventionalized leaf.</note>
              <pb id="VAB9263-058" n="58"/> other short lines above the fork, it is rather to be
              considered as merely one of those lines than as a part of a quite unusual if not
              impossible form of the letter or a ligature of TA.</p>

          </div3>

          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="center">IX.</head>

            <p>It seems, therefore, that the arguments hitherto urged in favor of the theories that
              these bars are specimens of <hi rend="i">aes signatum</hi> issued by the state for
              ceremonial and monetary uses are insufficient. On the other hand, for more or less
              positive considerations the conclusion, already tentatively advanced in regard to some
              varieties but generally rejected, that they were merely commercial ingots seems most
              likely to be correct. Some of them are ingots of unrefined copper or of scrap copper
                (<hi rend="i">aes collectaneum</hi>) probably destined for the refineries, others
              prepared by the refiners to supply the large number of artisans engaged in the
              manufacture of the numerous articles, both useful and ornamental, then so commonly
              made of bronze. These ingots were, of course, the products of private enterprise; and
              the types they bear are to be regarded as trade-marks to identify the products of a
                manufacturer.<ref id="ref_055" rend="super">¹</ref></p>
            <p>The manufactures of bronze in antiquity were very extensive and of wide variety, as
              is attested by the writers and by the great accumulations of antique bronze objects
              brought together in our museums. Large factories, such as modern times have produced,
              were then the exception, bronze manufactures for the most part coming from the hands
              of numerous artisans working in small shops of limited equipment and capacity. Since
              these artisans would rarely have either the ability to assay a mass of copper of
              unknown alloys or the means of refining it and then making up the alloy they required,
              it was plainly necessary for them to procure their supplies of copper or bronze in a
              state ready for use. Nor was that practice followed by the ancient artisan solely
              because of his defective equipment, but also because it was certainly cheaper; for
              which reason in our own times even large consumers not uncommonly follow the same
              practice and secure their supplies of bronze in the required alloy rather than make
              the alloys themselves. The Elder Pliny has allusions to numerous refineries (<hi
                rend="i">officinae aerariae</hi>) throughout Italy where copper pigs (<hi rend="i"
                >panes</hi>) were refined and prepared in various alloys for the requirements of the
              makers of bronze articles and for artists. While it is not a fact to be insisted upon
              too strongly, yet it is interesting that the <note id="note_055"><ref target="ref_055"
                  rend="super">¹</ref>See Darmberg et Saglio, <hi rend="i">Metallum</hi>, p. 1865,
                for examples of large ingots of lead and other metals with trade-marks.</note>
              <pb id="VAB9263-059" n="59"/> analysis of some of the extant ingots shows a
              considerable agreement with the figures given by Pliny for certain alloys<ref
                id="ref_056" rend="super">¹</ref> produced for consumers in his time. For example,
              two fragments of these ingots show respectively 8.22% and 6.3% tin and no other alloy,
              which compares very well with Pliny's <hi rend="i">aes Campanum</hi> alloyed with 8%
              of tin (<hi rend="i">plumbum argentarium</hi>) by the refineries in the provinces of
              Italy except at Capua, where 10% of tin was used.</p>

            <p>The view that these bars were commercial ingots helps us to a rational explanation of
              certain facts which have perplexed those who found it difficult to accept the theories
              that they were issued for use as coins or money and have misled the exponents of such
              views. For instance, it has been accepted as a sound principle that the discovery of
              bars along with specimens of the heavy bronze coins warranted the conclusion that the
              bars had been issued for use as money. Thus Willers states clearly: Aus diesem
              wertvollen Fundnachricht (<hi rend="i">i. e.</hi>, that bars with the character
              resembling the letter A were found together with heavy bronze coins) <hi rend="i"
                >ergiebt sich also, dass unsere Barren neben Rohund Schwerkupfer als Geld gedient
                haben und der Zeit von etwa 300 bis 250 v. Chr. angehören.</hi><ref id="ref_057"
                rend="super">²</ref></p>
            <p><hi rend="i">On the contrary quite as logical and more probable is the inference that
                the heavy bronze coins were, at the time the hoard was buried, being converted to
                the same use as that for which the ingots were made.</hi> For in about 290 B. C.,
              possibly as late as 286, the weight of the <hi rend="i">As</hi> was reduced by one
              half, and repeated heavy reductions brought the bronze coinage down to the triental
              standard by B. C. 268. It is not known that the Roman government made provision for
              the exchange, without loss to the holder, of the heavy coins for the new ones of
              lighter weight; it is not improbable that they did. But experience has shown that in
              spite of such measures a considerable proportion of the issues it is desired to
              replace will always be retained by the public. This result was assured in the case of
              the Roman <hi rend="i">aes grave</hi> by the very rapidity with which repeated
              reductions of standard followed each other. And after the coins of the older and
              heavier standard had become worth as much <note id="note_056"><ref target="ref_056"
                  rend="super">¹</ref>Pliny N. H. XXXIV, 820, 20; <hi rend="i">aes Campanum</hi>,
                "utensilibus vasis probatissimum"; two varieties, (1) produced at Capua, 90% copper
                and 10% tin (plumbum argentarium), (2) produced elsewhere in Italy, only 8% of tin.
                  <hi rend="i">Aes statuarium</hi>, 12½% of tin, one third of the whole being of
                scrap copper (<hi rend="i">aes collectaneuum</hi>). <hi rend="i">Aes
                  Graecanicum</hi>, 85% copper, 10% lead (<hi rend="i">nigrum plumbum</hi>), 5% tin
                  (<hi rend="i">plumbum argentariurm</hi>). <hi rend="i">Aes ollarium</hi>, copper
                and 3% to 4% of tin.</note>
              <note id="note_057"><ref target="ref_057" rend="super">²</ref>Willers, <hi rend="i"
                  >Italische Bronzebarren, Num. Zeitsch</hi>., 1904, p. 28.</note>
              <pb id="VAB9263-060" n="60"/> in the metal market as when exchanged for the new and
              smaller coins, or possibly more, it was but natural that large quantities of the
              former should be converted to use in the arts; and the finding of <hi rend="i">aes
                grave</hi>, some of them in fragments, along with commercial ingots of bronze shows
              that such was the practice.</p>

            <p>Again, the fact that most of the bars have been found in a fragmentary state has been
              considered by many scholars as strong proof that they were issued for use as money;
              for it is held that, whenever it was desired to obtain a sum less than the value of an
              entire bar, the practice was to break off from it a piece of the necessary weight and
              value. The absurdity of this theory has been pointed out repeatedly and its chief
              weakness has been stated above. Considering the bars as money, in any sense, the
              breaking of them into fragments would be most remarkable; but it is not difficult to
              understand why commercial ingots should be found in fragments; it is in fact just what
              an expert worker in bronze would expect. For at the present time, with greatly
              improved facilities for melting bronze, including an abundance of cheap gas, it is the
              very common practice to reduce the ingots to fragments because the smaller pieces pack
              better in the crucible and at the same time the surface directly exposed to the heat
              is thereby greatly increased.</p>
            <p>The form in which bronze and copper appeared on the Italian markets ready for the
              artisan's use is something we do not know. But it is well known that the form of the
              commercial ingots of gold and silver was quadrilateral and that such ingots were
              technically known as "bricks," <hi rend="i">lateres</hi>.<ref id="ref_058"
                rend="super">¹</ref> It does not follow, of course, that the bronze ingots, refined
              and in the various alloys the trade required, had the same form and designation as
              those of the more valuable metals. But if we accept the views of some investigators,
              there was a time in Italy when copper was considered much more a precious metal than
              it was in historical times, and that is probably true; so that it is not a far-fetched
              inference that the term <hi rend="i">later</hi> as well as the brick-form was first
              employed for bronze and was subsequently adopted for gold and silver ingots when these
              metals became more abundant in the country. However that may have been these bars have
              a form quite foreign to that of any acknowledged coin in antiquity, while they do have
              one of the recognized metal ingot forms. <note id="note_058"><ref target="ref_058"
                  rend="super">¹</ref>Compare the gold bricks found at Sirmio, now in British and
                Pesth museums. See also Varro, <hi rend="i">Vita, P. R.</hi>, in Nonius, p. 520:
                lateres argentei . . . . in aerarium conditi. Pliny, <hi rend="i">N. H.</hi>,
                XXXIII, 3, 17; C. Caesar primo introitu urbis civili bello suo ex aerario protulit
                laterumm aureorum XV, argenteorum XXX, et in numerato CCC; anid Tacitus, <hi
                  rend="i">Ann</hi>., XVI, 1, 2.</note></p>

            <pb id="VAB9263-061" n="61"/>
            <p>That among the Greeks the refiner's trade-mark should have undergone a marked
              development and become a device adapted to the size and form of the comparatively
              small ingot prepared for the manufacturer and bronze founder and that the device
              should have been executed by a really clever artist can hardly occasion any surprise;
              while the influence of contemporary political events upon the subjects chosen for the
              devices was certainly nothing inconsistent with the independent thought and practice
              of the western Greeks.</p>


            <pb id="VAB9263-062" n="[]"/>



            <pb id="VAB9263-063" n="[63]"/>

            <figure>
              <p>Plate I.</p>
              <p>Three-quarters actual size.</p>
            </figure>






            <pb id="VAB9263-064" n="[]"/>
            <pb id="VAB9263-065" n="[65]"/>
            <figure>
              <p>Plate II</p>

              <p>Three-quarters actual size.</p>

              <p><hi>TYPE OF TRIPOD--BARLEY-EAR BAR RECONSTRUCTED FROM TWO FRAGMENTS<lb/> OF
                  DIFFERENT BARS.</hi></p>
            </figure>


            <pb id="VAB9263-066" n="[]"/>


            <pb id="VAB9263-067" n="[67]"/>
            <figure>
              <p>Plate III</p>

              <p>Three-quarters actual size.</p>
            </figure>


            <pb id="VAB9263-068" n="[]"/>


            <pb id="VAB9263-069" n="[69]"/>
            <figure>
              <p>Plate IV</p>

              <p>Three-quarters actual size.</p>
            </figure>


            <pb id="VAB9263-070" n="[]"/>
            <pb id="VAB9263-071" n="[71]"/>
            <figure>
              <p>Plate V</p>

              <p>Three-quarters actual size.</p>
            </figure>

            <pb id="VAB9263-072" n="[]"/>
            <pb id="VAB9263-073" n="73"/>
            <figure>
              <p>Plate VI</p>

              <p>Three-quarters actual size.</p>
            </figure>

            <pb id="VAB9263-074" n="[]"/>
            <pb id="VAB9263-075" n="[75]"/>
            <figure>
              <p>Plate VII</p>

              <p>Thre-qutarters actual size</p>
            </figure>


            <pb id="VAB9263-076" n="[]"/>
            <pb id="VAB9263-077" n="[77]"/>
            <figure>
              <p>Plate VIII</p>

              <p>Three-quarters actual size.</p>
            </figure>

          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
    <back/>


  </text>

</TEI.2>
