<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//IA Books//DTD TEI for Indiana Authors Books//EN"
                       "teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="VAC0877">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">The growth of socialism</title>
				<author>Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926.</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded By</resp>
					<!--Update the value of the element below with your name in
                                direct order.-->
					<name>Peter Kaczmarczyk</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
				<address>
                    <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
                </address>
				<idno>VAC0877</idno>
				<availability status="unknown">
					<p>Copyright 2009 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
					<p>Indiana University provides the information contained on this web site for
						non-commercial, personal, or research use only. All other use, including but not limited
						to commercial or scholarly reproductions, redistribution, publication or transmission,
						whether by electronic means or otherwise, without prior written permission of the
						copyright holder is strictly prohibited.</p>
				</availability>
				<!--Update the value of the date element with the year the document
                        is being encoded.-->
				<date>2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblFull>
					<titleStmt>
						<title type="main">The growth of socialism</title>
						<author id="ina-v1-entry-0238">Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926.</author>
					</titleStmt>
					<extent>21, [5], 4 p. ; 15 cm.</extent>
					<publicationStmt>
						<publisher>C.H. Kerr</publisher>
						<pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
						<date>1902</date>
					</publicationStmt>
					<notesStmt>
						<note>"Written for Success magazine ... Here reproduced in full."</note>
					</notesStmt>
				</biblFull>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>The Digital Library Program was awarded a Library Services and Technology Act (LSTA)
					grant in 2005 to make available online the three-volume, reference work, <title>Indiana
						Authors and Their Books</title> along with selected monographs by Indiana authors.</p>
			</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl n="3">
				<p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and has
					been encoded and edited using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
					Guidelines following the TEI Lite standard. Digital page images are linked to the text
					file.</p>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<tagUsage gi="div1">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy id="lcsh">
					<bibl>
						<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language>English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="lcsh">
					<list>
						<item>Socialism</item>
						<item>Working class</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<!--The revision description tracks significant changes made to the file
                    after completion. This information will remain commented out unless someone has
                    conducted quality assessment of the texts and have made changes to the file as a
                    result.-->
		<!-- <revisionDesc> <change>
                    <date>$Date</date> <respStmt>
                    <name>$Name</name>
                    <resp>$Responsibility</resp>
                    </respStmt> <item>$Changes</item>
                    </change> </revisionDesc> -->
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>

			<pb id="VAC0877-001" n="[1]"/>
			<titlePage>
				<docTitle rend="center">
					<titlePart type="main">The Growth of Socialism</titlePart>
				</docTitle>
				<byline>By<docAuthor> EUGENE V. DEBS--</docAuthor></byline>

				<docImprint rend="center">Sixty copies of this book, or sixty socialist books no two alike,
					mailed for $1.00<lb/>
					<pubPlace>CHICAGO</pubPlace><lb/>
					<publisher>CHARLES H. KERR &amp; COMPANY CO-OPERATIVE</publisher></docImprint>
			</titlePage>
		</front>
		<body>
			<p/>

			<pb id="VAC0877-002" n="[2]"/>




			<pb id="VAC0877-003" n="3"/>
			<div1 type="book">
				<head rend="center">The Growth of Socialism. By Eugene V. Debs.</head>
				<p>(The following article was written for Success Magazine. On account of demand for space
					the editor reduced the length of the article, omitting many of the vital paragraphs. The
					entire article is here reproduced in full.)</p>

				<p>Not many of those schooled in old-party politics have any adequate conception of the true
					import of the labor movement. They read of it in the papers, discuss it in their clubs,
					criticise labor unions, condemn walking delegates, and finally conclude that organized
					labor is a thing to be tolerated so long, only, as it keeps within "proper bounds," but to
					be put down summarily the moment its members, like the remnants of Indian tribes on the
					western plains, venture beyond the limits of their reservations. They utterly fail or
					refuse to see the connection between labor and politics, and are, therefore, woefully
					ignorant of the political significance of the labor movement of the present day.</p>
				<p>It is true that in all the centuries of the past labor has been "put down" when it has
					sought some modicum of its own, or when it has even yearned for some slight amelioration
						<pb id="VAC0877-004" n="4"/> of its wretched condition, as witness the merciless
					massacre of the half-famished and despairing subjects of the Russian czar, a few months
					ago, for daring to hope that their humble petition for a few paltry concessions might be
					received and considered by his mailed and heartless majesty.</p>
				<p>It is likewise true, that, in the present day, and in the United States, all the powers
					of government stand ready to "put down" the working class whenever it may be deemed
					necessary in the interest of its industrial masters.</p>
				<p>All great strikes prove that the government is under the control of corporate capital and
					that the army of officeholders is as subservient to the capitalist masters as is the army
					of wage-workers that depends upon them for employment.</p>
				<p>But, true as these things are, it is not true that labor is ignorant of them, nor is it
					true that such conditions will continue forever.</p>
				<p>The labor movement has advanced with rapid strides, during the last few years, and is,
					today, the most formidable factor in quickening the social conscience and in regenerating
					the human race. It is not the millions that are enrolled as members of labor unions that
					give power and promise to this world movement, but the thousands, rather, that are not
					trade-unionists merely, <pb id="VAC0877-005" n="5"/> but working-class unionists as well;
					that is to say, working men and women who recognize the identity of the industrial and
					political interests of the whole working class; or in other words, are conscious of their
					class interests, and are bending all the powers of their minds and bodies, spurred by the
					zeal that springs from comradeship in a common cause, to effect the economic and political
					solidarity of the whole mass of labor, irrespective of race, creed or sex.</p>
				<p>These class-conscious workers--these Socialists--realize the fact that the labor
					question, in its full and vital sense, is a political question, and that the working class
					must be taught to extend the principle of unionism to the political field, and there
					organize on the basis of their economic class interests; and, although they are engaged in
					a herculean task, the forces of industrial evolution and social progress are back of them,
					and all the powers of reaction cannot prevail against them.</p>
				<p>The labor movement has had to fight its way, inch by inch, from its inception to its
					present position, and to this very fact is due the revolutionary spirit, indomitable will,
					and unconquerable fiber it has developed, and which alone fit it for its mighty historic
					mission.</p>
				<p>In the beginning the workers organized in <pb id="VAC0877-006" n="6"/> their respective
					trades simply to improve working conditions. They had no thought of united political
					action. The employing class at once combined to defeat every attempt at organization on
					the part of its employes; but, notwithstanding this opposition, the trade union, which had
					become an economic necessity, grew steadily until at last the employers were compelled to
					recognize and deal with it. Being unable to destroy it, they next proceeded to control its
					operations by confining it to its narrowest possible limits, thus reducing it to
					inefficiency--from a menace to a convenience.</p>
				<p>The late Marcus A. Hanna crushed the trade union with an iron boot in the beginning of
					his career as a capitalist. In his maturer years he became its patron saint. He did not
					change in spirit, but in wisdom. What is true of Mr. Hanna is true of the principal
					members of the Civic Federation, that economic peace congress conceived by far-sighted
					capitalists, sanctified by plutocratic prelates and presided over by a gentleman who, but
					a few months ago, engaged James Farley and his army of five thousand professional strike
					breakers to defeat the demands and destroy the unions of his New York subway employes.</p>
				<p>A new unionism has struggled into existence, and the coming year will witness some <pb
						id="VAC0877-007" n="7"/> tremendous changes. The old forms cramp and fetter the new
					forces. As these new forces develop, the old forms must yield and finally give way to
					transformation.</p>
				<p>The old unionism, under the inspiration of a Civic Federation banquet, exclaims
					jubilantly: "The interests of labor and capital are identical. Hallelujah!"</p>
				<p>To this stimulating sentiment the whole body of exploiting capitalists gives hearty
					assent; all its politicians, parsons, and writers join in enthusiastic approval; and woe
					be to the few clear, calm, and candid protestants who deny it. Their very loyalty becomes
					treason, and the working class they seek to serve is warned against them, while the false
					leaders are loaded with fulsome adulation.</p>
				<p>But nevertheless, the clear voice of the awakened and dauntless few cannot be silenced.
					The new unionism is being heard. In trumpet tones it rings out its revolutionary
					shibboleth to all the workers of the earth: "Our interests are identical--let us combine,
					industrially and politically, assert our united power, achieve our freedom, enjoy the
					fruit of our labor, rid society of parasitism, abolish poverty, and civilize the
					world."</p>
				<p>The old unionism, living in the dead past, still affirms that the interests of labor and
					capital are identical.</p>
				<p>The new unionism, vitalized and clarified by <pb id="VAC0877-008" n="8"/> the living
					present, exclaims: "We know better; capitalists and wage-workers have antagonistic
					economic interests; capitalists buy and workers sell labor power, the one as cheaply and
					the other as dearly as possible; they are locked in a life-and-death class struggle;
					there can be no identity of interests between masters and slaves--between exploiters and
					exploited--and there can be no peace until the working class is triumphant in this
					struggle and the wage system is forever wiped from the earth."</p>
				<p>The months immediately before us will witness a mighty mustering of the working class, on
					the basis of the class struggle, and the day is not far distant when they will be united
					in one vast economic organization in which all the trades will be represented, "separate
					as the waves, yet one as the sea," and one great political party that stands
					uncompromisingly for the working class and its program of human emancipation.</p>
				<p>In the late national election, for the first time, the hand of the working class was
					clearly seen.</p>
				<p>The Socialist party is distinctively the party, and its vote is distinctively the vote,
					of the working class.</p>
				<p>More than four hundred thousand of these votes were counted; probably twice as many were
					cast. This was but the beginning. From <pb id="VAC0877-009" n="9"/> now on there is "a new
					Richmond in the field."</p>
				<p>There is but one issue from the standpoint of labor, and that is: "Labor versus Capital."
					Upon that basis the political alignment of the future will have to be made. There is no
					escape from it.</p>
				<p>For the present the ignorance of the workers stands in the way of their political
					solidarity, but this can and will be overcome. In the meantime, the small capitalists and
					the middle class are being ground to atoms in the mill of competition. Thousands are being
					driven from the field entirely, beaten in the struggle, bankrupt and hopeless, to be
					swallowed up in the surging sea of wage-slavery; while thousands of others cling to the
					outer edge, straining every nerve to stem the torrent that threatens to sweep them into
					the abyss, their condition so precarious that they anticipate the inevitable and make
					common issue with the wage-workers in the struggle to overthrow the capitalist system and
					reconstruct society upon a new foundation of co-operative industry and the social
					ownership of the means of life.</p>
				<p>Of all the silly sayings of the self-satisfied of the present day, the oft-repeated
					falsehood that there are "no classes" in this country takes the lead, and is often made to
					serve as the prelude to the preposterous warning that <pb id="VAC0877-010" n="10"/>
					periodically peals from rich and sumptuous club banquets, at which the president and other
					patriots are guests, that "it is treason to array class against class in the United
					States."</p>
				<p>If there are no classes, how can they be arrayed against each other?</p>
				<p>The fact is that precisely the same classes and conditions that exist in the monarchies
					of the old world have also developed in our capitalist republic. The working-class
					sections, including the tenements and slums of New York and London, are strikingly
					similar; and the wealth-owning class of the United States represents as distinct an
					aristocracy as England can boast, while the laboring elements of both countries are
					distinctively in the "lower class" by themselves and practically on the same degraded
					level.</p>
				<p>Deny it as may the retainers of the rich, the classes already exist; they are here, and
					no amount of sophistication can remove them, nor the chasm that divides them. The rare and
					exceptional wage-worker who escapes from wage-slavery simply proves the rule and
					emphasizes the doom of his class in capitalist society.</p>
				<p>The existing classes and the struggle going on between them are not due to the
					mischievous influence of labor agitators, as certain politicians and priests, the
					emissaries of the "rich and respectable," would have it appear.</p>


				<pb id="VAC0877-011" n="11"/>

				<p>The long swell of the wave but expresses the agitation of the deep.</p>
				<p>The agitator is the product of unrest--his is the voice of the social deep; and, though
					he may be reviled as a demagogue who preys upon the ignorance of his fellows, the unrest
					continues and the agitation increases until the cause of it is removed and justice is
					done.</p>
				<p>Classes and class rule and their attendant progress and poverty, money and misery,
					turmoil and strife, are inherent in the capitalist system. Why? Simply because one set of
					men owns the tools with which wealth is produced, while another set uses them, and there
					is an irrepressible conflict over the division of the product.</p>
				<p>The capitalist owns the tools he does not use; the worker uses the tools he does not
					own.</p>
				<p>The principal tools of production and distribution in the United States--mammoth
					machines, complex social instruments, made and used co-operatively by millions of
					workingmen, their very lives, their wives and babes being dependent upon them--are the
					private property of a few hundred capitalists, and are operated purely to make profits for
					these capitalists, regardless of the poverty and wretchedness that ensue to the
					masses.</p>
				<p>In virtue of the individual ownership of the social instruments of production, one
					capitalist <pb id="VAC0877-012" n="12"/> may exploit the labor of a million workingmen and
					become a billionaire, while the million workers struggle through life in penury and want,
					to a bleak and barren old age, to find rest at last in the pauper asylum, the morgue and
					the potter's field.</p>
				<p>This vast and resourceful country should be free from the scourge of poverty and the
					blight of ignorance; but it never will be until the private ownership of the means of life
					is abolished and society is organized on the basis of social ownership of the social means
					of wealth production and the inalienable right of all to work and to produce freely to
					satisfy their physical needs and material wants. It is for this great organic change, this
					world-wide social revolution, that the Socialists of all countries are organizing, that
					it may be intelligently guided, and come, if possible, in peace and order when the people
					and conditions have been prepared for it.</p>
				<p>The present order of society is developing all the symptoms of degeneracy and
					dissolution. Only the individualist self-seekers and their mercenaries--they who believe
					in making the animal struggle for existence perpetual, in climbing to the top over the
					corpses of their fellows--only they are satisfied, or would appear to be, and expatiate
					upon our marvelous prosperity, and the incomparable glory of our free institutions.</p>


				<pb id="VAC0877-013" n="13"/>

				<p>The man who can look upon New York or Chicago, today, and utter such sentiments should
					blush for his perverted sense of justice, to say nothing of his total lack of
					humanity.</p>
				<p>Many thousands of men, women and children suffer for food and shiver in the cold in these
					typical capitalist cities, while the beef trust is crammed to bursting and the cotton
					kings of the South burn cotton to keep up prices.</p>
				<p>Has the world ever heard of such monstrous iniquity--such unspeakable crime? In the name
					of all that has heart in it not yet turned to adamant, has human life any value, even that
					of the lowest grade of merchandise? And is it not high time to call a halt to the ravages
					of capitalism and give a little thought and consideration to humanity?</p>
				<p>Let us briefly note some of the crying evils which infest the class-ruled society of the
					present day. First of all, millions are poverty-stricken, the result, mainly, of no work
					or low wages. The great book of Robert Hunter, on "Poverty," recently published, abounds
					in facts, supported by incontrovertible proofs, which silence all doubt upon this
					point.</p>
				<p>In New York City, alone, fifty thousand children, when they go to school at all, go
					without sufficient and proper food, and one <pb id="VAC0877-014" n="14"/> corpse in every
					ten is dumped into the potter's field.</p>
				<p>New York and Chicago are filled with unemployed and suffering, and in the country at
					large ten millions are in want. In the shoemaking industry, fifty-one per cent of the
					laborers receive less than three hundred dollars per year. In cotton spinning, the wages
					of thousands average from two hundred and twenty dollars to four hundred and sixty dollars
					per year. During the last year tens of thousands of coal miners were allowed to work but
					from one to three days per week. Fall River capitalists reduce wages three times in rapid
					succession, and lock out and starve their employes for six months, declaring that they
					cannot afford to pay the high prices for cotton, while the planters of the South burn up
					the cotton to keep up prices rather than clothe the naked whose labor produced it.</p>
				<p>The state of Colorado seethes with military brutality and recks with political corruption
					because the mine owners are practically proprietors of the state and propose to do as they
					please with their own; and they who have the temerity to protest are branded outlaws and
					bull-penned, deported, or shot dead in their tracks.</p>
				<p>The United States senate is dominated by the special representatives of the trust and <pb
						id="VAC0877-015" n="15"/> corporations, and several of its members are under indictment
					for playing the game of their masters in their own personal interests. Think of Senator
					Chauncey M. Depew reforming the abuses of the railroads, or Thomas C. Platt stopping the
					extortion of the express companies, in the interest of the people!</p>
				<p>The Pennsylvania Railroad company dictated the recent election of the United States
					senators from Pennsylvania, and the most flagitious political debauchery attended the
					election of many others, such proceedings being regarded as so entirely in consonance with
					our capitalist-owned republic as to excite little more than passing notice.</p>
				<p>Only a short time ago the late John H. Reagan, the venerable ex-senator of Texas, in
					discussing the federal courts, said that he expected no improvement in them "as long as
					railroad lawyers are allowed to go on the bench to interpret legislation affecting the
					management of the railroads." As long as the railroads are privately owned they will have
					their judges on the bench, and the government, that is to say, the capitalist politicians,
					will do their bidding.</p>
				<p>Judge Reagan closed his sweeping arraignment of the courts as follows: "I have seen such
					gross perversions of the law by the courts that I have lost confidence in them and <pb
						id="VAC0877-016" n="16"/> regret I cannot feel the respect for them that I once
					felt."</p>
				<p>These are ominous words and from a source that gives them the weight of high
					authority.</p>
				<p>Census figures recently published show that "every fifth child between the ages of ten
					and fifteen in the United States is a breadwinner. One out of every three of these
					children workers is a girl. There are one million seven hundred and fifty thousand one
					hundred and seventy-eight children employed, an increase of thirty three and one-third per
					cent in ten years."</p>
				<p>The land frauds, postal steals, and Indian graft all cry out in condemnation of private
					ownership of capital, the source and inspiration of all the political corruption that,
					like a pestilence, blights the land.</p>
				<p>Charles F. Kelly, speaker of the house of delegates, at St. Louis, the convicted boodler,
					in making his confession, described in a few graphic words the methods and motives of
					office-holders and politicians in the grab-all regime of profitocracy. Said he: "Our 
					combine was not along party lines. Both democrats and republicans belonged to it. My 
					experience has been that boodlers line up according to their own interests, and not under
					party standards. In the majority of the wards of St. Louis both the democratic party and
					the republican usually nominate men to go to <pb id="VAC0877-017" n="17"/> the house of
					delegates for the money they can get out of it. Each party man votes for his own fellows,
					and either one that gets in serves those who rob the city of franchises."</p>
				<p>Be it noted that the corrupters of courts, the bribers of legislators, and the debauchers
					of public morals are all capitalists in high standing, the gentry whose subservient and
					hypocritical underlings are forever preaching about "law and order" to the working
					class.</p>
				<p>In the face of these frightful eruptions on the body-politic, President Roosevelt coolly
					informs us that we are passing through a period of "noteworthy prosperity," and that "we
					must raise still higher our standard of commercial ethics, and we must insist more and
					more upon those fundamental principles of our country--equality before the law and
					obedience to the law. <hi rend="b">In no other way can the advance of Socialism, whether
						evolutionary or revolutionary, be checked."</hi></p>
				<p>The words "still higher" seem like sarcasm when applied to our so-called "standard of
					commercial ethics," that is mired in profit-mongering and can never rise above the sordid
					level of brutal self-interest in the declining stages of the competitive system.</p>
				<p>The commercial pirates who rob the nation of its franchises and organize monopolies to
					exploit the people are not in the business of <pb id="VAC0877-018" n="18"/> raising the
					standards of ethics, commercial or otherwise. The only ethics they know is to "get there;"
					the end always justifying the means.</p>
				<p>Just at present President Roosevelt, typical capitalist executive that he is, is after
					the railroads--so we are told. His organs assure us that he proposes to bring these great
					corporations to their knees, and make them obey the law and stop robbing the people. And
					yet, President Roosevelt has had one of these criminal offenders in his own cabinet.</p>
				<p>It is known of all men that Paul Morton, late secretary of the navy, is a self-confessed
					lawbreaker who would now be serving a prison sentence if the law in his case had been
					enforced.</p>
				<p>Then, again, can President Roosevelt consistently crack the whip above the heads of these
					corporations after sharing in the special privileges they enjoy at the expense of the
					people? In making his political campaigns, and on other occasions since he has become a
					commanding figure in national politics, the railroad corporations have provided Mr.
					Roosevelt with the most luxurious special trains, sumptuously furnished and abundantly
					stocked, <hi rend="b">free of charge.</hi> The thousands of dollars of expense thus
					incurred by the railroad corporations could not have been without some consideration, and,
					whatever that <pb id="VAC0877-019" n="19"/> may be, it is not calculated to inspire self-
					respecting and candid men who think for themselves with faith in the sincerity of the
					president when he vaults into the arena to do battle against the railroads as the champion
					of the people.</p>
				<p>It is not to reform the evils of the day, but to abolish the social system that produces
					them, that the Socialist party is organized. It is the party, not of reform, but of
					revolution, knowing that the capitalist system has had its day and that a new social
					order, based upon a new system of industry, must soon supplant the fast decaying one we
					now have.</p>
				<p>Every social system changes ceaselessly, and, ultimately, having fulfilled its mission,
					passes away.</p>
				<p>Capitalism is the connecting link between feudalism and Socialism.</p>
				<p>The industrial forces are now making for Socialism, preparing the way for it, and sooner
					or later it is sure to come.</p>
				<p>On the one hand the capitalist class are combining their resources, centralizing their
					capital, co-operating instead of competing, organizing industry, and eliminating
					competition. This is the new and better way. It is good as far as it goes. It is the
					limited application of the economic principles of Socialism.</p>
				<p>On the other hand, the working class are <pb id="VAC0877-020" n="20"/> organizing. They
					are beginning to spell solidarity and to pronounce Socialism. They are yearning for
					emancipation from the galling yoke of wage-slavery, and with all the power of their minds,
					all the strength of their bodies and all the passion of their souls they are crusading
					against the ignorance of their fellow-workers and the prejudice of the people.</p>
				<p>Steadily the number of class-conscious toilers is increasing, and higher and higher rises
					the tide that is to sweep away the barriers to progress and civilization.</p>
				<p>Let others talk about the tariff and finance --the enlightened workers demand the
					ownership of the tools of industry and they are building up the Socialist party as a means
					of getting them.</p>
				<p rend="b">The working class alone made the tools; the working class alone can use them,
					and the working class must, therefore, own them.</p>
				<p>This is the revolutionary demand of the Socialist movement. The propaganda is one of
					education and is perfectly orderly and peaceable. The workers must be taught to unite and
					vote together <hi rend="b">as a class</hi> in support of the Socialist party, the party
					that represents them as a class,and when they do this the government will pass into their
					hands and capitalism will fall to rise no more; private ownership will give way to social
					ownership, <pb id="VAC0877-021" n="21"/> and production for profit to production for use;
					the wage-system will disappear, and with it the ignorance and poverty, misery and crime
					that wage-slavery breeds; the working class will stand forth triumphant and free, and a
					new era will dawn in human progress and in the civilization of mankind.</p>
			</div1>

		</body>
		<back>
			<pb id="VAC0877-022" n="[22]"/>
			<div1 type="advertisemnet">
				<head rend="center b">THE MAGAZINE FOR WORKERS</head>
				<p rend="center b">"Absolutely the finest Socialist publication I have ever come across," is
					what a man in England wrote in renewing his subscription to THE INTERNATIONAL SOCIALIST
					REWIEW the magazine that fights for the working class.</p>
				<p>The R<hi rend="sc">EVIEW</hi> is the only publication of its kind in the world. It is the
					only monthly illustrated magazine which is devoted exclusively to the interests of working
					men and working women. It is the only magazine which actually gets <hi rend="i">right down
						into the ranks</hi> of the toilers and tells what they are doing and thinking and
					feeling. It stands for <hi rend="center b">REVOLUTIONARY SOCIALISM,</hi> aggressive and
					uncompromising. The R<hi rend="sc">EVIEW</hi> is not only a magazine for Socialists; it is
					with the workers everywhere in their every struggle, not only in America but in other
					countries as well. Wherever there is a conflict between men and masters, there the Review
					has its correspondents and its photographers. Every month it is filled with pictures right
					from the scene of action. Its articles and stories come not only from trained writers but
					from the workers themselves. Its circulation has <hi rend="i">tripled in the last four
						years</hi>. It is growing bigger and better from month to month.</p>
				<p rend="b">10 cents a copy; S1.00 a Year; 20 copies for $1.00</p>
				<p rend="center b">Special terms to Agents. Address</p>
				<p rend="b">CHARLES H. KERR &amp; CO. 118 West Kinzie St.. CHICAGO</p>
				<p rend="b">Largest Publishers of Socialist Literature in the World</p>
			</div1>


			<pb id="VAC0877-023" n="[23]"/>
			<div1 type="advertisement">
				<head rend="center b">ANCIENT SOCIETY<lb/> OR<lb/> Researches in the Lines of Human
					Progress: From Savagery Through Barbarism to Civilization</head>
				<p>One American and only one is recognized by the universities of Europe as one of the
					world's great scientists. That American is <hi rend="b">Lewis H. Morgan,</hi> the author
					of this book. He was the pioneer writer on the subject. His conclusions have been fully
					sustained by later investigators.</p>
				<p>This work contains a full and clear explanation of many vitally important facts, without
					which no intelligent discussion of the "Woman Question" is possible. It shows that the
					successive marriage customs that have arisen have corresponded to certain definite
					industrial conditions. The author shows that it is industrial changes that alter the
					relations of the sexes, and that these changes are still going on. He shows the historical
					reason for the "double standard of morals" for men and women, over which reformers have
					wailed in vain. And he points the way to a cleaner, freer, happier life for women in the
					future, through the triumph of the working class. All this is shown indirectly through
					historical facts; the reader is left to draw his own conclusions.</p>
				<p>Cloth, 586 large pages, gold stamping. Until lately this book could not be bought for
					less than $4.00, Our pride is $1.50, and we will mail the book to YOU for 50c, provided
					you send $1.00 <hi rend="b i">at the same time</hi> for a year's subscription to the <hi
						rend="b">International Socialist Review</hi>. Address</p>
				<p rend="b">Charles H. Kerr &amp; Company</p>
				<p>118 West Kinzie Street, Chicago</p>
			</div1>


			<pb id="VAC0877-024" n="[24]"/>
			<div1 type="advertisement">
				<head rend="center"><hi rend="b">THE HAPPY HUNTING GROUNDS</hi><lb/> By James Hightower, the
					son of<lb/> a full-blooded Cherokee Indian.</head>
				<p>A real story of a real Indian; how the Indian boys helped gather supplies for winter; how
					they trapped the "varmints" and stalked big game; how they fished, made their paints,
					their clothes and their houses; how they learned to imitate the animals of the forest.</p>
				<p><figure>
						<head rend="right supplied">The Happy Hunting Grounds</head>
					</figure></p>
				<p>Terrible adventures and daring achievements come thick and fast; the Indian boys have a
					thrilling fight with a black bear; they are tracked by a panther and chased by the
					wolves.</p>
				<p>The only book by a real Indian you have ever read. Interesting and true from cover to
					cover; the boys and girls will find it the most thrilling story in their collection, and
					it will teach them more than a dozen books on natural history. Best of all, it will help
					them later on to understand what our Socialist writers say about the primitive communism
					in which our ancestors lived before capitalism began. It was from the Indians that Morgan
					learned most of the facts in "Ancient Society."</p>
				<p rend="center">Cloth, illustrated, $1.00 postpaid.</p>
				<p rend="center">Address</p>
				<p rend="center b">CHARLES H. KERR &amp; COMPANY</p>
				<p rend="center b">118 West Kinzie Street, CHICAGO</p>
			</div1>


			<pb id="VAC0877-025" n="[25]"/>
			<div1 type="advertisement">
				<head rend="center b">THE MILITANT PROLETARIAT</head>
				<milestone unit="typography" n="* * * * * "/>
				<p>Austin Lewis, already long recognized as one of the foremost Socialist writers in
					America, has now made what time will prove to be the most valuable American contribution
					to the literature of Socialism thus far produced. His new book, <hi rend="b">The Militant
						Proletariat,</hi> applies the fundamental principles of Socialism to the most recent
					economic and social developments. The great Socialist classics were written a generation
					or more ago. Marx prophesied the American trust. Now in all its fullness it is here. How
					is it to be met by the political and industrial organizations of the working class? For
					five years heated discussions have centered around this question. In <hi rend="b">The
						Militant Proletariat</hi> Austin Lewis presents the most valuable results of this
					discussion. No wide-awake Socialist will fail to read it. Cloth, 50 cents.</p>
				<p rend="center">CHARLES H. KERR &amp; COMPANY,</p>
				<p rend="center">118 West Kinzie Street, Chicago.</p>
			</div1>


			<pb id="VAC0877-026" n="[26]"/>
			<div1 type="advertisement">
				<head rend="center b">PURITANISM</head>
				<p>America and England inherit from long-past economic and historical conditions a peculiar
					disease from which the wage-workers of other countries are usually free, but from which
					American wage-workers must cure themselves by a conscious effort. This disease is called
						<hi rend="b">Puritanism</hi>, and its cause and cure are not by any means generally
					known. <hi rend="b">Clarence Meily</hi> has written a short book that explains the whole
					subject in a clear, scientific, straightforward fashion that will convince any
					unprejudiced reader and probably even some who have been prejudiced. He shows that the so-
					called virtues of the Puritan had a very distinct economic reason which was perfectly
					valid in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries for the little capitalists who preached
					and practised the virtues, but that they are positively harmful to any wage-workers who
					foolishly accept the Puritan code to-day. Cloth, 50c.</p>
				<p rend="b">Prices include postage.</p>
				<p rend="center b">CHARLES H. KERR &amp; COMPANY,</p>
				<p rend="center b">Publishers, Chicago.</p>
			</div1>


			<pb id="VAC0877-027" n="[27]"/>
			<div1 type="advertisement">
				<head rend="center b">GREAT AMERICAN FORTUNES.</head>
				<milestone unit="typography" n="* * * * * "/>
				<p>From time immemorial paid biographers, parasitical panegyrists, preachers and Sunday
					school teachers have sung the praises of the rich and wealthy citizens of the land;
					muckrakers have muckraked Rockefeller and members of the Standard Oil Company group until
					a magazine no longer sells merely because it is publishing stories of graft and
					corruption; books have been published by the score telling magnificent and marvelous tales
					concerning the holders of the great fortunes of the United States, but it has fallen to
					the lot of Gustavus Myers to write the first full and authentic account of the actual
					sources of these vast accumulations of wealth and to disclose the methods used in their
					acquisitions. His "History of Great American Fortunes," in three volumes, published by
					Kerr &amp; Company, of Chicago, marks an era in the field of economic research.</p>
				<p>Mr. Myers is unlike most authors in that he has no axe to grind, he has no philosophy to
					preach, he has no monthly check from capitalist or corporation. He is a searcher after
					truth, and, unlike most writers, he does not hesitate to publish the facts when he finds
					them, be they good or bad. The result is a three-volume work filled to the brim with
					startling disclosures and surprising statements based upon Congressional and State
					documents, <pb id="VAC0877-028" n="[28]"/> court records and various other authoritative
					sources. At no stage of his narrative does Mr. Myers mince his words; he bores directly
					into the heart of his subject and leaves nothing undone to show that our parents and
					teachers have filled our minds with falsehoods of the most baseless sort when we were
					children by telling us that as we grew up we could become wealthy and still retain our
					ideals of honesty, in both theory and practice. Through three volumes containing more than
					a thousand pages Mr. Myers gives us a most depressing story of the graft, bribery,
					corruption, avarice, debauchery and chicanery lying behind the great American fortunes.
					Truthfully, the story is a sickening recital of man's inhumanity to man in his greedy
					pursuit of wealth, but it is nevertheless a work which should be read by every American
					citizen be he high or low, rich or poor, naturalized or native.</p>
				<p>Volume I, already in its second edition, tells the economic conditions prevailing during
					the colonial period of the United States, and of the origin and development of the large
					land fortunes such as those of the Astor and Marshall Field families. Volume II, also in
					its second edition, and Volume III, just published, deal with the great railroad fortunes
					of Vanderbilt, Gould, Sage, Elkins, Hill, Morgan and others. It is in this volume that the
					author devotes a chapter to the Pacific quartet, composed of Huntington, Crocker, Stanford
					and Hopkins. Future volumes are to describe the acquisition of vast railroad <pb
						id="VAC0877-029" n="[29]"/> properties by Harriman and the Standard Oil Company, and
					will also deal with those great fortunes which have grown out of the control of public
					franchises, mines and various manufacturing industries.</p>
				<p>The author arrives at no conclusions as a result of his investigations, but leaves the
					readers to do so in accordance with the facts which he has presented. In brief, there can
					be but one conclusion, and that is that thrift, temperance and hard work are not the
					recipe for getting rich, else many millions of people who have to work hard and who are
					thrifty and temperate would forthwith become so. Through all fortunes large and small
					there runs the same heavy streak of fraud and theft, of bribery, graft and corruption. The
					little trader with his misrepresentation and swindling is different from the "big fellow"
					in degree only.</p>
				<p>The three volumes will prove to be a perfect arsenal of facts for the economist,
					newspaper man, trade unionist and reformer. They will take their place among the season's
					books as the most important work ever issued in this field, far surpassing any other study
					of the same sort by their scope, by their foundation on facts disclosed by years of
					patient study and investigation, by the temperate yet graphic and sarcastic presentation
					of the author, and by many other things which mark them as a most unique contribution to
					the economic literature of our time.--<hi rend="i">Prof. Ira B. Cross. in San Francisco
						Bulletin.</hi></p>


				<pb id="VAC0877-030" n="[30]"/>

				<p rend="center b">SPECIAL COMBINATION OFFER.</p>
				<p>We want to make it possible for a million wage-workers to read Gustavus Myers' History
					of the American Fortunes. Our retail price for the three volumes, $4.50, is very low
					considering the heavy expenses involved in publishing the book. But we realize that it is
					a large sum for the average wage-worker. So we have devised a plan by which you can get
					the full set of books without paying a cent, but simply in return for a little easy
					work.</p>
				<p>THE INTERNATIONAL SOCIALIST REVIEW is now a large, popular, illustrated magazine, that
					every intelligent wage-worker WANTS as soon as he sees it. Only a few newsdealers sell it,
					and the only sure way to get a copy promptly each month is to pay $1.00 for a year's
					subscription.</p>
				<p>If YOU will send us $5,00 with the names of five yearly subscribers for the REVIEW, we
					will send as your premium a full set of GREAT AMERICAN FORTUNES, also a cloth-bound copy
					of SOCIALISM FOR STUDENTS, by Joseph E. Cohen. If you are in a hurry for the books and
					have not found the names, send the $5,00 and we will send the books together with five
					yearly Review Subscription Cards. If you have not the money to spare, write us for a
					package of Reviews free to use as samples in taking subscriptions.</p>
				<p>Address</p>
				<p rend="center b">CHARLES H. KERR &amp; COMPANY</p>
				<p rend="left b">118 West Kinzie Street</p>
				<p rend="right b">Chicago</p>
			</div1>


			<pb id="VAC0877-031" n="[31]"/>
			<div1 type="advertisement">
				<head rend="center b">Don't Talk Socialism</head>
				<milestone unit="typography" n="* * * * * "/>
				<p>without first studying. It is too big a subject to learn from one booklet. But it costs
					only a little in time and money to get a clear understanding of the subject.</p>
				<milestone unit="typography" n="* * * * * "/>
				<p><hi rend="i">INDUSTRIAL SOCIALISM</hi>, by William D. Haywood and Frank Bohn, is the best
					general explanation of Socialism for beginners. Price 10 cents.</p>
				<milestone unit="typography" n="* * * * * "/>
				<p><hi rend="i">SHOP TALKS ON ECONOMICS</hi>, by Mary E. Marcy, shows how the unpaid labor
					of the wage-worker makes profits for the capitalist, and why no reforms can benefit the
					working class. Price 10 cents.</p>
				<milestone unit="typography" n="* * * * * "/>
				<p><hi rend="i">THE CLASS STRUGGLE</hi>, by Karl Kautsky, one of the greatest Socialist
					books ever writen, explains the whole structure of capitalist society and of the Socialist
					Republic of the future. Cloth, 50 cents; paper, 25 cents.</p>
				<milestone unit="typography" n="* * * * * "/>
				<p>The Appeal to Reason, Girard, Kansas, 50 cents a year, is the greatest Socialist weekly
					in the world, with a circulation of more than half a million.</p>
				<milestone unit="typography" n="* * * * * "/>
				<p>The International Socialist Review is the only great illustrated magazine advocating
					socialism. $1.00 a year, 10 cents a copy. This and the books named above are published
					by</p>
				<p rend="center b">CHARLES H. KERR &amp; COMPANY</p>
				<p>118 W. Kinzie Street :: Chicago</p>
			</div1>


			<pb id="VAC0877-032" n="[32]"/>
			<div1 type="advertisement">
				<head rend="center b">DEBS<lb/>
					<hi rend="center b">His Life, Writings and Speeches.</hi></head>
				<p>Socialists are not hero-worshipers. We do not put our faith in leaders. Methods of class
					warfare do not come from the brains of the isolated scholar, but from the brains and
					experience of fighters.</p>
				<p>That is why we publish the life, writings and speeches of Eugene V. Debs. He has never
					set himself up as a leader or the labor movement. But by choice of it, joy in it, love of
					it, he has remained a part of the movement itself. Separate him from the revolutionary
					working class movement and you lose Eugene V. Debs. He is bone of its bone, flesh of its
					flesh. His very life, his hopes and aims are interwoven into the very mesh of the labor
					movement.</p>
				<p>All his writings the he thinks worth preserving are included in this book, which also
					tells the story of his life and work.</p>
				<p>Two large editions have been sold at $2.00 a copy. But Debs does not wish to make money
					from the book; he wishes to carry the message of socialism to an ever growing circle of
					readers. He has therefore authorized our co-operative publishing house to bring out a new,
					neat, compact library edition, illustrated, and containing over 500 pages, at a dollar a
					copy, postpaid, with special prices to comrades who buy in quantities and put their energy
					into finding new readers. We will send five copies by express prepaid for $3.00 or twenty
					copies by express prepaid for $10.00. Address</p>
				<p rend="center b">Charles H. Kerr &amp; Company</p>
				<p rend="center b">118 West Kinzie St., Chicago</p>
			</div1>


		</back>

	</text>
</TEI.2>
