<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//IA Books//DTD TEI for Indiana Authors Books//EN"
                       "teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="VAC0881">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">The mission to the Ouabache</title>
				<author>Dunn, Jacob Piatt, 1855-1924.</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded By</resp>
					<!--Update the value of the element below with your name in
					direct order.-->
					<!--Brenda Beaman.-->
					<name>Brenda Beaman</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
				<address>
                    <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
                </address>
				<idno>VAC0881</idno>
				<availability status="unknown">
					<p>Copyright 2009 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
					<p>Indiana University provides the information contained on this web site for
						non-commercial, personal, or research use only. All other use, including but not limited
						to commercial or scholarly reproductions, redistribution, publication or transmission,
						whether by electronic means or otherwise, without prior written permission of the
						copyright holder is strictly prohibited.</p>
				</availability>
				<!--Update the value of the date element with the year the document
                        is being encoded.-->
				<date>2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblFull>
					<titleStmt>
						<title type="main">The mission to the Ouabache</title>
						<author id="ina-v1-entry-0263">Dunn, Jacob Piatt, 1855-1924</author>
					</titleStmt>
					<extent>255-330 p. front. (facsim. in 6 fold. l.) 25 cm.</extent>
					<publicationStmt>
						<publisher>The Bowen-Merrill company</publisher>
						<pubPlace>Indianapolis</pubPlace>
						<date>1902</date>
					</publicationStmt>
					<seriesStmt>
						<p>Indiana Historical Society publications ; v. 3, no. 4</p>
					</seriesStmt>
				</biblFull>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>The Digital Library Program was awarded a Library Services and Technology Act (LSTA)
					grant in 2005 to make available online the three-volume, reference work, <title>Indiana
						Authors and Their Books</title> along with selected monographs by Indiana authors.</p>
			</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl n="3">
				<p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and has
					been encoded and edited using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
					Guidelines following the TEI Lite standard. Digital page images are linked to the text
					file.</p>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<tagUsage gi="div1">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy id="lcsh">
					<bibl>
						<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language>English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="lcsh">
					<list>
						<item>Catholic Church --Mississippi River Valley.</item>
						<item>Indians of North America.</item>
						<item>Vincennes (Ind.)--History.</item>
						<item>Wabash River Valley--History.</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<!--The revision description tracks significant changes made to the file
                    after completion. This information will remain commented out unless someone has
                    conducted quality assessment of the texts and have made changes to the file as a
                    result.-->
		<!-- <revisionDesc> <change>
                    <date>$Date</date> <respStmt>
                    <name>$Name</name>
                    <resp>$Responsibility</resp>
                    </respStmt> <item>$Changes</item>
                    </change> </revisionDesc> -->
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>


			<pb id="VAC0881-001" n="[]"/>

			<titlePage>
				<docTitle>


					<titlePart type="series"><hi rend="sc">INDIANA HISTORICAL SOCIETY PUBLICATIONS.<lb/>
							VOLUME III. NUMBER IV.</hi></titlePart>
					<lb/>

					<titlePart type="main">THE MISSION<lb/>
						<hi rend="sc">TO THE</hi><lb/> OUABACHE</titlePart>
				</docTitle>

				<byline>
					<hi rend="sc">BY</hi><lb/>
					<docAuthor>JACOB PIATT DUNN.</docAuthor></byline>


				<docImprint><pubPlace>INDIANAPOLIS:</pubPlace><lb/>
					<publisher>THE BOWEN-MERRILL COMPANY.</publisher><lb/>
					<docDate>1902.</docDate></docImprint>
			</titlePage>


			<pb id="VAC0881-002" n="[]"/>
		</front>
		<body>
			<p/>
			<pb id="VAC0881-003" n="255"/>

			<div1 type="book">

				<head rend="center">THE MISSION TO THE OUABACHE.</head>

				<milestone unit="typography" n="-----" rend="center"/>

				<p>To the student who enjoys puzzling over knotty problems, the early history of Post
					Vincennes has long afforded an interesting field. The chief source of perplexity has been
					a lack of authentic documents, but this has been added to by the change of nations in
					control of the region, and a change in nomenclature that has not always been fully allowed
					for. Perhaps the most important instance of this was in the word "Ouabache," which is
					frequently taken as equivalent to "Wabash," and so it was in its later use, but for many
					years it signified not only the river Wabash as we know it, but also the Ohio river from
					the mouth of the Wabash to the Mississippi. In other words, up to the middle of the
					eighteenth century, the Wabash was treated as the main stream and the Ohio as a tributary
					of it. As the word "Ouabache" was used in this sense all through the period to which this
					paper refers, and has this signification in all the documents hereto appended, it has been
					deemed best to leave it in this form without any attempt at translation.</p>
				<p>It was the ambiguity of this word that led Judge Law, although he understood and stated
					its earlier meaning, to confound Post Vincennes with the post established by Sieur
					Juchereau at the mouth of the Ohio, on the site of Cairo, Ill., in 1702, at which place
					the historic discussion between Father Mermet and the Indian medicine-man occurred.<ref
						id="ref_001" rend="super" target="note_001">1</ref> This error was followed by others,
					some ignorantly <note id="note_001"><ref target="ref_001" rend="super">1</ref> Shea's
						Charlevoix, Vol. V, p. 133.</note>
					<pb id="VAC0881-004" n="256"/> and some with deliberate intent to fabricate history, the
					latter asserting that Post Vincennes was originally established by Sieur Juchereau. This
					was an inexcusable absurdity, for the one point that has been clear and unquestionable all
					the time, and as to which all the testimony is in entire harmony, is that our post was
					established by Sieur de Vincennes. The location of Juchereau's post is unquestionable. Its
					complete history is preserved in contemporary official documents. It was abandoned three
					years after it was established, and existed thereafter only as a landmark.<ref
						id="ref_002" rend="super" target="note_002">2</ref></p>
				<p>The exact identity of Sieur de Vincennes has not yet been established beyond the
					possibility of question,<ref id="ref_003" rend="super" target="note_003">3</ref> but it is
					known certainly that he commanded at the post from the time of its foundation until 1736,
					when he was killed in the war against the Chickasaws. The post did not take his name for
					some years after his death. It was at first commonly referred to as "Au Ouabache," and the
					first official title given it was "Poste des Pianguichats." After Louis St. Ange assumed
					command, following the death of Vincennes, it was often called Poste St. Ange, which was
					anglicized to "Ft. St. Anne." It was also known as "Little Ouyatanon," which on English
					maps appeared in the abbreviated form "L. Wiaut." About the middle of the eighteenth
					century the name "Vincennes" began to be applied to it, but more commonly it was known
					simply as "the post," and from the phrase "au poste" came the name "Opost," which is often
					given to it in early American documents.</p>
				<p>Up to the present time the nearest approach to a documentary account of the establishment
					of the post that has been discovered and published, is the letter from the Company <note
						id="note_002"><ref target="ref_002" rend="super">2</ref> Dunn's Indiana, pp. 36-40;
						Magazine of Western History, Vol. XII, p. 579; Magazine of American History, Vol. XXII,
						p. 143.</note>
					<note id="note_003"><ref target="ref_003" rend="super">3</ref>Ind. Hist. Soc. Pubs., Vol.
						III, No. 2.</note>
					<pb id="VAC0881-005" n="257"/> of the Indies to M. Perier, then governor of Louisiana,
					directing the establishment.<ref id="ref_004" rend="super" target="note_004">4</ref> This
					is dated September 30, 1726. From this it appears that Sieur de Vincennes was then
					commanding at the home of the Ouiatanons, who were established on the Wabash, just below
					the site of Lafayette, and within the jurisdiction of Canada. The plan of the Company was
					for Vincennes to induce these Indians to remove to the Ohio river above the mouth of the
					Wabash, and to build a fort at the mouth of the Tennessee river. But this direction was
					not absolute, and the most significant part of the letter is in these words: <q
						rend="blockquote"> "M. Perier will reflect well on this subject, and consider if, by
						giving eight or ten soldiers to the said Sieur de Vincennes, with the missionary
						destined for the Ouabache, he will not find himself in condition to assure, by the
						Indians, the communication between Louisiana and Canada, and to prevent the English from
						penetrating into our colony, without obliging the Company to construct a fort on the
						lower Ouabache, of which the expense of the establishment and the support of the
						garrison make an object of consequence."</q></p>
				<p>This is the course which was, in reality, attempted to be followed, and it will be noted
					that what was contemplated was not the fortification of an existing French village, but
					the transfer of an Indian tribe to unoccupied territory, the formation of a small military
					establishment, and the erection of a new Indian mission.</p>
				<p>But who was "the missionary destined for the Ouabache," and how was he destined? There is
					a hazy impression in the minds of many persons that the Catholic missionaries of the
					eighteenth century used to roam through the wilderness rather at random, seeking for
					Indians whom they might convert. As a matter of fact, <note id="note_004"><ref
							target="ref_004" rend="super">4</ref>Margry's Découvertes et Etablissements des
						Francais dans L'Amerique Septentrionale, Vol. VI, pp. 659-60; Dunn's Indiana, p.
						53.</note>
					<pb id="VAC0881-006" n="258"/> missionary undertakings of that period were on quite as
					systematic a basis as those of the present day. The missionary had to be supported, and in
					the Province of Louisiana, in which Post Vincennes was included, provision was made either
					by the company in control, or by the crown, for both subsistence and salary of every
					priest or other clerical engaged in missionary work. Fortunately, a concise, and
					apparently reliable memoir on the church establishment of this period, in the province of
					Louisiana, is preserved in the French archives at Paris,<ref id="ref_005" rend="super"
						target="note_005">5</ref> and I quote from it the following: <q rend="blockquote"><p>"By
							ordinance of the Commissioners of the Council, of May 16, 1722, made with the consent
							of the Bishop of Quebec, the Province of Louisiana was divided into three religious
							jurisdictions.</p></q>
					<q rend="blockquote"><p>"The first included all the country which is found in ascending
							the river St. Louis (Mississippi) from the sea to the height of the entry of the river
							Ouabache (Ohio) into the river St. Louis; and all that part to the west of this river
							in the said extent of country. The churches and missions of this jurisdiction were to
							be filled by the Capuchins, and their superior officer was to be always grand vicar of
							the Bishop of Quebec in the department, and to reside at New Orleans.</p></q>
					<q rend="blockquote"><p>"The second jurisdiction was to extend over all the country which
							is found in the upper part of the province above the river Ouabache, and was to be in
							control of the Jesuits, whose superior officer, residing at the Illinois, was to be
							always grand vicar of the Bishop of Quebec in this part. <note id="note_005"><ref
									target="ref_005" rend="super">5</ref>Memoir Concerning the Church of Louisiana
								(1722-1728) Dated Nov. 21, 1728. From the Archives of the Ministry of Marine;
								Appended to the Edition of Madeleine Hachard's Letters under the title of "Relation
								of the Voyage of the Ursuline Sisters of Rouen," etc., by Gabriel Gravier, Paris,
								1872.</note></p></q>
					<pb id="VAC0881-007" n="259"/>
					<q rend="blockquote"><p>"The third was to extend over all the country which is found to
							the east of the river (Mississippi), from the sea to the Ouabache, and was to be given
							to the Carmellites, whose superior officer was likewise grand vicar, and was
							established ordinarily at Mobile.</p></q>
					<q rend="blockquote"><p>"In the same year the Capuchins took possession of their district.
							The Jesuits had been for a long time established in theirs. The Carmellites were at
							Mobile, but the Bishop of Quebec, little satisfied with their management, united their
							jurisdiction to that of the Capuchins by ordinance of December 19, 1722, and they
							returned to France.</p></q>
					<q rend="blockquote"><p>"In the month of December, 1723, the Company, judging that the
							Capuchins would not be able to furnish enough clergymen to supply all the curés and
							missions in a region so vast as that which had been given to them, fixed the boundary
							of their jurisdiction at Natchez, leaving to them all the country below this post, in
							descending the river, both to the east and to the west, and giving the remainder to
							the Jesuits, who, in this department, had for fellow-laborers two priests of the
							foreign missions.</p></q>
					<q rend="blockquote"><p>"This arrangement alarmed the Capuchins; they demanded guaranty of
							that which remained to them, although that which remained to them comprised a very
							large extent of country, and the most thickly settled. The Company, to tranquilize
							them, drew up, on June 17, 1725, an ordinance providing that all the curés and
							missions established and to be established in the country last reserved to the
							Capuchins should be filled by them, without putting any other friars or priests there
							except by their consent. This was, according to their desire, confirmed by a patent of
							the King on July 15, 1725.</p></q>
					<q rend="blockquote"><p>"But the Capuchins had more of zeal than ability to furnish men.
							The parish of Champagne, from which those of Louisiana came, is small and unfruitful
							of subjects. The Company, then seeing that they were not providing <pb
								id="VAC0881-008" n="260"/> as many clergymen as were needed to fill the
							ecclesiastical posts of their district, and knowing elsewhere that they were little
							fitted for missions among the savages, decided that it was absolutely necessary to
							establish a new partition, which being fitted to the character and the particular
							talents of the two orders, fixed unalterably their relations from this time forward.
							It decided to establish the Capuchins in all the French posts, and to charge the
							Jesuits with the spiritual management of the savages, under the will and pleasure of
							the Bishop of Quebec, who had warmly approved this arrangement by his letters.
						</p></q>
					<q rend="blockquote"><p>"In consequence it made an agreement on February 20, 1726, with
							the Jesuit Fathers, by which they engaged to furnish missionaries not only in all the
							places of their district, but also at the homes of the savage nations, where it might
							be to the interest of religion and of the state to establish them, in the territory
							formerly conceded to the Capuchins.</p></q>
					<q rend="blockquote"><p>"It was not possible to avoid, in this agreement, according an
							establishment in New Orleans to the superior of the Jesuit missions. He could not
							receive without it those who came from France for his missions. It is this residence,
							moreover, which puts him in position to render account to the Commandant-General, and
							to the council, of that which the missionaries inform him touching the disposition of
							the savages, whose friendship is our security. But the Company did not accord this
							establishment to the superior of the Jesuits except on the condition that there should
							not be any ecclesiastical functions without the consent of the Capuchins.</p></q>
					<q rend="blockquote"><p>"In the month of December, 1726, there departed from France the
							number of Jesuits necessary to supply the missions which they had agreed to establish.
							Their arrival at New Orleans and the publication of their agreement caused at first a
							great deal of jealousy in the Capuchins, but as <pb id="VAC0881-009" n="261"/> this
							jealousy was poorly founded it would have been easily explained and all would have
							been tranquil if Pere Beaubois, superior of the Jesuit missions, had been punctual to
							keep his engagements. He had agreed, in drawing up the articles of agreement with the
							Company, on the express condition <hi rend="i">that there should not be at New Orleans
								any ecclesiastical function without the consent of the Capuchins.</hi> He had signed
							with his superiors the same agreement carrying this condition. He had promised M. de
							Mornai, then coadjutor and now Bishop of Quebec, to comply with it faithfully. And
							finally he had written to Pere Raphael, superior of the Capuchins, that he was soon
							coming to New Orleans to live there as a plain, private citizen, and meanwhile, during
							all this time, he was working at Quebec with the bishop to have him accord to him the
							rank and authority of his grand vicar, even for New Orleans.</p></q>
					<q rend="blockquote"><p>"Arrived in this city with the reply of the bishop, which was
							nothing more than a simple acquiescence in his demand, he pretended that this
							acquiescence was an absolute order, a command from the master. He lodged the letter of
							the prelate, at this rating, in the public record office; he carried himself haughtily
							as grand vicar; exercised the functions; made himself superior of the Ursuline
							community; and seized all authority. The Company has the proof of all these facts and
							of the scandal which resulted; and these proofs are such that the superiors of Pere de
							Beaubois simply deposed and dismissed him after having read them.</p></q>
					<q rend="blockquote"><p>"This dismissal was the more necessary because the Capuchins
							seriously demanded to return to France if Pere de Beaubois remained; because M. de
							Mornai on whom Monseignieur of Quebec had conferred all his authority over the church
							of Louisiana demanded of the Company the removal of this priest; and because M. de la
							Chaise, with whom he was excessively embroiled, was not able to put <pb
								id="VAC0881-010" n="262"/> up with him any longer. According to the last letters of
							M. de la Chaise and those of Pere Raphael there is every reason to hope for a good
							understanding between the two orders, Pere Petit, who succeeded Pere de Beaubois,
							being, according to assurances, of a character very moderate and very
						circumsect.</p></q>
					<q rend="blockquote"><p>"Here should be added the list of the missionaries and of the
							places where they labor:</p>
						<table rows="10" cols="2">

							<head rend="center b">CAPUCHINS.</head>

							<row role="label">

								<cell>Pere Raphael, Vicar-General of the Bishop of Quebec, and Curé of the
									City</cell>
								<cell>At New Orleans</cell>
							</row>

							<row>
								<cell>Pere Hyacinthe, Vicar</cell>
								<cell>At New Orleans</cell>
							</row>

							<row>
								<cell>Pere Cécile, Schoolmaster</cell>
								<cell>At New Orleans</cell>
							</row>

							<row>
								<cell>Pere Theodore</cell>
								<cell>With the Chapitoulas</cell>
							</row>

							<row>
								<cell>Pere Philippe</cell>
								<cell>At Village Ailemand</cell>
							</row>

							<row>
								<cell>Pere Gaspard</cell>
								<cell>At Balize</cell>
							</row>

							<row>
								<cell>Pore Mathias</cell>
								<cell>At Mobile</cell>
							</row>

							<row>
								<cell>Pere Maximin</cell>
								<cell>With the Natchitoches</cell>
							</row>

							<row>
								<cell>Pere Philbert</cell>
								<cell>With the Natchez</cell>
							</row>

							<row>
								<cell>Pere Victorin, Recollet, joined to the Capuchins</cell>
								<cell>With the Apalaches</cell>
							</row>
						</table>
						<table rows="9" cols="2">

							<head rend="center b">JESUITS.</head>

							<row role="label">

								<cell>Pere Petit, Superior</cell>
								<cell>At New Orleans</cell>
							</row>

							<row>
								<cell>Pere Poissen</cell>
								<cell>With the Arkansas</cell>
							</row>

							<row>
								<cell>Pere D'Outreleau</cell>
								<cell>At the Ouabache</cell>
							</row>

							<row>
								<cell>Pere Tartarin</cell>
								<cell>With the Kaskaskias</cell>
							</row>

							<row>
								<cell>Pere Boulenger</cell>
								<cell>With the Kaskaskias</cell>
							</row>

							<row>
								<cell>Pere Guimoneau</cell>
								<cell>With the Metchigamias</cell>
							</row>

							<row>
								<cell>Pere Souel</cell>
								<cell>With the Yasous</cell>
							</row>

							<row>
								<cell>Pere Beaudouin</cell>
								<cell>With the Chickasaws</cell>
							</row>

							<row>
								<cell>Pere Guienne</cell>
								<cell>With the Alabamas</cell>
							</row>
						</table> "Pere Petit had been with the Choctaws. There will be a new missionary to the
						Caiouitas. Messrs. Taumar and Mercier, priests of the foreign missions, are with the
						Jesuits with the Cahokias and Tamarois."</q></p>

				<pb id="VAC0881-011" n="263"/>

				<p>According to this memoir, evidently prepared by some official of the Company of the
					Indies, there were in 1728, only these twenty-one Catholic clergymen working in the
					Province of Louisiana, in all capacities, in the settlements and among the Indians, and
					this is the first official mention known of any priest engaged on the "Ouabache," with the
					exception of the brief labors of Pere Mermet among the Indians who gathered about the post
					of Sieur Juchereau, on the site of Cairo, Ill., at the mouth of the Ohio river. In other
					words it is the earliest official mention of a priest at the French establishment
					subsequently known as Post Vincennes. In addition to this mention of Pere D'Outreleau this
					memoir also introduces another character closely connected with the establishment of the
					mission on the Wabash, Pere de Beaubois. It must be confessed that the introduction is not
					at all flattering to this clergyman, yet it is probably just, except that it should be
					borne in mind that it presents him at the worst point in his record, and is written by an
					official who was thoroughly out of patience with this energetic Jesuit.</p>
				<p>Nicolas Ignace de Beaubois was born at Orleans, France, October 15,1689. His sympathies
					were apparently enlisted in church work at an early age for he entered the Jesuit order as
					a novice just after completing his seventeenth year. He came to Canada in 1718, and was
					installed as curé at Kaskaskia in 1720, that place being then raised from a mission to the
					dignity of a parish. In this position his great energy in his work was first displayed by
					preparing new copies of the parish records, as is still evidenced by the following entry
					in the Register of Baptisms: <q rend="blockquote"><p>"All that which precedes is an
							extract which I, Nicolas Ig. de Beaubois, S. J. Curé of the parish of the Conception
							of our lady of the Cascaskias, certify to be correct and conformed to the original,
							which I have suppressed because it was not in order, and because it was kept on
							scattered <pb id="VAC0881-012" n="264"/> leaves, and the present extract is signed by
							two witnesses, who have compared the present copy with the original; the 25th of July,
							1720: De Beaubois, S. J."</p></q></p>
				<p>This work of zeal has been regretted by historians because it destroyed the original
					signatures of a number of interesting characters of the early Illinois settlements,<ref
						id="ref_006" rend="super" target="note_006">6</ref> but it is eminently characteristic
					of the man. When Sidney Smith described Daniel Webster as "a locomotive in trousers," he
					made an apt figure for representing men of tremendous energy, and Father de Beaubois
					belonged to that class. When they get off the track they are liable to work havoc, but
					while they keep to it they are capable of performing great service. The ordinary
					management of Louisiana affairs must have been very trying to a man of the de Beaubois
					temperament. He wanted to accomplish something, but on every side was delay, inefficency,
					failure. There was only one chance of improvement, and that was for someone to lay hold
					and do things. He undertook it.</p>
				<p>There can be no question that he was a man of some ability. The fact that he was chosen
					to represent his order at New Orleans, that he was sent to France to bring out the nuns
					and missionary priests, that he was appointed vicar-general by the Bishop of Quebec, all
					evidence that. And the evidence is equally strong that he was pushing the interests of his
					country, his religion and his order in every way. All of these interests combined in the
					establishment of a mission on the Ouabache, within the jurisdiction of Louisiana. On July
					19, 1720, his name first appears on the records as parish priest at Kaskaskia, and on
					September 15, 1720, the Company of the Indies petitions the government to establish a post
					on the Ouabache. The next year Father Charlevoix visited the Illinois settlements on his
					way down the Mississippi, and in his letter of November 8, 1721, he calls attention to the
					importance of a <note id="note_006"><ref target="ref_006" rend="super">6</ref>Kaskaskia
						and Its Parish Records, p. 10.</note>
					<pb id="VAC0881-013" n="265"/> post on the Ouabache. In 1724 La Harpe repeated the
					suggestion. On February 9, 1725, Commandant de Boisbriant, of Fort Chartres, wrote how
					desirable a thing it would be, but expressed fear that as it had been neglected so long it
					would not be attended to then. All this may be mere coincidence, but it is at least
					striking that Sommervogel, the Jesuit biographer, in his notice of de Beaubois, mentions
					this writing by him: <q rend="blockquote"><p>"Mémoire sur l'importance de fortifier
							l'Ouabache que les Anglais peuvent facilement occuper. 12 pages.--Ce MS. se conserve à
							Paris, au bureau des Fortifications et des Colonies."<ref id="ref_007" rend="super"
								target="note_007">7</ref></p></q></p>
				<p>It was a search for this memoir that brought to light the documents which form the
					appendix hereto, and though the document was not found, and though Father Sommervogel
					himself has forgotten where he found reference to it, there is no reason to doubt that it
					exists somewhere. Such references do not spring from nothing.</p>
				<p>But Father de Beaubois did not confine his efforts to writing memoirs. He prepared to
					descend on the French authorities in full force and present the needs of the colony in
					person. The Chevalier de Bourgmont gathered twenty-two Indian chiefs and prominent tribal
					representatives to accompany him, but as they were about to embark the vessel sank at its
					moorings, and only half a dozen of them could be persuaded to risk a voyage in another
					ship. With these he proceeded to France, presented his cause to the court and made an
					impression there--as related in the appendix--collected the nuns for the proposed convent
					at New Orleans and the missionaries needed for the various Louisiana points, arranged for
					their transportation, and returned to New Orleans to prepare for their reception.</p>
				<p>Of the fact that his efforts secured the results, we have not only the evidence of the
					record of his presentation of <note id="note_007"><ref target="ref_007" rend="super"
							>7</ref>Bibliothéque de la Compagnie de Jesus. Tome 1, column 1075.</note>
					<pb id="VAC0881-014" n="266"/> the cause at court, and his letter to M. de la Loe,
					Secretary of the Company of the Indies, detailing the difficulties he encountered,<ref
						id="ref_008" rend="super" target="note_008">8</ref> but also the testimony of those
					familiar with the proceedings. A very full account of the trip of the nuns to New Orleans
					is preserved in the letters of Madeleine Hachard,<ref id="ref_009" rend="super"
						target="note_009">9</ref> one of the party, and she not only speaks of Pere Beaubois as
					"the able conductor of this entire enterprise," but also says: <q rend="blockquote"> "It
						is the Reverend Pere de Beaubois, of the Society of Jesus, who formed the noble project
						of our establishment at New Orleans; this missionary is full of zeal and wisdom; you can
						not imagine how many obstacles he has had to surmount to make his enterprise succeed; it
						is now happily come to a conclusion by the aid of heaven."</q></p>


				<p>Madeleine Hachard journeyed from Rouen to Paris in the latter part of October, 1726, in
					company with two Ursuline sisters, Marie Mahieu and Cécile Cavalier, having been preceded
					thither by Mother Marie Tranchepain, the superior of the new community, Sister Marguérite
					Jude, the assistant, and Sister Marianne Boulanger, the depositary, who had gone ahead to
					make the necessary contracts with the Company. Her account of the trip is so pleasantly
					written that it is worthy of free quotation. She says: <q rend="blockquote"> "We left
						Paris with the Reverend Pere D'Outreleau<ref id="ref_010" rend="super" target="note_010"
							>10</ref> and Brother Crucy, Jesuits, who were to go with us to Louisiana, the 8th of
						December, at five o'clock in the morning, after having heard the holy mass, recited the
						prayers of travelers, and breakfasted. The Brittany coach came to take us at the door of
						the convent; it cost us forty livres for each person to carry us to Rennes, without
						including meals. * * *</q></p>

				<note id="note_008"><ref target="ref_008" rend="super">8</ref>Written from L'Orient, Nov. 2,
					1726. Jesuit Relations, Vol. LXVII, p. 265.</note>
				<note id="note_009"><ref target="ref_009" rend="super">9</ref>Relation du Voyage de Dames
					Ursulines de Rouen à la Nouvelle-Orleans. Gravier's Edition, Paris, 1872.</note>
				<note id="note_010"><ref target="ref_010" rend="super">10</ref>She spelled the name
					"Doutrelo."</note>

				<pb id="VAC0881-015" n="267"/>

				<p>"The 10th we dined at Hodan, where we found a good-looking cavalier who was following the
					same route; he wished, by paying something to the driver, to occupy the eighth place in
					our coach, in order, he said, to pass the time more agreeably with so amiable a company.
					We did not receive him very well; Reverend Pere D'Outreleau, to disgust him with his
					purpose, gave him to understand that we should have three hours of silence to preserve
					morning and evening. The cavalier replied that if we should not wish to talk he would
					entertain himself with Brother Crucy, but when he made himself known we saw that we indeed
					had need of him, that he was wanted in the management, for being the President of Mayenne,
					where our boxes, valises and packages ought to be examined, he was able to save us this
					visitation, which always causes delay and embarrassment; we received him then and he
					treated us with great politeness. Reverend Pere D'Outreleau begged him to use his
					authority in the city to prevent the opening of our baggage; he promised us and kept his
					word; he had the honesty to go to the custom house, and nothing was examined. We slept at
					Mortagne after passing a rather dangerous place where the coach from Caen to Paris had
					been robbed eight hours before; the roads began to be very bad.</p>
				<p>"The 11th we dined at Mesle and slept at Allencon. I am not able to say anything of this
					city; we arrived in the night and left on the morning following, before day. We were not
					three hours en route, the roads being so bad that we had with difficulty made half a
					league, when it became necessary to dismount. Our coach was completely mired down,
					wagoners joined to the twelve horses which we drove thirty oxen to pull our equipage out
					of a bad place. We did not remain with them, but continued our road, and made about a
					league on foot. We were very cold and we could not find a house for shelter. We were
					obliged <pb id="VAC0881-016" n="268"/> to seat ourselves on the ground. The Reverend Pere
					D'Outreleau mounted a little elevation in a neighboring wood, where, like another St. John
					the Baptist, he exhorted us to penitence, though we had more need of patience. After
					having rested a little we took up our journey and finally had the good fortune to find a
					little cottage in which there was only a poor woman in bed. It was only after many
					supplications and promises that she did us the favor to open her door. She had neither
					wood nor candle and we had to make a fire of broom, by the light of which the Reverend
					Pere said his breviary while awaiting the day; we did not fail to recompense the charity
					of the good woman. Our coach did not come to join us for more than ten hours; we were able
					to make but four leagues that day, mostly on foot. Notwithstanding the fatigue we often
					laughed; there occurred from time to time little adventures that diverted us. We were
					splattered to the ears, the veils of our two meres were speckled with gray mud, making a
					very droll effect. We arrived at the city of Mayenne, and Monsieur, our President, in
					quitting us urged us warmly to come to his house to lodge, but we did not think we should
					accept his offer, gracious as it was. We went to the inn where we did not remain long
					before going to bed, for we were very weary. I forgot to mention to you that on the trip
					we did not observe very scrupulously our six hours of silence announced by the Reverend
					Pere D'Outreleau."</p>
				<p>And so they journeyed on through romantic Brittany, meeting hardships at one point and
					narrowly escaping robbers at another, but withal a very pleasant party as the cavalier of
					Mayenne had judged. Our novitiate says: <q rend="blockquote"><p>"When you are traveling
							you laugh at everything," and she evidently contributed not a little to the relaxation
							of the journey. She says, "I forgot to tell you, my dear father, that on the way from
							Paris to Hennebon, Frere <pb id="VAC0881-017" n="269"/> Crucy and I were almost
							constantly at war. The reverend Pere Davangour [Procurator of the Canadian and
							Louisiana missions at Paris] had charged me to be his directress, and Madame de Saint
							Amand, Superior of Saint Jacques, had charged him to be my director. We acquitted
							ourselves of our commission to a marvel, telling our truths with freedom, though
							always in good humor. Naturally I am not melancholy and the good Frere is not more so,
							and often they laughed at our expense, but being the youngest it was proper that we
							should entertain the party."</p></q></p>
				<p>Finally they came to Hennebon, the last station in their stage journey, one of the
					ancient strong-walled towns of France, dear to every chronicler of French valor. It was
					one of the towns from which Bertrand du Guesclin expelled the English, and is still more
					famous for the long and brave defense of it made by Countess Jeanne de Montfort against
					the allied armies of Philip of Valois and Charles of Blois, the rival claimant of her
					captive husband to the ducal crown of Bretagne. This was a religious center, with the fine
					cathedral of Our Lady of Paradise, then well on in its second century, a Jesuit college,
					and an Ursuline convent. At the latter Madame Tranchepain, the Mother Superior of the new
					mission, together with Sister Marguerite Jude, her assistant, and Sister Marianne
					Boulanger, the depositary, were awaiting them. Here, also, they were joined by Sister
					Renée Guiquel and Sister Marguerite de Saloan, from Ploermel, and Sister Marianne Dain, of
					Hennebon, who, with the party from Paris, made up the new community. At Hennebon Madeleine
					Hachard was allowed to take the habit of the order, under a special dispensation which
					Pere D'Outreleau obtained from the Bishop of Vannes. Then Pere D'Outreleau went on to
					L'Orient, to make the vessel ready, accompanied by Pere Tartarin, a Louisiana missionary
					who had come in charge of the sisters from Ploermel, and who <pb id="VAC0881-018" n="270"
					/> thenceforward was with the party. A few days later the sisters entered a barge and
					dropped down the Blavet river to L'Orient, accompanied by several servants, one colored,
					and "a very pretty little cat which wished to join our community, supposing apparently
					that there were rats and mice in Louisiana as well as in France."</p>
				<p>L'Orient was then at the beginning of its glory as the great port of the French East
					Indies Company, for though the Company had maintained warehouses there for half a century
					the building of the town did not begin till 1720, and it was not fortified until 1745.
					Here they embarked for Louisiana, February 22, 1727, on La Gironde, commanded by Captain
					Vauberci. The vessels of that day were not built for the special accommodation of
					passengers, but an effort was made to make La Gironde more than usually convenient for the
					ladies. A temporary cabin, eighteen feet long and nearly half as wide was partitioned off
					between decks and in this four tiers of berths were constructed, three in each. There was
					no extra space. Our chronicler says the lighter-weight sisters, of whom she was one, were
					put in the upper berths and that she often bumped her head against the ceiling in heedless
					moments. As there were but twelve berths the thirteenth sister slept on the floor during
					the passage. The remainder of the passengers were huddled together in the gun-room,
					excepting the reverend fathers. These last were given "a wretched little hole which had no
					light, they were obliged to quit it, being unable to sleep in the excessive heat, and
					preferred to sleep on the poop deck, in spite of wind and rain, with head shut in a hamper
					to receive the rain when it came." They had many head winds and much rough weather, which
					caused the passengers to "pay tribute to the sea" as usual, but no special adventure until
					after passing Madeira where they put in for supplies, and were hospitably entertained by
					the Portuguese clergy.</p>
				<pb id="VAC0881-019" n="271"/>
				<p>After passing this island some two hundred leagues they sighted a vessel that appeared to
					be a pirate or corsair, and at once prepared for a desperate encounter. Even the secular
					women put on men's dress and took their places with the crew. The post of "the first
					captain was on the poop deck, and Pere Tartarin was stationed with him; that of the second
					captain was on the forecastle, and Pere D'Outreleau was stationed with him; and Frere
					Crucy was on the main deck to supply cartridges to all these warriors, all armed to the
					teeth and of admirable courage. We others had for arms only our beads in our hands. We
					were not sad, thank the Lord. None of our company showed any weakness. We were charmed to
					see the courage of our officers and passengers, who appeared ready to overthrow the enemy
					at the first blow." But the pirate deemed it wise to keep away from such warlike
					preparations, and withdrew. The same experience was had with four other corsairs which
					approached the Gironde during the voyage. One of them, manned by Englishmen, sent a boat
					to the vessel under plea of a desire to trade for wine, but treachery was suspected and
					the boat was ordered to withdraw or be fired upon. The principal effect of these dangers
					was to increase the religious exercises, which came to be as frequent and regular on the
					ship as in a religious establishment.</p>
				<p>The greatest danger encountered was in the Gulf of Mexico, where, after much annoyance
					from bad weather and contrary winds, the ship struck on a shoal off an island called
					"Blanche," and was in a way to go to pieces. The captain began lightening the vessel by
					putting the cannon overboard, supported by wooden buoys. Then the ballast was thrown over,
					but this was not enough, and the baggage of the passengers was considered as the next
					sacrifice, but it was decided first to throw over the sugar, of which everyone seemed to
					have a private supply, and this was <pb id="VAC0881-020" n="272"/> followed by sixty-one
					barrels of brandy belonging to the Company. This let the vessel off, and a favoring tide
					soon after carried them to safety. Our chronicler says they were not desirous to land on
					this island because it was inhabited by savages who were said to be "very cruel," and
					justly so by her report, for "not only do they eat the whites but first make them suffer
					torments a thousand times worse than death. Sometimes they make the whites drink their own
					blood, and in brief make them endure most cruel martyrdom."</p>
				<p>On July 23 they arrived at Balise, the French port at the mouth of the Mississippi. Here
					they remained till the 29th awaiting news from Pere De Beaubois, who had supposed them
					lost at sea on account of their long voyage of five months. They made the trip to New
					Orleans, twenty leagues up the river, in three boats, and the fatigues of the six days
					required for this were worse than anything endured on the ship. The mother superior, with
					the younger sisters, Pere D'Outreleau and Frere Crucy were in a pirogue--a boat made from
					a hollowed log. The other sisters occupied a launch, and the domestics and workmen of the
					reverend fathers came in a second pirogue. There were no settlements along the river and
					the vegetation was so dense that they had to camp at night on the immediate banks of the
					river. Among the greatest troubles were the mosquitoes, which, our chronicler asserts,
					"were at times in so great number that one could cut them with a knife," and whose
					assaults called for much precaution. "Our sailors, to make us bars, stuck canes in the
					ground in the form of a bower, over a mattress, and we retired two by two under our bars
					where we slept fully dressed; then they covered the bower with a large sail cloth in a way
					that the mosquitoes were not able to find any little opening through which to visit us. We
					slept twice in the midst of mud and of water which fell from the skies in <pb
						id="VAC0881-021" n="273"/> abundance, and penetrated to us as well as our mattresses,
					which almost floated in the water. The storm having occurred in the middle of the night
					the pirogue was not able to go on the next day, it, as well as our clothing and the
					mattresses, being soaked with water. On this occasion several of our mothers were much
					indisposed. Some took colds and catarrhs; others had inflammation of the face and limbs;
					and one had an even more considerable illness. For me, although I was equally steeped in
					water, I was not at all unwell. We also suffered the annoyance in the pirogue of not being
					able to sit, stand or kneel, or to make any movement, for the pirogue would have upset and
					we would have served as food for the fishes. All our baggage of mattresses and chests
					filled it, and we had to be on top of all that in a little heap, and when the pirogue
					stopped we changed our positions. We ate biscuit and salt meat taken from the Gironde
					which the master of our pirogue had us cook at night in his saucepan. All these little
					troubles wearied us at the time, but one is well recompensed in the end by the pleasure
					found in recounting each her own little adventures, and one is surprised on considering
					the strength and courage which God gives in these trials; it proves indeed that he never
					fails anyone, and that he does not permit that we shall be tried beyond our strength,
					giving each grace sufficient for the trials which come to us. It is true that the ardent
					desire which we had to arrive at this promised land made us endure all with joy."</p>
				<p>The new additions to the colony were received with unbounded joy, and most distinguished
					attentions were paid to them. Our missionaries tarried with them for about a month, for in
					a letter of October 17, 1727, Madeleine Hachard says:</p>
				<q rend="blockquote">
					<p>"The reverend fathers Tartarin and D'Outreleau left six weeks ago to find their post in
						the Illinois country."</p></q>
				<p>She also mentions their arrival at the Illinois <pb id="VAC0881-022" n="274"/>
					settlements in a letter of April 24, 1728, saying:</p>
				<q rend="blockquote">
					<p>"I must not neglect to acquaint you with the sorry adventure come to our two reverend
						fathers, Tartarin and D'Outreleau, our worthy conductors of the voyage. We learn from
						their letters that when within twenty leagues of the Illinois the canoe which carried
						Pere D'Outreleau was destroyed in passing a river. He saved himself in his shirt by
						swimming, having lost all his church equipment, his robes and his baggage. He had come
						five hundred leagues happily enough, to be thus shipwrecked at port. As soon as he
						reached Pere Tartarin, who was in another canoe, he had the charity, having two
						cassocks, to give him one, and so they proceeded."</p></q>
				<p>Aside from the reference to Father D'Outreleau as "at the Ouabache" in the memoir of
					November 21, 1728, before quoted, we have no further account of him, until his arrival at
					New Orleans, in 1730, gave the French definite information of the great Indian outbreak of
					that year. Writing from New Orleans, following an account of the murder of Father Souel,
					Father Petit says: <q rend="blockquote">
						<p>"One of the Yazous having stripped the Missionary (Father Souel), clothed himself in
							his garments, and shortly afterwards announced to the Natchez that his nation redeemed
							their pledge, and that the French settled among them were all massacred. In this city
							there was no longer any doubt on that point, as soon as they learned what came near
							being the fate of Father D'Outreleau. This Missionary had availed himself of the time
							when the Indians were engaged in their winter occupations, to come and see us, for the
							purpose of regulating some matters relating to his mission. He set out on the first
							day of this year, 1730, and not expecting to arrive at the residence of Father Souel,
							of whose fate he was ignorant, in time to say Mass, he determined to say it at the
							mouth of the little river of the Yazous, where his party had camped.</p></q>
					<pb id="VAC0881-023" n="275"/>
					<q rend="blockquote">
						<p>"As he was preparing for this sacred office, he saw a boat full of Indians landing.
							They demanded from them, of what nation they were? 'Yazous, comrades of the French,'
							they replied, making a thousand friendly demonstrations to the voyagers who
							accompanied the Missionary, and presenting them with provisions. While the Father was
							preparing his altar, a flock of bustards passed, and the voyagers fired at them the
							only two guns they had, without thinking of reloading, as Mass had already commenced.
							The Indians noted this, and placed themselves behind the voyagers, as if it was their
							intention to hear Mass, although they were not Christians.</p></q>
					<q rend="blockquote">
						<p>"At the time the Father was saying the <hi rend="i">Kyrie Eleison</hi>, the Indians
							made their discharge. The Missionary, perceiving himself wounded in his right arm, and
							seeing one of the voyagers killed at his feet, and the four others fled, threw himself
							on his knees to receive the last fatal blow, which he regarded as inevitable. In this
							posture he received two or three discharges. But although the Indians fired while
							almost touching him, yet they did not inflict on him any new wounds. Finding himself,
							then, as it were, miraculously escaped from so many mortal blows, he took to flight,
							having on still his priestly garments, and without any other defense than an entire
							confidence in God, whose particular protection was given him, as the event proved. He
							threw himself into the water, and after advancing some steps, gained the boat in which
							two of the voyagers were making their escape. They had supposed him to be killed by
							some of the many balls which they had heard fired on him. In climbing up into the
							boat, and turning his head to see whether any of his pursuers was following him too
							closely, he received in the mouth a discharge of small shot, the greater part of which
							were flattened against his teeth, though some of them entered his gums, and remained
							there for a long time. I have myself <pb id="VAC0881-024" n="276"/> seen two of them.
							Father D'Outreleau, all wounded as he was, undertook the duty of steering the boat,
							while his two companions placed themselves at the oars. Unfortunately one of them, at
							setting out, had his thigh broken by a musket-ball, from the effects of which he has
							since remained a cripple.</p></q>
					<q rend="blockquote">
						<p>"You may well imagine, my Reverend Father, that the Missionary and his companions had
							no thoughts of ascending the river. They descended the Mississippi with all the speed
							possible, and at last lost sight of the boat of their enemies, who had pursued them
							for more than an hour, keeping up a continual fire upon them, and who boasted at the
							village that they had killed them. The two rowers were often tempted to give
							themselves up, but encouraged by the Missionary, they in their turn made the enemy
							fear. An old gun which was not loaded, nor in a condition to be, which they pointed at
							them from time to time, made them often dodge in their boat, and at last obliged them
							to retire.</p></q>
					<q rend="blockquote">
						<p>"As soon as they found themselves freed from their enemies, they dressed their wounds
							as well as they could, and for the purpose of aiding their flight from that fatal
							shore, they threw into the river everything they had in their boat, preserving only
							some pieces of raw bacon for their nourishment.</p></q>
					<q rend="blockquote">
						<p>"It had been their intention to stop in passing at the Natchez, but having seen that
							the houses of the French were either demolished or burned, they did not think it
							advisable to listen to the compliments of the Indians, who from the bank of the river
							invited them to land. They placed wide distance between them as soon as possible, and
							thus shunned the balls which were ineffectually fired at them. It was then that they
							began to distrust all these Indian nations, and therefore resolved not to go near the
							land until they reached New Orleans, and supposing that <pb id="VAC0881-025" n="277"/>
							the savages might have rendered themselves masters of it, to descend even to the
							Balize, where they hoped to find some French vessel provided to receive the wreck of
							the colony.</p></q>
					<q rend="blockquote">
						<p>"In passing the Tonikas, they separated themselves as far as possible from the shore,
							but they were discovered, and a boat which had been dispatched to reconnoitre them was
							not a long time in approaching. Their fear and distrust was renewed, and they did not
							decide to stop until they perceived that the persons in that boat spoke very good
							French, when they overcame their fears, and in the weak state they were, gladly
							availed themselves of the opportunity to land. There they found the little French army
							which had been formed, the officers compassionate and every way kind, a surgeon and
							refreshments. After recovering a little from the great dangers and miseries they had
							endured, they on the next day availed themselves of a boat which had been fitted out
							for New Orleans.</p></q>
					<q rend="blockquote">
						<p>"I can not express to you, my Reverend Father, the great satisfaction I felt at
							seeing Father D'Outreleau, his arm in a scarf, arrive after a voyage of more than four
							hundred leagues, all the clothes he had on having been borrowed except his cassock. My
							surprise was increased at the recital of his adventures. I placed him immediately in
							the hands of brother Parisel who examined his wounds, and who dressed them with great
							care and speedy success.</p></q>
					<q rend="blockquote">
						<p>"The missionary was not yet entirely cured of his wounds when he departed to go and
							act as chaplain to the French army, as he had promised the officers, in accordance
							with their request. He endured with them the fatigues of the campaign against the
							Natchez, and there gave new proofs of his zeal, his wisdom, and his courage.</p></q>
					<q rend="blockquote">
						<p>"On his return from the Natchez he came to recruit himself here for six weeks, which
							he found very long, but which appeared to me very short. He was impatient to <pb
								id="VAC0881-026" n="278"/> return to his dear mission, but it was necessary for me
							to fit him out generally with everything proper for a missionary, and he was obliged
							to wait for the escort which was going to the Illinois. The risks which they ran on
							the river during this insurrection of the Indians induced the Commander to forbid
							voyagers going in separate companies. He set out, therefore, on the 16th of April,
							with many others, in a body sufficiently large to relieve them from all fear of their
							enemies; I learned, in fact, that they had proceeded above the Akensas without any
								accident."<ref id="ref_011" rend="super" target="note_011">11</ref></p></q></p>

				<p>After this experience there is another hiatus in the record of the doings of Father
					D'Outreleau until he is mentioned in the letter of Bienville, of May 13, 1737,<ref
						id="ref_012" rend="super" target="note_012">12</ref> where he is spoken of as living at
					the house of the Jesuits in New Orleans, and is recommended for appointment as chaplain at
					the hospital. It appears that he received this appointment, and remained in the
					Mississippi Valley some ten years longer, then returning to France.<ref id="ref_013"
						rend="super" target="note_013">13</ref></p>

				<p>Etienne D'Outreleau was unquestionably "the missionary destined for the Ouabache," but
					whether he ever arrived at this destination is a much more difficult question to answer.
					The probability is that he did not. The documents that have been unearthed in this search
					for the memoir of de Beaubois, and which are appended hereto, furnish more information as
					to the founding of Post Vincennes than has ever been in the possession of Indiana
					historians heretofore. First in importance of them is the letter of Sieur de Vincennes,
					written from the post March 7, 1733. This furnishes the information, that the post had
					then been under construction for three years. The term "depuis trois années" is somewhat
					ambiguous. <note id="note_011"><ref target="ref_011" rend="super">11</ref>The Early Jesuit
						Missions, Kip, p. 290; Jesuit Relations, Vol. LXVIII, p. 175.</note>
					<note id="note_012"><ref target="ref_012" rend="super">12</ref>Appendix, Second Report,
						Section 24.</note>
					<note id="note_013"><ref target="ref_013" rend="super">13</ref>Jesuit Relations, Vol.
						LXVII, p. 342; ibid, Vol. LXXI, p. 169.</note>
					<pb id="VAC0881-027" n="279"/> It may mean three full years, or parts of three years, as
					in the biblical statement that Christ was three days in the tomb. That the latter is the
					meaning of Sieur de Vincennes is assured by the fact that in the accounts of the Company
					the first allowance for salary of the commandant at the post is in 1731, and only for the
					last six months of the year. In 1732 M. de Vincennes receives his full annual allowance of
					800 livres. We have, therefore, the fact established by unimpeachable testimony that the
					post was begun in the summer of 1731. And this harmonizes with all other evidence, with
					the local traditions and with the oldest local records, for Judge Law, after his study of
					them, came to the conclusion that Sieur de Vincennes came there about the year 1732.<ref
						id="ref_014" rend="super" target="note_014">14</ref></p>
				<p>The letter also furnishes practically conclusive evidence that there was no French
					settlement at this point prior to the founding of the post. He states expressly that in
					1733 the only buildings there were the fort, or stockade, and two houses within it. It
					might be urged that he was describing only the work he had done, and that this statement
					does not preclude the existence of the houses of settlers, but there are other evidences
					to the same effect. If there had been any French settlement at this point the Louisiana
					authorities would have known it, and Vincennes would have mentioned it in describing the
					location of the post, but he does this only by giving its distance from the rivers by
					which the English descend. Furthermore, the place was so exposed to attacks from the
					Southern Indians that a settlement could not have been maintained there before a fort was
					built. As is shown by the appended documents, and numerous others, these Indians, as well
					as the Sioux and the Foxes, were attacking French settlers even in the vicinity of Fort
					Chartres. And, furthermore, <note id="note_014"><ref target="ref_014" rend="super"
							>14</ref>Law's History of Vincennes, p. 19.</note>
					<pb id="VAC0881-028" n="280"/> although casualties throughout the Province are very fully
					reported, there is no mention known of any injury by Indians to persons or property in the
					vicinity of any settlement on the Ouabache prior to the letter of Vincennes. It may be
					added that there is no known indication of any settlement at this point on any map of
					earlier date than 1731, and that the first known intimation, in the Canadian documents, of
					any such settlement is in that year.<ref id="ref_015" rend="super" target="note_015"
						>15</ref></p>
				<p>The danger of attack by hostile Indians at this point was the greater because at this
					time there were no friendly Indians--in fact no Indians at all--located on the Ouabache
					within the boundaries of Louisiana. It has often been surmised that there was an Indian
					village at the site of Vincennes prior to the French settlement, but these documents
					disprove that. As we have seen, the original project was to have Sieur de Vincennes induce
					the Ouiatanons to remove to the lower Ouabache to serve as a protection against the
					Southern Indians. He did not succeed in this, but he did induce the Piankeshaws to move.
					As appears by Bienville's letter of June 22, 1737, it was his intention to have the
					establishment made at "the mouth of the Ohio"--i. e., the mouth of the Wabash--but this
					was prevented, and the post was placed at Vincennes, because the Indians refused to go any
					lower down.<ref id="ref_016" rend="super" target="note_016">16</ref> And after the
					disastrous Chickasaw campaign, and the death of Sieur de Vincennes, St. Ange reported that
					the greater part of the Piankeshaws had abandoned the post, and "returned to their old
					village on the Vermillion."<ref id="ref_017" rend="super" target="note_017">17</ref> The
					boundary line between Louisiana and Canada crossed the Wabash about the site of Terre
						Haute,<ref id="ref_018" rend="super" target="note_018">18</ref> and consequently this
					Piankeshaw village was in Canada. There was no Indian village on the Ouabache below it.
						<note id="note_015"><ref target="ref_015" rend="super">15</ref>N. Y. Col. Docs., Vol.
						IX, pp. 1027, 1035.</note>
					<note id="note_016"><ref target="ref_016" rend="super">16</ref>Appendix Second Report,
						Section 25. </note>
					<note id="note_017"><ref target="ref_017" rend="super">17</ref>Appendix Second Report,
						Section 26.</note>
					<note id="note_018"><ref target="ref_018" rend="super">18</ref>Ind. Hist. Soc. Pubs., Vol.
						II, p. 437.</note></p>

				<pb id="VAC0881-029" n="281"/>

				<p>This explains the special interest of Father de Beaubois in having a post on the
					Ouabache. When he went to France, in 1725, there were no Indians on the Ouabache, within
					the Province of Louisiana, among whom a mission could be established, and yet he arranged
					for such a mission, and brought Father D'Outreleau over to take charge of it. It was not
					until 1726 that the project of having Sieur de Vincennes bring the Ouiatanons within
					Louisiana was announced. Indeed the Company, in its letter to De Boisbriant, of December
					22, 1725, advised only that Vincennes and the Ouiatanons be asked to co-operate from
					Canada, and not to move into Louisiana. The change of plans was coincident with the
					appearance of Father de Beaubois in France, and in the absence of any other known cause
					for the change, and in consideration of its harmony with his preparations for a mission,
					it is quite probable that he induced it.</p>
				<p>But there is no indication that Father D'Outreleau was actually on the Ouabache except in
					the memoir of 1728, before quoted, and he could not possibly have been there actually
					then, because there was no post, no settlement no Indians on the Ouabache within Louisiana
					at that time. The contract of the Jesuits was to supply missionaries for Louisiana, not
					Canada, and their support was paid for by the Louisiana Company. In what little mention
					there is of Father D'Outreleau, he is spoken of as coming from the Illinois and going to
					the Illinois. In the letter of Bienville and Salmon, of May 13, 1737, he is spoken of as
					"former superior at the Illinois."<ref id="ref_019" rend="super" target="note_019"
						>19</ref> The key to the situation is probably found in the statement of the same letter
					that he was "too old to learn the Indian idiom." This is a curious statement to be made
					nine years after his supposed entry on the mission work, for, of course, no one could do
					such work effectively without understanding the <note id="note_019"><ref target="ref_019"
							rend="super">19</ref>Appendix, Second Report, Section 24.</note>
					<pb id="VAC0881-030" n="282"/> Indian language, and he was not "too old" when he
						began.<ref id="ref_020" rend="super" target="note_020">20</ref> The probability is that
					he went to the Illinóis to study the Indian tongue while waiting for the establishment of
					the Ouabache post, and discovered that he was one of those persons who have no aptitude
					for acquiring languages. But he had other gifts, and in accordance with Jesuit policy he
					was set at work for which he was fitted, and became superior of the order in the Illinois
					settlements. His recommendation for appointment as chaplain of the hospital at New Orleans
					was in the same year (1737) as the announcement of the return of the Piankeshaws to
					Canada, and presumably this first attempt at a mission to the Ouabache, from the Louisiana
					side, was then abandoned. As a missionary enterprise it was a failure, but it is probable
					that the effort to secure it was largely instrumental in securing the establishment of
					Post Vincennes, and caused the attempt to hold the Indian trade against the English by
					means of Indian allies and a small fort, instead of by a fort with a considerable garrison
					located at some point on the Ohio river. <milestone unit="typography" n="-----"
						rend="center"/>
					<note id="note_020"><ref target="ref_020" rend="super">20</ref> Etienne D'Outreleau was
						born in the Province of Champagne, October 11, 1693. He entered the order July 27, 1715.
						Jesuit Relations, Vol. LXXI, p. 169.</note></p>
			</div1>
		</body>


		<back>
			<pb id="VAC0881-031" n="283"/>
			<div1 type="appendix">

				<head rend="center">APPENDIX.</head>

				<milestone unit="typography" n="-----" rend="center"/>

				<p>In the summer of 1901 the Indiana Historical Society applied to Hon. John K. Gowdy,
					Consul-General at Paris, to obtain, if possible, a copy of a memoir in manuscript which is
					stated by the Jesuit historian, Sommervogel, to be on file in the colonial archives there.
					It is described as a memoir on the importance of fortifying the Ouabache, twelve pages in
					length, and as the author, Father de Beaubois, was for several years stationed at
					Kaskaskia, in the Illinois settlements, it was thought the document would contain some
					valuable information concerning the Wabash region at that time. Mr. Gowdy very kindly
					undertook the task, and secured for the Society the services not only of his secretary,
					Mr. G. E. Light, but also of Mr. Robert B. Douglas, the well-known author. In his first
					search Mr. Douglas did not find the memoir desired, but he found other documents throwing
					light on our early history, and a request was thereupon made for further research,
					covering the first half of the eighteenth century. The result of this was the discovery of
					the documents following, which give more information as to the founding of Post Vincennes,
					and the occurrences for twenty years after in its vicinity, than has heretofore been
					obtained by Indiana historians from all other sources. The two letters written by Sieur de
					Vincennes, from the post, in 1733, are the earliest known documents extant written within
					the boundaries of Indiana. On account of their importance photographs <pb id="VAC0881-032"
						n="284"/> of them were obtained, by the generous aid of Mr. Gowdy, and fac-similes of
					them are presented in this publication.</p>
				<p>The Beaubois memoir was not found, although Mr. Douglas found Father Sommervogel in
					Paris, and made inquiries of him. He had forgotten where he found his reference to the
					memoir, but thought it was in some manuscript catalogue of documents that he had
					consulted.</p>

				<div2>

					<p>
						<text>
							<body>
								<div type="letter">
									<head rend="center">FIRST REPORT OF MR. DOUGLAS.</head>
									<dateline>
										<address>
<addrLine>PARIS,</addrLine> 
					</address>
										<date>June 27, 1901.</date>
									</dateline>

									<salute>DEAR MR. LIGHT--</salute>

									<p>In accordance with your instructions, I went to the Colonial Office and
										searched for the document required by the Indiana Historical Society. The
										Librarian and other officials gave me every assistance, and I examined fully a
										dozen long letters and memoirs by Nicolas Beaubois, and about three hundred
										other MSS., but could not find either the paper or any reference to it.</p>
									<p>The following extracts from the official reports of the Governor of Louisiana
										show, however, that Beaubois arrived in New Orleans, from Illinois, in January
										1725, and that he sailed for France, in the Bellona, after Easter in that year.
										He remained in France about fifteen months, and returned to New Orleans in the
										winter of 1726-27. He seems to have been a typical Jesuit, and is described by
										one of his many enemies as being "d'un vivacité insuportable, d'un turbulence
										sans egal, et d'une ambition demesurée."</p>
									<p>I am inclined, therefore, to believe that the approximate date given by Mr.
										Dunn--1725--is correct, and that the scheme for fortifying the Wabash against
										the English was written during his stay in Paris, with a view to ingratiate
										himself with the Minister. In that case, it would probably have been filed
										amongst the state papers in some <pb id="VAC0881-033" n="285"/> other
										department, and would be extremely difficult to find. On the other hand, Father
										Beaubois may have written the memoir several years later. He certainly does not
										appear to have been in any dread of the English when he wrote--on 11th December,
											1727--<q rend="blockquote">
											<p>"J'ai mis du monde en campagne pour nous trouver quelques Anglais de la
												Virginie que nous puissons attirer à la Louisiane pour nous mettre bien au
												fait du tabac."</p></q></p>

									<q rend="blockquote"><p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION</hi>. I have made every
											possible effort to find some Englishmen of Virginia whom we might be able to
											attract to Louisiana to instruct us in making tobacco.]</p></q>

									<p>Too much importance should not be attached to this, however, for, I regret to
										say, he appears to have been in the habit of writing what he thought would best
										please his correspondent--but always keeping his own ends steadily in view--and
										this letter was to a Governor who was anxious to squeeze as large a revenue as
										possible out of the colony.</p>

									<p>The Governor seems to have summed him up pretty accurately almost at their
										first interview, for he says--in the report to which I have alluded, and which
										is dated 11 January, 1725:<q rend="blockquote">
											<p>"Le Père Beaubois, Jesuite, descendu des Illinois passe dans la Bellona
												pour France; il nous a paru dans quelques conversations que nous avons eu
												avec ce Pere qu'il voudroit avoir une maison icy pour y èlever la jeunesse,
												cela seroit bon dans un sens, mais nous prevoyons par la qu'ils veulent
												commencer à chasser les Capucins comme ils ont fait au Cap, pour rester les
												mâitres la dessus; les unes et les autres sont des tres honnestes
											gens."</p></q>
										<q rend="blockquote"><p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION</hi>. Pere Beaubois, who came
												down from the Illinois, goes to France by the Bellona. It appears to us from
												several conversations which we have had with this <pb id="VAC0881-034"
													n="286"/> Father, that he would like to have an establishment here for
												educating the youth. That would be excellent in one sense, but we foresee by
												this that they wish to commence to run out the Capuchins, as they have done
												at the Cape, in order to become the masters there. They are both very honest
												people.]</p></q></p>

									<p>All the documents written by or about Pere Beaubois relate to his continual
										bickerings with the Compagnie des Indies and the Capuchins. Many of them are
										intolerably long. The charges against the Capuchins occupy fifty-one closely
										written pages of foolscap, and are rebutted by the Superior of that order in a
										memoir which runs to seventy-five foolscap pages. As far as I could gather from
										a necessarily cursory examination, Father Beaubois claimed to have contracted
										"treaties," whilst in Paris, with his ecclesiastical superiors and the Compagnie
										des Indies, which would have practically given the Jesuits complete control,
										spiritual and temporal, of a large extent of country, but--very
										unfortunately--the deeds were lost in the wreck of the vessel which brought him
										back to America. The infinite pains he takes to prove there really had been a
										shipwreck, have, somehow or other, quite a contrary effect.</p>

									<p>In none of Beaubois' letters do I find any reference to fortifications. My
										researches hitherto have extended from 1725 to 1730, and I also inspected--but
										not thoroughly--the previous and succeeding volumes, and M. Moulin, the
										sub-librarian, has also searched independently, but without result.</p>

									<p>It is singular that in these volumes I came across no reference to Vincennes,
										though the French settled there in 1702. The name of Beaubois' curé was
										Cascaquia. The following extract from the accounts of the colony for 1726 will
										perhaps prove of interest:<q rend="blockquote">
											<pb id="VAC0881-035" n="287"/>
											<table rows="7" cols="4">
												<head>A Ouabache, lors qu'il sera etably--</head>

												<row role="label">


													<cell>Un Pretre</cell>
													<cell>600</cell>
													<cell>1</cell>
													<cell>s</cell>
												</row>

												<row>
													<cell>Pour vin, farine, cierges, etc.</cell>
													<cell>195</cell>
													<cell>980</cell>
													<cell>8</cell>
												</row>

												<row>
													<cell>Pour un domestique</cell>
													<cell>185.8</cell>
												</row>
											</table>
											<p rend="center">Aux Cascaquia<lb/> Village Français et Curé<lb/> Le R. P.
												Beaubois, Jesuitte<lb/> qui passe en France par la Bellona.</p>
											<p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi></p>
											<table rows="7" cols="4">
												<head>At the Ouabache (Post), when it shall be established</head>

												<row role="label">

													<cell>A Priest</cell>
													<cell>600</cell>
													<cell>1</cell>
													<cell>s</cell>
												</row>

												<row>
													<cell>For wine, flour, wax tapers, etc.</cell>
													<cell>195</cell>
													<cell>980</cell>
													<cell>8</cell>
												</row>

												<row>
													<cell>For a domestic</cell>
													<cell>185.8</cell>
												</row>
											</table>
											<p rend="center">At Cascasquia<lb/> French village and curé,<lb/> The Rev.
												Father Beaubois, Jesuit,<lb/> who went to France by the Bellona.]</p>
										</q></p>

									<p>On one of the Governor's reports (dated 13th March, 1726) some one has written,
										in pencil, "Vincennes Ouabache Chactas," though the names do not occur in the
										report. I will conclude with an excerpt from this report, which may, perhaps,
										give a new version of some well known or little known incident, and interest
										local historians:</p>
									<q rend="blockquote">
										<p>"Depuis le depart de Mons. de Bienville il n'est rien que les Anglais n'ayent
											faits pour gaigner les nations sauvages. Ils ont envoyés tant aux Alebamons
											qu'aux Abecars Chactas et Chicachas plus de deux cent chevaux chargés de
											Marchandise pour les attirer dans leur party, heureusement que les Chactas et
											Chicachas qui sont les plus proches voisins (à nous) se sont brouillés avec
											eux après cependant leur avoir traitte beaucoup de pelletries, il y a en dans
											leur Brouilleries de deux Anglais de tués et la charge de dixhuit a dix-neuf
											chevaux pilles. Ces sauvages donnerent apres les autres Anglais qui estoient
											partis il y avoit environ huit jours qu'ils ne purent joindre. Cette
											catastrophe n'a point rebute les Anglais, ils ont envoyés dire aux Chactas
											qu'ils estoient prest à faire la paix avec eux aux <pb id="VAC0881-036"
												n="288"/> conditions qu'ils leur apporteroient la teste de l'interprette
											Francais qu'ils accusent fort malapropos de leur avoir fait tués et pillés
											quoique ces sauvages paroissent fort bien intentiones pour nous il est à
											craindre que les Anglais ne les gagnent parcequ'on manque toujours icy de
											Marchandises convenables pour les sauvages."<ref id="ref_021" rend="super"
												target="note_021">21</ref></p>
									</q>

									<q rend="blockquote"><p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION</hi>. Since the departure of M.
											de Bienville, the English have done nothing but make attempts to win over the
											Indian tribes. They have sent not only to the Alabamas but also to the
											Abecars, Choctaws and Chickasaws more than two hundred horses loaded with
											goods to win them over to their side. Happily the Choctaws and Chickasaws, who
											are our nearest neighbors, quarreled with them after having sold them a large
											quantity of skins. In their altercation two English were killed and the loads
											of eighteen or nineteen horses were stolen. The Indians went in pursuit of the
											other English, who had left about eight days before, but were unable to
											overtake them. This catastrophe has not rebuffed the English. They have sent a
											message to the Choctaws that they were ready to make peace with them on
											condition that they would bring them the head of the French interpreter, whom
											they accuse, most wrongfully, of the killing and robbery. Although these
											Indians appear very well-intentioned toward us there is danger that the
											English may win them over, because we lack here always satisfactory goods for
											the Indians.]</p></q>

									<closer>
										<salute>I am, dear Mr. Light,<lb/>
											<hi rend="center">Yours faithfully,</hi></salute><lb/>
										<signed rend="left">ROBERT B. DOUGLAS.</signed>
									</closer>

									<milestone unit="typography" n="-----" rend="center"/>

								</div>
							</body>
						</text></p>
					<note id="note_021"><ref target="ref_021" rend="super">21</ref> Reports, Louisiana, Vol.
						X.</note>
				</div2>



				<pb id="VAC0881-037" n="289"/>

				<div2>
					<head rend="center">SECOND REPORT OF MR. DOUGLAS.</head>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 1.</head>

						<p>A<hi rend="sc">DDRESS OF</hi> P. N<hi rend="sc">ICOLAS</hi> B<hi rend="sc">EAUBOIS TO
								THE</hi> K<hi rend="sc">ING</hi>. This address is included in an article entitled
							"Relation de l'arrivée en France de quatre Sauvages de Missicipi, de leur sejour &amp;
							des audiences qu'ils ont eues du Roi, des Princes du Sang, de la Compagnie des Indes,
							avec les compliments qu'ils ont reçus, &amp;c.," which occupies thirty-three pages of
								<hi rend="i">Le Mercure de France</hi>. (Vol. I, December, 1725, pp. 2827-2859.) It
							relates that the Chevalier de Bourgmont collected twenty-two chiefs of various Indian
							tribes to accompany Pere Beaubois to France, but, just as they were about to embark,
							the ship "sank in an instant," which so discouraged the greater number of the chiefs
							that they returned home. Only half a dozen Indians had the pluck to cross the Great
							Water. They were Agapit Chicagou, chief of the Metchigamia, an Illinois nation;
							Menspéré (a Missouri chief), Boganienhein (Osage), Aguiguida (Otoptata); also Ignon
							Ouaconisen, daughter of the Missouri chief, and a slave named Pilate, of the Atanana
							nation.</p>
						<p>These Indians had a good time in Paris, and were especially astounded at the kitchen
							of the Invalides, the opera, and the fountains at Versailles. On November 24, 1725,
							they were taken to the Fontainebleau, and presented to the Duc de Bourbon and other
							princes. The Duc promised to present them the next day to the King, when he returned
							from hunting, and, on the morrow, they were introduced, dressed "in savage costume,"
							into the King's cabinet. The R. P. Beaubois had the honor of delivering the first
							address, and of presenting to the King a letter from the Illinois chief:</p>



						<pb id="VAC0881-038" n="290"/>

						<p>
							<text>
								<body>
									<div type="letter">

										<opener>
											<hi rend="center">HARANGUE AU ROY DU PÈRE DU BEAUBOIS, JESUITE.</hi></opener>
										<salute>S<hi rend="sc">IRE--</hi></salute>
										<p>Ce sauvage, qui a l'honneur de parâitre devant Vostre Majesté, n'est point un
											homme de commun,--cependant quoique Chef de son village, &amp; un des plus
											considerés de sa nation, il n' a rien de cet eclat ni de cette grandeur qui
											environnent les Princes &amp; qui les rendent si respectables aux Peuples qui
											leur sont soûmis, mais qui sont inconnus aux nations de l'Amerique. Au reste,
											ce qui Vostre Majesté estimera, sans doute, dans lui, c'est que cet Indien,
											né, pour ainsi dire, dans un autre monde, &amp; elevé au milieu des forests,
											ait pu concevoir une assez haute idée de Vostre Suprême Grandeur pour desirer
											si ardemment de l'envisager de plus près &amp; de lui venir faire hommage. Un
											triste nauffrage, qui a disconcerté ceux qui l'accompagnoient, ne l'a point
											intimidé, &amp; depuis qu'il est en France la vue de ce qui fait l'etonnement
											de tous les Etrangers n'a fait qui augmenter en lui l'empressement qu'il avoit
											de voir la Monarque d'un si puissant Empire. Le plus considerable chef de
											toute la Nation Ilinoise a mille fois envié le bonheur de celui-ci, comme il
											le dit lui-même à Vostre Majesté d'une maniere si ingenieuse &amp; mille fois
											il à regretté, pour ainsi dire, d'être si necessaire dans son pays à la Nation
											Française.</p>
										<p>Daignez, Sire, recevoir avec bonté la lettre qu'il ose ecrire à Vostre
											Majesté &amp; lui repondre favorablement. Pour moi, Sire, je m'estime trop
											heureux d'approcher aujourd'hui de vôtre Trône, &amp; d'y être temoin des
											merveilles que la France admire dans vôtre Personne sacrée. Permittez moi,
											Sire, de demander a Vostre Majesté sa Royale protection pour les Missions de
											la Louisiane, cette vaste Province, où l'on ne scaurait trop les multiplier
											pour le bien de vôtre Colonie, &amp; procurer à tant de nations sauvages qui
											l'habitent, la connoissance du vrai Dieu. Louis <pb id="VAC0881-039" n="291"/>
											le Grand, de glorieuse mémoire se fit toujours un plaisir de protéger ceux que
											la Providence honore d'un si saint Ministère, &amp; de marquer par la zéle
											qu'il avait pour la propagation de la Foi. Heritier de ses heroiques vertus,
											comme vous l'êtes de son superbe Diadême, Sire, faites éclates le même zéle,
											qui ne peut que vous être infiniment glorieux. Nous avons droit, ce semble, de
											l'attendre de vôtre piété, qui a paru si eminente dans le choix que vous avez
											fait de la plus vertueuse Princesse du monde, pour la placer à côté de vous
											sur le plus auguste Trône de l'univers.</p>
									</div>
								</body>
							</text></p>

						<q rend="blockquote"><p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi></p>
							<text>
								<body>
									<div type="letter">

										<opener>ADDRESS TO THE KING OF PERE DU BEAUBOIS, JESUIT. <salute>S<hi rend="sc"
													>IRE--</hi></salute></opener>
										<p>This savage, who has the honor to appear before Your Majesty, is not a common
											man, and yet, although chief of his village, and one of the most distinguished
											of his nation, he has nothing of that splendor nor of that grandeur which
											surround princes, and which make them so estimable to the peoples who are
											subject to them, but which are unknown to the nations of America. In addition
											to this, that which Your Majesty will esteem, without doubt in him, is that
											this Indian, born, so to speak, in another world, and reared in the midst of
											forests, has been able to conceive a high enough idea of your supreme grandeur
											to desire so ardently to see it more closely, and to come to pay homage. An
											unfortunate shipwreck, which frightened those who were to accompany him, did
											not intimidate him, and since he has been in France the sight of that which is
											the wonder of all foreigners has served to increase his ardor to see the
											monarch of so powerful an empire. The principal chief of all the Illinois
											nation greatly envies the good fortune of this one, as he himself <pb
												id="VAC0881-040" n="292"/> says to Your Majesty in so striking a manner, and
											has often regretted, so to speak, that his presence in his own country was so
											necessary to the French nation.</p>
										<p>Deign, Sire, to receive with kindness the letter which he has ventured to
											write to Your Majesty, and to respond favorably. For myself, Sire, I consider
											myself most happy to approach today to your throne, and to be witness of the
											marvels which France admires in your sacred person. Permit me, Sire, to ask of
											Your Majesty the royal protection for the missions of Louisiana, that vast
											province, where one could not increase them enough for the good of your colony
											and to give sufficiently to the savage nations which dwell there the knowledge
											of the true God. Louis the Grand, of glorious memory, made it always his
											pleasure to protect those whom Providence honored with so holy a ministry, and
											to testify by the zeal he had for the propagation of the faith. Heir of his
											heroic virtues, as you are of his superb diadem, Sire, make resplendent the
											same zeal, which is able to make you eternally glorious. We have the right, it
											would appear, to expect this of your piety, which is shown so notably in the
											choice which you have made of the most virtuous princess in the world to place
											by your side on the most august throne of the universe.]</p>
									</div>
								</body>
							</text></q>

						<p>Pere Beaubois also presented a letter and necklace from Mamantouensa, the head chief,
							who said in his letter he would have liked to come--</p>

						<q rend="blockquote"><p>"Mais mes Pères de Boisbriant &amp; du Tisné qui tiennent la
								place, m'ont dit du rester pour maintenir mon Village, defendre les Robbes noires
								&amp; le village français contre les Renards, tes ennemis &amp; les nôtres."</p></q>


						<q rend="blockquote"><p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> But my fathers de Boisbriant
								and du Tisne, who command here, have told me to remain to <pb id="VAC0881-041"
									n="293"/> maintain my village, to defend the Jesuits and the French village
								against the Fox Indians, your enemies and ours.]</p></q>

						<p>The King took the Indians out hunting on Tuesday, 27th November. The Queen much
							wanted to see them, but the King thought their "assortiment sauvage &amp; trop
							bizarre" might be bad for her health--he was fifteen, and just married--so she had to
							be content with an interview with Pere Beaubois. Before they left the King presented
							each chief with a medal hung on a gold chain, a musket, game bag, sword, watch, and a
							picture representing their interview with the King.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 2.</head>

						<p>J'ay envoyé un Père Jesuite d'jey aux Caouitas pour scavoir ce qui se passera chés
							eux, et pour voir si on pourra Establir une mission dans cette nation. * * * Il faudra
							attendre que la Colonie rende d'auvantage avant que de proposer de nouveaux
							Establissements.</p>

						<closer>
							<signed rend="center">(Signed)</signed>
							<signed>
								<hi rend="right">P<hi rend="sc">ERIER.</hi></hi></signed>
							<address>
						<addrLine> <hi rend="left">Nouvelle Orleans, le pᴿ Avril, 1729.</hi></addrLine></address></closer>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<q rend="blockquote"><p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> I have sent a Jesuit father
								from here to the Caouitas to learn what is going on there, and to see if we could
								establish a mission with this nation. * * * It should be expected that some
								advantages would result to the colony before proposing new establishments.</p></q>

						<closer>
							<signed>
								<hi rend="right">P</hi><hi rend="sc">ERIER.</hi></signed>
							<address>
<addrLine> 
	
	<hi rend="left">New Orleans,							
							April 1, 1729.]</hi></addrLine></address></closer>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 3.</head>

						<p>J'ay fait remonter cette année une fregatte aux Natchez qui est à cent vingt lieues.
							J'espere faire remonter les vaisseau beaucoup plus haut.</p>

						<closer>
							<signed>
								<hi rend="right">I</hi><hi rend="sc">BID.</hi></signed>
							<dateline>
								<date>
									<hi rend="right">(Same date.)</hi></date>
							</dateline></closer>
					</div3>


					<pb id="VAC0881-042" n="294"/>


					<div3>
						<q rend="blockquote"><p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> I have this year sent a frigate
								up the river to the Natchez, which is an hundred and twenty leagues. I hope to send
								the vessels much higher up than that.]</p></q>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 4.</head>

						<p>Il est vray, Monsieur, que depuis le depart du Rᵈ P. de Beaubois tout est plus
							tranquile icy. * * * I faudra Monsieur penser d'Etablir un Curé à la Pointe Coupbée a
							quarente lieues d'icy ce Canton commence à ce bien peupler, il y a une quarantaine
							d'habitants, etc.</p>
						<closer>
							<signed>
								<hi rend="left">Letter of J. Delaihaye to Abbé Raguet.</hi></signed>
							<dateline>
								<date>
									<hi rend="left">N. O. 20 Aôust, 1729.</hi></date>
							</dateline></closer>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<q rend="blockquote"><p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> It is true, Monsieur, that
								since the departure of the reverend Pere de Beaubois all is more tranquil here. * *
								* There should be considered, Monsieur, the establishment of a curé at Pointe
								Coupee, forty leagues from here. This canton begins to be well populated; it has
								forty residents.</p></q>


						<closer>
							<signed>
								<hi rend="left">J. Delaihaye to Abbe Raguet.</hi></signed>
							<dateline>
								<date>
									<hi rend="left">New Orleans, August 20, 1729.]</hi></date></dateline></closer>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 5.</head>

						<p>Memoire pour la Père de Beaubois, Superieur des Missions de la Compagnie de Jesus à
							la Louisiane.</p>
						<p>No date; no signature. A defense of P. Beaubois against the charges of immoral
							conduct, being a noisy, turbulent, ambitious man, who had "gaté l'esprit du
							commandant," usurped clerical functions at New Orleans without permission, etc. In all
							this long document there is no allusion to any memoir about the Wabash. It appears to
							have been written about 1729.</p>
					</div3>
					<pb id="VAC0881-043" n="295"/>


					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 6.</head>

						<p>The Capuchins of the Province of Champagne were charged with a mission to Louisiana,
							by the King's commission, decree dated 16 May, 1722. Some time afterwards it was
							arranged that the colony should be divided between the Capuchins and the Jesuits.
							"Suivant ce parlage les Jesuites avoient tout le pays du haut du fleuve St. Louis
							jusques à la Rivière de Ouabache exclusivement. * * * En 1724 on revancha en faveur
							des Jesuites la partie du district des Capucines qui s'entendre depuis Ouabache
							jusques au Natchez exclusivement."</p>
						<p>From a "memoire sur ce qui a donné lieu au Rapel du P. de Beaubois" (evidently by a
							Capuchin, and dated--in a later hand--"X<hi rend="super">bre</hi> 1729.")</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<q rend="blockquote"><p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> After this conference the
								Jesuits had all the country on the upper Mississippi as far down as the Ohio
								exclusively. * * * In 1724 they gave to the Jesuits exclusively that part of the
								district of the Capuchins which extended from the Ohio to Natchez.</p>
							<p>From a memoir on that which has occurred on the recall of Pere de Beaubois.
								December 1729.]</p></q>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 7.</head>

						<p>Pour ce qui regarde les missionaries de Alibamons, des Apachez, des Natchitoches, et
							D'Ouabache que j'espere voir placer de l'année prochaine, etc.</p>
						<p>From a "Memoire sur les Missions de la Louisiane, Pour estre Presenté à messieurs de
							la Compagnie des indes," signed N. J. de Beaubois, Sup. Jes. Marked 1729, in pencil,
							but not dated.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<q rend="blockquote"><p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> Concerning the missionaries of
								the Alabamas, the Apaches, the Natchitoches, and of the Ouabache which I hope to see
								located next year, etc.</p>
							<p>From a Memoir on the Missions of Louisiana, to be presented to Messieurs of the
								Company of the Indies.]</p></q>
					</div3>
					<pb id="VAC0881-044" n="296"/>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 8.</head>
						<p>A Ouabache qui a toujours esté negligé et sur lequel selon moi pour les connaissances
							que j'en ay, on auroit du premier y etablir par rapport que cest une clef des Anglais
							par laquelle ils pourroient plûtot s'emparer de la Province de La Louisiane que par
							aucun endroit, et seduire nos nations quoyqu'en paix ils ont fait de ce Tentatif
							plusieurs fois; il seroit necessaire dans cette poste J'enverois pour ainsy dire le
							nombre il faudroit plûtot y mettre quartre cent hommes que trois.</p>
						<p>From Memoire de M. de St. Denis commandant aux Natchitoches, du 30 Novembre 1731.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<q rend="blockquote"><p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> On the Ouabache, which has
								always been neglected, and on which, in my opinion, by the information I have had,
								we should be the first to form an establishment, for by report it is a key of the
								English by which they would be better able to get hold of the Province of Louisiana
								than by any other place, and to entice away our tribes, because in peace they have
								made this effort many times. There will be necessary in this post--I would advance
								the number needed there, so to speak, to four hundred men rather than
							three.]</p></q>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 9.</head>

						<p>From Estat des Officiers que le Roy a resolu d'Etablir à la Louisiane et des
							Appointements quelle leur a Reglé à commencer du premier Juillet 1731.</p>

						<table rows="1" cols="2">
							<head>Aux Illinois.</head>

							<row role="label">

								<cell>Un commandant tout pour ses appointements que pour l'Entretien du fort</cell>
								<cell>2,000</cell>
							</row>
						</table>

						<table rows="1" cols="2">
							<head>A Ouabache.</head>

							<row role="label">

								<cell>Un commandant id</cell>
								<cell>800</cell>
							</row>
						</table>

						<p>Fait a Versailles le 30 Janvier 1731.</p>

						<closer>
							<signed>
								<hi rend="right">Signé Maurepas.</hi></signed>
						</closer>
					</div3>


					<pb id="VAC0881-045" n="297"/>


					<div3>
						<q rend="blockquote"><p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> From Roll of the officers that
								the King has decided to establish in Louisiana and of the salaries which have been
								fixed for them, to commence July 1, 1731.</p></q>

						<table rows="1" cols="2">
							<head>At the Illinois.</head>

							<row role="label">

								<cell>A commandant, in full for salaries and for the support of the fort</cell>
								<cell>2,000 (livres)</cell>
							</row>
						</table>

						<table rows="1" cols="2">
							<head>At the Ouabache.</head>

							<row role="label">

								<cell>A commandant, the same</cell>
								<cell>800</cell>
							</row>
						</table>

						<p>Done at Versailles, January 30, 1731.</p>
						<closer>
							<signed>
								<hi rend="right"> Signed Maurepas.]</hi></signed>
						</closer>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 10.</head>

						<p>From Projet de l'Estat des Depenses pour l'année 1731.</p>

						<table rows="1" cols="1">
							<head>A Ouabache.</head>

							<row role="label">

								<cell>A l'officier commandant tout pour suplem<hi rend="super">t</hi>
									d'appointements que pour l'entretien du fort pour les six d<hi rend="super"
										>ers</hi> mois 1731, à raison de 800 par an</cell>
								<cell>400:--:</cell>
							</row>
						</table>

						<p>(In these same estimates I also find)</p>

						<table rows="3" cols="1">
							<head>Offrs reformés.</head>

							<row role="label">

								<cell>Au S. Jantzen, lieutenant, pour les appointements des 6 d<hi rend="super"
										>ers</hi> mois, à raison de 480 par an</cell>
								<cell>240</cell>
								<cell>Au S. de St. Ange Père, id</cell>
								<cell>240</cell>
								<cell>Au S. de Vincennes, id</cell>
								<cell>240</cell>
							</row>
						</table>

						<q rend="blockquote"><p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> From Statement of Expenses for
								the year 1731.</p></q>

						<table rows="1" cols="1">
							<head>At the Ouabache.</head>
							<row role="label">




								<cell>To the commandant, both for the allowance of salary and for the maintenance of
									the post for the last six months of 1731, at the rate of 800 livres per
									year</cell>
								<cell>400:--:</cell>
							</row>
						</table>

						<pb id="VAC0881-046" n="298"/>

						<table rows="3" cols="1">
							<head>Half Pay Officers.</head>
							<row role="label">


								<cell>To Sieur Jantzen, lieutenant, for salary for the last six months, at the rate
									of 480 livres per year</cell>
								<cell>240</cell>
								<cell>To Sieur de St. Ange, the father, id</cell>
								<cell>240</cell>
								<cell>To Sieur de Vincennes, id</cell>
								<cell>240]</cell>
							</row>
						</table>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 11.</head>

						<p>Les habitants de la Prairie du fort de Chartres aux Ilinois, nous ont addressés pour
							demander la confirmation du choix qu'ils ont fait d'un prêtre des missions Etrangeres
							pour la deserte de 1'Eglise qu'ils ont fait batir à leurs frais avec un Presbiterre.
							Nous sommes informés qu'avant la batiss de cette paroisse ces habitans n'avoient point
							d'autres desservant que le jesuite missionaire de Mitchigamia qui est en même-temps
							aumonier du fort de Chartres. * * * Nous marquons cependant à M. de St. Ange qui
							commande en ce poste qui nostre avis est qu'il n'a pas esté au pouvoir de ces habitans
							d'appeler un prestre, etc.</p>
						<p>Letter from Perier and Salmon to the Minister, N. Orleans, 20 July, 1732.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<q rend="blockquote"><p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> The settlers of the Prairie of
								Fort Chartres, at the Illinois have addressed us demanding the confirmation of the
								choice they have made of a priest of the foreign missions to officiate at the church
								which they have built, with a parsonage, at their own expense. We are informed that
								before the building of this parish church these settlers had no one to serve them
								but the Jesuit Missionary to the Mitchigamia, who is at the same time Chaplain of
								Fort Chartres. * * * We informed M. de St. Ange, who commands at this post, that our
								understanding is that these settlers have not had any right to call a
							priest.]</p></q>
					</div3>

					<pb id="VAC0881-047" n="299"/>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 12.</head>

						<p>Quoyque trés propre pour le poste qu'il occupé il rendroit de meilleurs services s'il
							avoit un commandem<hi rend="super">t</hi> dans quelque poste. Celuy des Islinois luy
							conviendroit fort, il est aimé de ces sauvages, il y a demeuré longtemps, et il ne
							seroit pas eloigné (?) d'y retourner. Il y feroit plus de progres que le S. de St.
							Ange, Père qui y commande, et qui les Sauvages trouvent trop vieux.</p>

						<p>Concerning D'Artaguiette, from a report by Salmon to the Minister, Maurepas, 29
							March, 1732.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<q rend="blockquote"><p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> Although very well fitted for
								the position he occupies, he would render greater service if he had command in some
								post. That of the Illinois would suit him admirably. He is loved by these Indians;
								he lived there a long time; and he will not have to remove far to return there. He
								will make more progress there than Sieur de St. Ange, the father, who commands
								there, and whom the Indians find too old.]</p></q>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 13.</head>
						<p>In "The estimate of public expenses for the year 1732" I find an entry,</p>

						<table rows="1" cols="1">
							<row role="label">
								<cell>Au garde magazin à Ouabache</cell>
								<cell>300</cell>
							</row>
						</table>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<q rend="blockquote"><p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi></p></q>
						<table rows="1" cols="1">
							<row role="label">
								<cell>For a storekeeper at the Ouabache</cell>
								<cell>300]</cell>
							</row>
						</table>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 14.</head>

						<p>Is a long "Ordonnance donnée par monsieur de St. Ange au Sujét de l'assasinat commis
							en Lapersonne dunommée pierre roston Dit Langeuin soldat De Lagarrison du fort de
							Chartre." The Court Martial consisted of the St. Anges, father and son, Lieut. Bassée
							and Ensigns Dutisné and Buchet. St. Ange fils is described as an ensign. I do not find
							any matter of general interest in the trial. The murderer, Francois Frétél, was
							executed Oct. 16th, 1732.</p>
					</div3>



					<pb id="VAC0881-048" n="300"/>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 15.</head>
						<p>"Memoire contenant les services que Raymond Amyault, Ecuyer, Sr. D'Auseville, a
							rendus à l'Etat, les facultés de la Colonnie de la Louisiane, les Moyens de la faire
							fleurir, et la scittuation affreuse ou elle est presentement reduitte avec les causes
							de la Guerre." A long document of 92 foolscap pages (but the writing is only half
							across the page) containing about 15,000 words. It is an interesting account of the
							Colony. He suggests that 4,000 men would be needed to insure the safety of the post,
							viz.:</p>

						<list type="simple">

							<item>600 hommes à la Mobille, ce gros nombre y est necessaire pour contenir cette
								grosse Na<hi rend="super">n</hi> Chaquetas.</item>
							<item>100 aux Alibamons.</item>
							<item>200 aux Chaquetas.</item>
							<item>100 à la Balize.</item>
							<item>300 à la No<hi rend="super">lle</hi> Orleans.</item>
							<item>50 à l'entree de la Rivière Rouge.</item>
							<item>50 aux Tonnicas.</item>
							<item>100 aux Natchitoches.</item>
							<item>50 aux Akansas.</item>
							<item>400 aux Natchers dispersees en quatre forts faits de Gros Dieus Ronds.</item>
							<item>100 a l'entree de la Rivière de Yazous.</item>
							<item>50 a l'entree de la Ri<hi rend="super">re</hi> de Maramet.</item>
							<item>200 a la Rivière de Ouabach qui prend sa source prés la No<hi rend="super"
									>lle</hi> York.</item>
							<item>600 aux Ilinois afin de mettre les mineurs en seurette contre les
								sauvages.</item>
							<item>200 hommes en quatre postes du bas de la Ri<hi rend="super">re</hi> de
								Missouri.</item>
							<item>600 pour faire l'etablissement le plus pris des Espagnols au haut de la dite R.
								Missouri.</item>
							<item>300 hommes restans.</item>

							<milestone unit="typography" n="-----" rend="center"/>
							<item>4,000</item>
						</list>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 16.</head>
						<p>From a letter of Bienville and Salmon to the Minister, dated 20 May, 1733.</p>
						<p>"Par la même lettre le Sr. St. Ange temoigne estre peu assuré de la fideliteé des
							Ilinois, qui luy donnent souvent des alarnimes et font semblant de Craindre notre
							Ressentiment sur leurfautes passées pour avoir un pretexte de Remuer.</p>

						<pb id="VAC0881-049" n="301"/>

						<p>D'un autre Costé le Sr. de Vincennes, qui command aux Miamis, marque que les Sauvages
							etablis sur Ouabache ne sont pas plus tranquilles que les Illinois, qu'il n'est point
							en Etat de les Empecher d'avoir Commerce avec les Anglois, parce qu'il faudroit tous
							les faire reunis, et qu'il n'a point de Marchandise pour les y engager, que la
							Garrison d'ailleurs est trop foible pour contenir ces Nations.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<q rend="blockquote"><p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> By the same letter Sieur St.
								Ange testifies that he is little assured of the fidelity of the Illinois, who often
								give him alarm, and make pretense of fear of our resentment for their past faults to
								have a pretext for agitation.</p>
							<p>On another side Sieur de Vincennes, who commands at the home of the Miamis, states
								that the savages established on the Ouabache are not more tranquil than the
								Illinois; that he is not in condition to prevent them from trading with the English,
								because it would be necessary to bring them all together, and he has not the
								merchandise to invite them, in addition to which the garrison is too feeble to
								constrain this nation.]</p></q>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 17.</head>
						<p>Letter of M. Perier, 25 Jan., 1733, to the Minister:<lb/> Les Ouyatonons chez qui est
							Le Sr. de Vincennes se sont liez avec les Akansas pour faire La Guerre ensemble aux
							Chicachas, etc.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<q rend="blockquote"><p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> The Ouiatanons, at whose home
								is Sieur de Vincennes, are united with the Arkansas to make war together on the
								Chickasaws, etc.]</p></q>
					</div3>


					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 18.</head>
						<p>Letter from M. de Vincennes,--presumably, as also with the one following, to the
							Governor, but with no address given. The spelling is as in the original.</p>
					</div3>


					<pb id="VAC0881-050" n="302"/>
					<div3>
						<p>
							<text>
								<body>
									<div type="letter">
										<opener>
											<dateline>
												<date>
													<hi rend="right">Le 7 Mars, 1733.</hi></date>
											</dateline>
											<salute>M<hi rend="sc">ONSIEUR:</hi></salute><lb/></opener>
										<p>pour faire reponse a l honneur De Lavostre je Commenceray par vous informé
											que Le Ouabache est compoze De Cinq nations, qui Compoze quatre Villages Dont
											Lemoindre ets de soixante hommes portant Les armes et Letout peut faire six a
											sept Cent hommes qu'il serais necessaire Derassembler pour Lebien Du service
											et Leurs oster La proximite Des Langlais ille ma Esté impossible De faire
											rassembler toutes ces Nations parcequil a toutjours manqué De marchandise Dans
											Cette androit. Lefort que jay fait faire est à quatre Vinq Lieues Dans Le
											Ouabache au Desus Des Rivieres par oules anglais auront peu Disendre et ouvir
											commerce avec Ces nations. Landroit est fort propre pour y faire Ungros
											Establissement ceque jaurois fait si jauvis eut Des forces, à Lesgard du
											Commerce que Lonny (l'on y?) peu faire est Lapelletrie ille pent sortir toute
											les annee De Ce poste pour trante milluire (milliers?) Depelletrie Voyla
											Monsieur tout Le Commerce que Lonpourrit faire pour Lepresent.</p>
										<p>jamais onna eut plus Debesoing Detroupe Dan Ces androit qua present Les
											Sauvages tant illinoi, que miamis et autres sont plus insollent quil nont
											jamais eté et ce La Depuis que Lerenard est Defait. Le peut Dexperiance que
											jemesuis acquis Depuis 20 (?)<ref id="ref_022" rend="super" target="note_022"
												>22</ref>anneés que je suis avec eux mefait craindre quelque mauvais Retour
											De Ces nations surtout Les miens qui Voyt Une Establissement que jay Commancé
											et qui ne paroitre pas vouloir Estre continue puisque Depuis trois années
											ilnevient Rien cepandant monsieur Cest Lapassage Detoutes les nations tant Des
											Laes que Des autres androyts.</p>
										<p>Vous mefaitte Lhonneur Dememarquer Devous anvoy Une Estats Des ouvrages
											faitte et faire à ille ny a quun <note id="note_022"><ref target="ref_022"
													rend="super">22</ref>This is a very doubtful reading as may be seen from
												the fac simile. <pb id="VAC0881-051" n="303"/> fort et Deux maisons dedans
												et ille faudroyt presentement y faire faire Uncordegarde avec Des Cazernes
												pour loger Lessols Dats ille nest pas possible Dereste Dans cette androy
												avec si peut Detroupe ille faudroyt trante hommes avec Une officier Jesuis
												plus anbarasée que jamais Dans cette androyt par Laguerre Des chicachies qui
												Sont Venus Deux fois depuis leprintamps ille ny a que Douze jours que
												Ledernier party a améné trois personnes et Comme Cest Lefrancois qui leurs
												amis Le Cassetete alamain je suis obligé Defaire tout les jours De Ladepence
												jespere Devostre Bontez que Vous voudré Bien avoir Esgard acette androit et
												a Lapeine oujesuis tant pour moy que pour Lapetite garnizon que jay cest
												Lagrace quattand Devous Ce Luy qui a Lhonneur Destre avec Unprofond respect
											</note></p>

										<closer>
											<signed>
												<hi rend="center">Monsieur</hi><lb/> Vostre trés humble et trés obeissant Servituer<lb/>
												<hi rend="right">V<hi rend="sc">INSENNE</hi></hi>
											</signed>
										</closer>
									</div>
								</body>
							</text></p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi>
							<text>
								<body>
									<div type="letter">

										<opener>
											<dateline>
												<date>
													<hi rend="right">March 7, 1733.</hi></date></dateline>
											<salute>M<hi rend="sc">ONSIEUR</hi></salute>
										</opener>

										<p>To make reply to the honor of yours, I will commence by informing you that
											the Ouabache nation is composed of five tribes, which include four villages,
											of which the least is of sixty men bearing arms, and in all about six or seven
											hundred men, whom it will be necessary, for the good of the service, to gather
											together and remove from proximity to the English. It has been impossible for
											me to bring together all these tribes because I have always lacked merchandise
											in this place. The fort which I have had built is eighty leagues up the
											Ouabache, above the rivers by which the English will be able to descend and
											open trade with these tribes. The place is well fitted for the location of a
											large establishment, which I would have made if I had had the troops. In
											regard to the trade which can be had, it is in furs. It <pb id="VAC0881-052"
												n="304"/> is possible to send out from this post every year about thirty
											thousand skins. That, monsieur, is all the trade that can be secured for the
											present.</p>
										<p>There has never been so great need of troops at this place as at present. The
											Indians, Illinois as well as Miamis and others, are more insolent than they
											have ever been, and that since the Foxes have been overthrown. The little
											experience I have acquired in the twenty (?) years I have been with them,
											makes me fear some bad return from these nations, especially mine, which sees
											an establishment that I have begun and which there has appeared no desire to
											continue in the past three years. The only thing that can come in the
											meantime, Monsieur, is the loss to us of all the tribes, both of the lakes and
											of other places.</p>
										<p>You have done me the honor to ask me to send you a statement of the works
											finished and to be constructed. There is only a fort and two houses in it, and
											there should at once be built a guard room with barracks for lodging the
											soldiers. It is not possible to remain in this place with so few troops. It
											will need thirty men with an officer. I am more embarrassed than ever in this
											place by the war with, the Chickasaws who have come here twice since spring.
											It is only twelve days since the last party brought in three persons, and as
											it is the French who have put the tomahawk in their hands, I am obliged to be
											at expense continually. I hope of your kindness that you will give special
											attention to this place and to the trouble which I experience, as well for
											myself as for the little garrison that I have. It is a favor expected of you
											by him who has the honor to be with profound respect,</p>

										<closer>
											<signed>
												<hi rend="right">Monsieur,</hi><lb/> Your very humble and very obedient servant,<lb/>
												<hi rend="right">V<hi rend="sc">INCENNES</hi></hi>
											</signed></closer>
									</div>
								</body>
							</text></p>
					</div3>

					<pb id="VAC0881-053" n="305"/>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 19.</head>
						<p>A second letter from M. de Vincennes--as above.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<p>
							<text>
								<body>
									<div type="letter">
										<opener>
											<dateline>
												<date>
													<hi rend="right">21 Mars, 1733.</hi></date>
											</dateline>
											<salute>M<hi rend="sc">ONSIEUR:</hi></salute><lb/></opener>


										<p>je viens derecevoir Un paquit demonsieur Lemarquis De bauharnois que janvoy
											partire amons<hi rend="super">r</hi> de St. Ange pour vous Lefere tenir
											antoute dilligence.</p>
										<p>monsieur Lemarquis de Bauharnois manvoy Un collier et Uncalumet pour Les
											illinois que janvoy a monsr. de St. Ange pour insister Les nations a aller
											frapér sur les chicachias toutes les nations du Canada et de Lacs parte Ce
											printamps pour y aller tous ceux Dicy isont alles jusqua Leurs chef ille nest
											pas resté dan tous ces Villages un seule homme et tout ca apasée par ce poste
											cequi napas L'etée de bien court.</p>
										<p>jay eut lhonneur Devous marquer par ma derniere que Les chicachias onts tuez
											cette otthomne six francois Dans Ouabache qui savenoit a ce poste et dont ils
											estoit abitant ce meme party atuez Unde ces sauvages De ceposte avec sa feme
											sille commance avenir dans Ces Lieux il sera Dificile De voyager monsieur
											Lemarquis debauharnois me marque quil vent absolument faire detruire les
											chicachias et Leurs allies et dinviter (?) ces nations a Ci joindre a Ceux du
											Canada.</p>
										<p>Nous sommes Denuéz de tout Dans ceposte je suis obligé danprunter Des
											voyageurs et dedonner Le peu que jay pour obvier (?--illegible) a toutes Les
											affaires qui arrive journellement jay Lhonneur de vous suplier monsieur
											Devouloir bien avoir esgard a ce la et De me faire Rambourcér ceque jay fourny
											je previens quil maura ancore couter Baucoup quand ces nations Reviendron puis
											que tout Les prisonniers quil ameniront Nous seront donnés et quil faut payer
											Ce sorte dechose aussi bien que Decouvrir Les morts sille perde Dumonde
											jespere quils yront cette <pb id="VAC0881-054" n="306"/> otthomne y faire coup
											Dumoins je les y inviter Bien ils y sont toute a fait dispozes je vais partir
											dans quelques jours pour aller au grand village et si jevoy tout tranquille je
											pouré desendre au canada monsieur Lemarquis Debauhar nois me marque quil me
											permit daller faire dutour pour vacquer aux afaires demafamille jenecera (sera
											?) aux plus que sing mois Dans cevoyage jecrit am<hi rend="super">r</hi> De
											St. ange quil anvoy m<hi rend="super">r</hi> sonfis (son fils?) a mon apsance
											(absence?) jes pere monsieur que vous ne trouverez pas mavais que fasee ce
											voyage puisque jene Lefais quand car que jevoy toute anbontraing dans ces
											continent je Lhonneur Destre avec Un profond respect</p>
										<closer>
											<signed>
												<hi rend="center">Monsieur</hi><lb/> Vostre trés humble et trés obeissant Servituer<lb/>
												<hi rend="right">V<hi rend="sc">INSENNE</hi></hi>
											</signed>
											<dateline>
												<date>
													<hi rend="left">Du fort de Uabache ce 21ͤ mars
												1733.</hi></date></dateline>
										</closer>
									</div>
								</body>
							</text>
						</p>
					</div3>


					<div3>
						<p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi>
							<text>
								<body>
									<div type="letter">

										<opener>
											<dateline>
												<date>
													<hi rend="right">March 21, 1733.</hi></date></dateline>
											<salute>M<hi rend="sc">ONSIEUR--</hi></salute>
										</opener>

										<p>I received a pacquet from Monsieur the Marquis de Beauharnois which I sent to
											Monsieur de St. Ange that you might receive it with all diligence.</p>
										<p>Monsieur the Marquis de Beauharnois sent me a belt and a pipe for the
											Illinois, which I sent to Monsieur de St. Ange to insist that the tribes go to
											strike the Chickasaws. All the nations of Canada and of the lakes leave this
											spring to go there. All from this place have gone even to their chief. There
											does not remain in all these villages a single man and all is so quiet about
											the post that the summer will not seem very short.</p>
										<p>I had the honor to inform you by my last that the Chickasaws have killed this
											fall six Frenchmen on the Ouabache who were coming to this post and who lived
											here. The same party killed one of the Indians of this post, with his wife. If
											they begin to frequent this region <pb id="VAC0881-055" n="307"/> it will be
											difficult to travel. Monsieur the Marquis de Beauharnois informs me that he
											wishes to have entirely destroyed the Chickasaws and their allies, and to
											invite the tribes here to join those of Canada.</p>
										<p>We are stripped of everything in this post. I am obliged to borrow of the
											voyageurs, and to give the little I have to avoid difficulty from things that
											occur daily. I have the honor to beg you to give especial attention to this,
											and to reimburse me for what I have furnished. I anticipate that I will be put
											to still greater expense when the tribes return, because all the prisoners
											which they bring will be given to us, and it is necessary to pay for this sort
											of thing, as well as to hunt up the dead if anyone is lost. I hope that they
											will go to make war this fall. At least I shall urge them. They are much
											disposed to do so. I shall start in several days to go to the large village,
											and if I find all quiet I will be able to go on to Canada. Monsieur the
											Marquis de Beauharnois has said that he would permit me to make this trip to
											attend to the business affairs of my family. I shall not be more than five
											months on the route. I wrote to Monsieur de St. Ange to send Monsieur his son
											during my absence. I hope Monsieur that you will not be displeased that I make
											this trip, for I shall not make it unless I find everything in good shape
											among my charges.</p>
										<p>I have the honor to be, with profound respect,<lb/></p>

										<closer>
											<signed>
												<hi rend="center">Monsieur,</hi><lb/> Your very humble and obedient servant,<lb/>
												<hi rend="right">V<hi rend="sc">INCENNES</hi></hi>
											</signed>
											<dateline>
												<date>
													<hi rend="left">Of the Fort of the Ouabache, this 21 March, 1733.]
													</hi></date></dateline>
										</closer>

									</div>
								</body>
							</text></p>
					</div3>


					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 20.</head>
						<p>In the "Etat des Depenses de 1732,--Appointements et Gratiffications dans les
							Postes," I find:</p>
						<table rows="1" cols="1">
							<row role="label">
								<cell>A Mr. De Vincennes command<hi rend="super">t</hi> a Ouabache pour
									gratiffication</cell>
								<cell>800 (livres)</cell>
							</row>
						</table>
					</div3>


					<pb id="VAC0881-056" n="308"/>
					<div3>
						<p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> List of public expenses of 1732,--salaries and
							perquisites in the posts:</p>
						<table rows="1" cols="1">
							<row role="label">
								<cell>To M. de Vincennes, commandant at the Ouabache. For allowance</cell>
								<cell>800 livres.]</cell>
							</row>
						</table>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 21.</head>
						<p>From "La Louisiane "--M. de Bienville sur les sauvages Chicachas, Natchez &amp;
							Chactas:</p>
						<p>Le Sr. De Vincennes qui y commande lui mande qui les Peanguichas qui sont établis
							auprès de nôtre fort ont envie d'attirer à eux un village de la même nation qui est
							resté a 60 lieues plus haut Deux raisons lui font goûter ce dessein, la première pour
							fortifier notre Etablissement, et la Seconde pour ôter a ce village la commodité de
							commercer avec les Anglois qui out deux Magazins etablis chez les Chaouanons sur la
							Riviere d'Oio.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> Sieur de Vincennes, who commands there, informs me
							that the Piankeshaws, who are established near our fort, wish to draw to them a
							village of the same tribe which is located sixty leagues higher up. Two reasons make
							him approve this plan; the first is to strengthen our establishment, and the second to
							remove from this village the chance to trade with the English, who have established
							two store-houses in the country of the Shawnees on the River Ohio.]<ref id="ref_023"
								rend="super" target="note_023">23</ref></p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 22.</head>
						<p>From a report by the Governors--Bienville and Salmon--addressed to the Minister, and
							dated 8th April, 1734:</p>
						<p>Pour ce qui concerne Ouabache, M. de Vincennes de qui nous n'avions point encore eu
							des nouvelles, nous marque <milestone unit="typography" n="-----" rend="center"/>
							<note id="note_023"><ref target="ref_023" rend="super">23</ref>The Ohio above the
								mouth of the Wabash. In all this early period the Wabash was considered the main
								stream emptying into the Mississippi, while the Ohio was a tributary of the
								Ouabache.</note>
							<pb id="VAC0881-057" n="309"/> par un convoy qui vient de descendre des Ilinois, que
							le fort qu'il avoit fait pour la garnison, qui n'etoit que de 10 hommes, est tres
							petit, et en assez bon estat, qu'il convient seulement d'y mettre un doublage de
							pierres, qu'il a fait construire dedans une maison à son frais, pour son logement, et
							quelques soldats de leur part ont fait euxmemes des Baraques pour se loger, que
							presentement que la garnison sera augmenté jusquà 30 hommes, comme M. de Bienville en
							a donné les ordres à M. Dartaguiette.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> Concerning the Ouabache M. de Vincennes, from whom
							we have not yet had news, informs us by a convoy which has come down from the
							Illinois, that the fort which he has built is very small for the garrison, which is of
							only ten men, and is in good enough condition; that it is desirable only to add a
							sheathing of stone; that he had constructed within it, at his own expense, a house for
							his lodging, and several soldiers, on their part, have built a barracks for their
							lodging; that now the garrison will be increased to thirty men, as M. de Bienville has
							given orders to M. D'Artaguiette.]</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 23.</head>
						<p>Report of M. de Bienville on the Chickasaws, August 20, 1735:</p>
						<p>Le Sr. de Vincennes qui commande au fort des Peanguichias a determine les sauvages de
							son Quartier à faire la même chose (i. e., declare war against the Chickasaws) et a
							obtenu de M. Dartaguiette l'agréement de marcher avec eux avec ce quil pourra ramasser
							de Francois. Comme cet officier a beaucoup de credit sur l'esprit des sauvages, M. de
							Bienville est persuadé qu'il les engagera à bien faire.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> Sieur de Vincennes, who commands at the fort of the
							Piankeshaws, has induced the Indians of 309 <pb id="VAC0881-058" n="310"/> his region
							to do the same thing and has obtained from M. D'Artaguiette an agreement to march with
							them with such of the French as he can collect. As this officer has much influence on
							the spirit of the Indians, M. de Bienville is convinced that he will get them to act
							well.]</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 24.</head>
						<p>In a letter of Bienville and Salmon to the minister, May 13, 1737, it is mentioned
							that as the Jesuits live close to the hospital, one of the fathers might be appointed
							chaplain, and be on duty all day.</p>
						<p>Il pourroit même y rester la nuit dans Les cas pressants. Nous avons pour cela jetté
							la veue sur Le P. Doutreleau Cydevant superieur aux Ilinois, c'est un homme d'Environ
							45 ans qui n'est plus D'age à apprender l'Idiome sauvage, nous ne disons pas pour cela
							qu'il convienne de donner cette place d'Aumonier aux Jesuites. * * * Au sujet de la
							curé du fort de Chartres aux Ilinois nous attendons l'Effet de ce que Monseigneur en
							aura dit à M. L'evesque de Quebec.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> He would also be able to remain there over night in
							pressing cases. We have had in mind for this Pere D'Outreleau, former superior at the
							Illinois. He is a man of about forty-five years, who is no longer of an age to learn
							the Indian idiom. We express no opinion on the propriety of giving this place of
							chaplain to the Jesuits. * * * On the subject of the curé of Ft. Chartres, in the
							Illinois country, we await the effect of that which Monseigneur has said about it to
							the Bishop of Quebec.]</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 25.</head>
						<p>Extract from a letter of M. de Bienville to the Minister, June 21, 1737:</p>
						<p>Les Peanghikias chez qui nous avons un poste ou commandoit feu Mr. de Vincennes ont
							presque tous quittés <pb id="VAC0881-059" n="311"/> leur Village depuis sa mort, à
							reserve d'environ 15 hommes qui etoient encore avec le Sr. de St. Ange. Ils sont allés
							plus haut dans Ouabache à un autre village. Je prevOisque puisque cette station se
							retire on seroit inquieté par les Chikachas dans ce poste où la garnison n'est pas
							forte. Cette Circonstance et Les Tentatives recentes et reiterées des Anglais pour
							penetrer dans la Colonie par la rivière Oyo par laquelle ils descendent dans Ouabache
							me determine à replacer ce fort à 40 Lieues plus bas à l'entree de cette Rivière. Je
							l'y aurait mis d'abord si les Sauvages eussent voulus nous y suivre. Il se trouve
							aujourdhui que Les Kikapous et Maskoutins qui sont venus il y a deux ans faire Village
							avec les Miamis ne s'accordent point avec eux et Mr. De La Buissonière m'assure que
							pour peu qu'on les invitat ils viendront s'y établir. Je luy envoyeray les ordres pour
							ce Changement qui ne sera pas d'une grande depense et j'espère que Monseigneur les
							approuvera. Tout ce que je crains c'est que Left. de Linquetot<ref id="ref_024"
								rend="super" target="note_024">24</ref> officier de Canada qui commande aux Miamis
							et Ouyatanons, ne s'oppose à laisser aller Les Kikapous et Maskoutins, parceque ces
							deux nations sont de son departement. Je lui ecriverai a ce sujet.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> The Piankeshaws, in whose country we have a post
							where the late Sieur de Vincennes commanded, have almost all left their village since
							his death with the exception of about fifteen men who are still with Sieur de St.
							Ange. They have gone higher up the Ouabache to another village. I foresee that since
							this station shrinks we will be troubled by the Chickasaws in this post, which has a
							weak garrison. This circumstance and the recent and repeated attempts of the English
							to penetrate the colony by the river Ohio, by <milestone unit="typography" n="-----"
								rend="center"/>
							<note id="note_024"><ref target="ref_024" rend="super">24</ref> Presumably De
								Linctot--one of the Godefroy family--Tanguay, Dict. Genealog.</note>
							<pb id="VAC0881-060" n="312"/> which they descend to the Ouabache, determine me to
							relocate this fort forty leagues lower down, at the mouth of this river. I would have
							located it there in the first place if the Indians had been willing to follow us
							there. At the present time the Kickapoos and Mascoutins, who came two years ago to
							make their village with the Miamis, do not harmonize with them, and M. De la
							Buissoniere assures me that they will go for little more than an invitation if we
							establish there. I will send him orders for this change, which will not be of much
							expense, and I hope that Monseigneur will approve them. All that I fear is that
							Lieutenant de Linctot, officer of Canada, who is in command at the Miamis and
							Ouiatanons, may oppose letting the Kickapoos and Mascoutins go, as these two tribes
							are in his department. I will write to him on this subject.]</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 26.</head>


						<p>Letter from M. Salmon to Minister, 22d June, 1737: J'apprends par le Sr. Delaloire
							que le Sr. St. Ange, fils, qui etoit monté a Ouabache pour prendre le Commandement de
							ce poste à la place de feu M. de Vincennes luy marque que les Sauvages qui
							l'avoisinnent ont Envie de l'abandonner que quelques uns d'Entre Eux se sont déja
							retirés à leur ancien Village du Vermilion, en sorte que ne reste plus qu'environ 25
							hommes que s'il n'abandonment Comme Ily apparence, on sera Contraint de relever la
							garnison qui se Troveroit a la mercy des Ennemies. Il ajoute qu'il na point vu Jusques
							à present que ce poste fut d'une Grande utility, et qu'il cause beaucoup de Depense,
							pour moy Je pense qu' Effectivement Il est plus couteux qu'il n'est utile. Cependant
							Il seroit de Consequence de le Conserver pour Empecher les Anglais de s'y Etablir, ce
							qu'ils feront certainement si nous l'abandonna.</p>
					</div3>

					<pb id="VAC0881-061" n="313"/>
					<div3>
						<p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> I learn from Sieur Delaloire that Sieur St. Ange,
							the son, who had gone up to the Ouabache to take command of that post in place of the
							late M. de Vincennes, informs him that the Indians of that neighborhood wish to
							abandon it; that part of them have already retired to their old village of Vermillion,
							so that there remain only about twenty-five men who have not deserted it. Apparently,
							we shall be obliged to increase the garrison, which will be at the mercy of the enemy.
							He adds that he has never seen to the present time that this post was of much utility,
							and that it causes much expense. For myself, I think that really it is more expensive
							than useful. However, it will be important to maintain it to keep the English from
							establishing there, which they will certainly do if we abandon it.]</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<p>
							<text>
								<body>
									<div type="letter">
										<opener>
											<dateline>
												<date>
													<hi rend="right">64 R<hi rend="sc">UE DES</hi> M<hi rend="sc">ARTYRS,</hi>
															P<hi rend="sc">ARIS,</hi><lb/></hi> 10 September,
												1901.</date></dateline>
											<salute>D<hi rend="sc">EAR</hi> S<hi rend="sc">IR--</hi></salute></opener>
										<p>I have looked through sixteen volumes of MSS.--from the year 1730 to 1744 (I
											had previously been through the years 1725 to 1730)--but have failed to find
											the document by Father Beaubois, nor do I find any allusion to it. On his
											return to New Orleans (early in 1727) he stayed there some years and performed
											clerical functions, which so annoyed the Capuchins--who claimed an
											ecclesiastical monopoly--that they denounced him, and insisted on his being
											recalled. Extract No. 5 is from a long document in his defense by a Jesuit.
											Every possible argument in his favor is adduced, and if he had done the State
											some service, and they knew it, his apologist would have mentioned the fact;
											nor, though it would have been a signal instance of the "meddlesome ambition"
											with which the Capuchins charged him, do his opponents say anything about it.
											He returned to France, in 1729, to answer these <pb id="VAC0881-062" n="314"/>
											charges, but seems to have been back in New Orleans in 1731, but little or
											nothing is recorded about him after that date.</p>
										<p>The following observations on the excerpts made may perhaps prove useful:</p>
										<p>No. 1. There is nothing in this long article of any interest; a great part
											consists of speeches made up of fulsome compliments which the Indians probably
											never uttered. I have given the names of all the Indians, as you may be able
											to identify some of the personages or tribes. The picture representing the
											King receiving the Indians, I have a distinct recollection of having seen-at
											Versailles, I fancy.</p>
										<p>No. 4. Portion of a letter from a Capuchin monk, I imagine, to one of the
											heads of the order in France. The extract shows that Father Beaubois had left
											for France in August, 1729.</p>
										<p>No. 6. Is interesting as showing the division of the country between the
											missionaries of both sorts.</p>
										<p>No. 7. Is signed by Beaubois, as Superior of the Jesuits. If the date is
											1729--and we have just seen that it could not be later--that would give 1730
											as the foundation of the post on the Wabash, which agrees with the date given
											by M. de Vincennes. No doubt a Jesuit was sent there, but in the budgets and
											estimates the Capuchins are paid separately, but the Jesuits receive a lump
											sum (8,000 livres) for the support of 12 missionaries.</p>
										<p>No. 8. Is the earliest reference I find to the importance of the Ouabache as
											a "key" by which the English would seek to invade the colony. It is perhaps
											only a coincidence that the phrase "pour ainsy dire" also occurs twice in the
											course of Beaubois' short address to the King.</p>
										<p>Nos. 9 and 10. I find the commandant at Ouabache mentioned in every
											succeeding report as far as I have looked--i.e., to 1744. It is curious that
											he received 800 <pb id="VAC0881-063" n="315"/> livres a year whilst at the
											other posts the pay was 600 livres. Was this on account of the danger, or a
											recognition of Vincennes' influence with the Indians?</p>
										<p>No. 13. The proposed storekeeper does not seem to have been allowed, for
											there is no mention of such an official in any succeeding budget.</p>
										<p>Nos. 18 and 19. I have preserved the original spelling of these two letters.
											Bad writing, the absence of all stops and accents, and a curious habit of
											inserting a capital letter in the middle of a word made them difficult to
											decipher. It would seem that the fort was founded three years before the date
											of the first letter. In No. 19 the writing is even worse, and I have been
											obliged to query several words.</p>
										<p>No. 23. Here, for the first time, I find mention of the "fort des
											Peanguichas."</p>
										<p>No. 24. This is the only mention I find of Père D'Outreleau. As will be seen,
											he is proposed as hospital chaplain, because he is too old to learn the
											language of the Indians. This seems rather puzzling if he had been a
											missionary on the Wabash for two years.</p>
										<p>No. 25. Vincennes, Dartaguiette, St. Ange, the son, and a dozen other French
											officers were killed in a battle with the Chicachias on Palm Sunday, 1736.
											Several "relations" of this battle are found in these volumes. Was the fort
											ever moved, as proposed in this letter and the following?</p>
										<p>The mystery concerning Père Beaubois' memoir still remains unsolved. He could
											hardly have written it before his visit to France in 1725, for the post did
											not then exist. On his return he was superior of the order, and would hardly
											have gone to a distant post where there was a garrison of ten men. Perhaps he
											was disgraced when he went to France the second time, in 1729. Possibly the
											document was written during his stay in France, on either occasion. Father
											Sommervogel is unable to tell me where he found mention of the document, but
											thinks it was in <pb id="VAC0881-064" n="316"/> some catalogue of MSS.--but
											whether in France or in Canada, or whether in a public library or private
											collection, he has omitted to note. I will do my best to elucidate the
											mystery, and if I can find the document will at once communicate with you.</p>

										<closer>
											<salute rend="left">I am, dear sir, yours faithfully,<lb/></salute>
											<signed>R<hi rend="sc">OBERT</hi> B. D<hi rend="sc"
											>OUGLAS</hi>.</signed></closer>

									</div>
								</body>
							</text></p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">THIRD REPORT OF MR. DOUGLAS.</head>


						<p>
							<text>
								<body>
									<div type="letter">
										<opener>
											<dateline>
												<date>
													<hi rend="right">64 R<hi rend="sc">UE DES</hi> M<hi rend="sc">ARTYRS,</hi>
															P<hi rend="sc">ARIS,</hi><lb/></hi> 13 November,
												1901.</date></dateline>
											<salute>D<hi rend="sc">EAR</hi> S<hi rend="sc">IR</hi></salute></opener>

										<p>In accordance with your instructions, I have searched the volumes for the
											years 1720 to 1725 for the Beaubois memoir, and those of the years 1744 to
											1750 for any information I could find regarding the Ouabache, but, I regret to
											say, the success of my search has not been commensurate with the time and
											labor involved.</p>
										<p>There is no reference to Father Beaubois in any of the series from 1720 to
											1725. In several places I find lists and descriptions of the forty or fifty
											letters taken from New Orleans to France in some particular vessel, but there
											is nothing at all resembling the document of which we are in search. That,
											however, does not surprise me. The Governor would not have looked favorably on
											a Jesuit missionary who interfered in civil and military affairs, and Beaubois
											would, in all probability, have entrusted the document to some priest--a
											Jesuit for choice--returning to France. On the other hand, if this had been
											the case, I should think there would have been some memorandum about the
											document in the archives at the headquarters of the Jesuits. But Father
											Sommervogel himself pointed out to me that in the first edition of his book
											there was no mention of this memoir, and therefore he must have found <pb
												id="VAC0881-065" n="317"/> the reference to it between the appearance of the
											first and second editions--i. e., between 1886 and 1889. Unfortunately he can
											not tell me where this reference is, but he thinks it is in some catalogue of
											MSS. that he has seen--in France, he believes--but it might be in Canada.</p>
										<p>There are two other points which suggest themselves to me, and which I give
											for what they are worth. If Beaubois had written his memoir prior to his visit
											to the King (an account of which I sent you), and were the ambitious,
											meddlesome man his enemies describe him to have been, would he not have made
											some reference to his services in the course of his speech? The second is,
											could Beaubois have known sufficient about the country, before 1729--when he
											was in disgrace--to make his account of any value?</p>
										<p>At any rate I feel tolerably confident that the memoir is not in the Colonial
											Office. The nearest approach to it I have been able to find is a memoir by
											Père Baudoin, which, however, contains nothing of interest. These volumes
											contain from 500 to 700 pages each. In the earlier days of the colony, one
											volume suffices for two years, but after 1730 or so, two volumes are needed
											for one year. I have examined in all about twenty-five of these volumes, and
											in the six weeks I have worked it would have been impossible to go as
											carefully through each volume as I should have wished, and no doubt anyone who
											gleaned after me would find enough to repay his trouble. In fact, in hunting
											up the letters for the photographer to copy, I came across two extracts which
											I send herewith. My search in the years 1744-50 has not been prolific of
											results. De Vaudreuil, who was Governor then, gives hardly any news in his
											letters, which are filled with generalities about the Indians, the English and
											financial matters.</p>
										<p>No. 1. Shows that the Compagnie des Indes was fully alive to the importance
											of establishing factories on the <pb id="VAC0881-066" n="318"/> Ouabache. I
											presume it was the transfer of the colony to the royal authority that delayed
											the execution of these orders for several years.</p>
										<p>No. 2. I have found no previous reference to the writer of this letter, who I
											judge from the letter to have been an oldish or middle-aged man, long resident
											in the colony. He says (after the words "en attendant mieux"):</p>
										<p>"Vous voyez Mr. qu'il ne me manque plus pour faire un établissement solide a
											La Louisiane qu'un certain meuble qu'on se repent souvent d'avoir pris, et
											dont je me passeray, comme les autres."</p>
										<p>The "certain meuble" was a wife! He complains that the girls sent from Canada
											were "a very licentious lot," whilst those who came from France "had at least
											an appearance of virtue." He had expected that his sister would send him over
											a wife, but "his hopes in that quarter had ended in smoke." In his description
											of the massacre of the Canadian family, he mentions that one of the men with
											his wife and sister, went off for help, leaving the others "cabanés sur le
											bord du Mississipi a quatre ou cinq lieues de Ouabache." When help arrived,
											all had been murdered or taken prisoners by the Scioux.</p>
										<p>No. 3. From this it would seem that M. de Noyan had been appointed commandant
											on the Ouabache by the company, but had been superseded by the King's nominee
											when the colony came under royal control.</p>
										<p>No. 4. Is a long essay on Louisiana with a scheme for improving that colony
											and St. Domingo. I have copied out all that was of interest.</p>
										<p>No. 5. The same items occur in the accounts of every year. The Jesuits are
											always paid a lump sum, and the only officers mentioned by name are those at
											or near New Orleans.</p>
										<p>No. 6. He gives the same figures in a tabulated form on another page, where
											he makes the total number of <pb id="VAC0881-067" n="319"/> white men in the
											colony to be 1,700, with about 1,500 women and children. He adds, "the climate
											is healthy and the women prolific."</p>
										<p>No. 7. I do not know whether this alludes to enlarging or strengthening the
											old fort, or creating a new one. In 1750, I find two copies of a proposal by a
											M. Bailly Messager to found a new colony midway between New Orleans and
											Canada, and independent of both. He had an ax, or rather a whole cutlery store
											to grind, for he suggested that the King should make him Governor-General;
											present him with six square leagues of ground on the river front, with
											seigniorial rights over the property; send three regiments from France, and
											make him a lieutenant-colonel. As nothing ever came of this modest proposal, I
											did not think it worth while to copy it out.</p>
										<p>No. 8. I found while searching for the letters of Vincennes. It shows that
											Pere Baudoin was posted somewhere near the Ouabache, though apparently not on
											it. I presume that the prisoners from whom he derived his information were
											some of the Chicachas, who had captured the young Canadian, and had, in turn,
											been themselves captured by the Chactas. At any rate, it proves that Père
											Baudoin was posted somewhere near,<ref id="ref_025" rend="super"
												target="note_025">25</ref> and lends color to my supposition that some
											copyist may have confounded him with Beaubois.</p>
									</div>
								</body>
							</text></p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 1. 1720.</head>

						<p>Mèmoire pour M. du Vergier, Directeur Ordonnateur de la Colonie de la Louisiane,
							concernant les differents operations qu'il est chargé de faire pour perfectionner les
							établissements de la ditte Colonie. (22 pages foolscap.)</p>

						<milestone unit="typography" n="-----" rend="center"/>

						<note id="note_025"><ref target="ref_025" rend="super">25</ref> Père Baudoin was then
							with the Choctaws, with whom he remained for eighteen years. He was then withdrawn to
							New Orleans, on account of the hostile attitude of the Indians, and was made Superior
							General of Missions. Kips Early Jesuit Missions, p. 316. There is nothing to show that
							he was ever in the vicinity of the Ouabache.</note>

						<pb id="VAC0881-068" n="320"/>

						<p>(P. 3.) Les principaux postes que la Compagnie s'est proposée de faire fortifier sont
							l'Isle aux Vaisseaux, les Alebamons, et Ouabache.</p>
						<p>(P. 12.) Il est aussy necessaire de se poster sur la Riviere d'Ouabache où les
							Anglais semblent vouloir s'approcher, la Compagnie mande au Commandant de la Colonie
							d'y placer un corps de Troupes pour occuper le premier tout ce Terrain et empecher que
							les Anglais n'y penetrer. L'Ordonnateur y etablira une Tannerie pour l'aprest des
							peaux que l'on y traitera, ce qui empechera que les Mittes ne les gastent, ce que l'on
							n'a pu eviter jusque à present malgré les precautions que l'on y a prises.</p>
						<p>(P. 15.) L'on pourra tirer une grande quantité de peaux de boeuf de Ouabache, lorsque
							notre Etablissement y sera fait, mais il sera apropos de les tanner pour les
							conserver, et à cet effet d'y construire des Moulins à Tan.</p>
						<p>(P. 21.) Fait et arresté par nous, Directeurs de la Compagnie des Indes, a Paris, en
							l'hostel de la Compagnie, le quinze Septembre, Mil sept cent vingt. Signatures
							follow.)</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> The principal posts which the company proposes to
							fortify are the Isle aux Vaisseaux, the Alabamas and Ouabache. * * *</p>
						<p>It is also necessary to have a post on the River Ouabache where the English appear
							desirous to push forward. The company requests the commandant of the colony to place
							there a body of troops to occupy first this territory and prevent the English from
							penetrating there. The manager will establish there a tannery for the preservation of
							the skins which will be bought there, to prevent the mites from spoiling them, which
							we have not been able to avoid heretofore, notwithstanding the precautions that have
							been taken. * * *</p>
						<p>It will be possible to gather a great quantity of buffalo skins at the Ouabache, when
							our establishment shall be <pb id="VAC0881-069" n="321"/> made there, but it will be
							desirable to tan them for preservation and, for this purpose, to construct tan mills.
							* *</p>
						<p>Done and ordered by us, Directors of the Company of the Indies at Paris, in the hotel
							of the Company, the fifteenth of September, 1720.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 2. 1722.</head>

						<p>Extract from a letter of M. Chassin,<ref id="ref_026" rend="super" target="note_026"
								>26</ref> dated "Aux Illinois, le 1r. Juillet, 1722," and marked in corner, "Je l'ay
							recue à Versailles le 16<hi rend="super">e</hi> Decembre, 1722."</p>
						<p>Les Renars continuent toujours leurs insultes et ont deja frapé trois fois depuis le
							printens sur les sauvages du village auprès du fort de Chartres. Je ne scais meme
							s'ils ne m'ont pas laissé échaper exprès dans un voiage que j'ay fait aux Kaoukias
							avec M. Thaumar et un officier de cette garnison, peutêtre aussique comme nous etions
							tous trois bien montés et bien armés, ils nous ont vû sans oser nous attaquer.</p>
						<p>Enfin deux jours apres que nous fumes passer ils tuerent une femme à une lieue du
							fort de Chartres, au bord de la rivière. (Pages 3 and 4. Then follows on p. 5, a
							description of the massacre of a Canadian family by the Scioux.)</p>
						<p>Ils avoient deux canots bien chargés des marchandises qui avoient descendu fort
							heureusement des Miamis par Ouabache. * * *</p>
						<p>(P. 6.) Je me suis avisé aussi d'en prendre une (concession) à environ une demie
							lieue de fort de Chartres, où je vais resider. Elle fera au moins de vingt arpens de
							face sur une lieue où plus de profondeur, et j'espère avoir cette <milestone
								unit="typography" n="-----" rend="center"/>
							<note id="note_026"><ref target="ref_026" rend="super">26</ref> Nicolas Michel Chassin
								was a Commissary, or representative, of The Company of the West--John Law's
								Mississippi Company--afterwards merged in the Compagnie des Indes. He, with the
								Principal Commissary, who was then Marc Antoine de la Loire, and the Commandant, who
								was then De Boisbriant, formed the Provincial Council of the Illinois. Kaskaskia and
								its Parish Records, p. 2; Old Fort Chartres, p. 27.</note>
							<pb id="VAC0881-070" n="322"/> terre en franc aleu et titre seigneurial. Je compte y
							mettre l'année prochaine une demi douzaine de négres, en attendaut mieux. * * * Les
							Jesuites qui longtems avant que les français vinssent s'etablir en ce lieu avoient une
							mission chez les Kaskassies, sont nos curés, en cette qualité ils ont fait jusqu'a
							present les fonctions de Notaire mais on m'a charge de cette pratique jusqu'a ce que
							la Compagnie en ait envoyé un plus expert que moy.</p>
						<p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> The Fox Indians continue constantly their insults
							and have already, three times since spring, attacked the Indians of the village which
							is near Fort Chartres. I do not know, indeed, but that they allowed me to escape
							purposely, in a trip which I made to Cahokia with M. Thaumar and an officer of this
							garrison; it is possible, however, that as we were all three well mounted and well
							armed they saw us but were afraid to attack us. * * * At least, two days after we
							passed, they killed a woman a league from Fort Chartres, on the bank of the river. * *
							*</p>
						<p>They (the Canadian family) had two canoes well loaded with goods, which had descended
							very safely from the Miamis by the Ouabache. * * *</p>
						<p>I am thinking, also, of taking a concession about a half-league from Fort Chartres,
							where I am going to reside. It is of at least twenty arpents front by a league or more
							in depth, and I hope to have this land in freehold and seigniorial title. I expect to
							put there next year a half-dozen negroes to make improvements. * * *</p>
						<p>The Jesuits, who came a long time before the French to establish in this place, and
							who have a mission with the Kaskaskias, are our curés, and in this capacity they have
							performed until now the functions of notary, but I have been charged with this duty
							until the company has sent out someone more expert than myself.]</p>
					</div3>

					<pb id="VAC0881-071" n="323"/>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 3. 1722.</head>

						<p>Letter from M. Leblond de la Tour to the Compagnie des Indes, apparently.</p>

						<p>
							<text>
								<body>
									<div type="letter">
										<opener>
											<dateline>
												<date>
													<hi rend="right">Au for Louis le 17e May 1722.</hi></date></dateline>
											<salute>M<hi rend="sc">ESSIEURS</hi>--</salute></opener>
										<p>La crainte que j'ay que les lettres que j'ay l'honneur de vous écrire, et les
											plans et cartes qui les accompagnent n'ait le même que mes precedentes, fait
											que j'en ay chargé M. de Noyan, neveu de M. de Bienville, qui passe en France
											en veue de Retourner dans la Colonie, il doit prendre la poste des son
											arrivée, ainsy vous les recevres aussitôt. Comme il y a quelque temps qu'il
											est dans le pays où il a fait quelques voyages il vous rendra compte au vray
											Messieurs de ce que en ait; d'ailleurs c'est un Cavalier qui a du merite, la
											Compagnie l'avoit nommé commandant aux Ouabaches qui vient de luy estre osté
											par le dernier Reglement qui a esté fait; J'ose vous assurer Messieurs qu'il
											seroit bien plus propre de commander aux natchitoches que le Sr St Denis, sur
											lequel on ne peut conter et qui est meme d'engereux (sic) il ne connoit aucune
											subordination et n'execute aucun ordre qu'un luy donne ne faisant qu'a sa
											teste, d'ailleurs il a epousé une Espagnolle et il a des frequentes
											Conversations et grande liaison avec cette nation qu'il a deja voulu servir
											autrefois, mais il ne peut s'acomoder du prix, et il est capable de tout quand
											il est dans le vin ce qui luy arrive très souvant; nous avons l'honneur d'en
											ecrire notre sentiment.</p>
									</div>
								</body>
							</text></p>

						<closer>
							<salute rend="right">J'ay l'honneur etc etc<lb/></salute>
							<signed>L<hi rend="sc">EBLOND DE</hi> L<hi rend="sc">ATOUR</hi>.</signed></closer>
					</div3>

					<div3>

						<p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> The fear I have that the letters which I have the
							honor to write you, and the plans and maps which accompany them, are different from
							those of my predecessors, causes me to put them in charge of M. de Noyan, nephew of M.
							de Bienville, who goes to France with a <pb id="VAC0881-072" n="324"/> view of
							returning to the colony. He should take post on his arrival, in order that you may
							receive them as soon as possible. I would add that he is a cavalier of merit; the
							company had named him commandant at the Ouabaches which is taken away from him by the
							last orders. I venture to assure you Messieurs, that he would be much more proper to
							command at the Natchitoches than Sieur de St. Denis, on whom you cannot rely, and who
							indeed is dangerous. He knows no subordination, and does not execute any order that is
							given him, doing nothing but what suits him. Moreover he has married a Spanish woman,
							and he has frequent communications and great intrigue with that nation, which he
							formerly wished to serve but could not agree on the price; and he is capable of
							anything when he is in liquor, which is very often. I have the honor to express my
							opinion of him.</p>

						<closer>
							<salute rend="right">I have the honor, etc.,</salute>
							<signed>L<hi rend="sc">EBLOND DE</hi> L<hi rend="sc">ATOUR.]</hi></signed></closer>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 4.</head>

						<p>Instruction sommaire pour achever en peu de temps un solide etablissement dans la
							Louisiane, dirigée par le Sr. Drouot de Valdeterre, Capitaine Reformé au regiment du
							Prince de Pons, cydevant Commandant L'isle Dauphine et les Biloxy dans la
							Louisiane.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>

						<p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> Brief instruction for accomplishing in a short time
							a permanent establishment in Louisiana, prepared by Sieur Drouot de Valdeterre,
							invalided captain of the regiment of Prince de Pons, and former commandant of Isle
							Dauphin and Biloxi, in Louisiana.]</p>
						<p>The author proposes that there should be five "postes principaux," attached to each
							of which should be several "postes particulieres." The "3e poste principal a etablir"
								<pb id="VAC0881-073" n="325"/> is Alcanza. In the margin of page 22 is written "Les
							houabaches a etablir." Opposite this is:</p>
						<p>Il y a deux grosses Rivières qui se jettent ensemble dans le fleuve lesquelles
							forment une pointe ou L'auteur du memoire estime qu'il sera necessaire d'y faire un
							Etablissement et même d'y construire un fort.</p>
						<p>L'une de ces Rivières prend sa source du coté de La Caroline qui porte le nom de la
							nation, et L'autre du grand Lac des Illinois qui en porte le nom. L'entredeux de ces
							Rivieres est un terrain des plus beaux pour former les etablissements.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>

						<p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> There are two large rivers which flow together
							forming a point, where the author of the memoir thinks that it will be necessary to
							make an establishment, and indeed to build a fort. One of these rivers takes its rise
							in the direction of Carolina, and bears the name of the tribe, and the other comes
							from the direction of the great lake of the Illinois, and bears its name. The land
							between the two is most excellent for an establishment.]<ref id="ref_027" rend="super"
								target="note_027">27</ref></p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 5.</head>

						<p>In the accounts of the year 1743, I find:</p>
						<table rows="1" cols="1">
							<row role="label">
								<cell>Au commandant D'ouabaches par gratiff'on la somme de huit cent livres,
									cy</cell>
								<cell>800</cell>
							</row>
						</table>
						<p>(Most of the others received 600 l., but St. Denis, commandant aux Natchitoches had
							90 l. a month, or 1080 l. for the year.)</p>
						<p>At most of the posts--Natchitoches, Natchez, Mobile, Balise, etc.--the priest
							received 600 l., but the Jesuits still kept at Ouabache, I presume, for it is not
							mentioned, but there is the usual entry:</p>
						<milestone unit="typography" n="-----" rend="center"/>
						<note id="note_027"><ref target="ref_027" rend="super">27</ref>
							<p>This is very obscure. It is possible that the writer may refer to the junction of
								the Tennessee and the Ohio.</p></note>

						<pb id="VAC0881-074" n="326"/>
						<table rows="1" cols="1">
							<row role="label">
								<cell>Aux P. Jesuites missionaires, pour l'entretien et subsistance de deuze
									Religeuses prestres, et de deux freres pour le service des missions, la somme de
									huit mil livres, cy</cell>
								<cell>8000 </cell>
								<cell>800</cell>
							</row>
						</table>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> To the Jesuit fathers, for salary and subsistence of
							twelve priests and two brothers, for the service of the missions, the sum of 8000
							livres.]</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 6.</head>

						<p>Memoire sur l'Etat de la Colonie de la Louisiane en 1746.</p>
						<p>(P. 11.) Telles sont les habitations Françaises qui se trouvent sur le fleuve du
							Mississipi: Il y en a encore deux autres qu'il ne faut point omettre le premier sur le
							Missouri a environ 90 lieues de son embouchure dans le fleuve du Mississipi, et a 100
							lieues des Illinois. L'autre appelé les petits ouyas, situé sur le Ouabache qui prend
							le nom de cette riviere après sa reunion avec l'oyo, et de la se rend dans le
							Mississipi. Les petits ouyas sont environ a 70 lieues de l'embouchure de la Belle
							riviere et a 100 lieues des Illinois. Ces deux établissements sont encore très peu
							considerables. Celui des Missouris n'etant compose que d'environ 20 hommes et 10
							negres; celui des petits ouyas n' étant que d'environ 40 hommes et de 5 negres. Leur
							occupation est la chasse, la culture du blés et celle du tabac.</p>
						<p>(P. 27.) Nous avons deja parlé du poste des petits ouyas sur le Ouabache, lequel
							depend de la Louisiane. En remontant plus haut la même riviere, a 60 lieues de
							distance, il y a un petit etablissement aux grands ouyas, c'est de ceux qui qui
							dependent du Canada celui qui est le plus avancé vers la Louisiane. Il n'est composé
							que d'environ 20 habitans. Il s'y fait un commerce de traite assez considerable. * * *
							A la Source du Ouabache on trouve les Miamis qui sont environ au nombre de 300
							guerriers, <pb id="VAC0881-075" n="327"/> et ou il ya encore un poste François a peu
							près aussi foible que celui des grands ouyas. L'objet est le meme, qui est de
							s'assurer de la traite des pelleteries.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> Such are the French settlements on the Mississippi
							river. There are still two others which should not be omitted. The first is on the
							Missouri about 90 leagues from where it empties into the Mississippi river, and about
							100 leagues from the Illinois. The other is called the Little Weas,<ref id="ref_028"
								rend="super" target="note_028">28</ref> situated on the Ouabache, which holds this
							name after its junction with the Ohio, and under it flows into the Mississippi. The
							Little Weas is about 70 leagues from the junction of the Ohio, and about 100 leagues
							from the Illinois. These two establishments are quite inconsiderable, that of the
							Missouris being composed of only about 20 men and 10 negroes, and that of the Little
							Weas having about 40 men and 5 negroes. Their occupation is hunting and the culture of
							wheat and tobacco. * * *</p>
						<p>(P. 27.) I have already spoken of the post of the Little Weas, which belongs to
							Louisiana. Going higher up the same river, at a distance of 60 leagues, there is a
							little establishment at the Great Weas; it is the nearest to Louisiana of those
							belonging to Canada. It has about 20, residents. It has quite a considerable Indian
							trade. * * * At the head of the Ouabache are found the Miamis, who are about 300
							warriors in number, and here there is still another French post almost as weak as that
							of the Great Weas. Its purpose is the same, which is to assure the trade in
							skins.]</p>

						<milestone unit="typography" n="-----" rend="center"/>

						<note id="note_028"><ref target="ref_028" rend="super">28</ref>
							<p>The Vincennes post. The name refers to the Ouiatanon or Wea Indians, of whom the
								Piankeshaws were sometimes considered a part. At that time the common English
								rendering of this name was Little Wiautanon, which was usually abbreviated "L.
								Wiaut."</p></note>
					</div3>
					<pb id="VAC0881-076" n="328"/>

					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 7.</head>

						<p>Letter of M. de Vaudreuil, Governor, dated 8th April, 1747.</p>
						<p>(P. 3.) La crainte que j'en ai eu m'a fait insister Monseigneur a vous faire sentir
							de quelle importance nous seroit le fort projetté sur Ouabache, et j'en sens tellement
							la necessité, que j'aurois pris sur moi a le commencer cette année si je n'eusse
							trouvé a ce sujet vos ordres trop precises. Ces considerations me font esperer
							Monseigneur que vous voudré bien m'en donner par le prochain vaisseau qui puissent
							déterminer cet etablissement suivant les plans que vous en ayes recu.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> The fear which I have always had makes me insist,
							Monseigneur, that you consider of what importance to us will be the projected fort on
							the Ouabache, and I feel the necessity of it so much that I should have taken it on
							myself to commence it this year, if I had not found your orders on this subject very
							explicit. These considerations make me hope, Monseigneur, that you may be willing to
							authorize me, by the next vessel, to make this establishment, according to the plans
							which you have received.]</p>
					</div3>


					<div3>
						<head rend="center">No. 8.</head>

						<p>Report of de Bienville, 27 July, 1734.</p>
						<p>Le Pere Baudoin lui mande aussy que le jeune Canadian qui avoit êté pris par les
							Chicachas il y a 2 ans avoit êté ramené sur la Riviere d'Ouabache au dessus
							1'etablissement francais où les sauvages l'on mis dans une Pirogue avec un aviron et
							les vivres necessaire pour se conduire au fort; il tient cette nouvelle des
							prisonniers que les Chactas ont emmené.</p>
					</div3>

					<pb id="VAC0881-077" n="329"/>

					<div3>
						<p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi> Father Baudoin reports also that the young Canadian
							who was taken by the Chickasaws two years ago has been released on the river Ouabache,
							below the French establishment, where the Indians put him in a pirogue with a paddle
							and the food necessary to supply him to the fort; he obtained this information from
							the prisoners whom the Choctaws have brought in.]</p>
					</div3>


					<div3>
						<head>SAUVAGES DE LA RIVIERE OUABACHE.<ref id="ref_029" rend="super" target="note_029"
								>29</ref></head>

						<p rend="center">(From the same Report.)</p>

						<p>Le Sieur de Vincennes qui y commande lui mande que les Peanguichas qui sont etablis
							auprès de notre fort ont envie d'attirer à eux un Village de la même nation qui en
							reste à 60 lieues plus haut. Deux raisons lui font gôuter ce dessein, la première pour
							fortifier nôtre etablissement, et la seconde pour ôter à ce village la commodité de
							commercer avec les Anglais qui ont deux Magasins établis chez les Chaouanons sur la
							Rivière d'Oio. Cet officier ajoute qu'il ne seroit pas difficile de leur enlever cette
							nation qui ne leur donne la préference que parcequ'ils ne sont pas à portée de tirer
							leur besoins de nous comme des Anglais. Il assure qu'une partie a dessein dese retirer
							au Detroit et l'autre auprès de luy. Si Monseigneur juge que ces changements
							conviennent je donnerais les ordres en consequence au Sieur de Vincennes. Au surplus,
							comme le poste d'Ouabache est un des plus importants de la Colonie puisque c'est une
							Barrière qu'on oppose aux progres des Anglais, qui de tout temps ont beaucoup fre
							quenté ces Quartiers, il a donné ordre a M. Dartaguiette de detacher 30 hommes avec
							deux officiers pour en composer la garnison.</p>

						<p rend="center">(Marked "approuvée.")</p>

						<milestone unit="typography" n="-----" rend="center"/>

						<note id="note_029"><ref target="ref_029" rend="super">29</ref>This is in part the same
							as section 21 of the second report.</note>
					</div3>

					<pb id="VAC0881-078" n="330"/>

					<div3>
						<p>[T<hi rend="sc">RANSLATION.</hi></p>
						<p rend="center">INDIANS OF THE RIVER OUABACHE.</p>

						<p>Sieur de Vincennes, who commands there, reports that the Piankeshaws, who are settled
							near our fort, desire to draw to them a village of the same nation which is 60 leagues
							higher up. Two reasons make him favor this design; the first to strengthen our
							establishment, and the second to take from this village the opportunity for trading
							with the English, who have two warehouses at the home of the Shawnees on the Ohio
							river. This officer adds that it will not be difficult to win over this tribe, as they
							give them the preference only because they are not urged to supply their needs from
							us, as they are by the English. He states that one part intends to withdraw to
							Detroit, and the other near to him. If Monseigneur considers these changes desirable I
							will give orders in accordance to Sieur de Vincennes. In addition, as the post of
							Ouabache is one of the more important ones of the Colony, since it is a barrier to
							obstruct the advance of the English, who always have commonly frequented these parts,
							he has given orders to M. D'Artaguiette to detach 30 men with two officers to garrison
							it.]</p>
					</div3>

					<div3>
						<head>Amended Translation</head>
						<p>Line 7. ing with the English, who two warehouses among</p>
						<p>Line 8. the Shawnees on the Ohio River. This officer</p>
					</div3>
					<!--
    			-->

				</div2>

			</div1>

		</back>

	</text>


</TEI.2>
