<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//IA Books//DTD TEI for Indiana Authors Books//EN"
                       "teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="VAC1126">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Alt Heidelberg and its student life</title>
				<author>Miller, George Morey</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded By</resp>
					<!--Update the value of the element below with your name in
                                direct order.-->
					<name>Beth Gucinski</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
				<address>
                    <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
                </address>
				<idno>VAC1126</idno>
				<availability status="unknown">
					<p>Copyright 2009 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
					<p>Indiana University provides the information contained on this web site for
						non-commercial, personal, or research use only. All other use, including but not limited
						to commercial or scholarly reproductions, redistribution, publication or transmission,
						whether by electronic means or otherwise, without prior written permission of the
						copyright holder is strictly prohibited.</p>
				</availability>
				<!--Update the value of the date element with the year the document
                        is being encoded.-->
				<date>2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblFull>
					<titleStmt>
						<title type="main">Alt Heidelberg and its student life</title>
						<author id="ina-v1-entry-0596">Miller, George Morey</author>
					</titleStmt>
					<extent>38 p. : ill. ; 23 cm.</extent>
					<publicationStmt>
						<publisher>O. Petters</publisher>
						<pubPlace>Heidelberg</pubPlace>
						<date>1911</date>
					</publicationStmt>
				</biblFull>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>The Digital Library Program was awarded a Library Services and Technology Act (LSTA)
					grant in 2005 to make available online the three-volume, reference work, <title>Indiana
						Authors and Their Books</title> along with selected monographs by Indiana authors.</p>
			</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl n="3">
				<p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and has
					been encoded and edited using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
					Guidelines following the TEI Lite standard. Digital page images are linked to the text
					file.</p>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<tagUsage gi="div1">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy id="lcsh">
					<bibl>
						<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language>English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="lcsh">
					<list>
						<item>Universität Heidelberg--Students.</item>
						<item>Students</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<!--The revision description tracks significant changes made to the file
                    after completion. This information will remain commented out unless someone has
                    conducted quality assessment of the texts and have made changes to the file as a
                    result.-->
		<!-- <revisionDesc> <change>
                    <date>$Date</date> <respStmt>
                    <name>$Name</name>
                    <resp>$Responsibility</resp>
                    </respStmt> <item>$Changes</item>
                    </change> </revisionDesc> -->
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<pb id="VAC1126-001" n="[1]"/>
			<titlePage>
				<docTitle>
					<titlePart type="main">Alt Heidelberg<lb/> and its Student Life</titlePart>
				</docTitle>
				<byline>by<lb/>
					<docAuthor>George Morey Miller</docAuthor><lb/> Indiana University, '92<lb/> (Φ.Γ.Δ.
					&mdash; Φ.Β.Κ.)<lb/> With 10 illustrations</byline>
				<lb/>
				<docImprint><publisher>Otto Petters</publisher>
					<pubPlace>Heidelberg</pubPlace>
					<docDate>1911</docDate></docImprint>
			</titlePage>
			<pb id="VAC1126-002" n="2"/>
			<div1 type="figures">
				<head rend="center">LIST OF ILLUSTRATIONS:</head>
				<list type="ordered" rend="decimal">
					<item><hi rend="left">Heidelberg from The Scheffel Monument</hi>
						<hi rend="right">3</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC1126-003"/></item>
					<item><hi rend="left">The University</hi>
						<hi rend="right">9</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC1126-009"/></item>
					<item><hi rend="left">The Fox Riding (1842)</hi>
						<hi rend="right">13</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC1126-013"/></item>
					<item><hi rend="left">The Hirschgasse</hi>
						<hi rend="right">17</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC1126-017"/></item>
					<item><hi rend="left">The Carcer</hi>
						<hi rend="right">21</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC1126-021"/></item>
					<item><hi rend="left">A Mensur between Burschenschaft Students (1902)</hi>
						<hi rend="right">25</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC1126-025"/></item>
					<item><hi rend="left">A Mensur between Corps Students (1908)</hi>
						<hi rend="right">29</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC1126-029"/></item>
					<item><hi rend="left">The last work of Pauk Doctor Immisch after a duel of Corps Students
							(1885)</hi>
						<hi rend="right">31</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC1126-031"/></item>
					<item><hi rend="left">Pauk Doctor Huber, the Duel Surgeon of to day, at work (1909)</hi>
						<hi rend="right">33</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC1126-033"/></item>
					<item><hi rend="left">The Hirschgasse with the castle in the distance</hi>
						<hi rend="right">36</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC1126-036"/></item>
				</list>
			</div1>
			<pb id="VAC1126-003" n="[3]"/>
			<div1 type="frontispiece">
				<head type="supplied">FRONTISPIECE</head>
				<p><figure>
						<p rend="i">Heidelberg from The Scheffel Monument</p>
					</figure></p>
			</div1>
			<pb id="VAC1126-004" n="4"/>
			<div1 type="epigraph">
				<head rend="center">ALT HEIDELBERG.</head>
				<lg>
					<l>Old Heidelberg! Thy beauty</l>
					<l>Is crowned with honours rare;</l>
					<l>No town on Rhine or Neckar</l>
					<l>Can unto thee compare.</l>
				</lg>
				<lg>
					<l>Thou home of merry comrades.</l>
					<l>Of wisdom deep and wine,</l>
					<l>Within thy stream's clear water</l>
					<l>Blue eyes reflected shine.</l>
				</lg>
				<lg>
					<l>And when with southern breezes,</l>
					<l>Spring comes o'er hill and lea,</l>
					<l>She weaves with fairest blossoms</l>
					<l>A bridal robe for thee.</l>
				</lg>
				<lg>
					<l>And like a bride, thy image</l>
					<l>I hold within my heart, &mdash;</l>
					<l>Emblem to me for ever</l>
					<l>Of Love and Youth thou art!</l>
				</lg>
				<lg>
					<l>If worldly cares torment me,</l>
					<l>And life seems dull and stale,</l>
					<l>I'll spur my horse and gallop</l>
					<l>Out to the Neckar vale.</l>
				</lg>
				<p>Translated by<lb/> K. v. T.</p>
				<p rend="right">Victor v. Scheffel<lb/> 1826-1886.</p>
			</div1>
		</front>
		<body>
			<pb id="VAC1126-005" n="5"/>
			<div1 type="book">
				<head rend="center">"ALT HEIDELBERG" AND ITS STUDENT LIFE.</head>
				<p>Some four years ago it was my privilege to make a pilgrimage to a shrine, to the
					birthplace of the American college fraternity system, old William and Mary College in
					Virginia, the college where Jefferson learned how to write the Declaration of
					Independence. Yet the founding of the Greek letter fraternity of ΦΒΚ, with all the
					principles of the American national college fraternities of today, was only part of a
					larger movement. The movement so well expressed in the opening sentence of the first
					minute of old ΦΒΚ, dated December 5, 1776,&mdash;"a happy spirit and resolution of
					attaining the important ends of society"&mdash;was embodied not alone in the New World
					with the birth of the new nation and the new Greek letter fraternity, but also found
					notable contemporary expression among the enlightened progressive spirits of western
					Europe and especially among the students of the German universities.</p>
				<p>Since making that pilgrimage to William and Mary College I have had the chance to see
					again at least a bit of the outside of Oxford and Cambridge, where, living together within
					the college pales, young Englishmen have for centuries received that education from their
					fellows which has so well fitted them for national leadership. The individuality of
					English university life <pb id="VAC1126-006" n="6"/> has helped to create the
					individuality of the English nation. Yet English college life offers no close parallel to
					American student life or to anything found in Germany. It has been my good fortune
					recently, as an old American college fraternity man, to come into fairly close contact
					with a college fraternity system that traces its descent back far beyond the hundred and
					thirty-five years of the American college fraternity, back for nearly a thousand years
					into the dark ages, back to the dawn of university education in Europe. Since the spring
					of 1907, I have spent the larger part of two college years in, with the possible exception
					of Oxford, the best known, the most typical home of student life in Europe, in what the
					students themselves have called for generations, "Alt Heidelberg."</p>
				<p>Heidelberg, its Castle, its University and its student life are known, by fame at least,
					throughout the world. Every year thousands of English and Americans gratefully break their
					journey between the Alps and the Rhine with a few hours, or days, in Heidelberg. Americans
					so unlike as Longfellow and Mark Twain have surrendered themselves equally to its charm.
					Goethe lingered here because he said the town had something ideal in its position and
					entire surroundings. It was not a mere boyish outburst of college spirit that caused
					Victor von Scheffel to write: <q rend="blockquote"><lg>
							<l>"Alt Heidelberg, du feine,</l>
							<l>Du Stadt an Ehren reich,</l>
							<l>Am Neckar und am Rheine</l>
							<l>Kein' andre kommt dir gleich."</l>
						</lg></q></p>
				<p>One of the latest historians of German student life, Dr. Fick, boldly asserts that
					Heidelberg is the most beautiful university city in the world.</p>
				<pb id="VAC1126-007" n="7"/>
				<p>The visitor who has heard such opinions is certain to be disappointed at first on his
					arrival at the railway station. Nothing appears but a new postoffice building and the
					broad, busy streets of a modern, prosperous, rather commonplace little German city. A few
					steps further, however, and he sees the mountains rising abruptly to the right and to the
					left and rolling grandly away into the distance; and after a few days' wandering over the
					old city and its environs, or even after one look from the terrace of the Castle, the
					stranger is ready to acknowledge that the Laureate of Heidelberg has not said enough in
					its praise.</p>
				<p>Heidelberg has the essentials of beauty in unique combination&mdash;mountain and plain,
					river and forest, the work of nature unspoiled by the hand of man, and the work of man
					moulded, colored and harmonized by the hand of nature. It lies just where the Neckar
					bursts through the mountain portals of the Odenwald from the east to wander peacefully
					westward over the broad plain toward the Rhine. The newer part of the city is working its
					way out into the Rhine plain, while the old town nestles along the river under the shelter
					of the mountains to the south.</p>
				<p>There are scores of lookout points, each one furnishing its individual picture; but
					perhaps the most inclusive is from the Molkenkur, half way up the Königstuhl, one of the
					highest mountains in the Odenwald. Far above you the <hi rend="i">Berg-bahn</hi> threads
					its way toward the summit of the Königstuhl. Immediately to the left you look down into
					the gorge-like valley of the Klingenteich, which separates the Königstuhl from the
					dome-shaped, forest covered Gaisberg on the west. Across the Neckar to the north rises the
					Heiligenberg, its huge, pine billows above dwarfing <pb id="VAC1126-008" n="8"/>the
					vineyards and terraced villas audaciously climbing up its sides from the river below.
					Toward the northeast the eye loses itself in the variegated checkerboard green and gold of
					meadows and grain fields climbing the mountain side toward the horizon, while just below
					them the Neckar disappears in a magnificent curve around the Königstuhl.</p>
				<p>Then your eye follows the river toward the west, past the <hi rend="i">Alte Brücke</hi>,
					with its gates and statuary, down for nearly a mile to the <hi rend="i">Neue Brücke</hi>,
					connecting Heidelberg with Neuenheim, and on past the site of the old Roman bridge and out
					along its graceful curves over the Rhine plain, across fields and orchards, past little
					hamlets, busy towns and chimneyed cities, clear on to the Haardt mountains, rising
					cloud-like on the western horizon.</p>
				<p>Below you, huddled between the Königstuhl, the Gaisberg and the river, lies the old town,
					with its narrow winding streets and alleys, its dirty-white plaster covered, or dull red
					sandstone houses with their gray-black tiled roofs, its half dozen old church spires, its
					little open public squares and its bits of private gardens enclosed by blocks of
					houses.</p>
				<p>Immediately below you to the right, on a broad bench of the Königstuhl, the majestic ruin
					of the Castle frowns down upon the city below. The Castle, when one views it nearer, is a
					huge but strangely harmonious jumble of rugged medieval strongholds, with tower walls over
					twenty feet thick, and beautifully ornamented renaissance palaces of the sixteenth and
					seventeenth centuries. With an enthusiasm and emotion unlike the jester we are accustomed
					to hear speak, Mark Twain pictures the Castle as every beholder of sensitive soul must see
					it: "Out of a billowy upheaval <pb id="VAC1126-009" n="[9]"/><figure>
						<p rend="i">The University</p>
					</figure>
					<pb id="VAC1126-010" n="10"/> of vivid green foliage rises the huge ruin of Heidelberg
					Castle, with empty window arches, ivy-mailed battlements, mouldering towers&mdash;a Lear
					of inanimate nature, deserted, discrowned, beaten by the storms, but royal still, and
					beautiful."</p>
				<p>Such is Heidelberg, its Castle and its setting. But after all the heart of Heidelberg is
					the University, the oldest in Germany. It was founded in 1386, a hundred and six years
					before Columbus discovered America. It has been a center of the great movements in the
					history of modern civilization and in the history of the Fatherland&mdash;humanism, the
					Reformation, liberalism, romanticism, nationalism and modern science. But its great age
					and renown and the inimitable romantic charm of its surroundings mean more to a college
					man, and especially to a college fraternity man, than to others. All these have united to
					furnish a continuous student tradition for centuries. Moreover, the conditions governing
					this tradition more nearly approximate those found in American universities, while the
					conditions of student life in Paris or Oxford or Cambridge are almost wholly dissimilar to
					ours. Heidelberg, therefore, offers a continuous history of the movement that has led up
					to the modern American fraternity.</p>
				<p>The University itself, like the town, at first sight, is certain to be disappointing to
					the casual visitor. There are no grounds, no campus, nothing of the charm of "the Backs"
					at Cambridge, nor of the inimitable grouping of the inimitable colleges of Oxford. The
					buildings, with a few late exceptions, are severely plain, commonplace and even ugly. They
					are scattered all over the city, with almost nothing to distinguish them in architecture
					or inscription from their <pb id="VAC1126-011" n="11"/> immediate neighbors, and their
					location is a partial index both to the growth of the town and to the history of
					education. The faculties first organized still make their home in the upper part of the
					city under the protection of the Castle, while the laboratories for natural science and
					medical research, the clinics and hospitals have had to find places in the newer western
					part of the city. The three or four buildings usually shown to visitors as the
					"University", the ones occupied by the "humanities", are on the Ludwig Platz just off the
					Hauptstrasse. One of these is nearly two hundred years old, built after the French had
					destroyed the old University in 1693 (see page 9). With the exception of the beautiful <hi
						rend="i">Aula</hi>, or public hall, restored for the celebration of the five hundredth
					anniversary in 1886, every room in the building looks its age. The benches upon which
					students sit and write in the lecture rooms are as primitive as those in the schoolhouse
					of Eggleston's "<hi rend="i">Hoosier Schoolmaster</hi>." In this same building is the
					renowned <hi rend="i">Carcer</hi>, or students' prison (see page 21). Contrasting with the
					old building, known because of its age as "Die Universität", is the more modern lecture
					hall across the Ludwig Platz, with a central hall imitating the old cloisters and with a
					secluded shady old garden, at the the back of which stands the mysterious old Witch's
					Tower. Still newer, a few steps away, is the magnificent Library, housing one of the
					richest university libraries in the world&mdash;but it takes you twenty-four hours to draw
					a book out!</p>
				<p>The methods of work in the University, on the whole, differ but little from those in
					advanced classes in American universities. Two or three little things, however, strike the
					American as odd. Women have entered the universities several centuries after the men, <pb
						id="VAC1126-012" n="12"/> and it should be noted in passing that Heidelberg has been a
					leader in the comparatively liberal treatment of women. Yet in most cases, outside or
					inside of the universities, women are likely, in Germany, to be considered after the men,
					and the result is that the German professor is perfectly polite&mdash;according to German
					standards&mdash;when he begins his lecture with a polite bow and a "Meine Herren und
					Damen"&mdash;gentlemen and ladies! As the professor enters the door he is greeted by a
					thunderous trampling of feet and the same respectful applause is given when he leaves. If
					the students are annoyed by some late-coming student, they hiss him by shuffling their
					feet. One great advantage they have over American students&mdash;absolutely no record is
					kept of class attendance. Moreover, a man can escape being called upon in the "exercises"
					if he will just tack his card on a seat far enough back in the room. Freedom in
					attendance, a large degree of freedom from recitation and migration from university to
					university are things that suggest anarchy to the American student, but they do not so
					result in Germany.</p>
				<p>Let it be remembered once for all that it is not necessarily the business of German
					students to study, and it is certainly not the business of the professors to make them.
					You see a certain proportion of the students in the lecture rooms, but at any hour, day or
					night, you are likely to see students anywhere, in the city or out. They are literally
					everywhere. They pervade the whole town. And you have no trouble in distinguishing them
					from the three other most prominent elements in the life of Heidelberg&mdash;the good
					burghers, the soldiers and the tourists.</p>
				<pb id="VAC1126-013" n="[13]"/>
				<figure>
					<p>The Fox Riding, 1842<lb/> (From Otto Petters, "Heidelberger Studentenleben einst und
						jetzt")</p>
				</figure>
				<pb id="VAC1126-014" n="14"/>
				<p>A walk along the crowded Hauptstrasse, about noon, say, will show you how cosmopolitan
					the old place is. The crowds jostle you off the sidewalk into the street, at the peril of
					your life from a squad of blue-coated soldiers tramping heavily along in their cowhide
					boots like a bit of human juggernaut, or from the push carts of the jabbering bareheaded
					peasant market women, from a clanging lilliputian street car, or a tourist car honking
					angrily at a manger-like wagon ahead, piled high with huge bundles of weekly wash, and
					crawling slowly into a side street by the help of two fat cows placidly chewing their
					cuds. But the explosive crack of a whip behind you causes you to make a frightened jump
					back to the sidewalk, where you bump into a little group of three or four gentlemen in
					slouch hats and baggy trousers, standing oblivious to the crowd to hear a joke one of them
					is telling, or perhaps serenely conscious that all good Germans will pass respectfully
					around them. They are professors, men of international reputation, as philosophers,
					philologists, scientists or surgeons. You haven't a moment to attend to them, however, as
					you turn hastily to stare with the crowd at the carriage-and-four rattling by with
					tremendous flourishings and staccato crackings of the whip in the hands of the coachman in
					uniform. The coachman's glory is altogether dimmed by the occupants of his carriage, two
					or three or four young fellows of twenty, clad in resplendent uniforms and in a dignity
					elaborate enough for field marshals. They are the chief officers of a student Corps on
					their way to make a formal call or to attend some Corps or student celebration. Students
					on the sidewalk are not so conspicuous, but you know them at a glance&mdash;slender, pale,
					young Germans <pb id="VAC1126-015" n="15"/> hurrying past by ones and twos and threes with
					lecture notes and books under their arms; occasional women students clad, perhaps, if very
					"progressive", in some striking phase of "dress-reform"; representatives of the nations
					making a low-toned Babel of the street&mdash;fair-haired Finns and Swedes, long-haired
					Russians, athletic-looking young Englishmen, dandified little Frenchmen, polyglot speaking
					Greeks, dark-eyed, well-dressed young Italian noblemen, a slender high caste Hindoo
					talking fluent English to an alert young American, dapper be-spectacled Japanese, and,
					perhaps, His Royal Highness, Prince Rangsit of Siam, pushing his way through the motley
					crowd like a hustling young broker on Broadway, but followed by his German tutor and his
					Siamese lord-in-waiting.</p>
				<p>Students as well as tourists give the cosmopolitan air to Heidelberg, but the
					characteristic student groups are altogether German. They come lounging along in little
					crowds of half a dozen or so, each group wearing their own peculiar tri-colored bands of
					ribbon diagonally across their breasts and their own peculiarly shaped brilliantly colored
					caps. They carry canes, but few books. Other similar groups, but with differently shaped
					caps and differently colored ribbons, can be seen through the open windows and doors of
					restaurants clustered around their reserved table, eating, drinking beer, smoking and
					playing cards. They are the Corps or other "corporation" students, the brothers or formal
					enemies of the young fellows in the coach-and-four. These are the men that represent the
					latest development in the German college fraternity system.</p>
				<p>Student organizations have always flourished luxuriantly in Heidelberg. At the present
					time, out of an enrollment of about two thousand five hundred, there are <pb
						id="VAC1126-016" n="16"/> nearly two dozens regular color-bearing fighting <hi rend="i"
						>Verbindungen</hi>, about as many more duel clubs and some twenty-odd other regular
					organizations, with some of the latter organized <hi rend="i">against</hi> duels (see page
					37). The color-wearing <hi rend="i">Verbindungen</hi> are not all "Corps", in the precise
					use of that word by the German students. In Heidelberg there are five of the old Corps,
					founded in the order named, between 1810 and 1849&mdash;Suevia, Guestphalia,
					Saxo-Borussia, Vandalia and Rhenania. Then come the Burschenschaften, with three
					"chapters"&mdash;as I may call the local <hi rend="i">Verbindung</hi> by analogy with our
					own fraternity system&mdash;Allemannia and Franconia, both founded in 1856, and Vineta,
					founded in 1879. Then come the two chapters of Turnerschaften, founded in 1885-6,
					Rhenopalatia and Ghibellinia. Finally come three chapters of Landsmannschaften, founded in
					the early eighties, Zaringia, Teutonia and Cheruskia. Each of these groups is affiliated
					with similar groups in the other German universities, Corps with Corps, Burschenschaften
					with Burschenschaften, Turnerschaften with Turnerschaften and Landsmannschaften with
					Landsmannschaften, thus forming what are practically national fraternities. These
					different groups meet in annual national conventions, where the interests of the orders
					are discussed and laws are formulated to govern the conduct of the individual chapters. A
					man belonging to a corps in one university, say the white-cap Corps in Bonn, to which
					Emperor William and his sons belong, would affiliate on coming to Heidelberg, not with a
					Burschenschaft or a Turnerschaft, but with a Corps belonging to the same national
					"convent" as his own, and in this particular case with the white-cap Prussian Corps at
					Heidelberg most closely affiliated with his own Prussian Corps at Bonn. My friend Dr.
					S&mdash;&mdash;, to whom I am <pb id="VAC1126-017" n="[17]"/><figure>
						<p>The Hirschgasse<lb/> (From Otto Petters, "Heidelberger Studentenleben einst und
							jetzt")</p>
					</figure>
					<pb id="VAC1126-018" n="18"/> indebted for the kindly hospitaly of some of the <hi
						rend="i">Verbindungen</hi> at <hi rend="i">Kneipen</hi> and duels, joined a <hi rend="i"
						>Verbindung</hi> originally in Marburg, and therefore he was cordially received as a
					visiting "alter Herr" by the fraternity men in Heidelberg "in cartel" with his chapter at
					Marburg.</p>
				<p>The color-bearing <hi rend="i">Verbindungen</hi> as they exist today are the results of
					centuries of evolution. In the earliest medieval universities, like Bologna and Paris,
					students were grouped for the purposes of university government or for mutual assistance
					into "nations" and these "nations" were still further subdivided into "provinces". In
					Paris, for example, the students were divided into four "nations", Gallici, Anglici,
					(later Alemanni), Normanni and Picardi. The Gallici were subdivided into "provinces" of
					Frenchmen, Italians, Spaniards, etc., and the Alemanni into Englishmen and Germans. When
					the earliest German universities were founded, the system of "nations" was taken over from
					the older foreign universities; but modified into general divisions of the old German
					empire. For a century or so the "nations" were rather loosely organized. But by the middle
					of the seventeenth century they became much more closely organized under the command of
					"senioren" and "consenioren", carried particular colors, fought constantly against each
					other and by 1660 had become such a nuisance to the authorities that they were officially
					dissolved.</p>
				<p>From the beginning, the new student, called at first a "Beanus" and later a "Pennal", was
					compelled to join his proper "nation" and do anything his superiors in the "nation"
					demanded, give up his new clothes, his furniture, the provisions brought from home, and
					endure all sorts of mock initiations and personal <pb id="VAC1126-019" n="19"/>
					indignities. There was nothing voluntary in membership; a student belonged to a certain
					"nation" because he came from a certain district.</p>
				<p>The attempted dissolution of the "nations" about 1660 succeeded only in bringing about
					the maintenance of the organizations in secret; but by 1700 they had become mere loose
					social organizations without any definite end. From this date they began to reorganize as
					"Landsmannschaften", i. e., men from the same province, real fellow countrymen, banded
					together for the purpose of attaining "mutual friendship and advancement, amicable
					settlement of (internal) disputes, absolute satisfaction for insults from a stranger,
					pleasures in common, and complete obedience to the common law and to the seniors". This
					declaration of principles is still in a large measure the aim of the modern Corps. By the
					middle of the eighteenth century two degrees began to develop in the Landsmannschaften.
					The inner circle was chosen from the older and more active members, while the "foxes"
					(descendants of the Beanus and Pennal) constituted the outer circle and the word
					"Landsmannschaft" soon came to mean only the inner circle.</p>
				<p>In the middle of the eighteenth century a new spirit began its work among university
					students. It was the spirit of the age, the result of long years of philosophizing and
					discussion in England, France and Germany, the "Aufklärung". It was the work of exact
					science, of the "Glorious Revolution", of Locke and the Deists in England, of the
					Encyclopedists and Voltaire and Rousseau in France, of the Rationalists, of Leibniz and
					Lessing and Kant and Frederick the Great in Germany. Among the educated it was a time of
					theories and systems and secret orders for the <pb id="VAC1126-020" n="20"/> regeneration
					of the world. Out of mysticism came the Rosicrucians in 1760. Among the rationalists in
					protestant Germany the Freemasons spread everywhere, while in Bavaria in 1776 the
					Catholics founded the order of the Illuminati. From the influence of the Masons, the
					Rosicrucians and the Illuminati, the student Orders arose. In Jena, the old
					Landsmannschaft, the Mosellanerbund, already had the Latin motto, "<hi rend="i">Vivat
						unus, vivant omnes</hi>", the vital principle of later Corps and of our own
					fraternities. Out of this Landsmannschaft in 1771, the first student Order, "Die
					Amicisten" (L'ordre de l'amitié), was founded. It is noteworthy that the Amicisten were
					founded only five years before the founding of ΦΒΚ at William and Mary, and that the
					Amicisten and all other similar German student orders, like "Harmonie". "Concordia", and
					"L'Espérance", were founded in response to the same philosophical and philanthropical
					spirit that voiced itself in the ΦΒΚ "happy spirit and resolution of attaining the
					important ends of society."</p>
				<p>The student Orders, in contrast to the Landsmannschaften, chose their members without
					reference to the place of their birth. Their outward form, their mystic symbols, badges
					and colors they got partly from the Masons. The Amicisten, for example, wore a badge in
					the form of a Maltese cross with Roman letters on the arms and a heart with the date
					engraved on it on one side of the center, while on the other was the monogram of their
					motto, "<hi rend="i">Vivat amicitia, fructus honoris"</hi>. Their principles involved the
					maintenance of academic freedom, combined with respect for the university authorities and
					teachers, friendship and mutual helpfulness that should last through life and the endeavor
					for the ethical perfection of every <pb id="VAC1126-021" n="[21]"/><figure>
						<p>The Carcer<lb/> (From Otto Petters, "Heidelberger Studentenleben einst und
							jetzt")</p>
					</figure>
					<pb id="VAC1126-022" n="22"/> member of the Order. But they already held the liberal
					principles in politics that tended toward the downfall of autocracy. They were at once
					attacked, therefore, by the princely benefactors and governors of the various
					universities, ostensibly because they were creating disturbances among students&mdash;one
					Order alone had to fight some four hundred duels in one year&mdash;but really because of
					their liberalism. They flourished under oppression, however, and in the midst of
					persecution the Amicisten of Jena founded "daughter lodges" at three other universities.
					When the Orders began to celebrate the victories of the French Revolution the authorities
					encouraged the Landsmannschaften to try to help put them down.</p>
				<p>Jahn ("Vater Jahn" of the Turners), who studied in Halle from 1796 on, and other liberal
					minded men tried to encourage a spirit different from those prevailing in either the
					Orders or the Landsmannschaften. Jahn said the only questions a Landsmannschaft asked when
					a new "fox" entered the University were: "Is he tall? Is he strong? Has he money?"
					Patriotic men saw that the Orders wished the Rights of Man, but they were too
					cosmopolitan; they tended towards denationalization, while the Landsmannschaften were
					wholly provincial in their patriotism. If a new national ideal was to grow up among the
					students a new organization with new principles must be founded. The result was the
					founding of the old Burschenschaft, with the first general student organization, June 10,
					1815, eight days before Waterloo. The principles of the old Burschenschaft were
					"Burschenfreiheit, Ehre über Leben, Vaterland über Alles" ("Student Freedom, Honor before
					Life, Fatherland before All"). The two significant principles, then, were equality and
					democracy <pb id="VAC1126-023" n="23"/> of all students among themselves and an intense
					national patriotism. These were the patriotic principles that lay back of the war of
					freedom against Napoleon, back of the risings in 1830 and 1848, that made possible the
					success of the Six Weeks War against Austria, that forced liberal constitutions from the
					autocrats of the petty German states, and that finally, through the wars against Austria
					in 1866 and against France in 1870, brought about a united Germany. It was the German
					university students, trained in such principles, who become the concious creators of the
					great nation of today.</p>
				<p>The <hi rend="i">Verbindungen</hi> now known as "Corps" arose in the beginning of the
					nineteenth century out of the old Landsmannschaften and Orders. The names of the Corps go
					back to the Landsmannschaften and their membership is still chosen largely from one state
					or province, but they may take in anybody by free choice, the membership is limited in
					numbers, they have a strong, firm organization, a formal initiation, symbolistic insignia,
					and all this they get from the Orders. They have always been exclusive and aristocratic in
					tendency, and conservative, if taking any stand at all, in politics. Their aims are
					practically those of the American fraternities&mdash;close personal friendship, the fixing
					of definite ideals of conduct and character, and social enjoyment and culture, while they
					claim at the same time to be the special conservators of student traditions, a claim they
					can probobly substantiate. One of the strongest motives of the old Burschenschaften, on
					the other hand, was to foster democratic equality among all students, and therefore Corps
					and Burschenschaften have often come into direct conflict. The authorities in the early
					part of <pb id="VAC1126-024" n="24"/> the last century fostered the Corps at the expense
					of the Burschenschaften, just as they had fostered the Landsmannschaften against the
					Orders in the century before. As my readers will notice from the dates above, the first
					Corps founded in Heidelberg was Suevia (the Latin form of Suabia) in 1810, while the
					earliest Burschenschaft now in existence in Heidelberg was founded in 1856. The original
					Burschenschaften were driven out of the universities by the severest persecution. The
					Corps really took the place in student life of the old Landsmannschaften and of the
					Orders, except that the Corps have always shunned the liberal principles of the Orders.
					The new Landsmannschaften and the Turnerschaften, and even the new Burschenschaften have
					few essential differences in principles or in manner of life from the Corps of today.
					Since 1886, at the great celebration of the five hundredth anniversary of Heidelberg, the
					various <hi rend="i">Verbindungen</hi> have worked together harmoniously in all matters
					that concern the general student body.</p>
				<p>Naturally, the large mass of the students at Heidelberg and in most of the German
					universities belong to that class we in America call "barbarians'. So far as this class
					feels itself in need of organization it forms clubs for sport, special study, and so on.
					In Heidelberg, the "barbarians" have formed themselves into a great organization known as
					the <hi rend="i">Frei Studenten</hi>. The purpose of the <hi rend="i">Frei
						Studentenschaft</hi> is mutual acquaintance, company on various forms of pleasure
					excursions, exchange of views in conversation or of second hand books for a price, the
					conduct of an employment agency for members, and of certain forms of social settlement
					work.</p>
				<pb id="VAC1126-025" n="[25]"/>
				<figure>
					<p>A Mensur between Burschenschaft Students, 1902<lb/> (From an original photograph by Max
						Kögel in Heidelberg)</p>
				</figure>
				<pb id="VAC1126-026" n="26"/>
				<p>The <hi rend="i">Verbindungen</hi> themselves have changed much in the last half century.
					They formerly wished to control all student life, and arrogated to themselves the right to
					think, plan, and make customs for the whole student body. This was especially true of the
					Corps. It was partly against such exclusiveness and arrogance that the Burschenschaft were
					first organized. Now the Corps have largely lost their arrogance, while the
					Burschenschaften are no longer such fiery exponents of democracy and the Landsmannschaften
					have lost something of their provinciality. All the <hi rend="i">Verbindungen</hi>, the
						<hi rend="i">Freistudenten</hi> and the large body of students not incorporated at all
					now act together through a Central Committee of Students. To this Central Committee each
						<hi rend="i">Verbindung</hi> sends one respresentative and there are seven
					representatives from the unincorporated students of the different faculties. This Central
					Committee is practically a representative body for student self-government. From the
					general committee an executive committee of three members is chosen: one member from the
					Senioren-Convent of the Corps, one from the Deputiertien-Convent of the Burschenschaften,
					and one from the other Verbindungen and all other student bodies together. This
					arrangement shows that the Corps and Burschenschaften still have a preponderance of
					influence in student affairs in Heidelberg.</p>
				<p>The more moderate ambitions of the German fraternities now center within the
					organizations themselves. The maintenance of student traditions, so far as in the judgment
					of the different organizations they have proved their worth, the fostering of a manly
					character and a sense of honor through the severe discipline of obedience to superiors and
					the test of <pb id="VAC1126-027" n="27"/> the duel, the cultivation of permanent
					friendships and the enjoyment of social life together&mdash;these are in general the aims
					of all the <hi rend="i">Verbindungen</hi>.</p>
				<p>The life of German fraternity men in Heidelberg outside of the lecture room is more or
					less alike in all the organizations. As a rule the members spend their mornings as each
					individual pleases, but from the mid-day meal on till they go to bed they are expected to
					be together. They are together at the mid-day and evening meals, on excursions and tramps
					through the mountains, or up the Neckar, at the informal <hi rend="i">Kneipen</hi> or
					ordinary social or business meetings, at the more formal meetings for some special
					occasion called the <hi rend="i">Kommers</hi>, and at the duels. <hi rend="i">Kneipen</hi>
					and <hi rend="i">Kommers</hi> take place in their own house, if the chapter has a house.
					Two-thirds of the chapters in Heidelberg do have houses, secured largely through the
					interest and contributions of graduate members, the "<hi rend="i">alte Herren</hi>". The
					houses are generally simple. The first story usually has a big hall for the <hi rend="i"
						>Kommers</hi> and smaller rooms for the ordinary <hi rend="i">Kneipen</hi> and mid-day
					dinners. In the story above are a few rooms for the active members, usually the officers
					of the chapter, and rooms for the steward and his wife, the cook. Every possible chance is
					taken to celebrate something. The old members like to come back to the <hi rend="i"
						>Kneipen</hi>; the good fellowship and brotherly feeling of such occasions is at least
					equal to that found in one of our "smokers" or banquets.</p>
				<p>The customs most characteristic of German fraternity life are connected with the
					reception, training and initiating of the new student, the ceremonial beer drinking and
					singing at <hi rend="i">Kneipen</hi> and <hi rend="i">Kommers</hi>, and the <hi rend="i"
						>Mensuren</hi> or student duels. The "fox" is now <pb id="VAC1126-028" n="28"/> greeted
					politely on his arrival, instead of with the contumely of earlier times. If he comes
					recommended by an <hi rend="i">alter Herr</hi>, he is met at the station, his baggage is
					looked after by the house steward, and he himself is taken to the house and introduced to
					the members at a <hi rend="i">Kneipe</hi>, what we should call a "feed". He must announce
					himself as a candidate, but must serve a term of probation before being accepted. His
					initiation is of the burlesque type of our "fake" initiations. The so-called "Fox Major",
					whose business it is to train the "foxes" and keep them in order, asks the candidate all
					sorts of impossible questions in a horrible mixture of monkish Latin and German, but at
					last gives him a diploma, declaring him to be the quintessence of all impoliteness,
					stupidity and ignorance. After this he used to be baptised in beer, or be tossed in a
					blanket, but these customs are disappearing. After his return from his first vacation he
					becomes a "Brandfuchs" by having his hair singed and quenched in beer, and perhaps he is
					forced to take part in the Fox-Riding, on stools, under the guidance of the Fox-Major (see
					page 13). All this time he is receiving serious instruction in the history of the chapter,
					its customs, its insignia and its relations to other fraternities. He must learn to make
					with absolute exactness the so-called "Zirkel" or monogram of his chapter and to recognize
					the "Zirkel" of every other fraternity chapter in the nation. Then he is constantly
					training himself for the duels. Altogether he is so busy that lectures see little of him
					for the first year or so.</p>
				<p>The chief function of the "play" <hi rend="i">Kneipe</hi> is to promote good fellowship.
					The means are beer and singing. The members honor each other, and especially the <hi
						rend="i">alte Herren</hi> and visitors present, by drinking <pb id="VAC1126-029"
						n="[29]"/><figure>
						<p>A Mensur between Corps Students, 1908<lb/> (From an original photograph by Max Kögel
							in Heidelberg)</p>
					</figure>
					<pb id="VAC1126-030" n="30"/> with the one to be honored. Later in the evening the one so
					honored must return the compliment. An <hi rend="i">alter Herr</hi>, a visitor, or an
					officer is liable to have to stand a good deal of "honor". The peculiar ceremony called
					the "Salamander" comes perhaps from "Sauft alle mit einander"&mdash;drink altogether. The
						<hi rend="i">Salamander</hi> opens and closes a <hi rend="i">Kommers</hi> or official
						<hi rend="i">Kneipe</hi>. It is performed by everybody present, first drinking
					absolutely in unison, then slamming the glasses upon the table together, then rubbing on
					the table in unison and finally slamming them down hard together. At a <hi rend="i"
						>Kommers</hi> the songs come at regular intervals between the drinking, and they are
					sung with the carefulness of trained musicians. Every man at table has his <hi rend="i"
						>Kommersbuch</hi>. My copy of the <hi rend="i">Kommers</hi> song book is the 85th
					edition, it contains 832 songs and it is bound in brass to enable it to escape the beer on
					the table and to withstand heavy pounding. We have nothing to equal the German song book
					or the German singing in American fraternities, for the Germans have kept up through the
					centuries the singing traditions of the medieval <hi rend="i">Vaganten</hi> and Followers
					of Golias.</p>
				<p>The student duel, or <hi rend="i">Mensur</hi> (see pages 25 and 29), is a medieval custom
					preserved among students after it has entirely disappeared among other civilized human
					beings. In the sixteenth century the "Fechtmeister", or master-at-arms, ranked above the
					professor, and with some men of the twentieth century he still seems to do so. Yet the
					Corps and other fighting fraternities defend the <hi rend="i">Mensur</hi> as one of the
					greatest builders of character. American football to them is brutal, but the <hi rend="i"
						>Mensur</hi> "steels the character, awakens manhood, gives the power of deeds, strength
					of will, self-knowledge and a sense of honor". I took an old American football <pb
						id="VAC1126-031" n="[31]"/><figure>
						<p>The last work of Pauk Doctor Immisch after a Duel of Corps Students, 1885<lb/> (From
							Otto Petters, "Heidelberger Studentenleben einst und jetzt")</p>
					</figure>
					<pb id="VAC1126-032" n="32"/> player to see the duels one morning and he got sick at the
					blood and went away cursing.</p>
				<p>The old idea of the necessity of wearing a chip on your shoulder so it could easily be
					knocked off has about passed away. Instead of the statisfaction of honor for a real or
					fancied insult, a means of avenging insult, the <hi rend="i">Mensur</hi> has now become an
					end in itself, a means of education. The new conception of a knigthly contest, arranged
					for beforehand without the least ill-feeling and possibly between men who never saw each
					other, grew out of the custom of the Corps in Heidelberg and Jena meeting together <hi
						rend="i">to be insulted</hi>. Such a method was seen to be foolish, so it has now become
					the custom for the officers of one fraternity to arrange with the officers of another for
					a certain number of duels on a definite date. A "fox" must fight at least three times very
					well in order to win his ribbon and become a "Bursch" or full-fledged member. "Foxes" used
					to fight only ten minutes, but now they fight full fifteen minutes, the better to try
					their metal, while duels between experienced "Burschen" vary in length according to
					prearrangement.</p>
				<p>Practically all student duels now take place in the Hirsch-Gasse (see pages 17 and 36) at
					the old inn, "Zum Hirsch", directly across the river from the Castle. Here the duels have
					been fought since 1820. Each week of term time is divided up among the different classes
					of fighting orders, certain days for the Corps, others for the Burschenschaften, etc., for
					in general Corps students fight only with Corps students, and Burschenschaften with
					Burschenschaften. The duel itself is not so shocking as the sewing up afterwards. It you
					are fortunate enough to be invited as a guest you go directly out <pb id="VAC1126-033"
						n="[33]"/><figure>
						<p>Pauk Doctor Huber, the Duel Surgeon of to day, at work, 1909<lb/> (From an original
							photograph by Max Kögel in Heidelberg)</p>
					</figure>
					<pb id="VAC1126-034" n="34"/> upon the duelling floor instead of having to peep through a
					window or bribe a waiter to take you up into a gallery. The fighters are so protected by
					armour, except on the head, the forehead, the cheeks and the chin, that there is no real
					danger. The doctor always stands by, in his suggestive white surgeon's coat, to examine
					each contestant after each round. The <hi rend="i">Mensur</hi> is the only contest I know
					where, in a sense, the more defeated a man is the prouder he is&mdash;because the scars
					will always show. In the actual fighting the swords are raised directly above the heads of
					the contestants and the stroke is a quick cut directly downwards. A round is from five to
					ten strokes each, and the duel lasts for, say, fifteen rounds, or until one man is too
					badly wounded to continue. The victory is awarded by the umpire to the man who has made
					the largest number of cuts drawing blood. After the battle the fighters sit down over a
					sort of lead bath, so the blood will drain away, and the surgeon sews up the cuts. Dr.
					Immisch, who died 1892, is said to have assisted from 1849 to 1885 at some 13,000 duels
					and therefore used his needle and thread say about 100,000 times (see page 31). During the
					whole operation of sewing up the duelist must maintain as stoical a countenance as a Sioux
					Indian (see page 33). And that is the <hi rend="i">Mensur</hi>!</p>
				<p>Fraternity men take their full share, however, in all phases of general university life.
					The older men usually cease fighting in the last few semesters of their university life
					and devote themselves to a careful preparation for their examination for the university
					degree. The active members, however, continue to be the leaders in the great torchlight
					processions in honor of the Pro-Rektor, or some national feast day. <pb id="VAC1126-035"
						n="35"/> These active members generally manage to do enough mischief of some kind to get
					put, once anyway, into the old Students' Prison, the <hi rend="i">Carcer</hi> (see page
					21). It is a disgrace to leave Heidelberg without that honor! Then on a night of the most
					wonderful spectacle in Europe, the illumination of the Castle, they come floating down the
					Neckar under the Old Bridge in great barges, and as the dark Castle suddenly blooms out
					into a gigantic rose-coloured castle-in-the-air, they take up the strains, hundreds
					strong, of <q rend="blockquote center"><p>"Alt Heidelberg, du feine".</p></q></p>
				<p>On such a night a stranger on the Philosophenweg, halfway up on the Heiligenberg, looking
					across at the castle and down on the Neckar, will never forget what he sees and what he
					hears. One who has been a part of it, even in the least, can only regret that <q
						rend="blockquote center"><lg>
							<l>"Those days of yore</l>
							<l>Will come no more".</l>
						</lg></q></p>
				<pb id="VAC1126-036" n="[36]"/>
				<figure>
					<p>The Hirschgasse with the castle in the distance<lb/> (From a photograph by Dr. C. Fäger
						in Aarau)</p>
				</figure>
				<pb id="VAC1126-037" n="37"/>
				<div2 type="part">
					<head rend="center">TABLE OF VERBINDUNG COLORS.</head>
					<p>English speaking visitors to Heidelberg often express a desire to distinguish between
						the different <hi rend="i">Verbindungen</hi> as they meet the color-wearing students on
						the street. The easiest way to tell one <hi rend="i">Verbindung</hi> from another is to
						notice the shape and color of the cap; the complex color scheme of the ribbons worn
						diagonally across the breast is not so easily distinguished. There are two kinds of
						caps&mdash;the ordinary cap, called a "Mütze" and shaped a bit like a yachting cap, and
						the so-called "Stürmer". The latter has a small mortar-board top, which is inclined
						forward toward the bill; the cap as a whole is shaped like the caps worn by Union
						soldiers in the American Civil War. Besides they wear sometimes a small cap without a
						bill, like an English soldier's service cap, called a "Cerevis-Käppchen". The colors of
						the more important <hi rend="i">Verbindungen</hi> are as follows: <lb/><list
							type="simple">
							<head rend="i">CORPS:</head>
							<item><hi rend="i">Suevia</hi>: white, yellow, black; yellow cap.</item>
							<item><hi rend="i">Guestphalia</hi>: green, white, black; green cap.</item>
							<item><hi rend="i">Saxo-Borussia</hi>: white, green, black, white; white
								stürmer.</item>
							<item><hi rend="i">Vandalia</hi>: gold, red, gold; crimson cap.</item>
							<item><hi rend="i">Rhenania</hi>: blue, white, red; dark-blue cap.</item>
						</list>
						<list type="simple">
							<head rend="i">BURSCHENSCHAFTEN:</head>
							<item><hi rend="i">Allemannia</hi>: black, white, red; red cap.</item>
							<item><hi rend="i">Franconia</hi>: gold, black, red, gold; crimson stürmer.</item>
							<item><hi rend="i">Vineta</hi>: light-blue, white, black; light-blue cap.</item>
						</list>
						<pb id="VAC1126-038" n="38"/>
						<list type="simple">
							<head rend="i">TURNERSCHAFTEN:</head>
							<item><hi rend="i">Rhenopalatia</hi>: light-blue, white, dark-blue; light-blue
								stürmer.</item>
							<item><hi rend="i">Ghibellinia</hi>: moss-green, white, rose; moss-green cap.</item>
						</list>
						<list type="simple">
							<head rend="i">LANDSMANNSCHAFTEN:</head>
							<item><hi rend="i">Zaringia</hi>: red, white, light-blue; white cap.</item>
							<item><hi rend="i">Teutonia</hi>: red, white, violet; violet cap.</item>
							<item><hi rend="i">Cheruskia</hi>: black, gold, green; black cap.</item>
						</list></p>
					<p>Besides the colors of the regular fighting <hi rend="i">Verbindungen</hi> given above,
						still other colored caps can be seen, like the silver-gray cap of the newly-founded
						Freie Burschenschaft, <hi rend="i">Normannia</hi>, the carmine cap of the Sängerschaft,
							<hi rend="i">Thuringia</hi>, and finally of three of the corporations organized <hi
							rend="i">against</hi> duels&mdash;the black cap of the Catholic <hi rend="i"
							>Arminia</hi>, the blue cap of the Protestant <hi rend="i">Wingolf</hi> and the violet
						cap of <hi rend="i">Hercynia</hi>, recently founded on old burschenschaft principles.
						When caps of different <hi rend="i">Verbindungen</hi> are shaped alike and have the same
						basic color, the only resource of the stranger who desires to tell one from another is
						to look at the ribbon colors, or to notice what other colors may be combined in the cap
						with the basic color.</p>
				</div2>
			</div1>
			<trailer rend="center">Printed by J. Hörning, Heidelberg.</trailer>
		</body>
		<back>
			<pb id="VAC1126-039" n="[39]"/>
			<div1 type="advertisement">
				<head rend="center">List of works published by<lb/>
					<hi rend="b">OTTO PETTERS HEIDELBERG</hi><lb/> on Heidelberg, The University and its
					student life</head>
				<list type="simple">
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Acta Saecularia zur Erinnerung an die
								Zentenarfeier</hi> der Erneuerung der Universität Heidelberg durch S. Kgl. H. den
							Grossherzog Carl Friedrich. Hrsg. im Auftrage d. Senats. Heidelberg 1904. 4.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">M. 9.-</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Der Ausschuss der Heidelberger Studentenschaft</hi>.
							Eine Denkschrift zu seinem 25 jährigen Bestehen von Rudolf Sperling, cand. chem.,
							Sueviae. Heidelberg 1911. M. &mdash;.75. Geb. in Lwd.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">M. 1.20</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Binsenbub</hi>. Straisschen g'fällig meine Herre'?
							Portr. 24:27½ cm. Lichtdruck m. breit. Rande. M.2.&mdash;.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">Cabinetphotogr. M. 1.&mdash;</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Chronik der Hirschgasse</hi>. 90 S. m. 25 Abbildungen.
							Heidelberg 1910. Ppd.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">M. 3.&mdash;</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Das Corpsleben in Heidelberg</hi> während des 19.
							Jahrhunderts. Festschrift zum 500jähr. Jubiläum der Universität. Herausg. vom
							Heidelberger S. C. Heidelberg 1886.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">M. 3.&mdash;</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Dietz, Ed., Die deutsche Burschenschaft in
								Heidelberg</hi>. Ein Beitrag zur Kulturgeschichte deutscher Universitäten. Mit 13
							Abbildg. i. Text u. 3 Vollbild. Heidelb. 1895. M. 3.&mdash;.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">Geb. M. 3.50</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">&mdash; Neue Beiträge zur Geschichte des Heidelberger
								Studentenlebens</hi>. Heidelberg 1903. M. 1.50</hi>
						<hi rend="right">Lwdbd. M. 2.&mdash;</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">&mdash; Das Frankfurter Attentat vom 3. April 1833 und
								die Heidelberger Studentenschaft</hi>. Ein Stück deutscher Kultur- und
							Rechtsgeschichte. Mit 5 Abb. Heidelberg 1906. M. 1.50</hi>
						<hi rend="right">Lwdbd. M. 2.&mdash;</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Festzug</hi> zum Jubiläum der Universität Heidelberg.
							1386-1886. 5½ Meter lang, den von Prof. Carl Hoff, Karlsruhe, entworfenen, costümlich
							interessanten Festzug darstellend, gezeichnet v. H. Kley. Heidelbg. 1886. Kart.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">M. 1.&mdash;</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Graeser, Kurt, Der Zweikampf</hi>. Eine Studie. Zweite
							verm. Aufl. Heidelberg 1911.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">M. 2.&mdash;</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Gutmann, Gust., "Hoch die Palz"</hi>. Gedichte in
							Pfälzer und Hochdeutscher Mundart. Heidelberg 1887. Lwdbd.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">M. 2.&mdash;</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Hemskerk, H. v., Adele und Adolar</hi>. Eine traurige
							Liebesgeschichte. Heidelberg 1904. 46 S. m. vielen Abbildgn. im Text.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">M. 1.50</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Hoffmann, W.</hi>, Bismarck-Ehrung durch die deutsche
							Studentenschaft. Mit Titelbildnis Bismarcks und 2 Abbildungen im Text. Heidelberg
							1899.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">M. &mdash;.50</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Holsten, Rich., "Hoch Heidelberg."</hi> Burschenlieder.
							1886.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">M. 1.&mdash;</hi></item>
					<pb id="VAC1126-040" n="[40]"/>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Immisch, Ueber das "Pauken"</hi> und die bei der
							Behandlung der "Schmisse" eintretenden sowie die schnelle Heilung der Wunden
							hindernden Störungen. Heidelb. 1885. 15 S.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">M. &mdash;.5</hi>0</item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Jubiläums-Medaille</hi>. Geprägt im Auftrage Sr. Kgl.
							Hoh. des Grossh. Friedrich zum 500jährigen Jubiläum der Universität Heidelberg. In
							Bronze. Nur noch wenige Stücke vorhanden.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">M. 12.&mdash;</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Lehardy, B., Liesel ou le roman d'un étudiant français
								à Heidelberg</hi>. Heidelberg 1901. 256 p.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">M. 2.80</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Mays, Alb., Heidelberg, gefeiert von Dichtern und
								Denkern seit 5 Jahrhunderten</hi>. Festgabe zum Jubiläum der Universität Heidelberg.
							1885. M. 3.&mdash;.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">Lwdbd. M. 3.50</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Porten, M. v. d.</hi>, Geschichte und Ziele der
							studentischen Reformpartei. Vortrag, gehalten im Heidelberger Studentenverein am 7.
							XII. 1870. Heidelberg o. J. 35 S.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">M. &mdash;.75</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Ruperto-Carola. Illustrierte Festchronik der V.
								Säcularfeier der Universität Heidelberg</hi>. Red. von Karl Bartsch. Heidelberg
							1886. Fol. M. 8.&mdash;</hi>
						<hi rend="right">Lwdbd. M. 12.&mdash;</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Schulze, F., Die Fechtkunst mit dem Haurapier</hi>,
							unter besonderer Berücksichtigung des Linksfechtens, mit Uebungsbeispielen und 5 Taf.
							in Lichtdruck, darunter ein Paukbild des Heidelberger S. C. Heidelberg 1885.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">M. 3.&mdash;</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">&mdash; Die Säbelfechtkunst</hi>. Eine gründliche
							Anleitung zum Rechts- und Linksfechten, zugleich Lehr- und Lernbuch für den Gebrauch
							an Universitäten u. Militärbildungsanstalten, sowie für Turn- und Fechtvereine. Mit 7
							Taf. Heidelberg 1889.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">M. 3.&mdash;</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Struwelpeter, Kurzer gynäkologischer</hi>. Nach d.
							neuesten Forsch. zusammengestellt von C. H. S. Mit 12 Textillustrationen. Zum ersten
							Male veröffentlicht zum Leipziger klinischen Vogelschiessen am 29. Juli 1882. 5. Aufl.
							Heidelberg 1885.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">geh. M. 1.&mdash;</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Studenten-Struwelpeter, Heidelberger</hi>. Struwelpeter
							für artige Studenten und solche, die es werden wollen. Von C. H. S., Verfasser des
							"Kurzen gynäkolog. Struwelpeters". Mit 10 Textillustrationen. Heidelberg 1887.
							Geh.</hi>
						<hi rend="right">M. 1.&mdash;</hi></item>
					<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="b">Studentenleben, Heidelberger</hi>, einst und jetzt. 36
							Lichtdruck-Bilder nach Naturaufnahmen, Handzeichn. und Kupferst. Mit erläuterndem
							Texte. Heidelberg 1886. 4. O.-Lwd. m. G. Statt M. 25.&mdash;</hi>
						<hi rend="right">M. 12.&mdash;</hi></item>
				</list>
			</div1>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
