<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//IA Books//DTD TEI for Indiana Authors Books//EN"
                       "teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="VAC1322">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Fort Harrison on the banks of the Wabash, 1812-1912</title>
				<author>Scovell, J. T. (Josiah Thomas), b. 1841.</author>
				<author>Fort Harrison Centennial Association.</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded By</resp>
					<name>Taemin Park</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
				<address>
                    <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
                </address>
				<idno>VAC1322</idno>
				<availability status="unknown">
					<p>Copyright 2009 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
					<p>Indiana University provides the information contained on this web site for
						non-commercial, personal, or research use only. All other use, including but not limited
						to commercial or scholarly reproductions, redistribution, publication or transmission,
						whether by electronic means or otherwise, without prior written permission of the
						copyright holder is strictly prohibited.</p>
				</availability>
				<date>2012</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblFull>
					<titleStmt>
						<title type="main">Fort Harrison on the banks of the Wabash, 1812-1912</title>
						<author id="ina-v1-entry-0762">Scovell, J. T. (Josiah Thomas), b. 1841.</author>
						<author>Fort Harrison Centennial Association.</author>
					</titleStmt>
					<extent>72 p. incl. map. front., pl., 2 port. 27 cm.</extent>
					<publicationStmt>
						<publisher>The Moore-Langen Printing Co</publisher>
						<pubPlace>[Terre Haute, Ind.]</pubPlace>
						<date>1912</date>
					</publicationStmt>
				</biblFull>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>The Digital Library Program was awarded a Library Services and Technology Act (LSTA)
					grant in 2005 to make available online the three-volume, reference work, <title>Indiana
						Authors and Their Books</title> along with selected monographs by Indiana authors.</p>
			</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl n="3">
				<p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and has
					been encoded and edited using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
					Guidelines following the TEI Lite standard. Digital page images are linked to the text
					file.</p>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<tagUsage gi="div1">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy id="lcsh">
					<bibl>
						<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
					</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language>English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="lcsh">
					<list>
						<item>Fort Harrison, Battle of, Ind., 1812</item>
						<item>Indians of North America</item>
						<item>Terre Haute (Ind.)</item>
						<item>Wabash River Valley&mdash;History.</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<!--The revision description tracks significant changes made to the file
                    after completion. This information will remain commented out unless someone has
                    conducted quality assessment of the texts and have made changes to the file as a
                    result.-->
		<!-- <revisionDesc> <change>
                    <date>$Date</date> <respStmt>
                    <name>$Name</name>
                    <resp>$Responsibility</resp>
                    </respStmt> <item>$Changes</item>
                    </change> </revisionDesc> -->
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>

			<pb id="VAC1322-001" n="[]"/>
			<div1 type="frontispiece">
				<head type="supplied">FRONTISPIECE</head>

				<p><figure>
						<p>FORT HARRISON IN 1812</p>
					</figure></p>
			</div1>
			<pb id="VAC1322-002" n="[1]"/>
			<titlePage>
				<docTitle rend="center">
					<titlePart type="main"><hi rend="b">F<hi rend="sc">ORT</hi> H<hi rend="sc"
							>ARRISON</hi></hi><lb/> ON THE BANKS OF THE WABASH<lb/> 1812-1912<lb/></titlePart>
				</docTitle>
				<docImprint rend="center"><hi rend="i">Published at the Direction of the</hi><lb/>
					<lb/>F<hi rend="sc">ORT</hi> H<hi rend="sc">ARRISON</hi> C<hi rend="sc">ENTENNIAL</hi>
						A<hi rend="sc">SSOCIATION</hi><lb/></docImprint>
				<byline rend="center"><hi rend="i">Compiled and Edited by the Historical Committee</hi>
					<lb/><docAuthor>DR. J. T. SCOVELL</docAuthor>, CHAIRMAN; <docAuthor>MRS. ALICE P.
						DRYER</docAuthor>, <docAuthor>MAX EHRMANN</docAuthor>, <docAuthor>JOHN D.
						BELL</docAuthor>, <docAuthor>JAMES B. HARRIS</docAuthor>, <docAuthor>EDWARD
						GILBERT</docAuthor>, <docAuthor>JOHN C. WARREN</docAuthor>, <docAuthor>WILLIAM H.
						WILEY</docAuthor>, <docAuthor>DR. E. T. SPOTSWOOD</docAuthor>, <docAuthor>PROF. HERBERT
						BRIGGS</docAuthor>, <docAuthor>C. T. JEWETT</docAuthor></byline>
			</titlePage>


			<pb id="VAC1322-003" n="[2]"/>
			<div1 type="verso">
				<p rend="center"> COPYRIGHT 1912<lb/>JOHN MORTON CHAPTER, SONS OF THE<lb/> AMERICAN
					REVOLUTION</p>

				<p>THE MOORE-LANGEN PRINTING CO., TERRE HAUTE, IND.</p>
			</div1>

			<pb id="VAC1322-004" n="[3]"/>
			<div1 type="dedication">
				<head type="supplied">DEDICATION</head>

				<p><hi rend="b">T</hi>O the descendants of the men and women who participated in the Battle
					of Fort Harrison and of the pioneers who made possible the peaceful settlement of the
					Wabash Valley this work is offered as a patriotic tribute. </p>
			</div1>

			<pb id="VAC1322-005" n="[4]"/>
			<pb id="VAC1322-006" n="5"/>
			<div1 type="introduction">
				<head>INTRODUCTION</head>

				<p>Four hundred years ago North America was a panorama of Nature. All the geological and
					geographical forms were represented in generous proportions. Mountains and plains, forests
					and prairies, great lakes and mighty rivers, all abounding with the varied forms of life.
					There were vast areas of rich agricultural lands and quantities of coal and iron, and of
					copper, lead and zinc, of silver and gold and of many useful minerals. It was an ideal
					home for the fisherman and hunter, and for the savage who accepted nature as he found it,
					being scarcely more than another feature of the panorama. There were perhaps 500,000 of
					these native people in North America. They were called Indians. Physically they were fully
					developed with acute senses and strong passions; but intellectually and morally they were
					more like children. For their support they did not utilize even a tithe of the natural
					products so abundant everywhere.</p>
				<p>Through a more complete utilization of these natural resources, North America has become
					the home of more than a hundred million of people. The history of North America for the
					last four hundred years will be the story of this transformation of a continent; an
					account of the gradual crowding out of the savage or child-like races by stronger races,
					those able to utilize more fully the gifts of nature. In reality the history of North
					America is a record of human development.</p>
				<p>The story of Fort Harrison discusses an important incident in the history of the United
					States, and through it Terre Haute is brought into conspicuous connection with national
					affairs.</p>
				<p rend="right b">J. T. S.</p>
			</div1>


			<pb id="VAC1322-007" n="[6]"/>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div1 type="book">
				<head type="supplied">Fort Harrison on the banks of the Wabash, 1812-1912</head>

				<pb id="VAC1322-008" n="7"/>
				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER I.<lb/> THE BATTLE OF FORT HARRISON.<lb/> BY EDWARD
						GILBERT.</head>
					<p>"The Battle of Fort Harrison" is a high-sounding title to be applied to what was, from
						a material point of view, a very small affair. When is taken into consideration the fact
						that not more than fifty persons were present,. and, according to the report of Captain
						Taylor, not more than ten or fifteen men were capable of duty, as well as all the
						particulars we can now know, why should we be celebrating memories of the event one
						hundred years after it happened ?</p>
					<p>Like many small affairs in the world's history, it was not the battle itself, it was
						not that these few men-and women-behind that stockade, for one night withstood the
						efforts of the savages and were not massacred.</p>
					<p>It was the events preceding and the results following, as well as the heroic efforts of
						the few, which render their defense of Fort Harrison one of the important items in the
						history of the United States.</p>
					<p>That those few men and women and children had been killed and scalped by the Indians
						would not have been fatal to the cause nor in itself would have been even as bad as many
						other massacres that did take place previously and subsequently during the same
						troublous times.</p>
					<p>Not one word shall be written by this hand that would detract from the credit due them.
						All their doings were heroic; every one of them was a patriot. True, they were fighting
						for their lives, the first incentive of all such, but they were also doing patriotic,
						noble duty.</p>
					<p>These people represented a phase of the contest between civilization and barbarism. All
						was fighting and contest around them. These people were of the advance guard of the
						world-wide warfare between that element of humanity which has always sought to advance
						and improve, on the one side and, on the other, savagery and barbarism, which is devoid
						of pride of ancestry or hope of posterity, caring for and seeking nothing but present
						comfort or gratification of present passions.</p>
					<p>These Englishmen had emigrated originally from their former homes, and had progressed
						far into the wilderness, for what ? To improve their condition. That is a broad
						proposition that is not controvertible. They found here a race that had inhabited the
						country, God only knows how long. In that time they had killed game, caught fish, raised
						a scanty supply of the simplest grains by the simplest methods, the same from <pb
							id="VAC1322-009" n="8"/> one generation to another. No student of the Indian race has
						ever discovered that any generation of them had ever done on its own incentive, any,
						even the simplest thing by a better method than its ancestors.</p>
					<p>These Englishmen belonged to a race that believed the injunction laid upon them in the
						first chapters of Genesis, to replenish the earth, populate it, cultivate its soil and
						utilize its natural resources. They found here a people and a land barren of results.
						They found a people evidently diminishing in numbers by brutish wars and ravaging
						diseases, which they were too simple-minded to try to overcome. They believed a Divine
						Providence intended the land for those who would make the best use of it. And if any of
						them did not stop to think out the question, the simplest knew that he could utilize
						such a land and that the Indian did not. The Anglo-Saxon race was dynamic and the Indian
						race was static. Therefore they were in opposition, and the history of the world is that
						the war was on perpetually between them.</p>

					<p>That they were heroic, that they were brave and that they all showed the highest
						intelligence is proven by the simple story of what took place. This little garrison
						found themselves isolated, fifty miles, through the wilderness to the nearest succor.
						Fifty men, thirty-five to forty of them sick with that vile, bone-racking malaria that
						pervaded the country, which makes one wish he were dead, even if to be scalped
						afterward; nine women and children. The little stockade was impervious to the bullets of
						the then known rifles, but the walls were not proof against fire. The official report
						tells that the commandant had for some time very seriously doubted his ability to
						withstand an attack.</p>
					<p>At dusk four shots are heard. What does this mean? Out of the stillness of nature comes
						this warning alarm. There is no known reason for it except hostility. Two white men are
						known to be somewhere in the vicinity of the shots making hay. But they could not have
						fired the four shots in quick succession from the rifles of those days. Caution was the
						watchword of every experienced Indian fighter. Captain Taylor dared not investigate so
						near dark. He placed his little force on the best footing for defense. In the morning he
						sent out a detachment, warned to be wary of ambush, to investigate. These found the two
						hay-makers, citizens&mdash;one named John Guffy, the name of the other not known&mdash;
						had been shot, twice each, from a sneaking foe without opportunity to defend themselves.
						Their bodies had been mutilated in a shocking manner. Yet the detachment saw no signs of
						Indians.</p>
					<p>The next evening there appeared before the gates of the Fort, old Lenar, accompanied by
						some thirty chiefs and "old men" of several tribes, pretending to seek a friendly
						conference in want of food.</p>
					<p>This was a naive attempt on their part to gain admission to the Fort under false
						pretense, when, without doubt, a massacre would have <pb id="VAC1322-010" n="9"/> taken
						place. These thirty, with their arms beneath their blankets, once inside, outnumbering
						the effective force, were there for no other purpose.</p>
					<p>Inexperienced and confiding people often have been taken in by such pretenses on the
						part of Indians. But Captain Zachary Taylor was not of that class. He knew his enemies.
						He had studied the Indian character, in an experience with them in the Illinois country,
						he had learned that the Indian's word was never to be taken at its face value.</p>
					<p>He refused the interview, which was postponed until the morrow, when the Indians were
						again to come for peaceable pow wow.</p>
					<p>What other fighting people would have, in the face of the atrocious outrage of the
						evening before, expected to be received as friends ? This, with many other examples,
						goes to prove that the primitive mental condition of the Indian was not in advance of
						his material status. His norm of war was the deceit of his adversary. He could not see
						that the white man had learned by experience, and expected him to be imposed on, over
						and over again by the same ruse. What other race of people would have come in such
						manner, not under a flag of truce, as from avowed enemies seeking parley, but under the
						pretense of friendship? None. It was an act of men in primitive ignorance.</p>
					<p>Captain Taylor, on the contrary, proceeded at once to prepare, as far as his limited
						resources would permit, for defense. He says he had not been able for some time to mount
						a full guard, that his effective force was not to exceed ten or fifteen men. These he
						stationed to the best advantage, made a close inspection, personally of all arms,
						distributed ammunition to the extent of sixteen rounds to the man, and ordered the
						strictest watch at all points. He required his subaltern to parade the rounds of the
						Fort all night and to give the alarm at the first indication of hostilities.</p>
					<p>Contrary to the usual habits of the Indians, who very often made their secret attacks
						an hour or two before daylight it came on about eleven o'clock. The first alarm was from
						the firing of one of the sentinels who discovered that an Indian, under cover of the
						darkness, had set fire to the blockhouse at the southwest angle of the Fort.</p>
					<p>Legend says this was done by placing coals of fire in a kettle and covering it with a
						blanket, not to attract attention while being carried to the stockade in the dark. Also,
						it is told that there were holes in the logs of the block house made by the cattle
						licking the logs for the salt that was stored in the blockhouse among the supplies of
						the army contractor, and through them the coals of fire were dropped.</p>
					<p>The only official account of the proceedings of the night is in the report of Captain
						Taylor to General Harrison at Vincennes. This plain, straightforward account of his
						performance of his duties is given in a separate chapter. He gives a graphic account of
						his feelings, when the <pb id="VAC1322-011" n="10"/> apparent condition has its effect
						on the men and women. At first, with shrieks of terror, all was confusion and
						helplessness. The yells of the savages, the fire destroying what seemed their only
						protection, together with constant rifle firing and showers of arrows which poured into
						the Fort. All these were enough to quail the stoutest heart. It presaged, not only
						death, but death of the most horrid kind, torture and mutilation.</p>


					<p>No wonder that, as he tells, near the first, two of his little force, men on whom he
						had relied for strong support, should become panic-stricken, jump the palisades and seek
						safety by flight under cover of the darkness.</p>
					<p>Immediately after the first there was a recovery of nerve. There were a few cool heads
						who inspired the others and determination showed itself, not to supinely give up, but
						defend themselves as best they could or at least sell their lives at greatest cost to
						the enemy. In his report, Captain Taylor speaks of those who helped bring it about, and
						were most efficient both in work and in inspiring the others. It is regrettable that he
						mentions only one name that we can place in the hero class. Doctor William A. Clark was
						the surgeon of the post, and to him Captain Taylor gives all honor for his personal
						efforts. He seemingly inspired the erection of a breastwork that would prevent the
						entrance of the Indians after the blockhouse was destroyed, and led in the extinguishing
						of the fire so that it was confined to the one place. As an example of the bravery shown
						by the men, it is told that William Cowen, one of the soldiers killed inside the Fort,
						stood on the bastion. He had fired and turning to his companions, laughingly shouted, "I
						killed an Indian that time." In doing so he neglected to stoop behind the ramparts and
						the next second was struck by an Indian bullet and instantly killed. A brother, Josey
						Cowen, a mere boy, a soldier, was among those sick of the malaria and died the next day.
						This family furnished two heroes of Fort Harrison.</p>
					<p>It has been told before that Captain Taylor had distributed sixteen rounds of
						ammunition to each man. This, in the day of rapid-firing arms, seems a very small amount
						in the face of the prospective fight. But it must be taken into consideration that those
						old muskets or squirrel rifles were slowly loaded at the muzzle And they were not pumped
						out at random, as in modern war, when it is said to take more than a man's weight in
						lead to kill or wound one. Those Indian fighters each waited to find his mark and when
						found he drew a bead and shot as if after a wild turkey or deer for his dinner.</p>
					<p>Legend also brings another reason for this limited ammunition. It was probably all he
						had. For it is told how, long before the fight was over, several of the women in the
						Fort were busy moulding bullets.</p>

					<p>There was another dreadful condition that was met by heroic action on the part of one
						of the women. The only supply of water was from a <pb id="VAC1322-012" n="11"/> well,
						and that was raised by the slow process of lowering and winding up a bucket. And soon it
						was discovered that, as the fire raged the fiercest the water in the well had been so
						nearly exhausted that the bucket came up only partly filled. Some were again
						panic-stricken. Julia Lambert&mdash;and her name should go down to posterity in the list
						of heroines&mdash;said: "Lower me into the well and I will fill the buckets with a
						gourd." This was done and not only did her energetic work send up a full supply, but to
						the surprise of all the water soon appeared to raise so that the buckets filled when let
						into it. This was hailed as a miracle, enacted for the sakes of these beleaguered
						mortals.</p>
					<p>It was explained, however, that in dipping the water she had dipped so much sand that
						the bottom of the well had been lowered beyond the water level.</p>
					<p>Soon after daylight came, the Indians retired beyond rifle range, and the battle
						practically ended. They hovered around for some time and disappeared. With no force
						sufficient to make a reconnoissance Captain Taylor and his little band were in a sad
						plight. Their stores destroyed by fire, their cattle killed, they were forced, as he
						says, to subsist on green corn.</p>
					<p>All this happened on the fourth of September, the battle, but it was not until the
						tenth of the same month, if it may be judged by the date of Captain Taylor's letter to
						General Harrison, that he thought it safe to attempt to send even one of his small force
						out to try to open communication. This was done first by sending two men down the river
						in a canoe. They started by night, hoping to escape detection. On arriving at the
						narrows, a little below where Terre Haute now stands, they found Indian camp fires on
						both sides and, a guard out watching for them. They were forced to return. Captain
						Taylor then wrote a supplemental letter, which is dated September 13, 1812. Captain
						Taylor says in his letter that he will send this by the hands of the orderly sergeant
						and one other, though there is a popular legend that one man by the name of Peter
						Mallory carried it. He, or they, were ordered to go through the woods, avoiding all
						roads, and taking the greatest care to not attract the attention of any Indians, whether
						presumably friendly or not.</p>
					<p>It is unfortunate that the records of the War Department at Washington are so meagre or
						so unsatisfactorily arranged, that they can not furnish a roster of the soldiers of the
						company under the command of Captain Taylor. The names of Captain Zachary Taylor,
						afterwards so notable as a general of the army in Mexico and elsewhere, and as President
						of the United States, with that of Dr. William A. Clark, spoken of before, are the only
						ones the department can give. It is, however, <pb id="VAC1322-013" n="12"/>known that
						these soldiers were of the Seventh United States regular infantry.</p>
					<p>Of the citizens, settlers and others, together with the women and children, a pretty
						accurate account is given elsewhere in this history.</p>
					<p>Dr. Clark remained here some years after, and was a valued citizen and practicing
						physician.</p>
					<p>There should, however, be recorded here, though it is so elsewhere, the remarkable fact
						that Fort Harrison was built and first commanded by William Henry Harrison, and later,
						at the time of the only hostilities ever occurring there, by Zachary Taylor, both of
						whom gained fame, not only as soldiers but as statesmen. Each later became President of
						the United States. And each died in office as such. General Harrison was the first to be
						succeeded by a Vice&mdash;President, John Tyler, and General Taylor the second by
						Millard Filmore.</p>
					<p>As to exactly who the attacking parties were at Fort Harrison, Captain Taylor says he
						is unable to be positive. He mentions several chiefs and parts of tribes, but as there
						appeared in daylight, only some forty who sought the interview, he merely surmises as to
						the rest. It was thought at the time that the Indians were merely a marauding band of
						miscellaneous origin.</p>
					<p>Later developments of historical research have shown that the attempt to capture Fort
						Harrison was a part of the plan of campaign of the British Army in Canada. In August,
						1812, an expedition was started out from Malden, Canada, under command of Major Muhr.
						This was composed of a small company of British regulars, some Canadian volunteers and a
						host of Indians. These numbers were never definitely known.</p>
					<p>The object, so soon after the declaration of war, was to capture the two outposts of
						Fort Wayne and Fort Harrison. Both of these objects failed. We have seen how Captain
						Taylor successfully defended Fort Harrison. Fort Wayne was stubbornly defended for a
						short time until reinforcements arrived and the besiegers driven out of the country. The
						British regulars and the Canadians all went in the expedition against Fort Wayne. It was
						left to the Indians to proceed against the less strongly defended Fort on the
						Wabash.</p>
					<p>The attacks on the two posts were made on Fort Wayne September 3, 1812, and on Fort
						Harrison September 4, at night.</p>
					<p>General Hull had ignominiously surrendered Detroit to the British a short time before.
						This left the way open for the enemy almost to the Ohio River, except for these two
						posts. It was no doubt the idea of the British General Brock that if Fort Wayne and Fort
						Harrison were subdued, the seat of the war would be transferred from the Lakes to the
						Ohio River. But for the stubborn and gallant defense of these posts, the history of the
						War of 1812 in the Northwest might have been differently written.</p>
				</div2>



				<pb id="VAC1322-014" n="13"/>
				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER II.<lb/> CAUSES LEADING UP TO FORT HARRISON<lb/> BY EDWARD
						GILBERT.</head>
					<p>The history of Fort Harrison covers part of two epochs. The causes that led up to the
						building of the Fort, followed by,the Tippecanoe campaign, are a part of the history of
						the troubles that continued to exist between the United States and Great Britain after
						the treaty of peace at Paris in 1783. The Battle of Fort Harrison, the defense by
						Captain Taylor, was a part of the war between the same nations, openly declared June 18,
						1812, known commonly as the War of 1812-15.</p>
					<p>That marvelous expedition of General George Rogers Clark, conceived by him almost
						alone, and executed almost without any help from the general government, encouraged by
						the peace loving French settlers of the Mississippi and Wabash valleys, and supported by
						the financial aid of "Colonel" Francis Vigo, the "Spanish Merchant" of Vincennes and
						Kaskaskia, had won an empire for our people.</p>
					<p>At the Paris convention in 1783, His British Majesty's envoys asserted that the western
						boundary should be the Allegheny mountains, or at most the Ohio and Mississippi rivers.
						They insisted that Clark's little band had merely taken possession of unimportant posts
						of French inhabitants the sovereignty over which had been ceded to Britain by France.
						Nevertheless there was the fact that this territory was held, at the close of the war,
						by right of conquest. British power had been represented there by the garrisons at
						Vincennes and Kaskaskia, had been overcome and extinguished. And no feasible effort had
						been made on His Majesty's part to recover it.</p>
					<p>Failing to make that claim good the British envoys sought to have the land of our later
						Northwest Territory declared neutral ground, a land for the Indians. This obnoxious
						proposal was promptly rejected by our commissioners, and insistence made that it was
						conquered territory to be transferred or there could be no agreement. England was
						whipped, and had to concede the terms.</p>
					<p>While this agreement was made and the terms of peace settled, they were not carried out
						on the part of England in good faith. Under one excuse or another, or with no pretense
						of excuse, the land was practically held, and garrisons were maintained on American
						territory.</p>
					<pb id="VAC1322-015" n="14"/>
					<p>Many historians hold that England, from the declaration of peace in 1783, foresaw
						another war which was to recover to her, if not the Colonies she had lost, at least a
						part of this territory. The United States was poor, heavily loaded with debt, her army
						exhausted and her resources unavailable. Her government for some years a mere fabric,
						and later, still an experiment. It required the constant encroachments of England to
						drive our people into this second war.</p>
					<p>These encroachments consisted largely of interference with our commerce on the high
						seas. But the features that concern our story of Fort Harrison were the interference
						with our Indian relations, sub rosa, by the British powers through Canada.</p>
					<p>While His Majesty's ministers were claiming innocence of any offense against the terms
						of the treaty, there was ample proof that the Indians of the Northwest were being
						encouraged in every opposition to the settlement of the country. As a single instance of
						proof: General Harrison, then Governor of Indiana Territory, in 1809, wrote to the
						Secretary of War that the Indians of the Northwest Territory were receiving subsidies
						from the British. He found the Indians equipped with arms and clothing beyond their
						means of procuring by purchase, and amply supplied with provisions. To corroborate his
						suspicions he sent trusted agents among them to offer to sell them clothing and even
						arms and ammunition. To these offers the Indians replied no, we get all we want from
						English traders free of cost. He found that the Indians were being constantly incited to
						deeds of violence and outrage by English.</p>
					<p>About this time came into great prominence, Tecumseh and his brother,"The Prophet."
						"The Prophet" was an old fraud of a medicine man who had gained a temporary influence
						over part of the restless Indians by his mystical arts, played on the ignorant minds.
						Tecumseh was perhaps as near being a statesman as an Indian ever was. He conceived the
						idea that he could unite all the Indians of America into a great confederacy and drive
						the whites into the sea. He had been preaching his crusade among the northern people for
						some time, and had gone among those of Alabama and Georgia, and perhaps as far as
						Florida.</p>
					<p>Tecumseh's contention on the question of treaty cession of land by the Indians was that
						the land belonged to the whole Indian race, and that cession could not be justly made by
						the different tribes, but on the full consent and approval of all the tribes. What basis
						there was for such claim it is hard to understand, in the light of the fact that ever
						since Europeans knew them, the Indians had been fighting among them selves over these
						same lands. War and pestilence therefrom was the rule. Whole tribes were at times
						exterminated.</p>
					<p>Tecumseh was far-seeing, being an Indian, and no doubt believed that the race war would
						ultimately result in the extinction of one race. He <pb id="VAC1322-016" n="15"/> could
						not dispute that the several Indian Treaties had been freely entered into, so, like the
						advocate desiring to save his case, he attacked the treaty making power.</p>
					<p>It was during his absence that General Harrison, seeing the coming storm of, to say the
						least, great disturbance, having exerted all his influence to dissuade the Indians
						against their foolhardy plan, decided that aggressive measures must be adopted and the
						poor creatures brought to a sense of their duty, or severely punished. It is believed
						that Tecumseh had enjoined on "The Prophet"that under no conditions was a battle to be
						risked until he had returned, having succeeded in uniting the whole of the various
						tribes.</p>
					<p>In stating in the first paragraph of this chapter that the causes that led up to the
						building of Fort Harrison were the troubles that continued to exist between our country
						and Great Britain, it is not claimed that there would have been none with the Indians
						except for British interference.</p>
					<p>But for the support, before mentioned, and the encouragement, which later historical
						investigation has proven, principally to Tecumseh and "The Prophet," their dream of a
						confederation would never have been. The Indians had never prevailed in any of their
						wars with the Americans, but were persuaded they might, at least, as allies of
						Britain.</p>
					<p>Sundry missions and emissaries to "The Prophet's"town having brought no satisfactory
						response to General Harrison, he resolved on a demonstration into the enemy's country.
						He would have a renewed peaceable agreement, or must resort to punishment.</p>
					<p>The organization of his army at Vincennes, its personality, and its march and the
						Battle of Tippecanoe are told in another chapter.</p>
					<p>There has been for a hundred years in America a controversy between philanthropists and
						fanatics on the one side and the settlers and radical Indian haters on the other as to
						the justice and humanity of the treatment of the Indians. Especially has this applied to
						the question of how the lands have been transferred. The contention on the part of the
						former has been that the Indians owned the lands and they should not have been taken
						from them except by their full and free consent, which means by purchase at prices that
						made them anxious to sell. The latter have contended that the Indians were an inferior,
						a worthless race, and that they had no rights. Now, history shows that as between the
						two views the general practice has leaned largely towards the philanthropic side. No set
						of land traders ever came together for a deal without at least a semblance of sharp
						practice being a feature of their transactions. There have been instances of trickery.
						The ignorance of the Indians has been taken advantage of more than once. But the basis
						of every accession of <pb id="VAC1322-017" n="16"/> land by the United States Government
						has been on terms of proper compensation. With exceptions enough to prove the rule, this
						is an historical fact that cannot be disputed.</p>
					<p>Others will say that, admitting the purchase of the lands, the prices given haven't
						been commensurate with the values. Here brings us back to the question of value as based
						on the uses to which they were put. Taking all that is known of the Indians in their
						primal state, they made a precarious living in squalor and hardship, using only the
						superficial products that came without labor. The fish in the lakes and rivers and the
						game in the forest were increasing, and the soil, none richer in the world, capable of
						bountiful production, was idle. With this condition the Indians lived in poverty and
						want. They did not utilize the land, and they were paid for it, more than the value,
						based on their occupation.</p>
				</div2>



				<pb id="VAC1322-018" n="17"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER III<lb/>CAPTAIN TAYLOR'S REPORT</head>
					<lb/>
					<p>Letter from Captain Z. Taylor, commanding Fort Harrison, Indiana Territory, to General
						Harrison.</p>
					<p><text>
							<body>
								<div type="letter">


									<opener><dateline><address><addrLine>FORT HARRISON,</addrLine></address><date>September
												10, 1812.</date></dateline>
										<salute>DEAR SIR:</salute>&mdash;</opener>


									<p> On Thursday evening, the 3rd instant, after retreat beating, four guns were
										heard to fire in the direction where two young men (citizens who resided here)
										were making hay, about four hundred yards distant from the fort. I was
										immediately impressed with an idea that they were killed by the Indians, as the
										Miamis or Weas had that day informed me that the Prophet's party would soon be
										here for the purpose of commencing hostilities, and that they had been directed
										to leave this place which we were about to do. I did not think it prudent to
										send out at that late hour of the night to see what had become of them; and
										their not coming in convinced me that I was right in my conjecture. I waited
										until eight o'clock next morning, when I sent out a corporal with a small party
										to find them, if it could be done without running too much risk of being drawn
										into an ambuscade. He soon sent back to inform me, that he had found them both
										killed, and wished to know my further orders; I sent the cart and oxen, had them
										brought in and buried; they had been shot with two balls, scalped and cut in the
										most shocking manner. Late in the evening of the 4th inst. old Joseph Lenar and
										between 30 and 40 Indians arrived from the Prophet's town, with a white flag;
										among whom were about ten women, and the men were composed of the chiefs of the
										different tribes that compose the Prophet's party. A Shawanoe man, that spoke
										good English, informed me that old Lenar intended to speak to me next morning,
										and try to get something to eat. At retreat beating I examined the men's arms
										and found them all in good order, and completed their cartridges to 16 rounds
										per man. As I had not been able to mount a guard of more than six privates and
										two non-commissioned officers, for some time past, and sometimes part of them
										every other day from the unhealthiness of the company, I had not conceived my
										force adequate to the defense of this post should it be vigorously attacked, for
										some time past. As I had just recovered from a very severe attack of the fever,
										I was not able to be up much through the night. After tattoo, I cautioned the
										guard to be vigilant, and ordered one of the non-commissioned officers, as the
										sentinels <pb id="VAC1322-019" n="18"/> could not see every part of the
										garrison, to walk around on the inside during the whole night to prevent the
										Indians taking advantage of us provided they had any intention of attacking us.
										About 11 o'clock I was awakened by the firing of one of the sentinels. I sprang
										up, run out and ordered the men to their posts, when my orderly sergeant (who
										had charge of the upper block-house) called out that the Indians had fired the
										lower block-house, which contained the property of the contractor which was
										deposited in the lower part, the upper having been assigned to a corporal and
										ten privates as an alarm post. The guns had began to fire pretty smartly from
										both sides. I directed the buckets to be got ready and water brought from the
										well and the fire extinguished immediately, as it was perceivable at that time.
										But from debility or some other cause, the men were very slow in executing my
										orders. The word fire seemed to throw the whole of them into confusion, and by
										the time they had got the water and broken open the door the fire had
										unfortunately communicated to a quantity of whiskey (the stock having licked
										several holes through the lower part of the building after the salt that was
										stored there through which they had introduced the fire without being
										discovered, as the night was very dark), and in spite of every exertion we could
										make use of, in less than a moment it ascended to the roof and baffled every
										effort we could make to extinguish it. As that block-house adjoined the barracks
										that made part of the fortifications most of the men immediately gave themselves
										up for lost, and I had the greatest difficulty in getting my orders executed;
										and, sir, what from the raging of the fire-the yelling and howling of several
										hundred Indians -the cries of nine women and children (a part soldiers' and a
										part citizens' wives, who had taken shelter in the Fort)-and the desponding of
										so many of the men, which was worse than all-I can assure you that my feelings
										were very unpleasant-and indeed there were not more than ten or fifteen men able
										to do a great deal, the others being either sick or convalescent-and to add to
										our other misfortunes, two of the stoutest men in the fort, and that I had every
										confidence in, jumped the picket and left us. But my presence of mind did not
										for a moment forsake me. I saw that by throwing off part of the roof that joined
										the block-house that was on fire, and keeping the end perfectly wet, the whole
										row of buildings might be saved, and leave only an entrance of eighteen or
										twenty feet for the Indians to enter after the house was consumed; and that a
										temporary breastwork might be erected to prevent their even entering there. I
										convinced the men that this could be accomplished, and it appeared to inspire
										them with new life, and never did men act with more firmness or desperation.
										Those that were able (while the others kept up a constant fire from the other
										block-house and the two bastions) mounted the roofs of the houses, with Dr.
										Clark at their head <pb id="VAC1322-020" n="19"/> (who acted with the greatest
										firmness and presence of mind the whole time the attack lasted, which was seven
										hours) under a shower of bullets, and in less than a moment threw off as much of
										the roof as was necessary. This was done only with the loss of one man and two
										wounded, and I am in hopes neither of them dangerous. The man that was killed
										was a little deranged, and did not get off the house as soon as directed, or he
										would not have been hurt; and, although the barracks were several times in a
										blaze, and an immense quantity of fire against them, the men used such exertion
										that they kept it under and before day raised a temporary breastwork as high as
										,a man's head, although the Indians continued to pour in a heavy fire of ball
										and innumerable quantity of arrows during the whole time the attack lasted, in
										every part of the parade. I had but one other man killed, nor any other wounded
										inside the fort, and he lost his life by being too anxious. He got into one of
										the galleys on the bastions and fired over the pickets, and called out to his
										comrades that he had killed an Indian, and neglecting to stoop down in an
										instant he was shot dead. One of the men that jumped the pickets returned an
										hour before day, and running up towards the gate begged for God's sake for it to
										be opened. I suspected it to be a stratagem of the Indians to get in, as I did
										not recollect his voice. I directed the men in the bastion, where I happened to
										be, to shoot him let him be who he would, but fortunately he ran up to the other
										bastion, where they knew his voice, and Dr. Clark directed him to lie close to
										the pickets behind an empty barrel that happened to be there, and at daylight I
										had him let in. His arm was broke in a most shocking manner, which he says was
										done by the Indians which I suppose was the cause of his returning. I think it
										probable that he will not recover. The other they caught about 130 yards from
										the garrison and cut him all to pieces. After keeping up a constant fire until
										six o'clock the next morning, which we began to return with some effect after
										daylight, they removed out of the reach of our guns. A party of them drove up
										the horses that belonged to the citizens here, and as they could not catch them
										very rapidly shot the whole of them in our sight, as well as a number of their
										hogs. They drove off the whole of the cattle, which amounted to sixty-five head,
										as well as the public oxen. I had the vacancy filled up before night (which was
										made by the burning of the block-house) with a strong row of pickets, which I
										got by pulling down the guard house. We lost the whole of our provisions, but
										must make out to live upon green corn until we can get a supply, which I am in
										hopes will not be long. I believe the whole of the Miamies or Weas were among
										the Prophet's party, as one chief gave his orders in that language which
										resembled Stone Easter's voice, and I believe Negro Legs was there likewise. A
										Frenchman here understands their different languages, and <pb id="VAC1322-021"
											n="20"/> several of the Miamies or Weas that have been here frequently, were
										recognized by the Frenchman and soldiers next morning. The Indians suffered
										smartly, but were so numerous as to take off all that were shot. They continued
										with us until the next morning, but made no further attempt on the Fort, nor
										have we seen anything more of them since. I have delayed informing you of my
										situation, as I did not like to weaken the garrison, and I looked for some
										person from Vincennes, and none of my men were acquainted with the woods, and
										therefore I would either have to take the river or the road, which I was fearful
										was guarded by small parties of Indians that would not dare attack a party of
										rangers that was on a scout; but being disappointed, I have at length determined
										to send a couple of my men by water and am in hopes that they will arrive safe.
										I think it would be best to send the provisions under a pretty strong escort, as
										the Indians may attempt to prevent their coming. If you carry on an expedition
										against the Prophet this fall, you ought to be well provided with everything, as
										you may calculate on having every inch of ground disputed between this and there
										that they can defend with advantage.</p>
									<closer>
										<salute>Wishing, &amp;c.</salute>
										<signed>(Signed) Z. TAYLOR.</signed> His Excellency Governor Harrison.</closer>
								</div>
							</body>
						</text></p>

					<p><text>
							<body>
								<div type="letter">

									<opener><dateline><address><addrLine>FORT HARRISON,</addrLine></address><date>September
												13, 1812.</date></dateline>
										<salute>DEAR SIR:</salute>&mdash;</opener>

									<p>I wrote you on the 10th inst., giving you an account of the attack on this
										place, as well as my situation which account I at tempted to send by water, but
										the two men whom I despatched in a canoe after night found the river so well
										guarded that they were obliged to return. The Indians had built a fire on the
										bank of the river a short distance below the garrison, which gave them an
										opportunity of seeing any craft that might attempt to pass, and were waiting
										with a canoe to intercept it. I expect the Fort as well as the road to Vincennes
										is as well or better watched than the river. But my situation compels me to make
										one other attempt by land, and my orderly sergeant, with one other man, sets out
										tonight with strict orders to avoid the road in daytime and depend entirely on
										the woods, although neither of them have ever been to Vincennes by land, nor do
										they know anything of the country, but I am in hopes they will reach you in
										safety. I send them with great reluctance from their ignorance of the woods. I
										think it very probable there is a large party of Indians waylaying the road
										between this and Vincennes, likely about the Narrows, for the purpose of
										intercepting any party that may be coming to this place, as the cattle they got
										here will supply them plentifully with provisions for some time to come.</p>
									<closer><salute>Please, &amp;c., &amp;c.</salute><signed>(Signed) Z. TAYLOR. His
											Excellency Governor Harrison.</signed>
									</closer>
								</div>
							</body>
						</text></p>
					<bibl>(Nile's Register, Vol. 3, p. 90.)</bibl>






					<pb id="VAC1322-022" n="[19]"/>
					<figure>
						<p>ZACHARY TAYLOR</p>
					</figure>


					<pb id="VAC1322-023" n="[20]"/>
				</div2>

				<pb id="VAC1322-024" n="21"/>


				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER IV.<lb/>ZACHARY TAYLOR<lb/>A BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH BY HERBERT
						BRIGGS.</head>

					<p>Zachary Taylor, the hero of Fort Harrison, was the twelfth President of the United
						States. He was baptized into the world of fame within the shadow of Terre Haute.</p>
					<p>He was born in Orange County, Virginia, September 24, 1784, soon after the Treaty of
						Paris, which closed the Revolutionary War. His father, Colonel Richard Taylor, had borne
						a conspicuous part in the struggle for independence, and was on intimate terms with
						General Washington.</p>
					<p>His mother was Mary Strother, said to have been a handsome young lady of nineteen whose
						marriage August 20, 1779, to Colonel Richard Taylor, then almost a grizzled veteran of
						thirty-six, was one of the romances of the time. But the marriage seemed in every way to
						have been a happy one, and Zachary was the third son of that union. One son and three
						daughters were born after Zachary, but the father made ample provision for all of his
						eight children.</p>
					<p>Like Indiana, Kentucky was once a part of the Old Dominion, and was known as one of the
						western counties of Virginia. To compensate her soldiers who had fought in the
						Revolution, Virginia gave liberally of her grants of land, and Colonel Taylor, accepting
						the bounties of his native State, moved his family to a large tract near the present
						City of Louisville, Ky., when Zachary was one year old.</p>
					<p>Colonel Taylor was not a total stranger to these Kentucky wilds; as a young man less
						than twenty-one, he journeyed westward through Kentucky to the Mississippi river, thence
						southward as far as Natchez, then as one biographer remarks, "without guide or
						companion, through pathless woods, over rivers and mountains, fearless alike of the
						seasons, of savages, or of any peril of his long and lonely way, he walked back to his
						father's house in. Virginia."</p>
					<p>The spirit of adventure and the courage of the pioneer seemed to have been an integral
						part of the Taylor family-it was the summons to the new and untried that led early
						members of the Taylor family to leave their English home and seek their fortunes in
						Virginia-the lure of the wilderness that had induced Hancock Taylor, a brother of
						Colonel Taylor, <pb id="VAC1322-025" n="22"/> to lead the way to Kentucky, and thus it
						was that a welcome had been provided for the family of our hero when they arrived at
						their wilderness home.</p>
					<p>Zachary's father decided that the boy should be a farmer, but destiny seemed to have
						ordered his life differently. But whatever parental plans included, nothing received
						more careful attention than the education of his children, and for that purpose Elisha
						Ayres, a young New England school teacher, was installed in a school house nearby, so
						that the children of Colonel Taylor as well as those of his neighbors for several miles
						around might be properly instructed. Zachary was said to have been "quick in learning
						and still patient in study."</p>
					<p>There were other means of education for the boy&mdash;his mother's force of character
						and strong influence, say his biographers, exerted a guidance all but controlling.</p>
					<p>Again, the neighbors must not be overlooked; in many instances they had been the
						father's companions in arms during the revolution. They gathered around the hospitable
						Taylor family hearthstone, entertained themselves and instructed the children with
						rehearsals of their hardships, adventures and triumphs; the almost daily encounter of
						some settler with the Indians; the killing of the uncle, Hancock Taylor, by an Indian in
						British uniform&mdash;all left their imprint on the minds of the youthful listeners.
						Ideals of life were thus formed&mdash;ideals not necessarily at variance with the
						paternal plans, but more in harmony with the ambitions and environments of the one who
						was to become the real responsible person, not only for his, but the Nation's
						destinies.</p>
					<p>Then there came the position of Collector of the Port of Louisville&mdash;an
						appointment from President George Washington, bestowed upon Colonel Taylor in
						recognition of faithful performance of duties in past days of trial.</p>
					<p>The Aaron Burr episode in American history, that real or imaginary prospect of a
						hostile southwestern empire, served to take young Zachary away from his home for a few
						months where he joined a volunteer company to receive training both in the instincts and
						art of warfare; this was his initial step in serving his country. If his ambitions had
						been dormant, they were now thoroughly aroused; the axe, the plough and the scythe,
						those instruments of peace and production, no longer entertained him-the Kentucky farm
						no longer satisfied his aspiration&mdash;war seemed to have been his trade, surely his
						ambition. Opportunity was not long in opening her doors to him. In the early days of the
						two States, Kentucky and Indiana, held many things in common; many pioneers left their
						Kentucky homes and sought the fertile soil of the Wabash Valley. The two States had a
						common enemy, the Indian. William Strother Taylor, older brother of Zachary, and a
						second lieutenant of artillery, <pb id="VAC1322-026" n="23"/> died removing whatever
						obstacle that might have been in the way so that President Jefferson appointed Zachary
						first lieutenant in the Seventh Regiment of Infantry, May 3, 1808. His first assignment
						took him to New Orleans, but an uncongenial climate compelled him to seek the
						recuperating attention of his home and his mother. He remained on furlough for about two
						years, during which time he completed one of his greatest conquests, the winning of Miss
						Margaret Smith, of Calvert County, Maryland, to be his wife throughout his long and
						eventful career. His biographers agree that the domestic life of Mr. and Mrs. Taylor, so
						far as exigencies of camp life would permit, was ideal&mdash;an example to be imitated.
						His affection for Mrs. Taylor was thoroughly reciprocated, and when General Taylor
						became President she declined the honors and duties of the first lady of the land, and
						surrendered to her daughter, Miss Betty, or Mrs. Bliss, and pronounced her husband's
						elevation to the presidency a part of a plan to deprive her of his society and to
						shorten his life by unnecessary care.</p>

					<p>With the election of James Madison to the presidency, Lieutenant Taylor's. plans
						suffered no relapse, and on November 30, 1810, he was promoted to the rank of Captain.
						About one-half of the Seventh Regiment to which he had been assigned, was sent north to
						Vincennes there to join General Harrison, Governor of the Northwest Territory. This was
						a favorable time for a young man with Captain Taylor's ambition. Great influences were
						at work to test the defensive power of the National Government. The British Government
						had as yet failed and refused to carry out the terms of the Treaty of 1783, and even in
						that treaty the independence of the United States was not recognized. England recognized
						"thirteen free, separate and independent sovereignties," and demanded of the American
						Commissioners making the Treaty of Paris that the old Northwest Territory be left as
						neutral ground to be occupied by the Indians. English Emissaries were busy everywhere
						with their allies, the Indians. Pioneers in frontier districts were in constant danger
						of Indian fury. Aggravated by the English conspirators, this state of affairs was
						especially true in the Wabash Valley where the great natural resources were attracting
						vast numbers of settlers. Many Indian tribes under the leadership of Tecumseh, a Shawnee
						Chieftain of great sagacity and influence, had been organized to resist the
						encroachments of the Whites.</p>
					<p>That Tecumseh was a force with which the United States must deal was well illustrated
						by a Canadian historian, who said: "No one can fully calculate the inestimable value of
						those devoted red men, led on by the brave Tecumseh during the struggle of 1812. But for
						them it is probable that we should not now have a Canada, and if we had we would not en-
						joy the liberty and privileges we possess in so eminent a degree."</p>


					<pb id="VAC1322-027" n="24"/>

					<p>Tecumseh's brother, Ellskwatawa, known as the "Prophet," a mixture of medicine man and
						sorcerer, also exercised great influence over many Indians.</p>
					<p>Many things combine to confirm the belief that the British Government had a working
						agreement with the Indians. Tecumseh had received a commission as Brigadier-General in
						the British Royal Army, 1812-1813, and led two thousand warriors at Fort Meigs; it was
						upon Tecumseh's advice that the final place was selected for the Battle of the Thames,
						where he put aside his English uniform and sword, and donned his native costume, the
						better to inspire his savage warriors. He was killed in a hand to hand encounter with a
						United States soldier, said to have been Colonel Richard M. Johnson, but the controversy
						as to who killed the famous Chief has never been settled.</p>
					<p>The Prophet received a pension from the British Government until 1826. Other instances
						of Indian loyalty to English plans might be recited, but enough has been given to convey
						an understanding of the difficult task undertaken by Governor Harrison when he attempted
						to acquire possession of a large tract of land from the Delaware, Pottawatomies and
						Miamis, extending along the Wabash river to a point a few miles north of where Terre
						Haute is now situated. General Harrison's headquarters were at the territorial capital,
						Vincennes. Indians under the leadership of the Prophet had assembled at Prophets Town
						near the present site of Lafayette. It was against this formidable foe that General
						Harrison marched from Vincennes, September 26, 1811. At a point about three miles due
						north of the court house, in Vigo County, he built the Fort named in his honor. About
						one year later, September 4, 1812, this Fort was commanded by Captain Zachary Taylor,
						who had about fifty men under his command, less than a score of whom were available for
						military duty, the others having been incapacitated by sickness. Some citizens and their
						families who had sought refuge in the Fort aided in the defense. The Indians fought with
						all their savage fury. All facts go to show the attacking Indians were an adjunct to the
						British plan to exterminate Fort Harrison. Captain Taylor's conduct on that trying night
						was characteristic of his entire life-he superintended every detail of the defense. His
						heroic conduct won for him the rank and title of Major by brevet, an unusual thing in
						Indian warfare. Peaceable settlement could now go forward. English hope of an internal
						empire in any part of what is now the United States seemed more and more remote, a very
						significant victory for a young man not yet twenty-eight years old. Today the Northwest
						Territory, much of which was made accessible by Captain Taylor's achievement, contains
						more than eighteen millions of people, about one-fifth of the population of the United
						States.</p>


					<pb id="VAC1322-028" n="25"/>

					<p>At the close of the War of 1812, Congress ordered the National standing army reduced to
						ten thousand men, and as a consequence Captain Taylor was reduced in rank, but rather
						than submit to the humiliation in the face of the service he had rendered, he resigned
						without comment or complaint, returned to his Kentucky farm "to make a crop of corn."
						Without any effort on his part he was restored to the army with the rank of
						Lieutenant-Colonel of the First Regiment of Infantry.</p>
					<p>During the next twenty-four years Captain Taylor was engaged in defending frontier
						settlements against the encroachments of the Indians. Black Hawk, Chief of the Sacs and
						Foxes, was his chief adversary. It was during the northwestern campaign that an episode
						in the story of Captain Taylor changes the scene from English conspiracies and savage
						conquests to the more peaceful pursuit of that prince of archers, Master Cupid. This
						dauntless sprite had enlisted with a young officer, Captain Davis, later known as
						Jefferson Davis, President of the Southern Confederacy. Captain Davis disappeared and
						with him had gone Miss Sarah Taylor, daughter of Colonel Taylor. Captain Davis resigned
						immediately from the army, and became a cotton planter in Mississippi, served with
						distinction in the Mexican War, and later wrote the biography of General Taylor in which
						he refers to his own elopement, saying "Sarah, the oldest daughter of General Taylor,
						became the wife of Jefferson Davis."</p>
					<p>Colonel Taylor continued in the northwest until 1836, when repeated depredations of the
						Indians in Florida and on the Gulf coast required a man of his caliber to restore order
						and safety to the settlers from the ferocity of the Seminoles. He was now fifty-two
						years old. He had had a quarter of a century of successful experience with the Indians.
						In a decisive battle at Okechobee he won the title of Brigadier-General by brevet, and
						was appointed to the chief command in Florida.</p>
					<p>The trouble between the United States and Mexico on account of the annexation of Texas
						brought General Taylor again to a conspicuous place, but the story of his achievements
						in the war which followed constitutes a volume too great in proportion for this sketch.
						His success in the Mexican War was the culmination of a great military career-a hero's
						part in a foreign war that added an empire to our National dominions and made of him a
						popular idol of national dimensions. He had been respected, honored and trusted by every
						President, beginning with Jefferson and ending with Polk, a period of nearly forty
						years. General Taylor's hope of retirement to the quiet and peaceful walks of a farmer's
						life was rudely shocked by his election to the presidency of the United States by the
						Whigs in 1848. He was President but sixteen months, though in that brief period he is
						said to have fully comprehended the nation's perils and by his sturdiness, sagacity and
						devotion to the Union, <pb id="VAC1322-029" n="26"/> postponed the Civil War for ten
						years. The brevity of his term as President forbids a conclusive opinion of his ability
						as an executive officer administering civil affairs. He was candid and straightforward
						in his methods. His state papers show models of pure forcible English and undoubted
						honesty of purpose. He urged the building of an isthmian canal; he ordered the
						preliminary surveyal for the railroad to the Pacific Ocean; he urged the establishment
						of the Department of Agriculture to promote the productive resources of the country, and
						favored many other progressive measures.</p>
					<p>General Taylor's successes were due to his simplicity of character, his moral courage,
						his exalted patriotism, moderation in the exercise of power, justice, magnanimity,
						benevolence, his wisdom.</p>
					<p>He died July 9, 1850, in the full consciousness of "having always done his duty." His
						death was probably due to the effect of excessive heat while attending the exercises of
						the laying of the corner-stone of the Washington monument. His remains are buried on the
						old Taylor farm, now within the City of Louisville, Ky.</p>
				</div2>



				<pb id="VAC1322-030" n="27"/>
				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER V.<lb/> COMMANDANTS AT FORT HARRISON<lb/> BY J. T.
						SCOVELL.</head>
					<p>LIEUTENANT COLONEL JAMES MILLER was in command from October 31 to November 14 while the
						army was on the Tippecanoe campaign.</p>
					<p>CAPTAIN JOSIAH SNELLING, of the Fourth Regiment of the United States Infantry. He was
						in command from November 14, 1811, to some time in June, 1812. He was promoted to
						Colonel of the Fifth Infantry, June 2, 1819. Fort Snelling, Minn., is named for him.</p>
					<p>CAPTAIN ZACHARY TAYLOR, of the Seventh Regiment of the United States Infantry. Captain
						Taylor was in command from some time in June, 1812, to September 16, but we find no date
						of appointment or transfer. He defended Fort Harrison September 4 and 5, 1812. He
						afterward became General Taylor, "Old Rough and Ready," of the Mexican War, and later
						President of the United States.</p>
					<p>It is known that MAJOR WILLOUGHBY DMORGAN was in command of the Fort December, 1815.
						When he succeeded Captain Taylor or whether there was another officer between them is
						not known. In about May, 1816, he was ordered to other duty by General Jackson, then
						Commander-in-Chief of the Army, and left Major John T. Chunn in command of the Fort. It
						is said that he rebuilt the Fort.</p>
					<p>MAJOR JOHN T. CHUNN having reported to Major-General Arthur McComb, Commandant of the
						Department at Detroit, the departure of Major Morgan, General McComb issued an order May
						10, 1816, transferring Major Chunn from Fort Knox, and placing him in command at Fort
						Harrison. This order instructed Major Chunn to remove government property from Fort Knox
						to Fort Harrison. This apparently was the end of Fort Knox as a government post. Major
						Chunn had helped to build the Fort at the time of the Harrison campaign to Tippecanoe.
						He was then a Lieutenant in one of the companies of that army. He was appointed Captain
						of the Nineteenth Regiment of the U. S. Infantry, April 14, 1812. He was transferred to
						the Third Regiment on May 17, 1815. He resigned from the army June 12, 1821, after a
						long and honorable service. He returned to Terre Haute to spend the rest of his life,
						and leave a long list of descendants to honor his name.</p>



					<pb id="VAC1322-031" n="28"/>
					<p>There was no trouble with hostile Indians during the time of Major Chunn's command of
						the Fort. But in 1816 there was a scare. Reports came to the Fort of depredations by the
						Indians in Michigan and Northern Indiana, and the Fort was thronged with refugees. An
						autograph letter from Major Chunn to Mr. Gilbert, dated September 8, 1816, indicated
						possible danger, but no attack was made. During the succeeding years, 1817 and 1818,
						1819 and 1820, even after the Fort had been abandoned by the garrison, there were these
						scares about the Indians.</p>
					<p>MAJOR ROBERT STURGIS. Appointed Ensign of the Second Infantry, September 28, 1812.
						Promoted to First Lieutenant March 9, 1814, and resigned February 10, 1818. He had
						served as a volunteer private in Captain Benj. Parks' troop of light dragoons, in the
						Tippecanoe campaign, and so was a builder of Fort Harrison. From many legends, he was so
						interesting a character, 'tis a pity more is not known of his history. He never married.
						He died in Terre Haute about 1828. July 4, 1817, was the first one ever celebrated in
						Terre Haute. The celebration ball was in Henry Redford's new hewn log house, known as
						The Eagle and Lion Tavern. The record says, "Major Chunn with his officers, Lieutenants
						Sturgis and Floyd, Drs. Clark and McCullough, with several other gentlemen with their
						ladies residing at the Fort, were of the happy crowd of celebrants." According to these
						dates, Major Chunn was transferred and Major Sturgis was appointed Commandant after July
						4, 1817. As Major Sturgis resigned from the army February 10, 1818, he was Commandant
						but a few months. He was Treasurer of Vigo County 1823-1824, and Sheriff 1825-1826.
						Probably Fort Harrison ceased to be a military post about the time Major Sturgis
						resigned.</p>
				</div2>







				<pb id="VAC1322-032" n="29"/>
				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER VI.<lb/> INMATES OF FORT HARRISON<lb/> BY J. T.
						Scovell.</head>
					<p>At time of siege, September 4 and 5, 1812, there were in the fort some sixty persons,
						soldiers and citizens. We only know the names of the following:</p>
					<p>Captain Zachary Taylor, Commandant.</p>
					<p>Dr. William A. Clark, Army Surgeon. He was commended by Captain Taylor as acting with
						the greatest firmness 'and presence of mind in defense of the Fort. Dr. Clark also
						practiced among the citizens outside the Fort.</p>
					<p>Drummer Davis, a deserter from the English army, who joined the Americans as ,a
						musician. After the war he lived across the river. Died in 1847.</p>

					<list type="simple" rend="right">
						<item>William Bandy, a Virginian and soldier. Lived in Fayette Township after the
							war.</item>
						<item>William Cowen, who was killed in the fight.</item>
						<item>Josey Cowen, his brother, who died the next day of disease.</item>
						<item>Joseph Dickson and family, wife and children.</item>
						<item>Jonathan Graham and wife. No further notice of Jonathan Graham.</item>
						<item>Isaac Lambert and wife, Julia Lafferty Lambert.</item>
						<item>Mrs. Briggs and her daughter, Mary.</item>
						<item>Mrs. Isaac Anderson and her daughter, Matilda.</item>
						<item>Mary Dickson and Joseph Dickson, young children of John Dickson, in care of their
							aunt, Julia Lambert.</item>
						<item>Peter Mallory and family, wife and children.</item>
						<item>John Clinton Bradford, a baby about a year old.</item>
					</list>


					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">PIONEERS OF THE WABASH VALLEY<lb/></head>
						<p>Joseph Liston, who helped to build the Fort, writes that Isaac Lambert, John Dickson,
							Mr. Hudson, Mr. Chatry and Mr. Mallory cultivated the lands under the protection of
							the Fort. Mr. Hudson and Mr. Chatry may have been in the Fort, but we find no evidence
							of it. One report says that John Dickson and family were in the Fort September 4,
							1812, but a reliable family history shows that Mr. Dickson and wife were in Vincennes
							September 4, 1812. In his report, Captain Taylor speaks of <pb id="VAC1322-033" n="30"
							/> "nine women and children, a part citizens' and part soldiers' wives, who had taken
							shelter in the Fort." The above list contains the names of six women, one a soldier's
							wife, and there are the names of several children.</p>
						<p>Joseph Dickson came to Indiana in 1811 and cultivated lands under the protection of
							the Fort. Joseph Dickson and family were in Fort Harrison September 4 and 5, 1812, and
							helped in the defense. Joseph Dickson, a son, and another man, were killed by the
							Indians as they were returning to the Fort. The daughters of Joseph Dickson were
							Margaret Dickson Handy, Elizabeth Dickson McFadden, Nancy Dickson Lee, Mary Dickson
							Clarke, and Hannah Dickson Harris.</p>
						<list type="simple" rend="right">
							<item>Margaret Dickson married Stephen D. Handy at the Fort in 1813.</item>
							<item>Eliza Handy, daughter of Margaret, married Samuel Archer.</item>
							<item>Orinthia Archer, daughter of Eliza, married Alexander McGregor.</item>
							<item>Alexander Archer McGregor is the only child.</item>
							<item>Isadora Archer, daughter of Eliza, married Jacob White in 1867.</item>
							<item>The children are Cecil Duleny White, Eliza White Bartholomew, Charles Archer
								White and Effie Aileen White Davison.</item>
							<item>Sarah Handy, daughter of Margaret Dickson Handy, married James Lawrence, father
								of Edward E. Lawrence, Terre Haute.</item>
						</list>
						<p>John Dickson came to Vigo County some time in 1811, and may have helped to build the
							Fort. John Dickson had a contract to supply beef and other materials to the garrison
							in the Fort. Goods belonging to him were burned in the block-house September 4, 1812.
							John Dickson lived in the Fort, but September 4, when the Fort was attacked he and his
							wife, Elizabeth Lambert Dickson, were in Vincennes, but two of their children, Mary
							and Joseph, were in the Fort at the time of the siege under the care of their aunt,
							Julia Lambert. Rebecca Dickson was born March 23, 1813, at Vincennes, and John Wesley
							Dickson was born June, 1815, at Fort Harrison. Rebecca Dickson married William Durham,
							son of Daniel Durham. Their daughter, Harriet Durham, married Samuel Royse in 1875.
							Samuel Royse was Auditor of Vigo County from 1870 to 1878. There are four children:
							Samuel, William, Martha and Anna.</p>
						<p>Isaac Lambert came to the region in 1811 and cultivated lands under the protection of
							the Fort. Isaac Lambert and family were in the Fort September 4, 1812, and helped in
							the defense. Mrs. Julia Lambert was a sister of James Lafferty, and aunt of Aquilla
							Lafferty. Isaac Lambert and his brother-in-law, John Dickson, built Lambert &amp;
							Dickson's mill on Honey Creek. Isaac Lambert was a member of the first Board of
							Commissioners of Vigo County. Julia Lambert helped to settle the estate of Isaac
							Lambert in 1829 and 1830.</p>



						<pb id="VAC1322-034" n="31"/>

						<p>Matilda Anderson, daughter of Isaac Anderson, was born at Fort Knox June 7, 1804.
							Isaac Anderson belonged to the army, and was mail carrier between Fort Knox and St.
							Louis. Isaac Anderson was an Orderly Sergeant in General Harrison's army. When Matilda
							was eight years old, Mr. Anderson moved his family to Fort Harrison, so that Mrs.
							Anderson and Matilda Anderson were in the Fort at the time of the siege. After the
							siege, Matilda became acquainted with an Indian who claimed that he set fire to the
							block-house. He said he filled a camp kettle with bark and soaked it with bear's
							grease, put it in a hole under the block-house and set fire to it. In 1824, Matilda
							Anderson married William Taylor. Caroline Taylor, daughter of Matilda and William
							Taylor, was born in September, 1831, and in September, 1850, married Isaac Ball. Mr.
							Ball was an undertaker, a prominent and much respected citizen. Isaac Ball and
							Caroline Ball are survived by two children, Mrs. Matilda E. Ball Hess and Frank H.
							Ball, who reside in Terre Haute.</p>
						<p>Peter Mallory came to this region in 1811, and probably helped to build the Fort. He
							was in Vincennes when Governor Harrison and Tecumseh had a conference during which the
							Indians sprang to their feet threatening attack. Mr. Mallory cultivated lands under
							the protection of the Fort, sometimes plowing with his loaded gun strapped to his back
							in anticipation of an attack from Indians. Mr. Mallory and wife were in the Fort at
							the time of the siege September 4 and 5, and helped in the work of putting out the
							fire and in defending the Fort. Peter Mallory was one of the messengers from Captain
							Taylor to General Harrison at Vincennes after the siege.</p>
						<p>Dr. Thomas Bradford was an Army Surgeon under General Harrison. His son, John Clinton
							Bradford, was in Fort Harrison September 4, 1812. John Clinton Bradford and wife, Mary
							Bradford, owned land in the southeast part of Lost Creek Township. They had two
							daughters: Jane Bradford Coffman and Mary Bradford Brannon. Amelia Brannon, daughter
							of Mary, married Daniel B. Joice. They live in Terre Haute. Josephine Brannon,
							daughter of Mary, married George Stump. Mrs. Stump lives in Terre Haute.</p>
						<p>Mary Briggs and another girl molded bullets in Fort Harrison September 4, 1812. Mary
							Briggs married George Wright. There was one son, William Wright, who had three sons.
							George Wright, Terre Haute; Lincoln Wright, Clinton, Ind., and Charles Wright, New
							Goshen, Ind.</p>
						<p>Joseph Liston came to what is now Vigo County in 1811. He was in company with Edmond
							Liston, his father, Reuben Moore, his <pb id="VAC1322-035" n="32"/> brother-in-law,
							William E. Adams, Martin Adams and William Drake. They planted, cultivated and
							harvested seventy-five acres of corn and sold the corn to General Harrison for use of
							the army while they were building the Fort. Liston and perhaps others of his company
							were militia soldiers. The location of the corn field, the location chosen for the
							Fort and the time of the army movement look very much as if General Harrison had
							planned the whole thing several months before. Joseph Liston was a scout. He was
							famous for his skill in getting knowledge of the movements of the Indians, and thus
							preventing the destruction of the property and loss of life. It was the boast of the
							old man that he had never taken a human life. Joseph helped to build the Fort, but did
							not go to Tippecanoe and was not in the Fort September 4 and 5, 1812.</p>
						<p>Some descendants of Joseph Liston by his first wife: Thomas Liston, of Clay County.
							Gilbert Liston, son of Thomas, lives near Lewis, Ind. Mary Liston, a daughter of
							Thomas, married Moses Pierson. Mary and Moses Pierson had two sons, Moses and Isaac T.
							Pierson, and one daughter, Lida, who married Thomas Donham, of Terre Haute. Moses
							Pierson land wife have two sons, Charles and Frank, and one daughter, Mary, who
							married Gustave Willius, Jr. Joseph Liston by his second wife, Louisiana Lloyd, a
							widow, had one son, Henry Clay Liston. A son of Henry Clay Liston, Samuel Liston,
							lives in the southern part of Vigo County.</p>
						<p>There are several Listons in Vigo County, but they seem to be descendants of the
							brothers of Joseph Liston.</p>
						<p>Abraham Markle and Joseph Richardson, of Genesee County, New York, visited Fort
							Harrison in 1815, making the trip on horseback. In 1816 they crossed the mountains to
							Olean on the Allegheny river. There a large boat was built for the accommodation of
							both families, and late in the spring the voyage began. At Pittsburg Mr. Richardson
							left the company for a trip to Washington, the family with Mr. Markle continuing the
							voyage and reaching Fort Harrison July 4, 1816.</p>
						<p>Mrs. Richardson occupied a house near the Fort, but was greatly annoyed by the
							Indians. There was considerable alarm among the whites. There were rumors of war
							dances and other signs of mischief. One night Mrs. Richardson and others went into the
							Fort, as there were signs of an Indian attack. Mrs. Richardson remained in the Fort
							three days, then loaded her family and goods in a boat, and against the advice of the
							commandant and others started for Vincennes, arriving there in safety.</p>


						<pb id="VAC1322-036" n="33"/>

						<p>George Berkely Richardson, a son, became a citizen of Terre Haute. H. S. Richardson,
							his son, is well known in Terre Haute. Sarah Elizabeth Richardson married Edward V.
							Ball, for many years a prominent physician in the city. They had four children:
							Matilda Ball Mancourt, Caroline Ball Cheever, Lawrence S. Ball, of Prairieton, whose
							children are Edward Halsey Ball, Agnes Ball Ogle and Bertram E. Ball, and Mary E. Ball
							Peddle. Her children are Caroline Peddle Ball, wife of Bertram E. Ball, Mary Peddle
							Peckham, Margaret Peddle Bodde, John B. Peddle.</p>
						<p>Curtis Gilbert, then a young man, not quite of age, arrived at Fort Harrison in
							December, 1815. He had visited the settled portions of Western Pennsylvania, Ohio and
							Kentucky, and had spent some months in New Orleans, prospecting for a location. On his
							return up the river to Louisville, Ky., he was so impressed with the stories told him
							of the richness of the Wabash Valley that he immediately went to Vincennes and there
							formed a partnership with Mr. N. B. Bailey, and pushed on to Fort Harrison with a
							stock of goods for trade with the settlers as well as the Indians. He was so well
							pleased with the value of the country that he remained here for sixty-five years,
							until his death.</p>
						<p>As a government licensed trader, he spent some time on the Vermillion river. It was
							to him there in September, 1818, that Major Chunn, Commandant of Fort Harrison, wrote
							of the atrocities of the Indians at Machinac, and the unrestfulness of those in
							Northern Indiana, advising Mr. Gilbert to return to the Fort until the scare was over.
							Major Chunn might have ordered him to come down the river, but he did not consider
							there was any real danger, so gave him the information and left him to act on his own
							judgment.</p>
						<p>He returned some time later and remained at the Fort as trader and postmaster until
							the fall of 1818, when he removed to Terre Haute, where he was the first Clerk,
							Auditor and Recorder of the county, and held the office for twenty-one years.</p>
						<p>His old account books, kept at the Fort, have largely helped the Historical Committee
							in settling locations and dates.</p>
						<p>He was the fifth in direct descent from Jonathan Gilbert, one of the founders of
							Hartford, Conn., in 1635, and was the founder of the Gilbert family of Terre
							Haute.</p>
						<p>Abraham Markle came to Fort Harrison along with the Richardson family in 1816. As a
							soldier in the war of 1812, Mr. Markle had a warrant for several quarter sections of
							land which were located in the vicinity of Fort Harrison. The family settled on Otter
							Creek, where Mr. Markle had a mill built. Abraham Markle and his family have been
							prominent citizens of Terre Haute and Vigo County, but did not have much to do with
							the Fort. Two of the sons were with the father in the <pb id="VAC1322-037" n="34"/>
							war of 1812. One was in the Blackhawk War, and several of the descendants were in the
							Civil War. Major Markle's children were: Sons William, Abraham, Henry, Nelson, George,
							Frederick, Joseph and Napoleon Bonaparte, and daughters Sarah and Aula.</p>
						<p>Nelson Markle had two sons, George and Theodore. Gertrude Markle, daughter of George,
							married Arthur Richmond. Theodore Markle has two sons, Augustus R. and Paul, and two
							daughters, Grace Markle Starr and Florence Markle. Frederick Markle had two sons,
							Abraham and William. William lives in Otter Creek Township, and has two sons, Herbert
							and Daniel, and one daughter, Mabel, who married William Wier.</p>
						<p>James Matthew Stewart was one of the pioneers at Fort Harrison. He came with his
							bride in 1817, and remained a few months. He returned to the Falls of the Ohio where
							he had large contracts as a builder. But as soon as they were completed (1819) he came
							back to Terre Haute to live. Two sons, Colonel Robert R. Stewart and Lieutenant
							Colonel James Stewart, were noted cavalry officers in the Civil War. Another was
							William H. Stewart, a leading and highly honored citizen, Mayor of Terre Haute and
							Sheriff of Vigo County. The family were for years identified by the "Stewart House," a
							noted hostlery.</p>
						<p>Dr. Charles B. Modesitt came to the Fort in 1816. The doctor was a public-spirited
							man of affairs. He was a good doctor, a good business man and a good citizen. His sons
							were James A. Modesitt and Wilton M. Modesitt, and he had one daughter, Frances Anna,
							who married Chauncey Warren. At her death, in 1904, she left surviving her, and who
							now reside in Terre Haute, three daughters, Eliza B. Warren, Clara W., wife of Egbert
							Curtis, Frances Deming Warren, and one son, John Crawford Warren.</p>
						<p>Susan Spencer was in the Fort about 1816 with her uncle, Andrew Brooks. She married
							Andrew Wilkins, who was at one time Sheriff of Vigo County, and at another time Clerk
							of the county. The children were: Emily Wilkins Early, Rachel E. Wilkins, Mary B.
							Wilkins, Lida Wilkins Merrill, John E., William and George D. Wilkins.</p>
						<p>Caleb Crawford and family came to Fort Harrison, May, 1817. One daughter, Ann Mary,
							married David W. Rankin. Their children were Sarah E. Rankin, Morton C. Rankin and
							Oscar Rankin. Another daughter, Emeline, married Henry Fairbanks. Their son, Crawford
							Fairbanks, built the Public Library, and named it for his mother. Caleb Crawford and
							his descendants were not closely related to the Fort, but were under its protecting
							wings as living on the farm at a short distance during the Indian scares of 1817 and
							1818, and have been prominent and valuable citizens of Vigo County.</p>
					</div3>
				</div2>




				<pb id="VAC1322-038" n="35"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER VII.<lb/> THE NORTHWEST TERRITORY<lb/> BY J. T.
						SCOVELL.</head>
					<p>The larger part of North America is a great plain extending from the Gulf of Mexico to
						the Arctic Ocean. On the west are the Rocky mountains. On the east are the Alleghenys
						This great plain is drained by the St. Lawrence and the Great Lakes into the North
						Atlantic; by the Saskatchewan into Hudson Bay; while the southern portion is drained to
						the Gulf by the Mississippi, Ohio and Missouri rivers. The region between the Ohio and
						the Great Lakes and between the Alleghenys and the Mississippi river is called "The
						Northwest Territory.</p>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">EUROPEAN DISCOVERY AND DIVISION.<lb/></head>


						<p>When the Europeans about 1500 discovered North America, the whole country was
							occupied by tribes of savages whom they called Indians. Spain, France and England
							claimed the whole continent by right of discovery. These nations did not consider that
							the Indian had any proprietary rights in this broad domain, in these lands which he
							called home.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">THE CLAIMS OF SPAIN.<lb/></head>
						<p>Spain made the earliest discoveries, the West Indies, the regions bordering on the
							Gulf and on the Carribbean Sea. Spain, at first, was disposed to claim the whole
							continent, but occupied regions along the Gulf and across to the Pacific with
							indefinite northern boundaries. Spain built St. Augustine and held the region for many
							years not for industrial purposes, but as a protection to her commerce with Mexico.
							Spain made no attempt to explore the Mississippi river nor to occupy its valley for
							agricultural purposes, but later treaties show that her claims were recognized as
							extending as far north as the sources of the Mississippi river.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">THE CLAIMS OF FRANCE.<lb/></head>
						<p>France claimed the Valley of the St. Lawrence and the "wilderness world westward and
							southward to its uttermost bounds? The French early discovered the Great Lakes and the
							Ohio and the Mississippi rivers. They established a chain of trading posts and
							missionary stations from <pb id="VAC1322-039" n="36"/> the mouth of the St. Lawrence
							along the Mississippi to the Gulf of Mexico, Detroit, Fort Wayne, Vincennes,
							Kaskaskia, Cahokia, one on Red river, one near Natchez, and another near the site of
							New Orleans. Among the French leaders were Champlain, Joliette, LaSalle and Mar-
							quette. The Fr'ench engaged in the fur trade doing but little agriculture. Thus the
							French were the first Europeans to occupy the Northwest Territory.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">THE CLAIMS OF ENGLAND.<lb/></head>
						<p>The English claimed the regions along the Atlantic coast, south of the St. Lawrence
							valley, and westward from "sea to sea." England made grants to Virginia, New York,
							Massachusetts and Connecticut with such indefinite western boundaries that each
							claimed an interest in the Northwest Territory. English, Dutch, French Huguenots,
							Germans and others settled along the coast regions and engaged in agriculture, built
							towns, established manufacturing industries, engaged in mining, fishing, fur trading
							and other lines of commerce. These people increased rapidly in numbers encroaching
							continually upon the hunting grounds of the Indians, and restricting the fur trade of
							the French. In some cases treaties were made with the Indians and they were paid for
							their interest in the lands, but there was no definite uniform custom in the matter
							and there was continual strife. In the last half of 1600, Dutch and English traders
							began to compete with the French in the fur trade. In 1684 the Iroquois Indians placed
							themselves under the protectorate of King Charles which gave the English some claim to
							the Northwest Territory. During the first half of 1700, many English crossed the
							mountains. In 1754 General Braddock was defeated with great loss of life by the French
							and Indians. In 1758 Colonel Forbes drove the French out of the upper Ohio Valley, and
							in 1759 Quebec was captured by the English under General Wolfe, and the French
							dominion in America was at an -end. By the Treaty of Paris in 1763, the King of France
							ceded to his Britanic Majesty, in full right, Canada and all its dependencies, the
							western boundary to be a line drawn along the middle of the Mississippi river.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">GREAT BRITAIN AND THE INDIANS.<lb/></head>
						<p>The Indians at first did not seem to object to the British supremacy in America. The
							English seemed inclined to treat the Indian about as the French treated him. But
							during the year 1762 Pontiac, an Ottawa Chief, formed a conspiracy involving several
							Indian tribes. They hoped to capture all of the military posts and to drive all the
							white people out of the country. In 1763 these Indians captured Mackinaw, Sandusky,
							Ouiatenon, Fort Miamis, Venango and others, but failed in their attack upon Detroit,
							and they failed at Fort Pitt. A vigorous campaign under General Bradstreet and Colonel
							Boquet broke up the Indian power <pb id="VAC1322-040" n="37"/> so completely that they
							sued for peace and all the tribes interested concluded treaties with the English. For
							several years the Indians were peaceable, "although in the meantime many English
							colonists, disregarding the proclamation of the King, the provisions of treaties and
							the remonstrances of the Indians, continued to harass the Indians by making
							settlements upon their lands." "The fur trader seldom had trouble with the Indian; he
							probably paid a small price for furs and cheated the Indian in other ways, but he did
							not destroy his hunting grounds. The farmer was continually in difficulty. He cut down
							the forests and polluted the streams, destroying both hunting grounds and fishing
							ponds. The British as fur traders were friends; the colonists, the settlers, changing
							forests into corn fields, were not friends.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">CLARK'S CAMPAIGN.<lb/></head>
						<p>During the War of the Revolution, in the summer of 1778, George Rogers Clark, a
							Virginian, with an army of Virginians, captured and occupied the British posts of
							Kaskaskia, Cahokia and Vincennes. The success of the expedition was largely due to the
							active co-operation of the French priest, Father Gibault. The people living about
							these posts were chiefly of French descent. Father Gibault explained the situation to
							these people and they transferred their allegiance to Virginia with scarcely a murmur.
							Later, Francis Vigo, a "Spanish Merchant" of St. Louis, saved the expedition from
							probable failure by advancing money to pay the expenses of the army. At the close of
							the war with Great Britain by the treaty of peace concluded at Paris in 1783, "His
							Britanic Majesty acknowledges the United States to be free and independent states and
							relinquishes all claims to the government, propriety and territorial rights of the
							same and every part thereof." The territory mentioned being south of the St. Lawrence
							and the Great Lakes and east of the middle of the Mississippi river, excepting
							Florida. Spain preferred claims to portions of this territory, and objected to the
							Mississippi boundary, and France also objected to that boundary, but both finally
							waived their objections and signed the treaty. Thus all the title and all the claims
							of European countries to the Northwest Territory were vested in the United States.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">COLONIAL CLAIMS.<lb/></head>
						<p>The close of the war found the United States deeply in debt with no prospective
							resource except as might be derived from the sale of public lands. The title to the
							lands in the Northwest Territory was not quite clear. The cession of lands by Great
							Britain had been to the United States as a nation. Virginia, New York, Massachusetts
							and Connecticut <pb id="VAC1322-041" n="38"/> had valid claims to the lands in the
							Northwest Territory. By an Act of Congress passed September 6, 1780, the States
							preferring claims to lands in the Northwest Territory were recommended to cede their
							claims to the General Government for the good of the Union. In accordance with this
							suggestion, New York in 1781, Virginia in 1784, Massachusetts in 1785, and Connecticut
							in 1786, ceded their claims to lands in the Northwest Territory to the General
							Government, Virginia and Connecticut making some minor reservations.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">ACQUIRING THE INDIAN TITLE.<lb/></head>
						<p>Immediately after the conclusion of the treaty with Great Britain, Congress undertook
							measures for acquiring the Indian title to the lands in the Northwest Territory. At
							Fort Stanwix October 22, 1784, the Iroquois, or the Six Nations, yielded to the United
							States all claims to the territory west of a line running from Johnson's Landing,
							about four miles east of Niagara river, southerly to the Ohio river in the extreme
							western part of Pennsylvania. On January 21, 1785, the United States concluded a
							treaty with the Delaware, Wyandot, Chippewa and Ottawa Indian tribes by which lands in
							Ohio east of the Cuyahoga and Muskingum rivers were ceded to the United States. The
							territory northwest of the Ohio river was organized in 1787, and General Arthur St.
							Clair was appointed Governor and Minister of Indian Affairs.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">THE ORDINANCE OF 1787.<lb/></head>
						<p>The Ordinance of 1787 for the government of the Northwest Territory, guarantees
							religious liberty, the benefit of the writ of habeas corpus and of the trial by jury.
							Article 3 is as follows: "Religion, morality and knowledge being necessary to good
							government and the happiness of mankind, schools and the means of education shall
							forever be encouraged. The utmost good faith shall always be observed toward the
							Indian; their lands and property shall never be taken from them without their consent,
							and in their property rights and liberty they never shall be invaded or disturbed
							unless in just and lawful wars authorized by Congress; but laws formulated in justice
							and humanity shall from time to time be made for preventing wrongs being done to them
							and for preserving peace and friendship with them." For several years there had been
							desultory warfare between the Indians and the settlers for the most part carried on
							between small parties conducted by irresponsible persons. Such warfare was often
							accompanied by treachery and shocking cruelty on both sides. After the appointment of
							Governor St. Clair, the war assumed a different character as far as the Whites were
							concerned. There was more humanity in the treatment of prisoners and non-combatants,
							and all operations were under the direction of the government.</p>
					</div3>
					<pb id="VAC1322-042" n="39"/>
					<figure>
						<p>INDIANA IN 1811</p>
					</figure>
					<figure>
						<p>GENERAL HARRISON'S LINE OF MARCH FROM VINCENNES TO PROPHET'S TOWN IN 1811 Chart
							prepared by Prof. W. D. Pence of Purdue University</p>
					</figure>
					<pb id="VAC1322-043" n="[]"/>
					<pb id="VAC1322-044" n="41"/>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">GENERAL WAYNE AND THE GREENVILLE TREATY.</head>
						<p>All efforts of Governor St. Clair to make peace with the Indians failed. The military
							expeditions sent out against the Indians were failures or disasters, so that in 1794
							Indian affairs were in a very critical condition. On August 20, 1794, General Wayne
							near the Falls of the Maumee defeated the Indians. He says: "The enemy were routed
							from their position and driven more than two miles through the woods. The savage
							hordes with their British and Canadian allies abandoned themselves to flight and
							dispersed with terror and dismay, leaving our victorious army in full and quiet
							possession of the field of battle." General Wayne returned to Greenville for the
							winter. During the winter, parties of Indians from several different tribes visited
							General Wayne and signed preliminary articles of peace.</p>
						<p>At Greenville, August 3, 1795, General Wayne concluded a treaty of peace with the
							Wyandots, Ottawas, Chippewas, Sacs, Eel Rivers, Kaskaskias, Kickapoos, Pottawattomies,
							Weas, Miamis and Shawnees by which old boundary lines, including all of what is now
							Ohio, were confirmed, and for "the same considerations, and as an evidence of
							returning friendship, and to provide for that convenient intercourse which will be
							beneficial to both parties, the said Indian tribes do also cede to the United States
							certain pieces of land, to-wit, one piece six miles square at the old Wea towns on the
							Wabash, and fourteen other pieces of land in the Northwest Territory. The Indians also
							release the lands granted to General Clark, and the lands in other places in
							possession of the French people, or others, of which the Indian title has been
							extinguished. Considerations. And for the same considerations and with the views above
							mentioned, the United States now deliver to the said Indian tribes a quantity of goods
							to the value of $20,000, the receipt whereof they do hereby acknowledge and
							thenceforward every year forever, the United States will deliver at some convenient
							place, northward of the Ohio, like useful goods to the value of $9,500, reckoning that
							value as the first cost of the goods. Mutual concessions. And the said Indian tribes
							will allow the people of the United States free passage by land or water through their
							country. And the said Indian tribes shall be at liberty to hunt within the territory
							which they have now ceded to the United States.</p>
						<p>This treaty was signed by several Indians from each tribe, by General Wayne and
							General Harrison, and several other army officers and by several sworn
							interpreters.</p>
						<p>From this time, 1795 to 1810, the United States maintained pacific relations with the
							Indian tribes that were parties to the Greenville treaty.</p>
					</div3>
					<pb id="VAC1322-045" n="42"/>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">INDIANA TERRITORY ORGANIZED.</head>
						<p>Indiana Territory was organized in 1800 and May 13, 1800, William Henry Harrison was
							appointed Governor. The United States "authorized Governor Harrison to promote peace
							and harmony among the different tribes of the Northwestern Indians and to induce them,
							if possible, to abandon their modes of living, and to engage in the practice of
							agriculture and other pursuits of civilized life." The Governor was also authorized to
							negotiate treaties for the purpose of extinguishing the Indian title to lands within
							the boundaries of the territory.</p>
						<p>The principal subjects which attracted the attention of the people of Indiana were
							the purchase of Indian lands, the adjustment of land titles, and the hostile
							proceedings of Tecumseh and his brother, the Prophet.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">INDIAN TREATIES.</head>
						<p>Treaties for land in Indiana along the Ohio river as far west as the Wabash and up
							the Wabash to a point above Vincennes were made with the Delaware, Pottawattomies,
							Miamis, Eel River, Wea and other tribes who at the time were recognized as having
							title. These treaties seem to have been made in good faith and were signed by the
							Indians after full consideration and discussion. But the consideration paid, including
							the initial payment and the annuities, seem small and inadequate, at least for
							agricultural lands. Considered as hunting grounds, the price seems inadequate. The
							lands certainly were worth more to the world, but were they worth more to the Indian
							than the United States paid him for them Did the colonists and the speculators who
							obtained grants from England pay more than the United States paid the Indians ? The
							prices though small, must have been about what public sentiment considered fair.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">OPPOSITION TO INDIAN TREATIES.</head>
						<p>August 21, 1805, a treaty was made which conveyed to the United States certain lands
							along the Ohio river. Some Indians, as Tecumseh and his brother, the Prophet, and
							others, began to realize something of the value of the land for agriculture, and tried
							to hinder the making of treaties, claiming that the Indians were being robbed. This
							idea was encouraged by certain speculators who opposed the government policy of making
							treaties for the Indian title, as it prevented them from buying direct from the
							Indian. Then it is well known that British emissaries were trying to make trouble
							between the Indians and the United States. This opposition was strong, and for several
							years no treaties were made.</p>
					</div3>
					<pb id="VAC1322-046" n="43"/>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">TREATY OF FORT WAYNE, 1809.</head>
						<p>But September 30, 1809, at Fort Wayne, General Harrison, in spite of the opposition,
							was able to conclude a treaty with the chiefs and head men of the Delaware, Miami, Eel
							River, Wea and Kickapoo tribes, by which about 2,900,000 acres of land, southeast of
							the Wabash below the mouth of Raccoon Creek, were sold .and ceded to the United
							States. And December 9, 1809, the Kickapoos ceded to the United States about 113,000
							acres of land lying west of the Wabash river and below the Vermillion river, being
							about twelve miles wide along the Wabash. The northeastern boundary of this Fort Wayne
							cession of 1809 runs from northwest to southeast, and is called the ten o'clock line,
							as it runs toward the sun at ten o'clock. Why was the line run in that direction?</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">GENERAL HARRISON's LETTER.</head>
						<p>General Harrison writes: "I was extremely anxious that the cession should extend to
							this river (the Vermillion) by the Treaty of Fort Wayne, but there was objection
							because it would include a Kickapoo village. This small tract of land, about twenty
							miles square, is one of the most beautiful that can be conceived, and is moreover
							believed to contain a rich copper mine. I have myself frequently seen specimens of the
							copper, one of which I sent Mr. Jefferson in 1802." The letter was dated at Vincennes,
							December 10, 1809. This letter seems to explain the ten o'clock line. It included more
							of the beautiful country that contained a rich copper mine than an east-west line
							would include.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">TECUMSEH AND THE PROPHET.</head>
						<p>Tecumseh and his brother continued their opposition to the making of treaties for the
							disposal of Indian lands. In fact they were more active after the treaty made in 1809.
							August, 1810, in a conference with General Harrison, Tecumseh intimated that he would
							resist any attempt to survey the lands ceded to the United States by the Treaty of
							Fort Wayne. Tecumseh claimed that the lands belonged to the Indians as a nation, not
							as individual tribes. In fact each tribe had special rights in some territory which
							Tecumseh and his brother had to recognize. Tecumseh and his brother were Shawnees.
							They were crowded out of Delaware towns on the White river to Greenville in Ohio. The
							people in that region desired them to move on, and by permission of the Pottowattomies
							and Kickapoos, they settled on the Wabash near the mouth of the River Tippecanoe.</p>
						<p>The new settlement was called Prophets Town.</p>
					</div3>

					<pb id="VAC1322-047" n="44"/>

					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">GENERAL HARRISON AND TECUMSEH.</head>
						<p>There were many, both Indians and Whites, who denounced Tecumseh and the Prophet and
							their followers as enemies of the United States. The General at length came to regard
							Tecumseh and his brother as dangerous persons who, having received some encouragement
							from the British, were endeavoring to form a confederacy of Indian tribes which in the
							event of war between the United States and Great Britain, would become allies of Great
							Britain. Tecumseh and the Prophet did not have supreme power over the Indians. At a
							conference of Indian tribes in May, 1810, Winamac, a Pottawattomie Chief, and some
							Delawares op-= posed the Prophet, and prevented the Ottawas, Pottawattomies and
							Chippewas from placing themselves under the control of the Prophet. At this time
							Winamac and others estimated the warriors following the Prophet at about 650, made up
							mainly of restless bands from several different Indian tribes, but not the leading men
							of any of the tribes. On one occasion the Prophet declared, "That it was not his
							intention to make war on the Whites, that some of the Delawares and others had been
							bribed to make false charges against him. Tecumseh was haughty, claimed that the land
							was sold by only a few of the members of the tribes and that the Fort Wayne Treaty was
							made through the threat of Winamac. Tecumseh threatened the Chiefs who sold the lands,
							and said to General Harrison, "If you do not restore the lands you will have a hand in
							killing them." About the 1st of August, 1811, Tecumseh with a few followers went south
							for conference with southern tribes.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">TREATMENT OF INDIANS BY THE WHITES.</head>
						<p>In a message in 1806 Governor Harrison said, "The Indians will never have recourse to
							arms unless driven to it by injustice and oppression. Of this they already begin to
							complain, and I am sorry to say that their complaints are far from being groundless.
							The laws of the territory provide the same punishment for offenses committed against
							the Indians as against White men. Experience shows that there is a wide difference in
							the execution of those laws. The Indian always suffers and the White man never. This
							partiality has not escaped their notice. Every regulation which would promise more
							impartiality in the execution of the laws in favor of those unhappy people will be
							highly acceptable to the United States and honorable to yourselves. I pray you lose no
							opportunity of inculcating among your constituents an abhorrence of that detestable
							doctrine which would make a distinction of guilt between the murder of a White man and
							an Indian. The principal matters of which the Indian complained were: The
							encroachments of the White people upon the lands which belonged to the Indians; the
							invasion of their hunting grounds and the unjustifiable killing of some of their
							people. <pb id="VAC1322-048" n="[]"/>
							<figure>
								<p>WILLIAM HENRY HARRISON</p>
							</figure>
							<pb id="VAC1322-049" n="[]"/>
							<pb id="VAC1322-050" n="45"/> These complaints were not groundless, but neither the
							laws of the United States nor those of Indiana Territory were sufficiently strong to
							prevent the evil conduct of a few bad White men."</p>
						<p>Subsequent events and later dealings with the Indians apparently convinced General
							Harrison that he was in error regarding the traits of the savages.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">THE TIPPECANOE CAMPAIGN.<lb/></head>
						<head rend="i center">Preparations for War.</head>

						<p>July 31, 1811, at a meeting of the citizens of Vincennes and vicinity, a petition was
							made to the President for protection from the depredations of the Indians. The
							President fully informed as to Indian affairs in Indiana Territory, had, earlier in
							the season, authorized the Governor to call out the militia and at his discretion to
							call into service the Fourth Regiment of the United States Infantry under the command
							of Colonel John P. Boyd. The General was instructed to preserve pacific relations with
							the Northwestern Indians by the use of all means consistent with the protection of the
							citizens of the territory and the maintenance of the rights of the General Government.
							Governor Harrison having determined to erect a new fort on the Wabash river, and to
							break up the assemblage of hostile Indians at Prophets Town, ordered Colonel Boyd's
							regiment of infantry to move from the Falls of the Ohio to Vincennes, at which place
							the regulars were to be reinforced by militia.</p>
					</div3>


					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="i center">Calling Out the Militia.</head>
						<p>About the 1st of September, according to Mr. William Naylor, "General Harrison sent a
							requisition to Colonel Joseph Bartholemew to raise three companies of militia and one
							troop of horse and equip them according to law and to march to Vincennes.</p>
						<p>Colonel Bartholomew mustered the companies into service September 10, 1811, equipped
							with ten days' rations in their knapsacks, weighing about thirty-five pounds exclusive
							of arms and accoutrements. This command consisted of Captain Biggers' volunteer
							company of riflemen from Clark County, Captain Spencer's company of mounted riflemen
							from Harrison County, Captain John Norris' company of infantry, and Captain Beggs'
							troop of horse. This detachment reached Vincennes September 20, 1811. John T. Chunn
							was Lieutenant in Captain Biggers' company, and Mr. William Naylor was a private. The
							militia from the vicinity of Vincennes were under the command of Lieutenant Colonel
							Luke Decker. The command consisted of Captain Warrick's company, infantry, Captain
							Hargrove's company, infantry, Captain Scott's company, infantry, Captain Wilson's
							company, infantry, Captain Wilkins' company, infantry, and a troop of horse commanded
							by Captain Parke.</p>
					</div3>



					<pb id="VAC1322-051" n="46"/>

					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center i">The Regulars.</head>
						<p>The Fourth Regiment, United States Infantry, consisted of Captain Josiah Snelling's
							company, Captain George Prescott's company, Captain William C. Bean's company, Captain
							Joel Cook's company, Captain R. B. Brown's company, Captain Robert C. Barton's
							company, a company commanded by Lieutenant Charles Fuller and a company commanded by
							Lieutenant O. G. Burton.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center i">The Organization of the Army.</head>
						<p>The army was organized as follows: "The infantry, both the regulars and the State
							militia, are to form one brigade under the command of Colonel John P. Boyd as
							Brigadier General. Lieutenant Colonel Miller will command the first line composed of
							all the regular infantry, and Lieutenant Colonel Bartholomew will command the second
							line composed of the militia infantry. These two officers will report to and receive
							orders from Colonel John P. Boyd, Joseph Hamilton Daviest from Kentucky, is appointed
							and commissioned Major of Dragoons in the militia and to command the whole of the
							cavalry. Major Daviess will receive orders from the Commander-in-Chief. Captain Spier
							Spencer's company of mounted volunteers will act as a detached corps. Captain Spencer
							is to receive orders from the Commander-in-Chief." Captain Robert Buntin was appointed
							Quarter-master for the militia. The time from September 21st to September 26th was
							spent in drilling the men and in making other preparations for the campaign. September
							26, 1811, the army moved northward, encamping October 3rd on the east bank of the
							Wabash river, about two and one-half miles north of the site of Terre Haute.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center i">Fort Harrison.</head>
						<p>The Fort was to be a storehouse of supplies for the army and a protection in case of
							a defeat or disaster in the campaign. The site selected was the point nearest the
							Indian boundary that was suitable for a fort. It was on a sharp eastward bend of the
							river so that there was a good view both up and down stream. The land rises
							twenty-five to thirty feet above low water and was covered with light forest of oak,
							honey locust and others, which furnished the timber used in building the fort. The
							fort was about 150 feet square. The west side consisted of a two-story block-house
							about twenty feet square at each corner with barracks between. These were stoutly
							built log houses with shed roofs, the upper stories of the block-houses projecting
							beyond the lower so that the outside of the three walls of the fort could be seen from
							the block-houses. The guard house on the north was a log house. The balance of the
							structure <pb id="VAC1322-052" n="47"/> including the bastions on the east, were of
							palisades in a trench about four feet deep. The gate was on the east. The fort was
							finished October 23, 1811. Soon afterward the army was called out and Major Joseph
							Hamilton Daviess, after a little speech, broke a bottle of spirits on the gate and
							named the structure Fort Harrison.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center i">Lack of Supplies and Threatened Mutiny.</head>
						<p>The first crop of corn raised in Vigo County was used to feed the army while building
							the fort. Joseph Liston, who helped cultivate the crop, was a soldier, and it is
							supposed that Liston and his companies were sent out by General Harrison to raise corn
							for the army. Other supplies were shipped by the river. "The water was low; the boats
							were delayed; the men were on short rations, and many of them were ready to turn back
							toward Vincennes. General Harrison called them together, made a little speech,
							explaining the situation, and said that no more flour and beef should be used in his
							tent than was assigned to a common soldier. He then made an appeal to the army and
							said if any company or individual wanted to go home they could have the privilege. He
							then said all that were willing to bear the privations of the army and want of
							provisions and go to the Prophet's town would manifest it by raising their firearms or
							swords. There was not one down in the whole army, and there was not a murmur heard in
							the camp afterwards."</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center i">Appeal to Kentucky.</head>
						<p>General Harrison appealed to Kentucky for volunteers as they were interested in
							breaking up the power of the hostile Indians. While building the fort Captain Fred
							Guiger's company of mounted riflemen of the Kentucky militia and Peter Funk's company
							of mounted Kentucky militia joined the army. The new fort was garrisoned by a small
							company of men under Lieutenant Colonel James Miller. A number of these men were
							invalids. October 29, 1811, the army took up its march toward Prophets Town, the boats
							having ,arrived with the belated supplies.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center i">March to Fort Boyd.</head>
						<p>October 31st, the army crossed the Wabash at a point about three miles below the
							mouth of the Big Vermillion river. Prophets Town was west of the river; the route east
							of the river was shorter, but mostly through forests; the route west of the river was
							longer, but mostly through prairie, less danger of ambuscade. It was considered safer
							to cross near the mouth of the Vermillion with the aid of boats than near Prophets
							Town in the face of the enemy. Near the mouth of the Vermillion they built a
							block-house twenty-five feet square, and called it Fort <pb id="VAC1322-053" n="48"/>
							Boyd. Here a Sergeant and eight men were left as guard of boats and supplies. "From
							Fort Boyd General Harrison detailed twelve men, including William Bruce of Captain
							Dubois' company, to return to Vincennes for the purpose of keeping the militia alert,
							and to keep up a daily patrol between Vincennes and White river, to prevent the
							Indians from making incursions against the settlers in the rear of the army." This
							account was written by William Bruce. On November 3rd the army resumed its march up
							the river. They waded the Vermillion and other streams. It was cold, sometimes below
							freezing. The roads were bad, in some places dangerous, but no Indians were seen until
							November 6th, when they reached the vicinity of Prophets Town. General Harrison was
							urged to attack at once, but he finally turned aside and camped in order of battle for
							the night. Toward morning the Indians attacked the camp with great vigor, but they
							were defeated and driven away. The loss of life was heavy on both sides and many were
							wounded. The Indian town was burned, the dead were buried, and November 9th the re-
							turn march was begun. Fort Harrison was reached November 13th without special
							incident. Leaving Captain Snelling with his company of regulars at Fort Harrison the
							army continued its march southward.</p>
					</div3>


					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center i">General Harrison's Farewell Speech.</head>

						<p>At Shakers Town the General made a speech eulogizing the dead and praising the
							bravery and soldierly conduct of the living. The General said: "The larger part of the
							troops had never been in action, and yet they behaved in a manner that can never be
							too much applauded." General Harrison speaks highly of the officers and men of the
							Fourth Regiment and of Posey's company of the Seventh Regiment, commanded by
							Lieutenant Jacob W. Albright of the First Infantry. In short they supported the fame
							of American regulars. The General also says,"that several of the militia companies
							were in no wise inferior to the regulars. He mentions specially Spencer's, Warrick's,
							Guiger's and Robb's companies, and calls attention to their heavy losses. And that
							Wilson's and Scott's companies charged with the regular troops and proved themselves
							worthy of doing so. Norris' company behaved well. Hargrove's and Wilkins' companies
							had no opportunity of distinguishing themselves or I am satisfied they would have done
							so."</p>
					</div3>

					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center i">Some Results of the Campaign.</head>
						<p>Dillon says that among the immediate results of the Tippecanoe expedition were the
							breaking up of the Indian settlements at Prophets Town, the destruction of the
							Prophet's influence among the northwestern Indian tribes, the defeat of the plans of
							Tecumseh, and a temporary relief to the frontier settlements from Indian
							depredations.</p>


						<pb id="VAC1322-054" n="49"/>

						<p>The battle at Tippecanoe was considered a great victory. The adventures incident to
							this campaign furnished fireside talks for many years in both Indiana and Kentucky. It
							became an unwritten law of those days that new counties should be named after some
							hero of Tippecanoe as: Spencer, Tipton, Daviess, White, Parke, Warrick, Dubois,
							Bartholomew, Floyd and Randolph. Many of the men who perished in the campaign were
							volunteers, not on duty as soldiers, but as men, as citizens, who recognized a crisis
							in the affairs of Indiana, a crisis in the affairs of Kentucky, and that duty to
							humanity called them to arms and perhaps to death.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">FORT HARRISON AS A REFUGE FOR SETTLERS.</head>
						<p>Fort Harrison was built as a refuge in case of defeat at Tippecanoe. It served the
							army as a storage for supplies. When the army disbanded Captain Snelling and company
							were left as a protection for the settlers on the frontier. The victory at Tippecanoe
							so crippled the power of the Indians that there was no danger of a large body of
							hostile warriors. But the successes of the British and the Indians at the opening of
							the War of 1812 did encourage a number of small war parties to invade the .Indiana
							settlements, killing stock, burning houses and murdering settlers. Block-houses were
							built on the frontiers, one on the farm of William Bruce, east of Vincennes, large
							enough to protect several families. Sometime during the summer of 1812 Captain Zachary
							Taylor was made Commandant at Fort Harrison with a garrison of fifty men. It was a
							sickly season, and seldom more than one-third of the force were fit for duty. Many
							families moved into the Fort and block-houses, the men going out to do a little
							farming or hunting.</p>
					</div3>

					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">THE SIEGE OF FORT HARRISON AND SUBSEQUENT EVENTS.</head>
						<p>September 3rd, occurred the Pigeon Roost Massacre in which twenty-four persons were
							killed and the same day two men were killed near Fort Harrison. In the afternoon of
							September 4th a body of Indians approached the Fort under a flag of truce, asking for
							a conference regarding provisions. Captain Taylor, suspecting treachery, would not
							treat with them, but made careful preparations to resist an attack by the Indians.
							Beside the garrison there were several citizens in the Fort, as Joseph Dickson, Peter
							Mallory and others, and there were several women and children in the Fort for
							protection. About midnight the attack was made and immediately came the cry of "Fire."
							The southwest block-house containing the stores of the contractor was on fire. The
							citizens and their wives under Dr. Wm. Clark battled with the fire, and the soldiers
							battled with the Indians. Captain Taylor ordered out buckets and soon there were
							buckets of water passing from the well to the fire. By the time the door <pb
								id="VAC1322-055" n="50"/> was broken out the fire had reached a quantity of whiskey
							and there was no hope of saving the block-house. The roof next the barracks was thrown
							off and the barracks kept so wet that the fire did not spread to them. The burning of
							the block-house would make an opening in the walls of the Fort about twenty feet wide.
							When the fire was under control a number of men were put to work building a barricade
							across this opening, and before the fire had cooled down so that persons could pass
							through, a barricade had been completed and the walls of the Fort were again suitable
							for defense. During the fire the women drew the water from the well and the men passed
							it up to the roof. In a short time the water got so low in the well that they could
							not dip the bucket full. Then Julia Lambert said, "Let me down into the well and I
							will fill the buckets." In doing this Julia dipped up so much sand that after a while
							the well was made deeper so that the buckets dipped full again. This was talked of as
							a miracle. It is said that Julia never recovered from the fatigue and exposure in the
							well. After the fire was under control, the women loaded the guns for the men and the
							girls moulded bullets. Soon after the attack, two frightened men jumped over the
							palisade, thinking it safer outside than inside a burning Fort. One was killed in a
							few minutes. After a while the other, severely wounded, crawled back to the shelter of
							the walls of the Fort. The contest was kept up until morning. As it began to get light
							so that the fire from the Fort became more effective, the Indians retired, giving up
							the fight. They drove away the cattle, shot the horses they could not catch, and
							killed a number of hogs. The losses were two killed and two wounded in the Fort, one
							killed and one wounded outside the Fort. Two killed in the field September 3rd and two
							were killed on the 4th as they were coming into the shelter of the Fort. Total loss
							seven killed and three wounded. Nothing is known of the number of Indians engaged in
							the attack and nothing is known about their losses, but they were thought to have been
							small. When news of the attack on Fort Harrison reached Vincennes, about 1,200 men
							under Colonel William Russell, marched to the relief of the Fort. The force consisted
							of Colonel Wilcox's Regiment of Kentucky Volunteers, three companies of rangers under
							Colonel Jordan, and two regiments of Indiana militia under Colonel Evans. When these
							troops without opposition reached the Fort September 16th, the Indians had retired.
							The Kentucky Volunteers remained at the Fort for some time. The others returned to
							Vincennes.</p>
						<p>Early in October, 1812, General Hopkins with an army of about 2,000 mounted riflemen
							moved northward from Vincennes for the purpose of destroying villages of hostile
							Indians on the Wabash and Illinois rivers. They crossed the river near Fort Harrison
							and the Fort was to serve as a refuge in case of accident. The expedition was a
							failure. The <pb id="VAC1322-056" n="51"/> men turned back in spite of efforts of
							General Hopkins, Major Lee, Captain Taylor and others.</p>
						<p>Another expedition under General Hopkins reached Fort Harrison November 5, 1812, on
							the way to Prophets Town and vicinity. Captain Zachary Taylor commanded a small
							company of regulars on this expedition. The expedition was successful and several
							villages were destroyed. General Hopkins speaks highly of the behavior of officers and
							men, especially of Captain Z. Taylor. Again Fort Harrison was the base of
							operations.</p>
					</div3>
				</div2>

				<pb id="VAC1322-057" n="52"/>

				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER VIII.<lb/>DISTINGUISHED MEN AT FORT HARRISON<lb/>AND
						TIPPECANOE<lb/>J. T. SCOVELL.</head>

					<p>WILLIAM HENRY HARRISON was a great man. He was successful as a General, as Governor, as
						Superintendent of Indian Affairs and as a politician, having been elected ninth
						President of the United States in 1840. He came from a distinguished family, his father,
						Benjamin Harrison, signed the Declaration of Independence; was a delegate to the first
						Colonial Congress; was elected Governor of Virginia in 1782, and was twice re-elected.
						William Henry Harrison was born February 9, 1773. He abandoned the study of medicine for
						the military. He was commissioned Ensign in 1791. He served with General Wayne in the
						campaign against the Indians in 1794. Was Governor of Indiana Territory 1801-1813. At
						the same time he was Superintendent of Indian Affairs he built Fort Harrison, and gained
						a victory over the Indians at Tippecanoe in the fall of 1811. In 1812 Governor Harrison
						was commissioned Commander-in-Chief of the Kentucky forces, later he was made Brigadier
						General in the United States Army, and assigned to the command of the Northwestern army.
						In general he was successful in his military operations against the British and Indians,
						defeating the joint forces at the battle on the Thames, thus regaining all that General
						Hull lost. William Henry Harrison was especially successful in dealing with the Indians,
						concluding many treaties with them. Tecumseh and others were hostile; Winemac, Captain
						Logan, and others were generally friendly. After the battle on the Thames General
						Harrison resigned his commission. William Henry Harrison was a member of Congress from
						Ohio 1816-1819, and United States Senator 1825-1828. In 1836 he was defeated as Whig
						candidate for the Presidency, but was elected ninth President of the United States in
						1840. He died April 4, 1841, one month after his inauguration. President Harrison was a
						strong arid convincing speaker, and in general was popular with the people. General
						Harrison, a grandson of William Henry Harrison, was elected twenty-third President of
						the United States in 1888. He was born on August 20, 1833. He was a distinguished lawyer
						in Indianapolis. He was breveted Brigadier General in the Civil War; was United States
						Senator 1881-1887. He was elected to the Presidency in 1888. Benjamin Harrison was an
						exceptionally strong man, and made a good President, but he lacked some elements of
						popularity so characteristic of his great ancestor, and failed of <pb id="VAC1322-058"
							n="53"/> reelection. It is seldom that three such conspicuously strong men occur in
						one family. The celebration of the Centennial of Fort Harrison emphasizes our relations
						with these distinguished men.</p>
					<p>There are a great number of descendants of General Harrison. Among whom are John Scott
						Harrison, a brother of President Benjamin Harrison, lives in Kansas City, Mo.</p>
					<p>Mrs. Anna H. Morris, a sister of President Benjamin Harrison, lives in Minneapolis.</p>
					<p>Colonel Russell B. Harrison, son of President Benjamin Harrison, lives in Indianapolis.
						William Henry Harrison, son of Russell Harrison, born in Terre Haute, lives in Omaha,
						and daughter, Mrs. Martina Harrison Williams, lives in Norfolk, Va.</p>
					<p>Mrs. J. R. McKee, daughter of President Benjamin Harrison, and her children, Benjamin
						Harrison McKee and Mary Lodge McKee, live in New York.</p>
					<p>COLONEL JOHN P. BOYD, of the Fourth Regiment of the United States Infantry. He helped
						to build Fort Harrison. In the battle General Harrison says, "He manifested equal zeal
						and bravery in carrying into execution my orders." Colonel Boyd was shortly after Major
						General Boyd, and in command of the Department of New Hampshire, Massachusetts, Rhode
						Island and Connecticut.</p>
					<p>MARSTON G. CLARK came to Vincennes as a volunteer private in one of the militia
						companies. His standing as a citizen and capacity as a man prompted General Harrison to
						make him Brigade Inspector on his personal staff. He served with credit through the
						campaign. Afterwards he took prominent position in civil affairs. Among other things, he
						was one of the commissioners appointed by the Governor to establish Vigo County.</p>
					<p>CAPTAIN ROBERT BUNTIN, Quartermaster of the Brigade, had seen active service before in
						the Indian wars. He served with and later wrote an interesting account of the defeat of
						General St. Clair in 1791.</p>
					<p>TOUISSAINT DuBOIS, Captain of Guides and Spies. He was an influential man with the
						Indians and early pioneers. United States Senator Fred T. Dubois of Idaho is a grandson
						of Captain Dubois. Dubois County, Indiana, was named for Captain Dubois.</p>
					<p>JOHN TIPTON, promoted on the field to Captain in command of Captain Spencer's company
						after the death of Captain Spencer and of First Lieutenant Richard McMahon. He afterward
						became Major, then Colonel, and then General Tipton. After the war, General Tipton was a
						member of the State Legislature, and in 1831 became United States Senator. General
						Tipton in 1829 bought the ground on which the Battle <pb id="VAC1322-059" n="54"/> of
						Tippecanoe was fought, and in 1836 conveyed sixteen and one-half acres of it to the
						State of Indiana. Tipton County was named for General Tipton.</p>
					<p>WILLIAM BRUCE, a volunteer in Captain Toussaint Dubois' company of guides and spies,
						lived in the neighborhood of Vincennes. He was Captain and later Major Bruce of the
						Indiana militia He is an ancestor of Professor Bruce of the Indiana State Normal
						School.</p>
					<p>CAPTAIN ANDREW WILKINS, of the Indiana militia. The Captain's nephew, Andrew Wilkins,
						was for several years Sheriff of Vigo County, and later Clerk of the county.</p>
					<p>CAPTAIN JAMES BIGGER of a company of riflemen of the Indiana militia. The company was
						from Clark County.</p>
					<p>ISAAC NAYLOR, Sergeant in Captain Bigger's company. Afterward Judge at Crawfordsville,
						Ind.</p>
					<p>WILLIAM NAYLOR, private in Captain Bigger's company. Business man in Terre Haute, also
						Assessor and Justice of the Peace, and author of interesting reminiscences of the
						Tippecanoe campaign.</p>
					<p>DAVIS FLOYD, Sergeant in Captain Beggs' company. Floyd County, was named for Sergeant
						Floyd.</p>
					<p>MAJOR GEORGE CROGHAN, Aide-de-Camp of Colonel John P. Boyd. About twenty years old.
						Afterward distinguished himself at the defense of Forts Meigs and Stephenson in
						1813.</p>
					<p>JAMES HITE, private in Peter Funk's company of Kentucky mounted militia. About eighteen
						years of age. He is said to have acted bravely in battle. For many years a citizen of
						Terre Haute.</p>
				</div2>




				<pb id="VAC1322-060" n="55"/>
				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER IX.<lb/> TERRE HAUTE UNDER FOUR FLAGS</head>
					<p>"Terre Haute Under Four Flags" is one of the historical sketches prepared by Edward
						Gilbert, and read in the city schools. The work of Mr. Gilbert was undertaken under the
						direction of John Morton Chapter, Sons of the American Revolution.</p>
					<p>How many of the school children know that this land has been under four flags ? At
						different times four separate nations have held dominion over our country. It is not
						meant that each has held some part of the United States, but over this very land on
						which Terre Haute now stands.</p>
					<p>And these four flags do not include the Indians or aboriginal inhabitants. The Indians
						did not have flags. There is nothing in Indian archeology that shows anything that stood
						to them as the flags of civilized nations stand to their people. Some of the first known
						tribes of parts of America had what they called "Totem poles." These generally had
						carved on them emblems of the tribe or family, such as a beaver, bear or a fox. These
						were fixtures and stood where for the time the tribe might be located; they were not
						carried about and there was supposed to be but one for each tribe.</p>
					<p>The first claim to this land by an European was more than three hundred years ago, when
						the Spanish adventurer, DeSoto, landed on the shores of Tampa Bay, Florida, and
						traversed a great part of the western country. Though he did not come so far north as
						Indiana, he took formal possession of the whole country which was watered by the
						Mississippi river and its tributaries, in the name of the King of Spain. Besides, the
						Pope, who claimed jurisdiction over the whole world, had given North America to the King
						of Spain.</p>
					<p>This part of the world was first explored by Frenchmen. About the year 1680 men of that
						nation were the first to tread this land. These were called "voyaguers" or "couriers de
						bois." Their trading or exploring expeditions were voyages made up or down the rivers or
						lakes, as it might be, from the points where the first settlements were located.</p>
					<p>The "voyaguers" were the forerunners of such explorers as LaSalle, Marquette and
						Joliette, who made great exploring expeditions and took possession in the name of the
						King of France. This was often done with elaborate ceremonies, especially if, as usual,
						they were accompanied by priests or missionaries. Sometimes it was done by hewing a
						cross on the flattened side of a great tree, or carving on a rock the arms of the King
						of France. <pb id="VAC1322-061" n="56"/> For many years there was undisturbed French
						possession, undisputed by any other European nation. At times there was much trouble
						with the Spanish, who invaded the land from the west side of the Mississippi river, who
						established mission posts, nominally for the conversion of the heathen, but more for the
						sake of the trade with the Indians. This trade was very profitable for, to the Indians,
						everything the foreigners had was new, and consequently, so they thought, very valuable.
						The Indians would give great stacks of the most costly furs for the cheapest trinkets.
						These furs were sent to Europe and sold at enormous profits.</p>
					<p>There was for years, in places, much controversy between the French and Spanish for
						control, which ultimately resulted in the Spanish being confined to the west side of the
						Mississippi river and the French to the east side.</p>
					<p>The French and the French flag held sway for about ninety years, until, in consequence
						of the capture of Quebec by the English General, Wolfe, in 1759, all French possessions
						in this part of North America passed to the hands and under the flag of England.</p>
					<p>So our land was English territory until 1778 during the Revolutionary War, when, by the
						capture of Kaskaskia, on the east bank of the Mississippi river and Vincennes on the
						east bank of the Wabash by General George Rogers Clark, all this western country came
						under the control of the American Confederation, and the Star Spangled Banner.</p>
					<p>As a consequence of this campaign and capture by General Clark, when the treaty of
						peace was made between the United States and England, at the close of the Revolutionary
						War, the western boundary of our country was made the Mississippi river, whereas, but
						for that expedition, it would have been the Allegheny mountains or the Ohio river,
						leaving all to the north and west as part of Canada.</p>
					<p>There was more or less trouble with the Indians all the time after the peace with
						England. The Indian nature is so different from that of the Whites that they have never
						been able to live together in peace, except when the Indians were under a strong control
						backed by force. All experiences with them shows that force was the only characteristic
						they respected. As an example: After the treaty there were a number of forts throughout
						the West that had to be transferred. The English soldiers remained in some instances for
						months. It is told that at one of these there was a large English garrison and that but
						few Americans were in the party to succeed them. The Indians that were about and
						witnessed the transfer were utterly disgusted at their English friends for giving up the
						fort. They said it was cowardly for so large a force to surrender to a smaller, and
						without even a fight. They could not understand that the war was over and the two
						nations were now friends.</p>


					<pb id="VAC1322-062" n="57"/>
					<p>The Indian character had little respect for obligations or treaties. It is true many
						treaties have been neglected or violated on the part of the Whites, but always at least
						with the pretense of an excuse. The Indian characteristic was, when there was a chance
						in case of a fight, then fight.</p>
					<p>For nearly thirty years, until the Battle of Fort Harrison in 1812, there was always
						trouble with them and danger to all who lived away from the larger settlements. The
						defeat of the Indians at that battle so completely ended all depredations that there has
						been peace all over this part of the country ever since, for a hundred years. And until
						there is no one living who personally knew of or had personal experience of danger from
						Indians. It is this century of peace that we propose to celebrate this September, as the
						beginning of a new school year and century for the school children of Terre Haute.</p>
				</div2>



				<pb id="VAC1322-063" n="58"/>
				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER X.<lb/> THE BLUE GRASS OF FORT HARRISON PRAIRIE<lb/> BY C. T.
						JEWETT.</head>
					<p>Fort Harrison's lasting reward to the valiant Kentucky Mounted Riflemen for the
						important part they played in building and defending the historic post on the bank of
						the Wabash was the seed for the now famous blue grass. Sod of the Fort Harrison prairie,
						transplanted in the beautiful hills of Kentucky, gave to that Commonwealth a State name
						that is historic.</p>
					<p>The incident of the campaign of 1812 was almost forgotten in the stirring events of the
						half century following, but from oft repeated tradition and musty letters of the
						soldiers, authentic evidence is supplied to bear out the claim that Indiana really is
						the original blue grass state. Not with the intention of taking the least bit of honor
						from the country south of the Ohio is this item set down. What the Wabash Valley and the
						highlands of Terre Haute gave to the followers of William Henry Harrison and Zachary
						Taylor, Kentucky has given to the world.</p>
					<p>In the campaign against Tippecanoe, when Fort Harrison was built, were volunteers from
						Kentucky. These men provided their own mounts and not the least concern to them was
						suitable provision for their horses. Next to the beautiful women of his Commonwealth the
						thoroughbred holds the affections of the true Kentuckian.</p>
					<p>When the soldiers went into camp during the erection of Fort Harrison the army .of the
						Northwest Territory was short of provisions for men, and there was little forage for the
						horses. The Kentuckians were willing to go hungry if need be, but they insisted that
						their horses suffer nothing from neglect or lack of feed. This point they were not slow
						in impressing on Captain Buntin, Quartermaster of the Fort.</p>
					<p>Their complaint called attention to the fact that there was "no feed for the horses
						except that coarse grass out on the prairie." One of the letters from a soldier to his
						home told of the incident. Quoting from that message we have the following: <q
							rend="blockquote">"Captain Buntin, who had been here before, replied, 'Turn your
							horses out on that coarse grass and listen to what he says about it.' Morgan took to
							it like a duck to water and in a few days I had never seen him with so sleek a coat
							and generally in such fine fettle."</q>
						<pb id="VAC1322-064" n="59"/> The Kentuckians were not slow to appreciate the offering
						of the prairie. When the time came to return home each saddle bag contained a parcel of
						seed of blue grass. The soil of Kentucky was rich and soon the blue grass took root. The
						hardy vegetation of the Fort Harrison prairie became the luxurious blue grass of the
						hills of Kentucky. Not less patriotic Kentuckian than Henry Clay attested to the truth
						of this incident. In the prime of his eventful life, when the country rang with his
						eloquent voice the repeatedly recalled what he confessed was Kentucky's debt to Indiana
						and the Wabash valley-the blue grass. Terre Hauteans of the present day offer as their
						authority for this the frequent statement of the late Judge John G. Crane, an intimate
						of Henry Clay. Judge Crane often repeated the words of the great Kentuckian who honored
						Indiana in his graceful acknowledgment that Kentucky was proud to be known as the Blue
						Grass State, and revered the soil of Fort Harrison prairie-the first home of the blue
						grass.</p>

					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">COPPER AND COAL MINES ON THE WABASH<lb/> BY EDWARD GILBERT.</head>
						<p>In one of General Harrison's reports he speaks of the difficulty of securing the
							inclusion in a treaty of certain lands which he much desired, but was objected to by
							the Indians, partly on account of the location thereon of a valuable copper mine. He
							speaks of having seen samples of the copper, one of which he had sent to Mr.
							Jefferson, in 1802. The immediate location of this mine was held a profound secret by
							the Indians, but General Harrison supposed it to be somewhere on the west side of the
							Wabash between about where Lafayette now stands and Vincennes. General Harrison no
							doubt hoped that this would in time prove a valuable item in the possession of
							Indiana. Later research proved that the supply of copper was limited to light washings
							of several small creeks. And the hopes of development have never been realized.</p>
						<p>At the same time it is of record that when the scouts of the Tippecanoe army advanced
							up the river ahead of the army, they found several settlers freely working drifts for
							the coal that cropped out. Ensign Tipton, in his journal of his investigations, makes
							many references to these coal mines.</p>
						<p>In those days copper was an object of great worth, for it was scarce and of great
							value. While the forests were being cut down to clear the land, coal as a fuel was not
							so interesting. In these modern times, conditions are reversed. The copper mine has
							vanished from memory, but those drifts of coal have opened the way to the discovery,
							fifty years later, of the enormous deposits under this whole region, which have proven
							the basis of all our prosperity.</p>
					</div3>


					<pb id="VAC1322-065" n="60"/>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="enter">THE FIRST CROP OF CORN ON FORT HARRISON PRAIRIE<lb/> BY EDWARD
							GILBERT.</head>
						<p>Early in the spring of 1811 there appeared five men, in the vicinity of what is now
							the southeast part of the City of Terre Haute. These men proceeded to break up the
							land and plant a crop of seventy-five acres of corn, Why they selected this remote
							place was a mystery at the time. By their own statement there were no inhabitants of
							the country roundabout, nearer than Carlisle, the town long the capital of Sullivan
							County, some thirty miles away. Where were they to get a market for their crop ? While
							there is no historical authority for the statement, it is believed that it was an
							example of the long headedness of General Harrison, who foresaw the coming expedition,
							and sent these men here to prepare the crop for the use of his army that was to march
							through the country in the Fall. It is told how four of the five were wary of reports
							of Indian threats, and being willing to abandon their enterprise, the fifth bought out
							their interests and secured the crop. It was, as expected, later sold either to the
							army direct or to the contractors who supplied the expedition.</p>
						<p>It is true that one of the men was a soldier enlisted in the army, and that he
							disappears from the rolls for a time.</p>
						<p>Whatever may have been the inducement that led to the enterprise, it is admitted by
							all historians that then was the first plowing of Fort Harrison prairie for
							cultivation by civilized people.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">PICTURE OF FORT HARRISON<lb/> BY EDWARD GILBERT.</head>
						<p>The picture of Fort Harrison presented to our readers is a photographic copy of a
							print made and copyrighted in 1848 by Luther G. Hager and James A. Modestly.</p>
						<p>It can well be called the only existing, authentic picture portrayal of what Fort
							Harrison looked like.</p>
						<p>Luther G. Hager was a young and enthusiastic amateur artist who came here in 1836.
							James A. Modestly was a son of Dr. Charles B. Modestly, one of the early pioneers of
							the county, who was at and in Fort Harrison for some time during its maintenance as a
							post. He was the father of Mrs. Chauncey Warren, perhaps the last person to live who
							had known Fort Harrison as such.</p>
						<p>On the occasion of a "Grand Barbecue" held at Fort Harrison Grove, half a mile east
							of the Fort, in October, 1848, during the campaign which resulted in the election of
							General Zachary Taylor to the Presidency of the United States, these two young men of
							Terre Haute filled with the same patriotic sentiments that have inspired this
							centennial <pb id="VAC1322-066" n="61"/> observance, undertook to preserve the Fort by
							the aid of the "printer's art."</p>
						<p>Luther G. Hager had never seen the Fort in its original state, but James A. Modestly,
							as a boy, had. They consulted with several then living citizens who "knew it like a
							book," among them Curtis Gilbert, who had spent near three years under the shadow of
							its stockade. They made the picture to represent it as it had been.</p>
						<p>Originally the block-houses were covered by shed roofs, slanting inward. In
							rebuilding, after the destruction of one by fire during the battle, and, later, in
							repairing the other the hip roofs, as shown in the picture, were put on.</p>
						<p>These young men who made the picture sold scores of them at the "barbecue." They also
							utilized some of the old walnut logs of the stockade, which were yet solid, turning
							them into walking canes which they sold to visitors. It is the regret of the
							Historical Committee that they are not able to find one of these canes to show at this
							time.</p>
						<p>Fort Harrison Grove, some time the home of Judge Elisha M. Huntington, of the Indiana
							Supreme Court, was a beautiful hillside, studded with massive maple and oak trees. It
							was a favorite picnic ground. Many a venerable man and woman of Terre Haute remembers
							how they looked forward to the annual Sunday school picnic, a great feature of which
							was the ride up and back on a canal boat.</p>
					</div3>
				</div2>



				<pb id="VAC1322-067" n="62"/>
				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER XI.<lb/> THE CENTENNIAL OF THE BATTLE OF<lb/> FORT
						HARRISON<lb/> BY JAMES B. HARRIS.</head>
					<p>A few miles north of the City of Terre Haute lies the beautiful site of Old Fort
						Harrison, conspicuous in the history of the territory of the Northwest for its great
						influence in the national life. It is located on high ground at a bend in the Wabash
						river and affords a beautiful and commanding view of the country beyond for many
						miles.</p>
					<p>The United States Government has from time to time been solicited to assist in the
						acquisition and preservation of such historic spots, and the National officials,
						recognizing that the patriotic spirit of the people is largely promoted by favorable
						action, has adopted a liberal policy, friendly to such appeals.</p>
					<p>Among the many purely patriotic societies with unselfish ends and exclusively devoted
						to patriotism is, "The Sons of the American Revolution." That organization has been
						regularly incorporated by the Congress of the United States.</p>
					<p>There is a National Society, State Societies in nearly every State of the Union, and
						local chapters. Also, there are chapters under the control of the National Society
						located in Hawaii and the Philippines, of Americans living there, and in Paris, France,
						where descendants of the Frenchmen who helped in the Revolutionary War are also members.
						The organization is under the system of our National and State and local form of
						political organization.</p>
					<p>"The Sons of the American Revolution" is composed of lineal descendants of those
						American colonists and of their French allies who took part in the American struggle for
						independence, either in military, naval or civil action.</p>
					<p>The purpose and object of such corporations are declared to be patriotic, historical
						and educational, and shall include those designed to perpetuate the memory of the men
						who, by their services or sacrifices during the war of the American Revolution, achieved
						the independence of the American people; to unite and promote fellowship among their
						descendants; to inspire them and the community at large with a more profound reverence
						for the principles of the government founded by our forefathers; to encourage historical
						research in relation to the American Revolution; to acquire and preserve the records of
						the individual <pb id="VAC1322-068" n="[]"/>
						<pb id="VAC1322-069" n="[]"/>
						<pb id="VAC1322-070" n="63"/> services of the patriots of the war as well as documents,
						relics and landmarks; to celebrate the anniversaries of the prominent events of that
						period; to foster true patriotism and extend institutions of freedom.</p>
					<p>The story told elsewhere affords justification for the appeal for the acquisition,
						improvement and dedication of Fort Harrison site as a National Park by the government of
						the United States.</p>
					<p>The conception of a Fort Harrison Centennial celebration has long been entertained in
						the John Morton Chapter of the Indiana Society of the Sons of the American Revolution,
						located at Terre Haute. The project was brought before the annual meeting of the Indiana
						State Society of the Sons of the American Revolution at Indianapolis in 1907 by the
						delegates from John Morton Chapter, and was received with grand acclamation, but no
						action could be taken at that time. The next year, February, 1908, the State meeting was
						held at Terre Haute. There was a large attendance and the compatriots were conveyed in
						carriages to the old site and the meeting was held there in a modern building, in the
						construction of which a few of the old logs of the Fort stockade had been retained and
						which were carefully and reverently inspected by the visitors.</p>
					<p>Resolutions looking to the preservation of the site of Fort Harrison and its dedication
						as a National Park were presented by Compatriot James B. Harris, of John Morton Chapter,
						Terre Haute. Mr. Harris said:</p>
					<p><q rend="blockquote">"At a meeting of John Morton Chapter, Sons of the American
							Revolution, the desirability of securing Fort Harrison for a National Historical Park
							was discussed and a resolution passed looking toward its acquisition for this purpose.
							It is desired to enlist the interest, approval and assistance of the Local, State and
							National Societies, S. A. R., and also the general public and the State and National
							Governments.</q></p>


					<p><q rend="blockquote">"It is appropriate that the Sons of the American Revolution should
							inaugurate this movement as it is the mission of the organization to inspire
							sentiments of loyalty, patriotism and veneration.</q></p>
					<p><q rend="blockquote">"We must preserve the sites of these actions that our children's
							children may read them and visit them and become enthused with patriotism. Nothing
							could show so baneful a lack of patriotism as allowing this evidence of the deeds of
							our ancestors to go unmarked, to fade in memory and become mythical by loss of records
							and markers from neglect or destruction for commercial ends.</q></p>

					<p><q rend="blockquote">"The Fort was built and named in honor of a lineage noted for
							patriotism and statesmanship and prominently devoted in patriotism to the National
							service for several generations.</q></p>
					<q type="blockquotation">"The following resolutions are therefore offered for
						adoption:</q>


					<pb id="VAC1322-071" n="64"/>

					<p><q rend="blockquote">"<hi rend="i">Resolved,</hi> That the Indiana Society of the Sons
							of the American Revolution approve and recommend that the site of Fort Harrison be
							secured and dedicated as a National Historic Park.</q></p>



					<p><q rend="blockquote"><hi rend="i">"Resolved,</hi> That this action shall also be placed
							before the National Society of the Sons of the American Revolution and the approval
							and influence of that organization be requested to aid in said purpose.</q></p>
					<p><q rend="blockquote"><hi rend="i"/>"Resolved, That the President of the Society appoint
							a committee to formulate a memorial to the Congress of the United States that the
							National Government take appropriate action to acquire and dedicate the site of old
							Fort Harrison as a National Historic Park."</q></p>
					<p>The resolutions were unanimously adopted by the Indiana Society of the Sons of the
						American Revolution.</p>
					<p>At a regular meeting of John Morton Chapter held April 1, 1912, it was resolved to call
						a meeting of all citizens of Terre Haute for the purpose of forming a Fort Harrison
						Centennial Association.</p>
					<p>Such a meeting was held at the rooms of the Terre Haute Commercial Club on April 5,
						1912. There was a large and enthusiastic attendance and the organization was completed.
						The aim and object was decided to be "to provide for the suitable patriotic observance
						of the one hundredth anniversary of the Battle of Fort Harrison, fought between the
						United States soldiers, under Captain Zachary Taylor, and the hostile Indians, under
						Chief Lenar, at Fort Harrison, on the banks of the Wabash, September 4, 1812.</p>
					<p><q rend="blockquote">"To initiate a movement for the proper and permanent marking of
							the battle field.</q></p>
					<p>"To collect and preserve historical records and records of the battle.</p>
					<p><q rend="blockquote">"To provide a suitable memorial to the men and women who
							participated in the campaign that made possible the peaceful settlement of the Wabash
							valley."</q></p>


					<p>The following officers and committees were selected:</p>
					<list type="simple">
						<head rend="center">EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE</head>


						<item><hi rend="left"> THATCHER A. PARKER, President.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left">Miss MARY ALICE WARREN, Vice-President.</hi></item>

						<item><hi rend="left
							">MRS. MARY MURPHY, Vice-President.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left">DAVID J. WILLIAMS, Vice-President.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left">HARRY T. SCHLOSS, Vice-President.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left">WILL W. ADAMSON, Vice-President.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left">CLARENCE F. WILLIAMS, Vice-President.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left">CAPT. A. W. DUDLEY, Vice-President.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left">EDWARD GILBERT, Secretary.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left">GEORGE W. KRIETENSTEIN, Treasurer.</hi></item>
					</list>




					<pb id="VAC1322-072" n="65"/>
					<list type="simple">
						<head rend="center">COMMITTEES</head>



						<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="i">Finance</hi>-W. W. ADAMSON, Chairman.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="i">Municipal and State</hi>-ADOLPH HERZ,
							Chairman.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="i">Publicity</hi>-W. L. STAHL, Chairman.</hi></item>

						<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="i">Buildings and Grounds</hi>-MAX EHRMANN,
								Chairman.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="i">Transportation</hi>-WILLIAM PENN,
							Chairman.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="i">Parades</hi>-C. T. JEWETT, Chairman.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="i">Invitations</hi>-PRESIDENT W. W. PARSONS,
								Chairman.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="i">Speakers</hi>-D. J. WILLIAMS, Chairman.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="i">Decorations</hi>-MARX MYERS, Chairman.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="i">Schools and School Children</hi>-HERBERT BRIGGS,
								Chairman.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left"><hi rend="i">History</hi>-DR. J. T. SCOVELL, Chairman.</hi></item>
					</list>

					<list type="simple">
						<head>ADVISORY COMMITTEE</head>

						<item><hi rend="left">GEORGE O. DIX, Chairman.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left">W. R. McKEEN.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left">PRESIDENT W. W. PARSONS.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left">CRAWFORD FAIRBANKS.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left">DAVID W. HENRY.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left">RABBI E. LEIPZIGER.</hi></item>

						<item><hi rend="left">JUDGE C. M. FORTUNE.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left">PRESIDENT C. LEO MEES.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left">JOHN L. CRAWFORD.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left">ADOLPH HERZ.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left">JUDGE JOHN E. COX.</hi></item>
						<item><hi rend="left">CHAPMAN J. ROOT.</hi></item>
					</list>



					<p>The present result of these efforts is this observance of the Centennial of the Battle
						of Fort Harrison, September 4, 1912.</p>



				</div2>

				<pb id="VAC1322-073" n="66"/>
				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER XII.<lb/> ROLL OF MEMBERS OF JOHN MORTON CHAPTER, INDIANA
						SOCIETY OF THE SONS OF THE AMERICAN REVOLUTION</head>

					<p>Floyd Allen.<lb/> William Ward Adamson.<lb/> Frank Baird.<lb/> David Bacon.<lb/>
						Herbert Briggs.<lb/> Ralph Albin Coltharp.<lb/> Orville E. Conner.<lb/> Charles Edward
						Conner.<lb/> George Oscar Dix.<lb/> Charles R. Dryer.<lb/> Jacob Drennon Early.<lb/>
						Charles E. Erwin.<lb/> Linus A. Evans.<lb/> Isaac Flenner.<lb/> Edward Gilbert.<lb/>
						Chalmers Martin Hamill.<lb/> William A. Hamilton.<lb/> Lloyd B. Hamilton.<lb/> Paul
						Bitner Hamilton.<lb/> James B. Harris.<lb/> Benjamin G. Hudnut.<lb/> Charles Timothy
						Jewett.<lb/> John Patton Kimmel.<lb/> Earle Portmess Lee.<lb/> John M. Manson.<lb/>
						William Payne Martin.<lb/> Austin A. Miller.<lb/> Thatcher Anspenk Parker.<lb/> Lemuel
						Ford Perdue (deceased).<lb/> Eli Hilton Redman.<lb/> James Ellis Somes.<lb/> John D.
						Steele.<lb/> Robert J. Scovell.<lb/> Henry Keys Stormont.<lb/> Richard Sibley.<lb/>
						George Albert Schaal.<lb/> Dalton B. Shourds.<lb/> Wilbur Topping.<lb/> Horace E.
						Tune.<lb/> David Russ Wood.<lb/> H. E. Wildy.<lb/></p>
				</div2>



				<pb id="VAC1322-074" n="67"/>
				<div2 type="chapter">
					<head rend="center">CHAPTER XIII.<lb/> ROLL OF DESCENDANTS.</head>

					<p>One of the objects of the Fort Harrison Centennial Association was to collect and
						preserve records of the descendants of the pioneers of Fort Harrison. The committee gave
						every effort to obtain names, but in many instances all trace of families has been lost.
						The following names are from the register of the Association, and are of the known
						living descendants of those who assisted in building and maintaining the fort or
						participated in its defense:</p>
					<p><hi rend="i">Descendants of William Henry Harrison.</hi> Russell B. Harrison, John
						Scott Harrison, Mrs. Sallie H. Devin, Mrs. Anna H. Morris, Miss Anna H. Devin, S. H.
						Devin, Mrs. Elizabeth Reed, Mr. Sam S. Morris, Jr., Allen Morris, Mrs. Charles
						Stevenson, Mrs. Madge Curtiss, Scott Harrison, Mrs. William T. Buckner, Scott Harrison
						Morris, Scott Harrison Eaton, Mrs. John C. Lewis, Seymour Hunt, John Scott Harrison, W.
						H. Harrison, Miss J. W. Farrar, James Findley Harrison, Arch I. Harrison, Captain J. T.
						Taylor, Mrs. Bessie Ogden, Mrs. D. W. McClung, A. T. Harrison, Lytle Harrison, J. S.
						Harrison, Jr., Mrs. M. S. Robinson, Benjamin Harrison, William H. Harrison, Mrs. J. R.
						McKee, Mrs. Benjamin Harrison</p>
					<p><hi rend="i">Descendants of Robert Buntin.</hi> Mrs. Emma Buntin Wagner, Miss Frances
						Buntin, Davis C. Buntin, Mr. Henry Shannon Buntin's children, Touissiant C. Buntin,
						George C. Buntin, Mr. Rollin H. Buntin.</p>
					<p>Descendants of Susan Spencer Wilkins. Noyes E. Anderson, Ora Davis, Mrs. Addie Davis,
						Charles M. Trout, Susan Early Trout, George D. Wilkins, John E. Wilkins, Edwin Wilkins,
						David Wilkins, Mrs. George Wilkins, Mrs. Beulah Wilkins.</p>
					<p>Descendants of Major John T. Chunn. Charles Chunn, Miss Caroline Chunn, J. T. Chunn,
						Miss Maoma Hale, Mrs. Bruce Whitesell, S. C. Wright, David Wright, W. G. Wright,
						Margaret Wright, Mrs. Levi Taylor, Mrs. E. Dyer, Miss Maria Van Dyne.</p>
					<p>Descendants of Stephen D. Handy. William A. Handy, Sol. Handy, Mrs. Charles Prevo, W.
						W. Handy.</p>


					<pb id="VAC1322-075" n="68"/>

					<p><hi rend="i">Descendants of Peter Mallory.</hi> Mrs. John Tobery, Isaac Brady, Scott
						Green.</p>
					<p><hi rend="i">Descendants of Wm. Naylor.</hi> W. N. Garrtrell, Charles Naylor, Louis
						Naylor, Mrs. Anna Naylor, Miss Marie Naylor, Samuel S. Shumard, John W. Swindler, Glenn
						Swindler, Mrs. Lena Swindler, Lena Swindler-Spencer, Esther Swindler, Harrison Swindler,
						Mayme Swindler.</p>
					<p><hi rend="i">Descendant of Major John D. White.</hi> James M. Chandler.</p>
					<p><hi rend="i">Descendants of General John A. Thomas.</hi> Charles Thomas, Ralph L.
						Thomas, Frank H. Thomas; John D. Thomas, William H. Thomas, George M. Thomas, Charles L.
						Thomas, William Tichenor, W. E. Robinson, Overton Thomas, Clem Thomas, George Thomas,
						George W. Shanks, Ed. F. Moster, W. H. McLaughlin, Raymond Neice, Victor Vancheiser,
						Ernest Lackard, Willard P. Hedrick, Robert W. Thomas.</p>
					<p><hi rend="i">Descendants of Joseph Liston.</hi> Mrs. Thomas Donham, Gilbert Liston,
						Moses Pierson and. family, Isaac Pierson.</p>
					<p><hi rend="i">Descendants of John Hamilton.</hi> Andrew C. Nelson and Sister C.
						Nelson.</p>
					<p><hi rend="i">Descendants of Isaac and Julia Lambert.</hi> Mrs. Irene Casto, Mrs.
						Virginia Eppert, Mrs. J. S. Hamaker, Mrs. Alice H. Harris, Mrs. Jane Kelley, James
						Laverty, Geo. W. Laverty, C. H. Lambert, Mrs. Louise Moore, Mrs. Sarah C. Meredith, Paul
						J. Meredith, John McCune, R. W. McCune, Mrs. Josephine Pickard, Mrs. Almeda Thompson,
						Mrs. Ermine Ten Brook.</p>
					<p><hi rend="i">Descendant of Rev. Soldier Woodruff.</hi> Rula Woodruff.</p>
					<p><hi rend="i">Descendants of John Dickson.</hi> Mrs. Charles Bartholomew, William C.
						Durham, John C. Durham, Joseph H. Durham, Mrs. Jos. G. Cannon, Jr., John Dickson, Isaac
						Dickson, Mrs. E. G. Davison, Mrs. O. A. McGregor, Alex. McGregor, Mrs. W. H. Shephard,
						Mrs. W. B. Schofield, Mrs. Samuel Royse, Samuel Royse, Martha Royse, Anna Royse, William
						Royse, Mrs. I. A. White, Charles White, Cecil D. White.</p>




					<pb id="VAC1322-076" n="69"/>

					<p><hi rend="i">Descendants of Major John Bond.</hi> Mrs. Cedelia Van Houtin, J. B.
						Johnson, John W. Jones, William Jones, John Murray.</p>
					<p><hi rend="i">Descendants of Curtis Gilbert.</hi> Joseph Gilbert, Mrs. Sadie Gilbert
						Cooter, Mrs. Helen L. Gilbert Gillum, Curtis Gilbert, Mrs. Madge Gilbert Champion,
						Edward Gilbert, Helen Steel Gilbert, Mrs. Emma Gilbert Curtis, Henry Curtis Gilbert,
						Richard Law Gilbert, Mary Gilbert, Henry Curtis Gilbert, Jr., Mrs. Susan B. Ball, Miss
						Mary G. Beach, Mrs. Mary G. Gilbert Blake, Mrs. Helen G. B. Ross, Mrs. Helen C. Gilbert
						Warner, Mr. Gilbert Warner, Mrs. Ethel Warner Greeson, Mrs. Alice Warner, Miss Susan B.
						Warner.</p>
					<p><hi rend="i">Descendants of Abraham Markle.</hi> Mrs. Oscar Anderson, Augustus R.
						Markle, Miss Laura Markle, Raymond Denman, Abraham Markle, John M. Markle, William D.
						Markle, Herbert M. Markle, Mrs. Mable Weir, Miss Sarah Markle, Harry Markle, Ed. Markle,
						William Green, Charles Green, Mrs. Bertha Hornberger, Mrs. Myrtle Tanner, Harry Green,
						George Markle, Herbert Markle, Miss Anna Markle, Guert Markle, Harvey Markle, Robert
						Markle, Miss Florence Markle, Paul S. Markle, Harry Markle, Clay C. Markle, Ermina
						Markle, Maurice Markle, Mrs. Morton Grismer, Miss Matilda Markle, Miss Eva Markle,
						Napoleon B. Markle, W. Lincoln Browning, John Brockway, James Baldwin, Warren Brockway,
						Chauncey Baldwin, Mrs. Ernest Drake, George Duffield, Frederick Elkin, Walter Green,
						Mrs. Ivan B. Harris, Mrs. Arthur Richmond, Mrs. Mary Ross, Mrs. George Starr.</p>
					<p><hi rend="i">Descendants of Henry Redford.</hi> Mrs. Raymond Cummings, Mrs. Kate
						Markle, Mrs. Dr. Scott, Mrs. M. S. Tyler.</p>
					<p><hi rend="i">Descendants of Joseph Richardson.</hi> Dr. Lawrence S. Ball, E. H. Ball
						and family, Mrs. S. R. Freeman, Jr., Miss Maude Freeman, Mrs. H. B. Hibben, William R.
						Richardson, Mrs. J. A. Root, Mrs. Josephine Lake, Mrs. Charles Minshall and family, Mrs.
						R. H. Pritchard, Miss Clint Richardson, Wm. P. Richardson, John M. Richardson, Mrs. Mary
						E. Peddle, John Peddle, Mrs. Matilda Ball Mancourt.</p>
					<p><hi rend="i">Descendant of John Clinton Bradford.</hi> Mrs. Amelia Brannon Joice.</p>


					<pb id="VAC1322-077" n="70"/>

					<p><hi rend="i">Descendants of Dr. Charles B. Modesitt.</hi> Mrs. Catherine Curtis, Mrs.
						Cora E. Carter, Chauncey Warren Curtis, Mrs. George B. Mathews, Welton Modesitt, John C.
						Warren, Miss Frances Warren, Miss Mary Alice Warren, Miss Eliza Warren, Mrs. Herbert
						Westfall, Miss Helen Frances Warren, Robert E. Warren and family, Frederick Warren and
						family, Miss Mary Elizabeth Warren.</p>
					<p><hi rend="i">Descendants of Mary Briggs.</hi> George Wright, Lincoln Wright, Charles
						Wright.</p>
					<p><hi rend="i">Descendants of Caleb Crawford.</hi> Walter Crawford, Fred Crawford, H. F.
						Crawford, W. G. Crawford, Miss Florence Crawford, Wm. David Crawford, Crawford
						Fairbanks, Mrs. Bruce F. Failey, Grant Fairbanks, Mrs. William Fairbanks, Mrs. Nellie
						Jordan, E. P. Fairbanks, Miss Helen Fairbanks, Mrs. Hallie Freeland, Henry S.
						Montagnier, Mrs. Daisy E. Noe, Morton L. Rankin, Oscar Rankin, Mrs. James Townley, Miss
						Minnie Martin, Miss Janie Martin, Sarah E. Rankin.</p>
					<p><hi rend="i">Descendants of John E. Wilmoth&mdash;Kentucky Volunteer.</hi> George T.
						Smith and family. Descendants of Matilda A. Taylor Ball. Mrs. M. E. Ball Hess, Frank
						Ball.</p>
					<p><hi rend="i">Descendant of Captain Touissiant Dubois.</hi> Hon. Fred Dubois.</p>
					<p><hi rend="i">Descendants of James Burgan.</hi> W. C. Burgan, James J. Burgan, Samuel W.
						Burgan, Mrs. E. A. Perkins, Miss Elizabeth J. Burgan, Lyman M. Burgan, Mrs. Josephine
						Bowsher, James A. Burgan, Samuel Burgan.</p>





					<pb id="VAC1322-078" n="71"/>

					<div3 type="part">
						<head rend="center">CHRONOLOGY OF FORT HARRISON</head>
						<list type="simple">
							<item><hi rend="left">DeSoto landed on Tampa Bay, Florida, and, later "took
									possession" of all<lb/>the land drained by the waters of the Mississippi river, in
									the name of<lb/>the King of Spain</hi>
								<hi rend="right">1540</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">LaSalle traversed a part of Indiana on his voyage of discovery
									of Ohio river</hi><hi rend="right">1676</hi>
							</item>
							<item><hi rend="left">LaSalle again crossed a part of Indiana, from the St. Joseph
									river, near<lb/>where South Bend now is, to the Illinois river</hi>
								<hi rend="right">1678</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">The Five Nations claimed to have driven out, or massacred the
									aborigines, whoever they were, and taken possession of Indiana</hi>
								<hi rend="right">1621</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">The Five Nations ceded all lands west and south of Albany, N.
									Y., to King William III</hi>
								<hi rend="right">1701</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="right">The claims of Spain to the region were transferred to
									France</hi>
								<hi rend="right">1702</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">Francis Vigo born at Mondovia, Sardinia</hi><hi rend="right"
									>1740</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">Francis Vigo died at Vincennes, Mar. 22, 1836.</hi>
							</item>
							<item><hi rend="left">Mons. de Aubry marched his 400 French recruits and 100 tons of
									flour up<lb/>the Wabash from Vigo County to assist the French at Quebec. This
									connects<lb/>our land with the French-English wars</hi><hi rend="right"
								>1759</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">Conspiracy of Pontiac</hi>
								<hi rend="right">1761</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">After the treaty between England and France, St. Ange,
									commandant of Fort<lb/>Chartres (Vincennes) surrendered the post to Captain
									Sterling of the<lb/>British army</hi>
								<hi rend="right">Oct. 10, 1765</hi></item>

							<item><hi rend="left">General George Rogers Clark started on his expedition of
									conquest of the land from about where Louisville, Ky., now is on</hi>
								<hi rend="right">June 24, 1778</hi></item>

							<item><hi rend="left">General Clark captured Kaskaskia on the Mississippi river</hi>
								<hi rend="right">July 4, 1778</hi></item>

							<item><hi rend="left">Father Gibault secured the transfer of the allegiance of the
									French<lb/>inhabitants of Vincennes from England to the American colonies</hi>
								<hi rend="right">Fall of 1778</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">Captain Helm and his cook took possession of Vincennes in the
									name of<lb/>the United States</hi><hi rend="right">Dec. 1778</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">The British General, Hamilton, with thirty British regulars,
									fifty French<lb/>Canadian volunteers and four hundred Indians, marched across
									Vigo<lb/> County, enroute to recapture Vincennes, the only connection of
									Vigo<lb/>County soil with the Revolutionary War</hi>
								<hi rend="right">Dec. 1778</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">Captain Helm and his cook, the only garrison of Vincennes,
									surrendered to<lb/>General Hamilton on honorable terms </hi>
								<hi rend="right">Dec. 1778</hi></item>

							<item><hi rend="left">First meeting of General George Rogers Clark and Francis Vigo at
									Kaskaskia</hi>
								<hi rend="right">Jan. 29, 1779</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">British General Hamilton surrendered Vincennes to General George
									Rogers Clark</hi>
								<hi rend="right">Feb. 24, 1779</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">Peace of Paris between Great Britain and the United States,
									Great Britain<lb/>surrendered all claims on land east of the Mississippi
									river</hi><hi rend="right">1783</hi></item>

							<item><hi rend="left">Virginia surrendered all claims to the Northwest Territory to
									the United States</hi>
								<hi rend="right">1784</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">The Northwest Territory organized by Congress, under General
									Arthur St. Clair as Territorial Governor </hi>
								<hi rend="right">1787</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">Indiana Territory organized by Congress, and General William
									Henry Harrison made Territorial Governor</hi>
								<hi rend="right">1800</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">Plan of survey by range, township and sections adopted by
									Congress </hi><hi rend="right">May 7, 1784</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">Survey of lands in Indiana Territory authorized by Congress </hi>
								<hi rend="right">1804</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">General William Henry Harrison marched up the Wabash to locate
									and build Fort Harrison.</hi>
								<list type="simple">
									<item><hi rend="left">Left Vincennes</hi>
										<hi rend="right">Sept. 26, 1811</hi></item>
									<item><hi rend="left">Arrived at location and commenced building the Fort</hi>
										<hi rend="right">Oct. 30, 1811</hi></item>
									<item><hi rend="left">Completed the Fort </hi>
										<hi rend="right">Oct. 30, 1811</hi></item>
								</list></item>

							<item><hi rend="left">General Harrison, with his army, started on his march to the
									Prophets Town</hi>
								<hi rend="right">1811</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">General Harrison defeated the Indians under Elskamatawa, the
									Prophet</hi><hi rend="right"> Nov 7, 1811</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">Battle of Fort Harrison, defense by Captain Zachary Taylor,
									against the Indians under the old chief, Lenar</hi>
								<hi rend="right">Sept. 4, 1812</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">First public sale of lands of Vigo County at the Vincennes land
									office</hi>
								<hi rend="right">Sept. 13-14, 1816</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">Terre Haute platted by the Terre Haute Company, and first sale
									of lots in Terre Haute</hi>
								<hi rend="right">Oct. 31, 1816</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">Vigo County organized</hi>
								<hi rend="right">1818</hi></item>
							<item><hi rend="left">Indiana became a State in the Union</hi>
								<hi rend="right">Dec. 1816</hi></item>
						</list>
					</div3>



					<pb id="VAC1322-079" n="72"/>
					<div3 type="part">

						<head rend="center">FREEDOM'S LAND<lb/>THE NEW NATIONAL ANTHEM</head>
						<p><hi rend="center">BY DR. E. T. SPOTSWOOD</hi></p>
						<p><hi rend="center i">Sung to the Tune Dixie Land</hi></p>

						<lg>
							<l>The land we love, the land of glory</l>
							<l>Famed in song and grand in story</l>
							<l rend="ti-1">To thee! To thee! To thee we sing.</l>
							<l>United free and strong and grand We'll keep and hold our Fatherland. </l>
							<l>For Aye! For Aye!! For Aye!!! in Freedom's land.</l>
						</lg>

						<p><hi rend="i">Chorus&mdash;</hi></p>
						<lg>
							<l>Our glorious Union ever,</l>
							<l rend="ti-1">Hurra! Hurra !!</l>
							<l>In freedom's land we all will stand</l>
							<l>And live and die for freedom's land.</l>
							<l>Hurra! Hurra!! Hurray for the Union ever.</l>
						</lg>
						<lg>
							<l>No North. No South. No East. No West,</l>
							<l>But one grand Union heaven blessed;</l>
							<l rend="ti-1">For Aye! For Aye!! For Aye! in Freedom's land.</l>
							<l>To keep it pure and keep it right</l>
							<l>We'll always for its honor fight</l>
							<l>For Aye! For Aye!! For Aye!!! in Freedom's land.</l>
						</lg>

						<lg>
							<l>And this shall be our battle song,</l>
							<l>To hold the true and right the wrong,</l>
							<l rend="ti-1">Alway ! Alway !! Alway !!! in Freedom's land. </l>
							<l>For we love our own our Freedom land. </l>
							<l>To guard her rights we'll ever stand.</l>
							<l rend="ti-1">Alway! Alway!! Alway!!! in Freedom's land.</l>
						</lg>

						<lg>
							<l>O, may our God within whose hand</l>
							<l>Is held the future of our land,</l>
							<l rend="ti-1">Alway. Alway. Alway in Freedom's land.</l>
							<l>From strife and danger keep us free,</l>
							<l>And lead us on to victory,</l>
							<l rend="ti-1">We pray! We pray!! We pray for Freedom's land.</l>
						</lg>
					</div3>



				</div2>
			</div1>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
