<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//IA Books//DTD TEI for Indiana Authors Books//EN"
                       "teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="VAC1124">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">History of Lake Maxinkuckee</title>
        <author>McDonald, Daniel, 1833-1916</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded By</resp>
          <!--Update the value of the element below with your name in
                                direct order.-->
          <name>Beth Gucinski</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
        <address>
                    <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
                </address>
        <idno>VAC1124</idno>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>Copyright 2009 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
          <p>Indiana University provides the information contained on this web site for
            non-commercial, personal, or research use only. All other use, including but not limited
            to commercial or scholarly reproductions, redistribution, publication or transmission,
            whether by electronic means or otherwise, without prior written permission of the
            copyright holder is strictly prohibited.</p>
        </availability>
        <!--Update the value of the date element with the year the document
                        is being encoded.-->
        <date>2012</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">History of Lake Maxinkuckee</title>
            <author id="ina-v1-entry-0549">McDonald, Daniel, 1833-1916</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>61 p. : ill. ; 24 cm.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Maxinkuckee Lake Association</publisher>
            <pubPlace>[S.l.]</pubPlace>
            <date>1905</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>"To which is appended Fishes and fishing in the Lake, by A.C. Capron; The
              Maxinkuckee Lake Association, by W.T. Wilson; and The Aubbeenaubbee Yacht Club, by
              T.H. Wilson, Jr."</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Digital Library Program was awarded a Library Services and Technology Act (LSTA)
          grant in 2005 to make available online the three-volume, reference work, <title>Indiana
            Authors and Their Books</title> along with selected monographs by Indiana authors.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="3">
        <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and has
          been encoded and edited using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
          Guidelines following the TEI Lite standard. Digital page images are linked to the text
          file.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <tagUsage gi="div1">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
      </tagsDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language>English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list>
            <item>Fishing</item>
            <item>Maxinkuckee, Lake (Ind.)--History.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <!--The revision description tracks significant changes made to the file
                    after completion. This information will remain commented out unless someone has
                    conducted quality assessment of the texts and have made changes to the file as a
                    result.-->
    <!-- <revisionDesc> <change>
                    <date>$Date</date> <respStmt>
                    <name>$Name</name>
                    <resp>$Responsibility</resp>
                    </respStmt> <item>$Changes</item>
                    </change> </revisionDesc> -->
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb id="VAC1124-001" n="[]"/>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">HISTORY<lb/>
            <hi rend="sc">OF</hi><lb/> LAKE MAXINKUCKEE</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline><hi rend="sc">BY</hi><lb/>
          <docAuthor>DANIEL McDONALD</docAuthor>
          <lb/>TO WHICH IS APPENDED</byline>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">FISHES AND FISHING IN THE LAKE,</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>BY <docAuthor>JUDGE A. C. CAPRON</docAuthor>;</byline>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">THE MAXINKUCKEE LAKE ASSOCIATION,</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>BY <docAuthor>W. T. WILSON</docAuthor>, AND THE</byline>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">AUBBEENAUBBEE YACHT CLUB,</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>BY <docAuthor>T. H. WILSON, J<hi rend="sc">R</hi>.</docAuthor></byline>
        <docImprint><hi rend="sc">PUBLISHED BY</hi><lb/>
          <publisher>THE MAXINKUCKEE LAKE ASSOCIATION</publisher><lb/>
          <docDate>1905</docDate><lb/> Printed by<lb/> L<hi rend="sc">EVEY</hi> B<hi rend="sc"
            >RO'S</hi> &amp; C<hi rend="sc">O</hi>., Inc.,<lb/>
          <pubPlace>Indianapolis</pubPlace>. </docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <pb id="VAC1124-002" n="[1]"/>
      <div1 type="ack">
        <head rend="center">Acknowledgments.</head>
        <p>Grateful acknowledgments for the use of the cuts shown in the following pages are due the
          officers of the Culver Military Academy, the officers of the Vandalia Railroad, the Hon.
          Z. T. Sweeney, Commissioner of Fish and Fisheries of Indiana, and to the printers, Messrs.
          Levey Bro's &amp; Co., for their pains and liberality in producing the work.</p>
        <p>The map is a reproduction of the one prepared by Prof. B. W. Everman, of the U. S.
          Commission of Fish and Fisheries.</p>
        <p rend="right">THE COMMITTEE.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="VAC1124-003" n="[2]"/>
      <pb id="VAC1124-004" n="[3]"/>
      <div1>
        <head type="supplied">MAP OF LAKE MAXINKUCKEE, IND.</head>
        <p><figure>
            <p>MAP OF LAKE MAXINKUCKEE, IND.</p>
          </figure></p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="VAC1124-005" n="[4]"/>
      <pb id="VAC1124-006" n="[5]"/>
      <div1 type="epigraph">
        <head rend="center">MAX-IN-KUCK-EE LAKE.</head>
        <byline rend="center">(By Jerome Burnett.)</byline>
        <lg>
          <l>Ah, here is a scene for a painter,</l>
          <l rend="ti-1">A gleaming and glorified lake,</l>
          <l>With its framing of forest and prairie,</l>
          <l rend="ti-1">And its etching of thicket and brake;</l>
          <l>With its grandeur and boldness of headland,</l>
          <l rend="ti-1">Where the oaks and the tamaracks grow,</l>
          <l>A league with the sunlight of heaven,</l>
          <l rend="ti-1">And the spirit-like shadows below.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Where the swallows skim over the surface,</l>
          <l rend="ti-1">And quaff as they touch the clear wave;</l>
          <l>Where the robins seek out the cool waters,</l>
          <l rend="ti-1">And warily venture to lave;</l>
          <l>Where the sand piper toys with the plashes,</l>
          <l rend="ti-1">And whistles his passionate note,</l>
          <l>And the water-bugs sail like a navy</l>
          <l rend="ti-1">Of fairies for battle afloat.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Where the blackbirds go noisily over,</l>
          <l rend="ti-1">And the mallard wings rapidly by,</l>
          <l>And the heron that flies like a snowflake,</l>
          <l rend="ti-1">Comes down from the clouds in the sky;</l>
          <l>Where the bobolink lights on the flag blade,</l>
          <l rend="ti-1">And so proudly and prettily sings,</l>
          <l>Or watches askance the swift minnow,</l>
          <l rend="ti-1">That out of his element springs.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Where the lilies abloom on the surface,</l>
          <l rend="ti-1">Held down by their cable-like stems,</l>
          <l>And the tints of the bright cardinals,</l>
          <l rend="ti-1">Have the semblance of loveliest gems;</l>
          <l>Where the mosses in festoons are hanging,</l>
          <l rend="ti-1">In the richest of fashion and fold,</l>
          <l>To decorate submarine dwellings,</l>
          <l rend="ti-1">O'er pavements of amber and gold.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Where the spirit of mortal may worship,</l>
          <l rend="ti-1">In the freedom of unwritten creeds,</l>
          <l>Hearing many and joyous responses</l>
          <l rend="ti-1">In the music that comes from the reeds.</l>
          <l>And where in my fancy I've pictured</l>
          <l rend="ti-1">A temple that's builded so high,</l>
          <l>It reaches in grandest proportions</l>
          <l rend="ti-1">From the beautiful lake to the sky.</l>
        </lg>
      </div1>
      <pb id="VAC1124-007" n="6"/>
      <div1>
        <head type="supplied">The Arrival at Culver (Lake Maxinkuckee).</head>
        <p><figure>
            <p>The Arrival at Culver (Lake Maxinkuckee).</p>
          </figure></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb id="VAC1124-008" n="7"/>
      <div1 type="book">
        <head rend="center">HISTORY OF LAKE MAXINKUCKEE.</head>
        <p rend="center">By Daniel McDonald.</p>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head type="supplied">HISTORY OF LAKE MAXINKUCKEE.</head>
          <div3 type="chapter">
            <head type="supplied">HISTORY OF LAKE MAXINKUCKEE.</head>
            <p>One of the most beautiful small bodies of water in the Northwest is, without doubt,
              Maxinkuckee Lake, a brief description of which, written and compiled from various
              sources, will be of interest to those who admire the beauties and grandeur of
              nature.</p>
            <p>The lake is oblong in shape, about three miles long and two and a quarter wide, with
              somewhat irregular shore lines and some small bays and undulations. The shores present
              about ten miles of lake front of almost every character of approach; the level beach,
              the gradual slope, the steep incline, the abrupt bluff, the rounded headland, and
              these of various elevations, from the water's edge to nearly fifty feet in places. The
              water is wholly from springs, except the natural rainfall, there being no inlet that
              may be called such, and springs of delicious water are found everywhere along its
              shores. The banks are bold, clear, shaded, and occupied by all sorts of summer
              cottages, mansions, hotels, club-houses, academies, schools of learning, etc. On the
              west side of the lake a small strip of lowland gives outlet to the surplus water into
              a small lake close by, and thence to the Tippecanoe river some miles southwest. There
              is very little grass, weeds, drift, or other unsightly things in or around the lake,
              and but little brush, trees, logs, or other debris along the shores. All is clean,
              pure, and healthy. Flowing wells abound on the north, east and south sides, and the
              most delicious cool water rushes up to about eight or ten feet above the level of the
              lake on boring a distance of about 50 to 100 or more feet. Once on its shores at
              almost any point, and as long as you remain, be it days or years, the surroundings
              impress you constantly and if there be a particle of love for the beautiful in your
              composition, that sense is called into action at all times and on all occasions, in
              sunshine or in storm, the beauties of spring, the charms of summer and the glories of
              the autumn.</p>
            <p>Surrounded with unbroken forests, as the writer has seen it, with the deer drinking
              of its limpid water without fear of molestation, the wild fowl floating on its bosom,
              the forest songsters noisy amid the otherwise silent woods on all sides, and the few
              hardy pioneers with their new beginnings and humble surroundings, scattered here and
              there within easy reach of it, it was a gem of imperishable beauty.</p>
            <p>Again, surrounded as it is now with fertile and highly cultivated farms, charming
              cottages, and handsome dwellings with white tents amid the trees, cozy hamlets on
              either side, railroad stations and conveniences, its surface covered with sail boats,
              row boats, yachts and steamers, and on all sides the pleasures of fashion and those
              seeking relief from ennui, overwork or study; music, dancing and social gatherings of
              strangers from all quarters and temporarily fraternizing, to each and all it is still,
              notwithstanding the marvelous changes that have been wrought during the past more than
              half century, what it was to the Indian&mdash;the <pb id="VAC1124-009" n="8"/>
              sparkling water&mdash;the beautiful Maxinkuckee. Once having come within the witching
              spell of its voiceless charms, in the language of Othello, we can say: "If heaven
              would make me such another world of one entire chrysolite, I would not give thee for
              it."</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">STATE GEOLOGIST'S REPORT.</head>
            <p>Maurice Thompson, one of Indiana's most beloved authors, was State Geologist, and in
              his report for 1886, he spoke of the lake as follows: <q rend="blockqutoe"
                  ><p>"Max-in-kuck-ee.&mdash;In many respects this is the most beautiful of the
                  multitude of small lakes with which northern and northwestern Indiana is studded.
                  Its shores are high, beautifully rounded, and clothed with the native forest. The
                  waters are clear and cold. Hundreds of springs flow out from the banks, and many
                  more rise from the bottom of the lake. Very few weeds grow in the water, and there
                  is far less of moss and peaty formation than is common to our Indiana lakes. Here,
                  to a large extent, sand gives place to gravel, and the beach is firm and clean.
                  Nowhere in the United States is there a lovelier body of pure, cold water. It has
                  become a famous summer resort, and deserves all the good praise it has
                  received.</p>
                <p>"Though it is one of the deepest of our small lakes, it scarcely merits the name
                  of 'bottomless' given it by many of the people who reside on its shores and allow
                  their imagination to fill the blue depths with wonders. The result of our
                  soundings gave seventy-six feet as the maximum depth. This was found at a point
                  almost in the center of the lake, being very slightly to the west of the middle on
                  an east and west line drawn through Long Point and a little to the north of that
                  line. There is, however, a large area of this deep water, perhaps a thousand
                  acres, which will average a depth of fifty feet. A cross section taken by a line
                  of soundings from Long Point on the west shore in a direction about thirty degrees
                  north of east to West Point on the east shore, gave the following depths: Six
                  feet, seven feet, thirty-four feet, seventy-two feet, sixty-eight feet, sixty-six
                  feet, seventy-six feet, sixty-two feet, sixty feet, forty-one feet, thirty-one
                  feet, seventeen feet.</p>
                <p>"The springs which feed Maxinkuckee are very abundant, not only from the shores,
                  but they may be seen in the clear waters at a depth of ten feet gushing up from
                  the bottom, and from the deepest parts of the lake rise columns of cold water
                  chilling the bather like an ice bath. These springs suggested the probability of
                  obtaining flowing wells, and now so many have been found that along the east shore
                  one can scarcely get beyond the sound of the spouting waters. The water from these
                  wells is very clear and cold, and more or less ferruginous, a few of the wells
                  being so highly impregnated with iron as to render the water slightly unpleasant
                  to the taste until one gets used to it. Most of the water, however, is excellent
                  at the first taste, and all of it is perfectly wholesome in use. Indeed, one of
                  the causes of the prevailing good health of the cottagers, as well as the
                  residents on the shores of Maxinkuckee, is found in the purity of the waters of
                  the flowing wells and abounding springs. The borings made to obtain these wells
                  have not <pb id="VAC1124-010" n="9"/> been watched with sufficient care, nor have
                  the meager notes made at the time been sufficiently preserved to enable us to
                  obtain accurate information as to the true depth and character of the strata of
                  each. Enough can be known, however, to prove that at least two, and probably
                  three, strata of water-bearing sand and gravel will be passed through in a bore of
                  two hundred feet, and each of which will lift its water to heights of from six to
                  twenty feet above the level of the lake surface.</p>
                <p>"The construction of the Vandalia Railroad's northern branch to South Bend, with
                  a station at the northwest shore of the lake, so facilitated access that the
                  beautiful groves along the east side began to be dotted with cottages; hotels were
                  established; club houses were erected; steamers began to puff about the new
                  buildings, and a fleet of little white sailboats blew over the water. The
                  cottagers have shown most excellent taste in that they have preserved the natural
                  beauty of the groves and green banks, while building large and costly summer
                  houses, and the careful ornamentation of lawns and groves has handsomely
                  supplemented without destroying the natural beauties of the place."</p></q></p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">FISH COMMISSIONERS' REPORTS.</head>
            <p>The biennial report of Z. T. Sweeney, Commissioner of Fish and Fisheries of Indiana,
              1901-2, is a pretentious volume of over 600 pages, voluminously illustrated, and
              describes the various kinds of river and lake fish common to Indiana. It has, however,
              nothing new in regard to Maxinkuckee not already embraced in this paper. From the
              statement contained in the work of fish deposited in the lake by the United States
              Commission of Fish and Fisheries during the fiscal years from June 30, 1900, to June
              30, 1902, it is shown that 10,000,000 perch pike were so deposited, and of black bass
              during the same period, 800. Those who have watched the catch of fish from the lake
              during that time will wonder what became of all these millions of spawn with which the
              lake was stocked.</p>
            <p>The report of Prof. B. W. Everman, Ichthyologist of the United States Commission of
              Fish and Fisheries, who surveyed the lake and made a complete report of everything
              pertaining to it during the year of 1900 under the direction of the Government, has
              not yet been issued. The map, however, to accompany the report has been printed and a
              few copies have been distributed to those interested in the future of the lake. The
              map is drawn from surveys and soundings made under the direction of Professor Everman.
              The area of the lake is shown to be 1,864 acres. The contour lines of the bottom of
              the lake are from soundings taken on section and half section lines and is the first
              and only map of the "bottom of the lake" ever published. The deepest place in the lake
              is on a line about half way across between Long Point and Maxinkuckee Landing. At that
              point it is eighty-eight feet deep. In the immediate vicinity the depth ranges from
              seventy to eighty-five feet in several places. What is designated as "Sugar Loaf," is
              a few hundred feet north of the deepest place, and the water there is but ten feet
              deep. The "Weed Patch," which is only ten feet deep, is a few hundred feet south of
              the east and west section line, being the north line of section 28, or nearly half way
              across the lake from Long Point to <pb id="VAC1124-011" n="10"/><figure>
                <p>Behold Beautiful Lake Maxinkuckee.</p>
              </figure><pb id="VAC1124-012" n="11"/> Indianapolis Pier on the east side. The "Kettle
              Hole," forty feet deep, is a short distance west of Colonel Farrar's cottage on the
              south side. The remarkable thing about it is, that while it covers only an acre or
              two, the water surrounding it is from six to twelve feet deep. There is a tradition
              that there are some very large fish in the "Kettle Hole," but the experience of the
              writer is that it is nothing but "tradition."</p>
            <p>The map is a valuable production, and undoubtedly the most correct one that has yet
              been made. It is to accompany a full report prepared by Professor Everman embracing a
              description of the numerous varieties of fish found in the lake which is soon to be
              published by the Government.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">ORTHOGRAPHY OF MAXINKUCKEE LAKE.</head>
            <p>The numerous ways of spelling the name of the lake has led the compiler of this
              sketch to investigate the question, and the result is as follows: <text>
                <body>
                  <div type="letter">
                    <opener><dateline rend="right"><address><addrLine>DEPARTMENT OF THE INTERIOR,</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Washington, D. C.,</addrLine></address>
                        <date>September 13, 1889.</date></dateline>
                      <salute>Dear Sir&mdash;</salute></opener>
                    <p>In reply to your letter of the 18th, I have to say that the lake referred to
                      is spelled "Muk-sin-cuck-u" in the official field notes of the survey of the
                      township in which the lake is situated.</p>
                    <closer rend="right"><salute>Respectfully yours,</salute>
                      <signed>W. M. STONE, Acting Commissioner.</signed></closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                    <opener><dateline rend="right"><address><addrLine>AUDITOR OF STATE,</addrLine>
                <addrLine>Indianapolis, Ind.,</addrLine></address>
                        <date>September 27, 1897.</date></dateline>
                      <salute>Dear Sir&mdash;</salute></opener>
                    <p>On examination of our field notes I find in the survey made by Deputy
                      Surveyor David Hillis he spells it "Mek-in-kee-kee." In another place in a
                      survey of a small fraction of land on the lake Jerry Smith, deputy surveyor,
                      spells it "Muk-sen-cuk-ee." This is all the field notes show as to name.</p>
                    <closer rend="right"><salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
                      <signed>A. C. DAILY, Auditor of State.</signed></closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                    <opener><dateline rend="right"><address><addrLine>COUNTY SURVEYOR'S OFFICE,</addrLine>
                <addrLine>Plymouth, Ind.,</addrLine></address>
                        <date>February 1, 1898.</date></dateline>
                      <salute>Dear Sir&mdash;</salute></opener>
                    <p>On examination of the records of the surveyor's office of Marshall county,
                      containing copies of the original field notes, I find the following in regard
                      to the orthography of Maxinkuckee lake. On page 43 of the survey of town 32
                      and 33, David Hillis, deputy surveyor, makes the following note: "There are
                      also several lakes in the county. The Max-in-kuck-ee lake is large and
                      beautiful, with a fine sandy and gravelly margin, supposed to be ten or twelve
                      miles in circumference with an outlet and first rate for fish. July &mdash;nd.
                      1834."</p>
                    <p>In a survey of section 32, range 1 east, Jerry Smith, deputy surveyor, on
                      page 48 says "Set post on 'Muk-sen-cuck-ee' Lake." Also on same page he says:
                      "Meanders of Lake Muk-sen-cuck-ee. Variation 6 degrees E." These records are
                      copies of the original field notes on file in the Land Department of the
                      Auditor of State at Indianapolis, and in the Department of the Interior of the
                      United States at Washington.</p>
                    <closer rend="right"><salute>Yours,</salute>
                      <signed>JOHN C. BUTLER,<lb/> Deputy Surveyor, Marshall
                      County.</signed></closer>
                  </div>
                </body>
              </text>
            </p>
            <p>On page 705 of the revision of the Indian Treaties of the United States, in a treaty
              made at Nees-wau-gee Camp, at the lake between William Marshall and Com-o-za, March
              16, 1838, it is spelled Max-ee-nie-kee-kee.</p>
            <pb id="VAC1124-013" n="12"/>
            <p><text>
                <body>
                  <div type="letter">
                    <opener><dateline rend="right"><address><addrLine>Hartford, Mich.,</addrLine></address>
                        <date>February 5, 1898.</date></dateline>
                      <salute>My Dear Sir&mdash;</salute></opener>
                    <p>Your inquiry of February 3d, relative to the meaning and pronunciation of the
                      word Muk-sen-cuk-ee at hand. I have written it as nearly correct as the white
                      man's o-daw-naw (tongue) can pronounce it. It means in the Algonquin dialect,
                      "There is grass."</p>
                    <closer><salute>Thanking you for the unselfish interest you have taken in my
                        people in advocating their rights connected with the dominant, I am your
                        friend,</salute>
                      <signed rend="right">SIMON PO-KA-GON.</signed></closer>
                  </div>
                </body>
              </text></p>
            <p>(N. B.&mdash;Po-ka-gon was a full-blooded Indian and the last of the Pottawattomie
              chiefs in this part of the United States, prior to his death in 1900.)</p>
            <p>From these official sources it is shown that the usual
              spelling&mdash;Max-in-kuck-ee&mdash;appears but once and that is on the records of
              Marshall County, which is a copy of the original field notes from the records of the
              Auditor of State at Indianapolis, where the auditor says Mr. Hillis spells it
              Mek-in-kee-kee. Therefore, whoever transcribed the field notes of Mr. Hillis from the
              records at Indianapolis, for the records of Marshall County, made a mistake when he
              copied it Max-in-kuck-ee. The record in the department at Washington has it
              Muk-sen-cuck-u. At the time the field notes were made by the deputy Government
              surveyors, quill pens were used and it is possible&mdash;in fact, probable&mdash;that
              the final "u" was intended for "ee," the top running together and making a letter like
              "u." The "i" in sin was probably an "e" with the top run together. This is a
              reasonable conclusion as based on the spelling of Jerry Smith on the Marshall County
              records and at Indianapolis. The correct spelling is undoubtedly Muk-sen-cuck-ee.
              There is no authority for Max-in-kuck-ee. The word from which it was erroneously
              copied is Mek-in-kee-kee, as is shown in the letter of the Auditor of State above
              quoted.</p>
            <p>The name of this lake as now spelled lacks a good deal of being a pure Indian word.
              "Max" is German and the balance of the word is made up of Scotch, Irish, American and
              Algonquin. In making the treaties, etc., the name was taken down by the interpreters,
              as the Indians knew not how to spell or write and the interpreters spelled it
              according to the sound as well as they could and it is therefore not strange that it
              appears in so many different ways. But no matter. The present spelling,
              Max-in-kuck-ee, has come to stay, and no power on earth can change it even were it
              desirable to do so. The railroad company, the Culver Military Academy, the Postoffice
              Department, and the people generally about the lake recognize the present spelling,
              and that fixes it beyond any possibility of change. As to meaning of the word in its
              present form, it has none. Originally it was an Indian word, but what its meaning was
              I have been unable to find out. For a long time it was generally believed that it was
              the name of an Indian chief, but the Government records fail to show that name or
              anything like it. The late Charles Cook, who lived a few miles north of the lake, in
              his early days lived with the Pottawattomie Indians in this region over twenty years
              and understood their language perfectly, said it was the Indian word for moc-ca-sin,
              because the lake was the shape of an Indian moccasin, and further because of the
              prevalence of moccasin snakes about the lake at that time. Simon Pokagon, the last of
              the chiefs of the <pb id="VAC1124-014" n="13"/> Pottawattomie Indians in this part of
              the country, whose death occurred in Michigan a few years ago, in reply to an inquiry
              as to its meaning above quoted, said it means, "There is grass." Pokagon was a
              graduate of Notre Dame University and knew the meaning of words. As his definition has
              no relevance to the lake it is additional evidence that the word as we have it is a
              bungling translation of the original Pottawattomie name. But notwithstanding the
              marvelous changes that have taken place during the more than two-thirds of a century
              since its discovery by the American, what it was to the Indian it is yet to the white
              men of today, the sparkling, laughing water, the beautiful Max-in-kuck-ee. That is
              what it means; let it go at that.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">FIRST SETTLERS ABOUT THE LAKE.</head>
            <p>The owners of the land and the first settlers about the lake of which any record can
              be found were American Indians known as the Pottawattomies. They belonged to the great
              Al-gon-quin family. The first trace we have of them locates their territory in the
              Lake Superior region on the islands at the entrance to Green Bay. About 1817 it was
              estimated that there were in the region north of the Wabash river and south of Lake
              Michigan something more than 2,000 Pottawattomies, nearly one-half of them located in
              the region of country surrounding Maxinkuckee Lake, embracing Marshall, Cass, Fulton,
              Pulaski, St. Joseph and Kosciusko counties. At that time they had no uniform abiding
              place or residence. During the fall, winter and a portion of the spring they were
              scattered in the woods hunting and fishing. Their wigwams were made of poles stuck in
              the ground and tied together with strips of bark, slender hickory wythes or rawhide
              strings. They were covered with bark or a kind of mat, out of a growth of flag grass.
              There was an occasional rude hut made of logs or poles, but nearly all the dwellings
              were wigwams hastily put up as here described. They raised some corn, but lived
              principally on wild game, fish, fruits, nuts and roots, and were clothed during cold
              weather with blankets and untanned skins.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">INDIAN RESERVATIONS.</head>
            <p>In the year 1836 when Marshall County, embracing the lake, was organized under an act
              of the legislature, there were three Indian reservations bordering on the east shore
              of the lake. One of these was a reservation granted to Chief Nees-wau-gee, containing
              two sections of land. It covered all the ground on which all the cottages north of the
              road leading down to Maxinkuckee landing north to the residence of Mrs. H. H. Culver,
              at the north end of the lake. South of the Maxinkuckee landing road to the south line
              of the farm belonging to Mr. Van Schoiack and east a considerable distance was the
              reservation belonging to an Indian chief named Quash-qua. The Au-be-nau-be reservation
              extended south from the Quash-qua reservation along the east shore of the lake to a
              considerable distance into Fulton County.</p>
            <pb id="VAC1124-015" n="14"/>
            <p><figure>
                <p>Where Lake and Forest Meet.</p>
              </figure></p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="VAC1124-016" n="15"/>
          <div3 type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">CHIEF NEES-WAU-GEE.</head>
            <p>Nees-wau-gee was a chief over a village which was located a few rods north of the
              present residence of Peter Spangler. The log cabin in which he lived was built in 1828
              by Mr. M. H. Scott, late of &mdash;&mdash;, Illinois, who owned a summer cottage on
              the east shore near the residence of Judge John Mitchell, and who died a year or so
              ago. It is fortunate that we are able to correctly locate this log house, the first
              dwelling erected on the lake. The field notes on file in the surveyor's office at
              Plymouth give the following information in regard to it: "Commencing at the southeast
              corner of section 22, township 32 north, range 1 east of second principal meridian,
              thence north 40 chains and 46 links, Nees-wau-gee house 5 chains east, and set quarter
              section corner which is in center of public road running east and west." Therefore,
              starting from the southeast corner of section 22 in the center of the Maxinkuckee road
              running east and west and measuring 20 rods east, then two rods north to the exact
              spot where Nees-wau-gee's cabin stood. The place has been marked so that those who may
              have curiosity in that direction may have no trouble in finding it. In 1836
              Nees-wau-gee entered into a treaty ceding his land to the United States Government and
              agreeing to remove with his band west of the Missouri river within two years. The
              residence which he occupied was an unpretentious log cabin, while his little band of
              about one hundred occupied log cabins or wigwams built of poles and bark. Nees-wau-gee
              was a quiet peaceable citizen chief, and made friends with all the white settlers
              round about who had come in the year or two prior to his leaving. Before the time came
              for him to leave, he determined to go peaceably as he had agreed he would. The day
              before he started he sent word to all the white settlers to come to his village as he
              wished to bid them farewell. A large number assembled, and through an interpreter he
              said substantially as follows: <q rend="blockquote"><p>"My White Brethren&mdash;I have
                  called you here to bid you farewell. Myself and my band start at sunrise tomorrow
                  to remove to an unknown country the Government of the United States has provided
                  for us west of the Missouri river. I have sold my lands to the Government and we
                  agreed to leave within two years. That time will soon expire, and according to the
                  agreement we have made we must leave you and the scenes near and dear to all of
                  us. The Government has treated us fairly and it is our duty to live up to that
                  contract by doing as we agreed, and so we must go. The white settlers here have
                  been good and kind to us, and in leaving them it seems like severing the ties of
                  our own kindred and friends. We go away and may never return, but wherever we may
                  be, wherever in life our lot may be cast, we shall always remember you with
                  feelings of respect and esteem. Farewell."</p></q></p>
            <p>The old chief was visibly affected and tears were seen to flow from his eyes. All the
              people present took him by the hand and bade him a final adieu, as well as most of the
              members of his band. Early the next morning, with their personal effects packed on
              their ponies, they marched away in single file, following the Indian trail along the
              east shore to the south end of Maxinkuckee Lake, thence southward to Ke-wan-na, where
              they joined the other bands and immediately proceeded on their long <pb
                id="VAC1124-017" n="16"/> and wearisome journey. Nees-wau-gee was a good Indian, and
              Captain Crook is to be commended for perpetuating his memory by naming his new and
              elegant double-deck steamer in his honor. It would be most appropriate if the public
              road now known as the Maxinkuckee road, leading down to the lake, on which his cabin
              and village were located, was called Nees-wau-gee avenue.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">CHIEF QUASH-QUA.</head>
            <p>A log cabin was built for Quash-qua on the high ground southeast of Mr. Van
              Schoiack's residence, and a little northeast of the residence of Stephen Edwards.
              There was no village there, however, and how long he lived there is not known. That
              part of this reservation bordering on the lake north from Mr. Van Schoiack's residence
              to the Maxinkuckee landing was at one time without doubt inhabited by the Indians, as
              prior to its occupancy by those now owning ground along the lake shore when it was
              plowed up for cultivation, Indian arrow points and stone implements of various kinds
              were found there in abundance.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">CHIEF AU-BE-NAU-BE.</head>
            <p>The most of Au-be-nau-be's reserve was in Fulton County, and that noted chief never
              lived on that part of his reservation on the lake or in Marshall County. He lived in a
              village bearing his name in Fulton County, but was frequently seen in and about the
              lake. As he is the only Indian whose name has heretofore been perpetuated at the lake
              by the use of his name, a few words as to who and what he was may be of some interest
              in this connection. His reservation covered thirty odd sections of land, and he
              presided as chief over his band numbering two or three hundred men, women and
              children. Polygamy was permitted among the Indians, and Au-be-nau-be provided himself
              with five or six wives. He was very fond of spirituous liquors, and was generally
              pretty full, and when in that condition was very quarrelsome, which resulted in many
              fights and knockdowns. On one of these occasions, when he was more than ordinarily
              drunk, he got into a fracas with one of his wives and in the melee killed her. A
              council of his tribe was called, as the story goes, to deliberate as to what his
              punishment should be. This council, following an ancient custom, decided that a son of
              the murderer should be the avenger of the murder and slay his father. The sentence of
              death was pronounced, and the son was given a certain number of moons to carry it into
              execution. The father had the right to defend himself, and if he could keep out of the
              way and escape the infliction of the penalty until the time had expired he was to be
              considered a free man. His son kept watch of him, and, as he wanted the old man out of
              the way so he could succeed him as chief of the band, he was really in earnest in
              wanting to kill him. Finally the opportunity presented itself. One day the old man
              drank to excess, sat down in a log cabin west of the Michigan road, just over the line
              in Fulton County, about eight miles southeast of this lake, and went to sleep. His son
              having followed him, stole in upon him, pulled his tomahawk from his belt, and, with a
              terrific blow, thrust it into his head up to the handle. The blood spurted to the low
              ceiling above, and with a single groan and struggle, the noted chief, Au-be-nau-be,
              fell over on the floor dead.</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="VAC1124-018" n="17"/>
          <div3 type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">CHIEF PAU-KOO-SHUCK.</head>
            <p>The son, whose name was Pau-koo-shuck, succeeded his father as chief of the tribe,
              and the same year disposed of the lands belonging to the reservation by treaty to the
              government, and with his band in September, 1838, started for the reservation west of
              the Missouri river. According to the account of one who accompanied the Indians on
              that expedition, Pau-koo-shuck, when near the Missouri river, refused to go any
              further and finally escaped and returned to the old hunting grounds. He spent the
              remainder of his days, which were few, hunting and fishing along the rivers and lakes
              in the neighborhood where he had formerly lived. His life, however, had proven a
              failure; his kindred and friends had been dragged from him, and he grew restless and
              discontented, drank whiskey to excess and went from place to place, getting into
              frequent quarrels and fights. In one of these disturbances which occurred at or near
              Winamac, he was so badly hurt that disease set in and he died. The writer of this was
              informed by one who said he was one of the pall-bearers, that the body of
              Pau-koo-shuck was carried from Winamac and buried on Long Point on the west bank of
              Maxinkuckee Lake. Whether this story is true or not is not of much consequence. Human
              bones were found many years ago, and many of the early settlers had implicit
              confidence that Pau-koo-shuck was buried there as stated. Many who were about the lake
              in the early days believed that his ghost came forth on almost every favorable night
              and skipped about on the water, and floated around among the trees and bushes that
              grew on Long Point where he had been buried, like a thing of life, "cutting such
              fantastic tricks before high heaven as make the angels weep." Sometimes he would be
              seen in his little canoe, apparently paddling with all his might for the south east
              shore where his father, Au-be-nau-be had formerly owned a reservation, and while the
              spectator was gazing the ghost would instantly disappear in the rippling waves and
              would be lost to sight. Turning to the shore again, he would be observed floating
              about as if in search of something, and then all at once would disappear and would not
              be seen again for several nights. With the coming of civilization his ghostship has
              permanently disappeared, and the places that knew him so well in the primitive days
              will know him no more forever.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">ONLY TREATY MADE ON THE LAKE.</head>
            <p>A treaty, and the only one made on the lake so far as is known, was concluded at the
              Nees-wau-gee village December 4, 1834, between William Marshall, on behalf of the
              United States, and Com-o-za, a chief of the Pottawattomies and his band. The lake,
              which is named in the treaty, is spelled Muk-ee-nie-kuc-kee. The treaty conveyed to
              the United States two sections of land on the Tippecanoe river for the consideration
              of four hundred dollars in goods and an annuity for one year of four hundred dollars.
              The treaty was signed by William Marshall, Nee-see-aw-quet, Com-o-za, Ah-he-pah-am-sa,
              and Paw-pee, and was witnessed by J. B. Duret, secretary, and Cyrus Taber and Joseph
              Barren, interpreters.</p>
            <p>Cyrus Taber was a wealthy citizen of Logansport and was familiar with all the
              principal Indian chiefs in this part of the country. Joseph Barren was a son-in-law of
              Chief Nees-wau-gee, having married one of his daughters. He kept a little store at the
              village until the Indians removed to the West. Whether he went with them or what
              became of him is not known.</p>
            <pb id="VAC1124-019" n="18"/>
            <p><figure>
                <p>A Launch Starting on a Voyage.</p>
              </figure></p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="VAC1124-020" n="19"/>
          <div3 type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">REMOVAL OF THE INDIANS.</head>
            <p>Mr. Moses H. Scott, whose cottage was on the east shore of the lake, in a
              conversation a year or more ago, said that he had the contract for the building of the
              cabins for Nees-wau-gee and Quash-qua, and that they were erected in 1828-32. He also
              participated in the removal of a large band of Indians that were taken away in 1837.
              In speaking of it he said: "The party who removed the Indians consisted of Col. Abel
              C. Pepper, of Rising Sun, Indiana, Louis H. Sands, John B. Duret and myself. We went
              from Logansport to the Indian village near South Bend, where we collected them. There
              were about 500 removed, most of whom were under Chief To-pin-e-bee. We wished to
              remove Chief Po-ka-gon and his tribe also, but he refused to go and obtained
              permission from the Government to remove his tribe to Saginaw, Michigan. We took the
              500 Indians to Chicago. Our instructions were to get them to Kansas if possible;
              otherwise to Council Bluffs. At a consultation held at Chicago 200 agreed to go to
              Kansas, and I took them there. Sands took the others to Council Bluffs. We had no
              military organization whatever."</p>
            <p>The largest removal of Indians from this part of the country that occurred during the
              removal period took place from Me-no-mi-nee village, five miles north of Maxinkuckee,
              at Twin Lakes, September 2, 1838. A dispute having arisen in regard to the terms of
              the treaty, the Indians refused to go. Under authority of the Government, Gen. John
              Tipton, of Logansport, recruited a company of soldiers and marched to the village.
              They were a few days gathering in the stragglers from the surrounding villages and
              making preparations for the journey. When all was ready the caravan consisted of 859
              Indians, squaws, papooses, etc., the old and the young, the lame, the halt and the
              blind. It was a sorry procession, the details of which it were better to leave untold,
              stating only that 150 persons were lost on the whole way, 102 by death. What amount of
              suffering fell to the lot of these poor Indians every day on this horrible journey it
              is well never will be known. Hundreds of them were daily burning with terrible
              malarious fever so universally prevalent during the warm part of 1838. These hundreds
              were crowded into common rough wagons and compelled to bear the downpouring rays of a
              sultry sun and the only beverage to quench the prevailing thirst dipped from some mud
              stream just drying up. The food was composed of beef and flour cooked as might be
              while encamped for the night. Alas, how these poor little dusky infants must have
              suffered. No wonder that their graves marked the daily journeys. This was the only
              removal in the United States where force was used by the Government, and mention of it
              is made here because it occurred in sight of this beautiful lake.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">THE FIRST WHITE SETTLERS.</head>
            <p>At the end of 1838 the Indians had all gone or been driven away west of the
              Mississippi river, the lands which had been held by them by treaty from the Government
              had been reconveyed to the Government and had been made subject to entry by the white
              people. A considerable portion of the lands surrounding the lake had never been in
              possession <pb id="VAC1124-021" n="20"/><figure>
                <p>A Scene from the Lake Road.</p>
              </figure>
              <pb id="VAC1124-022" n="21"/> of the Indians and was open to entry about 1834-5, and
              most of it had been entered by speculators and others who had decided to make this
              part of the country their future home.</p>
            <p>The first settlers about the lake came in 1836. Several heads of families came in
              1835 and entered lands and early in the following spring built log cabins, cleared off
              little patches of ground, planted corn, potatoes, etc., and early in the summer
              returned to bring their families and take up their permanent residences here. They
              came in a caravan from Southern Indiana in wagons drawn by ox teams, on horseback and
              on foot. They started on their long and tiresome journey on the 12th of July, and
              arrived at the east of the lake July 26, 1836, just six days after the county and
              county seat had been organized, which occurred July 20, 1836. At that time there were
              only about six hundred white people in the county and about fifteen hundred
              Pottawattomie Indians. The household goods of the members of the caravan were
              carefully packed away in the wagons, leaving room for the women and children and the
              supply of eatables prepared for the journey. The wagons were covered with sheeting for
              protection against rain and the hot rays of the sun. Fourteen days were occupied in
              making the trip. The roads most of the distance were through swamps and over log
              bridges, and much of the way was but little better than Indian trails. From
              Indianapolis the Michigan road was followed. The lands for this road had been secured
              from the Indians for the purpose of making a great thoroughfare for their benefit from
              lake Michigan to the Ohio river. It ran through contiguous sections of land, the
              income of which was appropriated to building the road from the mouth of Trail creek,
              at Michigan City, to Madison, Indiana. At that time it had only just been opened
              through this part of the State, and that only to such an extent as to make it passable
              by cutting down the trees and bushes along the line and bridging over the worst
              places, with brush, poles and logs.</p>
            <p>The country through which the road ran at that time was mostly thick-timbered lands,
              and all along was an abundance of wild game and fruits of all kinds, which the hunters
              of the little band brought into camp. The lack of suitable water to drink was the most
              serious difficulty they had to overcome. There were seldom any springs along the way,
              and the water for drinking and cooking purposes was mostly from stagnant ponds and
              small streams which were not much better. Every night on the way they camped wherever
              night overtook them, slept in the wagons and under the trees, the cattle and horses
              browsing about the camp and resting from the day's toil as best they could. The
              mosquitoes and flies were a terrible pest, much more so than people now-a-days can
              imagine. It was late in the afternoon of July 26, 1836, when the tired and worn-out
              caravan obtained first sight of the ever beautiful Maxinkuckee Lake. The glorious sun
              was just making a golden set, "and by the track of his fiery car gave token of a
              goodly day tomorrow." It was indeed, as our own "Hoosier Poet" has so beautifully
              said, "A picture that no painter has the coloring to mock." A sunset on Maxinkuckee is
              always beautiful, and no matter how often seen never loses its charm to the beholder.
              None of them had ever seen a lake before, and the beauty of the scene, <pb
                id="VAC1124-023" n="22"/><figure>
                <p>A View on the East Shore.</p>
              </figure>
              <pb id="VAC1124-024" n="23"/> the rippling water, the rays of the golden sunset, and
              the shore lines, with their "etchings of forest and prairie," left a picture on their
              memory that lasted during life. The final stop was made just east of the lake, not far
              from the residence of the late David R. Voreis. It was twilight then. A signal of
              their arrival in the neighborhood had been agreed upon before they started, and as the
              ox teams were halted at the end of the journey, a long, loud blast was given on a
              conch shell, which resounded and echoed and re-echoed through the trees and over the
              hills, for miles in every direction. The night birds began to carol their sweetest
              melodies and sing their glad songs of welcome. And then the weary travelers listened
              eagerly for the response. It soon came from the residence of Vincent Brownlee, a short
              distance farther away. The echoes of that response still rings loud and clear in the
              ears of all still living who heard it. It was in one sense a most joyful occasion. The
              women who had borne the burden and heat of the long and wearisome days and were
              well-nigh exhausted, cried for joy, and even the stalwart men of the party let fall a
              silent tear that the hardships of the journey to the new country were at an end. Less
              than half a dozen who came at that time are still living, and the writer knows of
              none, except himself, who was then an infant, who still linger about the lake. All the
              others are living elsewhere, or "have gone to join that innumerable caravan that moves
              to that mysterious realm from which no traveler ever returns."</p>
            <p>At that time there was no house about the lake except the log cabin of Nees-wau-gee
              heretofore referred to. The only one of the caravan who settled on the lake was
              Eleazer Thompson, who built a log cabin a year or two later where the residence of
              Mrs. H. H. Culver is now located on the northeast shore. The old cabin still stands
              just north of the Culver residence, but has been remodeled, losing thereby some of its
              primitive beauty. Mr. Thompson was, therefore, the first white settler to take up his
              permanent residence on the banks of the lake. He died a few years later, and the
              property has changed hands many times since then. The elder Adam Mow lived there in
              the early forties, rearing a large family of boys and girls who are well remembered by
              the survivors of that early period in the history of the lake. About that time there
              also settled on that side of the lake, Samuel Jones, Samuel Peeples and Debolt Klein.
              On the lake where the town of Culver now stands lived Ephraim Moor, James Lyon, Minard
              Taplin, Bayless L. Dickson, Dr. L. M. Bowles, and possibly one or two others whose
              names are not now recalled. Among the first fishermen from a distance after summer
              resorters began to come to the lake about 1866, was R. J. Bright (better known as Dick
              Bright), then proprietor of the Indianapolis Sentinel, and later for many years
              Sergeant-at-Arms of the United States Senate, who built a little boathouse at
              Maxinkuckee landing in which he kept his boat and fishing tackle. J. H. Vajen, also of
              Indianapolis, was among the first to discover the beauties of the lake. Peter Spangler
              kept the only hotel, on Nees-wau-gee Hill, and had some heavy plank fishing boats, the
              only boats about the lake at that time.</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="VAC1124-025" n="24"/>
          <div3 type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">ROW AND SAIL BOATS.</head>
            <p>Up to about 1850 the only water crafts about the lake were Indian canoes or
              "dug-outs" as they were called. They were made out of round logs, dug out with a
              foot-adz, so that one person, and sometimes two, could ride in them, if the waves did
              not run too high. They were generally propelled with a long pole, and of course it was
              not safe to venture very far from shore. They were only used for fishing purposes,
              such as seining and spearing. In 1850, Isaac N. Morris, father of Capt. Ed. Morris,
              moved to the lake, locating on the north shore, on the farm now owned by A. N.
              Bogardus. His land ran down to the lake, taking in all the lake front from Lake View
              Hotel grounds to and including the Palmer House. In the spring of 1852 Mr. Morris
              built a flat bottom skiff which he called the "Queen of the Lake." This was the first
              boat other than dug outs on the lake.</p>
            <p>In 1874, W. W. Hill, of Plymouth, then a member of the old Plymouth Club on the east
              side of the lake, built a large sail boat, which he called "The Anna," after a model
              of his own, equipped it with a tall mast, large sail, rudder, and center board. In
              ordinary light breezes it would run steadily and was considered safe. On one occasion,
              in company with three others, Mr. Hill set out for a sail across the lake from the
              east side to Long Point. A dark and threatening cloud was rapidly coming from the
              west, with a light wind blowing from that direction. After a brief consultation it was
              decided that the boat could easily cross the lake before the storm could overtake
              them. The boat was righted about, the big sail unfurled, and the craft sailed away
              rapidly. When about a quarter of a mile out from Long Point, the storm broke in all
              its fury. It proved to be almost a tornado. The mast and sail were blown off
              instantly, the boat capsized, and those in it thrown indiscriminately out into the
              angry billows. The sand-bag ballast had slipped down into the stern of the boat, which
              had sunk to the bottom, the bow being out of the water. There were two life preservers
              in the stern of the boat which Mr. Hill succeeded in getting out and which he gave to
              the two boys, he and the other man with him swimming about and holding to the bow of
              the boat, as it was pounded about, as best they could. The people from the other shore
              saw the boat go down, but after that the wind and rain and hail and breaking waves
              made it impossible to see anything that far away. A double oar row boat with two stout
              men at the oars started for the scene of the disaster, but the wind was so strong and
              the waves ran so high that slow progress was made. Finally the wind abated to some
              extent and the rescuing boat reached the place, not much too soon, however, to save
              the exhausted men from drowning. This is the nearest a fatal sail boat accident that
              ever occurred on the lake, and practically ended the sailing career of "The Anna."</p>
            <p>In 1874, Capt. Ed. Morris built the first flat bottom sail boat, and in the spring of
              1876 built the celebrated sail boat, "Nancy Lee." It took its name from a boat song of
              that name just then quite popular about the lake. He afterwards sold it to the Peru
              Club. He then built "The <pb id="VAC1124-026" n="25"/> Fleetwing," which he used for
              sailing purposes until the coming of the railroad in 1883, when steamers were put on
              the lake and broke up sailing as a business.</p>
            <p>This sketch of the sail boats on the lake would not be complete without brief mention
              of the "Elephant," owned by the Lake View Club, which was launched on the lake in the
              early '80's. It was an 18 by 30 foot craft, built in Chicago for service on Lake
              Michigan. It was the largest sailing yacht ever on the lake, and rode the waves,
              however boisterous the weather might be, with ease and grace. None of the club members
              were expert sailors, and it soon became noised about that there was danger of it
              capsizing. As its name indicated, it proved to be an "Elephant" on the hands of the
              club, and in course of time it was run up on the shore, a bonfire made of it, and now
              only the memory of the "Elephant" remains.</p>
            <p>During the life of the "Elephant," Ed. R. Wheeler, of Shady Bluff, built a large and
              well equipped sail boat, which was intended to be, and probably was, the finest boat
              of its kind on the lake up to that time. It proved to be faulty in its construction,
              leaked badly, and was so much annoyance to the owner that he saturated it with coal
              oil, set a match to it and it went up in smoke.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">STEAM BOATS.</head>
            <p>The first steam boat on the lake was brought from Rochester, Ind., by a man whose
              name can not now be ascertained. It was launched at Maxinkuckee landing on the east
              side in the spring of 1878, and was christened "The Victor." It was a small,
              unpretentious vessel, with a diminutive engine and boiler, and was not considered
              entirely safe. There were not many people about the lake at that time, and the few
              that patronized it did not justify the owner in keeping it on the lake, and it was
              removed elsewhere the same year. And thus "The Victor" was vanquished.</p>
            <p>The next steam boat brought to the lake came from the St. Joseph river at South Bend
              in February, 1883, by a man by the name of Davis. It was called "The Bessie," but when
              the railroad reached the lake early the same year the name was changed to "The
              Vandalia." The patronage was not sufficient to make it a paying investment, and it was
              removed not long after it came to Cedar lake, now Bass lake, in Starke county.</p>
            <p>Capt. R. K. Lord brought the iron clad steamer which he named "The W. R. McKeen," in
              honor of the president of the Vandalia railroad, about the first of April, 1883. Capt.
              Lord purchased it from a man by the name of Conover, at Cleveland, Ohio, where it had
              been run on Lake Erie for the accommodation of the owner. It was a small boat, but
              modern in all its appointments, and had a fair patronage from the first. Capt. Lord
              continued to run it for several years, but becoming despondent, drowned himself in the
              lake a short distance east of Long Point in the spring of 1889. Mrs. Lord continued to
              run it for a few years, when she sold it to a man who removed it to the Lake of the
              Woods. During the first winter it was there, water was left in the boiler and pipes,
              which <pb id="VAC1124-027" n="26"/> were bursted from freezing, and the boat was so
              badly injured that the owner did not consider it worth repairing, and thus ended the
              career of "The W. R. McKeen."</p>
            <p>About 1886 Capt. A. J. Knapp purchased a small steamer which had been built for
              service on Pretty Lake, near Plymouth, but as there was not sufficient patronage to
              justify the owner in keeping it there he sold it to Mr. Knapp, who launched it on
              Maxinkuckee lake in connection with his hotel, "The Arlington," christening it "The
              Lloyd McSheehy," in honor of a son of editor McSheehy, of the Logansport Chronicle,
              and it has been doing service on the lake ever since.</p>
            <p>Capt. Ed. Morris began building boats in 1872. His first White Hall clinker row boat
              was built for B. F. Jones, of Indianapolis, in the spring of 1879. About that time he
              also built boats for N. H. Oglesbee and C. E. Toan, of Plymouth. He built and launched
              the first side wheel steamer "Welcome" in 1885. It was 50 by 14 feet, but was so badly
              built and equipped, owing to lack of experience in boat building, that it proved a
              failure and was abandoned during the year. The next year he built "The Peerless,"
              which he run for ten years, when it was laid aside and the present "Peerless" No. 2
              was constructed. Capt. Morris has the distinction of having been the first to build
              all kinds of boats now on the lake that were built here, except gasoline and naphtha
              launches, and in all has built more than one thousand boats which have been used on
              the lake. This is a record that probably no other man in this country can
              duplicate.</p>
            <p>After the coming of the railroad in 1883-4, naphtha and gasoline launches, steamers
              and sail boats became numerous, so that now it is but the truth to say that no lake of
              its size anywhere is so well stocked as is Maxinkuckee with every kind of up-to-date
              water craft.</p>
            <figure>
              <p>The Peerless.</p>
            </figure>
          </div3>
          <pb id="VAC1124-028" n="27"/>
          <div3 type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">LITERATURE OF THE LAKE.</head>
            <p>The lake has been embalmed in poetry, song and story by some of the most famous
              authors of the State. George O. Work composed and published an instrumental piece of
              music entitled "The Rippling Maxinkuckee," which, however, was nothing out of the
              ordinary and has gone out of print.</p>
            <p>LeRoy Armstrong, an Indiana author of some note, wrote a beautiful short love story
              in which a handsome Indian girl was the heroine, the principal events of which took
              place at the lake and in the vicinity, and was published in the Chicago Herald, on
              which Mr. Armstrong was employed as one of the special writers at that time, about a
              decade ago.</p>
            <p>Mr. John C. Butler, ex-surveyor of Marshall County, under the nom de plume of Hagon
              Deischmartz, published in the Plymouth Democrat, in March, April and May, 1898, a
              serial story entitled, "The Lily of the Valley," a story of Maxinkuckee, in which the
              "Webb is Truth, but the Love is Fiction." In his exordium he pays the following
              tribute to the beautiful lake: <q rend="blockqutoe"><p>"There is no lovelier piece of
                  scenery by its expression of sweet picturesqueness than that in the vicinity of
                  Maxinkuckee Lake.</p>
                <p>"No clearer or diviner waters ever sang with constant lips of the hand which
                  sendeth rain on the just and the unjust than the beautiful Maxinkuckee. No
                  pastures ever brightened in springtime with more passionate blossoming than the
                  sloping hills and moors bordering on its waters; no sweeter homes ever hallowed
                  the heart of the owners with a pride of possession, fain hidden, but
                  self-confessed, than those of the surrounding farms."</p></q></p>
            <p>At a celebration of the Fourth of July, 1878, Judge A. C. Capron, now president of
              this association, responded to the toast, "Our Navy," a portion of which, relating to
              this lake is deemed appropriate in this connection. After speaking at some length on
              the deplorable condition of the United States Navy, he turned his thoughts to our home
              navy, and in relation to Maxinkuckee Lake, he said: <q rend="blockquote"><p>"And now
                  we come to the beautiful Maxinkuckee Lake&mdash;a bright sheet of pure water,
                  surrounded by shady banks and pleasant groves. What a squadron we have there.
                  First and foremost we have the 'Queen Anna,' a magnificent three-decker, spreading
                  wide her snowy sails, of which our well-known townsman W. W. Hill is captain, H.
                  G. Thayer is mate, and C. C. Buck is crew. Go down there almost any time&mdash;and
                  it is worth your while to do it&mdash;you will find Captain Hill in full command,
                  bare-footed, with coat and hat off, ready for a swim in case of an upset. But the
                  way he sails his vessel, makes your head swim in spite of yourself. There is next
                  'Nancy Lee,' manned by Capt. Ed. Morris, who is always on hand with his fast
                  sailing craft, for a fish, ride or race. But our navy would be incomplete without
                  the 'Kittie Mac,' a duck of a boat, clinker built, with all appointments complete,
                  of which my friend here, D. McDonald is captain, mate and crew. Nor must we forget
                  the row of <pb id="VAC1124-029" n="28"/> staunch gunboats, anchored off the east
                  shore, commanded by Captain Spangler, the genial host of the Allegheny House,
                  whose flag is never at half-mast, and whose larder never runs out. These, my
                  friends, are some of the vessels that belong to our Marshall County Navy, and on
                  all occasions, they and their trusty officers and crews, can be depended upon for
                  a ride or a fishing trip, or any kind of warfare you may wish to make upon the
                  finny tribe. Let us be thankful for what we have and not be cast down for what we
                  have not, and may the flags of our home navy wave as long as the fishing is good,
                  and the water holds out."</p></q></p>
            <p>From an address of welcome by Hon. C. H. Reeve, of Plymouth, to the Northern Indiana
              Teachers' Association, held at the lake June 29, 1886, the following charming
              description of the "Beautiful Maxinkuckee" is inserted as a literary gem&mdash;a
              classic in its way. Mr. Reeve said: <q rend="blockquote"><p>"Many years ago, near
                  where we are now located, I came in sight of the lovely lake yonder for the first
                  time.</p>
                <p>"When I first saw it, the primeval forest around it was almost untouched. Some
                  settlers were near it, but mainly the forest came to the margin. Some rushes grew
                  in the shallow spots. A log canoe rocked on the shore near me as the light waves
                  pulsated to and fro. The sunlight glinted from the surface of the water and the
                  whole space above was filled with a kind of glowing haze I have seen nowhere else.
                  The undulations of the shores and the deep green of the trees were reflected in
                  black shadows from the water below. Near me a robin was caroling his liquid song.
                  The red-winged blackbird flew chirping across the narrow bends, alighting now and
                  then on the limber twig of a bush, or some stout bulrush that bent to the water
                  and allowed him to seize something he saw and wanted. The lazy gulls rose and
                  fell, and turned from side to side as they crossed and recrossed above the water.
                  Here and there in some still spot a fish would spring out and leave a circlet of
                  tiny waves following each other in glowing circles, soon broken by others made in
                  like manner near by them. Some wild ducks arose from near the shore with a cry of
                  alarm and winged a rapid flight around the bends to light in some obscure place.
                  Away near the opposite shore a figure sat in a dugout, holding a pole that would
                  occasionally rise to the perpendicular and then come down to the horizontal, and
                  it looked as completely alone as if it were the only being in its form alive.
                  These trifling incidents attracted momentary notice only. But the lights and
                  shades; the outlines and the undulations; the glittering and shimmering of sun and
                  water and shadowy reflections; the life and motion and stillness; the strange
                  mellow haze, like an invisible veil, yet obstructing no light, that was above and
                  over it all like a halo; the something, indescribable and seen nowhere else, were
                  before me in the fullness of Nature's most perfect work. I reined in my horse and
                  sat still on him, almost entranced by the indescribable feelings created by the
                  scene. There are no words I know to describe it. It could be felt&mdash;a glow of
                  pleasure and wonder mingled with awe&mdash;a sense of beauty with a glow of
                  exaggeration that went beyond words for comparison.</p>
                <p>"I had met an Indian only a few moments before seeing the lake; just up yonder on
                  the road coming through the woods. He was <pb id="VAC1124-030" n="29"/>
                  bare-headed, had on a calico shirt, deerskin leggings and moccasins and carried a
                  gun; and he had told me in broken English with short pauses between the words
                  about the road I desired to follow. 'Go so,' he said, pointing the drection,
                  'see&mdash;big&mdash;trail. Mabbe&mdash;go&mdash;so,' pointing another direction,
                  'see&mdash;chemoke&mdash;man's&mdash;wigwam. Yes.' That was, I would soon come to
                  the main wagon road, and following that would come to a white man's house. I
                  followed the first direction, and soon after the weird and beautiful glamour of
                  the wonderful Max-in-kuck-ee was before me. I shall see it always. You can never
                  see it as I did then.</p>
                <p>"But it has another beauty now, that you gaze on. I have them both before me, and
                  year by year have seen the changes as they grew in it and in the country regions
                  round and about. How many can go back to that log canoe, as, half filled with
                  water, it oscillated upon the shore yonder, and step by step follow the changes
                  down to the graceful hulls and sails that daily skim the surface of the lake, or
                  the shapely little steamers that <q rend="blockquote"><p>"'Walk the water like a
                      thing of life.'</p></q> while the echoes on the shore awake to the throbs of
                  their fiery, imprisoned hearts, as the pulsations evolve the forces of their
                  artificial life.</p>
                <p>"To me there is a strange blending of the sights and sounds here now with the
                  memory of those of long ago. The carol of the robin and the bell of the steamer;
                  the whistle of the blackbirds and the scream of the locomotive; the grace of the
                  waterfowl and its rapid flight, and the white-sailed yachts; the presence of the
                  lonely fisherman and the silent Indian; the knowledge of the fewer wants and fewer
                  means of gratifying them then, and the many needs and boundless resources of the
                  present; of the lighter burdens that rested then and the mighty ones that rest
                  now, all pass before me like the cloud-capped towers, the gorgeous palaces and
                  solemn temples created by the baseless fabric of some weird vision."</p></q></p>
            <figure>
              <p>Sunset on the Lake.</p>
            </figure>
            <pb id="VAC1124-031" n="30"/>
            <div4 type="part">
              <head rend="center">POETRY OF THE LAKE.</head>
              <p>Several fine poems have been written concerning the lake, but in this sketch it is
                deemed best to give only the compositions of our own Indiana writers. The following
                tribute to "The Beautiful Rippling Maxinkuckee," is by George H. Taylor, of Terre
                Haute:</p>
              <lg>
                <l>Amid fair Indiana's verdant hills,</l>
                <l>Supplied by crystal springs and sparkling rills,</l>
                <l>There sleeps a lake, a gem of emerald hue</l>
                <l>Whose face reflects the sky's ethereal blue.</l>
                <l>Along its shore, around its crystal deep,</l>
                <l>Tall oaks, grim sentinels, their vigils keep.</l>
                <l>Here, far from men's tumultuous haunts, at rest</l>
                <l>Gleams Maxinkuckee's placid, dimpled breast.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>O, lovely spot, whose tranquil beauty lends</l>
                <l>To human hearts its Sabbath peace and sends</l>
                <l>New life through every frame that breathes the air,</l>
                <l>Or seeks upon thy shore surcease of care.</l>
                <l>'Tis lovely when the skylark soars to meet</l>
                <l>The rosy gleam of morn and with his song to greet</l>
                <l>The god of day, whose flood of golden light</l>
                <l>Dispels the shades, but leaves the hush at night.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>'Tis lovely when at high noon's he</l>
                <l>The varied foliage along its side</l>
                <l>Casts its reflection in the waters clear</l>
                <l>And rears a phantom landscape in the mere.</l>
                <l>'Tis lovely when at eve pale Luna's ray</l>
                <l>Is struggling with the light of day;</l>
                <l>When from yon cliff the whippoorwill's sad note</l>
                <l>Falls on the wave and with the breeze doth float.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Here childhood sports through all the summer day</l>
                <l>Along these shores secure from evil's way;</l>
                <l>Here youth, as o'er the moonlit deep they sail,</l>
                <l>May breathe in softest accents love's sweet tale.</l>
                <l>Here busy prime may taste the fragrant air</l>
                <l>And on the wave forget all toil and care,</l>
                <l>And ripened age, life's vanities resigned,</l>
                <l>Sweet peace and comfort on these shores may find.</l>
              </lg>
            </div4>
            <pb id="VAC1124-032" n="31"/>
            <div4 type="part">
              <head rend="center">THE HOOSIER POET'S TRIBUTE TO MAXINKUCKEE.</head>
              <p>A few years ago, James Whitcomb Riley, Indiana's famous poet, spent some time at
                the lake, and gave his impressions of it as follows:</p>
              <lg>
                <l>The green below and the blue above&mdash;</l>
                <l>The waves caressing the shores they love;</l>
                <l>Sails in haven and sails afar,</l>
                <l>And faint as the water lilies are</l>
                <l>In inlets haunted of willow wands,</l>
                <l>Listless rowers, and trailing hands,</l>
                <l>With spray to gem them and tan to glove&mdash;</l>
                <l>The green below and the blue above.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The blue above and the green below.</l>
                <l>Would that the world was always so&mdash;</l>
                <l>Always summer and warmth and light,</l>
                <l>With mirth and melody day and night;</l>
                <l>Birds in the boughs of the beckoning trees,</l>
                <l>Chirr of locusts, and whiffs of breeze&mdash;</l>
                <l>World old roses that bud and blow&mdash;</l>
                <l>The blue above and the green below.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The green below and the blue above,</l>
                <l>Heigh, young hearts and the hopes thereof&mdash;</l>
                <l>Kate in the hammock and Tom sprawled on</l>
                <l>The sward&mdash;like a lover's picture drawn</l>
                <l>By the lucky dog himself, with Kate</l>
                <l>To moon o'er his shoulder and meditate</l>
                <l>On a fat old purse or a lank young love&mdash;</l>
                <l>The green below and the blue above.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>The blue above and the green below,</l>
                <l>Shadow and sunshine to and fro&mdash;</l>
                <l>Seasons for dreams&mdash;whate'er befall</l>
                <l>Hero, heroine, hearts and all.</l>
                <l>Wave of wildwood&mdash;the blithe bird sings,</l>
                <l>And the leaf-hid locust whets his wings&mdash;</l>
                <l>Just as a thousand years ago&mdash;</l>
                <l>The blue above and the green below.</l>
              </lg>
              <pb id="VAC1124-033" n="32"/>
              <p><figure>
                  <p>Culver Military Academy (The North Shore).</p>
                </figure></p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
          <pb id="VAC1124-034" n="33"/>
          <div3 type="chapter">
            <head rend="center">MISCELLANEOUS.</head>
            <p>What is now the town of Culver, was originally called Union Town. It was surveyed and
              regularly laid out in 1844 by Bayless L. Dickson, the owner of the land on which it
              was situated. The town was resurveyed in 1851, when its name was changed at the
              suggestion of Dr. G. A. Durr. to Marmont, in memory of the French General Marmont.
              About 1898 the name of Marmont was changed to Culver, in honor of Mr. H. H. Culver,
              founder of Culver Military Academy, located on the northeast shore of the lake, and by
              that name it is now known and undoubtedly will continue to be known for all time to
              come.</p>
            <p>Maxinkuckee town was never regularly laid out. Like Topsy, it "jist grow'd." It is
              situated on a high bluff half mile east on the east side of the lake, and contains a
              population of about one hundred.</p>
            <p>Culver Military Academy, on the northeast shore of the lake, was founded in 1894 by
              Mr. Henry H. Culver, a generous and philanthropic citizen of St. Louis, Mo., with a
              view to help the boys of the present day to secure that kind of education which would
              best fit them for college or university, or for an honorable and useful business
              career. A history of the rise and progress of this great institution, only excelled by
              the government academy at West Point, would require more space than is at our command
              in this brief history. In its establishment, Mr. Culver has erected a monument to his
              memory as lasting as the beautiful lake whose banks it adorns.</p>
            <p>The Maxinkuckee Assembly was organized in 1900 by Elder J. V. Coombs. He purchased
              several acres of lake front on the west side of the lake near the town of Culver,
              leased it to the Assembly Association, who erected an auditorium and several other
              buildings. It is owned and managed by the Disciple's Church. Religious and other
              exercises, lectures, musical concerts, etc., have been held there each summer since
              its organization.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <pb id="VAC1124-035" n="34"/>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head type="supplied">FISH AND FISHING IN LAKE MAXINKUCKEE.</head>
          <argument>
            <p><figure>
                <p>Large Mouth Black Bass&mdash;<hi rend="i">Micropterus Salmonides.</hi></p>
              </figure></p>
          </argument>
          <pb id="VAC1124-036" n="35"/>
          <head rend="center">FISH AND FISHING IN LAKE MAXINKUCKEE.</head>
          <byline rend="center">By Judge A. C. Capron.</byline>
          <table rows="18" cols="2">
            <row role="label">
              <cell cols="2" rend="center">THE EDIBLE FISH.</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="label">
              <cell rend="center i">Common Name.</cell>
              <cell rend="center i">Scientific Name.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Black Bass (Large mouth)</cell>
              <cell>Micropterus Salmonides.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Black Bass (Small mouth)</cell>
              <cell>Micropterus Dolomieu.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Rock Bass (Red-eye)</cell>
              <cell>Ambloplites Rupestris.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Crappie (New Comer)</cell>
              <cell>Pomoxis Annularis.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Warmouth (Goggle-eye)</cell>
              <cell>Chaenobryttus Gulosus.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Yellow or Ringed Perch</cell>
              <cell>Perca Flavescenes.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Blue Bream (Blue Gill)</cell>
              <cell>Lepomis Pallidus.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Sunfish (Common)</cell>
              <cell>Eupomotis Gibbosus.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Long Eared Sunfish</cell>
              <cell>Lepomis Megalotis.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Wall-eyed Pike (Salmon)</cell>
              <cell>Stizostedion Vitreum.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Catfish (Bullhead)</cell>
              <cell>Americus Nebulosis.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Calico Bass</cell>
              <cell>Pomoxis Sparoides.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>American Eel</cell>
              <cell>Anguilla Chrysypa.</cell>
            </row>
            <row role="label">
              <cell cols="2" rend="center">NON-EDIBLE FISH.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Long Nosed Gar</cell>
              <cell>Lepisosteus Osseus.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Bow Fin (Dogfish)</cell>
              <cell>Amia Calva.</cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <p>Any history of Lake Maxinkuckee that did not make favorable mention of its fish and the
            opportunity its waters have always afforded for genuine sport to all lovers of the
            "gentle art," would be deemed incomplete to a large majority of those who have lived in
            its vicinity or had been visitors to this famous summer resort, for there is not another
            lake in the State of Indiana, large or small, that has or ever had the enviable
            reputation this lake has always maintained in this respect. And this reputation is well
            and honestly earned. Nowhere else in the State do the edible fishes grow to larger size
            or attain a more delicious flavor than those of this beautiful lake. There are two good
            reasons for this: One, the exceeding purity of its waters; the other, the abundance of
            fish food, both insectivorous and vegetable, found therein. There is no doubt but what
            its water is the cleanest and purest of any lake water in the West. It has no permanent
            surface inlets, its water supply being mainly from innumerable small springs along its
            margin and at the bottom, and from nearly half a hundred artesian flowing wells, which
            reach a depth of from fifty to one hundred and twenty-five feet, located along the
            north, east and south shores, from which there pours, summer and winter, unceasing
            streams of as cold, pure water as ever came from the inner recesses of old mother earth.
            The lake is really an immense whitewater spring, out of which flows through its outlet
            on the west side a goodly stream of sparkling water, averaging some twenty inches in
            depth and eighteen or more feet wide. The contour of the bottom of the lake is of a
            character to afford a great amount of fish food, it being very <pb id="VAC1124-037"
              n="36"/><figure>
              <p>Small Mouth Black Bass&mdash;<hi rend="i">Micropterus Dolomieu.</hi></p>
            </figure>
            <pb id="VAC1124-038" n="37"/> uneven, with a depth ranging from six to almost ninety
            feet, with deep gullies, shallow flats and bars and ridges with steep and sloping sides,
            where several varieties of aquatic plants and lake grasses grow profusely, which furnish
            excellent pasturage for the grazing varieties of fish (and these are more numerous than
            most people imagine), and also hiding places for the newly hatched game fishes and the
            crabs, sticklebacks, minnows and water insects, upon which the large fish are accustomed
            to feed. The bottom of the lake on the north and east, where the water is rather
            shallow, is fairly paved with small cobble-stones, with now and then a good sized
            boulder, where the soft-shelled crabs are found in profusion, which makes a famous
            feeding ground for the black bass during certain seasons.</p>
          <p>The first colonies of white settlers who located themselves at and near the lake were
            not at first much addicted to the fishing habit. They came from southern Ohio and
            Indiana, where there were no lakes and the streams were muddy and afforded little sport
            in that line. To open a new farm in a timber country required the hardest kind of labor,
            and every able-bodied person put in six days of steady work each week in clearing the
            ground for crops, building log houses for shelter and getting ready to live in some
            degree of comfort. All except the very small children were devout church members, and
            such a thing as a fishing excursion on the Sabbath was never dreamed of. But in their
            forced and hurried evacuation of the territory around the lake the Indians had left some
            of their "dugouts," and it was not a long time until the boys were paddling them up and
            along the lake shores, and they soon discovered there were plenty of fish to be seen
            sporting in the clear waters, and of course the next thing was to try and catch them.
            The writer of this history can not, however, learn that any particular attention was
            given to fishing in the lake until about the year 1840. There are yet living in Marshall
            County a few of those who as boys fished there with their fathers in those early times,
            and the stories they tell of the schools of fish to be seen and the quantities caught
            are enough to make the modern fisherman green with envy. With fishpoles cut from the
            grubs, homemade linen lines and hooks of antique make, a couple of farmers would man a
            canoe, paddle to the first bar and with worms and grubs for bait an evening's fishing
            would bring in a bushel of as fine fish as ever swam in lake or river. It was not many
            months before a longer, a trolling line, with bucktail bait, was used, and a pull across
            the lake was all that was needed to furnish a small neighborhood with a hearty fish
            meal. There were no statutory fish laws at that time, and spearing at night was one of
            the favorite methods of fishing, and if the occupants of a boat got less than a hundred
            pounds of fish during a night they considered themselves in bad luck. Between the years
            1850 and 1860 seining the waters for fish became quite common, and loads of fish of all
            kinds were annually taken out of the lake.</p>
          <p>But it was not until in the '60s that the sporting fraternity&mdash;the fishermen with
            rod, reel and line&mdash;began to visit Lake Maxinkuckee. By that time a few fairly
            comfortable row boats had been put on the lake and a small visiting party could find
            accommodation for a day or two <pb id="VAC1124-039" n="38"/><figure>
              <p>Rock Bass (Red-eye)&mdash;<hi rend="i">Ambloplites Rupestris.</hi></p>
            </figure>
            <pb id="VAC1124-040" n="39"/> with some of the farmers near by, and the fame of the lake
            as a fisherman's paradise began to spread abroad. The first lakeside cottage was built
            in the early '70s by a club of about a dozen Plymouth fishermen on the lot now known as
            the McOuat Place. The completion of the I., P. &amp; C. railroad (now the Lake Erie
            &amp; Western) brought the cities along its line within eight miles of the lake, and
            parties from Rochester, Peru and Logansport began to camp upon its shores, and their
            white tents could be seen all through the fishing seasons beneath the shady groves of
            Long Point, Edward's Landing and Peeples' Point. And after the completion of the
            Vandalia railroad to South Bend the Terre Haute people came in goodly numbers. The good
            qualities of the lake were first made known to the Indianapolis people by Hon. Martin H.
            Rice, who had known the lake since 1855, and when the railroad was completed the
            fishermen from the Capital City came up, first singly, then by twos and threes, and
            finally by the dozen, to try their luck in the clear waters of our beautiful lake. They
            found good quarters at the Allegheny House, and they brought along their finest fishing
            tackle, their well-tried fly rods, their Frankfort reels and the most approved
            artificial baits, and they all caught fish&mdash;all kinds of fish&mdash;and enough to
            make a goodly show in their fish baskets, and nearly every man of them had a bundle of
            smashed fishing tackle to take home to prove the truth of his story of the big fish he
            had hooked, but which got away. And the men from these cities came again and again, and
            they caught something besides the fishes; they caught a vision of the glory of the lake,
            with its clear waters, its tree-lined shores, its wooded bluffs, its clean sandy beaches
            over which gurgled the cool waters of its crystal springs, and the vision went with them
            to their homes, to their business rooms, and it would not depart, and they began to long
            for a portion of bluff, of shore or beach, where they might abide for days or months and
            take into their souls all the beauties that vision had revealed to them, and shortly
            they became possessors of jutting points, of stretches of beach, of tracts of wooded
            shores, of acres of the shady bluffs, and there they built the row of artistic cottages
            that now encircle the lake like rich tinted gems set around a luminous pearl&mdash;and
            out of that vision was born the Maxinkuckee Association, the most rational and pleasure
            giving summer resort association in the State of Indiana today.</p>
          <p>And what were the fish these Maxinkuckee fishermen caught? Well, they caught a dozen
            varieties at least, all clean, nice edible fish, all gamy and full of fight, and all
            ready to take the proper bait in season. At the head of the list we must put the two
            varieties of black bass&mdash;the big and the small-mouthed. They are the "king fish" of
            the Indiana lakes, as every real fisherman knows. It is the general opinion amongst
            those who are accustomed to catch black bass that the small-mouthed are the gamiest and
            best fighters of the two varieties, but the big mouthed give plenty of trouble and
            excitement to the fisherman, and in the writer's experience he has found that pound for
            pound the latter variety make just as bitter a fight for liberty and life as do the
            other variety. But the big mouthed grow to almost twice the weight of the small mouthed,
            and as they increase in size they are less active and <pb id="VAC1124-041" n="40"/><figure>
              <p>Crappie (New Comer)&mdash;<hi rend="i">Pomoxis Annularis.</hi></p>
            </figure>
            <pb id="VAC1124-042" n="41"/> when struck do not spring out of water as often or as
            nimbly as when they are smaller; but the big fellows adopt different tactics. They dart
            for the nearest grass or weed patch and once within it they whirl and circle and soon
            wind the fisherman's line around a resisting mass of weeds which gives them a chance to
            tear loose from the hook. This variety of black bass has been known to attain a weight
            of ten pounds and over. A quite well authenticated tradition has it that one was speared
            in the lake in the early '50s, brought to Plymouth and sold, that weighed twelve pounds
            without the entrails. The largest the writer ever saw caught in our lake was taken by a
            lady in the year 1874. It weighed a trifle over seven and one-half pounds. Of late years
            several have been caught that weighed over six pounds. But, after all, the snappy, saucy
            small mouth is the favorite among the fishermen. There is grit and determination in his
            every movement and he keeps the fisherman continually guessing until he is fairly in the
            landing net. Probably more "strikes" of this fish are failures to "catch" than those of
            any other variety in the lake.</p>
          <p>While there is yet a goodly supply of black bass in the lake, it is true that their
            numbers are much less than twenty years ago. Still, good strings have been caught during
            last season and this spring season of 1904, and during the past six or eight years there
            has been very little falling off in the catches, though the number of fishermen has
            increased. The United States Department of Fisheries has started in to replenish the
            lake with the small-mouthed variety, and for several years quite a large number of fry
            have been placed in its waters, and the experienced fishermen are claiming that they are
            now catching the new bass and that they can distinguish quite a difference between the
            old and the new varieties.</p>
          <p>Next in size and interest to the fish gourmand are the wall-eyed pike, or salmon, as
            they are usually named by the people around the lake. They are the most toothsome of all
            the large fishes, having, when properly cooked, a most delicious flavor of their own,
            while the rich, even grain of the flesh presents a most appetizing appearance. They are
            not as numerous as formerly, but they are caught during the entire season and the number
            taken is considerable. They frequent the lowest and deepest growths of weeds and grasses
            in their search for food and are usually caught in from twenty-five to forty feet of
            water (though occasionally one will be found in much shallower spots), and the long pull
            makes the catch quite exciting, especially if the salmon wakes up to the situation and
            gives fight. All at once he becomes ambitious, often just as the fisherman is about to
            slip the landing net beneath him, and he puts up a battle worthy of a black bass and it
            takes skill and caution to save him. They are quite handsome fish and present an
            appearance of health and solidity that is entirely satisfactory to the lucky one who
            makes the catch. These fish are always of good size, weighing from two to five pounds,
            and heavier ones are occasionally caught, and, strange to say, no really small salmon
            have ever been caught in the lake; at least, this is the writer's experience. The United
            States Fish Department has been trying for the past few years to replenish the lake with
            these <pb id="VAC1124-043" n="42"/><figure>
              <p>Warmouth (Goggle-eye)&mdash;<hi rend="i">Chaenobryttus Gulosus.</hi>
              </p>
            </figure>
            <pb id="VAC1124-044" n="43"/> fish, and probably fifteen millions of fry have been
            planted here, and it is expected that in a reasonably short time the wall-eyes will be
            more plentiful than they were half a century ago.</p>
          <p>There are two other varieties of fish in the lake that deserve special mention for
            their good qualities, viz., the yellow-ringed perch and the blue bream, often called the
            buffalo blue gill. The perch are the most plentiful of any fish in the lake, and larger
            or finer ones are nowhere caught. They are by all odds the handsomest fish in our
            Indiana waters, and to fish for them is the especial delight of the lady cottagers who
            spend the season at our lake. They are caught in great numbers on the bars and about the
            weed and grass patches in the early season; later they are found in deeper water. The
            large perch are especially brilliant fish. Dressed in ribbons of silk and satin they
            come out of the water wet and shining, their golden yellow sides and red and orange fins
            making pleasing contrast with their green brown stripes as they flash and
            sparkle&mdash;genuine jewelled water sprites. They are of a most delicious flavor when
            properly cooked, and they really furnish the greater part of the fish food used by the
            lake cottagers. They often grow to weigh a pound and a half, though the greater number
            caught weigh less than half a pound. Every year some extremely large catches are made,
            often as many as 200 by one fisherman. Not long ago a catch of 110 perch weighed
            eighty-seven pounds, and the writer has seen strings of these fish laid upon the shore
            fully six feet long, all of which indicates that the "fish hog" is not yet an extinct
            species.</p>
          <p>The notable thing about the blue gills or bream in Maxinkuckee Lake is their uncommonly
            large size, the majority of them weighing a pound or more. They are a handsome, active
            fish, and game to the backbone. When struck they have a way of darting sidewise swift as
            an arrow, and for a time they pull like a three-pound bass. It is a fact that more tips
            of fine rods are broken by these gritty fish in their sudden springs and dartings while
            trying to escape than in all other ways put together, and much the safest way of fishing
            for them is to use a long, light bamboo. They are a most excellent pan fish, their flesh
            having a peculiar sweetness much liked by most fishermen and their families. At times
            they can be caught in great numbers, and again not a blue gill can be got in the lake
            for a month. They are great wanderers, and except when on their beds they do not stay in
            one locality any length of time. When the blue gill spawning beds are found the word
            goes quickly around the lake and a dozen or more boats loaded with country boys and men
            will be early on the grounds, and, with bamboo poles, cork on line and fish worms for
            bait, the murder of the innocents goes steadily on until the spawning is done or the
            last fish caught. And the sporting crowd and the cottagers are not a whit behind the
            country folk in their eagerness to get a share of the sport and fish. No wonder that the
            blue bream are getting scarce, and the State fishing laws do not protect them.</p>
          <p>The other varieties of edible fishes found in the lake may properly be classed as
            pan-fish, of good quality every one, but they need no extended mention. From rock bass
            to catfish, all are gamy and put up the <pb id="VAC1124-045" n="44"/>
            <figure>
              <p>Yellow or Ringed Perch&mdash;<hi rend="i">Perca Flavescenes.</hi></p>
            </figure>
            <pb id="VAC1124-046" n="45"/> best fight possible. The crappies and calico bass both
            take the fly at times, when they afford rare sport, for many of them grow to large size,
            often weighing a pound and a half or more. They are gamy and full of fight, having some
            of the tricks of the blue bream, and the fly rod fisherman is often put to his best to
            land his catch. There are two rare species of sunfish&mdash;the long-eared and the
            butter-bellies&mdash;both noted for their beautiful markings. Only a few are caught in
            the lake. The smaller species of sunfish are quite plentiful, and as they frequent
            shallow water, especially about the piers and landings, they afford rare sport for the
            small children of the cottagers, who industriously fish for them and religiously insist
            on having all they catch cleaned and cooked for their own especial benefit, ofttimes
            much to the annoyance of the culinary department.</p>
          <p>It will hardly do to omit all mention of the two species of non-edible fish which to
            some extent infest the lake. The meek-eyed dogfish quite often makes himself manifest,
            much to the annoyance and always to the disappointment of the fisherman, for his
            "strike" is exactly like that of the wall-eye. A bitter fight is sure to follow, for Mr.
            Calva never knows when to quit, and it is only after ten or fifteen minutes of keen
            excitement when the flat tail and the mouse-like eyes of the catch comes to view that
            the situation clears up, and a collapse follows. Several mild "cuss" words from the
            fisherman and the other occupants of the boat are in order, and they are brought forth
            with the greatest unanimity.</p>
          <p>During July and August the long-nosed gars make themselves manifest, greatly to the
            disgust of the fishermen. Apparently they are getting more plentiful each year. They
            frequent the edges of the bars, where, as a usual thing, the trolling is the best, and,
            as their strike is similar to that of the black bass, they get up as much or more
            commotion as the dogfish. To the novice who enjoys a pull with anything that gets on his
            hook a tussle with a five or six-pound gar is rare sport. If, however, he manages to get
            his ugly customer in his boat, the three feet of round solid fish and the six-inch bill
            filled with sharp teeth discourages all attempt to disengage his tackle, and hook and
            snood are quickly sacrificed and the ugly "beast" dumped in short order. It is said that
            the gars are of some use as scavengers, but the fishermen would gladly forego this if
            the lake could be rid of them.</p>
          <p>According to Professor Everman there are more than thirty varieties of minnows in the
            lake. They are extremely numerous and furnish an inexhaustible supply of bait.</p>
          <p>To be even moderately successful one must be fairly well acquainted with the "lay of
            the land" in the lake. There are considerable areas that are absolutely barren of fish
            at all seasons, where one may fish a week and not get a nibble. The large map of the
            lake made under the supervision of Prof. Barton W. Everman, Ichthyologist of the United
            States Fish Commission, furnishes an accurate description of the contour of the bottom
            of the lake, and it may be studied with profit by all newcomers who wish to get a decent
            catch of fish. Where the water is <pb id="VAC1124-047" n="46"/><figure>
              <p>Blue Bream (Blue Gill)&mdash;<hi rend="i">Lepomis Pallidus.</hi></p>
            </figure>
            <pb id="VAC1124-048" n="47"/> sixty, seventy or eighty feet deep there are no fish,
            unless it be a few gars swimming near the surface in a migration from one side of the
            lake to the other.</p>
          <p>And there are days when the lake appears absolutely without fish of any kind, when the
            experienced fisherman with both live and artificial bait may search the bars and gullies
            of the very best fishing grounds from "morn till dewy eve" with not a single strike. But
            even such a day is not without its recompense to the genuine fisherman, for he is always
            a lover of nature in her various moods. After a fruitless pull of a couple of hours and
            he realizes that the fish are hugging the bottom among the lake weeds and grasses and
            beyond the temptation of his alluring baits, he can drop his oars and drift idly in the
            summer breeze that brings to him across the lake the odor of the woods, the fields or
            the new mown hay, and watch the changing colors of the lake as the shadows of the fleecy
            clouds creep slowly over the surface; or, looking shoreward beyond the line where land
            and water meet his eyes will rest upon a sylvan picture of wooded bluff and shady beach
            with their bright tinted cottages nestling among the trees, wordless invitations to the
            weary to come and find rest therein, and, as the evening comes on and the winds are
            hushed and all the west, both sky and water, is painted in gorgeous colors by the
            glorious sunset, there comes creeping over the glassy lake a tinkling music as of water
            bells touched by the sparkling streams that gush from the flowing wells and splash upon
            the margin of the lake. And, as his boat glides to his landing place, the joy and
            sweetness of life fills his being with a new and thrilling sense of pleasure, and as he
            picks up his creel and saunters slowly toward his cottage he feels in his heart more
            than half glad that it is an empty creel&mdash;with nothing dead in it. Surely such a
            day is not a lost day, not a day to be regretted!</p>
          <p>And there are other days, red-letter days for the fisherman; days when every good-sized
            fish in the lake appears to have wakened up hungry from a two or three days' snooze in
            the grass, and every one of them seems to be hunting the fisherman's bait; and, whether
            anchored on the edge of a bar or trolling deep among the gullies, the time between
            strikes is little more than enough to adjust a new bait and get the lines well out
            again. On these days the catch of a couple of hours half fills the creel with three or
            four varieties of goodly sized fish&mdash;all the small ones discarded and thrown into
            the lake. On these days the fisherman finds no time to watch the shadows on the lake; no
            matter how gorgeous the sunset, he sees it not. The winds may waft the odor of the
            spices Araby across the lake&mdash;he perceives it not; the music of the rippling
            streams that gush from the flowing wells is drowned by the chirr of his reel, and the
            cottage-lined shores are simply a landing place, where he will beach his boat and step
            proudly upon the shore, holding up to the gaze of family and friends his wonderful catch
            on this his lucky day. Well, it's only human nature to enjoy success, and these are the
            days the fisherman loves to talk and think of&mdash;the days he remembers best.</p>
          <pb id="VAC1124-049" n="48"/>
          <p><figure>
              <p>Sunfish (Common)&mdash;<hi rend="i">Eupomotis Gibbosus.</hi></p>
            </figure></p>
          <pb id="VAC1124-050" n="49"/>
          <p><figure>
              <p>Long Eared Sunfish&mdash;<hi rend="i">Lepomis Megalotis.</hi></p>
            </figure></p>
          <pb id="VAC1124-051" n="50"/>
          <p><figure>
              <p>Wall-eyed Pike (Salmon)&mdash;<hi rend="i">Stizostedion
                  Vitreum.</hi><lb/>Catfish&mdash;<hi rend="i">Americus Nebulosis.</hi></p>
            </figure></p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="VAC1124-052" n="51"/>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head rend="center">THE MAXINKUCKEE LAKE ASSOCIATION.</head>
          <byline rend="center">By W. T. Wilson.</byline>
          <p>In America the Civic League has become an institution. To aid the officers of the law
            by intelligent organized action, backed by conservative public opinion, private citizens
            can do much to advance neighborhood improvement, in highways, in good order, in health,
            in reputation and in the social pleasures of life. This is particularly true of a
            community like that about Lake Maxinkuckee. The natural beauty of the place, its growing
            repute as a summer pleasure resort, the fish supply, the large number of transient
            visitors as excursionists and the number of residents who are away from their summer
            lake homes during a part of the year, all call for protection, regulation, and fostering
            care, which the regular township machinery can not easily supply.</p>
          <p>To fill such a want, the Maxinkuckee Association, afterwards called the Maxinkuckee
            Lake Association, was organized by the residents of Union Township, about the lake, in
            the summer of 1897. Trespassing tramps, in that part of the year when many summer homes
            were vacant, had given trouble. Fish culture and protection, sanitary regulation and
            local improvements in roads, trees, walks and piers, all called for united action.</p>
          <p>In such an organization much depends upon its first officers. The Maxinkuckee
            Association was fortunate in this respect. Mr. Otto Stechhan, of Indianapolis, president
            for 1897, 1898 and 1899, while a busy manufacturer at the State Capital, was, and is, an
            enthusiastic lover of Maxinkuckee, and as sailor, fisherman and home builder, had done
            much to advance and improve the community. His "Indiana" home on the east lake shore is
            a picturesque and attractive place, worthy of the banks of the Rhine or Lake Geneva.
            With the energy, enthusiasm, and thoroughness of his nature, and the force of his
            excellent example, Mr. Stechhan did much to put the Association in a position to command
            the respect, and serve the wants of the community.</p>
          <p>Mr. Franklin Vonnegut, also a busy merchant of Indianapolis, secretary of the
            Association in 1897 and 1898, perhaps more than any other, by his public spirit, devoted
            industry, and organizing capacity, gave life to the organization in its early efforts
            which is still felt in its work. The Association met a serious loss when Mr. Vonnegut's
            family and business cares prevented his longer coming to the lake.</p>
          <p>Mr. W. F. Kuhn, of Indianapolis, treasurer in 1897, 1898 and 1899, was a trusty "keeper
            of wampum."</p>
          <p>These officers, with the veteran Capt. Edward Morris, who, ever since the days of the
            "Nancy Lee," has been one of the lake's guardians, and Mr. D. G. Walter, an enterprising
            citizen of Culver, constituted an executive committee, which gave the Association
            organic life and the generous support of the membership and the community gave it soul
            and strength.</p>
          <p>A patrolman, Mr. Buswell, the engineer of the "Peerless" steamer, was employed to keep
            good order and sanitary regulation, and did excellent work policing the neighborhood. In
            1899 Mr. Buswell was succeeded by Mr. L. C. Wiseman, of Culver, who still continues very
            efficiently the patrol work. A card to him at Culver from any of the members will bring
            a prompt report as to the condition of property, and the public health and order are his
            greatest care.</p>
          <p>Committees on Roads and Shade Trees, Health, Boats and Piers, Fish <pb id="VAC1124-053"
              n="52"/> and Fish Culture, Law and Order, Membership, Entertainments and Regattas,
            Finance, History and Literature were appointed and did excellent work.</p>
          <p>In 1899 Mr. Franklin Vonnegut, being absent by reason of business cares and the health
            of his family, was succeeded as secretary by W. T. Wilson, of Logansport, Ind., who
            served one year as secretary, and in 1900 and 1901 served as president for those years.
            In 1900 Mr. A. Herz, of Terre Haute, was chosen vice-president and served two years. In
            1900 Mr. Kuhn retired as treasurer and Mr. J. G. Mueller, of Indianapolis, was elected
            and served in that office faithfully for two years.</p>
          <p>For two years Dr. Everman and his assistants studied the fish life and food at
            Maxinkuckee&mdash;classified its fish&mdash;found two new varieties among its darters,
            surveyed the banks and bottoms and prepared a map showing the depths of water, shore
            outlines and feeding grounds. Dr. Everman has used the organization to help his work and
            has been a pleasing factor in the work of the Association. In 1900 at the annual meeting
            he delivered an exceedingly interesting lecture on the methods of the Fish Commission
            work, and was followed by his friend, Dr. Scovell, of Terre Haute, also a member of the
            Association, on the fish foods, illustrated by the vegetation of Lake Maxinkuckee.
            Through the kind effort of Dr. Everman many millions of fish have been deposited in the
            lake from the Government hatcheries. In this work the Association has aided by
            collecting money for freight, and through its members, Captains Morris, Crook and Knapp,
            with their steamboats, in putting the fish in proper waters. In this connection a good
            story is told by himself on our late excellent treasurer, Mr. J. G. Mueller.</p>
          <p>Mr. Mueller had enthusiastically collected money to pay freights on the fish spawn for
            the lake. The next week he spent a day at the lake, fished all day and had never a bite
            at his hook. Thoroughly disgusted he wrote a friend that he was convinced that the
            wall-eyed pike fry from the Fish Commission had so sated the appetite of the game fish
            that they would not touch his bait and that the whole ten million then deposited must
            have been eaten.</p>
          <p>Dr. Everman, in his Government work, has studied the fish of Porto Rico, Hawaii,
            California and Alaska, but he turns to Lake Maxinkuckee in our own State as his first
            love. Like our Hoosier poetess, he seems by his returning footsteps each season to say
              <q rend="blockquote"><lg>
                <l>"The wind of heaven never fanned,</l>
                <l>The circling sunlight never spanned</l>
                <l>The borders of a better land</l>
                <l>Than our own Indiana."</l>
              </lg></q></p>
          <p>The Vandalia Railway, which follows the west lake shore, has also been a valued and
            useful member. Through its efficient superintendents, Messrs. F. T. Hatch and J. O.
            Crockett, it has done much to advance the general work, besides making many handsome
            improvements on its own account. The Lake View Hotel and the handsome grounds, extending
            to the depot, are its property. It has for years maintained a landing pier at the depot
            shore, and has put its road tax work on the roads adjoining its lake properties. It has
            carried the Government fish cars over its lines without charge and has aided the Fish
            Committee by placing a screen over the outlet to keep fish from escaping down
            stream.</p>
          <p>If all our members would do as well in proportion to their opportunities we should soon
            have a marked improvement at Maxinkuckee.</p>
          <p>Culver Academy is also a member of the Association. Besides the <pb id="VAC1124-054"
              n="53"/> handsome showing of its buildings and its work proper it has done much to
            improve lake sanitation, draining the shallows on the shore into beautiful canals and
            moats, drawing off sewage into the fields, working its highways into drives, aiding the
            social features of lake life by the charming hospitality, not only of the institution,
            but of its commandant, Col. A. F. Fleet, and of the corps of professors and students.
            Long may its saluting gun at morning and sunset greet the flag and its "Star Spangled
            Banner" give music to the patriotic teaching of our youth. The Culver family are high in
            the esteem of the people who love and know Lake Maxinkuckee. To Mr. H. H. Culver, now
            deceased, the founder of the Academy, and to his widow and sons, who follow his example
            in enterprise and public spirit, we look as to our best friends.</p>
          <p>Our newspapers, particularly the Culver Herald and Citizen, have ever been kind,
            publishing reports of meetings and accounts of regattas and urging good roads and public
            work and improvement on their readers.</p>
          <p>In 1900 Mr. John C. Capron, of Plymouth, was elected and served two years as secretary,
            with much efficiency. In 1902 the Association chose for its officers Hon. A. C. Capron,
            judge of the Marshall Circuit Court, as president; Frank R. New, Esq., of Indianapolis,
            vice-president; Henry M. Speyer, of Culver, for secretary; Richard E. Edwards, of Peru,
            Ind., treasurer; and for its Executive Committee with these officers: Capt. Edward
            Morris; Mr. A. N. Bogardus, Trustee of Union Township; Mr. J. O. Ferrier, of Culver; Mr.
            A. Herz, of Terre Haute, and W. T. Wilson, of Logansport. These officers still continue,
            with the exception of Mr. Edwards, who was called away by business interests and was
            succeeded at his own request, by Mr. H. R. Bliss, of Indianapolis, in 1903.</p>
          <p>The Association is particularly fortunate in these officers. Judge Capron is known as a
            fair-minded gentleman, who has been and can be trusted by his neighbors with their best
            interests. The judge's love for the lake is of long standing and grows out of his love
            of nature herself. Mr. Speyer, the secretary, is a merchant of Culver, known to the
            whole community for his public spirit and high character. Mr. Bliss, the treasurer, has
            a beautiful home on the east shore of the lake, and is enthusiastic in his love for the
            place. The resident members of the Executive Committee, Captain Morris and Messrs.
            Bogardus and Ferrier, are good citizens, who need no introduction to Union Township
            people. The Association is equally fortunate in having members who are able to aid it in
            its work. Prof. Barton W. Everman, honorary chairman of the Committee on Fish
            Protection, is the Ichthyologist of the United States Fish Commission. He has long been
            an admirer of Lake Maxinkuckee and selected it as a specimen study of our Indiana
            waters.</p>
          <p>The steamers and their captains, Edward Morris, Oliver Crook and A. J. Knapp, have been
            good and useful members. Inspection of boilers, life-saving apparatus, piers, landings,
            running schedules, and many like works have cheerfully come at the request of the
            Committee on Boats and Piers, and there is "more to follow."</p>
          <p>The work of the Road Committee, aided by Mr. A. N. Bogardus, the township trustee, and
            a member of the committee, has brought our road tax into several miles of beautiful
            drives, and a good road all around the lake is one of the promises of the near
            future.</p>
          <p>Sailing on the lake is one of its pleasures and attractions. To encourage such
            entertainment the Association, in 1901, appropriated fifty dollars for the purchase of
            challenge cups for regattas and assisted in the organization of the Aubbeenaubbee Yacht
            Club.</p>
          <pb id="VAC1124-055" n="54"/>
          <p>That veteran mariner, Mr. Henry C. Adams, of Indianapolis, a leader in this as in all
            good works, became its first commodore, and the club has become a permanent feature of
            the place. Regattas have been held frequently in the seasons of 1902, 1903 and 1904, and
            the fleet of white-sailed yachts is a beautiful sight.</p>
          <p>The history and literature of a place like this is interesting and the Committee on
            History, headed by the late lamented Judge John Mitchell, and with the efficient aid of
            Hon. Daniel MacDonald, who has been for so many years an authority on Marshall County
            historical questions, has supplied the principal sketch herewith presented.</p>
          <p>Of the members who have been conspicuously helpful and who are known throughout
            Indiana, but whose modesty has kept them from official mention hitherto, it is right to
            name Messrs. Charles H. Brownell and R. A. Edwards, of Peru; John M. Judah, A. M. Ogle,
            B. and C. Vonnegut, J. C. Schaff, Simon P. Sheerin, Armin Koehne, J. H. Vajen, Hervey
            Bates, and John Twiname, of Indianapolis; Joseph Strong, W. H. Albrecht and Louis
            Duenweg, of Terre Haute; M. W. Simons, of Plymouth; A. J. Murdock, J. E. Barnes, F. M.
            Harwood, W. H. Snider, and H. J. McSheehey, of Logansport.</p>
          <p>The Association has also a lamented roll of honor in its deceased members. Messrs. L.
            B. Martin, of Terre Haute; Milton Shirk and Judge John Mitchell, of Peru; E. R. Wheeler,
            of Chicago; A. B. Gates and W. E. Vajen, of Indianapolis, all of whom have left the
            memory of good neighbors and helpful citizens, and who are missed in the places which
            once knew them with so much respect and esteem. In a sketch such as this it is, of
            course, impossible to note all the excellent work done and attempted or all the
            possibilities of the future. All such a narrative can do is to give outlines which may
            lead inquirers to a closer knowledge.</p>
          <p>The Association has about sixty members. Those named hereinbefore are by no means all
            who have aided its work. No slight is intended for the unnamed. Their work will yet
            praise them, for all have done well. There should be several hundred members. When the
            work it can do is well appreciated, it is hoped that the Association will include every
            substantial and enterprising citizen of Union Township, as well as every lover of the
            beautiful Lake Maxinkuckee in the State of Indiana.</p>
          <p>Lake Maxinkuckee is the best and most attractive feature in Marshall County, and the
            people who want to see the neighborhood grow in beauty, in health and in fame, should
            all unite in the common work of forwarding such ideas by united effort. During the
            season of 1904 a similar association was organized at Wawassee. Throughout the United
            States civic leagues have been the instruments of improvement, as we trust will continue
            to be the Lake Maxinkuckee Association.</p>
          <p>Among the members now enrolled are such well-known citizens as Dr. O. A. Rea, A. N.
            Bogardus, Edward Morris, George Peeples, J. O. Ferrier, H. M. Speyer, L. T. Van Schoiack
            and Peter Spangler, and it ought to be understood that every citizen of the community
            who wishes to see it grow can become a member.</p>
          <p>In united action there is strength.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="VAC1124-056" n="55"/>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head rend="center">CLUB HOUSES AND HOTELS.</head>
          <byline rend="center">By W. T. Wilson.</byline>
          <p>The first club house on the lake was built by several gentlemen from Plymouth in 1873.
            The building was located on the east bank of the lake on the farm of L. T. Van Schoiack,
            and is now known as the McOuat cottage. It was a story and a half building, with
            sleeping apartments above, and parlor and dining room and kitchen below. It became quite
            a place of resort, and many times during the hot summer months as many as fifty persons
            were entertained there at one time. The officers of the club were Joseph Westervelt,
            president; W. W. Hill, treasurer, and C. H. Reeve, secretary. In 1878 eight members of
            the club purchased fifteen acres of ground on the north side, organized themselves into
            the Lake View Club, erected a large club house, with reception room, dining room and
            kitchen, eight rooms above for each of the eight families, put down several flowing
            wells, and erected the six cottages on the grounds now known as "The Lake View Hotel,"
            owned by the Vandalia Railroad Company. Those forming the club were: W. W. Hill, H. G.
            Thayer, C. E. Toan, Daniel McDonald, Horace Corbin, C. C. Buck, Joseph Westervelt and N.
            H. Oglesbee, the last four with their wives being dead. The club existed for fifteen
            years, and was the largest and most noted organization in the history of the lake. After
            the summer resorters began to come to the lake in the '80s, and especially after the
            completion of the Vandalia railroad, their receptions and dances during the seasons were
            considered the finest given about the lake and were always largely attended. The club
            did much to popularize the lake and bring it into general notoriety, and in its
            dissolution left pleasant memories among the many who enjoyed its hospitality.</p>
          <p>The Peru Club was organized about 1878. The members of the club at its organization as
            near as can be remembered were Louis V. Fulwiler, Milton Shirk, John Muhlfield, John S.
            Hale, and Mrs. Lizzie Wiggins. They purchased Peeples Point on the east side and erected
            a fine two story club house for the accommodation and convenience of the members and
            their families. The club in its earlier days was one of the most noted organizations on
            the lake, and in its disbandment several years ago was a distinct loss to the cottagers
            who made their homes there during the summers.</p>
          <p>About the time of the coming of the railroad, several Rochester people formed a club
            and erected a club house on Long Point, and occupied it with considerable irregularity
            for several years. The club went out of existence a decade ago, but the club house still
            stands, and is owned by individuals at Rochester. The Rochester people were the pioneers
            in discovering the beauties of Long Point, being the first to erect a building <pb
              id="VAC1124-057" n="56"/> there. For that reason, for many years it was called
            "Rochester Point," and even yet, many of the early comers about the lake call it by that
            name.</p>
          <p>Possibly the organization that will longest be remembered about the lake was "The
            Hilarity Club," composed of gentlemen from Indianapolis. The club erected a club house
            with sleeping and cooking conveniences on a high bluff a short distance north of the
            Peru club house, and named it "Hilarity Hall." It was what its name indicated&mdash;a
            place where hilarity and mirth prevailed, and dull care and the vexations of life had no
            audience. The following constituted the members of the Club: Charles Keifer, A. C.
            Koehne, C. R. Myers, B. F. Myers, Charles Wocher, Adolph Wocher, Rowland Evans, Prof.
            Beissenherz, Prof. Ernestinoff. The club as a club is no longer in existence, although
            several members of it still come to the lake every summer. "Hilarity Hall" still remains
            in statu quo, and no one who was familiar with the club in its "hilarious" career, can
            gaze upon it without bringing back pleasant memories of bygone days.</p>
          <p>The Palmer House was the first hotel immediately on the lake. It was started by J. W.
            Palmer, then of Plymouth, in the early 70's, and by adding here a little and there a
            little it has become one of the most pretentious caravansaries on the lake. This was
            followed by the erection of the Arlington Hotel on Long Point, and later by the building
            of the Chadwick House, also on Long Point. The progress made in the improvements about
            the lake since the coming of the railroad are marvelous, a description of which would
            require more space than the limits of this sketch will permit.</p>
          <figure>
            <p>The White Caps.</p>
          </figure>
        </div2>
        <pb id="VAC1124-058" n="57"/>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head rend="center">THE AUBBEENAUBBEE YACHT CLUB.</head>
          <byline rend="center">By Thos. H. Wilson, Jr.</byline>
          <p>During the summer of 1901 the Maxinkuckee Association offered three pennants as prizes
            for a yacht race. This race was sailed and awakened the yachting enthusiasm of those who
            had sailboats. The outcome of this enthusiasm was the formation of the Aubbeenaubbee
            Yacht Club. In August, 1901, a number of lake sailors met at Edwards' Boathouse and
            organized the club, adopting a constitution and electing the following officers: <list
              type="simple">
              <item>Henry C. Adams, Sr., of Indianapolis, commodore.</item>
              <item>Harvey J. Elam, of Indianapolis, first vice-commodore.</item>
              <item>Milton A. Edwards, of Peru, second vice-commodore.</item>
              <item>Thomas H. Wilson, Jr., of Logansport, secretary and treasurer.</item>
              <item>S. E. Howe, Jr., of Logansport, Anton Vonnegut and Alfred M. Ogle, Jr., of
                Indianapolis, directors.</item>
            </list></p>
          <p>The first race under the auspices of the club was sailed in August, 1901. An entrance
            fee of fifty cents to each boat formed a fund to purchase pennants for the winners. In
            this race "The White Lady," Elbert Shirk, captain, won the pennant for sloops, and the
            "Natty," Harry Wheeler, captain, won the pennant for catboats.</p>
          <p>In the summer of 1902 three races were sailed. A pennant was given to the winning
            catboat and sloop in each race and a silver cup to the boat of each class making the
            most points during the season. First place in a race counted five, second place three,
            third place two, and fourth place one point. "The Old Scout," S. E. Howe, Jr., captain,
            won all these sloop races. Of the catboats, "Le Vite," Milton A. Edwards, captain, won
            two races, and "Uncas," T. H. Wilson, Jr., captain, won the last race. The standing of
            the various yachts was as follows: <list type="simple">
              <item>Sloops&mdash;"Old Scout," 15; "Lady Jane," 5; "Indiana," 5; "Crescent," 4;
                "Margaret," 3; "Nautilus," 1.</item>
              <item>Catboats&mdash;"Le Vite," 12; "Uncas," 11; "Tadpole," 5; "Natty," 3; "Indian,"
                3.</item>
            </list></p>
          <p>The officers for the second year 1902-3 were Henry C. Adams, commodore, M. A. Edwards,
            first vice-commodore, A. M. Ogle, Jr., second vice-commodore, T. H. Wilson, secretary
            and treasurer. Directors: Anton Vonnegut, S. E. Howe, Jr., Harry Wheeler.</p>
          <p>The yachts were divided into four classes. Flat-bottomed sloops and catboats and
            round-bottomed sloops and catboats. Five races were sailed. The first two for a pennant
            and the rest for cups given in each class and challenge cup. The challenge cups are held
            for a season only. The class cups are held permanently by the winners. In the pennant
            series for class "A" a tie resulted between "The Old Scout" and "Diana," each <pb
              id="VAC1124-059" n="58"/><figure>
              <p>Sailing on the Lake.</p>
            </figure>
            <pb id="VAC1124-060" n="59"/> having eight points. "The Old Scout" won the third race
            and pennant. The "Katherine" won in class "B" with eight points. "Nautilus" was second
            with five points.</p>
          <p>Kenneth Ogle's "Flip" won in class "C," and "Uncas" in class "D."</p>
          <p>The cup series resulted as follows: <list type="simple">
              <item>Class "A"&mdash;"Old Scout," 15; "Diana," 6.</item>
              <item>Class "B"&mdash;"Eleanor," Hervey Perrin, captain, 15; "Nautilus," Anton
                Vonnegut, captain, 4; "Katherine," Alan Williams, captain, 4.</item>
              <item>Class "C"&mdash;"Indian," Jno. Routh, captain, 11; "Flip," 10; "Snark,"
                2.</item>
              <item>Class "D"&mdash;"Tadpole," Henry Bliss, captain, 13; "Natty," 8; "Uncas,"
                5.</item>
            </list></p>
          <p>The challenge cups were given to "The Old Scout" and "Flip."</p>
          <p>The officers for 1903-4 are Commodore, Anton Vonnegut; First Vice-Commodore, S. E.
            Howe, Jr.; Second Vice-Commodore, Glen Wheeler; Secretary and Treasurer, Henry W. Bliss;
            Directors: Joseph Wilson, Kenneth Ogle and John B. Perrin.</p>
          <p>There are to be seven races in 1904. All are to count for the challenge cups won with
            the same scoring system which was used in 1903. The first three races are for pennants
            and the rest for prize cups.</p>
          <p>It is hoped at some future time the Yacht Club will have a club-house where meetings
            and the social functions of the lake may be held.</p>
          <pb id="VAC1124-061" n="60"/>
          <p><figure>
              <p>A Beautiful Forest Path on the East Shore.</p>
            </figure></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
    <back>
      <pb id="VAC1124-062" n="61"/>
      <div1>
        <head rend="center">MEMBERS OF LAKE MAXINKUCKEE ASSOCIATION, 1905</head>
        <list type="simple">
          <head rend="center">INDIANAPOLIS</head>
          <item>Adams, H. C.</item>
          <item>Bates, Hervey</item>
          <item>Bliss, H. R.</item>
          <item>Bohlen, D. O.</item>
          <item>Brandon, H. J.</item>
          <item>Chandler, H. C.</item>
          <item>Coffin, C. E.</item>
          <item>Gates, Mrs. A. B.</item>
          <item>Glossbrenner, A. M.</item>
          <item>Griffice, Mrs. C.</item>
          <item>Haynes, H. F.</item>
          <item>Haywood, F. D.</item>
          <item>Judah, J. M.</item>
          <item>Ketcham, J. L.</item>
          <item>Koehne, A. C.</item>
          <item>Kuhn, W. F.</item>
          <item>Marmon, D. W.</item>
          <item>Mueller, J. G.</item>
          <item>Ogle, A. M.</item>
          <item>Perrin, John</item>
          <item>Potts, A. F.</item>
          <item>Schaff, J. C.</item>
          <item>Sheerin, S. P.</item>
          <item>Schumacker, J. A.</item>
          <item>Twiname, John</item>
          <item>Vajen, J. H.</item>
          <item>Vonnegut, C., Jr.</item>
          <item>Vonnegut, Bernard</item>
          <item>Vonnegut, A.</item>
          <item>Vonnegut, Walter</item>
          <item>Wheeler, A. L.</item>
          <item>Wood, W. J.</item>
          <item>Woldorf, H. J.</item>
          <item>Yandes, George B.</item>
        </list>
        <list type="simple">
          <head rend="center">PERU</head>
          <item>Brownell, C. H.</item>
          <item>Edwards, R. E.</item>
          <item>Edwards, M. A.</item>
          <item>Edwards, R. A.</item>
          <item>Shirk, Elbert W.</item>
          <item>Shirk, Joseph H.</item>
          <item>Shirk, Mrs. M.</item>
        </list>
        <list type="simple">
          <head rend="center">CULVER</head>
          <item>Borgardus, A. N.</item>
          <item>Caples, Dr. Z.</item>
          <item>Chadwick, S. S.</item>
          <item>Culver Military Academy</item>
          <item>Ferrier, J. O.</item>
          <item>Koontz, J. H.</item>
          <item>Koontz, E.</item>
          <item>Lamson, Frank</item>
          <item>Medbourn, T.</item>
          <item>Morris, Edward</item>
          <item>Peeples, George</item>
          <item>Porter, W. H.</item>
          <item>Sea, Dr. O. A.</item>
          <item>Spangler, P.</item>
          <item>Speyer, H. M.</item>
          <item>Van Schoiack, L. T.</item>
        </list>
        <list type="simple">
          <head rend="center">LOGANSPORT</head>
          <item>Barnes, J. E.</item>
          <item>Harwood, F. M.</item>
          <item>Holbruner, C. E.</item>
          <item>Kreuzberger, Robert</item>
          <item>Mitchell, S. C.</item>
          <item>Murdock, A. J.</item>
          <item>Rice, F. M.</item>
          <item>Reitemeyer, J. H.</item>
          <item>Schroyer, Mrs. A. R.</item>
          <item>Snider, W. H.</item>
          <item>Wilson, Wm. T</item>
          <item>Wilson, T. H., Jr.</item>
        </list>
        <list type="simple">
          <head rend="center">TERRE HAUTE</head>
          <item>Albrecht, W. H.</item>
          <item>Darnell, Miss Jennie</item>
          <item>Duenweg, L.</item>
          <item>Herz, A.</item>
          <item>Hord, Mrs. F. T.</item>
          <item>Martin, Mrs. L. B.</item>
          <item>Strong, Joseph</item>
          <item>T. H. &amp; L. R. R. Co.</item>
        </list>
        <list type="simple">
          <item>Capron, Judge A. C., Plymouth, Ind.</item>
          <item>Culver, H. H., St. Louis, Mo.</item>
          <item>Knapp, A. J., South Bend, Ind.</item>
          <item>Knapp, Walter, Westfield, Ill.</item>
          <item>Meredith, H. J., Denver, Ind.</item>
          <item>McDonald, Hon. Daniel, Plymouth, Ind.</item>
          <item>Stevenson, Rome E., Rochester, Ind.</item>
          <item>Wolfert, J. W., Plymouth, Ind.</item>
        </list>
      </div1>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
