<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//IA Books//DTD TEI for Indiana Authors Books//EN"
                       "teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="VAC1018">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The revival of Italy</title>
<author>Herron, George Davis, 1862-1925.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Encoded By</resp>
<!--Update the value of the element below with your name in
                                direct order.-->
<name>taemin park</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
<lb/>
<pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
<address>
                    <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
                </address>
<idno>VAC1018</idno>
<availability status="unknown">
<p>Copyright 2009 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
<p>Indiana University provides the information contained on this web site for non-commercial,
personal, or research use only. All other use, including but not limited to commercial or scholarly
reproductions, redistribution, publication or transmission, whether by electronic means or
otherwise, without prior written permission of the copyright holder is strictly prohibited.</p>
</availability>
<!--Update the value of the date element with the year the document
                        is being encoded.-->
<date>2012</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The revival of Italy</title>
<author id="ina-v1-entry-0399">Herron, George Davis, 1862-1925</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>128 p. ; 19 cm.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>G. Allen &amp; Unwin</publisher>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<date>1922</date>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>The Digital Library Program was awarded a Library Services and Technology Act (LSTA) grant in
2005 to make available online the three-volume, reference work, <title>Indiana Authors and Their
Books</title> along with selected monographs by Indiana authors.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl n="3">
<p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and has been
encoded and edited using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines
following the TEI Lite standard. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<tagsDecl>
<tagUsage gi="div1">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
</tagsDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy id="lcsh">
<bibl>
<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
</bibl>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language>English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="lcsh">
<list>
<item>Reconstruction (1914-1939)</item>
<item>Italy--History--1914-1922.</item>
</list>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<!--The revision description tracks significant changes made to the file
                    after completion. This information will remain commented out unless someone has
                    conducted quality assessment of the texts and have made changes to the file as a
                    result.-->
<!-- <revisionDesc> <change>
                    <date>$Date</date> <respStmt>
                    <name>$Name</name>
                    <resp>$Responsibility</resp>
                    </respStmt> <item>$Changes</item>
                    </change> </revisionDesc> -->
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>

<pb id="VAC1018-001" n="[1]"/>
<div1 type="halftitle">
<head rend="center">THE REVIVAL OF ITALY</head>
<p/>
</div1>





<pb id="VAC1018-002" n="[2]"/>
<div1 type="advertisement">
<head rend="center">BY THE SAME AUTHOR</head>

<p>THE DEFEAT IN THE VICTORY<lb/> THE MENACE OF PEACE<lb/> WOODROW WILSON AND THE WORLD'S PEACE<lb/>
GERMANISM AND THE AMERICAN CRUSADE<lb/> THE GREATER WAR</p>
</div1>


<pb id="VAC1018-003" n="[3]"/>

<titlePage>
<docTitle rend="center">
<titlePart type="main">THE REVIVAL OF ITALY </titlePart>
</docTitle>

<byline rend="center">BY<lb/>
<docAuthor>BY GEORGE D. HERRON </docAuthor></byline>



<docImprint>
<pubPlace>LONDON</pubPlace> : <publisher>GEORGE ALLEN &amp; UNWIN LTD.</publisher>
<address><addrLine>RUSKIN HOUSE, 40 MUSEUM STREET, W.C.I.</addrLine></address>
</docImprint>
</titlePage>




<pb id="VAC1018-004" n="[4]"/>
<div1 type="verso">
<head type="supplied">VERSO</head>
<p rend="center">First published in 1922<lb/> [All rights reserved]</p>
</div1>


<pb id="VAC1018-005" n="5"/>
<div1 type="introduction">
<head type="supplied">PREFATRORY NOTE</head>

<p rend="center b">PREFATORY NOTE</p>

<p>WHILE these chapters were being written, Giolitti was still the Prime Minister of Italy. But the
substance and contention of the chapters are in no whit changed by the change of ministry. It was
Bonomi who had largely to do with Giolitti's programme of industrial solution. The motivity of
Giolitti and that of Bonomi are identical. The Italian purpose making for industrial democracy, for
social conciliation and economic providence, continues its momentous course. Moreover, the
intellectual revival and spiritual renewal among the Italian youth ate increasing and not
decreasing. Hence there is no call for the change of a syllable of definition or a single accent of
hope which these chapters have uttered.</p>
<p>A complete translation of all the documents concerning the Revolution of September, .1920, may be
found in the <hi rend="i">Contemporary Review</hi> of November, I920.</p>
<p>A translation of Giolitti's Bill to establish workers' control in Italy, with documents and
comments appertaining thereto, may be found </p>

<pb id="VAC1018-006" n="6"/>
<p> in Pamphlet No. 7, Series B, in the Studies and Reports of the International Labour Office in
Geneva. The pamphlet bears the date of February 28th, l921. </p>

<p>The clearest and most synthetic accounts of the Revolution I have seen were written by Mr. Hiram
K. Moderwell, a thoroughly equipped American observer and journalist, for different American
journals, especially <hi rend="i">The Nation</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Freeman</hi> of New York.</p>
<p>Let it be said, however, that the accounts of the matter in question are derived chiefly from
personal contact with' the Revolution, and from conversations I have had with many Italian
participants, as well as with Prime Minister Giolitti, Count Sforza, Minister Croce, and other
members of the Government. For help given in this direction I feel especially indebted to Signor
Giuseppe Prezzolini of Rome. I wish also to express my profound gratitude to his Excellency,
Marchese Paulucci di Calboli, Ambassador and devoted lover of his country, for his generous
criticism of my manuscript, and of some of the opinions therein expressed.</p>
</div1>


<pb id="VAC1018-007" n="[7]"/>

<div1 type="contents">
<head rend="center">CONTENTS</head>
<list type="simple">



<item><hi rend="sc">PREFATORY NOTE</hi><hi rend="right">5</hi><ptr targType="pb"
target="VAC1018-005"/>
</item>

<item>I. <hi rend="sc">THE PERENNIAL QUEST OF THE ITALIAN PEOPLE</hi><hi rend="right">9</hi><ptr
targType="pb" target="VAC1018-009"/></item>
<item>II. <hi rend="sc">THE PARADOX OF ITALIAN NATIONAL CHARACTER</hi><hi rend="right">21</hi><ptr
targType="pb" target="VAC1018-021"/></item>
<item>III. <hi rend="sc">THE REVOLUTION OF SEPTEMBER</hi>, 1920<hi rend="right">33</hi><ptr
targType="pb" target="VAC1018-031"/></item>
<item>IV. <hi rend="sc">THE GREAT ADVENTURE</hi>
<hi rend="right">51</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC1018-051"/></item>
<item>V. <hi rend="sc">ALSO THE AGRARIAN REVOLUTION</hi><hi rend="right">66</hi><ptr targType="pb"
target="VAC1018-066"/></item>
<item>VI. <hi rend="sc">THE STRIFE OF THE EXTREMES</hi>
<hi rend="
right">76</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC1018-076"/></item>
<item>VII. <hi rend="sc">THE NEW RENAISSANCE</hi>
<hi rend="right">88</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC1018-088"/></item>
<item>VIII. <hi rend="sc">THE THIRD ROME</hi>
<hi rend="right">112</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC1018-112"/></item>
</list>
</div1>

<pb id="VAC1018-008" n="[8]"/>

<div1 type="dedication">
<head type="supplied">Dedication</head>
<p rend="center">TO MY SON,<lb/> ELBRIDGE RAND HERRON,<lb/> FAITHFUL WORSHIPPER AT THE<lb/> SHRINE
OF ITALIA </p>
</div1>


</front>
<body>
<div1 type="book">
<pb id="VAC1018-009" n="9"/>
<head type="supplied">The Revial of Italy</head>


<div2 type="chapter">


<head rend="center">I<lb/> THE PERENNIAL QUEST OF THE ITALIAN<lb/> PEOPLE</head>
<p> FROM Augustus till now, the annals of Italy are an essential rehearsal of a single quest&mdash;
the quest of some clue to the unity of mankind in a Roman-born but universal society. And it is
always a society in which authority is reverently identical with liberty&mdash;a society, a divine
ongoing of human life, upon whose upward way the single man and his total world keep step. Thus the
quest speaks always from the consciousness and in the terms of religious adventure. On the part of
its inspired ones, in its noblest accents and avowals, it is the quest of some prehensible high
secret of social creation, some celestial law of earthly order, some enabling revelation of a
heavenly love humanly applicable, whereby freedom and association are happily wedded; whereby the
life individual and the life collective are goldenly harmonised; and whence human society, thus for
the first time really appearing, dissolves the ancient anarchy conditioning the world.</p>



<pb id="VAC1018-010" n="10"/>
<p>And the quest is largely peculiar to the Italian people. It is only the prophets of Israel who
furnish it with an antecedancy ; but never did they so conceive or formulate it, so project it into
popular compulsion, as to identify it with the being of the nation. In this they are transcended by
the prophets of Italy. Nor only by her individual prophets: her religious initiatives and renewals,
the intellectual revivals she has so widely communicated, her high-born revolutions, her worst
anarchies even&mdash;in fact the whole processional and paradox of her history&mdash;are all sourced
in this vision and quest of a heavenly society upon the earth, are all predictive of an eventual
human perfectionment universal. It is only in the light thereof that Italian history becomes
intelligible. Indeed, the quest constitutes the very vocation of Italian history. And it is this
that gives Italy a place as unique and prophetic in the last two thousand years as was the place of
Israel in the centuries preceding the birth of Christ.</p>
<p>I do not mean that the Italian peoples are always, are even often, conscious of their quest. They
rarely know what it is they pursue, what their questions and quarrels are about, what their
revelations and revolutions portend. It is but in the great epochal moments of their history that
they perceive its meaning, its direction, its goal. But this, of course, is universally true :
neither individuals nor nations commonly know the way they take, or the end to which they go. But
the uniqueness of Italy is in this&mdash;that her high appointment, her <pb id="VAC1018-011" n="11"
/> ensuing responsibility for the ultimate weal or woe of the human universe, is proclaimed to her
by all the voices really interpretative of the national soul&mdash;from Virgil to Carducci, from
Saint Francis and Dante to Mazzini and Cavour. Naught else than the vision was Virgil's, and his the
quest also, when he reported" those last days that the Sybil sang "&mdash;those days wherein "a
wondrous race " would descend from high heaven to end the age of iron, " bid a golden dawn upon the
broad world," trample out the remaining prints of crimes, and "free the nations from perpetual
fear." Nor else than this did the Emperors and the Popes&mdash;or the just and great among
them&mdash;blindly pursue; and of the Italian idea was even Machiavelli's political philosophy but a
monstrous perversion. It was this that Saint Francis saw-and this that he knew he had
lost&mdash;when he sank sweetly but baffled to his death. He had bespoken, this gay troubadour of
Christ, and also had he sung, a common love so inclusive as to take in not only the warring cities
and their monstrous rulers, but even the natural elements and the creatures that prowled and
crawled. Not only were Perugia and Assisi to become brothers and lovers one of another: the wild
beast was to repent and to shepherd the village children; the bird and the fish were to join the sun
and the moon, the fire and the water, as members of an ineffable communion of man. A revolution
reaching to the very roots of life&mdash; a practical social philosophy as well-an implied
constitution of universal man&mdash;were all in that <pb id="VAC1018-012" n="12"/> command of
Francis to Brother Wolf to " come, nothing doubting, and establish peace in the name of Jesus
Christ." And equally revolutionary to human society (and greatly to be commended to the Powers now
parcelling between themselves the peoples and lands of three continents) was the Saint's command to
his disciples, made momentarily wrathful by an ill-reception of themselves and their spiritual
gifts, to consider and copy that " courtesy of God " which causeth the sun to shine equally upon the
just and the unjust, and sendeth rain indiscriminately upon the good and the evil.</p>
<p>The inspiration of Francis was not far, perchance, from the splendid pirates who, according to
legend, founded Venice " in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ," in order that, " for the saving of
innocent blood," " a great power, beneficial to the whole world, should arise in a spot strange
beyond belief." Nor uninspired were those long generations of strife between city and city, between
despot and despot, culminating in the Florentine Renaissance. These strifes all had an economic
origin, it is true: each despotism was founded upon the personal possession of great wealth by the
despot, and the wars between the cities were motived by loot and destruction. But it is also true
that many of the great merchants were at least troubled by civic ideals, and each city populace
betimes bestirred by the denunciations and predictions of some flaming reformer or friar. It was "
no vulgar issue," says John Addington Symonds, " that joined Guelf and <pb id="VAC1018-013" n="13"/>
Ghibelline, Pope and Emperor, in uncontrollable intrigue, tumult and massacre." " No merely
egotistic interests were at stake." " Guelfs and Ghibellines alike interrogated the oracle, with
perfect will to obey its inspiration for the common good. But they read the utterances of the Pythia
in adverse senses. The Ghibelline heard Italy calling upon him to build a citadel that should be
guarded by the lance and shield of chivalry, where the hierarchies of feudalism, ranged beneath the
dais of the Empire, might dispense culture and civic order in due measure to the people. The Guelf
believed that she was bidding him to multiply arts and guilds within the burgh, beneath the mantle
of the Pope, who stood for Christ, the preacher of equality and peace for all mankind, in order that
the beehive of industry should in course of time evolve a civic order and a culture representative
of its own freely acting forces." And, speaking later of the Florentines, he says : "One thing at
least is clear amid so much apparent confusion, that Florence was living a vehemently active and
self-conscious life, acknowledging no principle of stability in her constitution, but always
stretching forward after that ideal <hi rend="i">Reggimento</hi> which was never realised."</p>
<p>But it was Dante, trying to translate the politics of eternity into the terms of temporal power
and mediaeval theology, who most profoundly predicated the principles of that World-State for which
the Empire and the Church had ever and alike striven; for which, <pb id="VAC1018-014" n="14"/>
indeed, the nations and religions have all striven, however wilderedly and woefully. It was Dante
who most highly foreshowed the World-State&mdash; Dante who bespoke that true society of nations,
that indissoluble union of the peoples in pursuit of universal good, which the victors in the Great
War have so responsibly failed to procure, and upon the early realisation of which the civilised
continuance and spiritual existence of humanity depend. It was Dante, too, who proclaimed, even unto
a society wherein cupidity and murder had become as fundamental law, that there is " some distinct
function for which humanity as a whole is ordained, a function which neither an individual nor a
household, neither a village nor a city nor a particular kingdom, has power to perform." And, also,
" since it is true that whatever modifies a part modifies the whole, it is plain that amid the calm
and tranquillity of peace the human race accomplishes most freely and easily its given work. . .
Whence it is manifest that universal peace is the best of the things which are ordained for our
beatitude." And it was Dante who at the same time declared that " the human race is ordered for the
best when man is most free." " Upright governments have liberty as their aim, that men may live for
themselves ; not citizens for the sake of the consuls, nor a people for a king, but conversely,
consuls for the sake of the citizens, and a king for his people."</p>
<p>Coming down to the Risorgimento, no interpretation of that supreme human moment is comprehensive
or scientific that regards it as <pb id="VAC1018-015" n="15"/> a mere struggle for national unity.
It was in Joseph Mazzini&mdash;whom not a few believe to be the most illuminated of the sons of men
since Jesus of Nazareth&mdash;that the Risorgimento was truly articulate. And in him we see the
Italian revolution as more than Italian, more than European: the motive for the liberty and unity of
Italy lay in the resultant liberty and unity of mankind. Mazzini struggled to deliver Italy from the
Austrians, in order that Italy might deliver the nations from a materialist civilisation already
then bearing them down to perdition. He beheld the peoples corrupted and benighted by the
materialism of the politician and the capitalist on the one side ; he beheld, on the other side, the
world's workers passing under the strong delusion laid upon them by the materialist Messianism of
Marx. He conceived it to be the mission of Italy to speak the new word, to take the sure initiative,
that would save the nations from the degradation and dissolution, from the tyranny and the slavery
inhering in the materialism of both the left and the right. It was an Italy anointed and
commissioned from on high, an Italy redemptive among the peoples international, not an Italy content
with the mere conquest of her own liberty, that moved Mazzini from the days of his .childhood in
Genoa until the hour of his lone death at Pisa. It was this that moved the arm of Garibaldi as well;
and it was the failure of Mazzini's motivating vision to fulfil itself, it was the unpreparedness of
the official shepherds and the peoples alike for the <pb id="VAC1018-016" n="16"/> social republic
for which Garibaldi at first fought, that thereafter filled the hero with foreboding as to the human
future, and sombred the days of his passing.</p>
<p>Could Mazzini return to these more evil days of ours, who would hear him? Or if the curious or
the alarmed gave ear, to what a strange tongue would they listen? " Are we advancing," he would
imperiously ask, " towards anarchy or towards a new mode of things&mdash; towards dissolution or
towards a transformed life? All ask themselves this question ; all could resolve it, if the point of
view of each man were not narrowed by his position in some one of the adverse camps. . . . The old
generation may be doomed to pass away amid this moral anarchy, but the new already aspires toward a
faith, and will not expire without having realised its aspiration." " And it is madness," he would
exclaim, " to persist in a struggle between the individual and the forces of the universe&mdash;when
it may be that the sole liberty of the individual consists in acquiring the power of harmonising his
existence with them." It is therefore " time to re-link earth with heaven ; to re-unite the finite
being with the Infinite Idea, to give human liberty the divine consecration, and&mdash;if I may be
allowed the expression&mdash;confer upon the creature the citizenship of the universe hitherto
denied him. . . . An intellectual epoch is now dawning upon us which will comprehend the two; and by
accepting them as its point of departure, advance one step farther in that knowledge of God which is
the ultimate term <pb id="VAC1018-017" n="17"/> of every human synthesis." Upon the ruins of two
former worlds, " the human intellect will raise up a third, destined to solve the enigma of
Prometheus and put an end to the grand struggle."</p>
<p>"Humanity is one," he would cry. " God has made nothing in vain, and since there exists a
collective Being, a multitude of men, there exists one aim for them all-one work to be accomplished
by them all. ,Whatever this aim may be, it certainly exists, and it is our duty to endeavour to
discover and attain it. Mankind, then, ought to work together in unity and concord, in order that
the intellectual power bestowed upon them may receive the highest possible development in the double
sphere of thought and action. It is only by harmony, consequently by association, that this is
possible."</p>
<p>" Your task," he would conclude, " is to found that Universal Family, to build up the City of
God, and unremittingly to labour towards the active progressive fulfilment of His great work in
Humanity." And " when each of you, loving all men as brothers, shall reciprocally act like brothers,
when each of you, seeking his own well-being in the well-being of all, shall identify his own life
with the life of all, and his own interest with the interest of all; when each shall ever be ready
to sacrifice himself for all the members of the Common Family, equally ready to sacrifice themselves
for him ; most of the evils which now weigh upon the human race will disappear, as the gathering
vapours of the horizon vanish on the rising of the sun; <pb id="VAC1018-018" n="18"/> and the will
of God will be fulfilled, for it is His will that love shall gradually unite the scattered members
of Humanity and organise them into a single whole, so that Humanity may be One, even as He is
One."</p>
<p>Such are the logos and the beatitude of the quest, as relentless as it is holy, as perennially
new as it is anciently old, forever compelling the Italian nation, devoting it to liberty's largest
fulfilments, to God's great ends in humanity. If we press the high quest for its ultimate word, we
shall hear Italy held responsible for the quality of the world&mdash;for the world's social or
spiritual creation-for the creation of a world that is no creation yet, nor yet a thing of the
Spirit, but a world without form or mind, consisting chiefly of chaos and the Spirit's raw material.
Yet the responsibility is no burden: it is rather an epiphanous empowerment, whence the right and
the law and an all&mdash;inclusive loveliness lay fast upon the earth&mdash;the light and law of
social being embracing, as I have written in the beginning, the entire life of man in one concordant
and continuous creativity: yet a creativity effecting,, just because it proceeds from the total
human collectivity, and by the very virtue and precise force of its harmony, an infinite
differentiation of persons and actions, showing forth the work of each hand, each mind, in a special
and distinctive glory.</p>
<p>The divine empowerment is not alien to the present Italian hour : it is rather the meaning of the
precipitate crisis through which Italy is passing. The crisis, if the heart of it be heard, <pb
id="VAC1018-019" n="19"/> is naught else than a summons to the Italian people to set a courageous
and compelling example of social solution. And the summons is as urgent as the ongoing of God, the
opportunity as importuning as the storied gates of heaven. For the nations, broken and bewildered,
and cringing under the rule of the harshest reaction whereof history hath knowledge, are seeking a
way of salvation from a demented international finance on the one side, from the strong delusion of
Moscow on the other side. The urgency of the summons, of the opportunity whose gates may soon be
darkened and hushed, lies in this dual advance of the one denial that dooms humanity to moral
extinction-the denial of the right of the single man to his own labour, hence to his own body and
his own soul. Nor matters it whether the denial be enthroned by the lords of finance or the lords of
herded labour-by capitalist government or socialist state. Upon this denial have been based all the
tyrannies and all the slaveries of history, all the exploitations of men and nations by the
capitalist system of production; and thereupon is based the now destructive exploitation of
capitalist industry by a superseding and more parasitic financialism. Upon this selfsame denial the
fabled dictatorships of the proletaire are each likewise based. And now, while the Russian delusion
leads the workers international, into the wilderness of their last despair, the sovereign maniacs of
finance grow but the madder, their damnations daily deepening upon all mankind. It is given unto <pb
id="VAC1018-020" n="20"/> Italy to prepare the great, the inclusive salvation -to effect, first
within her own borders and thence by universal apostleship, that affinity between freedom and
association which her poets and prophets all pronounce, which her noblest national efforts all
affirm, and the quest whereof has been her divine vocation and her Holy Grail.</p>
</div2>


<pb id="VAC1018-021" n="21"/>

<div2 type="chapter">


<head rend="center">II<lb/> THE PARADOX OF ITALIAN NATIONAL<lb/> CHARACTER </head>
<p> ITALY to-day teems with the voices, with the clamours and vital forces&mdash;with the turbulent
over-life indeed&mdash;of a new national springtime. Yet the springtime rises not from the soil of
the present, but from sources beneath the foundations of history-sources that were' perhaps ancient
when Rome was young. And these sources seem always freshly flowing: the springtime of the Italian
people seems perennial. For time appears to leave no trace upon this people: the ages do not age
Italians. If they are the oldest in the years of their history, they are yet the youngest of the
peoples who have made western civilisation. They have experienced every glory of empire, and every
evil also ; every sort of civic invention, of national adventure, of civic disease and national
decay. They have looked up every height of social vision; they have gone down into every depth of
social dissolution and savagery. Every religious initiative or degeneration or renovation has run
its course with them, and every political or ecclesiastical tyranny or liberation. Indeed, every
experiment the human imagination can <pb id="VAC1018-022" n="22"/> conceive has had its day with the
Italian communities, has exhausted itself upon the Italian peoples. Yet whatever happens, however
whelming the devastations of nature, whatever domestic tyrants or barbarian invaders overcome the
land, from each event of wasteful woe or death, however deep or vast, the Italian rises as youthy,
as joyous and angry, as foolish and wise, as altogether ready to live and to laugh, to love and to
hate, as if human life had begun but yesterday. To the Italian, it is always the morning of the
world.</p>

<p>Thus the ongoing of Italy is as the processional of a perpetual paradox ; and this is at once the
despair and the hope of their history. Just as some of them are to-day killing each other in the
streets, in their determination to find social unity and fulfil the law of love, so they probably
strove between themselves when the first two or three Italians prehistorically gathered together.
Between themselves they have always been fighting: yet they have always been determined upon a
spiritual unity of the world. Their whole national life, yesterday and to-day if not for ever, has
its setting and continuity in this baffling dualism. And caught in this dualism also, and often
enough crucified by it, we behold all the men whom Italy has apotheosed. Julius Caesar&mdash;per-
haps the most just and enlightened ruler of two millenniums save England's Alfred and America's
Lincoln&mdash;could exercise the forgiveness of Christ toward a hypocrite so base and bombastic as
Cicero. Virgil sings the arrival <pb id="VAC1018-023" n="23"/> of a Messianic race, and of a
resultant peace and goodwill inclusive of even the serpent and the lion, while the world rots with
the splendid, poison of Augustus. Francis of Assisi, replete with the conscience and the cunning of
angels, his saintship the delight of both heaven and earth, springs his revolution-still
continuing-amidst the rise of despots whose inhumanities are untellable except in the speech of
hell. The great Leonardo broods upon wickedness so prevalent, so profound and apparently
irremediable, as to predicate the end of the world in a deluge of divine wrath; he also ponders a
possible world in which economic uncertainty exists not, and wherein every form of genius or
activity is free to fulfil itself ; and he was reported to have invented a boat that would go under
water, but refused to give out the invention, because men were so wicked, they would be using it for
sinking other boats; yet he builds forts and digs trenches for Cæsar Borgia, and serves the tyrant
of Milan. Dante sees the kingdoms of the world become " the kingdom of our God and His Christ ''; he
calls upon angels to join men in singing hosannas to the kingdom's near approach ; yet it is amidst
orgies of treachery and sensuality inconceivable, amidst cruelties wanton beyond words, that the
poet stalks upon his stern and solitary way. Angelo glimpses a purified world peopled with the free
sons of God and brothers of Christ, and sings it all in the sonnets wherewith he immortally crowns
Vittoria Colonna ; but he is at the same time Titanically wrathful about the oligarchs and <pb
id="VAC1018-024" n="24"/> princes who compete in betraying Italy to marauding northern monarchs ;
and about perfidious Popes who intrigue to divide city against city, array Italians against
Italians, in the interests of Papal authority. The primitive Christian purity of Giotto is expressed
on plaster and canvas, and his Santa Maria Novella is progressing, his matchless campanile arising,
while the Florentine families, issuing from their fortress houses, fill the streets with daily and
nightly murder. The angels of Angelico were born amidst barbarities unmatched by oriental tyrants,
and in an epoch wherein a Gonzaga puts captive hundreds to torture and death for a holiday show. The
fires of Savonarola's soul, quenched by the fires that consumed his body, blaze forth amidst the
impending ruin of Italy &mdash;and this partly at the hands of the detestable Charles VIII whom
Savonarola himself had summoned from France as a saviour.</p>
<p>And so Italian history proceeds&mdash;the passion for unity, the vision of social perfection,
always contesting the field with a militant and often wanton individualism. Indeed, her annals at
times seem nothing else than a revelation of Italy's amazing capacity for producing con-
temporaneous saints and sinners&mdash;and saints and sinners unrivalled at that. And the paradox
presents the sorest problem of the Italian past and present&mdash;a problem thus far insoluble,
except momentarily, when great national peril or transcendant national purpose serves to organise
and concentrate, for the time being, the disorderly public mind.</p>


<pb id="VAC1018-025" n="25"/>
<p>For the exaggerated individualism of the Italian is not synonymous with personal freedom. Or
rather it is rooted in a freedom that is not freedom but waywardness&mdash;the waywardness of the
child not yet taught or disciplined to think and act out of consideration "for others. Hence in his
perspective of whatever cause or problem is uppermost, in any given hour, his own personal idea or
program occupies a place out of all proportion to the place he gives to the ideas and programs of
others. And thus he begets within himself an habitual scepticism toward men and movements seeking
ends other or higher than his own. Nor only scepticism: it also develops a mental attitude that is
cynical and deadly both to himself and his nation.</p>
<p>So we come to the cardinal sin of the Italian &mdash;his too common inability to think
trustfully, and therefore to act candidly and with constancy, in his relations to others, or as a
social being. Where faith and self-sacrificing cooperation ought, to exist, where such co-operation
is indeed the sole salvation of a cause or of the nation, we find lamentable and fatal division. We
find also individual intelligence over-reaching itself and becoming cleverness.; and we find the
cleverness exercising itself anarchically and futilely&mdash;a cleverness without conscience,
without social sense or utility, and achieving only social destruction. Or again, as in the time of
the Renaissance, we find one Italian community camped against another, and each community living in
a continuous riot of conflicting individual geniuses within its own borders.</p>


<pb id="VAC1018-026" n="26"/>
<p>Perhaps there was no time, during that entire millennium of Nordic invasion, when invasion could
not have been withstood by a united Italy. It was always through the gates of division&mdash;of the
divisions of Italians among themselves&mdash;that the earlier barbaric tribes came ; and through the
same gates came the later French and Spanish lords and mercenary armies. Indeed, the invasions were
oftener than not invited : the Italian despot called in the invader against other Italian despots ;
the Italian city called in the enemies of all Italy to ravage other Italian cities. Nor was it
merely the despot, the city, the oligarch; the Popes called in the foreigners, again and again;
Dante summoned Henry of Luxembourg as the anointed of God : Savonarola hailed Charles VIII as the
redeemer of Italy. And it was through the division of Italian against Italian that the Austrian
tyranny so long endured. It was indeed the inability of the men of the Risorgimento to co-operate
that enabled France to snatch Nice as the price of her help in the wars of liberation.</p>
<p>There has never been a moment when there was not enough intelligence in Italy, not enough
idealism, to transform the land and its people into a phenomenally free and happy commonwealth ; a
commonwealth, too, redemptive to the world. Yet individual intelligence has for ever schemed against
individual intelligence; individual idealists have exhausted themselves in conflicts with other
idealists. And so the soul of Italy, ever youthful and ever radiant, and betimes almost rampant with
high vision and <pb id="VAC1018-027" n="27"/> consecration thereto, has never been able to realise
itself effectively, never been able to fulfil its divine appointment to unite humanity. And this
division of Italian against Italian, of ideal against ideal, of intelligence against intelligence
&mdash;this is not only the cardinal sin of Italy : it is the consequent cardinal curse, the curse
which only Italians them elves can lift from themselves, from their national life.</p>
<p>Yet how often has the curse seemed just about to be lifted I How often has this anarchic
individualism been able, in great epochal moments, to transcend itself in miracles of co-operate
devotion, heroism and victory I The apostolic mutualism of the friends of Mazzini, the fidelity of
the followers of Garibaldi, will live among the .holiest memories of mankind. The few but
resplendent days of Mazzini's Roman Republic will remain a proof of man's divine capacity for
freedom&mdash;a capacity so rarely perceived or summoned forth by the official shepherds. That
Republic will remain, also, as almost the chief approximate realisation of an ideal society. And the
World-War furnishes no greater achievement, no sublimer or more hallowing spectacle, than the rally
of Italy to the Piave, after the devastating disaster of Caporetto. Caporetto itself was due to
division among Italians; and the Piave was due to that marvellous response, to that almost
miraculous unity, of the young men reacting against the disaster.</p>
<p>The Italian nation of that period was typified, was indeed glorified, in one of her young <pb
id="VAC1018-028" n="28"/> noblemen, Fulcieri Paulucci di Calboli, who, wounded and mutilated, and
dying by inches, was taken from city to city, addressing great audiences from the wheel-chair to
which he was confined, appealing for the military and moral rehabilitation of his country. When
still in the hospital, he would appeal to his wavering countrymen in words like these: " When the
day of a divine revenge will come&mdash;and it will come-then the tombs will open and, as in the
song of the Garibaldian epic, the dead will rise. They will come to meet us, and they will lend us
their hands. . . . And when, in the hardest of the fights, the inevitable moment of discouragement
and of weakness comes, they will cry out to us : Avanti, avanti I forward on the ground which our
blood has consecrated to Italy ! Forward, always forward, and farther still, until the
three-coloured flag waves on the frontiers given by God to Italy. . . . Then shall we rest in peace
i " He was called, also still in the hospital, to the presidency of the Section of Patriotic Defence
in the Committee of Action. The work of this Section was to watch and combat all those who tried to
discourage the people in Italy's darkest hour ; those who secretly sabotaged the war, trying to
neutralise the efforts and to paralyse the courage of the armies. Nor only was he untiring in his
work: a spiritual tragedy was added to the physical. It became his solemn duty to his country to
accuse, in the name of the " combattenti " or fighting men, the father of the friend who had once
saved his life on <pb id="VAC1018-029" n="29"/> the battlefield. As his labours increased, he became
transfigured, his soul invested with a mystic flame. Fulcieri Paulucci "personified in himself,"
says one of his comrades in arms, "the sublimity of that spontaneous chivalrous order of the
mutilated which was among the noblest and most outstanding creations of Italy in war, and which was
worth a whole army to Italy after Caporetto."</p>
<p>So always, notwithstanding the extreme individualism so characteristic of the Italian people,
notwithstanding the almost wilful determination of each Italian to go his own way, when this
individualism is withal seized by some patriotic passion, when some compelling and associating
vision lays hold of it, then we find it exemplifying the highest order of renunciation for the sake
of national or moral unity. This has been often manifested in the economic sphere. The glass workers
of Italy long carried on a co-operative production and administration that equalled the devoted
unity of Garibaldi's immortal Thousand. The Emilian and Romanogle co-operatives&mdash;which are
models of administration&mdash;reveal a quality of economic and social mutualism far surpassing the
old Rochdale or English co-operators. The Rochdale co-operatives are essentially commercial
partnerships, along somewhat conventional lines, on the part of a great number of individuals for
their mutual advantage, but carrying with it no social passion or purpose. But the Italian
co-operative movements differ from the English in the fact that they are <pb id="VAC1018-030" n="30"
/> fervently apostolic : they are regarded as modes of initiating the transformation of industrial
and political society. And should once this kind of co-operative spirit seize the Italian peoples as
a whole, moving them by a single purpose and toward a single end, then the nation might suddenly
pass into a social order whose antecedancy could be found only in some of the earlier Christian
communities.</p>
<p>Yet, even so, it would always be a co-operation leaving free play to the individual. The Italian
must find freedom in association or association in freedom,&mdash;or he will not associate. It was
this that Mazzini so clearly discerned, and this that led to his antagonism toward every form of the
socialist state, the hierarchical collectivism, predicated by the socialism of his day. Mazzini knew
that an industrial and civil society founded upon the Marxian doctrine&mdash; issuing thus from the
sheer war between classes which was the core of that doctrine&mdash;would be impossible of
realisation in Italy. The Italian temperament would never endure the Marxian state&mdash;even if it
could be experimentally initiated. So, also, would the Soviet system of Russia be impossible of
realisation in Italy, as Lenin himself now well knows. Without discussing the necessity or
non-necessity of the proletarian dictatorship, as applied to the Russian peoples; even admitting
that no other programme than that of the Bolshevist was or is yet possible of realisation in
Russia&mdash;it yet remains true that the system would prove a tragic absurdity if attempted by or
among the Italian peoples. The Italian socialists of the left seem unaware of <pb id="VAC1018-031"
n="31"/> how little they themselves would submit to the Russian regime; of how immediately
unmanageable they would be in the first hour of a like dictatorship. Lenin, with all his genius for
organisation and control, would not last overnight in Italy ; and the Italian communists would be
the first to turn against him. Especially is this true, when we consider that the Russian
proletarian dictatorship is but a candid fiction&mdash;that it is, in fact, but the administrative
sovereignty of a few very able men in the <hi rend="i">name</hi> of the proletariat.</p>
<p>Whatever the difficulties and tragedies through which Italy must pass, in the order of her
industrial solution and social reconstruction, whatever her final industrial and political society
proves to be, it must eventually be, as I have already emphasized, a synthesis of both unity and
liberty&mdash;a society in which unity completes itself in liberty, in which liberty finds and
fulfils itself in unity. In fine, the only social solution tolerable to the Italian lies in such a
sincere and inclusive application of the principle of democracy as has not hitherto been attempted,
as has not even been considered, by the nations we conventionally call civilised.</p>
<p>The paradoxical character of the Italian people presents an especially portentous problem to-day.
The Italian race now confronts its third commanding moment of choice and of destiny. The war and its
evil issues, the betrayals and disillusionments of this people, have been in a sense uncreative of
both industrial and political society. Governmental and economic systems have been thrust together
into the melting-pot. <pb id="VAC1018-032" n="32"/> All the old Italian passions, good and evil
alike, the old vices and virtues, the old scepticisms and ideals, are awake and astir. The forces of
national reaction are at work, stimulated by the unbelievably brutish reactions of stronger nations
; while the extreme left, incited also from abroad, thinks to establish a communist commonwealth by
violence. And into the midst of the conflicts and cross-purposes comes the Government&mdash;we may
hope supported by the body of the people&mdash;seeking a solution and synthesis of productive
capital and labour that shall be an approach to industrial democracy. As I shall elsewhere point
out, no other government has essayed such an adventure ; no other national ministry has thus
proposed an immediate social goal; no other nation has been so significantly called upon to make up
its mind. If now the Italian people deliberately enter upon this adventure, if the nation soon gird
itself for the pursuit of this goal, then not only will the new order implicit in her Government's
programme be achieved : beyond that, by virtue of the prodigious achievement, Italy may quickly pass
into an unexampled international leadership, providing promise to a world now besotted with despair
and bereft of hope. Moreover, by thus keeping her providential appointment, so pregnant with
universal weal, may the ancient paradox of her national being, the ageless tragedy inhering in her
national ongoing, be resolved in a democracy of onward action truly divine, a progress empowered
with the purpose of the Christ.</p>
</div2>



<pb id="VAC1018-033" n="[33]"/>


<div2 type="chapter">


<head rend="center">III<lb/> THE REVOLUTION OF SEPTEMBER, 1920<lb/>
</head>
<p> ON September 2nd, 1920, and during the week following, the metal and engineering industry of
Italy underwent a revolution potential with that country's international leadership along the only
true path of social salvation. Except in the camp of Lenin on the extreme left, and in the camp of
the financial internationalists on the extreme right, there is little or no apprehension of what
this Italian revolution portends. Yet the question it has raised, the opportunity it has projected,
constitute a judgment day for our civilisation.</p>


<p>The prelude to the uprising was the demand of the metal-workers, about the middle of August, for
an increase of wages, the demand being based upon the highly increased cost of living. The employers
refused the increase. For ten days thereafter, the workers practised a " white strike " in the
metallurgical industries. By obeying literally the rules of the factory, and by other methods of
obstruction, all within legal bounds, the output of the factories was so reduced as to exhaust the
patience of the employers. On September 2nd, the National Federation of Employers declared a
lock-out of <pb id="VAC1018-034" n="34"/> the men, and a closing down of the works. The order of the
General Council asserted " that the policy of obstruction has already degenerated into a condition
of absolute anarchy within the factories," bringing " production almost to a complete standstill,
entailing a useless consumption of coal and raw material," and creating " in the engineering and
metal industry so grave a situation that the owners have only abstained from closing down the works
because of their desire to prove themselves animated at all points by a conciliatory spirit." The
Council therefore resolved that firms which were members of the Federation, and which were closing
down their works, would be prepared to examine the demands of the workers' organisations " only in
the event of the existing abnormal and illegal state of affairs ceasing." At the same time, the
Italian Federation -of Metal-workers, acting through a Trade Union Committee of Action, immediately
countered the lock-out order of the owners with a " lock-in " order of the workers. According to its
pronouncement of September 3rd, the Committee of Action had foreseen the intention of the owners, "
and had already instructed its delegates to return to their constituencies and urge the workers to
seize the factories at the first sign " of their shutting down. This prompt decision of the
Committee " thus nullified the decision of the owners. The workers have everywhere prevented the
interruption of work; in spite of the fact that the owners have everywhere tried to remove the
technical staff by <pb id="VAC1018-035" n="35"/> threatening them with dismissal." It is, there-
fore, upon the owners the responsibility for all damage caused to production falls. '" It is true,"
continues the pronouncement, that the owners, "while passing their resolution&mdash;a resolution
which, professing to be only a simple lock-out, really means war to the knife&mdash;they at the same
time pretend, as soon as an abnormal situation has ceased to exist, to be willing to discuss the
workers' demands. But in order to force the owners to a concession such as this, it has been
necessary to use obstruction and the workers have been obliged to occupy the factories 1 Let us hope
that the workers' firmness in continuing their policy of struggle and self-sacrifice will end in
inducing the owners to take further steps along the path towards a solution." The Committee
furthermore declares that " the occupation of the factories in no way alters the orders issued
'before the period of obstruction. We therefore urge upon all workers the desirability of avoiding
any useless waste of time in the factories. All should direct their efforts towards preventing the
disorganisation of the works and towards making good the absence of the technical staff."' And "all
meetings and reunions should be held outside work-hours, i.e., during meal hours and at change of
shifts."</p>
<p>The first lock-out had been on the part of the Romeo works at Milan, on August 3oth, and on the
'3Ist this was answered 1y the occupation by the workers of about two hundred and eighty
metallurgical establishments in <pb id="VAC1018-036" n="36"/> Milan. Then came the promulgation of
the order of the Council of Employers on September 2nd, followed by the order of the Metal-workers
on September 3rd. Within fortyeight hours thereafter, and with extraordinary quiet and order,
unanimity and discipline, the workers occupied the factories of all the large industrial centres of
Italy.</p>
<p>But the workers were under no illusions as to their ability to carry on the works without
technical skill and business administration. At first, such of the technical and administrative
employees as refused to make common cause with the manual workers were allowed to depart in peace:
this was thought advisable, and also thought to be good class-strategy, in view of the fact that
considerable numbers of such employees remained of their own choice. But when it was found that
these were not enough, and where such skill and administration was not voluntary, the technicians
and engineers were compelled to proceed with their duties. They were not otherwise molested ; on the
contrary, they were treated with great consideration and respect. In some instances, such as
Bianchi's motor works, the whole staff remained, the factory running with clock-work precision, the
output augmented by approximately thirty per cent. Buying and selling also continued in general as
between factories. A general bureau of sale was created in Milan. Many clients refused to cancel
their orders, but took the goods as they were delivered. The workers seized raw materials on the
railways, and occupied coalmines<pb id="VAC1018-037" n="37"/> and subsidiary industries essential to
the operation of the metal-works.</p>
<p>Of highest significance is the harmony which prevailed among the workers, and the evident
hopefulness and even happiness with which they obeyed the somewhat Draconic orders of their
Committee of Action. <hi rend="i">A discipline much ~everer than that' which any of the employers
had dared was established and exercised by the workers themselves by mutual consent</hi>. Instant
and drastic punishment was visited upon any one found slacking. They also established an eight hour
shift whereby work was continuous. The men were not allowed to leave the factories, but slept at
night on cots provided by the respective local Committees .of Action. The women were instructed to
depart at night, in order to care for their families. The use of all intoxicating drinks was
prohibited, and likewise the petty gambling so common in some Italian communities. All in all, it
was a Puritan austerity that was prescribed and commonly practised; even enforced where rare
necessity occurred. During rest-hours, lectures on economic subjects were given, and sometimes on
subjects of literary or general intellectual interest. Even classical concerts were given, I am
told, in a few instances. Ofttimes the rest-hour was occupied by the reading aloud of books by some
one appointed. Nor was the instruction or reading based, as is the case in Russia, upon a strict
materialistic doctrine of life and society, Questions of morals and religion were freely discussed,
and most divergent views advanced. <pb id="VAC1018-038" n="38#"/> In one instance, so I am told by
an Italian scholar of high distinction&mdash;which instance he declared to be fairly typical&mdash;a
body of young workers asked his participation in a conference upon the subject of the higher
spiritual preparation of Italian workers for " the new society." It was indeed of immense
significance that the workers, while engaged in their revolution, thus manifested, at one point and
another, an interest in things above and beyond the immediate struggle&mdash;manifested the presence
in their midst of a quest for spiritual increase, for a clue to a social order including and
harmonising ;the whole life of man.</p>
<p>It is true that the employees established their Red Guards in different factories, especially
those of Milan, Turin and Genoa ; and, in some factories, they erected barbed wire defences. But
these were never needed, :as the military was nowhere and at no time either ordered or permitted to
act, except at a preliminary struggle at Genoa. The employers appealed to the Government for
intervention ; but the Government made it plain, from the outset, that force would not be used to
eject the workers from the occupied works. The Government was both willing and urgent for
arbitration; but this the employers would not have, and thus they turned the tide of public feeling
against them. It may safely be said that, during the month of September, the sympathy of the Italian
population on the whole was with the workers.</p>
<p>Then came the further struggle, involving the Government and the Socialist Party with the <pb
id="VAC1018-039" n="39"/> Confederation of Owners and the Confederation of Labour, and finally
issuing in the virtual surrender of the owners to the Decree of the Government. On September 7th,
there was a conference at Milan between the General Confederation of Labour and the Executive of the
Socialist Party. This conference resulted in the decision of the Socialist Executive to support the
action of the Federation. This decision was due in large part to the mutual leadership of Turati and
d'Aragona in the Socialist Party. On September 8th, the Employers' Federation met and passed a
resolution, demanding the evacuation of the factories as an indispensable condition to any further
negotiation with the workers. The employers contended that it was the workers and not themselves who
had precipitated the crisis ; " that the workers' organisations, after accepting discussion " on the
basis of the difficult situation in which the metal and engineering trades had become involved, then
" suddenly and brusquely put an end to it, perhaps realising the impossibility of refuting the facts
and figures advanced by the owners." The employers further declared the occupation of the factories
to be illegal and arbitrary, and to be not only directed against " liberty of the person, against
the rights of property, against public law and order," but to constitute a series of " public crimes
and a subversion of the constituted order of society." The employers also attacked the Government as
having " under a pretence of neutrality, concealed its hesitation not merely to keep law <pb
id="VAC1018-040" n="40"/> and order, but to maintain the position of the State as a superior body,
representative of the national interest, armed both with the will and the capacity to guarantee the
security of civil and of social life." On September 2th, a conference of workers in occupation of
the factories was held at Milan, and a decision was reached to hand over to the General Federation
of Labour the direction of the movement. The National Council of the General Federation agreed "
that the logical cause of the failure to arrive at any solution of the struggle must be ascribed to
the obstinacy of the employer. The Conference is of the opinion that the extension and importance of
the movement do not tolerate or admit of any solution on the simple basis of wages ; and " that this
historic moment sees the impossibility of the existing relations between employer and employed. ...
It resolves that the object of the struggle be the recognition by the employer of the principle of
labour control of the factories, hereby proposing to open a branch towards those large conquests
which must infallibly tend to collective control and to socialisation, with a view to an organic
solution of the problem of production. Labour control will afford the working classes an opportunity
for technical preparation ; it will allow them, if they unite to themselves the technical and
intellectual classes, who will not be able to deny their assistance to this high task of
civilisation "&mdash;the substitution of the authority of the workers for that of the employers in
industry.</p>


<pb id="VAC1018-041" n="41"/>
<p>It should be clearly understood that the word " control," in this connection, has quite another
meaning than that conveyed by the English usage of the world. The common ignorance of this
difference of meaning has given rise to much irrelevant discussion in the Anglo-American press, and
even among publicists who ought to know better. The control of the factories, according to the Latin
use of that word, means much the same, though in a more intimate and comprehensive sense, as the
expert's inspection of an English or American financial institution. The demand of the workers was
this: the recognition and establishment of the right to examine all the accounts and operations,
both financial and technical, of the industry in which they were engaged. This control included the
discussion and mutual decision, between themselves and the employers, of the rate of wages&mdash;the
wages to be based upon the actual condition of the industry. It also involved the participation of
the workers in the improvement of machinery, conditions of labour, and hygiene and mechanical
safety.</p>
<p>In mid-September, Giolitti, acting as President of the Council of Government, intervened with
what was substantially an ultimatum to the employers to accept the principle of the workers'
control. The employers therefore gave way on September I7th, though deploring the " continued
demonstration by the Government of its failure to grasp the fact that the occupation of the
factories and the violations of personal freedom and liberty committed by the workers <pb
id="VAC1018-042" n="42"/> have transferred the struggle from the economic sphere to a political and
constitutional basis." They also declared that, though accepting the Government's ultimatum, they
had no intention of resuming negotiations until they had obtained the evacuation of the factories,
and had thereby procured " recognition of the principle that such methods of struggle are
incompatible with any civilised order 'of society " and for the prevention of " the complete
discredit and dissolution of the country." Nevertheless, the employers agreed it to be "necessary
that the existing state of antagonism between the employer and employed classes should cease, so
that the harmonious co-operation of the employers themselves with their technical and administrative
staff on the one hand, and with the manual workers on the other, may give rise to an intensified,
secure, and disciplined progress in production." Hence, notwithstanding all their objections to the
action of the Government, " being now face to face with the Government's announced intention to
issue a Decree concerning the control of industry, they invite the Premier to make their own
co-operation on an equally representative committee, mentioned in the Decree, absolutely dependent
on the contingent evacuation of the factories."</p>
<p>A Council of Employers and a Council of ,Workers, meeting immediately in Rome under the
chairmanship of Giolitti, reached an agreement regarding the wage dispute wherein the lock-out and
the resulting occupation of the factories had originated. But the agreement <pb id="VAC1018-043"
n="43"/> contained a clause to the effect that the employers' representatives wished it noted that
they could not, "by reason of the explicit instructions conferred upon them, accept the proposal of
the President of the Council with regard to the conditions for the re-admission to work of the
workers, and hereby declare that submission to 'these proposals is only made as to an act of
authority, the responsibility for which they leave to the Government." Notwithstanding the
reluctance of the employers' representatives, however, the meeting was immediately followed 1by the
issue of a Royal Decree, appointing a Commission to prepare a programme for the introduction of
industrial control by the workers. And the Decree was at once supported by the General Federation of
Labour, in a public pronouncement giving an account of the workers' effective action, and also by
the Prime Minister in a speech' to Parliament, on September 27th, defending the position which the
Government had taken.</p>
<p>Of extraordinary significance was the speech of the Prime Minister. " ,We are face to face," he
said, " with a real change in the social order ; it is useless to deny it. Every politician and
statesman ought to realize this truth. The advent of the Fourth Estate began to be apparent towards
the close of last century, and the attempts then made to arrest its course had evil consequences ;
these movements are dangerous to regulate and 'cannot be arrested. . . . The outbreak of the war had
certain economic, social, and financial results. The <pb id="VAC1018-044" n="44"/> trenches were the
most opportune fields for propaganda, and all the parties made impossible promises. But those who
heard them looked on these promises as rights. Moreover, the habit of serious and orderly work
disappeared, and not in Italy alone." Besides, " during the period of the war certain special
industries arose which were dependent on a single buyer, the State ; and the employer consented to
grant increases of wages on condition of being allowed to compensate himself by raising his own
prices to the buyer. Another consequence arising out of the war was the unpleasant spectacle of an
ill-gotten wealth impudently displayed. The country believed that with the end of the war all these
results would themselves come to an end. This was a delusion." "I advised the employers," he
continues, " against proclaiming the lock-out, and told them that they must not count on the support
of the public authorities; no promises, therefore, have been broken by the Government. It has been
argued that the Government ought to have prevented the occupation of the factories, or ought to have
caused them to be evacuated when occupied. In order to have prevented the occupation it would have
been necessary to place a garrison in each of the 6o00 factories (supposing such garrisons could
have arrived in time, with lightning speed), and thus to have used up the whole forces at the
Government's disposal, leaving none to deal with the workers outside the factories, and totally
neglecting the security of the public. I should have been shutting up the <pb id="VAC1018-045"
n="45"/> public armed forces in the factories, exposing them to the danger of a siege ; or, in order
to obtain the evacuation of the factories, a struggle involving grave consequences would have had to
take place, while all the time the Labour Federation had guaranteed the movement to be an economic
and not a political one." " But," he concludes, " in dealing with so vast a movement, it is not
possible to apply ordinary standards. The act of the worker in occupying a works from which the
owner wishes to have him ejected is an act of disobedience; to employ force against him is to punish
him with the death penalty. On the contrary, I felt myself called upon to intervene in the relations
between employer and employed, and, as the Senate is aware, an agreement has been reached." Reading
then the text of the Decree, Giolitti frankly explained that it aimed at changing the structure of
industry. " When the worker is acquainted with these conditions," the Prime Minister concluded, " he
will be able to calculate the directions in which he may make a successful demand. Moreover, the
Decree prejudges nothing. The joint Commission is to formulate proposals which will serve as the
basis for a Bill aiming at the organisation of industry on the principle of the workers' inter-
vention in technical, financial, and working administration. The same Commission is to propose
principles of factory regulation and of the engagement and dismissal of employees. <hi rend="i">In
this way the worker will take his place as an associate, and not as an enemy, of the
employer</hi>."</p>


<pb id="VAC1018-046" n="46#"/>

<p>So ends the first stage of the Revolution: it is accepted and consecrated by the Government : and
it ends, I am convinced, according to the desire and the plan of the Prime Minister. I am of the
opinion that the Council'of the Confederation of Labour was mistaken in its conclusion and statement
that the workers forced the surrender of the Government, Signor Giolitti could well afford to let
the workers' representatives think so&mdash;to let their pronouncements have free play. And one must
not be too sure, of course, of what is in the back of another man's head. But I am pretty certain
that the result, far from being a surrender on the part of the Prime Minister, was rather his
complete victory&mdash;was indeed the culminating triumph of this extraordinary politician's life.
It was not merely Giolitti who was playing the workers' game : the workers were playing Giolitti's
game from the first. Only it so happened that Giolitti and the workers were pursuing an identical
goal; and this notwithstanding the ignorance and distrust of Giolitti on the part of both workers
and employers.</p>
<p>The political press of the great industrial nations, particularly of France and the United
States, has been clamorous in its denunciation of the manner in which the Italian Government met the
crisis. They have cried aloud against the acquiescence of Giolitti in the occupation of the great
industrial works. It was incredible that such a thing could be-that the Government should not only
refuse to expel the workers but should even look benevolently upon an <pb id="VAC1018-047" n="47"/>
action which, for the time 'being, dispossessed the owners of their factories. But they might have
understood&mdash;perhaps they did understand !&mdash; that Giolitti was minded to teach the
capitalist a lesson. He wished the owners to discern the advancing doom of industrial
monarchicalism. He hoped the crisis might teach them that their only safety, even of a temporary
sort, lay in the direction of industrial democracy. And he intended them to glimpse what he himself
fully foresees&mdash;that along this path of industrial democratisation lies the only possible
preservation of civilisation.</p>
<p>Nor did Giolitti for a moment intend to plunge Italy into civil war for the sake of the men who
had made unclean and fabulous fortunes out of the war with the Central Empires. It is probable that
there is no extreme socialist to whom the war-profiteer is more hateful than to the Italian Prime
Minister. He has done his best to make such profiteers disgorge their profits to the public
treasury&mdash;I am not sure but he would gladly have their heads if he could. In any case, he had
no intention of ordering, on the profiteers' behalf, a conflict between Italian soldiers and Italian
workmen&mdash;a conflict that probably would have precipitated social war throughout the length and
breadth of the peninsula. Furthermore, he was well aware of a fact to which ,the industrials
themselves seemed blind&mdash;that to have evacuated the workers from the works by military force
would have been but a prelude to an economic disintegration from which Italy would not soon <pb
id="VAC1018-048" n="48"/> have recovered. Signor Giolitti is, besides, in principle averse to
military intervention in industrial crises ; he knows the fatuousness of attempting military
solutions of economic problems.</p>
<p>Giolitti wished also the workers to learn a conclusive lesson through their sudden contact with
the economic facts of industry. He wished them to see the impracticability of administering the
machinery of production and distribution with their present training and capacity, and in the midst
of an international production and distribution capitalistically owned and operated. The workers
demonstrated, however, that they were not in the least deluded about the great matter. Mr. Hiram K.
Moderwell, an accomplished and profound American observer of the revolution, says of the
metal-workers: '" They did not fancy that they could run the factories without direction and
discipline. On the contrary, so highly did they prize direction that they arrested their directors
and threatened them with dire penalties if they did not go on directing."</p>
<p>Yet there is not the slightest reason for doubting, there is every reason for trusting, the
sincerity of Giolitti's sympathy with the workers. There is also every reason for trusting his dis-
cernment and intelligence concerning the present human hour. He is aware, even if the capitalist
owner is not aware, that the old order of production and distribution is doomed. He is, furthermore,
sufficiently sure in his own mind that it ought to be doomed. Finally, he is <pb id="VAC1018-049"
n="49"/> entirely honest in his determination that it shall be doomed. His intention predicates a
human order which shall eliminate all socially useless men or institutions. Not Lenin himself is
more intent upon wresting production (from the profiteer, upon ridding industry and society of
parasitic persons and performances, than the Prime Minister of Italy. But he wishes to initiate the
inevitable change, he wishes his Italy to enter upon this great adventure which has the new order
for its goal, through processes wasting as little as possible of life and labour and wealth ;
processes that shall also, as they run their creative course, gain as much as possible of common
consent and goodwill.</p>
<p>The worst of all delusions is that of social solution through war between the proletaire and the
proprietor, the workers and the owners. If the world-problem narrows down to such a conflict, the
result can only be the end of existing society in a new series of dark ages, with probably the death
of a large part of the earth's population and the return of what is left to the jungle. It was thus
a wisdom weighted with the world's destiny that enabled Giolitti to prevent the transformation of
his Italy into an arena of the class-war, and that also invested him with the righteous shrewdness
whereby he brought both the owners and the workers, both his government and its principal socialist
opponents, to a mutual commitment to his programme of social conciliation.</p>
<p>The divers governments are still so occupied with the pursuit of their respective recoupments <pb
id="VAC1018-050" n="50"/> of the cost of the war, that the peoples have not even glimpsed the
prodigious portent of the step taken by the Italian Premier. It is indeed an amazing
spectacle&mdash;that of this aged and adroitest politician of Europe alone discerning the signs of
his times, and, as if acting under the impulsion of some high vision, deliberately committing his
government to a programme purposing an entire reconstruction of industrial society, and a
re-orientation of the functions of the State. Thus, for the first time, a modern government
initiates, of its own foresight and volition, an actual and comprehensive revolution. A revolution,
it is true, to be wrought out through enlightening experiment and enlightened purpose : but no less,
therefore, rather thereby all the more, a radical change of the structure of society. As I elsewhere
point out, no other national government has proposed such an adventure in social creation to its
people. And it is a national adventure which, if carried through to its proposed issue, will
logically place Italy in the forefront of social mankind, even enabling her, mayhap, to summon the
nations to a common good over-paying the infinite woe and waste of the World-War.</p>
</div2>


<pb id="VAC1018-051" n="51"/>


<div2 type="chapter">

<head rend="center">IV<lb/> THE GREAT ADVENTURE<lb/> PEOPLE</head>
<p> THE political realist&mdash;if he b'e really real&mdash;is inevitably a practical idealist,
seeking so to conjoin the real and the ideal as to avoid breaks and chasms in progress. He not only
discerns the highest desires of his times: he at least reckons, if he does not always steer, his
course by them. He does not wait to be driven by events: he envisions their approach, and goes forth
to meet them . The idealized to-morrow, he leads captive, impressing it into the redemptive service
of to-day. He substantivizes, so far as he may, to-day's human fact with the nobler to-morrow of his
perception or faith. Thus he proceeds always upon the knowledge&mdash; so fundamental to the true
political practitioner &mdash;that there is no such thing as a static social condition. Society is
always fluid, and the elements thereof are always revising the proportions in which they stand to
one another. The predominant fact or force of one day may be the subordinate of another. Social
equilibrium lies in keeping the balance between the conditions of the present and the desired or
portended conditions of the future. The wisdom <pb id="VAC1018-052" n="52"/> of the State&mdash;if
one may still be so bold as to presume the existence of such a wisdom&mdash; consists in the daily
discovery and concretion of this balance. National health and stability are thus identical with
perpetual change, with unresting onward movement ; and resistance to change, the refusal of a people
to move on, is significant of national senility and decay.</p>


<p>Doubtless Giovanni Giolitti has not exactly said this sort of thing to himself. It is no less in
the spirit of an idealistic realism that he, pre-eminently a political practitioner, has projected
the great adventure which now interrogatively horizons his country, awaiting its yea or nay.
Fantastic as his programme seems to the Lords of Big Business, it yet rises out of a discernment
rare in the records of politicians, partaking of a shrewdness worthy of that shrewdest of all
Italians&mdash;the Saint of Assisi. Signor Giolitti knows&mdash;as the ministers of no other state,
save one, know&mdash;that the sheer profit-making mode of production and distribution is nearing its
end ; that it must either deliberately pass into a more social mode, or else violently disappear,
with a long period of industrial death and social chaos ensuing. It is either a wilderness and a
guerrilla world, or a world socialized in freedom, that mankind will soon be entering&mdash;this
Giolitti sees, and that whether his sight be clear or dim.</p>


<p>Nor is it suddenly or recently that he has become aware of the approaching crisis of human
society. He has been foreseeing it for a score or more of years ; and for a score or <pb
id="VAC1018-053" n="53"/> more of years he has broodingly, silently, sought some solution other than
the red result of the class-war now universally preparing. Supremely shifty as his political course
has been, he is withal endowed with a social purpose that is as phenomenal as it is redemptive.
Believing in his heart in both the justice and the inevitability of social rather than private
production&mdash;of production for the use of all rather than for the profit of the few&mdash;and
reaching his conclusions, not through the books of the economists, but through contact with the
human fact-he has conceived the initial industrial solution which constitutes, at least up to the
time of this writing, the programme of the Italian Government.</p>
<p>It is charged by the extreme socialist press that Giolitti's motive is the salvation of the
capitalist society. It seems to me that the programme in itself is a sufficient answer to the
charge. For the programme leads precisely to an opposite result&mdash;to the eventual elimination of
capitalist control. But an elimination reached through the preparation of the workers: for Giolitti
knows well&mdash;and it is upon this knowledge that he acts&mdash;and it is a knowledge which the
whole World-War and its respective national crises clearly teach-that the workers are not prepared,
are indeed far from competent, to take over the immediate operation and administration of industry.
Even admitting-as indeed we must admit if we are truthful-that the workers' lack is the result of
the centuried spoliation of themselves, of the centuried <pb id="VAC1018-054" n="54"/> appropriation
of their lab'our-product, by the entrenched and empowered owners, it still remains true that the
workers are as yet incapable of organising and administering a new economy of life and labour. It
remains true, also, that every attempt at .violent and instant change&mdash;a change impinging upon
war between social classes&mdash;can result only in a new series of dark ages, if not a return of
mankind to the jungle.</p>
<p>Giolitti's programme is not different from that of the true socialist : but he seeks its
fulfilment through the progressive but complete technical and spiritual preparation of the workers.
In speaking to Mr. Edward Mowrer, an unusually able and lettered American journalist living in Rome,
the Premier said: " We count on Trade Union supervision to lead to the reconciliation of the
classes. Hitherto the workers have always received the same salaries regardless of the condition of
industry. Henceforth they will know the exact condition of industry, and will base their demands
accordingly, having a direct interest that industries pay. I expect to see all production greatly
increased. . . . Certainly, the industrial education of the workers will permit them to hasten the
day when they are capable of administering industry by themselves, but that is a long process.
Supervision will also force industrial owners to pay more attention to production, and less to stock
exchange operations. This should increase production and tend to prevent over-great industrial
concentration."</p>


<pb id="VAC1018-055" n="55"/>
<p>It is a sort of industrial monism that Signor Giolitti predicates&mdash;a monism dissolvent of
the industrial and social dualism, destructive and diabolic, which arraigns and arms workers and
owners over against each other in hateful camps of deathful purpose. And he perceives, pr, seems to
perceive, in this monism of his, the possibility of a provisionally wedded capital and labour, the
happy issue whereof would be an eventual society in which all would be at once owners and workers.
It was some such hope as this that constituted, so far as Giolitti was concerned, the heart of the
Government Decree of September 19th.</p>
<p>According to this Decree, a Commission was constituted, consisting of six members named by the
General Federation of Employers and six named by the General Federation of Labour. The Commission
was instructed to formulate proposals which should serve as a basis for a Government Bill embodying
the principle of the workers' participation in industrial decision and administration. The
representatives of the employers set about its task of formulating propositions ; the
representatives of the workers did the same. But neither workers nor employers were able to
construct a programme upon which they could or would mutually agree. It was then that Giolitti
practically sent both' Commissions about their business, and decided to formulate his own programme
for presentation to Parliament.</p>
<p>The Bill or Project of Law thus presented by the Prime Minister, who was also Minister of <pb
id="VAC1018-056" n="56"/> the Interior, in consort with Signor Alessio, Minister of Industry and
Commerce, and Signor Labriola, Minister of Labour and Social Providence, consisted of twelve
articles providing for the " control of the industries by the workers of these same industries."
Only the barest skeleton of these articles can be given within the brief space of this chapter. But,
dry as they are, these bare outlines should be well considered by the reader&mdash;who should also
keep in mind the explanation I have given, in the preceding chapter, of the usage and sig-
nificance, on the part of both the Government and the workers, of the word " control."</p>
<p>The first Article related to (a) making the workers acquainted with the conditions of the
industries wherein they are employed ; (b) improving the technical instruction as well as the moral
and economical conditions of the workers ; (c) insuring the execution of the laws made for the
protection of the workers; (d) advising improvements in the methods of production with a view to
increasing production and economising its costs ; (e) rendering the relations between employers and
workers increasingly normal and peaceful.</p>
<p>Article II arranges for the separate control of each industry or category of industry, chiefly
the following industries: (a) iron and metal and mechanical works ; (b) textile works and clothing
manufactories ; (c) chemical industries and those relating to sugar, soap, dyes and so forth ; (d)
production of articles of food; (e) tanneries and leather manufactories ; <pb id="VAC1018-057"
n="57"/> (f) electrical industries ; (g) building construction, woodworks, glass, pottery and
related industries ; (h) land transportation; (i) navigation and the loading and unloading of
cargoes; (j) paper mills and printing industries; (k) mines and quarries. Excluded from this control
are industries carried on by the State or by municipalities, and new industries employing less than
sixty men.</p>
<p>Article III provides for the election on the part of each category of industry, by a system of
proportional representation, of a Commission of Control composed of nine members, six elected by the
workmen and three elected by the engineers and technical heads of the industries.</p>
<p>Article IV provides that the Commission elected according to Article III shall choose a delegate
for each industrial establishment, which delegate shall exercise the control and report to the
Commission. The delegate must be chosen from the workmen of age who belong to the establishment to
be controlled, and from the workmen who have had at least three years of service. The regulations
which must be established according to Article IX will determine the manner in which the delegates
will exercise their function, taking into account the special conditions of each category of
industry. The Commission must be renewed every three years, and the delegates may be re-elected.</p>
<p>Article V provides that the delegates of the Commission of Control shall have the right to <pb
id="VAC1018-058" n="58"/> the means of knowing in each industry (a) the cost of the raw materials ;
(b) the cost price of production'; (c) the administrative methods; ,(d) the methods of production ;
(e) the salaries of workmen ; (f) the constitution of the capital; I(g) the returns of the works;
(h) the way in which laws protecting the workmen and the laws concerning the recruiting and
discharging of workmen are executed. The data collected by the delegates cannot be communicated to
persons outside the Commission of Control.</p>
<p>Article VI provides that at the meetings of the Commission of Control the industrials or
employers may be represented by two delegates., A representative of the Superior Council of Labour
may also participate in the meetings.: The representatives of the employers and of the Council of
Labour may make observations and present demands that shall be inscribed word for word ; but they
have no right to vote. , They have, however, the right to forbid the communicating of news that
might prejudice the interests of industry or the interests of the Superior Council of Labour.</p>
<p>Article VII provides that the industrials or employers in each of the categories shall also
nominate, according to regulations to be fixed, representatives to negotiate with the Commission of
Control whenever it becomes necessary to impose upon particular industrials or employers obligations
growing out of the present law, The representatives of the industrials, like the Commissions of
Control, will be composed of nine members, and will be renewed every three years.: <pb
id="VAC1018-059" n="59"/> Also at the meetings of the delegates of the industrials and employers two
delegates of the Commission of Control-that is the delegates of the workers&mdash;can participate
and present their observations, but also without the right to vote.</p>
<p>Article VIII provides that, whenever special circumstances make it advisable, and in any case
once a year, the representatives of industrials and the delegates of the Commission of Control shall
meet under the presidency of a member of the Superior Council of Labour, in order to examine
together the improvements in machinery or labour or production which the experience of previous
months makes advisable, and for settling controversies that may have arisen during the exercise of
the control.</p>
<p>Article IX provides that, after hearing the opinion of the representatives of the industrials,
then of the representatives of the Commission of Control, and of the Superior Council of Labour, new
regulations may be instituted for the discipline of the workers and the employers, always taking
account of the special conditions obtaining in each industry. These regulations must, however, be in
conformity with the principles exposed in Articles X and XI.</p>
<p>Article X provides for the establishment of offices arranged for the reunions of representa-
tives of the industrials and employers and of the Commissions of Control. These offices will also
serve in some sense as labour exchanges, registering the men seeking work and regulating the order
of preference by which each shall be employed. In the placing of the workers the <pb
id="VAC1018-060" n="60"/> political or syndical affiliations of the worker must never be taken into
account. Every industrial firm, however, can refuse to employ men who have been condemned for crime
or who have been sent away from employment for disciplinary reasons. Disputes between employers or
industrials and the Commission of Control, concerning any work or workers, shall be decided by two
arbitrators, chosen one from the workers, one from the employers, acting under the presidency of a
third person chosen by these, or, in case the two are not able to agree, chosen by the President of
the Tribunal. And as no one can be refused employment for political or syndical reasons, so also no
one can be dismissed for such reasons.</p>
<p>Article XI provides that, whenever the conditions of an industry render the reduction of the
number of workers necessary, then, before proceeding with dismissals, the industry must, if the
nature of the work permits, reduce the normal working hours to a minimum of thirty-six hours a week,
with a corresponding reduction in wages ; and, if this is not sufficient, the employer must, if
possible, arrange for such shifts among the workmen as will make their retention possible. But when
dismissal becomes a necessity, the older workmen and those having families should be kept. If
controversies between employers and workers arise concerning the dismissals, then the questions at
issue shall be decided by arbitrators nominated and acting in the same way as provided in the
preceding article.</p>


<pb id="VAC1018-061" n="61"/>
<p>Article XII provides that when special conditions in an industry demand it, and especially when
there is great difference between the methods or conditions of an industry in different parts of
Italy, then the regulations foreseen in Article III can decide that for one and the same industry
there can be more than one Commission of Control, and in such case the number of the representatives
of the industrials must be correspondingly increased. Article XII also provides that the expenses of
the Commissions of Control are to be borne half by the industrials or employers and half by the
workers, and that the apportionment of contributions and methods of collection shall be determined
by the special regulations of Article III ; and finally provides that the same regulations shall
determine the sanctions necessary for assuring the observance of the present law of control.</p>
<p>The Bill was not passed upon by Parliament at the time it was presented. The question of bread,
as well as questions of foreign policy, occupied much of the winter sessions. Besides, at no time
was the Government assured, as regards this particular measure, of a satisfactory majority. The
Socialist Party, which was the strongest and best organised in Italy before the occupation of the
factories, and which has a large representation in Parliament, would have supported the Bill if the
councils of Turati and d'Aragona had prevailed. Turati-a man of highest cultivation and possessing
the potencies of great statesmanship, obtained the pledges of <pb id="VAC1018-062" n="62"/> a
majority of Socialist deputies to join him in supporting the Government. But the violent left, led
by Bombacci, was able to control the National Executive Party, which thus instructed the Socialist
deputies against the proposed Project of Control, on the ground that it originated outside the
Socialist Party and would help to perpetuate the life of capitalism. The :(Catholic) Partito
Popolare wavered, and, in the critical hour, proved itself to be practically without settled policy,
The Conservative Parties, or fractions of parties, naturally opposed the measure. But,
notwithstanding his lack of support on the part of any dependable Parliamentary coalition, it seems
probable that Giolitti could have passed his Bill, had he forced the issue. But, hoping for a
favourable majority really representative of the nation, he decided for dissolution and a new
election.: Whence the chief issue of the election, despite all divergent claims upon the voter's
attention, is the question of whether or no the nation shall enter upon the industrial adventure.
The probabilities, at the time of this writing, are upon the side of Giolitti's obtaining a majority
in support of his programme. And upon this election&mdash;upon the decision which it
renders&mdash;the future of Italy, if not the immediate future of civilisation, may well depend.</p>
<p>Yet whatever the issue of the election, no long return to a sheer capitalist society is possible
in Italy. The challenge of the revolution of September, :1920, is final. Either the Bill of Signor
Giolitti, premising the evolution of an industrial democracy, will be substantially <pb
id="VAC1018-063" n="63"/> accepted, or another futile move of lalour towards Bolshevism, countered
by a harsh reaction toward sheer capitalism, will precipitate a social war akin to the wars of the
Guelfs and the Ghibellines.</p>
<p>But even if Giolitti triumph, and the Government Project be thus accepted, against its
effectuation two extremes will strive relentlessly. The first consists of that wing .of the
Socialist Party which takes orders from Moscow, and of the Anarchist Party acting under the inspira-
tion of the capable Malatesta. Both Bolshevists and Anarchists believe the destruction of the
existing society to be absolutely essential to the new society's appearing. These two extremes,
antithetical as they are in both philosophy and purpose, are yet alike led by doctrinaires who have
erected class&mdash;hatred into a religion ; who have converted the theory of the class&mdash;war
into an orthodoxy ; and who teach that every effort towards human betterment, every social solu-
tion proposed within or by the existing society, is but a capitalist trap&mdash;a scheme whereby the
workers are tricked into continuing their ancient servitude and despoilment. This dual Italian left
is still a fighting force in Italy. And this notwithstanding its recent defeats in the streets of
Florence and elsewhere ; and notwithstanding, also, the socialist schism at the Congress of
Leghorn.</p>
<p>Nor will the support of the Italian left come only or chiefly from Moscow. Sadly enough&mdash;
and a fact not so paradoxical as would seem&mdash; the revolutionaries who fight Giolitti's project
will be secretly aided by financial internationalists <pb id="VAC1018-064" n="64"/> and their agents
provocateurs. Nor only by the financiers: in conflicts wherein Italian blood has been shed, the
money of at least one great Power, ostensibly allied with Italy, has been found upon the persons of
men proclaiming themselves Bolshevists. It is too frequently these&mdash;the pseudo-apostles of a
foreign Bolshevism&mdash;the disguised agents of a foreign capitalism&mdash;that Italian workmen
follow, blindly fighting thus for a reaction ultimately conditioning them in both economic and
political impotence.</p>
<p>The other extreme opposition to the effectuation of the Government Bill will come directly from
industrials and financiers. The financialism of all nations, now as fearful and fanatical as it is
watchful and conservative, will resort to every device, both foul and fair, tending to thwart the
great adventure. For a successful initiation of industrial democracy in Italy becomes an , incentive
and an example to the peoples international, everywhere endangering the thrones of the financiers,
whether they be in America, England, France or far Japan. Indeed, if you could get at the back of
the sovereign financier's head, you would find therein a dread of the success of the Italian
adventure twofold greater than his dread of Moscow. He still believes in the power of his
governments to confine the Soviet experiment to Russia, and there to transform if not to end it. But
if an industrial democracy be undertaken by a people as potent and alive as the Italians of to-day
are; if this initiative be organised and urged by a so-called capitalist government ; if it be <pb
id="VAC1018-065" n="65"/> prepared by so able a political practitioner as Giolitti ; and if he have
behind him the support of a Ministry of such as Sforza and Bonomi, Croce and Labriola; then
international financialism stands challenged by an authority not easily withstood. It will
consequently feel that, at all costs, it must bring the Italian adventure to naught, even if the
social structure of the nation be brought down in 'the process.</p>


<p>The left and the right are alike wrong. In either capital or labour, it is now only the creative
spirit, only the constructive mind, that can save a society already in a state of dissolution, or
bring forth therefrom a society responsible for the soul of man. And it is upon the turning back or
transformation of the forces of destruction, it is upon the mobilisation of the nation in a united
effort to effect a nobler human order, that the best minds of Italy have now centred their
attention. It is to give these minds a task calling for their last consecration, a task exhausting
their last resource, that their Prime Minister has set before them so great an adventure in
industrial solution and social conciliation. It is indeed in answer to the divinest desire to-day
surgent in the heart of the world, as well as in answer to the peril portending the world's end,
that this extraordinary politician has propounded his programme for a new mode of economic pro-
duction and administration&AElig;a programme envisioning an industry experimentally involving, by
its own freely acting forces, a spiritual culture finally creative of economic justice and a
complete society.</p>
</div2>

<pb id="VAC1018-066" n="66"/>
<div2 type="chapter">
<head rend="center">V<lb/> ALSO THE AGRARIAN REVOLUTION<lb/>
</head>
<p> OF the converging movements making for a new Italian society, the most fundamental is that of
the revolution in the ownership and cultivation of the land. Because of the startling nature of the
industrial revolt, because of the orderly occupation and successful operation of the metallurgical
works by the workers, and because of the effect of this astounding achievement upon a civilisation
largely centred in industrial production, the Italian agrarian revolt has had comparatively little
attention. Indeed, the world is quite unaware of what has happened with regard to the land in Italy.
Yet because of the fact that Italy is an agricultural country, her people chiefly dependent upon the
cultivation of the soil, the revolt of the agricultural workers is even more significant than the
revolt begun by the workers in the factories. Indeed, without the basic revolution in the use and
ownership of the land, the industrial revolution could not hope for ultimate success. For industry
depends, in the last analysis, upon the tenure and treatment of the land. Moreover, <pb
id="VAC1018-067" n="67"/> the agrarian revolt has nearly passed beyond the problematical stage: it
has proceeded so far, and with such urgent if tacit approval on the part of the Government, that
there is no probability of reaction. There is now hardly a question but that henceforth the
cultivatable land in Italy will pass into the hands of the actual users.</p>



<p>The revolt has had many phases. The Italian peninsula, stretching from the Alps almost to North
Africa, comprehends many varieties of climate and of soil; also several varieties of Italian
character and development.: In no two regions, therefore, has the revolt had exactly the same
manifestations and aims. In each locality, it has accorded with the conditions peculiar thereto-with
the aptitudes of the peasants, with the nature and products of the soil, with the methods of tillage
and the system of tenure.</p>
<p>The best exposition of the agrarian problem of Italy is in a very remarkable monograph by Pro-
fessor Adolfo Bellucci, bearing the title, " Come si risolve la Questione Agraria in Romagna." But,
as regards the revolution, especially in Southern Italy, the clearest summary has been made by
Signor Giuseppe Prezzolini, a noble Italian publicist of international authority, in articles
contributed to The Nation (of New York) and other American journals.: Prezzolini declares " the
seizure of the land by the peasants in Italy to be far more important than the seizure of the
factories by the workers," because of the fact that, while industry is <pb id="VAC1018-068" n="68"/>
relatively recent, " everything which concerns agriculture touches the most sensitive chords of
Italian social and economic life." In Sicily, where the revolt has been most conclusive, Prezzolini
points out that " one-sixth of the island is owned by 173 persons in a population of four millions ;
one-third is owned by 787 persons." The agricultural workers, numbering 725,000, possess practically
nothing. The great landowners live away from their lands, in Palermo, in Rome, on the French
Riviera, and in Paris., They rent their lands to a class of publicans called <hi rend="i"
>Gabellotti</hi>. The <hi rend="i">Gabellotto</hi> advances money to the peasant for the year's
crops; or frequently he re-rents to others, who in their turn sublet, so that the peasant has to pay
three or four middlemen. " The <hi rend="i">Gabellotto</hi> is the financier of the agrarian
management of the proprietor; he is usually a peasant who has grown rich,, a usurer without
scruples, who tries to get what profit he can from the land without improving it, not being sure of
having it again, and also running the risk of losing the harvest by the frequent droughts. He
employs a personnel of tyrants (rural guards, superintendents, etc.) to keep the peasant under
strict guard for fear he should eat the seed instead of sowing it, or rob the harvest, or go to work
on other lands. The <hi rend="i">Gabellotto</hi> pays the master and the peasant in advance, but he
cannot rob the master and he can rob the peasant, and out of the advance payment which he gives to
the peasant, he takes from thirty to fifty per cent. as interest. It is not to be wondered that the
<hi rend="i">Gabellotto</hi> is <pb id="VAC1018-069" n="69"/> the most despised and hated person in
Sicily." It was against the <hi rend="i">Gabellotti</hi> the revolt of the peasants was originally
directed. The occupation of the land came as an expansion of the revolt. Prezzolini cites, as a
typical instance, the case of the Duke of Bivona, a Spanish grandee, who came to sell his Italian
estate to his <hi rend="i">Gabellotto</hi>. At Rome, envoys of the Catholic co-operatives and unions
of ex-soldiers offered him three million lire for a part of his estate. He refused to accept because
he hoped for better terms from his <hi rend="i">Gabellotto</hi>. But during the night, the Catholics
and ex-soldiers attacked his fortress with stones, and forced the Duke to give up the land they
wanted&mdash;Ioo,ooo hectares thus becoming the property of the peasants. This was the only act of
violence during a revolt which resulted in the occupation of the land of an entire third of
Sicily.</p>
<p>But the seizures as a rule have taken on not only a peaceful but a religious character.
Prezzolini reports that " Crusades of peasants from the crowded cities would leave for tenures six
or eight miles away, walking in fours, preceded by their leaders and flags, sometimes red, sometimes
black, sometimes tri-coloured, and sometimes all three kinds. On foot and on mules, the population
would take possession of the land, planting their banners and stationing their guards. They would go
back to the land accompanied perhaps by gendarmes-who prevented disorder but had not been able to
stop the invasion&mdash;and from there they would telegraph the King or the Prefect, announcing <pb
id="VAC1018-070" n="70"/> their taking of possession, and asking for the authorisation even to
defend the land against the owners by means of the gendarmes. There is often an agreement between
two neighbourhoods, between two associations. Only once did a conflict break out between two
neighbourhoods which had built trenches on disputed territory."</p>
<p>The revolt in Southern Italy is a direct issue of the war. The Italian peasant, unlike the
workers of England, quite naively took the Government at its word-much as the little child takes the
word of its mother. The Government had promised to provide for the peasants, who constituted the
major part of the armies. To provide for the peasant meant to give land&mdash; there was no other
way of providing for him. Nor does he seem ever to have questioned the will and the power of the
Government to keep its promise. So, on being demobilised, and acting according to his interpretation
of the Government's good pleasure, he simply took the land of the feudal owners, moved on to it and
went to work. And it so happened that the Government was pleased&mdash;and made no pretence of being
displeased&mdash;at having its hand thus forced by these childlike citizens. Nor was the Church less
pleased than the Government. Indeed, the Catholics were the very first, writes Prezzolini, to incite
the peasant to take the lands ; and, in many instances, the invasions were led by priests or monks.
In one case, a Dominican friar led the struggle against the Gabellotti and the proprietors.
Moreover, the revolt had, particularly in Southern Italy, no <pb id="VAC1018-071" n="71"/> political
character or purpose ; it was absolutely economic, with a tinge of early Christian idealism.</p>
<p>But in Central and Northern Italy, the agrarian movement is older, and its manifestations are not
the same as those depicted by Prezzolini in his account of Southern Italy. An exception must be
made, however, in the instance of the Campagna, where many thousands of hectares have been occupied
in the course of the recent revolt. Most of this land, some of it close under the walls of Rome, has
been taken over by unions of ex-soldiers, who are not only happily cultivating it, but are also
scientifically restoring the long exhausted soil. Near Rome, too, 40,00o hectares belonging to the
Duke of Bivona, whose Sicilian estate I have already spoken of, were seized by the same unions, and
with governmental approval. But in Lombardy, especially in regions comprehended by the great rice
plantations, also in like regions on the Venetian mainland, and more especially in Romagna, the
present agrarian movement began, roughly speaking, five to ten years before the ;War. Years before
the revolt, co-operative agriculture had been carried on in the North&mdash;particularly in those
provinces where the contadini had come under the influence of the Socialist Party. And it is due to
the Socialist propaganda that the agrarian movements of Northern and Central Italy have generally
taken on a political character, and that they have often adopted the communist programme.</p>


<pb id="VAC1018-072" n="72"/>
<p>In the more recent movement, the attitude of the Government, especially in the agrarian revolt of
the South, is clear enough ; and as wise as it is clear. The Government has not hindered the revolt,
has perhaps covertly guided it, with a view to securing in the peasantry a permanent stabilising
social force. It is pretty certain, too, that on the ground of sheer social justice Signor Giolitti
desired to give the land to its users, and to rid Italy of the socially useless or parasitic class
that has for ages fattened on the peasantry, thereby impoverishing the nation and balking its normal
development. However shifty a politician he may be, he is at bottom a thoroughly sincere and even
ardent social reformer.</p>
<p>Equally clear and commendable is the attitude of the Church. For several reasons of its own, and
especially as an antidote to extreme, socialist doctrine, the Church as well as the Government
desires the stabilising social force inherent in peasant ownership. True, the sincerity of the
Church's action has been denied by both Conservatives and Socialists. But I am certain there is no
reason for such denial&mdash;no reason for doubting that the Church, both in principle as well as a
matter of policy, actually wished the land rendered back to the peasantry. Despite what is evil in
Roman ecclesiastical history, it yet remains true that the Catholic Church is profoundly democratic
at the core&mdash;at least in its genesis-and has historically taken the part, whenever put to the
test, of men against masters. The Church also builds upon <pb id="VAC1018-073" n="78"/> a broad
communistic base. Moreover, despite the splendours of the Cardinals and the Church processions,
nowhere can be found more true shepherds of the people, more really Christlike persons, walking in
the dignity of simple goodness, than among the 'village and rural priests of Italy. And it is not to
be questioned, I am convinced, that the priests and friars who led the agrarian revolt in
Sicily&mdash;and led it with the approval of the Church&mdash;were inspired by a genuine and
passionate sympathy for the peasants, and even by something like an early Christian apostleship.</p>
<p>But granting that Church and State together secure in the peasantry the stabilising social force
they each desire ; granting that peasant proprietorship be thus permanently and happily established
; it does not therefore follow that the matter there ends. What happened in France, as a result of
the Revolution, furnishes neither analogy nor precedent for what will happen in Italy. Peasant
ownership in Italy will take on no such character, will provide no such anti-social phenomena, as we
find in the peasant owners of France. The Italian peasant and the French constitute a quite complete
antithesis. It is not to be denied that the French peasant is moved by monetary and narrow family
considerations ; nor that he is unsocial in both his actions towards others and in his labour on his
land. The Italian peasant, on the other hand, is not primarily moved by money ; while along with his
desire to possess his own life and act in his own way along with <pb id="VAC1018-074" n="74"/>his
inability either to be a machine or to use one, runs a continuous stream of inclusive kindness. His
neighbourliness is indispensable to his individual being. Towards strangers, also, he is ever
courteous, even chivalrously attentive. Besides all this, he will never work alone&mdash;no one ever
saw him working alone. Whether he be peasant proprietor or agricultural employee, he must work in
company. Individualist that he is in regard to the possession of himself and his land, as a worker
he is incorrigibly social.</p>
<p>So it would seem that peasant proprietorship and co-operative labour must inevitably wed in
agricultural Italy ; and the co-operative labour will include much of the common life, eventually
rendering it unprecedentedly free and happy. Of course, the matter is not so simple as I seem to
have put it ; nor is the conclusion to be so easily reached as I seem to indicate. The whole Italian
agrarian movement is complicated by many divergencies, deflections and cross-currents. Yet two main
lines are fairly distinct&mdash;the one leading to and intensifying peasant proprietorship, the
other leading to an altogether communistic tenure and tillage. It is not easy to decide along which
of these two main lines the larger tendency proceeds. In some regions, private ownership seems to be
the inclusive end of the struggle ; in others, an extreme Soviet ideal seems to be at work. But when
the two main tendencies are studied in action, they are everywhere .seen to be converging. WVhen all
the facts and forces, both <pb id="VAC1018-075" n="75"/> major and minor, are analysed and
synthesised, the Italian agrarian revolt as a whole may be posited as a stage in an evolution which
will result in a union of private ownership with cooperative cultivation and barter. The
peasant&mdash; owners will co-operate in the tillage of the soil, in the purchase of seeds and
tools, in the marketing of their produce: gradually, but totally, the middleman or traditional
profiteer will be eliminated. And, since the Italian farmer, like his industrial fellow-worker, is
an extremely intelligent person, he will come to economic knowledge by native instinct. And this
knowledge will ultimately lead him to base his ownership of the land, his co-operative agricultural
activity, along with the well-being and happiness thus secured, upon a system of taxation whereby
the government supports itself by the appropriation of that economic increment of the land which
only society earns. And this Italian solution&mdash;this synthesis of peasant proprietorship and
co-operative agricultural labour and barter-the whole based upon the seizure of economic rent by the
national community&mdash; will, I prophesy, become the ultimate land system universal. For it is the
only system that takes account of the economic facts and spiritual forces of the human creature.</p>
</div2>


<pb id="VAC1018-076" n="76"/>


<div2 type="chapter">
<head rend="center">VI<lb/> THE STRIFE OF THE EXTREMESE<lb/>
</head>
<p> ONLY in Italy could a sort of civil war be carried on amidst disregarding populations going
gaily about their daily affairs. One is carried back to the times wherein the creators and the
creations of the Renaissance arose in a Florence whose every palace was an armed fortress, with wars
between the families the normal condition of the streets. One remembers how that long line of
marvellous men, from Saint Francis to the great Leonardo, performed their unequalled tasks amidst
City-States, wherein successive despots ruled by the law of assassination ; and wherein no man and
no people knew what new strife and ruin the morrow might bring. Those tumultuous splendid yesterdays
are surely ancestral to the Italy of to-day&mdash;an Italy straitened with the pangs of new birth;
an Italy haunted as well as instinct with a splendour that, because it is spiritual, surpasses
infinitely the splendours of the great yesterdays ; yet an Italy teeming with a civil tumult betimes
uncontrollable. While the Government is proposing a momentous adventure in social solution to the
people, while the land quickens to the call of a new human springtime, Fascisti and Communists are
fighting in the streets of the towns <pb id="VAC1018-077" n="77"/> and along the country highroads.
Yet the effect produced upon the mind of the world is extraordinarily disproportionate to the effect
produced upon the Italian populations. The strife between these two extremes is serious enough in
all conscience, as every Italian publicist anxiously knows ; yet to the populace it seems but
incidental to a period of transition, and creates incredibly little derangement of the common
life.</p>
<p>But the strife is no less there, raging up and down the peninsula, constituting not only a sad
phenomenon, but a critical problem of the national life ; a phenomenon clouding the Italian prospect
with doubt, and threatening the better being of the nation. The future place and power of Italy
among the nations, as well as the success or failure of her Government's beneficent programme, will
depend much upon how soon and into what issues the strife be resolved.</p>
<p>Yet the roots of the present strife are not of Italy-they are an importation. And this,;too,
recalls the past. It is the recurrent tragedy of Italy's history that there have always been
exterior forces interested in her disruption. There have always been Powers beyond the Alps seeking
to divide the Italian people. This was as certainly true during the World-War as it was during the
Middle Ages, or as it was during the struggles preceding the Risorgimento. Caporetto. was largely
due to an intensive German propaganda-an imported propaganda aided, alas, by responsible Italians.
Prior to Caporetto, a foreign bureau was maintained in Switzerland for the purpose of inspiring and
subsidising a revolution that would take Italy <pb id="VAC1018-078" n="78"/> out of the war. After
the Armistice, and up to a few months ago, Lenin sent his labourers to reap what he thought to be a
ready Bolshevist harvest : he confidently expected Italy to follow Russia in the establishment of a
Soviet state. At the same time&mdash;nor at all paradoxical to such as understand&mdash;certain
foreign financial and governmental interests, fearful of a possible rivalry resulting from the
general recovery of Italy, also worked&mdash;but covertly and not openly &mdash;for her national
impotency. As much from the capitalist West as from the more candid Soviet East&mdash;and more from
Italy's formal Allies than from all her formal enemies&mdash;came the influences making for
division.</p>
<p>Thus it came about, as a result of the open Bolshevist propaganda on the one side, as a result of
the secret propaganda of financially controlled foreign Powers on the other, that Italy was, for
months at a time, in a state of almost continuous industrial and civil tumult. There were strikes
everywhere, and mostly for political reasons. Public services were paralysed : a train or telegram
or letter might or might not reach its destination. The tramcars of a city were stopped only because
an employee had a quarrel with a passenger. The railway&mdash; men refused, whether rightly or
wrongly, to conduct convoys of arms and soldiers. Electrical workers left cities in darkness. Social
security &mdash;even social probability&mdash;seemed extinct. And whoever did not know well the
Italian people could not conclude otherwise than that Italy was in the way of becoming
Bolshevist.</p>
<p>It was in the Emilia that the conditions were <pb id="VAC1018-079" n="79"/> worst. The masses of
these provinces are Socialists of the extreme left ; and a virtual dictatorship of the proletariat
had been in existence for years before the war. After the war, the dictatorship grew daily more
irrational and ruthless. Boycotts embittered personal relations to a high degree. Whoever did not
accept the conditions imposed by the Socialist Leagues was exposed to reprisals. The baker would not
sell him bread, the shoemaker would not furnish him shoes. Even if he died, his body would not be
buried if the grave-diggers belonged to one of the Leagues. The clergy suffered also: in certain
regions the Socialist Parties demanded an income from the revenues of the Church; the people would
be forbidden to go to Mass, only because a village priest had employed a boycotted peasant, or had
made hay in a boycotted field. The League would exact a tribute from this bourgeois and that, ac-
cording to his wealth or according to the gravity of his offence against some edict of the League.
Signor Prezzolini declares the regime thus established to have been worthy of the Middle Ages.</p>
<p>It was against this increasing violence, and because of the practical breakdown of social
organisation, that the Fascisti arose. The roots of the movement reach back to the national revival
succeeding the disaster of Caporetto and culminating on the Piave. It was the young men of that
revival, again rising spontaneously throughout Italy, that constituted themselves into. the Fasci.
Their originating purpose was the ending of a social disorganisation of nearly two years' duration.
And it is a curious phenomenon <pb id="VAC1018-080" n="80"/> of the movement that its chief should
be Benito Mussolini, a former Socialist editor and leader, who separated himself from the Socialist
Party because of his advocacy of Italy's participation in the war.</p>
<p>The Fascisti groups, but loosely held together, varying according to the characteristics of their
respective regions, at first consisted largely of young men of the upper middle classes, though some
were of the nobility. The major groups were composed of students, ex-officers, and demobilised
Arditi; but now there are among them an increasing number of workers, and of the sons of peasants
and smaller shopkeepers. Indeed, in some cases, groups of Socialists and workmen&mdash;such as the
Socialist League of Ferrara, and a band of railway workers of Florence&mdash;have passed over
entirely to the Fascisti. Doubtful elements are among them, of course, whence they are in some
degree compromised by men who are more or less adventurers. But, all in all, they are young men,
says Prezzolini, " daring and disposed to let their heads be broken, or to break the heads of their
adversaries." And the most amazing fact of their movement is their exercise of a power out of all
proportion to their numbers. Relatively small bands of Fascisti have reduced large communities to
submission&mdash;sometimes communities that were overwhelmingly of the revolutionary Socialist
faith.</p>
<p>Yet the Fascisti must not be taken for mere reactionaries. They stand to a certain degree for
social reforms, and they indeed rival the Communists in the bitterness of their feeling <pb
id="VAC1018-081" n="81"/> against war-profiteers. Also the agrarian revolution, returning the lands
to the peasants as it does, receives from the Fascisti an urgent advocacy. And recently they have
forcibly brought down the cost of living, almost throughout the whole of Italy, by means almost as
humorous as they were startling and efficacious.</p>
<p>But, of course, it was against the Bolshevist propaganda the Fascisti arose, and against this
propaganda it still proceeds, purposing no less than its complete suppression&mdash;or else con-
version. Thus, degree by degree, they have practically destroyed the earlier Bolshevist
manifestations and possibilities throughout Italy, rendering a real service to their country in a
time of portentous crisis. And this notwithstanding the doubtful elements among them, or the
reprehensible extremes to which they have latterly gone. Fascismo represents, as Prezzolini has
said, "a justified reaction against the excesses of the Socialists." " If," he continues, " their
resources are forced upon them, as certain people believe, by the industrials, it is none the less
true that the reaction is often quite spontaneous, and that the public opinion of the populations,
tired of the violences of the Socialists, also helps the movement." He asks us to remember, too, "
that in Italy the political parties are not always well defined or separated. Italy is a country in
which public opinion has a great force, and disposes of the masses between the political parties.
These masses follow occasional considerations more than principles, and they are influenced by the
Press and by the brilliancy of certain energetic men." <pb id="VAC1018-082" n="82"/> "Fascismo," he
concludes, " is very probably only a passing phenomenon; it will disappear. But, for the moment, it
is a phenomenon of great importance, and one which we must face in its reality."</p>
<p>Yet it must not be supposed that the violence of the Socialists of the left, seduced and deluded
as they were by the representatives of Moscow, and producing its own nemesis in the form of the
Fascismo, had either the sympathy or the support of true Socialist leaders. The Socialist Party of
Italy has produced some remarkable men&mdash;some unusually able leaders of noble quality. No abler
or braver Italian than Leonidas Bissolati has ever appealed to the Italian people. Turati has the
mental and'moral equipment of a high order of statesmanship, the capacities of a great minister.
Serrati, though standing somewhat to the left, is nevertheless a man of judgment and discretion, as
well as of unquestioned integrity. D'Aragona and Treves, more directly representing labour than
those I have named, are men of both political wisdom and force of character. These have all, each in
his own way, sought to lead Italian Socialism along the path of a peaceful revolution, accomplished
by constitutional procedure. They have not compromised the Socialist ideal: but they hold that this
ideal can be realised only through the education of the workers, through political conquest and
experience. At Congress after Congress, they have tried to prevent the disruption of the Socialist
Party&mdash;till recently the strongest and most united political force in Italy. The <pb
id="VAC1018-083" n="83"/> attitude of these responsible leaders has always been one of conciliation,
so much so that, when the left withdrew at the Congress of Leghorn&mdash; taking the name of the
Communist Party, according to orders from Moscow&mdash;Turati and d'Aragona withheld any
condemnation of the separatists. They have also tried, as I have already pointed out, to rally the
Party to the support of the Government Bill. And the repudiation of their action by the Party
Executive, instead of strengthening the Socialist cause, in reality served the dearest desire of the
supercapitalists.</p>
<p>Nor did the separatists act in ignorance of what they did. They were in possession of the report
of their own representatives concerning conditions existing in Russia. In the spring of I92o, an
Italian Socialist delegation was sent to Russia with instructions to ascertain the success or
failure of the revolutionary regime. The mission returned to Italy in a state of disillusionment as
regards Soviet Russia. In the report of Serrati, who had previously favoured the Moscow
International, one may read a fearful indictment of the Bolshevist rule. " There is nothing left but
a brute mass, incapable of organic conception, hating work, resigned to misery, to obedience, and to
death I " " There is no liberty of the press or personal liberty, but terrorism holds subject more
than a hundred million people." " The ignorant masses are grouped in peasant labour armies, which do
little work and do that little badly." Nor are the impressions of d'Aragona any less vivid or
antagonistic to the Soviet <pb id="VAC1018-084" n="84"/> society. "Russian industry continues to
retrograde, and it cannot regenerate until many years have passed-until, the blockade removed, a
different system of control than the present one has been established." " Half the towndwellers of
Northern Russia will perish of cold and starvation during the coming winter." " Because of lack of
nourishment, individual production is less than thirty per cent. of what it is in normal times." Yet
despite this deterring knowledge&mdash;as well as despite the restraining influence of Serrati and
d'Aragona &mdash;the advocates of violence continue their essentially Bolshevist apostolate.
Strangely enough, too, neither the champions of the Proletarian Dictatorship nor the Anarchist
advocates are themselves of the proletariat. They are generally, if not always, the offspring of the
aristocracy or the intelligensia they would destroy. Just as Lenin is a noble, Krassin a great
industrialist, Bombacci a former school teacher, so is Professor Graziadei, a violent Italian
communist, not only a man of wealth, but retains his seat in a university under the direction of the
government he would destroy, and Gramsci, of Turin, is a student and idealist of rarest
qualities.</p>
<p>So the strife of the extremes continues.. And its continuance can only strain and imperil the
Italian social structure. For the continuance, too, a solemn and very heavy responsibility :rests
now with the Fascisti. It is they who now have the power, having overcome the violence against which
they rose. If they would now surely and sanely serve Italy, they must stand as strongly <pb
id="VAC1018-085" n="85"/> for social conciliation, for an inclusive civil freedom, as they formerly
stood against the terrorisation of the nation by a single class. Granting the patriotic origin of
the Fascisti, granting they have saved Italy from anarchy, they must perceive that <hi rend="i">in
violence rests no permanent redemptive or preservative social force. Violence cannot really cure the
evils which violence has created. Violence begets only violence in the end</hi>. Just as the
violence of the Socialist left begot the violence of the Fascisti, so will the violence of the
Fascisti, if it continue, produce a Bolshevist renaissance. They will thus thwart the fulfilment of
Italy's greatest modern opportunity &mdash;the opportunity presented by her Government's programme
of social solution and conciliation. And, moreover, they will thus be taking the course precisely
desired by Lenin and his disciples.</p>
<p>Will the young men of the Fasci, upon whom so great a weight of responsibility thus rests, read
to-day the true meaning of their victory? Will they now go on to that greater victory, without which
the victory they have won is worse than useless&mdash;is indeed but a victory for the forces of
darkness? Will they stand, in this the high-tide of their success, for a new freedom comprehending
the whole social body? Will they rise against the terrorisation of the Socialist by the public, just
as they rose against the terrorisation of the public by the Socialist? The future of Italy not only,
the, future of all humanity also, waits now upon what answer their actions give. If the answer be
nay, then will the Fascisti, following the <pb id="VAC1018-086" n="86"/> fatal historic course of
all such movements as theirs in the past, become but worse oppressors of the people they went forth
to deliver. If the answer be yea, then soon may these young men, become thus apostles of
conciliation and a fairer freedom, enter upon a triumph increasing infinitely the spiritual fund of
the Italian peoples, resourcing them anew and anew consecrating them to their historic quest. Let
them henceforth aspire to such a triumph; and in pursuit thereof, let them re-inspire themselves
with words spoken by Italy's last great inspirer, Giosu6 Carducci, when making fiery appeal to the
students of Padua. " Let not the weak, the anemic, the sceptical, come to provoke us ; let them not
come to deprive us of the Ideal, to deprive us of God. Recreants ! The Ideal was so stored up in our
fathers' souls and in ours that, merely in freeing itself and confounding the false prophets, it
revealed a people to itself, renewed a nation, determined the fate of an historic epoch. The God of
love and of sacrifice, the God of life and of the future, the God of the people and of humanity, 'is
in us, with us, and for us. . . . Be good and have faith: have faith' in love, in virtue, in justice
: have faith in the high destinies of the human race, which mounts, glorious, along the ways of its
ideal transformation."</p>
<p>The appeal comes not only to the Fascisti&mdash; to the youth of Italy: it comes with equal force
to the whole Italian citizenry. It comes to the possessors of economic power, to the owners of the
machinery of production, bidding them discern the historical doom of the old <pb id="VAC1018-087"
n="87"/> order; bidding them be wise in this their perhaps last valley of decision; bidding them so
to consent and so to act that the passing of the old shall be identical with a providential coming
of the new. It comes to the workers, bidding them perceive that their every act of violence is but
the lifting of their hands against themselves. It comes to all Italians, bidding them now for the
sake of Italy, now for the sake of the whole family of man, absolve themselves of their
divisions&mdash;divisions to-day tearing down the golden gates inviting Italy to enter immediately
upon the mission which all her prophets have proclaimed as her divine portion among the nations.</p>
<p>The world is blood-drunken, and staggers towards an , ageless spiritual torpor. More wanton grow
the wounds mankind inflictetlh upon itself. ;Whole peoples are being transformed into wolf-packs.
Civilisation is becoming the wilderness and the howling&mdash;place of governments growing ever more
bestial. Amidst the universal horror, the soul of Ifaly still lives and strives ; and that soul is
able even yet to speak, I believe, the word that goes forth for the healing of humanity&mdash;a word
empowered to end the ancient delay, to answer the ancient question, whereof the Titan painter cried
to his Vittoria: <q rend="blockquote">
<lg>
<l>Blind is the world; and evil here below</l>
<l>O'erwhelms and triumphs over honesty:</l>
<l>The light is quenched; quenched too is bravery:</l>
<l>Lies reign, and Truth hath ceased her face to show.</l>
<l>When will that day dawn, Lord, for which he waits</l>
<l>Who trusts in Thee ? Lo, this prolonged delay</l>
<l>Destroys all hope and robs the soul of life.</l>
</lg>
</q>
</p>
</div2>

<pb id="VAC1018-088" n="88"/>
<div2 type="chapter">
<head rend="center"> VII<lb/> THE NEW RENAISSANCE</head>
<p>WHICHEVER of the Alps you cross, you are at once aware, on coming into Italy, of an ongoing of
life contrasting so startlingly with the life whence you came as to seem either unreal or
miraculous. You have left behind you a world grown old and weary and dry of soul-a world upon which
the gods seem to lay some mysterious disablement, some cosmical despair. But the Italian world into
which you have come seems riotous with hope, as if the childhood of the race were about to be
renewed. Time is as young, nature is as human, the wonder of life just as pagan and as present, as
if you were in the Tuscany of two or mayhap four thousand years ago. You find excitement and tumult,
to be sure; yet amidst all, and despite all, and despite the war's manifold disappointments and its
human and material cost, you behold a new human springtime buoyantly blossoming. You are transported
yet bewildered. You had forgotten that these Italians never grow old. And when you thus unexpectedly
find them as fresh as if the years of battle and death and betrayal had not been, as resurgent and
unbaffled and impossible to <pb id="VAC1018-089" n="89"/> bind, you feel yourself, as Robert Louis
Stevenson would probably have said, in the presence of a people whom God likes.</p>
<p>It is no use trying to account for the phenomenon-at least not closely. The Italian has always
been like that-as far back through the centuries as we know anything about him. But one may venture
this-that his perennial youth is due to the precise cause of our chief complaint against him: that
is, the Italian has never bowed down to the god of sheer efficiency. He has never submitted his life
to material measurements ; has never admitted that the worth of a man or a nation consisteth in the
abundance of the things which the man or the nation hath; has never looked upon the human race as
existing for the production and barter of things.</p>
<p>But it is the development rather than the explanation of the revival that is the concern of this
chapter. According to Professor Paolo Emilio Pavolini, a most cultured and comprehending critic, its
first and most meaningful characteristic is its " vulgarisation of letters." The social question, in
all its aspects ; questions of foreign policy, in all their ramifications ; these have so entered
into the common life as to compel writers who would treat of them to use its language. Nor is it
only these who have been forced from the academy into the public square : writers upon every sort of
subject, even the apostles of " pure literature," more and more speak the tongue of the people. The
common intellectual eagerness has invaded the schools, also, so that they are filled with <pb
id="VAC1018-090" n="90"/> discussions of the new and more social pedagogy. The demand for larger
culture has resulted, too, in a considerable popularisation of the numerous institutes of French,
English and German literature. It has at the same time manifested itself in the amazing number of
schools and clubs which have sprung up among workmen, eager not only for a knowledge of social
economics, but for the literature, both classic and current, of all nations. And the researches of
the specialist, even though they be more profound than formerly, are now presented in a language and
form that has the common man in view. It may be, thinks Professor Pavolini, that this intellectual
revival pervades the common life all the more deeply and prophetically because it springs from no
Dante, from no single commanding figure, but is rather compelled by the ongoing rebirth of
industrial society. In any case, it is with the desire for industrial and social regeneration that
every phase of intellectual expression must now reckon.</p>
<p>So inclusive, indeed, as well as popular, are these questions of life and society that the
various intellectual and philosophical cults, so numerous and militant in Italy before the war, have
disappeared. And the literary pre-war Chauvinism&mdash;which Benedetto Croce declares to have been
mainly a French importation-has been dissolved in a literary nationalism springing from Mazzinian
roots, and looking, one may fairly say, to a Christian solution of both historic and present
problems. Even journalism&mdash;whicli in Italy maintains a higher intellectual character <pb
id="VAC1018-091" n="91"/> than in any other country&mdash;must constantly deal with matters of
social philosophy and international morality. One has only to peruse editorial articles by such as
Professor G. A. Borgese and Dr. Giulio Caprin for evidence of the superior quality of the journalism
of Italy.</p>
<p>" This vulgarisation of literature is really a response," says Pavolini, " to the prodigious and
unprecedented love for reading and culture which grew up after the war. Thus we find, in the
artistic field, reviews printed with a quite unprecedented luxury of paper and of reproduction (for
instance the 'Dedalo ' of Ugo Ojetti and ' II Primato ' of Podrecca) ; in the critical field, the
phenomenal diffusion of newspaper articles and articles from reviews, which are continuously
gathered and republished in book form ; in the literary field, the innumerable translations from
French, English, German, Spanish, Russian and even remote oriental languages: not all of them really
good, and often the choice made without discernment, but whoever is thirsty of letters and of
culture does not choose the drink given to him: very critically. We must therefore not complain
about these phenomena: even if we deplore the low tastes of a not small part of the public. Of this
taste and for it has been born the so-called 'entertaining' literature, whose capital is in Milan
and whose chief representative is Guido da Verona; and with his cinematographical titles, and his
covers embellished with nude women, he inundates all the windows of the bookstores in the Kingdom.
These volumes are having quite an incredibly high number of editions, they <pb id="VAC1018-092"
n="92"/> are sold at a rather high price, and their publishers and authors gain hundreds of
thousands of lire. We understand it, because it is the literature of the 'nouveaux riches,' who
thirst for enjoyment and prodigality. The only merit of this vain and somewhat disgusting inundation
is, that it has closed the way to the French novels which before the war dominated our book
market."</p>
<p>But the chief purport of this new passion for reading, indiscriminate as it is, pervading as it
does the whole Italian social body, is its preparation for the prophetic literary leadership,
perhaps more potential than manifest as yet, that seems about to call to young Italy. In fact, the
high intellectual promise of Italy lies in just this dual manifestation-the precipitate and
universal thirst for knowledge, for reading on every sort of subject, and the growing seriousness
and high resolvement on the part of so many special literary and scholastic leaders. There is every
promise that the popular thirst will ultimately be quenched by the springs of life bursting forth in
response to this new leadership's authentic word. About this Pavolini has no doubt. Nor has Italy's
illustrious philosopher, Benedetto Groce. And Croce is sure, also, that in Italy, more than in any
other country, " reigns a large spirit of sympathy and esteem for other peoples " ; and that this
spiritual internationalism is rooted in the ancient mental habit of Italy-in a history which reveals
" political wisdom, equilibrium, good sense, horror of exaggeration, as all a part of the nature of
the Italian people." He <pb id="VAC1018-093" n="98"/> is also certain that, as the economic,
scientific and literary life of mankind becomes ever more international, the Italian people, because
of both historical tradition and the present state of the national soul, is highly disciplined for
serving this developing universal society.</p>
<p>Another thing is certain: the new Italian literature will not take its cue from d'Annunzio.
D'Annunzio will indeed have his due as a master and an artist, and also as a patriot&mdash; without
him Fiume would have been lost to Italy&mdash;but the day of his school is done. Not to him nor his
art, nor to the like of these, does the younger intellectual life of Italy to-day look. That
literary chemistry of the senses, that artistic glorification of moral disease, of cruelty and
sodden brutality, which is the solemn code of the French novel and drama, and which has its climax
in d'Annunzio, has mayhap made its last appeal to Italy. The search of the Italian is now for
spiritual and social verities. He is seeking out paths for the soul of man, and for verbal pictures
whereby to disclose them. And the quest has its prophet, for the moment, in Giovanni Papini-in
Papini turning aside to spend long months in preparing an account of Christ that shall appeal to the
people.</p>
<p>As to philosophy, one may behold chiefly a reaction toward Hegel. It is indeed an extreme
post-Hegelianism that now holds the field. Even such resolvements of Hegelian oppositions as Croce
has attempted do not satisfy Giovanni Gentile or Guido de Ruggiero. A full-winged and untrammelled
idealist is de Ruggiero.<ref id="ref_001" rend="super" target="note_001">I</ref></p>
<note id="note_001"><ref target="ref_001" rend="super">I</ref>His work on Modern Philosophy has
recently been issued in English in the Library of Philosophy (George Allen and Unwin, Ltd.).</note>


<pb id="VAC1018-094" n="94"/>
<p>For him " philosophy emerges from the restricted specialism of the schools and is historical
reality itself in the fulness of its manifestations ; it is the reflected consciousness of the
world, <hi rend="i">the invisible God manifested In the visible world</hi>." History is to him,
apparently even more than to Hegel, " the phenomenological process of the spirit." But this reaction
is no theme for mockery, even on the part of the Physicists, the New Materialists, the
Behaviourists, to say nothing of the latter Pragmatists who so unreasonably claim William James for
their father. The reaction in philosophy but betokens that high seriousness, that search for man's
reason for being, which is so distinctly the leitmotiv of the whole Italian intellectual
revival.</p>
<p>The intellectual revival is not so manifest in painting and sculpture. But the signs are
there-not so much in the new tendency of art as in the utter end of old tendencies. " Futurism " and
" Cubism," with all their progeny, and with their undue assumption of authority, are among the
things of yesterday. They have no place in the Italian attention of to-day. For that matter, it was
only by themselves they were ever taken seriously. And their origin, too, was French. There is
reaction, it is true, but it is toward classicism, and in the way of a search for art's profounder
meanings. It is a reaction that renews Carducci's scorn of " Art for Art's sake." Yet the classicist
tendency is not merely a new imitation: it is <pb id="VAC1018-095" n="95"/> really a return to the
spirit, to the motives and interpretative powers of the great ancients. And this classical revival
has been stimulated by the two recent centenaries of Leonardo da Vinci and of Raphael; it has also
received, along with Italian letters, a profound inspiration from the Dante centenary.</p>
<p>But the most significant indication of the state of mind in which' Italian art now finds itself,
has been best analysed, so far as I know, by Riccardo Nobili, a very keen and just Italian critic,
apparently better known to English and American readers than to Italian. The significance and
promise of 'the newer Italian art lies in what Signor Nobili calls its period of " Mutism." The
artists of other nations have tried-have indeed felt obliged to try&mdash;to paint the war, just as
the poets have felt obliged to sing it. What surprised Nobili, after visiting the different
expositions since the armistice, was the fact that the war seemed not to have touched the painter.
So far as the expositions were concerned, his first thought was: to the artist the war had not been.
Of course, there were some of the older painters who felt obliged to essay the battles ; but they
were few and negligible. Italian painters as a whole, by some native but rare instinct, had let the
war alone. Most of them had been to the front, had participated in all the horror and slime and
blood ; had taken part in scenes which were but mildly foreechoed by Dante's Inferno. And they had
come back to their ateliers dumb. The war simply could not be painted. The greatest catastrophe
through which historic mankind had ever passed <pb id="VAC1018-096" n="96"/> was beyond the reach or
power of art&mdash;indeed beyond the understanding of the mankind that had suffered it. The Italian
artist felt that it was stupid to attempt to paint it, or to more than hint at it in backgrounds of
his pictures. The horrors of war, as they had been painted by the artists of old, constituted but a
cheap and misleading melodrama to the artist who had fought and come back alive. This was no time,
thought Nobili, for " Cyrano de Bergeracs of the brush or chisel." Heroics became disgusting in the
presence of the sacrifices of whole peoples in a universal struggle that will for long remain
inexplicable, and the sources of which are doubtless in other worlds than the one we see. The char-
acteristic of all the Italian artists who came back-indeed of the fighters as well-was one of
reticence. The things they had seen and done could not be reported by speech or symbols. It were
mockery to talk about them, to write about them, to paint them. And it is in this sober renunciation
of present effort, in this pregnant " Mutism " of which Nobili speaks, that the promise of the new
Italian art lies. For it is an art that will not trifle with truth; that will not desecrate what is
too great for portrayal by attempts that can only be paltry and misinforming at best. The Italian
artist will therefore-and this is according to the very logic of the Italian national character-be
silent about the great catastrophe. " What coruscation of colours," exclaims Nobili, " could give
the true idea of the war, what vermilion paint the blood, what hues stolen from the blaze <pb
id="VAC1018-097" n="97"/> of Vulcan depict burning cities and blasted mountains, and the battle and
death of thousands amidst the unnamable horrors of the trenches i " There is naught for the artist
but to take the war's experience into his soul, to wait patiently for its fruition, and meanwhile
turn his brush or chisel to things less cosmical and more comprehensible.</p>
<p>Yet there is no despair, no groping in the dark, in the Italian school now in its beginnings,
even if its guiding light be as yet dim. It is merely that the new Italian art is content to walk
for a time in a renunciatory way. And this, in the mind of Nobili, constitutes its spiritual genius
and its potential greatness. The artist, after the great catastrophe, understands that art is now
called to a period of " raccoglimento "&mdash;to spiritual self-discovery and synthesis. This art
will not take refuge in some new or old futurism, or in some new and daring technique, but will
rather enter upon a period of meditation, of both spiritual adventure and tentative experiment. It
is this which distinguishes the new Italian art-this that so significantly sets it apart from the
immediate art of other nations, and that makes it so vital a part of the new intellectual
revival.</p>
<p>But it must not be thought that the Italian revival is purely a thing of letters and of art. In
science, too, may be noted fruitful activity and progress, chiefly in mathematics, Iphysics and
biology. And Italian research is always international in scope and sympathy&mdash;as may be seen by
random perusal of its well-known review, Scientia. It is also manifesting itself in the <pb
id="VAC1018-098" n="98"/> urgent practical ends to which eminent specialists are turning their
attention and applying their knowledge. For instance, the most comprehensive programme of social
providence yet submitted to any country has been presented to Italy by Dr. Ettore Levi, now at Rome,
but formerly a professor in the Medical Academy of Florence. While I cannot here go into details of
his stupendous project, I may state that it is one that literally comprehends the entire social
being of the nation. It involves a national ramification and application of such an inclusive social
foresight as must ultimately provide a healthy home for every family; a room for every person ; a
full education for every child; and an opportunity to each citizen for a complete life. I mention
the project of Dr. Levi, not because it is exceptional, but because it is typical of the living
activism attending the Italian revival.</p>
<p>Of the part of music in the revival, there is less to say. There are not wanting signs, however,
of a reaction against the musical melodrama which has so long possessed the Italian people. It may
be that Verdi and Puccini and the rest will give place to composers worthy of the divinest of the
arts. There are signs, too, of the end of French domination&mdash;of the prettinesses and
puerilities, as well as the brilliant mental derangement, so characteristic of the modern French
school. Chief among those creative of the new tendency is Ildebrando Pizzetti, Director of the
Academy of Music in Florence, and composer of the marvellous music for d'Annunzio's " Fedra.'" He
has become <pb id="VAC1018-099" n="99"/> the founder of an essentially new school of composers-a
school which has now quite emancipated itself from its earlier French influence. This school of
Pizzetti, with whose name must be linked that of Francesco Malipiero, is characterised by "a
revolt," says Henrietta Straus, "against that slipshod and irregular relationship between ,the text
and the score, in which the voice is supreme, and which' is ever ready to sacrifice dramatic action
and continuity to effective recitative and aria; against, too, those arid wastes of Wagnerian
declamation which, in the end, leave one thirsting for a lyrical oasis." But the revolt is
accompanied by an ideal&mdash;" a desire for a more perfect marriage, a more spiritual union,
between the verbality and the music." It is thus that " Fedra " is "almost a model of musical
declamation, in ,which the lyrical flow is unbroken by either recitative or parlando, or the
orchestral development by isolated episodes of programmatic character." This passion for unity, for
the elimination of " everything that may clog the action or mar the unity of the component factors,
has been carried to even greater extreme by Malipiero." His " Orpheo " Henrietta Straus considers to
be, "with its marvellously woven texture, its wonderful play of emotional lights and shades, the
most boldly conceived musical form that the Italy of to-day has given us." And also must be noted,
in this relation, the curious adventures in futurist music on the part of Marinuzzi. But, better
than all else, these young masters seem to be seeking to re-unite Italian <pb id="VAC1018-100"
n="100"/> music with those sacred sources from which Beethoven drew the breath of his art
supreme&mdash; Palestrina and Cherubini and their lesser followers. Thus Italian music will become
once more the music of worship, the music of the soul, which is the only true music. Indeed, if
music be not essentially devotional, if it exalt not and refresh not the spirit of man, it is not
music. But this music will not come, be it said, except as the divine fruit of a new spiritual
springtime.</p>
<p>But the portents of the spiritual .springtime are many: the rumours of its coming, and the glad
trouble of it, are abroad in the Italian soul. It is this, above all else, that the intellectual
revival foreshadows and prepares. It could not be otherwise in Italy. For the Italian mind
peculiarly combines insistence upon analysis with purposeful capacity for synthesis ; and the ,union
of these two qualities always converts intellectual research into a quest for spiritual reality, for
human roots and meanings. And the quest for the roots and meanings of life releases the mind from
trammels and rigidities, setting it free for adventure and discovery. No hostages are thus required
for the inquiring intellect: it may go forth upon its quest without obligations, save to win the
truth, and to render it to the soul of man. Unless it be truth that is workable, truth that is
humanly applicable, the Italian intellect will not be satisfied : truth which is not usable is no
truth at all. It is the quest of this order of truth which keeps the Italian mind from the fogs
wherein the German mind loses itself; and from the sterile logic and the brilliant superficialness
<pb id="VAC1018-101" n="101"/> of the French intellect. And it is this that converts even the
scientific research of the Italian into human idealism or spiritual revelation. " Truth," once said
Carducci, " conceived under all its aspects by a great and serene intellect, by a lofty and pure
nature, becomes of itself ideality."</p>
<p>Thus, borne on by the quest for truth, Papini turns from futurist art and politics, and from an
earlier and somewhat d'Annunzian nationalism, to an apostolic advocacy of the need of men and
nations for the Christ. Except in the conversion of men and institutions to Christ, so preaches
Papini, nothing can save the Italian nation ; naught else can save civilisation from disintegration.
And it is a sign of national renewal, of spiritual as well as intellectual virility, that Papini is
superseding d'Annunzio as Italian master. Then we find Giovanni Amendola, a former associate of
Papini in Florence, turning from his promising philosophical career to politics. A desire to invest
political action with spiritual reality was the reason Amendola gave the writer for his change; and
one may well pray that so gifted a man prove true to his initial purpose, and be not seized by the
evil forces which so universally wait upon the possession of political power.</p>
<p>But most of those engaged in the new spiritual quest, following the example of Papini, are
keeping apart from active participation in politics. And many if not most of them are either present
or recent students of universities. In the University of Naples you will find&mdash;if <pb
id="VAC1018-102" n="102"/> you are fortunate enough to gain access to the midst of those of whom I
speak&mdash;some remarkable modern Quietists, living saintly lives of sincere austerity, preparing
themselves for regenerative service in the nation. And it is also in Naples that Professor Antonio
Anile, while teaching anatomy in the University, and while also serving as a member of the Italian
Parliament, is active in inciting his students to spiritual adventure, to self-discovery and self-
discipline. In keeping with this effort, he has written a remarkable book, La salute del
pensiero&mdash;" The Health of Thought."</p>
<p>The writer has come in contact with equally serious though differing groups among the younger
citizenry of Rome. There is the Circolo Universitario di Studii Storico-Religiosi, recently
inaugurated by Senatore Luigi Luzzatti, a former Prime Minister of Italy, who combines a clear
insight into financial problems with an ardent interest in religious questions. Lectures are given
before these students by such as Professors Bonaiuti, Formichi and Turchi. There is also the more
Modernist movement, up till now opposed by the Church, led by Professor Bonaiuti, Professor of the
History of Religion in the University of Rome, who combines great spiritual fervour with genuine
criticism and superior scholarship. He has a group of attached followers, mostly students. He was
recently excommunicated by the Church, but, upon his submission, the punishment was cancelled. ,With
Professor Bonaiuti is associated Professor Nicola Turchi, also a priest. And one must take note of
the group bearing <pb id="VAC1018-103" n="103"/> the name of the Independent Theosophical League,
deserving mention because of its distinctive character and the serious work it performs in many
directions.</p>
<p>In Milan there is; a society of philosophic and religious studies, led by Professor Piero
Mlartinetti, which is creating a philosophical library and organising public lectures for spiritual
instruction, especially among the young intellectuals. There is another Milanese group, chiefly of
literary men, but animated by high ideals, which cultivates "spiritual patriotism." Prominent among
those constituting this group is Signor Ettore Cozsoni, editor of the beautiful editions, <hi
rend="i">L'Eroica</hi>. There is Gianelli, a very active and ambitious Franciscan, who is organising
a Catholic University of Milan. And in the North, also, is the serious assemblage at Turin called
Gruppo Torinese per la Ricerca Spirituale. Its leader is Professor Vittorino Vezzani, who, like his
colleague in Naples, combines severe scientific training with deep ,spiritual aspirations. He is
also the editor of the review, <hi rend="i">Ultra</hi>, which records all the movements that are
making for the revival of Italy.</p>
<p>But much more significant is the work of Father Pio, living humbly and ascetically in his convent
near Foggia, and increasingly influencing Catholic Italy. Father Pio is a real son of Saint Francis.
He has wonderful mystical experiences and manifests extraordinary yet actual spiritual phenomena,
such as the stigmata. A powerful spiritual radiation and renewal falls upon his visitors.</p>
<p>Then, scattered throughout Italy, are the <pb id="VAC1018-104" n="104"/> Democratic Christians,
working along moral and social lines. These groups tried independent political action at first, but
have since renounced such action in favour of a more intensive work among the people. They publish a
review, <hi rend="i">Democrazia Cristiana</hi>, at Bologna. One of their chief leaders is Giuseppe
Donati.</p>
<p>It is in the Florence of to-day, however, as it was in the Florence of the fifteenth century,
that the new human springtime is most urgently manifested&mdash;only now it is a spiritual revival;
then it was intellectual. Florence is the most active centre of intellectual and spiritual com-
munion between persons and groups of all nationalities. Significant of this&mdash;more significant
than the barricades upon the opposite sides of which the Fascisti and the Communists lately
fought&mdash;is the fact that the Municipality of Florence has adopted, by a unanimous vote of all
parties, from the Conservative to the Socialist, Mazzini's <hi rend="i">Duties of Man</hi> as a
reading book in all the public schools.</p>
<p>It is in Florence that the new Catholic Modernism is most manifest-up to the present time
unrejected by the Church, and spreading forth from Florence unto other Italian cities. These new
Modernists contend that within the Church itself the new and more spiritual society of man will find
its sources and its realisation. They would even argue, and not without historic reasons, that the
Church is the real Society of Nations. They would contend, too, that within the forms of the Church
there is a possible infinite freedom for the pursuit of the human verities, and for the furtherance
and fulfilment <pb id="VAC1018-105" n="105"/> of the true universal society. Among these groups are
ardent new converts; and these, as well as those who are hereditarily Catholic, accept the authority
of the Church. Their apostolic inspirer was Giosu Borsi, a brilliant literary man who became
converted to the Church shortly before the war, and who wrote a notable <hi rend="i">Colloqui</hi>.
Tie <hi rend="i">Lettere</hi> of Borsi are regarded by some as the most beautiful Italian literary
issue of the war. He was passionately mystical, of the temper of 'Saint Augustine; yet he was
ardently Italian also, and went as a volunteer to the front, where he laid down his life. Of those
creatively responsible for the continuance of this new Modernism (I use the term in a very broad
sense) and forming an apostolate of the movement, are Professors Guido Ferrando and Piero Marrucchi.
Ferrando, with his fine fervour and intellectual attainments, gathers many young men around him,
leading them into a new catholicity of desire and understanding. Marrucchi's rare culture, his
intellectual integrity, his sweetness and sanity of spirit, make his personality as well as his
writing and teaching an irradiant spiritual force.</p>
<p>But the Modernist Movement is only one of numerous kindred activities in Florence. Of especially
fair portent are the groups gathering about the Philosophical Library, founded some years ago by
Mrs. Julia H. Scott, a revered and remarkable American woman. These groups are led and inspired by
Dr. Roberto Assagioli, a young psychologist known to English and Americans, and possessed of an
unusual discernment of mind as well as purity and power of spirit; <pb id="VAC1018-106" n="106"/>
and also by Professors Ferrando and Marrucchi Under their direction, the Library is the centre of
varied intellectual pronouncements and efforts, each with a spiritual purpose, and all marking a
high tide in the spiritual springtime. Crowded audiences gather to hear lectures upon innumerable
subjects&mdash;upon the social psychology of Christ; upon Buddha and Buddhism; upon Tagore and.
Young India; upon William James and Walt Whitman ; upon sexual education and civic. morality ; upon
whatever men and movements' may, in any and every part of the world, be making for the
reconciliation of classes and nations. Also at the Philosophical Library was created the Association
for Religious and Moral Progress, instituted by Professor Puglisi. It was initiated by a powerful
appeal on the part of Senatore Alessandro Chiapelli for the creation of a spiritual synthesis of the
east and the west, of inner regeneration and constructive activity. This appeal has appeared in the
review, <hi rend="i">II Progresso Religioso</hi>, published by the Association.</p>
<p>Dr. Assagioli would accredit the spiritual ferment in the Italian Youth to their "great
dissatisfaction with old forms and old methods in every field: religion, philosophy, education,
social and political activities. There is in them a deep yearning, a passionate impatience, for
something new and better." They are " eagerly searching, looking into the past and toward the
future, to the East and to the West," for somewhat to satisfy their spiritual hunger. " There is
still confusion and groping," but the young men and women " are finding their way," <pb
id="VAC1018-107" n="107"/> and finding it through a quest that is at once " spiritual and practical,
mystical and constructive." And Assagioli himself, if asked for his purpose, and if asked to state
wherein it is typical of the Italian revival, would say that he is seeking the formation of a true "
science of the soul "&mdash;in which science may be included a vital synthesis of all recent
discoveries and developments of scientific psychology with the intuitions and inner experiences and
methods of oriental spiritual experience and Christian mystical consciousness. He has recently
expressed his conceptions in a course of lectures on " The Phases and Methods of Spiritual
Development."</p>
<p>Also should be mentioned, in connection with Florence, the highly significant young women's
movement of the "Lamp-Bearers "; for it is in Florence the international direction of the movement
centres, in the person of Countess Matilde Marfori Savini. The movement was founded and is inspired
by Miss Nella Ciapetti, a young woman of great spiritual and intellectual power. But the work of the
Lamp&mdash;Bearers was preceded and predicated by the admirable movement started in Rome, under the
name of Vita Morale, by Professor Guglielmina Ronconi, a true apostle of love, knowing 'the hearts
of the women of Italy, and understanding the Italian peoples, even unto the downmost outcasts. The
movement has taken its motto from Mazzini, and has made of his writings somewhat of a gospel. " We
desire to feel," so runs a sentence in a Lamp&mdash;Bearer prospectus, " that there exists, under
all the diversities of races, creeds or <pb id="VAC1018-108" n="108"/> tendencies of thought, the
same fundamental and sacred humanity." These young women have a very complete programme of inner
spiritual work, of individual regeneration, of mutual spiritual and practical help, of education on
modern advanced subjects, such as the new free methods of teaching in the schools, sexual
instruction, social work among the children of the workers. They also devote themselves to prison
reform and moral help among the prisoners. And one of their chief purposes is the promotion of
international goodwill and fraternity, through seeking to bring together in mutual understanding and
various services the women of all nations and races.</p>

<p>The work of the Lamp&mdash;Bearers is, of course, but part of the great awakening and amazing
progress among Italian women in recent years. Among these kindred movements may be named the Unione
delle Donne Cattoliche, whose large membership is well organised and kept in hand by the Church
authorities. These are doing useful social work, though of a restricted kind, and also somewhat in
opposition to the more progressive feminist movements. Then there is the Consiglio Nazionale delle
Donne Italiane, which promotes and co-ordinates the activities of all other free feminist movements.
It is ably led by Gabriela Spalletti Rasponi, an indeed superior woman, who combines genuine
religious fervour with clear intellectual insight and practical efficiency and adaptability. Under
her wise leadership, the Italian feminist movements have avoided the excesses of militant feminism
of other countries ; and this while working vigorously <pb id="VAC1018-109" n="109"/> for all the
rights of women as citizens and for their education and preparation for public activity and
position.</p>
<p>Nor, while we are still at the City of the Renaissance, must the unique and beneficent place, the
very vitalising influence, of the British Institute be left out of account. Under the discriminating
yet sympathetic direction of Dr. Spender, with whom is associated Professor Ferrando, this
Institute, while not departing from its proper place and function, has yet lent itself so wisely and
helpfully to Florence,. that it has in itself become a chief centre of Florentine intellectual life.
Here one may meet many English writers, especially poets, Mr. Herbert Trench, for instance, being
one of the Institute's active founders. With these may be met Guglielmo Ferrero, who, perhaps more
than any man living, has connected the history of the past with modern problems ; and who, by reason
of his great literary gifts, has also made history intelligible to the common readers. And here one
may meet the beloved dramatist, Sem Benelli, with his fellow-writers.</p>
<p>I have already indicated that it is the blend of high intellectual understanding with spiritual
perception and purpose that characterises these Italian groups and movements. And this wedded
intellectual understanding and spiritual purpose produces what might be called a glowingly
optimistic pessimism. While hopeless concerning the present human order, it is at the same time
apostolically confident of the hid presence and ultimate emergence of a human order radically and
divinely new. The underlying <pb id="VAC1018-110" n="110"/> idea of all present Italian spiritual
movements, and also of the Italian intellectual revival, has been best expressed to the writer by
Duca Colonna di Cesarb, an Italian deputy who is also a member of an ancient family. His twofold
insistence is this: that civilisation has become so materialistic in its psychology, as well as in
its economic facts and political processes, that it is better for mankind that it perish ; but that,
even so, we must stay the dissolution of the old as long as we can, in ;order to prepare ourselves
spiritually for the creation of the new.</p>
<p>However that be, this is certain&mdash;that the problems of industrial and political society, so
far as Italy is concerned, will ultimately be solved according to human values and affections. No
problem, however fundamentally economic it be, however deeply it reaches to material roots and
comprehends material processes, can be to the Italian merely material or economic: it is always a
religious or affectional problem in the end.</p>
<p>Nor can any such problem ever escape the solving influence of the inherent and wholesome
romanticism of the Italian. It is a part of the paradox of his mind that he is as romantic as he is
scientific, as mystical as he is sceptical. lIe is at once too close to nature and too conversant
with ritual to be otherwise: he is a weaver of romance, just as he is a singer and a poet, even in
the making and the measurement of things. His economic problems all, as well as his questions of the
soul's origin and destiny, will proceed to their solution amidst <pb id="VAC1018-111" n="111"/> that
eternal procession of Pan, and,through those sacraments and sanctions of Holy Church, which together
keep Italy perennially young, and which convert so much of Italian labour into the likeness of the
play of children. And indicative of this is Professor Vittorio Grandi's original and profound work,
now in process of writing, on the drama and reconciliation of Pan and Christ.</p>
<p>The tremendous miracle of the common life still moves and rejoices the Italian in a way
incomprehensible to the Anglo-Saxon and to the Italian's kindred Frenchman. Saint Francis,
traversing the highways with " the courtesy of God " for his creed, his divine gaiety mocking the
drama of his poverty, is a typification of the Italian country and nation; so also is Saint Clara,
hardly seeking to translate her Jove for Francis into conventual duties. To the Umbrian of to-day,
as to his two altogether lovely saints of yesterday, life is still a delightful pageantry. And in
the Tuscan hills, invisible natural presences accompany the contadini across the fields and through
the vineyards, and lurking dryads still look out upon him from ancient olive trees. The Solemn Mass
and the vendemmia are still equally sacred. The young maiden's morning confession to her priest and
her evening dance at the wine harvest are of one and the same spiritual sort. And all this blent and
inseparable worship of Christ and Pan, with all the festology thereof, will inevitably affect and
colour the Italian social transformation, and invest life and labour with the gladness and freshness
of perpetual spring.</p>
</div2>


<pb id="VAC1018-112" n="112"/>
<div2 type="chapter">
<head rend="center"> VIII<lb/> THE THIRD ROME</head>


<p>IF from the beginning it be obvious that these chapters are written by a lover rather than a
critic, by an advocate rather than a judge, they are nevertheless inspired by other than the
writer's predilection for Italy. The reason for their writing lies in that healing of the nations
which the writer sees, or seems to see, potential within the Italian domestic programme, and the
Italian foreign policy. This programme and this policy carry in themselves the only governmental
promise, up till to-day, of a developing dlan sufficient to prevent the final catastrophe of our
civilisation. And they are the witness that, alone among the nations, the Italian people &mdash;or
some divine force still alive in this people &mdash;perseveres in a path appointed by historic
ideals. Up till yesterday, at least, Italy was the one tolerably free country left in the world ; up
till yesterday, at least, Italy was the one remaining approximate democracy ; up till yesterday, at
least, Italy was the sole country that had kept the promises made during the war ; up till
yesterday, at least, Italy alone stood for reconciliation between classes and between nations.</p>


<pb id="VAC1018-113" n="113"/>
<p>In her insistent efforts toward reconciliation, Italy has indeed made herself an evangel of
goodwill to the peoples of Europe. Highly prophetic of this were the words spoken by Count Sforza,
at the time of the Roman Conference between Italy and the States succeeding the Austro-Hungarian
Empire: " I trust, for all of us who come together here, that this will not be only for the
advantages which we shall get out of it, but because we shall have again proved, with the
incomparable eloquence of facts, that in the present society we cannot conceive of the economic
well-being of one without connecting it indissolubly with the wellbeing of his neighbours." And, be
it said, it is in accordance with the faith implicit in these historic words, it is in reliance upon
the law which they affirm, that Italy is governmentally proceeding. It is the indissoluble
membership of men in one another, it is the like membership in one another of the nations, that
posits Italy's developing plans for her own and the world's redemption from millennial evils
culminating in the war. It is thereupon that her adventure in industrial solution and her effort
toward international conciliation now hand in hand proceed. And when her total programme is
perceived and appreciated, when its courage is accounted together with its universal import, one
permissibly may imagine Dante again saying of his countrymen, and with better reason than he said of
the citizens of imperial Rome, " We behold them as a nation . . . putting aside avarice, which is
ever averse to <pb id="VAC1018-114" n="114"/> the general welfare, cherishing universal peace and
liberty, and disregarding private profit to serve the common weal of humanity."</p>
<p>Significant of the national spirit of this people is its manifestation of a magnanimity rare in
the history of nations. If it be true, as Beethoven once said, that forgiveness is the highest
spiritual genius, then has this spiritual genius, like a sacred fire, purged the soul of this people
ofi the enmities of the war. For instance, while the Supreme Council continued its trifling with God
and man, it was Italy that came to the rescue of the Austrians, sending the wheat that kept yet
alive the inhabitants of the capital city of her ancient enemy. It was Italy that greeted the head
of the Austrian Government, in the spring of 192o, not only with hearty welcome, but with sincere
and reverent sympathy. It was Italy, poor as her populations were, that took thousands after
thousands of Austrian children to her homes, to her cities and country-sides, giving these "enemy"
children the same care she gave her own. It was the head of an Italian city who exclaimed : " This
is our revenge, to wipe away the memories of enmity by rendering salvation to our enemies!"</p>
<p>Nor has Italy forgiven only her enemies&mdash; the German, the Austrian, the Croatian, the
Bulgarian, and the Turk: she has done the infinitely harder thing : she has forgiven her Allies-from
whom she in some senses suffered worse than ever she suffered at the hands of her enemies.
Moreover&mdash;and equally extraordinary <pb id="VAC1018-115" n="115"/> &mdash;it is only in Italy
to-day that one hears words of sympathy and understanding for Wilson. In England, one hears
depreciation; in France, one hears a revilement nearly equalling that visited upon this greatest of
Americans, save one, by his countrymen. But in Italy you hear no syllable of bitterness against the
man who stood so stubbornly against her, even unto the exhaustion of her resources. On the
contrary&mdash;and wonderful to know&mdash;you hear the name of Woodrow Wilson coupled with that of
Joseph Mazzini&mdash;surely the highest tribute that an Italian may render to mortal man.</p>
<p>Again, and in accord with the new spirit of the people, the Italian Government, alone among the
Governments participating in the Great War, has fulfilled the promise made by President
kWilson&mdash;and so ostentatiously and repeatedly ratified on British platforms during the days
that were dark&mdash;that the end of the war should also be the end of secret diplomacy. Almost
immediately on coming into power, Signor Giolitti presented to the Italian Chamber a Bill,
consisting of a single clause, which reads as follows : " Treaties and international under-
standings, whatever their subject and their character, are only valid after they have been approved
by Parliament. The Government of the King can only declare war with the approval of the two
Chambers." And Italy alone, since the beginning of the fabled peace-making, has fulfilled her
engagements. For instance, after signing the Treaty of Rapallo, she kept her word
strictly&mdash;this a hostile Serbian diplomat <pb id="VAC1018-116" n="116"/> reluctantly admitted
to the writer. " Since the Peace of Valona," said an Albanian chieftain, " Italy has kept her
promise to us in spirit and in letter ; and now all Albania would fight for Italy, if ever she were
attacked by another Power." " It is Italy alone," said a Turkish Minister, " that has dealt
honourably with us among the Powers, and whose word we have been able to trust during the war and
since." " Italy alone," said a Georgian prince, " has put the new diplomacy into honest practice in
the Near East." And it is Italy alone that still struggles for the realisation of the Wilson
principles in Europe.</p>
<p>Then among the stronger Powers assembled in the General Conference of the League of Nations at
Geneva, November and December, 1920, Italy alone fought for the fulfilment of the promise by which
the League of Nations had been initiated; and without which fulfilment the League is but a
contrivance whereby three Governments may pursue a super-capitalist exploitation of the planet. "
Had Italy been backed by the States that would have liked to back her," wrote Mr. Robert Dell, a
very keen and comprehending observer of the Conference, " things would, perhaps, have been
different. Italian policy throughout the session . . . was towards international reconciliation and
peace. No doubt this attitude was dictated by selfinterest, but at any rate it is enlightened
selfinterest, which is more than can be said of French policy, and it happens to coincide with the
interest of the world at large. If Italy <pb id="VAC1018-117" n="117"/> is now ruled by men with the
sense to see that universal free trade would be to the advantage of Italy, that the continuance of
an imperialist policy will ruin the country, and that Italian interests will not be served by the
annihilation of Germany and Central Europe, so much the better for Italy and everybody else."</p>
<p><hi rend="i"><hi rend="i">Now let it be kept in mind, when the ways whereby Italy has made
herself an evangel of international goodwill be considered, that this attitude has not been induced
by this group or that: it is the attitude which the Government has cultivated in the
people</hi>.</hi> And the significance of this is too tremendous to admit of exaggeration. At a time
when governments are passing into the hands of what might pardonably be called a self-glorified
mediocracy, practising a pseudo-realism or political quackery constituting the crowning ignominy of
a civilisation turning to imposture for salvation, this one people has withstood the abomination. In
contradistinction to this now common sovereignty of imposturous men and methods, Italy is investing
her wisest and best with the powers of government. Premier Giolitti has doubtless made many shifts
in the course of his long career. For all that, he alone, among present administrative heads of
State, discerns the early choice which civilisation must perforce make between regeneration and
dissolution. And his discernment is evidenced by his choice of governmental associates. First beside
him stands Count Sforza, his Foreign Minister, unquestionably the most serious as well as
accomplished <pb id="VAC1018-118" n="118"/> diplomat of Europe&mdash;indeed a true heir of Cavour.
Sforza is economical in his use of words, and austere as to manners. But he is a. practical idealist
of the highest order. When, for instance&mdash;bespeaking the integrity of his own soul and the soul
of Italy as well&mdash; he said that Italy placed the reconciliation of Europe before the indemnity
due from Germany, he spoke with a divinely practical sense rare, in these days, among the councils
of nations. His diplomacy bears the impress of Mazzini's expostulation to Daniel Stern : " Little it
matters to me that Italy, a territory of so many square leagues, eats its corn and cabbages cheaper
; little I care for Rome if a great European initiative is not to issue from it. What I do care for
is that Italy shall be great and good, moral and virtuous, that she comes to fulfil a mission in the
world."</p>
<p>There is, it is true, complaint that Sforza has conceded too much where the claims of Italy were
concerned. But if Italians who complain had been behind the scenes presented by the meetings of the
Supreme Council, they would better appreciate the saving services Sforza has rendered to his
country. They would discern, too, the element of moral tragedy inherent in positions he has been
obliged to take. Italy is not economically independent; and until she is, she cannot be wholly
politically free. Italy's Allies are in a position, economically speaking, to beat her to her knees
at any moment she too forcibly resists their decisions. Sforza has been obliged, time after time, to
compromise <pb id="VAC1018-119" n="119"/> his personal ideals of right and justice for the sake of
saving Italy from manifold disaster. But more than that&mdash;as the future historians will
discover&mdash;Sforza has quite deliberately sacrificed his personal popularity with Italians in
order that he might serve the true interests of Italy.</p>
<p>With Sforza stands the able and upright Bonomi, a statesman of superior wisdom and insight into
the affairs of his country. There is also Benedetto Croce, the greatest among the living of those
who make philosophy their trade. And the services of Minister Meda have been incalculable in
restoring Italian finances to a securer basis. Labriola and Alessio have served highly not only
Italy, but the peoples international, in the construction and advocacy of their Government's
programme of industrial solution; nor is there a man in the Government who is not of high
intellectual mark and moral quality, and who has not the welfare of both Italy and the world at
heart.</p>
<p>Behind these stands the reticent and elusive personality of the King, helping on, so far as a
king set over a democracy may, every good work, every cause of social betterment. And there lives no
better man, no braver soul, no more enlightened ruler, no truer lover of his country and of
humanity, than Victor Emmanuel, King of Italy. If fault must be found with this exemplary man and
ruler, it is that he is too reticent ; that he keeps himself too much in the background; that his
regard for the constitution is over-scrupulous; that he does not use the power and the prerogatives
which <pb id="VAC1018-120" n="120"/> are really and rightly his. " The King is put there for
something," said a devoted and intelligent Italian to the writer, " and there are thousands of us
who wish that he, with his intelligence and courageous goodness, would make himself felt more than
he apparently does; the heart of the people is with him more than he realises, and would respond to
him more than to the politicians if he would lead." Whether the criticism be judicious or not,
whether or not the King does well and wisely to keep himself so far in the background, is not for a
foreign observer to say. Of that only an Italian can speak. But this much is certain, however
overshadowed the King chooses to be, however hid and quiet the currents of his influence, he is all
for a national order that shall provide every Italian with the means and opportunity essential to
the living of a complete life; and he, is all for an inclusive concord and mutual freedom among the
nations &mdash;a freedom and concord creative of that wedded heaven and earth whereof the soul of
Italy ever dreams.</p>
<p>So, all in all, Italy stands to the writer as the citadel, assaulted and mayhap shaken, of
civilisation's last hope. For the conclusive catastrophe comes apace, blindly forced by the very
arrogance, by the precise repressions, wherewith the bearded Interests brutishly think to avert it.
Over the peoples the Interests ride hard, with whips of scorpions scourging them awhile into servile
submission. But if the reason for the world's being fail in its approaching last <pb
id="VAC1018-121" n="121"/> effort ; if it be able to cast no restraining shadow upon the Interests
and their wanton governments ; if the puerilities and putridities pf their parliaments wax worse;
then we may be sure that the servility of the peoples will change not only into savage revolt, but
into universal madness&mdash;into conflagrations consuming our civilisation's innermost core as well
as its outermost forms. Then midst the ruins of the centuries, thorns and thistles will grow, and
hairy human creatures creep; and many bleak years, if not ages, will pass before the rebirth of
history&mdash;before the coming forth of a human race willing to use worthily the infinite natural
and spiritual resources that were always at hand, and always sufficient for the creation of the
earthly paradise.</p>
<p>It is in this most crucial hour of the human ongoing that Italy remembers her historic Idea, and
glimpses therein a worthy escape for her own and the international peoples. And thus is she
repeating her own latter history. Italy came into the war at its most critical moment as the right
flank of the Allies. She saved them. But by these she thus saved, and by the world at large, the
services she rendered: were not appreciated: on the contrary, they, were&mdash;they still
are&mdash;the subject of a depreciation as mischievous as it is malign. And to the future historian
it will be one of the most insearchable curiosities of the war that Italy's claims, so territorially
paltry, of so little economic value, were none the less set forth to the world by interested
enemies-namely, her professed Allies <pb id="VAC1018-122" n="122"/> &mdash;as an imperialism second,
only to that of Prussia in predatory purpose. Italy, in fact, became the victim of a propaganda,
that may be fairly termed hydrophobic. If the proverbial reader from Mars had taken his cue from <hi
rend="i">The Times</hi> or <hi rend="i">The New Europe</hi>, he would naturally have thought that it
was Italy, not Germany, with which the Entente and America were at war. And all this,
notwithstanding that the cost of the war to Italy, when balanced by her resources and gains, greatly
out-proportioned the cost of the war to her Allies. All the more is this true&mdash;and iniquitously
true at that&mdash;when the price Italy paid and the little she received are contrasted with the
enormous appropriations which the Entente Governments have made of territories of continental
proportions, and replete with the sources of an unimaginable future wealth.</p>
<p>And so it is to-day. In a world cleft atwain by a dual reaction&mdash;a world wherein owners and
workers are arming against each other for ;a " fight to the finish "&mdash;Italy stands again in the
breach. The left wing of the reaction, indoctrinated and directed from Moscow, and thus ensouled
with the idea of finding freedom in tyranny-this Italy has already met, and met victoriously: not in
Italy will Bolshevism again lift up its head. But the greater fight&mdash;the fight against the
reaction's right wing-the fight against the repression and government of the peoples by a
super-capitalist despotism-this fight is still on, is indeed but begun. And in this, as in her fight
against the left, it is to <pb id="VAC1018-123" n="123"/> the worthy preservation of civilisation
that Italy devotes her best men, her moral resources. But her Allies no more appreciate what she
does for them to-day than they appreciatedwhat she did for them yesterday. Instead of reverently
helping her to a deliverance which would surely be to all peoples, the Great Powers would thwart her
programme of industrial solution, and with it her policy of international conciliation, in order to
secure the planetary hegemony of the masters they serve: the international money-lenders. Yet if the
masters and their governments were wise, instead of looking upon the Italian initiative with
derision or dread, they would greet it with bended knees of prayer for its realisation.</p>
<p>The heart of the world is still bitter and hounded, the eyes of the peoples are still blinded, by
the treason of the Peace of Versailles. The makers of that Peace have invested mankind with a
scepticism, with a cynicism, for which there is no precedent., Faith in a power that is spiritual;
faith in the practicability of what men commonly account good ; faith in either the sincerity, the
authority, or the executancy of human ideals&mdash;it is this, along with blockaded millions of
women and children, that the peace-makers have monstrously put to death. It is from the graves of
dead faith&mdash;as from the graves of the millions slain through economic war&mdash;that the
peoples turn to the worship of the super-wolf : to sheer and unmoral might as their only law and
saviour. And the shrines of the super-wolf, <pb id="VAC1018-124" n="124"/> newly raised from
primeval human swamps, are attended with like reverence in London and Petrograd, in New York and
Moscow. That the Bolshevist and the super-capitalist are like manifestations of one fundamental
reaction&mdash;of one reaction to armed material might as the sole preservative and procurative
law&mdash;of this the peoples have not yet taken knowledge.</p>
<p>But, even if the apparent triumph lies with Moscow, it is the super-capitalist who thus will
prevail. For, mark it well, it is not the fabled proletarian revolution that will be Moscow's last
word: it is the international financialism that is to-day encoiling the world&mdash;reaching forth
to convert the nations into a single profit-making machine&mdash;it is for this Moscow really,
though all blindly, labours ; and it is this that will be the last word of the Bolshevist autocracy.
It is unto this worst despotism, unto this extinguishing degradation of the human race, and not unto
the proletariat, that the Bolshevist autocracy will render power and dominion. And it is over
against this harshest of historic tyrannies, over against this extinction of whatever of worth our
Christian era has produced, over against this negation of the really human life of man, that the
Roman Government marshals its programme for an industrial solution initiative of a new society. And
this programme, could it be fulfilled, would be but the realisation of the leitmotiv of Italian
history.</p>

<p>I have often spoken, in the course of these chapters, of Joseph Mazzini, who was the heir of
Dante, who was the heir of Virgil. Each <pb id="VAC1018-125" n="125"/> was possessed of the idea of
an immanent but omnipotent empire, centred at Rome, but there&mdash; from effecting a harmonious
organisation of the world, perfect unto the last material detail, unto the last moral and mental
enablement, and every part or people or man marching in step with every other part or people or man.
And the last of the envisioned Triumvirate was at once the most enlightened and most ardent in his
Roman faith. Looking out over the tendencies of his own world, Mazzini foresaw, he in many ways
foretold, the catastrophe that has overtaken 'and engulfed the present world. He foresaw this
catastrophe as the inevitable result of the materialism then becoming the content of both the
policies and the psychology of nations. Nor saw he any prevention of the catastrophe, any redemption
for the nations, any salvation for civilisation, in the movements and doctrines then making headway
in Europe. In International Socialism, which he at first yearningly considered, he soon saw only the
completion of the foreseen catastrophe through the delusion of the world's' workers. By its
materialist foundation and orthodoxy, by its basic principle of the class-war, by its Marxian
concept of the Collectivist Society, Socialism had merely appropriated, he contended, the
fundamental falsities of the capitalist society. To Mazzini, the conception of the worker as a
well-kept cog in the wheels of an international economic machine was blasphemous and intolerable. So
over against the Marxian idea, over against the collectivist tyranny of the Marxian State, he set
<pb id="VAC1018-126" n="126"/> forth a social philosophy derived from Christ and from Dante, and not
distantly akin to the creed of Peter Kropotkin. It was a philosophy predicative of a human order, in
which freedom and association find their perfect fulfilment in each other.</p>
<p>In Mazzini's ideal of society&mdash;a society in which men are both socially united and in-
dividually free&mdash;he saw the realisation of the Third Rome. Indeed, it was by the initiative of
this Third Rome, as well as under its worlded wings, that the nations would sit down together as one
common family, around one common table of universal love. ",Why," he asks, ' should not
Rome&mdash;which has already twice given unity to the world, under the Caesars and under the
Popes&mdash;utter a third Word, of import still more vast, and consequences still more fruitful? Why
should not' the priest, himself a son of the people, elevate the hand that bears the martyr's cross,
and sanctify with his blessing the crusade of the oppressed, in the pilgrimage ordained for them by
God towards liberty, equality, and love? " Nor far from Mazzini's thought were the words of Sforza,
spoken to the members of the Roman Conference to which I have already referred. " Permit me to
consider it," he says, " of happy augury for your labours that you are meeting in the city of Rome,
which prides herself, more than on anything else; on her just claim to be the mother of righteous
law."</p>
<p>I do not ;say that the Italian initiative certainly promises the Third Rome of the prophets. I
say that it at least carries in itself <pb id="VAC1018-127" n="127"/>the portent or possibility of
that Rome. It might well be, indeed, if Italy's programme of industrial solution and her policy of
international reconciliation should together prevail, that thus in Rome would rise, and rise
equipped for divine conquest, that : social sense which alone can vanquish the increasing Great
Curse, and prepare the descent of that society which Saint John and Mazzini alike called the City of
God : that heavenly society, stablished firmly upon the earth, wherein all men might at last enjoy
the abundant life of that freedom, which, as JDante has said, " all upright governments have for
their aim, and which' is the greatest gift bestowed by God on human nature, and through which men
attain to that joy which is as the blessedness of the gods."</p>
<p>It is between Moscow and Rome that Italy and the nations will choose, and choose soon, whether
knowingly or unknowingly. For the choice is between universal dissolution, issuing from universal
despotism, and the path to social salvation, which the Government of Italy has pronounced. If the
super-capitalist intention to defeat the Roman programme succeed, then it is Moscow that will become
the centre of the world: and the unity therefrom proceeding, super-capitalist as it will be in the
end, sterilising as it must the soul of man, will destroy what of creative life still strives
beneath the death now so deep upon the nations. But if Rome be the choice&mdash;if Italy herself
choose first the programme put before her by her present Government ; if she consecratedly achieve
the good issue of her whole adventure in conciliation <pb id="VAC1018-128" n="128"/>; then it is not
too much to hope, then it is not too much to expect, that her brave solution will hence lay
compulsion upon the whole family of nations, bidding them partake of the new <hi rend="i">Pax
Romana</hi> and be healed.</p>
<p>What the end ofItaly's phenomenal errantry will be, either at home within her own borders or
abroad in Europe, I cannot surely foresee. The forces of the Italian revival are not yet organised ;
nor are they yet certain of the way they take ; and it is therefore impossible to predict positively
their ultimate direction. But this I know: that the things for which Giolitti and his associates
stand constitute the sole way of salvation before society. They thus confront Italy, in the most
crucial moment in the history of mankind, with the supreme and crucial moment of her own history.
Through the darkness of to-day and to-morrow, already depthless and altogether uncharted, hers is
now the opportunity and the responsibility of shepherding the nations into the light of that
commonwealth of man which her great voices have all announced. This opportunity and this
responsibility seem like a final effort of God on behalf of the civilisation now existing. And,
indeed, upon the success or failure of Italy's present Government, or of some new Govern-ment that
shall be of the same spirit and shall present the same programme, may impinge the divine decision as
to whether or no our civilisation's continuance be worth while.</p>



</div2>
</div1>
</body>


<back>
<div1 type="colophon">
<head type="supplied">COLOPHON</head>
<p><hi rend="i">Printed in Great Britain by</hi> UNWIN BROTHERS, LIMITED, THE GRESHAM PRESS, WOKING
AND LONDON </p>
</div1>
</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>
