<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//IA Books//DTD TEI for Indiana Authors Books//EN"
                       "teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="VAC2096">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">When fairies were friendly</title>
        <author>Stein, Evaleen, 1863-1923</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded By</resp>
          <!--Update the value of the element below with your name in
                                direct order.-->
          <name>Beth Gucinski</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
        <address>
                    <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
                </address>
        <idno>VAC2096</idno>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>Copyright 2009 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
          <p>Indiana University provides the information contained on this web site for
            non-commercial, personal, or research use only. All other use, including but not limited
            to commercial or scholarly reproductions, redistribution, publication or transmission,
            whether by electronic means or otherwise, without prior written permission of the
            copyright holder is strictly prohibited.</p>
        </availability>
        <!--Update the value of the date element with the year the document
                        is being encoded.-->
        <date>2012</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">When fairies were friendly</title>
            <author id="ina-v1-entry-0815">Stein, Evaleen, 1863-1923</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>6 p. ℓ., 3-190 p. : front., plates ; 20 cm.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The Page Company</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
            <date>1922</date>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The Digital Library Program was awarded a Library Services and Technology Act (LSTA)
          grant in 2005 to make available online the three-volume, reference work, <title>Indiana
            Authors and Their Books</title> along with selected monographs by Indiana authors.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="3">
        <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and has
          been encoded and edited using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
          Guidelines following the TEI Lite standard. Digital page images are linked to the text
          file.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <tagUsage gi="div1">Numbered divs used.</tagUsage>
      </tagsDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language>English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list>
            <item>Fairies</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <!--The revision description tracks significant changes made to the file
                    after completion. This information will remain commented out unless someone has
                    conducted quality assessment of the texts and have made changes to the file as a
                    result.-->
    <!-- <revisionDesc> <change>
                    <date>$Date</date> <respStmt>
                    <name>$Name</name>
                    <resp>$Responsibility</resp>
                    </respStmt> <item>$Changes</item>
                    </change> </revisionDesc> -->
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb id="VAC2096-001" n="[]"/>
      <div1 type="halftitle">
        <head rend="center b">WHEN FAIRIES WERE FRIENDLY</head>
        <p/>
      </div1>
      <pb id="VAC2096-002" n="[]"/>
      <div1 type="advertisement">
        <head rend="center"><hi rend="sc">STORIES BY</hi><lb/> EVALEEN STEIN</head>
        <list type="simple">
          <item><hi rend="left">The Circus Dwarf Stories</hi>
            <hi rend="right">$1.65</hi></item>
          <item><hi rend="left">Children's Stories</hi>
            <hi rend="right">1.65</hi></item>
          <item><hi rend="left">Pepin: A Tale of Twelfth Night</hi>
            <hi rend="right">1.65</hi></item>
          <item><hi rend="left">When Fairies Were Friendly</hi>
            <hi rend="right">1.65</hi></item>
          <item><hi rend="left">Gabriel and the Hour Book </hi>
            <hi rend="right">1.65</hi></item>
          <item><hi rend="left">The Christmas Porringer</hi>
            <hi rend="right">1.65</hi></item>
          <item><hi rend="left">A Little Shepherd of Provence</hi>
            <hi rend="right">1.65</hi></item>
          <item><hi rend="left">The Little Count of Normandy</hi>
            <hi rend="right">1.65</hi></item>
          <item><hi rend="left">Our Little Celtic Cousin of Long Ago</hi>
            <hi rend="right">1.00</hi></item>
          <item><hi rend="left">Our Little Crusader Cousin of Long Ago</hi>
            <hi rend="right">1.00</hi></item>
          <item><hi rend="left">Our Little Frankish Cousin of Long Ago</hi>
            <hi rend="right">1.00</hi></item>
          <item><hi rend="left">Our Little Norman Cousin of Long Ago</hi>
            <hi rend="right">1.00</hi></item>
        </list>
        <p rend="center">L. C. PAGE &amp; COMPANY (Inc.)<lb/> 53 Beacon Street, Boston, Mass.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="VAC2096-003" n="[]"/>
      <pb id="VAC2096-004" n="[]"/>
      <div1 type="frontispiece">
        <head type="supplied">Frontispiece</head>
        <p><figure>
            <p>"VERY BIG AND AWKWARD HE LOOKED KNEELING THERE BEFORE THE LITTLE LADY"</p>
          </figure></p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="VAC2096-005" n="[]"/>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main" rend="b">When Fairies Were Friendly</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>BY<lb/>
          <docAuthor><hi rend="b">Evaleen Stein</hi></docAuthor><lb/> Author of "A Little Shepherd
          of Provence," "Gabriel and the Hour Book," "The Christmas Porringer," "The Little Count of
          Normandy," "Our Little Crusader Cousin of Long Ago," etc.</byline>
        <lb/>
        <byline><hi rend="b">Illustrated by Thelma Gooch</hi></byline>
        <docImprint><publisher><hi rend="b">The Page Company</hi></publisher><lb/>
          <pubPlace><hi rend="b">Boston</hi></pubPlace>
          <docDate><hi rend="b">Mdccccxxii</hi></docDate></docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <pb id="VAC2096-006" n="[]"/>
      <div1 type="verso">
        <head type="supplied">Verso</head>
        <p rend="center"><hi rend="i">Copyright, 1922</hi>,<lb/> B<hi rend="sc">Y</hi> T<hi
            rend="sc">HE</hi> P<hi rend="sc">AGE</hi> C<hi rend="sc">OMPANY</hi></p>
        <p rend="center i">All rights reserved</p>
        <p rend="center">Made in U. S. A.</p>
        <p rend="center">First Impression, September, 1922<lb/> Second Impression, March, 1929</p>
        <p rend="center sc">PRINTED BY C. H. SIMONDS COMPANY<lb/> BOSTON, MASS., U. S. A.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="VAC2096-007" n="[]"/>
      <div1 type="dedication">
        <head type="supplied">Dedication</head>
        <p rend="center">To<lb/> MY MOTHER</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="VAC2096-008" n="[]"/>

      <pb id="VAC2096-009" n="[]"/>
      <div1 type="contents">
        <head rend="center b">Contents</head>
        <list type="ordered" rend="upper-roman">
          <item><hi rend="left">T<hi rend="sc">HE</hi> B<hi rend="sc">ABE IN THE</hi> M<hi rend="sc"
                >ANGER</hi></hi>
            <hi rend="right">3</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC2096-015"/></item>
          <item><hi rend="left">O<hi rend="sc">LAF AND</hi> A<hi rend="sc">STRID'S</hi> C<hi
                rend="sc">HRISTMAS</hi> E<hi rend="sc">VE</hi></hi>
            <hi rend="right">37</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC2096-049"/></item>
          <item><hi rend="left">H<hi rend="sc">OW</hi> N<hi rend="sc">IAL</hi> W<hi rend="sc">ON
                THE</hi> B<hi rend="sc">EAUTIFUL</hi> P<hi rend="sc">RINCESS</hi></hi>
            <hi rend="right">61</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC2096-075"/></item>
          <item><hi rend="left">T<hi rend="sc">HE</hi> W<hi rend="sc">ISHING</hi>-S<hi rend="sc"
                >PRING</hi></hi>
            <hi rend="right">107</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC2096-123"/></item>
          <item><hi rend="left">T<hi rend="sc">HE</hi> G<hi rend="sc">OOD</hi> Y<hi rend="sc"
                >EAR</hi></hi>
            <hi rend="right">133</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC2096-151"/></item>
        </list>
      </div1>
      <pb id="VAC2096-010" n="[]"/>

      <pb id="VAC2096-011" n="[]"/>
      <div1 type="figures">
        <head rend="center b">List of Illustrations</head>
        <list type="simple">
          <item><hi rend="left">"V<hi rend="sc">ERY BIG AND AWKWARD HE LOOKED KNEELING THERE BEFORE
                THE LITTLE LADY</hi>" (<hi rend="i">see page 86</hi>)</hi>
            <hi rend="right i">Frontispiece</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC2096-004"/></item>
          <item><hi rend="left">"T<hi rend="sc">HE CHILDREN CREPT OUT A LITTLE WAY FROM BENEATH ITS
                BOUGHS</hi>"</hi>
            <hi rend="right">50</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC2096-063"/></item>
          <item><hi rend="left">"A<hi rend="sc">S SOON AS HE SAID OVER THE CHARM WORDS THE</hi> Q<hi
                rend="sc">UEEN HAD TAUGHT HIM, BACK THEY CAME</hi>"</hi>
            <hi rend="right">93</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC2096-107"/></item>
          <item><hi rend="left">"'L<hi rend="sc">OOK</hi>! L<hi rend="sc">OOK</hi>!' <hi rend="sc"
                >CRIED</hi> B<hi rend="sc">IDDY</hi>. 'T<hi rend="sc">HERE IS ONE OF THE LITTLE
                PEOPLE NOW</hi>!'"</hi>
            <hi rend="right">116</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC2096-133"/></item>
          <item><hi rend="left">"'T<hi rend="sc">HE LITTLE</hi> N<hi rend="sc">EW</hi> Y<hi
                rend="sc">EAR LAY ROCKING IN HIS CRADLE UP IN THE SKY</hi>'"</hi>
            <hi rend="right">136</hi><ptr targType="pb" target="VAC2096-155"/></item>
        </list>
      </div1>
      <pb id="VAC2096-012" n="[]"/>
      <pb id="VAC2096-013" n="[1]"/>
      <pb id="VAC2096-014" n="[2]"/>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb id="VAC2096-015" n="3"/>
      <div1 type="book">
        <head rend="center b">When Fairies Were Friendly</head>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head rend="center">THE BABE IN THE MANGER</head>
          <p><hi rend="b">O</hi>VER an old city of Europe&mdash;never mind which&mdash;the
            Christmas-eve stars were twinkling faintly as the north wind drove the gathering clouds
            across the sky. Soon the snow began to fall, drifting whitely over the steep brown roofs
            of the ancient houses and covering the cobble-stones of the winding streets with a soft
            fleece. In the <pb id="VAC2096-016" n="4"/> midst of the city rose a great cathedral,
            where the shining flakes touched lightly the stone fruits and flowers wreathing the
            beautiful portal, and tufted the wings of the marble angels carved above it till they
            seemed all plumed and feathery for flight.</p>
          <p>Within the gray walls, here and there before some shrine, a few worshippers knelt; or a
            tall candle shone with a twinkling flame, as if the stars, blotted out of the sky, were
            coming down to shine on earth. But though these little, golden flames lighted a small
            space about them, the echoing aisles and high vaulted roof were still dim and shadowy,
            for it was not yet time for the <pb id="VAC2096-017" n="5"/> midnight mass when hundreds
            more of the tall white candles would blaze out in honor of the Christ-child's
            birthday.</p>
          <p>Indeed, everything was ready and waiting for the holy hour. Green Christmas garlands
            wound the fluted pillars and decked the walls between the lovely stained windows, and
            twined about the altar where a wonderful little scene,&mdash;or "creche," as it was
            called,&mdash;had been made in memory of the place in Bethlehem where the little Jesus
            was born. There at the back were the stalls where one might see the heads of the ox and
            the ass, carved from wood and painted to resemble life; while directly in front was the
            manger <pb id="VAC2096-018" n="6"/> lined, like a pretty nest, with soft hay and golden
            straw, and in it lay the image of the blessed Christ-child, wrapped in swaddling clothes
            of white linen and with a halo of pure gold about his soft curls. At the head of the
            manger was a waxen figure of Mother Mary in a robe of heavenly blue, her hands clasped
            and her sweet eyes gazing lovingly into the face of her little Son. Near her stood Saint
            Joseph, and in front of the manger knelt the shepherds who had come to worship the
            newborn Babe, their crooks in their hands and their shaggy brown cloaks looking very
            rough beside the splendid mantles of the three wise kings. These were kneeling also, the
            aged <pb id="VAC2096-019" n="7"/> Gaspar, with his long silvery beard, Melchior, strong
            and thoughtful, and Balthazzar, young and handsome, all sparkling with jewels and cloth
            of gold. Their heads were bare, for their precious crowns lay before the manger of the
            little Jesus, to whom they offered also their gifts of gold and frankincense and myrrh.
            Over all hung a golden star which would shine and sparkle when the many tall candles
            were lighted, and round about hovered waxen angels in robes of purest white.</p>
          <p>Everything was very still and beautiful, ready for the coming of the holy midnight. The
            star waited to twinkle, the candles to flash into golden flame, the white-robed <pb
              id="VAC2096-020" n="8"/> angels seemed impatient to break into joyous song, and the
            shepherds and kings to bow lower still before the little Jesus. And high up in the
            cathedral tower the chime of bells waited also to ring out their gold and silver
            notes.</p>
          <p>While all these things were thus hushed expectantly, now and again some worshipper
            entered through the beautiful open portal; and presently, all alone, there slipped in a
            little girl. A ragged shawl partly covered her head and her thin little figure, and she
            clasped in her arms a bundle wrapped in a tattered quilt. If you had lifted the corner
            of this, you would have seen the wan face of a baby, its tiny cheeks pale and <pb
              id="VAC2096-021" n="9"/> sunken and its little lips blue with cold; for both shawl and
            quilt were thickly powdered with snowflakes.</p>
          <p>The little girl looked timidly about her, and then slowly drawing near the altar where
            stood the creche, sank down on the stone floor to rest.</p>
          <p>Who was she, and where did she come from? Listen, and I will tell you. She was called
            Margot; I do not know her other name, but that does not matter. In the poorest part of
            the city was the little hovel that had been her home. Her father had been dead since
            early summer, and for more than a week now her mother had been lying ill with a burning
            fever, so that she did not <pb id="VAC2096-022" n="10"/> know how cold was their one
            room. Margot had been forced to use almost the last bit of firewood to keep herself and
            little brother from freezing in the bitter cold. Nor did the poor mother know that only
            a crust of bread and a few drops of milk were left in the bare cupboard. Her eyes were
            very bright and her cheeks flushed, but that was because of the fever which made her
            talk at times so strangely that Margot was frightened; but at last, on Christmas eve,
            she had come to herself for a little while, though so pale and weak she could scarcely
            call the little girl to her bedside.</p>
          <p>When the child came to her, she whispered faintly, stopping often to <pb
              id="VAC2096-023" n="11"/> gather her fluttering breath, that she was going to their
            father, and that Margot must take little brother and seek out the God's House for
            children; for so was called the home where poor orphans were cared for in the old city.
            Then the mother's eyes closed and she lay so white and still that Margot knew it was
            useless to try to waken her; for thus her father had lain, and all her tears had not
            aroused him.</p>
          <p>Nevertheless, bending over the still face on the pillow, poor little Margot began to
            cry bitterly. But she was a brave child and, sad and forlorn though she was, soon she
            tried to dry her tears and to obey her mother's last words. In truth, she <pb
              id="VAC2096-024" n="12"/> knew she must find help somewhere, for there were only gray
            ashes on the hearth and no longer was there even a crust on the cupboard shelf. So
            wrapping little brother in the old quilt, she took him in her arms, and putting the
            ragged shawl around her she tried to cover them both in its scanty folds. Then for the
            last time kissing her mother's cold forehead she set out to find the children's God's
            House. Why did not their neighbors help? Well, that was because all those dwelling in
            that part of the city were almost as poor and miserable as the family of Margot, and
            child though she was, she shrank from asking aid from them.</p>
          <p>So, shivering and sorrowful, she <pb id="VAC2096-025" n="13"/> had stumbled out into
            the darkness while the black clouds were driving across the sky and the snow beginning
            to fall. On and on the little girl wandered, for soon she lost her way. Colder and
            wearier and weaker she grew with every step; and though poor little brother lay very
            quietly, his eyes closed in a kind of stupor from cold and hunger, his thin, tiny body
            seemed a leaden weight in her tired arms. At last, when almost ready to faint, she had
            come to the cathedral, and seeing the open door and the lights within, had slipped in,
            as I have told you; and there she was, sunk on the floor before the altar.</p>
          <p>Presently, when she had rested a <pb id="VAC2096-026" n="14"/> little, she lifted her
            eyes to the wonderful creche. Though only the few candles lighted it, the more she
            stared at it the more wonderful it seemed to her. She had never before been in the
            cathedral in the evening; and while at the few Christmas times she could remember, once
            or twice she had seen the creche by day, never had she ventured so close to it. Perhaps
            it was the dim light that had made her dare to do so now. As she looked long and
            intently at the worshipping figures clustering around the little Jesus, slowly Margot's
            dark eyes grew deeper and dreamier, and her face filled with a strange light. More and
            more real it all became to her; Mother Mary, <pb id="VAC2096-027" n="15"/> with her
            sweet loving face, seemed to breathe and smile, and so also did the white-winged angels;
            even the three kings, in their splendid mantles and gold and jewels, did not over-awe
            her, but everyone seemed so beautiful and kind and gentle. Then her gaze rested on the
            manger in the midst of all. From her place on the floor she could not see the
            Christ-child as he lay within it, but only the rim of his golden halo that shone amid
            the soft hay that brimmed around him as he nestled there.</p>
          <p>Just then little brother slipped from her knees to the stone floor. As she stooped and
            gathered him in her arms and his tiny cold <pb id="VAC2096-028" n="16"/> hands lay
            against her own, a thought came to her, filling her eyes still deeper with dreams. "Oh,"
            she said to herself, "if only I could tuck him in the manger of the little
            Jesus,&mdash;it is so soft and warm,&mdash;surely, surely the dear Christ-child would
            not be angry,&mdash;the manger has plenty of room, and little brother is so small!" The
            more she gazed at the overflowing hay, the more she wished that he might lie there, if
            only for a little while till he grew warm and she could rest; the stone floor was so
            cold, and her arms were so tired. Surely, she thought, Mother Mary would not forbid her,
            she looked so loving and compassionate; and the white-winged <pb id="VAC2096-029" n="17"
            /> angels, had they not all come down from the sky? So perhaps they would pity little
            brother and would take him with them when they flew back to heaven where everything was
            bright and happy.</p>
          <p>Now, at any other time, Margot would never have dared to think of anything so bold as
            laying poor ragged little brother near the blessed Christ-child. But everything seemed
            so strange and wonderful as she knelt there,&mdash;perhaps it was the holy night,
            perhaps it was the little Lord Jesus himself who whispered to her,&mdash;well, never
            mind what it was. But presently, scarcely knowing what she did, and moving as one in a
            dream, Margot rose to her feet, <pb id="VAC2096-030" n="18"/> and lifting little brother
            in her arms, slipped softly up the steps of the altar, gliding past the kneeling kings
            and the shepherds, past Mother Mary and Saint Joseph, till she stood before the stalls
            where the ox and the ass seemed to watch her with wondering eyes. Then, stooping over
            the manger, swiftly she laid little brother, still wrapped in his tattered quilt, at the
            feet of the Christ-child shining in his snowy white linen and his golden halo. Pausing
            only to tuck some soft wisps of hay over the quilt, she moved quickly and silently back
            to her place on the floor; and there, the last bit of strength leaving her, she drew her
            shawl about her and sank into a <pb id="VAC2096-031" n="19"/> heavy sleep, such as comes
            to those who are too weak and weary to bear more.</p>
          <p>It seemed strange that no one had seen what Margot had done; but, as you know, the
            light was still dim and the worshippers at the different shrines were all kneeling with
            heads bowed in prayer. So they did not guess that little brother, who had never known a
            cradle of his own, was tucked there in the warm hay of the holy manger; while overhead
            still the golden star waited to twinkle, and round about, the candles to flame into
            radiant light, the angels to sing their glad songs, and the wise kings and the shepherds
            to bow lower still before the little <pb id="VAC2096-032" n="20"/> Jesus. And still, up
            in the gray old tower, the bells were fairly quivering with the gold and silver notes
            they would by and by chime forth. Nor had they long now to wait, for the midnight was
            drawing near.</p>
          <p>Soon came a troop of altar boys in white tunics and collars of lace and crimson velvet,
            and, stepping quickly from candle to candle, tipped them with shining flame till the
            shadowy cathedral blazed into golden light and the star over the manger glittered with a
            dazzling brightness. By this time the aisles were filled with a throng of people, who
            crossed themselves reverently, while on the altar the ox and the ass, the shepherds, the
            wise kings and <pb id="VAC2096-033" n="21"/> the angels seemed listening breathlessly as
            suddenly the bells pealed forth their joyous message that the Christmas morning had
            begun. And then, while strains of sweet music came thrilling through the air, with a
            sound of solemn chanting the midnight service began.</p>
          <p>Very stately, and almost as splendid as the three wise kings, looked the white-haired
            bishop, who led the chant, as he stood clad in his beautiful Christmas vestments richly
            embroidered with jewels and golden thread; and the two young priests beside him, though
            their robes were not so wonderful as his own, were none the less shining with white and
            gold in honor of the blessed <pb id="VAC2096-034" n="22"/> birthday. Round them all rose
            clouds of fragrant incense as sparkling censers were swung to and fro;&mdash;and still
            no one knew of little brother lying in the holy manger, nor noticed Margot, whom the
            music had roused from her sleep and who knelt now in the shadow of the altar steps,
            gazing with fascinated eyes at the creche.</p>
          <p>As she watched the candles and the star, shining and twinkling, and listened to the
            glorious music, her pale, pinched little face grew lovely with happiness; so sure she
            was that her dream was true, that all was real; that it was indeed a bit of heaven
            itself up there on the altar, and that the little Jesus, Mother <pb id="VAC2096-035"
              n="23"/> Mary, and the hovering angels would somehow take away all her troubles. As
            for little brother lying there at the feet of the Christ-child, at first he had been too
            cold and wretched to stir. But, by and by, the soft hay warmed his numb little body, and
            then, when the lights blazed out, slowly he opened his eyes, and oh! if you could have
            seen the wonder in them! He stared at the golden candle flames and the twinkling star in
            amazed delight, stared and stared, as if he would never leave off looking. Then at last
            his gaze fell on Mother Mary bending over the manger with her sweet face and her loving
            smile, and little brother, struggling feebly, <pb id="VAC2096-036" n="24"/> freed his
            tiny arms from the covering quilt and reached them toward her with a little cry of
            gladness. But no one heard it, for at that moment a wave of music filled the air, quite
            drowning his baby voice.</p>
          <p>So the service went on, till presently the last song was finished, and softly and
            slowly the joyous music trembled into silence. But the glad notes had scarcely died away
            and the worshippers had not yet risen to their feet, when suddenly little brother, who
            had reached his tiny hands in vain to Mother Mary, gave a shrill wail of despair. At
            first those farthest back in the cathedral paid no heed, thinking only that some mother,
            who had no one with <pb id="VAC2096-037" n="25"/> whom to leave it, had brought her
            little one with her to the midnight mass. But those nearer the altar heard with
            surprise, for the cry sounded&mdash;but no, they thought, it could not possibly come
            from the <hi rend="i">manger</hi>!</p>
          <p>But <hi rend="i">hark</hi>! Again it rose, the shrill cry of a baby, and there could no
            longer be any doubt that it was indeed the holy manger from which it came.</p>
          <p>At once a great thrill of wonder swept through the cathedral. Some of the kneeling
            throng bowed their heads still lower in prayer, while others sprang to their feet crying
            out, "<hi rend="i">A miracle! A miracle! The holy Babe lives again on earth</hi>!" <pb
              id="VAC2096-038" n="26"/> For they could think of nothing but that the image of the
            Christ-child, with his pretty curls and his golden halo, had come to life as it lay
            there in the hay.</p>
          <p>But their cries were quickly hushed when they saw the look of horror and amazement on
            the face of one of the priests, who had hurried to the manger and was now bending over
            it. He was young and full of zeal for his faith. No doubt he became gentler as he grew
            older and saw more of the suffering of the world, but just then it seemed to him a
            dreadful and deadly sin that anyone should have dared to lay so ragged and miserable a
            waif as little brother in the manger of the blessed <pb id="VAC2096-039" n="27"/> Jesus!
            At first he could not speak for horror; then slowly lifting from the nest of hay the
            forlorn little bundle, as if the poor wailing baby were an unholy thing, he held it at
            arm's length, taking care that it's rags did not touch his own shining garments. And
            then, looking accusingly around, he asked, in a loud, harsh voice, "<hi rend="i">Who has
              dared to do this impious thing?</hi>"</p>
          <p>At his look and his words the happy dream that had laid its spell upon little Margot
            was broken and fled away; and starting with fright, she could only gasp for breath. She
            felt now that she had been guilty of a dreadful sin, and she did not know what
            punishment she would <pb id="VAC2096-040" n="28"/> receive. She was afraid; but then
            there was little brother who was not to blame and who might be punished instead, if they
            did not know; so, for his sake, she resolved to speak, for I have told you she was a
            brave child. Gathering together all her courage, "O reverend father," she said faintly,
            "It is only little brother. I laid him in the manger because he was so cold. It was just
            for a little while!" she added pleadingly.</p>
          <p>On hearing this, the priest looked sternly at her. "Wicked girl," he said, "have you no
            parents to teach you reverence for sacred things?"</p>
          <p>Poor Margot shook her head, and then bursting into terrified sobbing, <pb
              id="VAC2096-041" n="29"/> she reached out her arms, crying piteously, "O sir, give him
            to me, and I will go and find the children's God's House! I had lost the way."</p>
          <p>The priest was about to hand little brother to her, perhaps glad thus to be rid of him,
            when suddenly the white-haired bishop, who had been listening to every word, stepped
            between.</p>
          <p>Looking down at Margot with pitying eyes, "There, little one," he said gently, "dry
            your tears, and do not go away." Then, turning to the young priest, he held up a warning
            finger. "Have a care, my son! Have you forgotten the words of our Master concerning such
            as <pb id="VAC2096-042" n="30"/> these?" And he looked meaningly at the two forlorn
            waifs. "Give the child to me!" he commanded, holding out his hands.</p>
          <p>Bewildered and shame-faced, the young priest obeyed; and had poor little brother been
            in very truth the living Christ-child himself, the good bishop could not have received
            him more tenderly or more reverently. Closely he pressed him to his breast, quite
            heedless that the tattered quilt lay against his beautiful white robe with its sparking
            jewels and embroidery of golden thread. And as he felt the gentle arms about him, little
            brother, his eyes still full of tears, stopped crying and smiled up into the eyes of the
            bishop, which&mdash; <pb id="VAC2096-043" n="31"/> would you believe it?&mdash;were
            filled with shining tears also.</p>
          <p>And then the good bishop stood up very straight and tall beside the manger, and oh, it
            was wonderful to see him, as, still clasping little brother close to his heart, he
            lifted his right hand! When he did that, over the throng of people, who had been
            watching and listening in silent amazement, there fell such a hush that I think you
            could almost have heard the snowflakes falling softly without. And then he spoke. His
            voice was not loud, but as clear and sweet and trembling with golden and silvery notes
            as the Christmas bells up in the tower; and, like them, it seemed to fill every <pb
              id="VAC2096-044" n="32"/> shadowy nook of the gray old cathedral. "My children," he
            said to the people, "when the dear Christ-child, whose image lies in this manger, grew
            to be a man and walked on earth, you know He loved nothing so much as to have the little
            ones clustering about His feet; and you remember how often and how tenderly He held them
            in His arms." And then very simply, neither adding nor taking away a single syllable, he
            repeated the beautiful words which our Lord Jesus spoke concerning little children. That
            was all.</p>
          <p>When he ended, there was a moment's pause, but only a moment, so the people might be
            quite sure he <pb id="VAC2096-045" n="33"/> had finished; and then more than one, moved
            with compassion for the poor waifs, began to press forward. But hurrying swiftly ahead
            of all came a beautiful woman. Flinging back her furred mantle, she knelt before the
            altar and lifting up her arms imploringly to the bishop, "Reverend father," she said,
            "give me the little ones, and they shall be to me as my own children!" And a kindly
            faced man, who had followed her, knelt beside her, saying, "My lord bishop, as my wife
            says, even so they shall be to me."</p>
          <p>The good bishop looked into the woman's face, as sweet and tender as the face of Mother
            Mary bending over the manger.</p>
          <pb id="VAC2096-046" n="34"/>
          <p>"Daughter," he said, smiling gently, "the good God has chosen, and it is not for me to
            deny His choice." Then solemnly blessing them all, he laid little brother against the
            wife's breast, while the husband lifted in his strong arms little Margot, into whose
            eyes the dream of heaven had returned, brighter and more lovely than before.</p>
          <p>The people stood back for them, and thus they moved down the long aisle; and as they
            passed through the beautiful portal, the marble angels overhead seemed to flutter their
            white-plumed wings and watch them happily as they went out into the Christmas
            morning.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="VAC2096-047" n="[35]"/>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head rend="center">OLAF AND ASTRID'S CHRISTMAS EVE</head>
          <pb id="VAC2096-048" n="[36]"/>
          <pb id="VAC2096-049" n="37"/>
          <p rend="center sc">OLAF AND ASTRID'S CHRISTMAS EVE</p>
          <p><hi rend="b">O</hi>NCE upon a time, in a small village in a far-away country, lived a
            little brother and sister, named Olaf and Astrid. Most of the village folk had
            comfortable cottages, with thatched roofs and cozy chimney corners; but the home of Olaf
            and Astrid was only a tumble-down hut by the edge of the road; for they were very poor.
            Their father was dead, and their mother, who was not strong, was obliged to toil all day
            long to keep them in bread; and it was only hard, black <pb id="VAC2096-050" n="38"/>
            bread at that. All day long&mdash;stitch, stitch, stitch&mdash;she sewed at the work
            brought to her by her more well-to-do neighbors; and while she toiled, the children, who
            were bright, cheerful little souls, did their best to help. Every day Astrid tidied up
            the hut, while Olaf would trudge off to the near-by forest to gather faggots to burn;
            and it meant many weary loads for the little boy; for it was near Christmas time, and
            the winter was very cold. Nevertheless, though the wind whistled through the crevices of
            the hut, they managed always to keep a bit of fire on the hearth, and they did not
            complain if their bread was scanty and their fingers often numb with frost.</p>
          <pb id="VAC2096-051" n="39"/>
          <p>When the day before Christmas came, Olaf and Astrid went out with the village folk to
            the forest to gather the ground-pine and juniper berries which everybody liked to twine
            into pretty, green garlands to brighten their homes and make gay their windows against
            the time for lighting the Christmas candles. For you know that when, on the blessed
            Christmas-eve, the dear Christ-child comes down from heaven and softly treads the earth
            again, it pleases him to have those who love him set candles in their windows to cheer
            and guide him on his way.</p>
          <p>As now the merry folk strayed through the forest, looking for the <pb id="VAC2096-052"
              n="40"/> pine and juniper, there was much happy chatter of the beautiful Christmas
            trees trimmed and waiting for the morrow and of all the holiday goodies being made ready
            for the great day. Poor little Olaf and Astrid listened in silence, as they filled their
            arms with the trailing greens; but they thought that, even though they had neither tree
            nor sweetmeats, at least they could garland their window and set a light for the
            Christ-child.</p>
          <p>But, alas, when dusk fell, and from the village windows one by one the tall wax
            candles&mdash;kept for the blessed night&mdash;began to twinkle, the poor children
            looked in vain for something to light. All they could <pb id="VAC2096-053" n="41"/> find
            was the half-burned end of a tallow candle&mdash;the last in the house. The mother
            sighed; but, "Never mind," she said, "set it in the window. At least it will show the
            dear Christ-child that we love him."</p>
          <p>"And perhaps it will light him a few steps on his way," said Astrid.</p>
          <p>"Yes," said Olaf, "and if he comes on the road through the forest, ours will be the
            first light he will see! Do you think he will come that way, mother?"</p>
          <p>"I cannot tell, my child," answered the mother, as, gathering up her work, she drew her
            chair near the window. She had many stitches to take before it was finished, and must
            sew as long as possible by the <pb id="VAC2096-054" n="42"/> Christ-child's light; for
            she had no other. The wind blew in around the chinks of the window, and made the candle
            flame leap and flicker; but she drew her threadbare shawl closer about her shoulders and
            bravely stitched on.</p>
          <p>Meantime the children had gone to the tiny bedroom, as she had bidden them; but, as
            they lay on their straw bed, they were not asleep. They were whispering together about
            how wonderful it was that the Christ-child should come down to earth for that one night;
            and, "Oh," cried Astrid, "how I wish we could see him!"</p>
          <p>Olaf thought a moment, and then said, "I believe we could if we tried."</p>
          <pb id="VAC2096-055" n="43"/>
          <p>"But how?" said Astrid. "You know last year we watched, but the snow blew against the
            window pane, so nothing was to be seen!"</p>
          <p>"Well," replied Olaf, "if we walked out in the road, perhaps we could see him; and, if
            he reaches the village from this side, it might be we would meet him as he comes out of
            the forest."</p>
          <p>Astrid drew a long breath. "But&mdash;but&mdash;," she said, "do you think mother will
            let us?"</p>
          <p>"We can ask her," answered Olaf. "But we will get ready first." For Olaf, being a boy,
            was bolder than Astrid and always took the lead.</p>
          <p>Hurriedly they sprang out of bed and eagerly dressed themselves in <pb id="VAC2096-056"
              n="44"/> their carefully patched little garments, put on their thin stockings and worn
            little shoes, and then went into the other room. But their poor, tired mother was
            sitting motionless by the window. The work had fallen from her numb fingers, and, her
            head drooped on her breast, she slept in spite of herself.</p>
          <p>As the children stood irresolute, "Poor mother!" they whispered. "We will not waken
            her. We will not be gone long. Surely the Christ-child will soon be coming, and we shall
            be back before she misses us."</p>
          <p>Then quietly they opened the door, and closing it softly behind them, stepped out into
            the night. <pb id="VAC2096-057" n="45"/> They looked anxiously down the long village
            street, and, though the snow was falling, here and there they caught the twinkle of the
            wax candles; but no Christ-child could they see. Then they turned and looked toward the
            dark road beyond the village; for their hut stood on its outskirts.</p>
          <p>"Somehow," said Olaf, "it seems to me that he will come through the forest and down
            this road to the village. Let us walk along it a little way, and maybe we shall meet
            him."</p>
          <p>Astrid shivered a little, but she did not want Olaf to think her a coward; so, putting
            her hand in his, she trudged along beside him. Soon the wind, which had been <pb
              id="VAC2096-058" n="46"/> blowing in fitful gusts, rose to a fierce gale, whirling the
            heavy snow in their faces and chilling them with bitter cold. As they tried vainly to
            make their way against the cruel blast, at last Astrid began to sob. "Oh, Olaf," she
            cried, "let us go back!"</p>
          <p>By this time Olaf, too, was quite willing to turn back; but where? The blinding snow
            hid all the twinkling candles from sight, and everywhere it was very dark. They had no
            idea where their own little hut stood, for they had quite lost their way. On and on they
            stumbled, every moment their little bodies growing colder and colder in the piercing
            wind. By and by they <pb id="VAC2096-059" n="47"/> found themselves in the great forest,
            and now and again, as they tried to feel for some path, they would bruise their little
            hands against the icy trunks of the giant trees.</p>
          <p>All the while the bitter cold was creeping closer and closer around their hearts and
            the chill white flakes falling faster and faster as they wandered on, till at last, in
            despair, they were about to sink down in a snowdrift to die. But just as they had given
            up all hope, suddenly a low, murmuring voice reached their ears. It was like the soft
            whispering of pine boughs in summer, only clearer and plainer, and it came from a young
            fir tree growing near by. "Come hither, little ones," it <pb id="VAC2096-060" n="48"/>
            murmured, "and nestle under my boughs! I will shelter you."</p>
          <p>Tremblingly the shivering children groped their way toward the friendly voice, and,
            sinking down in the snow, crept beneath the fir branches, which, as it was a young tree,
            grew very near the ground. Immediately the soft green boughs seemed to close about and
            caress them. The icy chill thawed from around their hearts and the warm blood tingled to
            their finger-tips.</p>
          <p>Before long the fir boughs began murmuring and whispering again, as if they had
            something wonderful to tell; but as neither Olaf nor Astrid could quite understand them,
            presently their eyes began to blink as <pb id="VAC2096-061" n="49"/> they nestled in
            their cozy little shelter. Perhaps they slept a little; but soon they sat up very wide
            awake, for the most marvelous white light was beginning to stream through the rustling
            branches.</p>
          <p>"Can it be the moon?" whispered Astrid. Olaf peered from out their shelter; but, though
            the snow had ceased to fall, he could see no moon,&mdash;only the bleak, cloudy sky.</p>
          <p>Yet brighter and brighter grew the strange white light. It was like the whiteness of
            thousands of Easter lilies, flooding the fir tree with a dazzling radiance. And all at
            once the children were overwhelmed with happiness; they did not know why, but their
            little hearts <pb id="VAC2096-062" n="50"/> seemed fairly bursting with joy. Never in
            all their lives had they felt so glad. The fir tree, too, seemed filled with joy; for
            its soft whispering had changed to a flute-like, silvery singing, high and sweet and
            thrilling with gladness, and all its little icy cones were clapping together with a
            tinkling music.</p>
          <p>Wonder-struck, the children crept out a little way from beneath its boughs, so they
            could look up at it; for the most marvelous things were happening. As the lovely white
            light poured over it, they saw that the snow on its topmost branches had turned into a
            glittering golden star; all the filmy threads of hoar-frost which had covered it became
              <pb id="VAC2096-063" n="[]"/><figure>
              <p>"THE CHILDREN CREPT OUT A LITTLE WAY FROM BENEATH ITS BOUGHS"</p>
            </figure><pb id="VAC2096-064" n="[]"/>
            <pb id="VAC2096-065" n="51"/> shimmering silver and gold cobwebs; while, as they looked,
            they could see all the little icy cones swelling&mdash;some into pink-cheeked apples of
            sugar, others into gilded nuts or cornucopias of sugar-plums. And then all the feathery
            green boughs broke into the strangest blossoming. Suddenly they were hung with the
            gayest and most bewitching playthings.</p>
          <p>As Olaf and Astrid gazed at the marvelous tree, more beautiful than anything they had
            ever dreamed of, with little cries of delight they reached out their arms toward it, as
            if they would hug it to their breasts, though they did not venture to touch it. But,
            even as they stretched out <pb id="VAC2096-066" n="52"/> their arms, they felt them
            filled with the wonderful sweetmeats and playthings. As they sank back with joyous sighs
            of content, slowly the white radiance began to pale&mdash;and pale; and then a great
            drowsiness came upon the children, and, still clasping their treasures close to their
            hearts, they crept back beneath the fir boughs and fell asleep.</p>
          <lb/>
          <p>At daybreak there came a tinkle of sleigh-bells through the forest; for a traveler from
            a distant village was on the road early. As he drove along between the great pines and
            hemlocks, all at once he noticed the young fir tree. Not that there was anything strange
            about it, as it stood <pb id="VAC2096-067" n="53"/> green and feathery, laden only with
            little drifts of snow; but under its boughs there was a bright gleam of scarlet.</p>
          <p>The traveler stopped his sleigh, and, going to the spot, what should he see but Olaf
            and Astrid still sound asleep! They were dressed in little red coats with shining
            buttons, and warm caps and mittens. On Olaf's feet were red-topped boots, such as he had
            long wished for, and Astrid wore pretty little shoes of scarlet leather. The pockets of
            their coats were stuffed with sugar-plums and sweetmeats, and the children were still
            hugging their wonderful toys.</p>
          <p>The traveler looked at them in utter amazement. At first he <pb id="VAC2096-068" n="54"
            /> thought they must be frozen, lying there in the bitter cold. But, as he stooped to
            lift them from the snow, they opened happy eyes and smiled at him. "How now!" he
            exclaimed in astonishment. "Who are you, and how came you here?"</p>
          <p>"Please, sir," said Olaf, gathering his wits together, "we are Olaf and Astrid, and we
            came out to see the Christ-child." Here he caught sight of all his new finery, and was
            dumb with surprise. So, too, was Astrid, who was so bewildered that she could answer no
            more questions. The traveler decided they were children from the village who must have
            strayed from home, and he was about to lift them into the sleigh <pb id="VAC2096-069"
              n="55"/> when suddenly he paused; for he had noticed something in the snow where a
            drift had left it smooth. "Where," he asked Olaf, "is the <hi rend="i">other</hi> child
            who was with you?"</p>
          <p>"There was no one but Astrid, sir," answered Olaf.</p>
          <p>"But look!" said the traveler sharply. "There must have been another; for here in the
            snow are the prints of little bare feet!"</p>
          <p>But, even as they stared at these, tiny white flames seemed to play over them, melting
            the snow; and where every footprint had been there sprang up a tuft of violets. At this
            the traveler uncovered his head and knelt in the snow beside them.</p>
          <pb id="VAC2096-070" n="56"/>
          <p>When he rose to his feet, he said no more, but, placing the children in the sleigh,
            drove to the village; and when Olaf pointed out their hut, he took them to the door and
            softly opened it. The mother, still sitting by the window, started from her sleep; for
            so weary had she been that all night long she had not wakened. The candle had burned to
            its socket, and the faggots on the hearth were only a heap of ashes; but, in spite of
            the wintry cold, the room was warm and pleasant, and the work, which had fallen from her
            tired fingers, lay finished and folded in her lap.</p>
          <p>The traveler went on to the village inn for his Christmas breakfast; and, <pb
              id="VAC2096-071" n="57"/> when he told the strange things he had seen, the news
            quickly flew from mouth to mouth, and soon all the villagers were flocking to the little
            hut. There, when they saw Olaf's and Astrid's wonderful gifts, and heard the marvelous
            happenings of the night, they looked at each other in awe, and whispered one to another:
            "Surely it was no other than the blessed Christ-child himself who passed through the
            forest last night and took compassion on these fatherless little ones!"</p>
          <p>And then more than one face among them reddened with shame, as they remembered how
            selfish and thoughtless they themselves had been to let their poor neighbors suffer. <pb
              id="VAC2096-072" n="58"/> Right away they set to work with hammers and saws, and
            stopped up the chinks and made the little hut warm and comfortable; for how better, they
            said, could they keep the Christ-child's birthday? Then they saw to it that the rickety
            little table held a share of their own Christmas cheer.</p>
          <p>Nor did the good villagers, now that they had wakened up, forget their kindnesses, and
            day by day the poor mother found her burdens lightened by many a helping hand. And, as
            for Olaf and Astrid, why, there were no happier children in all the world!</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="VAC2096-073" n="[59]"/>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head rend="center">HOW NIAL WON THE BEAUTIFUL PRINCESS</head>
          <pb id="VAC2096-074" n="[60]"/>
          <pb id="VAC2096-075" n="61"/>
          <p rend="center sc">HOW NIAL WON THE BEAUTIFUL PRINCESS</p>
          <p><hi rend="b">L</hi>ONG, long ago in Ireland there were no towns or villages; only
            wattled houses, made of hazel-rods and plaster, scattered through the country. Everybody
            had a bee-hive and a cow and a little oatfield, because the things they liked best of
            all to eat and drink were honey and milk and porridge. In the middle of the kingdom rose
            a high mound, and on top of this stood the King's palace, which was made of wood
            handsomely carved, with the door-posts inlaid with gold <pb id="VAC2096-076" n="62"/>
            and silver and precious stones.</p>
          <p>The King was good-natured and easy-going; and though he wore a rich mantle and wide
            torque or collar of gold, and many bracelets, and his crown was of fine gold and covered
            his head like a broad-brimmed hat, nevertheless every day he and the Queen and their
            only child, a beautiful young Princess, ate their honey and porridge and drank their
            milk just like everybody else. This greatly displeased the high chamberlain who managed
            the affairs of the palace, and who was proud and haughty and thought it wrong that the
            King did not put on more airs.</p>
          <p>So one morning, as breakfast was being served to the royal family, the <pb
              id="VAC2096-077" n="63"/> chamberlain made bold to go before the King. "Your
            Highness," he said, bowing very low, "though your dishes are gold and silver, the food
            they hold is the same as the common people have, and they will think you no better than
            they. Shall I not order something more rare and costly?"</p>
          <p>"Why, no," said the King, looking at him in surprise, "we like these things best."
            Then, as he was about to dip a spoonful of honey over his porridge, "If it will satisfy
            you," he added, "I will make a law that nobody but myself and the Queen and the Princess
            be allowed to eat honey on their porridge for breakfast. That will show them I <pb
              id="VAC2096-078" n="64"/> am a King and can make laws which they must obey."</p>
          <p>With that, he dismissed the chamberlain, who was not at all pleased with the way things
            had turned out, but who was obliged to proclaim the new law throughout the kingdom.
            Nobody else liked it, either, when they found they might no longer eat honey on their
            porridge. But the people were peaceable and well-behaved, and the King had always before
            treated them kindly, so no one dreamed of disobeying him; indeed, if they did, they knew
            they would be punished by the high chamberlain.</p>
          <p>So much for the folks who lived above ground. But they were not <pb id="VAC2096-079"
              n="65"/> the only people in Ireland; for, hidden under all the green hills and
            meadows, were hundreds and hundreds of fairies.</p>
          <p>These fairies, who had once been mortals like the rest, had been conquered in war and
            about to be sold into slavery, but, being wise in magic, had been able to cast a spell
            over themselves, so that they became smaller and smaller, and at last turned into
            fairies. Then they crept under-ground and built themselves wonderful halls and palaces.
            In these they feasted every day on magic meat and mead which kept them forever young and
            beautiful. Often, on moonlight nights, they would come out to dance and frolic <pb
              id="VAC2096-080" n="66"/> in the meadows; though always they kept out of sight of
            grown folks, for they had not forgotten that it was grown folks who conquered them in
            war. But if now and then a boy or girl chanced to spy their merry-making, they did not
            mind; though they would whisper to them to keep what they had seen to themselves. And
            the children promised, and always kept their word to the little people.</p>
          <p>Now at this time, in one of the smallest of the wattled houses, lived a poor woman
            named Bridget, and her only child, a bright-eyed boy called Nial. They had no torques or
            bracelets, and their clothes were old and ragged; but they had a <pb id="VAC2096-081"
              n="67"/> little bee-hive, and a cow, and a tiny bit of ground where they raised a few
            oats for porridge. A peat bog was near, so they always had a fire on the hearth; and
            that contented they were, Bridget would sing over her work and Nial whistle as merrily
            as if he were a king's son.</p>
          <p>Every day Nial took the cow to pasture; but one spring evening, when he went as usual
            to bring her to the byre, she had strayed into the bog. It took a while to find her, and
            when he did and started for home, the moon was up and flooding the meadow ahead of him
            with a silvery light. As he stepped along through the green grass, all at once he heard
            a low, tinkling sound, for <pb id="VAC2096-082" n="68"/> all the world like a brook when
            the ice begins to thaw in April. Then the tinkling grew livelier and faster and turned
            into a rollicking dance tune.</p>
          <p>"Musha!" said Nial to the cow walking soberly ahead of him, "D'ye hear that, and can ye
            still keep your hoofs on the ground? I've a mind to jig it with ye myself!"</p>
          <p>Just then there rose a flutter of gauzy wings, and the little people began to come.
            They seemed to creep from under the tufts of cowslips and butter-cups, hundreds of them,
            till "Whisht!" cried Nial softly to the cow, "Now just run along to the byre&mdash;ye
            know the way. As for me, I must bide here a <pb id="VAC2096-083" n="69"/> while!" And he
            quickly hid himself in a clump of hazel bushes, though not before the fairies had caught
            sight of him.</p>
          <p>Immediately the fairy Queen sent a messenger to discover who he was; but when they
            found it was only Nial, "Let him be," said the Queen, "he is a good boy and will do no
            mischief." For they knew Nial for a kindly soul who never harmed a living creature, bird
            or beast, and who always took pains never to tread on a flower if he could help it. So,
            catching hold of hands, the little people began to dance. Round and round they tripped
            in the maddest, merriest frolicking, their gauzy wings glimmering, their little <pb
              id="VAC2096-084" n="70"/> silver shoes twinkling, and their gay little caps and
            mantles looking like bits of whirling rainbows. And no wonder, for they were made of the
            brightest spring flowers, tulips and daffodils, peach-blossoms and hyacinths,&mdash;Nial
            fairly blinked as he watched them.</p>
          <p>"Now," said he, admiringly to himself, "did ever ye see a handsomer sight? And look at
            the colors on yonder little lady! Sure, our Queen herself has nothing finer!" For the
            more bright colors the Irish folk had in their clothes, the better they liked it.</p>
          <p>As the moon now began to wane and the fairies to creep out of sight, he noticed that
            the gay little mantles <pb id="VAC2096-085" n="71"/> and caps and what not, that he had
            thought so handsome, were many of them torn and frayed from their wild frolicking.</p>
          <p>"Musha!" again said Nial to himself, "'Tis no matter for the likes of me to be wearing
            of a ragged coat, but 'tis a pity for the little people not to be spic and span. I'll
            warrant it took a good two hours to hunt through the meadows for all those pretties
            they've got on their backs, and since they have behaved so fine to me, it's I that will
            be helping of them another night."</p>
          <p>When Nial had crept out of the hazel bushes and reached home, "Och now!" said his
            mother, "'Tis that worried I've been! The cow's <pb id="VAC2096-086" n="72"/> in the
            byre since moonrise, and sure I was that the little people had carried ye off!"</p>
          <p>"'Tis a bit of a handful they would be having, Mother!" said Nial, as he laughed and
            straightened himself up; for he was a likely lad, strong and well grown for his years.
            "It's moon-struck I must have been, Mother, as I came through the meadow." And Nial
            threw himself on his bed and pretended to fall asleep; for he did not want to be
            questioned about what he had seen.</p>
          <p>The next day, when he drove the cow through the meadow, there was a ring of tall green
            grass where the fairies had danced, and he could think of nothing else.</p>
          <pb id="VAC2096-087" n="73"/>
          <p>"Maybe," he said to himself, "they will come again tonight. Anyway, it's ready I'll
            make for them."</p>
          <p>So before dusk fell, he went about gathering handfulls of cowslips and daisies,
            primroses and harebells, all the gayest flowers he could find, and heaped them on the
            grass near the fairy ring. Then he slipped into the spring-house where Bridget had set
            the evening's milk, and filling a small gourd dipper, carried it out and stood it in the
            grass beside the flowers. "I'm thinking," he said, "the little people will be liking of
            a drop of new milk as well as anybody!" For everybody knows that fairies are very fond
            of fresh milk.</p>
          <pb id="VAC2096-088" n="74"/>
          <p>After supper, when Bridget was sound asleep, Nial quietly slipped out of bed, and
            unbarring the door, ran swiftly down to the meadow and hid in the hazel bushes as
            before. By and by, when the moon came up, sure enough, out crept the little people to
            dance and frolic again. When they saw the preparations Nial had made for them, they were
            mightily pleased. They frisked about sipping the new milk, and then they whisked the
            flowers on, caps and mantles of harebells and hyacinths, cowslips and primroses. My, how
            gay they looked and how they danced!</p>
          <p>Before they flitted away to their underground palaces, the fairy <pb id="VAC2096-089"
              n="75"/> Queen said that as Nial had shown his kind heart, they would do something for
            him. So flying to the bee-hive, she touched it with her wand, bewitching the bees so
            that they might make the finest flavored honey in all Ireland. Also she stroked with her
            wand the forehead of the cow, so she might give an inexhaustible supply of the richest
            milk.</p>
          <p>The next day Nial slept late, and Bridget, not wishing to wake the lad, ate her
            porridge alone. After a while, when her work was done, seeing the honey dish was empty,
            she went to the hive and brought in a fresh comb;&mdash;and then, when she tasted it,
            she smacked her lips in amazement. "Musha!" she <pb id="VAC2096-090" n="76"/> exclaimed,
            tasting and smacking again, "Was ever there the likes of this! Why, lad, our bees must
            be bewitched!"</p>
          <p>Nial, who had roused up, laughed to himself, but said nothing of how near the truth she
            had guessed.</p>
          <p>"Why," went on Bridget, "'tis honey fit for a king!" Then, her words putting an idea
            into the good woman's head, "Bedad, now," she said, "'tis just stepping up to the King's
            palace I'll be to carry a bit for the porridge of the young Princess!" For all the Irish
            folk knew that the Princess was exceedingly fond of honey.</p>
          <p>"All right, Mother," said Nial, who was beginning to eat the plain <pb id="VAC2096-091"
              n="77"/> oat porridge Bridget had set before him for breakfast, "but before ye go,
            just give me a bit on my porridge here."</p>
          <p>"What?" cried his mother, bewildered. "Ye know well 'tis not for the likes of us to be
            eating honey on porridge; that's only for king folks! But sure, lad, 'tis only plaguing
            me ye are!" And never doubting that Nial was only teasing her, off she bustled for the
            palace, which was not far away.</p>
          <p>But the minute she shut the door, Nial, who was a bold lad, reached over for the honey
            dish, and, with a twinkle in his eye, muttering, "'Tis a pity if I can't be playing it's
            a king's son I am!" dipped his big <pb id="VAC2096-092" n="78"/> horn spoon full and
            poured it over his porridge. Then he smacked his lips, as Bridget had done, when he
            tasted it, and made haste to pour on some more.</p>
          <p>Before he had finished, Bridget, who walked quickly, had reached the palace. The young
            Princess was just ready for breakfast, and when her porridge was brought in covered with
            the bewitched honey, and she tasted it, my, my, that pleased she was, you never saw the
            like! Immediately she begged the King, her father, to buy Bridget's bees and have their
            hive placed in the royal garden. At once the King sent out a generous purse of gold, and
            commanded the high <pb id="VAC2096-093" n="79"/> chamberlain to buy the bees and to
            reward the good woman who had brought the honey.</p>
          <p>But the chamberlain, who was as dishonest and grasping as he was proud, determined to
            find some other way to get the bees, and to keep the purse for himself:&mdash;and the
            chance came quicker than he thought. For, as bad luck had it, just as Nial was pouring
            the honey from his horn spoon over his porridge, along came a withered old crone, who
            was friend to nobody; and peering in the window, she saw Nial. Nodding her head
            knowingly, she hobbled off to the palace to tell what she had seen.</p>
          <p>The high chamberlain rubbed <pb id="VAC2096-094" n="80"/> his hands with pleasure, and
            immediately sent a servant to seize Bridget's bee-hive as punishment for Nial's act.</p>
          <p>When the poor woman reached home and found how things were, "<hi rend="i">Ochone!
              Ochone!</hi>" she moaned to herself, and covering her head with her apron, all day
            long she rocked to and fro weeping bitterly.</p>
          <p>When dusk fell, Nial, who was very miserable, went out into the meadow. The moon was
            waning, so there was not light enough for the fairies to dance; nevertheless, a few were
            flitting about enjoying the cool air and sipping the dew. When Nial, who had become very
            good friends with the little people, <pb id="VAC2096-095" n="81"/> told them about
            losing the bewitched bee-hive, they were very indignant. And when they slipped
            underground and repeated it to their Queen, she was downright angry and vowed that if
            Nial could not have the wonderful honey, neither should the King's daughter. So she
            commanded a messenger to go to the hive and whisper to the bees that the meadows of the
            King of France were much finer and flowerier, and they would do well to go there.</p>
          <p>The bees, at hearing this, at once prepared to fly across the sea; and as they are
            gossippy little creatures, they told the other bees in the royal hives, and soon the
            word spread through all the kingdom, <pb id="VAC2096-096" n="82"/> and, swarm after
            swarm, all the bees flew away to the meadows of the King of France.</p>
          <p>When the Irish folk found their bees gone, they set up a great lamentation! Nobody
            could understand what had become of them, and they did not see how they could get along
            without their favorite food. The high chamberlain, thinking Nial must have something to
            do with the matter, sent and had him brought before the King. But to all their questions
            and threats the lad answered so bravely and fearlessly, and declared so truthfully that
            he knew nothing about it (for he did not know the fairy queen had sent the bees away),
            that they were obliged <pb id="VAC2096-097" n="83"/> to let him go; though the high
            chamberlain took away the milk cow, just for spite, and poor Bridget wrung her hands in
            vain.</p>
          <p>Soon it was whispered about that the beautiful young Princess was pining away! Having
            no honey for it, she would not touch her porridge, and was growing so pale and thin that
            the court physician declared that, unless the bees were brought back, she would surely
            die.</p>
          <p>At this, the King, in despair, sent heralds through the kingdom, blowing on trumpets
            and proclaiming that whoever brought the bees back should be richly rewarded, and, if a
            young man, should be solemnly betrothed to the beautiful Princess <pb id="VAC2096-098"
              n="84"/> and marry her as soon as she reached a suitable age. The word spread through
            neighboring kingdoms, and many handsome young princes set their wits to work to win the
            beautiful Princess; but all in vain, for nobody knew where the bees were, or how to get
            them back again.</p>
          <p>Meantime it was the dark of the moon, and Nial's friends, the fairies, no longer came
            to the meadow, but danced and froliced in their underground palaces. Still, Nial kept
            hoping that, by and by, they would come out again; and then, he thought, he would make
            bold to ask their help. For he was a fearless lad, and, despite his ragged coat, did not
            see why he should not try for the <pb id="VAC2096-099" n="85"/> Princess the same as
            anybody else.</p>
          <p>So when next the moon was full and the meadow flooded with silver, he took pains to
            gather handfulls of the finest flowers he could find, and heaped them up as before. He
            could not bring new milk, because the high chamberlain had taken their cow; but he
            looked about and, spying some foxgloves, "There, now!" he cried, "'tis like pitchers of
            dew they are, for the little people!" Then, <hi rend="i">snip! snap!</hi> the evening
            primroses began to break, and filling his hands with their yellow cups, he set them with
            the foxgloves by the fairy rings. "Sure," he said to himself as he looked at them, "I'll
            be thinking the gold cups and <pb id="VAC2096-100" n="86"/> platters of the King's folks
            are no handsomer sight!"</p>
          <p>Nial had scarcely finished making ready for them, when, sure enough, the little people
            began to come out, and they all felt very friendly toward Nial for his kindness. He kept
            behind the hazel bushes and waited till they had finished their frolic; and had poured
            all the dew from the foxglove pitchers into the primrose cups, from which they sipped it
            gladly, as their dancing had made them very warm and thirsty. Then, stepping out, he
            dropped on his knees before the fairy Queen. Very big and awkward he looked kneeling
            there before the little lady, but she <pb id="VAC2096-101" n="87"/> listened soberly as
            he told about the lost bees and how anxious he was to win the beautiful Princess.</p>
          <p>When he had finished, the Queen frowned a bit, for she remembered sending away the bees
            without thinking what mischief it would do; for the fairies are fickle little folks, and
            do not greatly trouble themselves about the affairs of mortals. She was sorry for Nial,
            though, and determined to help him. So she thought a minute, and then she said, "Well,
            lad, it was I who sent off the bees to the meadows of the King of France; but it was
            easier to send them off than it will be to get them back again. I cannot send one of my
            messengers there, as we fairies <pb id="VAC2096-102" n="88"/> never leave our own
            country; and besides, the fairies of France are not friendly to us and might do an ill
            turn. Nor would it do any good for you to go, for the bees would pay no attention to
            you. There is another way, however to get them back."</p>
          <p>"Faith, Ma'am," said Nial eagerly, "I'll do your bidding, though 'tis to fight the King
            of France himself!"</p>
          <p>The lad looked so very brave and bold, that the fairy Queen smiled. "No," she said,
            "'tis not to France you must be going, but to the Northland. So get your knapsack ready
            for a journey. Put in it some oat-cakes, this ball of silver cord (and she handed Nial a
            glittering ball), <pb id="VAC2096-103" n="89"/> and a cage large enough for two birds;
            you can make this yourself from the osiers by the brook. Then carry a spade over your
            shoulder, and set out for the seashore. There you must take ship for the Northland. When
            you get there, walk inland till you come to a green meadow where a small silver birch
            tree is growing. There will be a number of cuckoos singing from its branches, and where
            the notes of their song fall to the ground you will see hundreds of golden yellow
            flowers springing up. Now you must get two of these cuckoos and put them in your
            cage."</p>
          <p>"Musha, Ma'am!" exclaimed Nial, "And is it salting of their <pb id="VAC2096-104" n="90"
            /> tails I must be doing? Never yet have I managed to salt a bird's tail, Ma'am, and
            'tis many times I've tried." And he looked so hopeless, that the Queen was like to
            laugh.</p>
          <p>"No," she answered, "you need not trouble yourself about their tails; I will teach you
            some charm words, and when you say them to the birds they will come to your hand easily.
            Then you must dig up the birch tree and wrap its roots carefully with the silver cord;
            then sling it over your shoulder&mdash;for you are a stout lad&mdash;and bring it along;
            for unless the cuckoos sing from the boughs of the silver birch of the Northland, the
            yellow flowers will not spring up."</p>
          <pb id="VAC2096-105" n="91"/>
          <p>"Bedad, Ma'am," broke in Nial again, "but how is all that going to bring back the
            bees?"</p>
          <p>"Never mind," said the Queen sharply, "and ask no more questions! It is your business
            to do exactly as I bid you."</p>
          <p>So Nial listened meekly as the Queen taught him the charm words, and told him to bring
            the birch tree home and plant it in the meadow, and then to hang the cuckoos' cage on
            its boughs and open the door and see what happened.</p>
          <p>When she had finished, Nial thanked her as politely as he knew how, and then he hurried
            back home; and early the next morning he set about to do her bidding. He <pb
              id="VAC2096-106" n="92"/> found an old knapsack, and Bridget baked some oat-cakes for
            his journey. These he put in the knapsack, together with the ball of silver cord and the
            cage, which he made from osiers as the fairy said. Then carrying a spade over his
            shoulder, he set out for the seashore. There he found a ship about to sail for the
            Northland; and though he had not a penny, he whistled so merrily and laughed so heartily
            and promised so faithfully to work his way, that the captain took him along right
            willingly.</p>
          <p>When he reached the Northland, it all turned out exactly as the fairy Queen had said.
            He found the green meadow with the silver birch <pb id="VAC2096-107" n="[]"/><figure>
              <p>"AS SOON AS HE SAID OVER THE CHARM WORDS THE OUEEN HAD TAUGHT HIM, BACK THEY
                CAME"</p>
            </figure><pb id="VAC2096-108" n="[]"/>
            <pb id="VAC2096-109" n="93"/> tree full of cuckoos, and thousands of yellow flowers
            dotting the grass as they sang. Carefully stepping between these so as not to crush
            them, and taking the osier cage in one hand, he walked toward the tree; and though at
            first all the cuckoos flew away, as soon as he said over the charm words the Queen had
            taught him, back they came; and the first thing he knew two of them were fluttering
            round his head, and then they perched, one on each shoulder.</p>
          <p>"Whishst now, my pretties!" he said, laughing softly. "Sure and if ye'll be stepping
            into this handsome cage here, I'll take ye to a land as much finer than this as a
            shamrock <pb id="VAC2096-110" n="94"/> than a cockle-burr!" Then as he hummed over the
            charm once more, the cuckoos flew into the cage, and he shut the door.</p>
          <p>Next he set to work to dig up the birch tree, and carefully wrapping its roots with the
            silver cord, he slung it over his shoulder together with the spade, and with the cage in
            his hand, again set out for the seashore. There he found the same ship in which he had
            sailed to the Northland, and the captain, who was about to start back to Ireland, took
            him along right willingly, as before.</p>
          <p>When they reached the land and Nial set off for the home meadow, now and then folks
            came out of their <pb id="VAC2096-111" n="95"/> wattled houses and asked him where he
            was going with his birch tree and cage of yellow birds; for no cuckoos had ever before
            come to Ireland. And when Nial answered, "'Tis bringing back the bees I'm after doing!"
            the people pricked up their ears and followed along to see how he would do it.</p>
          <p>There were so many of them that they made a great circle about the home meadow, where
            they stood and watched as Nial carefully planted the birch tree and hung the open cage
            on its branches, as the fairy Queen had told him. Immediately the little people
            underground unwrapped the silver cord from its roots and spread them out so that <pb
              id="VAC2096-112" n="96"/> the birch tree at once began to grow and flourish. Then the
            cuckoos, flying out of the cage, perched on its branches and began to sing; and as their
            notes fell to the ground, thousands of golden flowers sprang up through the grass. And
              <hi rend="i">whiff! whiff!</hi> as the Irish sun, so much warmer than in the
            Northland, shone on them, my, my, how sweet they smelled! Never was there anything like
            it! All the roses and honeysuckles in the world were as nothing to it!</p>
          <p>"Och! Och!" cried everybody, "was ever the likes of it for pleasantness!"</p>
          <p>Soon the wind began to blow toward the meadows of the King of <pb id="VAC2096-113"
              n="97"/> France; stronger and stronger it blew, till <hi rend="i">sniff! sniff!</hi>
            the bees there stopped in their buzzing. <hi rend="i">Sniff! sniff!</hi> right away,
            swarm after swarm, they flew straight across the sea for Ireland and began to fill their
            honey-bags from the golden flowers; and then they settled down in their old hives and
            forgot all about the meadows of the King of France.</p>
          <p>Everybody was mightily pleased to have the bees back again; but the high chamberlain
            was very angry when he found it was Nial who had coaxed them home. When the King asked
            him who had brought them back, he told him it was one of the handsome young Princes who
            had tried in vain. But the truth <pb id="VAC2096-114" n="98"/> could not be kept back,
            for too many people had seen what Nial had done; and his friends soon found means to
            tell the King. They told him also how wicked the high chamberlain was, and the King was
            very angry and commanded the hive of bewitched bees and the milk cow to be restored at
            once to Bridget, together with the purse of gold which the chamberlain had kept from
            her. Then he banished the high chamberlain himself to a wattled hut in a far-off corner
            of the kingdom, and ordered that he was to have nothing but thin porridge and water to
            live on the rest of his life.</p>
          <p>Nevertheless, though the King had tried to set things to rights with <pb
              id="VAC2096-115" n="99"/> Nial and his mother, he was very sad to think that the hand
            of the beautiful Princess was promised to a poor ragged lad; and as for the Princess,
            she began to weep bitterly. At this the King, who could not bear to see her cry, said,
            "Never mind, my dear. 'Tis a poor lad he is, and I'll warrant for a few bags of gold
            'tis willing enough he'll be to let me off from my promise; and to make it sure, I'll
            tell him plainly that if he marries you 'tis nothing at all he'll be getting but a wife
            to support!"</p>
          <p>At this, the tears of the Princess broke out afresh, and the King, distracted, sent at
            once for Nial.</p>
          <p>When the lad was brought into <pb id="VAC2096-116" n="100"/> the palace, the King
            commanded that a large chest be placed before him, and then told him to lift the lid.
            When Nial did so, he opened his eyes wide, for it was filled with the finest golden
            torques and bracelets, besides bags of gold and jewels. "Nial," said the King, "if you
            free me from my promise to betroth the Princess, the chest is yours. But I will tell you
            plainly, lad," and here the King frowned, "if 'tis the Princess you are set on having,
            not a penny goes with her, and 'tis only a wife to support you will be getting."</p>
          <p>On hearing this, Nial, turning up his nose at the chest full of gold, fell on his knees
            before the beautiful Princess, just as he had knelt to the <pb id="VAC2096-117" n="101"
            /> fairy queen, and smiling up at her,</p>
          <p>"Bedad, Ma'am," he said, "if it's willing to marry me ye are, why, as for yonder
            torques and bags of gold, the King, your father, may toss them into the sea for all I'll
            be caring! It's my stout two hands that will work for ye, and 'tis I that will wait on
            ye like as if ye were the fairy Queen herself!"</p>
          <p>To the surprise of everybody, when Nial began to speak the Princess had quickly dried
            her eyes; and when he finished, in spite of his ragged coat he looked so bold and
            handsome with his yellow hair and his ruddy cheeks and merry blue eyes, and he lifted
            his head so proudly, that the beautiful Princess <pb id="VAC2096-118" n="102"/> smiled
            back at him. Putting out both her hands, "Nial," she said, "'tis yourself and nobody
            else I'll be marrying, and the torques and bracelets and bags of gold may go to the
            bottom of the sea for all I'll be caring either!"</p>
          <p>At the speech of the Princess everybody stared in amazement; and the King, being
            good-natured and easy-going, laughed outright when he saw how things were turning out
            and that the Princess was happy. "Well, well," he said, "so be it! And 'tis changing my
            mind I'll be about the Princess having no dowry." Then he told Nial to pick from the
            chest the handsomest torques and bracelets for himself <pb id="VAC2096-119" n="103"/>
            and Bridget, and he commanded the court tailors and dress-makers to set to work on the
            finest clothes for them; and when these were finished he ordered a grand feast, and Nial
            and the Princess were solemnly betrothed. The Princess wore a gown of white velvet sewn
            with pearls, and carried a bouquet of the wonderful yellow flowers from the meadow; and
            while the betrothal was going on, the two cuckoos came and perched, one on her shoulder
            and one on Nial's, and sang as if they would burst their throats.</p>
          <p>In due time, when Nial was grown to a fine strong young man and the Princess was more
            beautiful than ever, they had a splendid <pb id="VAC2096-120" n="104"/> wedding and
            lived happily ever after. And proud enough the King and Queen were to have so brave and
            handsome a son.</p>
          <p>This is the story of how Nial won the beautiful Princess, and of how the first cuckoos
            came to Ireland.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="VAC2096-121" n="[105]"/>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head rend="center">THE WISHING-SPRING</head>
          <pb id="VAC2096-122" n="[106]"/>
          <pb id="VAC2096-123" n="107"/>
          <p rend="center sc">THE WISHING-SPRING</p>
          <p><hi rend="b">I</hi>T was Midsummer Eve, and the Irish meadows glimmered green and
            flowery beyond a little cabin close to a grass-grown road. It had clay walls and a roof
            thatched with straw, and near by were a potato-patch and a pen holding a white pig with
            a curly tail; in the door-yard a few hens were clucking, now and then straggling in and
            out of the open door as they pleased.</p>
          <p>Within the cabin a little girl was tending a baby, while her mother stirred a pot of
            porridge hanging over an open fire of peat, and her <pb id="VAC2096-124" n="108"/>
            father sat smoking his pipe beside the hearth. Presently, "Come now, Biddy!" said her
            mother. "Bring Peter here whilst we have a bite and sup. 'Tis to the bonfire soon your
            father would be going." And she took the baby on her lap, and dished the porridge into
            earthen bowls, and poured the tea from a cracked teapot.</p>
          <p>As Biddy took up her wooden spoon, "Mother," she asked, "did ever ye see the midsummer
            fairies?"</p>
          <p>"Bedad, no!" said her mother. "Not I! But folks do say the little people will be
            creeping out and playing of their pranks tomorrow."</p>
          <p>"Yes," said Biddy's father, nodding his head wisely, "and some say <pb id="VAC2096-125"
              n="109"/> their magic begins this night. I dare say they will soon be dancing with the
            young folks around the bonfire, if only we could be seeing of them."</p>
          <p>Here Peter, who had got a spoonful of hot tea when his mother was not looking, began to
            scream, and cried so hard that Biddy could ask no more questions; and her father, not
            waiting for him to stop, took his cap and went across the meadow to a hill where a
            bonfire was already lighted, and young people were dancing around it and singing at the
            tops of their voices.</p>
          <p>Why were they doing it? Dear me, I do not know, except that they always did so on
            Midsummer Eve&mdash; <pb id="VAC2096-126" n="110"/> and perhaps do now, for all I can
            tell. Neither do I know why Irish folks declare that on Midsummer Day, which is the
            twenty-fourth of June, the fairies&mdash;or "little people," as they like to call
            them&mdash;will creep out from under the fields and hills, where they have beautiful
            palaces, and play around above ground, where they may do one a good or ill turn,
            according to whether they are pleased or not. Folks say, too, that the fairies swim
            about in certain little bubbling springs of Ireland, and that, if you sip the water from
            one of these on Midsummer Day and make a wish, at the same time offering some gift the
            fairies like, they will surely cause the wish to come <pb id="VAC2096-127" n="111"/>
            true. Why they say all these things, as I told you before, I am sure I cannot tell; but,
            as everybody agrees that Ireland has always been a fine place for fairies, I dare say
            the people there know a great deal about them. It might even be that, if you look sharp
            on the twenty-fourth of June, you may see some fairies in this country. Mind, I do not
            say you will; but then, neither do I say you won't!</p>
          <p>Now, of course Biddy had heard much of the little people, and she could not understand
            why, though there was a "wishing-spring" not far from the cabin, and she had tried it
            for two Midsummer Days, her wish had not come true. The trouble <pb id="VAC2096-128"
              n="112"/> was that she did not know about taking a gift of the right kind for the
            fairies. But the day of our story she had found out. That afternoon a very wise old
            woman had chanced to come hobbling along the road by the cabin and had stopped to rest,
            and Biddy had brought her a drink from the spring and had fallen to talking with her. It
            was she who told Biddy that there were five kinds of herbs which, though just ordinary
            plants at other times, became magical on Midsummer Eve; and, if their flowers were
            gathered then under the light of a full moon, a bunch of them offered to the fairies
            would please them so that they would not fail to grant any wish.</p>
          <pb id="VAC2096-129" n="113"/>
          <p>When Biddy heard this, she made up her mind to get some that very night, when the moon
            would be full, and the next day to try the wishing-spring again. And she had a very good
            chance to go and gather them; for, when Peter at last stopped crying and went to sleep,
            her mother was so worn out with him that, throwing herself down on the bed beside him,
            she was soon sound asleep, too. Then, softly opening the door, Biddy ran to the meadow.
            The moon had risen, and it was so light that she had little trouble in finding what she
            wanted; for the meadow was full of wild flowers. "There," said she presently, counting
            to herself, "I have a rose, and <pb id="VAC2096-130" n="114"/> vervain, and trefoil, and
            St. John's-wort, and meadow-rue&mdash;that's the five; and it's a sprig of honeysuckle
            I'll be putting in for the nice smell of it, and 'tis sure I am the little people will
            like it, too, even if it's not magical!" And she sniffed the sweet cluster as she tucked
            it into her nosegay. Then, hurrying home, she put the flowers in a pitcher of water and
            crept into bed.</p>
          <p>The next morning, just as soon as she had her breakfast of porridge and before Peter
            had wakened up to be tended, taking her nosegay she ran to the wishing-spring and,
            kneeling beside it, began dabbling it in the water. Just then, "Och, Biddy!" called out
            a red-haired boy <pb id="VAC2096-131" n="115"/> who had come up behind her. "Are ye
            after trying the wishing-spring again? The fairies won't heed ye!"</p>
          <p>"Whisht, Pat!" said she, looking up at the boy, who was her good friend and playmate.
            "You just watch and see now!"</p>
          <p>"What will ye be wishing this time, Biddy?" asked Pat, coming nearer to the spring.</p>
          <p>"Silly!" said Biddy. "It's well enough ye know that, if I tell, 'tis spoilt the wish
            will be!" Here she stooped low over the spring and, loosening the nosegay, let it float
            about, as, scooping up some water in her hand, she sipped it and whispered softly, so
            Pat could not hear; "'Tis a beautiful Princess I'm <pb id="VAC2096-132" n="116"/>
            wishing to be, and wearing of a velvet gown and a pearl necklace, and to be living in a
            grand castle and marrying of a king's son!"</p>
          <p>Then, as she and Pat peered into the bubbling water, "Look! Look!" cried Biddy. "There
            is one of the little people now! See him down there in the sand playing with the
            bubbles? It's a red cap he's wearing and a blue coat! Oh, Pat, there's another&mdash;a
            little lady fairy!"</p>
          <p>Pat stared open-mouthed, and, "Biddy," he began,&mdash;but all at once she seemed
            fading away from him, and on her part she could no longer see Pat. Tall stone walls
            began to rise around her; higher and higher they grew, into a castle tower; and <pb
              id="VAC2096-133" n="[]"/><figure>
              <p>"'LOOK! LOOK!' CRIED BIDDY. 'THERE IS ONE OF THE LITTLE PEOPLE NOW!'"</p>
            </figure><pb id="VAC2096-134" n="[]"/>
            <pb id="VAC2096-135" n="117"/> soon she found herself in a large room, all hung with
            wonderful embroidered silk, and furnished with carved chairs and tables and chests, such
            as Biddy had never seen the like of before. She was sitting on a kind of throne, richly
            carved and cushioned with cloth of gold. Looking down at her feet, which had been bare,
            she saw she was wearing golden slippers worked with pearls, and, instead of her ragged
            dress, she had on one of purple velvet, stiff with gold thread. Around her throat was a
            necklace of pearls, and on her head she could feel a fine lace cap. Her hair was braided
            with strands of jewels, and her eyes were very bright and her cheeks <pb
              id="VAC2096-136" n="118"/> glowing; though Biddy had really been pretty enough before,
            with her tangled black curls and eyes of Irish blue. Indeed, Pat thought her quite as
            beautiful as any Princess; though, to be sure, he had never seen a King's daughter.</p>
          <p>When Biddy looked around her she saw six handsomely dressed waiting-maids standing on
            each side of her, and a very grand-looking lady who seemed to be directing them. Soon
            one of them came and, bowing very low, said, "Will Your Highness be served with
            breakfast now?"</p>
          <p>Biddy, you remember, had already had her porridge; but, as Princesses are not expected
            to get up so early, <pb id="VAC2096-137" n="119"/> she thought best not to mention it;
            so she just nodded her head, and at once they brought in a golden tray and set it before
            her. There was fine white bread, milk in a golden goblet, a golden bowl full of barley
            porridge covered with honey, and a number of other things of which Biddy did not even
            know the names. She awkwardly picked up a gold spoon and dipped it in the porridge, but
            she was staring around so hard that, instead of putting it into her mouth, it bumped
            against her nose, and all the porridge fell in her lap; and then, as she put down the
            spoon in dismay, over went the goblet of milk on top of the rest. "Musha!" she cried.
            "'Tis my grand velvet <pb id="VAC2096-138" n="120"/> gown that is all spoilt! Och!
            Och!"</p>
          <p>But most of the waiting-maids only stared in surprise, though some tittered a bit till
            frowned on by the grand lady. Then one of them, again bowing, said, "Will Your Highness
            have on another gown before time for lessons? The masters will soon be here."</p>
          <p>Biddy, turning red and feeling very uncomfortable, faltered out, "Yes, mam. Bedad, and
            it's sorry I am to be a-spoiling of this!" And she looked down shame-facedly at the
            purple velvet all dripping with milk and porridge.</p>
          <p>At this, the waiting-maids could hardly keep from laughing outright, <pb
              id="VAC2096-139" n="121"/> as they led her to a fine bedroom and put on her another
            velvet dress&mdash;this time a crimson one and, like the other, very stiff with
            embroidery and reaching nearly to the floor, which was the fashion for little girl
            Princesses.</p>
          <p>Then they took her back to the big room, and again she sat on the throne-like chair,
            which was beginning to feel rather straight and hard, in spite of its rich carving and
            heavy cushions.</p>
          <p>Presently in came the spelling-master&mdash;a solemn-looking man with a large book in
            his hand. At the sight of this Biddy was decidedly frightened, for she had never been to
            school a day in her life; there <pb id="VAC2096-140" n="122"/> were no places in Ireland
            then where children who lived in cabins might be taught. "Now, Your Highness," said the
            spelling-master, opening the book and bowing as had the others, "will you deign to spell
            'cat'?"</p>
          <p>"Oh sir!" gasped Biddy. "Is it me that must be spelling of cat? 'Tis only priests, sir,
            that can read the mass-book, that can do hard things like that!"</p>
          <p>The spelling-master looked perplexed, and, after talking a few minutes with the grand
            lady, the latter came and said respectfully, but rather sternly, "Your Highness, if you
            will not learn to spell, how then can you read? And then there are <pb id="VAC2096-141"
              n="123"/> your music- and drawing-masters waiting."</p>
          <p>"Musha! Musha! ma'am!" cried Biddy in despair. "And is it all such things Princesses
            must be doing of? I&mdash;I didn't know, ma'am, King's daughters had to work the likes
            of that! Why, I'd rather&mdash;rather be a-tending of Peter!"</p>
          <p>At Biddy's speech the grand lady looked very stern indeed, and stared very hard; but
            she only said, "Very well, Your Highness. I will dismiss your masters for today. And
            what are your commands for the morning, in place of the lessons?"</p>
          <p>Biddy was silent a while, and then she said faintly, "If you please, <pb
              id="VAC2096-142" n="124"/> ma'am, I'd&mdash;I'd like to play, I would!"</p>
          <p>The grand lady brightened up then, and said, "Does Your Highness mean to keep your
            music-master here and play on your harp?"</p>
          <p>"Oh dear, no, ma'am!" answered Biddy, frightened again. "'Tis to play outdoors I'm
            meaning! Tag and ball it is, and games like Pat and I know!"</p>
          <p>The grand lady stiffened up again, and, turning to the twelve waiting-maids, said
            coldly, "Conduct the Princess to the garden. She wishes to play ball and tag." And
            Biddy's cheeks burned, the way she said it.</p>
          <p>She followed meekly as the <pb id="VAC2096-143" n="125"/> waiting-maids led the way
            down a winding stair&mdash;which made her quite dizzy, as she had never before been on
            stairs&mdash;and out into a large garden. There were fountains in it, and very fine
            flowers; but the flowers were all in straight stiff beds and did not look as if meant to
            be picked. As Biddy gazed at them, she could not but think she liked the meadow ones
            better. Then nobody but herself knew how to play tag, and the waiting-maids looked very
            scornful when she tried to show them; and, when she wanted to run, her long heavy dress
            was terribly in her way; while, as for the gold slippers, they tripped her up so she
            tumbled down twice, and the <pb id="VAC2096-144" n="126"/> waiting-maids laughed out
            loud at her. "Bedad!" moaned Biddy to herself. "'Tis the feel of the grass under my toes
            that I'm wanting!" For never had she worn shoes, except thick calfskin ones in winter,
            and she was quite unused to the high heels of slippers for Princesses. Then, too, she
            soon found that in the game of tag the waiting-maids never tagged <hi rend="i">her</hi>,
            because it was not considered proper for Princesses to be beaten in any game; and, of
            course, that took all the fun away.</p>
          <p>Biddy soon tired of playing like that, and she sat down on a stone bench to think;
            though it was not very easy to think with twelve tittering waiting-maids standing
            stiffly <pb id="VAC2096-145" n="127"/> behind her. Biddy could hear them, and the more
            they tittered the angrier she grew; till presently, in quite a rage, she tore off her
            lace cap and&mdash;I'm sorry to tell it, but she threw it down and stamped on it. Then
            she kicked off the golden slippers, and pulled off her fine silk stockings, and, running
            to a fountain near by, flung them all in; and then she sat on the edge of it and cried.
            "Och! Och!" she wailed, as the tears streamed down her cheeks. "If only ye were a
            wishing-spring and I could wish again!"</p>
          <p>In a moment a sweet, tinkling little voice seemed to come from under a water-lily in
            the fountain, and then a tiny fairy crept out and sat <pb id="VAC2096-146" n="128"/> on
            the big green leaf of the lily. It was the same little lady she had seen in the
            wishing-spring that morning. "There, there, child!" said the fairy, smiling kindly. "I
            have been watching you today; for I wondered how you would like being a Princess. If you
            want to wish again, you may."</p>
          <p>"Oh, ma'am," cried Biddy eagerly, "I wish I was back in the Cabin again, and&mdash;and
            'tis barefooted I'm wanting to go, and to be tending of Peter and feeding of the pig,
            and playing in the meadow with Pat&mdash;and never, <hi rend="i">never</hi> to be a
            Princess again so long as ever I live!"</p>
          <p>And, of course, the good fairy made Biddy's wish come true, and <pb id="VAC2096-147"
              n="129"/> she became a ragged, happy little girl as before; and, when they grew up,
            she forgot all about the King's son she had once wanted to marry, and married Pat
            instead; and of course, too, they lived happily ever after.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="VAC2096-148" n="[130]"/>
        <pb id="VAC2096-149" n="[131]"/>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head rend="center">THE GOOD YEAR</head>
          <pb id="VAC2096-150" n="[132]"/>
          <pb id="VAC2096-151" n="133"/>
          <p rend="center sc">THE GOOD YEAR</p>
          <p><hi rend="b">S</hi>UPPER was over, the pewter porringers and platter put back on the
            dresser shelves, and the curtains drawn over the farmhouse windows so as to keep out the
            chill wind; for it was the very last of December, and in Norway the winter nights are
            always long and cold.</p>
          <p>Grandfather was sitting on the big settle close to the hearth, and Arne and Olga had
            crept up, one on either side of him. It was the time when they loved to talk to him, or
            perhaps listen to a story or two before going to their queer little beds, <pb
              id="VAC2096-152" n="134"/> which were built into the wall, like cupboards, their
            polished doors open now and shining in the firelight.</p>
          <p>Two red-cheeked apples were roasting on the hearth, and as the flames from the blazing
            logs leaped and flickered, they lighted up the brick oven beside the settle and the
            carved and painted rafters overhead. From these hung strands of onions, and dried herbs,
            and odd, flat loaves of bread, each with a hole through the middle and strung on a
            slender pole. Mingled with and half hiding these things, were the green holiday garlands
            of pine, which still decked the house. The firelight flickered also on the gay wooden
              <pb id="VAC2096-153" n="135"/> cradle where baby Hilda lay sleeping, and on the deal
            table beyond, where stood a pretty fir-tree that had shed its Christmas gifts but was
            still bright with tinsel and paper flowers.</p>
          <p>The children's father and mother had gone to the village church for the last service of
            the year, and as now Arne and Olga drew closer to Grandfather, they all sat dreaming a
            while, and then Arne spoke; "Grandfather," he said, "it is nearly another year, isn't
            it?"</p>
          <p>"Yes, lad," answered Grandfather.</p>
          <p>"And," went on Arne, "you must remember ever so many New Years?"</p>
          <p>"Yes, indeed!" agreed <pb id="VAC2096-154" n="136"/> Grandfather, with a half-sad
            smile; for he was very old and his hair was quite white. "Would you like me to tell you
            about some New Year I remember?"</p>
          <p>"Oh yes, please do!" put in Olga, and Grandfather, stroking her yellow curls, began to
            think.</p>
          <p>"Well, well," he said presently, "I will tell you about the one we village folk (you
            know I lived in the village then) called 'The Good Year.' That was long and long ago,"
            he added, with a sigh. "I must have seen fifty others since that one." Then, brightening
            up, he went on: "It was the thirty-first of December, just like now, and at midnight the
            little New Year lay <pb id="VAC2096-155" n="[]"/><figure>
              <p>"'THE LITTLE NEW YEAR LAY ROCKING IN HIS CRADLE UP IN THE SKY'"</p>
            </figure><pb id="VAC2096-156" n="[]"/>
            <pb id="VAC2096-157" n="137"/> rocking in his cradle up in the sky."</p>
          <p>"Was it like Hilda's, with tulips painted on the rockers and bluebirds on the sides?"
            asked Olga.</p>
          <p>"Why, yes," said Grandfather, "I dare say it was, only finer. Maybe it was made of gold
            like the stars, or silver like the moon; I am not sure. But at any rate, suddenly the
            little New Year sat up listening. There was a great shrieking of whistles and ringing of
            church-bells. '<hi rend="i">Boom! Boom!</hi>' drums were being beaten by the young men
            watching with the old bell-ringer up in the belfry, and everywhere rose a confused sound
            of shouting voices, though he could make out the words, '<hi rend="i">Happy New</hi>
            <pb id="VAC2096-158" n="138"/>
            <hi rend="i">Year! Happy New Year! We wish you a happy New Year!</hi>'</p>
          <p>"The little New Year laughed merrily. 'Ho! Ho!' he cried. 'It is time I was flying down
            there to earth. They seem to be giving me a hearty welcome, and hoping I will be happy.
            Well, I am sure I mean to be!' And again he laughed, as flinging off his starry
            coverlid, he sprang from his cradle and began fluttering his pretty white wings, that
            glistened like the little wings one sees in pictures of baby angels.</p>
          <p>"But before he could fly to the earth, two heavy objects thrust themselves, one in
            either hand. The first was a big, old-fashioned scythe, and the other an hour-glass, in
            which <pb id="VAC2096-159" n="139"/> the golden-brown sand was already beginning to
            trickle from one half to the other."</p>
          <p>"Why did he have those things to carry?" asked Arne.</p>
          <p>"That was what the little New Year wanted to know," replied Grandfather. "He frowned,
            and tried to let go of them, but he could not. 'Not so fast, young sir!' said the
            scythe. 'You must take me along!'"</p>
          <p>"'But why?' asked the little New Year, in surprise.</p>
          <p>"'Because,' answered the scythe, 'all the years since the beginning of the world have
            carried me. You see, down there on earth a certain number of people must die every <pb
              id="VAC2096-160" n="140"/> year, and it is your business once in a while to swing me,
            just as a mower cutting grass in the meadow; and when you do, the people will die, just
            as the grass and flowers wither away after the mowing.'</p>
          <p>"'But,' cried the little New Year, shrinking back, for he was a kindly little soul, 'I
            do not want to make anybody die! Why must I?'</p>
          <p>"'That I cannot tell,' answered the scythe, after a moment's pause. 'But it seems to be
            the way of the world, and you cannot escape it. However, when you reach the earth, you
            can put me down between whiles; for I know I am heavy to carry, and of course you
            mustn't <pb id="VAC2096-161" n="141"/> be swinging me all the time, or there would be
            nobody left there.'</p>
          <p>"The little New Year frowned again, but said no more. But when he looked at the
            hour-glass, he smiled. 'Oh,' he said, 'when I get to a good place, I will empty it out
            and make a fine sand pile to play in!'</p>
          <p>"'Indeed you will not!' said the hour-glass. 'You must take me along, for I am very
            important to you. My sand is divided into twelve parts, one for each month, and when
            they have all run from one half of me to the other, your time is up, and you must die,
            just like everybody else. My January sand is already trickling down, so <pb
              id="VAC2096-162" n="142"/> you had better hurry up with your work.'</p>
          <p>"'Dear me!' said the little New Year, looking a trifle blank, 'My baggage is surely not
            very cheerful! But never mind, perhaps in twelve months I shall be tired of tugging
            these things around, and quite ready to stop.' And with a brave little cry, 'Come on,
            January!' he plunged straight down to earth, a gust of white, sparkling snowflakes
            whirling around him as he went."</p>
          <p>"Where did he land?" asked Arne.</p>
          <p>"Why," said Grandfather, "that was the odd part of it. It was right in our village,
            which happened, to be just underneath his cradle."</p>
          <pb id="VAC2096-163" n="143"/>
          <p>"Did you see him?" inquired Olga.</p>
          <p>"No," replied Grandfather. "Didn't I tell you that he had on a cap that made him and
            his scythe and glass invisible to everybody but babies? You know babies always like each
            other, and so little New Years always smile when they see one. You just watch Hilda
            tomorrow and see if you don't find her looking into the air and laughing as if she saw
            another baby. Of course," added Grandfather, "I have lived through so many years, that
            once in a while, when perhaps their caps have tumbled off for a minute, I have caught a
            glimpse of them, but not often.</p>
          <pb id="VAC2096-164" n="144"/>
          <p>"Well, as I was telling you, the little New Year came straight to our village. To be
            sure, he had to fly all over the world and see that it was January everywhere, and
            attend to all manner of affairs, but years are wonderfully quick about things, so he
            could do his work in a twinkling and still have a good deal of time to spend with us. I
            think he specially liked our village because it was so pretty and peaceful and was the
            first place he came to on earth. Of course, too, that first morning he felt very
            important, for everybody was going around, calling on each other, and talking about him,
            and eating sugar-cake and drinking elderberry wine in his honor.</p>
          <pb id="VAC2096-165" n="145"/>
          <p>"The children all got out their sleds, some of them brand new from Santa Claus and with
            the red paint still fresh and bright, and how they all laughed and shouted! And all the
            while, though none of them knew it, the little New Year was romping with them. Sometimes
            when they dragged their sleds up hill, they wondered what made them so heavy, never
            dreaming that the little New Year had jumped on them; and often, when they thought it
            was passing sleigh-bells, it was really his merry, silvery laughter that they
            heard."</p>
          <p>"I should think he <hi rend="i">would</hi> have been pretty heavy to pull up hill <pb
              id="VAC2096-166" n="146"/> with that big scythe and hour-glass!" said Olga.</p>
          <p>"Well," said Grandfather, "he didn't carry the scythe all the time, but put it down
            whenever he could. Old Lars Anderson declared that as he came through the forest that
            day he saw a queer old-fashioned scythe hanging on an oak tree. But one never could be
            quite sure of what old Lars said, though of course the scythe might have been there and
            become visible when the little New Year let go of it.</p>
          <p>"And it wasn't only the children the little New Year played with. When he got tired of
            romping with them, he flew to the pond at the edge of the village, where the young men
              <pb id="VAC2096-167" n="147"/> and girls were skimming by on their shining skates.
            There, with his silvery laugh, he would tuck up his little white mantle, and sliding
            along in his little bare feet,&mdash;for he did not mind the cold&mdash;<hi rend="i"
              >pouf</hi>! he would push against some flying couple who thought themselves the finest
            skaters in the world, and over they would tumble, wondering how it could possibly have
            happened! Sometimes he would mischievously put his hour-glass down in front of them, and
              <hi rend="i">bump</hi>! over they would go! But they were always well wrapped up in
            thick coats and furs, so nobody was hurt, and their peals of merry laughter only added
            to the fun.</p>
          <pb id="VAC2096-168" n="148"/>
          <p>"Then in the long January evenings, when the young folks of the village would gather
            together and dance, and play blind-man's-buff, and twirl-the-platter, and cut-the-oats,
            the little New Year would often be there playing with them, and nobody knew, only that
            then they always had the best times of all.</p>
          <p>"When the January sand was all run out and February began, the New Year was no longer
            so little, but growing very fast. Still he frolicked with the children, and caused the
            snow that fell to be so very moist and soft that never were there finer snow-men than
            the boys and girls made. Often when they were rolling the big balls for these, <pb
              id="VAC2096-169" n="149"/> they wondered that they grew so fast and that it was so
            easy to push them along. That was because the New Year was helping them. And then, when
            a snow-man was finished, and, running into the house, they would bring out bits of
            charred fagots from the hearth and make two black eyes for his round white face and
            perhaps find a clay pipe for his mouth, the New Year would laugh like a chime of
            sleigh-bells."</p>
          <p>"The snow-man we made yesterday has eyes like that, and a pipe," said Arne, "only it
            was hard to make him stay together; the snow was so dry."</p>
          <p>"Ah, ha!" said Grandfather, with a twinkle in his eye, "so that is what <pb
              id="VAC2096-170" n="150"/> has become of my pipe? I missed it today."</p>
          <p>Arne reddened, "But Grandfather," he said, "you know it was only your old pipe; we
            thought maybe, as it was holiday time, you would be smoking your good one."</p>
          <p>"To be sure," said Grandfather, good-naturedly, though he really liked the old one
            best. "You may bring it to me now, Arne."</p>
          <p>The little boy slid from his seat and, running to a shelf, took down the pipe with a
            wonderful silver lid and two tassels of scarlet and green. Grandfather carefully filled
            it, and lighting it with a coal from the hearth, puffed slowly two or three times before
            he replied to Olga's <pb id="VAC2096-171" n="151"/> question, "But what else did the New
            Year do?"</p>
          <p>"Well," he said presently, "he did a great many things. Sometimes he amused himself by
            piling up the snow on all the forest trees, and the thatched roofs in the village, and
            the gate-posts and well-sweeps till it looked as if the whole world was made of white
            flakes. But the prettiest thing of all that he did was to fly about at night and cover
            everything with ice, so that in the morning, when the sun shone, the brightness
            everywhere was like the dazzling light of millions of diamonds. Of course other years
            have done this also, and you children have seen these wonderful icy mornings, but <pb
              id="VAC2096-172" n="152"/> never were there so many, or such magic ones, as in the
            time of The Good Year. And then, when the nights were clear and starry, he loved to get
            Jack Frost, and between them such beautiful white pictures as they painted on our
            village windows!"</p>
          <p>"Did you see our windows today, Grandfather?" asked Olga. "One of them had a frost
            picture of a mountain and a river, and some houses, and a little pasture all full of
            woolly sheep!"</p>
          <p>"Yes," said Arne, "and we heated a copper penny at the hearth, and played that we
            burned down the houses when we held it on them and melted a hole to see through!"</p>
          <pb id="VAC2096-173" n="153"/>
          <p>Grandfather smiled gently as he puffed slowly at his pipe, still thinking of The Good
            Year. Then he went on, "When March came with his blustering winds, The Good Year saw to
            it that they blew only the dead limbs from the forest trees, so there were always plenty
            of fagots and even the poorest village people could keep blazing fires on their hearths.
            Then, by and by, the April sands began to run; and The Good Year&mdash;for by this time
            people no longer called him the New Year, but had begun already to give him the name he
            afterward went by&mdash;breathed a warm breath over the earth, and '<hi rend="i">Crack!
              Crack!</hi>' the ice began to melt and break in the river <pb id="VAC2096-174" n="154"
            /> and crash over the cataract in great glittering sheets. Then everywhere the buds
            started to swell, till <hi rend="i">puff!</hi> out burst the cherry blossoms, and, by
            and by, the pear and apple bloom."</p>
          <p>At this, "Oh!" said Olga, "I almost forgot our apples!" And, jumping down from the
            settle, she went to the dresser and taking two of the pewter porringers and putting into
            them the roasted apples, their red skins fairly bursting with savory juice, she gave one
            to Arne,&mdash;for Grandfather did not wish any&mdash;and with the other for herself,
            climbed back to her place. As the children slowly dipped their spoons into the
            porringers, enjoying their <pb id="VAC2096-175" n="155"/> holiday treat, Grandfather
            went on, "The trees were a sight, the pink and white flowers so thick on every bough
            that there was hardly room for them to burst open. The village folk all said, 'See, what
            a wonderful year for fruit!' Then one day, when The Good Year was off attending to
            matters in a distant part of the world, along came Jack Frost meaning to play an evil
            trick.</p>
          <p>"He had grown jealous of hearing The Good Year praised, and determined to do something
            to injure his fair name. He had made up his mind to nip all the pretty blossoms so they
            could not grow, and no one that season would have any pears or apples or cherries. At
            dusk of that <pb id="VAC2096-176" n="156"/> day all the village knew that he had come,
            for he made the air so cold; and then, when the stars began to twinkle, they were in
            despair, because Jack Frost always chooses starry nights for his work.</p>
          <p>"But just as he was about to blight all the pink and white trees, The Good Year came
            flying back, and seizing him by his shining coat,&mdash;it looked like white wool, but
            was all made of hoar-frost&mdash;he shook him soundly. 'Jack Frost,' he said, 'I thought
            you were my friend; but you are a wicked fellow to slip here while I was away, and try
            to do this evil deed! It is all right for you to make the grass and trees sparkle on
            autumn mornings and to paint the <pb id="VAC2096-177" n="157"/> window-panes in winter,
            but you know very well you have no business to show yourself when the April sand is
            running in my hour-glass, and you shall not spoil my village people's fruit-trees! Now
            go away!' And with that he shook him again, and then putting him down, he swayed his
            hour-glass so the April sand was stirred, and at once a cloud came and a warm rain began
            to fall, and Jack Frost ran away as fast as he could, for fear he would melt, and he
            dared not show himself again till autumn."</p>
          <p>"I am glad Jack Frost didn't nip our apple-tree this year!" said Arne, as he dipped up
            the last spoonful from his porringer. "You know he <pb id="VAC2096-178" n="158"/> did
            the spring before, Grandfather, and we had no apples."</p>
          <p>"Yes," said Grandfather, "I remember. After The Good Year chased him away, he was
            afraid to show himself in the spring for a long time. Then came some bad years, who let
            him do as he pleased, and since then he has been growing tricky again, and one never
            knows just what he will do."</p>
          <p>"Go on about The Good Year," said Olga, as she put down the porringers.</p>
          <p>"Well, let me see," said Grandfather. "Oh yes, it was the May sand that soon began to
            run, and the woods were carpeted with big, blue violets on long pale green stems, <pb
              id="VAC2096-179" n="159"/> and golden cuckoo-buds, and white wind-flowers, and the
            children filled their May-baskets and hung them on everybody's door. Then they went to
            the green and sang and danced around the May-pole which the village folk had raised and
            trimmed with gay garlands. And I remember how pretty little Elsa, the apothecary's
            daughter, looked as she danced in her white sprigged frock and red shoes; and how
            Hendrick, the parson's little boy, held her hand tightly all the while and danced with
            her and looked at her as if he thought her sweeter than a Christmas sugar-plum! That was
            a great Maytime for fairy rings, too; every day the big meadow would be <pb
              id="VAC2096-180" n="160"/> full of the tall circles of deep green grass showing where
            the fairies had danced by moonlight; and you know when the fairies dance a great deal it
            always means a lucky season."</p>
          <p>"I wish I could see some fairies!" said Olga wistfully.</p>
          <p>"Bless me!" cried Grandfather, in surprise. "Have you never? Why, I had seen a number
            when I was no bigger than you. Of course I can't see them now, because it's only to
            children the fairies ever show themselves."</p>
          <p>"I saw one last summer," said Arne.</p>
          <p>"Where?" asked Olga, enviously.</p>
          <p>"It was one day when I was going through the forest," answered Arne, <pb
              id="VAC2096-181" n="161"/> "and under a big hemlock tree there was a tuft of moss and
            something bright that I thought was some kind of a flower I had never seen before. But
            when I came nearer, I saw it was a fairy sitting in a little spot of sunlight and
            singing all to himself."</p>
          <p>"How big was he?" asked Olga.</p>
          <p>"Why, I should think he would have been about half as high as my knee if he had stood
            up, and he had on a little green suit with a red cap and mantle. In a minute he spied
            me, and jumped away and hid under a toad-stool, and I went on and pretended not to see
            him, for I didn't want to frighten him."</p>
          <p>"That was right," said <pb id="VAC2096-182" n="162"/> Grandfather, "for fairies are
            generally kind, friendly little creatures, and it would be a pity to frighten them. It
            is pretty to see them; and that fairy of yours, Arne, reminds me of one I saw when I was
            about your size. This one was sitting in the forest, too, only he was dressed all in
            sky-blue, and what do you suppose he was doing?"</p>
          <p>"I don't know," said Arne.</p>
          <p>"Well," said Grandfather, "a white butterfly was resting on his knee, and the fairy had
            a dewy buttercup in one hand, and a little wisp of grass like a paint-brush in the
            other. With this he was mixing the golden powder in the heart of the buttercup with the
            drops of dew and <pb id="VAC2096-183" n="163"/> painting the butterfly's wings a
            beautiful bright yellow. I knew then where the pretty yellow butterflies came from."</p>
          <p>"Do you think the fairies paint all the butterflies?" asked Olga.</p>
          <p>"I have no doubt of it," answered Grandfather. And then, as the little wreaths of smoke
            floated upward from his pipe, he went on. "But I haven't finished yet about The Good
            Year. You know his June sand was beginning to run and he was fairly well grown by that
            time; for years have to grow very fast, as they are always quite old at the end of the
            twelve months. So, as the year had passed his childhood, he was more interested in the
            doings <pb id="VAC2096-184" n="164"/> of the young people than of the boys and girls as
            he had been at first.</p>
          <p>"When the roses were all in bloom and midsummer night came, there was a full moon, and
            all the young folks went to dance on the village green where the May-pole had been. It
            was a fine sight, the girls looking so handsome in their holiday bodices and starched
            petticoats, and their gay flowered kerchiefs and embroidered aprons; and the young men
            in their velvet jackets and knee breeches with silver braid and buttons.</p>
          <p>"The Good Year watched them for a while, and then he quietly flew over to the church
            and into the belfry where the big bell was hanging. <pb id="VAC2096-185" n="165"/> 'My
            friend,' he said, 'you have a fine deep voice, and I remember how musically you rang the
            night I was born. And I have heard you calling the people to church on Sundays. But are
            there not other things for which you ring?'</p>
          <p>"'Yes,' answered the bell, slowly and softly, 'I sometimes toll for funerals.'</p>
          <p>"'No, no!' cried The Good Year quickly, with a sudden frown, 'that is not what I mean!
            You shall not toll again so long as I live! You know I have never used my scythe in this
            village, and I never shall.'</p>
          <p>"And didn't he, Grandfather?" asked Arne, opening his eyes.</p>
          <p>"No," said Grandfather, "that <pb id="VAC2096-186" n="166"/> was the strange thing! Not
            a single person in the village died that whole year! Such a thing has never happened
            before or since, and wasn't that reason enough to call him 'The Good Year'? Of course he
            had to use his scythe somewhere in the world, but it seemed he could not bear to harm
            any one in our village. So when he said to the bell that he would not hear it toll, it
            was dumb with amazement, but soon recovered itself and tinkled, as with soft laughter,
            when he asked again, 'But is there not something else for which you ring?'</p>
          <p>"'To be sure,' answered the bell, 'there are weddings!'</p>
          <p>"'That is it!' said The Good Year, <pb id="VAC2096-187" n="167"/> in a pleased tone. 'I
            want to hear you peal for a wedding. Is it possible that none of those handsome young
            people down there on the green are thinking of such a thing?'</p>
          <p>"'Of course they are!' answered the bell. 'I know of several young couples who would
            like nothing better. But none of them are ready yet to marry, except Jan Viborg down
            there&mdash;that tall, awkward fellow in the green jacket&mdash;and Frieda, the
            school-master's daughter,&mdash;he is dancing with her now; she is the prettiest girl in
            the village'&mdash;</p>
          <p>"<hi rend="i">Jan Viborg, and Frieda?</hi>" interrupted Olga, sitting up straight.
            "Why, Grandfather, that was <hi rend="i">your</hi>
            <pb id="VAC2096-188" n="168"/> name, and&mdash;and <hi rend="i">Grandmother's</hi>!"</p>
          <p>"Well, child," went on Grandfather, with a dreamy smile, "perhaps it was,&mdash;but the
            bell wasn't through talking. 'Jan,' it said, 'has a small farm at the edge of the
            village, and he has built a little wooden house with his own hands, and has carved its
            beams and rafters and door-posts, and he has made carved chairs, and a bench, and table,
            and a clothes-press and dresser all ready to begin housekeeping; and Frieda's
            linen-chest is filled with fine things of her own spinning and weaving, and her bridal
            crown and silver necklace are all ready, and a wonderful embroidered apron for her
            wedding day, and yet they have <pb id="VAC2096-189" n="169"/> not married though they
            have been betrothed these three years.'</p>
          <p>"'What is the matter?' asked The Good Year.</p>
          <p>"'Well,' answered the bell, 'Jan's little farm is not quite paid for, and for two years
            the harvest has failed so he could not free the debt, and they have been afraid to marry
            till they knew this summer's harvest would be plentiful.'</p>
          <p>"'Oh,' said The Good Year, 'if that is all that troubles them, they need have no fear;
            I will see to the harvest.' With that, he slyly caught hold of the bell-rope and softly
            rang a joyous peal or two, as for a wedding.</p>
          <p>"The young folks down on the <pb id="VAC2096-190" n="170"/> green heard it, and stopped
            dancing, to listen. 'Hark!' they said, 'it must be the midsummer fairies ringing the
            bell!' And then they laughed and chattered of the pranks the fairies play on midsummer
            night,&mdash;but Jan and Frieda took it for a luck sign; they pressed each other's hands
            and looked into each other's faces, and&mdash;well&mdash;never mind what they said, but
            all fear about the debt and the harvest vanished, and it was settled the church-bell
            should really peal for a wedding in a week's time."</p>
          <p>"And did they have it then?" asked Arne.</p>
          <p>"Yes, indeed!" said Grandfather. "And never was there so beautiful <pb id="VAC2096-191"
              n="171"/> a bride as Frieda, or so proud and happy a bridegroom as Jan."</p>
          <p>Grandfather still spoke of himself that way, for looking back so many years to his own
            youth, it seemed to him almost like talking of some one else.</p>
          <p>"You know, Grandfather," said Olga, "Mother keeps Grandmother Frieda's bridal crown and
            necklace and embroidered apron in the chest yonder, and she says when I grow up and am
            married, I am to wear them, just as she and Grandmother did on their wedding days."</p>
          <p>But Grandfather did not hear; his thoughts had flown back to the time, scarcely more
            than a twelvemonth from his own wedding, when there <pb id="VAC2096-192" n="172"/> came
            a cruel year who swung his scythe in the happy village, till at last the church-bell
            tolled for beautiful Frieda's funeral, and Grandfather was left with her little baby
            girl, who was to grow up and be the mother of Arne and Olga.</p>
          <p>Grandfather's eyes were misty with tears, but, straightening up, he hastily brushed
            them away so the children might not see them; and then stirring the ashes of his pipe,
            which he had quite forgotten for a while, with a brave smile he went on. "Of course
            Frieda and Jan had a fine wedding feast for the village folk, and there was music and
            dancing all day long. The little <pb id="VAC2096-193" n="173"/> children, too, played
            and frolicked and enjoyed it all, and I must tell you what happened the very next day.
            You remember I told you how Hendrick, the parson's son, and Elsa, the apothecary's
            daughter, danced together around the May-pole? Well, Hendrick was eight years old and
            Elsa six, and they had been sweethearts ever since they could toddle. So the day after
            the wedding they decided they would like to be married too. The parson's children had a
            playhouse in the corner of the garden, and Hendrick said they could live in that; then
            Elsa ran to her home and filled the pockets of her little apron with sugar buns which
            she said would do <pb id="VAC2096-194" n="174"/> for their wedding cake, and they were
            all ready.</p>
          <p>"But when Hendrick went in to ask his father to marry them, the parson only laughed and
            told him to run out and play. Of course Hendrick was angry," went on Grandfather,
            smiling a bit to himself, "but Elsa told him not to mind it, for she had an uncle who
            was a parson and lived in the next village, only ten miles away. She said he always gave
            them sugar-plums at Christmas time and told them pretty stories, and she was quite sure
            he would marry them and not make fun of them. So, taking hold of hands, the poor little
            things set out.</p>
          <p>"Elsa did not know the way, only <pb id="VAC2096-195" n="175"/> that they must cross
            the river at the edge of the village. When they reached it, Hendrick looked about for a
            boat, and saw an old skiff, with one oar in it, tied to a tree on the bank. He managed
            to unfasten it, and they both climbed in and Hendrick tried to lift the oar; but he
            could do nothing with it, and the skiff began to drift down the river."</p>
          <p>"<hi rend="i">But the cataract</hi>, Grandfather?" interrupted Olga. "<hi rend="i">They
              might go over it</hi>!"</p>
          <p>"Yes," said Grandfather, gravely, "that was just the trouble, for it would have been
            certain death. The skiff kept drifting nearer and nearer, and soon the children heard
            the roar of the falling water, and <pb id="VAC2096-196" n="176"/> they were terribly
            frightened. Elsa began to scream, and a woodcutter in the forest beyond heard her, and
            throwing down his ax, he hurried toward the river. He was terror stricken when he saw
            the skiff with the two helpless children, for he had no boat, and even if he had had
            one, it seemed impossible to save them.</p>
          <p>"But just when the woodcutter had given up hope, The Good Year, who had been looking
            after the grain fields beyond the forest, came flying along and saw the danger."</p>
          <p>"What did he do?" asked Arne.</p>
          <p>"Why," replied Grandfather, "he quickly whirled his hour-glass round and round, just as
            he did when he caught Jack Frost, only <pb id="VAC2096-197" n="177"/> faster; and the
            June sand, which was running in a smooth stream, suddenly twisted and fell all
            topsy-turvy, and immediately a great funnel-like black cloud rolled up in the sky and a
            fierce blast of wind rushed up the river. Stronger and stronger it blew, till, with the
            force of a hurricane, catching the little skiff as if it were an egg-shell, it tossed it
            up on the bank and out jumped the children, not two yards from the brink of the
            cataract! The wood-cutter gathered them in his arms and carried them all the way home,
            though they were a good load. He said that when the wind blew along the river, the mist
            from the cataract rose like two great white wings;&mdash; <pb id="VAC2096-198" n="178"/>
            he did not know it, but they were the wings of the The Good Year."</p>
          <p>"I suppose his invisible cap came off when he was twisting the hour-glass," said Olga,
            "so the wood-cutter could see the wings."</p>
          <p>"I dare say that was the way of it," said Grandfather.</p>
          <p>"Did Hendrick and Elsa ever get married?" went on the little girl.</p>
          <p>"To be sure!" answered Grandfather. "But that was years after, when they grew up, and a
            handsome young couple they were."</p>
          <p>"Did The Good Year keep his promise about the harvest?" asked Arne.</p>
          <p>"Of course he kept his promise," said Grandfather. "All through <pb id="VAC2096-199"
              n="179"/> July and August the wheat and oats and barley grew and ripened, till the
            fields looked like gold and silver. When the sun shone too hot, The Good Year shook his
            hour-glass till showers came, and there was no burning drought as in the bad years
            before. In the autumn, when everything from all the fields and orchards was gathered,
            and the village folk trimmed the church for the harvest festival, never were seen such
            golden sheaves or such red-cheeked apples; and everybody thanked the good God for
            sending them such a wonderful year. And not only was there plenty for the village, but
            plenty for the forest creatures, too; so the wolves were <pb id="VAC2096-200" n="180"/>
            satisfied to stay in their hiding places and did not trouble us."</p>
          <p>"Why, Grandfather," said Arne, with round eyes, "would they come out of the forest
            then?"</p>
          <p>"Indeed they would!" answered Grandfather. "In those days, when their food was scarce,
            they would often come at night and rob our sheep-folds; and sometimes, when things were
            very bad with them, they would even venture boldly into the village in broad
            daylight."</p>
          <p>"Did you ever see one do that?" asked Olga.</p>
          <p>"No," said Grandfather, "I didn't see it myself, but I remember well one day when it
            happened. It was the time of a bad year, and little Lief, <pb id="VAC2096-201" n="181"/>
            the shop-keeper's son, was playing in the door-yard of their cottage, which was on the
            edge of the village, when suddenly a gaunt, hungry wolf came running from the forest,
            and seizing little Lief's jacket in his teeth, was about to carry him off. But little
            Lief screamed so loud that his elder brother heard him, and hurrying out with a big
            cudgel bravely drove away the wolf. Little Lief was so frightened that it was many weeks
            before he would play outdoors again, and then he never would go alone. Indeed, all the
            rest of that year, the village people were afraid to let their children out of their
            sight."</p>
          <p>Arne and Olga each drew a long <pb id="VAC2096-202" n="182"/> breath, and "Oh!" cried
            Olga, "I should think you <hi rend="i">would</hi> have been glad of a Good Year that
            kept the wolves away!"</p>
          <p>Grandfather puffed at his pipe in silence for a few minutes, and then he said, "But he
            was growing old and tired, and by the time the December sand began to run, his hair and
            long beard were as white as his mantle, and every day the scythe and hour-glass seemed
            to be heavier to carry. Of course the things he must look after over all the world were
            a great care to him, and though he tried hard, he could not please everybody, especially
            as now and then he was obliged to swing the great scythe. But he was <pb
              id="VAC2096-203" n="183"/> pleased when he heard the people of our village call him
            'The Good Year'; he would smile to himself, and say how glad he was that he had been
            able at least to make this little place happy. There was only one thing more he wanted
            to see, and that was that we had a merry Christmas. 'After that,' he would say to
            himself, 'when my time is up, I shall be quite ready and willing to go.'</p>
          <p>"And did you have a fine Christmas? So fine as ours?" asked Arne.</p>
          <p>"Indeed, yes!" answered Grandfather, "the merriest ever seen! The harvest had been so
            bountiful, that the week before Christmas when we went to put up our sheaves <pb
              id="VAC2096-204" n="184"/> of oats and barley for the birds, it wasn't only to the
            cottage roofs we fastened them, as you children did, but we tied them, besides, in a
            golden fringe all around the eaves, and clusters nodded from even the fence posts; and
            the snow-birds came in great flocks for their holiday feast. And there was not a house
            in the village but had its Yule-log wound with greens, and a Christmas tree all trimmed
            with paper flowers and gay tinsel."</p>
          <p>"I don't believe they were any prettier than ours!" said Olga, looking toward the table
            where the fir-tree twinkled in the firelight.</p>
          <p>"No, no, child, perhaps not," said <pb id="VAC2096-205" n="185"/> Grandfather, "only
            everybody had one; and you know this year some folks in the village are too poor to trim
            a tree. And then how we danced and sang and feasted!" he went on, his mind, as old
            people's are apt to do, still dwelling on the golden past.</p>
          <p>"Did you have boiled fish and roast goose, like we have on Christmas?" asked Olga
            again.</p>
          <p>"Yes," answered Grandfather, "and fresh cinnamon bread, and sweet cheeses, and sugar
            cake, and ale and nuts and red apples. And then, in the evening, two little boys went
            around singing pretty carols, just as you and Svend Hardin did this year, Arne. Little
            Hendrick, <pb id="VAC2096-206" n="186"/> the parson's son was one, and I forget the
            other."</p>
          <p>"Were they dressed in white, like we were, and did they carry a star lantern and
            dolls?" interrupted Arne.</p>
          <p>"Yes," said Grandfather, "they wore little white suits, and Hendrick carried a lantern
            shaped like a star, in memory of the Star of Bethlehem, and the other little boy held
            two dolls dressed to represent the blessed Christ-child and his Mother, and the lads
            sang so sweetly,&mdash;though not sweeter than you did, Arne," added Grandfather,
            patting his hair&mdash;"and everybody praised them and gave them cakes and
            sugar-plums.</p>
          <p>"When the happy Christmas was <pb id="VAC2096-207" n="187"/> over, The Good Year smiled
            contentedly; his last wish had been fulfilled and he was quite satisfied to go, for he
            knew the December sands were almost run. But the village people mourned about it. They
            said he had made them so happy, they wished he would never fly away. I think we dreaded
            the New Year a bit, for one never knows what sorrows the new-comer may have in
            store.</p>
          <p>"When The Good Year saw that there was only a tiny trickle of sand left in the upper
            half of his hour-glass, he folded his white mantle about him and put down the scythe,
            which he knew he would soon be rid of; and we village folk went to <pb id="VAC2096-208"
              n="188"/> the church, where your father and mother are now, to watch until midnight,
            just as they are doing.</p>
          <p>"After the parson had finished the service, we all sat quietly till from the belfry
            came the first stroke of twelve, and the young men up there with the old bell-ringer
            began to beat on their drums.</p>
          <p>"Then we opened the door, and looked out across the snowy fields. Far away a white mist
            seemed to be rising. Up and up it floated, higher and higher. Some thought they could
            see in it two shining white wings, others a trailing white mantle, but nobody could tell
            for certain. Higher and higher it rose, drifting lightly across the moon, <pb
              id="VAC2096-209" n="189"/> and then beyond a cluster of golden stars, till at last it
            vanished in the deep blue midnight sky. So it was that The Good Year passed away from
            earth."</p>
          <p>When he had finished the story, Grandfather shut the silver lid of his holiday pipe and
            smoothed its gay tassels; then, leaning his head back on the settle, he closed his eyes;
            Arne and Olga crept up closer, nestling at either side of him, and soon all three were
            fast asleep. They slept so soundly that they did not hear when the bell struck for
            midnight, nor the booming of the New Year's drums. Nor did they hear the merry tinkling
            of the little silver bells as presently the sleighs <pb id="VAC2096-210" n="190"/> went
            flying by, taking the farmer folk to their homes. Indeed, they only wakened when the
            door opened and in came the father and mother, shaking off a flurry of twinkling
            snowflakes as they entered, and calling out, "<hi rend="i">A Happy New Year! A Happy,
              Happy New Year!</hi>"</p>
        </div2>
        <trailer rend="center">THE END</trailer>
      </div1>
    </body>
    <back>
      <pb id="VAC2096-211" n="[1]"/>
      <div1 type="advertisement">
        <head rend="center">Selections from L. C. Page &amp; Company's Books for Young People</head>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head rend="center b">THE BLUE BONNET SERIES</head>
          <p><hi rend="i">Each large 12mo, cloth decorative, illustrated, per volume</hi>
            <hi rend="right">$1.75</hi></p>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">A TEXAS BLUE BONNET</head>
            <p>By C<hi rend="sc">AROLINE</hi> E. J<hi rend="sc">ACOBS</hi>.</p>
            <p>"The book's heroine, Blue Bonnet, has the very finest kind of wholesome, honest,
              lively girlishness."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Chicago Inter-Ocean</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">BLUE BONNET'S RANCH PARTY</head>
            <p>By C<hi rend="sc">AROLINE</hi> E. J<hi rend="sc">ACOBS AND</hi> E<hi rend="sc"
                >DYTH</hi> E<hi rend="sc">LLERBECK</hi> R<hi rend="sc">EAD</hi>.</p>
            <p>"A healthy, natural atmosphere breathes from every chapter."&mdash;<hi rend="i"
                >Boston Transcript</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">BLUE BONNET IN BOSTON</head>
            <p>By C<hi rend="sc">AROLINE</hi> E. J<hi rend="sc">ACOBS AND</hi> L<hi rend="sc"
                >ELA</hi> H<hi rend="sc">ORN</hi> R<hi rend="sc">ICHARDS</hi>.</p>
            <p>"It is bound to become popular because of its wholesomeness and its many human
                touches."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Boston Globe</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">BLUE BONNET KEEPS HOUSE</head>
            <p>By C<hi rend="sc">AROLINE</hi> E. J<hi rend="sc">ACOBS AND</hi> L<hi rend="sc"
                >ELA</hi> H<hi rend="sc">ORN</hi> R<hi rend="sc">ICHARDS</hi>.</p>
            <p>"It cannot fail to prove fascinating to girls in their teens."&mdash;<hi rend="i">New
                York Sun</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">BLUE BONNET&mdash;DÉBUTANTE</head>
            <p>By L<hi rend="sc">ELA</hi> H<hi rend="sc">ORN</hi> R<hi rend="sc">ICHARDS</hi>.</p>
            <p>An interesting picture of the unfolding of life for Blue Bonnet.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">BLUE BONNET OF THE SEVEN STARS</head>
            <p>By L<hi rend="sc">ELA</hi> H<hi rend="sc">ORN</hi> R<hi rend="sc">ICHARDS</hi>.</p>
            <p>"The author's intimate detail and charm of narration gives the reader an interesting
              story of the heroine's war activities."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Pittsburgh Leader</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <pb id="VAC2096-212" n="2"/>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head rend="center b">THE HENRIETTA SERIES</head>
          <p rend="center">By L<hi rend="sc">ELA</hi> H<hi rend="sc">ORN</hi> R<hi rend="sc"
              >ICHARDS</hi>.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Each one volume, 12mo, illustrated</hi>
            <hi rend="right">$1.90</hi></p>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">ONLY HENRIETTA</head>
            <p>"It is an inspiring story of the unfolding of life for a young girl&mdash;a story in
              which there is plenty of action to hold interest and wealth of delicate sympathy and
              understanding that appeals to the hearts of young and old."&mdash;<hi rend="i"
                >Pittsburgh Leader</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">HENRIETTA'S INHERITANCE</head>
            <p>"One of the most noteworthy stories for girls issued this season. The life of
              Henrietta is made very real, and there is enough incident in the narrative to balance
              the delightful characterization."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Providence Journal</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head rend="center b">STORIES BY I. M. B. OF K.</head>
          <p><hi rend="i">Each one volume, 12mo, illustrated</hi>
            <hi rend="right">$1.75</hi></p>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">THE YOUNG KNIGHT</head>
            <p>The clash of broad-sword on buckler, the twanging of bow-strings and the cracking of
              spears splintered by whirling maces resound through this stirring tale of knightly
              daring-do.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">THE YOUNG CAVALIERS</head>
            <p>"There have been many scores of books written about the Charles Stuarts of England,
              but never a merrier and more pathetic one than 'The Young Cavaliers.'"&mdash;<hi
                rend="i">Family Herald</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">THE KING'S MINSTREL</head>
            <p>"The interesting situations are numerous, and the spirit of the hero is one of
              courage, devotion and resource."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Columbus Dispatch</hi>.</p>
            <p>"It is told with spirit and action."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Buffalo Express</hi>.</p>
            <p>"The story will please all those who read it, and will be of particular interest for
              the boys for whom it was intended. It is a tale of devotion to an ideal of service and
              as such will appeal to youth."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Portage Register-Democrat</hi>.</p>
            <p>"There is a lofty ideal throughout, some court intrigue, a smattering of the
              decadence of the old church heads, and a readable story."&mdash;<hi rend="i"
                >Middletown Press</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <pb id="VAC2096-213" n="3"/>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head rend="center b">THE BOYS' STORY OF THE RAILROAD SERIES</head>
          <p rend="center">By B<hi rend="sc">URTON</hi> E. S<hi rend="sc">TEVENSON</hi></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Each large 12mo, cloth decorative, illustrated</hi>, <hi rend="right"
              >$1.75</hi></p>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">THE YOUNG SECTION-HAND; O<hi rend="sc">R</hi>, T<hi rend="sc">HE</hi>
                A<hi rend="sc">DVENTURES OF</hi> A<hi rend="sc">LLAN</hi> W<hi rend="sc"
              >EST</hi>.</head>
            <p>"The whole range of section railroading is covered in the story."&mdash;<hi rend="i"
                >Chicago Post</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">THE YOUNG TRAIN DISPATCHER</head>
            <p>"A vivacious account of the varied and often hazardous nature of railroad
                life."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Congregationalist</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">THE YOUNG TRAIN MASTER</head>
            <p>"It is a book that can be unreservedly commended to anyone who loves a good,
              wholesome, thrilling, informing yarn."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Passaic News</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">THE YOUNG APPRENTICE; O<hi rend="sc">R</hi>, A<hi rend="sc">LLAN</hi>
                W<hi rend="sc">EST'S</hi> C<hi rend="sc">HUM</hi>.</head>
            <p>"The story is intensely interesting."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Baltimore Sun</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head rend="center b">THE DAYS OF CHIVALRY SERIES</head>
          <p rend="center b">Of Worth While Classics for Boys and Girls</p>
          <p rend="center i">Revised and Edited for the Modern Reader</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Each large 12mo, illustrated and with a poster jacket in full color</hi>
            <hi rend="right">$2.00</hi></p>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">THE DAYS OF CHIVALRY</head>
            <p>By W. H. D<hi rend="sc">AVENPORT</hi> A<hi rend="sc">DAMS</hi>.</p>
            <p>"The hero is Aimery, son of a poor armorer, who becomes page to the Lord of Rulamort.
              It is a tale of wars, but a tale which brings peace; a peace and contentment in the
              knowledge that right, even in the darkest times, has survived and
                conquered."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Portland Express</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">THE CHAPLET OF PEARLS</head>
            <p>By C. M. Y<hi rend="sc">ONGE</hi>.</p>
            <p>Catherine de Medici and gay King Henri II; their sons Francois II, Charles IX, and
              Henri III; and finally the great and martial figure of Henri of Navarre are prominent
              in these pages.</p>
            <p>"A splendid piece of work, and lovers of French history will find it most agreeable
                reading."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Buffalo Courier and Express</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <pb id="VAC2096-214" n="4"/>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head rend="center b">BARBARA WINTHROP SERIES</head>
          <p>By H<hi rend="sc">ELEN</hi> K<hi rend="sc">ATHERINE</hi> B<hi rend="sc"
            >ROUGHALL</hi></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Each one volume, cloth decorative, 12mo, illustrated</hi>
            <hi rend="right">$1.75</hi></p>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">BARBARA WINTHROP AT BOARDING SCHOOL</head>
            <p>"The book has pleasing spontaneity, high ideals and wholesomeness."&mdash;<hi
                rend="i">New York Continent</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">BARBARA WINTHROP AT CAMP</head>
            <p>"High ideals and a real spirit of fun underlie the story, which will be a decided
              addition to the bookshelves of the young girl for whom a holiday gift is
                contemplated."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Los Angeles Saturday Night</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">BARBARA WINTHROP: GRADUATE</head>
            <p>There is in this new story gaiety and laughter, the light-heartedness of youth, with
              its little tragedies and a real mystery to complicate matters and make the days of
              Barbara Winthrop and her chums, Peggy and Jo, more alluring. A story of the highest
              order written by "a real girl" for girls, up-to-date in all that is helpful.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head rend="center b">DOCTOR'S LITTLE GIRL SERIES</head>
          <p rend="center">By M<hi rend="sc">ARION</hi> A<hi rend="sc">MES</hi> T<hi rend="sc"
              >AGGART</hi></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Each large 12mo, cloth, illustrated, per volume</hi>, <hi rend="right"
              >$1.75</hi></p>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">THE DOCTOR'S LITTLE GIRL</head>
            <p>"A charming story of the ups and downs of the life of a dear little maid."&mdash;<hi
                rend="i">The Churchman</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">SWEET NANCY: T<hi rend="sc">HE</hi> F<hi rend="sc">URTHER</hi> A<hi
                rend="sc">DVENTURES OF THE</hi> D<hi rend="sc">OCTOR'S</hi> L<hi rend="sc"
                >ITTLE</hi> G<hi rend="sc">IRL</hi>.</head>
            <p>"Just the sort of book to amuse, while its influence cannot but be
                elevating."&mdash;<hi rend="i">New York Sun</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">NANCY, THE DOCTOR'S LITTLE PARTNER</head>
            <p>"The story is sweet and fascinating, such as many girls of wholesome tastes will
                enjoy."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Springfield Union</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">NANCY PORTER'S OPPORTUNITY</head>
            <p>"Nancy shows throughout that she is a splendid young woman, with plenty of
                pluck."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Boston Globe</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">NANCY AND THE COGGS TWINS</head>
            <p>"The story is refreshing."&mdash;<hi rend="i">New York Sun</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <pb id="VAC2096-215" n="5"/>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head rend="center b">THE FRIENDLY TERRACE SERIES</head>
          <p rend="center">By H<hi rend="sc">ARRIET</hi> L<hi rend="sc">UMMIS</hi> S<hi rend="sc"
              >MITH</hi></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Each one volume, cloth, decorative, 12mo, illustrated, per volume</hi>
            <hi rend="right">$1.75</hi></p>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">THE GIRLS OF FRIENDLY TERRACE</head>
            <p>"It is a book that cheers, that inspires to higher thinking; it knits hearts; it
              unfolds neighborhood plans in a way that makes one tingle to try carrying them out,
              and most of all it proves that in daily life, threads of wonderful issues are being
              woven in with what appears the most ordinary of material, but which in the end brings
              results stranger than the most thrilling fiction."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Belle Kellogg
                Towne in The Young People's Weekly, Chicago</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">PEGGY RAYMOND'S VACATION</head>
            <p>"It is a clean, wholesome, hearty story, well told and full of incident. It carries
              one through experiences that hearten and brighten the day."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Utica,
                N. Y., Observer</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">PEGGY RAYMOND'S SCHOOL DAYS</head>
            <p>"It is a bright, entertaining story, with happy girls, good times, natural
              development, and a gentle earnestness of general tone."&mdash;<hi rend="i">The
                Christian Register, Boston</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">THE FRIENDLY TERRACE QUARTETTE</head>
            <p>"The story is told in easy and entertaining style and is a most delightful narrative,
              especially for young people. It will also make the older readers feel younger, for
              while reading it they will surely live again in the days of their youth."&mdash;<hi
                rend="i">Troy Budget</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">PEGGY RAYMOND'S WAY</head>
            <p>"The author has again produced a story that is replete with wholesome incidents and
              makes Peggy more lovable than ever as a companion and leader."&mdash;<hi rend="i"
                >World of Books</hi>.</p>
            <p>"It possesses a plot of much merit and through its 324 pages it weaves a tale of love
              and of adventure which ranks it among the best books for girls."&mdash;<hi rend="i"
                >Cohoes American</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <pb id="VAC2096-216" n="6"/>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head rend="center b">FAMOUS LEADERS SERIES</head>
          <p rend="center">By C<hi rend="sc">HARLE</hi>S H. L. J<hi rend="sc">OHNSTON</hi></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Each large 12mo, cloth decorative, illustrated, per volume</hi>
            <hi rend="right">$2.00</hi></p>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">FAMOUS CAVALRY LEADERS</head>
            <p>"More of such books should be written, books that acquaint young readers with
              historical personages in a pleasant, informal way."&mdash;<hi rend="i">New York
                Sun</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">FAMOUS INDIAN CHIEFS</head>
            <p>"Mr. Johnston has done faithful work in this volume, and his relation of battles,
              sieges and struggles of these famous Indians with the whites for the possession of
              America is a worthy addition to United States History."&mdash;<hi rend="i">New York
                Marine Journal</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">FAMOUS SCOUTS</head>
            <p>"It is the kind of a book that will have a great fascination for boys and young
                men."&mdash;<hi rend="i">New London Day</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">FAMOUS PRIVATEERSMEN AND ADVENTURERS OF THE SEA</head>
            <p>"The tales are more than merely interesting; they are entrancing, stirring the blood
              with thrilling force."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Pittsburgh Post</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">FAMOUS FRONTIERSMEN AND HEROES OF THE BORDER</head>
            <p>"The accounts are not only authentic, but distinctly readable, making a book of wide
              appeal to all who love the history of actual adventure."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Cleveland
                Leader</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">FAMOUS DISCOVERERS AND EXPLORERS OF AMERICA</head>
            <p>"The book is an epitome of some of the wildest and bravest adventures of which the
              world has known."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Brooklyn Daily Eagle</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">FAMOUS GENERALS OF THE GREAT WAR</head>
            <p>Who Led the United States and Her Allies to a Glorious Victory.</p>
            <p>"The pages of this book have the charm of romance without its unreality. The book
              illuminates, with lifelike portraits, the history of the World War."&mdash;<hi
                rend="i">Rochester Post Express</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <pb id="VAC2096-217" n="7"/>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head rend="center b">FAMOUS LEADERS SERIES (Con.)</head>
          <p rend="center">By E<hi rend="sc">DWIN</hi> W<hi rend="sc">ILDMAN</hi></p>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">THE FOUNDERS OF AMERICA (Lives of Great Americans from the Revolution to
              the Monroe Doctrine)</head>
            <p/>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">THE BUILDERS OF AMERICA (Lives of Great Americans from the Monroe
              Doctrine to the Civil War)</head>
            <p>"How can one become acquainted with the histories of some of the famous men of the
              United States? A very good way is to read these books by Edwin Wildman, wherein the
              life stories of fifteen men who founded our country are told."&mdash;<hi rend="i">New
                York Post</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">FAMOUS LEADERS OF CHARACTER (Lives of Great Americans from the Civil War
              to Today)</head>
            <p>". . . Is a book that should be read by every boy in the whole country. . .
                ."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Atlanta Constitution</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">FAMOUS LEADERS OF INDUSTRY.&mdash;First Series</head>
            <p>"Are these stories interesting? Let a boy read them; and tell you."&mdash;<hi
                rend="i">Boston Transcript</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">FAMOUS LEADERS OF INDUSTRY.&mdash;Second Series</head>
            <p>"These biographies drive home the truth that just as every soldier of Napoleon
              carried a marshal's baton in his knapsack, so every American youngster carries
              potential success under his hat."&mdash;<hi rend="i">New York World</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <opener rend="center">By C<hi rend="sc">HARLES</hi> L<hi rend="sc">EE</hi> L<hi
                rend="sc">EWIS</hi><lb/>
              <hi rend="i">Professor, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis</hi></opener>
            <head rend="b">FAMOUS AMERICAN NAVAL OFFICERS</head>
            <p rend="b">With a complete index.</p>
            <p>"In connection with the life of John Paul Jones, Stephen Decatur, and other famous
              naval officers, he groups the events of the period in which the officer distinguished
              himself, and combines the whole into a colorful and stirring narrative."&mdash;<hi
                rend="i">Boston Herald</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <pb id="VAC2096-218" n="8"/>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head rend="center b">STORIES BY EVALEEN STEIN</head>
          <p><hi rend="i">Each one volume, 12mo, illustrated</hi>
            <hi rend="right">$1.65</hi></p>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">THE CHRISTMAS PORRINGER</head>
            <p>This story happened many hundreds of years ago in the quaint Flemish city of Bruges
              and concerns a little girl named Karen.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">GABRIEL AND THE HOUR BOOK</head>
            <p>"No works in juvenile fiction contain so many of the elements that stir the hearts of
              children and grown-ups as well as do the stories so admirably told by this
                author."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Louisville Daily Courier</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">A LITTLE SHEPHERD OF PROVENCE</head>
            <p>"The story should be one of the influences in the life of every child to whom good
              stories can be made to appeal."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Public Ledger</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">THE LITTLE COUNT OF NORMANDY</head>
            <p>"This touching and pleasing story is told with a wealth of interest coupled with
              enlivening descriptions of the country where its scenes are laid."&mdash;<hi rend="i"
                >Wilmington Every Evening</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">WHEN FAIRIES WERE FRIENDLY</head>
            <p>"The stories are music in prose&mdash;they are like pearls on a chain of
              gold&mdash;each word seems exactly the right word in the right place; the stories sing
              themselves out, they are so beautifully expressed."&mdash;<hi rend="i">The Lafayette
                Leader</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">PEPIN: A Tale of Twelfth Night</head>
            <p>"A creation almost as perfect as her 'Christmas Porringer.'"&mdash;<hi rend="i"
                >Lexington Herald</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="part">
            <head rend="b">CHILDREN'S STORIES</head>
            <p>"The stories are light and fanciful and worthy of a place beside Grimm and Hans
              Andersen in the child's library."&mdash;<hi rend="i">Cincinnati Post</hi>.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
