<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd" xml:id="VAB7152">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sea-Thrift</title>
                <author>Radford, Dollie (1858-1920)</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcribed, encoded and edited by </resp>
                    <name>Perry Willett</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="bn">
                    <resp>E-text Editor</resp>
                    <name>Brian Norberg</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Corrected By</resp>
                    <name xml:id="elizabethmunson">Elizabeth Munson</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>TEI formatted filesize uncompressed: approx. 198 kbytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
                <date>January 6, 1998 </date>
                <idno>VAB7152</idno>
                <availability status="unknown">
                    <p>© 2009, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim
                        of copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women
                        Writers Project participants and other members of the university community.
                        Indiana University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.
                        Permission is granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce,
                        distribute or display the contributions to this work claimed by Indiana
                        University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is
                        included in its entirety. For inquiries about commercial uses, please
                        contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Digital Library Program</addrLine><addrLine>Main Library</addrLine><addrLine>Indiana University</addrLine><addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>EMail: diglib@indiana.edu</addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>Victorian Women Writers Project: an Electronic Collection</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Perry Willett, </name>
                    <resp>General Editor.</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>The transcribed copy is from the Research Collections, Indiana
                    University.</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Sea-Thrift</title>
                        <author>Radford, Dollie</author>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>by </resp>
                            <name>Dollie Radford </name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>133 p. </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Alexander Moring Limited </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>London </pubPlace>
                        <date when="1904">1904</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl><p><note n="false" xml:id="noPageImages">Page images not available for this text.</note></p>
                <p>All quotation marks, hyphens, dashes, apostrophes and colons have been
                    transcribed as entity references.</p>
                <p>All apostrophes and single right quotation marks are encoded as
                    &amp;rsquo;.</p>
                <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been removed; all hyphens are encoded
                    as &amp;hyphen; and em dashes as &amp;mdash;.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="address" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="addrline" occurs="3"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="body" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="byline" occurs="2"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="corr" occurs="6"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="div" occurs="2"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="div0" occurs="15"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="docauthor" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="docdate" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="docimprint" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="doctitle" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="emph" occurs="43"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="epigraph" occurs="3"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="figure" occurs="20"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="foreign" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="front" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="head" occurs="30"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="hi" occurs="16"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="l" occurs="92"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="lg" occurs="8"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="name" occurs="10"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="orig" occurs="5"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="p" occurs="977"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="pb" occurs="133"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="publisher" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="pubplace" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="q" occurs="12"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="term" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="text" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="titlepage" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="titlepart" occurs="2"/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                        <ptr target="http://authorities.loc.gov/"/>
                        <note>
                            <p>Library of Congress Subject Headings originate from the source MARC
                                record for the monograph when available.</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="mla">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Modern Language Association Thesaurus</title>
                        <ptr target="http://www.mla.org/publications/bibliography/howtouse_mlabiblio/howtosearchmlabiblio#mla" type="source"/>
                        <ptr target="http://dlib.indiana.edu/vocabulary/modernlangassocgenre/" type="webservice"/>
                        <note><p> The MLA Bibliography staff has created a thesaurus of over 50,000 terms and 200,000
                            names to ensure consistency in the terms and names assigned during indexing. The VWWP
                            project will utilize a subset of the MLA Thesaurus to assign genre headings to the VWWP
                            texts. </p></note>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#mla">
                <list>
                    <item><term ref="http://terminology.dlib.indiana.edu/vwwpgenre/fiction">fiction</term></item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change><date>17-Dec-1997</date><label>general editor.</label><name>Perry Willett,
                </name>finished TEI-conformant encoding, editing and proofing</change>
            <change><date>2005-02-06</date><label>Programmer</label><name>Mark Millard,
                </name>Converted from SGML to TEI-XML</change>
            <change when="2009-05-10" who="#bn">Coverted from P4 to P5</change>
            <change when="2009-10-27" who="#bn">Normalized id scheme and encoding</change>
            <change when="2010-07-29" who="elizabethmunson">Removed date from fileDesc title</change>
            <change when="2010-07-29" who="elizabethmunson">Corrected hyphen in fileDesc and sourceDesc titles</change>
            <change when="2010-07-29" who="elizabethmunson">Added LCNAF form of author name to sourceDesc (hyphen 
            adjusted for fileDesc)</change>
            <change when="2010-07-29" who="elizabethmunson">Normalized date in biblFull/publicationStmt</change>
            <change when="2010-09-03" who="elizabethmunson">Added genre term</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">SEA‐THRIFT </titlePart>
                    <titlePart type="sub">A FAIRY TALE</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <byline>BY <docAuthor>DOLLIE RADFORD</docAuthor></byline>
                <byline>WITH ILLUSTRATIONS BY GERTRUDE BRADLEY</byline>
                <docImprint>
                    <publisher>ALEXANDER MORING LIMITED
                        <address><addrLine>THE DE LA MORE PRESS</addrLine><addrLine>32 GEORGE STREET</addrLine><addrLine>HANOVER SQUARE</addrLine></address></publisher>
                    <pubPlace>LONDON W</pubPlace>
                </docImprint>
                <docDate>1904</docDate>
            </titlePage>
            <pb xml:id="VAB7152-001"/>
            <div type="dedication">
                <p>TO LUCY AND JOHN</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" xml:id="VAB7152-002"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
                <epigraph>
                    <l><hi>SEA‐THRIFT</hi> grows by the summer sea,</l>
                    <l rend="ti-2">Till the summer’s close,</l>
                    <l>On a grassy cliff, ’neath a radiant sky,</l>
                    <l rend="ti-1">While sun and summer and wind go by,</l>
                    <l rend="ti-1">Sea‐thrift blows and blows.</l>
                </epigraph>
                <p><hi>THE</hi> Sea‐thrift about which I am going to write was not a flower growing
                    on the cliff, it was a cottage standing in a garden at some distance from the
                    sea; but, like the sea‐thrift growing on the cliff, it was full of joy all the
                    summer through.</p>
                <pb n="2" xml:id="VAB7152-003"/>
                <p>One hot morning in August, at one of the great London stations, three children
                    were struggling with bundles of rugs, umbrellas, tennis‐rackets, and countless
                    packages, while their parents tried to take tickets at the booking‐office.</p>
                <p>Such crowds of parents and children were running away from the airless town: the
                    station people were distracted.</p>
                <p>Perhaps the intense heat tried them, and perhaps they were all longing for a
                    seaside holiday themselves. The porters, especially, were dreadfully cross, and
                    the three children decided that one of themselves would be beheaded or befooted,
                    or have some important limb broken, in the violent rushing of overladen trolleys
                    and men.</p>
                <p>The children were called “The Three Rs” because all their names began with an
                    R—Roger, Rachael, and Ruby.</p>
                <p>The Three Rs, then, who were determined children, had no intention of being left
                    behind this hot afternoon at the station, so they pushed vigorously through less
                    determined families and, by degrees, conveyed their smaller bundles and
                    belongings to the train.</p>
                <p>Ruby, the youngest of the three, was not quite satisfied with the manner of their
                    progress.</p>
                <p>“It seems so rude,” she said, when at last they breathed freely in front of an
                    empty carriage, “to push and poke like that.” She had begun by saying “I beg
                    your pardon,” politely, each time she was knocked by somebody against somebody
                    else; but this had <choice>
                        <orig>hap‐<pb n="3" xml:id="VAB7152-004"/> pened</orig>
                        <reg>happened</reg>
                    </choice> so often she grew tired of repeating it, and when at last a deaf old
                    gentleman—on to whose hat her umbrella by some strange manœuvre had hooked
                    itself—asked in a loud and angry voice why she was muttering, she gave it up
                    altogether, and finished her scramble like the others without any attempt at
                    apology.</p>
                <p>“Never mind,” said Roger, “we’ve found a carriage, and that’s the chief thing:
                    one <emph>must</emph> push and poke if one wants to go. Here we are,
                    father—mother—and there are your corner seats.”</p>
                <p>“You wonderful children,” exclaimed their father. “I went back to find you and
                    decided you were all lost! I never expected such luxury as this,” he continued
                    as he stepped into the carriage and leaned back in one of the precious corner
                    seats. “I thought we should probably travel in the guard’s van, or on the
                    engine.”</p>
                <p>“Well now,” said Roger, when they were seated comfortably in the carriage, and
                    the last package, a bursting hamper, had been placed on the seat beside him,
                    “let’s shut the door and have dinner.”</p>
                <p>“My dear son,” began his mother; and as she spoke a crowd of faces surged round
                    the door, and three more than its proper number of passengers suddenly filled
                    the compartment.</p>
                <p>“Must get in somewhere,” explained the extra ones as they squeezed themselves in
                    beside Roger, Rachael, and Ruby.</p>
                <p>The Three Rs contrived not to be quite squeezed out of their seats, but they
                    inwardly resented the situation.</p>
                <pb n="4" xml:id="VAB7152-005"/>
                <p>“There isn’t room to eat any dinner,” sighed Rachael, holding out her arms
                    stiffly in front of her.</p>
                <p>“Don’t let us be like the porters,” whispered Ruby anxiously.</p>
                <p>“I wonder what the porters have for dinner?” she went on aloud. “I hope they have
                    it comfortably all together.”</p>
                <p>“That is unlikely,” said her mother, from her safely‐secured corner. “I expect
                    they snatch it in picnic manner between whiles.”</p>
                <p>“Poor porters!” Ruby looked compassionately at the great army of them
                    disappearing now along the platform.</p>
                <p>“We’re off.”</p>
                <p>“Yes; we’re off.”</p>
                <p>“We shall soon be at Sea‐thrift—hurrah!”</p>
                <p>And in a few minutes the children had forgotten the porters, and the noisy
                    station, and the crowded, uncomfortable carriage, for they were really on their
                    way to the sea, to the fresh air and the fields—to their long‐promised
                    Sea‐thrift. Nothing is so sweet as the first few miles of country when one
                    travels out from the town on a summer holiday. The spirits of the Three Rs rose
                    higher and higher, as the train hurried along through miles and miles of green
                    fields, and left the miles and miles of houses behind them.</p>
                <p>Their train was determined to lose no time on the journey. It flew through the
                    little country stations and across the narrow bridges without stopping, and it
                    swayed from side to side in its haste like a ship at<pb n="5" xml:id="VAB7152-006"/> sea. But the Three Rs only laughed, and said: “We
                    shall be there directly.”</p>
                <p>It was a flat country through which they were whirled, and it showed them a great
                    stretch of summer sky, and they thought, as they looked at it, how clear and
                    blue it was and how delicate and beautiful the little fleecy clouds were away on
                    the horizon.</p>
                <p>By‐and‐by the banks on each side of the line grew red and yellow with poppies and
                    hawkweeds, and beyond the banks, on each side, cornfields shone like gold in the
                    sunshine.</p>
                <p>Then they came to a land of rivers, where white sails shone upon the water and
                    danced gaily along in a light wind; but their train never stopped. On and onward
                    it rushed, regardless of the pleasant things by the way.</p>
                <p>“How dreadfully tired it will be,” said Ruby, after a longer silence than
                    usual.</p>
                <p>“What is ‘it’?” asked Roger.</p>
                <p>“The train; don’t you think it must be out of breath by now?”</p>
                <p>“Oh dear, no,” answered Roger, laughing; “and if it were it would have to hurry
                    on just the same to keep its appointment.”</p>
                <p>“Appointment!” </p>
                <p>“With the station clock,” explained Roger. “It’s obliged to dash along with its
                    eyes shut.”</p>
                <p>When at last the train, after many hours, did stop, it was at the prettiest
                    little station the children had ever seen. Flower‐beds, full of blossom,
                    stretched along the<pb n="6" xml:id="VAB7152-007"/> gravel platform, and behind
                    the flowers were leafy trees. It was more like a cherished garden than a
                    station.</p>
                <p>“We’ve come, we’ve come.” The children clapped their hands and sprang up and
                    danced with delight in spite of the limited space.</p>
                <p>“Rachael, Rachael,” cried Ruby excitedly, quite forgetful of their
                    fellow‐travellers, “I <emph>do</emph> hope we shall find fairies here; don’t you
                    think we shall? <emph>Do</emph> say you think we shall!”</p>
                <p>Rachael looked critically at the flowers and trees.</p>
                <p>“I know you will find them here,” said a white‐haired old gentleman whom they had
                    not noticed in the carriage before. “I know you will,” he repeated, while
                    Rachael still looked doubtful. And in the bustle of leaving the closely‐packed
                    compartment, the white‐haired old gentleman slipped away without further
                    explanation. He was wise, perhaps, in doing this, for Ruby had thought of some
                    searching questions, while the bundles were being collected and the door handle
                    turned; and when Ruby asked questions she insisted upon clear answers.</p>
                <p>“Who is he?” asked the children eagerly, as they passed through the little
                    booking‐office into a sweet country road. “What a dear old man! Does he live
                    here—shall we see him sometimes?”</p>
                <p>“I hope not,” smiled their mother. “He is the doctor.”</p>
                <p>A sudden silence fell upon the party. Measles and whooping‐cough, and lesser
                    complaints, had <choice>
                        <orig>in‐<pb n="7" xml:id="VAB7152-008"/> terrupted</orig>
                        <reg>interrupted</reg>
                    </choice> several terms and obliged them to put aside their books; and once
                    Rachael had been so ill‐advised as to have bronchitis on a Christmas holiday,
                    and thereby missed a Christmas tree and a bran pie. These misfortunes, however,
                    had been borne without complaint, especially the interruption of the school
                    work; but the idea of being pursued by illness on a seaside holiday had never
                    before been presented to them, and they dismissed it in serious silence.</p>
                <p>Then they jumped, light‐hearted once more, into the trap which had come to meet
                    them, and bowled along grassy roads, across commons, and through sweet‐smelling
                    lanes, till they came to a cottage with “Sea‐thrift” printed neatly on its
                    garden gate.</p>
                <p>The cottage was covered with fuchsia and white jasmine, and over its porch roses
                    and honeysuckle hung in masses of blossom.</p>
                <p>The children opened the gate and stepped soberly into the garden—their very own
                    garden—they could not believe in it now they saw it. So long had they imagined
                    and talked of a garden of their very own—a garden by the sea, a garden full of
                    flowers and birds and butterflies—that when they actually saw it they could
                    scarcely believe in its reality. Until now the Three Rs had spent their summer
                    holidays in seaside lodgings; and, however nice seaside lodgings may be, and
                    however kind a seaside landlady may be, there never can be anything so lovely as
                    a garden of one’s very own.</p>
                <p>The father and mother of the Three Rs went<pb n="8" xml:id="VAB7152-009"/>
                    quietly into the cottage, leaving the children to accustom themselves to this
                    happier new arrangement; and the children walked up the broad gravel path, hand
                    in hand, and looked round their garden without speaking.</p>
                <p>There was a great deal in it at which to look. On each side of the path was a
                    wide border of flowers: giant thistles, sunflowers, hollyhocks, and scarlet
                    gladioli; making a flowery hedge at the back of each bed; with marigolds,
                    larkspurs, love‐in‐a‐mist, old man, sweet‐peas, and masses of bloom for which
                    the Three Rs had no name, filling in the spaces between the hedge and the thick
                    row of pink flowers which ran along the bed close to the path. This was the
                    “sea‐thrift,” from which the cottage had its name, and this they knew and
                    greeted joyously. Their seriousness vanished as they stooped down to touch
                    it.</p>
                <p>Then they walked up the path to the porch, and here, on the other side of the
                    flower hedge, was a big lawn for games and sports, and along one side of the
                    lawn was a row of leafy trees. Beyond the other border of flowers was a
                    vegetable garden, stocked with vegetables and fruits, and in the middle of this
                    was a well. To the well they, of course, rushed, and were much disappointed to
                    find its lid securely fastened.</p>
                <p>“Why, where is the bucket,” exclaimed Roger, “and the rope, and pulley? Why, it
                    isn’t a proper well after all.”</p>
                <p>“It dried up,” said a voice from the cottage; “it is a deep pit now. We had the
                    lid fastened because we didn’t want anyone to tumble in: it is very very
                    deep.”</p>
                <pb n="9" xml:id="VAB7152-010"/>
                <p>“Oh! what a pity,” came in chorus from the well.</p>
                <p>“I can’t agree with you,” answered the voice. “But come in now, tea is ready; you
                    have not seen the inside of your house.”</p>
                <p>Roger and Rachael ran in to make further discoveries, but Ruby lingered
                    thoughtfully beside the well. She stood so long and so quietly beside it, that a
                    robin flew from the ivy on the wall and perched upon the bar, from which the
                    bucket should have been hanging, and began to sing. He looked at Ruby, as though
                    he expected her to understand what he was saying.</p>
                <p>“You are a little dear,” she said gently; “but what <emph>is</emph> the use of a
                    well that has no water in it and doesn’t work?”</p>
                <p>The robin stopped singing and put his head on one side.</p>
                <p>“Of course, <emph>you</emph> don’t know,” she laughed, “and if you did you
                    couldn’t tell me; but I can’t think of anything else to say to you.”</p>
                <p>Ruby always talked to the creatures with whom she came in contact, and she held
                    out her hand to the robin, expecting him to come and be stroked like her pets at
                    home; but he made no more advances. He was offended, perhaps, at having his
                    ignorance so quickly taken for granted. Whatever may have been the reason, he
                    suddenly flew off and disappeared among the bushes.</p>
                <p>“Good‐bye,” called Ruby after him, “I’ll play hide‐and‐seek with you to‐morrow.”
                    And she turned to the house to join the exploring party indoors.</p>
                <pb n="10" xml:id="VAB7152-011"/>
                <p>Indoors, there were many things to discover. Though there were but few rooms in
                    the cottage, there were, in all the rooms, and up the steep little staircase,
                    the funniest little shelves and cupboards in the world. They were in all kinds
                    of unexpected places, and it took the children quite a long time to find
                    them.</p>
                <p>From the window at the top of the stairs they looked across a barley field to the
                    sea. How big and blue and beautiful it was! Far away two or three ships seemed
                    to be sailing from it into the clouds. The children stayed at the window a long
                    time, until their father called them into a room overlooking the garden in front
                    of the cottage.</p>
                <p>“There is the ruined Priory.”</p>
                <p>And there, beyond another barley field, in a great meadow of ripening wheat, was
                    a pile of old buildings overgrown with ivy. The wheat field was on rising
                    ground, and at the top of the slope stood the Priory church, looking down upon
                    the village and over the spreading country around it.</p>
                <p>“Is it <emph>very</emph> old, father?”</p>
                <p>“Hundreds of years old. I will tell you all about it one day. How sweetly that
                    robin sings!”</p>
                <p>For Ruby’s little friend was again perched on the top of the well, singing with
                    all his might.</p>
                <p>“I think I know all about it now,” said Ruby suddenly.</p>
                <p>“About which?”</p>
                <p>“The well.”</p>
                <pb n="11" xml:id="VAB7152-012"/>
                <p>“The well!” By this time everyone had forgotten the well.</p>
                <p>“I think the fairies live in it, and the robin knows, and is trying to tell us
                    about them.”</p>
                <p>The Three Rs leaned eagerly out of the window to listen more attentively to the
                    singer, but although they listened patiently for some time none of them could
                    translate his song.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="12" xml:id="VAB7152-013"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>CHAPTER II</head>
                <p><hi>THE</hi> children next morning were up betimes. Before eight o’clock they had
                    explored the village, climbed all over the ruined Priory, and set up their
                    bathing‐tent upon the sand, ready for occupation; and they had carried down to
                    the seashore a real shrimping net, two small camp‐chairs, a good‐sized wooden
                    bench, and a boat of Roger’s own making, which last was believed capable of
                    carrying the whole family in safety, and in turn, through smooth water.</p>
                <p>“Well now,” said Roger, as soon as the family was assembled that morning at
                    breakfast, “let’s plan out the day. Directly we’ve finished we’ll have footer on
                    the lawn, then we’ll bathe and try the boat, then we’ll have rounders, then
                    we’ll come up and go for a bicycle ride, and then—well—what shall we do then,
                    mother? ”</p>
                <p>“It may, perhaps, be dinner‐time by then,” suggested his mother.</p>
                <p>“Oh yes, of course.” Dinner seemed a remote possibility at this time of day, and
                    Roger dismissed<pb n="13" xml:id="VAB7152-014"/> the thought of it lightly.
                    “Well, dinner won’t take long, and we can go for another ride directly
                    afterwards, and I must get in a second bathe in the afternoon, and we mustn’t
                    forget tennis. You’ll soon be ready to come down to the sea, won’t you, mother?”
                    he continued, still busy with the porridge course.</p>
                <p>“There is the housekeeping—” began his mother from behind the coffee‐pot.</p>
                <p>“Oh, <emph>that</emph> won’t take more than a minute,” interrupted the children
                    simultaneously; “we can all help.”</p>
                <p>“Thank you, dears, very much; but I can’t help believing I shall do it more
                    quickly alone. When you have had your footer you had better go down to the sea
                    and I will come as soon as I can.”</p>
                <p>So when breakfast and football were over the children began packing up for the
                    beach. It was an elaborate packing, there were so many things to take. First of
                    all there were biscuits and fruit; the fruit had to be first picked from the
                    garden bushes, and the selection of it, with attendant discussion, took a long
                    time. Then bathing‐dresses and towels had to be rescued from the depths of
                    unpacked boxes, and books had to be drawn up through masses of clothes, in case
                    the party should want something to read if it happened to be resting for a few
                    moments. Then Ruby insisted upon finding her knitting, and Roger undertook the
                    discovery of the bicycle foot‐pump. Each of these last quests took a long time,
                    and proved so exhausting, that when, at the end of two hours, the children
                        were<pb n="14" xml:id="VAB7152-015"/> ready to start for the beach, they
                    declared they must be revived by a first lunch before anything more could be
                    done. At last they really were ready, and made a start, and as they reached the
                    gate they discovered their mother had been writing letters for ever so long at
                    the open window.</p>
                <p>“The housekeeping is done,” she said, smiling.</p>
                <p>“But, mother, to‐day doesn’t count, you know, we had so much to do. We shall be
                    ready in a few minutes to‐morrow. Where is father?”</p>
                <p>“On the beach, waiting.”</p>
                <p>Then they did all set out for the bathing tent; and in about ten minutes were
                    standing beside a smooth, blue sea. They were splendid sands which ran along
                    there below the cliffs; on either hand they stretched as far as the eye could
                    see. The children looked and laughed for joy.</p>
                <p>“We can see the North Pole from here,” said Rachael, who had lately won a prize
                    for geography. “It’s over there,” she added, pointing to the horizon.</p>
                <p>“What is it like to look at?” asked Ruby severely.</p>
                <p>Ruby never could see objects which were pointed out to her in views, and at home
                    always missed the Crystal Palace in the landscape which was shown to visitors
                    from the top windows.</p>
                <p>“I don’t want to see it, thank you,” she always said when they pointed and
                    explained. It tired her to search the distance for things which could not be
                    properly seen when discovered.</p>
                <pb n="15" xml:id="VAB7152-016"/>
                <p>“I do hope we can’t see it,” she said again a little anxiously; “but, of course,
                    we can’t, except on the map.”</p>
                <p>“No; of course we can’t <emph>really</emph> see it,” interposed Rachael hastily;
                    “but if we <emph>could</emph> see it it’s nice to know we should see it from
                    here.”</p>
                <p>“I don’t feel sure,” said Ruby.</p>
                <p>Then Ruby looked thoughtful and turned to Roger; and from her expression Roger
                    divined she was about to ask him questions concerning the poles and the equator
                    and the circumference of the earth, so he caught hold of her by the shoulders
                    and made her run briskly to the tent.</p>
                <p>“Be quick and undress, Ruby, you shall make the trial trip in the boat; there’s a
                    treat for you!”</p>
                <p>Ruby looked even more thoughtful as she passed Roger’s boat, and saw the gaping
                    cracks in its keel and sides.</p>
                <p>The boat was of Roger’s unaided manufacture, and, in form, resembled a
                    washing‐tub. It had a stern at each end, and it was puttied lavishly, and
                    painted all over, though not very evenly, with white paint.</p>
                <p>It was called <name>The Recruit</name>, and its name was printed boldly in red
                    letters on one of its sterns.</p>
                <p>In a few minutes <name>The Recruit</name> was launched by Roger and his father,
                    and all the family ran to the water’s edge and wished it well.</p>
                <p>“You think <name>The Recruit</name> is safe, don’t you, father?” said Ruby as she
                    came up conscientiously for the trial trip.</p>
                <pb n="16" xml:id="VAB7152-017"/>
                <p>“Well, it won’t carry you far,” he answered, lifting her in, “but you sha’n’t be
                    upset.”</p>
                <p>“Make way there, heave ahoy!” shouted Roger, giving <name>The Recruit</name> a
                    mighty shove, and the boat, so it seemed to Ruby, glided out for yards and yards
                    and yards, into the vast ocean.</p>
                <p><name>The Recruit</name> was not very comfortable. It heaved over dreadfully to
                    one side, and each time Ruby moved the water came welling up through the cracks
                    in the bottom. At last she put her hands nervously to the sides and tried to
                    turn it round.</p>
                <pb n="17" xml:id="VAB7152-018"/>
                <p>“Quite safe, Ruby; we’re all here. Don’t get out; we’ll hold it up till you’re in
                    your depth again.” And Roger, Rachael, and her father laid hold of <name>The
                        Recruit</name> and swam with it to the shore.</p>
                <p>“We were close all the time,” said Roger; “but I thought she would have floated
                    better than that!” Roger was a little depressed; he had spent so many
                    half‐holidays, and worked so hard, in making his boat.</p>
                <p>“So did I,” said Ruby as she stepped out of it; “but I did enjoy some of it,” she
                    added as she noticed Roger’s disappointment. “I really did enjoy some of it, and
                    perhaps she will go better next time. You won’t mind if I like an ordinary bathe
                    best, will you?”</p>
                <p>“Not a bit,” cried Roger, cheering up. “Come along and let’s have an ordinary
                    bathe.”</p>
                <p>And he picked up the football, which had accompanied them to the beach, and threw
                    it at Rachael. Rachael caught hold of it and swam with it to their father; then
                    their father threw it to Ruby, who missed it; and finally their mother caught it
                    and swam away with it, pursued by all the others.</p>
                <p>“It isn’t quite like ordinary bathing,” said Ruby, as she scrambled up after
                    being knocked down for the third time by Roger, Rachael, and the ball; and
                    Roger, to make amends, begged her to let him swim with her on his back, and
                    tried to persuade her to sit on the ball and be pushed into really deep water;
                    then he implored her to try diving from his shoulder, until at last their mother
                    took Ruby away and gave her a swimming lesson in a quiet pool by herself.</p>
                <pb n="18" xml:id="VAB7152-019"/>
                <p>A little later in the morning, as the children sat in the sun drying their hair
                    and enjoying a second luncheon, they observed <name>The Recruit</name> beginning
                    to float out to sea uncommanded, and Roger, of course, had to dash to its rescue
                    and drag it up the beach above high‐water mark.</p>
                <p>“I can’t help thinking,” said his mother as she looked at it critically,
                        “<name>The Recruit</name> would make an excellent wheelbarrow. We badly need
                    a wheelbarrow for the garden.”</p>
                <p>“O mother! It’s such a beautiful boat.” The children were shocked at the idea of
                    such abasement for Roger’s handiwork. Even Ruby, who had so nobly proved its
                    un‐seaworthiness, defended its present profession.</p>
                <p>“Oh no, mother! <emph>Not</emph> a wheelbarrow! Perhaps when it’s more accustomed
                    to the water, and has more putty in the cracks,” she added hopefully, “it will
                    be all right, and, you see, we shall never want to go far in it.”</p>
                <p>“That will be wise,” said their mother, smiling.</p>
                <p>“You <emph>won’t</emph> have anything done to it, will you?” implored
                    Rachael.</p>
                <p>“No, certainly not; but I can’t help thinking, as I sit here and look at it, what
                    a nice, useful wheelbarrow it <emph>would</emph> make.”</p>
                <p>“Then please, mother, don’t look at it,” cried Roger; “it makes me anxious—you
                    seem to be dooming it.”</p>
                <p>“Well, I’ll try not to look at it,” laughed his mother; “but such an object—”</p>
                <pb n="19" xml:id="VAB7152-020"/>
                <p>The children rushed at her in a body and prevented the sentence from being
                    finished. Then they ran to the threatened <name>Recruit</name> and laboriously
                    buried it in the sand, lest their mother’s thought should develop into a
                    determined plan for its transformation.</p>
                <p>When this was over they began “rounders,” according to the morning’s programme;
                    and they played, and they played, and they played, until Ruby sat down beside
                    the tent and said she was too tired to move any more.</p>
                <p>“We must put off the ride, I’m afraid, till after dinner,” said Roger, sitting
                    beside Ruby and gasping for breath.</p>
                <p>“It is dinner‐time now.” Their mother looked at her watch and rose hastily, and
                    in a few minutes they were all clambering up the cliff to the loke, leading to
                    Sea‐thrift, Ruby seated on her father’s shoulder.</p>
                <p>A “loke” in the land of Sea‐thrift is the name given to a roadway which is too
                    narrow to be a proper road, and too wide to be a proper lane; it has no
                    footpath, and it has hedges on either side, with cottages at irregular
                    distances.</p>
                <p>As the children came to it they looked up the flag‐staff which stood at the head
                    of the sandy slope, and there, perched on the very top, was a robin, and his red
                    breast shone brightly against the blue sky.</p>
                <p>“It is our robin,” said Ruby, from her father’s shoulder.</p>
                <p>“He quite dogs our steps,” said Roger.</p>
                <p>“He isn’t singing,” said Rachael.</p>
                <pb n="20" xml:id="VAB7152-021"/>
                <p>“Perhaps he’s just <emph>had</emph> his dinner,” suggested Roger; “one can’t sing
                    immediately after a meal.”</p>
                <p>But as he spoke the robin began to sing as sweetly as he had sung in the garden
                    the day before.</p>
                <p>“He’s telling us something very important,” said Ruby drowsily from her father’s
                    shoulder.</p>
                <p>“Is he? then I wish we could understand,” began Roger; “but see—who are they?” as
                    two grown‐up figures stepped through a gap in the hedge—“they are Ethel and
                    Charlie. No! Yes!” And Roger and Rachael ran excitedly towards them.</p>
                <p>“Where have you come from? Are you staying here? Are you going to stay long?
                        <emph>Do</emph> stay a nice long time! Isn’t it jolly? We’ve got a
                    boat—Roger made it—but you can’t stay in it for long. Ruby made the trial trip:
                    Ruby’s very tired, so father’s carrying her.”</p>
                <p>All the news of the morning was poured into Ethel and Charlie’s ears before they
                    met the rest of the party.</p>
                <p>“I’m so sorry I’m tired,” said Ruby, as she kissed them.</p>
                <p>“Oh, don’t mind being tired,” laughed Charlie, “that’s soon cured; I expect you
                    want your dinner.”</p>
                <p>But when they reached Sea‐thrift Ruby couldn’t sit up to dinner. She lay,
                    instead, in her own little room and looked at the yellow wheat and ruined
                    Priory, while the others had their meal; and after dinner her mother thought her
                    so poorly that she undressed her and put her to bed.</p>
                <p>Roger and Rachael were greatly troubled and disappointed, and, after some debate
                    as to what they could<pb n="21" xml:id="VAB7152-022"/> do for Ruby, decided to
                    pay a long call on Ethel and Charlie, whose lodgings were near by, and to come
                    back every now and then to see if she were better. They were sure she would be
                    better by tea‐time.</p>
                <p>But little Ruby grew worse and worse as the day went on.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="22" xml:id="VAB7152-023"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>CHAPTER THREE</head>
                <p><hi>AT</hi> half‐past six the next morning Roger and Rachael walked to Ethel and
                    Charlie’s lodgings, to see if they were up, but although the window of their
                    room was wide open its curtains were drawn. Then they walked down to the beach
                    to see if they could bathe.</p>
                <p>It was a beautifully sunny morning, and the sea was as smooth as it had been
                    yesterday, so they hastened back to Sea‐thrift and filled a basket with tennis
                    balls. Then they went back to Ethel and Charlie’s lodgings, and, the curtains
                    being still drawn, Rachael threw one of the balls at the window; but the ball
                    merely shook the curtain gently and tumbled into the jasmine, so she threw
                    another, which bounced off again from the window‐sill and lodged on the top of
                    the porch.</p>
                <p>“Let me have a shy,” said Roger, and he shied furiously. His first ball went over
                    the house into the<pb n="23" xml:id="VAB7152-024"/> potato patch behind, but his
                    second and his third ball dashed in boldly through the curtains.</p>
                <p>“That wasn’t a bad shot,” he whispered to Rachael, as the sound of shattered
                    glass fell upon their ears.</p>
                <p>“No, it wasn’t,” she answered; “I’m afraid they are chimney ornaments.”</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding the three balls and their evident effect upon some object, or
                    objects, unknown, no sign came from the window.</p>
                <p>“Perhaps they’ve gone for a walk,” suggested Rachael.</p>
                <p>“Perhaps they have.” Roger looked at his watch, but his watch had stopped, so he
                    swung it round and round violently by its chain.</p>
                <p>“I can’t imagine what’s come to it,” he exclaimed; “it won’t go at all unless I
                    shake it like this, and then it only goes for a few minutes.”</p>
                <p>He looked at his timepiece critically, then he thrust it into his pocket with a
                    gesture of despair.</p>
                <p>“Well, let us come and find father.” So they turned homeward again to see if
                    anything could be done with their father, with regard to a bathe: but when they
                    reached their own gate their father was starting off for the doctor.</p>
                <p>“Ruby is worse,” he said; “I’m going to find that white‐haired old man who
                    believes in fairies.”</p>
                <p>“Poor little Ruby! what a pity! and it’s going to be such a lovely day!” Rachael
                    lifted up her face to the blue sky, and her curls shone like burnished
                    copper.</p>
                <pb n="24" xml:id="VAB7152-025"/>
                <p>For a few minutes the children stood silent with disappointment—they had been so
                    sure Ruby would be well to‐day—then they turned and walked back to Ethel and
                    Charlie’s.</p>
                <p>This time the curtains were drawn back, and Ethel’s face appeared at the
                    window.</p>
                <p>“Good morning, Roger, good morning, Rachael; thank you for the balls.”</p>
                <p>“I’m so sorry, I’m afraid I’ve broken something,” apologised Roger; “I do hope it
                    doesn’t matter very much.”</p>
                <p>“We shall hear what our landlady thinks.”</p>
                <p>“What was it?”</p>
                <p>“It <emph>was</emph> a large owl, made of green glass, and he had a piece of blue
                    ribbon tied in a bow round his neck, and he had a candle growing out of the top
                    of his head.”</p>
                <p>“Poor thing,” said Rachael, who had a passion for creatures of every kind and of
                    all degree. “How tired of holding it he must have been.”</p>
                <p>“Well, he won’t have to hold it any more. How is Ruby?”</p>
                <p>“She isn’t so well; father has just gone for the doctor.”</p>
                <p>“Poor little Ruby.”</p>
                <p>The children looked downcast for some time, and the conversation flagged until
                    Charlie came running out with towels over his shoulder, then their spirits rose
                    with a bound.</p>
                <p>“Oh, is there time for a bathe?”</p>
                <p>“Of course there is. When did you get up?”</p>
                <pb n="25" xml:id="VAB7152-026"/>
                <p>“I don’t know—exactly—my watch isn’t going properly just now. I got up as soon as
                    I woke, and called Rachael.”</p>
                <p>“Well, come along and let us see how far Rachael can swim.”</p>
                <p>So they ran down to the beach with Charlie.</p>
                <p>Charlie was a painter, and Ethel was his wife. The Three R’s had often wished for
                    definite information about Charlie’s profession, and this morning seemed to them
                    an excellent opportunity for beginning his examination.</p>
                <p>“I am going to be an artist,” said Rachael suddenly, when a little later she was
                    swimming along beside him. “Roger is going to be a millionaire; but I don’t want
                    many different kinds of things when I grow up, I only want to keep a few
                    animals.”</p>
                <p>“What is Roger going to do to become a millionaire?” asked Charlie.</p>
                <p>“Oh, he isn’t going to <emph>do</emph> anything; he is going to be one right
                    off.”</p>
                <p>“And are you going to be an artist ‘right off’?”</p>
                <p>“I’m afraid one can’t be, there is so much to learn; there <emph>is</emph> a
                    great deal to learn, I suppose?” she added, hoping for contradiction.</p>
                <p>But Charlie was swimming out farther than she cared to follow, so Rachael
                    reserved further questioning for the dry land.</p>
                <p>“When did you begin to draw?” she asked, when, by‐and‐by, they were all toiling
                    up the cliff to the lake.</p>
                <p>“As long ago as I can remember.”</p>
                <pb n="26" xml:id="VAB7152-027"/>
                <p>“Did they make you draw wooden blocks, and cups, and jugs, and ornaments and
                    things, and teach you perspective? We have done all the ornaments all over the
                    house at home, and all the jugs in the kitchen, and oh, such a lot of
                    candlesticks! Did you do candlesticks?”</p>
                <p>“Oh yes; I did all that kind of thing.”</p>
                <p>“Did you like it?”</p>
                <p>“Not much.”</p>
                <p>“What did you like best?”</p>
                <p>“I liked doing things out‐of‐doors best.”</p>
                <p>“Yes, that is what I like,” said Rachael approvingly; “father has given us all
                    sketch‐books, and Ruby and I are going to fill ours these holidays.”</p>
                <p>“I expect the sea is jolly difficult to paint, isn’t it?” said Roger.</p>
                <p>“It is.”</p>
                <p>“It must be awfully hard to get the right colours.”</p>
                <p>“It is.”</p>
                <p>“Now what <emph>could</emph> you mix together to get that?”</p>
                <p>Rachael made them stop and look back at the sea. From where they were standing
                    the water was clear grey along the edge of the sand; then, a little beyond, it
                    was pale blue; farther off it was a beautiful transparent green; and farther out
                    still it was a deep sapphire.</p>
                <p>“I should have to think it over,” said Charlie, “and then, after all my thinking,
                    I shouldn’t paint anything like it.”</p>
                <p>“But it would be like enough to remind us of it,” said Rachael encouragingly;
                    “when I haven’t my little<pb n="27" xml:id="VAB7152-028"/> Winky with me I
                    always look at the picture of a kitten in my animal book.”</p>
                <p>“Let’s have a run,” exclaimed Roger, hastily turning the conversation from Winky,
                    knowing from experience how long the subject was likely to last. So they chased
                    Charlie home to his breakfast, and then hastened along to their own.</p>
                <p>After breakfast, at Sea‐thrift, the white‐haired doctor drove up to see Ruby.</p>
                <p>“Well,” he said, as he sat down by her bed, “is this the way to see fairies?”</p>
                <p>Ruby was a polite little girl, and didn’t feel able to begin a conversation in
                    the middle like that, so she said: “How do you do?” and held out her hand.</p>
                <p>“Thank you, I am very well, and I want to know what you have done to get ill so
                    soon.”</p>
                <p>“I don’t know,” said Ruby; “but I am not going to be really ill, am I? Shall I
                    have to stay in bed?”</p>
                <p>“I am afraid so.”</p>
                <p>“But not for long?”</p>
                <p>“For some time, I think,” said the doctor, as he examined her.</p>
                <p>“Oh dear!” Ruby was dreadfully disappointed, and, in spite of all her efforts to
                    keep them back, tears filled her eyes; but she struggled bravely, and did not
                    let them fall.</p>
                <p>“You are a good child,” said the doctor, holding her small hot hand in his big
                    cool one. “There is a kind little neighbour already trying to cheer you,” he
                    said, as, through the open window, they heard the robin singing from his perch
                    on the well.</p>
                <pb n="28" xml:id="VAB7152-029"/>
                <p>“Yes; isn’t he a little dear? He hopped on to the window‐sill this morning.”</p>
                <p>“Perhaps he has something to tell you! Well, good‐bye, I shall come again
                    to‐morrow, and then you may be able to tell me the secret.”</p>
                <p>“What secret?” asked Ruby.</p>
                <p>“The robin’s. I expect he has one, don’t you?”</p>
                <p>“Yes, perhaps,” answered Ruby, smiling; but, when the door closed on the kind
                    white‐haired doctor, she turned her aching head away from the window. “I can’t
                    look any more, mother, it hurts my eyes.”</p>
                <p>And her mother drew the curtains and sat down beside her and soothed her to
                    sleep.</p>
                <p>“Poor little thing,” she said, “she has had no sleep all night.”</p>
                <p>And then Ruby’s mother lay down upon the other little bed and went to sleep
                    too.</p>
                <p>Ruby slept a long while. When she awoke the sun shone more brightly than ever,
                    the room was full of beautiful warm air, and the scent of roses and jasmine
                    reached her from the garden. Her mother was still asleep, and Ruby turned
                    towards the window very gently lest she should wake her.</p>
                <p>She lay still and listened to the birds in the creepers. There were several nests
                    outside the window, and their owners just now seemed very busy. By‐and‐by her
                    curtains began to stir, and suddenly a little shadow fell upon it. A bird had
                    hopped on to the lowered window‐sash, and presently began to sing: Ruby knew at
                    once what bird it was.</p>
                <pb n="29" xml:id="VAB7152-030"/>
                <p>“How kind of you to come so near,” she said softly.</p>
                <p>“Do you like my song?” asked the Robin.</p>
                <p>Ruby, of course, ought to have been surprised by his sudden speech, but it
                    seemed, just then, quite natural and usual.</p>
                <p>“I like it very much, thank you,” she answered.</p>
                <p>“But you don’t understand what I say?”</p>
                <p>“No, I don’t—at least—I think I know in a <emph>kind</emph> of a way what you are
                    singing about, but, of course, I can understand better when you really
                    speak.”</p>
                <p>“Well, if you like, I will come sometimes and talk to you while you are in bed.
                    You are going to be in bed a long time.”</p>
                <p>“Oh, am I?”</p>
                <p>“Yes; but you are going to be very good and cheerful. I can tell you many
                    interesting things if you like to listen to them, and perhaps show you some,” he
                    added.</p>
                <p>“Thank you very much—but—how long will it be?”</p>
                <p>“How long will what be?”</p>
                <p>“My staying in bed.”</p>
                <p>“Oh—I don’t know exactly—it really doesn’t matter—you will be so busy when you
                    have once met—I mean when you know all I can tell you.”</p>
                <p>“I don’t quite see how I can be busy lying here,” said Ruby questioningly.</p>
                <p>The robin pushed his head between the curtains.</p>
                <p>“Being in bed makes no difference, <emph>She</emph> doesn’t mind—”</p>
                <pb n="30" xml:id="VAB7152-031"/>
                <p>But just then Ruby’s mother stirred and woke, and the robin withdrew his head and
                    flew away.</p>
                <p>“Have you had a nice sleep, my darling?” she said as she arose. “Ah, I see you
                    have. I have been having such a sweet dream, and in my dream you were dreaming
                    sweetly too.”</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="31" xml:id="VAB7152-032"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>CHAPTER IV</head>
                <p><hi>RUBY</hi> was ill for a long time, too ill to think of the robin, too ill to
                    see Roger or Rachael, too ill to do anything but lie in a half‐waking,
                    half‐dreaming, unrefreshing sleep. All this while Roger and Rachael felt very
                    dismal and anxious, but they went on bravely with the holiday and tried to keep
                    cheerful. Each. day they stopped the doctor to ask if Ruby would be better
                    to‐morrow, and each day the doctor smiled and said he hoped so. But at last,
                    after patient waiting, one day Ruby really was better—so much better that
                    Rachael that evening was allowed to have tea with her upstairs.</p>
                <p>“O Ruby,” said Rachael, as she followed the<pb n="32" xml:id="VAB7152-033"/> tray
                    into the long‐prohibited room, “it <emph>is</emph> nice you are better, you will
                    soon be quite strong now, and oh, there is <emph>so</emph> much to tell you I
                    don’t know how to begin!”</p>
                <p>“Begin in the middle,” said Ruby, smiling.</p>
                <p>“Well, we’ve bathed twice nearly every day, and I can swim ever so far; and I’ve
                    made friends with the three setters at the big red house and with the greyhound
                    from the post office; and the piebald mongrel at the bicycle shop is friendly
                    too. Ethel and Charlie have taken us for such lovely picnics! One day we went on
                    the river and brought back some water lilies: you <emph>must</emph> come there
                    when you are up. Hasn’t it been dreadfully dull lying here?”</p>
                <p>“I don’t think I’ve been dull,” began Ruby reflectively.</p>
                <p>“Well, never mind now,” interrupted Rachael. “You’ll soon be well, and we’ll do
                    everything all over again.”</p>
                <p>Then Rachael gave Ruby her tea, and waited upon her very carefully and
                    gently.</p>
                <p>“How cosy it is,” she said when they had finished, and she had put the tray on
                    one side and settled down at the foot of Ruby’s bed, and begun the history of a
                    Persian kitten which lived at one of the coastguard cottages. In the middle of
                    the story, however, she remembered that her mother had cautioned her against too
                    much talking.</p>
                <p>“Am I tiring you?” she asked anxiously, breaking off in the middle of an exciting
                    adventure of the Persian mother cat with the farm donkey.</p>
                <pb n="33" xml:id="VAB7152-034"/>
                <p>“Oh no; do go on.”</p>
                <p>So Rachael finished her story and then opened a book she had brought with
                    her.</p>
                <p>“I’ll read to you now; it will be quieter.”</p>
                <p>“Thank you very much. What are you going to read?”</p>
                <p>“I thought of reading a story about a horse, from my animal book, it’s so
                    exciting.”</p>
                <p>And from her animal book Rachael read stories of horses, and of lions, and of
                    tigers, and of polar bears, and of duck‐bills, and of creatures which lived
                    before the flood, until she couldn’t see to read any more.</p>
                <p>“Isn’t it awfully interesting?” she exclaimed, as she closed the book. “I should
                    like to see all those creatures; shouldn’t you?”</p>
                <p>But by this time Ruby was asleep, and Rachael, with a mixed feeling of
                    disappointment and satisfaction, crept downstairs to tell her mother that she
                    thought Ruby had settled down for the night, as, indeed, was the case.</p>
                <p>Ruby had great arrears to make up in the matter of sleep, and to‐night her rest
                    was deeper and more peaceful than it had been since her illness.</p>
                <p>“I don’t think tales of lions and tigers would make <emph>me</emph> sleep like
                    that,” said Roger, as he stepped in gently to wish her good‐night. “ It must
                    have been the sound of your voice, Rachael. I’ve often noticed—” And then Roger
                    quietly and quickly disappeared, with Rachael in pursuit.</p>
                <p>The next morning Ruby awoke very early and watched the sunlight shining in
                    through the window.<pb n="34" xml:id="VAB7152-035"/> She had been too ill until
                    now to notice sunlight or shadow; but to‐day she woke feeling quite gay, and
                    bright, with all the tiredness and headache gone.</p>
                <p>“I wish the robin would come,” she thought, and, before her thought was finished,
                    she heard him singing outside her window. She listened eagerly: he was singing
                    words: <q>
                        <lg type="verse_paragraph">
                            <l>“Wake, wake, Ruby, wake,</l>
                            <l rend="ti-1">There is so much to see,</l>
                            <l>You’ve a journey to take,</l>
                            <l rend="ti-1">And quite safe you shall be.</l>
                            <l>Wake, wake, and listen to all I am singing,</l>
                            <l>And learn what the dawn and the sunlight are bringing.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="verse_paragraph">
                            <l>The sun has just climbed</l>
                            <l rend="ti-1">From the sea to the sky,</l>
                            <l>And my first song was rhymed</l>
                            <l rend="ti-1">When the night clouds passed by.</l>
                            <l>Wake, wake, and listen to all I am singing,</l>
                            <l>And learn what the dawn and the sunlight are bringing.”</l>
                        </lg>
                    </q></p>
                <p>Ruby crept softly from her bed.</p>
                <p>“Come, learn what the dawn and the sunlight are bringing,” repeated the robin,
                    before she could get to the window.</p>
                <p>“Yes, yes; I am coming,” said Ruby, pushing her head between the curtains, “but I
                    must put on my dressing‐gown and slippers.”</p>
                <p>“Why?” asked the robin, and he fluttered his wings impatiently.</p>
                <p>“Because mother says I must, in the early morning.<pb n="35" xml:id="VAB7152-036"/> I always do so at home when I sit up in bed to have a biscuit or banana.”</p>
                <p>“I see,” said the robin.</p>
                <p>“But he can’t see,” thought Ruby, looking at the drawn curtains as she buttoned
                    up her dressing‐gown.</p>
                <p>“Oh yes, I can,” repeated the robin in answer to her thought. “You are fastening
                    the last button but two, and you are not being nearly quick enough.”</p>
                <p>Ruby bustled through the rest of her early morning toilet, and began to spread
                    her bedclothes over the chairs, as she had been taught to do on rising.</p>
                <p>“Why do you do that?” called the robin. “You will be back before anyone is awake.
                    Come, be quick; the window is open wide; step on to the sill.”</p>
                <p>So Ruby stepped through the curtains and over the low window‐sash on to the
                    sill.</p>
                <p>“Now,” said the robin, “put one hand on my back, stretch the other arm out on the
                    air, and fly along with me.”</p>
                <p>“But,” began Ruby anxiously, “I have never learned—”</p>
                <p>“Very likely not,” interrupted the robin. “But it is wise to learn something new
                    whenever one has the chance. We are not going far this time.”</p>
                <p>“I’m glad of that,” answered Ruby, in a tone of relief “How far are we
                    going?”</p>
                <p>“As far as the well.”</p>
                <p>“Our well?”</p>
                <p>“Your well.”</p>
                <p>Ruby was greatly disappointed and about to remonstrate, but the robin suddenly
                    said:</p>
                <pb n="36" xml:id="VAB7152-037"/>
                <p>“Are you ready? Go—”</p>
                <p>And in a moment she had dived through the air and was standing beside the well,
                    and saw the robin perched in his accustomed place over it.</p>
                <p>“It wasn’t difficult, was it?” he said, turning his bright eyes upon her.</p>
                <p>“Oh no; very easy. I should like to try a long distance.”</p>
                <p>“You shall some time, but we have something more important to do just now.” He
                    tapped with his beak on the big lid.</p>
                <p>When he had tapped three times the lid began to lift slowly, up and up, until it
                    stood upright on the edge of the well, then it fell lightly over into the
                    currant bushes.</p>
                <p>“Here She is,” said the robin; and up from the darkness came a wonderful figure,
                    who stepped out and stood beside Ruby. She was tall and strong, and her face was
                    so sweet and beautiful, Ruby thought, as she raised her eyes, that here was the
                    most beloved of all the spirits of the earth. Her hair was the colour of ripened
                    wheat, and it was wound in great yellow plaits around her head, and in it were
                    bunches of scarlet poppies; her eyes were clear and deep and blue, like the sky
                    on a summer day. Soft green raiment hung about her in deep folds, and between
                    the folds the sun shone and sparkled on embroideries of flowers, and patterns
                    set in precious stones: while butterflies, more bright than Ruby had ever seen,
                    made a rainbow cloud about her feet. Ruby looked up at the beautiful lady and
                    smiled.</p>
                <pb n="37" xml:id="VAB7152-038"/>
                <p>“I am not a stranger, then?” said the lady, smiling in return.</p>
                <p>“No; I seem to know you quite well.” As she spoke Ruby put her hand into the kind
                    hand beside her. “But I have never seen you before,” she went on. “I
                    wonder—”</p>
                <p>“Do not wonder about it, we are friends now—that is better than wondering. I
                    watched you while you were ill; did you sometimes have pleasant dreams?”</p>
                <p>“Oh! beautiful dreams—dreams about the fields and the lanes, and the wind and the
                    sea. Oh yes; I can remember them all now. Do you know about them?”</p>
                <p>“Yes; I know about them.”</p>
                <p>“Did you give me the dreams?”</p>
                <p>“Yes. Ruby, look—”</p>
                <p>And the beautiful lady held out both her arms, and, as her cloak spread open in
                    the sunshine, Ruby saw wonderful pictures painted upon it—pictures which changed
                    as she looked at them, and moved over the mantle as lightly as clouds over the
                    sky.</p>
                <p>“When will they come to an end?” asked Ruby, as she watched them.</p>
                <p>“When my mantle is worn out.” And the beautiful lady let the heavy folds fall
                    once more about her.</p>
                <p>“That will not be for a long time,” said Ruby, gently touching its jewelled
                    edge.</p>
                <p>“Not for a long long time—not for a longer time than you, little Ruby, can think
                    of or imagine.” As she spoke the beautiful lady looked on the sweet summer land
                    around her, and across the fields to the blue sea,<pb n="38" xml:id="VAB7152-039"/> and upwards at the morning sky, and as she looked she
                    smiled lovingly. Then she bent down and looked earnestly at Ruby.</p>
                <p>“Can you trust me?” she whispered; “are you sure you are in no way afraid of me?
                    ”</p>
                <p>“Quite sure” answered Ruby, laughing; “why should I be afraid? You have been so
                    kind to me.”</p>
                <p>“That is well. I shall be able to show you some of my secrets. I cannot show them
                    to people who are afraid.” Then she wrapped her mantle about Ruby and lifted her
                    in her arms.</p>
                <p>“Now,” she said, “you shall know what is down the well. You have been wanting
                    very much to know?”</p>
                <p>“Very much.”</p>
                <p>Then the beautiful lady stepped back into the well, and Ruby heard the lid close
                    upon them as they began their descent. She thought there must be darkness now
                    the sky was hidden, but all about her was a warm, clear light; she could see
                    distinctly, and felt safe in the strong arms which bore her down, down, she knew
                    not to what depths.</p>
                <p>They had descended some distance in silence when the beautiful lady pointed to
                    the sides of the well.</p>
                <p>“These are my sick children,” she said.</p>
                <p>Ruby perceived that all around them were banks of flowers; not healthy,
                    full‐grown flowers, like those in the lanes above, but delicate fragile blossoms
                    of the same kind.</p>
                <p>“I keep them here until they are strong enough to bear the night winds and the
                    rains, then I send them back to the sunlight.” She touched the flowers with
                        her<pb n="39" xml:id="VAB7152-040"/>
                    <pb n="40" xml:id="VAB7152-041"/> fingers as she passed, and as she did so the
                    air became full of fragrance.</p>
                <p>Then the banks grew green with ferns that shone and glistened with raindrops, and
                    the scent of the wet ferny earth was sweeter than the flowers. Still they sank
                    lower and lower.</p>
                <p>“How deep it is,” said Ruby.</p>
                <p>“Yes; and we have not come to our journey’s end.”</p>
                <p>Then all about them Ruby saw the roots of trees, like a mighty wall. Oak, elm,
                    ash, sycamore, birch, poplar, and fir; all the trees she had ever seen had their
                    roots here, and from their roots she was able to name them. Then deeper than the
                    tree roots came piles of precious stones—diamonds, rubies, emeralds, sapphires,
                    amethysts—and they lay as piles of stones lie upon the roads in repairing
                    times.</p>
                <p>“They are dreadfully precious,” said Ruby, remembering the care with which her
                    mother made her store her little jewels, in her trinket‐box, at home.</p>
                <p>“Not so precious as these.” And Ruby knew that they had stopped; she was being
                    freed from the kind arms.</p>
                <p>“These are most precious of all.”</p>
                <p>Ruby looked round her. On either hand, as far as she could see, stretching away
                    along paths on every side, and rising upwards and lost in the height above her,
                    were walls and walls of seed; they were so marvellously made, she knew that not
                    the smallest seed of them all could be taken from its place, without disturbing
                    the entire structure.</p>
                <pb n="41" xml:id="VAB7152-042"/>
                <p>“What are they?” asked the beautiful lady.</p>
                <p>“The seeds of all the earth,” answered Ruby readily. Her mind seemed suddenly
                    clear and strong, and she felt she was going to understand some of the great
                    secrets about which she had so often asked in vain.</p>
                <p>“Yes; the seeds of all the earth.” The beautiful lady bent down and kissed Ruby
                    on the forehead as she repeated her words, and as she did so the words were sung
                    by a chorus of sweet voices: <q>
                        <l>“The seeds of all the earth, that all,</l>
                        <l>Both strong and great and weak and small,</l>
                        <l>May flower and flourish, fade, and fall.”</l>
                    </q></p>
                <p>“And now Ruby must go home.”</p>
                <p>“Not yet—please—not yet!”</p>
                <p>But, as she petitioned, Ruby’s eyes closed, and she felt numberless little arms
                    tighten about her. When she opened her eyes again she was in her own little bed,
                    with her mother standing beside her.</p>
                <p>“What is it, my darling? You called me; you have been dreaming.”</p>
                <p>“Have I, mother? But I do not think it was a dream.” Ruby sat up and looked about
                    her. “Is it getting‐up time now?”</p>
                <p>“Yes.”</p>
                <p>Ruby’s mother drew back the curtains and the full morning sun shone in upon them.
                    As her hand touched the curtain, a group of dancing shadows passed across it and
                    disappeared, and through the window with the sunshine came another verse of the
                        song.<pb n="42" xml:id="VAB7152-043"/>
                    <q>
                        <l>“That every valley, plain, and hill,</l>
                        <l>Their faithful promise may fulfil,</l>
                        <l>And all Her ways, by land and sea,</l>
                        <l>Be fair and sweet for you and me.”</l>
                    </q></p>
                <p>“Do you hear the singing, mother?”</p>
                <p>“Yes; it is very kind of your little robin to sing as soon as we wake; we must
                    give him some breakfast.” </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="43" xml:id="VAB7152-044"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>CHAPTER V</head>
                <epigraph>
                    <l>“And all Her gates, by land and sea,</l>
                    <l>Will open to you, wide and free,</l>
                    <l>If you can turn the magic key.”</l>
                </epigraph>
                <p><hi>RUBY</hi> was roused next morning by the robin’s song.</p>
                <p>“Are you ready for another lesson in flying?” he asked through the curtain.</p>
                <p>“Oh yes, please! I will be ever so quick.” Ruby bustled into her dressing‐gown
                    and slippers with extraordinary speed.</p>
                <p>“Would you like to see the fairy of the well again?”</p>
                <p>“Oh yes; is that her name? ”</p>
                <p>“She has many names; that is one of them. She is waiting for us. Put your hand on
                    me, spread out both arms, and fly.”</p>
                <p>And Ruby put her fingers on the robin’s back, and threw herself on the fresh
                    morning air. She sank into it as gently as she slipped into the sea when she
                    bathed, and floated through it much more easily. She never thought of asking the
                    robin not to go too quickly, or too<pb n="44" xml:id="VAB7152-045"/> far, or too
                    anything, his little feathery back gave her all the support she needed. They
                    flew much farther than the well this time.</p>
                <p>“How beautiful it is,” cried Ruby, “and how easy. Look, look, I should like to
                    fly like that,” she went on delightedly, as a lark fluttered from the grass
                    beneath them and flew straight up into the sky.</p>
                <p>“One must not want to do <emph>everything</emph>—” began the robin
                    reprovingly.</p>
                <p>“Of course not,” interrupted Ruby hastily; “you are not disappointed, are you? I
                    am enjoying this so much; oh, I do hope you are not disappointed. This is the
                    most beautiful thing I have ever done.”</p>
                <p>“That’s right,” said the robin cheerfully again. “You see, I can’t go up like
                    that myself. Now shut your eyes, and don’t open them till I tell you.”</p>
                <p>Ruby closed her eyes obediently, and everything grew suddenly dark and still, and
                    she felt herself flying down‐wards—down—down—down—farther down than the seed
                    land at the bottom of the well.</p>
                <p>“Open.”</p>
                <p>It was not the robin who spoke but the beautiful lady; and when Ruby opened her
                    eyes she found herself standing beside Her in a wonderful garden—in a garden of
                    magical flowers and perfumes—and playing in and out among the trees were groups
                    of fairies. Ruby knew at once they were fairies, by their small stature, by
                    their coats and caps of beetles’ wings, by the dew which dropped from their feet
                    as they danced, and by their cloaks of floating, shining gossamer.</p>
                <pb n="45" xml:id="VAB7152-046"/>
                <p>“Are you ready to try the golden gate?” she asked, smiling at Ruby.</p>
                <p>She was more beautiful, and her trailing skirts more splendid, than
                    yesterday.</p>
                <p>“The golden gate! I do not understand,” said Ruby. And for answer the beautiful
                    lady took her by the hand and led her into a wide avenue of blossoming trees; as
                    they walked along it, fairies from all parts of the garden came and formed a
                    shining procession behind them.</p>
                <p>“While we are young,” said the beautiful lady, “we should learn which gates are
                    open to us, and which gates are closed against us, it saves our strength and
                    tears when we are old. There are many gates,” she continued, as Ruby looked up
                    in surprise. “One person can open but a few of them; and, as some are better
                    worth opening than others, I want you to try to open one which I consider the
                    best of all. If you succeed, I shall no longer have a doubt concerning you; you
                    will be safe and happy in whatever strange and barren land you may abide. But if
                    you cannot open it easily, do not try; trying, in this case, will be
                    useless.”</p>
                <p>As she spoke they came to a bend in the path, and there, just in front of them,
                    Ruby beheld a great gate of gold. Its height was so vast she could not see the
                    top, and it hung upon mighty crystal hinges, which shone like the sun, and its
                    width was more than a dozen Rubys could have compassed. All over it were
                    pictures beaten in gold, and she perceived that<pb n="46" xml:id="VAB7152-047"/>
                    none of the pictures were finished. Each was the beginning of a wonderful story,
                    which became, as soon as she read it, the beginning of another story, which in
                    its turn gave place to another; and so on, all over the great gate, as far as
                    she could see. Ruby turned to her guide in disappointment.</p>
                <p>“They are finished inside,” said the beautiful lady; “come, try to open it.”</p>
                <p>Ruby put her little hand upon the gate. It had no handle or fastening, so she
                    placed one finger on the petal of a buttercup, in a buttercup border that was
                    worked round one of the panels, and the procession of fairies crowded closely
                    round her, peeping eagerly over her shoulders.</p>
                <p>“One, two, three,” they sang. And Ruby turned and smiled—she felt sure of opening
                    the gate.</p>
                <p>“One, two, three,” they sang again. And Ruby laughed for joy—the great gate swung
                    back to the first pressure of her finger. Then the fairies clapped their hands,
                    and threw their shining caps into the air, and danced round her so wildly, she
                    could not see what glories were disclosed. <q>
                        <l>“She can open the gate,</l>
                        <l>All our treasure can see;</l>
                        <l>All the wealth she can take,</l>
                        <l>From the land and the sea:</l>
                        <l>She can learn all the wonder of days long ago,</l>
                        <l>She can hear every story and song that we know.”</l>
                    </q></p>
                <p>“Please let me see,” she said, but for answer the<pb n="47" xml:id="VAB7152-048"/> fairies danced round her, until she was obliged to take hands and dance with
                    them. So fast they danced, she could not see the gate for the shimmer and
                    flutter of gossamer.</p>
                <p>“Please—please,” she began again, but they only danced more wildly than
                    before.</p>
                <p>“Oh, very well,” she gasped at length, “I’ll dance as long as you like, and go
                    there afterwards.” Then all the fairies ceased dancing and began to laugh.</p>
                <p>“Why do you laugh?” asked Ruby, a little offended, for she had made a great
                    effort to oblige them.</p>
                <p>“Don’t you see?” they cried, as they began dancing once more; “don’t you see?
                    ”</p>
                <p>“<emph>Do</emph> tell me what you mean,” said Ruby, quite provoked.</p>
                <p>“Don’t you see you <emph>are</emph> there?” And the fairies clapped their hands
                    and danced away, one by one, until Ruby stood alone and heard the shower of
                    silvery laughter pass into the distance.</p>
                <p>“<emph>There</emph>!”</p>
                <p>Ruby looked about for the golden gate, but the golden gate was nowhere to be
                    seen. The beautiful lady had disappeared, and Ruby stood alone in a world of
                    blue. Above her head, beneath her feet, and on either hand, as far as she could
                    see, a clear blue mist lay over a great country, in which no outline of
                    mountain, or tree, or building, told what manner of country it was. She was a
                    little afraid, and wished the fairies would come back. As she wished she felt<pb n="48" xml:id="VAB7152-049"/> a strong hand take hers, and the voice of the
                    beautiful lady whispered in her ear:</p>
                <p>“You are safe, Ruby; I am beside you.”</p>
                <p>“But I cannot see you.”</p>
                <p>“I am beside you none the less.” And at the sound of the familiar voice Ruby’s
                    heart grew strong again.</p>
                <p>“What would you like to see?” the voice continued. “You can go where you will.
                    Shall we fly upwards, above the clouds, to the distant stars, and follow the
                    planets in their courses round the sun; or shall we dive through forests of
                    seaweed, into the cold still waters, that lie hundreds of fathoms deeper than
                    the sun can send his rays? Or shall we turn to some bygone age which has passed
                    away into the shadows, and travel backward through time, and see it truly?”</p>
                <p>Ruby looked across the vast expanse before her to the farthest haze of blue; then
                    she looked into the blue at her feet, and, as she gazed into its depths, it grew
                    like the summer sea, bluer and bluer and more shining, until the sunny ripples
                    broke over her feet.</p>
                <p>“We will dive into the sea.” Ruby spoke now as one in command. “We will dive into
                    the still waters, and see the creatures that live beneath the sea forests.”</p>
                <p>Then the waves broke over her ankles and reached her knees, then they splashed
                    against her shoulders, and sparkled over her head: and all the time a kind hand
                    held hers firmly.</p>
                <p>“How lovely, how lovely,” she cried; “I have been thinking about the sea, and
                    longing so much to be in it. Are we far from shore?”</p>
                <pb n="49" xml:id="VAB7152-050"/>
                <p>“A hundred miles from shore,” answered the voice, as Ruby slipped through the
                    water; “a hundred miles from shore, in the sea valleys where the herrings
                    hide.”</p>
                <p>And Ruby saw she was in a mighty forest of seaweed, of beautiful colours, and
                    about her were wonderful sea animals, sponges, star‐fish, sea‐snails, and
                    urchins, and hundreds of creatures she had never seen before: and rising and
                    falling, at a short distance from her, was the great herring army, hundreds of
                    millions in number, waiting in the shadows till night and darkness should come
                    and help it to swim away unseen.</p>
                <p>“Now deeper than the seaweeds,” said the voice. And the water grew colder and
                    colder, until it was icy cold; and deeper and deeper they went, till the
                    movement of the waves ceased, and the waters grew still and dark, so dark that
                    Ruby could not see.</p>
                <p>“Down, down, three hundred fathoms down: it is a deep bathe, Ruby.”</p>
                <p>Then out of the darkness came strange fish, which swam about her, each creature
                    carrying his own lamp. One held it on his head, another carried several along
                    his sides, and another one’s body shone all over, so that the darkness was
                    illumined, and she could see the fashion of this silent world. How vast a world
                    it was, so far away from the fresh air and the sunlight. She looked through
                    miles and miles of dark waters, and on every side the darkness was made visible
                    by gliding, shining fish. She was suddenly oppressed by the great silence.</p>
                <p>“Nearer to the surface,” she said; and immediately the hand which held hers
                    tightened its grasp, and she<pb n="50" xml:id="VAB7152-051"/> felt herself
                    rising upwards through the water. Upwards and upwards, until it grew warmer, and
                    she saw seaweeds stirring in the waves; and up and up, until she came to the
                    urchins and sea snails, to the feather stars and bright‐coloured sponges.</p>
                <p>“Up and up,” she said again, for she began to long greatly for the whole warmth
                    of the sunshine. “Up, quite up to the top.” The strong hand answered at once to
                    her words, and she was floating on the top of the water close to her own shore,
                    with the warm sun shining upon her.</p>
                <p>“Now, little Ruby, I must bid you good‐bye.” The beautiful lady took shape and
                    floated beside her. “You can open the gate; you have but to tell me your wish
                    and you shall see—”</p>
                <p>“Everything! oh, everything!” cried Ruby, as the beautiful lady paused.</p>
                <p>“No; not everything yet, but perhaps everything by‐and‐by, if you do not let the
                    crystal hinges grow stiff from want of use. But the sun mounts high; shut your
                    eyes, Ruby—Ruby—Ruby—”</p>
                <p>And when Ruby opened them again she was in her own cosy bed, and her mother was
                    standing beside her.</p>
                <p>“O mother, so much has happened!”</p>
                <p>“In your dreams, dear?”</p>
                <p>“No; in the early morning, mother, while you were sleeping.”</p>
                <p>But her mother kissed her and smoothed her hair from her brow.</p>
                <p>“Wake up, little Ruby, it is breakfast‐time,” she said, as she drew back the
                    curtains from Ruby’s window. </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="51" xml:id="VAB7152-052"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>CHAPTER VI</head>
                <p><hi>RUBY</hi> grew so much better in the next few days, she was able, at the end
                    of the week, to come downstairs and hear what the others were doing. And the
                    others gave up their picnics and long excursions, and played in the garden,
                    looking in every now and then to see how she was getting on, and to bring her
                    flowers, gulls’ feathers, cornelians, and other treasures.</p>
                <p>Ruby had never enjoyed being up and dressed as she enjoyed it the first morning
                    she came downstairs, to breakfast, after her illness. It was so comfortable to
                    be wearing her frock again, so nice to have her hair tied up quite properly with
                    her best ribbon, so pleasant to see everything in the little sitting‐room.</p>
                <p>“O Ruby, we’ve made heaps of friends. The coast‐guards are jolly—we know them
                    all—they have told us a lot about the coast, and wrecks, and being at sea, and
                    we have wished all the time you could hear it, but we’ll tell you all we
                    remember.”</p>
                <pb n="52" xml:id="VAB7152-053"/>
                <p>It was afternoon, and Roger and Rachael were in the garden talking to Ruby
                    through the window.</p>
                <p>“But I haven’t been a bit dull,” cried Ruby. “I have a great deal to tell you
                    too; so much has happened.”</p>
                <p>“I think I know what has happened most often,” said Roger, laughing, “but it
                    sha’n’t happen any more.” And he left the window abruptly and rushed upstairs,
                    pursued, immediately, by Rachael.</p>
                <p>Ruby wondered what their sudden departure portended, and when she heard them in
                    her room overhead, laughing and talking excitedly, she wondered still more.
                    Suddenly she heard a tremendous thump on the floor—Roger was evidently doing a
                    high jump: then he jumped again, and again, and again, and again. It was
                    impossible to sit quietly there under such a commotion. She crept upstairs and
                    opened her bedroom door to see the fun. In the middle of the room she beheld all
                    her medicine bottles arranged in a large circle. There were a great many—it gave
                    her quite a pang to see <emph>how</emph> many she had emptied—and in the middle
                    of the circle stood Roger waving the thermometer round his head.</p>
                <p>Ruby was alarmed; she had come to regard the thermometer with respectful awe, it
                    had ruled her life for so long. It was an object, she thought, with which it
                    would not be wise to take a liberty. It had, she felt, her future health in its
                    keeping, and if an accident befell it she herself must have a relapse.</p>
                <p>“Roger, Roger!” she cried anxiously, as Roger continued his triumphant dance
                    among the medicine bottles, and Rachael skipped around him.</p>
                <pb n="53" xml:id="VAB7152-054"/>
                <p>“Children, children, what is the matter?”</p>
                <p>“It’s all right, mother, we’re only bringing the thermometer down a bit. You said
                    it had kept up in a provoking way; I’m giving it a lesson.” Roger waved the
                    instrument around him, and jumped about so violently that it slipped, at last,
                    from his fingers and lay in several pieces on the floor.</p>
                <p>“O mother, what <emph>shall</emph> we do?”</p>
                <p>“You’ll do much better without it,” said the doctor’s familiar voice, as he came
                    into the room. “I’m glad Roger has been so high‐handed with it, it has had its
                    day. They have been having a fine time while you have been in bed,” he
                    continued, smiling at Roger and Rachael.</p>
                <p>“Yes; but I have been doing nice things too.”</p>
                <p>“Have you? When?”</p>
                <p>“In the early mornings, when mother was asleep.”</p>
                <p>“And Ruby dreaming?”</p>
                <p>“No; I don’t think I was dreaming. Is it true,” she went on, as the doctor took
                    her upon his knee, “that we are always trying to open gates?”</p>
                <p>“Some of us are always trying, but it is of no use, I am afraid, unless we try
                    when we are young.”</p>
                <p>“What is the most important gate of all?”</p>
                <p>“Opinions differ.”</p>
                <p>“There is a great one made of gold that hangs on crystal hinges,” said Ruby
                    thoughtfully, “and all over it are wonderful pictures, which change as you look
                    at them, and when you open that gate you see at first—” She stopped, and looked
                    troubled. “Oh dear—I am so sorry—I cannot remember—but do you know its
                    name?”</p>
                <pb n="54" xml:id="VAB7152-055"/>
                <p>“There are many gates,” said the doctor, smiling at her tenderly, “very many; and
                    each gate has many names, but their names do not matter. I think that when your
                    golden gate swings open on its crystal hinges, and you pass through, you can see
                    and understand everything.”</p>
                <p>“Not everything,” said Ruby, remembering the beautiful lady’s words.</p>
                <p>“Not everything,” repeated the doctor thoughtfully, “but nearly everything. Some
                    of the gates open into the past, some into the future; those which lead us to
                    the past show us the great events of the world as they happened, and
                        <emph>then</emph> we know and understand them as we could never know or
                    understand them from books.”</p>
                <p>“I shall be a historian,” said Roger, as the doctor paused; “history is awfully
                    fine. Which gate would you like to open, Rachael?”</p>
                <p>Rachael hesitated. After some deliberation she said:</p>
                <p>“I should like to open one that would show me all the animals in the world, and
                    all that have ever lived.”</p>
                <p>“Oh!” cried Roger, “what a crowd there would be; you couldn’t see them all.”</p>
                <p>“They might pass in a procession,” said Rachael. “Imagine an enormous procession,
                    headed by—by—”</p>
                <p>“The great Eft,” suggested the doctor, “followed by creatures standing thirty
                    feet high without their socks, pawing the air with their legs, and gnashing
                    teeth in heads five feet long.”</p>
                <p>“I am sure I should be pleased to see them,” said Rachael politely.</p>
                <pb n="55" xml:id="VAB7152-056"/>
                <p>“But scarcely to tea,” added her mother, as the gong sounded: and the doctor’s
                    talk turned from “gates” to directions concerning Ruby’s daily life.</p>
                <p>“Do not trouble your little head about the gate of gold,” he said, as he bade her
                    good‐bye in the garden. “Let the dreams come and go—or the fairies come and
                    go—we shall understand everything one day if we are patient.”</p>
                <p>“The doctor believes in fairies,” said Rachael, when Ethel and Charlie came in
                    and they sat down to tea.</p>
                <p>“Perhaps we all should,” said Ethel, “if the fairies gave us a chance.”</p>
                <p>“Or we gave them a chance,” corrected Charlie.</p>
                <p>“Well, I’m ready for them,” said Roger, “whenever they like to come.”</p>
                <p>“So am I,” added Rachael, “but I wish we could do something to <emph>make</emph>
                    them come. Do think of something, Roger.”</p>
                <p>Roger plunged into thought for a few minutes, then he cried:</p>
                <p>“I’ve got it—I’ve got it!”</p>
                <p>“What—what?”</p>
                <p>“Never mind; I will tell you directly after tea.” And directly after tea Roger
                    took Rachael into the garden, and they remained there so long, in excited
                    conversation, that when they returned the tea‐party was hopelessly dispersed,
                    and Ruby fast asleep in her bed upstairs. Had Ruby not been fast asleep she
                    would have heard a great buzzing and bustle, on the little landing outside her
                    door, and the words, <term>moonlight, sea, tide, towels</term>, would<pb n="56" xml:id="VAB7152-057"/> have reached her ears, and she would have roused
                    herself to learn what new plot was being made. As it was, she slept through all
                    the buzzing till the plot was perfected, and silence reigned again on the
                    landing. Then her sleep seemed to break up into pieces, and between the pieces
                    she heard voices singing outside her window. Once she opened her eyes and saw
                    the room full of moonlight, and through the half‐drawn curtains she glanced at
                    the Priory, and thought how clear and cold it looked in the sharp silvery light.
                    Then again she opened them, and, as she did so, there was a rushing of little
                    shadows across the curtains—fairy shadows every one, dancing, dancing, in a long
                    procession. And as the last shadow danced by, Ruby heard them singing in the
                    garden, and their song seemed to be of her. <q>
                        <lg type="verse_paragraph">
                            <l>“She has opened the gate,</l>
                            <l>And she must not delay,</l>
                            <l>Every step she may take</l>
                            <l>On the wonderful way.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="verse_paragraph">
                            <l>Through the land and the sea,</l>
                            <l>She may travel at will,</l>
                            <l>And her eyes shall be free</l>
                            <l>From all shadow of ill.”</l>
                        </lg>
                    </q></p>
                <p>All through the night Ruby heard fairies singing round the cottage. She did not
                    rouse herself: it was natural now to hear them singing.</p>
                <pb n="57" xml:id="VAB7152-058"/>
                <p> </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="58" xml:id="VAB7152-059"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>CHAPTER VII</head>
                <p><hi>IT</hi> was the beautiful lady herself who called Ruby next morning at
                    dawn.</p>
                <p>“I thought you would come,” said Ruby, as she stepped out to her. “Where are we
                    going?”</p>
                <p>“It is for you to say.”</p>
                <p>“We will see what the Priory was like in the old times, when the monks lived
                    there.” Ruby looked across the wheat‐fields at the ruins which had shone in the
                    moonlight.</p>
                <p>“Then put your hand in mine, shut your eyes, and wish.” Ruby closed her eyes and
                    wished, and at once felt herself borne upwards beside her companion. She could
                    feel the touch of the soft mantle as they moved through the air. They flew a
                    great distance, and Ruby could see beneath her lids that their flight was
                    through darkness. She longed many times to open her eyes, and learn what manner
                    of country it was they were passing, but the voice beside her each time said:
                    “With closed eyes, Ruby,” and she kept them shut obediently, until her feet
                    touched ground, and the hand which held hers withdrew its clasp.</p>
                <p>“You may open them now.”</p>
                <pb n="59" xml:id="VAB7152-060"/>
                <p>Ruby opened them and looked about her in wonder. She was in a great church, and
                    she was standing at the end of it, with huge pillars on either side of
                    her—immense round stone pillars with a great zigzag pattern cut deeply into them
                    and running round them from top to bottom—and beyond the pillars, were the
                    aisles of the church; but here the light was dim, for across them the huge
                    pillars cast their shadows. Overhead were great round stone arches, reaching
                    from pillar to pillar, resting upon them as if they had rested thus for ever. At
                    the end of the building a great tower rose up, and the pillars turned off to
                    right and left. The church was built in the form of a cross, and Ruby was
                    looking up the nave to the choir, and to the great east window above it. She
                    walked towards the window slowly, as a ray of sunlight shone through the
                    lightly‐stained glass, and the few pieces of colour in it sparkled like precious
                    stones. Soon the sunlight grew stronger; and throughout the church it shone from
                    pictured windows, painted in deep blues and reds; filling the building with a
                    haze of colour, but through the jewelled east window the sun sparkled most
                    beautifully of all. And upon the windows, and over all the walls, were pictures
                    of Bible stories: and everywhere Ruby saw lovely draperies, embroidered with
                    delicate silks and rarest gems, and figures and fruits and foliage carved in the
                    stone.</p>
                <p>The beautiful lady had disappeared, but Ruby did not miss her, so absorbed was
                    she in all she saw: she felt quite safe in this fair place.</p>
                <pb n="60" xml:id="VAB7152-061"/>
                <p>As she drew near the choir she heard an organ, and voices singing, and, on coming
                    quite near, she saw that people were standing there, singing from sheets of
                    parchment, on which the music was written in such large notes she could read it
                    from where she stood. When the music ceased the monks left their seats one by
                    one, and passed her silently in a solemn procession. Ruby knew they were monks,
                    by their long black gowns tied in at the waist with leathern girdles, by their
                    shaven heads, and bare feet. She hastened after them.</p>
                <p>“Oh, please tell me all about yourselves,” she was going to say, but stopped
                    abruptly, as the last monk in the procession turned and looked at her, and put
                    his finger to his lips to enjoin silence. He looked for a moment, then he held
                    out his hand to her and led her after the others. The procession passed down the
                    church to a door in the aisle, and through it each monk stepped slowly, Ruby’s
                    friend closing it behind him. She observed him curiously as he did so, and
                    thought how sad and tired he looked.</p>
                <p>“Are you happy here?” she asked, as he turned to walk again.</p>
                <p>The monk bent a grave face towards her.</p>
                <p>“I was happy long ago, and long ago I was unhappy: here we have peace only.” Then
                    in a lighter tone he continued: “We lead a busy life. We are in the cloisters
                    now.” And he pointed down the walk in which they stood. It was a long stone
                    gallery, with a wall on one side, and on the other side a line of stone pillars,
                    upon which rested round arches, open to the air: and overhead was a stone<pb n="61" xml:id="VAB7152-062"/> roof fashioned likewise in arches. Three other
                    such galleries made, with this one, a long walk round a square lawn, in the
                    middle of which a fountain played and sparkled.</p>
                <p>“We work here,” said the monk. And he led Ruby up to a group of monks who were
                    writing at a table.</p>
                <p>“They are illuminating books for use in our Church services,” he said, as Ruby
                    examined their painting and thought how delicate and wonderful it was. Farther
                    on he showed her another group of workers, binding and mending books, and
                    rubbing out the thumb marks upon the pages. Then, in one of the other galleries,
                    he showed her a monk teaching Latin to a class of boys, and in another a group
                    of choir‐boys, practising the psalms for a later service.</p>
                <p>In the last gallery she saw a number of monks writing at a long table. They were
                    not illuminating like the others. Ruby looked at her guide for explanation.</p>
                <p>“They are making notes for the great diary in the writing‐room.”</p>
                <p>“Diary!” said Ruby, in surprise.</p>
                <p>“Yes; we keep a diary in this monastery—you know, of course, you are in a
                    monastery—a diary of everything that happens, not only here, but throughout the
                    kingdom. In it are written all the deeds of our king and of his enemies.”</p>
                <p>“But,” said Ruby, “how can you know about everything?”</p>
                <p>“There are so many of us, you see, we each contribute different news and
                    information. Any news we think<pb n="62" xml:id="VAB7152-063"/> important enough
                    to be entered, we write on a piece of parchment and slip into the diary, and
                    one, who is carefully chosen, reads the slips and decides whether or not they
                    shall be entered. Then, if he approves, he copies them carefully into the big
                    book.”</p>
                <p>“What a clever plan,” said Ruby. She began to feel quite at home with this
                    blackly‐draped monk, he had so kind a smile and so pleasant a voice. “Please let
                    me see where you live.”</p>
                <p>“We live here mostly, in the cloisters.”</p>
                <p>“But where do you sleep and have meals?”</p>
                <p>“The names for the rooms are rather long; will you remember them?”</p>
                <p>“Oh yes; I shall remember if you tell me.” Ruby always remembered things after
                    one lesson.</p>
                <p>“These are the dormitories, where we sleep.” He led her upstairs into a room over
                    the cloisters.</p>
                <p>Along the wall was a row of narrow beds, side by side, and of furniture in the
                    room this was all. It looked very bare, and felt very cold, as the wind blew in
                    from the open roof at the end.</p>
                <p>“I suppose you have studies of your own?” said Ruby, looking about her with
                    dissatisfaction.</p>
                <p>“No; we sleep, eat, work, and do everything together.”</p>
                <p>Then her guide led her downstairs into the big dining‐hall or refectory, and he
                    told her to be sure to remember its name, as he showed her the big fireplace in
                    the middle of the room. Then he took her into the chapter‐house, or
                    council‐chamber, where the heads<pb n="63" xml:id="VAB7152-064"/> of the
                    monastery met to discuss important matters; and then he showed her the great
                    kitchen, with its army of cooks and scullions. After this he took her into the
                    guest‐room, which was richly provided with hangings and delicate furniture, and
                    more carefully ornamented than any part of the monastery, except the church. And
                    he told her the names of the kings who had slept there, and of the famous people
                    who had accepted the monastery’s hospitality.</p>
                <p>“The poorest traveller, also, has a right to food and shelter from us,” he said;
                    “we entertain all who knock at our gates.” And then he led her through several
                    buildings into the wheat‐field outside. “Now, Ruby, look at our church, at the
                    ruin you have so often watched from your window.”</p>
                <p>Ruby looked, and there stood the Priory, perfect and complete: with its two rows
                    of round‐topped windows, and its strong tower, and its beautiful east window
                    looking out over the sea. She could see clearly now that the great building was
                    in the shape of a cross, and all around it stretched its fields, in which
                    numberless servants of the monastery were working.</p>
                <p>“And now, little Ruby, I must go, I must go, I must go.” The monk’s voice grew
                    faint as he spoke, his black garments grew bright, the dark folds grew luminous
                    and green and full of sweet embroideries. Then, raising her eyes, Ruby beheld
                    the face of the beautiful lady.</p>
                <p>“But the monk! Were you the monk?”</p>
                <p>The beautiful lady smiled in answer to Ruby’s question.</p>
                <pb n="64" xml:id="VAB7152-065"/>
                <p>“Perhaps,” she said. “Look, it will not endure longer.”</p>
                <p>And Ruby, turning her eyes again to the Priory, saw it fade and disappear in a
                    golden haze: but the face of the beautiful lady grew clearer, and her raiment
                    shone more brightly, as the mist grew denser.</p>
                <p>“Rest in my arms,” she said. And she took Ruby in her arms, and sprang upwards
                    with her into the air. Up and up she flew, and the birds sang their morning song
                    about her head; then upwards and upwards through the sunshine, and the birds
                    sang at her feet; and higher and higher, to the delicate white clouds which the
                    sea breeze had scattered along the sky, and the songs of the birds came faintly
                    from the distance beneath.</p>
                <p>“And up and up,” said Ruby, “until I see the rosy world on the other side of the
                    clouds.”</p>
                <p>But the beautiful lady shook her head.</p>
                <p>“You have seen enough this morning; it is downwards now—down to your own
                    Sea‐thrift and another day. Shut your eyes, shut your eyes.”</p>
                <p>Ruby’s eyes closed and her head sank on to the beautiful lady’s shoulder. When
                    she awoke, it was to the sound of the breakfast gong, and to find herself tucked
                    up cosily in her own little bed. </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="65" xml:id="VAB7152-066"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>CHAPTER VIII</head>
                <p><hi>AT</hi> breakfast that morning, Roger and Rachael were quieter than usual,
                    and as soon as Ruby came downstairs they took her into the garden and said they
                    must all go for a walk. Roger wheeled round the big basket bath‐chair, that had
                    been borrowed for their invalid, and began packing it with shawls, cushions, and
                    biscuits.</p>
                <p>“I don’t think I want to go just yet,” said Ruby.</p>
                <p>“Oh, you must come now, please, Ruby,” whispered Rachael; “we’ve something to
                    tell you.”</p>
                <p>“It’s about last night,” said Roger, “about something which happened. Do you
                    think it really <emph>did</emph> happen?” he added, turning to Rachael.</p>
                <p>“Oh, it must have happened,” exclaimed Rachael, “because of the—” She broke off
                    abruptly, and nodded her head in the direction of the clothes‐line outside the
                    kitchen door, on which their bathing things were hanging. Ruby walked towards it
                    and examined the garments, then she came back to Roger and the chair.</p>
                <pb n="66" xml:id="VAB7152-067"/>
                <p>“I don’t see anything strange about the bathing things!”</p>
                <p>“Didn’t you notice <emph>anything</emph> different?”</p>
                <p>“They are not wet; you didn’t bathe this morning.”</p>
                <p>“No; but they are not dry, are they?”</p>
                <p>“Oh, I see, you had a bathe in the evening?”</p>
                <p>“Not exactly in the evening.”</p>
                <p>“In the night! No; you didn’t bathe in the night?”</p>
                <p>Roger and Rachael nodded their heads solemnly.</p>
                <p>“In the moonlight,” they answered, as Ruby seated herself in the chair in
                    obedience to their arrangements.</p>
                <p>“We’ll tell you when we get to the lane; but I wish I knew whether it really
                    happened or not!” Roger spoke with a puzzled and rather worried air.</p>
                <p>“It is difficult to be quite sure,” said Ruby sympathetically, thinking of the
                    golden gate, the deep sea, and the restored Priory. “But I am <emph>sure</emph>
                    it all really happened,” she added, as she remembered the beautiful lady.</p>
                <p>“But you don’t know,” began Roger.</p>
                <p>“I was thinking of things that have happened to me,” said Ruby; “but mine will
                    take a long time to tell, so tell yours first.”</p>
                <p>“Ours will take ever so long, too, so we must be quick,” said Rachael, as she
                    opened the gate. Then Rachael pulled, and Roger pushed, and the chair rolled
                    away at a great pace through the village, until it came to Honeysuckle Lane, the
                    prettiest of all the lanes leading to the sea. Here they stopped to take breath,
                    and sat down under the hedge.</p>
                <pb n="67" xml:id="VAB7152-068"/>
                <p>“Well,” began Roger, as soon as he could speak, “you know how bright the moon was
                    last night; we got up and dressed by it when everyone was asleep, and slipped
                    out of the window.”</p>
                <p>“How did you get out?” asked Ruby, greatly interested.</p>
                <p>“We fastened the strap of the big trunk to the bed, and slid down it; it isn’t
                    much of a drop.”</p>
                <p>“Did anyone help you?”</p>
                <p>“Of course not; everyone was asleep. Well, we took our bathing things and went up
                    the barley‐field, to the flagstaff, and down by the coast‐guard gap to the
                    sand.”</p>
                <p>“Didn’t the coast‐guard see you?”</p>
                <p>“No one was there—we were quite alone—everywhere it was still and bright. The
                    only sound we heard was made by the cows on the cliff, crunching their food and
                    moving about the grass.”</p>
                <p>“And,” said Rachael, taking up the story, “the moon was so bright we could see
                    everything clearly all along the coast, and along the silvery path across the
                    sea we could see for miles and miles, much farther than we see by day.”</p>
                <p>“But,” went on Roger, “although the sea was perfectly smooth, along the sand the
                    waves were breaking, in that tiresome way they have, on the pebbles. Rachael was
                    afraid of getting her feet cut, and just as I was going to carry her into the
                    water we heard voices calling us. Everywhere, as the waves curled over, and the
                    silvery foam rolled down their smooth sides, we saw faces nodding to us and
                    hands beckoning us.”</p>
                <pb n="68" xml:id="VAB7152-069"/>
                <p>“Did they say anything?” asked Ruby.</p>
                <p>“But, Ruby, are you not astonished?”</p>
                <p>“No,” said Ruby; “do tell me what they said, or sang.”</p>
                <p>Roger and Rachael thought for a few minutes, then they repeated together: <q>
                        <lg type="verse_paragraph">
                            <l>“To the sea, the sea,</l>
                            <l rend="ti-2">For a moonlit while,</l>
                            <l>For the path is free</l>
                            <l rend="ti-2">To the Silver Isle;</l>
                            <l>And the waves now break on the shining sand,</l>
                            <l>But a fairy mile from the sleeping land.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="verse_paragraph">
                            <l>He who comes must stay</l>
                            <l rend="ti-2">From the dawn till night,</l>
                            <l>And from night till day</l>
                            <l rend="ti-2">And the sun’s first light,</l>
                            <l>If he comes to sail for a fairy mile,</l>
                            <l>To the sea‐girt shore of the Silver Isle.”</l>
                        </lg>
                    </q></p>
                <p>“We’ve both remembered!” they cried delightedly, as they finished. “Then it must
                    be true!”</p>
                <p>“Oh, please go on,” said Ruby; “what did they do then?”</p>
                <p>“They sang the words over and over many times, and beckoned to us more and more;
                    then I carried Rachael as far as the first wave, and somehow she dropped, and I
                    slipped, and we were both pulled under and borne out into the smooth water
                    beyond the breakers; we felt little arms and hands all about us.”</p>
                <p>Roger paused, and Rachael took up the tale.</p>
                <p>“They hid from us as soon as we began swimming<pb n="69" xml:id="VAB7152-070"/>
                    about. We heard them sing the same song over and over and over, and we tried to
                    find them; but we did not see them again until we tried to come in. Then the
                    little hands and arms helped us back in the same way, and, as we stepped on to
                    the firm sand, they all arose from the water and took hands, and danced away
                    across the sea along the silvery path. We waited a long time for them to come
                    back, but they did not sing or come any more, so we ran home and climbed in at
                    the window again and went to bed.”</p>
                <p>“What do you think about it, Ruby?” asked Roger. “Do you think we both dreamed
                    it?”</p>
                <p>“No; it really happened,” said Ruby. And then, of course, she told them of her
                    own adventures in the early mornings. When the long story of them was finished
                    Roger asked the same question.</p>
                <p>“What do you think about it, Ruby? Do you think you dreamed it?”</p>
                <p>“No; I am sure the things really happened,” said Ruby, “but if one could stay for
                    a day and a night—” <q>
                        <l>“From the dawn till night,</l>
                        <l>And from night till day,”</l>
                    </q> sang the others.</p>
                <p>“Of course, then,” continued Ruby thoughtfully, “there <emph>could</emph> be no
                    doubt. I wonder if we could find the Silver Isle by ourselves.”</p>
                <p>After a long discussion they agreed it would be useless to try, but later in the
                    morning, when they reappeared in the garden, they all seemed strangely
                        preoccupied.<pb n="70" xml:id="VAB7152-071"/> Even the morning bathe did not
                    rouse them. Ruby was allowed to go down to the sea this morning for the first
                    time, and she stood beside the tent and looked at the sky and at the water, and
                    at the line of ripples along the sand. There were no waves this morning, no
                    hiding‐places for fairies along the shore. She stood and wondered about the
                    Silver Isle; and when Roger and Rachael ran races after their bathe, and Ethel
                    and Charlie built the Coliseum at her very feet, she still wondered about
                    it.</p>
                <p>“The sea‐birds must go there when they fly out to sea and disappear,” she said,
                    when Charlie told her the Coliseum was completed. Charlie, of course, was
                    surprised.</p>
                <p>“Must go where?” he asked—“to the Coliseum?”</p>
                <p>“No; to the Silver Isle. I forgot you did not know about it. I’m afraid I have
                    been thinking of it all the time. But the Coliseum is very nice; thank you for
                    making it. I think the birds <emph>do</emph> stop at the Silver Isle, when they
                    fly across the seas to the warm countries. They cannot fly for days and nights
                    without resting, can they? I am so glad they have the Silver Isle.”</p>
                <p>“The albatross flies for weeks without resting, and some of the small birds must
                    fly for days and nights, every year, to cross the seas they do cross. How
                    strange it is that no one ever sees them set out upon their journey, or arrive
                    at their journey’s end.<choice>
                        <corr>”</corr>
                        <sic/>
                    </choice></p>
                <p>“They rest at the Silver Isle,” repeated Ruby.</p>
                <p>“Where is the isle?” asked Ethel, looking up from her finishing touches to the
                    Coliseum.</p>
                <pb n="71" xml:id="VAB7152-072"/>
                <p>“I’m not sure; I’m going to find out.”</p>
                <p>“In your dreams, Ruby?”</p>
                <p>“No; not in dreams,” said Ruby decidedly. “By this time to‐morrow I shall have
                    seen it and know all about it.”</p>
                <p>Charlie took out his watch. “Very well, then,” he said ; “this time to‐morrow I
                    shall remind you, and expect a full description. If I like your account of it I
                    shall take Ethel there on a visit.”</p>
                <p>When bedtime came that evening, Ruby wished Roger and Rachael good‐night at the
                    top of the steep little stairs, outside her door.</p>
                <p>“I will tell you all about it to‐morrow,” she said.</p>
                <p>“About what?” Roger and Rachael were sure now that their adventure of the night
                    before had been a dream.</p>
                <p>“The Silver Isle,” explained Ruby; “I shall go and see it at sunrise.”</p>
                <p>“Well, you will be sure to tell us, won’t you?”</p>
                <p>“Yes; quite sure. I promise. Good‐night.” </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="73" xml:id="VAB7152-073"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>CHAPTER IX</head>
                <epigraph>
                    <l>When you have opened the golden gate,</l>
                    <l>You never more shall in longing wait,</l>
                    <l>You have but to wish, and to close your eyes,</l>
                    <l>And you go wherever your new wish lies.</l>
                </epigraph>
                <p><hi>THE</hi> next morning, very early, Ruby heard a chorus of sweet voices in the
                    garden. She stepped out of bed and drew back the curtains. All the world was
                    grey—no blue was in the sky, no green was in the grass, no yellow was in the
                    wheat—everywhere was greyness. In the garden a number of small figures were
                    dancing on the lawn; these, too, were dressed in grey, but in greys which melted
                    into rose colours and pale yellows. On their heads the singers wore silver caps,
                    that changed from silver to gold as they danced and sang. Ruby stepped on to the
                    window‐sill, and saw a silvery‐gold streak stretching across the big barley
                    field, from the garden to the cliff.</p>
                <pb n="74" xml:id="VAB7152-074"/>
                <p>“It is an army of silver‐gold caps,” she said, as she watched it.</p>
                <p>“An army to take you prisoner,” answered the voices from the garden, and the
                    sound of the voices was as of silver bells.</p>
                <p>“Prisoner, why?”</p>
                <p>“Oh, we don’t know why. We’ve come because we were sent.”</p>
                <p>“Who sent you?”</p>
                <p>“The beautiful lady sent us to take you to the Silver Isle.”</p>
                <p>“The Silver Isle!” Ruby clapped her hands.</p>
                <p><q>
                        <l>“He who comes must stay</l>
                        <l rend="ti-2">From the dawn till night,</l>
                        <l>And from night till day</l>
                        <l rend="ti-2">And the sun’s first light,”</l>
                    </q> sang the fairies.</p>
                <p>“I suppose I shall not be kept longer than that,” said Ruby, somewhat
                    anxiously.</p>
                <p>“We cannot tell. Come, we are waiting.” And suddenly the whole company drew up in
                    military order, and each fairy touched his cap respectfully.</p>
                <p>Ruby looked along their lines with great interest.</p>
                <p>“I am so fond of drilling,” she. said; “and what beautifully even lines you make.
                    I suppose you know all the exercises—skipping‐ropes, and clubs, and balls. I
                    never can do balls, they fly about so; can you do them?”</p>
                <p>The fairies, for answer, stepped into position, and<pb n="75" xml:id="VAB7152-075"/> in an instant were all doing the double ball exercise
                    beautifully. In all the company not one little silvery gold ball fell to the
                    ground.</p>
                <p>“Oh dear!” sighed Ruby, “I wish mine would keep up like that!”</p>
                <p>“Practise,” came from the company, in a tone of command that quite startled
                    her.</p>
                <p>“I do practise,” she explained, “when I am well.” Then, to bring them back to
                    their respectful manner, she said: “I suppose you do not know how long I shall
                    stay in the Silver Isle?”</p>
                <p>The remark had not the effect she expected. Instead of touching caps in line, the
                    whole company broke up in confusion and began dancing wildly.</p>
                <p>“Be quick! Do not ask any more questions. We shall be late.”</p>
                <p>“We must be there before the sun is up.”</p>
                <p>“Before the first streak of light stretches across the sky.”</p>
                <p>“Before the sea‐birds leave their footmarks on the sand.”</p>
                <p>The fairies crowded together beneath her window.</p>
                <p>“Jump,” they cried. And a soft grey something, looking like meadow mist, was
                    unrolled.</p>
                <p>Ruby had no time to examine it, she was urged so peremptorily to be quick. She
                    jumped obediently into the midst of the dancing company.</p>
                <p>Then they ceased dancing, and some behind, and some in front, and others at the
                    sides, carried her across the garden.</p>
                <pb n="76" xml:id="VAB7152-076"/>
                <p>“I like going quickly,” she said, smiling at them.</p>
                <p>“We shall go quickly enough directly,” they answered, as they skipped with her
                    over the wall.</p>
                <p>“It’s a kind of tandem,” laughed Ruby, looking at the long line in front of
                    her.</p>
                <p>“No, no! it is random—random—random—” And the fairies ran swiftly through the
                    barley, through the big field to the edge of the cliff; but although they ran so
                    swiftly and so lightly that the barley closed up again behind them as they
                    passed, Ruby felt quite safe in her carriage. She moved along as smoothly as
                    upon still waters.</p>
                <p>At the cliff edge they set her upon the grass; and the company of twilight
                    fairies called the sea fairies from the sandy grey shore. The sea fairies called
                    again in answer, and the sound of their voices was as of sea‐spray falling upon
                    the rocks.</p>
                <p>“We wait for Ruby,” they said. And, from each wave that broke upon the shore, a
                    silvery figure rose up out of the foam. All along the shore they arose, as far
                    as Ruby could see, and as they ran towards her each stooped and picked up a
                    gossamer mantle, grey, green, and blue. Ruby could not tell their colours; they
                    changed continually as the fairies ran up with them from the sea.</p>
                <p>“I have seen the spiders spinning them,” she said, “from one pebble to another,
                    all over the beach.”</p>
                <p>Then one of the fairies, on the cliff, pointed to a streak of yellow stretching
                    from the east across the sky. The fairies below turned and looked, and beckoned
                    to Ruby.</p>
                <pb n="77" xml:id="VAB7152-077"/>
                <p>“The sails are set for the Silver Isle, and we must reach it before to‐day’s sun
                    leaves the sea.”</p>
                <p>And, drawn up out of the water, on the dry sand, Ruby saw a silver boat, with
                    silvery sails moving to and fro in the breeze. The boat was long and slim.</p>
                <p>“Will she sail quickly?” asked Ruby.</p>
                <p>“As quickly as the swallows.”</p>
                <p>Twined round the masts of the boat were garlands of sea flowers, and corals; and,
                    as the light grew brighter, the inside of the boat shone like mother‐of‐pearl.
                    Some of the sea fairies ran up the cliff and took Ruby’s hands, and led her to
                    the boat. She stepped in at once and put her hand upon the rudder.</p>
                <p>“Where will you steer?” they asked in chorus.</p>
                <p>“Across the sea to the sun.”</p>
                <p>As she spoke the sun showed above the water, a red arc on the horizon. Before her
                    boat was launched delicate pink clouds spread lightly up the sky, up and up,
                    over her head; and landwards farther than she could see: and, as the arc grew
                    bigger, a rosy light filled the sky, and the sand‐banks shone like rose
                    petals.</p>
                <p>Higher rose the sun, and, when the boat touched the water, orange and yellow
                    cloud‐ways filled the sky. Then higher and higher it rose, until blue and green
                    shone between opal dyes, and all the glory of the dawn was about her. Then the
                    wind filled her sails, and the sea fairies slipped into the sea behind her; and
                    as the boat moved over the water the sunshine fell upon her face. She turned to
                    wave her<pb n="78" xml:id="VAB7152-078"/> hand to the twilight fairies who
                    waited still at the edge of the cliff.</p>
                <p>“Good‐bye; thank you so much for coming for me. I shall see you again?”</p>
                <p>“Maybe, maybe; good‐bye,” they answered, as they waved hands in a long line.</p>
                <p>As Ruby turned to wave hers again, she saw they were no longer the grey twilight
                    company of the garden, but a brilliant army in golden armour, shining and
                    sparkling in the sun.</p>
                <p>“Good‐bye, then,” she said, waving her hand for the seventh time; “do not wait
                    any longer.”</p>
                <p>“We wait till you return,” said they on the land. And the shining company
                    twinkled for a moment along the cliff, and disappeared.</p>
                <p>“But they do not know <choice>
                        <corr>how</corr>
                        <sic>now</sic>
                    </choice> long I shall be,” said Ruby to her sea friends—“at least, they did not
                    tell me when I asked them—but that does not matter: this is so beautiful, I do
                    not mind how far the fairy mile may be.” And her boat went skimming over the
                    water like a silver bird.</p>
                <p>The sea fairies all the time swam round her. They were so many, they made a long
                    shining track behind her, and as they swam after her they sang: <q>
                        <l>“He who comes must stay</l>
                        <l rend="ti-2">From the dawn till night,</l>
                        <l>And from night till day</l>
                        <l rend="ti-2">And the sun’s first light,</l>
                        <l>If he comes to sail for a fairy mile,</l>
                        <l>To the sea‐girt shore of the Silver Isle.”</l>
                    </q></p>
                <pb n="79" xml:id="VAB7152-079"/>
                <p>“Shall I see all there is to see in a day and a night?” asked Ruby, of the
                    fairies who swam beside the boat.</p>
                <p>The sea fairies laughed. “Days and nights,” said they, “cannot show you the
                    stores of the ages.”</p>
                <p>“But you will bring me again,” she said, “many times, and let me see by
                    degrees?”</p>
                <p>“That is for you to decide,” they answered solemnly. “If you tell of what you see
                    in the Silver Isle you can never visit it again.”</p>
                <p>“Oh dear!”</p>
                <p>Ruby was dreadfully disappointed. She already longed for Roger and Rachael to
                    share her delight. She began to argue the matter; but as she did so the wind
                    suddenly blew more strongly, and more strongly: and more strongly it blew until
                    the boat flew faster than her sea friends could follow: they lay back upon the
                    waves and disappeared, leaving Ruby to sail alone to the unknown isle.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="80" xml:id="VAB7152-080"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>CHAPTER X</head>
                <p><hi>AT</hi> the moment Ruby beheld the Silver Isle, Ruby’s mother opened her eyes
                    and looked at Ruby’s bed, and wondered to see it empty. As she wondered she
                    heard laughter from the other room, and thought Ruby had awakened early and
                    joined the others for company.</p>
                <p>Now Ruby, although recovered from her illness, was by no means quite well and
                    strong, and her mother rose hastily, fearing the doings of the other room. She
                    had had a long experience of early morning pillow‐fights, and sponge‐matches;
                    and she pictured the upheaved state of the other room, with Ruby sitting in the
                    middle of damp washing materials.</p>
                <p>“Ruby, you should not have come without asking me,” she said, as she opened
                    Rachael’s door.</p>
                <p>“Ruby, mother! Ruby isn’t here.”</p>
                <p>Rachael was already dressed, and Roger had come in to tell her to look at a
                    “purple emperor” from the window.</p>
                <pb n="81" xml:id="VAB7152-081"/>
                <p>“Not here! She must be downstairs. Run down, Roger, and tell her to come up
                    quickly.”</p>
                <p>Roger ran downstairs, but Ruby was nowhere to be seen.</p>
                <p>Their mother grew anxious, and went back to Ruby’s room. There were Ruby’s
                    clothes lying neatly on the chair by the bed: everything was there except the
                    little dressing‐gown and woolly slippers.</p>
                <p>Ruby’s mother dressed quickly and ran downstairs. Had the servants or the
                    gardener seen Ruby<choice>
                        <corr>?</corr>
                        <sic>.</sic>
                    </choice> Was the door unfastened when they came down this morning?</p>
                <p>No; no one had seen her, and the door had not been unfastened.</p>
                <p>“O mother,” said Rachael, “do you think anything has happened to Ruby? We told
                    her about the fairies we saw—or thought we saw—in the sea, when we bathed in the
                    moonlight; and last night Ruby said she was going to the Silver Isle: the
                    fairies sang to us of the Silver Isle.”</p>
                <p>The children’s mother sat upon Ruby’s little empty bed, and put her hands to her
                    head in bewilderment.</p>
                <p>“My dear children, what are you saying? What moonlight bathe, what Silver Isle,
                    and what do you mean when you tell me you have seen fairies?”</p>
                <p>“We saw fairies in the foam, mother,” began Roger confidently; “at least, I was
                    sure we saw them until I began to question myself.”</p>
                <p>“And so was I,” cried Rachael. “They called us from the waves, and sang the same
                    song over and over many times.”</p>
                <pb n="82" xml:id="VAB7152-082"/>
                <p>“Yes, yes,” added Roger eagerly. “O mother, we really did see them. Don’t you
                    remember the song, Rachael?”</p>
                <p>“Yes, yes.”</p>
                <p>The two children repeated the words of the song: <q>
                        <lg type="verse_paragraph">
                            <l>“To the sea, the sea,</l>
                            <l rend="ti-2">For a moonlit while,</l>
                            <l>For the path is free</l>
                            <l rend="ti-2">To the Silver Isle;</l>
                            <l>And the waves now break on the shining sand,</l>
                            <l>But a fairy mile from the sleeping land.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="verse_paragraph">
                            <l>He who comes must stay</l>
                            <l rend="ti-2">From the dawn till night,</l>
                            <l>And from night till day</l>
                            <l rend="ti-2">And the sun’s first light,</l>
                            <l>If he comes to sail for a fairy mile,</l>
                            <l>To the sea‐girt shore of the Silver Isle.”</l>
                        </lg>
                    </q></p>
                <p>“We told Ruby the song,” continued Roger, in distress. “She has been thinking
                    ever since of the Silver Isle, and last night, when we wished her good‐night,
                    she said she was going to find it.”</p>
                <p>“Where do you suppose it is?” asked their mother quietly.</p>
                <p>“Across the water, at the end of the shining moonlight‐way, where the sea touches
                    the sky.”</p>
                <p>“Come, you must help me to find Ruby now,” said their mother, rising. “Put the
                    Silver Isle out of your heads.”</p>
                <p>“Wonderful things have been happening to Ruby, mother, during her illness,”
                    persisted Rachael and Roger.<pb n="83" xml:id="VAB7152-083"/> But their mother
                    looked at them with anxious eyes, and told them to tell their story to their
                    father, while she went to Ethel and Charlie’s.</p>
                <p>As she went, she had an uneasy feeling that she should not find Ruby there; and
                    she did not find her. When she had retold Roger and Rachael’s story of the
                    moonlight fairies, and the Silver Isle, Charlie said:</p>
                <p>“The children have dreamed, and imagined, and talked about fairies, until they
                    can no longer distinguish between dreaming and reality.”</p>
                <p>“How does the second verse go?” he added, for Ruby’s mother had told them the
                    song. “Oh yes; I remember— <q>
                        <l>‘He who comes must stay</l>
                        <l rend="ti-2">From the dawn till night,</l>
                        <l>And from night till day</l>
                        <l rend="ti-2">And the sun’s first light,</l>
                        <l>If he comes to sail for a fairy mile,</l>
                        <l>To the sea‐girt shore of the Silver Isle.’</l>
                    </q> How easily I remember, and you remembered it too: that is the way with
                    fairy songs.”</p>
                <p>But Ruby’s mother could no longer be patient.</p>
                <p>“Come, come,” she said, “you are dreaming too. We must <emph>do</emph> something;
                    we cannot sit down and wait for a day and a night.”</p>
                <p>“It might be the wisest plan,” said Charlie, beginning to roll a cigarette.</p>
                <p>When Charlie began to roll a cigarette, in conversation, every one knew that his
                    contribution to it had come<pb n="84" xml:id="VAB7152-084"/> to an end; so
                    Ruby’s mother turned from Ethel and Charlie’s window, and went into the road
                    again. There she met Roger and Rachael with their father.</p>
                <p>“They have been dreaming,” said the children’s father.</p>
                <p>“Charlie has been dreaming too,” said the children’s mother.</p>
                <p>“And Ethel—”</p>
                <p>“I am coming to help you look for Ruby,” said Ethel cheerfully, running from the
                    cottage. “First of all we’ll go down to the tent; she may be there.”</p>
                <p>Ethel led the way with Rachael, along the loke and down the sandy hill, followed
                    by Roger and his father and mother; Charlie watched them quietly from the
                    window.</p>
                <p>“Perhaps Charlie has seen fairies when he has been sketching. He gets up at all
                    times to paint things—sometimes at sunrise, sometimes before it is light—and he
                    is often on the beach in the moonlight. He finds out‐of‐the‐way places along the
                    cliffs, where no one ever comes. Perhaps he has been to the Silver Isle
                    himself,” said Roger, as his father and mother remained silent.</p>
                <p>“My dear boy, this strong air has got into your heads. We shall find Ruby in the
                    tent,” said Roger’s father, as they stepped on to the sand.</p>
                <p>But Roger’s father was mistaken. Ruby wasn’t in the tent, or anywhere near the
                    tent; neither was she in the big fishing‐boat that lay upon its side at the
                    water’s edge, nor in the boat of Roger’s making, that still eluded its
                    wheelbarrow metamorphosis. Then the<pb n="85" xml:id="VAB7152-085"/> search
                    party divided, and went in different directions: Ethel and Rachael turning
                    southward to the next gap, where the beach‐path ran up into the main road, while
                    Roger, with his father and mother, climbed the steep road leading to the
                    coastguard look‐out, where the long‐boat was kept. Then Roger and his party came
                    down to the beach again, and walked farther north, to Honey Gap, at the end of
                    Honeysuckle Lane. Then they went on farther, to the fishermen’s storehouse;
                    where the shrimping‐nets and tarred ropes and sails and oars were kept. They
                    asked the fishermen if any of them had seen a little girl, in dressing‐gown and
                    woolly slippers, on the sand that morning. The fishermen shook their heads and
                    expressed astonishment; and this was all.</p>
                <p>After a long, tiring search, the party turned back.</p>
                <p>When they reached the tent, they found Ethel and Rachael waiting for them.</p>
                <p>“We’ve had no luck,” said Ethel; “we have been as far as the lighthouse, and have
                    asked everyone we met.”</p>
                <p>Then the whole party sat down upon the sand and looked anxiously out to sea.</p>
                <p>“Here is Charlie,” said Rachael, suddenly breaking the silence; “perhaps he knows
                    something about Ruby. Mother, see, he is beckoning to us, and coming down the
                    cliff from the barley‐field.”</p>
                <p>Rachael rushed off to meet Charlie, and came running back with him, breathless
                    with haste and excitement.</p>
                <p>“Look, look!” she cried, holding up a woollen slipper crocheted in green and
                    blue; “it is Ruby’s, and Charlie found it in the middle of the barley‐field.”
                </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="86" xml:id="VAB7152-086"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>CHAPTER XI</head>
                <p><hi>EACH</hi> of the party examined the slipper carefully. Yes; it certainly was
                    one of Ruby’s little bedroom slippers—the pair had been made for her last
                    birthday by a kind friend. Each of the party questioned Charlie eagerly. Where
                    exactly had he found it? Could he find only one? Was he sure nothing else of
                    Ruby’s was there? Was there any mark in the barley to show in which direction
                    Ruby had strayed?</p>
                <p>Charlie answered none of the questions.</p>
                <p>“Come with me,” he said, “I will show you.”</p>
                <p>He led them to the foot of the cliff down which he had just come.</p>
                <p>“Look carefully,” he said again, pointing up the steep footpath to the
                    barley.</p>
                <p>Everyone began to examine the path, Roger and Rachael more minutely than the
                    others. After some minutes of close scrutiny, up and down, Rachael, from the
                    top, called to the others:</p>
                <p>“Here are marks of tiny feet, close to the barley,<pb n="87" xml:id="VAB7152-087"/> and they show among the barley, too, for a short distance.” She knelt down to
                    examine the marks more thoroughly.</p>
                <p>“Bare feet,” added Roger, quickly on his knees beside her. “Tiny bare feet.”</p>
                <p>“Well,” said Charlie, from below, “what next?”</p>
                <p>“They come down the path,” continued Roger, crawling along on hands and knees.
                    “There are so many, they cross and recross, all the time, down to the bottom.”
                    Roger looked up at Charlie for his explanation.</p>
                <p>“Well,” repeated Charlie, “they do not stop there.”</p>
                <p>“No; of course they don’t. Look, look!” cried Rachael; “they are all over the
                    beach.”</p>
                <p>“Not all over,” corrected Charlie. “Do you notice anything peculiar in the
                    position of the footmarks?”</p>
                <p>“From the top of the path,” said Roger, running up to it quickly, “many of the
                    feet go backwards.”</p>
                <p>“Perhaps they didn’t only come down,” suggested Rachael; “perhaps they went up
                    first.”</p>
                <p>“Precisely,” said Charlie; “that is what happened. The marks are in perfect
                    order.”</p>
                <p>He pointed to the little footmarks, stretching at regular intervals across the
                    sand, from the water’s edge to the cliff, and then up the cliff‐path to the
                    barley. The marks were so slight and delicate, they looked, at first sight, like
                    the footprints of birds.</p>
                <p>“These,” explained Charlie, “were made by feet running up from the sea.”</p>
                <pb n="88" xml:id="VAB7152-088"/>
                <p>“Yes, yes,” cried Rachael; “the sea fairies ran across the sand and up the
                    cliff.”</p>
                <p>“Yes.”</p>
                <p>“But the other feet?” said Roger.</p>
                <p>“The land fairies carried Ruby across the barley‐field,” explained Charlie.</p>
                <p>All this time Ruby’s father and mother, and Ethel, listened in silence. They were
                    not sure that the marks down the cliff, and upon the wet sand, were not the
                    footprints of gulls, and sand‐pipers, and sanderlings.</p>
                <p>Suddenly Rachael called from the water’s edge.</p>
                <p>“Do come quickly. Here are the prettiest things.” She held out her hands full of
                    beautiful little shells, red, yellow, blue, and dainty mother‐of‐pearl.</p>
                <p>“They were all in one place,” she said; “the tide must have left them. And here
                    are seaweeds, and corals, and anemones, that we never get on this coast.”</p>
                <p>Roger went down on his knees beside her, and, in spite of the waves, examined the
                    wet sand.</p>
                <p>“Here is the mark of a keel,” he said in a few minutes. “It is a longboat, and on
                    either side of it are the tiny footmarks, going with it out to sea.”</p>
                <p>“And here,” said Rachael, “is Ruby’s handkerchief, with Ruby’s name embroidered
                    in the corner; it is the one Roger gave her last holidays. O mother, Ruby has
                    certainly gone to the Silver Isle; the fairies have taken her.”</p>
                <p>Roger turned eagerly to his father, but his father shook his head.</p>
                <pb n="89" xml:id="VAB7152-089"/>
                <p>“You have the shoe and the handkerchief, but—” Ruby’s mother and Ethel came up as
                    he paused.</p>
                <p>“Let us go and make inquiries in the village,” they said: and the three turned
                    from the sea and went up to the village.</p>
                <p>But Charlie, with Roger and Rachael, sat by the tent. They were sure Ruby was
                    safe, and, this being so, inquiries were useless. They sat a long time watching
                    the waves and the sky, and Charlie took a sketch‐book from his pocket, and in it
                    drew fairies and fairy boats. By‐and‐by he looked at his watch.</p>
                <p>“Do you know we have been sitting here for two hours? We must go home at once and
                    get something to eat.”</p>
                <p>Roger and Rachael, of course, were not hungry, and said they wanted to wait
                    there, until the fairies brought Ruby back in the morning.</p>
                <p>“That is impossible. We must have a meal immediately,” insisted Charlie, and he
                    took each of them by the hand, and made them run nearly all the way home.</p>
                <p>At Sea‐thrift they met the others, much depressed with unsuccess, having enquired
                    in vain at the Inn, and at the Post‐office, and at every cottage in the village.
                    Charlie made them come indoors with the children. With much reluctance the three
                    seekers obeyed, but, directly the meal was<choice>
                        <corr/>
                        <sic>,</sic>
                    </choice> over<choice>
                        <corr>,</corr>
                        <sic/>
                    </choice> they set out again on their quest. They now made a long and searching
                    examination of all the coastguards. The coastguards said that one or other of
                    them had been at the “look‐out” all<pb n="90" xml:id="VAB7152-090"/> night.
                    Nothing like a little girl in dressing‐gown and slippers had been seen, and as
                    for a boat, or anything else, leaving the beach unnoticed by them, the idea was
                    ridiculous.</p>
                <p>“We are always on the watch,” said the tallest of the men; “nothing can escape
                    us.” And he swept the horizon with his glass in a masterful way, defying the sea
                    to keep any secret from His Majesty’s servants.</p>
                <p>Then the seekers returned to the cottage: and Ruby’s mother said she would
                    bicycle to the doctor’s house, to consult him: and all the others, for differing
                    reasons, decided to ride with her.</p>
                <p>The doctor’s house was about four miles inland. The bicycles were quickly
                    collected, and, in about fifteen minutes, the whole party had left the village
                    and were moving rapidly along the lanes, between hedges of blackberry
                    blossom.</p>
                <p>The doctor’s house stood beside two fine old barns, and the doctor’s front garden
                    was full of flowers; and through an arch of roses, at the end of a gravel path,
                    was a beautiful lawn, with a fruit‐covered wall sheltering it on three sides;
                    and overtopping the wall were poplars and great elms. The doctor himself sat
                    reading in a low chair on the lawn. He put down his book and came towards them,
                    apparently in no way surprised by their number.</p>
                <p>“And how is little Ruby to‐day,” he said, leaning the last bicycle against his
                    hedge.</p>
                <p>“Ah, that is why we are all here!” exclaimed Ruby’s mother. “Ruby has gone!” And
                    she told<pb n="91" xml:id="VAB7152-091"/> him the story of Ruby’s disappearance,
                    and of Roger and Rachael’s account of the fairies, before she and the doctor
                    reached the lawn.</p>
                <p>“Then,” said the doctor, when at last she sat down in the chair he brought for
                    her, “you must wait patiently until to‐morrow morning; that is not
                    difficult.”</p>
                <p>Ruby’s mother looked at him in astonishment.</p>
                <p>“You do not mean—” she began.</p>
                <p>“Of course I mean the children are right,” he interrupted, with a smile. “Wait
                    patiently. Don’t you remember, Ruby said she wanted to see fairies, the day she
                    arrived? She is quite safe.”</p>
                <p>“Yes,” said Rachael, delighted to find the doctor on her side, “yes; Charlie,
                    Roger, and I, know she is safe.”</p>
                <p>“That is all right then,” said the white‐haired doctor, smiling at the children,
                    and looking thoughtfully at Charlie.</p>
                <p>“And your father, and mother, and Ethel,” he continued, turning his kind eyes
                    upon the doubting trio, “think that you, and Charlie, and I, are suffering from
                    a delusion. Is it not so?”</p>
                <p>He turned to the three doubters, and none of the three contradicted him.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="92" xml:id="VAB7152-092"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>CHAPTER XII</head>
                <p><hi>THAT</hi> night Roger and Rachael agreed to sit up in Ruby’s room and watch
                    for Ruby’s return: they were sure she would return. The children’s mother was
                    worn out with the day’s search and anxiety, and too tired to try to persuade
                    them of the uselessness of such a proceeding. The children’s mother had left the
                    doctor with the conviction that he, too, had been dreaming, and was, like the
                    others, suffering from a sudden hallucination; but, in spite of this, she kept
                    the assurance of Ruby’s safety in her heart, and lay down upon her bed with a
                    faint hope that perhaps<pb n="93" xml:id="VAB7152-093"/> she would find Ruby
                    safely asleep, in hers, in the morning.</p>
                <p>The children’s father had ridden, early in the evening, to the nearest town, to
                    make enquiries; and Ethel, until far into the night, was searching the
                    neighbouring villages, in spite of Charlie, who accompanied her, and told her
                    all the time she would have no success.</p>
                <p>“I have never been awake for long in the dark,” said Rachael. “It will be fun to
                    sit up a whole night.”</p>
                <p>“We shall see what Ruby calls the ‘consternations,’ in the sky,” said Roger
                    gaily, placing two chairs by the window.</p>
                <p>“You won’t mind if we have a little meal in the night, will you, mother?” he
                    asked, as Rachael brought in an ample tray of biscuits, bananas, and milk. “We
                    thought we might be hungry before the early morning, and we don’t want to be
                    eating when they arrive.”</p>
                <p>His mother smiled. “No, I don’t mind; I’m afraid I’m nearly asleep. Wake me up,
                    dears, if you feel lonely.”</p>
                <p>“We sha’n’t feel lonely, mother. Need we draw the curtains? We shall see them
                    much sooner—”</p>
                <p>“No; you need not draw the curtains. Good‐night.”</p>
                <p>Ruby’s mother fell into a deep sleep as she spoke, and Roger and Rachael sat down
                    quietly by the window.</p>
                <p>“Mother believes in the Silver Isle at last,” whispered Rachael.</p>
                <pb n="94" xml:id="VAB7152-094"/>
                <p>“Yes;” said Roger; “and when Ruby comes back she can never doubt again.”</p>
                <p>“What time will they bring Ruby?” asked Roger, after a quarter of a hour’s
                    silence.</p>
                <p>“Just before sunrise.”</p>
                <p>There was a long pause.</p>
                <p>“It’s a long time to wait, isn’t it? ” said Roger again. “What is that?”</p>
                <p>They put their heads out of the window, as the gate closed behind their
                    father.</p>
                <p>“It is all right, father,” they said, leaning out to him; “mother’s asleep.”</p>
                <p>Their father looked up in surprise.</p>
                <p>“Is there some news then?”</p>
                <p>“She will be here in the morning, father; do believe she will be here! Mother
                    believes it now, and has gone to sleep happily; we are going to sit up and watch
                    for Ruby across the barley‐field.”</p>
                <p>But their father opened the cottage door, and entered without speaking. They
                    heard him walking up and down the little parlour for a long time, then he went
                    into the garden again, and walked slowly down the path to the gate, and into the
                    road.</p>
                <p>The children sat and talked quietly, until the night was well advanced. The moon
                    was clear and beautiful, and between the banks of fleecy grey cloud were patches
                    of blue sky.</p>
                <p>“They are lakes and rivers,” said Roger, pointing to the blue.</p>
                <p>“How nice to sail along them,” said Rachael, <choice>
                        <orig>look‐<pb n="95" xml:id="VAB7152-095"/> ing</orig>
                        <reg>looking</reg>
                    </choice> up. “The clouds are continents and islands. I should like to land on
                    that little isle in the middle of the biggest lake.” She pointed across the
                    barley‐field, to a silvery grey cloud which hung over the sea. All about it the
                    sky was clear and blue, and the cloud shone silvery in the moonlight.</p>
                <p>“Perhaps that is the Silver Isle,” she whispered.</p>
                <p>“Or its reflection,” suggested Roger.</p>
                <p>By‐and‐by a mass of black cloud drifted up the sky from the west, and a wind blew
                    over the fields; the children shivered, and began to feel the night‐time long
                    and lonely.</p>
                <p>“Let’s have something to eat,” said Roger. They drew up to the tray and ate their
                    midnight meal, and were quickly revived. The rain now began to fall steadily; it
                    poured down in big heavy drops, and heavy thunder rolled across the sky. The
                    storm came very near, the thunder‐clouds seemed to break immediately overhead;
                    but the children’s mother did not wake.</p>
                <p>“How tired mother must have been,” they whispered, as they watched her sleeping
                    peacefully through the storm.</p>
                <p>“Where is father? he did not come back; he will be very wet!”</p>
                <p>“And Ruby, poor little Ruby—I wonder,” began Rachael, thinking of a change of
                    dressing‐gown and slippers for the traveller.</p>
                <p>“They will know how to keep her safe and dry in the storm,” said Roger; “don’t be
                    anxious. How much she will have to tell us,” he went on. “I wish the<pb n="96" xml:id="VAB7152-096"/> morning would come more quickly; a whole night is a
                    long time, isn’t it?” Roger yawned. “I’m not sleepy,” he said, when the storm
                    ceased, “but I’ll just lie down for a bit, it’s rather dull sitting here now
                    there’s nothing to look at.” And he curled up in a rug at the end of Ruby’s
                    bed.</p>
                <p>“Don’t—don’t go to sleep, Roger,” implored Rachael. “We don’t know what time she
                    will come; it would be a dreadful pity if both of us were not watching. Do wake
                    up.”</p>
                <p>“All right, in a minute,” murmured Roger, and he pulled the rug closer about him,
                    and fell into a deep sleep.</p>
                <p>Rachael stood beside him in a despairing attitude for some minutes, then she went
                    and sat alone by the window. She was determined that someone should watch the
                    night through. She managed to it watch for another hour, until the rain stopped
                    and the sky began to clear; but it seemed an endless time, and she began to
                    wonder if she should rest for a few minutes. She wrapped herself in a shawl,
                    leaned back in her chair, closed her eyes, and wondered again if she should have
                    he very shortest nap; and was, of course, in a few minutes, as fast asleep as
                    Roger.</p>
                <p>Ruby’s robin woke her at sunrise. He flew on to the window‐sill and looked at
                    Rachael.</p>
                <p>“Wake, wake,” he chirped.</p>
                <p>Rachael opened her eyes to the bright sunshine, and looked hastily at Ruby’s bed.
                    No; it was all right, Ruby had not come yet; only Roger lay there, still fast
                    asleep. She jumped up and shook him briskly.</p>
                <pb n="97" xml:id="VAB7152-097"/>
                <p>“Wake up Roger; be quick: it is sunrise, and Ruby will be here directly.”</p>
                <p>Roger opened his eyes slowly and stared at Rachael.</p>
                <p>“What’s up?” He looked about him in surprise; then he remembered. “Ah! she hasn’t
                    come yet; but look—look!” he cried excitedly, going to the window. “They are
                    coming—over there—close to the cliff—I see bright little figures dancing about.
                    See how they shine and sparkle! They are coming through the barley;
                    look—look!”</p>
                <p>“Yes,” cried Rachael, clapping her hands; “how quickly they come. See, Ruby is in
                    the middle; they are carrying her.”</p>
                <p>“She is in a chair of gold, and the chair has a canopy hung with curtains of
                    gold, and golden draperies flow behind it as they come.”</p>
                <p>And through the barley‐field the fairy procession came, with Ruby in its midst,
                    and it set her down upon the grass beneath her window.</p>
                <p>“O Ruby,” cried Roger and Rachael, “how glad we are to see you, and how beautiful
                    it all is!”</p>
                <p>“Yes.” Ruby smiled up through the shining crowd.</p>
                <p>“May we speak to them?” asked Rachael anxiously.</p>
                <p>Ruby nodded.</p>
                <p>“What shall we say? May we talk ordinarily?”</p>
                <p>“Of course.”</p>
                <p>“We are glad to see you,” said Rachael, smiling and bowing politely.</p>
                <p>The fairies drew up in line and bowed politely in return. </p>
                <pb n="98" xml:id="VAB7152-098"/>
                <p>“We knew you would bring Ruby back safely,” said Roger.</p>
                <p>The fairies bowed again, and kissed their hands, but none of them spoke.</p>
                <p>“We told the others, but they could not believe it,” said Rachael.</p>
                <p>The fairies nodded their heads, with a quick understanding of the difficulty.</p>
                <p>“And oh!” cried Rachael, grown suddenly bold, “we do so long to hear about the
                    Silver Isle; we want Ruby to begin at once.”</p>
                <p>At this, to her surprise, all the fairies put their fingers to their lips and
                    solemnly shook their heads.</p>
                <p>Roger and Rachael were alarmed. “Oh, you don’t mean she mustn’t tell us! Do you
                    mean that?” they added anxiously.</p>
                <p>The fairies nodded their heads.</p>
                <p>“Oh dear!”</p>
                <p>They were dreadfully disappointed. No time, however, was given for remonstrance.
                    After again nodding their heads, and this time with great vigour, the fairies
                    surrounded Ruby, and, jumping lightly on one another’s shoulders, made a ladder
                    from the window to the ground. Then the bearers of her chair climbed up with
                    Ruby to the window‐sill, and she stepped from it into her room. When the
                    children had finished their greetings, the golden chair and every fairy had
                    disappeared.</p>
                <p>When Ruby’s mother opened her eyes, on the morning following the dreadful day of
                    anxiety, she saw<pb n="99" xml:id="VAB7152-099"/> Ruby sleeping peacefully in
                    her own little bed, with her dressing‐gown, and one woolly slipper, placed
                    neatly on the chair beside her.</p>
                <p>“My dear child,” cried Ruby’s mother, as she ran across the room and kissed her.
                    “How strange and wonderful it is! What has happened to you? What has happened to
                    us all?”</p>
                <p>Ruby opened her eyes and smiled.</p>
                <p>“Good morning, mother.”</p>
                <p>“Ruby, Ruby, where have you been? Father and I have been greatly troubled and
                    alarmed. What has happened?”</p>
                <p>Ruby sat up in bed. “I am so sorry you were frightened, mother; I was quite safe
                    all the time. Rachael and Roger knew I wanted to see the Silver Isle. I am so
                    sorry, I mustn’t tell them about it; if I do I can never go there again.”</p>
                <p>“Dear little Ruby, I don’t want you ever to go there again! I could not endure
                    another such day.”</p>
                <p>“But, mother, I haven’t seen it all—not nearly all—there wasn’t time. There are
                    so many wonderful things to see and learn in the Silver Isle, and the fairies
                    are so kind and careful, no harm can come to me. Please, mother, don’t be
                    anxious! I wish I could tell you all about it, then you would not mind; it is
                    such a beautiful place. Please, please don’t say you do not want me to go there
                    again.”</p>
                <p>And Ruby, who never cried with disappointment, looked at her mother with eyes
                    full of tears.</p>
                <pb n="100" xml:id="VAB7152-100"/>
                <p>Ruby’s mother was much distressed. She went on to the landing, and called Ruby’s
                    father from the sitting‐room below. He had wandered by the sea all night, and
                    had come in, not long ago, tired out with his fruitless search. When the fairies
                    were dancing through the barley with Ruby, Ruby’s father was far away down the
                    coast; but had he been in the barley‐field he would not have seen her. He came
                    upstairs quickly, and took his little daughter in his arms.</p>
                <p>“My dear child, where have you been?”</p>
                <p>“To the Silver Isle, father. I was quite safe; but I must not tell you about it,
                    if I do I cannot go there again. You don’t think me selfish do you, father, not
                    to tell you? I do so much want to go back.”</p>
                <p>“Go back!” Ruby’s father stared at Ruby in bewilderment. Then he looked at Ruby’s
                    mother for an explanation, but Ruby’s mother only shook her head.</p>
                <p>“No, no,” she said decidedly; “I do not understand about this Silver Isle, but,
                    whatever it is, and wherever it is, Ruby must never go away again as she did
                    yesterday; we could not bear it.”</p>
                <p>Roger and Rachael came in as she spoke. “Well, Ruby,” they said, “are you
                    rested?”</p>
                <p>“Yes; quite rested, and ready to get up.” Ruby made a brave effort to hide her
                    disappointment.</p>
                <p>“My dear,” said her mother, “you must not get up before breakfast, you are not
                    strong enough yet, for a long day.”</p>
                <pb n="101" xml:id="VAB7152-101"/>
                <p>“I am quite strong since yesterday,” explained Ruby. “I am quite well since
                    yesterday—the fairies made me quite well—you will see I shall not be tired.”</p>
                <p>And when Ruby’s mother examined her carefully, she saw that her looks, this
                    morning, were quite different from those of the day before yesterday. She really
                    did look quite well. Her eyes were as clear and bright, and her cheeks as rosy,
                    as Roger’s and Rachael’s.</p>
                <p>“And see, mother.” She put out her arms and legs; and the arms and legs which had
                    been, the day before yesterday, poor little thin arms and legs; were, this
                    morning, round and plump as they should be.</p>
                <p>“Do let me get up!”</p>
                <p>“Very well.” Ruby’s mother was more and more astonished.</p>
                <p>“It is very strange,” she said downstairs, when breakfast was brought in, and
                    Ruby appeared with the others, bright and brisk and full of spirits,—Ruby who
                    had been a pale, tired little girl, for so many weeks.</p>
                <p>“It is very strange,” said the maids in the kitchen, when, after breakfast, they
                    heard Ruby running about the cottage.</p>
                <p>“It is very strange,” thought Ruby’s father, as he sat outside in the garden; but
                    he did not say anything, he only sat there and smoked. As for the milkman, and
                    the baker, who came up the garden with the day’s provisions, and the butcher,
                    who had supplied<pb n="102" xml:id="VAB7152-102"/> gallons of beef tea, and the
                    manager of the Post‐office emporium, who had brought constant boxes of grapes
                    from kind and distant friends, and the woman who had brought dozens of new‐laid
                    eggs, to be beaten up with brandy and milk,—they all declared, with
                    astonishment, that Miss Ruby’s sudden recovery was “past them altogether, but
                    they was right down glad to see her about again, strange or no.”</p>
                <p>The news of Ruby’s return, and complete cure, spread rapidly through the village:
                    and, immediately after breakfast, many visitors presented themselves at
                    Sea‐thrift, hoping to hear the story of her day‐and‐night adventure.</p>
                <p>One old man brought her a big bunch of roses, another a bundle of lavender, a
                    third brought her an enormous basket of plums, big enough to keep a family in
                    plum pies for a month. Ruby thanked each of them delightedly.</p>
                <p>“How kind of you,” she said. “I am quite well now, thank you, and I should so
                    much like to tell you about my adventures, but I mustn’t.”</p>
                <p>Quite a crowd of villagers had collected, before Charlie and Ethel came round.
                    They were standing in rows along the low garden‐wall, the front row having its
                    elbows firmly established on the top of the wall. Ruby was talking to each in
                    turn, and assuring each of her complete recovery.</p>
                <p>“You will have to tell them about the Silver Isle,” whispered her mother; “they
                    will stay here until you do! But I don’t suppose they would <choice>
                        <orig>be‐<pb n="103" xml:id="VAB7152-103"/> lieve</orig>
                        <reg>believe</reg>
                    </choice> your story if you told it,” she added, smiling. “I can’t be sure that
                    I should myself.” She kissed Ruby’s cheek lightly. She was so happy at having
                    her child well and gay once more.</p>
                <p>“Ruby!” cried Ethel, as she opened the gate, and Ruby ran to meet her.</p>
                <p>“Well, Ruby,” said Charlie, following, “did you have a good time?”</p>
                <p>“Oh yes; a lovely time!”</p>
                <p>“That’s right. And how are you?”</p>
                <p>“Quite, quite well.”</p>
                <p>“Yes; so you are. Come, this is evidence: here is your slipper.” He gave Ruby the
                    woolly shoe he had picked up in the barley‐field.</p>
                <p>“It is very strange,” began Ethel.</p>
                <p>“Oh, please, don’t say that,” interrupted Ruby, laughing; “everyone has been
                    saying that—father and mother and all of them.” She turned towards the audience
                    along the wall. “It isn’t really strange at all.”</p>
                <p>“Let us come indoors, then the crowd will disperse, and you can tell Charlie and
                    me quietly by ourselves.”</p>
                <p>“Yes; let us go in, but I cannot tell you about it, Ethel; I am so sorry. If I
                    tell you or anyone about the Silver Isle, I can never go back.”</p>
                <p>“Dear Ruby, we don’t want you to go back. You must never, never go away again, as
                    you did yesterday.”</p>
                <p>“Ethel!”</p>
                <pb n="104" xml:id="VAB7152-104"/>
                <p>Ruby’s father followed them into the cottage.</p>
                <p>“No; you must never go away as you did yesterday, Ruby; we were very anxious and
                    unhappy.”</p>
                <p>“O mother, were you very <emph>very</emph> unhappy?” asked Ruby, as they went
                    into the parlour.</p>
                <p>“Very.”</p>
                <p>“And you, father?”</p>
                <p>Her father nodded his head, and smoothed some of the wrinkles out of his
                    forehead.</p>
                <p>Then Ruby looked serious and thoughtful. Roger and Rachael came and sat quietly
                    beside her. They were very eager to hear of Ruby’s adventures in the Silver
                    Isle, but anxious she should not deprive herself of future visits, so they sat
                    quietly beside her and said nothing.</p>
                <p>Ruby sat with her elbows on the table, and her chin supported on her hands. It
                    was her favourite position when she had a difficult problem to solve. So
                    absorbed was she, she did not notice a tall figure come up the garden, nor hear
                    the door open, nor see the white‐haired doctor’s smile as he looked at her.</p>
                <p>“Well, Ruby, you are safely back, I see.” Ruby roused herself.</p>
                <p>“Yes, yes; and I am quite strong again now. Isn’t it nice?”</p>
                <p>“Capital.” He sat down and looked at her critically.</p>
                <p>“Yes; you are quite well. You must tell us how it happened.”</p>
                <pb n="105" xml:id="VAB7152-105"/>
                <p>Ruby slipped suddenly from her chair to her mother’s knee.</p>
                <p>“You shall not be anxious about me again, mother,” she said. “I have made up my
                    mind to tell you.”</p>
                <p>As she spoke, the robin looked in from the window sill, and chirped a few notes
                    of encouragement. When he had finished, Ruby began her story of the Silver
                    Isle.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="106" xml:id="VAB7152-106"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>CHAPTER XIII.</head>
                <p>“<hi>THEY</hi> came for me in the early morning,” began Ruby, “just before
                    sunrise.”</p>
                <p>“Who came, my child?” interrupted her mother, as she stroked Ruby’s hair.</p>
                <p>“The fairies, while you were asleep, dear mother,” said Ruby. “They came in the
                    early grey morning, and took me across the barley‐field to the sea; and then the
                    sea fairies led me down to their boat, and we set off as the sunshine began. At
                    first the sea fairies came with me, and played round the boat; but soon the wind
                    grew so strong, and carried the boat along so quickly, they could not keep up;
                    so they lay back upon the water, and the waves covered them. Then for a long
                    time I saw only miles and miles of blue water, and the boat dashed on faster and
                    faster, until I was out of breath. I had to hold the sides of the boat, I
                    couldn’t steer it a bit.”</p>
                <p>“Were you not afraid of being upset?” asked Rachael.</p>
                <pb n="107" xml:id="VAB7152-107"/>
                <p>“I never thought of being upset,” said Ruby; “but I wanted to look about; and we
                    went so fast, I could not see anything for the spray, and sun and wind.”</p>
                <p>“Like a trip in a life‐saving apparatus,” suggested Roger.</p>
                <p>“After a time,” continued Ruby, “the wind went down, and I looked back to see the
                    land, but there was no land anywhere, there was nothing but the sea and the sky,
                    and sunshine. Then suddenly I saw a great cloud overhead, that came nearer and
                    nearer and lower and lower, until I thought it was going to fall upon me. It
                    broke just above the top of the sail, and from it a flock of white swans fell
                    lightly into the waves, and came swimming round me. They guided my boat into
                    smooth water, where the waves broke only in gentle ripples, and we sailed along
                    slowly for some time. Then by‐and‐by I heard overhead a great singing of
                    birds.”</p>
                <p>“What kind of birds? ” asked Rachael eagerly.</p>
                <p>“Every kind I knew, and ever so many I did not know; they gathered from every
                    part of the sky. Then they all made a great flight together, and swept along in
                    front of me across the sea, singing all the time. I heard their song long after
                    I could see them. The singing kept in front, growing fainter and fainter until
                    it ceased altogether, and, as it ceased, I saw the Silver Isle.”</p>
                <p>Roger and Rachael leaned forward eagerly as Ruby paused.</p>
                <p>“Yes, yes,” they exclaimed; “did it come up suddenly out of the sea? Do go
                    on.”</p>
                <pb n="108" xml:id="VAB7152-108"/>
                <p>“No; it didn’t come up out of the sea. It had been in its place all the time, but
                    the light about it was so bright I could not see through. When the song of the
                    birds died away, the light lifted like a veil, and behind it the cliffs of the
                    Silver Isle glistened like precious stones. It was a big, little island,” said
                    Ruby, in answer to their questioning eyes, “and its cliffs were high and steep,
                    and ran right down to the water. There was no sand or beach, or landing place,
                    as there is here, but all along the shore were birds flying in and out of the
                    rocks and deep caves; and the rocks shone like pearls, and the caves looked like
                    great sapphire stones hiding among the pearls. As my boat drew near a fairy
                    figure stepped down the side of the cliff. ‘Welcome, Ruby,’ she said, and held
                    out her hand. The boat answered to it quickly, and sailed to the spot where she
                    stood. I jumped up, thinking she was there to help me land, but, when I held out
                    my hand to her, she pointed to the water and said: ‘One deep dive, Ruby, to make
                    you quite well before you come ashore.’ I looked into the water and wondered how
                    I should do it, the sea was so deep and blue. As I looked she said again: ‘Those
                    who come to the Silver Isle must obey its rules, if they would land upon its
                    shore,’ so I shut my eyes and jumped. Oh dear,”—Ruby shut her eyes tightly at
                    the recollection,—“it was such a long, long way down, I thought I should never
                    come up again. I kept my eyes shut all the time, and, when at last I came to the
                    top, my boat had gone, but at the edge of the rock stood the shining figure. As
                    she held out both hands to me I recognised her face; she was<pb n="109" xml:id="VAB7152-109"/> the beautiful lady of the well. I felt quite safe
                    then. She carried me up the cliff and gave me fairy clothes to wear, all bright
                    and soft and shining; then she clapped her hands, and hundreds of fairies came
                    running towards me, and made me dance with them in a great circle round the
                    island. While we danced the beautiful lady moved about among the flowers.</p>
                <p>“The isle was like a big garden, but the flowers and fruits in it were different
                    from any I had ever seen before. Their colours were more beautiful, and their
                    shapes more delicate. There were trees, and lawns, and paths winding between
                    hedges of ripe fruits, and arbours of sweet‐smelling blossoms, and fresh
                    fountains playing and sparkling, and all the time I could see the sea shining
                    beyond the rocks.</p>
                <p>“Very soon the beautiful lady called me to her side, where she stood in the
                    middle of the isle, and as I ran to her the fairies hid away again.</p>
                <p>“Then she told me the Silver Isle was set there, far away in the sea, for her
                    wandering birds. ‘For my wanderers,’ she said, ‘who cannot bear the winter’s
                    cold, but fly after the sunshine, this is their resting‐place—this is the garden
                    at which they rest when they cross the seas.’ She lifted one hand as she spoke,
                    and, from the rocks and caves, the birds flew up like leaves blown by a sudden
                    wind. When I asked her how they found the isle, she asked me how I found it,
                    and, of course, I did not know. Then she laughed, and said: ‘Neither do the
                    birds know; it does not matter so long as they do find it.’ She said some of the
                    birds lived always on the<pb n="110" xml:id="VAB7152-110"/> isle—the weak ones,
                    and those who had grown too tired to keep up with the others, on their longer
                    journeys. I sat beside her, and she told me many wonderful things about their
                    songs and travels. I cannot remember half the things she told me.” Ruby looked
                    dreamily out of the window. “But she said it would not matter if I forgot: I
                    should remember again when needful.</p>
                <p>“By‐and‐by she stood up and spread out her hands towards the sea, and as she did
                    so the North Wind came flying over the water. He looked very big as he came
                    towards us. His face was hidden in a great grey mantle, and his wings, as he
                    spread them, swept away all the colour from the sea; but he moved very gently.
                    As soon as his feet touched the isle, he came and sat beside me at the beautiful
                    lady’s feet. Then she put her hand on his cloak and drew it away from his face,
                    and his eyes were so bright and blue and twinkling, and his smile so kind, and
                    he looked so strong, I began to think of our very nicest, oldest friends; and to
                    wonder who of them all he most resembled. The beautiful lady answered my thought
                    as I wondered.</p>
                <p>“‘He himself is an old friend,’ she said, and she again put her hand upon his
                    mantle. ‘Show her,’ she said to him; ‘Ruby will remember.’</p>
                <p>“Then the North Wind rose, and looked across the water, and breathed some words
                    through the air; and out of the air came the heroes of the northern seas, in
                    shining coats of mail, with gleaming, winged helmets on their heads, and
                    battle‐axes in their hands; and the sails of their ships filled with the breath
                    that he<pb n="111" xml:id="VAB7152-111"/> breathed. The heroes sailed round and
                    round the isle, singing of their deeds in olden times. Some of the tales I knew
                    and some I did not know till then. They were such splendid heroes, so big and
                    strong; and as the breath of the North Wind blew upon them more strongly, their
                    eyes sparkled and their faces shone more brightly from their ships. But suddenly
                    the North Wind spread his wings, and flew out to the heroes and gathered them
                    all up in his arms: then he dropped with them gently into the sea. When they had
                    disappeared, the beautiful lady again rose and stretched her hands over the sea,
                    on the other side of the Isle: and as I watched to see what would happen, over
                    the waves came the South Wind. Her trailing blue raiment, patterned with gold,
                    shone gloriously as she came. Her wings were golden and flashed across the
                    water, and in her hands were garlands of myrtle and olive.</p>
                <p>“She, too, stepped gently upon the isle and came and sat beside me at the
                    beautiful lady’s feet. Then, by‐and‐by, the beautiful lady said to her:</p>
                <p>“‘Show Ruby, and Ruby will remember.’ And, as the North Wind had arisen, the
                    South Wind arose, and stood by the sea and breathed through the air.</p>
                <p>“As she breathed, the heroes of the Greeks, Theseus and Jason and Perseus, and
                    all the mighty Trojan chiefs whom Roger loves, came sailing about us. They
                    carried spears and bucklers, and wore helmets with waving plumes, and sang of
                    the deeds we know so well. They were beautiful as they moved about in the
                    sunshine; but in a little while the South Wind, too, rose and<pb n="112" xml:id="VAB7152-112"/> spread her wings about the heroes and sank with them
                    beneath the waves.</p>
                <p>“Then I asked the beautiful lady what the East Wind could bring us: and
                    immediately, from the east, the sunshine spread like a cold clear flame, and the
                    isle was full of daffodils. Through all the grass they shone, and at the
                    beautiful lady’s feet, and in her hair, and in the folds of her mantle; then
                    suddenly, as they had come, so they were gone. When I asked for the West Wind, a
                    rainbow shone in the sky, and a mist, like dissolved opal, surrounded us. Pearly
                    drops of moisture fell upon us, and in the garden I smelt the sweet smell of
                    ferns, and leaves, and woods, and earthy things, and I said: ‘She is the best of
                    all,’ but the beautiful lady shook her head.</p>
                <p>“‘Each in turn is best,’ she said.</p>
                <p>“Then the West Wind rose as the others had risen: she was taller and stronger
                    than them all. As she spread her wings the isle trembled.</p>
                <p>“‘Where shall I waft the Silver Isle? The seas are deep and wide,’ she said to
                    the beautiful lady. But the beautiful lady answered:</p>
                <p>“‘Let the isle this day abide in its place; depart gently as you came.’</p>
                <p>“The West Wind then bent her head and flew away lightly, up the sky. Her raiment
                    left a little ripple on the water as she passed.</p>
                <p>“The beautiful lady rose and watched the waters, where the West Wind passed over
                    them, then she turned to me and said:</p>
                <p>“‘A day and a night, Ruby; and, see, the night is<pb n="113" xml:id="VAB7152-113"/> coming.’ She pointed to the clouds into which the West Wind had flown. Their
                    colour was fading, and the light in the sky was growing dim.</p>
                <p>“‘A day and a night,’ she repeated, and she drew me nearer to her and wrapped me
                    in the folds of her cloak. Then, as I closed my eyes to think about Roger and
                    Rachael, she pointed upwards, and I looked and saw the night had begun; the
                    clouds were gone, and the moon and stars were shining in the sky.”</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="114" xml:id="VAB7152-114"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>CHAPTER XIV</head>
                <p><hi>RUBY</hi> made a long pause, and the company waited patiently for her to
                    continue, but Ruby was busy remembering.</p>
                <p>“I wish you had asked some questions about the winds,” said Rachael at last.</p>
                <p>“I didn’t think of any,” Ruby answered apologetically; “and I thought I should go
                    again very often and in time understand everything.”</p>
                <p>“And if you hadn’t told us,” said Roger, “you might have gone back. O Ruby, would
                    you like not to tell us any more? Is it too late now?”</p>
                <p>“I shouldn’t enjoy thinking about it alone,” said Ruby, “I would much, much
                    rather tell you.”</p>
                <p>“Well,” said Rachael, “please go on; what happened when the stars came out? Was
                    it cold?”</p>
                <p>“No; not a bit, it was soft and warm under the beautiful lady’s cloak. The
                    fairies crept out again from the flowers and trees, and sang quietly, and danced
                    slow minuet‐like dances in the moonlight. The beautiful<pb n="115" xml:id="VAB7152-115"/> lady stroked my hair, and I think I was asleep for a
                    long time.</p>
                <p>“When I opened my eyes the fairies had again disappeared, and big purple clouds
                    floated between us and the sky. The isle was full of mists and shadows, and the
                    beautiful lady was walking to and fro among great white flowers. She moved her
                    hands as though she were weaving, and, as she did so, pictures grew up out of
                    the sea and out of the shadows of the isle, and upon the clouds above us. She
                    turned and saw me watching her, and told me she was weaving dreams for the
                    sleepers of that night. Then she came and took me by the hand, and my fingers
                    weaved with hers. I wished beautiful dreams for Roger and Rachael, and father
                    and mother: and the pictures grew as I wished, and came floating landwards over
                    the sea. Don’t you remember them?”</p>
                <p>Everyone tried to remember, but without success.</p>
                <p>“I wished such a sweet dream for you, mother. Can’t you remember it?”</p>
                <p>Ruby’s mother shook her head. “I cannot remember my dream,” she said, “but my
                    sleep was deep and beautiful.”</p>
                <p>“I expect all the dreams came to you, mother,” said Roger, “as father and Rachael
                    and I did not go to bed. That was why you slept so soundly.”</p>
                <p>“Were all the dreams, the beautiful lady weaved, nice ones?” asked Rachael.</p>
                <p>“Yes; no ugly ones are woven on the Silver Isle; they are made in a land to which
                    we need never go.<pb n="116" xml:id="VAB7152-116"/> When they were all finished,
                    the beautiful lady stepped down the rocks and lifted her head and sang softly,
                    and as she sang flights of birds fell about her. They seemed to be shaken from
                    the clouds that were drifting over the stars. She knelt down among them, and
                    they fluttered their wings and waited for her to speak.</p>
                <p>“‘I shall show you the path to‐morrow,’ she said to them, ‘to‐night you must
                    rest.’ And then they all flew into the trees and caves, and sang their thanks,
                    as we hear them sing when the sun shines after rain.</p>
                <p>“After this, mer‐men and sea‐maidens came up from their homes in the deep water,
                    and played in the pools among the rocks, and every now and then a flock of
                    sea‐birds flew swiftly past.</p>
                <p>“When the first streak of light showed in the sky, the beautiful lady waved her
                    hand to the mer‐men and sea‐maidens, and they wished me good‐bye.</p>
                <p>“‘Good‐bye, Ruby,’ they said; ‘don’t forget us.’ And they slipped back into the
                    deep water. When they were gone, the fairies of the isle crept from the shadows,
                    and stood in a large company awaiting orders.</p>
                <p>“‘A day and a night in the Silver Isle,’ said the beautiful lady, pointing to the
                    yellow streak in the east.</p>
                <p>“‘Please let me stay longer,’ I said. ‘The time has gone so quickly.’ But she
                    repeated the verse and shook her head.</p>
                <p>“Then I begged her to let me come again, in the early mornings, and she said it
                    could be only on the<pb n="117" xml:id="VAB7152-117"/> condition that I told no
                    one what I had seen or heard in the Silver Isle. I promised to tell no one,
                    but,” Ruby added quickly, “I am sure the beautiful lady knew it would be too
                    difficult a promise. She took both my hands in hers, and said:</p>
                <p>“‘Roger and Rachael will want to hear; your parents will be troubled if they
                    never know where you have been. Be careful of promises, little Ruby.’</p>
                <p>“As she spoke the silver boat came gliding out from the rocks, and she lifted me
                    into it in the early grey morning. I wished her good‐bye, but she said it was
                    not to be a good‐bye, I should see her again very soon. Then the sails filled,
                    and the boat ran along so quickly I could not see her any more. I sailed swiftly
                    through miles of grey water, till we came to golden and crimson pools, and wells
                    of sapphire blue: and the light in the east lengthened and broadened, till the
                    cloud banks were broken down, and the sun climbed up out of the sea. As we came
                    to our shore, I saw the fairies waiting along the cliff, as they had promised.
                    They ran down to the water’s edge, and helped me over the sand and brought me
                    home.”</p>
                <p>“Yes, yes; we know,” cried Roger and Rachael. “And what happened to the
                    boat?”</p>
                <p>“It sailed back across the sea.”</p>
                <p>“And for us,” said Ruby’s mother, kissing her, “you have given up seeing these
                    wonders again.”</p>
                <p>“You are glad I have told you, mother?”</p>
                <p>“Yes; very glad.”</p>
                <p>Then Ruby slipped from her mother’s knee, and the party sat in silence for some
                    time. At last Ethel rose<pb n="118" xml:id="VAB7152-118"/> and said it was all
                    very strange, at which remark Ruby laughed gaily.</p>
                <p>Then Charlie rose. “I wish I could remember the dream you made for me,” he said
                    to Ruby. “Can’t I have it again?”</p>
                <p>Ruby shook her head.</p>
                <p>“Well, the great thing is that Ruby is now strong and well,” said Ruby’s father.
                    Then he lit his pipe and walked up and down the garden, pondering Ruby’s
                    tale.</p>
                <p>“How do we know she <emph>is</emph> quite strong?” said Ruby’s mother.</p>
                <p>“I’ll soon find out,” said Roger; and he darted at Ruby and lifted her in his
                    arms. “Of course, we must test her. Hold tight, Ruby.” And he rushed with her
                    into the garden, pursued by Rachael. He dropped Ruby on the lawn.</p>
                <p>“Let’s have a regular examination,” said Rachael. “We’ll begin with running.”</p>
                <p>“Yes; that’s capital. What about her weight, Roger?” asked the doctor, coming out
                    after them.</p>
                <p>“She weighs too much,” said Roger, rather breathlessly. “She’s as heavy as
                    Rachael now.”</p>
                <p>“Come, that’s evidence.”</p>
                <p>“Yes,” responded Rachael; “but we don’t know exactly how much she weighed
                    yesterday morning, do we?”</p>
                <p>“Near enough.”</p>
                <p>The sports then began in earnest, umpired by Charlie. And although Ruby did not,
                    of course, win<pb n="119" xml:id="VAB7152-119"/> all the prizes—the children
                    insisted upon prizes, and Ruby’s mother ransacked the cottage for suitable
                    knick‐knacks—she held her own, as she had never done before; being even with
                    Rachael in several runs, and above her in jumping.</p>
                <p>“You are much more springy than you were,” exclaimed Roger admiringly.</p>
                <p>When the runs and jumps were over, there came a tug‐of‐war, the doctor being
                    pressed into the service to side with Ruby; and, in spite of Roger’s gallant
                    struggle, Ruby and the doctor won, and pulled Roger and Rachael over at each
                    trial.</p>
                <p>But, through all the excitement of the sports, Ethel sat indoors by
                    herself—thinking. She sat in the parlour, in spite of Charlie’s and Roger’s
                    entreaties, through the window, to cheer up and join them; and when the sports
                    came to an end, and the doctor went away, she walked through the barley‐field to
                    the sea, and there sat down to think again.</p>
                <p>After dinner, when the children ran along the sand with their football, they
                    found her still sitting close to the sea; but now Charlie was near by, painting
                    busily.</p>
                <pb n="120" xml:id="VAB7152-120"/>
                <p>“May we see?” cried Ruby, as they came up to him.</p>
                <p>He turned his canvas towards them, and upon it was a picture of Ethel, standing
                    beside the sea, surrounded by a band of fairies, who pulled her skirts and tried
                    to make her look at them; but her head was turned away.</p>
                <p>“Poor Ethel,” said Rachael; “how they pull.”</p>
                <p>“Why doesn’t she turn her head?” asked Ruby.</p>
                <p>“We’ll come and ask her,” said Charlie. They all ran up to Ethel, and Charlie put
                    his picture down in front of her. Ethel looked at it, and laughed.</p>
                <p>“It isn’t a good portrait, is it?” Then she turned to Ruby. “We must see the
                    fairies at our own time, and in our own way, mustn’t we, Ruby? We can’t be made
                    to see them: but I have finished thinking. Come, we will have a game while
                    Charlie finishes his picture. The fairies are very pretty.”</p>
                <p>“But they are not a bit like my fairies,” said Ruby.</p>
                <p>“I haven’t seen your fairies,” said Charlie apologetically.</p>
                <p>“You have been trying to paint them,” said Ruby.</p>
                <p>Charlie laughed now, and, in spite of their remonstrances, tore his picture into
                    little pieces.</p>
                <p>“I must not paint Ruby’s fairies until I have seen them,” he said, “and perhaps I
                    shall never see them. We must be content with those we see ourselves, mustn’t
                    we? And if we do not see any ourselves, we must wait patiently.”</p>
                <pb n="121" xml:id="VAB7152-121"/>
                <p>“But you have seen some,” said Rachael; “you have, haven’t you?” Charlie
                    smiled.</p>
                <p>“Perhaps—one cannot always remember—but come along, let us have this game.”</p>
                <p>So they played, and they played; until the champion Ruby was tired, and said they
                    must rest.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="122" xml:id="VAB7152-122"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>CHAPTER XV.</head>
                <p><hi>ONE</hi> morning the children’s mother looked up from behind the
                    coffee‐pot.</p>
                <p>“Does anyone remember,” she asked, “that we go home the day after to‐morrow?”</p>
                <p>The whole party started in alarmed surprise.</p>
                <p>“No! Not so soon! Impossible! Must we really?”</p>
                <p>“We must—really. To‐day is Thursday, and schools begin on Monday, our duty is
                    clear.”</p>
                <p>“Oh dear!” cried Ruby.</p>
                <p>“Oh dear!” cried Rachael.</p>
                <p>“Oh bother!” said Roger.</p>
                <pb n="123" xml:id="VAB7152-123"/>
                <p>Ethel and Charlie, who had just put in their heads through the window, looked
                    sympathetic.</p>
                <p>“We must go home on Saturday too,” they said, by way of comfort.</p>
                <p>Then Roger’s spirits rose with a bound.</p>
                <p>“Mother,” he exclaimed delightedly, “we can’t be ready on Saturday—we haven’t
                    packed anything.”</p>
                <p>“Someone else has been doing that,” came their father’s voice from behind the
                    paper.</p>
                <p>“O father! Well, we’ll help directly we’ve finished breakfast. How quickly the
                    time has gone! It seems such a pity to leave everything!” Roger looked at the
                    flowers in the garden, and at all the spreading country beyond. Then he turned
                    to his breakfast with a business‐like air. “We must make a programme for the
                    day,” he said. “Let me see—there are the bicycles to clean—I suppose they
                        <emph>ought</emph> to be cleaned,” he added doubtfully; “then there is the
                    tent to take down, and the boat to bring up.”—Roger’s handiwork still went by
                    this name, although it had ceased to maintain any but an inverted position in
                    the water. “And we must say good‐bye to our friends.”</p>
                <p>“We must go in the afternoon to see our dear doctor,” said Ruby; “he does not
                    know we are leaving so soon.”</p>
                <p>The programme being settled, they all, after breakfast, busied themselves
                    greatly; and, owing to their extraordinary exertions, the bicycles were cleaned,
                    the tent taken down, <name>The Recruit</name> dragged up and<pb n="124" xml:id="VAB7152-124"/> stowed away in the woodshed, and a bathe squeezed in,
                    before dinner‐time.</p>
                <p>“You have worked nobly,” said Charlie, looking in early in the afternoon, on his
                    way to the Post‐office for luggage‐labels, a strong cord, and other articles
                    significant of departure.</p>
                <p>After dinner, as had been arranged, they set off to bid the doctor good‐bye.
                    Roger and Rachael rode their freshly‐cleaned bicycles, but Ruby, not having a
                    bicycle or being able to ride one, accompanied them in a donkey‐chair. The
                    children had frequently been assured by the donkey’s mistress, that that donkey
                    was “as quick as lightning to go,” so they decided to test its speed on this
                    occasion.</p>
                <p>“We can ride on either side,” said Roger, “and if he goes too fast, we’ll hold on
                    to the sides of the chair, and act as drags. Ruby can drive, there’s no traffic
                    along the road, and a hedge on either side to fall into, so we’re quite safe.”
                    And, as soon as Charlie passed on to the Post‐office, the children set out with
                    the lightning steed.</p>
                <p>The steed did not justify his character even at first. He did, indeed, start off
                    in high spirits with the bicycles, and for a few yards closely followed them,
                    but as soon as the party turned from the main road into the blackberry lane, he
                    became depressed. His loss of spirits may have been caused by the length of
                    straight road suddenly presented to his view, or he may have started with the
                    idea of following some plan of his own; whatever was the reason, as soon<pb n="125" xml:id="VAB7152-125"/> as they turned into the blackberry lane, he
                    stopped, and refused to move.</p>
                <p>Ruby used all the driver’s art she had ever seen, or heard, or read of, to
                    persuade him to change his mind and pursue his course. She called him by name,
                    cheerfully and severely; she jerked and shook the reins until her arms ached;
                    and at last she got out of her chair and tried to reason with him.</p>
                <p>Of course, as we all know, one cannot reason successfully with determined
                    obstinacy ; and, when this last plan of Ruby’s failed, she sat down in her
                    carriage, feeling very helpless and disappointed. Roger and Rachael were ever so
                    far away down the blackberry lane, speeding happily onward: the steed had made
                    so fine a start, they took for granted that he was following in the same
                    style.</p>
                <p>“They might look round to make sure,” thought Ruby, as the riders grew smaller in
                    the distance; and, just as they began to look like two black dots upon the road,
                    they did stop and look round. They came racing back.</p>
                <p>“What has happened? What is the matter?” they asked breathlessly. “What are you
                    stopping for?”</p>
                <p>“He won’t go any more,” explained Ruby, rather dismally; “I expect I’d better
                    turn back and let you go without me.”</p>
                <p>“Nonsense,” said Roger, “I think I can make him go. Here, Rachael, hold my wheel
                    and we’ll see!”</p>
                <p>Roger handed his bicycle to Rachael, and rushed at the steed in so threatening a
                    manner that the<pb n="126" xml:id="VAB7152-126"/> creature plunged violently
                    forward, and set off at a hand gallop, with the chair and Ruby swaying from side
                    to side behind him. Roger ran excitedly beside them.</p>
                <p>“He’s all right now,” he gasped. “I’ll go back for the wheel.”</p>
                <p>“I’m afraid I don’t like it quite so fast,” began Ruby, as Roger dropped behind;
                    but, before she could finish her sentence, the lightning steed twitched his
                    right ear, and came once more to a dead stop.</p>
                <p>When Roger and Rachael came up again, Ruby was nearly in tears with disappointment<choice>
                        <corr>.</corr>
                        <sic/>
                    </choice></p>
                <p>“I did think I could drive a donkey,” she said; “we shall never get there at this
                    rate.”</p>
                <p>“Don’t trouble!” cried Roger cheerfully; “I’ll ride at his head and keep him up
                    to the mark that way.” So Roger rode at the steed’s head, and, by his masterful
                    manner, threatening voice, and occasional reminder with a stick, obliged him to
                    keep up a fairly good pace till the doctor’s house was reached.</p>
                <p>“Thank you,” said Ruby, as she stepped out; “I hope he will be better going
                    home.”</p>
                <p>“It has been rather a noisy drive hasn’t it?” said Rachael. “Roger’s throat must
                    be sore.”</p>
                <p>“Not a bit,” said Roger huskily; “but I shall want an explanation from his owner
                    when we get back.”</p>
                <p>By the time they had fastened the steed to a post, the doctor was at his gate
                    giving them a welcome.</p>
                <p>“So you’ve come to bid me good‐bye,” he said, smiling; “that is nice of you.”</p>
                <pb n="127" xml:id="VAB7152-127"/>
                <p>“Did you know we were going to‐morrow?” asked Rachael.</p>
                <p>The doctor smiled. “A little bird told me.”</p>
                <p>“Was it our robin? He has not told us anything for a long time.”</p>
                <p>“It was one of my own birds,” said the doctor, smiling again. “I have a great
                    many, as you hear.” And as the children walked down the path to the doctor’s
                    lawn, they heard a chorus of birds in the trees around it.</p>
                <p>“How beautifully they sing,” said Ruby; “but my robin’s song—”</p>
                <p>“Ah, your robin has been a useful friend,” said the doctor.</p>
                <p>Then, when tea came, the children asked him endless questions about his flowers
                    and birds, and the creatures that strayed into his garden; and they gave a
                    graphic account of the behaviour of the lightning steed, and besought the doctor
                    never on any account to hire it.</p>
                <p>During a short pause, that occurred between the plain cake and the fancy cakes,
                    Rachael asked if the doctor remembered the day of their arrival at
                    Sea‐thrift—the very first day of the holidays—when he had told them they would
                    find fairies in this part of the country.</p>
                <p>The doctor said, of course he remembered.</p>
                <p>“Will you tell us how you knew?” she asked again. “Have you been to the Silver
                    Isle, or met the beautiful lady?”</p>
                <p>The doctor smiled, and shook his head.</p>
                <p>“Supposing I had been once, and might not tell<pb n="128" xml:id="VAB7152-128"/>
                    without forfeiting the right to go again, would you think me very selfish in not
                    telling?”</p>
                <p>“No, no, no!” they all cried; “of course we should not think you selfish; of
                    course you must not tell us.”</p>
                <p>“But I don’t say I have been to the Silver Isle, or seen any fairies,” said the
                    doctor, “and I don’t say that I haven’t,” he added, with a twinkle in his eyes.
                    “In any case, it is kind of you to forgive me for wanting to keep such knowledge
                    to myself. There are fairies, you know, all over the world for young people, but
                    for old people—they can be found in only one place.”</p>
                <p>Ruby put her hand in his. “I am sure you see them, that is why you look so kind
                    and happy.”</p>
                <p>The doctor did not answer; he just passed the fancy cakes round again.</p>
                <p>When tea was finished, and the garden several times explored, the children said
                    good‐bye.</p>
                <p>“We shall meet again next year,” they said to him at the gate.</p>
                <p>“Well, well, I hope so; a year is a long time.”</p>
                <p>“Oh, not so very long,” said Ruby; “but won’t you come and see us at home?”</p>
                <p>“What would become of my poor patients?”</p>
                <p>“We could send someone else to take care of them.”</p>
                <p>“A <foreign xml:lang="lat">locum tenens</foreign>,” said Rachael, with a grand
                    air, remembering the abstracted young man who had come one day at home, instead
                    of their own cherished doctor.</p>
                <p>“Yes; do come,” they begged. And they begged until Ruby was seated in her chaise,
                    and the others on their bicycles, and they left saying that they should<pb n="129" xml:id="VAB7152-129"/> send him an invitation to their Christmas
                    party, and he <emph>must</emph> come.</p>
                <p>On the return journey the lightning character of the steed was at last
                    discovered. At the first shaking of the reins, it set off and headed for home,
                    not at the wild hand gallop of the earlier part of the day, but at a quick, even
                    trot, which showed a determination to get over the ground without break or
                    hindrance.</p>
                <p>“We shall have to settle down like that to lessons on Monday,” said Roger, when
                    they stopped at their own gate.</p>
                <p>Rachael stroked the steed affectionately.</p>
                <p>“Compared with his conduct at starting, this may, of course, be called a
                    lightning speed; but I think we ought to tell Mrs Brown we think she
                    exaggerated.”</p>
                <p>So they galloped the steed round to his owner, and gave her their kind, but
                    conscientious, opinion of his character.</p>
                <p>Sea‐thrift was astir early next morning, for, in spite of the united family
                    exertions, many things had been left unfinished the night before.</p>
                <p>Ruby was awakened, as of old, by the robin. He was standing on the window‐sill,
                    singing sweetly. She listened attentively, and, although she could distinguish
                    no words this morning, she knew he was bidding her good‐bye, and a happy year,
                    till she came again.</p>
                <p>“You will be here, won’t you?” she said, getting out of bed and going to the
                    window.</p>
                <p>The robin, for answer, hopped on her shoulder and sang more sweetly than
                    before.</p>
                <pb n="130" xml:id="VAB7152-130"/>
                <p>“You little dear,” she said, “I wish you would come home with us! Can’t you come
                    home with us? It is not as nice a one as this, but there <emph>is</emph> a
                    garden at home, with trees and bushes, and you will be quite free.”</p>
                <p>But at the mere suggestion of such a thing the robin ceased singing, and flew
                    away to his old perch over the well.</p>
                <p>Ruby leaned out of the window in great distress. “Come back,” she cried, “please
                    come back; I won’t ask you to come home with us any more.”</p>
                <p>But he did not come back, and Ruby began to dress rather sadly. Presently she
                    looked out of the window again.</p>
                <p>“I have thought of a nice plan for you,” she said cheerfully. “I will show you
                    what it is as soon as I come out.”</p>
                <p>She completed her toilet quickly, and ran downstairs to the parlour. She took a
                    small wooden box from the cupboard. It was a deep box, with half its lid left to
                    it, and it was full of fine hay. A glass bowl had been carefully packed and sent
                    in it from home. Ruby ran into the garden. The robin was still singing on the
                    well.</p>
                <p>“Do you see this little box?” she said, showing it to him, “I shall put it in the
                    shed, it will make a warm bed for you in the winter. There is a hole in the roof
                    of the wood‐shed, and a little shelf near the hole, just big enough for the
                    box.” Ruby ran into the shed, and put the little box on the shelf near the hole
                    in the roof. When she had done this, the robin flew in through the hole and
                    hopped into the box, to show her he <choice>
                        <orig>under‐<pb n="131" xml:id="VAB7152-131"/> stood</orig>
                        <reg>understood</reg>
                    </choice>: then he sang cheerfully for a few minutes, and flew away again.</p>
                <p>Oh, how busy everyone was that morning at Sea‐thrift! Father and mother, Ethel
                    and Charlie, Roger and Rachael and Ruby, and the maids in the kitchen, were all
                    strapping and cording and labelling, until Mr Blogg drove up in his big cart for
                    the luggage. Then, of course, many forgotten friends came, at the last moment,
                    to say good‐bye. The setters, and the foxhound puppy, came for a last petting
                    from Rachael; and, after a safe interval, the big tabby cat and fluffy Persian
                    kitten, dropped over the wall from the coastguards’ garden, and purred round her
                    legs; and, just as they were all packed safely into the trap, Mrs Mayes came up
                    the loke with cuttings from her garden for Roger.</p>
                <p>At last, after several false starts, they set off, along the sunny road, and up
                    and down the green lanes, to the station. As they drove along, and looked across
                    the beautiful great stretch of country to the sea, they all felt sad at having
                    to change this space and freedom, for streets and squares and parks. The drive
                    was silent until they reached the little hill close to the station. Here a
                    chirping in the elms made them look up.</p>
                <p>“It is the robin,” cried Ruby; “look, Rachael, look, Roger, he has come to see us
                    off.”</p>
                <p>And the robin darted along from branch to branch, his red breast flashing in the
                    sun. On the last elm he stopped and trilled his farewell notes.</p>
                <pb n="132" xml:id="VAB7152-132"/>
                <p>“Good‐bye,” cried the children; “please be here to meet us when we come
                    again.”</p>
                <p>And he fluttered his wings, and sang a few notes by way of promise; then he flew
                    back along the road through the elms.</p>
                <p>At the station another friend waited to bid them good‐bye. As their waggonette
                    rattled over the stones, the doctor stepped out of the booking‐office, and
                    opened the door for them.</p>
                <p>“Oh, how kind of you to come,” they said; “how did you know we should go by this
                    train?”</p>
                <p>“Another little bird.” Then he helped them out, and carried some of their
                    packages.</p>
                <p>“The train is full of children,” he said, “all going back to school after the
                    holidays. I wonder if many of them have had as good a time as you?” he whispered
                    to Ruby.</p>
                <p>“I hope so,” she answered; “don’t you think they have?”</p>
                <p>“Perhaps; we’ll hope so, at anyrate; and if they haven’t, the wish may help them
                    another time.”</p>
                <p>Then the train began to move.</p>
                <p>“Good‐bye—good‐bye.”</p>
                <p>“Be sure you come to stay with us,” said Roger.</p>
                <p>“Please don’t forget,” said Rachael; “we’ll write and tell you all about the
                    trains, and meet you at the station.”</p>
                <p>The doctor laughed, and kissed his hand to them; and as the train steamed away
                    there was a great waving of hats and hands, and handkerchiefs. Then the doctor
                    turned homewards, and the train steamed<pb n="133" xml:id="VAB7152-133"/> faster
                    and faster, back to the great station it had left seven weeks before.</p>
                <p>I am not going to tell you what they did when they reached home; enough that they
                    arrived there safely, and were soon happily busy in the old routine, with
                    lessons and school companions; and Ruby kept well and strong as the others.
                    There is much to tell about their home life, but I shall not tell it. The three
                    Rs belonged especially to Sea‐thrift, for they were never so happy as in its
                    fragrant garden, and beside its sunny sea. But the beautiful lady watched them
                    in their town home; their footsteps followed hers through many an autumn day,
                    when the wind brought down the chestnuts from the park trees, and the brown
                    leaves lay in heaps under the beeches. Through the winter days, too, she walked
                    beside them in her snowy mantle, and they knew how to find the beauties and
                    wonders to which she pointed. And when the spring time came round, ah! who shall
                    say what sweetness and promise she showed them, in every square and garden, and
                    plot of ground. I must not tell of this—it belongs to another story—and this
                    story has to do only with Sea‐thrift.</p>
                <q>
                    <l>Sea‐thrift grows by the summer sea,</l>
                    <l rend="ti-1">Till the summer’s close,</l>
                    <l>On the grassy cliff, ’neath a radiant sky,</l>
                    <l>While sun and summer and wind go by,</l>
                    <l rend="ti-1">Sea‐thrift blows and blows.</l>
                </q>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>