<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd" xml:id="VAB7023">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Story of Bessie Costrell</title>
                <title type="filing">Story of Bessie Costrell</title>
                <author>Ward, Humphry, Mrs. (1851-1920)</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Optically scanned, encoded and proofed by </resp>
                    <name>W. Charles Morrow</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edited by </resp>
                    <name>Perry Willett</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="bn">
                    <resp>E-text Editor</resp>
                    <name>Brian Norberg</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Corrected By</resp>
                    <name xml:id="elizabethmunson">Elizabeth Munson</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>TEI formatted filesize uncompressed: approx. 158 kbytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
                <date>18-May-1999</date>
                <idno>VAB7023</idno>
                <availability status="unknown">
                    <p>© 2009, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim
                        of copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women
                        Writers Project participants and other members of the university community.
                        Indiana University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.
                        Permission is granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce,
                        distribute or display the contributions to this work claimed by Indiana
                        University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is
                        included in its entirety. For inquiries about commercial uses, please
                        contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Digital Library Program</addrLine><addrLine>Main Library</addrLine><addrLine>Indiana University</addrLine><addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>EMail: diglib@indiana.edu</addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>Victorian Women Writers Project: an Electronic Collection</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Perry Willett, </name>
                    <resp>General Editor.</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>The transcribed copy is from the Research Collections, Indiana University
                    Libraries</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>The Story of Bessie Cotrell</title>
                        <author>Ward, Humphry, Mrs., 1851-1920</author>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>by </resp>
                            <name>Mrs. Humphry Ward </name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>140 p. </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Smith, Elder </publisher>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1895">1895</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl><p><note n="false" xml:id="noPageImages">Page images not available for this text.</note></p>
                <p>All quotation marks, hyphens, dashes, apostrophes and colons have been
                    transcribed as entity references.</p>
                <p>All apostrophes are encoded as &amp;apos;.</p>
                <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been removed; all hyphens are encoded
                    as &amp;hyphen; and em dashes as &amp;mdash;.</p>
                <p>The publisher's advertisement following p.140 has been omitted.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="address" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="addrline" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="body" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="byline" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="div1" occurs="5"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="docauthor" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="docdate" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="docedition" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="docimprint" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="doctitle" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="emph" occurs="63"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="foreign" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="front" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="head" occurs="6"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="hi" occurs="5"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="p" occurs="603"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="pb" occurs="140"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="publisher" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="pubplace" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="sic" occurs="5"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="text" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="title" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="titlepage" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="titlepart" occurs="1"/>
                    <tagUsage gi="trailer" occurs="1"/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                        <ptr target="http://authorities.loc.gov/"/>
                        <note>
                            <p>Library of Congress Subject Headings originate from the source MARC
                                record for the monograph when available.</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="mla">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Modern Language Association Thesaurus</title>
                        <ptr target="http://www.mla.org/publications/bibliography/howtouse_mlabiblio/howtosearchmlabiblio#mla" type="source"/>
                        <ptr target="http://dlib.indiana.edu/vocabulary/modernlangassocgenre/" type="webservice"/>
                        <note><p> The MLA Bibliography staff has created a thesaurus of over 50,000 terms and 200,000
                            names to ensure consistency in the terms and names assigned during indexing. The VWWP
                            project will utilize a subset of the MLA Thesaurus to assign genre headings to the VWWP
                            texts. </p></note>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>                
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="fre">French</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#mla">
                    <list>
                        <item><term ref="http://terminology.dlib.indiana.edu/vwwpgenre/fiction">fiction</term></item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change><date>07-May-1999 </date><label>contributing editor.</label><name>W. Charles
                    Morrow, </name>finished data entry, encoding and proofing</change>
            <change><date>18-May-1999 </date><label>general editor.</label><name>Perry Willett,
                </name>finished editing</change>
            <change><date>2005-02-06</date><label>Programmer</label><name>Mark Millard,
                </name>Converted from SGML to TEI-XML</change>
            <change when="2009-05-10" who="#bn">Coverted from P4 to P5</change>
            <change when="2009-10-27" who="#bn">Normalized id scheme and encoding</change>
            <change when="2010-07-27" who="elizabethmunson">Removed date from fileDesc title</change>
            <change when="2010-07-27" who="elizabethmunson">Added filing title</change>
            <change when="2010-07-27" who="elizabethmunson">Added LCNAF form of author name to sourceDesc and fileDesc author</change>
            <change when="2010-07-27" who="elizabethmunson">Normalized date in biblFull/publicationStmt</change>
            <change who="elizabethmunson" when="2010-08-24">Added genre term</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">THE STORY OF BESSIE COSTRELL </titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <byline>BY <docAuthor>MRS. HUMPHRY WARD </docAuthor> AUTHOR OF “ROBERT ELSMERE,”
                    “THE HISTORY OF DAVID GRIEVE,” “MARCELLA,” ETC.</byline>
                <docImprint>
                    <pubPlace>LONDON: </pubPlace>
                    <publisher>SMITH, ELDER &amp; CO.,
                        <address><addrLine>15, WATERLOO PLACE.</addrLine></address></publisher>
                </docImprint>
                <docDate>1895.</docDate>
                <docEdition>(All rights reserved.)</docEdition>
            </titlePage>
        </front>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="VAB7023-001"/>
            <head>THE STORY OF BESSIE COSTRELL</head>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>SCENE I</head>
                <p><hi rend="b">IT</hi> was an August evening, still and cloudy after a day
                    unusually chilly for the time of year. Now, about sunset, the temperature was
                    warmer than it had been in the morning, and the departing sun was forcing its
                    way through the clouds, breaking up their level masses into delicate latticework
                    of golds and greys. The last radiant light was on the wheat-fields under the
                    hill, and on the long chalk hill itself. Against that glowing background lay the
                    village, already engulfed by the advancing shadow. All the nearer trees, which
                    the daylight had mingled in one green monotony, stood out sharp and distinct,
                    each in its own plane, against the hill.<pb n="2" xml:id="VAB7023-002"/> Each
                    natural object seemed to gain a new accent, a more individual beauty, from the
                    vanishing and yet lingering sunlight.</p>
                <p>An elderly labourer was walking along the road which led to the village. To his
                    right lay the allotment gardens just beginning to be alive with figures, and the
                    voices of men and children. Beyond them, far ahead, rose the square tower of the
                    church; to his left was the hill, and straight in front of him the village, with
                    its veils of smoke lightly brushed over the trees, and its lines of cottages
                    climbing the chalk steeps behind it. His eye as he walked took in a number of
                    such facts as life had trained it to notice. Once he stopped to bend over a
                    fence, to pluck a stalk or two of oats. He examined them carefully; then he
                    threw back his head and sniffed the air, looking all round the sky meanwhile.
                    Yes, the season had been late and harsh, but the fine weather was coming at
                    last. Two or three days' warmth now would ripen even the oats, let alone the
                    wheat.</p>
                <pb n="3" xml:id="VAB7023-003"/>
                <p>Well, he was glad. He wanted the harvest over. It would, perhaps, be his last
                    harvest at Clinton Magna, where he had worked, man and boy, for fifty-six years
                    come Michaelmas. His last harvest! A curious pleasure stirred the man's veins as
                    he thought of it, a pleasure in expected change, which seemed to bring back the
                    pulse of youth, to loosen a little the yoke of those iron years that had
                    perforce aged and bent him; though, for sixty-two, he was still hale and
                    strong.</p>
                <p>Things had all come together. Here was “Muster” Hill, the farmer he had worked
                    for these seventeen years, dying of a sudden, with a carbuncle on the neck, and
                    the farm to be given up at Michaelmas. He—John Bolderfield—had been working on
                    for the widow; but, in his opinion, she was “nobbut a caselty sort of body,” and
                    the sooner she and her children were taken off to Barnet, where they were to
                    live with her mother, the less she'd cost them as had the looking after her. As
                    for the crops, they wouldn't pay the debts; not they. And there<pb n="4" xml:id="VAB7023-004"/> was no one after the farm—“nary one”—and didn't seem
                    like to be. That would make another farm on Muster Forrest's hands. Well, and a
                    good job. Landlords must be “took down;” and there was plenty of work going on
                    the railway just now for those that were turned off.</p>
                <p>He was too old for the railway, though, and he might have found it hard to get
                    fresh work if he had been staying at Clinton. But he was not staying. Poor Eliza
                    wouldn't last more than a few days; a week or two at most, and he was not going
                    to keep on the cottage after he'd buried her.</p>
                <p>Aye, poor Eliza! She was his sister-in-law, the widow of his second brother. He
                    had been his brother's lodger during the greater part of his working life, and
                    since Tom's death he had stayed on with Eliza. She and he suited each other, and
                    the “worritin' childer” had all gone away years since and left them in peace. He
                    didn't believe Eliza knew where any of them were, except Mary,<pb n="5" xml:id="VAB7023-005"/> “married over to Luton”—and Jim, and Jim's Louisa.
                    And a good riddance too. There was not one of them knew how to keep a shilling
                    when they'd got one. Still, it was a bit lonesome for Eliza now, with no one but
                    Jim's Louisa to look after her.</p>
                <p>He grew rather downhearted as he trudged along, thinking. She and he had stuck
                    together “a many year.” There would be nobody left for him to go along with when
                    she was gone. There was his niece Bessie Costrell and her husband, and there was
                    his silly old cousin Widow Waller. He dared say they'd both of them want him to
                    live with them. At the thought a grin crossed his ruddy face. They both knew
                    about <emph>it</emph>—that was what it was. And he wouldn't live with either of
                    them, not he. Not yet a bit, anyway. All the same, he had a fondness for Bessie
                    and her husband. Bessie was always very civil to <emph>him</emph>—he chuckled
                    again—and if anything had to be done with <emph>it</emph>, while he was five
                    miles off at Frampton on a job<pb n="6" xml:id="VAB7023-006"/> of work that had
                    been offered him, he didn't know but he'd as soon trust Isaac Costrell and
                    Bessie as anybody else. You might call Isaac rather a fool, what with his
                    religion, and “extemp'ry prayin', an' that,” but all the same Bolderfield
                    thought of him with a kind of uneasy awe. If ever there was a man secure of the
                    next world it was Isaac Costrell. His temper, perhaps, was “nassty,” which might
                    pull him down a little when the last account came to be made up; and it could
                    not be said that his elder children had come to much, for all his piety. But, on
                    the whole, Bolderfield only wished he stood as well with the powers talked about
                    in chapel every Sunday as Isaac did.</p>
                <p>As for Bessie, she had been a wasteful woman all her life, with never a bit of
                    money put by, and never a good dress to her back. But, “Lor bless yer, there was
                    a many worse folk nor Bessie.” She wasn't one of your sour people—she could make
                    you laugh; she had a merry heart. Many a pleasant evening had he passed chatting
                    with her and Isaac;<pb n="7" xml:id="VAB7023-007"/> and whenever they cooked
                    anything good there was always a bite for him. Yes, Bessie had been a good niece
                    to him; and if he trusted any one he dared say he'd trust them.</p>
                <p>“Well, how's Eliza, Muster Bolderfield?” said a woman who passed him in the
                    village street.</p>
                <p>He replied, and then went his way, sobered again, dreading to find himself at the
                    cottage once more, and in the stuffy upper room with the bed and the dying
                    woman. Yet he was not really sad, not here at least, out in the air and the sun.
                    There was always a thought in his mind, a fact in his consciousness, which stood
                    between him and sadness. It had so stood for a long, long time. He walked
                    through the village to-night in spite of Eliza and his sixty years with a free
                    bearing and a confident glance to right and left. He knew, and the village knew,
                    that he was not as other men.</p>
                <p>He passed the village green with its pond, and began to climb a lane leading to
                    the hill. Half-way<pb n="8" xml:id="VAB7023-008"/> up stood two cottages
                    sideways. Phloxes and marigolds grew untidily about their doorways, and straggly
                    roses, starved a little by the chalk soil, looked in at their latticed windows.
                    They were, however, comparatively modern and comfortable, with two bedrooms
                    above and two living-rooms below, far superior to the older and more picturesque
                    cottages in the main street.</p>
                <p>John went in softly, put down his straw dinner-bag, and took off his heavy boots.
                    Then he opened a door in the wall of the kitchen, and gently climbed the
                    stairs.</p>
                <p>A girl was sitting by the bed. When she saw his whitish head and red face emerge
                    against the darkness of the stair-hole, she put up her finger for silence.</p>
                <p>John crept in and came to look at the patient. His eyes grew round and staring,
                    his colour changed.</p>
                <p>“Is she a-goin'?” he said, with evident excitement.</p>
                <p>Jim's Louisa shook her head. She was rather a<pb n="9" xml:id="VAB7023-009"/>
                    stupid girl, heavy and round-faced, but she had nursed her grandmother well.</p>
                <p>“No; she's asleep. Muster Drew's been here, and she dropped off while he was
                    a-talkin' to her.”</p>
                <p>Mr. Drew was the Congregational minister.</p>
                <p>“Did she send for him?”</p>
                <p>“Yes; she said she felt her feet a-gettin' cold, and I must run. But I don't
                    believe she's no worse.”</p>
                <p>John stood looking down, ruefully. Suddenly the figure in the bed turned.</p>
                <p>“John,” said a comparatively strong voice which made Bolderfield start—“John,
                    Muster Drew says you'd oughter put it in the bank. You'll be a fool if yer
                    don't, 'ee says.”</p>
                <p>The old woman's pinched face emerged from the sheets, looking up at him. Bluish
                    patches showed here and there on the drawn white skin; there was a great change
                    since the morning, but the eyes were still alive.</p>
                <p>John was silent a moment, one corner of his<pb n="10" xml:id="VAB7023-010"/>
                    mouth twitching, as though what she had said struck him in a humorous light.</p>
                <p>“Well, I don't know as I mind much what 'ee says, 'Liza.”</p>
                <p>“Sit down.”</p>
                <p>She made a movement with her emaciated hand. John sat down on the chair Louisa
                    gave up to him, and bent down over the bed.</p>
                <p>“If yer woan't do—what Muster Drew says, John—whatever <emph>wull</emph> yer do
                    with it?”</p>
                <p>She spoke slowly, but clearly. John scratched his head. His complexion had
                    evidently been very fair. It was still fresh and pink, and the full cheek hung a
                    little over the jaw. The mouth was shrewd, but its expression was oddly
                    contradicted by the eyes, which had on the whole a childish, weak look.</p>
                <p>“I think yer must leave it to me, 'Liza,” he said at last. “I'll do all for the
                    best.”</p>
                <p>“No—yer'll not, John,” said the dying voice. “You'd a done a many stupid
                    things—if I 'adn't<pb n="11" xml:id="VAB7023-011"/> stopped yer. An' I'm
                    a-goin'. You'll never leave it wi' Bessie?”</p>
                <p>“An' who 'ud yer 'ave me leave it with? Ain't Bessie my own sister's child?”</p>
                <p>An emaciated hand stole out of the bed-clothes and fastened feebly on his
                    arm.</p>
                <p>“If yer do, John, yer'll repent it. Yer never were a good one at judgin' folk.
                    Yer doan't consider nothin'—an' I'm a-goin'. Leave it with Saunders, John.”</p>
                <p>There was a pause. Then John said with an obstinate look—</p>
                <p>“Saunders 'as never been a friend o' mine, since 'ee did me out o' that bit o'
                    business with Missus Moulsey. An' I don't mean to go makin' friends with him
                    again.”</p>
                <p>Eliza withdrew her hand with a long sigh, and her eyelids closed. A fit of
                    coughing shook her; she had to be lifted in bed, and it left her gasping and
                    deathly. John was sorely troubled, and not only for himself. When she was more
                    at ease<pb n="12" xml:id="VAB7023-012"/> again, he stooped to her and put his
                    mouth to her ear.</p>
                <p>“'Liza, don't yer think no more about it. Did Mr. Drew read to yer? Are yer
                    comfortable in yer mind?”</p>
                <p>She made a sign of assent, which showed, however, no great interest in the
                    subject. There was silence for a long time. Louisa was getting supper
                    downstairs. John, oppressed by the heat of the room and tired by his day's work,
                    had almost fallen asleep in his chair, when the old woman spoke again.</p>
                <p>“John—what 'ud you think o' Mary Anne Waller?”</p>
                <p>The whisper was still human and eager.</p>
                <p>John roused himself, and could not help an astonished laugh.</p>
                <p>“Why, whatever put Mary Anne into your head, 'Liza? Yer never thought anythink o'
                    Mary Anne—no more than me.”</p>
                <p>Eliza's eyes wandered round the room.</p>
                <pb n="13" xml:id="VAB7023-013"/>
                <p>“P'raps—” she said, then stopped, and could say no more. She seemed to become
                    unconscious, and John went to call for Louisa.</p>
                <p>In the middle of the night John woke with a start, and sat up to listen. Not a
                    sound—but they would have called him if the end had come. He could not rest,
                    however, and presently he huddled on some clothes and went to listen at Eliza's
                    door. It was ajar, and hearing nothing he pushed it open.</p>
                <p>Poor Eliza lay in her agony, unconscious, and breathing heavily. Beside her sat
                    the widow, Mary Anne Waller, and Louisa, motionless too, their heads bent. There
                    was an end of candle in a basin behind the bed, which threw circles of wavering
                    light over the coarse whitewash of the roof and on the cards and faded
                    photographs above the tiny mantelpiece.</p>
                <p>John crept up to the bed. The two women made a slight movement to let him stand
                    between them.</p>
                <pb n="14" xml:id="VAB7023-014"/>
                <p>“Can't yer give her no brandy?” he asked, whispering.</p>
                <p>Mary Anne Waller shook her head.</p>
                <p>“Dr. Murch said we wer'n't to trouble her. She'll go when the light comes—most
                    like.”</p>
                <p>She was a little shrivelled woman with a singularly delicate mouth, that quivered
                    as she spoke. John and Eliza Bolderfield had never thought much of her, though
                    she was John's cousin. She was a widow, and greatly “put upon” both by her
                    children and her neighbours. Her children were grown up, and settled—more or
                    less—in the world, but they still lived on her freely whenever it suited them;
                    and in the village generally she was reckoned but a poor creature.</p>
                <p>However, when Eliza—originally a hard, strong woman—took to her bed with
                    incurable disease, Mary Anne Waller came in to help, and was accepted. She did
                    everything humbly; she even let Louisa order her about. But before the end,
                    Eliza had come to be restless when she was not there.</p>
                <pb n="15" xml:id="VAB7023-015"/>
                <p>Now, however, Eliza knew no more, and the little widow sat gazing at her with the
                    tears on her cheeks. John, too, felt his eyes wet.</p>
                <p>But after half an hour, when there was still no change, he was turning away to go
                    back to bed, when the widow touched his arm.</p>
                <p>“Won't yer give her a kiss, John?” she said timidly. “She wor a good sister to
                    you.”</p>
                <p>John, with a tremor, stooped, and clumsily did as he was told—the first time in
                    his life he had ever done so for Mary Anne. Then, stepping as noiselessly as he
                    could on his bare feet, he hurried away. A man shares nothing of that yearning
                    attraction which draws women to a death-bed as such. Instead, John felt a sudden
                    sickness at his heart. He was thankful to find himself in his own room again,
                    and thought with dread of having to go back—for the end. In spite of his still
                    vigorous and stalwart body, he was often plagued with nervous fears and fancies.
                    And it was years now since he had seen death—he had, indeed, carefully avoided
                    seeing it.</p>
                <pb n="16" xml:id="VAB7023-016"/>
                <p>Gradually, however, as he sat on the edge of his bed in the summer dark, the new
                    impression died away, and something habitual took its place—that shielding,
                    solacing thought, which was in truth all the world to him, and was going to make
                    up to him for Eliza's death, for getting old, and the lonesomeness of a man
                    without chick or child. He would have felt unutterably forlorn and miserable, he
                    would have shrunk trembling from the shapes of death and pain that seemed to
                    fill the darkness, but for this fact, this defence, this treasure, that set him
                    apart from his fellows and gave him this proud sense of superiority, of a good
                    time coming in spite of all. Instinctively, as he sat on the bed, he pushed his
                    bare foot backwards till his heel touched a wooden object that stood underneath.
                    The contact cheered him at once. He ceased to think about Eliza, his head was
                    once more full of whirling plans and schemes.</p>
                <p>The wooden object was a box that held his money, the savings of a labourer's
                    lifetime. Seventy-one<pb n="17" xml:id="VAB7023-017"/> pounds! It seemed to him
                    an ocean of gold, never to be exhausted. The long toil of saving it was almost
                    done. After the Frampton job, he would begin enjoying it, cautiously at first,
                    taking a bit of work now and again, and then a bit of holiday.</p>
                <p>All the savour of life was connected for him with that box. His mind ran over the
                    constant excitements of the many small loans he had made from it to his
                    relations and friends. A shilling in the pound interest—he had never taken less
                    and he had never asked more. He had only lent to people he knew well, people in
                    the village whom he could look after, and seldom for a term longer than three
                    months, for to be parted from his money at all gave him physical pain. He had
                    once suffered great anxiety over a loan to his eldest brother of thirty pounds.
                    But in the end James had paid it all back. He could still feel tingling through
                    him the passionate joy with which he had counted out the recovered sovereigns,
                    with the extra three half-sovereigns of interest.</p>
                <pb n="18" xml:id="VAB7023-018"/>
                <p>Muster Drew indeed! John fell into an angry inward argument against his
                    suggestion of the savings bank. It was an argument he had often rehearsed, often
                    declaimed, and at bottom it all came to this—without that box under his bed, his
                    life would have sunk to dulness and decrepitude; he would have been merely a
                    pitiful and lonely old man. He had neither wife nor children, all for the
                    hoard's sake; but while the hoard was there, to be handled any hour, he
                    regretted nothing. Besides, there was the peasant's rooted distrust of offices,
                    and paper transactions, of any routine that checks his free will and frightens
                    his inexperience. He was still eagerly thinking when the light began to flood
                    into his room, and before he could compose himself to sleep the women called
                    him.</p>
                <p>But he shed no more tears. He saw Eliza die, his companion of forty years, and
                    hardly felt it. What troubled him all through the last scene was the thought
                    that now he should never know why she was so set against “Bessie's 'avin'
                    it.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <pb n="19" xml:id="VAB7023-019"/>
                <head>SCENE II</head>
                <p><hi rend="b">IT</hi> was, indeed, the general opinion in Clinton Magna that John
                    Bolderfield—or “Borrofull,” as the village pronounced it, took his
                    sister-in-law's death too lightly. The women especially pronounced him a hard
                    heart. Here was “poor Eliza” gone, Eliza who had kept him decent and comfortable
                    for forty years, ever since he was a lad, and he could go about whistling,
                    and—to talk to him—as gay as a lark! Yet John contributed handsomely to the
                    burial expenses—Eliza having already, through her burial club, provided herself
                    with a more than regulation interment; and he gave Jim's Louisa her mourning.
                    Nevertheless these things did not avail. It was felt instinctively that he was
                    not beaten down as he ought to have been, and Mrs. Saunders, the smith's<pb n="20" xml:id="VAB7023-020"/> wife, was applauded when she said to her
                    neighbours that “you couldn't expeck a man with John Bolderfield's money to have
                    as many feelin's as other people.” Whence it would seem that the capitalist is
                    no more truly popular in small societies than in large.</p>
                <p>John, however, did not trouble himself about these things. He was hard at work
                    harvesting for Muster Hill's widow, and puzzling his head day and night as to
                    what to do with his box.</p>
                <p>When the last field had been carried and the harvest supper was over, he came
                    home late, and wearied out. His working life at Clinton Magna was done; and the
                    family he had worked for so long was broken up in distress and poverty. Yet he
                    felt only a secret exultation. Such toil and effort behind—such a dreamland in
                    front!</p>
                <p>Next day he set to work to wind up his affairs. The furniture of the cottage was
                    left to Eliza's son Jim, and the daughter had arranged for the carting of it to
                    the house twelve miles off where her parents<pb n="21" xml:id="VAB7023-021"/>
                    lived. She was to go with it on the morrow, and John would give up the cottage
                    and walk over to Frampton, where he had already secured a lodging.</p>
                <p>Only twenty-four hours!—and he had not yet decided. Which was it to be—Saunders,
                    after all—or the savings bank—or Bessie?</p>
                <p>He was cording up his various possessions—a medley lot—in different parcels and
                    bundles when Bessie Costrell knocked at the door. She had already offered to
                    stow away anything he might like to leave with her.</p>
                <p>“Well, I thought you'd be busy,” she said as she walked in, “an' I came up to
                    lend a hand. Is them the things you're goin' to leave me to take care on?”</p>
                <p>John nodded.</p>
                <p>“Field's cart, as takes Louisa's things to-morrer, is a-goin' to deliver these at
                    your place first. They're more nor I thought they would be. But you can put 'em
                    anywheres.”</p>
                <p>“Oh, I'll see to them.”</p>
                <pb n="22" xml:id="VAB7023-022"/>
                <p>She sat down and watched him tie the knots of the last parcel.</p>
                <p>“There's some people as is real ill-natured,” she said presently, in an angry
                    voice.</p>
                <p>“Aye?” said John, looking up sharply. “What are they sayin' now?”</p>
                <p>“It's Muster Saunders. 'Ee's allus sayin' nassty things about other folks. And
                    there'd be plenty of fault to be found with 'im, if onybody was to try. An'
                    Sally Saunders eggs him on dreadful.”</p>
                <p>Saunders was the village smith, a tall, brawny man, of great size and
                    corresponding wisdom, who had been the village arbiter and general councillor
                    for a generation. There was not a will made in Clinton Magna that he did not
                    advise upon; not a bit of contentious business that he had not a share in; not a
                    family history that he did not know. His probity was undisputed; his ability was
                    regarded with awe; but as he had a sharp tongue and was no respecter of persons,
                    there was of course an opposition.</p>
                <pb n="23" xml:id="VAB7023-023"/>
                <p>John took a seat on the wooden box he had just been cording, and mopped his brow.
                    His full cheeks were crimson, partly with exertion, partly with sudden
                    annoyance.</p>
                <p>“What's 'ee been sayin' now? Though it doan't matter a brass farthin' to me what
                    'ee says.”</p>
                <p>“He says you 'aven't got no proper feelin<choice>
                        <sic> </sic>
                        <corr>'</corr>
                    </choice>s about poor Eliza, an' you'd ought to have done a great deal more for
                    Louisa. But 'ee says you allus were a mean one with your money—an' you knew that
                        '<emph>ee</emph> knew it—for 'ee'd stopped you takin' an unfair advantage
                    more nor once. An' 'ee didn't believe as your money would come to any good; for
                    now Eliza was gone you wouldn't know how to take care on it.”</p>
                <p>John's eyes flamed.</p>
                <p>“Oh! 'ee says that, do 'ee? Well, Saunders wor allus a beast—an' a beast 'ee'll
                    be.”</p>
                <p>He sat with his chin on his large dirty hands, ruminating furiously.</p>
                <p>It was quite true that Saunders had thwarted him<pb n="24" xml:id="VAB7023-024"/>
                    more than once. There was old Mrs. Moulsey at the shop, when she wanted to buy
                    those cottages in Potter's Row—and there was Sam Field the higgler—both of them
                    would have borrowed from him if Saunders hadn't cooled them off. Saunders said
                    it was a Jew's interest he was asking—because there was security—but he wasn't
                    going to accept a farthing less than his shilling a pound for three months—not
                    he! So they might take it or leave it. And Mrs. Moulsey got hers from the
                    Building Society, and Sam Field made shift to go without. And John Bolderfield
                    was three pounds poorer that quarter than he need have been—all along of
                    Saunders. And now Saunders was talking “agen him” like this—blast him!</p>
                <p>“Oh, an' then he went on,” pursued Bessie with gusto, “about your bein' too
                    ignorant to put it in the post-office. 'Ee said you'd think Edwards would go an'
                    spend it” (Edwards was the post-master), “an' then he laughed fit to split
                    'imself. Yer couldn't see more nor the length of your own nose, he said,—<pb n="25" xml:id="VAB7023-025"/> it was edication <emph>you</emph> wanted. As
                    for 'im, 'ee said, 'ee'd have kep' it for you if you'd asked him, but you'd been
                    like a bear with a sore 'ead, 'ee said, ever since Mrs. Moulsey's affair—so 'ee
                    didn't suppose you would.”</p>
                <p>“Well, 'ee's about right there,” said John, grimly; “'ee's talkin' sense for onst
                    when 'ee says that. I'd dig a hole in the hill and bury it sooner nor I'd trust
                    it to 'im—I would, by—” he swore vigorously. “A thieving set of magpies is all
                    them Saunders—cadgin' 'ere and cadgin' there.”</p>
                <p>He spoke with fierce contempt, the tacit hatred of years leaping to sight.
                    Bessie's bright brown eyes looked at him with sympathy.</p>
                <p>“It was just his nassty spite,” she said. “He knew '<emph>ee</emph> could never
                    ha' done it—not what you've done—out o' your wages. Not unless 'ee got Sally to
                    tie 'im to the dresser with ropes so as 'ee couldn't go a-near the Spotted Deer
                    no more!”</p>
                <p>She laughed like a merry child at her own<pb n="26" xml:id="VAB7023-026"/>
                    witticism, and John relished it too, though he was not in a laughing mood.</p>
                <p>“Why,” continued Bessie with enthusiasm, “it was Muster Drew as said to me the
                    other afternoon, as we was walkin' 'ome from the churchyard, says 'ee, ‘Mrs.
                    Costrell, I call it splendid what John's done—I <emph>do</emph>,’ 'ee says. ‘A
                    labourer on fifteen shillin's a week—why, it's an example to the county,’ 'ee
                    says. ‘'Ee ought to be showed.’”</p>
                <p>John's face relaxed. The temper and obstinacy in the eyes began to yield to the
                    weak complacency which was their more normal expression.</p>
                <p>There was silence for a minute or two. Bessie sat with her hands on her lap and
                    her face turned towards the open door. Beyond the cherry-red phloxes outside it,
                    the ground fell rapidly to the village, rising again beyond the houses to a
                    great stubble field, newly shorn. Gleaners were already in the field, their bent
                    figures casting sharp shadows on the golden upland, and the field itself
                    stretched upwards to a great wood that lay folded round the<pb n="27" xml:id="VAB7023-027"/> top of a spreading hill. To the left, beyond the
                    hill, a wide plain travelled into the sunset, its level spaces cut by the
                    scrawled elms and hedgerows of the nearer landscape. The beauty of it all—the
                    beauty of an English midland—was of a modest and measured sort, depending
                    chiefly on bounties of sun and air, on the delicacies of gentle curves and the
                    pleasant intermingling of wood and cornfield, of light spaces with dark, of
                    solid earth with luminous sky.</p>
                <p>Such as it was, however, neither Bessie nor John spared it a moment's attention.
                    Bessie was thinking a hundred busy thoughts. John, on the other hand, had begun
                    to consider her with an excited scrutiny. She was a handsome woman, as she sat
                    in the doorway with her fine brown head turned to the light. But John naturally
                    was not thinking of that. He was in the throes of decision.</p>
                <p>“Look 'ere, Bessie,” he said suddenly; “what 'ud you say if I wor to ask Isaac
                    an' you to take care on it?”</p>
                <pb n="28" xml:id="VAB7023-028"/>
                <p>Bessie started slightly. Then she looked frankly round at him. She had very keen,
                    lively eyes, and a bright red-brown colour on thin cheeks. The village applied
                    to her the epithet which John's thoughts had applied to Muster Hill's widow.
                    They said she was “caselty,” which means flighty, haphazard, excitable; but she
                    was popular, nevertheless, and had many friends.</p>
                <p>It was, of course, her own settled opinion that her uncle ought to leave that box
                    with her and Isaac; and it had wounded her vanity, and her affection besides,
                    that John had never yet made any such proposal, though she knew—as, indeed, the
                    village knew—that he was perplexed as to what to do with his hoard. But she had
                    never dared to suggest that he should leave it with her, out of fear of Eliza
                    Bolderfield. Bessie was well aware that Eliza thought ill of her, and would
                    dissuade John from any such arrangement if she could. And so formidable was
                    Eliza—a woman of the hardest and sourest virtue—when she chose, that Bessie
                        was<pb n="29" xml:id="VAB7023-029"/> afraid of her, even on her death-bed,
                    though generally ready enough to quarrel with other people. Nevertheless, Bessie
                    had always felt that it would be a crying shame and slight if she and Isaac did
                    not have the guardianship of the money. She thirsted, perhaps, to make an
                    impression upon public opinion in the village, which, as she instinctively
                    realized, held her cheaply. And then, of course, there was the secret thought of
                    John's death, and what might come of it. John had always loudly proclaimed that
                    he meant to spend his money, and not leave it behind him. But the instinct of
                    saving, once formed, is strong. John, too, might die sooner than he thought—and
                    she and Isaac had children.</p>
                <p>She had come up, indeed, that afternoon, haunted by a passionate desire to get
                    the money into her hands; yet the mere sordidness of “expectations” counted for
                    less in the matter than one would suppose. Vanity, a vague wish to ingratiate
                    herself with her uncle, to avoid a slight—these were, on the whole, her
                    strongest motives. At any rate,<pb n="30" xml:id="VAB7023-030"/> when he had
                    once asked her the momentous question, she knew well what to say to him.</p>
                <p>“Well, if you arst me,” she said hastily, “of course <emph>we</emph> think as
                    it's only nateral you should leave it with Isaac an' me, as is your own kith and
                    kin. But we wasn't goin' to say nothin'; we didn't want to be pushin' of
                    ourselves forward.”</p>
                <p>John rose to his feet. He was in his shirt-sleeves, which were rolled up. He
                    pulled them down, put on his coat, an air of crisis on his fat face.</p>
                <p>“Where 'ud you put it?” he said.</p>
                <p>“Yer know that cupboard by the top of the stairs? It 'ud stand there easy. And
                    the cupboard's got a good lock to it; but we'd 'ave it seen to, to make
                    sure.”</p>
                <p>She looked up at him eagerly. She longed to feel herself trusted and important.
                    Her self-love was too often mortified in these respects.</p>
                <p>John fumbled round his neck for the bit of black cord on which he kept two
                    keys—the key of his<pb n="31" xml:id="VAB7023-031"/> room while he was away, and
                    the key of the box itself.</p>
                <p>“Well, let's get done with it,” he said. “I'm off to-morrer mornin', six o'clock.
                    You go and get Isaac to come down.”</p>
                <p>“I'll run,” said Bessie, catching up her shawl and throwing it over her head. “He
                    wor just finishin' his tea.”</p>
                <p>And she whirled out of the cottage, running up the steep road behind it as fast
                    as she could. John was vaguely displeased by her excitement; but the die was
                    cast. He went to make his arrangements.</p>
                <p>Bessie ran till she was out of breath. When she reached her own house, a cottage
                    in a side lane above the Bolderfields' cottage and overlooking it from the back,
                    she found her husband sitting with his pipe at the open door and reading his
                    newspaper. Three out of her own four children were playing in the lane,
                    otherwise there was no one about.</p>
                <p>Isaac greeted her with a nod and slight lightening of the eyes, which, however,
                    hardly disturbed<pb n="32" xml:id="VAB7023-032"/> the habitual sombreness of the
                    face. He was a dark, finely featured man, with grizzled hair, carrying himself
                    with an air of sleepy melancholy. He was much older than his wife, and was a
                    prominent leader in the little Independent chapel of the village. His melancholy
                    could give way on occasion to fits of violent temper. For instance, he had been
                    almost beside himself when Bessie, who had leanings to the Establishment, as
                    providing a far more crowded and entertaining place of resort on Sundays than
                    her husband's chapel, had rashly proposed to have the youngest baby christened
                    in church. Other Independents did it freely—why not she? But Isaac had been
                    nearly mad with wrath, and Bessie had fled upstairs from him, with her baby, and
                    bolted the bedroom door in bodily terror. Otherwise, he was a most docile
                    husband—in the neighbours' opinion, docile to absurdity. He complained of
                    nothing, and took notice of little. Bessie's untidy ways left him indifferent;
                    his main interest was in a kind of religious dreaming, and in<pb n="33" xml:id="VAB7023-033"/> an Independent paper to which he occasionally wrote a
                    letter. He was gardener at a small house on the hill, and had rather more
                    education than most of his fellows in the village. For the rest, he was fond of
                    his children, and, in his heart of hearts, exceedingly proud of his wife, her
                    liveliness and her good looks. She had been a remarkably pretty girl when he
                    married her, some eight years after his first wife's death, and there was a
                    great difference of age between them. His two elder children by his first
                    marriage had long since left the home. The girl was in service. It troubled him
                    to think of the boy, who had fallen into bad ways early. Bessie's children were
                    all small, and she herself still young, though over thirty.</p>
                <p>When Bessie came up to him, she looked round to see that no one could hear. Then
                    she stooped and told him her errand in a panting whisper. He must go down and
                    fetch the box at once. She had promised John Borrofull that they would stand by
                    him. They were his own flesh and blood—and the<pb n="34" xml:id="VAB7023-034"/>
                    cupboard had a capital lock—and there wasn't no fear of it at all.</p>
                <p>Isaac listened to her at first with amazement, then sulkily. She had talked to
                    him often certainly about John's money, but it had made little impression on his
                    dreamer's sense. And now her demand struck him disagreeably.</p>
                <p>He didn't want the worrit of other people's money, he said. Let them as owned it
                    keep it; filthy lucre was a snare to all as had to do with it; and it would only
                    bring a mischief to have it in the house.</p>
                <p>After a few more of these objections, Bessie lost her temper. She broke into a
                    torrent of angry arguments and reproaches, mainly turning, it seemed, upon a
                    recent visit to the house of Isaac's eldest son. The drunken ne'er-do-weel had
                    given Bessie much to put up with. Oh yes!—<emph>she</emph> was to be plagued out
                    of her life by Isaac's belongings, and he wouldn't do a pin's worth for her.
                    Just let him see next time, that was all.</p>
                <pb n="35" xml:id="VAB7023-035"/>
                <p>Isaac smoked vigorously through it all. But she was hammering on a sore
                    point.</p>
                <p>“Oh, it's just like yer!” Bessie flung at him at last in desperation. “You're
                    allus the same—a mean-spirited feller, stannin' in your children's way! 'Ow do
                        <emph>you</emph> know who old John's going to leave his money to? 'Ow do
                        <emph>you</emph> know as he wouldn't leave it to <emph>them</emph> poor
                    innercents”—she waved her hand tragically towards the children playing in the
                    road—“if we was just a bit nice and friendly with him now 'ee's gettin' old? But
                    you don't care, not you!—one 'ud think yer were made o' money—an' that little
                    one there not got the right use of his legs!”</p>
                <p>She pointed, half crying, to the second boy, who had already shown signs of hip
                    disease.</p>
                <p>Isaac still smoked, but he was troubled in his mind. A vague presentiment held
                    him, but the pressure brought to bear upon him was strong.</p>
                <p>“I tell yer the lock isn't a good 'un!” he said, suddenly removing his pipe.</p>
                <p>Bessie stopped instantly in the middle of another<pb n="36" xml:id="VAB7023-036"/> tirade. She was leaning against the door, arms akimbo, eyes alternately wet
                    and flaming.</p>
                <p>“Then, if it isn't,” she said, with a triumphant change of tone, “I'll soon get
                    Flack to see to it—it's nobbut a step. I'll run up after supper.”</p>
                <p>Flack was the village carpenter.</p>
                <p>“An' there's mother's old box as takes up the cupboard,” continued Isaac
                    gruffly.</p>
                <p>Bessie burst out laughing.</p>
                <p>“Oh! yer old silly,” she said. “As if they couldn't stand one top o' the t'other.
                    Now, do just go, Isaac—there's a lovey! 'Ee's waitin' for yer. Whatever did make
                    yer so contrairy? Of course I didn't mean nothin' I said—an' I don't mind
                    Timothy, nor nothin'.”</p>
                <p>Still he did not move.</p>
                <p>“Then I s'pose yer want everybody in the village to know?” he said with
                    sarcasm.</p>
                <p>Bessie was taken aback.</p>
                <p>“No—I—don't—” she said undecidedly—“I don't know what yer mean.”</p>
                <pb n="37" xml:id="VAB7023-037"/>
                <p>“You go back and tell John as I'll come when it's dark, an', if he's not a
                    stupid, he won't want me to come afore.”</p>
                <p>Bessie understood and acquiesced. She ran back with her message to John.</p>
                <p>At half-past eight, when it had grown almost dark, Isaac descended the hill. John
                    opened the door to his knock.</p>
                <p>“Good evenin', Isaac. Yer'll take it, will yer?”</p>
                <p>“If you can't do nothin' better with it,” said Isaac, unwillingly. “But in
                    gineral I'm not partial on keeping other folk's money.”</p>
                <p>John liked him all the better for his reluctance.</p>
                <p>“It'll give yer no trouble,” he said. “You lock it up, an' it 'll be all safe.
                    Now, will yer lend a hand?”</p>
                <p>Isaac stepped to the door, looked up the lane, and saw that all was quiet. Then
                    he came back, and the two men raised the box.</p>
                <p>As they crossed the threshold, however, the door of the next cottage—which
                    belonged to Watson, the<pb n="38" xml:id="VAB7023-038"/> policeman—opened
                    suddenly. John, in his excitement, was so startled that he almost dropped his
                    end of the box.</p>
                <p>“Why, Bolderfield,” said Watson's cheery voice, “what have you got there? Do you
                    want a hand?”</p>
                <p>“No, I don't—thank yer kindly,” said John in agitation. “An', if <emph>you</emph>
                    please, Muster Watson, don't yer say nothin' to nobody.”</p>
                <p>The burly policeman looked from John to Isaac, then at the box. John's hoard was
                    notorious, and the officer of the law understood.</p>
                <p>“Lor' bless yer,” he said, with a laugh, “I'm safe. Well, good evenin' to yer, if
                    I can't be of any assistance.”</p>
                <p>And he went off on his beat.</p>
                <p>The two men carried the box up the hill. It was in itself a heavy, old-fashioned
                    affair, strengthened and bottomed with iron. Isaac wondered whether the weight
                    of it were due more to the box or to the money. But he said nothing. He had no
                    idea how<pb n="39" xml:id="VAB7023-039"/> much John might have saved, and would
                    not have asked him the direct question for the world. John's own way of talking
                    about his wealth was curiously contradictory. His “money” was rarely out of his
                    thoughts or speech, but no one had ever been priviledged for many years now to
                    see the inside of his box, except Eliza once; and no one but himself knew the
                    exact amount of the hoard. It delighted him that the village gossips should
                    double or treble it. Their estimates only gave him the more ground for vague
                    boasting, and he would not have said a word to put them right.</p>
                <p>When they reached the Costrells' cottage, John's first care was to examine the
                    cupboard. He saw that the large wooden chest filled with odds and ends of
                    rubbish which already stood there was placed on the top of his own box. Then he
                    tried the lock, and pronounced it adequate; he didn't want to have Flack
                    meddling round. Now at the moment of parting with his treasure he was seized
                    with a sudden fever of secrecy. Bessie meanwhile<pb n="40" xml:id="VAB7023-040"/> hovered about the two men, full of excitement and loquacity. And the
                    children, shut into the kitchen, wondered what could be the matter.</p>
                <p>When all was done, Isaac locked the cupboard, and solemnly presented the key to
                    John, who added it to the other round his neck. Then Bessie unlocked the
                    kitchen, and set the children flying, to help her with the supper. She was in
                    her most bustling and vivacious mood, and she had never cooked the bloaters
                    better or provided a more ample jug of beer. But John was silent and
                    depressed.</p>
                <p>He took leave at last with many sighs and lingerings. But he had not been gone
                    half an hour, and Bessie and Isaac were just going to bed, when there was a
                    knock at the door, and he reappeared.</p>
                <p>“Let me lie down there,” he said, pointing to a broken-down old sofa that ran
                    under the window. “I'm lonesome somehow, an' I've told Louisa.” His white hair
                    and whiskers stood out wildly round his red face. He looked old and ill, and the
                    sympathetic Bessie was sorry for him.</p>
                <pb n="41" xml:id="VAB7023-041"/>
                <p>She made him a bed on the sofa, and he lay there all night, restless, and sighing
                    heavily. He missed Eliza more than he had done yet, and was oppressed with a
                    vague sense of unhappiness. Once, in the middle of the night when all was still,
                    he stole upstairs in his stockinged feet and gently tried the cupboard door. It
                    was quite safe, and he went down contented.</p>
                <p>An hour or two later he was off, trudging to Frampton through the August dawn,
                    with his bundle on his back.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <pb n="42" xml:id="VAB7023-042"/>
                <head>SCENE III</head>
                <p><hi rend="b">SOME</hi> five months passed away.</p>
                <p>One January night the Independent minister of Clinton Magna was passing down the
                    village street. Clinton lay robed in light snow, and “sparkling to the moon.”
                    The frozen pond beside the green, though it was nearly eight o'clock, was still
                    alive with children, sliding and shouting. All around the gabled roofs stood
                    laden and spotless. The woods behind the village, and those running along the
                    top of the snowy hill, were meshed in a silvery mist which died into the moonlit
                    blue, while in the fields the sharpness of the shadows thrown by the scattered
                    trees made a marvel of black and white.</p>
                <p>The minister, in spite of a fighting creed, possessed a measure of gentler
                    susceptibilities, and the beauty<pb n="43" xml:id="VAB7023-043"/> of this basin
                    in the chalk hills, this winter triumphant, these lights of home and fellowship
                    in the cottage windows disputing with the forlornness of the snow, crept into
                    his soul. His mind travelled from the physical purity and hardness before him to
                    the purity and hardness of the inner life—the purity that Christ blessed, the
                    “hardness” that the Christian endures. And such thoughts brought him pleasure as
                    he walked—the mystic's pleasure.</p>
                <p>Suddenly he saw a woman cross the snowy green in front of him. She had come from
                    the road leading to the hill, and her pace was hurried. Her shawl was muffled
                    round her head, but he recognized her, and his mood fell. She was the wife of
                    Isaac Costrell, and she was hurrying to the Spotted Deer, a public-house which
                    lay just beyond the village, on the road to the mill. Already several times that
                    week had he seen her going in or coming out. Talk had begun to reach him, and he
                    said to himself to-night as he saw her,—that Isaac Costrell's wife was going to
                    ruin.</p>
                <pb n="44" xml:id="VAB7023-044"/>
                <p>The thought oppressed him, pricked his pastoral conscience. Isaac was his
                    right-hand man: dull to all the rest of the world, but not dull to the minister.
                    With Mr. Drew sometimes he would break into talk of religion, and the man's dark
                    eyes would lose their film. His big troubled self spoke with that accent of
                    truth which lifts common talk and halting texts to poetry. The minister, himself
                    more of a pessimist than his sermons showed, felt a deep regard for him. Could
                    nothing be done to save Isaac's wife and Isaac? Not so long ago Bessie Costrell
                    had been a decent woman, though a flighty and excitable one. Now some cause,
                    unknown to the minister, had upset a wavering balance, and was undoing a
                    life.</p>
                <p>As he passed the public-house a man came out, and through the open door Mr. Drew
                    caught a momentary glimpse of the bar and the drinkers. Bessie's handsome,
                    reckless head stood out an instant in the bright light.</p>
                <p>Then Drew saw that the man who had emerged was Watson the policeman. They greeted
                        each<pb n="45" xml:id="VAB7023-045"/> other cordially and walked on
                    together. Watson also was a member of the minister's flock. Mr. Drew felt
                    suddenly moved to unburden himself.</p>
                <p>“That was Costrell's wife, Watson, wasn't it, poor thing?”</p>
                <p>“Aye, it wor Mrs. Costrell,” said Watson in the tone of concern natural to the
                    respectable husband and father.</p>
                <p>The minister sighed. “It's terrible the way she's gone downhill the last three
                    months. I never pass almost but I see her going in there or coming out.”</p>
                <p>“No,” said Watson, slowly, “no, it's bad. What I'd like to know,” he added
                    reflectively, “is where she gets the money from.”</p>
                <p>“Oh, she had a legacy, hadn't she, in August? It seems to have been a curse. She
                    has been a changed woman ever since.”</p>
                <p>“Yes, she had a legacy,” said Watson, dubiously; “but I don't believe it was
                    much. She talked big, of course, and made a lot o' fuss—she's that kind o'
                    woman—just as she did about old John's money.”</p>
                <pb n="46" xml:id="VAB7023-046"/>
                <p>“Old John's money?—Ah! did any one ever know what became of that?”</p>
                <p>“Well, there's many people thinks as Isaac has got it hid in the house somewhere,
                    and there's others thinks he's put it in Bedford bank. Edwards told me private
                    he didn't know nothing about it at the post-office, an' Bessie told my wife as
                    John had given Isaac the keepin' of it till he come back again; but he'd knock
                    her about, she said, if she let on what he'd done with it. That's the story
                    she's allus had, and boastin', of course, dreadful, about John's trustin' them,
                    and Isaac doin' all his business for him.”</p>
                <p>The minister reflected.—“And you say the legacy wasn't much?”</p>
                <p>“Well, sir, I know some people over at Bedford where her aunt lived as left it
                    her, and they were sure it wasn't a great deal; but you never know.”</p>
                <p>“And Isaac never said?”</p>
                <p>“Bless yer, no, sir! He was never a great one for talking, wasn't Isaac; but
                    you'd think now as he'd<pb n="47" xml:id="VAB7023-047"/> never learnt how. He'll
                    set there in the Club of a night and never open his mouth to nobody.”</p>
                <p>“Perhaps he's fretting about his wife, Watson?”</p>
                <p>“Well, I don't believe as he knows much about her goin's-on—not all, leastways.
                    I've seen her wait till he was at his work or gone to the Club, and then run
                    down the hill,—tearin'—with her hair flyin'—you'd think she'd gone silly. Oh,
                    it's a bad business,” said Watson, strongly, “an' uncommon bad business—all them
                    young children too.”</p>
                <p>“I never saw her drunk, Watson.”</p>
                <p>“No—yer wouldn't. Nor I neither. But she'll treat half the parish if she gets the
                    chance. I know many young fellers as go to the Spotted Deer just because they
                    know she'll treat 'em. She's a-doin' of it now—there's lots of 'em. And allus
                    changin' such a queer lot of money too—odd half-crowns,—years and years old—King
                    George the Third, sir. No—it's strange—very strange.”</p>
                <p>The two walked on into the darkness, still talking.</p>
                <pb n="48" xml:id="VAB7023-048"/>
                <p>Meanwhile, inside the Spotted Deer Bessie Costrell was treating her hangers-on.
                    She had drunk one glass of gin and water—it had made a beauty of her in the
                    judgment of the tap-room, such a kindling had it given to her brown eyes and
                    such a redness to her cheek. Bessie, in truth, had reached her moment of
                    physical prime. The marvel was that there were no lovers in <choice>
                        <sic>adddition</sic>
                        <corr>addition</corr>
                    </choice> to the drinking and the extravagance. But the worst of the village
                    scandalmongers knew of none. Since this new phase of character in her had
                    developed, she would drink and make merry with any young fellow in the place,
                    but it went no farther. She was <foreign xml:lang="fre">bonne camarade</foreign>
                    with all the world—no more. Perhaps at bottom some coolness of temperament
                    protected her; nobody, at any rate, suspected that it had anything to do with
                    Isaac, or that she cared a ha'porth for so lugubrious and hypocritical a
                    husband.</p>
                <p>She had showered drinks on all her friends, and had, moreover, chattered and
                    screamed herself<pb n="49" xml:id="VAB7023-049"/> hoarse, when the church-clock
                    outside slowly struck eight. She started, changed countenance, and got up to pay
                    at once.</p>
                <p>“Why, there's another o' them half-crowns o' yourn, Bessie,” said a
                    consumptive-looking girl in a bedraggled hat and feathers, as Mrs. Costrell
                    handed her coin to the landlord. “Wheriver do yer get 'em?”</p>
                <p>“If yer don't ask no questions, I won't tell yer no lies,” said Bessie, with
                    quick impudence. “Where did you get them hat and feathers?”</p>
                <p>There was a coarse laugh from the company. The girl in the hat reddened
                    furiously, and she and Bessie—both of them in a quarrelsome state—began to bandy
                    words.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile the landlord was showing the coin to his assistant at the bar.</p>
                <p>“Rum, ain't it? I niver seed one o' them pieces in the village afore this winter,
                    an' I've been 'ere twenty-two year come April.”</p>
                <p>A decent-looking labourer, who did not often visit<pb n="50" xml:id="VAB7023-050"/> the Spotted Deer, was leaning over the bar and caught the words.</p>
                <p>“Well, then, I 'ave,” he said promptly. “I mind well as when I were a lad,
                    sixteen year ago, my fayther borrered a bit o' money off John Bolderfield, to
                    buy a cow with—an' there was 'arf of it in them 'arf-crowns.”</p>
                <p>Those standing near overheard. Bessie and the girl stopped quarrelling. The
                    landlord, startled, cast a sly eye in Bessie's direction. She came up to the
                    bar.</p>
                <p>“What's that yer sayin'?” she demanded. The man repeated his remark.</p>
                <p>“Well, I dessay there was,” said Bessie—“I dessay there was. I s'pose there's
                    plenty of 'em. Where do I get 'em?—why, I get 'em at Bedford, of course, when I
                    goes for my money.”</p>
                <p>She looked round defiantly. No one said anything; but everybody instinctively
                    suspected a lie. The sudden silence was striking.</p>
                <p>“Well, give me my change, will yer?” she said<pb n="51" xml:id="VAB7023-051"/>
                    impatiently to the landlord. “I can't stan' here all night.”</p>
                <p>He gave it to her, and she went out showering reckless good-nights, to which
                    there was little response. The door had no sooner closed upon her than every one
                    in the tap-room pressed round the bar in a close gathering of heads and
                    tongues.</p>
                <p>Bessie ran across the green and began to climb the hill at a rapid pace. Her thin
                    woollen shawl blown back by the wind left her arms and bosom exposed. But the
                    effects of the spirit in her veins prevented any sense of cold, though it was a
                    bitter night.</p>
                <p>Once or twice, as she toiled up the hill, she gave a loud sudden sob.</p>
                <p>“Oh my God!” she said to herself. “My God!”</p>
                <p>When she was half-way up she met a neighbour.</p>
                <p>“Have yer seen Isaac?” Bessie asked her, panting.</p>
                <p>“'Ee's at the Club, arn't 'ee?” said the woman.<pb n="52" xml:id="VAB7023-052"/>
                    “Well, they won't be up yet. Jim tolt me as Muster Perris”—Muster Perris was the
                    vicar of Clinton Magna—“'ad got a strange gen'leman stayin' with 'im, and was
                    goin' to take him into the Club to-night to speak to 'em. 'Ee's a bishop, they
                    ses—someun from furrin parts.”</p>
                <p>Bessie threw her good-night and climbed on.</p>
                <p>When she reached the cottage the lamp was flaming on the table and the fire was
                    bright. Her lame boy had done all she had told him, and her miserable heart
                    softened. She hurriedly put out some food for Isaac. Then she lit a candle and
                    went up to look at the children. They were all asleep in the room to the right
                    of the stairs—the two little boys in one bed, the two little girls in the other,
                    each pair huddled together against the cold, like dormice in a nest. Then she
                    looked, conscience-stricken, at the untidiness of the room. She had bought the
                    children a wonderful number of new clothes lately, and the family being quite
                    unused to such abundance, there was no place to<pb n="53" xml:id="VAB7023-053"/>
                    keep them in. A new frock was flung down in a corner just as it had been taken
                    off; the kitten was sleeping on Arthur's last new jacket; a smart hat with a
                    bunch of poppies in it was lying about the floor; and under the iron beds could
                    be seen a confusion of dusty boots, new and old. The children were naturally
                    reckless like their mother, and they had been getting used to new things. What
                    excited them now, more than the acquisitions themselves, was that their mother
                    had strictly forbidden them ever to show any of their new clothes to their
                    father. If they did, she would beat them well, she said. That they understood;
                    and life was thereby enriched, not only by new clothes but by a number of new
                    emotions and terrors.</p>
                <p>If Bessie noted the state of the room, she made no attempt to mend it. She
                    smoothed back the hair from the boys' foreheads with a violent, shaky hand, and
                    kissed them all, especially Arthur. Then she went out and closed the door behind
                    her.</p>
                <p>Outside she stood a moment on the tiny landing<pb n="54" xml:id="VAB7023-054"/>
                    —listening. Not a sound; but the cottage walls were thin. If any one came along
                    the lane with heavy boots she must hear them. Very like he would be half an hour
                    yet.</p>
                <p>She ran down the stairs and shut the door at the bottom of them, opening into the
                    kitchen. It had no key or she would have locked it; and in her agitation, her
                    state of clouded brain, she forgot the outer door altogether. Hurrying up again,
                    she sat down on the topmost step, putting her candle on the boards beside her.
                    The cupboard at the stair-head where John had left his money was close to her
                    left hand.</p>
                <p>As she sank into the attitude of rest, her first instinct was to cry and bemoan
                    herself. Deep in her woman's being great floods of tears were rising, and would
                    fain have spent themselves. But she fought them down, rapidly passing instead
                    into a state of cold terror—terror of Isaac's step—terror of discovery—of the
                    man in the public-house.</p>
                <p>There was a mousehole in the skirting of the stairs<pb n="55" xml:id="VAB7023-055"/> close to the cupboard. She slipped in a finger, felt
                    along an empty space behind, and drew out a key.</p>
                <p>It turned easily in the cupboard lock, and the two boxes stood revealed, standing
                    apparently just as they stood when John left them. In hot haste Bessie dragged
                    the treasure-box from under the other, starting at every sound in the process,
                    at the thud the old wooden trunk made on the floor of the cupboard as its
                    supporter was withdrawn, at the rustle of her own dress. All the boldness she
                    had shown at the Spotted Deer had vanished. She was now the mere trembling and
                    guilty woman.</p>
                <p>The lock on Bolderfield's box had been forced long before; it opened to her hand.
                    A heap of sovereigns and half-sovereigns lay on one side, divided by a wooden
                    partition from the few silver coins, crowns and half-crowns, still lying on the
                    other. She counted both the gold and silver, losing her reckoning again and
                    again, because of the sudden anguish of listening that would overtake her.</p>
                <pb n="56" xml:id="VAB7023-056"/>
                <p>Thirty-six pounds on the one side, not much more than thirty shillings on the
                    other. When John left it there had been fifty-one pounds in gold, and rather
                    more than twenty pounds in silver, most of it in half-crowns. Ah! she knew the
                    figures well.</p>
                <p>Did that man who had spoken to the landlord in the public-house suspect? How
                    strange they had all looked! What a silly fool she had been to change so much of
                    the silver, instead of sticking to the gold! Yet she had thought the gold would
                    be noticed more.</p>
                <p>When was old John coming back? He had written once from Frampton to say that he
                    was “laid up bad with the rheumatics,” and was probably going into the Frampton
                    Infirmary. That was in November. Since then nothing had been heard of him. John
                    was no scholar. What if he died without coming back? There would be no trouble
                    then, except—except with Isaac.</p>
                <p>Her mind suddenly filled with wild visions,—of<pb n="57" xml:id="VAB7023-057"/>
                    herself marched through the village by Watson, as she had once seen him march a
                    poacher who had mauled one of Mr. Forrest's keepers—of the towering walls of
                    Frampton jail—of a visible physical shame which would kill her—drive her mad.
                    If, indeed, Isaac did not kill her before any one but he knew! He had been that
                    cross and glum all these last weeks—never a bit of talk hardly—always snapping
                    at her and the children. Yet he had never said a word to her about the drink—nor
                    about the things she had bought. As to the “things” and the bills, she believed
                    that he knew nothing—had noticed nothing. At home he was always smoking, sitting
                    silent, with dim eyes, like a man in a dream—or reading his father's old books,
                    “good books,” which filled Bessie with a sense of dreariness unspeakable—or
                    pondering his weekly paper.</p>
                <p>But she believed he had begun to notice the drink. Drinking was universal in
                    Clinton, though there was not much drunkenness. Teetotalers were unknown, and
                    Isaac himself drank his beer freely, and a glass<pb n="58" xml:id="VAB7023-058"/> of spirits, like anybody else on occasion. She had been used for years to
                    fetch his beer from the public, and she had been careful. But there were
                    signs—</p>
                <p>Oh! if she could only think of some way of putting it back—this thirty odd
                    pounds. She held her head between her hands, thinking and thinking. Couldn't
                    that little lawyer man to whom she went every month at Bedford, to fetch her
                    legacy money—couldn't he lend it her, and keep her money till it was paid? She
                    could make up a story, and give him something for himself to induce him to hold
                    his tongue. She had thought of this often before, but never so urgently as now.
                    She would take the carrier's cart to Bedford next day, while Isaac was at work,
                    and try.</p>
                <p>Yet all the time despair was at her heart. So hard to undo! Yet how easy it had
                    been to take and to spend. She thought of that day in September, when she had
                    got the news of her legacy—six shillings a week from an old aunt—her fathers
                    aunt, whose very existence she had forgotten. The<pb n="59" xml:id="VAB7023-059"/> wild delight of it! Isaac got sixteen shillings a week in wages—here was
                    nearly half as much again. She was warned that it would come to an end in two
                    years. But none the less it seemed to her a fortune—and all her life, before it
                    came, mere hard pinching and endurance. She had always been one to spend where
                    she could. Old John had often rated her for it. So had Isaac. But that was his
                    money. This was hers, and he who, for religious reasons, had never made friends
                    with or thought well of any of her family, instinctively disliked the money
                    which had come from them, and made few inquiries into the spending of it.</p>
                <p>Oh! the joy of those first visits to Frampton, when all the shops had seemed to
                    be there for her, and she their natural mistress! How ready people had been to
                    trust her in the village! How tempting it had been to brag and make a mystery!
                    That old skinflint, Mrs. Moulsey, at “the shop,” she had been all sugar and
                    sweets <emph>then</emph>.</p>
                <p>And a few weeks later—six, seven weeks later—<pb n="60" xml:id="VAB7023-060"/>
                    about the beginning of October, these halcyon days had all come to an end. She
                    owed what she could not pay—people had ceased to smile upon her—she was
                    harassed, excited, worried out of her life.</p>
                <p>Old familiar wonder of such a temperament! How can it be so easy to spend, so
                    delightful to promise, and so unreasonably, so unjustly difficult, to pay?</p>
                <p>She began to be mortally afraid of Isaac—of the effect of disclosures. One night
                    she was alone in the cottage, almost beside herself under the pressure of one or
                    two claims she could not meet—one claim especially, that of a little jeweller,
                    from whom she had bought a gold ring and a brooch at Frampton—when the thought
                    of John's hoard swept upon her—clutched her like something living and
                    tyrannical, not to be shaken off.</p>
                <p>It struck her all in an instant that there was another cupboard in the little
                    parlour, exactly like that on the stairs. The lower cupboard had a key—what if
                    it fitted?</p>
                <p>The Devil must have been eager and active that<pb n="61" xml:id="VAB7023-061"/>
                    night, for the key turned in the lock with a smoothness that made honesty
                    impossible—almost foolish. And the old, weak lock on the box itself—why, a
                    chisel had soon made an end of that! Only five minutes—it had been so
                    quick—there had been no trouble. God had made no sign at all.</p>
                <p>Since! All the village smiles—the village flatteries recovered—an orgie of power
                    and pleasure—new passions and excitements—above all, the rising passion of
                    drink, sweeping in storms through a weak nature that alternately opened to them
                    and shuddered at them. And through everything the steadily dribbling away of the
                    hoard—the astonishing ease and rapidity with which the coins—gold or silver—had
                    flowed through her hands! How could one spend so much in meat and dress, in beer
                    and gin, in giving other people beer and gin? How was it possible? She sat lost
                    in miserable thoughts, a mist around her....</p>
                <p>“Wal, I niver!” said a low, astonished voice at the foot of the stairs.</p>
                <pb n="62" xml:id="VAB7023-062"/>
                <p>Bessie rose to her feet with a shriek, the heart stopping in her breast. The door
                    below was ajar, and through the opening peered a face—the vicious, drunken face
                    of her husband's eldest son, Timothy Costrell.</p>
                <p>The man below cast one more look of amazement at the woman standing on the top
                    stair, at the candle behind her, at the open box. Then an idea struck him: he
                    sprang up the stairs at a bound.</p>
                <p>“By gosh!” he said, looking down at the gold and silver. “<emph>By
                    gosh!</emph>”</p>
                <p>Bessie tried to thrust him back. “What are you here for?” she asked fiercely, her
                    trembling lips the colour of the whitewashed wall behind. “You get off at onst,
                    or I'll call yer father.”</p>
                <p>He pushed her contemptuously aside. The swish of her dress caught the candle, and
                    by good fortune put it out, or she would have been in a blaze. Now there was
                    only the light from the paraffin lamp in the kitchen below striking upwards
                    through the open door.</p>
                <pb n="63" xml:id="VAB7023-063"/>
                <p>She fell against the doorway of her bedroom, panting and breathless, watching
                    him.</p>
                <p>He seated himself in her place, and stooped to look at the box. On the inside of
                    the lid was pasted a discoloured piece of paper, and on the paper was written,
                    in a round, laborious hand, the name, “John Bolderfield.”</p>
                <p>“My blazes!” he said slowly, his bloodshot eyes opening wider than ever. “It's
                    old John's money! So yo've been after it, eh?”</p>
                <p>He turned to her with a grin, one hand on the box. He had been tramping for more
                    than three months, during which time they had heard nothing of him. His filthy
                    clothes scarcely hung together. His cheeks were hollow and wolfish. From the
                    whole man there rose a sort of exhalation of vice. Bessie had seen him drunken
                    and out at elbows before, but never so much of the beast as this.</p>
                <p>However, by this time she had somewhat recovered herself, and, approaching him,
                    she stooped and tried to shut the box.</p>
                <pb n="64" xml:id="VAB7023-064"/>
                <p>“You take yourself off,” she said, desperately, pushing him with her fist. “That
                    money's no business o' yourn. It's John's, an' he's comin' back directly. He
                    gave it us to look after, an' I wor countin' it. March!—there's your father
                    comin'!”</p>
                <p>And with all her force she endeavoured to wrench his hand away. He tore it from
                    her, and hit out at her backwards—a blow that sent her reeling against the
                    wall.</p>
                <p>“Yo take yer meddlin' fist out o' that!” he said. “Father ain't coming, and if he
                    wor, I 'spect I could manage the two on yer—<emph>Keowntin</emph> it—” he
                    mimicked her. “Oh! yer a precious innercent, ain't yer? But I know all about
                    yer. Bless yer, I've been in at the Spotted Deer to-night, and there worn't
                    nothin' else talked of but yo and yor goin's on. There won't be a tongue in the
                    place to-morrow that won't be a-waggin' about yer—yur a public charickter, yo
                    are—they'll be sendin' the reporters down on yer for a hinterview. ‘Where the
                    devil do she get the money?’ they says.”</p>
                <pb n="65" xml:id="VAB7023-065"/>
                <p>He threw his curly head back and laughed till his sides shook.</p>
                <p>“Lor, I didn't think I wor going to know quite so soon! An' sich queer
                    'arf-crowns, they ses, as she keeps a-changin'. Jarge somethin'—an old cove in a
                    wig. An' 'ere they is, I'll be blowed,—some on 'em. Well, yer a nice 'un, yer
                    are!”</p>
                <p>He stared her up and down with a kind of admiration.</p>
                <p>Bessie began to cry feebly—the crying of a lost soul.</p>
                <p>“Tim, if yer'll go away an' hold yer tongue, I'll give yer five o' them suverins,
                    and not tell yer father nothin'.”</p>
                <p>“Five on 'em?” he said, grinning. “Five on 'em, eh?”</p>
                <p>And dipping his hands into the box, he began deliberately shovelling the whole
                    hoard into his trousers and waistcoat pockets.</p>
                <p>Bessie flung herself upon him. He gave her one business-like blow which knocked
                    her down against the bedroom door. The door yielded to her fall, and<pb n="66" xml:id="VAB7023-066"/> she lay there half stunned, the blood dripping from
                    her temple.</p>
                <p>“Noa, I'll not take 'em all,” he said, not even troubling to look where she had
                    fallen. “That 'ud be playing it rayther too low down on old John. I'll leave 'im
                    two—jest two—for luck.”</p>
                <p>He buttoned up his coat tightly, then turned to throw a last glance at Bessie. He
                    had always disliked his father's second wife, and his sense of triumph was
                    boundless.</p>
                <p>“Oh! yer not hurt,” he said; “yer shammin. I advise yer to look sharp with
                    shuttin' up. Father'll be up the hill in two or three minutes now. Sorry I can't
                    'elp yer, now yer've set me up so comfortabul. Bye-bye! ”</p>
                <p>He ran down the stairs. She, as her senses revived, heard him open the back-door,
                    cross the little garden, and jump the hedge at the end of it.</p>
                <p>Then she lay absolutely motionless, till suddenly there struck on her ear the
                    distant sound of heavy steps. They roused her like a goad. She dragged<pb n="67" xml:id="VAB7023-067"/> herself to her feet, shut the box, had just time to
                    throw it into the cupboard and lock the door, when she heard her husband walk
                    into the kitchen. She crept into her own room, threw herself on the bed, and
                    wrapped her head and eyes in an old shawl, shivering so that the mattresses
                    shook.</p>
                <p>“Bessie, where are yer?”</p>
                <p>She did not answer. He made a sound of astonishment, and, finding, no candle,
                    took the lamp and mounted the stairs. They were covered with traces of muddy
                    snow, and at the top he stooped to examine a spot upon the boards. It was blood;
                    and his heart thumped in his breast.</p>
                <p>“Bessie, whatever is the matter?”</p>
                <p>For by this time he had perceived her on the bed. He put down the lamp and came
                    to the bedside to look at her.</p>
                <p>“I've 'ad a fall,” she said, faintly. “I tripped up over my skirt as I wor comin'
                    up to look at Arthur. My head's all bleedin'. Get me some water from over
                    there.”</p>
                <pb n="68" xml:id="VAB7023-068"/>
                <p>His countenance fell sadly. But he got the water, exclaiming when he saw the
                    wound.</p>
                <p>He bathed it clumsily, then tied a bit of rag round it, and made her head easy
                    with the pillow. She did not speak, and he sat on beside her, looking at her
                    pale face, and torn, as the silent minutes passed, between conflicting impulses.
                    He had just passed an hour listening to a good man's plain narrative of a life
                    spent for Christ, amid fever-swamps, and human beings more deadly still. The
                    vicar's friend was a missionary bishop, and a High Churchman; Isaac, as a
                    staunch Dissenter by conviction and inheritance, thought ill both of bishops and
                    Ritualists. Nevertheless he had been touched; he had been fired. Deep, though
                    often perplexed instincts in his own heart had responded to the spiritual
                    passion of the speaker. The religious atmosphere had stolen ahout him, melting
                    and subduing.</p>
                <p>And the first effect of it had been to quicken suddenly his domestic conscience;
                    to make him think painfully of Bessie and the children as he<pb n="69" xml:id="VAB7023-069"/> climbed the hill. Was his wife going the way of his
                    son? And he, sitting day after day like a dumb dog, instead of striving with
                    her!</p>
                <p>He made up his mind hurriedly. “Bessie,” he said, stooping to her and speaking in
                    a strange voice, “Bessie, had yer been to Dawson's?”</p>
                <p>Dawson was the landlord of the Spotted Deer.</p>
                <p>Bessie was long in answering. At last she said, almost inaudibly—</p>
                <p>“Yes.”</p>
                <p>She fully understood what he had meant by the question, and she wondered whether
                    he would fall into one of his rages, and beat her.</p>
                <p>Instead, his hand sought clumsily for hers.</p>
                <p>“Bessie, yer shouldn't; yer mustn't do it no more; it'll make a bad woman of yer.
                    I know as I'm not good to live with; I don't make things pleasant to yer; but
                    I've been thinkin'; I'll try if yo'll try.”</p>
                <p>Bessie burst into tears. It seemed as though her life were breaking within her.
                    Never since their<pb n="70" xml:id="VAB7023-070"/> early married days had he
                    spoken to her like this. And she was in such piteous need of comfort; of some
                    strong hand to help her out of the black pit in which she lay. The wild impulse
                    crossed her to sit up and tell him—to throw it all on Timothy, to show him the
                    cupboard and the box. Should she tell him; brave it all now that he was like
                    this? Between them they might find a way—make it good.</p>
                <p>Then the thought of the man in the public-house, of the half-crowns, a host of
                    confused and guilty memories, swept upon her. How could she ever get herself out
                    of it? Her heart beat so that it seemed a live creature strangling and silencing
                    her. She was still fighting with her tears and her terror when she heard Isaac
                    say—</p>
                <p>“I know yer'll try, and I'll help yer. I'll be a better husband to yer, I swear I
                    will. Give us a kiss, old woman.”</p>
                <p>She turned her face, sobbing, and he kissed her cheek.</p>
                <pb n="71" xml:id="VAB7023-071"/>
                <p>Then she heard him say in another tone—</p>
                <p>“An' I got a bit o' news down at the Club as will liven yer up. Parkinson was
                    there; just come over from Frampton to see his mother; an' he says John will be
                    here to-morrer or next day. 'Ee seed him yesterday—pulled down dreadful—quite
                    the old man, 'ee says. An' John told him as he was comin' 'ome directly to live
                    comfortable.”</p>
                <p>Bessie drew her shawl over her head.</p>
                <p>“To-morrer, did yer say?” she asked in a whisper.</p>
                <p>“Mos' like. Now you go to sleep; I'll put out the lamp.”</p>
                <p>But all night long Bessie lay wide awake in torment, her soul hardening within
                    her, little by little.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <pb n="72" xml:id="VAB7023-072"/>
                <head>SCENE IV</head>
                <p><hi rend="b">JUST</hi> before dark on the following day, a man descended from a
                    down train at the Clinton Magna station. The porters knew him and greeted him;
                    so did one or two labourers outside, as he set off to walk to the village, which
                    was about a mile distant.</p>
                <p>“Well, John, so yer coom back,” said one of them, an old man, grasping the
                    newcomer by the hand. “An' I can't say as yer looks is any credit to
                    Frampton—no, that aa can't.”</p>
                <p>John, indeed, wore a sallow and pinched air, and walked lamely, with a stick.</p>
                <p>“Noa,” he said peevishly; “it's a beastly place is Frampton; a damp, nassty hole
                    as iver I saw—gives yer the rheumaticks to look at it. I've 'ad<pb n="73" xml:id="VAB7023-073"/> a doose of a time, I 'ave, I can tell yer—iver sense
                    I went. But I'll pull up now.”</p>
                <p>“Aye, this air'll do yer,” said the other. “Where are yer stoppin'?
                    Costrells'?”</p>
                <p>John nodded.</p>
                <p>“They don't know nothin' about my cousin, but I dessay they'll find me somethin'
                    to sleep on. I'll 'ave my own place soon, and some one to look arter it.”</p>
                <p>He drew himself up involuntarily, with the dignity that waits on property. A
                    laugh, rather jeering than cordial, ran through the group of labourers.</p>
                <p>“Aye, yer'll be livin' at your ease,” said the man who had spoken first. “When
                    will yo' give us a drink, yer lardship?”</p>
                <p>The others grinned.</p>
                <p>“Where's your money, John?” said a younger man suddenly, staring hard at the
                    returned wanderer.</p>
                <p>John started.</p>
                <p>“Don't you talk your nonsense!” he said fretfully; “an' I must be getting on,
                    afore dark.”</p>
                <pb n="74" xml:id="VAB7023-074"/>
                <p>He went his way, but as he turned a corner of the road, he saw them still
                    standing where he had left them. They seemed to be watching his progress, which
                    astonished him.</p>
                <p>A light of windy sunset lay spread over the white valley, and the freshening
                    gusts drove the powdery snow before them, and sent little stabs of pain through
                    John's shrinking body. Yet how glad he was to find himself again between those
                    familiar hedges, to see the church-tower in front of him, the long hill to his
                    right! His heart swelled at once with longing and satisfaction. During his
                    Frampton job, and in the infirmary, he had suffered much, physically and
                    mentally. He had missed Eliza and the tendance of years more than he had ever
                    imagined he could; and he had found himself too old for new faces and a new
                    society. When he fell ill he had been sorely tempted to send for some of his
                    money, and get himself nursed and cared for at the respectable lodging where he
                    had put up. But no; in the end he set his teeth and went into<pb n="75" xml:id="VAB7023-075"/> the infirmary. He had planned not to touch his hoard
                    till he had done with the Frampton job, and returned to Clinton for good. His
                    peasant obstinacy could not endure to be beaten; nor, indeed, could he bring
                    himself to part with his keys, to trust the opening of the hoard even to
                    Isaac.</p>
                <p>Since then he had passed through many weary weeks, sometimes of acute pain,
                    sometimes of sinking weakness, during which he had been haunted by many secret
                    torments, springing mainly from the fear of death. He had almost been driven to
                    make his will. But in the end superstitious reluctance prevailed. He had not
                    made his will; and to dwell on the fact gave him the sensation of having escaped
                    a bond, if not a danger. He did not want to leave his money behind him; he
                    wanted to spend it, as he had told Eliza and Mary Anne and Bessie scores of
                    times. To have assigned it to any one else, even after his death, would have
                    made it less his own.</p>
                <p>Ah, well! those bad weeks were done, and here he was, at home again. Suddenly, as
                    he tramped<pb n="76" xml:id="VAB7023-076"/> on, he caught sight against the hill
                    of Bessie's cottage, the blue smoke from it blown across the rime-laden trees
                    behind it. He drew in his breath with a deep, tremulous delight. That buoyant
                    self-congratulation indeed which had stood between him and the pain of Eliza's
                    death was gone. Rather there was in him a profound yearning for rest, for long
                    dreaming by the fire or in the sun, with his pipe to smoke, and Jim's Louisa to
                    look after him, and nothing to do but to draw a half-crown from his box when he
                    wanted it. No more hard work in rain and cold; and no cringing, either, to the
                    young and prosperous for the mere fault of age. The snowy valley with its
                    circling woods opened to him like a mother's breast; the sight of it filled him
                    with a hundred simple hopes and consolations; he hurried to bury himself in it,
                    and be at peace.</p>
                <p>He was within a hundred yards of the first house in the village, when he saw a
                    tall figure in uniform approaching, and recognized Watson.</p>
                <pb n="77" xml:id="VAB7023-077"/>
                <p>At sight of him the policeman stopped short, and John was conscious of a moment's
                    vague impression of something strange in Watson's looks.</p>
                <p>However, Watson shook hands with great friendliness.</p>
                <p>“Well, I'm glad to see yer, John, I'm sure. An' now, I spose, you're back for
                    good?”</p>
                <p>“Aye. I'm not going away no more. I've done my share—I wants a bit o' rest.”</p>
                <p>“Of coorse yer do. You've been ill, 'aven't yer? You look like it. An' yer
                    puttin' up at Costrells'?”</p>
                <p>“Yes, till I can turn round a bit. 'Ave yer seen anythin' ov 'em? 'Ow's
                    Bessie?”</p>
                <p>Watson faced back towards the village.</p>
                <p>“I'll walk with yer a bit—I'm in no 'urry. Oh, she's all right. You 'eard of her
                    bit o' money?”</p>
                <p>John opened his eyes.</p>
                <p>“Noa, I don' know as I did.”</p>
                <p>“It wor an aunt o' hers, soa I understan'—quite a good bit o' money.”</p>
                <pb n="78" xml:id="VAB7023-078"/>
                <p>“Did yer iver hear the name?” said John, eagerly.</p>
                <p>“Some one livin' at Bedford, I did 'ear say.”</p>
                <p>John laughed, not without good-humoured relief. It would have touched his vanity
                    had his niece been discovered to be richer than himself.</p>
                <p>“Oh, that's old Sophy Clarke,” he said. “Her 'usband bought the lease o' two
                    little 'ouses in Church Street, and they brȧȧt 'er in six shillins a week for
                    years, an' she allus said she'd leave it to Bessie if she wor took afore the
                    lease wor up. But the lease ull be up end o' next year, I know, for I saw the
                    old lady myself last Michaelmas twelvemonth, an' she told me all about it,
                    though I worn't to tell nobody meself. An' I didn't know Sophy wor gone. Ah,
                    well! it's not much, but it's 'andy—it's 'andy.”</p>
                <p>“Six shillins a week!” said Watson, raising his eyebrows. “It's a nice bit o'
                    money while it lassts, but I'd ha' thought Mrs. Costrell 'ad come into a deal
                    more nor that.”</p>
                <pb n="79" xml:id="VAB7023-079"/>
                <p>“Oh, but she's sich a one to spend, is Bessie,” said John, anxiously. “It's
                    surprisin' 'ow the money runs. It's sixpence 'ere, an' sixpence there, allus
                    dribblin', an' dribblin', out ov 'er. I've allus tole 'er as she'll end 'er days
                    on the parish.”</p>
                <p>“Sixpences!” said Watson, with a laugh. “It's not sixpences as Mrs. Costrell's
                    'ad the spendin' of this last month or two—it's <emph>suverins</emph>—an' plenty
                    ov 'em. You may be sure you've got the wrong tale about the money, John; it wor
                    a deal more nor you say.”</p>
                <p>John stood stock still at the word “sovereigns,” his jaw dropping.</p>
                <p>“<emph>Suverins</emph>,” he said trembling; “suverins? Bessie ain't got no
                    suverins. Isaac arns sixteen shillin a week.”</p>
                <p>The colour was ebbing fast from his cheek and lips. Watson threw him a quick
                    professional glance, then rapidly consulted with himself. No; he decided to hold
                    his tongue.</p>
                <p>“Yo' <emph>are</emph> reg'lar used up,” he said, taking hold<pb n="80" xml:id="VAB7023-080"/> of the old fellow kindly by the arm. “Shall I walk
                    yer up the hill?”</p>
                <p>John withdrew himself.</p>
                <p>“<emph>Suverins!</emph>” he repeated, in a low hoarse voice. “She ain't got 'em,
                    I tell yer—she ain't got 'em!”</p>
                <p>The last words rose to a sort of cry, and without another word to Watson the old
                    man started at a feeble run, his head hanging.</p>
                <p>Watson followed him, afraid lest he should drop in the road. Instead, John seemed
                    to gather strength. He made straight for the hill, taking no heed whatever of
                    two or three startled acquaintances who stopped and shouted to him. When the
                    ground began to rise, he stumbled again and again, but by a marvel did not fall,
                    and his pace hardly slackened. Watson had difficulty in keeping up with him.</p>
                <p>But when the policeman reached his own cottage on the side of the road, he
                    stopped, panting, and contented himself with looking after the mounting figure.
                    As soon as it turned the corner of the<pb n="81" xml:id="VAB7023-081"/>
                    Costrells' lane, he went into his own house, said a word to his wife, and sat
                    himself down at his own back door to await events—to ponder, also, a few
                    conversations he had held that morning, with Mrs. Moulsey at “the shop,” with
                    Dawson, with Hall the butcher. Poor old John—poor old fellow!</p>
                <p>When Bolderfield reached the paling in front of the Costrells' cottage, he paused
                    a moment, holding for support to the half-open gate and struggling for breath.
                    “I must keep my 'edd, I must,” he was saying to himself piteously; “don' yer be
                    a fool, John Borroful, don' yer be a fool!”</p>
                <p>As he stood there, a child's face pushed the window-blind of the cottage aside,
                    and the lame boy's large eyes looked Bolderfield up and down. Immediately after,
                    the door opened, and all four children stood huddling behind each other on the
                    threshold. They all looked shyly at the newcomer. They knew him, but in six
                    months they had grown strange to him.</p>
                <pb n="82" xml:id="VAB7023-082"/>
                <p>“Arthur, where's your mother?” said John, at last able to walk firmly up to the
                    door.</p>
                <p>“Don' know.”</p>
                <p>“When did yer see her lasst?”</p>
                <p>“She wor 'ere gettin' us our tea,” said another child; “but she didn't eat
                    nothin'.”</p>
                <p>John impatiently pushed the children before him back into the kitchen.</p>
                <p>“You 'old your tongues,” he said, “an' stay 'ere.”</p>
                <p>And he made for the door in the kitchen wall. But Arthur caught hold of his coat
                    tails and clung to them.</p>
                <p>“Yer oughtn't to go up there—mother don't let any one go there.”</p>
                <p>John wrenched himself violently away.</p>
                <p>“Oh, don't she! yo' take your 'ands away, yer little varmint, or I'll brain
                    yer.”</p>
                <p>He raised his stick, threatening. The child, terrified, fell back, and John,
                    opening the door, rushed up the stairs.</p>
                <p>He was so terribly excited that his fumbling<pb n="83" xml:id="VAB7023-083"/>
                    fingers could hardly find the ribbon round his neck. At last he drew it over his
                    head, and made stupendous efforts to steady his hand sufficiently to put the key
                    in the lock.</p>
                <p>The children below heard a sharp cry directly the cupboard door was opened; then
                    the frantic dragging of a box on to the stairs, the creak of hinges—a groan long
                    and lingering—and then silence.</p>
                <p>They clung together in terror, and the little girls began to cry. At last Arthur
                    took courage and opened the door.</p>
                <p>The old man was sitting on the top stair, supported sideways by the wall, his
                    head hanging forward, and his hands dropping over his knees, in a dead
                    faint.</p>
                <p>At the sight all four children ran helter-skelter into the lane, shouting “Mammy!
                    mammy!” in an anguish of fright. Their clamour was caught by the fierce north
                    wind, which had begun to sweep the hill, and was borne along till it reached<pb n="84" xml:id="VAB7023-084"/> the ears of a woman who was sitting sewing in
                    a cottage some fifty yards further up the lane. She stepped to her door, opened
                    it and listened.</p>
                <p>“It's at Bessie's,” she said; “whativer's wrong wi' the childer?”</p>
                <p>By this time Arthur had begun to run towards her. Darkness was falling rapidly,
                    but she could distinguish his small figure against the snow, and his halting
                    gait.</p>
                <p>“What is it, Arthur?—what is it, lammie?”</p>
                <p>“O Cousin Mary Anne! Cousin Mary Anne! It's Uncle John, an' 'ee's dead!”</p>
                <p>She ran like the wind at the words, catching at the child's hand in the dark, and
                    dragging him along with her.</p>
                <p>“Where is he, Arthur?—don't take on, honey!”</p>
                <p>The child hurried on with her, sobbing, and she was soon on the stairs beside the
                    unconscious John.</p>
                <p>Mary Anne looked with amazement at the cupboard and the open box. Then she laid
                    the old<pb n="85" xml:id="VAB7023-085"/> man on the floor, her gentle face
                    working with the effort to remember what the doctor had once told her of the
                    best way of dealing with persons in a faint. She got water, and she sent Arthur
                    to a neighbour for brandy.</p>
                <p>“Where's your mother, child?” she asked, as she despatched him.</p>
                <p>“Don' know,” repeated the boy, stupidly.</p>
                <p>“Oh, for goodness' sake, she's never at Dawson's again!” groaned Mary Anne to
                    herself; “she wor there last night, an' the night afore that. And her mother's
                    brother lyin' like this in 'er house!”</p>
                <p>He was so long in coming round that her ignorance began to fear the worst. But
                    just as she was telling the eldest girl to put on her hat and jacket and run for
                    the doctor, poor John revived.</p>
                <p>He struggled to a sitting posture, looked wildly at her and at the box. As his
                    eye caught the two sovereigns still lying at the bottom, he gave a cry of rage,
                    and got upon his feet with a mighty effort.</p>
                <pb n="86" xml:id="VAB7023-086"/>
                <p>“Where's Bessie, I tell yer? Where's the huzzy gone? I'll have the law on 'er!
                    I'll make 'er give it up—by the Lord I will!”</p>
                <p>“John, what is it?—John, my dear!” cried Mary Anne, supporting him, and terrified
                    lest he should pitch headlong down the stairs.</p>
                <p>“Yo' 'elp me down,” he said violently. “We'll find 'er—we'll wring it out ov
                    'er—the mean, thievin' vagabond! Changin' suverins, 'as she? we'll soon know
                    about that—yo' 'elp me down, I tell yer.”</p>
                <p>And with her assistance he hobbled down the stairs, hardly able to stand. Mary
                    Anne's eyes were starting out of her head with fear and agitation, and the
                    children were staring at the old man as he came tottering into the kitchen, when
                    a sound at the outer door made them all turn.</p>
                <p>The door opened, and Bessie appeared on the threshold.</p>
                <p>At sight of her John seemed to lose his senses. He rushed at her, threatening,
                    imploring, reviling—<pb n="87" xml:id="VAB7023-087"/> while Mary Ann could only
                    cling to his arms and coat, lest he should attempt some bodily mischief.</p>
                <p>Bessie closed the door, leant against it, and folded her arms. She was white and
                    haggard, but perfectly cool. In this moment of excitement it struck neither John
                    nor Mary Anne—nor, indeed, herself—that her manner, with its brutality, and its
                    poorly feigned surprise, was the most revealing element in the situation.</p>
                <p>“What's all this about yer money?” she said, staring John in the face. “What do I
                    know about yer money? 'Ow dare yer say such things? I 'aven't anythin' to do
                    with it, an' never 'ad.”</p>
                <p>He raved at her, in reply, about the position in which he had found the box—on
                    the top of its fellow instead of underneath, where he had placed it—about the
                    broken lock, the sovereigns she had been changing, and the things Watson had
                    said of her—winding up with a peremptory demand for his money.</p>
                <p>“Yo' gi' me my money back,” he said, holding<pb n="88" xml:id="VAB7023-088"/> out
                    a shaking hand. “Yer can't 'ave spent it all—'tain't possible—an' yer ain't
                    chucked it out o' winder. Yer've got it somewhere 'idden, an' I'll get it out o'
                    you if I die for 't!”</p>
                <p>Bessie surveyed him steadily. She had not even flinched at the mention of the
                    sovereigns.</p>
                <p>“What yer 'aven't got, yer can't give,” she said. “I don' know nothin' about it,
                    an' I've tole yer. There's plenty o' bad people in the world—beside me. Somebody
                    came in o' nights, I suppose, an' picked the lock—there's many as ud think
                    nothin' of it. And it ud be easy done—we all sleeps 'ard.”</p>
                <p>“Bessie!” cried Mary Anne, outraged by something in her tone, “aren't yer sorry
                    for 'im?”</p>
                <p>She pointed to the haggard and trembling man.</p>
                <p>Bessie turned to her reluctantly. “Aye, I'm sorry,” she said sullenly. “But he
                    shouldn't fly out at yer without 'earin' a word. 'Ow should I know anythin'
                    about his money? 'Ee locked it up hisself, an' tuk the keys.”</p>
                <p>“An' them suverins,” roared John, rattling his<pb n="89" xml:id="VAB7023-089"/>
                    stick on the floor; “where did yer get them suverins?”</p>
                <p>“I got 'em from old Sophy Clarke—leastways, from Sophy Clarke's lawyer. And it
                    ain't no business o' yourn.<choice>
                        <sic>’</sic>
                        <corr>”</corr>
                    </choice></p>
                <p>At this John fell into a frenzy, shouting at her in inarticulate passion, calling
                    her liar and thief.</p>
                <p>She fronted it with perfect composure. Her fine eyes blazed, but otherwise her
                    face might have been a waxen mask. With her, in this scene, was all the tragic
                    dignity; with him, the weakness and vulgarity.</p>
                <p>At last the little widow caught her by the arm, and drew her from the door.</p>
                <p>“Let me take 'im to my place,” she pleaded: “it's no good talkin' while 'ee's
                    like 'ee is—not a bit o' good. John—John dear! you come along wi' me. Shall I
                    get Saunders to come an' speak to yer?”</p>
                <p>A gleam of sudden hope shot into the old man's face. He had not thought of
                    Saunders; but<pb n="90" xml:id="VAB7023-090"/> Saunders had a head; he might
                    unravel this accursed thing.</p>
                <p>“Aye!” he said, lurching forward, “let's find Saunders—coom along—let's find
                    Saunders.”</p>
                <p>Mary Anne guided him through the door, Bessie standing aside. As the widow
                    passed, she touched Bessie piteously.</p>
                <p>“Oh, Bessie, yer <emph>didn't</emph> do it—say yer didn't!”</p>
                <p>Bessie looked at her dry-eyed and contemptuous. Something in the speaker's
                    emotion seemed to madden her.</p>
                <p>“Don't yer be a fool, Mary Anne—that's all!” she said scornfully, and Mary Anne
                    fled from her.</p>
                <p>When the door had closed upon them, Bessie came up to the fire, her teeth
                    chattering. She sank down in front of it, spreading out her hands. The children
                    silently crowded up to her; first she pushed them away, then she caught at the
                    child nearest to her, pressed its fair head against her, then again roughly put
                    it aside. She was accustomed to chatter<pb n="91" xml:id="VAB7023-091"/> with
                    them, scold them and slap them; but to-night they were uneasily dumb. They
                    looked at her with round eyes; and at last their looks annoyed her. She told
                    them to go to bed, and they slunk away, gaping at the open box on the stairs,
                    and huddling together overhead, all on one bed, in the bitter cold, to whisper
                    to each other. Isaac was a stern parent; Bessie a capricious one; and the
                    children, though they could be riotous enough by themselves, were nervous and
                    easily cowed at home.</p>
                <p>Bessie, left alone, sat silently over the fire, her thin lips tight-set. She
                    would deny everything—<emph>everything</emph>. Let them find out what they
                    could. Who could prove what was in John's box when he left it? Who could prove
                    she hadn't got those half-crowns in change somewhere?</p>
                <p>The reflection of the day had only filled her with a passionate and fierce
                    regret. <emph>Why</emph> had she not followed her first impulse, and thrown it
                    all on Timothy?—told the story to Isaac, while she was still bleeding from his
                    son's violence? It had been<pb n="92" xml:id="VAB7023-092"/> her only chance,
                    and out of pure stupidness she had lost it. To have grasped it might at least
                    have made him take <emph>her</emph> part, if it had forced him to give up
                    Timothy. And who would have listened to Timothy's tales?</p>
                <p>She sickened at the thought of her own folly, beating her knee with her clenched
                    fist. For to tell the tale now would only be to make her doubly vile in Isaac's
                    eyes. He would not believe her—no one would believe her. What motive could she
                    plead for her twenty-four hours of silence, she knowing that John was coming
                    back immediately? Isaac would only hate her for throwing it on Timothy.</p>
                <p>Then again the memory of the half-crowns, and the village talk—and Watson—would
                    close upon her, putting her in a cold sweat.</p>
                <p>When would Isaac come? Who would tell him? As she looked forward to the effect
                    upon him, all her muscles stiffened. If he drove her to it, aye, she
                        <emph>would</emph> tell him—she didn't care a haporth, she vowed. If he must
                    have it, let him. But as the<pb n="93" xml:id="VAB7023-093"/> name of Isaac, the
                    thought of Isaac, hovered in her brain, she must needs brush away wild tears.
                    That morning, for the first time for months, he had been so kind to her and the
                    children, so chatty and cheerful.</p>
                <p>Distant steps along the lane! She sprang to her feet, ran into the back kitchen,
                    tied on her apron, hastily filled an earthenware bowl with water from the pump,
                    and carrying it back to the front kitchen, began to wash up the tea-things,
                    making a busy household clatter as she slid them into the bowl.</p>
                <p>A confused sound of feet approached the house, and there was a knock.</p>
                <p>“Come in,” said Bessie.</p>
                <p>Three figures appeared, the huge form of Saunders the smith in front, John and
                    Mary Anne Waller behind.</p>
                <p>Saunders took off his cap politely. The sight of his bald head, his double chin,
                    his mouth with its queer twitch, which made him seem as though perpetually about
                    to laugh, if he had not perpetually<pb n="94" xml:id="VAB7023-094"/> thought
                    better of it, filled Bessie with angry excitement. She barely nodded to him, in
                    reply to his greeting.</p>
                <p>“May we come in, Mrs. Costrell?” Saunders inquired, in his most deliberate
                    voice.</p>
                <p>“If yer want to,” said Bessie, shortly, taking out a cup and drying it.</p>
                <p>Saunders drew in the other two and shut the door.</p>
                <p>“Sit down, John. Sit down, Mrs. Waller.”</p>
                <p>John did as he was told. Dishevelled and hopeless misery spoke in his stained
                    face, his straggling hair, his shirt burst open at the neck and showing his
                    wrinkled throat. But he fixed his eyes passionately on Saunders, thirsting for
                    every word.</p>
                <p>“Well, Mrs. Costrell,” said Saunders, settling himself comfortably, “you'll be
                    free to confess, won't yer, this is an oogly business—a very oogly business?
                    Now, will yer let us ask yer a question or two?”</p>
                <p>“I dessay,” said Bessie, polishing her cup.</p>
                <p>“Well, then—to begin reg'lar, Mrs. Costrell—yo'<pb n="95" xml:id="VAB7023-095"/>
                    agree, don't yer, as Muster Bolderfield put his money in your upstairs
                    cupboard?”</p>
                <p>“I agree as he put his box there,” said Bessie, sharply.</p>
                <p>John broke into inarticulate and abusive clamour. Bessie turned upon him.</p>
                <p>“'Ow did any of us know what yer'd got in your box? Did yer ever show it to me,
                    or Mary Anne there, or any livin soul in Clinton? Did yer?”</p>
                <p>She waited, hawk-like, for the answer.</p>
                <p>“Did yer, John?” repeated Saunders, judicially.</p>
                <p>John groaned, rocking himself to and fro.</p>
                <p>“Noa. I niver did—I niver did,” he said. “Nobbut to Eliza—an' she's gone—she's
                    gone!”</p>
                <p>“Keep your 'ead, John,” said Saunders, putting out a calming hand. “Let's get to
                    the bottom o' this, quiet an' <emph>reg'lar</emph>. An' yer didn't tell any one
                    'ow much yer 'ad?”</p>
                <p>“Nobbut Eliza—nobbut Eliza!” said the old man again.</p>
                <p>“Yer didn't tell <emph>me</emph>, I know,” said Saunders, blandly.</p>
                <pb n="96" xml:id="VAB7023-096"/>
                <p>John seemed to shrink together under the smith's glance. If only he had not been
                    a jealous fool, and had left it with Saunders!</p>
                <p>Saunders, however, refrained for the present from drawing this self-evident
                    moral. He sat twirling his cap between his knees, and his shrewd eye travelled
                    round the kitchen, coming back finally to Bessie, who was washing and drying
                    diligently. As he watched her cool movements Saunders felt the presence of an
                    enemy worthy of his steel, and his emulation rose.</p>
                <p>“I understan', Mrs. Costrell,” he said, speaking with great civility, “as the
                    cupboard where John put his money is a cupboard <emph>hon</emph> the stairs? Not
                    in hany room, but <emph>hon</emph> the stairs? Yer'll kindly correck me if I say
                    anythin' wrong.”</p>
                <p>Bessie nodded.</p>
                <p>“Aye—top o' the stairs—right-'and side,” groaned John.</p>
                <p>“An' John locked it hisself, an' tuk the key?” Saunders proceeded.</p>
                <pb n="97" xml:id="VAB7023-097"/>
                <p>John plucked at his neck again, and, dumbly, held out the key.</p>
                <p>“An' there worn't nothin' wrong wi' the lock when yo' opened it, John?”</p>
                <p>“Nothin', Muster Saunders—I'll take my davy.”</p>
                <p>Saunders ruminated.</p>
                <p>“Theer's a cupboard there,” he said suddenly, raising his hand and pointing to
                    the cupboard beside the fireplace. “Is't anythin' like the cupboard on th'
                    stairs, John?”</p>
                <p>“Aye, 'tis!” said John, startled and staring. “Aye, 'tis, Muster Saunders!”</p>
                <p>Saunders rose.</p>
                <p>“Per'aps,” he said slowly, “Mrs. Costrell will do us the favour ov lettin' us
                    hexamine that 'ere cupboard?”</p>
                <p>He walked across to it. Bessie's hand dropped; she turned sharply, supporting
                    herself against the table, and watched him, her chest heaving.</p>
                <p>“There's no key 'ere,” said Saunders, stooping to look at the lock. <choice>
                        <sic/>
                        <corr>“</corr>
                    </choice>Try yours, John.”</p>
                <pb n="98" xml:id="VAB7023-098"/>
                <p>John rushed forward, but Bessie put herself in the way.</p>
                <p>“What are yer meddlin' with my 'ouse for?” she said fiercely. “Just mek
                    yourselves scarce, all the lot o' yer. I don't know nothin' about his money, an'
                    I'll not have yer <emph>insultin'</emph> me in me own place! Get out o' my
                    kitchen, if <emph>yo'</emph> please!”</p>
                <p>Saunders buttoned his coat.</p>
                <p>“Sartinly, Mrs. Costrell, sartinly,” he said with emphasis. “Come along, John.
                    Yer must get Watson and put it in 'is hands. 'Ee's the law, is Watson. Maybe as
                    Mrs. Costrell 'ull listen to <emph>'im</emph>.”</p>
                <p>Mary Anne ran to Bessie in despair.</p>
                <p>“Oh, Bessie, Bessie, my dear—don't let 'em get Watson; let 'em look into 't
                    theirselves—it'll be better for yer, my dear, it <emph>will</emph>.”</p>
                <p>Bessie looked from one to the other, panting. Then she turned back to the
                    table.</p>
                <p>“<emph>I</emph> don' care what they do,” she said, with sullen passion. “I'm not
                    stannin' in any one's way, I tell yer. The more they finds out the better I'm
                    pleased.”</p>
                <pb n="99" xml:id="VAB7023-099"/>
                <p>The look of incipient laughter on Saunders's countenance became more
                    pronounced—that is to say, the left-hand corner of his mouth twitched a little
                    higher. But it was rare for him to complete the act, and he was not in the least
                    minded to do so now. He beckoned to John, and John, trembling, took off his keys
                    and gave them to him, pointing to that which belonged to the treasure
                    cupboard.</p>
                <p>Saunders slipped it into the lock before him. It moved with ease, backwards and
                    forwards.</p>
                <p>“H'm! that's strange,” he said, taking out the key and turning it over
                    thoughtfully in his hand. “Yer didn't think as there were <emph>another</emph>
                    key in this 'ouse that would open your cupboard, did yer, Bolderfield?”</p>
                <p>The old man sank weeping on a chair. He was too broken, too exhausted, to revile
                    Bessie any more.</p>
                <p>“Yo' tell her, Muster Saunders,” he said, “to gie it me back! I'll not ast for
                    all on it, but some on it, Muster Saunders—some on it. She <emph>can't</emph>
                        'a<pb n="100" xml:id="VAB7023-100"/> spent it. She must 'a got it somewhere.
                    Yo' speak to her, Muster Saunders. It's a crule thing to rob an old man like
                    me—an' her own mother's brother. Yo' speak to 'er—an' yo', too, Mary Anne.”</p>
                <p>He looked piteously from one to the other. But his misery only seemed to goad
                    Bessie to fresh fury. She turned upon him, arms akimbo.</p>
                <p>“Oh! an' of course it must be <emph>me</emph> as robs yer! It couldn't be nobody
                    else, could it? There isn't tramps, an' thieves, an' rogues—'undreds of
                    'em—going about o' nights? Nary one, I believe yer! There isn't another thief in
                    Clinton Magna, nobbut Bessie Costrell, is ther? But yer'll not blackguard me for
                    nothin', I can tell yer. Now will yer jest oblige me by takin' yourselves off? I
                    shall 'ave to clean up after yer”—she pointed scornfully to the marks of their
                    muddy boots on the floor—“an' it's gettin' late.”</p>
                <p>“One moment, Mrs. Costrell,” said Saunders, gently rubbing his hands. “With your
                    leave, John and I 'ull just inspeck the cupboard <emph>hup</emph>stairs
                        before<pb n="101" xml:id="VAB7023-101"/> leavin'—an' then we'll clear out
                    double quick. But we'll 'ave one try if we can't 'it on somethin' as 'ull show
                    'ow the thief got in—with your leave, of <emph>coorse</emph>.”</p>
                <p>Bessie hesitated; then she threw some spoons she held into the water beside her
                    with a violent gesture.</p>
                <p>“Go where yer wants,” she said, and returned to her washing.</p>
                <p>Saunders began to climb the narrow stairs, with John behind him. But the smith's
                    small eyes had a puzzled look.</p>
                <p>“There's <emph>somethin'</emph> rum,” he said to himself. “'Ow <emph>did</emph>
                    she spend it all? 'As she been carryin' on with some one be'ind Isaac's back, or
                    is Isaac in it too? It's one or t'other.”</p>
                <p>Meanwhile Bessie, left behind, was consumed by a passionate effort of memory.
                        <emph>What</emph> had she done with the key, the night before, after she had
                    locked the cupboard? Her brain was blurred. The blow—the fall—seemed to have
                    confused even the<pb n="102" xml:id="VAB7023-102"/> remembrance of the scene
                    with Timothy. How was it, for instance, that she had put the box back in the
                    wrong place? She put her hand to her head trying in an anguish to recollect the
                    exact details.</p>
                <p>The little widow sat meanwhile a few yards away, her thin hands clasped on her
                    lap in her usual attitude of humble entreaty; her soft grey eyes, brimmed with
                    tears, were fixed on Bessie. Bessie did not know that she was there—that she
                    existed.</p>
                <p>The door had closed after the two men. Bessie could hear vague movements, but
                    nothing more. Presently she could bear it no longer. She went to the door and
                    opened it.</p>
                <p>She was just in time. By the light of the bit of candle that John held, she saw
                    Saunders sitting on the stair, the shadow of his huge frame thrown black on the
                    white wall; she saw him stoop suddenly, as a bird pounces; she heard an
                    exclamation—then a sound of metal.</p>
                <p>Her involuntary cry startled the men above.</p>
                <pb n="103" xml:id="VAB7023-103"/>
                <p>“All right, Mrs. Costrell,” said Saunders, briskly—“all right. We'll be down
                    directly.”</p>
                <p>She came back into the kitchen, a mist before her eyes, and fell heavily on a
                    chair by the fire. Mary Anne approached her, only to be pushed back. The widow
                    stood listening, in an agony.</p>
                <p>It took Saunders a minute or two to complete his case. Then he slowly descended
                    the stairs, carrying the box, his great weight making the house shake. He
                    entered the kitchen first, John behind him. But at the same moment that they
                    appeared the outer door opened, and Isaac Costrell, preceded by a gust of snow,
                    stood on the threshold.</p>
                <p>“Why, John!” he cried, in amazement—“an' <emph>Saunders!</emph>”</p>
                <p>He looked at them, then at Mary Anne, then at his wife.</p>
                <p>There was an instant's dead silence. Then the tottering John came forward.</p>
                <p>“An' I'm glad yer come, Isaac, that I am—thankful! Now yer can tell me what yer
                        wife's<pb n="104" xml:id="VAB7023-104"/> done with my money. D'yer mind that
                    box? It wor you an' I carried it across that night as Watson come out on us. An'
                    yo'll bear me witness as we locked it up, an' yo' saw me tie the two keys roun'
                    my neck—yo' <emph>did</emph>, Isaac. An' now, Isaac”—the hoarse voice began to
                    tremble—“now there's two—suverins—left, and one 'arf-crown—out o' seventy-one
                    pound fower an' sixpence—seventy-one pound, Isaac! Yo'll get it out on 'er,
                    Isaac, yer will, won't yer?”</p>
                <p>He looked up imploring.</p>
                <p>Isaac, after the first violent start, stood absolutely motionless, Saunders
                    observing him. As one of the main props of Church Establishment in the village,
                    Saunders had no great opinion of Isaac Costrell, who stood for the dissidence of
                    dissent. The two men had never been friends, and Saunders in this affair had
                    perhaps exercised the quasi-judicial functions the village had long by common
                    consent allowed him, with more readiness than usual.</p>
                <p>As soon as John ceased speaking, Isaac walked up to Saunders.</p>
                <pb n="105" xml:id="VAB7023-105"/>
                <p>“Let me see that box,” he said peremptorily. “Put it down.”</p>
                <p>Saunders, who had rested the box on the back of a chair, placed it gently on the
                    table, assisted by Isaac. A few feet away stood Bessie, saying nothing, her hand
                    holding the duster on her hip, her eyes following her husband.</p>
                <p>He looked carefully at the two sovereigns lying on the bit of old cloth which
                    covered the bottom of the box, and the one half-crown that Timothy had
                    forgotten; he took up the bit of cloth and shook it, he felt along the edge of
                    the box, he examined the wrenched lock.</p>
                <p>Then he stood for an instant, his hand on the box, his eyes staring straight
                    before him in a kind of dream.</p>
                <p>Saunders grew impatient. He pushed John aside, and came to the table, leaning his
                    hands upon it, so as to command Isaac's face.</p>
                <p>“Now look 'ere, Isaac,” he said, in a different voice from any that he had yet
                    employed, “let's come to business. These 'ere are the facks o' this<pb n="106" xml:id="VAB7023-106"/> case, and 'ow we're agoin' to get over 'em, I don'
                    see. John leaves his money in your cupboard. Yo' an' he lock it up, an' John
                    goes away with 'is keys 'ung roun' 'is neck. Yo' agree to that? Well an' good.
                    But there's <emph>another</emph> key in your 'ouse, Isaac, as opens John's
                    cupboard. Ah—”</p>
                <p>He waved his hand in deprecation of Isaac's movement.</p>
                <p>“I dessay yo' didn't know nowt about it—that's noather 'ere nor there. Yo' try
                    John's key in that there door”—he pointed to the cupboard by the fire—“an' yo'll
                    find it fits <emph>ex</emph>—act. Then, thinks I, where's the key as belongs to
                    that 'ere cupboard? An' John an' I goes upstairs to look about us, an' in noa
                    time at aw, I sees a 'ole in the skirtin'. I whips in my finger—lor bless yer! I
                    knew it wor there the moment I sets eyes on the hole.”</p>
                <p>He held up the key triumphantly. By this time, no Old Bailey lawyer making a
                    hanging speech could have had more command of his task.</p>
                <p>“'Ere then we 'ave”—he checked the items off on<pb n="107" xml:id="VAB7023-107"/>
                    his fingers—“box locked up—key in the 'ouse as fits it, unbeknown to John—money
                    tuk out—key 'idden away. But that's not all—not by long chalks—there's another
                    side to the affair <emph>hal</emph>together.”</p>
                <p>Saunders drew himself up, thrust his hands deep into his pockets, and cleared his
                    throat.</p>
                <p>“Per'aps yer don' know—I'm sartin sure yer don' know—leastways I'm hinclined that
                    way,—as Mrs. Costrell”—he made a polite inclination towards Bessie—“'ave been
                    makin' free with money—fower—five—night a week at the Spotted
                    Deer—fower—five—night a week. She'd used to treat every young feller, an' plenty
                    old uns too, as turned up; an' there was a many as only went to Dawson's becos
                    they knew as she'd treat 'em. Now, she didn't go on tick at Dawson's; she'd
                        <emph>pay</emph>,—an' she allus payed in 'arf-crowns. An' those 'arf-crowns
                    were curious 'alf-crowns; an' it came into Dawson's 'ead as he'd colleck them
                    'arf-crowns. 'Ee wanted to see summat, 'ee said—an' I dessay 'ee did. An' people
                    began to taak. Last night theer wor a bit of a<pb n="108" xml:id="VAB7023-108"/>
                    roompus, it seems, while Mrs. Costrell was a-payin' another o' them things, an'
                    summat as was said come to my ears—an' come to Watson's. An' me an' Watson 'ave
                    been makin' inquiries—an' Mr. Dawson wor obligin' enough to make me a small
                    loan, 'ee wor. Now, I've got just one question to ask o' John Borroful.”</p>
                <p>He put his hand into his waistcoat pocket, and drew out a silver coin.</p>
                <p>“Is that yourn, John?”</p>
                <p>John fell upon it with a cry.</p>
                <p>“Aye, Saunders, it's mine. Look ye 'ere, Isaac, it's a king's 'ead. It's
                    Willum—not Victory. I saved that un up when I wor a lad at Mason's, an' look
                    yer, there's my mark in the corner—every 'arf-crown I ever 'ad I marked like
                    that.”</p>
                <p>He held it under Isaac's staring eyes, pointing to the little scratched cross in
                    the corner.</p>
                <p>“'Ere's another, John—two on, 'em,” said Saunders, pulling out a second and a
                    third.</p>
                <p>John, in a passion of hope, identified them both.</p>
                <p>“Then,” said Saunders, slapping the table solemnly,<pb n="109" xml:id="VAB7023-109"/> “theer's nobbut one more thing to say—an' sorry I am
                    to say it. Them coins, Isaac”—he pointed a slow finger at Bessie, whose white,
                    fierce face moved involuntarily—“them 'arf-crowns wor paid across the bar lasst
                    night, or the night afore, at Dawson's, by <emph>yor wife</emph>, as is now
                    stannin' there, an' she'll deny it if she can!”</p>
                <p>For an instant the whole group preserved their positions—the breath suspended on
                    their lips.</p>
                <p>Then Isaac strode up to his wife, and gripped her by the arms.</p>
                <p>“Did yer do it?” he asked her.</p>
                <p>He held her, looking into her eyes. Slowly she sank away from him; she would have
                    fallen, but for a chair that stood beside her.</p>
                <p>“Oh, yer brute!” she said, turning her head to Saunders an instant, and speaking
                    under her breath, with a kind of sob. “Yer <emph>brute!</emph>”</p>
                <p>Isaac walked to the door, and threw it open.</p>
                <p>“Per'aps yer'll go,” he said grimly.</p>
                <p>And the three went, without a word.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <pb n="110" xml:id="VAB7023-110"/>
                <head>SCENE V</head>
                <p><hi rend="b">SO</hi> the husband and wife were left together in the cottage room.
                    The door had no sooner closed on Saunders and his companions than Isaac was
                    seized with that strange sense of walking amid things unreal upon a wavering
                    earth which is apt to beset the man who has any portion of the dreamer's
                    temperament, under any sudden rush of circumstance. He drew his hand across his
                    brow, bewildered. The fire leapt and chattered in the grate; the newly-washed
                    tea-things on the table shone under the lamp; the cat lay curled, as usual, on
                    the chair where he sat after supper to read his <title>Christian World</title>;
                    yet all things were not the same. What had changed?</p>
                <p>Then across poor John's rifled box he saw his wife sitting rigid on the chair
                    where he had left her.</p>
                <pb n="111" xml:id="VAB7023-111"/>
                <p>He came and sat down at the corner of the table, close to her, his chin on his
                    hand.</p>
                <p>“'Ow did yer spend it?” he said, startled, as the words came out, by his own
                    voice, so grinding and ugly was the note of it.</p>
                <p>Her miserable eyes travelled over his face, seeking, as it were, for some
                    promise, however faint, of future help and succour, however distant.</p>
                <p>Apparently she saw none, for her own look flamed to fresh defiance.</p>
                <p>“I didn't spend it. Saunders wor lyin'.”</p>
                <p>“'Ow did yer get them half-crowns?”</p>
                <p>“I got 'em at Bedford. Mr. Grimstone give 'em me.”</p>
                <p>Isaac looked at her hard, his shame burning into his heart. This was how she had
                    got her money for the gin. Of course, she had lied to him the night before, in
                    her account of her fall, and of that mark on her forehead, which still showed, a
                    red disfigurement, under the hair she had drawn across it. The sight of it, of
                    her, began to excite in him a quick<pb n="112" xml:id="VAB7023-112"/> loathing.
                    He was at bottom a man of violent passions, and in the presence of evil-doing so
                    flagrant, so cruel—of a household ruin so complete—his religion failed him.</p>
                <p>“When was it as yer opened that box fust?” he asked her again, scorning her
                    denials.</p>
                <p>She burst into a rage of tears, lifting her apron to her eyes, and flinging names
                    at him that he scarcely heard.</p>
                <p>There was a little cold tea in a cup close to him that Bessie had forgotten. He
                    stretched out his hand, and took a mouthful, moistening his dry lips and
                    throat.</p>
                <p>“Yer'll go to prison for this,” he said, jerking it out as he put the cup
                    down.</p>
                <p>He saw her shiver. Her nerve was failing her. The convulsive sobs continued, but
                    she ceased to abuse him. He wondered when he should be able to get it out of
                    her. He himself could no more have wept than iron and fire weep.</p>
                <p>“Are yer goin' to tell me when yer took that<pb n="113" xml:id="VAB7023-113"/>
                    money, and 'ow yer spent it? 'Cos, if yer don't, I shall go to Watson.”</p>
                <p>Even in her abasement it struck her as shameful, unnatural, that he, her husband,
                    should say this. Her remorse returned upon her heart, like a tide driven back.
                    She answered him not a word.</p>
                <p>He put his silver watch on the table.</p>
                <p>“I'll give yer two minutes,” he said.</p>
                <p>There was silence in the cottage except for the choking, hysterical sounds she
                    could not master. Then he took up his hat again, and went out into the snow,
                    which was by now falling fast.</p>
                <p>She remained helpless and sobbing, unconscious of the passage of time, one hand
                    playing incessantly with a child's comforter that lay beside her on the table,
                    the other wiping away the crowding tears. But her mind worked feverishly all the
                    time, and gradually she fought herself free of this weeping, which clutched her
                    against her will.</p>
                <p>Isaac was away for an hour. When he came back, he closed the door carefully, and,
                    walking to the<pb n="114" xml:id="VAB7023-114"/> table, threw down his hat upon
                    it. His face under its ruddy brown had suffered some radical disintegrating
                    change.</p>
                <p>“They've traced yer,” he said hoarsely; “they've got it up to twenty-six pound,
                    an' more. Most on it 'ere in Clinton—some on it, Muster Miles o' Frampton 'ull
                    swear to. Watson 'ull go over to Frampton, for the warrant—to-morrer.”</p>
                <p>The news shook her from head to foot. She stared at him wildly—speechless.</p>
                <p>“But that's not 'arf,” he went on—“not near 'arf. Do yer 'ear? What did yer do
                    with the rest? I'll not answer for keepin' my 'ands off yer if yer won't
                    tell.”</p>
                <p>In his trance of rage and agony, he was incapable of pity. He had small need to
                    threaten her with blows—every word stabbed.</p>
                <p>But her turn had come to strike back. She raised her head; she measured her news
                    against his; and she did it with a kind of exultation.</p>
                <p>“Then I <emph>will</emph> tell yer—an' I 'ope it 'ull do yer<pb n="115" xml:id="VAB7023-115"/> good. <emph>I</emph> took thirty-one pound o'
                    Bolderfield's money then—but it warn't me took the rest. Some one else tuk it,
                    an' I stood by an' saw 'im. When I tried to stop 'im—look 'ere.”</p>
                <p>She raised her hand, nodding, and pointing to the wound on her brow.</p>
                <p>Isaac leant heavily on the table. A horrible suspicion swept through him. Had she
                    wronged him in a yet blacker way? He bent over her, breathing fast—ready to
                    strike.</p>
                <p>“Who was it?”</p>
                <p>She laughed. “Well, it wor <emph>Timothy</emph>, then—yur precious—beautiful
                    son—Timothy!”</p>
                <p>He fell back.</p>
                <p>“Yo're lyin',” he cried; “yer want to throw it off on some one. How cud Timothy
                    'ave 'ad anythin' to do with John's money? Timothy's not been near the place
                    this three months.”</p>
                <p>“Not till lasst night,” she said, mocking him. “I'll grant yer—not till lasst
                    night. But it <emph>do</emph> 'appen, as lasst night Timothy took forty-one
                        pound<pb n="116" xml:id="VAB7023-116"/> o' John Borroful's money out o' that
                    box, an' got off—clean. I'm sorry if yer don't like it—but I can't 'elp that;
                    yo' listen 'ere.”</p>
                <p>And lifting a quivering finger she told her tale at last, all the beginning of it
                    confused and almost unintelligible, but the scene with Timothy vivid, swift,
                    convincing—a direct impression from the ugly immediate fact.</p>
                <p>He listened, his face lying on his arms. It was true, all true. She might have
                    taken more and Timothy less; no doubt she was making it out as bad as she could
                    for Timothy. But it lay between them—his wife and his son—it lay between
                    them.</p>
                <p><choice>
                        <sic>‘</sic>
                        <corr>“</corr>
                    </choice>An' I 'eard yer coming,” she ended; “an' I thought I'd tell yer—an' I
                    wor frightened about the 'arf-crowns—people 'ad been talkin' so at Dawson's—an'
                    I didn't see no way out—an'—an'—”</p>
                <p>She ceased, her hand plucking again at the comforter, her throat working.</p>
                <p>He, too, thought of the loving words he had said<pb n="117" xml:id="VAB7023-117"/> to her, and the memory of them only made his misery the more fierce.</p>
                <p>“An' there ain't no way out,” he said violently, raising his head. “Yer'll be
                    took before the magistrates next week, an' the assizes 'ull be in February, an'
                    yer'll get six months—if yer don't get more.”</p>
                <p>She got up from her chair as though physically goaded by the words.</p>
                <p>“I'll not go to jail,” she said under her breath. “I'll not—”</p>
                <p>A sound of scorn broke from Isaac.</p>
                <p>“Yo' should ha' thought o' that,” he said. “Yo' should ha' thought o' that. An'
                    what you've been sayin' about Timothy don't make it a 'aporth the better—not for
                        <emph>yo'!</emph> Yo' led <emph>'im</emph> into it too—if it 'adn't been for
                    yo', 'ee'd never ha' seen the cursed stuff. Yo've dragged 'im down worse nor 'ee
                    were—an' yerself—an' the childer—an' me. An' the drink, an' the lyin'!—it turns
                    a man's stomach to think on it. An' I've been livin' with yer—these twelve
                    years. I wish to the Lord I'd never seen yer—as<pb n="118" xml:id="VAB7023-118"/> the children 'ad never been born! They'll be known all their life now—as
                    'avin' 'ad sich a woman for their mother!”</p>
                <p>A demon of passion possessed him more and more. He looked at her with murderous
                    eyes, his hand on the table working.</p>
                <p>For his world, too, lay in ruins about him. Through many hard-working and
                    virtuous years he had counted among the righteous men of the village—the men
                    whom the Almighty must needs reckon to the good whenever the score of Clinton
                    Magna had to be made up. And this pre-eminence had come to be part of the
                    habitual furniture of life and thought. To be suddenly stripped of it—to be, not
                    only disgraced by his wife, to be thrust down himself among the low and sinful
                    herd—this thought made another man of him; made him wicked, as it were,
                    perforce. For who that heard the story would ever believe that he was not the
                    partner of her crime? Had he not eaten and drunk of it; were not he and his
                    children now clothed by it?</p>
                <pb n="119" xml:id="VAB7023-119"/>
                <p>Bessie did not answer him nor look at him. At any other moment she would have
                    been afraid of him; now she feared nothing but the image in her own mind—herself
                    led along the village street, enclosed in that hateful building, cut off from
                    all pleasure, all free moving and willing—alone and despised—her children taken
                    from her.</p>
                <p>Suddenly she walked into the back kitchen and opened the door leading to the
                    garden.</p>
                <p>Outside everything lay swathed in white, and a snowstorm was drifting over the
                    deep cup of land which held the village. A dull, melancholy moonlight seemed to
                    be somewhere behind the snow curtain, for the muffled shapes of the houses below
                    and the long sweep of the hill were visible through the dark, and the objects in
                    the little garden itself were almost distinct. There, in the centre, rose the
                    round stone edging of the well, the copious well, sunk deep into the chalk, for
                    which Bessie's neighbours envied her, whence her good nature let them draw
                    freely at any time of drought. On either side<pb n="120" xml:id="VAB7023-120"/>
                    of it the gnarled stems of old fruit-trees and the bare sticks of winter kail
                    made black scratches and blots upon the white.</p>
                <p>Bessie looked out, leaning against the doorway, and heedless of the wind that
                    drove upon her. Down below there was a light in Watson's cottage, and a few
                    lights from the main street beyond pierced the darkness. The Spotted Deer must
                    be at that moment full of people, all talking of her and Isaac. Her eye came
                    hastily back to the snow-shrouded well and dwelt upon it.</p>
                <p>“Shut that door!” Isaac commanded from inside. She obeyed, and came back into the
                    kitchen. There she moved restlessly about a minute or two, followed by his
                    frowning look—the look, not of a husband, but of an enemy. Then a sudden animal
                    yearning for rest and warmth seized her. She opened the door by the hearth
                    abruptly and went up, longing simply to lie down and cover herself from the
                    cold.</p>
                <p>But, after all, she turned aside to the children, and sat there for some time at
                    the foot of the little boys'<pb n="121" xml:id="VAB7023-121"/> bed. The
                    children, especially Arthur, had been restless for long, kept awake and
                    trembling by the strange sounds outside their door and the loud voices
                    downstairs; but, with the deep silence that had suddenly fallen on the house
                    after Isaac had gone away to seek his interview with Watson, sleep had come to
                    them, and even Arthur, on whose thin cheeks the smears left by crying were still
                    visible, was quite unconscious of his mother. She looked at them from time to
                    time, by the light of a bit of a candle she had placed on a box beside her; but
                    she did not kiss them, and her eyes had no tears. From time to time she looked
                    quickly round her, as though startled by a sound, a breathing.</p>
                <p>Presently, shivering with cold, she went into her own room. There, mechanically,
                    she took off her outer dress, as though to go to bed; but when she had done so
                    her hands fell by her side; she stood motionless till, suddenly wrapping an old
                    shawl round her, she took up her candle and went downstairs again.</p>
                <pb n="122" xml:id="VAB7023-122"/>
                <p>As she pushed open the door at the foot of the stairs, she saw Isaac, where she
                    had left him, sitting on his chair, bent forward, his hands dropping between his
                    knees, his gaze fixed on a bit of dying fire in the grate.</p>
                <p>“Isaac!”</p>
                <p>He looked up with the unwillingness of one who hates the sound he hears, and saw
                    her standing on the lowest step. Her black hair had fallen upon her shoulders,
                    her quick breath shook the shawl she held about her, and the light in her hand
                    showed the anguished brightness of the eyes.</p>
                <p>“Isaac, are yer comin' up?”</p>
                <p>The question maddened him. He turned to look at her more fixedly.</p>
                <p>“Comin' up? Noa, I'm not comin' up—so now know. Take yerself off, an' be
                    quick.”</p>
                <p>She trembled.</p>
                <p>“Are yer goin' to sleep down 'ere, Isaac?”</p>
                <p>“Aye, or wherever I likes: it's no concern o' yourn. I'm no 'usband o' yourn from
                    this day forth.<pb n="123" xml:id="VAB7023-123"/> Take yerself off, I say!—I'll
                    'ave no thief for <emph>my</emph> wife!”</p>
                <p>But instead of going she stepped down into the kitchen. His words had broken her
                    down; she was crying again.</p>
                <p>“Isaac, I'd ha' put it back,” she said imploring. “I wor goin' in to Bedford to
                    see Mr. Grimstone—'ee'd ha' managed it for me. I'd a worked extra—I could ha'
                    done it—if it 'adn't been for Timothy. If you'll 'elp—an' you'd oughter, for yer
                        <emph>are</emph> my 'usband, whativer yer may say—we could pay John
                    back—some day. Yo' can go to 'im, an' to Watson, an' say as we'll pay it
                    back—yo' <emph>could</emph>, Isaac. I can take ter the plattin' again, an' I can
                    go an' work for Mrs. Drew—she asked me again lasst week. Mary Anne 'ull see to
                    the childer. Yo' go to John, Isaac, to-morrer—an'—an'—to Watson. All they wants
                    is the money back. Yer couldn't—yer couldn't—see me took to prison, Isaac.”</p>
                <p>She gasped for breath, wiping the mist from her eyes with the edge of her
                    shawl.</p>
                <pb n="124" xml:id="VAB7023-124"/>
                <p>But all that she said only maddened the man's harsh and pessimist nature the
                    more. The futility of her proposals, of her daring to think, after his fiat and
                    the law's had gone forth, that there was any way out of what she had done, for
                    her or for him, drove him to frenzy. And his wretched son was far away; so he
                    must vent the frenzy on her. The melancholia, which religion had more or less
                    restrained and comforted during a troubled lifetime, became on this tragic night
                    a wild-beast impulse that must have its prey.</p>
                <p>He rose suddenly and came towards her, his eyes glaring, and a burst of invective
                    on his white lips. Then he made a rush for a heavy stick that leant against the
                    wall.</p>
                <p>She fled from him, reached her bedroom in safety, and bolted the door. She heard
                    him give a groan on the stairs, throw away the stick, and descend again.</p>
                <p>Then for nearly two hours there was absolute stillness once more in this
                    miserable house. Bessie<pb n="125" xml:id="VAB7023-125"/> had sunk, half
                    fainting, on a chair by the bed, and lay there, her head lying against the
                    pillow.</p>
                <p>But in a very short time the blessed numbness was gone, and consciousness became
                    once more a torture, the medium of terrors not to be borne. Isaac hated her—she
                    would be taken from her children—she felt Watson's grip upon her arm—she saw the
                    jeering faces at the village doors.</p>
                <p>At times a wave of sheer bewilderment swept cross her. How had it come about that
                    she was sitting there like this? Only two days before she had been everybody's
                    friend. Life had been perpetually gay and exciting. She had had qualms indeed,
                    moments of a quick anguish, before the scene in the Spotted Deer. But there had
                    been always some thought to protect her from herself. John was not coming back
                    for a long, long time. She would replace the money—of course she would! And she
                    would not take any more—or only a very little. Meanwhile the hours floated by,
                    dressed in a colour and variety they had never yet possessed for her—<pb n="126" xml:id="VAB7023-126"/> charged with all the delights of wealth, as such a
                    human being under such conditions is able to conceive them.</p>
                <p>Her nature, indeed, had never gauged its own capacities for pleasure till within
                    the last few months. Excitement, amusement, society—she had grown to them; they
                    had evoked in her a richer and fuller life, expanded and quickened all the
                    currents of her blood. As she sat shivering in the darkness and solitude, she
                    thought with a sick longing of the hours in the public-house—the lights, the
                    talk, the warmth within and without. The drink-thirst was upon her at this
                    moment. It had driven her down to the village that afternoon at the moment of
                    John's arrival. But she had no money. She had not dared to unlock the cupboard
                    again, and she could only wander up and down the bit of dark road beyond the
                    Spotted Deer, suffering and craving.</p>
                <p>Well, it was all done—all done!</p>
                <p>She had come up without her candle, and the only light in the room was a cold
                    glimmer from the snow<pb n="127" xml:id="VAB7023-127"/> outside. But she must
                    find a light, for she must write a letter. By much groping she found some
                    matches, and then lit one after another while she searched in her untidy drawers
                    for an ink-bottle and a pen she knew must be there.</p>
                <p>She found them, and with infinite difficulty—holding match after match in her
                    left hand—she scrawled a few blotted lines on a torn piece of paper. She was a
                    poor scholar, and the toil was great. When it was done, she propped the paper up
                    against the looking-glass.</p>
                <p>Then she felt for her dress, and deliberately put it on again, in the dark,
                    though her hands were so numb with cold that she could scarcely hook the
                    fastenings. Her teeth chattered as she threw her old shawl round her.</p>
                <p>Stooping down, she took off her boots, and pushing the bolt of her own door back
                    as noiselessly as possible, she crept down the stairs. As she neared the lower
                    door, the sound of two or three loud breathings caught her ear.</p>
                <pb n="128" xml:id="VAB7023-128"/>
                <p>Her heart contracted with an awful sense of loneliness. Her husband slept—her
                    children slept—while she—</p>
                <p>Then the wave of a strange, a just passion mounted within her. She stepped into
                    the kitchen, and walking up to her husband's chair, she stood still a moment
                    looking at him. The lamp was dying away, but she could still see him plainly.
                    She held herself steadily erect; a frown was on her brow, a flame in her
                    eyes.</p>
                <p>“Well, good-bye, Isaac,” she said, in a low but firm voice.</p>
                <p>Then she walked to the back door and opened it, taking no heed of noise; the
                    latch fell heavily, the hinges creaked.</p>
                <p>“Isaac!” she cried, her tones loud and ringing, “<emph>Isaac!</emph>”</p>
                <p>There was a sudden sound in the kitchen. She slipped through the door, and ran
                    along the snow-covered garden.</p>
                <p>Isaac, roused by her call from the deep trance of<pb n="129" xml:id="VAB7023-129"/> exhaustion which only a few minutes before had fallen upon his misery, stood
                    up, felt the blast rushing in through the open door at the back, and ran
                    blindly.</p>
                <p>The door had swung to again. He clutched it open; in the dim weird light, he saw
                    a dark figure stoop over the well; he heard something flung aside, which fell
                    upon the snow with a thud; then the figure sprang upon the coping of the
                    well.</p>
                <p>He ran with all his speed, his face beaten by the wind and sleet. But he was too
                    late. A sharp cry pierced the night. As he reached the well, and hung over it,
                    he heard, or thought he heard, a groan, a beating of the water—then no more.</p>
                <p>Isaac's shouts for help attracted the notice of a neighbour who was sitting up
                    with her daughter and a new-born child. She roused her son-in-law and his boy,
                    and through them a score of others, deep night though it was.</p>
                <p>Watson was among the first of those who gathered<pb n="130" xml:id="VAB7023-130"/> round the well. He and others lowered Isaac with ropes into its icy depths,
                    and drew him up again, while the snow beat upon them all—the straining men—the
                    two dripping shapes emerging from the earth. A murmur of horror greeted the
                    first sight of that marred face on Isaac's arm, as the lanterns fell upon it.
                    For there was a gash above the eye, caused by a projection in the hard chalk
                    side of the well, which of itself spoke death.</p>
                <p>Isaac carried her in, and laid her down before the still glowing hearth. A
                    shudder ran through him as he knelt, bending over her. The new wound had effaced
                    all the traces of Timothy's blow. How long was it since she had stood there
                    before him pointing to it?</p>
                <p>The features were already rigid. No one felt the smallest hope. Yet with that
                    futile tenderness all can show to the dead, everything was tried. Mary Anne
                    Waller came—white and speechless—and her deft gentle hands did whatever the
                    village doctor told her. And there were many other women, too,<pb n="131" xml:id="VAB7023-131"/> who did their best. Some of them, had Bessie dared to
                    live, would have helped with all their might to fill her cup of punishment to
                    the brim. Now that she had thrown herself on death as her only friend, they were
                    dissolved in pity.</p>
                <p>Everything failed. Bessie had meant to die, and she had not missed her aim. There
                    came a moment when the doctor, laying his ear for the last time to her cold
                    breast, raised himself to bid the useless effort cease.</p>
                <p>“Send them all away,” he said to the little widow, “and you stay.” Watson helped
                    to clear the room, then he and Isaac carried the dead woman upstairs. An old man
                    followed them, a bent and broken being, who dragged himself up the steps with
                    his stick. Watson out of compassion came back to help him.</p>
                <p>“John—yer'd better go home, an' to yer bed—yer can't do no good.”</p>
                <p>“I'll wait for Mary Anne,” said John, in a shaking whisper—“I'll wait for Mary
                    Anne.”</p>
                <p>And he stood at the doorway leaning on his stick;<pb n="132" xml:id="VAB7023-132"/> his weak and reddened eyes fixed on his cousin, his mouth open feebly.</p>
                <p>But Mary Anne, weeping, beckoned to another woman who had come up with the little
                    procession, and they began their last offices.</p>
                <p>“Let us go,” said the doctor kindly, his hand on Isaac's shoulder, “till they
                    have done.”</p>
                <p>At that moment Watson, throwing a last professional glance round the room,
                    perceived the piece of torn paper propped against the glass. Ah! there was the
                    letter. There was always a letter.</p>
                <p>He walked forward, glanced at it, and handed it to Isaac. Isaac drew his hand
                    across his brow in bewilderment, then seemed to recognize the handwriting, and
                    thrust it into his pocket without a word. Watson touched his arm. “Don't you
                    destroy it,” he said in warning; “it'll be asked for at the inquest.”</p>
                <p>The men descended. Watson and the doctor departed. John and Isaac were left alone
                    in the kitchen. Isaac hung over the fire, which had been<pb n="133" xml:id="VAB7023-133"/> piled up in the hope of restoring warmth to the
                    drowned woman. Suddenly he took out the letter and, bending his head to the
                    blaze, began to read it.</p>
                <p>“Isaac, yer a cruel husband to me, an' there's no way fer me but the way I'm
                    goin'. I didn't mean no 'arm, not at first, but there, wot's the good of
                    talkin'? I can't bear the way as you speaks to me an' looks at me, an' I'll
                    never go to prison—no, never. It's orful—fer the children ull 'ave no mother,
                    an' I don't know however Arthur ull manage. But yer woodent shew me no mercy,
                    an' I can't think of anythin' different. I did love yer an' the childer, but the
                    drink got holt of me. Yer mus' see as Arthur is rapped up, an' Edie's eyes ull
                    'ave to be seen to now an' agen. I'm sorry, but there's nothin' else. I wud like
                    yer to kiss me onst, when they bring me in, and jes say, Bessie, I forgive yer.
                    It won't do yer no 'arm, an' p'raps I may 'ear it without your knowin'. So
                    good-bye, Isaac, from yur lovin' wife, Bessie....”</p>
                <p>As he read it, the man's fixed pallor and iron calm<pb n="134" xml:id="VAB7023-134"/> gave way. He leant againist the mantelpiece, shaken
                    at last with the sobs of a human and a helpless remorse.</p>
                <p>John, from his seat on the settle a few yards away, looked at Isaac miserably.
                    His lips opened now and then as though to speak, then closed again. His brain
                    could form no distinct image. He was encompassed by a general sense of
                    desolation, springing from the loss of his money, which was pierced every now
                    and then by a strange sense of guilt. It seemed to have something to do with
                    Bessie, this last, though what he could not have told.</p>
                <p>So they sat, till Mary Anne's voice called “Isaac” from the top of the
                    stairs.</p>
                <p>Isaac stood up, drew one deep breath, controlled himself, and went, John
                    following.</p>
                <p>Mary Anne held the bedroom door open for them, and the two men entered, treading
                    softly.</p>
                <p>The women stood on either hand crying. They had clothed the dead in white and
                    crossed her hands upon her breast. A linen covering had been passed,<pb n="135" xml:id="VAB7023-135"/> nun-like, round the head and chin. The wound was
                    hidden, and the face lay framed in an oval of pure white, which gave it a
                    strange severity.</p>
                <p>Isaac bent over her. Was this <emph>Bessie</emph>—Bessie, the human, faulty,
                    chattering creature—whom he, her natural master, had been free to scold or
                    caress at will? At bottom he had always been conscious in regard to her of a
                    silent but immeasurable superiority, whether as mere man to mere woman, or as
                    the Christian to the sinner.</p>
                <p>Now—he dared scarcely touch her. As she lay in this new-found dignity, the proud
                    peace of her look intimidated, accused him—would always accuse him till he too
                    rested as she rested now, clad for the end. Yet she had bade him kiss her—and he
                    obeyed her—groaning within himself, incapable altogether, out of sheer
                    abasement, of saying those words she had asked of him.</p>
                <p>Then he sat down beside her, motionless. John tried once or twice to speak to
                    him, but Isaac shook his head impatiently. At last the mere presence<pb n="136" xml:id="VAB7023-136"/> of Bolderfield in the room seemed to anger him. He
                    threw the old man such dark and restless looks that Mary Anne perceived them,
                    and, with instinctive understanding, persuaded John to go.</p>
                <p>She, however, must needs go with him, and she went. The other woman stayed. Every
                    now and then she looked furtively at Isaac.</p>
                <p>“If some one don't look arter 'im,” she said to herself, “'ee'll go as his father
                    and his brothers went afore him. 'Ee's got the look on it awready. Wheniver it's
                    light I'll go fetch Muster Drew.”</p>
                <p>With the first rays of the morning Bolderfield got up from the bed in Mary Anne's
                    cottage, where she had placed him a couple of hours before, imploring him to lie
                    still and rest himself. He slipped on his coat, the only garment he had taken
                    off, and taking his stick he crept down to the cottage door. Mary Anne, who had
                    gone out to fetch some bread, had left it ajar. He opened it and stood on the
                    threshold looking out.</p>
                <p>The storm of the night was over, and already a<pb n="137" xml:id="VAB7023-137"/>
                    milder breeze was beginning to melt the newly-fallen snow. The sun was striking
                    cheerfully from the hill behind him upon the glistening surfaces of the distant
                    fields; the old labourer felt a hint of spring in the air. It brought with it a
                    hundred vague associations and filled him with a boundless despair. What would
                    become of him now—penniless and old and feeble? The horror of Bessie's death no
                    longer stood between him and his own pain, and would soon even cease to protect
                    her from his hatred.</p>
                <p>Mary Anne came back along the lane, carrying a jug and a loaf. Her little face
                    was all blanched and drawn with weariness; yet when she saw him her look
                    kindled. She ran up to him.</p>
                <p>“What did yer come down for, John? I'd ha' taken yer yer breakfast in yer
                    bed.”</p>
                <p>He looked at her, then at the food. His eyes filled with tears.</p>
                <p>“I can't pay yer for it,” he said, pointing with his stick; “I can't pay yer for
                    it.”</p>
                <pb n="138" xml:id="VAB7023-138"/>
                <p>Mary Anne led him in, scolding and coaxing him with her gentle trembling voice.
                    She made him sit down while she blew up the fire; she fed and tended him. When
                    she had forced him to eat something, she came behind him and laid her hand on
                    his shoulder.</p>
                <p>“John,” she said, clearing her throat, “John, yer shan't want while I'm livin'. I
                    promised Eliza I wouldn't forget yer, and I won't. I can work yet—there's plenty
                    o' people want me to work for 'em—an' maybe, when yer get over this, you'll work
                    a bit too now and again. We'll hold together, John—anyways. While I live and
                    keep my 'elth yer shan't want. An' yer'll forgive Bessie”—she broke into sudden
                    sobbing. “Oh! I'll never 'ear a crule word about Bessie in my 'ouse,
                        <emph>never!</emph>”</p>
                <p>John put his arms on the table and hid his face upon them. He could not speak of
                    forgiveness, nor could he thank her for her promise. His chief feeling was an
                    intense wish to sleep; but as Mary Anne dried her tears and began to go about
                        her<pb n="139" xml:id="VAB7023-139"/> household work, the sound of her step,
                    the sense of her loving presence near him, began for the first time to relax the
                    aching grip upon his heart. He had always been weak and dependent, in spite of
                    his thrift and his money. He would be far more weak and dependent now and
                    henceforward. But again, he had found a woman's tenderness to lean upon, and as
                    she ministered to him—this humble shrinking creature he had once so cordially
                    despised—the first drop of balm fell upon his sore.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, in another cottage a few yards away, Mr. Drew was wrestling with
                    Isaac. In his own opinion, he met with small success. The man who had refused
                    his wife mercy, shrank with a kind of horror from talking of the Divine mercy.
                    Isaac Costrell's was a strange and groping soul. But those misjudged him who
                    called him a hypocrite.</p>
                <p>Yet in truth, during the years that followed, whenever he was not under the
                    influence of recurrent attacks of melancholia, Isaac did again<pb n="140" xml:id="VAB7023-140"/> derive much comfort from the aspirations and
                    self-abasements of religion. No human life would be possible if there were not
                    forces in and round man perpetually tending to repair the wounds and breaches
                    that he himself makes. Misery provokes pity; despair throws itself on a Divine
                    tenderness. And for those who have the “grace” of faith, in the broken and
                    imperfect action of these healing powers upon this various world—in the love of
                    the merciful for the unhappy, in the tremulous yet undying hope that pierces
                    even sin and remorse with the vision of some ultimate salvation from the self
                    that breeds them—in these powers there speaks the only voice which can make us
                    patient under the tragedies of human fate, whether these tragedies be “the falls
                    of princes” or such meaner, narrower pains as brought poor Bessie Costrell to
                    her end.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>PRINTED BY WILLIAM CLOWES AND SONS, LIMITED, LONDON AND BECCLES.</trailer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>