<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
   xml:id="VAC5564">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>General Sherman's Indian Spy </title>
            <author>Bradshaw, Wesley (1837-1927)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC5564</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-0046</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                  copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction
                  project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                  University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is granted
                  to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                  contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                  educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                  inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University
                  Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
               Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>General Sherman's Indian spy</title>
                  <author>Bradshaw, Wesley (1837-1927)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>94 [i.e. 64] p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>C.W. Alexander</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Philadelphia </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1865">1865</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
               Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
               website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and has
               been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
               Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2000-08-23">Finished OCR, rough
            encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="Caroline Lilyard, University of Minnesota" when="2001-01-25">Finished TEI
            encoding and proofreading</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-04-30">Finished final
            editing</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-04-01">Converted document from SGML to TEI
            P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-04-01">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents
            and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="frontis">
            <pb n="Cover" xml:id="VAC5564-00000001"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>Gen'l. Sherman's Indian Spy.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC5564-00000002"/>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>GENERAL SHERMAN'S INDIAN SPY.</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">A SINGULARLY THRILLING NARRATIVE OF WENONAH, A YOUNG AND LOVELY
                  INDIAN GIRL, DESCENDED FROM TECUMSEH, THE RENOWNED INDIAN WARRIOR, WHOSE NAME GEN.
                  SHERMAN BEARS, WHILE SCOUTING FROM ATLANTA, THROUGH GEORGIA AND SOUTH
                  CAROLINA.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>BY <docAuthor>WESLEY BRADSHAW</docAuthor> Author of "Pauline of the Potomac,"
               "The Angel of the Battle-Field," "The Picket Slayer," "General Grant's Spy,"
               "Washington's Vision," "General Cocoran's Captivity," "The Soldier's Casket,"
               &amp;c., &amp;c.</byline>
            <docEdition>EMBELLISHED WITH SPLENDID ENGRAVINGS, AND BOUND IN A SUPERBLY COLORED PAPER
               COVER.</docEdition>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>PHILADELPHIA:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>PUBLISHED BY C. W. ALEXANDER,
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>123 SOUTH THIRD STREET.</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </publisher>
            </docImprint>
            <docEdition>Entered, according to Act of Congress, in the year 1865, by C. W. Alexander,
               in the Clerk's Office of the District Court in and for the Eastern District of
               Penna.</docEdition>
         </titlePage>
         <div type="illustrations">
            <pb n="Illustration-19" xml:id="VAC5564-00000003"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>THE WHIP FIGHT BETWEEN THE DROVERS.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <head>GENERAL SHERMAN'S INDIAN SPY.</head>
            <head>INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <p>AMONG the first movements of the wickedly ambitious men who, by the destruction of
               their country, expected to attain a bad eminence, was that of endeavoring to persuade
               the Indians of The Far West to join their vile cause. While a few of these savage
               warriors were, by large promises and deceptive representations, induced to dig up the
               tomahawk and make war upon the Union flag, we would be doing a brave race injustice
               not to record that the great majority of the Indians scorned to follow the example of
               their dusky friends. Not only did they scorn this, but immediately girding on their
               weapons, they promptly offered to fight for the flag of their "<emph>Great Father at
                  Washington,</emph>" as they called Mr. Lincoln.</p>
            <p>How noble and inspiring was this simple, dignified message from the Children of the
               Wilderness, sent by them on the wings of the "<emph>Fire Bird</emph>," (as they call
               the telegraph,) and how nobly and well these untamed warriors fulfilled their promise
               to battle for the cause of right and justice, let their mouldering ashes on many a
               battlefield testify.</p>
            <p>In the Federal armies of the West, the Indians were far more conspicuous than in
               those of the East, as their services in those regions were of more value. And no army
               profited more by our red allies than General Sherman's. We may add, also, that no
               General had more confidence in the Indians than did the gallant soldier who clove his
               way from Atlanta to Raleigh. And none did he hold in higher esteem than the gentle
               and brave maiden whose exploits we are about to record. The very manner in which she
               introduced herself to him proved decisively her powers as a spy or scout. But we
               prefer to let her own history speak for itself.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>General Sherman's Indian spy</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC5564-00000004"/>
               <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
               <head type="sub">HOW WENONAH REACHED SHERMAN.</head>
               <p>ONE night just previous to General Sherman's moving his headquarters to the
                  saddle, for his final conjoint movement with Grant on the rebellion, he sat
                  poring, in his absorbed yet nervous manner, over a pile of maps, diagrams and
                  reports. In his right hand were a pair of dividers, one limb of which he now and
                  then placed on the map immediately before him, at Chattanooga, while the other he
                  alternately turned upon Dalton and Cleveland. With his left forefinger he next
                  followed the rail and pike roads lined out on the map from these three towns,
                  first to Rome and Atlanta, then to Murfreesboro and Nashville, then to Huntsville
                  and along the winding line representing the Tennessee River. Then putting down his
                  dividers, he turned the map round, placed his two thumbs together to represent the
                  centre of his army, extended the fore finger of each hand for the wings, and with
                  rapid jerks, rather than motions, went through a pantomime as it were, pushing
                  first the right, then the left fore finger round the wings of an imaginary enemy,
                  then carrying forward his thumbs, until the right fore finger rested on the coast
                  town of Darien, and the left upon Savannah. Twice he repeated this pantomime,
                  moving, however, each time over different roads.</p>
               <p>"That is the move!" said he finally, in a satisfied tone, to himself, as one
                  finger stopped at Fort McAllister, the other extended up towards Charleston, and
                  the two thumbs covered the Savannah River. "And now," continued he, still speaking
                  to himself, "I'll have a nap."</p>
               <p>"General!"</p>
               <p>The voice that broke the deep stillness of the night with this slight exclamation
                  was very sweet, and came from a point in the room behind Sherman.</p>
               <p>The General started, paused for an atom of time far less than an instant, and then
                  wheeling in his chair, held a light above his head, and glanced with that sharp
                  look for which he is noted, at the person who spoke.</p>
               <p>It was a female.</p>
               <p>"Madam or Miss," said Sherman, still holding the candle above him, and moving it
                  from side to side, to cast a more favorable light, "How came you in here? I
                  ordered that no one be admitted. How long have you been here? What do you want?
                  and, above all, how did you get in?"</p>
               <p>As he ceased speaking, Sherman set the candle down on the table, and fastened his
                  gaze sternly on the girl before him, who, so far from being disconcerted, advanced
                  a pace or two, full into the light of the candle, and replied in a firm, but sweet
                  voice:</p>
               <p>"General, will you listen to me?"</p>
               <p>"Well, go on, what do you wish to say?"</p>
               <p>"General, I would help the good pale faces. I love the pale faces. Pale face blood
                  and Indian blood, Tecumseh's blood runs in my heart together, like brother and
                  sister."</p>
               <p>Sherman had already noted the fact from her costume, her complexion, hair and
                  features, that his unexpected guest was an Indian and though much fatigued, he
                  resolved to hear what she had to say to him. His knowledge of Indian character,
                  also, induced him to this course.</p>
               <p>"Well," said he, "how do you want to help the good pale faces?"</p>
               <p>"A woman," answered the Indian girl after a short pause, "makes but a poor
                  warrior. But the Great Spirit who made the blood of Tecumseh run in the veins of
                  Wenonah, gave to her, also, the brave heart of Tecumseh—gave to her the eagle's
                  eye and the fox's ear. Wenonah will fly before the pale face warriors, into the
                  land of the enemy, like an eagle, after sunset, and will creep like a fox in the
                  daytime. She will see and hear every thing, and she will come back to the good
                  pale faces, and tell them how to take the war-path."</p>
               <p>With hands and features did the maiden accompany her words, and with such power of
                  expression that General Sherman was struck with wonder.</p>
               <p>"You mean," said he, "that you would like to be a spy or scout?"</p>
               <p>Wenonah's eyes flashed joyous fire at these word, especially as they were spoken
                  in a much less stern tone than Sherman had previously used, striding within a pace
                  of the General, she abruptly nodded her head, and then suddenly recollecting
                  herself, she bowed gracefully, and resumed her former attitude.</p>
               <p>"I have good reason to know," spoke Sherman, "that my Indian men make the most
                  useful and prudent spies; but women, especially when so young as you are—" He
                  paused, and slightly shook his head, causing an expression of anxiety to flit over
                  the beautiful features of his guest. But suddenly, and in his usual manner, he
                  resumed: "Well, if you could give me an example of your powers as a spy, I will
                  see whether I can grant your request."</p>
               <p>"Good!" exclaimed the girl, with a second flashing of joy across her face. "The
                  pale face General makes Wenonah's heart laugh with happiness. See!" and placing
                  her two thumbs together, with her two fore fingers extended, as Sherman had done,
                  she stepped forward, and bending over the map that lay on the table, traced with
                  tolerable accuracy the route Sherman himself had traced but a few minutes before.
                  As her<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC5564-00000005"/> fingers rested on the coast she
                  exclaimed, in imitation of Sherman's manner, as nearly as possible:</p>
               <p>"That's the plan!" Then stepping back a pace, she added, gracefully extending her
                  arms and moving them like the wings of a large bird. "The pale face General is
                  like the warrior whose name he bears. Like Tecumseh<ref rend="super"
                     target="#note_001" xml:id="return_001">*</ref>
                   he flies as the War Eagle flies, over the heads of his enemies, so that
                  they cannot escape him!"</p>
               <p>This <choice>
                     <sic>raphsody</sic>
                     <corr>rhapsody</corr>
                  </choice>, however, was lost to Sherman, for the fact that his unbidden or, more
                  truly, forbidden guest knew all about at least the rough outline of his intended
                  campaign, which he had not imparted even to his most trustworthy Generals,
                  discomposed him.</p>
               <p>"Girl," he exclaimed, taking Wenonah by the arm, though not rudely, "How in the
                  name of Mischief did you get in here? Where was the guard? The careless villain!
                  I'll have him shot!"</p>
               <p>"He is asleep, General!" coolly replied Wenonah. "And none can awake him but the
                  Indian girl," she added, in a strangely solemn tone, as she, in turn, laid her
                  hand, on the arm of Sherman, who had sprung to his feet and taken a step toward
                  the door.</p>
               <p>The General paused but a moment, however, and then striding out, he found the
                  guard sunk, or crouched, as it were, on the ground, in a deep slumber, though
                  still grasping his musket.</p>
               <p>"Fellow, get up with you! Do you know what the punishment is for sleeping on
                  duty?"</p>
               <p>No answer came; the soldier remained as a figure hewn out of rock. Sherman grasped
                  him with no gentle hand, and shook him with no gentle strength, but as well might
                  he have done so to an image.</p>
               <p>For once the General was astonished, and he turned his eyes upon Wenonah, who
                  stood beside him. As he did so she spoke:</p>
               <p>"The pale face General asked for proof of Wenonah's power. She has given him one.
                  She will now give him another."</p>
               <p>With this she knelt on one knee before the sleeping soldier, and placing her open
                  hands on his face, slowly drew them backward and outward. This she repeated a few
                  times. Then rising to her feet, she resumed the strange moving of her hands, but
                  in a different direction. As though a mantle were being gently withdrawn from
                  about the guard, so he seemed to regain consciousness. But ere he was fully
                  aroused General Sherman drew back into his apartment, and was closely followed by
                  Wenonah, in whom he now felt a singular interest.</p>
               <p>"I have seen that done once before," said he to his guest. "Have you that power
                  over every one?"</p>
               <p>"No, General, only those whom the Great Spirit gives me power over," replied
               Wenonah, turning a look of the deepest reverence Heavenward.</p>
               <note place="foot" xml:id="note_001">
                  <p><ref target="#return_001">*</ref>Tecumseh was the renowned Indian warrior
                     whose deeds are familiar to every reader of Indian history.</p>
               </note>
               <p>"Then you fail sometimes?"</p>
               <p>"Never with the birds, beasts, or serpents of the forests, General; but sometimes
                  I fail with human beings."</p>
               <p>"Could you cause me to sleep?" asked the General; looking straight into Wenonah's
                  eyes, which, for the first time, he noticed were most peculiarly penetrating in
                  their expression.</p>
               <p>"No, General, I have already tried to do so, but have failed."</p>
               <p>"Ah!"</p>
               <p>By a strong effort Sherman prevented his face from exhibiting the slightest
                  emotion as he uttered this monosyllable; but as Wenonah informed him of her
                  attempt to control his will, he certainly had to acknowledge to himself that he
                  was somewhat startled. A long pause ensued, during which Sherman thought deeply,
                  and then, addressing Wenonah, he asked:</p>
               <p>"Who are you? Do you know any of my Indian scouts? Are you related to any of them?
                  If I could be made sure of being able to trust you, you would be more valuable for
                  the accomplishment of my designs than all the rest put together."</p>
               <p>Evidently gratified at her progress, Wenonah immediately and fully imparted to her
                  interrogator her whole history.</p>
               <p>By the time she concluded her artless and truthful narrative, General Sherman was
                  fully convinced of Wenonah's integrity, and that her offer was prompted by the
                  highest and holiest emotions towards the flag of the Union.</p>
               <p>"To-morrow evening, at this time," said Sherman, drawing his watch, and mentioning
                  the hour, "come here. I will be ready to impart to you certain details, and then
                  you can start on your dangerous mission, which, if you succeed in accomplishing,
                  you shall be amply rewarded with something more substantial than mere praise."</p>
               <p>The look that sprang to Wenonah's features as General Sherman made this allusion,
                  made him regret doing so.</p>
               <p>"The pale face General measures with gold; but all the gold that our Great Father
                  at Washington could give, would never buy a true Indian Heart! Wenonah will give
                  her heart and life to the cause of the good pale faces, but she will never sell
                  them!"</p>
               <p>"Well, well, never mind that now, you are a noble girl, and brave, and do honor to
                  the memory of your great ancestor, Tecumseh. Come at this time to-morrow, and you
                  shall have a real opportunity of testing your powers, and your devotion to your
                  country; which I doubt not. Good night!"</p>
               <p>"May the Great Manitou (the Indian word for God) make your sleep<pb n="24-25"
                     xml:id="VAC5564-00000006"/> to strengthen you, and watch over you all through
                  the dark night, till the sun comes up."</p>
               <p>As she thus spoke, Wenonah came, and kneeling on one knee before General Sherman,
                  bowed still lower, and taking his two hands with the innocent trust of a little
                  child, placed them upon her head, thus, as it were, invoking the blessing of a
                  father.</p>
               <p>The stern soldier was deeply moved with this expression of the poor Indian girl's
                  love and reverence for himself, and he did not draw his hands away until Wenonah
                  released them, and sprang to her feet with the noiseless bound of a wild deer.</p>
               <p>She had nearly reached the usual door of exit, when General Sherman bade her stay
                  a moment, and then taking her hand he led to another door in the rear; telling her
                  as he again wished her good night, to come that way to-morrow.</p>
               <p>The strange interview had entirely driven all drowsiness from Sherman, and instead
                  of retiring, as he originally intended, he reseated himself at his table, and
                  resumed the study of the plan he had marked out. Towards morning Nature, however,
                  demanded rest, and in a few moments the hero of the future campaign through
                  Georgia was sleeping profoundly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE SPY'S DEPARTURE.</head>
               <p>THE next night, true as the rising star to the hour, the brave and devoted Indian
                  girl tapped three times lightly on the private door of General Sherman's office.
                  The General, also prompt and punctual, quickly admitted his visitor, and after
                  greeting her warmly, handed her to a chair beside his own at the table which, as
                  on the previous evening, was covered with maps and books.</p>
               <p>After a short introductory, or rather explanatory, conversation, General Sherman
                  opened to Wenonah the real details of the perilous mission on which he intended to
                  send her, and on which she seemed eager as a caged bird to depart.</p>
               <p>"First," said he, directing Wenonah's attention to the map, "I wish you if
                  possible, to get to this point. From there reach with all speed that caution will
                  permit, the head-quarters of General Johnson, who commands the enemy. Once there,
                  I wish you to learn all you possibly can in regard to the strength of his army,
                  especially his cavalry, artillery, and wagon trains; whether he is going to move,
                  and if so, in what direction. Keep your eyes and ears open, miss nothing, however
                  trivial, and when you have obtained as much information as you can, retrace your
                  way to my army. There you will be arrested as a spy, and sent to me. In order to
                  insure security from discovery of your departure, you must make your way out
                  through our lines without a pass, a fact which, from what you have already done,
                  you will have no difficulty in accomplishing."</p>
               <p>"The Great Manitou," replied Wenonah, as the General ceased speaking, "will give
                  me the wisdom of the serpent, and the patience of the fox. Wenonah will pass as
                  safely through the lines as she would through the forest in the dark hours of the
                  night time."</p>
               <p>For nearly an hour longer did General Sherman detail to his lovely companion such
                  information and particulars and advice as he thought essential to her success, and
                  then giving her some money to pay all those accidental expenses that her journey
                  would necessarily incur, he bade her God speed.</p>
               <p>"I will come back soon," said Wenonah, as she parted from the General, "and like a
                  bird with swift wings I will bring you good news."</p>
               <p>"I pray to Heaven that you will," replied Sherman, shaking the spy's hand, and
                  speaking in a fervent tone, "I pray to Heaven that you will. Good night!"</p>
               <p>"Good night, General, good night!"</p>
               <p>With this adieu, in a low, hopeful voice, Wenonah tripped away, and was quickly
                  lost to view in the gloom of the night.</p>
               <p>No preparation had the devoted girl to make for her fearful journey, and no other
                  farewells to take, for she had no living relatives, and but a few friends, and
                  these latter were among the people of her tribe. She, therefore, set out at once
                  for her destination, and long ere sunrise had passed the last Federal line.</p>
               <p>This was hot done without considerable risk and trouble, for at the point of the
                  infantry line where she struck it, Wenonah found a squad of three or four men, two
                  of whom were wide awake and on the alert.</p>
               <p>Approaching as closely as possible, the Indian spy attempted, by the same manner
                  in which she had affected the sentinel at General Sherman's head-quarters, to
                  overcome the picket, but again her efforts failed, and she had nothing left but a
                  bold and cautious exit. To go either to the right or left of where she was would
                  expose her to equal peril as to go forward, and forward she resolved to go. The
                  picket to which we allude was posted directly on the edge of a forest, while in
                  front beyond was a sweep of country as clear as a stubble-field, excepting here
                  and there a slight knoll or bush. Taking up a short heavy stick, she whirled it as
                  far as possible, up and away into the air, giving it such a direction that when it
                  fell, it struck a short distance to the left of the picket, coming down<pb
                     n="26-27" xml:id="VAC5564-00000007"/> through the foliage of a tree, and making
                  considerable noise. For several moments this distracted the attention of the
                  pickets in that direction, and in an instant, throwing herself almost flat on the
                  ground, Wenonah crept forward into the open space beyond the woods, with the
                  silence and rapidity of a fox.</p>
               <p>"Halt! Halt! or I'll shoot!"</p>
               <p>The fierce, loud voice that uttered these ominous words came from the right, and
                  the Indian girl knew instantly that a picket there had seen her creeping
                  along.</p>
               <p>To halt was to be made a captive. All her chivalric nature was fired with
                  excitement, and uttering a wild yell, the spy leaped to her feet, and bounded away
                  farther into the darkness. Then came a flash, a report, and a whistling minie-ball
                  as it seemed altogether; but Wenonah was not struck, and she kept steadily running
                  forward at the top of her speed, until, fearful of encountering the cavalry line,
                  she deemed it prudent to move slowly. One or two of the infantrymen had started in
                  pursuit of the fugitive, but they very soon relinquished the chase, for two
                  reasons, first, that they depended on the cavalry line to stop her, and second,
                  that she outstripped them all as easily as the hare might a group of
                  tortoises.</p>
               <p>It was the horsemen she feared most, and yet not so much for themselves as their
                  horses, as she held the belief that a white man's horse invariably discovered the
                  approach of an Indian to his master, by violently snorting with terror in the
                  direction in which the Indian came!<ref rend="super" target="#note_002"
                     xml:id="return_002">*</ref>
                  
               </p>
               <p>On kept the noble and heroic girl, however, often making momentary halts to thank
                  the Great Manitou, and to invoke his continued protection.</p>
               <p>At the place where she expected to find the vidette line she discovered also, to
                  her intense joy, a long, narrow ravine, that, forming the bed of a little stream
                  of water, ran in the same direction as she was traveling. Down this she took her
                  way, and so securely that she never once beheld a single Union horseman.</p>
               <p>Thus safely outside of General Sherman's lines, Wenonah's perilous task was hardly
                  begun. But with a boldness and bravery characteristic of Tecumseh himself, did
                  this poor Indian girl, trusting in the Great Spirit, whom she had teen taught to
                  worship in her wilderness home, march forward into the enemy's country.</p>
               <p>As the dawn broke grayly over a wooded ridge of land to the Eastward, our heroine
                  fell in with a man who, mounted in a rough wagon, seemed to be making his way
                  Northward.</p>
               <note place="foot" xml:id="note_002">
                  <p><ref target="#return_002">*</ref>This is a physical though unaccountable fact out on the Plains, as every
                     hunter and trapper of the Far West will testify to. Whether it would be so
                     further East, we of course cannot say.</p>
               </note>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
               <head type="sub">AN APPARENT MISHAP.</head>
               <p>FROM the suspicious look of the lonely traveler, our Indian spy quickly repented
                  not having concealed herself, and letting him pass without seeing her.</p>
               <p>"Whar ar yer tote'in yerself to, wench?" asked the man, in a sullen, fierce
                  manner, jumping down from his wagon and planting himself in front of Wenonah, thus
                  bringing her to a dead halt.</p>
               <p>For a few seconds the girl hardly knew what reply to make to the inquiry. Indeed,
                  she felt a strong inclination to avoid answering, by a sudden flight. But besides
                  being close enough to her to seize her instantaneously, the man held in his hand
                  the butt of a revolver that was thrust within his leathern waist-belt.</p>
               <p>"Why don't you tell me, eh?" asked the man, more fiercely than before. "If yer
                  don't, I'll make buzzard food o' yer afore yer ken blink them ugly black eyes o'
                  yourn three times more!"</p>
               <p>"Oh! don't hurt me! I'll go with you!" exclaimed Wenonah, clasping her hands in
                  supplication, and speaking in tones of anguish, that from their very abjectness
                  would have convinced any one not so dull of perception as her rude companion, that
                  they were merely assumed for a purpose.</p>
               <p>"Whar'd yer run off frum, fur —— me ef I ken tell yer frum an Injun or a nigger?
                  But I'll guess yer fur a nigger, anyhow."</p>
               <p>"Oh, sir, I'm lost! I've been traveling all night! I'm a poor Indian girl; I'm not
                  a nigger."</p>
               <p>"Wal! now I'm a look'n closer at yer, I don't b'lieve y'ar a nigger! that's ef
                  that h'ar o' yourn aint quaker! Let's see."</p>
               <p>The brutal fellow while speaking had brought his face so close to that of his
                  captive that she instinctively turned her head away, to avoid his breath, which
                  was horribly offensive with rum and tobacco. And now, partly from anger and partly
                  from passion, he grasped Wenonah's long, beautiful tresses, and violently jerked
                  her face round to his own again.</p>
               <p>"Look hyur, gal," said he, "as y'ar an Injun! plump an' good look'n, an' I've left
                  my little wife fur awhile, why I'll hitch up with yer, an' when I git inside the
                  Yankee lines, why we'll git j'ined. I've been in he rebel army, an' I've cut
                  stick. But afore I did, I settled one ole devil, an I've buried his gold in a
                  place whar it'll be safe enough, till the war's over, an' then we'll come back an'
                  tote it off."</p>
               <p>From his expressive action while imparting this information, Wenonah<pb n="28-29"
                     xml:id="VAC5564-00000008"/> felt certain that the man before her, beside being
                  a traitor was a murderer.</p>
               <p>"But that's not all!" continued he. "I ken tell the Yankee Ginerals somethin'
                  that'll be wuth thousands o' cotton bales to 'em. I ken tell jest whar Joe
                  Johnson's mule is, I ken. An' ef they'll pay me well, I'll do it."</p>
               <p>"A spy also!" said Wenonah within herself. And more determined than before on a
                  resolve she had already made, the Indian girl rejoined:</p>
               <p>"Oh! I go! I go! you give me plenty pretty blankets, plenty shiney money, plenty
                  pretty beads."</p>
               <p>Her manner changed equally with her words, and completely off his guard, the man
                  answered:</p>
               <p>"Yer ken bet your mule on that thar, gal! Git up inter the cart; well hev ter be
                  agoin sharp. Wot's yet name, eh? I forgot ter ask yer that yit."</p>
               <p>The last part of this remark was made as Wenonah seated herself on a bag of corn
                  in the Wagon, into which she had sprung at a single bound.</p>
               <p>"Oh thunder!" exclaimed the man, as he got up to his seat and started his horse
                  into a brisk trot, "I can't chaw up any sich fancy Injun name as thot. I tell yer,
                  my wife's name's Molly, an' as y'ar goin' ter be her to me, why I'll call yer her
                  name. So mind now, yer name's Molly. I'm used ter that, an' I'll never miss fire
                  on't. An' my name's Bob Martin. Molly allers calls me Bob Martin, so as y'ar goin'
                  to be Molly to me, why I'll be Bob Martin to you. Now yer understand; when yer
                  want new fixins an' frocks, say Bob Martin, I want em, an' I'll say Molly, yer ken
                  hev 'em, or Molly, yer can't, jest as' it haps to be."</p>
               <p>Thus delivering himself, Bob Martin became silent, and began a rigid scrutiny of
                  the country ahead of him. In a very short time, however, he sank gradually down as
                  one in slumber, and the horse, which had meanwhile decreased his pace, now came to
                  a stand still in the middle of the road.</p>
               <p>A few minutes later, Bob Martin, the rough, powerful captor of the Indian girl,
                  was lying helpless as an infant, on the bottom of his own wagon, securely bound,
                  hand and foot, and disarmed of revolvers and bowie-knife. These deadly weapons
                  were in the possession of Wenonah, as were also the reins.</p>
               <p>"I must awake him before we are discovered," murmured the spy to herself, and in a
                  short time Bob Martin became fully conscious of his condition. He cursed, and
                  struggled, and plead to his fair captor, by turns, until he was completely
                  exhausted. But all to no purpose. She had her object to accomplish, and turning
                  the horses head, she urged the animal back, down the same road up which he had
                  come.</p>
               <p>After while she descried a party of rebel cavalry, who seemed to be beating about
                  the country for some one. With this party she soon fell in,and to the commanding
                  Lieutenant she told the story of her encounter with, and capture of, Bob
                  Martin.</p>
               <p>"Oh, yes!" said the officer, after hearing Wenonah through, "he's the identical
                  man we want." Then turning to the culprit, who had been quickly lifted from the
                  wagon by several men, he continued: "You infernal scoundrel, I ought to run you up
                  to that branch there, but you'll get the rope within forty-eight hours for your
                  bloody work the other day."</p>
               <p>Upon this the captive began a torrent of such vile and filthy abuse, directed at
                  Wenonah, that one of the rebel cavalrymen, in a rage doubled up his fist, and gave
                  the villain such a blow in the mouth, as sent all his teeth down his throat, and
                  cut his lips terribly.</p>
               <p>Thereafter Martin became sullen and morose, though as the party rode along, he now
                  and then cast looks of implacable hatred and ferocity at the girl who had been the
                  means of his capture. She, on the contrary, though having so justly taken him
                  prisoner, pitied the villain, as she beheld the blood running down from his
                  lacerated mouth, upon his breast. Still, if she could, she would not have
                  liberated him, as by his arrest she expected to make the most valuable capital
                  with the rebel authorities; for, stranger as she was, how could her loyalty to the
                  so-called Confederacy be doubted, when she had taken a deserter going over to the
                  enemy, taken him, too, after he had made a prisoner of her.</p>
               <p>The rebel soldiers were exceedingly pleased with their heroic companion, more
                  especially that she was an Indian girl, and beautiful, and much pity was awakened
                  within them on her informing them that she was lost, and knew not where her people
                  were. And their appreciation of her bravery and shrewdness was but heightened,
                  when told by her that she had traveled always during the night, for fear of being
                  seen by the Yankees, whose country she was afraid of getting into.</p>
               <p>The Lieutenant in command of the squad, in an ebullition of romantic ardor, and
                  perhaps love, took from his own breast a handsome and valuable ornament, in the
                  shape of a secession flag, formed of jewels, and fastened it upon Wenonah's,
                  saying as he did so:</p>
               <p>"There, Wenonah, keep that as a memento from me, of my admiration of your bravery
                  and patriotism."</p>
               <p>With true Indian dissemblance the spy accepted the gift, examined it with great
                     <emph>apparent</emph> pleasure, and then, taking the donor's hand, pressed it
                  to her lips.</p>
               <p>That act settled the Lieutenant's business, and our spy felt in an instant that
                  she had made a friend, who, properly used, would be of the utmost value to her in
                  securing her objects.</p>
               <p>That evening Wenonah, after passing the day as she chose, was escorted by the
                  Lieutenant to a Court Martial, before which, Martin was arraigned. When the
                  culprit beheld her take the stand to witness against<pb n="30-31"
                     xml:id="VAC5564-00000009"/> him, his face became livid with rage, making him
                  perfectly hideous to behold.</p>
               <p>"You captured this man, did you?" asked the Judge-Advocate of Wenonah.</p>
               <p>"I did."</p>
               <p>"Well, give us a narrative of the whole affair, particularly as to the locality of
                  the arrest, and the direction in which the prisoner was going at the time."</p>
               <p>A suspicion instantly arose within the spy that the Judge-Advocate was endeavoring
                  to get herself in a committal of some sort, and she, therefore, very cautiously,
                  though with promptness, made a reply which, while it was entirely true, yet gave
                  no opportunity to any one to suppose that her representations concerning herself
                  were not fully correct.</p>
               <p>After she had finished, one or two other witnesses were examined, and in an
                  incredibly short time subsequent to the conclusion of the trial, the prisoner was
                  sentenced to be hung the next morning, at six o'clock.</p>
               <p>"Major!" exclaimed the condemned man, when the sentence was read, "I know I'm a
                  hard boy, an' I don't growl so much at gittin' hung, as bein' tuk by that Injun
                  devil. Now, afore I die I'll jest tell the whole truth 'bout her. She's a Yankee
                  spy, any she only done what she's done ter cotton <emph>your</emph> eyes up. I've
                  seed her fur weeks in this here region, an' I've helped her myself, an' ef you'll
                  jest hunt her, you'll find docermints nuff on to her to prove what I'm a sayin'.
                  Jest you hunt her sharp, that's all I've got ter say."</p>
               <p>When the villain first began to denounce her, Wenonah felt fearful of discovery;
                  but when she beard the last portion of his harangue to the Judge-Advocate she was
                  at once reassured.</p>
               <p>"His words are false!" said she, springing forward from her seat, "false as the
                  Wolf's tongue is his."</p>
               <p>The Judge-Advocate, and all the members of the Court regarded our heroine in
                  silence, for a few moments, and then one of the latter suggested that, at least,
                  to prove Martin's accusation false, his fair captor should be searched.</p>
               <p>"With pleasure!" exclaimed Wenonah, courting an examination, in the consciousness
                  that she had nothing about her that would sustain the charge.</p>
               <p>A lady, wife of an officer present, was called, and our spy retired with her, for
                  the purpose of proving her innocence. The matter was soon over, and the searcher
                  quickly returned to the Court-room with Wenonah and reported that not the
                  slightest thing had been discovered on the Indian girl, to implicate her at all
                  with the Yankees. And going a step further, she added that, in her belief, Wenonah
                  was truly loyal and devoted to the Confederacy.</p>
               <p>Martin, who, of course, concocted the story out of his own malicious brain, only
                  brought down on himself a fresh storm of indignation, and had he not been already
                  doomed to die, it is certain that the rebel soldiers would have lynched him then
                  and there.</p>
               <p>Thus, out of an exceedingly threatening cloud, had burst forth the brightest
                  sunshine, and, as was natural, our spy was correspondingly elated. But never for a
                  single moment did she allow herself to become unguarded. On the contrary, she lost
                  no opportunity of obtaining information in regard to everything that was going on
                  in the army, and very excellent use did she make of her rebel Lieutenant, towards
                  whom she displayed so much friendship, that he actually fell deeply in love with
                  her, notwithstanding the fact that he was already affianced to the daughter of a
                  wealthy planter.</p>
               <p>Of course this love was not that of a pure heart, but merely an ardent passion,
                  which flamed fiercely, but which, in time, would soon die out in the consumption
                  of its own fuel. This, Wenonah well knew, and, while affecting to reciprocate the
                  love that the Lieutenant vowed he had for her, she drew from him the most valuable
                  facts connected with the rebel military plans and strength.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE SPY RETURNS TO GENERAL SHERMAN.</head>
               <p>LIEUTENANT HASKINS—which was the name of Wenonah's rebel admirer—in a few days
                  received orders to go on a reconnaissance toward a certain point of country that
                  was occupied by the Federal Army. When he announced to the spy that he must leave
                  her for a short time, and informed her of the duty he was about to perform, she
                  became so inconsolable, and so determined to never forsake him, that he was forced
                  to give his consent for her to accompany him.</p>
               <p>The expedition was to set out at noon of the same day, and Haskins took great care
                  to secure for his Indian girl a horse of the best blood, high mettled, and of long
                  endurance.</p>
               <p>Before nightfall the party were a long on their march towards Sherman's lines, and
                  each moment, as she rode beside the Lieutenant, did our heroine pray fervently
                  that she might soon be captured by the Federals. And her prayer soon seemed likely
                  to be answered, for as they approached a densely wooded stretch of country the
                  advance guard rode back and told the Lieutenant that there were Yankees in the
                  timber ahead.</p>
               <p>A halt was at once made, and leaving Wenonah under the protection of a Sergeant,
                  the Lieutenant, who was withal a brave fellow, taking two<pb n="32-33"
                     xml:id="VAC5564-00000010"/> or three men with him, rode over toward the woods,
                  to inspect the position of his foes more closely, before deciding what course to
                  pursue.</p>
               <p>All was perfectly still, however, and apparently deserted, and Haskins came back
                  in no very good humor at what he denominated a stupid blunder.</p>
               <p>"Did you go far into the forest?" asked Wenonah, in great seeming anxiety.</p>
               <p>"Oh, no! not very far, but still far enough for my purpose," replied the
                  Lieutenant, smiling in a satisfied manner. "And," continued he, "we shall keep
                  straight on till we meet the Yankees, and then let them look out, for my boys wont
                  back out of a fight for a week's rations of coffee."</p>
               <p>The party resumed their march, though not without considerably more caution than
                  before, as their road lay directly through the forest referred to. Upon riding
                  into the woods it became dark, and the distance between the advance guard and the
                  main body was increased to about seventy-five yards. In this order the rebels had
                  nearly passed through the woods, when suddenly they were fired upon by a party of
                  Federals, who immediately charged, and a savage combat ensued.</p>
               <p>This was what Wenonah had so ardently wished for, and at the first fire she
                  wheeled her horse and dashed away into the forest. She would not have done so so
                  soon, for the reason that Haskins plunged his steed forward an instant before to
                  the front. As she supposed, she did not go far ere she was made a prisoner by the
                  Federals, who were much astonished at finding that their prisoner was an Indian
                  girl.</p>
               <p>However, they treated her with great kindness, and assured her that she would be
                  sent, as she desired, to General Sherman, especially if she would consent to
                  impart any information to him concerning the enemy. Her immediate captor insisted
                  upon her exchanging steeds with him, which showed him to be a connoisseur in the
                  matter of horses. The spy, of course, could not resist with any hope of success,
                  but at the same time she quietly ascertained his name, company and regiment, by
                  casually asking one of his comrades.</p>
               <p>The fight was of but short duration, and resulted in the retreat of the rebels,
                  with the loss of one killed and two wounded. These latter were carried off by
                  their comrades. On the Federal side none were killed and three were slightly
                  wounded. The results would have been more sanguinary, had the blue coat boys been
                  stronger in numbers, and had their orders not been strict in regard to not pushing
                  any fight, as yet, too zealously.</p>
               <p>All that night and the next day Wenonah remained in the camp of the cavalry
                  regiment which formed the outermost line of Sherman's army, as she could not until
                  then ascertain exactly where General Sherman was to be found.</p>
               <p>In a very short time after finding where she could see the commander of the
                  Federal Army, the Indian girl was in his presence.</p>
               <p>"Well" said Sherman, with sparkling eyes, "so you have come back safe, and sooner,
                  too, than I expected you to come. What do you bring me?"</p>
               <p>"The Great Manitou, General," answered Wenonah, "has heard you. He loves the pale
                  face General, and he has led me by the hand in the night and in the day. He
                  covered me up so that the enemy could not see who I was. But I saw him all the
                  time. I saw him as the eagle sees his prey."</p>
               <p>Wenonah then detailed with minuteness and precision, every event that had occurred
                  since she bade the General adieu, to depart on her dangerous mission. About her
                  description of Lieutenant Haskins, and his suddenly awakened love toward herself,
                  the spy cast such <emph>naiveté</emph> that General Sherman laughed heartily, over
                  and over again.</p>
               <p>Never was a General better pleased, or, more fully satisfied with the service of a
                  faithful servant, than General Sherman was with our heroine, and he warmly
                  congratulated her on her daring bravery and success.</p>
               <p>"But, General," said, she, "I do not want to stop now. Your enemy may alter his
                  armies. You will go to attack him; you will rush through his land like the fire on
                  the prairies. But, sometimes, you know, fire fights fire. Let me fly before you
                  into the enemy's country, and always keep on the wing between you and him. I will
                  be your eye, and thus he shall never escape you, and you shall fight him till he
                  throws down his tomahawk, and gives up to you."</p>
               <p>"That would be ten fold more perilous," rejoined the General, in a musing tone,
                  rather than addressing his companion, "than what you have just accomplished.
                  Still, if successful, it would likewise be even ten fold more valuable."</p>
               <p>At this juncture an orderly asked permission to speak to General Sherman on an
                  important matter. He informed the latter that a Union man, who had been terribly
                  maltreated by the rebels, had succeeded in making his escape, and desired to
                  impart some highly valuable information.</p>
               <p>"Bring him in," said the General.</p>
               <p>The new comer was presently ushered into the presence of Sherman, and was none
                  other than Bob Martin, whom Wenonah had seen led away to be hanged, such a short
                  time previously.</p>
               <p>Wenonah, who had stood back in the shadow of a kind of wardrobe, was so astonished
                  by the coming from the grave as it were, of this wicked wretch, that she was
                  unable to step forth and confront him, until he had begun to reply to General
                  Sherman's questions.</p>
               <p>Upon her doing so, however, Martin instantly recognized her and was<pb n="34-35"
                     xml:id="VAC5564-00000011"/> struck dumb. But suddenly collecting himself, he
                  mumblingly exclaimed, while a horrid grin spread over his features.</p>
               <p>"Didn't I tell the Major you wuz a Yankee spy! I know'd it! Yer done me a bad turn
                  once, now yer'll do me a good 'un, an' tell the Gin'ral I'm all right, wont
                  yer?"</p>
               <p>"No! I will not!" exclaimed Wenonah, vehemently. "You wish to <emph>sell</emph>
                  your knowledge for money, and not because you love your country. And you should
                  die, for your hands are red with murder."</p>
               <p>General Sherman had evidently decided the same way, for he almost interrupted
                  Wenonah with the command:</p>
               <p>"Orderly, take this man away, put him in irons, and turn him over to the Provost
                  Marshal for safe keeping, till his case can be attended to. And fellow," (this to
                  Martin,) "you shall have your deserts, if I have to send you back to General
                  Johnson to get them."</p>
               <p>From his anger, Sherman would have liked to have done so at once; but he feared if
                  he pursued such a course, that Martin would give such a description of Wenonah as
                  would discover to the rebels her real character, and thus prevent any future
                  service of <choice>
                     <sic>her's</sic>
                     <corr>hers</corr>
                  </choice> in that direction.</p>
               <p>After the dismissal of the deserter, General Sherman resumed his conversation with
                  the spy, during the course of which it was finally settled that she should once
                  more make her way through the rebel lines, and watch every movement of the wily
                  Joe Johnson, who had already made preparations as though he anticipated the
                  advance of Sherman's army at an early date.</p>
               <p>This time she was to go boldly in, and after being taken by the rebel pickets, was
                  to make her way to Lieutenant Haskins, telling him that she had been captured by
                  the Yankees, and made her escape.</p>
               <p>At Chattanooga there lived a true Union lady, who had a beautiful carrier dove,
                  which General Sherman had much admired, and which now he chanced to think might be
                  made of the utmost service, if taken by Wenonah on her mission of danger. Upon
                  stating this to the spy, he found that she fully understood the use this kind of
                  pigeon could be made of.</p>
               <p>It was, therefore, immediately determined that the General should ask the lady to
                  give him the dove, and that Wenonah should thereupon set forth, taking it with
                  her. The cipher which General Sherman gave to the spy, for her despatch, was so
                  plain and simple that, after a few minutes practice she became so conversant with
                  it that she could hold it easily in memory, and, therefore, needed not to assume
                  the risk of keeping it about her.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
               <head type="sub">ONCE MORE INTO SECESSIA.</head>
               <p>THE Union lady referred to was only too glad to have General Sherman accept of her
                  pet dove, though she was kept in entire ignorance of his object in asking for
                  it.</p>
               <p>That night, in the midst of a cold, drizzling rain, driven fiercely about by a
                  boisterous wind, did Wenonah commence her adventurous journey toward the rebel Joe
                  Johnson's army.</p>
               <p>This time she had no trouble whatever in passing out through the Union lines, nor
                  in making her way into the Confederacy, through the rebel lines. She took great
                  care and pains, also, to enter the latter as nearly as possible at the same point
                  she had done so before. And so accurately did she guess this, that she struck the
                  identical road on which she was traveling the morning she captured Bob Martin. On
                  the present occasion, however, she did not fall in with a single traveler, until
                  she had walked many miles further than she had the other time. True, she passed
                  several plantation mansions and negro quarters, but no living soul did she
                  encounter—though now daylight—until she came to a house or hut occupied by a
                  laboring man, a kind of wood-chopper, or better, a man of all work, one of that
                  miserable class who, though nominally free, are more degraded than the black
                  slaves themselves.</p>
               <p>This man had long since been dragged away by the rebel conscript officers, to fill
                  a place in Lee's army, and it was his wretched wife our heroine saw at this early
                  hour going forth to beg or steal something for her starving children, of which she
                  had three, all little girls, the oldest scarcely eight years of age.</p>
               <p>The woman started when she saw Wenonah, and seemed at first to labor under the
                  same indecision as to the race our spy belonged to, that Martin had. Wenonah
                  seeing that the miserable creature wished to avoid her, and, therefore, hung back
                  until she should pass by, went directly to her, and speaking kindly to her, asked
                  her name, and asked, also, for shelter, saying she had traveled all night, and was
                  much wearied.</p>
               <p>"Shelter!" almost laughed the woman. "Oh! yer welcome to the kiv'ring of my house;
                  but yer'll hey to git yer own mule when yer tork o' rations or bed!"</p>
               <p>"Why, have you nothing to eat?" asked the spy, in tones of commiseration.</p>
               <p>"No! nor ar'n't had fur two days! But my young 'uns' mouths is not ter be filled
                  afore I'm an hour older, or else I ar'n't thar mother!"</p>
               <pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC5564-00000012"/>
               <p>There was a ferocity and determination in the latter portion of this answer that
                  could only be induced by the monster starvation.</p>
               <p>"Yer kin go in if yer like, an' stay till I come back!" concluded the woman after
                  a momentary pause. And then gathering her scanty rag of a shawl about her
                  shoulders, she made as though to pass by our heroine, on her desperate errand.</p>
               <p>The latter, however, stayed her, and said, in tones of hopeful encouragement,</p>
               <p>"Stop, poor woman, I will help you!"</p>
               <p>"Why that thar pigeon yer've got wouldn't be a fly in one o' my young 'uns'
                  mouths, feathers an' all!"</p>
               <p>"Oh! no, I do not intend to help you with my sweet pet!" quickly rejoined Wenonah,
                  "but come in, I will give you money, and you can go and buy what you want."</p>
               <p>"Will yer, though!" exclaimed the woman, her eyes dilating with joy and anxiety;
                  while clutching the spy by the arm, she almost dragged her into the hut, where a
                  scene of woe and wretchedness was revealed, that made the blood chill and creep
                  with horror. One child, not older than three years, crouched in the dirt and ashes
                  of the fire-place, entirely nude, covered with sores, and looking like a little
                  wild beast, her hair being uncombed, owing to the agony that the operation
                  produced. The two sisters, aged five and seven, lay on a pile of leaves and twigs,
                  and, with the exception of a few rags, were as naked as the youngest child. They,
                  too, were covered with skin eruptions, and had the same wild stare as their
                  sister.</p>
               <p>Wenonah involuntarily closed her eyes, to shut out the awful sight, and drew back
                  almost stifled by the sickening odor of the room. She was aroused by the voice of
                  the woman, saying:</p>
               <p>"Come, if yer agoin' ter gin me money, gin it quick, an' don't be a waitin' till
                  it's too late!"</p>
               <p>Wenonah glanced at her companion. The old ferocity was in her eyes. She was going
                  insane with hunger, and a desire to save the lives of her children. The spy felt
                  that if she delayed much longer, the poor creature, in her frenzy, would spring on
                  her and attempt to kill her, and so hastily drawing forth a little money, she
                  placed it in the bony, feverish palm that was held out to receive it.</p>
               <p>Without a single word of thanks the recipient of this timely charity bounded away
                  on her errand, leaving Wenonah alone with the three starving, sick children, all
                  of whom silently stared at her, like voiceless spectres.</p>
               <p>In a short time the mother returned, bearing some corn, and hoe cake, and bacon in
                  her arms, which she had purchased from a friendly negro woman nearby.</p>
               <p>The poor creature's voice trembled violently with excessive delight as she spoke,
                  broke off pieces of the cake and handed to her children, who ate so ravenously of
                  the dry, unpalatable, but to them delicious cake, that several times they almost
                  choked themselves to death.</p>
               <p>"Eat! eat! eat! Annie, Sallie, Lou, eat so much as yer kin! Cuss this develish
                  rebellion that's stole away yer father, an' bless this 'ar lady who's saved yer
                  lives!"</p>
               <p>While she was thus speaking the woman, overcoming her own desire for food, that
                  her children might have the more, contented herself with picking up the scanty
                  crumbs and ravenously devouring them. This sad sight caused copious tears to flow
                  down the face of our spy, perceiving which, Mrs. Dexter—for such was the mother's
                  name—burst into tears herself, partly of sorrow, and partly of pleasure.</p>
               <p>"Oh! God bless yer! I God bless yer ten thousand times, for y'ar a good angel!
                  Yer've saved my young 'uns, an' me too! an' I hope they'll git well, so as ter
                  show yer they 're grateful!"</p>
               <p>"Ah! my poor woman, your little ones will never get well without you ask the Great
                  Spirit to make good medicine."</p>
               <p>"Medicine!" replied Mrs. Dexter, too ignorant to know the Indian application of
                  the word medicine, "why medicine or drugs of any kind fetches more than gold does.
                  Kinine (quinine she meant) aren't ter be had, 'cept it comes through the Yankee
                  lines, an' the' don't know wot ter do without it in the army!"</p>
               <p>"I don't mean that," explained the spy, "I mean that if you pray to the Great
                  Spirit, he may keep your little ones alive; but without he takes them in his arms,
                  and breathes life into their mouths, they will die."</p>
               <p>"Pray!" cried the woman, "God knows I've prayed an' prayed my throat sore. But no
                  help come till you come!"</p>
               <p>Wenonah quickly discovered that the unfortunate woman whom she had relieved was so
                  excessively ignorant, that it would, be worse than useless to waste time in
                  talking to her of anything beyond what to eat and drink, and how to get her
                  children well. Besides which, she came into the Confederacy on a different mission
                  than to enlighten its ignorant and degraded population. So, altering her tone and
                  manner, she questioned Mrs. Dexter concerning the length of time her children had
                  been sick, their present symptoms, and so on.</p>
               <p>Her next care was, if possible, to bring them back at least on the road to health.
                  The principal remedy, as she was aware, was good, wholesome food, and plenty of
                  it, but, in addition, some medicinal remedy was requisite. This Wenonah soon
                  concocted from some herbs she sent the mother out to gather, and by the next
                  night, contrary to her own expectations, she had the satisfaction of seeing her
                  protegés much better.</p>
               <p>All this time she had never for an instant forgotten the work she had<pb n="38-39"
                     xml:id="VAC5564-00000013"/> really come to do. But from Mrs. Dexter she could
                  learn nothing except that a great number of soldiers and cannon and wagons had
                  marched up the road a night or so previous. But how many there were of them she
                  could not tell, for she held rebel troops in too much fear to show herself while
                  they were passing.</p>
               <p>The special errand on which our spy had come was not so much concerning the
                  strength and position and movements of General Joe Johnson's army, as to ascertain
                  the character of the country from in front of Chattanooga, all the way down to,
                  and between Macan and <choice>
                     <sic>Milledgvillee</sic>
                     <corr>Milledgeville</corr>
                  </choice>. If time allowed and fortune proved favorable, she was instructed by
                  General Sherman to go even beyond these places, and note well the crops and roads.
                  Upon ascertaining all that would be possible, she was to make up a dispatch,
                  attach it securely to the carrier dove, and then let the bird loose, to find its
                  way back to its home in Chattanooga.</p>
               <p>In the house of the lady to whom the dove belonged, General Sherman had caused one
                  of his most trusty officers to obtain board. His duty was to take the dispatch the
                  moment it came, and bring it to the General. Thus, if all went well, the hero of
                  the Grand March through Georgia would be the possessor of intelligence that would
                  prove at once fatal to the rebels, and equally fortunate to himself.</p>
               <p>At the earliest practicable moment Wenonah bade Mrs. Dexter and her children good
                  bye, and set her face toward Macon. With great good sense she deemed the risk of
                  actually going up to Johnson's army too great, even under all the favorable
                  circumstances by which she was surrounded, to take. Besides, by keeping her ears
                  open, she felt certain that by the time she would be ready to send back word to
                  General Sherman, she would have ascertained with sufficient accuracy the general
                  position and strength of Johnson's army. She, therefore, hastened forward with
                  boldness and caution.</p>
               <p>The Indian girl had well and truly spoken when, in her figurative language, she
                  said to General Sherman, she would be his eye, and always see the enemy. For had
                  the General gone over the self-same route as Wenonah, he could not have noticed
                  with more correct judgment the points of military importance. But the greatest
                  triumph of the girl's genius was in the application of her memory to her dangerous
                  task, thus immensely lessening the peril thereof. So perfect was this power, that
                  never once, from the very outset of her journey, was Wenonah obliged to make a
                  note on paper of anything, no matter how trivial, that attracted her attention.
                  Yet if called upon, she could at once and without error, detail everything, and
                  draw out a sufficiently accurate map of roads, towns; stations for troops, and so
                  forth.</p>
               <p>Strange to say, the spy passed at her will and leisure in any direction she chose,
                  and made such good use of eyes, ears and limbs, that before the expiration of the
                  time allowed her, she had reached Milledgeville, the capital of Georgia, and had
                  made a note of every thing military. Here she learned, quite by accident, that her
                  rebel lover, Lieutenant Haskins, had been ordered on special duty, to Savannah. As
                  yet she had not mentioned his name since entering the Confederacy the second time;
                  but now she determined to make her way to him, certain that through him she could
                  get at a large amount of the most valuable information. Besides the very use of
                  his name would give her immunity and protection in case of unexpected danger. To
                  make "certainty more sure," our wily spy composed a letter, copied, and then
                  dispatched it to the unsuspecting rebel officer.</p>
               <p>As the spy had orders, if "time allowed and fortune proved favorable," to go a
                  short distance beyond Milledgeville, before sending back the dove, she promptly,
                  after mailing the letter to Haskins, started to complete her mission. For this
                  purpose she was obliged to go down by railroad, to within a short distance of
                  Macon.</p>
               <p>Alighting at the last station, Wenonah had already walked some distance down the
                  pike road, leading Eastward therefrom, when she heard the hoofs of a galloping
                  horse, also coming down. Looking back, she descried a cavalryman, riding like a
                  whirlwind toward her.</p>
               <p>In an instant she felt the conviction that he wanted her, and the result proved
                  correct.</p>
               <p>"Halt, thar you!" bawled the horseman, as, after thus turning to look back at him,
                  Wenonah resumed her walk. "Halt, I say!"</p>
               <p>As there was no one else on the road, the spy could not pretend to misunderstand
                  or unheed the peremptory order, so she turned again and stood still till the
                  cavalryman got up to her. He almost rode her down before he reined in his horse.
                  In one hand he held a hand-bill, which he deliberately conned over, each instant
                  raising his eyes and looking at the spy, and then returning them upon the
                  paper.</p>
               <p>"Yes, my red gal, you're the bird I want! Hey, yah! by old Joe I've got my
                  mule!"</p>
               <p>"What does the pale face mean?" asked Wenonah, in firm tones, and with unterrified
                  features.</p>
               <p>"What do I mean! Wall, as you're a female, why I'll explain, which I wouldn't if
                  you war a man! Read that, an' then pop up behind me, an' don't say a word, nor
                  make no fuss!"</p>
               <p>The spy took the paper and read;</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <head>"STOP HER!</head>
                           <head type="sub">$1,000 TO THE CAPTOR!</head>
                           <p>A young Indian girl, calling herself Wenonah (Here followed her full
                              description). She is a vile spy for the Yankees!</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>(Signed) LIEUTENANT A. B. HASKINS!"</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>In spite of her great courage, a deadly chill shot through the frame of<pb
                     n="40-41" xml:id="VAC5564-00000014"/> Wenonah, causing great drops of
                  perspiration to start out upon her forehead, and for a moment almost overwhelming
                  her with despair. But the agitation was <emph>only</emph> momentary, and the next
                  moment she vaulted up behind her captor, who immediately cantered back with her to
                  Macon. She had resolved to make a trial of her mysterious power, by means of which
                  she had been able to effect Bob Martin's capture. And she had already raised her
                  hands, when from a by-road dashed up two other cavalrymen, evidently comrades of
                  her capturer. This doubly unfortunate accident put out the light of hope, and
                  whether, by any event, it was to be rekindled, remained only to the future for
                  decision.</p>
               <p>"I found my mule, boys!" exclaimed he who had taken Wenonah.</p>
               <p>"Bully fur yer luck, Ned!" rejoined the new comers, in chorus, "we've had a hard
                  ride, an' scoured every rod! Where'd yer bag her?"</p>
               <p>"Just down the pike apiece, walkin' along as bold as a lion!"</p>
               <p>"Thunder!" said one of the horsemen, leaning over, and speaking low in his
                  comrade's ear, "she's pooty as a picter ar'n't she?"</p>
               <p>"Wall, she ar! ef I'd a tuk her, I'd a hid her, an' then married her."</p>
               <p>Wenonah's quick ears caught the gist of this last remark, and seeing from their
                  faces that her captors were impressed in her favor, she resolved, if possible, to
                  make friends of them.</p>
               <p>"The pale faces," said she, in a mournful voice, "wrong the poor Indian girl. She
                  has some wicked enemy, but not Lieutenant Haskins. He is her true friend, and
                  loves her, for he told her so, and he is too brave to have a lying tongue. He
                  called her sister in sunshine, and he will not say he is not her brother, when the
                  tempest makes the sky dark."</p>
               <p>Spoken, as they were, in a studied tone and manner, these words had a deep effect
                  in the direction wished for by Wenonah.</p>
               <p>"Why, see here, Bill," said one, in a wondering kind of manner, "I know that
                  Liften't Haskins wuz sent down to Savannah, fur he brought me as fur as this with
                  him."</p>
               <p>"Wall, what's that 'ar got ter do with it?" was the inquisitive rejoinder of
                  "Bill."</p>
               <p>"Why, jest this much. Them hand-bills come down to the barracks last night, from
                  Atlanta, or some place up that way. Now as Haskins is at Savannah, they'd a come
                  that way of <emph>he'd</emph> sent 'em, wouldn't they?"</p>
               <p>There was no disputing this logic, and he who had addressed Bill, followed up his
                  triumph with:</p>
               <p>"Blast me, ef I don't b'lieve the gal! Yer kin bet yer mule some feller's arter
                  her to trap her."</p>
               <p>"Kind pale face," murmured Wenonah, producing the copy of the letter she had
                  written to Haskins, and handing it to one of her captors, "read that, and then,
                  for the sake of the poor Indian girl who has no friend but him, send him word, and
                  he will come and save me."</p>
               <p>"Bill, read that thar; it looks pooty, but I can't read, yer knows."</p>
               <p>Bill took the letter and read it, not without some difficulty, for the task almost
                  exceeded his literary ability, and when he had done, he handed it back to Wenonah,
                  saying, as he did so:</p>
               <p>"I kinder think now, myself, thar's a bad break in the line somewhar; but ef yer
                  say so, gal, why I'll befriend yer by droppin' a line or so to the Lif'ten't 'bout
                  yer."</p>
               <p>"Oh the Great Spirit bless you, my brother, for you <emph>are</emph> a brother to
                  me now."</p>
               <p>She held the soldier's hand a moment; and then fervently, but with almost
                  sickening repugnance, touched the great, dirty paw with her lips.</p>
               <p>With a perception natural to all her sex, Wenonah knew the power of woman's
                  influence over man. And in pursuance of her object—one she held so dear, so
                  sacred—she continually made use of every charm, so far as maiden honor and purity
                  would permit.</p>
               <p>"Bill," the recipient of a favor unasked, for which he would have given almost
                  anything, was as much astonished as he was delighted, and swore upon the spot,
                  with an oath too strong for type to utter, that he didn't believe Wenonah to be
                  guilty, adding, also, with another oath, that he'd "tote a big load of friendship"
                  for her, and see, so far as he could help it, that no harm should come to her. He
                  wound up his address with the additional offer to procure something for the dove
                  to eat, while its mistress had to stay in Macon.</p>
               <p>In due time the spy arrived with her captors at Macon, and with great promptness
                  was hurried to a cell of the common jail. This, each of her three soldier rebel
                  friends would have prevented, if he could; but the officer in command was
                  imperative, and as a punishment to Bill, who ventured a remark, he ordered him to
                  stand guard over the cell in which our heroine was confined, with the threat of
                  hanging if he demurred or flagged in his duty. Just previous to going into the
                  Commandant's office, Wenonah adroitly concealed the carrier dove beneath the shawl
                  or mantle she wore about her. Her first care upon being ushered into her cell was
                  to ascertain if there were a window to it. Upon seeing that there was, she sank on
                  her knees, and offered up a fervent, though silent, prayer of thanks. This duty
                  done, she next set about another, which was attended with a fearful risk.</p>
               <p>She knew that the prison was guarded strongly by sentinels outside, and she knew
                  that she would not be long detained there. Therefore, she resolved to write up her
                  dispatch to General Sherman, fasten it to the dove, and then let the latter go out
                  through the window of her cell. The risk was that some one outside would catch
                  sight of the bird and its dispatch, shoot it, and then—then better the bullet had
                  pierced her own heart. Yet if she delayed, someone might see the bird in her
                  possession, and recognize it as a carrier, in which event her fate would be almost
                     as<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC5564-00000015"/> certain. Here, then, was just that
                  kind of crisis that always calls forth genius and strength of character.</p>
               <p>Wenonah quickly made her decision. Stepping to the cell door, which was opened
                  purposely that her guard might watch her, she expressed to him a desire to arrange
                  her dress, and asked him to allow her to hang up her shawl before the door, that
                  she might be entirely private.</p>
               <p>"Bill" was much more chivalric than the educated villains who had forced him and
                  thousands like him into the rebel ranks, and he instantly replied, in a low
                  whisper:</p>
               <p>"Yes, to be sure!"</p>
               <p>A moment more and our spy was shut in as safe from prying eyes as though she had
                  been in some dark, wilderness cave. She had a small lead pencil and one single
                  strip of paper, which she feared would not hold all she wished to write. But
                  regrets would lead only to despair; each instant fleeting by was a priceless gem
                  lost. Like lightning did the pencil run from edge to edge of the sheet; one side
                  was full, then over on the other side. The rude stool on which the paper lay
                  trembled like an aspen. The dispatch was finished, folded and ready to be sent.
                  Wenonah was becoming anxious; she thrust her hand into a pocket for the silk cord
                  with which she intended to secure the paper to the dove—<emph>but it was
                     gone!</emph> What should she do? She searched her clothing thoroughly, but no
                  cord came to light. In her extremity she thought of raveling out her dress, but
                  that would not hold—at least it would be unsafe to trust it. Next her shoe
                  strings, but these were of leather, and far too clumsy and heavy. Despair seemed
                  about to approach and mark her as his victim, when suddenly a happy idea suggested
                  itself to her.</p>
               <p>In a moment, with a nervous twitch, the spy plucked out from among her long raven
                  tresses, a dozen hairs. To make from these a light, strong, sure thread, was a
                  task easy of accomplishment to Wenonah's nimble fingers.</p>
               <p>Another instant saw the dreadful missive, on which two fates depended, secured to
                  the messenger bird, in a manner that precluded the possibility of its coming off;
                  and another beheld our spy standing at the opened window, with the dove in her
                  right hand.</p>
               <p>Had Raphael been there, in that poor cell, at this moment, and with his inspired
                  brush imprinted upon canvas the Indian girl's face, his would have been a double
                  immortality. Hope, fear, courage, anxiety, all these emotions, toned, as it were,
                  with a sunlight of childlike faith and dependence on God, played upon the features
                  of the captive.</p>
               <p>"May the Great Manitou breathe under your wings, good dove, and send you like the
                  first sweet wind of summer to your master! Good bye! Good bye!"</p>
               <p>These words came from Wenonah's lips in whispered accents. A steadying of the
                  hand, an opening of the fingers, a quick, upward jerk of the rounded arm, and the
                  deed was done—the bird rising instantly into the air.</p>
               <p>It went up to the height of about half-gunshot range, and then circled round and
                  round several times.</p>
               <p>"Stay not, bird! stay not! away! away!" exclaimed the spy, in bated breath, as she
                  strained her eyes round and round with the motion of the dove.</p>
               <p>Even as she spoke, the latter poised itself an instant, and then darted away
                  across the prison, disappearing, of course, from Wenonah's sight. She uttered a
                  sigh of relief, but had scarcely done so, when she was startled by a rapid
                  discharge of guns outside, and loud shouts, among which she could distinguish the
                  word "pigeon!"</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
               <head type="sub">DOUBT AND DANGER.</head>
               <p>THE keen point of an unseen sword seemed to pierce its way through the heart of
                  the spy, and staggering, she sank down upon the stool that had served her for a
                  desk.</p>
               <p>Had the bird been killed? Had the sharp eyes of the outside guards seen the folded
                  missive fastened to it? These were dreadful questions. If so, then her life was
                  forfeited, for even the slight fact of securing the dispatch with strands of her
                  own hair, would alone decide her doom.</p>
               <p>"Now for death!" she murmured, rising to her feet. With the action fear left her,
                  and with the stoicism of her race; she nerved herself to meet her doom. A ray of
                  hope, too, now, for the first, seemed to come dimly in upon her, in the thought
                  that, perhaps, the bird had escaped destruction or wounding.</p>
               <p>"Hist! thar gal! Down with that 'ar shawl; some 'uns comin'!"</p>
               <p>This order was uttered in hasty and constrained tones, by "Bill," the guard.</p>
               <p>In a moment the shawl, which had well served its office, was cast about the spy's
                  shoulders, and she seated herself upon the stool. By the time she had fully
                  composed herself to meet the impending storm, the Commander of the prison,
                  accompanied by a rebel infantryman, strode into the cell, and, in excited tones,
                  exclaimed:</p>
               <p>"So, you —— Yankee devil, you had a pigeon here! a carrier pigeon! and you sent it
                  out just now with a dispatch on it! You're sure this was the window, are you?"
                  turning to the soldier.</p>
               <p>"Yes, sir! this wuz the winder!"</p>
               <pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC5564-00000016"/>
               <p>"And why, in —— did'nt you shoot the slut herself?" roared the officer, in a
                  perfect rage.</p>
               <p>"Why," replied the soldier, "I thought you could take care o' the slut, an' that
                  the wust 'd be ter let the pigeon git off; so I fired at the pigeon, but did'nt
                  touch it."</p>
               <p>"Are you sure that it went down, wounded by the last shot?" asked the
                  Commandant.</p>
               <p>"Yes, sir, I'm pooty sure on that 'ar p'int," was the reply, "it kinder tumbled,
                  'an then went in behind a tree top."</p>
               <p>"Did it alight on the tree, or merely fly off behind it?"</p>
               <p>"I think it lit, sir!"</p>
               <p>"You think! Why don't you <emph>know</emph>, you addle pate! However, you and that
                  man who shot last shall go over at once, and hunt that patch of woods till you
                  find it! And you, you Yankee huzzy," he continued, turning fiercely upon our
                  heroine, "you had better confess, if you want anything like mercy showed you! What
                  was that paper on that pigeon's neck? Who was it sent to? Sherman, wasn't it?"</p>
               <p>"Oh! my poor pet dove! Why did you fly away, and leave me?" sobbed Wenonah,
                  keeping her face buried in her hands.</p>
               <p>"Here! none of your —— acting and putting on, here!" shouted the officer, thrown
                  into a terrible rage, by the apparent inattention of the prisoner to him, the most
                  important personage in the country. "Hold up your brazen face, and answer me!"</p>
               <p>Still Wenonah continued to weep and hide her face, which so exasperated her
                  jailor, that he seized her rudely by the shoulder, and shook her roughly.</p>
               <p>This was too much for the spy's Indian blood to endure, and, springing to her
                  feet, she confronted the rebel official with looks of the fiercest hatred and
                  defiance.</p>
               <p>"The pale face is a coward! Any squaw is a warrior to him! But I fear you not! One
                  step, and the Indian girl will battle with you to the death!"</p>
               <p>As she spoke, Wenonah seized a hickory walking-stick that chanced to be lying on
                  the floor, and brandished it above her head. Seeing this, the soldier who
                  accompanied the officer raised his piece and rushed forward, and deliberately
                  jagged the point of his bayonet into Wenonah's side, in order to make her drop her
                  arm. The next moment, however, he lay a corpse, for, as the spy uttered a faint
                  shriek of pain, a sabre gleamed in the air an instant, and then descended like a
                  flash of light to its bloody work. "Bill," the inside guard, was the executioner,
                  and she "recovered" his weapon, he said to the officer:</p>
               <p>"That wuz my duty, sir. You ordered me to see no harm come to this woman, as she
                  wuz a spy, an' 'ud be hung."</p>
               <p>So perfectly cool and collected was "Bill," that his superior was completely
                  surprised and baffled for some moments. But then recovering, he exclaimed:</p>
               <p>"Well, well, you shall both be hanged. Ho! there! guard!"</p>
               <p>Assistance was quickly at hand, and while the dead body of the soldier was borne
                  out, Bill was ironed and led away to another cell, to await trial for the
                  killing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE TRIAL.</head>
               <p>THE prison Surgeon was sent to the cell of our heroine to examine her injury. He
                  found that the point of the bayonet had penetrated the flesh nearly half an inch,
                  inflicting a painful, though not dangerous wound. And he was unreserved in his
                  condemnation of the brute who had done such a cowardly deed to a female, no matter
                  who or what she might be. As he was engaged in dressing the wound, the copy of
                  Wenonah's letter to Lieutenant Haskins fell to the floor, and, led by curiosity,
                  the Surgeon read it.</p>
               <p>"Do you know Lieutenant Haskins?" inquired he, in surprise.</p>
               <p>"Ah!" murmured Wenonah, in a faint voice. "He has been more than a brother to me
                  and, if he would only come, he would tell you that some enemy of the poor Indian
                  girl has laid this as a trap for her feet! He would not have signed his name to
                  that hand-bill."</p>
               <p>"Oh! I see your mistake!" exclaimed the Surgeon. "The Haskins whose name is
                  attached to that hand-bill you speak of, is cousin to Lieutenant Haskins who is
                  now at Savannah. Their names are the same exactly; but the younger one has,
                  through the influence of the other, lately obtained a position in the Adjutant's
                  office, connected with the Army of Northern Georgia. The accusation against you
                  must have been made by some person to him, and he, on the instant, issued the
                  hand-bills. However, with Lieutenant Haskins for your friend, I've no doubt you
                  would stand a good chance of escape, were it not for letting this said carrier
                  pigeon loose after your arrest."</p>
               <p>"Oh, my poor pet, it will never come back to me!" moaned Wenonah, as though in the
                  deepest distress about the loss of the bird. "It's very hard that all this cruelty
                  has been done to me, because my dear little pet has flown away."</p>
               <p>"Well, tell me truly, now," said the Surgeon, in a tone that left a doubt in the
                  mind of our heroine, whether he was deceiving, or asked the<pb n="46-47"
                     xml:id="VAC5564-00000017"/> question from mere curiosity, "did you send any
                  dispatch to any one by that bird. They are almost certain it came from your
                  window, and although the Commandant did not see it himself, he has sent for the
                  soldier who arrested you, in hopes that he may be able to tell something definite
                  about the affair."</p>
               <p>"How could I, kind sir, do that? I have neither paper—save that dear letter—nor
                  pencil about me!"</p>
               <p>The spy spoke the truth, for she had hastily chewed and swallowed the inch of lead
                  pencil with which she had indited the dispatch, immediately after the flight of
                  the dove. This was, in connection with other facts, a most lucky circumstance, as
                  the sequel will show.</p>
               <p>The Surgeon did not remain longer, but soon took his departure, assuring Wenonah
                  that she should be made as comfortable as possible.</p>
               <p>On the following day the Commandant sent an officer to the cell of our heroine, to
                  bring her to a more convenient apartment, where she found several Confederate
                  officers sitting as a court to try her for the offence of being a "spy in the
                  employment of the United States Government." She was arraigned, and a tedious
                  formal string of charges and specifications read to her. Several of these she knew
                  to have been manufactured specially against her, from the fact that the acts to
                  which they related had never been done.</p>
               <p>In this she gained composure and strength, and determined to allow her foes to
                  advance every point they could, before she made any defence. So with a quiet
                  serenity upon her features, though she keenly watched each development of the
                  case, Wenonah sat and listened to her accusers.</p>
               <p>"What have you to say to these heavy charges? You had better confess the truth,
                  and tell us the matter of the dispatches you sent to General Sherman. You see all
                  is known, that is, the facts that you are a spy, and that you twice sent
                  dispatches to our enemies!"</p>
               <p>This exhortation was addressed to Wenonah, by the officer who acted as
                  Judge-Advocate but she refused to say anything until the whole case was closed
                  against her.</p>
               <p>The witnesses for the Government (Confederate) were accordingly called.</p>
               <p>Robert Martin, first.</p>
               <p>
                  <emph>Robert Martin</emph>! As this name fell upon her ear, a feeling of horror
                  and almost despair took possession of our spy, but passed away in an instant, so
                  that when that villain entered the room from a side door, not the slightest
                  emotion appeared on Wenonah's features. But one of deep disappointment sprang to
                  those of Martin, who, seeing this unexpected firmness on the part of her whom, by
                  his presence alone he expected to crush, could not control himself.</p>
               <p>However, upon taking the stand, he testified to having seen Wenonah at General
                  Sherman's head-quarters, and not only this, but a long rigmarole fabricated by
                  himself for the occasion.</p>
               <p>The next witness was the soldier by whom Wenonah had been arrested. He testified
                  to the fact of the dove having been in the possession of the Indian girl. A woman
                  employed in the jail testified that when she searched the captive she found
                  nothing but the copy of the letter to Lieutenant Haskins, no cipher, no ink, no
                  pen, not even a pencil.</p>
               <p>"Bill" was the last witness, and he swore that he had stood guard over the
                  prisoner from the moment she had entered the cell, until ordered under arrest by
                  his officer, for killing the soldier who had wounded the Indian girl. He had not
                  seen the slightest thing that would lead him to suppose that our heroine had been
                  writing a dispatch. And he was too chivalrously inclined to Wenonah to mention the
                  incident of her hanging shawl before the door. Besides, the Court, who seemed to
                  think that "Bill" was rather friendly to the handsome captive, had strictly
                  cautioned him not to express any opinion, but merely to answer the questions it
                  might ask him.</p>
               <p>The only man who could have testified to actually seeing a folded note attached to
                  the carrier dove, was the outside guard, posted immediately near Wenonah's cell,
                  and he, as the reader is aware, was dead. The Commandant, however, took the stand,
                  and swore to having heard the dead man mention the fact. After a consultation the
                  Court decided to exclude this, as it already had sufficient evidence to convict
                  the prisoner.</p>
               <p>This exceedingly generous decision of course failed to excite within Wenonah any
                  feeling but one of disgust for the rebel Court.</p>
               <p>"Well, girl," said the Judge-Advocate, when the case for the Government had
                  closed, "what have you to say now?"</p>
               <p>There was a look of triumphant satisfaction upon the features of the rebel
                  official as he asked this question, which merely changed to one of semi-derision
                  as the spy answered:</p>
               <p>"I have only this to say, that nearly all that has been said against me by Robert
                  Martin is false, and that part which is true, I am ready to prove, if you will
                  allow me time, would not convict me of the offence with which I am charged.</p>
               <p>Would I have arrested that man and brought him back to trial, had I been a Union
                  spy? would I not rather have helped him to escape to the Federal camp to which I
                  found him flying? It is true that he did see me at General Sherman's
                  head-quarters. But the way in which I went there was because I was taken prisoner
                  by the Union Cavalry, and forced to go to General Sherman, who endeavors to find
                  out by prisoners what is going on in the Confederate army. If the Court will but
                  give me time to send to Lieutenant Haskins, at Savannah, he will come and tell you
                  that I speak the truth."</p>
               <pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC5564-00000018"/>
               <p>"Lift'nt Haskins! the d—l! is he alive!" exclaimed Bob Martin, the witness, who
                  had managed to escape from General Sherman's guard-house. From thence he had made
                  his way through the army lines, hoping to obtain his own pardon for the services
                  he could do to the rebel government, in denouncing our heroine, and giving, to
                  some extent, the strength and position of the Federal army. In an account of the
                  action in which Wenonah had been captured, he had seen Haskin's name among the
                  killed, and as the latter disliked him very much, he felt safe that he was out of
                  the road. Now, therefore, that he found him to be yet alive, he gave himself up
                  for a doomed man, and it was this that caused him to make the exclamation. Wenonah
                  took instant advantage of it, and sprang to her feet with the words:</p>
               <p>"See how the double-tongued fox crouches like a dog; see how he shakes, and how
                  fear makes his face lose its blood!"</p>
               <p>Furtively, anxiously Martin glanced at the doors and windows of the apartment, and
                  seeing an opportunity, bounded from his seat toward an open window. Ere any one
                  could stop him he had gained the sill, and in a twinkling more would have
                  disappeared. But at this moment the strong arm of "Bill," the other witness,
                  grasped him and jerked, him with merciless violence back into the room. Desperate
                  with fear, however, Martin closed with his captor, bit and tore at him like a wild
                  beast.</p>
               <p>Bill, however, beside being a powerful man, was a most determined one, and taking
                  his man by the throat, he rained upon his face and head heavy and continuous
                  blows. This soon had the desired effect, and Martin sunk down exhausted and
                  terrified. In a moment he was in charge of a guard, who received orders not to let
                  him escape. They accordingly placed him in double irons, and so confined him that
                  a repetition of his escape would be impossible.</p>
               <p>When the Court resumed its quiet, one of the officers composing it remarked to his
                  immediate companion:</p>
               <p>"Well, I never saw anything so curious in my life."</p>
               <p>"Nor I," was the rejoinder. "There's something wrong somewhere."</p>
               <p>This unexpected scene did more to benefit our heroine's cause than anything else
                  that could have happened, and the Court at last determined to remand Wenonah to
                  jail, until Lieutenant Haskins could be heard from, which was accordingly
                  done.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
               <head type="sub">FALLING IN LOVE WITH A FOE.</head>
               <p>THE spy was kept rigorously confined to her prison for nearly a week after the
                  trial, and was beginning to devise some mode by which she might escape and return
                  to General Sherman. Had she been assured in her own mind that the carrier dove had
                  reached its destination safely, she would have experienced no anxiety concerning
                  her own fate. But, alas! in regard to this point there was a dreadful doubt, for
                  although she was certain the bird had not been found, still it might have been so
                  badly wounded as to perish.</p>
               <p>One afternoon, as she was revolving the matter in her mind, she heard some person
                  coming toward her little, narrow room, and while she intently listened, who should
                  appear before her door but Lieutenant Haskins himself.</p>
               <p>"Oh, my brother! you have come! I knew you would come!" exclaimed Wenonah,
                  springing to the rebel officer, who embraced the Indian girl, as though she really
                  had been his sister.</p>
               <p>"Why, Wenonah, what is all this I hear? You a spy for Sherman! tell me all! Guard
                  just close that door ajar; I wish to speak in private with the prisoner. Now then,
                  Wenonah," continued Haskins, drawing the spy to a chair, and the seating himself
                  beside her on the stool, "I have come specially to see you through this trouble,
                  though I had most important duties to perform. So do not conceal aught, no matter
                  how trivial, from me. There is on the part of some persons here a great bitterness
                  against you, while there are a few who are in your favor."</p>
               <p>Wenonah, in reply, gave to her companion a full history of herself from the time
                  she was captured up to the present moment. She took good care, however, to so
                  shape the story, that even the most suspicious portions of it did not militate
                  against herself.</p>
               <p>"But the carrier pigeon and the dispatch," resumed Haskins, there seems to be the
                  most trouble about that."</p>
               <p>"Oh! my brother!" exclaimed Wenonah, with admirably feigned grief, "that was only
                  my pet. Everybody saw me have it. I had it when the soldiers seized me. True, when
                  I saw the officer who rules, here, he looked so fierce and cruel that I was afraid
                  he would take my pet away, and I hid it till I got to this room. By chance the
                  window as open, and the dove quickly flew away."</p>
               <p>"But the note, the dispatch," said Haskins; as our heroine paused.</p>
               <p>He spoke eagerly, as one in fear of discovering an unpleasant truth.</p>
               <pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC5564-00000019"/>
               <p>"If I had had all the materials for writing," rejoined the spy, gazing up into the
                  face of her interrogator, "how could I have written a dispatch, and when I was
                  searched immediately after, I had not even a lead pencil about me."</p>
               <p>Haskins continued the conversation for at least half an hour longer, and yet so
                  well did the Indian maintain the part she had assumed that he was unable to detect
                  the slightest flaw in her narrative.</p>
               <p>"Well, dearest Wenonah," said he, when he rose to depart, "to-night the Court will
                  sit, and I will clear you of the charge. And, in addition, I will see that Martin
                  gets his just deserts. He will not again escape. My cousin is too inexperienced in
                  his duties, and rashly zealous. Else he would not have issued that silly
                  hand-bill. But when you are free again you must be very circumspect, for the
                  Government has a host of detectives, and if you should do the smallest act that
                  looked suspicious, all the help that I could render would avail you nothing."</p>
               <p>Wenonah made no reply in words, but leaned her head on the rebel Lieutenant's
                  shoulder and wept.</p>
               <p>A few hours later our heroine was once more brought before the Court, and—as
                  Haskins had told her she would be—was acquitted of the charges preferred against
                  her. From the court-room the spy was taken by her rescuer to the house of a
                  friend, and there took place a long conversation, during which it was agreed that
                  Wenonah should go to the house of a relative of Haskins, on the line between
                  Gilmer and Fannin counties, Georgia.</p>
               <p>"But," objected Wenonah at first, "that is very close to the Federal army."</p>
               <p>"Ah! Wenonah," was the reply, "that is the safest spot in the whole country, and
                  I'll tell you why. From the nature of the position I now hold, I know all or
                  nearly all the military movements that are about to take place. Sherman will be
                  effectually kept still, exactly where he is, while all the active operations of
                  the war will occur in the East. And I would not have harm come to you for all the
                  world, for as I once loved you with only an impure, transient love, so now I love
                  you, as Heaven is my judge, with the holiest emotions of the heart. Just at this
                  juncture I can say no more, but I will see you soon again, and I shall then ask
                  you something which you must not deny me. In the meantime, endeavor, if you can,
                  to learn to—love me. No! no! do not advance excuse nor objection," continued
                  Haskins, as Wenonah starting back, commenced to speak, "I would not lightly say
                  what I have, and I wish you to do—or at least to try to do as I ask."</p>
               <p>Wenonah would again have attempted a reply, but in the very act a feeling took
                  possession of her that caused her to remain silent.</p>
               <p>"Will you promise me," asked Haskins, taking the Indian girl's hand in his, "will
                  you promise me to try?"</p>
               <p>"I will," replied the spy, after a lengthy pause.</p>
               <p>"Good night, then, and God bless you, dearest Wenonah."</p>
               <p>A moment, a kiss, and the lover was gone, leaving our heroine with feelings so
                  new, and so utterly indescribable, that she was astounded at herself. For some
                  time she paced the chamber to which she was afterward shown by a servant,
                  endeavoring to calm, and, if possible, analyze her mind.</p>
               <p>"Surely am I what the pale faces call in love? Oh, no! and yet what else can this
                  strange feeling be! Yes, yes, it must be so, I am in love! in love, too, with an
                  enemy of the holy cause in which I am laboring with so much zeal! What shall I do?
                  Oh! treacherous heart!"</p>
               <p>Wenonah threw herself on the bed, where she tossed and rolled for many hours, a
                  prey to conflicting emotions. When or how she fell asleep she knew not, but she
                  did not awaken until some one knocked at her chamber door, and asked if she were
                  sick, as the sun had been up so long.</p>
               <p>No sooner was she roused than the singular feelings of the previous night
                  returned. But now the Indian summoned all the resolution of her race, and
                  endeavored to banish them, and think only of her duty. So far as preventing her
                  newly-awakened affection from interfering with the latter, she was successful. But
                  the total oblivion she sought was impossible to find. And though an enemy, yet was
                  Lieutenant Haskins become the dearest being on earth to the Indian girl. Thus
                  passing strange are the workings of the human heart.</p>
               <p>On the same day, at about ten o'clock, Lieutenant Haskins came to bid Wenonah good
                  bye, before she set forward on her journey. He would gladly have accompanied her
                  himself, had not his duties imperatively interfered.</p>
               <p>"Shall I see you soon again, Alfred? It will seem very long without you."</p>
               <p>The tones in which Wenonah spoke were this time unassumed, and there was no
                  deception in the way in which she clung to her rebel lover. She would have spoken
                  to him about the high-born pale face maiden to whom she knew him to have been
                  betrothed, but she feared to do so.</p>
               <p>"No, dearest Wenonah, I shall not remain long from you, and when I see you again I
                  have so much to tell you; but not now. I must go now. Good bye. God bless
                  you."</p>
               <p>Half an hour later several leagues separated the two—and each moment increased the
                  distance, as Wenonah and Haskins were borne swiftly along to their respective
                  destinations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC5564-00000020"/>
               <head>CHAPTER IX.</head>
               <head type="sub">WHAT BECAME OF THE CARRIER DOVE.</head>
               <p>IN due time the spy reached the mansion of the friend to whose guardianship her
                  lover had desired to commit her. She proved to be a maiden aunt of Haskins', named
                  Miss Leonora Anderson, a warm-hearted lady, happily unafflicted with the usual
                  proclivities of that class of ladies vulgarly called "old maids." But she was a
                  most dreadfully bitter rebel, a failing that rendered her peculiarly odious to our
                  heroine, who, however, to serve her own purpose, pretended to coincide in all her
                  violent opinions, among which was a gentle one relative to all abominable Yankee
                  spies, namely—that they should be partially hung, then partially roasted by slow
                  fire, then lashed to four wild horses and torn apart.</p>
               <p>Leonora at short intervals visited General Johnson's army, carrying with her
                  garments, books, sweetmeats, and everything she could think of for the comfort of
                  the rebel soldiers. It so fell out that within a day or two of the arrival of our
                  heroine, she had prepared for one of these journeys. By the latter she was
                  entreated to go at once, instead of waiting longer, and to allow her the pleasure
                  of accompanying her. Of course Miss Leonora was delighted with her nephew's
                  protege, and decided to set off on her mission at once.</p>
               <p>In due time the camp of General Johnson was reached, and the distribution
                  commenced. "Miss Wenonah," as the rebel lady called her, expressed the most
                  romantic desire to ride out with some of the dashing and youthful gray-clad
                  officers, to view the Yankee positions, and, in company with three or four of
                  them, she dashed off on horseback, leaving her <foreign xml:lang="FRA">soi <choice>
                        <sic>distant</sic>
                        <corr>disant</corr>
                     </choice>
                  </foreign> aunt to visit the camp hospitals.</p>
               <p>The spy was a perfect equestriene, and against all remonstrances selected for her
                  ride a magnificent, blooded stallion, which everybody feared to mount. After a few
                  vicious efforts to free himself, however, the animal submitted to his new
                  mistress, and cantered away on his journey.</p>
               <p>The spruce chevaliers vied with each other in being polite to their lovely and
                  bewitching companion. One pointed out this position, another that position in the
                  Federal army, and each desired that Miss Wenonah should honor <emph>his</emph>
                  field glass by looking through it at the vile Yankees. Miss Wenonah felt deeply
                  obliged to all of them, magnanimously looked through every glass, and from the
                  inspection felt sure of being able to accomplish the desperate role she had
                  determined to play, and which was as follows:</p>
               <p>In the midst of a hearty laugh, caused by a joke of the Indian spy's, she adroitly
                  thrust a sharp thorn into her stallion's back. Instantly the animal reared, and
                  then, with a loud neigh, dashed away like a whirlwind, directly towards the
                  Federal lines.</p>
               <p>Wenonah, as though in an agony of fright, screamed wildly for help, and allowed
                  herself to slip nearly altogether down on the side of the flying steed. This act,
                  though perfectly easy of accomplishment to our heroine, seemed so terrific in the
                  eyes of her rebel chevaliers, that they stood completely transfixed with
                  horror.</p>
               <p>It did not take very long, at the speed at which the stallion galloped, to carry
                  our spy through the Union picket lines, after passing which, a convenient ridge
                  presently intervened between her and the Confederate vision. With some little
                  trouble and exertion she now managed to rein in the stallion, and render him
                  tractable, by which time she was taken in charge by a Federal cavalryman, who had
                  pursued her. She inquired for General Sherman's head-quarters, but they were too
                  far away for her for her to think of going thither, and she, therefore, requested
                  to be taken to the officer of the nearest signal station. At first the man
                  demurred, but finding the spy so urgent, he at length consented.</p>
               <p>Upon reaching the station, Wenonah sent the message she desired to General
                  Sherman, in the cipher he and she had adopted, so that the signal officer himself
                  did not know its import. A reply came promptly that the carrier dove had returned
                  safely to its home in Chattanooga, bearing, however, the mark of ball-graze on one
                  wing. The dispatch had been obtained, and was eminently satisfactory. After a
                  further exchange of messages, one came from General Sherman, directing the officer
                  to have our heroine passed back at once through the lines, under flag of truce,
                  with the message to General Johnson that, as Miss Wenonah <emph>Anderson</emph>
                  had become an involuntary prisoner, through the running away of her horse, it gave
                  General Sherman pleasure to allow her to return. This ruse was well played, and
                  our heroine was soon restored to the arms of her adopted aunt, who lectured her
                  somewhat sharply though, or being so incautious as to place herself in such
                  perilous proximity to the vile Yankee vandals.</p>
               <p>A happier being never existed than our heroine; the fearful suspense under which
                  she had existed so long, in regard to the real fate of the carrier dove, was
                  removed, for in that little note it carried so faithfully, was the doom of
                  Johnson's army, and the Confederacy. But ever and anon came over her, like a cloud
                  in the midst of this sunshine, her love for the rebel Haskins. Oh, how she labored
                  to shake this from her. How she strove to teach her heart to forget him. It was
                  impossible, and each passing hour only served to strengthen her new-born
                  affection.</p>
               <p>Wenonah's rebel lover must have been fully as much affected, if not more so, than
                  the Indian girl, for a fortnight did not elapse from the time he bade her adieu,
                  ere he came to his aunt's house on a visit, having<pb n="54-55"
                     xml:id="VAC5564-00000021"/> obtained a leave of absence. If our heroine's
                  affection was strong before his coming, it was now intense.</p>
               <p>One afternoon, as they both sat beneath a wide-spreading tree on the lawn, where
                  no ear could listen to their converse, Haskins made the following confession to
                  the spy. Said he:</p>
               <p>"Dearest Wenonah, I have long been very unhappy, and I see but one way to free
                  myself of it. Believe me it is not in regard to Miss Burton, to whom, as you are
                  aware, I was betrothed. Though we liked each other as youthful friends, yet she
                  never loved me as well as another, nor did I love her. Our projected union was
                  more a business matter, arranged between our families than anything else, and we
                  were both glad to rid ourselves of our mutual obligations. It is another subject
                  that makes me feel so badly. I know I can trust you with the heavy secret. I have
                  no heart with this rebellion, and never had ; but I was forced into it, as it
                  were, by circumstances by which my relatives surrounded me, and every time I have
                  gone into battle, I have looked upon myself as a contemptible traitor, and the
                  moment I have seen the old flag, my soul has died within me, and I could not lift
                  my hand against it. I would have gone over to the Federal cause long since; but
                  still that seems wrong also, after I have sworn myself to the Confederate
                  Government. Oh! sometimes I feel as though I ought to go and hang myself, as Judas
                  did."</p>
               <p>"Alfred, dear Alfred," rejoined Wenonah, after a short pause, and gazing earnestly
                  up into her lover's face, "you have confided in me, will you let me confide in
                  you, and promise me, by the Great Spirit above us, never to speak again to human
                  ear what I tell you?"</p>
               <p>"God judge between us, dearest. What you may say will be as safe with me as in the
                  grave."</p>
               <p>"Then," said the Indian, "I love the cause you are at enmity with. I have served
                  it, and so faithfully that ere another moon shall come the rebellion will receive
                  a blow from which it will die. Do not doubt me! Even now your Army of Northern
                  Georgia is at the mercy of General Sherman, and cannot save itself; and before the
                  moon is full, the feet of his horses will trample down the corn around Atlanta,
                  and the bayonets of his soldiers will shine in your roads like streams of water
                  coming down from the mountains. The Union eagle is in the air, and your
                  Confederacy is his prey!"</p>
               <p>While speaking, the spy becoming rapt in her subject, rose to her feet, and seemed
                  the impersonation of a sacred prophetess.</p>
               <p>For several minutes Haskins remained dumbfounded, and then said:</p>
               <p>"Dearest Wenonah, I thought so! I thought so! But hush, for the very wind has
                  ears. If Sherman moves at all, he must go to Savannah. I shall return thither
                  to-morrow, and await the final combat—"</p>
               <p>"No, no, dearest Alfred," interrupted Wenonah, "come with me. I will guide you
                  through the Federal lines, and General Sherman will pardon you."</p>
               <p>"Ah, that could never be, Wenonah," exclaimed Haskins, bitterly. "Oh, no much as I
                  love you, I could never, not even for you, do that. No! no! my plan is formed.
                  I'll earn my pardon like a man of honor. When Sherman nears Savannah, I will throw
                  up my commission, tell my superiors I intend to fight against them; then mount my
                  horse and join Sherman. Nothing will I betray; but in the thickest of the fight
                  I'll seek my pardon with my sabre. And if I fall, Wenonah, bear me in your memory
                  as an erring, justly punished man. Nay! nay! do not speak against it. Thus will I
                  make myself worthy of my country, and of you, or die while making the effort.
                  Come, let us go back to the house, my aunt is watching us."</p>
               <p>Slowly and silently the lovers returned to the mansion, each the prey of emotions
                  that could find no adequate expression in words.</p>
               <p>The day following, according to his determination, Haskins bade Wenonah farewell,
                  after a mutual pledge that if both lived, they should be united in that bond which
                  no tribunal but Heaven's can rightfully dissever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER X.</head>
               <head type="sub">THRILLING ADVENTURES.</head>
               <p>IMMEDIATELY after the departure of her affianced lover, our heroine redoubled her
                  vigilance in the performance of her perilous duties. As she had predicted, so it
                  happened, that at the time she mentioned to Haskins, Sherman's cavalry swept round
                  Atlanta.</p>
               <p>From that point up to the fall of Savannah, the reader is already too familiar
                  with Sherman's grand march, to require any description at our hands. Suffice it to
                  say, that amidst unparalleled dangers and perplexities, Wenonah, the Indian spy,
                  continued to serve the Union cause faithfully, and fully realized her own
                  expression to General Sherman, that she would be his eye to him. Back and forth
                  between the two armies she constantly hovered, and on many occasions narrowly
                  escaped capture and death.</p>
               <p>Once, when the advancing army had passed Macon and Milledgeville, on its march to
                  the sea, Wenonah had just left General Slocum's column a few miles to the rear,
                  when, as she was passing through a piece of dense forest, her attention was
                  attracted by the yells and curses of two men, and sharp cracking or snapping, as
                  of gun caps. Her curiosity<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC5564-00000022"/> was so excited
                  that she could not refrain from making her way to a spot from which she could see
                  what was going on.</p>
               <p>Doing so, she beheld two men, one of whom she recognized as "Bill," the
                  Confederate soldier who had so well befriended her once, and the other proved to
                  be another of the three by whom she had been arrested when near Macon. Both were
                  armed with long stock-whips, such as Australian herdsmen use with such fearful
                  effect and dexterity upon their droves of semi-wild cattle.<ref rend="super"
                     target="#note_003" xml:id="return_003">*</ref>
                  
               </p>
               <p>Both men were bleeding, while their rough clothing was cut all over as with sharp
                  knives. For a moment or two such a strange combat prevented Wenonah from
                  interfering, through very astonishment. Then, uttering a cry, however, and
                  stepping out from her concealment, she confronted both fighters, who, thus
                  unexpectedly surprised, desisted from their bloody work.</p>
               <p>"Why, Miss Wenonah!" exclaimed Bill, between the hard, quick breaths his pain and
                  previous exertions forced him to draw, "who'd a bet a mule—on seein' you
                  here?—Why—ter tell you—true, this here —fight wuz 'bout you—. Yer see we both got
                  'moted ter be army drovyers, an' jest 'while ago we begun torkin' 'bout you—an'
                  jest as is allers the way when two—fellers tork 'bout a gal—fust thing we know'd,
                  we wuz at it hot an' heavy."</p>
               <p>"Then be friends again, for my sake," replied Wenonah, in conciliating tones.</p>
               <p>"In course we will! won't we, Ned?" exclaimed Bill, thrusting out his great paw to
                  his foeman, who took it good-naturedly, and made up, and in a minute more both
                  were laughing and talking as though nothing had ever rippled their friendship.</p>
               <p>During the conversation that followed this adventure, our spy learned that the two
                  drovers were to take two hundred head of beeves across the country, to a certain
                  point, at which it was supposed they would be safe. She quickly decided on her
                  course. Informing her companions that the Yankee cavalry had gone off in that
                  direction, she advised them to get the cattle up the road as quickly as possible,
                  and she would show them a by-lane by which they could get round the raiders
                  without danger. Suspecting nothing, the drovers gladly consented, and rode back
                  with the spy until, unwittingly, they found themselves within half a mile of
                  Slocum's wing.</p>
               <p>Just as they discovered this disagreeable fact, the spy, having quietly drawn a
                  revolver, shot down both their horses, and then commanded them, under pain of
                  instant death, to surrender.</p>
               <note place="foot" xml:id="note_003">
                  
                  <p><ref target="#return_003">*</ref>These whips are sometimes fifteen and twenty feet long, formed of plaited
                     hide, thickening in the middle and tapering up and down like a serpent. The
                     handle is not over eighteen or twenty inches long, and is formed of tough
                     hickory. The lash is of silk or silver wire, and so terrible a weapon is it
                     in skilful hands, that the most ferocious bull will fly from it in
                     terror.</p>
               </note>
               <p>There was no help for the prisoners, and, with the best grace they were capable
                  of, they obeyed, and were marched into the Federal camp, where Wenonah obtained
                  for them, however, far better treatment than they could have expected, though she
                  insisted on their escape being made impossible. This was promptly attended to, as
                  was also the herd of cattle, to which Wenonah guided a detachment of Federal
                  cavalry. The spy felt sorry to make a captive of poor Bill, who had so warmly
                  befriended her, and she felt still more so, that she could not explain the reason
                  to him. However, he seemed rather to like being made a prisoner, and he afterwards
                  declared that he would not attempt to escape, even if the way had been left open
                  for him to do so.</p>
               <p>From the locality in which this adventure occurred, the Indian girl rapidly pushed
                  on in advance of the Union army, which was now marching to Savannah, at a quick
                  rate, though it threatened several other places, so as to keep the enemy separated
                  as widely as possible.</p>
               <p>Her next adventure, worth recording, happened at the town of Abbeville, on the
                  Ocmulgee river. In this place there chanced to be two Arkansas men who, having had
                  considerable experience as trappers and hunters in the Far West, recognized the
                  costume worn by our heroine as belonging to, and being used only by a tribe of
                  Indians who were friendly to the Federal cause. And they at once seized Wenonah,
                  and accused her being a spy for the Yankees. It was useless for her to protest or
                  to ask for a respite, or to plead the name of Lieutenant Haskins, with her brutal
                  captors; and the latter were speedily joined by the people of the place, many of
                  whom hearing fearful, and, of course, lying accounts of Sherman's ravages, the
                  burning of Atlanta, and a hundred other atrocities, longed for a victim to sate
                  their imagined injuries.</p>
               <p>Wenonah, finding all her efforts useless, gave up, or rather pretended to do so,
                  watching an opportunity continually, however, to make an attempt to escape. Her
                  tormentors obtained a particularly vicious mule and forced her to mount it without
                  a saddle, and ride before them up and down several roads, jeered, insulted and
                  pelted by the mob. As whisky began to be passed about, the passions of the vile
                  wretches began to be influenced, and just as the sun was setting, a cry was raised
                  to hang the Yankee spy. The cry at once rose to a perfect yell of</p>
               <p>"Hang her! hang her!"</p>
               <p>In an instant a noosed rope was cast about Wenonah's neck, and the mule was urged
                  at the top of its speed toward the river bank, where grew some trees convenient
                  for the hellish intention. The river! ah, there lay the only avenue of escape for
                  our poor spy. Fortunately her captors had not disarmed her of her trusty revolver.
                  Commending herself<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC5564-00000023"/> self to the Great
                  Spirit, she summoned all her nerve and determination for one desperate effort for
                  liberty.</p>
               <p>She was off the mule close under the fatal tree, between which and the water there
                  was not more than half a rod.</p>
               <p>"Hip! hip! up with her!" shouted the mob.</p>
               <p>At this moment the spy whipped out her revolver, and quick as lightening sent a
                  ball through the bodies of her two Arkansas executioners, who fell dead or dying
                  at her feet. The next instant the halter was torn from her neck, and the next she
                  was in the river, swimming underneath its surface with the celerity of an otter,
                  down stream; nor did she rise for air until she was nearly suffocated.</p>
               <p>Her action had been so rapid as to throw a spell of helplessness upon the mob,
                  which did not rush forward until she had risen to the top of the water.
                  Consequently the shots that greeted her were so wildly aimed that she remained
                  unharmed.</p>
               <p>Twice again was she forced to rise and be fired upon, ere she gained the friendly
                  shelter of a strip of marsh. She did not remain here, however, beyond nightfall,
                  for as soon as it was dark she again took to the water, and swam quietly across
                  the river. Next striking through the woods, she hastened on in a North-easterly
                  direction, confident that her pursuers would search for her in an opposite one. To
                  have stopped to wring the water from her saturated clothing, would have been a
                  waste of precious time, so our heroine strode forward with all her strength, and
                  did not halt until sunrise, by which time she had placed many a mile between
                  herself and her enemies. She found hundreds, white and black, flying in terror
                  before the advance of Sherman's army, and this fact proved of inestimable service
                  to her, for when all was disorder and fright, her condition could excite no
                  suspicion.</p>
               <p>Turning aside into a field in which stood some negro quarters, Wenonah, who was
                  excessively fatigued, took shelter in the most remote hut, and there, undisturbed
                  by any one, she slumbered for several hours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER XI.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE SPY'S RETURN TO SHERMAN.</head>
               <p>WHEN she awoke she was much refreshed, though her limbs were stiff and she was in
                  considerable pain. Looking out, she found that no one was on the road, as the
                  fugitives had hurried along without a halt. She, therefore, walked out to the
                  road, and crossing it, went on up through the woods, hoping every moment to fall
                  in with Sherman's cavalry. In her hope, however, she was disappointed, and after
                  wandering thus for some hours past noon, she finally resolved to make her way to
                  Savannah, to her affianced lover, Lieutenant Haskins, and she had just turned her
                  face in that direction, when she noticed a squad of horsemen coming down the road,
                  who proved to be Federals. From them she learned that General Sherman was with the
                  column behind, and two of them volunteered to take her back. Horses were not to be
                  had, so one of the men dismounted and walked, while Wenonah rode. In a
                  comparatively short time our heroine was once again in the presence of General
                  Sherman, who greeted her with the warmest expressions of thanks and friendship,
                  and would have loaded her with presents had she not positively refused.</p>
               <p>"I have a new Corps in my army," said the General, in the course of conversation,
                  with a smile, "which I think I shall name in your honor."</p>
               <p>"What is it, General?"</p>
               <p>"It is two carrier doves whose cote is in Washington. To-morrow, by noon; the
                  first one will be let go, and the other will be detained with me till I reach the
                  ocean, and can send an olive branch in its beak. By the by, you shall with your
                  own hands dispatch the first, and if you keep near me, the second also; for your
                  bravery, integrity and patriotism justly entitle you to the honor."</p>
               <p>"Thanks! thanks! General," replied Wenonah, "the first I will, but the second I
                  may not!"</p>
               <p>"Why?"</p>
               <p>The spy, in answer, imparted to General Sherman, like a child, confiding in a
                  beloved father, the whole history of her association with Lieutenant Haskins.</p>
               <p>"He is a noble fellow, a true-hearted man and soldier. He has my respect and my
                  influence for his pardon. He should have the last for your asking alone. However,
                  you must not again risk your life, by attempting to reach Savannah. By the service
                  you have already done me, I have been enabled to come thus far; with but a small
                  loss in men and material, and the rest of the way is easy. I do not think there
                  will be a battle at Savannah, and your lover will, therefore, meet with no harm,
                  while at the same time his notions of honor will be satisfied. You shall remain
                  with me until the consummation of our victory, which is not far off now."</p>
               <p>Wenonah's heart was too full for a reply to her generous and powerful friend, and
                  she, therefore, expressed her thanks as she had once before done, by kneeling
                  before Sherman, and placing his hands upon her head.</p>
               <p>At this moment General Sherman was summoned by on of his commanders to a certain
                  part of the line, where his personal inspection was<pb n="60-61"
                     xml:id="VAC5564-00000024"/> needed. So, with a hasty word of adieu to his
                  faithful spy, the hero of the Georgia march strode out of his tent, sprang to his
                  saddle, and galloped away.</p>
               <p>Now, that her services were no longer needed, our heroine's mind began to prey on
                  itself. The one great longing to see her lover, Lieutenant Haskins, grew more
                  intense and less bearable every hour. And her fear lest his resolution should
                  finally cause his death, became torture to her soul.</p>
               <p>Late in the afternoon General Sherman returned; and with smiles of gratification
                  he informed the spy that he wished her to let go the first carrier dove, in the
                  morning at sunrise, instead of at noon. Accordingly the succeeding day had
                  scarcely sent its gray light-shafts up the distant horizon, ere our spy was
                  stirring. Her eyes sparkled with delight, too, when General Sherman, after
                  securing his dispatch to General Grant about the neck of the bird, handed the
                  latter to her. As she took it, and felt the fluttering of its heart, she called to
                  memory the scene that occurred in Macon jail, when she gave liberty to the winged
                  messenger that carried her own dispatch to General Sherman. And the same words she
                  uttered on that occasion sprang to her lips now, as she unclasped her hand, and
                  cast the dove into the air.</p>
               <p>After circling a few times, the dove launched forth on its airy flight, and was
                  quickly lost to view in the morning haze, that hung like a pall above the face of
                  the country.</p>
               <p>"Now then, for the ocean!" exclaimed Sherman.</p>
               <p>In half an hour more all was bustle and activity, though not disorder. On the
                  contrary, the utmost precision was observed, so as to prevent the occurrence of
                  any accident that might mar success. Onward, ever onward, swept the grand army of
                  the Union, and its Commander was confident that within forty-eight hours, Grant's
                  Signal Officers would be waving the grand advance flags along the whole line of
                  the Army of the Potomac. How exhilarating were these thoughts, and how sturdily
                  tramped Slocum's and Howard's heroes, sending up from their feet the dense red and
                  yellow dust-clouds of Georgia soil. Still, however, there was danger, and not a
                  whit was discipline <choice>
                     <sic>relazed</sic>
                     <corr>relaxed</corr>
                  </choice>, for scouts brought in word that Johnson and Hardee were only awaiting
                  the appearance of Sherman; to annihilate him. Undismayed, however, the hero of
                  Georgia marched on, and in a short time had his right resting on the Ogeechee, and
                  his left on the Savannah river, a few miles above the doomed city. Here he quickly
                  perceived that Fort McAllister, which had once beaten off our gunboats, was the
                  key to the city, and he determined on its capture, sending Kilpatrick, meanwhile,
                  to the Southward, to communicate with the fleet.</p>
               <p>The honor of storming the position was awarded to General Hazen's Division, and
                  with alacrity these brave men started on their deadly mission. General Sherman
                  remained on the other side of the Ogeechee, and took post on the roof of a
                  building, to watch the final combat, distant two or three miles. In a short time
                  Sherman saw a column of smoke seaward, and exclaimed to General Howard: "There
                  comes a gunboat!". And true enough, the hull presently became visible. The
                  stillness, however, was unbroken, and continued so for more than half an hour,
                  when the guns of the fort opened, and Sherman knew that Hazen's skirmishers were
                  at work. Immediately afterward, and as Sherman was biting his lip with suspense,
                  up went Hazen's signal of investment and assault.</p>
               <p>"Ha! that's like it," smiled Sherman, straining his eyes through his field glass.
                  "What's that gunboat signal, Buckley?"</p>
               <p>"Dalghren wants to know if he can help, sir."</p>
               <p>"Help! yes; tell him to pitch in! Ha! there go the boys! I see their flags
                  advancing. Go in, boys! Not a waver in those lines! like a machine! Now, then, a
                  little quicker! quicker! quicker! Give 'em the prods! That's splendid! Ha! what's
                  that halt? No, no it's the parapet. Up it they go, and over it! One flag planted!
                  Hurrah for that! and another, and yet another! Splendid fellows! I'd like to strap
                  every shoulder there! The job's done! the fort's our own! thank God! Thank
                  God!"</p>
               <p>Springing down stairs, the elated Commander wrote a dispatch, and folded it. Till
                  this moment, in his excitement, he had forgotten his faithful spy, and was in the
                  very act of securing the dispatch to his last carrier dove, and letting the bird
                  go, when he recollected his promise.</p>
               <p>"Wenonah!" he called, "Wenonah! are you not here?"</p>
               <p>No voice replied, nor was the Indian girl any where to be seen, though the General
                  delayed the dismissal of the bird two or three minutes. Finding she was not at
                  hand, however, he gave the pigeon its freedom, with the significant words:</p>
               <p>"<emph>Grant</emph>, my compliments to Lee! Amen to victory!"</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CONCLUSION.</head>
               <p>BUT while we leave the dove winging its way to General Grant, and leave General
                  Sherman planning out his further advance, upon the same nap that lay on his table
                  when Wenonah first visited him, let us follow the footsteps of the devoted Indian
                  girl.</p>
               <p>Up to the time of the departure of General Hazen's storming division, Wenonah had
                  remained near General Sherman. But impressed suddenly by one of those mysterious
                  feelings with which Fate sometimes imbues<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC5564-00000025"/>
                  the human breast, she joined the column, and marched with it to the attack.</p>
               <p>All remonstrances were in vain, and, though the men by main force prevented her
                  going at first into the battle that ensued, yet, when the fray grew desperate, she
                  watched her opportunity, and ran to the extreme front, carrying with her a musket
                  and fixed bayonet that she snatched from the hands of a dying soldier.</p>
               <p>The closer the Federal line drew to the steep glacis of the rebel fort the more
                  furious did the battle become, and what, with the incessant rattling of musketry
                  and thundering of artillery, the very ground trembled, while the air was filled
                  with the flying death-missiles of foemen.</p>
               <p>Suddenly the rebels, who had hitherto kept to the shelter of their works, hurled a
                  column of determined men over the parapet, who rushed with hideous yells directly
                  at that part of the Federal line in which stood our heroine. The line there was
                  the thinnest, because the first standard was there, and had attracted the heaviest
                  fire of the enemy. Down went the Union standard-bearer; the flag was snatched from
                  his dying hands by a rebel soldier, who started for the rear, while his companions
                  pushed forward their own treasonable emblem. In a moment, however, the victorious
                  rebel who had taken the stars and stripes, fell dead, pierced by a ball from the
                  gun of the Indian spy, who, instantly leaping toward the rebel flag, shouted to
                  her companions:</p>
               <p>"Come on! if you are warriors, don't waver!"</p>
               <p>Like a lioness the dauntless girl charged the rebel guard, and had nearly reached
                  the standard-bearer, when she was confronted by a ferocious looking rebel, who,
                  parrying her thrusts with skill; laughed hideously, and shouted to his friends to
                  charge <choice>
                     <sic>th</sic>
                     <corr>the</corr>
                  </choice> d—d Yanks, and he'd take care of the "gal."</p>
               <p>Another yell was raised, the rebel column went forward and pushed back the
                  weakened Union line, while the combat still continued between our heroine and her
                  antagonist, who, finding himself growing tired, endeavored to rush upon his
                  victim, and wound or kill her.</p>
               <p>At this juncture a man, pale and bleeding from many a wound, rushed through the
                  Federal line, with a crimson sabre in his right hand, and something bound round
                  his left arm shield-wise.</p>
               <p>Without a halt or pause he charged straight at the advancing rebels, calling to
                  the Federals:</p>
               <p>"Why don't you fight! Forward; follow me like men!"</p>
               <p>The strength and fury of a dozen maniacs seemed to possess the new champion of the
                  stars and stripes, for none could stand before his tremendous blows.</p>
               <p>"Now's the chance—forward, in the name of God and your cause!" he shouted, and
                  with redoubled fury he rushed at the rebels.</p>
               <p>By this time the Union boys caught his fire, and amidst the wildest cheers and
                  yells of exultation, forward went Hazen's line. But the rebels were brave and
                  determined men, and the attack was met with considerable spirit.</p>
               <p>Suddenly the new champion beheld Wenonah, the Indian spy, still engaged in her
                  deadly combat. His pale face became like chalk and with a hoarse shriek, rather
                  than shout, he ran to her, and with a single blow of his sabre killed her
                  antagonist.</p>
               <p>His next act was to seize the rebel standard, and as he did so a panic came upon
                  the Confederates, and they fled in wild disorder, pursued closely by the boys in
                  blue, who, before their enemies could rally, went springing over the parapet into
                  the fort, and it was their own.</p>
               <p>The hero to whom was due this splendid deed was, as the reader may have already
                  suspected, none other than Lieutenant Haskins, the rebel lover of our heroine.
                  Poor, noble erring man! He had gloriously redeemed himself. But the performance of
                  the valorous act cost him dearly, for as he turned and pushed the captured flag
                  towards the dear idol of his heart, he sank dying at her feet.</p>
               <p>The battle was over, and no noise broke the quiet of the field, save the
                  occasional groaning of a wounded man, or some relief party shooting to their
                  comrades.</p>
               <p>One of these squads happened to come upon the spot where Haskins had fallen, and
                  as they gazed upon the scene, rough soldiers as they were, the tears sprang to
                  their eyes. Haskins was dead, while half reclining by him was Wenonah, who was
                  also evidently dying from her wounds. Ever and anon, as she grew weaker, she sank
                  down, but instantly raised on her elbow again, and smoothed the chestnut curls
                  back off the brow of the corpse.</p>
               <p>Ever and anon, too, she murmured "Alfred, dearest Alfred! You have earned your
                  pardon."</p>
               <p>A Surgeon being summoned, he examined Wenonah's injuries, and found them of such a
                  character as to preclude all idea of her recovery. The expiring maiden offered no
                  resistance, until, in the performance of his duty, the Surgeon began to dress her
                  wounds, when, however, she resolutely refused to allow him to proceed, exclaiming
                  that she did not wish to live, but to die there, where she was, by the side of her
                  betrothed. Finding her inexorable her discoverers were forced to permit the
                  wounded girl to have her own way, though two of them remained near her.</p>
               <p>The gentle wind from the sea set in at evening, making sad music among the bushes
                  and grass of the battlefield, a fitting vesper indeed for the passing soul of the
                  devoted, lovely young martyr, who had done her country such immeasurable service.
                  Poor child of the wilderness. Pure as the air of her prairie home, beautiful as
                  the rose, brave as the warrior from whom she was descended, and gentle as the
                  dove, she was passing away from earth and life.</p>
               <pb n="64" xml:id="VAC5564-00000026"/>
               <p>Now she could no longer raise herself, but with her beautiful face resting upon
                  the cheek of her dead lover, and her arm stretched over him, she lay calmly
                  awaiting death. That grim minister of eternity, at length came, and with a touch
                  of his mysterious wand released the soul of the noble, faithful maiden.</p>
               <p>"Alfred! I am coming!"</p>
               <p>A soldier who stood near at the time, afterwards averred that Wenonah said these
                  words, and something else, so low that he could not distinguish it, about
                  pardon.</p>
               <p>On searching Haskins, nothing was found upon him but a card with his own and
                  Wenonah's name written thereon, and though his uniform was of the rebel gray, yet
                  the burying party who took charge of his body, knowing that he had fought and died
                  so gloriously for the Union cause, bore him with tender respect to the grave which
                  they had dug wide enough for two bodies.</p>
               <p>By the merest chance, an officer mentioned the romantic incident the day following
                  to General Sherman, who was most deeply moved on hearing of the fate of his
                  faithful spy, and that of her erring, but repentant lover. And he made a special
                  visit to the island, and at his own expense caused the two mouldering bodies to
                  reinterred in a beautiful spot, which was marked, that at some future day he might
                  have a suitable monument erected over them.</p>
               <p>"For," said he, "such devotion and such repentance should never be allowed to be
                  forgotten."</p>
               <p>The spy had died for her country; her rebel lover had indeed earned his pardon,
                  and they now both sleep peacefully side by side. May Heaven's sunshine and rain
                  forever nurture the green grass and sweet wild flowers that cover their lonely
                  grave.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="advertisement">
            <head>THE SOLDIER'S CASKET.</head>
            <p>The Greatest Work of the Age,<lb/> Giving<lb/> The Brave Deeds of our Private
               Soldiers<lb/> As well as Officers<lb/> And an account of Serg't Willie Sherman,<lb/>
               Son of General Sherman.<lb/> Written by Mrs. Sherman.</p>
            <p>In Two Volumes, of nearly 400 pages each,<lb/> And each filled with Splendid
               Engravings,<lb/> Each Volume is complete in itself, and is<lb/> Bound in a<lb/>
               Magnificent Green and Gold Paper Cover.</p>
            <p>One Volume sent, post paid, for $1.50<lb/> Two Volumes " 3.00</p>
            <p>Agents wanted in every town.</p>
            <p>Address C. W. ALEXANDER, Publisher, Philadelphia, Pa.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
