<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
   xml:id="VAC5761">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Beautiful Jewess, Rachel Mendoza </title>
            <author>B. T.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC5761</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-0241</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                  copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction
                  project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                  University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is granted
                  to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                  contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                  educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                  inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University
                  Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
               Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The beautiful Jewess, Rachel Mendoza</title>
                  <author>B. T.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>39 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>E.E. Barclay</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Philadelphia </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1853">1853</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
               Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
               website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and has
               been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
               Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="spa">Spanish</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2000-10-06">Finished OCR, rough
            encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-08-24">Finished TEI encoding,
            proofreading, and final editing</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-04-22">Converted document from SGML to TEI
            P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-04-22">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents
            and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="illustrations">
            <pb n="Illustration (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC5761-00000001"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>"I PUSHED THE BODY IN THE GRAVE, WHEN, TURNING, I BEHELD THE GOOD CLERGYMAN,
                     HIS HANDS UPTURNED, AND HIS FACE WHITE WITH HORROR. 'CHARLES, CHARLES,' HE
                     FALTERED, 'YOUR BETROTHAL WITH RACHEL WAS THEN CEMENTED IN HUMAN BLOOD.' WITH
                     ONE BLOW I BEAT HIM TO THE EARTH WITH THE SHOVEL, AND LAID HIM IN THE GRAVE,
                     BESIDE THAT OF GABRIEL."</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>THE BEAUTIFUL JEWESS RACHEL MENDOZA,</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">HER LAMENTABLE CONNECTION WITH THE DARK AND EVENTFUL CAREER OF
                  CHARLES BERNARD OTHERWISE CALLED "PRINCE CHARLES."</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="desc">The late termination of whose adventures in Madrid, near the
                  Palace of the Queen, has created so much comment, and such intense interest in the
                  American press.</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="desc">Thousands throughout the United States are familiar with
                  portions of the career of "PRINCE CHARLES," but this narrative sets out in plain
                  colours his whole career; especially his connection with the rich and beautiful
                  Jewess, Rachel Mendoza, who only a year ago, mingled in the first circles of New
                  York.</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="desc">After relating his adventures in the United States, this
                  Narrative conducts us to Madrid, to the ROYAL COURT OF SPAIN REVEALING THE SECRETS
                  OF THE LIFE OF QUEEN ISABELLA.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>PHILADELPHIA:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>E. E. BARCLAY, 283 MARKET STREET.</publisher>
            </docImprint>
            <docDate when="1853">1853.</docDate>
         </titlePage>
         <pb n="0Illustration-7" xml:id="VAC5761-00000002"/>
         <div type="fly_title">
            <bibl>
               <edition>FROM A PORTRAIT. Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1853, by
                  B. B. BARCLAY, In the Office of the Clerk of the District Court for the Eastern
                  District of Pennsylvania.</edition>
            </bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <p>[The manner in which the present extraordinary narrative came into the hands of those
               who now make it public, can be explained in a few words. Last summer, a Spanish
               gentleman, (Don Raphael De Aranga,) who had been exiled from Spain, for certain court
               intrigues, called on an eminent New York lawyer, and consulted him upon some civil
               business, with regard to the purchase of property, etc. He left with the lawyer a
               package of papers, title deeds, etc., and soon after disappeared, no one knew
               whither. Among these papers the following extraordinary narrative was discovered; it
               is in no wise connected with said papers, but as there is some hope that its
               absorbing and peculiar revelations, will afford some clue to the fate of the missing
               Personage, it is herewith made public.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>B. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The beautiful Jewess, Rachel Mendoza</head>
            <head>RACHEL MENDOZA, THE JEWESS.</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE RETURN FROM COLLEGE—THE GOOD CLERGYMAN—PROMISED REVELATION OF
                  THE SECRET OF CHARLES BERNARD'S BIRTH—THE MANOR HOUSE—THE BEAUTIFUL WOMAN.</head>
               <p>I HAD just attained my twenty-first year, when I graduated, with all the honours,
                  at a celebrated New England College.</p>
               <p>Ignorant of the world save from books a bright future stretched before me. Having
                  decided upon my profession, I determined to visit the home of my childhood before
                  launching into the great world.</p>
               <p>My parents I had never known, but from earliest Infancy had been reared in the
                  family of a clergyman, the Rev. Mr. Williams, who had charge of a parish, in an
                  obscure valley, some miles east of the Hudson River. Mr. Williams a kind and
                  venerable man, had been to me as a father; had brought me up under his own eye
                  from childhood; had provided me out of his limited means, or out of means derived
                  from a source to me unknown, with money sufficient for the completion of my
                  collegiate course. And now I determined to pay him a last visit, before I launched
                  out in the great world. Bidding an affectionate good-bye to my classmates, I made
                  the best<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC5761-00000003"/> of my way to New York city, and
                  from thence up the Hudson River.</p>
               <p>It was in the first blush of a September twilight, that I found myself on the
                  hill-top which commanded a view of my childhood's home. The distant hills were yet
                  bright with the glow of sunset, but the valley was wrapt in shadows; and from
                  these shadows three objects arose distinctly into the light—the steeple of the
                  village church, the roof of the parsonage, and the roof of a deserted edifice,
                  which stood amid a grove of trees, on a gentle elevation to the right of the
                  view.</p>
               <p>This edifice I had remembered from my boyhood, as a huge pile of dark gray stone,
                  surmounted by steep roof, and buried in the shadows of a grove of oaks and pines;
                  it had never been inhabited within my memory; and there was a rumour that the
                  "Manor House" as it was called, had for years been the subject of a vexatious and
                  interminable lawsuit. And as the shadows gathered slowly over the steeple, over
                  the roof of my childhood's home, and upon the grove about the "Manor House," I
                  descended from the hill-top.</p>
               <p>Soon I stood upon the porch of the parsonage, and entered the small back room, on
                  the first floor, which from its narrow window commanded a view of the graveyard. A
                  light was burning there, upon a table overspread with books. And in the old arm
                  chair was the tall and venerable frame of my Benefactor, whose pale face glowed
                  with delight, as he took me by the hand, and welcomed me home.</p>
               <p>"Bless me, Charles, you have grown!" he cried, lifting his spectacles from his
                  clear gray eyes. "Not so much taller, indeed, but older, older. The last year has
                  made a great change in you. You have been thinking much, my son."</p>
               <p>And he eagerly surveyed me from head to foot.</p>
               <p>At that time I was about the medium size, my frame well knit, broad in chest and
                  shoulders, and sinewy and elastic in the movements of the limbs; my complexion was
                  dark—deep olive—my features boldly defined, my eyes large and gray, and my
                  forehead unusually large, and apparently disproportionate to the size of my
                  body.</p>
               <p>"One would say, Charles," continued the good clergyman with a smile, "that you
                  have the face of a man, who, according to circumstances, would achieve the
                  greatest good, or commit the worst crimes." He meant it as a jest—but there was
                  sad terrible truth his words, more truth than at that time entered his dreams or
                  mine.</p>
               <p>And as I sat by the open window, and he by the table, we conversed upon my future
                  prospects, and I disclosed all my plans to the good man. I had chosen the law for
                  my profession, and it was my purpose to enter my name in the office of a
                  celebrated New York lawyer. My benefactor said to me, with a serious look, and a
                  glance full of meaning:</p>
               <p>"Make no plans for the future, Charles, until after the 9th of September. It is
                  now the second. On the 9th I will disclose to you the secret of your parentage,
                  and place in your hands, certain documents which will have an important bearing on
                  your future life."</p>
               <p>Soon afterward I bade the clergyman good night, and returned to my room, but not
                  to sleep. Placing the candle upon the old fashioned bureau, I found myself
                  repeating the remarkable words of my benefactor.</p>
               <p>"The ninth of September! The secret of your parentage! Documents which will affect
                  your future life!" I found myself repeating these words, as I took my seat near
                  the window, and looked out upon the stars. And with my brain overburdened by
                  thought I found it in vain to attempt to sleep. Extinguishing my candle, I stole
                  down stairs (so as not to disturb Mr. Williams or the old housekeeper) and went
                  forth into the village, and wandered on buried in thought, until my progress was
                  abruptly arrested by the high walls of a garden,—the garden of the Manor House
                  aforesaid.</p>
               <p>A whim seized me (and what we call a whim is too often the iron hand of fate) to
                  cross the wall and explore the garden. And in a few moments, by the light of the
                  stars, I was threading the garden walks, which overgrown with weeds, wound here
                  and there, under the shadow of the tall oaks and solemn pines.</p>
               <p>Soon I reached the front of the mansion, and with a feeling akin to awe, remarked
                  its gloomy exterior,—doors and windows all hermetically closed from garret to
                  roof,—looking yet more gloomy, by the dim light of the stars. Passing along the
                  front of the mansion, I approached its southern wing, and started with
                  surprise—from an upper window, the rays of a lamp broke out upon the darkness.</p>
               <p>"Ah, I had forgotten the words of my Benefactor! The mansion is inhabited by a
                  widow lady, and a solitary servant—so Mr. Williams informed me this evening. How
                  could his words slip from my memory? Who this lady is, her exact age, her history,
                  nay, the very fashion of her features—all these matters very interesting to the
                  gossips of the village, are wrapt in mystery. She never appears<pb n="10-11"
                     xml:id="VAC5761-00000004"/> pears, save with her face thickly veiled. True, she
                  is kind hearted, for she has frequently made Mr. Williams the medium of munificent
                  charities to the village poor. I wonder if that light shines from her window?"</p>
               <p>With reflections such as these, I found myself standing amid the shrubbery, gazing
                  at the window, from which shone the light. It did not occur to me, that if
                  discovered I might be taken for a robber, and have the dogs set upon me; I felt
                  myself devoured by a burning curiosity to know more of this mysterious widow.</p>
               <p>After gazing for some time at the window, I returned to the front of the mansion,
                  and to my great surprise discovered the hall door wide open. I had hardly made
                  this discovery, before a piercing shriek reached my ears. Taking not a single
                  moment for thought I sprang through the hall door, and in the darkness ascended
                  the stairway. I reached a passage on the second floor,—and my eyes were greeted by
                  a ray of light, which (apparently from a door slightly open) streamed out upon the
                  passage.</p>
               <p>Toward that solitary ray I directed my steps, while the sounds of a deep hoarse
                  voice, and of a woman's voice, mingling together, by no means delayed my progress.
                  I reached the door, and paused for an instant—and heard the low groans, as of a
                  person in the last agony, and at the same time heard these words from the harsh
                  husky voice,—"<emph>Then die</emph>," and the groans grew lower and fainter. I
                  gently pushed open the door. The sight which I beheld fired my blood. It was a
                  large bed chamber, lighted by a lamp which stood upon a bureau. In the centre of
                  the floor, knelt a muscular thick set man, dressed in a rough great coat, and with
                  a fur cap down low over his face. And with his brawny right hand he clutched the
                  throat of a prostrate woman, who clad in her night clothes, which were torn and
                  disordered, and with her hair streaming over her face, now struggled faintly as if
                  in her death agony. She had evidently been torn from her bed, by the ruffian who
                  was now choking her to death. I was unarmed, but I sprang forward, uttering a wild
                  cry. The ruffian turned, sprang to his feet, and confronted me; the part of his
                  face which was visible, was altogether savage and brutal, and his eyes shone with
                  ferocious light. He drew a pistol from the pocket of his coat, and without a word
                  presented it, and drew the trigger. But it missed fire. At once I sprang upon him;
                  for a moment he seemed disposed to maintain the combat, but uttering an oath, he
                  rushed to the window, dashed it open, and disappeared. I followed him, and arrived
                  at the window in time to see him descend the lattice work, on the wall of the
                  mansion, (intended for trailing vines,) after which he disappeared among the
                  shrubbery. I now turned my attention to the fainting woman. Half clad and
                  fainting, she was stretched insensible at my feet. I knelt by her side, and took
                  her head upon my knee, and bathed her brow with water, which I took from a glass
                  upon the table—and all the while, I was spell bound, by the surpassing beauty of
                  her face, the luxuriant proportions of her form and limbs. Apparently in the full
                  bloom of womanhood,—say twenty years of age,—she was dark complexioned, of the
                  medium stature, her brows and hair intensely black, and her lips and the centre of
                  each cheek, as intensely red. The hue of her round neck and faultless shoulders
                  was a clear soft brown,—something like the pale gold of an Italian sunset. Her
                  prominent bosom, lithe and slender waist, the round outlines of her arms, the
                  flowing proportions of her shape, terminating in slender ancles and small feet,
                  all were but poorly concealed by her torn and disordered attire. And a certain
                  arch of her dark brows, a certain tendency of her nose, to the aquiline outline,
                  combined with an indescribable expression of her features in general, denoted her
                  lineage—she was evidently a Jewess. These particulars I gathered at a glance,
                  while I was endeavouring to revive her from the death-like swoon. At last, with a
                  wild frightened stare, she unclosed her eyes, at the same time her bosom heaved
                  with a long and apparently painful pulsation.—"No monster, again I say, no! Sooner
                  will I die!" were her first words.</p>
               <p>A beautiful woman in my arms, amid circumstances so peculiar! I was lost in
                  perplexity,—but I managed to utter the words, "Have no fears, lady. I heard you
                  scream, and arrived in time to defend you from the assassin. He is gone."</p>
               <p>She looked at me at first with a vague stare, and then hastily raising her head
                  from my knee, gathered her night robe over her bosom. She rose to her feet, and
                  regarded me attentively.</p>
               <p>"Sir! <emph>you</emph> have saved my life," she said, in a voice of rich clear
                  music,—"and may I ask the name of the gentleman to whom I am so much
                  indebted?"</p>
               <p>"Pardon me, madam. This is no time for explanation. You are wearied and worn out
                  by the excitement of the unusual incident. In the morning I will call, and explain
                  all that I know of this affair. For the present allow me to retire. I will call
                  your maid, who doubtless did not hear your cries for help,—" and I moved to the
                  door.</p>
               <pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC5761-00000005"/>
               <p>"Stay," cried the lady, "last evening I gave my maid permission to depart and
                  spend the night at the house of her parents, who are not far off. I am all alone.
                  And <emph>this wretch</emph> may return,"—a look of hatred almost fiendish came
                  over her face, and then a shudder agitated her from head to foot. From a sofa she
                  took a cloak of black velvet, and flung its rich fold over her shoulders—the
                  glossy blackness of this garment set off, and gave new lustre to her unbared feet
                  and shoulders.</p>
               <p>"Stay—do not leave me,—<emph>this wretch</emph> may return."</p>
               <p>What could I do? She was evidently suffering from a nervous terror, caused by her
                  late fright. I placed my hat on the table, and seated myself at some distance from
                  the lady, who had flung herself into a rocking-chair.</p>
               <p>I felt embarrassed, and for want of something better to say, remarked: "This is
                  the first time for many years, that a robber has dared to disturb the peace of our
                  quiet village."</p>
               <p>She opened her eyes until I was almost frightened by their glare—"<emph>A
                     robber</emph>?" she exclaimed, with a singular accent: "A <emph>robber</emph>
                  generally secures his plunder before attempting to choke to death a sleeping
                  woman. No, sir, he was <emph>not</emph> a robber. He is an assassin."</p>
               <p>"And what motive could any one have to harm you,—you, so,—" I blurted out the
                  words, "so young and beautiful."</p>
               <p>The smile which coursed over her face cannot be described; she bit her red lip
                  with her white teeth, and said,—"My friend, some other time I may tell you all
                  about it; but to-night I do not feel strong enough. And you,—you who if not young
                  and beautiful, are certainly something better, gifted and ambitious, tell me
                  something about yourself." The loneliness of the hour, the strangeness of the
                  adventure, the beauty of the woman who now confronted me within the precincts of
                  her chamber, all conspired to confuse and bewilder me. I was insensibly drawn into
                  conversation with her.</p>
               <p>I told her all my life,—all that I knew about myself,—my prospects, hopes, and the
                  promised revelation of the ninth of September. I grew earnest, perhaps eloquent.
                  And I found myself, at the end of my story, seated near this beautiful woman,
                  whose bosom was heaving, and whose eyes were glittering in evident sympathy.</p>
               <p>Seated in the rocking-chair, with the folds of the cloak, gathered loosely about
                  her form, she closed her eyes as if in profound thought,—and then opening them
                  full upon me, said—"And so your name is Charles Bernard, and this is the story of
                  your life! Well, Charles, (allow me to address you as though I was a sister,) fate
                  has evidently strange events in store for you. Your life is as singular almost as
                  my own."</p>
               <p>Is it a wonder that I was enchanted by this woman; I who had never loved, had
                  never even felt the pressure of a woman's kiss? I was enchanted, and while the
                  hours passed away, sat talking with her, gazing upon her, as one talks and gazes
                  in some delicious dream.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE MURDER—THE HISTORY OF RACHEL MENDOZA.</head>
               <p>TOWARD morning she slept; and reverently winding the folds of the cloak about her,
                  I withdrew into the corridor, and watched beside the door. After some time I fell
                  into a doze, from which I was roused by a smothered cry for help.</p>
               <p>I pushed open the door; the lady was still seated in the rocking-chair, but the
                  unknown ruffian (who had evidently entered by the window) stood before her, his
                  grip once more about her throat. At such a time a moment is an age. To seize the
                  first object which offered itself to my grasp; to strike the ruffian, madly and
                  blindly, as he stood, with his back toward me; and to strike him, until he fell
                  with a half uttered groan at my feet—this was all the work of an instant of
                  delirium and rage. When I recovered my presence of mind, I found myself standing
                  in the centre of the room, with a large pistol in my hand—the barrel was clutched
                  in my grasp—the stock was wet and dripping with blood. (The ruffian had evidently
                  laid it upon the table, before he proceeded to assault the lady; and from the
                  table, in that instant of mad excitement, I had seized it.) Before me was the
                  lady, fainting in her chair, her head dropped upon her right shoulder. At my feet,
                  with his face to the floor, was stretched the ruffian or assassin, call him as you
                  will. I bent down, and held the lamp close to him—O, horror! The back of his head
                  was crushed and broken in. I tore his cap from his brow, and turned him on his
                  face. That face was stamped with the death agony, but it was not the face of a
                  common ruffian; but the lamp shone upon<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC5761-00000006"/>
                  the chiselled features, and delicate complexion of an educated man—features
                  stamped with a look of craft and cunning, and relieved by a dark mustache,
                  whiskers, and masses of soft curling hair. I opened his ragged overcoat; and
                  discovered that the attire which this rough garment concealed, indicated wealth if
                  not respectability in the wearer. Snow white linen, a chain of massy gold, coat of
                  rich cloth, vest of dark satin; these by no means indicated a common ruffian. And
                  he was dead; I had killed him! I stood horror stricken at the thought.</p>
               <p>"He is dead!" I groaned in very agony—"there is blood upon my hands!" My groans
                  aroused the lady from her swoon.</p>
               <p>"Dead! Who is dead?" and she sprang from the chair in such haste, that the black
                  cloak fell from her form—she turned from my horror stricken face, and bent beside
                  the dead, now gazing upon the hideous wound at the back of the head, and now
                  surveying that <choice>
                     <sic>palid</sic>
                     <corr>pallid</corr>
                  </choice> countenance. "O, he <emph>is</emph> dead!" she cried in an accent, not
                  of horror, but of intense and quivering joy—and her eyes flashed, and her colour
                  went and came, and her bosom dilated—she was the picture of frenzied joy. "O,
                  Charles, you have made me your slave for life," and she sprang to me, and put her
                  arms about my neck, and kissed me on the cheeks and forehead, her bosom meanwhile
                  beating against my breast. "Have no remorse, Charles! <emph>He</emph> is dead! You
                  have done a holy deed!"</p>
               <p>"A holy deed!" I echoed, dropping the blood-stained pistol on the floor.</p>
               <p>"Yes, holy," she answered. "Charles, there is something about my history, full as
                  strange as the mystery which overhangs your birth. Listen to me, and do not let
                  the horror of the sight of blood prevent you from hearing every word I say."</p>
               <p>She resumed her cloak, and then, weak and trembling as I was from excitement,
                  urged me to the sofa, and seated herself by my side.</p>
               <p>"I am Rachel Mendoza. My parents were Hebrews, of great wealth, in Portugal. When
                  I was but a child they were forced to leave Cadiz, from some political cause.
                  Collecting all their wealth, in the shape of jewels and coin, they arrived in New
                  York city, but died a few years afterward of a prevalent epidemic. Before his
                  death my father made a will, constituting the son of his brother, my cousin,
                  Gabriel Mendoza, the trustee of the estate, and the guardian of his only
                  child—myself—until I attained the age of eighteen. Gabriel, a cold, crafty man,
                  anxious at once to possess my person and my wealth, pursued one object
                  undeviatingly, from the time of my infancy to the moment that I was eighteen—this
                  object, to influence me, in every possible manner, to marry him, as soon as I was
                  eighteen. I saw through the desperate nature of the man, and therefore was afraid
                  to give him a positive denial, until the day after I became eighteen, when he had
                  closed his trusteeship and surrendered my wealth and estate into my own hands. He
                  came into the parlour of my mansion in New York, and smoothly urged his suit,
                  complimenting me upon my beauty, my prospects, and professing unbounded adoration
                  for me. 'Gabriel,' said I, looking him full in the face, 'you will do very well
                  for a guardian or a father, but for a husband—never!' He said nothing, but went
                  from the room, white with rage. Soon—in a few days—he visited me again, affected
                  to laugh at himself for his folly in proposing to a girl like me, so much younger
                  than himself. And he made me believe that he had given up all idea of a marriage
                  with me. He won my confidence. One night he induced me to visit the Opera with
                  him, and after the Opera, instead of returning to my home, he directed the
                  coachman (whom he had bribed) to drive to a certain house, on a lonely road, some
                  miles from the city. Here everything was ready for his plot; he had his paid
                  minions in waiting; a Priest, whom he had hired or deceived, was his accomplice,
                  and stood prepared to celebrate our nuptials. I did not suspect anything until
                  stepping from the carriage I discovered in place of my own home the front of this
                  isolated house. Ere I had time to recover from my surprise, I was urged into the
                  house, and into the room, where by an altar stood the Priest and the hired guests.
                  Frightened, and certain that my life was in peril if I made resistance, I was led
                  to the altar, and the marriage ceremony was performed—and I was to all seeming
                  Gabriel's wife, although I had not made a single response. Then, while the guests
                  sat down to a banquet, I was led by hired female attendants up stairs, into a
                  large chamber, luxuriously furnished, and was told that this was my Bridal
                  Chamber. They disrobed me, and bade me soon to expect my husband, Gabriel
                  Mendoza—and then left me alone. It was then that I began to recover from the
                  fright or the stupor into which these events had thrown me. I rushed hurriedly to
                  the window, saw that it opened upon a garden, and that the garden could be reached
                  by a shed. Then assuming some male attire, which I found upon a chair, (it was
                  that which Gabriel had put off, in order to put on his wedding dress,) I lifted
                  the window, passed out upon the shed, and from the shed dropped into the garden.
                  An opening<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC5761-00000007"/> in the fence gave me free
                  passage into the highway. And along the highway I ran, nerved by despair, until I
                  reached the outskirts of the city, where I fortunately spied a hackney coach,
                  which soon conducted me safely to my home. Perhaps at the very moment that I
                  crossed my own threshold Gabriel entered the bridal chamber, eager to claim his
                  victim, and discovered—that the bird had flown. It is now three years since that
                  night. And for three years he has followed me with ceaseless persecutions, all
                  having one purpose—to force me into a public acknowledgement of the validity of
                  that atrocious marriage. With this view he has frequently sought to possess my
                  person; has surrounded me with his spies; has made me feel, as though I was not
                  secure from him on any place on God's earth. It was to escape from him that I left
                  New York, and hired this lonely mansion, thinking that here at least, in this
                  secluded valley, I would be safe from him. And yet to-night he entered my house,
                  threatened me with death unless I would yield to his embraces—you entered, and he
                  fled. But still he hung about the place, and watching his opportunity, again
                  entered my chamber, and maddened by my repeated refusals, was choking me to death,
                  when you stretched him dead at my feet. Yes, rejoice, Charles, Gabriel Mendoza
                  lies a corpse at my feet. I am free!"</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE BURIAL OF THE BODY—THE NEXT NIGHT—THE MARRIAGE.</head>
               <p>IT is in vain to attempt to depict the mingled emotions which her words caused me.
                  My brain was in a whirl.</p>
               <p>"But, Rachel,"—I found myself calling her by her first name,—"there must be a
                  public judicial investigation of the causes which led to this man's death."</p>
               <p>She looked at me steadily—"Was it not the very fear of publicity—of having my name
                  bandied about in the courts and the newspapers—that made me endure his
                  persecutions for years? And shall I now, when I am free from him for ever, make my
                  name and peace the sport of judicial mummery and newspaper gossip?"</p>
               <p>"But—the—body," said I, pointing with a shudder to the object. "Charles, Charles,"
                  she bent her face close to mine, and whispered, "that can be concealed, and all
                  memory of the miserable wretch perish from the earth for ever. You have saved my
                  life, my honour. Aid me in this, and"—her head drooped to my shoulder—"I am your
                  slave for ever."</p>
               <p>How could I refuse? Together we carried the body of Gabriel from the room where he
                  died, down two pair of stairs, into the cellar. While Rachel held the light I dug
                  a grave under an archway, and toiled on until it was some three feet in depth. In
                  this I placed the body, as it was, with the everyday attire damp with blood, and
                  then covered it with earth, and the earth with ashes, and loose fragments of
                  bricks, timber and rubbish.</p>
               <p>Then ascending once more into the fatal chamber, Rachel and myself washed the
                  stain of blood from the carpet, and from our hands, and threw the blood-stained
                  water from the basin which held it, into the garden beneath the window.
                  Fortunately there was no stain upon our garments. It was now near morning light;
                  and worn out by the emotions of the night, I stood ready to depart. Rachel, in her
                  dark cloak, with her black hair falling over her shoulders, confronted me: "Return
                  to-morrow night, Charles," she said, and all of the warmth, the life of her being
                  flashed from her eyes.</p>
               <p>I left the house and the garden, and reached my home and bed unperceived. It
                  seemed as if I had hardly fallen into a weary and troubled sleep, when I heard the
                  kindly voice of the old housekeeper calling me to breakfast. I arose, and as I
                  hurriedly dressed myself, I could hardly believe that the events of the previous
                  night were anything but a horrible dream. All day long, even while to all
                  appearance deeply engaged in conversation with my good friend the clergyman, I was
                  thinking of two things, the surpassing beauty of Rachel, and the dead body which
                  we had buried in the cellar. What a change had that one night made in my whole
                  life!</p>
               <p>The day passed, and soon after night, making some excuse to the clergyman, I stole
                  through the village, and approached the garden wall. I lightly bounded over it,
                  and presently, with a trembling hand, drew the bell at the hall door.</p>
               <p>Soon it was opened, and said a low voice, "Give me your hand," and I was led by a
                  soft hand along a dark passage, and then into a large parlour, furnished in a
                  style of dazzling splendour, and lighted by the blaze of wax candles. In the
                  centre, on a table, an elegant collation stood ready. And before me the owner of
                  the soft hand, which had led me through the darkness—Rachel, clad in a robe of<pb
                     n="18-19" xml:id="VAC5761-00000008"/> white satin, which, girdled to her waist
                  by a sash, fell in loose folds from her shoulders to her feet. Her dark hair was
                  disposed in thick masses about her face; a single white flower gleamed from its
                  intense blackness. Her arms and shoulders were bare; and the only ornament which
                  she wore, was a massive diamond bracelet about each wrist. She was ravishingly
                  beautiful; and I trembled with agitation as I found myself in the presence of a
                  woman whose loveliness called to mind all I had ever read of oriental beauty.</p>
               <p>"My maid has again received permission to visit her parents," she said, "and we
                  are alone, Charles." Then leading me to the sofa, she seated herself by my side,
                  and filled two glasses of wine, and handed one of them to me.</p>
               <p>"This wine my father brought from Portugal years ago; drink, Charles,"—and she
                  pressed her glass first to my lips, then to her own. Was it the fire of that wine,
                  stealing softly into every vein, or the magic of her eyes, which made me feel like
                  one who has crossed the doors of Mahomet's paradise? Every vein was full of
                  delight; every pulse a throb of pleasure; I forgot everything but the present, and
                  the beautiful being by my side. Hours passed away in a delirious intoxication—and
                  in the first dawn of morning I awoke, and found myself upon a couch, with the head
                  of Rachel, who was sleeping, pillowed on my breast. Her hair curled dark, and
                  black, and glossy over my neck and shoulders.</p>
               <p>"Husband!" was the first word she said, as her unclosing eyes met mine. And we
                  both forgot the dead man, who lay in his rude grave, in the cellar of the house,
                  in which was also our bridal bed.</p>
               <milestone n="——" unit="typography"/>
               <p>The next day I informed the good clergyman that I would like to visit New York for
                  a few days; he willingly complied with my wishes:—"Only, Charles," said he, "be
                  sure and be back before the ninth."</p>
               <p>It was the fourth of September. I promised him a faithful compliance with his
                  request, and left at once for the steamboat landing, some ten miles from the
                  village. I went on board of one of those magnificent boats which plow the North
                  River, and there met a lady veiled in black, who had arrived at the landing by
                  another route. I talked much with this lady on our journey down the river, and
                  when we arrived at New York took her arm, and placed her in a carriage. Then I
                  entered, and the carriage rolled away, and did not stop until it came to a
                  princely mansion in the north of the city. I led the lady from the carriage into
                  the mansion, and as we stood in the light of the hall lamp, she pushed aside her
                  veil, disclosing the beautiful countenance of Rachel the Jewess.</p>
               <p>"Husband," said she, "this house and all it contains, and all that your wife
                  inherited from her father, are yours." That night we were privately married by a
                  Catholic priest—for Rachel, like her parents, although pure Hebrew in blood, was
                  also like them in faith a Catholic.</p>
               <p>The next three days passed like days of Paradise—such a Paradise as the brain of
                  Mahomet peopled with high-bosomed houris. Shut out from the world, we passed the
                  hours within the walls of the splendid mansion which Rachel had inherited from her
                  father, and we knew nothing save that we lived, that we loved, and that we were
                  alone and happy together. There was a great deal of the oriental in the
                  organization of Rachel, and perhaps in my own. She knew how to temper and mingle
                  together the pleasures which we derive from the senses, and the enjoyments which
                  we derive from the intellect; thus, for instance, as every evening the candles
                  would be lighted in one of the richly furnished chambers of our mansion, the
                  banquet spread, and lip to lip, and eye to eye, Rachel and myself would pledge
                  each other in rich old wine. Days of enchantment, such as are rarely enjoyed in
                  these cold northern climes!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
               <head type="sub">"THE NINTH OF SEPTEMBER"—REVELATIONS—A PRINCE OF THE BLOOD
                  ROYAL.</head>
               <p>THE morning of the ninth of September came, and with a heavy heart I bade adieu to
                  Rachel, and took my way to the village, near the Hudson, in which the good Mr.
                  Williams lived. It was towards evening when the steamboat arrived at the landing
                  on the Hudson; and it was not until after dark that I reached the village, and the
                  house of my benefactor. As I stood upon the porch, I cast a glance toward the
                  "manor house," which rose gloomily among the trees—and shuddered, as I thought of
                  the secret which it concealed. Entering I found the venerable man seated in his
                  study, beside a table, upon which a single object was laid—a large package, bound
                     with<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC5761-00000009"/> red tape, and secured with heavy
                  seals of red wax. After greeting me, with his usual kindness, Mr. Williams said,
                  in a tone which was tremulous—"Charles, twenty-one years from to-day, when my wife
                  was living, and I had been but recently established as Pastor of this Church, a
                  carriage stopped at my door, and a lady richly dressed, and thickly veiled,
                  descended from it and entered the house. In her arms, wrapped in the costliest
                  apparel, she held a babe, but a few weeks old. And seated in this very room, with
                  myself and wife before her, she besought us to take charge of the babe, and to
                  rear it as our own. As she spoke she never once removed her veil. She said nothing
                  of the parentage, nothing of the name of the child.</p>
               <p>"'Take it, give it what name you please, rear it as your own, and for twenty-one
                  years you will receive, (whether it lives or dies,) once in every six months a
                  certain sum of money, from a source which will always be unknown to you.' Her
                  voice was touched with a foreign accent, but it was deep and impressive. Both
                  myself and wife were confounded by the novelty of the adventure, and the
                  singularity of the request. We hesitated ere we made a reply.</p>
               <p>"'Do not hesitate,' said the lady, 'I appeal to you as a minister of religion! And
                  I solemnly assure you, that unless you comply with my request, that this child
                     <emph>will not live</emph>. For its <emph>existence</emph>, and the
                     <emph>honour</emph> and <emph>reputation</emph> of certain families are at war
                  with each other. You are its only hope of life.' The tone of the lady awed both
                  myself and wife; we believed her words, and consented to rear the child.</p>
               <p>"'This packet you will give to him twenty-one years from to-day—if he dies before
                  that time, destroy it.' And with these words she kissed the child, gave me the
                  packet, and bade us adieu—she entered her carriage again, and from that hour I
                  have never seen or heard from her, although the semi-annual payment has been
                  regularly made. Charles, I need not inform you, that the child entrusted to my
                  care, by the strange lady, was yourself. In the course of twenty-one years I have
                  tried to discharge all my duty to you; the last part of my trust alone remains for
                  me to perform. There is the packet, Charles."</p>
               <p>As if overcome by emotion, he stopped abruptly.</p>
               <p>"I will leave you, so that you may read it at your leisure. Good night." He rose
                  from his chair, and left the room, closing the door behind him.</p>
               <p>It will easily be realized, that before opening the sealed packet, I regarded it
                  with my whole being, impressed with wonder and awe. It was sealed with a crest—I
                  was not learned in Heraldry, but knew it at once to be the crest of some noble
                  family. I cut the tape, broke the seals, and discovered that it contained a number
                  of manuscripts, upon the topmost of which was written, in a delicate hand—"<hi
                     rend="i"/>To my Son." Opening it eagerly, I perused its contents. It was as
                  follows:</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <head>"THE HISTORY OF YOUR PARENTAGE.</head>
                           <p>"In case you live twenty-one years from the day on which I leave you
                              in the charge of the Rev. Mr. Williams, (a good clergyman, in the
                              village of ——, near the Hudson River,) you will read these lines. They
                              are penned by the hand of your mother—that mother, who, having given
                              you existence, should herself nourish, rear and educate you, but who
                              is forced, by hard fate, to cast you upon the protection of strangers.
                              Before you judge me harshly, my son, listen to my history.</p>
                           <p>"I was born in the city of Madrid. My parents were Hebrew in blood,
                              but Catholic in faith. My father was the inheritor of wealth that had
                              been swelled by the accumulations of at least five generations. At the
                              time of my birth he was one of the richest merchants in Madrid—the
                              owner not only of stores of merchandize, and hoards of gold and
                              silver, but of vast estates. When I was thirteen—just out of
                              childhood, but ripened suddenly, by race and climate, into the
                              woman—my father, in order to increase his wealth, married me to a
                              wealthy merchant, a Hebrew in blood and in religion, who was old
                              enough to be my father. I never loved him, and but one child blessed
                              (or cursed) our marriage. After we had been married ten years he died
                              suddenly, leaving me still young and beautiful, and immensely rich.
                              About the time of his death stirring political events took place in
                              Madrid, as well as throughout Spain; my father lost his life upon the
                              scaffold; his wealth was confiscated; and I, turning all of my wealth,
                              all that I could, into gold and diamonds, fled with my only child from
                              Madrid to Cadiz, and from thence to New York. I sailed from Cadiz with
                              a brother of my late husband, who was also forced, by political
                              turmoils, to seek his fortunes in the New World. But it was not the
                              fate of my father, or the mere <emph>external</emph> political events
                              that shook Spain to its centre, that induced me to fly to the New
                              World. Even as I stood on ship-board, holding my son by the hand—that
                              son whom I could never love, for he had his father's hateful face and
                              soul—I was conscious that in my bosom throbbed<pb n="22-23"
                                 xml:id="VAC5761-00000010"/> another life. Yes, my son, I then bore
                              you in my bosom. And it was on your account, you, then unborn, that I
                              fled from Madrid. For soon after the death of my husband, my love was
                              sought by one, who, from his <emph>rank</emph>, could not marry any
                              one, save a woman of <emph>royal blood</emph>. I loved him,
                              passionately loved him, and you were the fruit of our love. And it was
                              to save you and myself from the wrath of <emph>his relatives</emph>,
                              who attributed to me <emph>political influence</emph> over <emph>your
                                 father</emph>, and who had determined to <emph>destroy you</emph>
                              as soon as you were born—it was for these reasons that I fled to New
                              York. After my arrival I placed my son in the family of his uncle, (my
                              husband's brother,) and secluded myself from observation in an obscure
                              part of the city. There I remained until you were born. Your existence
                              will always be kept a secret from my other son, your brother; from
                              every member of my family, or the family of my late husband. And it is
                              by the direction of your ILLUSTRIOUS FATHER, (and to save you from the
                              wrath of his relatives, which would strike you even in the New World,)
                              that I intend to place you in the charge of a good clergyman, (who
                              lives in an obscure village near the North River,) until you are
                              twenty-one. When you are twenty-one, you will read these lines from
                              your mother, and also the accompanying Documents from your father. The
                              name of my father's family was SALVADIN; the name of my husband's
                              family, MENDOZA; and your elder brother is named GABRIEL MENDOZA. As
                              for the name which you will bear after you are twenty-one, it is
                              designated by your father in the enclosed papers."</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <choice>
                     <sic>FRATRACIDE</sic>
                     <corr>FRATRICIDE</corr>
                  </choice>—MARRIAGE LIFE.</head>
               <p>I COULD read no further. The paper fell from my trembling hands. I gave no thought
                  to the royal blood which flowed in my veins—one thought, one living, breathing
                  horror alone possessed me—<emph>Gabriel Mendoza, whom I had murdered, and buried
                     in the "Manor House," WAS MY BROTHER!</emph>
               </p>
               <p>I uttered a wild cry, and fell insensible, my hand upon the packet, my head upon
                  the table.</p>
               <p>When I recovered my senses it was morning, and I found myself in bed, the
                  venerable clergyman watching by my side. Near the bed, on a table, was placed the
                  packet.</p>
               <p>"You have had a wild night, Charles," said he, "you have suffered much from fever
                  and delirium. How wildly you raved!"</p>
               <p>"What! I raved!" I cried, starting up in the bed—"And what did I say?"</p>
               <p>"Nothing coherent, nothing coherent," replied the clergyman; and I knew that he
                  spoke the truth. My heart beat for joy; I had not revealed that awful
                     secret—<emph>the murder of my Brother</emph>.</p>
               <p>After some time, still in bed, I examined the remaining portion of the contents of
                  the packet—there, among other papers, was a letter from my royal father, in which
                  he stated, that he had invested, in the city of New York, in the hands of
                  trustworthy persons, a large fortune. This fortune would be transferred to me at
                  the age of twenty-one, upon the presentation of certain papers—legal and
                  otherwise—embraced in the packet. I was amply directed how to proceed. And there
                  was the NAME, which my father desired me to bear instead of the plain name of
                  Charles Bernard. What mockery! Fortune and title to a bastard of royal blood,
                  whose hands were red with a brother's murder!</p>
               <p>I tied up the packet, and informed the good clergyman, in general terms, of my
                  mother's history, and of my accession to a name and fortune; and then thanking
                  him, again and again, for his kindness to me through long years, I told him that
                  he would hear from me during the week, but that immediate business (consequent
                  upon the revelations of the packet) required my presence in New York. I left at
                  once for the city, and arriving in the afternoon, I hastened to the office of a
                  Foreign Consul—a grave business-like man—to whom I presented a certain paper which
                  I took from the packet. He regarded me at first with great surprise, and then with
                  a look of the deepest respect. "To-morrow, sir, the property will be transferred
                  to you," he said with a low bow—and on the morrow, at an appointed hour, certain
                  tedious legal forms having been gone through, I found myself the proprietor, in my
                  own right, of a princely estate. It was my first care to visit the agent of the
                  "Manor House" estate, (the estate itself was in Chancery and could not be sold,)
                  and secure from him, in the name of the Rev. Mr. Williams, a lease of that estate
                  for ninety-nine years. I paid the lease-money, and forwarded the deeds to the
                  clergyman, telling him that the property was a gift from me. "And," said I to
                  myself, "the secret of the cellar is now safe for ever."</p>
               <pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC5761-00000011"/>
               <p>I then turned wearily home, and was met by my beautiful Jewess wife, who greeted
                  me with her accustomed caresses. A beautiful woman—but between her and me there
                  was the corpse of a murdered Brother. I told her of my accession to fortune, but
                  nothing of my <emph>royal</emph> blood, (O, mockery!) or of my relationship to
                  Gabriel Mendoza.</p>
               <p>And now for me a new life began. Instead of being simply a law student, toiling
                  day and night, and straining every nerve to achieve a fortune, I was at once, in
                  the very dawn of manhood, the owner of at least three hundred thousand dollars.
                  What motive was there now for exertion? For fame I cared not—was I not already of
                  royal lineage? For trade I had no taste. And so I sat down to enjoy my wealth—to
                  enjoy life—to please my tastes—to feed my passions. And immense wealth,
                     <emph>achieved without labour</emph>, had its natural result upon me. Had I
                  been poor, and forced to toil and study, my future life would, no doubt, have
                  ended in some high position, in senatorial honours, and professional fame. But so
                  rich, rich without effort, I gradually began to regard life as a pleasing dream,
                  in which the poor were only born to pamper and feed the appetites of the rich. Was
                  there not something of the disposition of my <emph>father's</emph> family
                  manifested in all this? A family counting Borgias and Bourbons among its
                  members—and the world knows for what the Borgias and the Bourbons were famed.</p>
               <p>I still loved Rachel Mendoza, my beautiful Jewess wife, but even when pressing her
                  to my bosom, it seemed to me that my brother's form, mangled and bloody, stood
                  near. And, impelled by my immense fortune, by my royal blood, I began to look
                  around the world, seeking only for the gratification of my appetites. My
                  adventures would fill volumes—this truth will be apparent when it is considered
                  that the scene was New York city, and my instrument money.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE $5000 SHAWL—THE PLIANT HUSBAND—THE SUICIDE.</head>
               <p>AMONG the families with whom my social position brought me into contact, was that
                  of a merchant, whom I shall call Godfrey, who, doing a business of hundreds of
                  thousands per year, was not, all his debts paid, worth a single dollar. His wife
                  was a vain, silly woman, fond of parade and show; his son, a fashionable idiot;
                  and his daughter Helen, a proud girl of remarkable beauty and considerable
                  intellect, but like her mother, mad after fashion and show. She was a tall girl,
                  with blue eyes, auburn hair, and a complexion like the sunny side of a peach. Her
                  step was languid and voluptuous, in harmony with her form, which was round, rich
                  and warm in all its proportions. Helen was engaged to be married to a stock broker
                  of great reputed wealth, but whose personal appearance reminded one of a cross
                  between the fox and the monkey. Before the marriage, I walked one day on Broadway
                  with Helen, and we chanced to enter one of those "Dry Good's Palaces" which rise
                  here and there along that great street. The trader had lately received a few
                  shawls of exquisite pattern and enormous price; they were from the native looms of
                  Hindostan, and were such in fact as very rarely pass into the possession of any
                  woman, save one that occupies a throne.</p>
               <p>"How much is this one?" said Helen, fixing her eyes longingly upon a particular
                  shawl.</p>
               <p>"<emph>Five thousand dollars</emph>," was the reply—and Helen's proud, beautiful
                  countenance fell. It was plainly to be seen from her face that her father
                     <emph>could not</emph> afford that price, and her intended husband <emph>would
                     not</emph>. After admiring the shawl for a long time, praising its pattern, and
                  descanting upon its price, we left the store, and I escorted Helen to her
                  home.</p>
               <p>The next day, dressed in a Spanish mantle, I called at her father's mansion, and
                  found no one but Helen at home—and she was seated upon a sofa, in the drawing
                  room, clad in an elegant undress—white in colour, and light and flowing in its
                  folds—which did full justice to her rounded form.</p>
               <p>The light came softly through the drawn window curtains, and tinted one side of
                  her face, as she sat with her cheek laying on her hand, and her elbow resting on
                  the arm of the sofa. She looked proud and beautiful, but also vexed and
                  troubled.</p>
               <p>I advanced and greeted her, but did not remove my cloak. But I looked at her
                  intently, and she returned my gaze, at first in surprise, and then—colouring like
                  a summer morning, from her cheeks to her bosom and brow, as if she was afraid to
                  confess that she had understood my look and its hidden meaning—she, in a tone of
                  assumed carelessness, invited me to lay aside my cloak. I slowly opened the cloak,
                  and held forth my right arm, upon which hung, in graceful folds, the <emph>five
                     thousand dollar shawl</emph>. How her eyes shone, and how her colour went and
                  came!</p>
               <pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC5761-00000012"/>
               <p>Without a word I flung it gently over her shoulders, and was arranging its folds,
                  when she said, in a tremulous voice, "How proud your wife will be of such a
                  present, Mr. Bernard!"</p>
               <p>"It is yours, Helen, if you will deign to accept it," I said, and dropped quietly
                  by her side. She said nothing, but surveyed the shawl, while her bosom sank and
                  rose, and her colour came and went.</p>
               <p>"A thousand thanks," she said, in a low voice, as she turned her face to me, but
                  with downcast eyes. I rose to take my leave—she was so much agitated that she
                  could hardly speak.</p>
               <p>"When shall I see you again, Mr. Bernard?" she faltered without raising her eyes.
                  And she rose. "To-morrow—" I began, but before the words were from my lips, Helen,
                  half-fainting, advanced a step, and fell into my arms. She knew at what a price
                  she had purchased the five thousand dollar shawl.</p>
               <p>A few days afterward she was married; there was a great party, great parade and
                  show; and everybody congratulated the happy pair. The stock broker took his bride
                  to a magnificent mansion, which he had prepared for her; and for months things
                  went on swimmingly.</p>
               <p>One day the stock broker came to me, and stated that he was forced to leave at
                  once for Boston on important business—but he had a note to take up before he
                  went—could I lend him two thousand dollars for a few days? I drew my check for the
                  amount.</p>
               <p>"By the bye, I shall not be able to go up town before I leave for Boston; may I
                  trouble you to give this to Helen, as you pass my house on the way home?" He
                  handed me a sealed note. I consented, of course, and he took his leave.</p>
               <p>I arrived at his residence just as the gas lamps were being lighted, and found
                  Helen in the parlour, magnificently attired—jewels, a japonica in her auburn
                  hair—as if for the Opera, or an evening party. I had never been alone with her
                  since the day of the five thousand dollar shawl. She seemed surprised at my
                  appearance, and blushed deeply—I gave her the note; she opened it and read, and
                  turned to me with a glowing cheek, but her eyes flashing with a light which I
                  could not understand.</p>
               <p>"Read this," she said quietly, and put the note in my hand. It was signed by her
                  husband, and read as follows:</p>
               <p>"<hi rend="i"/>My dear Helen—I have succeeded in making that loan of our friend
                  Bernard."</p>
               <p>Those words were very simple, but seemed to envelope a hidden meaning.</p>
               <p>"Well, what of this, Helen?" I said.</p>
               <p>"O, nothing," she replied, with a proud curl of her lip, "only that my husband has
                  married a wife with the intention of giving her as <emph>collateral
                     security</emph>, for any loan which he may make"—and tears of shame and rage
                  poured down her cheeks.</p>
               <p>"When, betrayed by a contemptible vanity, I sold myself to you for a five thousand
                  dollar shawl—that, one would think, was bad and base enough. But now, I am sunk
                  low indeed! Married to a man who bestows my person upon any friend who will lend
                  him two thousand dollars! That is to be my future it seems!" The scorn and shame
                  which stamped her face, as she said these words, cannot be described. I tried to
                  soothe her, but in vain.</p>
               <p>"Leave me," she said, "to-morrow night I will see you."</p>
               <p>I departed, and waited impatiently for the next night. Rather pleased by this new
                  feature of Helen's character, I took my way soon after night to her residence. To
                  my surprise I found a crowd before the door, and in the hall, every one talking to
                  his neighbour in whispers.</p>
               <p>I pushed through the crowd, and entered the parlour, where I had seen Helen the
                  night before—here also was a crowd, gazing with awed faces upon an object which
                  was stretched upon the sofa in their midst—the body of a woman, richly attired,
                  young and beautiful, but with her throat cut from ear to ear! Helen Godfrey!</p>
               <p>Horrified, I rushed from the scene, and made the best of my way to my own home,
                  that image of the beautiful woman, with the bleeding gash across the throat,
                  before me wherever I turned. Arrived at home, I avoided meeting my wife, and
                  hurried to my private room, where a light was burning. I flung myself in a chair
                  and buried my face in my hands, when my head servant entered—"Mr. Bernard," said
                  he, "there was a box left for you this morning. I placed it on the table near you,
                  but forgot to mention the circumstance before."</p>
               <p>As soon as the servant had retired I advanced to the table, and opened the box—it
                  was of paste-board—which stood on the table near the light. The box contained a
                  sealed note, and the <emph>five thousand dollar shawl!</emph> The note ran
                  thus:</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <p>"To-night you will visit my residence, expecting to enjoy the embraces
                              of a woman, whom her husband has sold for $2000. And you will find the
                              body of that woman; but it will be a living woman no longer, but a
                              corpse. <hi rend="i"/>Please accept, as a token of remembrance, this
                              beautiful shawl.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>HELEN.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC5761-00000013"/>
               <p>It is by no means easy to describe the horror which this letter created. I sat for
                  hours in a sort of stupor, silently contemplating the fatal lines. And for weeks
                  and months I could not banish from my mind the picture of the beautiful woman
                  stretched on the sofa, with her throat gashed from ear to ear.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE LAME GIRL—THE MARRIAGE—THE UNWELCOME INTRUDER.</head>
               <p>BUT the gloom which this event caused gradually wore away, and having nothing to
                  do, save to enjoy myself and spend my money, I became involved in a new adventure.
                  Walking along Broadway, one clear winter evening, I noticed a girl of about
                  sixteen years, poorly clad but of remarkable beauty. She was evidently a
                  seamstress, returning home after her day's work. Within her faded bonnet appeared
                  a face clear and bright, in complexion and eyes, and framed in thick masses of
                  dark brown hair. Her shawl was much worn, but its folds disclosed the outline of a
                  richly proportioned form, although she was lame on the right foot. This fact,
                  indeed, the slight limp which marked her gait, instead of detracting from, seemed
                  to add to her beauty. It certainly increased the interest which I felt for her,
                  upon the very sight of her face. Following her to her home, in an obscure part of
                  the city, I marked the house which she entered, and on the next day managed to
                  form some acquaintance with its occupants, the father and mother, and the lame
                  girl herself. Her parents were aged and poor; she was their only support.
                  Representing myself as a merchant's clerk of limited means—Alfred Harvey by name—I
                  managed to ingratiate myself with the old folks, and to secure the affections of
                  Ellen, their lovely child. The day of our marriage was fixed. I had removed the
                  parents into a respectable but modest house, which I furnished in a style in
                  harmony with my apparent means. And as the day of marriage approached I found
                  myself much perplexed. Madly enamoured of the lame girl, and determined to possess
                  her at all hazards, I still hesitated at inveigling her, as innocent as she was
                  beautiful, into a sham marriage.</p>
               <p>"And a real marriage would be bigamy, and—what if Rachel, my proud, beautiful
                  Jewess wife, should find out my little adventure with Ellen Norman?" However, one
                  evening in spring we were married by a Methodist preacher, in the small parlour of
                  our modest home, and in the presence of her aged parents. After the ceremony,
                  Ellen retired to her chamber, or rather to our chamber, whither I soon followed
                  her. I found her standing before the looking-glass, clad in a loose night dress,
                  her hair all unbound, and her cheeks brilliant with blushes.</p>
               <p>"My pretty wife," said I, folding her gently in my right arm, and pressing a kiss
                  upon her pure ripe lips.</p>
               <p>"Which one do you mean?" said a clear voice behind me—I turned—O, horror! There
                  stood Rachel, my Hebrew wife, pale as death, but with eyes that flashed like
                  living coals. I was dumb.</p>
               <p>"This gentleman is already married, my love," she said, advancing to Ellen, "and I
                  have arrived just in time to save you." Ellen looked at me—saw my face convulsed
                  with shame and rage—and without a word fell senseless on the floor. I was alone
                  with my <emph>real</emph> wife; certainly a very interesting position! Neither of
                  us spoke, but the looks which we exchanged!</p>
               <p>"I lost all my self-possession, and seizing my hat, rushed from the room, and from
                  the house. I went with all possible speed to my own mansion, where I shut myself
                  up in my study, a victim of emotions, that were certainly anything but pleasant in
                  their nature.</p>
               <p>"How did my wife discover this intrigue? Very likely she has been tracking me,
                  step by step, for months. And what will be the result of all this?" Thus I
                  remained cogitating until midnight, when my wife entered the study, and removing
                  her bonnet and shawl, seated herself near me. She was still deathly pale, and her
                  bosom heaved under her dark dress in quick and impetuous pulsations. And her
                  eyes—they were really startling in their lustre.</p>
               <p>"I have saved this girl from you, (without exposing your real name,) but the shock
                  has been too great for her reason," she began in a voice unnaturally calm. "Are
                  you not proud of your work, dear husband?"</p>
               <p>At these words the rage, which had been devouring me for hours, found vent.</p>
               <p>"Rachel, are you really a devil incarnate in a woman's form? Not satisfied with
                  forcing me to dip my hands in human blood—<emph>murderess</emph> and fiend that
                  you are—are you now determined to cross and thwart me at every turn of my life?
                  Woman!" My voice<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC5761-00000014"/> rose, and no doubt my
                  face expressed all that I felt. "Woman! I have long loathed the sight of you, but
                  now I hate you—do you hear me—hate you!"</p>
               <p>The effect of these words upon her was appalling. She grew even more deathly pale,
                  and pressed her hands convulsively upon her bosom, as though her emotions were
                  depriving her of life. Then she rose to her feet, and drew a pistol from the folds
                  of her dress. Alarmed for my safety I also started up.</p>
               <p>"Charles," she pronounced my name with livid lips—and then fired. But the pistol
                  was not aimed at me, but at her own bosom. She fell at my feet, and never spoke
                  again. She was dead.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE MANOR HOUSE AGAIN—A DARK DEED.</head>
               <p>FROM the moment in which I saw her, beautiful and dead at my feet, I was for
                  months stretched in the agonies of fever and delirium. Rachel was buried—the
                  papers were filled with the account of her "SUICIDE FROM JEALOUSY"—but I was all
                  unconscious. At last reason was restored—I awoke from my delirium, and found
                  myself in bed, surrounded by anxious attendants—I was alone in my magnificent
                  mansion. Rachel was in her grave, Ellen a hopeless lunatic, and I was utterly
                  alone in the world. Assuredly my reflections were dark and bitter.</p>
               <p>Soon after the death of Rachel a "crisis" (as the merchants and newspapers call
                  it) took place in the financial world; one of those "crashes" which strip away in
                  a single night the hoards of centuries. Thus one night I went to bed, the owner of
                  immense wealth; the next morning the banks had failed, an universal panic pervaded
                  the Union—my immense possessions were reduced to the mansion which I occupied, and
                  even that at a "forced sale" would not pay my debts. The Prince was a beggar! I
                  awoke as from a dream, and after a day's severe thought, resolved to sell my
                  mansion for what it would bring, pay my debts, and leave the country.</p>
               <p>"I will go to Spain," I thought; "I will visit Madrid—perhaps the
                     <emph>reigning</emph> family will do something to better my fortunes."</p>
               <p>My house was sold, my debts paid—<emph>six hundred dollars</emph> was all that
                  remained of my enormous wealth!</p>
               <p>Before leaving I determined to visit the Rev. Mr. Williams, which I did, and found
                  him comfortably domiciled in the Manor House, the lease of which had not been
                  affected by my changed fortunes.</p>
               <p>It was an evening in fall, when I found myself seated on one side of the broad
                  fire-place—a bright hickory fire was burning there—my aged Benefactor, with his
                  venerable face and white hairs, on the other. A shudder crept over me as I glanced
                  around the room—it was the same in which I had met Rachel on the <emph>second
                     night!</emph>
               </p>
               <p>The good old man alluded delicately to the death of Rachel, and also to my changed
                  fortunes, concluding with these words:</p>
               <p>"Strange, indeed, has been your life, dear Charles! Raised suddenly from obscurity
                  into the possession of an immense estate and a beautiful wife, you have now lost
                  both—lost everything but your education and your honour. But have courage, my dear
                  son! The future has bright deeds in store for you!"</p>
               <p>Bright deeds—alas! How could he know that Future? It was towards midnight when Mr.
                  Williams showed me to my bed chamber, and then bade me good night! It was the same
                  room in which I first beheld Rachel, in which I had murdered Gabriel Mendoza—there
                  was the bed upon which the beautiful Jewess pressed me to her bosom. It may be
                  imagined, that surrounded by such memories, sleep fled from my eyes.</p>
               <p>I placed the light on the table, and paced up and down the floor, my hands clasped
                  behind me, and my head buried on my breast. Bitter, indeed, were my reflections!
                  At length, urged by an impulse for which I cannot account, I took the light, and
                  through the still mansion descended stealthily to the cellar, and soon stood
                  beside the arch beneath which was buried the corpse of Gabriel. Still governed by
                  the unaccountable impulse, I removed the rubbish and loose timber from his grave,
                  and then with a spade (it had remained there since the fatal night) I rapidly
                  displaced the earth which covered the remains of my brother. Those remains at last
                  appeared, clad in the attire which Gabriel had worn on the night of his death. I
                  drew the half-decomposed body from the grave; the face was undistinguishable, for
                  it was one black mass of decay. Undismayed by the charnel smell which now pervaded
                  the cellar, I ran my hands over the apparel of the corpse, and soon held in my
                  hands a buckskin money belt and pocket book. The money belt was filled with
                  gold—the pocket book with notes, upon banks in Europe, which had<pb n="32-33"
                     xml:id="VAC5761-00000015"/> not been affected by the late panic. I shook with
                  joy—I was once more the owner of a fortune, not so great as the one which I had
                  lost, but still great—thirty thousand dollars!</p>
               <p>"Rest there, Gabriel," I said aloud—"I have suffered enough remorse on your
                  account, and now I am half paid for all my suffering."</p>
               <p>I pushed the body in the grave, and commenced shovelling the earth upon it, when
                  it seemed to me I heard the sound of breathing behind me. It was only fancy I
                  thought, and turned my head over my shoulder, and beheld the good clergyman, his
                  hands upraised, and his face white with horror! All was discovered; he knew that I
                  was a murderer; the gibbet began to darken horribly upon my sight.</p>
               <p>"Charles, Charles," he faltered, "your betrothal with Rachel was then cemented in
                  human blood"—and he paused and covered his face with his hands. I flung myself at
                  his feet, I told him all, I begged him to save me from exposure and disgrace, from
                  a public trial and the scaffold.</p>
               <p>He uncovered his face, and was horribly agitated; pity and horror struggled over
                  his venerable visage, but his eyes shone with a fixed resolve.</p>
               <p>"No, Charles, I cannot become your <emph>accomplice</emph>; justice must take its
                  course," he said, in a stern voice—and never spoke again. With one blow I beat him
                  to the earth with the shovel, and struck him again and again, until he ceased to
                  struggle. It was a horrible sight, his mangled face, his white hairs dabbled in
                  blood—but I had no time for remorse. I laid his body in the grave, beside that of
                  Gabriel, and then covered it from the light, with earth and pieces of loose
                  boards, until the place beneath the arch looked the same as before.</p>
               <p>Then hurrying up stairs to my room, I washed the blood from my hands and clothes,
                  and sat down to think.</p>
               <p>"The murderer of a brother, and the murderer of one who was more than father,
                  behold me!" I groaned in agony, as though addressing the dead Rachel—"Rachel, this
                  is your work!"</p>
               <p>But conscious that before morning dawned I must be far on my way, I secured the
                  money of Gabriel about my person, put on my hat and cloak, and made the best of my
                  way down stairs to the hall door. At the hall door, just as I had unclosed it, to
                  my horror I was confronted by Alice, the aged housekeeper.</p>
               <p>"Which way so early, Charles?" she said, holding the light near my face.</p>
               <p>"Mr. Williams has gone to visit a dying parishioner," I managed to frame the
                  words, "and he directed me to follow him. We'll be back ere morning, Alice."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER IX.</head>
               <head type="sub">NEW ORLEANS—CUBA—SPAIN.</head>
               <p>AND I dashed through the door, and passing through the garden, was soon upon the
                  high road. I walked rapidly from the village to she steamboat landing, where I
                  arrived about daybreak, just as the boat touched the wharf. I went on board, and
                  remained secluded in my state-room all day, until we arrived in New York. There I
                  remained concealed for a few days—long enough to see the papers filled with
                  accounts of the "Mysterious <emph>disappearance</emph> of the Rev. Abel Williams."
                  And then disguising myself with false hair and whiskers I turned my face to the
                  West. The adventures which I had in Buffalo, Cleveland, Cincinnati, Louisville,
                  St. Louis and New Orleans, would fill volumes. Some years of my history must
                  remain a blank forever.</p>
               <p>It was in the summer of 1851 that I found myself penniless and friendless in New
                  Orleans. After years of adventure I was miserably poor; my clothes almost worn to
                  rags; I had exhausted all the arts of libertine, gambler, and "man of the world,"
                  and now found myself, at the age of thirty, without a cent or a friend—a vagabond
                  upon the Levee.</p>
               <p>In this condition it was not strange that I should be induced to join the
                  expedition of Lopez "for the freedom of Cuba." Before I sailed I met with a
                  singular adventure, if adventure it can be called. One night in a gambling hell,
                  where I stood gloomily watching the chances of the game, I was accosted by a
                  gentleman of fine appearance, who, after some conversation, invited me to his
                  rooms. He was a man, as I have said, of fine appearance, elegantly dressed, but
                  there was a certain gloom upon his countenance, which showed that his heart was
                  ill at ease. Over the wine cup, won by his manner, I told him the story of my
                  life. This induced him to repose a similar confidence in me, and he told me his
                  history—what a singular and remarkable series of adventures! It was indeed as dark
                  and strange<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC5761-00000016"/> as the story of my own life.
                  Morning dawned before he had done; and he begged me to share his fortunes, but
                  Destiny beckoned me to Cuba. There were tears in his eyes as I refused his
                  generous offer. I left him, and hurried on board the steamer. He was a planter, of
                  Charleston; his name HENRY BALDWIN, or HENRY EDWARD; I forget which, or think
                  rather that he had borne both names. Where did his singular career end? I have
                  often found myself thinking of his fate as connected with "ESTHER LIVINGSTONE,"
                  and "NAOMI, the QUADROON SLAVE."<ref rend="super" target="#note_001"
                     xml:id="return_001">*</ref>
                   After our interview I went aboard the steamer, and never saw him
                   again.</p>
               <note place="foot" xml:id="note_001">
                  <p><ref target="#return_001">*</ref>NOTE BY THE EDITOR.—The singular history of the person hero named HENRY
                     BALDWIN or HENRY EDWARD, and NAOMI THE QUADROON GIRL, has lately been
                     published under the title of "HENRY BALDWIN and ESTHER LIVINGSTONE".—B.
                     T.</p>
               </note>
               <p>I sailed for Cuba, fought under Lopez at Bahia Ronda, and having been wounded and
                  left on the field for dead, awoke to life again within the dungeons of the Moro,
                  my head shaved and my right ancle confined by a heavy chain. As soon as I
                  recovered some portion of my strength, I learned that Lopez (he was a brave old
                  man) had been <emph>garoted</emph>; that Crittenden and fifty others had been
                  shot; and that the remainder of the compatriots (the Spanish-Cubans called us
                  pirates!) were to be shipped to Spain, where we were to end our days in the
                  galleys. The prospect was by no means pleasant.</p>
               <p>But in a few days I found myself on shipboard, and in thirty days we made the
                  harbour of CEULA, (I think it was,) where we were to remain until the pleasure of
                  Queen Isabella with regard to us was known. One fine autumnal day, as we were
                  swinging at anchor in the bay, a party of Spanish grandees, glittering with
                  epaulettes and embroidery, came on board to look at these "transatlantic" pirates.
                  One of these noblemen was about my height, dark complexioned, and with large
                  melancholy eyes; a sort of composition of "Don Juan" and the "Stranger." His name
                  was Don Raphael Arangua. It seems that the government had for some reason or other
                  given him a blank pardon, which he was at liberty to fill out with the name of any
                  one of the "<foreign xml:lang="SPA">filibustieros</foreign>" whom he might select.
                  He stopped before me; I was not exactly in "court dress;" my head had been shaved;
                  I was pale from my wounds; I presume I did no injustice, in appearance at least,
                  to the character of "Convict" or "Pirate."</p>
               <p>"Your name?" said Don Raphael, fixing his melancholy eyes upon me, and speaking
                  very good English.</p>
               <p>"Charles Bernard."</p>
               <p>"Your object in enlisting under Lopez?"</p>
               <p>"Others enlisted for patriotism and glory; I, because the summer was hot, I had
                  nothing to do, and what is worse, neither friends nor money."</p>
               <p>He looked stern, and then a quiet smile came over his handsome face; "Do you
                  regret having taken arms against Her Majesty?"</p>
               <p>"Very much," said I, glancing at the mark of the chain upon my ancle. "They shave
                  one's head very close at Havana."</p>
               <p>By the tone of my replies it will be easily perceived that I had become a reckless
                  desperado. Don Raphael mused for a moment, and then said to an officer who stood
                  near, "Here is a pardon for this person—release him—and let him go ashore with
                  me." I was accordingly released, clad in decent apparel, and as the sun was
                  setting over the bay, stepped on shore with Don Raphael De Arangua.</p>
               <p>"To-night, Carlos," he said familiarly, "we set out for Madrid. And at Madrid your
                  future course will be decided."</p>
               <p>This was all very mysterious, but I was ready for anything; and that night we set
                  out for Madrid, at which place we arrived next evening, just as the magnificent
                  palace of the Escurial rose grandly and dimly in the vague twilight. Our carriage
                  stopped before the doors of a lofty mansion; palace it might be called. Don
                  Raphael took my arm and conducted me through the high door, along a magnificent
                  corridor, and then into a small but antique apartment, lighted by a single wax
                  candle. He pointed me to a chair—and then seating himself near me, said:</p>
               <p>"The Queen gave me liberty to select for pardon such one of your number as I
                  pleased. I liked your face. You are now my private secretary. To-morrow you will
                  enter upon your duties. If you are faithful to me, you will never regret it." He
                  paused—"Does this meet your wishes, or do you desire to return to your own
                  country?" Bewildered by the mysterious interest which the young nobleman took in
                  me, and yet pleased with his manners and noble countenance, I replied warmly, "I
                  am yours for life, Don Raphael!"</p>
               <p>From that time I formed a prominent member of his household, was treated by him
                  with lavish kindness, and was the recipient of his most treasured and sacred
                  confidence. It seemed, in less than three months, that we had lived all our lives
                  together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC5761-00000017"/>
               <head>CHAPTER X.</head>
               <head type="sub">DON RAPHAEL IN LOVE—THE PHIAL—THE QUEEN OF SPAIN.</head>
               <p>ONE afternoon he led me to a window of the small apartment before named, and
                  pointed to the palace of the Escurial, which rose beyond the river, grand and
                  vast, in the rays of the winter sun. Pointing to the palace he made me the
                  confidant of a love adventure.</p>
               <p>"To-night, within yonder palace, in a chamber which I will reach by a private
                  stair-case, and by means of this ring, I will meet the object of this
                     <emph>intrigue</emph>—a lady high in rank—near the Queen—and what is worse,
                  wife of a nobleman, whose blood is well nigh royal." Then having detailed to me
                  minutely the manner in which he would enter the palace, he continued—</p>
               <p>"From this adventure, Carlos, I may never return. It may result in death or
                  hopeless imprisonment. If you do not see me before to-morrow night, it is my last
                  request that you deliver this packet to my nearest relative." He was much
                  agitated, and I shared his agitation as I received the packet.</p>
               <p>"Do you love this lady then so devotedly, as to peril life for her?" asked I.</p>
               <p>"<emph>She</emph> loves me," he said, passing his hand over his delicate mustache,
                  with a smile. "That is enough."</p>
               <p>Soon after cigars and wine were brought, and Don Raphael and I sat conversing upon
                  the adventure, by the light of a single wax candle. The wine was delicious; the
                  cigars of the Queen's own brand; and the hours glided pleasantly away.</p>
               <p>"At midnight I leave," said Don Raphael, glancing over his shoulder to the
                  window—I seized the moment to pour a powder into his wine glass—"It is now
                  eleven," he resumed, and drank the glass to the last drop.</p>
               <p>"This lady is then beautiful?" said I.</p>
               <p>"As an houri,"—the Don descanted on her beauty, grew eloquent, and—fell sound
                  asleep.</p>
               <p>I assumed his cap, and cloak, and poignard; took the ring from his finger; laid
                  him gently on the sofa, and covering him with my cloak—</p>
               <p>"I will dare this danger in your place, my gallant friend," I soliloquized
                  loquized, gazing on his handsome face as he slept—"In the first place I have an
                  affection for you, and in the second place—" but my second reason will be known in
                  due time. Conscious that the Don might awake in three hours, I hurried at once
                  from his palace, crossed the bridge, and in half an hour found myself in a dark
                  and narrow street, over which towers a wing of the Royal palace.</p>
               <p>A narrow door, between two pillars, rewarded a long and anxious search. I knocked
                  gently three times. It was opened—all was dark within—but a low voice, evidently a
                  woman's, pronounced the words, in Spanish of course, "You have the password?"</p>
               <p>"I have—'CUBA!'" The door opened wide, a hand was extended, and I was pulled
                  gently through the doorway. I found myself in thick darkness. The voice again
                  spoke—</p>
               <p>"Listen to my directions, and all will be well with you. Ascend the stairway right
                  before you. Take the first passage to the right. Pursue that until your course is
                  terminated by a door. At the door you will knock twice."</p>
               <p>The voice ceased, and I pursued my way, ascending the stairway, taking the
                  corridor to the right, until my progress was terminated by a door—all in thick
                  darkness. My heart beat rapidly. I knocked twice at the door. It was opened
                  gently—"The ring," said a low voice, and in the darkness I handed the ring through
                  the aperture.</p>
               <p>"All is well," said the voice, through the aperture, "take my hand and enter"—a
                  soft hand grasped mine, and I was led gently over the threshold. I found myself in
                  a gorgeous chamber, lighted very dimly, and before me stood a woman of noble form
                  thickly veiled. Even in the dim light I could see her bosom heave with rapid
                  pulsations.</p>
               <p>"Lady Isora," I whispered, and folded her in my arms. Her bosom beat against my
                  own, but she struggled and tore herself from my embrace.</p>
               <p>"I am indeed the Lady Isora," she whispered, "and it was I who asked you to dare
                  so much danger, and come hither, Don Raphael, but—" her voice faltered—"it is not
                  me alone who loves you. A mightier than myself seeks your love"—she led me gently
                  toward a curtain—"she waits for you beyond that curtain. Go—and meet—the QUEEN OF
                  SPAIN."</p>
               <p>These words were a thunderbolt; I had heard much of the Queen Isabel; of her idiot
                  husband, and numerous lovers, but to find myself in the position of one of those
                  lovers! I was for a moment utterly confounded. I rallied, however, lifted the
                  folds of a curtain,<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC5761-00000018"/> and passed from a
                  dimly lighted room into complete darkness. The place in which I stood may have
                  been large or small, poorly or magnificently furnished, but I could not tell
                  anything about it. I advanced a step—</p>
               <p>"Don Raphael De Arangua," said a woman's voice.</p>
               <p>"It is I," was the answer which I returned, and—a hand was laid upon my shoulder,
                  a bosom pressed against my own, and a form full to the extreme of voluptuousness,
                  girdled in my arms.</p>
               <p>"<emph>Queens dare not love save by stealth</emph>," said the woman's voice.</p>
               <milestone n="*     *      *      *      *" unit="typography"/>
               <p>I left the Royal palace, and regained the mansion of Don Raphael before three
                  o'clock. Happily I found him sleeping. The ring (which the Lady Isora had again
                  placed upon my finger, as I came from the apartment of the woman who called
                  herself "THE QUEEN,") I hastened to place upon Don Raphael's hand. Then, excited
                  almost to delirium by my late adventure, I sank on another sofa and feigned sleep.
                  It was not long before he awoke; he soon discovered that he had missed the hour of
                  his engagement, and raved like a madman. I did all I could to comfort him, but
                  overcome by mortification, he resolved to leave Madrid for a few days.</p>
               <p>"To think that a cup of wine should make me thus recreant!" Wine? He knew nothing
                  of the <emph>powders!</emph>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER XI.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE END.</head>
               <p>THUS far have I proceeded in my narrative. Events now gather to a
                  consummation;—to-night I am again to visit the ESCURIAL, and to-night will I tell
                  the Queen that it is not Don Raphael, but a PRINCE of the BLOOD ROYAL, <emph>her
                     own</emph> COUSIN, whom she folds to her arms! For I have discovered the secret
                  of Don Raphael's interest in me. My mother was lawfully married to the Prince, my
                  father—that marriage once acknowledged, and the <emph>crown of Spain might rest on
                     my head</emph>. For years my course has been watched by agents of Spain in the
                  United States. I was tracked from the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">levee</foreign> of
                  New Orleans, to the dungeons of the Moro, and the galleys of Ceuta. When Don
                  Raphael singled me out, he knew that the "<foreign xml:lang="SPA"
                     >Filibustier</foreign>" before him was of royal blood, but <emph>one
                     remove</emph> from the Crown! And he, backed by a powerful party, has been
                  keeping me in reserve for some important movement, of which I am kept in
                  ignorance. These facts I have discovered by an inspection of the packet, (which
                  the Don carelessly left behind him, together with the ring, before he left Madrid,
                  from which he has now been absent three days,) and having broken the seals of the
                  packet, all is now clear to me. How lucky that the thought struck me to take Don
                  Raphael's place! And to-night I will see my royal cousin, Isabel of Spain.<ref rend="super" target="#note_002" xml:id="return_002">*</ref>
               </p>
               <note xml:id="note_002">
                  <p><ref target="#return_002">*</ref>[NOTE.-The above is all that is written in the hand of CHARLES BERNARD,
                     otherwise PRINCE ——. What follows is written in a different hand; perhaps
                     the hand of the Lady Isora, or that of Don Raphael.]</p>
               </note>
               <p>The fate of the unfortunate Charles Bernard, otherwise PRINCE ——, was never known
                  to the world. But on the night designated above, he again visited the Royal
                  palace, and again passed into the chamber of the lady who called herself "THE
                  QUEEN." The Lady Isora, waiting in the next chamber, heard him utter these
                     words—"<emph>I am not Don Raphael De Arangua, but your cousin</emph>, PRINCE
                  ——!" He was never seen to emerge from the palace, and the Lady Isora and Don
                  Raphael have in vain tried to discover his fate. In vain! Among the galley slaves,
                  at Ceuta, there is one who much resembles the Prince, only he is sightless and
                  dumb, having been evidently deprived of his tongue and eyes. Unfortunate Prince!
                  To realize in the Nineteenth Century, in your own person, the dark history of the
                  Man in the Iron Mask!</p>
               <pb n="40 (Illustration) -41" xml:id="VAC5761-00000019"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>"SHE HAD EVIDENTLY BEEN TORN FROM HER BED, BY THE RUFFIAN WHO WAS NOW
                        CHOKING HER TO DEATH. I WAS UNARMED, YET I SPRANG FORWARD. THE RUFFIAN
                        TURNED, SPRANG TO HIS FEET, AND CONFRONTED ME; HE DREW A PISTOL FROM THE
                        POCKET OF HIS COAT, AND WITHOUT A WORD PRESENTED IT, AND DREW THE
                        TRIGGER."</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
