<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC5737">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>My Ten-rod Farm, or, How I Became a Florist </title>
            <author>Barnard, Charles (1838-1920)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC5737</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-0218</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                    participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>My ten-rod farm, or, How I became a florist</title>
                  <author>Barnard, Charles (1838-1920)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>119 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Loring</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1869">1869</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="AEL Data" when="2003-02-12">Finished transcription and SGML encoding</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2003-02-24">Finished TEI conversion and final editing</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-04-22">Converted document from SGML to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-04-22">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC5737-00000001"/>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>MY TEN-ROD FARM;</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">OR, HOW I BECAME A FLORIST.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>BY <docAuthor>MRS. MARIA GILMAN.</docAuthor>
            </byline>
            <docImprint>
               <publisher>LORING, Publisher,</publisher>
               <pubPlace>319 WASHINGTON STREET, BOSTON.</pubPlace>
            </docImprint>
            <docDate when="1869">1869.</docDate>
         </titlePage>
         <pb n="3" xml:id="VAC5737-00000002"/>
         <div type="fly_title">
            <bibl>
               <edition>Entered, according to act of Congress, in the year 1869, by A. K. LORING, In the Clerk's Office of the District Court for the District of Massachusetts.</edition>
               <publisher>ROCKWELL &amp; ROLLINS, PRINTERS AND STEREOTYPERS,</publisher>
               <pubPlace>122 Washington Street.</pubPlace>
            </bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <p>This,<lb/> THE AUTHOR'S FIRST EFFORT, IS RESPECTFULLY DEDICATED<lb/> TO<lb/> ALL TRUE WORKERS,<lb/> IN WHATEVER FIELD.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>My ten-rod farm, or, How I became a florist</head>
            <pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC5737-00000003"/>
            <head>MY TEN-ROD FARM;</head>
            <head type="sub">OR, HOW I BECAME A FLORIST.</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE COMING OF TROUBLE.—THE BEGINNING OF HOPE.</head>
               <p>MY name is Maria Gilman. I am a widow. These are my two children,—John, fifteen years of age, who is studying to be a gardener, and Mary, twelve years old, who attends the high school at the Centre, where I reside. I own the house in which I live, the furniture, the large greenhouse in the yard, and, in fact, the entire estate,—one hundred and sixty feet by seventy-five,—which I familiarly speak of as my Ten-Rod Farm. I keep a man-servant and a maid-of-all-work. My income is two thousand dollars a year, and I am out of debt. Five years ago I was poor and in great affliction. Now I am independent, though not quite free from sorrow, for the memory of my husband will always remain with me.</p>
               <p>If it would interest you, I will give you a portion of my life history, and explain how it was that I, a comparatively<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC5737-00000004"/> poor woman, have made a place for myself in the world and become rich, and all this with my own hands.</p>
               <p>My parents were in comfortable circumstances, and, like most girls of my class, I was brought up with little or no knowledge of how to work. I could play and sing as well as most girls. I knew how to sew; but, beyond this, comparatively nothing. I was married to Mr. Gilman when I was twenty. My parents both died soon after. My new home was always one of ease and comfort,—my husband being foreman of the large mill you see yonder, and in receipt of a liberal income. My life from my youth up was one long happiness, until that dark and sad day when my husband was brought home, on a lovely June morning, mangled and dead,—killed in the mill. From that moment my sorrows began. Let me pass over the terrible days that followed. I do not remember much about them. I seemed lost in a horrid dream, and only awoke to the sad reality when I was forced to attend to the pressing wants of myself and children.</p>
               <p>Then I knew the meaning of loneliness and poverty. At first I could not look at my condition. They said something to me about the house being sold.</p>
               <p>"Sell my husband's house and home! Leave this place, leave my home, go away from this garden planted and tended by his hands? No, I will never do it."</p>
               <p>"But you must. There is a mortgage on it, and you had better sell out and find a room or two to live in." It was my brother Joseph who had said this. He lives near by. He is a married man, with a large family, and is far from rich. Doubtless he was right in what he said. I did not know how that was. I was in too much trouble to think of anything then.</p>
               <p>"Joseph," I said, "give me time to think. Wait a few days, and I will talk with you again." Going to my room, I sat down to think. Yes, to think! Thinking was something I had never been called upon to do. It had been my lot simply to enjoy. I looked over the state of affairs, and found these hard facts: the house I occupied was worth two thousand dollars; part of the purchase money was paid, and five hundred dollars still remained on a mortgage; there was an insurance of two thousand dollars on my husband's life. And what else? Nothing. Not a cent of income of any sort. When the bills of the funeral were paid I found I should have just twenty-five dollars on hand from my husband's wages, and no more. Give up the house I would not,—at least, not until I was obliged to. No! I would stay where I was,—find something to do and support myself and children as best I could. But then what could I do? Teach? No, indeed. All I knew of music when I was a girl had been lost long ago. Take a school? Could I get one? I imagined not. All the places are spoken for long before they are vacant. What, then, could I do? Plainly, nothing but sewing. I must support myself by my needle. Thank God, I could do that. Accordingly<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC5737-00000005"/> ingly, the next day, after sending the children to school, I took the train for the city in search of work. Need I tell you the miserable story? How I went from shop to shop literally "despised and rejected of men." The second day was as the first—nothing. The third was still more hopeless. The fourth day I found some work, and took it home. After sitting up part of that night, all the next day, and far into the next evening, I finished the work, and carried it to the city, and received for my eighteen hours' labor, only seventy-nine cents. The price was so out of all proportion to the amount of toil, and seemed to me so utterly cruel, that I took the money, found my way to the cars somehow, and finally reached my home, tired and almost broken-hearted. I was awakened the next morning by confused noises in the street. Wondering what it could mean, I got up and went down stairs. I found the children already up and trying to make a breakfast of bread and water. "What is the matter?" asked I.</p>
               <p>"Fourth of July, mother. Didn't you know it? I am going to the pond to fish with the boys." The Fourth of July, and everybody happy and making holiday. All happy but me. And then—more tears. After a while I busied myself about the house until my brother Joseph came in after dinner. He began at once.</p>
               <p>"Now, Maria, do listen to reason. Sell this house, invest the money with the insurance, and live on the interest. It will give you about two hundred a year, and you can get on very well with that, if you put Johnny at a trade, and let Mary go into the factory."</p>
               <p>"Joseph," I cried, "what do you mean? My Mary in the mill?"</p>
               <p>"Well, just as you like,—I can't help you."</p>
               <p>After he had gone, I lay down sick, weary, and utterly dejected.</p>
               <p>I had not been in my room long, before Mary came to me and said a young lady wished to see me at the door. Washing away the tear-stains, I went down to the front door, and found Miss Dwight from the grand house over the way.</p>
               <p>"Mrs. Gilman, I have a great favor to ask; come into the garden a moment."</p>
               <p>Throwing something over my head, I followed her out into my flower-garden. The sun was bright, and the air fragrant with mignonette. The cheerful, balmy warmth revived me, and I felt better. We went into the walk, among the flowers. It was my husband's garden. He was passionately fond of flowers, and had planted and tended them with his own hands. I had not been in the garden since he died, yet the sight did not make me sad; I was rather pleased than otherwise. He seemed to be nearer to me, and from that moment I began to love the flowers for his sake. Presently Miss Dwight stopped before a brilliant geranium, and, turning to me, said:—</p>
               <p>"Mrs. Gilman, we have friends to dinner to-day. We ordered some flowers of the florist, but they have not come,<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC5737-00000006"/> and I wish you to do me the favor of selling some of yours."</p>
               <p>"Sell my flowers! No, indeed! I will give you all you wish."</p>
               <p>"No, I cannot take them so; I wish to buy them."</p>
               <p>"What, sell my husband's flowers? Oh, no!"</p>
               <p>"Now, Mrs. Gilman, please listen a moment. Flowers are a merchantable article. You have them, and I wish to purchase. I am sure your husband would not object, were he alive."</p>
               <p>Then I thought of my poverty, of my search for work, and of the children. That decided me.</p>
               <p>"Yes," I said at last, "I will sell you some, but I know nothing of their value."</p>
               <p>"But I do. I buy them often, and will give you just what others charge me."</p>
               <p>Without more words, she took out a pair of scissors and began snipping off the flowers. At first, I could not bear to see her do it, and walked apart by myself. After a while, I thought better of it, and even helped her fill her basket. When it was full, she turned to me with a smile, and said:—</p>
               <p>"I am greatly obliged to you, Mrs. Gilman. These are just what I wanted." And, handing me a bill, she went away.</p>
               <p>Re-entering the house, I drew down the curtains, to shut out the sight and sound of the happy people in the village street, and sat down to think over my wretched lot. While I turned over in my mind all the sad details of my situation, I twisted the bit of paper in my hand till I nearly tore it in two. This brought me to myself again, and I mechanically unrolled the bill and looked at it.</p>
               <p>"There must be some mistake. What could she have been thinking of? She has paid me too much. It was not possible that those flowers were worth five dollars." And yet, there it was,—a new, clean, five-dollar bill,—more money than I could earn in a week of sewing!</p>
               <p>In a moment I had my things on, and fairly flew across the street, and hastily rang the Dwights' bell. To the servant who came to the door I handed the bill, saying:—</p>
               <p>"Give that to Miss Dwight, if you please, and tell her that Mrs. Gilman thinks there is some mistake."</p>
               <p>In a few moments the servant returned, and, giving me the bill again, informed me, with Miss Dwight's compliments, that everything was quite correct.</p>
               <p>Turning from their door, I walked slowly home just as the sun was going down. As I entered my gate, a new idea suddenly came to me. Quickening my pace, I ran upstairs to my room. No time for tears now. My opportunity had come. God had not forsaken the widow and fatherless. It only remained for me to improve the opportunity which He had thrown in my path.</p>
               <p>Taking a bandbox from the closet, and an old penknife from my husband's bureau, I returned to the garden and<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC5737-00000007"/> began to cut the flowers,—verbenas, geraniums, mignonette, fuchsias, and roses, by the handful. Filling my box, I carried them into the kitchen, and, procuring all the empty pans I could find, I placed the flowers in water and arranged them on the table. "No, that will not do; the children will see them." So, one at a time, I carried the pans, now glowing with color, downstairs, and placed them all in the cool, dark cellar. The next morning, I was up very early; and, after getting the children's breakfast ready for them, gathered all the flowers together from the cellar, put them in the bandbox, got my hat, shawl, and veil, and started for the railroad.</p>
               <p>The cars had not arrived when I reached the station; so I was obliged to wait among a crowd of men and boys and a few girls, all going to their work in the city by the first morning train. Soon the engine appeared, and we started. I felt lonely indeed, and was almost the only woman in the throng. The conductor knew me, but seemed puzzled to see me. "What brings you here at this early hour?" I dare say, he thought.</p>
               <p>In due time we ran into the great depot in the city. I had never been in the streets so early in the morning before. Everything seemed strange. Plenty of people were stirring, but they were all of a class which I had seldom met. Only a few stores were open, and before these, boys and men were busily sweeping out and taking down the shutters. I had to pick my way along carefully, for it did seem as if the servants were washing down all the door-steps at once.</p>
               <p>Coming out upon Trimountain Avenue, near the park, I began to look about for a flower-stand, or seed store. Soon I came to one, and looked in. There was no one there but a boy with his broom, so I passed on. Presently I came to another. The clean marble floor and handsome showcase, filled with all sorts of garden nicknacks, tempted me in. Seeing a young man behind the counter, I went up to him, and, opening my box, laid it upon the wet marble slab before him.</p>
               <p>"Are those flowers for sale?" said he.</p>
               <p>"Yes, sir."</p>
               <p>"What will you take for them?"</p>
               <p>"Anything that is fair. I know nothing of their value. I trust to you to give me whatever they are worth."</p>
               <p>He at once turned the flowers out, and, pushing my box towards me, handed me a bill. Placing the box under my shawl, I went out, and reached the cars in time for the first train home. At my door I met the children.</p>
               <p>"Why, where have you been, mother? We thought you must have run away."</p>
               <p>"No, no. I have been to town on an errand among the shops."</p>
               <p>"What! shopping at this time of day?"</p>
               <p>"Yes; but come, eat your breakfast and be off to school, for I am busy now."</p>
               <pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC5737-00000008"/>
               <p>My pride forced me to say this. It was not strictly true; yet I had been shopping,—as a seller.</p>
               <p>After they had gone to school, I put away my things, and carefully locked up the still fragrant bandbox. I did not wish my children to know what I had done. It was a foolish pride,—that, after a fall or two, was quite cured. Taking my purse from my pocket, I unrolled the bill I received for the flowers. It was a two-dollar bill. To tell the truth, I was a little disappointed. From the sum I had received from Miss Dwight, I expected to get more than two dollars. But then, I remembered that Miss Dwight took them at first-hand, whereas the man bought at wholesale to sell again. However, I put the two dollars with Miss Dwight's five, and, going to market, I procured enough to supply our table for several days. After bringing my purchases home, I found I had still one dollar left. Quite overjoyed at the new turn affairs had taken, I put on my sun-bonnet and went out, ostensibly to walk in the garden, but really to take an account of stock in my new trade. I went carefully over the whole ground; counted every plant, and tried to estimate how much money I could cut from my flower-beds. If I could do as well as I had this morning, I might snap my fingers at the sewing-shops, keep my house, and be independent of Joseph and every one else. Soon I was surprised to hear the factory-bell ring for dinner, and directly the children returned from school. Going into the house, I spread a bountiful table, and sat down to dinner with a wonderful appetite. It seemed as if I had never been so hungry, nor in such good health and spirits before.</p>
               <p>The next morning I again made my appearance before the man in the flower store. This time he did not seem so much pleased with my flowers. He looked at them for a moment, and then carefully picked them over, arranging them in two heaps upon the wet counter.</p>
               <p>"I can't take all of these. Those," said he, pointing to one heap, "are not salable. They drop too quick."</p>
               <p>To this I could say nothing, so I took up my box and prepared to leave.</p>
               <p>But he detained me, and said, "I will pay you for the good ones, but you need not bring those poor sorts any more."</p>
               <p>He then passed me a bill with one hand, and with the other pushed one of the little heaps of flowers from the counter to the floor behind him. Just as they fell over I stole a glance at them, and observed among them some petunias and marigolds.</p>
               <p>So, then, I have learned one thing to-day. Petunias and marigolds are not salable. As soon as I reached the train, and was alone in the car, for there were but few people travelling at that hour of the morning, I opened the bill and again found two dollars.</p>
               <p>The next day was Sunday. It being a day of rest, I could not gather my flowers at evening, and the next morning<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC5737-00000009"/> ing I was obliged to get up quite early, in order to cut them in time for the early train. By working very hard and fast I managed to get a box full, carefully omitting the petunias and marigolds.</p>
               <p>When I opened my box on the counter, in the flower store, I found many of my flowers had wilted. Quite mortified at the wretched appearance they presented, I laid them before the man, expecting he would condemn the whole of them this time.</p>
               <p>As soon as he saw them he took up a watering-pot, and fairly deluged them with water.</p>
               <p>"You cut them in the sunlight," said he. "If you wish to have them fresh, you must cut them the evening before." Much wondering at this, I took my money and went home. This time I found I only had a dollar and a half. So much for not knowing that flowers must not be cut in the morning. However, the experience was well worth the cost. After breakfast, I took out my sewing and sat down to think over my new business. If I could go out in my garden every day, and in a few moments cut enough flowers to support me through that day, I should be well off; for all the remainder of the day I could be busy about something else. But could I do this? Would not the garden require some attention? I would go out and see. Suiting the action to the word, I put on my sun-bonnet, and started out to inspect. The first things I noticed were the weeds. Yes, weeds, plenty of them. Surely this will not do. I can't have flowers and weeds too. Ignorant as I was, I knew enough for that. Selecting a corner where I could not be seen from the street, I set to work pulling them up by hand. Pretty hard work I soon found it, and it did seem as if the sun was very powerful that day. After weeding a while, I had to give it up and rest. Walking about to get rid of the back-ache, I came to a large bed of petunias. What a pity there are so many of them, and yet no income from them! So mercenary had I become, weighing flowers by their money value only! Soon I went back to my weeding. Now this is all very well, but it is terrible hard work. Why did I not think of it before? Get a hoe. Going to the tool-room I found one, and returned to my work. Now, this is something like. I can get on twice as fast. Dear me! is it twelve already? Where has the morning gone? When the children came, we had dinner. Dear me! again, how hungry I am. I never had such an appetite! After dinner, I went at it again. After a while, I found my hoe so heavy that I sat down on a stone seat near a bed of marigolds. They were very weedy. What a pity to spend labor on them for nothing! I wish they had never been planted. About six, I got my box and began to cut again for the next day's sale. Somehow the flowers did not seem as plenty as on the day before. All I could get for them, the next day, was a dollar and seventy-five cents. The day after, I again tried the weeding. I was very tired at night, but it was vastly pleasanter<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC5737-00000010"/> anter work than sewing, and already I felt the good effects of my out-door life. That evening I experienced still more difficulty in filling my box.</p>
               <p>"You cut too often," said the man in the store, the next day. "If you cut every other day you will allow them time to recover, and get just as much money. You did not bring my mignonette this morning."</p>
               <p>"No; my bed is small, and I cut it quite close."</p>
               <p>"You should plant another; it will come in late for fall flowers."</p>
               <p>"Where can I get seed?" said I.</p>
               <p>"Oh, we have it. Johnny, bring the lady an ounce of mignonette."</p>
               <p>The boy brought the seed and placed it in my box; not quite knowing what to do, I hesitated about taking it.</p>
               <p>"I have not any room to plant more," said I.</p>
               <p>"Make room. Pull up something else."</p>
               <p>Taking my money, and paying the lad twenty cents for the seed, I went home.</p>
               <p>After the children had gone to school, I went into the garden to make my first horticultural venture. Now what shall I remove in order to gain room? Oh, the petunias. Not without a pang to think I was tearing up my husband's pets, I ruthlessly rooted them all out and threw them on the path. What a deal of trouble I might have saved myself, if I could have pulled up the weeds at the same time! Raking the ground smooth, I got ready to plant. Well, how is it done? I never planted a seed in my life. "Directions for planting." How nice! Full directions on the package. "Sow thinly on the surface, and rake it in." And I did, and afterwards contemplated my new-made bed with considerable satisfaction. It was not a large bed. About twenty feet by three.</p>
               <p>"Law sakes! do look at Miss Gilman."</p>
               <p>Turning round, to see where the voice that suddenly broke on my ear came from, I beheld the ruddy face of my next neighbor, surmounted by a "coal-scuttle" bonnet, peering over the fence at me.</p>
               <p>"Good-morning, Mrs. Jacques. Fine day, is it not?"</p>
               <p>"Day's fine enough, but what on airth are you doing?"</p>
               <p>"Me? Oh, I am putting my garden to rights."</p>
               <p>"I should say you was. Look at all them petunias lying there! I should say you was putting them to wrongs."</p>
               <p>Finding myself caught, I replied that "I never did think much of petunias. I preferred mignonette."</p>
               <p>"What, planting more, with all that bed full now. Well, I never!"</p>
               <p>Upon which she put up her linen-gloved hands and disappeared.</p>
               <p>"I shall not hear the last of that, I know," and, gathering up the remains of the petunias, I went into the house.</p>
               <p>Soon after dinner, I finished the weeding, and, as there did not seem to be anything more to do that day, I improved the time in some other way. As I intended to take<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC5737-00000011"/> the young man's advice, and not cut till the next day, I had a nice long evening at my sewing.</p>
               <p>The following morning I again inspected my garden, and found the flowers were coming out grandly. All the summer roses seemed to be doing their best, and verbenas, fuchsias, and lilies, all exhibited a cheerful show of flowers, ready to be turned into money for myself and little ones. I fairly laughed to see them. Perhaps if I had known how much labor and trouble they would give me before the summer was over I should not have been so cheerful; yet with all the labor came a sure reward. I cut an extra large lot that evening. I even called the children to help me, telling them I wished to send the flowers away.</p>
               <p>I received two dollars and a half for this lot of flowers.</p>
               <p>Again I omitted to cut the next day, and, on Saturday, took in a fine lot of flowers, as I thought. I found, however, that my ignorance again caused me a loss. All I received was one dollar and a half. Verbenas were not permanent enough. They could not be used for fine work. Only choice flowers were of any value in the summer. I must bring only nice green, buds, heliotrope, and choice stuff. Glad that my ignorance had not cost me more, I went home to the children, quite resolved on my future course. I had now found out one fact for certain. Flowers could be sold readily. Could I grow enough of them to support myself? That was a question I could not answer. But I could try. It would not cost much for the present, at least, and so far everything seemed encouraging. Yes, I would try. I would set up for a gardener. Why not? Could not I become a florist as well as a man? It was worth trying. It being Saturday, the children were both at home. After breakfast I called them to me and told them what I had been doing, and of my plans for the future. They did not quite understand it all, but were greatly pleased with the idea of working in the garden, and gathering the flowers.</p>
               <p>"I can cut the roses with the scissors Aunt Charlotte gave me. Mayn't I, mother?"</p>
               <p>"And I can rake the walks, and pull up the weeds, just as father used to do."</p>
               <p>"Oh, you can't rake, Johnny. You aint big enough."</p>
               <p>"Yes, I am. Mother knows I can."</p>
               <p>"Yes, dears, you shall both help mother, and we shall get on famously together."</p>
               <p>So this is the way in which I took my children into partnership, and began life as a florist. That night I made a small blank-book out of a sheet of foolscap and entered therein an account of the week's receipts and expenditures. It stood somewhat in this wise:— <table>
                     <head>July 14.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Received for flowers.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Paid.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>From last week,</cell>
                        <cell>9 00</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>For fares,</cell>
                        <cell>.40</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Rec'd this week,</cell>
                        <cell>7 50</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>For seed,</cell>
                        <cell>.20</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>16 50</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>For fare,</cell>
                        <cell>.80</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Paid,</cell>
                        <cell>1 40</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>$1 40</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>$15 10 Net.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC5737-00000012"/>
               <p>Fifteen dollars and ten cents so far, and little or no trouble as yet. It would be foolish to expect this all the time. Flowers could not be raised for nothing, or without labor. How much labor it did cost, and how much was left afterwards, must be told in the next chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
               <head type="sub">NEW FRIENDS AND NEW FLOWERS.</head>
               <p>THE next day opened fine and warm. In the morning we went to church. My husband had fortunately paid for pew-rent in advance; so I resolved to occupy it as long as I could. I did not intend to take a back seat until obliged to. In the afternoon the heat was so oppressive that I stayed at home and read aloud to the children. In the midst of our reading I heard a low rumble as of distant thunder. Not thinking anything about it I continued reading. Again the thunder pealed, and louder than before. A shower was evidently approaching. Then I remembered the garden, and wondered what effect the rain would have upon my flowers. I must go out and have a look at it. Calling the children to see the coming storm, we went out to the yard. On going outside the front gate, I looked up the village street and saw dark masses of clouds piling up the northwestern sky. Calling their attention to the sight, I tried to explain to them that, threatening and terrible as it seemed, yet the rain would wash away the dust and revive the grass and the flowers.</p>
               <p>"Yes, mother," said Johnny; "but won't it spoil all your flowers?"</p>
               <pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC5737-00000013"/>
               <p>"Why, yes. That is a bright idea, Johnny! Now what shall we do? If we leave them where they are, we shall not have very nice-looking flowers to take to the store in the morning." Just then the village clock struck three. But it is Sunday. We should not work on Sunday. But we must. It cannot be helped. It is a work of necessity.</p>
               <p>Getting my old box, I set the children at it, bidding them be careful and not injure the beds, and yet work as fast as they could. Hastily filling the box, I carried it to the house, emptied the flowers out upon the kitchen table, and returned for more. Suddenly I was startled by a loud clap of thunder, and by the noise of persons hurrying past our gate. Oh, here is the rain—and the people! I don't know which I dread most. Calling the children away, I seized the box and darted into the house. Just then the rain came down in torrents, and the sidewalk was filled with friends and neighbors hurrying home.</p>
               <p>"Well, that was a lucky escape!"</p>
               <p>But perhaps it was a foolish pride. I had no need to fear the opinion of the neighbors. What I had done was a work of positive necessity, and must be done even though it was Sunday.</p>
               <p>I overslept myself the next morning, and was late to the train. I had hardly time to take the cars before they started. The car I entered was quite full of men and boys. I found an empty seat beside an elderly man, and, as he kindly made room for me, I sat down. Just as I did so, the cover of my box, which in my haste I had not fastened down, came off, displaying the brilliant contents.</p>
               <p>"Them's fine flowers you have, ma'am."</p>
               <p>I stared at the man, quite surprised at what seemed to me a piece of impertinence.</p>
               <p>"No offence, ma'am, but they are fine ones."</p>
               <p>"Yes," I said, and, replacing the cover of the box, I attempted to pull down my veil, to show that I did not care for further conversation.</p>
               <p>"Goodness! I've left my veil at home. What shall I do now? Well, it can't be helped; I may as well put a cheerful face on it. Luckily I shall not meet any one I know or any of the Centre people. If I were at home I should have a fit of the blues, but here I am in the city and enough to do and think about in finding a market for my flowers."</p>
               <p>While I was in the flower store, who should enter but my railroad acquaintance, carrying a small green box in his hand! Coming to the counter, he laid it down, and said to the man:—</p>
               <p>"Good-morning, Thomas."</p>
               <p>"Good-morning, Mr. McTernan. Have you any white flowers?"</p>
               <p>"Tubes, jasmines, and lilliums. Will that suit ye?"</p>
               <p>Upon which he opened his box and took out a small handful of wax-like white flowers, with a most overpowering fragrance. All this time I had resolutely turned my back<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC5737-00000014"/> upon the two men, determined not to be recognized. But my curiosity was too much for me.</p>
               <p>"What are those flowers?"</p>
               <p>"Tubes, ma'am."</p>
               <p>"Tubes? I never saw or heard of them before!"</p>
               <p>"Tuberoses," suggested Thomas, behind the counter.</p>
               <p>"Are those tuberoses? I have heard of them, but never saw them before."</p>
               <p>"Yes, ma'am," said Mr. McTernan. "There's the double tuberose."</p>
               <p>He then turned out the remainder of his flowers, and afterward handed to the young man, who, as I had now discovered, rejoiced in the name of Thomas, a small slip of paper. Thomas merely glanced at it, and, writing something upon it, gave it back to my travelling companion. All these things I watched with interest, eager to find out all I could in relation to my new trade. But the man only took it and went away toward another part of the store.</p>
               <p>On my way to the cars, I turned over in my mind what I had seen and heard in regard to this to me new flower.</p>
               <p>I wonder if I could not grow tuberoses. Such flowers must be valuable. I wish I had been bright enough to ask the man about them. What is the use of my miserable pride? It is always standing in my way. Just because the man was illiterate, and had rough hands, I had avoided him. He was neatly but plainly dressed, and had a weather-stained, yet kindly and honest face. He must be a—</p>
               <p>"Ma'am? Excuse me, ma'am, but I must speak to ye a moment."</p>
               <p>Turning round to see who had the audacity to address me in the public street, I found Mr. McTernan,—box and all.</p>
               <p>"Excuse me, ma'am, if I make bold to say that ye mustn't sell your flowers so cheap. Ye must charge him more. Make 'em pay—"</p>
               <p>"Sir," I cried, "how dare you! What is it to you? I'll thank you to leave me."</p>
               <p>"Just as ye like. But it was for your own good I was telling ye."</p>
               <p>Somewhat mollified, I replied, "How is that?"</p>
               <p>"Why, ye see that box of flowers ye had was worth more than he gave ye."</p>
               <p>"How do you know anything about it?" said I, annoyed and perplexed at the whole adventure.</p>
               <p>"Well, ma'am, I grows flowers myself, and I know what they are worth; and all he gave you was two dollars for the lot."</p>
               <p>"How do you know what he gave me?"</p>
               <p>"I seen him hand it ye."</p>
               <p>Now, to tell the truth, I had not looked at the money; so I opened my purse, and sure enough it was two dollars.</p>
               <p>"And, ma'am, it's not right to take the money without<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC5737-00000015"/> looking at it. Them flower fellows is mighty sharp sometimes."</p>
               <p>All the time I walked rapidly on towards the depot; but Mr. McTernan quickened his pace, and kept by my side.</p>
               <p>Oh dear, he is, perhaps, very kind, but I do wish he would go away. But he would not, and after what he had said I had not the heart to be so rude as to ask him to leave me.</p>
               <p>As we entered the depot, a great crowd of people came out of a newly arrived train, filling the whole building and streaming for the doors.</p>
               <p>If this man would only go away. Here come plenty of my neighbors from the Centre. What will they think of me in the company of this man? If I only had my veil. I must give him the slip somehow. But it was of no use. He gravely escorted me to our train, and stood near the door for me to enter. I think I must have blushed scarlet, for it did seem as if everybody in our village had chosen to come to town on that particular train. Quite vexed, I entered the car and took a seat in a dark corner, entirely ignoring my companion. He did not seem to notice it, but took a seat not far off, and, opening a paper, began to read. As for me, I was in a perfect rage at the whole affair. Will the cars never start? Shall I never get home, away from this hateful place? I declare I'll never sell another flower. I'll starve first. After a while we <emph>did</emph> start. The motion and the changing scene turned the current of my thoughts, and I soon got over my pet.</p>
               <p>Tuberoses! I declare, I can smell them now. How lovely they were! Wish I could grow them. I wonder whether he'll tell me if I ask him? Without another thought, I boldly got up and went over and sat down in the next seat behind the man whom I had thought so rude.</p>
               <p>"If you please, Mr. McTernan, I wish to ask your pardon—"</p>
               <p>"Pardon, ma'am! for what? I was only telling ye for your own good. You see, this is the way he does it," and taking from his pocket a slip of paper, he handed it to me. This is a copy of it:— <table>
                     <head>July 17.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>CR.</cell>
                        <cell>JAMES McTERNAN.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3 doz. Tuberoses</cell>
                        <cell>$3 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4 doz. Buds</cell>
                        <cell>2 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6 doz. Heliotrope</cell>
                        <cell>1 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2 doz. Jasmine</cell>
                        <cell>1 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3 doz. Lillium Candidum</cell>
                        <cell>1 50</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Cut flowers</cell>
                        <cell>3 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>T. D.</cell>
                        <cell>$11 50</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>"That is my bill. I brought those flowers in this morning, and that's what I got for them. Thomas puts his mark on it, and then I shows it to Jane. She's the clerk. You see they pay us by the dozen, so much for each sort. I'm getting, as ye see, one dollar a dozen for my tubes. Now,<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC5737-00000016"/> if ye had counted the flowers ye brought in, ye would have got more for them."</p>
               <p>"Why, Mr. McTernan, you are indeed kind. I am greatly obliged to you for telling me this. It is very good in you. I had not expected such kindness from a perfect stranger."</p>
               <p>"Oh, never ye mind; I likes to help folks if I can."</p>
               <p>"Now, I have one favor more to ask, Mr. McTernan. Tell me about the tubes, as you call them. How do you grow them? They must be valuable to command a dollar a dozen."</p>
               <p>"Yes, they is a paying flower. They aint always worth that. In the fall they get down to fifty cents. Grow 'em? Oh, it's easy enough. I pots them in five inch and plunges them. When they show a stem I gives a shift and tie 'em up."</p>
               <p>"Thank you. I must try a few. Where can I get some seeds?"</p>
               <p>"Seed, ma'am? They isn't a seed. It's a bulb. Thomas Dacy has 'em for sale."</p>
               <p>"Thomas Dacy, who is he?"</p>
               <p>"The bouquet man at the store. He that buys all the flowers."</p>
               <p>Just then the train slacked up, and, looking out of the window, I found that I was at home.</p>
               <p>"Good-morning, Mr. McTernan."</p>
               <p>"Good-morning, ma'am."</p>
               <p>Reaching the house, I found Mary standing at the gate with a folded paper in her hand.</p>
               <p>"See, mother; father's paper has come."</p>
               <p>"What paper, dear?"</p>
               <p>"The 'Agriculturist.' I found it in our box at the post-office. May I open it, mother?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, if you wish. But let us have some breakfast."</p>
               <p>After eating our meal, and putting the house in order, I went to the garden to see if the shower of yesterday had done any harm. I found that it had; the beds I had raked so smooth, a few days since, were ploughed and torn up by the rain, and many of the plants were broken down by the wind. There were but very few flowers to be seen. Most of them were soiled and faded. How fortunate I was in cutting them yesterday afternoon! Finding things in such a deplorable condition, I resolved to spend the day in repairing damages. Getting a rake from the tool-house, I began to rake over the beds and put things as near right as I knew how.</p>
               <p>All the while I was so much interested in what I was doing, that I paid no attention to where or how I began. Indeed, I never thought of getting out of sight; but boldly went to work in full view of all the passers in the village street. I had not been occupied long before I was aware of some one standing on the sidewalk, and looking over the fence at me. I say I was aware of it; for I was too busy to stop to look up and see who it was.</p>
               <pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC5737-00000017"/>
               <p>Presently, whoever it was passed on. Soon some one else came up, paused, and stood looking at me. Then a third person joined the second, and stared over my fence. But I paid no heed to them, going on with my work as though there was no one there. Then the two ladies began to talk to each other. I could hear every word.</p>
               <p>"Sad, isn't it?"</p>
               <p>"Yes."</p>
               <p>"They do say the blow was too much for her."</p>
               <p>"She thinks her husband is coming home and wants his garden put to rights."</p>
               <p>"What a pity! And the children too."</p>
               <p>"Bad for them."</p>
               <p>At length one of them spoke aloud, and said, "Good-morning, Mrs. Gilman."</p>
               <p>"Good-morning, good-morning," replied I, looking at the pair. "Good-morning, Mrs. Smith, good-morning, Mrs. Carter,"—for those were the gossips' names.</p>
               <p>"Fine day, is it not?"</p>
               <p>"Yes."</p>
               <p>"I say, Mrs. Gilman, have you any petunias in your garden?"</p>
               <p>"No, I pulled them all up. They don't pay."</p>
               <p>Upon which the two women exchanged a meaning glance, as much as to say, "It is true then."</p>
               <p>"I don't think they are a profitable flower to raise."</p>
               <p>Then another meaning look, and, with a solemn shaking of heads, they departed, muttering to themselves:—</p>
               <p>"How sad! How sad!"</p>
               <p>As for me, I made a mock heroic flourish with my rake, and executed as profound a courtesy as I knew how. Then I stuck my rake up in the ground and made a speech at it. And this is the speech:—</p>
               <p>"Yes, my dears, I thank you for the news. And you, too, Mrs. Jacques, for circulating the report. Insane am I? Quite mad! and all because I, a woman, choose to become a florist, and work in my garden. Insane, indeed! Well, my dears, I shall not change my plans to suit you. Perhaps if you knew how I am paid, you would like to be insane too."</p>
               <p>It being very warm after dinner, I did not venture out, but decided to wait till the mid-day heat had passed off. Accordingly, I took my work and sat down to sew. Sewing being with me almost a mechanical occupation, my thoughts were free to wander where they would. And they did wander away to tuberoses. Then the tuberose is a bulb. He "pots in a five-inch, and plunges." A five-inch? What can he mean by a five-inch? A five-inch pot, perhaps. If I remember rightly, I have heard my husband speak of two-inch and three-inch pots. Yes, that must be it. But "plunging," I never heard of that before. Just then, I glanced at a ragged newspaper on the floor. Picking it up, I discovered it to be "The American Agriculturist, for the Farm, Garden, and Household." Little Mary, in her eagerness<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC5737-00000018"/> ness to get at the pictures, had torn it open,—hence its ragged condition. Now, here is a piece of good fortune; perhaps I can find just what I want in this. We subscribed for the paper last January, but as I was not until lately at all interested in agriculture, my husband and the children had been the only readers. I am sure, after the first number, I had never looked at it. Now I examined it with the greatest interest. But not a word could I find about "plunging" anything. Perhaps some other number may have something on this point. So I went to the book-case and dragged down the six preceding numbers, and, throwing my work one side, gave myself up to the search. My labor was all in vain; not a syllable about "plunging" plants or pots. Yet my labor was not fruitless altogether. I found a world of facts and hints about the cultivation of flowers that would prove of great value to me in my new profession. At last I gave up the search for "plunging," and prepared to go to work again in the garden. As I passed the book-case on my way out, I paused and ran my eye over the titles. There it is; just what I want. "Rand's Flowers for the Parlor and Garden." Taking the book down and turning to page 198, I found a chapter on "The Culture of the Tuberose." This I carefully read through twice. But, if Mr. McTernan was concise and obscure, Mr. Rand was profuse and darker still. The whole chapter involved the knowledge of so many facts of which I was ignorant, that really I was but little wiser for reading it.</p>
               <p>Determined to master the subject, I went to work to study it out. The book began by saying that a hot-bed was necessary. Perhaps so; but I had no hot-bed, and I knew not how to make one. To be sure, another chapter informed me how to prepare one; but the whole process was quite beyond me. Then I came to the words, "Prepare seven-inch pots with the usual drainage." There I stopped. "Seven-inch pots and drainage." I declare I can make nothing of it all. I might guess what "plunging" meant, and I could understand how to tell a good bulb, if I saw it, and how much it should cost. I learned also that each bulb would produce from twenty to thirty flowers, after which it was valueless, and must be thrown away. So much for book-farming and the pursuit of knowledge under difficulties. I know what I will do,—I will attack Mr. McTernan, and make him tell me all about it in the minutest detail, till I fully understand the whole. By this time it was getting towards sundown, and I resolved to return to my raking. Going to the tool-room, I found the rake was gone. Well, this is pleasing, no tools to work with! Seeing Johnny near, I asked him if he had seen the rake anywhere.</p>
               <p>"Yes, Uncle Joseph came in and took it."</p>
               <p>Now, I have no objection to lending tools, but I should like to be consulted first. Having no rake, I could do nothing; so I went back to the tool-room to inspect my stock in that line. If I am going to be a gardener, I must have suitable tools, and everything in good order. The tool-room<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC5737-00000019"/> room was a small closet in our wood-shed. Since my husband's death it had hardly been entered. Opening the door I found everything in the most perfect order, just as he had left it the day he was killed. The sight made me sad enough, but I had work to do, and must brush back the tears, and give my mind to the duty nearest me. Seeing things in such good condition, I then and there resolved it should always be so. Neatness and order should reign in my garden and work-shop, as in my own chamber. I always clung to this resolve, and to it I owe a large measure of my after success. On examining the tools, I found I was the possessor of two spades, a shovel, two hoes, an iron and a wooden rake, and a garden line and reel, for marking out beds. In one corner was a wheelbarrow, and in another a pile of flower-pots of all sizes, neatly sorted and piled up in rows. These I was glad to see; perhaps I should want them by and by, if I should attempt tuberoses in pots. On a shelf overhead I discovered a small watering-pot, a trowel, and sundry papers of seeds. In a small box on the floor I found a variety of carpenter's tools. Seeing a rule among them, I took it out, and, going to the pile of pots, I took up one and measured the side of it from top to bottom; then another and another, but they seemed to be of all sorts and sizes. Then I measured one across the top. Ah, that is it! A seven-inch pot is a pot that measures seven inches from side to side, over the top. In this lame and round-about way did I discover what a seven or eight inch pot was. Delighted to find myself so well furnished for my new profession, I locked the door and put the key in my pocket, determined that if people wished to borrow they must come to me first.</p>
               <p>Wandering out to the garden again, I walked along till I came to the bed of mignonette I had planted the week before. To my delight, I found the ground entirely covered with the young plants just breaking through the soil. They were very thick, and formed a perfect mat over the whole surface. But is this right? Should they be so thick? Turning towards the house, I went into the sitting-room, and, taking up the book I had thrown down in such disgust a short time before, began to search through the index for mignonette.</p>
               <p>There was not a word about it. Finding a chapter on "The Garden," I looked that through, but though I found plenty of information on various other matters of importance, there was nothing in regard to mignonette. Under the head of "Hardy Annuals" I found something about it, but nothing to help me. However, I found on the next page these words: "If the plants come up very thick, thin out the weakest; you will thus give room for the others, and secure a larger and a better bloom." <choice>
                     <sic>Shuting</sic>
                     <corr>Shutting</corr>
                  </choice> the book, I prepared to put the information to immediate use. But it was too late. Going to the door, I found the twilight just fading away, and darkness prevented further efforts that day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC5737-00000020"/>
               <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
               <head type="sub">TAKING LESSONS IN FLORICULTURE.</head>
               <p>ON finding, the next morning, that my rake had not been returned, I went over to my brother's to look for it. Meeting Joseph at the gate, I asked him if he had borrowed my rake.</p>
               <p>"Yes."</p>
               <p>"Well, where is it? for I wish it."</p>
               <p>"I suppose it is lying round somewhere,—among the peas perhaps."</p>
               <p>Going into the kitchen-garden, I found the rake lying on the grass, rusty and the worse for wear. Picking it up, I marched home, resolved, that if people who borrowed tools were so careless as to leave them out on the open ground all night, they could not borrow again. The remainder of that morning I worked in the garden as industriously as I could, and had the satisfaction, at noon, of seeing my garden again in nice order. After dinner I attacked the mignonette bed. It was terribly hard work, but, with the assistance of the children, when they returned from school, we accomplished the undertaking, leaving the plants standing about six inches apart, every way.</p>
               <p>That evening I cut all the flowers I could find, sorted them, and laid them on the kitchen-table, and with a slip of paper and a pencil I made a list of the flowers, as far as I knew their names, with the number of dozens of each sort. The next morning I was at the depot, bright and early. On entering the cars, I looked about for my Mr. McTernan, and, finding him readily, I bade him "Good-morning," and took a seat near by. After a while I ventured to take out my list, and asked if he would be so kind as to tell me what such a list of flowers would be worth.</p>
               <p>"That depends, ma'am, whether they are first-class or not,—if they aint first-class they aint worth anything."</p>
               <p>"Look at them," said I, "and tell me."</p>
               <p>Carefully turning over the contents of my box, he looked at them a while, then said, laconically, "Them's good enough!"</p>
               <p>Delighted to find that my flowers were up to the market-standard, I ventured to ask one more favor of him.</p>
               <p>"Would Mr. McTernan please fill out the price on my list, so that I might know what they were really worth in the market?"</p>
               <p>Putting on an old pair of silver-bowed spectacles, he studied the list for a few moments and then handed it back to me, saying, "I'll tell ye the price, but ye must write it yourself; my hands aint used to writing."</p>
               <p>So I took out my pencil, and, while the train stopped at a way-station, hastily wrote down the figures he gave me.</p>
               <p>When it was done, it read somewhat in this way:—<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC5737-00000021"/>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6 doz. Heliotropes,</cell>
                        <cell>$1 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4 doz. Roses,</cell>
                        <cell>1 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>½ doz. Tea-roses,</cell>
                        <cell>37</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1 doz. Lilliums,</cell>
                        <cell>75</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Cut flowers,</cell>
                        <cell>1 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>$4 12</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>The cut flowers consisted of a number of varieties. Mr. McTernan said he should "lump" those, and call them "cut flowers."</p>
               <p>After placing my flowers on the counter in the store, I quietly handed my list to the young man, Thomas. He looked at it for a moment, and then very significantly at me. I busied myself in tying up my box, preparatory to going home. Directly he went into a brown study over my list. Not knowing how long this would last, I moved as if to go. Upon which he woke up, scratched something upon the paper, and, handing it to me, said:—</p>
               <p>"Show it to the book-keeper."</p>
               <p>"Thank you, Mr. Thomas," I said to myself, "I fancy I am quite up to you this time. Thanks to Mr. McTernan, I know the value of flowers as well as you;" and I marched off triumphantly towards the book-keeper's desk.</p>
               <p>When I reached the desk, I was obliged to wait a moment, as the book-keeper was talking with a gentleman. While waiting thus I had an opportunity to have a good look at her, and I found her a young lady, small, plainly dressed in black, with delicate hands, and a face at once pleasant, cheerful, and just a grain pretty. Seated behind her handsome walnut desk, with the huge ledger spread out before her, she made quite a charming picture. When she had finished her business, she turned to me and held out her hand for my paper. Taking it, she looked at it a moment, and then said:—</p>
               <p>"What name?"</p>
               <p>"Gilman."</p>
               <p>"Does Mr. Gilman keep a private place?"</p>
               <p>"Mr. Gilman? There is no Mr. Gilman," said I, endeavoring to be as calm as possible.</p>
               <p>"Excuse me. Does Miss or Mrs. Gilman keep the house?"</p>
               <p>"Keep the house? Why, I am Mrs. Gilman. Of course, I keep my own house."</p>
               <p>"Yes, but is it a private or a commercial house?"</p>
               <p>"Really, I do not understand you at all." Then she explained to me that all greenhouses are divided into private or commercial. The private houses belong to people who follow some other occupation, or, being wealthy, keep a green house for their own pleasure, and, having more flowers than they can use themselves, sell a portion in the market. The commercial houses are owned by the florists proper, who make it their business to grow flowers, and do nothing else.</p>
               <p>Comprehending the distinction, I said that my place was a commercial one.</p>
               <p>"Where is your greenhouse?"</p>
               <p>"I have only a garden,—no greenhouse as yet. I am a widow, and live at the Centre."</p>
               <pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC5737-00000022"/>
               <p>Finding also that she desired to know more, I gave her my whole story up to that time.</p>
               <p>"Indeed, Mrs. Gilman, I am greatly interested in what you say, and can but applaud what you propose to do. The only wonder to me is that some one has not tried this before. Perhaps I can be of use to you in some direction. Now, is there any way in which I can help you? I know very little about raising flowers, but I can assist you as far as selling them is concerned."</p>
               <p>"Thank you, you are very kind. Doubtless you will be able to help me often. Yes, you can do so now."</p>
               <p>"That is pleasant. What is it?"</p>
               <p>"Tell me about tuberoses. Does it pay to grow them? how long does it take to get them to flower? and where can I buy them?"</p>
               <p>"One thing at a time. First, I suppose it does pay, for they all grow them. They bloom in ninety days, I think; and we have them for sale. But I am afraid you are too late, this year. In ninety days we must expect frosty weather, and, unless you have a greenhouse to put them in, you had better not attempt it this season. You will soon learn in gardening that, if a thing is not done at just such a time, it cannot be done again for a whole year."</p>
               <p>"Perhaps I can keep them in my dining-room window."</p>
               <p>The young lady smiled at my query, and said she had never heard of such a thing, but that it might be worth trying on a small scale.</p>
               <p>"Johnny, bring me some tubes."</p>
               <p>Johnny dived downstairs, and soon returned with a small quantity of curious-looking bulbs, quite dry and dusty.</p>
               <p>"That's all there are left, miss. Only twenty in all."</p>
               <p>"What is the price?" asked I.</p>
               <p>"A dollar and a half a dozen. But, as you are in the trade, we will take off something. You may have the lot for a dollar."</p>
               <p>I decided to take them, and Johnny turned them into my box.</p>
               <p>Then, placing my name and the date at the top of my paper, she made a note of it, and, handing it to me with a smile, began turning the leaves of her book. Bidding her good-morning, I took my bill and departed, thankful and happy; happy in meeting with success in my morning's sale, and thankful in finding such a friend as Miss Sampson, the book-keeper, bid fair to be.</p>
               <p>As I walked away, I passed a large dry goods store, with the shutters still up. Glancing at the door to see what it could mean, I saw a placard on the glass: "Taking Stock. Open next Monday." Now, there is an idea for me. Those business-men are taking an account of stock. I am a business woman and should follow their example. I'll do so before I go deeper into the business. But how about the money this morning? All I have is my list of flowers. What is that worth? I can't sell it, what shall I do? Will it ever be good for anything? Will they cash it at the<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC5737-00000023"/> store? Not a very business-like proceeding on my part after all. I'll go back and see about it. No, I'll consult Mr. McTernan. Finding him in the car, I asked what I should do with my list.</p>
               <p>"Keep it, and, at the end of the month, they will give a check for it."</p>
               <p>"Next, if you please, Mr. McTernan, I would like to know more about tubes."</p>
               <p>"Well, ma'am, I am planting some this afternoon, and, if ye come to my place, at Maple Hill, ye'll see it done. My place is near the depot. Anybody will tell ye when ye get from the cars."</p>
               <p>"Thank you, I must try to be there."</p>
               <p>Just as I was leaving the cars, when we reached the Centre, I met Joseph.</p>
               <p>"Good-morning, Maria, I was just looking for you."</p>
               <p>"Well, what is it?"</p>
               <p>"I have found a man who would like to buy your house."</p>
               <p>"But I do not intend to sell; I prefer to keep it for the present."</p>
               <p>"Keep your house? Why, how can you stand the expense?"</p>
               <p>"That's a question I hope to decide in time. Perhaps Providence will help me if I help myself."</p>
               <p>"Stuff and nonsense, Maria. I don't wonder people talk about you as they do."</p>
               <p>To this I paid no heed, but turned towards home.</p>
               <p>"Stop a moment, Maria. Now be sensible for once. How are you going to support yourself and your children in this house?"</p>
               <p>"By the labor of my two hands."</p>
               <p>"Oh, that's all very well, but I am afraid you will find it pretty poor pickings. What can a woman do?"</p>
               <p>"Joseph," I cried, "if Mr. Gilman were alive, you would not dare to say this. I'll thank you to say no more. I can, and shall, take care of myself."</p>
               <p>Upon which he left me, muttering something about the fools not being all dead. I quite agreed with him.</p>
               <p>That morning I spent at my housework. To tell the truth, this had been sadly neglected for the previous week. By dinner-time everything was finished up square, and all the threads gathered together and ready to go on again as smoothly as ever.</p>
               <p>After clearing away the dinner things, I told the children that, as they had a half holiday, we would all go out for a walk over Maple Hill. It was my intention to visit Mr. McTernan's place, and see what information I could pick up in regard to tuberoses or anything else. At first, I thought of going up in the train; but the fares for us all would be, at least, thirty cents. Only a trifle, to be sure; but then it would not take many such trifles to use up my daily receipts. So off we started on our two-mile tramp, the children happy and gay as possible, ready to see and<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC5737-00000024"/> enjoy everything, and I quiet and at peace with everybody. Hopeful for the future, and encouraged by the fortunate turn my affairs had taken in the past few days, I found myself fully alive to all the beauty and charm of the day and scenery, and with a sense of freedom and perfect health I had never known before. On leaving the village, and getting into the open country, I involuntarily glanced at the blue sky. All was clear and bright, and not a cloud to be seen, save in the far south-west, where a thin, gauze-like cloud streamed upward and outward over the wooded hills, in shape like a fan. In the east a low, brown bank of smoke from the city drifted up the valley, where the river courses to the sea. What does that mean? I said to myself. Not a storm, I hope. It was strange how quickly I had become apprehensive of the weather, and how keenly I had learned to watch for a change. Talking with the children, and admiring the lovely views on every hand, and feasting upon the wild raspberries by the roadside, we found ourselves entering Maple Hill village much sooner than we expected. Ours was a short and pleasant walk, and short because it was pleasant.</p>
               <p>On reaching Mr. McTernan's we entered his gate, and in a moment found ourselves in a perfect wilderness of flowers, drawn up in solid and orderly ranks, spread out in glowing masses, here, there, and everywhere. Huge beds of dazzling scarlet, great clouds of white, all colors and shades, mingled in charming confusion. Rose-beds literally glowing with color, and asters as thick as herd's grass, waved in the breeze like a field of wheat. Well, I don't wonder he can cut ten dollars a day from such a garden. Oh, I wish I was not so mercenary! Thinking of money as soon as I enter a garden like this.</p>
               <p>Seeing a man at work we approached him, and found him busily at work making a row of small holes in the earth. "For what purpose do you design those holes?" I ventured to ask.</p>
               <p>"Plunging, ma'am."</p>
               <p>Not being much the wiser for this, I was about to question him further, but he appeared to be so uncommunicative, that I merely said:—</p>
               <p>"Where is Mr. McTernan?"</p>
               <p>"Yonder, in the shed. Walk right in the door ye see standing open next the greenus."</p>
               <p>Sending the children to search out new wonders among the flowers, I entered the door as directed.</p>
               <p>The sight that met my view was not a pleasant one at first, and I am afraid I showed my disappointment in my face. There stood my honest acquaintance before a rude bench, on which was a huge pile of dirt. He was roughly dressed, with his sleeves rolled up, and eagerly plunging his bare hands and arms through and through the heap of loam before him.</p>
               <p>"Good-afternoon, ma'am. Clean dirt, marm,"—then a dig at the pile. "Just in time, ma'am,"—another plunge.<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC5737-00000025"/> "Just going to pot 'em. This is the stuff,—clean—fine—and—rich as butter." Another dive, another, and then a good slapping together of his hands, to shake off the soil. Hastily brushing a seat with his apron, he offered it to me, saying:—</p>
               <p>"Take a seat, and you shall see the whole thing in a jiffy."</p>
               <p>Thanking him, I sat down, not quite at my ease, however, in such a scene.</p>
               <p>"Now, if you watch me, ye'll learn by seeing in half the time I'd be telling ye."</p>
               <p>So saying, he took up a clean new flower-pot, and, taking from a box near by a handful of broken pots pounded up fine, he threw it into the pot, filling it about an inch deep. He then filled the pot nearly full of soil from the heap. Taking a bulb from a basket and holding it upright with one hand in the soil in the pot, he filled up the remainder of the pot with the other hand. Giving the pot a gentle rap on the bench, he set it on one side; going through the same operation, he next finished another. Quickening his motions, he began to do them very fast. Becoming interested in the ease and rapidity with which he worked, I left my seat, and came and stood close to the bench. Soon the rows of pots grew to a goodly size, and the busy workman stopped, and said:—</p>
               <p>"There, ye see the whole story so far. After they have been watered the man will plunge them, up to the rim of the pot, in the ground, and in about a month they will be taken up, shifted into the next size pot, and plunged again. If they are very tall, I stick a stake in the pot and tie 'em to it to keep the wind from breaking them off. They's very tender."</p>
               <p>"Yes, I think I understand it all now, except the shifting."</p>
               <p>"Shifting is taking a plant out of one size pot, and putting it into the next size."</p>
               <p>"Why, there is nothing difficult in that."</p>
               <p>"No, it's dreadful easy when ye know how."</p>
               <p>Just at this moment the door, that had been standing open, suddenly swung to with a loud slam.</p>
               <p>"Wind's changed! East, I guess. Going to have a storm to-morrow. I knew it would be east soon; I saw the wind coming up the river awhile since."</p>
               <p>"Saw the wind?"</p>
               <p>"Yes; didn't ye see it as ye came along? the smoke from the chimblies was a-going for it. But wait a bit, till I shut up."</p>
               <p>Upon this, he opened another door and stepped into the greenhouse. Presently he returned, and said:—</p>
               <p>"Will ye see me take off the air?"</p>
               <p>Wondering what that might be, I followed him to the greenhouse.</p>
               <p>"Now, ye see them ventilators up there; well, they are open to let out the heat, but the wind has changed, and<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC5737-00000026"/> these plants won't stand east wind; so I takes off the air in this way;" and, going to a large iron wheel fastened upon the wall, he began to turn it round by a handle affixed to the side. Instantly every window in the roof began to close, and soon they were all shut.</p>
               <p>"Why, I could do that. Please let me try;" and I did, opening and closing them with the greatest ease, by merely turning the crank.</p>
               <p>Now that is a revelation. As far as ventilation is concerned, I could conduct a greenhouse as well as a man.</p>
               <p>Returning to his shed, he began his potting again. Suddenly he stopped, and without a word went out of doors.</p>
               <p>Now's my chance. I'll try it myself. Throwing back my shawl, I boldly thrust my ungloved hand into the heap of soil. How odd! I expected to find it very dirty and disagreeable. On the contrary, it's rather nice. Seizing a pot and a bulb, I potted it, going through all the motions to the final rap on the bench. "There, I fancy that's even better than he can do it, for my hands are not so rough and leave the work looking much nicer. Really, this is much pleasanter than mixing dough or sewing on slop-work." Hearing some one coming, I hastily shook my hands, when, to my surprise, every trace of the soil came off, and they were as clean as ever. When Mr. McTernan opened the door, he saw what I had been doing, and, breaking out into a loud laugh, said:—</p>
               <p>"Well, ye are a smart un, aint ye?"</p>
               <p>Finding the sun going down, I called the children and, bidding him good-night, we started for home. A great change had come over things by this time. A cool east wind was blowing, and all the western sky was overcast. We reached home tired, hungry, and in excellent spirits.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC5737-00000027"/>
               <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
               <head type="sub">TAKING STOCK.</head>
               <p>THE next morning opened with a dull, cold, easterly storm. As I could do nothing out of doors, I spent the morning at housework. After dinner I took pen and paper to carry out my intention of taking an account of stock. First, I made a list of the tools; then, going to the book-case, I took down all the books I could find on the subject of gardening; these I also considered as tools and aids in my new profession. The books had been purchased by my husband at different times; but, to tell the truth, I had never examined them, not being interested in that direction. The first book I took up was "The Fruit Garden," by Mr. Barry, of Rochester, N. Y. This did not strike me as being anything of value to me in regard to flowers; yet perhaps the general principles of the book might be valuable; so I laid it aside for future reference. Then I opened "Country Life; a Hand-book of Agriculture, Horticulture, and Landscape Gardening," by R. Morris Copeland. This seemed to me to be just what I wanted. I next found an old copy of "Breck's Book of Flowers," and these, with Rand's "Flowers for the Parlor also an odd volume of "The Gardener's Monthly," and six numbers of "The American Agriculturist." As the rain continued to fall, I did not venture into the garden to make a list of the stock of growing plants out of doors; but, opening my husband's desk, searched through his papers for any bills of plants he might have purchased for the garden, as the bills would show the original cost of my plants. I found quite a number of them, but could not make out all the details; indeed, to be honest, I did not know the names of all the flowers I had in my grounds. For instance, hybrid perpetual roses were entered at four dollars a dozen, and tea roses at the same price. But what the difference was, I could not understand. So the bills helped me but little as far as the prices were concerned. Some things I understood readily,—such as heliotrope, which was put down at a dollar and a half per dozen. Taking this as a starting point, I could easily arrive at the cost and then estimate the probable return from the four dozen heliotrope plants in my possession. They cost six dollars. I had cut already at least one dozen flowers, nine different days. This, at a shilling a dozen, would be nine dollars, leaving me three dollars for the labor already spent in their cultivation. How much I might expect to cut for the remainder of the summer was more than I could guess; yet I felt safe in estimating a return of three dollars a week until the frost should destroy them in the fall. Thus it was plain, if I could make all my flowers pay at this rate,<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC5737-00000028"/> the whole question of my support was settled for the next two months. What I might do after that, when the winter came, was a question to be answered by and by. I was not so foolish as to think that I could make all the flowers yield such a return, yet, if one-half of them did as well, it was safe to go on with my new pursuit. Truly can I say, I had abundant reason to be contented and thankful with my condition and prospects.</p>
               <p>The storm continued all that night and the greater part of the next day. Towards evening the rain ceased, and, putting on an old straw hat, I ventured into the garden among the still dripping plants. I was apprehensive I should not be able to cut any flowers. Many of the plants were soiled and broken, yet I gathered a box full, and, carrying them to the house, dipped them, one at a time, in clean water, to remove the dirt. This operation I found injurious to some of them. The geraniums were quite spoiled, but the foliage and petals of the others seemed to be the better for the bath.</p>
               <p>The next morning I was complimented on the nice appearance of my flowers by Thomas. He endorsed my list, and, after showing it to Miss Sampson, I returned home.</p>
               <p>Having finished my household duties, I turned my attention to the subject of tuberoses. Going into the woodshed, I procured two empty flour barrels, and placed them side by side near the window. Getting some pieces of board, a few nails, and a hammer, I managed to construct with my own hands my first potting bench. It was a sorry-looking affair, but would answer my purpose quite as well as if I had ordered a carpenter to make it, at an expense which I could not afford. One thing I was determined to avoid, and that was debt. By making my own bench, as I have described, I steered clear of this rock, on which so many are wrecked. Next, getting a coal-hod and a spade, I procured the richest soil I could find in my garden, and in an hour had the satisfaction of seeing my tuberoses potted, plunged, and in order.</p>
               <p>The following morning I was up in good season, resolved to finish taking an account of stock before the heat became oppressive. My garden was at one side of the house, and extended along the street for ten rods. The width was about seventy-five feet. The ground was not cut up with walks; a single narrow path ran through the middle, leaving almost the entire space for cultivation. The plants were set out in solid rows, filling the whole ground from one end to the other. All the plants of a sort were placed by themselves. First came the roses, of all kinds, planted in regular ranks; then my four dozen heliotropes, then a quantity of lillium candidum, as Mr. McTernan called them. Adjoining was a broad strip of verbenas, and next a bed of mignonette. Beyond were several rows of white flowers,—feverfews, I supposed,—several also of double gillyflowers, a row of geraniums, some ranks of larkspur, six full rows of<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC5737-00000029"/> pinks (carnations, I think Thomas called them), and two rows of salvias, not yet in flower. A row of asters, just showing their buds, three rows of useless marigolds, then my new lot of mignonette, and lastly, next the fence, fuchsias. Such, with a portion which I could not name, was my stock in trade. On consulting the bills I found the whole lot of plants had been purchased the spring before at a total cost of about seventy-five dollars. My tools and books I valued at fifteen dollars, and I entered the whole at an appraisal of ninety dollars accordingly.</p>
               <p>Not finding anything further requiring attention out of doors I returned to my mending. That being soon finished I took my books again. Perhaps I can find something in them that will be of use to me. Opening Mr. Copeland's "Country Life," I found that the arrangement of the chapters was just what I needed. Each month all the important operations on the farm, in the greenhouse or flower garden, were taken up and discussed, so that I should know in advance what was to be done throughout the year. As July was nearly over, I turned to the seventy-seventh chapter on the garden in August; and there I read these words: "If you would have the full mid-summer glory in your flower garden be constant and careful in your attendance upon it." That's just the point.</p>
               <p>I must follow it up carefully, and keep things in perfect order. Having finished the chapter, I turned to "Hints about Work" in the August number of "The Gardener's Monthly," and in the newly arrived "Agriculturist," to learn what my duties would be for that month, now so soon to overtake me; and, to be frank, at first I was fairly bewildered and discouraged. Such an overwhelming amount of work to be done! I was in despair at the prospect. If my garden requires all this attention I may as well give it up at once. How could I ever expect to get through with such an immense amount of work? Quite disappointed to think I had embarked on such a laborious undertaking, I ventured out of doors to see if it were possible that there was so much to be done, and to consider whether I had not better abandon the whole project. Walking slowly along the path, I examined every plant to discover what ought to be done first, or, if anything should be done at all. Just as I reached the fuchsias I was startled by the sound of a voice from near the fence.</p>
               <p>"Evening, Miss Gilman!" Looking up I discovered Mrs. Jacques peering over the fence at me.</p>
               <p>"Good evening, Mrs. Jacques," I replied.</p>
               <p>"What on airth are you doing in your garden? If I should go puttering round all day like that, my man would say I was an old fool!"</p>
               <p>"I suppose he would," said I.</p>
               <p>"Yes, he would, and rightly too!"</p>
               <p>"Doubtless."</p>
               <p>"Come now, what are you doing all day among the posies?"</p>
               <pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC5737-00000030"/>
               <p>"Gardening, for my support."</p>
               <p>"Gardening for a living? You don't say so. How much do you get?"</p>
               <p>"That depends upon the kind of flowers I raise."</p>
               <p>This somewhat confused her; after a pause she returned to the charge.</p>
               <p>"Do you make it pay, Mrs. Gilman? My man says farming never will pay."</p>
               <p>A little provoked with the woman, I replied that I thought he might be a good authority on the point, for I had never heard that he made anything pay.</p>
               <p>"Pay or no, he aint such a fool as to stand round in a flower garden, all day, anyhow!"</p>
               <p>"I suppose not. It is so <emph>much</emph> more manly 'standing round all day,' with a yard-stick in one hand and a pair of scissors in the other."</p>
               <p>This shot told, for with a flout she disappeared. Turning towards the house I was surprised to discover a nicely dressed young gentleman standing in the path just before me, apparently very much taken up with my pinks. He was tall, well made, with a full-bearded face, that indicated at once good sense, education, and refinement. When he had finished examining the pinks, he came towards me, and taking off his hat very politely said, "Pardon the intrusion, but seeing your plants in nursery rows and in such perfect order, I guessed it must be a sales-place, and ventured in. Am I right?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, more than right. I do sell flowers, and you are free to examine if you wish."</p>
               <p>"You have some fine carnations, and they are in good order."</p>
               <p>"Are they? I am glad to hear it."</p>
               <p>"And your hybrid roses, too, are blooming very late. They are generally gone before this. Your garden evidently belongs to a gardener."</p>
               <p>"It was my husband's garden. He is dead now. Since he died I have taken care of it myself."</p>
               <p>"Indeed! and you sell the flowers too?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, I am my own gardener, saleswoman, and everything else."</p>
               <p>"Really, I am glad to hear it. I have long had an idea that women could become florists, as well as men. I am myself a florist, and as we are of one trade let me introduce myself. Edwin Felix. My greenhouses are on the turnpike, about two miles from here."</p>
               <p>"Thank you, sir. I am pleased to make your acquaintance. But do not consider, or call me, a florist. I know absolutely nothing about it. Not nearly so much as did my husband, Mr. Gilman."</p>
               <p>"Doubtless you can soon learn. Have you read any books on the subject?"</p>
               <p>"I have merely glanced at one or two, but they tell me so many things I am in despair at the prospect. I do not know where to begin."</p>
               <p>"I can understand your case. The books are important,<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC5737-00000031"/> yet it is only out-door practice that will make your reading of value. May I venture to tell you what to do first?"</p>
               <p>"Certainly."</p>
               <p>"You see these roses are divided into two sorts. These, having thick, rough leaves, are hybrid perpetuals. They are not quite perpetual in this country, yet with care you can get a second crop in September. You see there are no buds left, only full-blown roses. When these are gone there will be no more unless you cut them down with a sharp knife." So saying, he took out his knife and cut off a fine rose, stem and all. "It is better to cut them thus. It exhausts the plant more to bloom one full rose than to grow six buds. Besides, a new growth will start, and more flowers follow. The more flowers you cut the more you will have. This applies to almost all flowers. All plants seem determined to produce a certain quantity of flowers. If unmolested, they will perfect the flowers and then stop. If the flowers are removed, the plant at once sets to work to replace them. If they are again removed, it makes still another effort. I would not advise the culture of the hybrids for profit. The tea roses are the only true perpetuals."</p>
               <p>To this I listened with the closest attention, eager to learn all I could. Then, turning to the pinks, he pointed out how they should be tied up to stakes to prevent them falling to the ground. This, with weeding and keeping the soil open, was all that my garden required at present.</p>
               <p>"Do not be discouraged, Mrs. Gilman. Persevere, and you will be sure to prosper. When I pass this way again, I will tell you what to do next." So saying, he departed.</p>
               <p>Here, then, is another friend! Providence is certainly lending me a helping hand.</p>
               <p>No sooner, however, was one difficulty settled, when another came up. What should I do about money matters? The cards I received from the flower store would not pay Mr. Hardtack the grocer, nor would Sharpedge &amp; Co. give me meat for them. I do not mean to run into debt; indeed, I must not. Could I forget Mrs. Warren's experience in "How I managed my house on ¥200 a year"? Her opening chapter made too deep an impression on me, to leave me easy under debt. Yet, for all that, I had to yield. My children must be fed, and to be able to work in my garden I must have good, substantial food. The final result was my obtaining credit at the stores till the end of the month. When that time arrived, I presented all my tickets or checks, and was paid promptly in full. That very morning I settled every bill, and had something left besides.</p>
               <p>My whole income from the sale of flowers (including the fifteen dollars I mentioned before) amounted to forty-five dollars and fifty cents. By economy and care, we managed to live on a trifle less than this. To be sure, we had no rent to pay, and no repairs were needed at present. I had the interest on the mortgage and the taxes to pay, but neither were due till December. Perhaps by that time I shall be able to meet them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC5737-00000032"/>
               <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
               <head type="sub">A LONG LOOK AHEAD.</head>
               <p>THE month of August passed with very much the same record as July. My flowers continued to grow and bloom abundantly. They did not, however, yield me so much more money. Fifty dollars was all I received for the whole month. It was the dull season, I was told. Everybody in the country had their own flowers, and the city consumers were at the sea-side, or at the mountains. I kept my garden in perfect order all the time, and with but little labor. In fact, I had quite as much leisure as I had ever known. Once I visited Mr. McTernan, gathering much useful information. Mr. Felix called again, and seemed to find me doing well enough to be left to myself till the first of September, when, he said, many things would require attention.</p>
               <p>My doings, I found, had made a great stir in the village. All sorts of stories were afloat in regard to me. Some laughed at me, some pitied, and none helped me, save the two store-keepers and strangers I met in the way of business.</p>
               <p>At the close of the first week of September, I felt the first chill of the coming winter. My thermometer at my front door fell one morning to forty degrees. Thereupon, I fell to thinking. Yes, I began to think. I had learned to think now. With my out-door life had come increased bodily and mental capacity. The fresh air had improved my physique, and work had calmed down my mind, and turned my thoughts to more cheerful subjects. This, too, ought to be added to the profits of my undertaking, for is not health worth more than money? But what am I to do now, about money itself? According to the thermometer, I have come within eight degrees of being without it. Let the glass fall to thirty-two degrees, and my income from the garden is at an end. As soon as we have a frost I shall be utterly without means for the next eight months. I had anticipated this, but had not given it very serious attention. Something must be done, and quickly. I will consult the books. "The Gardener's Monthly" thought it high time to get ready for winter. "The Agriculturist" was in favor of taking things in hand early, and recommended removing tender plants to the house. Mr. Copeland informed me that the florist's year began with September. Now is the time to begin the year by gathering the plants together, preparatory to removing them to the greenhouse. That's it! They are all getting their greenhouses ready. And I have none! Suppose I build one? It is not to be thought of. It would cost several thousand dollars, and all I have is the two thousand dollars I received as the insurance on my husband's life. No, I must do something else. I must take in sewing, and struggle through the winter, until my flower garden<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC5737-00000033"/> will again make a return. Busy with the problem, I heard the bell ring, and, going to the door, found Mr. Felix on the steps.</p>
               <p>"Excuse me, Mrs. Gilman, I am in a hurry. I wish some flowers to fill an order. Will you cut me some?"</p>
               <p>"With pleasure," said I, and we both went to the garden, Taking out his knife he began to cut the tea-rose buds, saying, at the same time:—</p>
               <p>"Please, Mrs. Gilman, cut me six dozen heliotrope."</p>
               <p>We both worked rapidly, and in a few moments he placed three dozen buds with my heliotropes. Taking out his purse, he prepared to pay me.</p>
               <p>"Six dozen heliotropes, at a shilling, will be one dollar, and the buds will be a dollar and a half," said I.</p>
               <p>"More than that, Mrs. Gilman," said he, with a smile. "The cool nights have sent the price of flowers up. Roses sell at a dollar a dozen, and heliotrope advanced to twenty-five cents to-day,—four dollars and a half." And, handing me that amount, he took the flowers and going to his carriage that stood at the gate drove rapidly away.</p>
               <p>"There goes an honest man, and a gentleman," thought I. So the price of flowers has nearly doubled. The early frosts will soon kill off the garden-flowers, and then those who have greenhouses will control the market. In fact, only they will have any flowers to sell at all. I have supported myself by my garden for two months, earning nearly one hundred dollars, and now, in spite of all I can do, my income is at an end. And my mignonette too, that will be destroyed also. It is paying me twenty cents a day, and perhaps, tomorrow it will be dead. And my tuberoses also, what can I do with them? I can put them in my windows, but all I shall get for them will not support me for more than two weeks. And what then? Really I wish I had a greenhouse. Wonder what they do cost? I'll consult Mr. Rand on the point. Opening the book I read the entire first chapter. Then I shut the volume, and made up my mind on the spot,—I will build a greenhouse. The next thing was action. No time must be lost, if I wished to have the house ready before winter set in. I cast about for authorities on the subject. The books I had read through long ago, and I had a very tolerable idea of the different styles of horticultural structures. Woman-like, I first consulted a woman,—Miss Sampson. She was at first frightened at the boldness of my schemes. Yet she gave me a helping hand, and advised my visiting some of the best greenhouses in the neighborhood, and see for myself their cost, and the advantages of the different patterns.</p>
               <p>I followed her hint at once, and, taking the cars, went to Massawatlan Highlands, and in the course of the day visited three different establishments. The first consisted of two enormous lean-to houses, several hundred feet in length. (By a lean-to, I found they meant a house having but one sloping glass roof, facing the south, and with covered sheds on the north side.) On entering I found a broad walk,<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC5737-00000034"/> running the whole length of the building. Between the walk and the south wall was a long table containing plants in pots.</p>
               <p>On the other side and against the north wall was a bank of wooden steps rising like broad stairs almost to the roof. This, also, was covered with plants in pots. Along the path ran a number of iron pipes. These, I guessed, were for heating the building in winter. After looking about a short time, and wondering at the great strength and weight of the building, I found the proprietor, and ventured to ask the cost of such a structure. "Ten thousand dollars, and not a cent less." I did not stay to put any more questions. That settled the whole matter for me. I must not even dream of greenhouses. But as long as I had come to Massawatlan I ventured to glance at the next place, although quite sure I could never indulge in building. This place, likewise, had large lean-to houses, and, in addition, a house with two glass roofs, one against the other. This, I learned, was called a span-roof. Inside, I found two walks, one on each side, with the steps, or stage, placed in the middle, and following the line of the roof. And here was another trouble for poor me. How could I ever get up and down those steep steps to cut the flowers or water and tend the plants? I could not do it. It was wholly out of the question. The cost of such a house, I was told, was thirty dollars a running foot. That is, if the house was fifty feet long, it would cost fifteen hundred dollars, without the heating ing apparatus. This seemed more cheerful, but not enough so to warrant my erecting such a structure. The third place resembled the others, excepting that everything seemed cheaper and plainer. In this, too, I found the same alarmingly high stages, and as I watched a man at work upon them I felt sure I never should possess the strength or the steadiness required for such a position.</p>
               <p>In the train home I met Mr. McTernan, and ventured to approach him on the subject I was interested in.</p>
               <p>"Well, ma'am, they don't cost much, if ye builds 'em cheap. I gets a carpenter to build mine, and has 'em made kinder rough and cheap. They don't last as long, not more'n six years, but they does grow the flowers. I generally calculates to pay for 'em in two years, and when they tumbles down, I builds another. Come and see me, and I'll show ye all about 'em."</p>
               <p>And I did so, the very next day. He showed me a house one hundred feet long, and twelve feet wide, which, he said, cost, heating apparatus, stage, and all, about a thousand dollars. It was a rough affair indeed, very rude, if not shabby. Yet it was filled with flowers in the most vigorous and healthy condition.</p>
               <p>"How much do you cut from such a building, Mr. McTernan?"</p>
               <p>"Well, I gets about five dollars a day, take it all the year round, sometimes more, and sometimes nothing at all for a month."</p>
               <pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC5737-00000035"/>
               <p>"You think it a profitable operation then?"</p>
               <p>"Well, ma'am, I can't say as to that,—I aint very good at figgers,—but my greenhouse keeps me and my folks, and I always has a little money besides; but, bless ye, I can't keep it,—I always was a spending money since I was a boy."</p>
               <p>That afternoon, I visited Mr. Felix, and, laying before him the whole matter, asked his advice. When I had finished, he seemed lost in thought for a few moments, then starting up suddenly, went to the door and called to some one outside to put the horse in the carriage.</p>
               <p>"Come," said he, returning to me. "Get in my carriage and I will drive you over to Warkau. There is a house there I think will meet your views."</p>
               <p>I hesitated at first about accepting his kindness.</p>
               <p>"Why, Mrs. Gilman, I am sure you will go. I merely wish to put you on the right road in your business."</p>
               <p>"Thank you, sir, I will go with you."</p>
               <p>After a short ride, we turned down a lane, and, half buried in the woods, found a collection of curiously contrived glass covers merely, as they seemed at first; very long, quite narrow, and one house placed beside another; the whole together having the appearance of immense waves, as if some great sea had its billows suddenly frozen stiff; literally a sea of glass.</p>
               <p>"There," said Mr. Felix, "is the style of house that will be of use to you. Cheap,—adapted to many purposes,—and easily kept warm."</p>
               <p>"But I could not stand upright in such a low place. They are hardly three feet high in the centre."</p>
               <p>"All that is provided for. Come and see."</p>
               <p>So we got out, and walked through the garden towards a long shed that extended across the ends of all the houses. At the door I was introduced to the proprietor, Mr. Clockwell, a quiet, gentlemanly young man, plainly dressed as if about his work. Opening the door, he bade us enter, saying:—</p>
               <p>"I shall be glad to show you everything, and give you whatever information you desire."</p>
               <p>Inside the door, we passed down a few steps and found ourselves in a narrow, but very long shed, having windows on one side and a number of small doors on the other. Entering one of these, we were at once within a long and narrow building, with a pointed-glass roof overhead. A path extended through the centre, leaving just room to walk and not strike the roof with your head. On either side low tables, on which were placed growing plants in pots, ran along from end to end.</p>
               <p>In another house the tables had board edging and were filled with soil in which plants were growing. In a third, instead of tables, a low bed of border of loam filled each side of the path, and in this taller plants were growing as in a garden. Everything was in the most perfect order, and all the plants looked bright and healthy.</p>
               <p>"You see, Mrs. Gilman," said Mr. Felix, "the advantage<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC5737-00000036"/> of this pattern of house is that every plant is within easy reach. No climbing of lofty stages here. The labor of cultivation is greatly reduced. In fact it is quite fascinating to conduct such a house, so easy is it."</p>
               <p>"But it must be a great undertaking to carry water in a watering-pot through these narrow walks, and for such great distances."</p>
               <p>Mr. Clockwell smiled at this, and said that, with him, watering was no labor at all, rather amusing than otherwise. He never used a watering-pot. If we would like to see it done, we had only to come into another house. In the next building, which was filled with an immense number of small plants in pots, placed on tables, we found a long rubber hose stretched out on the floor. This Mr. Clockwell took up, and, calling to some one outside to let on the water, held the brass nozzle at the end of the hose over the plants. Immediately a fine spray of water rushed out, and spread over several dozen plants at once. In an instant they were well drenched, and, with a slight movement of the hand, the stream was diverted to other plants. I fairly laughed when I saw it.</p>
               <p>"Could anything be more easy? Why, I could do that myself!"</p>
               <p>"Try it."</p>
               <p>And I did. Really it was a charming way of watering. Bidding Mr. Felix take out his watch and time my movements, I held the hose over the plants just sixty seconds. Then we counted the plants I had watered. They amounted to nearly five hundred.</p>
               <p>"But where does the water come from?"</p>
               <p>"It is pumped up in a tank on the roof of the shed to give it 'head' or force. I have only to turn it on, and away it goes, as you see. When I have finished one house, I drag the hose along to the next."</p>
               <p>All these things and many more were shown to us, and, after spending an hour very pleasantly, Mr. Felix drove me home by another road. Just before we reached the gate, he said:—</p>
               <p>"Now, Mrs. Gilman, if you really intend to build a greenhouse, you should be about it at once. We may have a frost any night."</p>
               <p>"Yes, sir, I appreciate the necessity of haste, and must consult my carpenter at once in regard to the cost,—that point will decide the whole question."</p>
               <p>"The cost of such houses as we have just seen is not great. Can I help you in any other particular?"</p>
               <p>"Thank you, sir, you can indeed."</p>
               <p>"Well, have your carpenter on hand to-morrow evening, and I will drop in and show him how to draw his plans and estimate the cost."</p>
               <p>That very evening I went to Mr. Sawplane's shop, and said to him:—</p>
               <p>"Mr. Sawplane, I propose to build a greenhouse. Will you please call at my house to-morrow evening about it?"</p>
               <pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC5737-00000037"/>
               <p>He promised to do so. Bidding him good-night, I turned to leave, when who should I see but Mrs. Jacques. Wonder if she overheard what I said. It's just like her to be near and yet give no intimation of her presence.</p>
               <p>The following evening was quite cool, and as I had some fears for my tuberoses, I took them up, washed the pots, and placed eighteen of them in my windows. Two of them had failed to throw up flower stems. These I put in the shed, intending to ask Mr. Felix what I should do with them.</p>
               <p>About six Mr. Felix arrived.</p>
               <p>"I have come early, Mrs. Gilman, as I wish to talk to you before you take further steps in the matter."</p>
               <p>"I am all ears,—temporally," said I, showing him to our sitting-room.</p>
               <p>"There is one point I am afraid you have not taken into account in connection with your proposed greenhouse. It is the stock. The plants in your garden are not of the right sorts, nor is there enough of them."</p>
               <p>"Yes, I have looked into that matter already. I turned to the books for information, and think I know about what I require and the probable cost."</p>
               <p>"Yes, that is all very well, but the books tell too much. You must discriminate; you do not yet know the nature and wants of the hundred or more plants they mention. If you attempted them all you would fail. The most skilful gardeners would not succeed with them all if they tried. I, with all my experience, would not undertake to grow more than a dozen sorts. It is better for you to confine yourself to perhaps six varieties."</p>
               <p>"Thank you, Mr. Felix. I understand you perfectly. What six shall I take? Would heliotrope do for one?"</p>
               <p>"Admirably; the culture is easy and the return in flowers liberal."</p>
               <p>Just then the bell rang and Mr. Sawplane entered. Introducing the two gentlemen to each other, they got out drawing materials, and Mr. Felix began to unfold his plans to the carpenter. I sat near by, an absorbed and interested listener. We had not been so engaged long, before the bell rang again, and, opening the door, I found my brother Joseph, his wife Charlotte, and Mr. Dooless, the minister. There was no help for it, and I asked them into the room where the two gentlemen were sitting. After introducing them to my visitors, I offered seats, and we all sat down. The usual remarks on the weather followed, and then conversation suddenly ceased, and a dreadful pause ensued. Anxious for a change, I turned to Mr. Felix, and said:—</p>
               <p>"How do you get on with your drawings?"</p>
               <p>"Oh,—fairly,—thank you. I think Mr. Sawplane grasps my idea of a house, though it is a new one to him."</p>
               <p>Here the minister coughed, and his companions looked at each other with a peculiar smile. I paid no attention<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC5737-00000038"/> to them, but went on talking about the plans. Suddenly my brother broke silence.</p>
               <p>"Sister, is it true then that you intend to build a greenhouse?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, I had thought of it."</p>
               <p>"Thanks again, Mrs. Jacques. I'll remember this."—This to myself.</p>
               <p>"But do you think it a wise plan? Is it not likely to prove a foolish waste of money?"</p>
               <p>"I think not. It is designed to bring money, not sink it."</p>
               <p>"Perhaps it is not designed to sink money, but it will; you, your money, house, and everything else."</p>
               <p>"Remember your children," said Charlotte.</p>
               <p>"I do, they are always in my thoughts. For them do I labor with my hands."</p>
               <p>Then Mr. Dooless spoke. "Does your conscience approve of this plan, Mrs. Gilman?"</p>
               <p>"I never do what it does not, sir."</p>
               <p>"But, sister, how do you ever expect to get back the money you embark in this scheme?"</p>
               <p>"By selling the flowers I produce."</p>
               <p>At this the minister gave a pitying smile, and Charlotte tossed up her pretty nose in scorn.</p>
               <p>"Sell the flowers! How horrid! I'm ashamed of you, Maria."</p>
               <p>"Are you, madam?" said Mr. Felix. "Some people think it an honorable employment."</p>
               <p>"No gentleman would, I am sure, and no lady can stoop so low."</p>
               <p>"Ah, thank you for your opinion. Our tastes differ, I see."</p>
               <p>"Come, Maria, say you will give up this wild scheme."</p>
               <p>"No, Joseph, I had rather not. I have been so successful thus far that I do not intend to stop now. Having put my hand to the plough, I shall not turn back."</p>
               <p>"Indeed! I should like to know how much you have made. Did it pay for your shoe leather?"</p>
               <p>"I shall not tell you, Joseph. I never asked to see your ledger, and I'll not show you mine."</p>
               <p>"Nobody cares to see it, I am sure," said Charlotte.</p>
               <p>"Christian friends," said the minister, rising, "let us depart. 'Ephraim is joined to his idols.'"</p>
               <p>"Yes," said I, "and means to stay joined."</p>
               <p>Then they rose as if to go. I was glad and relieved, for the whole scene was annoying and painful. Just as they started for the door, Mr. Felix spoke.</p>
               <p>"Wait a moment, gentlemen. Let us hear more of this matter. The other side has not been heard yet. Perhaps, after all, Mrs. Gilman could be induced to give us some of the facts in relation to her business. I, for one, could judge of them correctly, as I am a practical florist."</p>
               <p>At this my sister literally wilted away, and endeavored to beat a retreat, but Joseph detained her. They then sat down again, but evidently in no pleasant mood.</p>
               <pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC5737-00000039"/>
               <p>"Mrs. Gilman, will you be so kind as to give us the amount of your sales the past month? The facts may help us in this difficulty."</p>
               <p>"Fifty dollars," I replied.</p>
               <p>"And in July?"</p>
               <p>"Forty-five and a half. While, already this month I have sold thirty-five dollars' worth, but this is owing to the increased price for flowers. My garden produces, however, no more this month than last."</p>
               <p>"Fifty dollars a month," observed Joseph. "Why, that's more than I pay my clerk."</p>
               <p>"And your expenses were—"</p>
               <p>"Nothing but my fare in the cars, and a dollar and twenty cents I paid for bulbs and seeds."</p>
               <p>"Nonsense, Maria, you must have had a man to take care of your plants."</p>
               <p>"I did not, Joseph. All the work was done by my own hands."</p>
               <p>"O Maria! how could you? I wonder you are not a perfect fright by this time."</p>
               <p>"Do I look so, Charlotte?"</p>
               <p>"Well, no,—not by lamplight."</p>
               <p>"One more question, Mrs. Gilman, and I am done. Can you tell us how much the plants in your garden cost? I think you said they were planted in the spring."</p>
               <p>"Yes; I examined my husband's bills and found he paid seventy-five dollars for the plants."</p>
               <p>"Seventy-five dollars? A great price. I would have sold him the lot for sixty. Now, gentlemen, you have heard the defendant in the case. What have you to say?"</p>
               <p>They had nothing to say at all. A short pause ensued and then Charlotte remembered she must hurry home to the baby, and the minister found he had another call to make that evening. I cheerfully ushered them to the door, and they departed into the night.</p>
               <p>"Gentlemen, let us go on with our plans.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC5737-00000040"/>
               <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
               <head type="sub">HOUSE-BUILDING.</head>
               <p>ON returning a few mornings after this from the city I found my garden in possession of a large gang of laborers. The fence in front had been removed, a pile of lumber lay on the sidewalk, and some men were unloading a quantity of posts from a wagon that stood in the street. Fearing for my flowers I hastened to find the foreman, to warn him about my plants. He knew all about it; had taken them up and placed them in the cellar, safely covered up with damp soil. Changing my dress, I went out to watch the proceedings. In this I was not alone. From the time the first man came till they all drove away there was constantly a crowd of idlers, men and boys mainly, standing on the sidewalk, watching the operations. Them I at once and forever ignored.</p>
               <p>The first thing done was to mark out a space on the ground one hundred and ten feet long, and twenty-one feet wide. This being done the whole gang of men began at once to dig up the soil enclosed in this space, and to throw it out on either side. There were so many of them the work progressed rapidly, and at noon the whole space was dug out to the depth of one foot. After dinner the men were divided into two parties. One party busied themselves in making holes along the edge of the pit they had excavated. The others set up in these short cedar posts. At evening the posts were all set, about six feet apart, around the entire space. These posts were sunk in the bottom of the pit and extended above the level ground about one foot. The next day being fair, the work went rapidly forward. At night the work presented this appearance; a portion of the pit, about ten feet wide by twenty long, had been sunk quite deep in the ground. At the west end nearest the house, in fact within ten feet of our dining-room window, stood the frame of a small shed, running the whole width of the excavation, and about ten feet wide. From end to end four feet from the posts the pit was sunk one foot deeper than the rest. Directly through the centre stood another row of posts similar to those on the outside. This may seem a great amount of work for two days, but I had instructed Mr. Sawplane to engage all the men he could find, and to do everything thoroughly, but at high pressure.</p>
               <p>The next day I received a package and this letter by mail:—</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <opener>
                              <dateline>"ALLEGAN, September 20,—.</dateline>
                           </opener>
                           <p>"MRS. GILMAN:—Accompanying this are several wholesale trade catalogues of greenhouse stock. By examining them you can ascertain the price of the plants you will require for your new house. The following are the sorts I would recommend:— <list>
                                 <item>Tea Roses.</item>
                                 <item>Carnations.</item>
                                 <item>Heliotrope.</item>
                                 <item>Violets.</item>
                                 <pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC5737-00000041"/>
                                 <item>Azaleas.</item>
                                 <item>Epacris and Bourvardia.</item>
                                 <item>Ericas (Heaths).</item>
                              </list>
                           </p>
                           <p>"These are standard greenhouse flowers. The roses will give you a succession of flowers through the late winter and spring months. The heliotrope, with care, can be made to bloom every day in the year. The carnations and violets will last about four months. The other kinds give but one crop in the year. As these do not all flower at once, you can cut one sort after another has gone, and so extend your income over a longer time. But to these I would add still another list, in order to extend your cutting season still farther. The plants I have mentioned will fill your houses, but that is not enough. You must have a reserved supply to bring in after these have gone out of flower. In order to do this all the plants on the following list must be stored in your house-cellar until you require them in January after the season turns. I will explain all this by and by. Here is the list:— <list>
                                 <item>Deutzia Gracelis.</item>
                                 <item>Fuchsias.</item>
                                 <item>Astilbe Japonica.</item>
                                 <item>Lillium Candidum.</item>
                              </list>
                           </p>
                           <p>"To still further extend your sales, you can in the spring sow seeds of various annuals, stocks, pansies, etc., trifles in themselves, yet useful to piece out your income.</p>
                           <p>"Enclosed are letters of introduction to the parties whose catalogues I have sent you. If you purchase of them it may be of advantage to you to have it known that you are in the trade.</p>
                           <p>"There are many more flowers it would be profitable for you to grow, yet here is quite enough to begin with.</p>
                           <p>"All the plants you purchase must be short, not more than two feet high. You must not attempt camellias at all, unless you can find them very short, in which case they would bear so few flowers it would not be worth while.</p>
                           <p>"Leave the violets till the last. When you have enough of the others, fill up the remainder of the house with them.</p>
                           <p>"I do not think the cost will exceed five hundred dollars in all. If it were May instead of September, they would not cost one half of this. As it is, you will have to pay the cost of the culture up to this time.</p>
                           <p>"Please inform me when the plants arrive and I will call and show you how to place them in your house.</p>
                           <p>"My object in sending you this letter is not to induce you to purchase of my colaborers, but because I am glad to help one who is so bravely carrying out what has long been a favorite idea of mine,—that women have a right to any field of labor in which they are able and willing to work.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <salute>"Respectfully yours,</salute>
                              <signed>"EDWIN FELIX."</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Immediately on reading this I sat down and wrote a note to Mr. Felix, expressing my hearty thanks for his kindness, and promising to call at his place in a day or two and thank him personally.</p>
               <p>At the rate at which my house progressed, it would be finished in ten days; so I set about getting my stock at once. On looking over the catalogues I found they all made specialities of certain classes of plants. One man had a great assortment of heaths, another had roses and carnations.</p>
               <p>Selecting the rose and carnation man, I went to him first. His place was the other side of the city, on another railroad. On reaching the place, I presented my letter of introduction to the proprietor, and he conducted me to his counting-room at once. Giving me a seat, he said he would bring me some samples of his plants.</p>
               <p>"My houses are not fit for a lady to enter. They are too<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC5737-00000042"/> low and narrow. I can show you our plants without the trouble of going over the house."</p>
               <p>Now this did not suit me. I was in search of information as well as plants. I wanted to see how he grew them.</p>
               <p>"Well, ma'am, if you are not afraid of a little dirt, you can come through my rose-house."</p>
               <p>Opening a side-door, we went out, crossed a small yard, and entered a large span-roofed house. This building was without stages, but had all the roses planted out in the border or floor as in an out-door garden.</p>
               <p>"That," said the man, pointing to a large and thrifty bush filled with long, almond-shaped rosebuds of a delicate straw or sulphur color, "is the sofrano. And that the bon silene," pointing to a blood-red rose-bud, similar in shape. "These two roses are the best for your use. They are adapted to all kinds of flower-work. The sofrano is used both for funeral or wedding orders, and the bon silene is unrivalled for brilliancy of color. I can sell you plants of these two kinds one foot high and one year old, in pots, for thirty-five dollars a hundred. They are all in good order and some are showing flower."</p>
               <p>"How many buds can I expect from each before next July?"</p>
               <p>"Well, I couldn't say exactly. If they are well grown, you can cut from six to twenty buds in that time. If you only cut six, you will more than pay for the plants. Good sofrano buds are worth eight cents each in the winter."</p>
               <p>I said I would take one hundred of each, and then asked to see the carnations.</p>
               <p>"I am sorry, ma'am, I can't let you have many carnations. I've sold about all I can spare. I require about ten thousand for my own use, and what few over that I have I must keep for my retail trade. Why do you not go to Mr. Felix? I heard him say he had fifteen thousand this year. He would sell you some, without doubt."</p>
               <p>After spending an hour in looking over the bewildering multitude of plants on the place, I ordered the plants sent to me in ten days with the bill, and went home. What struck me as remarkable in this place was the immense number of plants gathered together in one establishment. Ten thousand carnations and none to spare! I wonder if I shall ever conduct business on such a scale?</p>
               <p>The next day I went up our own railroad about twenty miles to see the heath and epacris man. This place was quite small. The man devoted his entire attention to this class of plants, and had a great reputation as a heath man. His houses were all like Mr. Clockwell's,—long and half sunk in the ground. All the plants were in fine condition, short, bushy, and of a rich green color. A portion were in flower. I had never seen a more remarkable sight. There were five thousand in bloom, he informed me. I found the price was much higher than for roses, but was told that these plants were two years old and would last in good order for five years to come. I bought one hundred heaths and<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC5737-00000043"/> one hundred epacris, at fifty cents each. They were in pots and would not require shifting for six months or a year.</p>
               <p>The following day I walked over to Mr. Felix's. After thanking him for his letter I asked to see his carnations. Showing the way through his grounds, we at last came upon an open field entirely filled with carnation plants growing closely together in long rows.</p>
               <p>"What an enormous collection of plants! Where did you get so many?"</p>
               <p>"Some I raised myself, and some I bought last spring."</p>
               <p>"How many plants are there here, Mr. Felix?"</p>
               <p>"About twelve thousand."</p>
               <p>"Twelve thousand! How could you ever count them all?"</p>
               <p>"I never did. I only counted the plants in one row, and then counted the number of rows. It would take too long to count them all."</p>
               <p>"They are coming into flower,—are they not?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, they have about ten buds on each now. In the winter they will have about five times as many."</p>
               <p>"What do you get for the flowers in the winter? if I may ask."</p>
               <p>"You may ask what you please. I have no secrets about it. They are worth from two to four cents each."</p>
               <p>"How much do you charge for the plants after they are taken up and potted?"</p>
               <p>"They are not potted at all,—only taken up and planted in the borders in the house. You must do the same. You thereby save the expense of the pots and the labor of potting. I must charge you forty cents each for them. You had best not take a great many, but let it go till next year. In the spring you can have all you want for six cents each."</p>
               <p>"I will take a hundred, at any rate. If the ten buds that are on them now bring four cents each, I shall get my money back."</p>
               <p>"You will do more than that, I am sure." But come into the plant-house and see my heliotrope."</p>
               <p>Going into the plant-house (which is the name of the style of house we had seen at Mr. Clockwell's, and also the style in which I was building my own), he showed me a quantity of young heliotrope plants in three-inch pots.</p>
               <p>"These are quite small, in fact mere rooted cuttings; yet I advice you to take them. They will not flower so soon as larger ones, but you can have them very cheap,—not more than ten dollars a hundred, if you take several hundred. There are few flowers that will give you a better return. There are some larger ones in six-inch pots. They are just showing flower. They are worth sixteen dollars a hundred."</p>
               <p>"Then I will compromise and take part of each,—one hundred at sixteen and three hundred at ten dollars."</p>
               <p>After again thanking him for his kindness, I started to walk to Mr. Clockwell's. I had brought some luncheon in my pocket, and, taking it out, ate it on the road as I walked along. A more delightful lunch I never had. The<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC5737-00000044"/> sun was shining brightly and the air was cool and crisp. The walking was good, and all nature seemed in her most charming autumnal mood.</p>
               <p>On reaching the place, I found Mr. Clockwell was not at home. Taking out my knife (I carried one always), I cut a stout stick from a bush and set out on my three-mile tramp homewards. Just before I entered the village I threw my cane away. My pride was not quite dead yet. I reached home just as the workmen were going away, tired and hungry from my five-mile walk. But what of that? A good supper and a night's rest would correct everything.</p>
               <p>The next day was devoted to housework. Perhaps you wonder how I attended to this at all. In the first place, I had all my evenings to myself; secondly, my children helped me as far as they were able; and, lastly, we are not any of us "idlers in the land."</p>
               <p>As I had some mending to do, I sat down by the window to watch the men at work on my new plant-house. The new shed was roofed over, doors and windows in, and all finished outside. A low stone wall had been built up between the posts extending around the cellar or pit. On top and firmly fastened to the posts was a narrow strip of two-inch plank having the top bevelled off at an angle of forty-five degrees. On top of the row of posts placed through the centre was a broad piece of plank having upright edges, so that it had the appearance of a long, narrow trough. This was also bevelled off like the top of the outside wall. Six feet from the bottom of the pit, and fastened up in a temporary manner, equidistant from the wall and the centre post, were two pieces of timber of a very peculiar shape. A drawing will best describe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head/>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>These were all the parts of the house completed, making a sort of skeleton. While I was studying all this out, two large teams drove up piled high with hot-bed sash,—as the farmers call them. They were plain sashes filled with glass six feet long by three wide, looking like exaggerated skylights. The workmen at once unloaded these and placed them in heaps in our yard. This done, they took up one sash, and, placing the bottom on the bevelled edge of the wall, dropped the top into the slot or groove in the ridge-pole, as you see in the drawing. Taking four screws they quickly fastened it down top and bottom. Then they put another on the opposite side so that the two sashes made an arch. Leaving a space the width of a sash, they put up two more, and then more, till half of all the sashes were in place. This done, the temporary supports were taken away and the building at once supported itself. Other men in the mean while had been fastening curious iron hooks to the wall opposite the spaces. They then took a sash, dropped the bottom in the iron hooks, and slid the whole thing neatly into place alongside the sash already in. In thirty minutes<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC5737-00000045"/> every sash was in place, and my plant-house was complete, except the inside. Delighted with the neat and compact appearance of the house, I went out to inspect. At the door I met Mr. Felix.</p>
               <p>"Allow me to congratulate you, Mrs. Gilman, on the appearance of your new house."</p>
               <p>"Thank you, sir. Will you come and look at it?"</p>
               <p>We then went to examine. It presented somewhat this appearance. First, a one-story shed with a door and two windows are towards the yard, and one looking south over the two glass roofs. These two roofs were placed side by side and extended to the limits of my garden, just one hundred feet. The street ran north and south, and the plant-house was parallel to it and about twenty feet from the sidewalk. You see the building occupied almost all my garden, but that was of no consequence, as I intended to farm under glass after this, and would not need so large a garden. In fact, my whole estate is very small. My whole place was only one hundred and sixty feet long and seventy-five wide. I called it my farm, and as the street front was just ten rods I gave it the name that heads this story.</p>
               <p>After examining the improvements, I asked Mr. Felix into the house. On entering the sitting-room he went to the window to look at my tuberoses.</p>
               <p>"Hardly a success, Mrs. Gilman."</p>
               <p>"How so? I thought they were looking well and would bear a full crop of tuberoses."</p>
               <p>"They will produce some, but not half a crop. The soil you used was too clayey. There was not enough sand in it."</p>
               <p>"Indeed. My ignorance is my only excuse."</p>
               <p>"Never be ashamed of your ignorance. I have made worse mistakes than that."</p>
               <p>"Now, Mrs. Gilman, in this new undertaking you may make more serious mistakes than this, and would it not be a good idea to have some man like McTernan come here once a week and tell you what attention your plants require from week to week, and how to give it; in fact, give you a lesson in gardening. I do not imagine he would have to come a great many weeks. You are an apt scholar in all that pertains to flowers."</p>
               <p>"Yes, I think I am quick to learn. But it is from the fact that by gardening I earn my livelihood."</p>
               <p>"There is one other thing I wish to mention. I think you ought to engage a lad to do the heavy work about your business. Building fires, pumping water, etc. Your income from the plant-house will fully warrant you in the expense. It is not important that he should know anything of plants. You must be your own gardener and instruct him,—not he you. It would be best to engage him before your plants arrive, as there is a great deal to be done to get the soil ready. If you will get a piece of paper I will write down a list of the soils you will require, and you had better order them at once.<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC5737-00000046"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>"Three cords of rich compost.</item>
                     <item>One cord of meadow muck, one year old.</item>
                     <item>Twenty loads of good loam.</item>
                     <item>Four loads of fine sand.</item>
                     <item>Two loads of rubble or small stones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>"Have them thrown up in separate heaps in the yard. and I will show you how to mix them when the time comes. The cost will be about fifty dollars. It may seem a great price to pay, but you can do nothing without it; and to offset it you will not have the expense of pots, as almost all your stock will be planted directly in the soil."</p>
               <p>"Thank you, Mr. Felix. You help me out wonderfully. But I do not like to be under so much obligation to you."</p>
               <p>"Never mind that. I am glad to help you, as you are so bravely trying to help yourself. Get your boy and the soils, and I will call next week." Saying this he took his hat as if to go.</p>
               <p>"Wait a moment, Mr. Felix, I have one little favor to ask. Why could you not come once a week and tell me more? Why cannot you be my teacher yourself?"</p>
               <p>"Oh, don't ask me. My time is so valuable in the winter, I should have to charge five dollars an hour while I was here."</p>
               <p>"I will pay it gladly if you will come whenever I wish. It will not be oftener than once a week."</p>
               <p>"I will consider it, Mrs. Gilman, and see you next week. Good-night."</p>
               <p>"Good-night, sir."</p>
               <p>In a few days I found a boy, Richard Dermand, by name, just out of school, knowing nothing of gardening, but willing to learn and able to work. By Wednesday of the following week, I had procured and paid for the various soils mentioned on the list I received from Mr. Felix. That evening Mr. Sawplane came and informed me that my plant-house was finished according to contract, and that nothing remained but to take the key and pay the bill.</p>
               <p>The next day was the first of October. Since my building operations began, my income from the garden had ceased. My sales up to that time amounted to forty-three dollars. In all, I have received from my garden thus far, one hundred and thirty-eight dollars and fifty cents.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC5737-00000047"/>
               <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
               <head type="sub">SUCCESS—FAILURE—SUCCESS AGAIN.</head>
               <p>LET me take you into my plant-house, now that it is finished. On entering the door we find ourselves in a small room, twenty feet long by ten wide. There are two windows, one looking on the front yard and one out over the two glass roofs. The floor extends over a portion of the shed; one end being sunk down into a cellar four feet deep. A few steps lead down to the "Hitching's Boiler" that heats the building. A coal-bin, a small force-pump with a coil of hose, and a spacious potting-bench, constitute the furniture of the place. Two short flights of steps lead down into the two plant-houses, for they are in reality two separate buildings, though the eaves of each come together on one side, forming a long valley. Entering the door of the right hand,—or west house, as I call it for the sake of a name,—we find ourselves under a glass roof in the form of an arch. The base of the arch is level with the ground outside. The ridge rises three feet higher than this, and the walk within is sunk three feet lower. This gives six feet for head room. Two rows of small posts, three feet high and two feet apart, extend the whole length of the place. To these are nailed boards planed on the inside, or towards the walk. Thus we have left a narrow path, two feet wide through the centre of the house. On each side of this walk about a foot from the floor runs a four-inch iron pipe, which, when filled with hot water from the boiler, keeps the place warm in the winter. Outside the path is a long trough four feet wide and two feet deep. This is to be filled with soil, and in or on this soil the plants are to grow or stand in pots. When it is full this is called "the border." The second house is precisely like this, except that it is divided in the middle by a partition, having a door in it. That portion I call the east house; beyond, the violet house. At the entrance of each of these houses is a "cut-off" in the hot-water pipe, to regulate the heat. The borders in these three houses form my winter farm. Their united length is four hundred feet. In this space, four hundred feet by four, or sixteen hundred square feet, I expect to produce all the flowers I require in my business. Beneath the shed is a deep pit, having the sides plastered over with cement. The rain falling on the glass roofs runs into this, and supplies the water for my plants. Directly over the walks, and within easy reach, iron rachets are fastened to every other sash. These enabled me to tilt the sashes up for ventilation, or remove them altogether if wished. I did not adopt Mr. McTernan's method of opening the ventilators, partly because I had no high stage to climb, and partly because my plan was cheaper.</p>
               <pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC5737-00000048"/>
               <p>Having thus described my plant-house, let me tell you how I stocked it. First I had my boy wheel all the rubble in his barrow up to the side of the house, and, taking out one of the loose sashes dump it into the bottom of the borders, spreading it out about six inches deep. Then I engaged a laborer to help the boy, and had the various heaps of sand, loam, etc., thrown up in one huge pile. This being done they began at one end, and turned it all over, breaking the lumps and mixing the whole well together. When this was accomplished the entire heap was removed in the wheelbarrow to the borders. When the work was completed the interior presented this appearance,—the right hand border in the west house filled up level with the boarding of the path; fifty feet on the other side filled in the same way, and the remaining fifty feet filled within twelve inches of the top. By so doing, I gained one foot in height for the taller plants. The border in the violet house was filled full. One half of the east house border was full, and one half one foot lower.</p>
               <p>By this time the plants began to arrive. First came the roses. These, together with a few from my garden, I had planted in the left-hand border in the west house, giving them half the length of the house. The opposite border was devoted to the four hundred heliotropes. All of these were taken out of the pots, and planted in the soil of the border, just as we would treat them in the open ground in summer. Then Mr. Felix sent the carnations. They were not in pots, but packed in large boxes. They were at once set out as thickly as they could stand in the east house. You now see why this border was not as deep as the other. The plants were tall, and by keeping the surface down I gained more room under the glass. Next came the heaths and epacris. As these were to remain in their pots, they were simply placed upon the border, just as they were.</p>
               <p>A few days after this I bought at auction sixteen hundred violets, which I planted as closely as possible in their own house, filling it completely.</p>
               <p>I also bought of Mr. Clockwell two hundred bourvardias in six-inch pots. As they would grow best in pots they were merely placed in rows on the border of the west house. All my borders were now stocked, except about thirty feet of the east house. This space I filled with fifty fine plants of azalea indica, which I purchased of Mr. McTernan.</p>
               <p>My new plant-house is now finished, stocked, and ready for business. I paid every bill promptly. Here is a list:— <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>MRS. MARIA GILMAN</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>TO REUBEN SAWPLANE, DR.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>To sashes</cell>
                        <cell>$400 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>To shed</cell>
                        <cell>75 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>To labor</cell>
                        <cell>50 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>To stone-work</cell>
                        <cell>50 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>To painting</cell>
                        <cell>60 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>To boiler and pipe</cell>
                        <cell>400 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>To posts, lumber, etc.</cell>
                        <cell>75 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>To force pump and hose</cell>
                        <cell>40 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>$1,150 00</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC5737-00000049"/>
               <p>My plants cost as follows:— <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>200 roses</cell>
                        <cell>$70 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>100 heliotrope</cell>
                        <cell>16 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>300 heliotrope</cell>
                        <cell>30 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>50 azalea indica</cell>
                        <cell>50 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>100 ericas (heaths)</cell>
                        <cell>50 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>100 epacris</cell>
                        <cell>50 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>200 bourvardia</cell>
                        <cell>40 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>200 deutzia gracelis</cell>
                        <cell>20 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>100 astilbe japonica</cell>
                        <cell>8 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>100 lillium candidum</cell>
                        <cell>8 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1,600 violets</cell>
                        <cell>160 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>$502 00</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Mr. Sawplane's bill</cell>
                        <cell>1,150 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Sand, loam, etc.</cell>
                        <cell>50 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Incidentals</cell>
                        <cell>10 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>$1,712 00</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>This, then, was the entire cost the day I set up as a regular florist. My bills were all settled on the fifteenth of October, and three days after I cut the first flowers from my new plant-house.</p>
               <p>The first week I passed in fear and trembling, not knowing exactly how to manage the watering and ventilation. After a little practice, however, I learned my lesson for once and all. This is the way in which I acquired the requisite skill. I hung up in each house a small thermometer; Mr. Felix then made three cards to be fastened up near each glass. For the west house, where the roses and heliotrope were growing, the card read:— <q>
                     <p>"Sunshine, 75°—cloudy, 65°—night, 60°."</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>This was intended to indicate the proper temperature under these three conditions. When the day was clear, with abundant sunshine, the thermometer must not rise above 75° If the heat of the sun sent it above that, enough ventilators must be opened to allow the surplus heat to escape, and so keep the inside temperature within one or two degrees of 75°. If the day was cloudy, the ventilators must be kept shut to preserve the temperature at 65°. If this was not enough, a fire must be started under the boiler, and the temperature forced up to that point and held there. At night sufficient fire must be provided to secure a temperature of at least 60° till morning.</p>
               <p>In the east house the card ran:— <q>
                     <p>"Sunshine, 70°—cloudy, 60°—night, 55°."</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The violet house required to be kept on still another scale. This was its card:— <q>
                     <p>"Sunshine, 60°—cloudy, 50°—night, 45°."</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>By the aid of these cards the whole subject of ventilation was reduced to a very simple affair. You will observe that in the night I was obliged to maintain three different temperatures with one fire. This was easily accomplished by means of the "cut-offs." I used the cards for about three months, when I found I could tell by the feeling of the air<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC5737-00000050"/> on my face just what the temperature was, and govern myself accordingly, without looking at the mercury any longer.</p>
               <p>How to manage the watering, I learned with equal facility, by observing the following rules:—</p>
               <p>Never water a plant till it requires it.</p>
               <p>Always water thoroughly. Fill the pots brimfull.</p>
               <p>The borders need water whenever the surface becomes dry.</p>
               <p>The pot plants are to be watered whenever the surface soil becomes dry or the pot becomes light-colored. The water must be enriched with guano, or some other fertilizer, twice a week, and applied with a watering-pot to the heliotrope, roses, and bourvardia. Once a week all the plants must be showered when the sun is shining brightly.</p>
               <p>Time to water,—the morning.</p>
               <p>Among other things, I took my tuberoses into the plant-house. As they were quite tall, I was obliged to stand them on the walk. They came into flower soon after coming into the house, and, although they did not bear half a crop, yet I cut an average of fifty cents' worth from each bulb.</p>
               <p>The deutzia, astilbe, and lilliums I bought in the city, and, when they arrived, stored them in the house cellar.</p>
               <p>The deutzia is a hardy shrub, and the astilbe is a herbaceous plant. They came packed in damp moss, and I placed them on the cellar floor and covered the roots with soil to prevent their drying. The lillium candidum is a hardy bulb, and came in a paper box, quite dry. I potted them, together with those from my garden, putting two in a seven-inch pot, and set them in the yard that they might be slightly frozen. After staying out one frosty night, they were removed to the cellar. The fuchsias were placed with the deutzias and the remainder of the garden plants were thrown away as valueless.</p>
               <p>The month of October had slipped away by the time that all this was accomplished, and November and cold weather were upon us. Let me give you the business operations for the month. As I have said already, my flowers began to bloom almost as soon as I received them. The violets came first, and ere long each carnation gave me a flower or two each day. The statement below shows that I lost money the first month; but this I expected. I drew for the deficit upon my capital, so that on the first of November my stock had cost me eighteen hundred and ten dollars:— <table>
                     <head>Paid.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Boy</cell>
                        <cell>$16 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Boy's board</cell>
                        <cell>20 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Mr. Felix</cell>
                        <cell>10 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Fares</cell>
                        <cell>2 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>My own support</cell>
                        <cell>60 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>$108 00</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <table>
                     <head>Received.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>For flowers</cell>
                        <cell>10 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Balance</cell>
                        <cell>98 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>$108 00</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC5737-00000051"/>
               <p>I started the first fire in my boiler on the evening of November second, and from this date kept it up every night till the first of May. The month of November passed away almost without incident. I gave up going to the city, but sent Johnny instead. He carried the flowers in a small wooden box covered with green paper, with a leather strap for a handle. When it became very cold, I used to place a bottle of hot water in the box to prevent the flowers from freezing on the road. As the greater part of my plants were planted in the borders, they required but little attention. To show how I passed my time, I will give you the routine of one day's labor. The first thing to be done was to cut the flowers before the sun was high. Then came breakfast. That over, the bill of the flowers was made out, and Johnny despatched. After clearing up affairs in the house, I went out to the plant-house again, at about half-past nine. If the day was cloudy, and the houses not up to the required temperature, I freshened the fire. If the sun shone, this would be unnecessary, as the heat of the sun alone was sufficient to warm the buildings without artificial aid. Then came the watering, if it was needed. That done, or found superfluous, I spent my time in keeping things clean and in order, for really this was all I had to do. At noon Johnny returned from school, where he had been since his flying visit to the city. He brought me the empty box, and the flower bill duly endorsed by Thomas Dacy. Mary returned at the same time, and at half-past twelve we had dinner ner. After dinner, I returned to my work. About three o'clock I closed the ventilators, if they had been opened, and at four had the fires built for the night. At sundown I returned to my own house, the labor for the day being nearly over. After supper, I sent the boy out to put on more coal, and, at ten o'clock, I went out with him to be sure that enough coal was on and everything made right for the night. After that,—bed. Now, this was not a hard day's work. In fact, I was surprised to find how easy it became after a little while. It is true, I always had enough both for the boy and myself to do; but it was all very light work, and not tiresome. I found the atmosphere of the plant-house was beneficial to my health. Working all day in a genial warmth and bathed in the full sunlight improved my appetite, and I actually gained two pounds during the first month. When my husband was alive, and, beyond my house-work, I had little or nothing to do, I was not in the best of health, and easily tired. Now, I felt strong, and could work all day, without being half as much fatigued at night.</p>
               <p>My flowers continued to thrive, and yielded steadily increasing returns. Here is the statement for November:— <table>
                     <head>Paid.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Boy and board</cell>
                        <cell>$36 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Fuel</cell>
                        <cell>20 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Mr. Felix (two visits)</cell>
                        <cell>10 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Season ticket</cell>
                        <cell>4 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Incidental</cell>
                        <cell>2 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC5737-00000052"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Family expenses</cell>
                        <cell>60 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Balance</cell>
                        <cell>18 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>$150 00</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <table>
                     <head>Received.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>For flowers</cell>
                        <cell>$150 00</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>To explain this great improvement in my income, I give below one of the daily bills Johnny carried to the city. At times the bill was larger than this. The amount varied with the weather. On cloudy and stormy days the flowers would not come out so freely as on pleasant days. In fact I soon found the amount of sunshine was a matter of dollars and cents to me. If I had less sunlight, I had less flowers, and, consequently, less money. I assure you, I looked out for the sun with all the eagerness of a photographer. Here is a day's return:— <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>400 violets</cell>
                        <cell>$4 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4 doz. heliotrope</cell>
                        <cell>1 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2 doz. bourvardia</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>$5 50</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>December passed without any mishap. The flowers bloomed more and more freely day by day. The fall heaths came into flower, and the tuberoses ceased and were thrown away. The people in the village began to look upon my operations with more favor, and even condescended to visit my establishment. When they commenced calling I was very attentive to them, but as this took so much time I left them to inspect things under their own guidance. As the days grew shorter I was obliged to light the fires much earlier, and even keep them up during the day. This added to the expense, but not materially. On Christmas day some of my neighbors wished to purchase some of my flowers; but I declined to sell, as the city store had a prior claim. That day I sent in twenty dollars' worth,—a larger amount than I had ever expected to receive in one day. This the December statement:— <table>
                     <head>Paid.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Boy</cell>
                        <cell>36 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Fuel</cell>
                        <cell>25 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Mr. Felix</cell>
                        <cell>5 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Season ticket</cell>
                        <cell>4 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Household</cell>
                        <cell>60 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Balance</cell>
                        <cell>45 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>$175 00</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <table>
                     <head>Received.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>For flowers</cell>
                        <cell>$175 00</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>The interest on the mortgage became due on the sixteenth of this month, but I readily obtained credit till my money came in, and then I paid it, together with the taxes, and had just two dollars left to begin the new year.</p>
               <p>Soon after the first of January we had a severe snowstorm that covered the ground two feet deep. This proved greatly to my advantage, for the snow acted as a blanket and kept the ground warm. My plant-house being half sunk in the soil received the full benefit of this, and my coal bill was actually reduced.</p>
               <p>On the last evening of the month we had a violent rainstorm<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC5737-00000053"/> storm. After supper I sat down to add up the amounts upon my flower cards, and ascertained that my sales at the store had reached one hundred and eighty dollars, while I had sold to persons who came to the door ten dollars' worth; making in all one hundred and ninety dollars for the month.</p>
               <p>The storm was so severe at ten o'clock that I called Richard and gave him the key with directions to put more coal on the fire, and see that the damper in the chimney was nearly closed. Delegating to my servant such work, instead of going out myself and seeing it done, was a fatal mistake, that nearly caused my failure in business. When the boy returned I asked him if everything was all right, and he said it was. During the night it cleared off and in the morning a cold north-west wind was blowing. As soon as I entered the plant-house it struck me as being very cold. Going to the thermometer in the west house I found the mercury down to 30°. I touched the leaves of a heliotrope. It was stiff,—frozen. Going to the east house, I consulted the glass again,—28°. Opening the violet house I discovered every plant completely frostbitten—and the glass at 26°. Returning to the shed, I opened the fire door in the boiler. The fire was quite out, and the pipes cold. Looking at the chimney I found the damper wide open. The boy had not touched it, and, the wind rising, had started the full draft, and the fire had burned out. Utterly mortified, discomfited, and heartbroken broken, I returned to the house, threw myself on the sofa, and burst into a flood of tears. And this is the end of all my labor, and all my waiting and watching. In one night my plants destroyed and my business prostrated. So much for the carelessness of my servant, and my own folly in trusting to another what I should have attended to myself. Surely, I have learned a lesson,—but at what a cost.</p>
               <p>Suddenly the door-bell rang, and in a moment Mr. Felix stood before me.</p>
               <p>"Why, Mrs. Gilman, what is the matter? Are you sick?"</p>
               <p>"No—yes—yes, I am sick,—It's enough to make any one sick. I've failed,—I know I have."</p>
               <p>"Failed! How so? Have you lost your pay through the failure of the store?"</p>
               <p>"No, no; it is not that. The fire went out, and—and—oh, I'm sure I have failed in everything."</p>
               <p>"The fire went out! when?".</p>
               <p>"Last night, and every plant is frozen stiff."</p>
               <p>Then I buried my face in my hands, and sobbed as if my heart would break. Presently I felt a light touch on my shoulder.</p>
               <p>"Mrs. Gilman, you must rouse yourself. You must not give up in this way. There is no time to lose. Everything depends upon prompt action."</p>
               <p>"No, I cannot, Mr. Felix. I have worked too long and too hard already, and I'll do no more. It is of no further use."</p>
               <pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC5737-00000054"/>
               <p>"You are not yourself, Mrs. Gilman. Come, make one more effort. Perhaps we can save a portion of your property."</p>
               <p>"No, I cannot."</p>
               <p>"But you must. What are the children to do if you give up in despair?"</p>
               <p>"The children! What of them?"</p>
               <p>"I say you must come out with me and see if we cannot repair damages."</p>
               <p>"I am ready. I <emph>will</emph> be calm. What must I do first?"</p>
               <p>"In the first place send Johnny and Mary for every blanket, sheet, cloth, or carpet they can find, and then let them cover the glass with them to shut out the sun. Bid them hasten as the sun will soon be high. Call your boy also, and have him build a fire as quickly as possible, and, as for yourself, come with me to the plant-house."</p>
               <p>On reaching the building he went to the pump, and, unrolling the hose, placed the brass nozzle in my trembling hands, saying:—</p>
               <p>"Now let me pump, and do you go carefully over every plant and drench it with water."</p>
               <p>Dragging the hose after me, I entered the west house, and at once the pump began to work. We worked in silence. There was no sound save the steady clank of the pump, the rush of the water, and the loud beating of my heart.</p>
               <p>While we were thus engaged the place was gradually darkened by the cloths placed on the glass outside by the children. By the time I had watered that house, every ray of sunlight was shut out. Then, with Mr. Felix's help, the hose was removed to the east house, and I began again.</p>
               <p>Suddenly the door opened, and my brother Joseph entered.</p>
               <p>"What's the matter, Maria?"</p>
               <p>"My fire went out, and the plants are frozen."</p>
               <p>"Frozen, are they? Just what I expected. I told you, you would fail up, some day."</p>
               <p>"Did you?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, I did, and now I hope you will listen to your friends and reason."</p>
               <p>"Move, Joseph, please move; I must water my plants. Come another time, please."</p>
               <p>"No, I'll not move."</p>
               <p>"But you must!"</p>
               <p>"No, I will not. You shall hear me now. I say you must give up this—"</p>
               <p>"Joseph, you must move on, or I shall wet you."</p>
               <p>"I say you must sell out and give this thing up."</p>
               <p>"Move on, please."</p>
               <p>But he would not, and, calling to Mr. Felix to give more force to the stream, I made a slight movement of the now powerful stream. My brother's coat-sleeve glistened with the spray.</p>
               <pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC5737-00000055"/>
               <p>"Now, Joseph, you must come another time. I am busy now. I cannot talk with you,—move, please. You will be drenched if you stand there."</p>
               <p>Finding me resolute, and observing my now really formidable weapon, he beat a sullen retreat. As he passed through the shed Mr. Felix said something to him. What it was I never knew, but I soon saw Joseph slinking out of our gate.</p>
               <p>Finishing this house, I moved on to the violets. But they looked so badly, that I called Mr. Felix from the pump.</p>
               <p>"What can we do with them?"</p>
               <p>"Do with them?—nothing, they are entirely spoiled. You had best shut up the house for the next two months. You can do nothing with it. It is a great pity! There must be upward of two thousand flowers on the plants."</p>
               <p>Just then Johnny, who was standing on the snow outside, called through the glass:—</p>
               <p>"See, mother, there aint any more sheets. We have covered the heliotrope and the violets. But we can't cover any more."</p>
               <p>"Take them off the violets and shade this house," said Mr. Felix.</p>
               <p>Accordingly the children made the change.</p>
               <p>"Now, Mrs. Gilman, let us see how great the damage is, and what we can do to repair it. So we went over the whole place and that night I had carried out his direction. We worked hard all day, and at evening the place presented this appearance: All the heliotrope had been pulled up and thrown away. The roses had been cut down to bare stems. The azaleas were not materially injured. All the ericas, azaleas and epacris were brought in and placed upon the borders in the west house. The flowers upon them were injured, though the plants were not hurt much. They would do for next winter's use. The bourvardia were in full bloom, but the flowers were quite spoiled. The plants were cut down, and the roots that remained in the pots were stored in the cellar. By this change one house was cleared, and the remaining plants gathered together in the other house. The empty house was shut up and the heat cut off to save fuel. The violet house was also closed. As I went in to cut off the heat, I noticed that all the plants were quite black and dead. Then I understood why Mr. Felix was so anxious to exclude the bright rays of the sun, and why I was directed to water the plants we hoped to save. The water took the frost out slowly, and the shade prevented a too sudden change from cold to heat.</p>
               <p>The next day the news was all over the village, and the whole place rang with one loud cry, "I told you so! I told you so!"</p>
               <p>As I had no flowers to send to the city by my son, his absence was at once noted. In a day or two Mr. McTernan called.</p>
               <p>"It's froze, are ye? I'm sorry for ye. I declare it's<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC5737-00000056"/> too bad. But, I tell ye what ye can do. Ye can fill up your empty house with bedding-stuff, and in the spring ye'll be all right again."</p>
               <p>"But what is bedding-stuff, Mr. McTernan?"</p>
               <p>"Why, verbenas and such."</p>
               <p>"But I know nothing of their culture."</p>
               <p>"Oh, they is easy enough. Ye rig up a sand bed, and I'll send ye the cuttings this day."</p>
               <p>"Thank you, Mr. McTernan, but I cannot pay for them. I have but little money left."</p>
               <p>"Never ye mind the pay. If ye make anything ye may give me a cent for each. If ye don't it's all the same."</p>
               <p>Determined to do something to help myself out of my troubles, I had further conversation on the subject, and agreed that he should send me a thousand cuttings the next day.</p>
               <p>Mr. Felix called in the afternoon, and to him I mentioned the bedding-plant idea.</p>
               <p>"Just the thing," said he, "and tomatoes. You can fill your east house with bedding-plants, and the violet house with tomato plants. They will sell readily in May and June. If you try it I am sure you can make up your losses, and come out on the first of July right side up. And there are your deutzias and other plants. Bring them from your cellar and place them in the empty house, and force them. Besides I have here some wonderful seeds, warranted to pull any one out of any pickle, though they sometimes get in themselves." And, laughing to himself, he laid in my hand a package of seeds.</p>
               <p>"What shall I do with them?"</p>
               <p>"Get two hundred three-inch pots, and fill them with fine soil from your violet house. Plant three of these seeds in each pot. When the plants come up, remove all but one from each pot. Keep them growing rapidly, shifting them from pot to pot as they advance, and in about sixty days you will see some flowers which I imagine will be new to you."</p>
               <p>"But what are they?"</p>
               <p>"Wait and you will see;" and, with a pleasant smile, he bade me good-night, and went his way.</p>
               <p>Miss Sampson also called. She told me not to be discouraged by my disaster. It was not such an uncommon occurrence. The best of florists' houses sometimes freeze, and yet the owners always manage to get out of it somehow, and there was no doubt that I should likewise.</p>
               <p>Now I cannot give you all the details of my doings for the next three months. It would take more time than I can command. I can only say that I went to work bravely, and by the first of May had raised five thousand bedding-plants and five thousand tomato plants. To bring this about and to make up my deficit for the months of February and March, I used up all I had made and all my capital besides. In April my plants had so far recovered<pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC5737-00000057"/> that the sales of the flowers met the expense of their culture. In the middle of April I put this advertisement in our weekly "Journal":— <q>
                     <p>"BEDDING AND TOMATO PLANTS FOR SALE.<lb/> M. GILMAN, FLORIST,<lb/> MAIN STREET."</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>I also put up a sign on my gate:— <q>
                     <p>"BEDDING AND TOMATO PLANTS FOR SALE."</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>About the tenth of May, the neighbors, and others living in the town, began to call for bedding-plants, and my time was fully taken up in retailing them to the crowd of people who thronged my place every pleasant day.</p>
               <p>Among them came Mrs. Jacques. She bought a few plants, and wanted credit for them. I gave it to her unwillingly, as the plant and flower trade is strictly a cash business. Its very nature makes it so.</p>
               <p>A few days after she called, there was a red flag displayed at her husband's door, and I overheard this conversation between two men on our sidewalk. I was in the plant-house at the time, but as the ventilators were open I could hear every word.</p>
               <p>"Old Jacques has gone up, they say."</p>
               <p>"Yes, served him right. He was too lazy to work, and so failed. By the way, Dick, if you do want to see a worker, you just step into the greenhouse yonder and see the woman-florist."</p>
               <p>While this was going on, a wagon drove slowly past the gate. In it sat a farmer with his little girl. Seeing my sign, he pulled up his horse, got out, and came in.</p>
               <p>"Is Mr. Gilman in?"</p>
               <p>"There is no Mr. Gilman."</p>
               <p>"Who is M. Gilman? I want some tomatoes any way."</p>
               <p>"I am Mrs. Gilman, and if you will come this way I will show you the plants."</p>
               <p>On entering the violet house, he seemed greatly pleased with the appearance of things. Walking up and down the path, he looked at the plants, and ran his hand over the tops as if to feel how stout and stocky they were.</p>
               <p>"Wall now, them be purty plants. Did you raise them yourself?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, sir."</p>
               <p>"Wall, now, that beats all I ever heard. And you are a woman-gardener, are you?"</p>
               <p>"I am trying to be."</p>
               <p>"Come now, they is good ones, aint they? Lordy! who'd a thought it? I must tell my old woman. A woman-gardener! How much do you ask for them, ma'am?"</p>
               <p>"Fifty cents a dozen."</p>
               <p>"Oh, don't mind the dozens. It's not by the dozen or hundred I wants them. What do you charge for a thousand?"</p>
               <pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC5737-00000058"/>
               <p>"Thirty dollars."</p>
               <p>"Take twenty-eight."</p>
               <p>"No, sir."</p>
               <p>"Wall, it's mor'n I'm paying, but they is extra, they is. I'll take three thousand. The boys will come over for them in a day or so. You may give them five hundred at a time. I can't come myself again, and, seeing you are a woman, I'll pay you now while I have the money." Taking out an old leather purse, he placed in my hand ninety dollars, and then drove away.</p>
               <p>When he had gone, I unrolled the money and looked at it. Suddenly the moisture gathered in my eyes. Leaning my head upon the edge of the border, I gave way to a flood of tears. Not tears of sorrow, this time, but tears of joy and thankfulness. Surely God deserts not the widow and the fatherless.</p>
               <p>From that day the Lord prospered me. I sold all my bedding-plants without any difficulty. The aggregate amount I received for them was four hundred and twenty-six dollars and fifty cents. The tomato plants yielded one hundred and twenty dollars more. With this money I paid Mr. McTernan, and, after settling every bill had enough left to take up one half my mortgage.</p>
               <p>On the evening of the Fourth of July, just a year from the day I began, I invited Miss Sampson, Mr. McTernan, Mr. Felix, his wife, whom I found to be a charming lady, and their two little girls, to a grand strawberry supper.</p>
               <p>While we were at tea, we heard a great pounding in the yard, and, sallying forth, discovered a man nailing up a new sign on top of the plant-house.</p>
               <p>"I thought I would celebrate the day by sticking up your new shingle."</p>
               <p>Waving aloft his hammer, he exhibited the result of his labor:— <q>
                     <p>"MARIA GILMAN,<lb/> FLORIST."</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>"Long may she wave!" shouted the sign-painter.</p>
               <p>Then the gentlemen all cheered, while the ladies waved their handkerchiefs, and we all had a merry time.</p>
               <p>At ten o'clock my friends departed. I shook them each by the hand, and, with tears in my eyes, thanked them for all their kindness.</p>
               <p>But stop,—let me tell you about the seeds Mr. Felix gave me. I planted them as he directed. They soon came up, and exhibited a tendency to run, proving they were vines. I shifted them from pot to pot till they were a yard long, and in a seven-inch pot. By this time they were covered with small yellow flowers. I asked Mr. Felix what I should do with the flowers. "Let them alone and see what becomes of them." After the bedding and tomato plants were gone, and the other plants, except the roses, removed out of doors, the vines were planted out three feet apart in the borders, filling both houses. They soon took root in<pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC5737-00000059"/> the rich soil and grew rapidly. In June they bore fruit, and in immense quantities. We were obliged to spend an hour every evening in gathering the fruit and packing it in boxes. Every morning Sharpedge &amp; Co. sent a light wagon and took it away. I sent them the following bill in August. If you read it you will see what it was:—</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <opener>
                              <address>
                                 <addrLine>MESSRS. SHARPEDGE &amp; CO.</addrLine>
                              </address>
                              <salute>TO MARIA GILMAN, DR.</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>
                              <table>
                                 <row>
                                    <cell>For 3,600 cucumbers at 3 cents,</cell>
                                    <cell>$108 00</cell>
                                 </row>
                              </table>
                           </p>
                           <closer>
                              <salute>Received payment,</salute>
                              <signed>MARIA GILMAN.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Let me now review my operations for the past six months. Here are my monthly sales:— <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>January, flowers</cell>
                        <cell>$190 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>February,</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>March, flowers</cell>
                        <cell>50 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>April, flowers deutzia, astilbe, etc.</cell>
                        <cell>140 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>May, flowers lillium, roses, etc.</cell>
                        <cell>150 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>May, flowers bedding-plants</cell>
                        <cell>426 50</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>June, flowers, roses, etc.</cell>
                        <cell>100 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>June, tomato plants</cell>
                        <cell>120 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>July and August, cucumbers</cell>
                        <cell>108 00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>$1,284 50</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>My expenses to July (including the support of my family) amounted to eight hundred and fifteen dollars.</p>
               <p>I was obliged to give up my flower garden after this, as the buildings occupied nearly all my land, and what little remained was filled with my flowering stock for the winter. However, this was a small affair. I could well dispense with my garden flowers now. In addition to the bedding-plants, I raised a quantity of violets and carnations for my next winter's use, so that I was not obliged to spend so much in the fall for new stock. In fact, I spent but very little. My last winter's stock so far recovered as to be used again the next season.</p>
               <p>And now my story is told. I have led you step by step through the first year of my business life. You have seen my failures and my successes. As I said at the outset, I am sole proprietor of "My Ten-Rod Farm," free from debt, and in receipt of an income of two thousand dollars a year. I did not reach this point the first nor the second year, but my income has gradually increased till it reached that amount.</p>
               <p>The village people speak of me with praise and respect. My brother and sister say but little. They let me alone, and treat me respectfully. To Mr. Felix and Mr. McTernan I owe a debt of gratitude I can never repay. However, you must not imagine I met with equal kindness from all the trade. I suppose I met the same amount of kindness, and the same amount of opposition and hindrance, that I should have met if I had started a cheese factory, or<pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC5737-00000060"/> built a stocking mill. Yet in my profession I am respected and treated with consideration by all. As I said at the outset, I have made a place for myself in the world. I have told you this, my story, with a purpose. Many have called upon me for the facts, that they might aid some deserving person left as I was, just removed from want's door.</p>
               <p>The consumption of flowers is enormous. The number of greenhouses has more than trebled since I built mine; yet to-day the price is higher. I cannot think that this will continue. The price will eventually come down, which will be an advantage, alike to the grower, seller, and consumer. In such a business as this, it is not the high price, but the great quantity demanded, that is advantageous to the producer.</p>
               <p>Flowers are the delight of every one. They are appropriate and acceptable at all times, and in all places. No place is too common or too sacred for them. They peer over the tops of the banking-house desk, and their fragrance adds a new charm to the solemn roll of the church organ.</p>
               <p>Hundreds of women living near our larger cities are eager and willing to do something to add to their slender income. If this account of my experience aids them in any way, my object is accomplished,—I am satisfied. Mrs. Warren's charming "Home Manuals," for house management, "Our Farm of Ten Acres," "The Garden that paid the Rent," "Ten Acres Enough," "How to Farm Profitably," are eagerly sought after. May I not have the same good fortune awarded to <q>
                     <p>MY TEN-ROD FARM;<lb/> OR,<lb/> HOW I BECAME A FLORIST.</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>