<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd" xml:id="VAC5911">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >De histori ov Magnus Maha'rba and de Blak Dragun </title>
            <author >Brown, Nathan, (1807-1886)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC5911</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >[Backwards D]e histori ov Magnus Maha'rba and de Blak Dragun</title>
                  <author >Brown, Nathan, (1807-1886)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >122 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >Printed for de Filolojikal Gemna</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Nu-York </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1866">1866</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-12-17">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5. Inserted OCR text. Linked image files</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>[Backwards D]e histori ov Magnus Maha'rba and de Blak Dragun</head> 
            <p>
               <pb  n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC5911-00000001"/>-  t&#xD;
. s&#xD;
a&#xD;
}&#xD;
F&#xD;
t'&#xD;
6&#xD;
n&#xD;
t =_&#xD;
i&#xD;
r&#xD;
r&#xD;
h&#xD;
t '3&#xD;
t&#xD;
f&#xD;
&#xD;
[E HISTORI&#xD;
ov.&#xD;
MIAGNUS            AHKARBA&#xD;
AND BE&#xD;
BLA.K DRAGITN.&#xD;
D3At&#xD;
KISTOFUR KADMUS.&#xD;
rt Z Vrnx T ~tv 43 ~oo guran t ttbvr~z&#xD;
Soun~dta ijz'i U .06 u  ofir. ---bidMaksim.&#xD;
Nil-YORK:&#xD;
PRINTED FOR GlE FILOLOJIKAI GEMANA.&#xD;
MtDC CCLXVI.t&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="0" xml:id="VAC5911-00000002"/>&#xD;
~,1,- no&#xD;
&#xD;
41A&#xD;
&#xD;
Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1865, by&#xD;
NATHAN BoW N,&#xD;
in the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United States for&#xD;
the District of NewJersey.&#xD;
Copy-right secured for this work in common Englih&#xD;
and rectided Saxon orthography,&#xD;
&#xD;
HE Publishers of this History owe&#xD;
it to themselves, as well as their&#xD;
Readers, to give a Word of Ex-&#xD;
planation regarding the Dress in&#xD;
which it appears. It was their first&#xD;
Impression that the Work would&#xD;
be nearly unintelligible in the Or-&#xD;
thography of the original Manu-&#xD;
scripts, and they had, therefore,&#xD;
considerable Hesitancy in complying with the Wish-&#xD;
es of their respected Townsman, Mr. C. Cadmus,&#xD;
who insisted with some Warmth that, if printed at&#xD;
all, it should be. without Alteration. He informs&#xD;
us that in the Country of which he writes, the&#xD;
Standard of Orthography has been fixed by a cer-&#xD;
tain learned Society, having the Oversight of such&#xD;
Matters, and he scarcely feels at Liberty to deviate&#xD;
from the Mode of Spelling which they have estab-&#xD;
lished. We found after reading a few Pages of&#xD;
the Work, that it was not so difficult as it at first&#xD;
appeared. The chief Peculiarity seems to be the&#xD;
A&#xD;
&#xD;
/&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="iv-5" xml:id="VAC5911-00000003"/>&#xD;
iv&#xD;
&#xD;
accenting of the vowels, a, e, i, o, u, to give them&#xD;
a long Sound, after the Manner of the ancient&#xD;
Saxons, who used the'Accents in such words as&#xD;
wrath,' wste (waste), fri (free), f6r (floor), rdm&#xD;
(room). We perceive, also,, that c stands for ch,&#xD;
as it did among the Saxons, who wrote cild for&#xD;
child, hwilc for which. They likewise employed a&#xD;
single Character, a peculiar Kind of D, to repre-&#xD;
sent the sound of th, and it is a curious Coinci-&#xD;
dence that a similar Letter is here used for the&#xD;
same Purpose. Perhaps we may find in these&#xD;
Circumstances a Clue to the Time and Place in&#xD;
History to which the Events here narrated belong.&#xD;
Mr. Cadmus does not inform us when or where&#xD;
he obtained the Documents used in compiling his&#xD;
Narrative; whether they are of remote Antiquity&#xD;
or recent Date, or what was the Language in&#xD;
which they were originally written. But from his&#xD;
Partiality for the Saxon Orthography, and from&#xD;
Resemblances, here and there, indicating Connec-&#xD;
tion with the Language, Thought and Customs&#xD;
of our early Ancestors, we have a strong Suspi,&#xD;
cion that this singular Record pertains to some&#xD;
Branch of the Saxon Family, and that it is a De-&#xD;
scription of one of those terrific Contests for which&#xD;
that warlike Race has ever been famous. But on&#xD;
this Subject we would not speak positively. We&#xD;
merely throw out the Suggestion for the Consid-&#xD;
eration of the Reader, whom we leave to form&#xD;
his own Conclusions after he has completed the&#xD;
Volume.&#xD;
&#xD;
jatiwflttcahrba.&#xD;
&#xD;
CAPTUR .&#xD;
&#xD;
~~~WUl ov  st'ri  klusterz on ai outr mar-&#xD;
jin ov ae ydnivers woz ae sin ov ae transak-&#xD;
gunz rikorded in ae folomii pejez.   b'okurd&#xD;
about sik aouzand yirz aftur c(at orb bigan tu bi&#xD;
pipkl wia ragunal intelijensez. ULi egzakt piriud,&#xD;
akordin tu aer rekni, hwen ce Blak Dragon koi-&#xD;
enst hiz wor upon ae gud kim Magnus Mahirba,&#xD;
woz A. M. VDCCCLX. Nou A. M. iz aer abrivieun&#xD;
for Anno Manni, or Anno Mundi, signifaiin yir&#xD;
ov ce man-wurld. For ae inhabitants sup6z   er&#xD;
wurld tu hav bin md out ov ae reinz ov sum former&#xD;
wurld, jujin from ae rimdnz ov hidius reptilz, enor-&#xD;
mus frogz, lizardz, dragunz and ucaur monsturz hwic&#xD;
ad hav found imbeded in ce roks, swomps and&#xD;
alvial dipozits. Uer tr at prezent on e planet&#xD;
a klas ov monomdniaks, kbld jiolojists, iu spend&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="6-7" xml:id="VAC5911-00000004"/>&#xD;
6              Ena     STa4trhn.&#xD;
ar laivz in digin up and asortin ad6z disgiabli&#xD;
krieurz, and kalkaldtin ie piriudz ov antikwiti in&#xD;
hwic  e respektivli flurigt. For ai amnzment ov&#xD;
YU  pip , uz emiabl enanziasts public knrius buks&#xD;
d wik outlandi9 pikcurz ov ae verius goblin form&#xD;
Qat kr ld, krept, swam or s6rd, amunst ae konfizd&#xD;
and worin elements, in ae fogi don ov kridgn-&#xD;
Hweaur ae Blak Dragun woz wun or..i original&#xD;
pri'human inhabitants, h  bai a rimirkahl tenasiti&#xD;
ov laif had survaivd ae revolngiunz oat swept bl ai&#xD;
uaur praimival oknpants intu kdos, or hweacr hi&#xD;
woz a mugrum    produkgun ov ltur ddt hwie it&#xD;
wud bi rait tu ekstermindt, woz a point muc dis-&#xD;
pited. Ge m6st lerned men wer divaided; but a&#xD;
majoriti ov ae lbyurz and spiricual dokturz wer ov&#xD;
opinyun aat ae Blak Dragun bilond tu e prim-&#xD;
itiv formegunz; or at hi woz at list k6ival in hiz&#xD;
orijin wia man, and gud bi trited wia dun respekt&#xD;
az a gud krieur ov God, and a joint propraiitur ov&#xD;
ae planetari domen.&#xD;
te gl6b of hwic ai rait, notwiastandin its inffri-.&#xD;
oritiin saiz, woz wun ov ae mdst bItiful in ae hd1&#xD;
surki ovrae hevnz. Its soil woz ric, its fridts dili-&#xD;
gus, its flourz ekskwizitli tdstful, and its erz redo-&#xD;
lent wia purfm. But ae men wer ov a bad rs;&#xD;
selfi, pagunet, kworelsun, and wurgipurz ov a grdt&#xD;
number ov aidul godz. It has bin aserted aat er&#xD;
necur, sun after it kem from (e hand o .e rid&#xD;
tur, risivd a tent from e brea ov a sndki apariun&#xD;
at insinyudted itself intu ai irbur ov ae furst par,&#xD;
and huiz poizn haz kontamindted bl -r ofspri,.&#xD;
&#xD;
ngUs"11u bantha.              7&#xD;
Lerned skolurz and antikwdrianz, hld hav  uroli&#xD;
t'ited ae subjekt, aink aer kan bi n6 dout&#xD;
at ve Blak Dragun iz a direkt disendant ov aat&#xD;
veriO 61d serpent hd injected hiz dedli venum intu aO&#xD;
vnz ov aer projeniturz.&#xD;
Gi orb on hwic man and ae Dragun dwelt had&#xD;
td -lrj ailandz, wun on iur said, hwic wer kbld,&#xD;
in ao langwej ov aat sfir, ae Gret Orient and (e&#xD;
Grstt Oksident.  (er wer ols6 veri waid 69eunz bi-&#xD;
twin aem. And ace Grdt Orient woz ae irjur ov&#xD;
ae td ailandz, for it, ekstended lenawaiz kwalt&#xD;
akros wun said ov ae planet, and its norawesturn&#xD;
and sonawesturn ekstremitiz, kbld Nora and Kuga&#xD;
street fir out intu ae si. Durin ae furst faiv aou-&#xD;
zand yirz ov man, ae Grdt Oksident woz skersli&#xD;
n6n tu ae dwelurz in ai Orient, and ivn ae dim&#xD;
tradigen (Tat sue an ailand -egzisted woz at lena&#xD;
forgotn. But wns upon a taim    an advencurus&#xD;
si-katin  nnd Kristofr, sdlin westward, cast&#xD;
tu diskuvur it. He found it pipld bai strenj resez,&#xD;
hd wer sizd wia terur at hiz apr6c, ainkin ae nu&#xD;
kumrz had disended from ao skaiz.  liwen Kris-&#xD;
tofur riturnd tu hiz 6n kuntri, and diskraibd ae&#xD;
bati ov ae land hi had found, and t6ld ov ae g6ld&#xD;
and silver and daimundz wia hwie it abounded,&#xD;
ae ripr't kwikli spred aril sitiz and provinsez, and&#xD;
b1 o pipl wer fild wici wundur. And ade bigan tu&#xD;
kum out in swormz, laik biz from a hundred haivz,&#xD;
ginkin tu betur aer kondigun bal rinmivix1 tu a kun&#xD;
tri aat woz sd ric. And ae prd vur in gips and&#xD;
galiz, and tuk pozecun ov ae Grdt Oksident, es-&#xD;
&#xD;
L6.&#xD;
&#xD;
l  R&#xD;
lr&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="8-9" xml:id="VAC5911-00000005"/>&#xD;
8&#xD;
&#xD;
tabligin ar koloniz in e soua and&#xD;
in aeesenter.adnin ae nora, and&#xD;
in are sentujr.&#xD;
Minhwail ae Blak Dra      b    m&#xD;
instinkt, pursivd cae grin grdtnes v  edaiabol-&#xD;
onz i ae land ov gdld, and hi sed tu himse lf, §al&#xD;
ae rds ov man enjoi ais na paradise aldn  d&#xD;
hav n6 part cerin? S6 hi formd hiz p, nd&#xD;
on a1 ovnin Ov a stormi dd hi mounted a hnurl-&#xD;
wind, and da9t of upon ce woturz  ufi a  nor-&#xD;
in Jaik a stim-enjin. And hi had sevuraln ipsnoat&#xD;
akumpanid him, tu suplai him wia fud and nesesa-&#xD;
riz dfrin hiz voiej. D6 aftur dd hi swep  non&#xD;
sorin aloft dvur ae mountain wdvz, nouln plin bU&#xD;
niu ae surfes and gutin ard ae bin wottrz laik&#xD;
Norwiian krdken. Mermen and      -d       - a&#xD;
sf-serpents and bl cie .fini traibz nekmdd  hLz&#xD;
aproc, and hid aemselvz in abr dgun kavurnz hwail&#xD;
hi past bai. About a muna had ilat hw       i&#xD;
ce dnbius lait ov a misti morning hiz dir sk&#xD;
form woz diskaid imerjin from e Wdvz and krb-&#xD;
in up on c(e sandi bic ov ai Oksident.  ,er hi&#xD;
langwidli 6ld himself about, suvdin wia bl6ted&#xD;
and fair1 aiz ce riun around, and kwaietli divourin&#xD;
evuri ain oat km in hiz we. It woz afturwnodz&#xD;
d.skuvurd  at on ce botum ov ai 69un, bl alon cec&#xD;
an ov hiz trak, aer woz paild up a grt haiw' o&#xD;
hwaitnd b6nz, ae skeletunz ov hnman viktimz at&#xD;
had bin id and ftn bai him on hiz assj from&#xD;
wun ailand tu ci ipr.&#xD;
N6 sunur woz ae Blak Dragun ferli setid upon&#xD;
i Oksident kdst aan hi bigan Ut gaaur around&#xD;
&#xD;
xwapo aitfuh.               9&#xD;
him gret numburz ov pipl, hum hi alard wia ac&#xD;
piomis ov vast ricez, iz from 14bur, and joint do-&#xD;
minyun ovol aat porgn ov ae grit ailand hwie&#xD;
woz kblad Sunland. ULi'z frendz and alaiz ov hiz&#xD;
wer kbld Drag6nianz, after ae nem ov abr patrun.&#xD;
Bai abr asistans hi fited out swift gips and sent&#xD;
aem akros ai 69un tu ae land ov ae Kuganz, aer tu&#xD;
bai, stil and kapeur strop men and yui wimin,&#xD;
helai boiz and fer damzelz, and bri aem dvur tu&#xD;
bikum minialz and helots, and tu til ae fildz, and&#xD;
tu priper soft and delikat rdment for himself and&#xD;
hiz servants. And aie kuntri bike'm ful ov pipi,&#xD;
and ae n6blz grd welai and proud, laik ae lordz&#xD;
ov ae 61d kindums hwens as kdm.&#xD;
Nou aer wer but fn lbz in Sunland, and nun wer&#xD;
konsidurd absolntli baindin eksept ae lbz for hold-&#xD;
in fast ace Kuganz and kilin of a sufigent numbr&#xD;
ov aem evuri yir tu fid ae Blak Dragun. For ae&#xD;
Dragoun woz a vorscus itur, olbiit hi woz veri ddn-&#xD;
ti, and did not relig ace fle9 ov hiz viktimz unles&#xD;
it had bin wel brdzd and flajelsted tu mek it ten-&#xD;
dur and sdvuri. (le Drag6nianz undurstandi ais,&#xD;
komenst ae manglin ov ae yun Kuganz at a veri&#xD;
erli dj, and bai a s16 proses ov torcur mdd aer fleg&#xD;
eksidili delikat and palatable. It woz a grit art&#xD;
tu faind out hou best tu prolon ae laivz ov aiz&#xD;
unhapi kricurz hwail undurg6in ce nigurus tritment&#xD;
tu hwic ad wer subjekted. (le Dragun had a pro-&#xD;
fegunal klas, kold Ovurlukurz, hi mdd' aat studio&#xD;
aer spegal biznez. Tu gratifai ibr pins ad invent-&#xD;
ed meni karius enjinz for lasurdtin and mangling ae&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="10-11" xml:id="VAC5911-00000006"/>&#xD;
10&#xD;
&#xD;
ieg ov ae helots; and daivurz aimnris&#xD;
o  al'iolsd  stoksfivr.a.n sand feturz&#xD;
gagz ov airn for    s or aer hand and ft, and&#xD;
ing miksourn tu   aer mouaz; and wundurful burn-&#xD;
Imksuzto por upon aer bodiz aftr k&#xD;
teria ae skin wia hw'    a     , anr putand&#xD;
wudn molz.ad purordted&#xD;
is enefoul monster ols6 praktist ae horibi rait ov&#xD;
eni bntiful       h never hi so amun ue Kuganz&#xD;
ore b      7jifdun wimmn, hwearr waivz or midnz hi&#xD;
orurbik  em tu hi brbt bifdr him and ad wer fdrst&#xD;
hiz wigez hiz Waivz, for as na aat if ad gud opdz&#xD;
hie Blak Dwud tr aem      from limn&#xD;
formtz    oz Dragun, lnotwiastandin hiz brdtig di-&#xD;
faon.ii oa grdt fevurit wi   p;pi ov wela and&#xD;
falendi retinkept a magnifisent kdrt, and had a&#xD;
raleid oreat  -iz servants praktist a grdt va -&#xD;
hrjinizo wert  u render hiz apirans kumli.  Hz&#xD;
hizorn  ameondbai ac kroun and jd.elz wia hwi,&#xD;
hip    hwzornaented . lhiz fes woz siminli hnan,&#xD;
grinpt hn i atemted tu small, and aen hiz&#xD;
grinin andtenis  n  -t gs   o a savej ekspregon&#xD;
tud rikounwenis anat hiz fiendz and adnairurz&#xD;
wud fkrkaventi start bak wia terur. Iliz hnj and&#xD;
skli karkas woz envelupt m  rdbz ov velvet and&#xD;
sik; and az hi sat upon- hiz ebn ,rdn, hiz atend-&#xD;
ant, wd azrtuihtienz, wer rdnjd around him in&#xD;
sue a we az toub-haid hiz Ion,             m iona  v  o&#xD;
viziturz. Fer lizd'    zl   " a fo    ev     r&#xD;
and wer loud iniz and gallant naits around hiz pales,&#xD;
pns hr lod in prdz ov ae glori and grdtnes ov abr&#xD;
imajind wud wun de bikum ae r     r&#xD;
ov ae wurid.                        Ule      r&#xD;
&#xD;
ISAIDZ ae Blak Dragun aer wer uaur lon-&#xD;
jivianz hi did not bilon tu ae rds ov men,&#xD;
and huz laivz wer not limited, laik abrz,&#xD;
rVoVI tu a hundred revolngunz ov ae planet, but&#xD;
hd rimund dj aftur dj, and egzerted a pourful&#xD;
infinens on pasin jenrdgnz. In ae kom-&#xD;
un daialekt ov ai inhabitants aiz old rezi-&#xD;
dents wer kbld bai sue ne'mz az sima  mst ekspresiv&#xD;
ov abr rispektiv karaktrz. Wn ov aem, a rinkd&#xD;
and ripulsiv antediluvian, woz kbld Tirani; anuaur,&#xD;
a fimdl, ov sumhwot maildur kountenans and mor&#xD;
polait diminur, woz n6n az Monirkia; and aer woz&#xD;
a waild krszi bakanal, wurs aan Tirani himself, hu&#xD;
went bai ae ndm ov Annrkia.                 .&#xD;
Hwail sum ov aiz lonjivianz wer malevolent biz,&#xD;
ai ofsprin ov ai infernalz, hd dilaited 6nli in mizuri&#xD;
and rdin, uaurz wer ov silescal bura, and b aer in-&#xD;
turk6rs wia mortal woz kaind and hapi; ae apird to&#xD;
hav n6 dizair but tu bring bak mankaind tu aer&#xD;
orijinal trea and vurcu. Cher wer ols6 on ae sdm&#xD;
planet jaiants, or demigodz, hu partuk ov boa ne-&#xD;
curz, ae silescal and ae mortal; kombaini ae pour&#xD;
and infinens ov ae wun wia a infurmitiz and erurz&#xD;
ov ai taur.&#xD;
&#xD;
krnir    Y 4fiuIrn.&#xD;
&#xD;
CAPTURE II.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="12-13" xml:id="VAC5911-00000007"/>&#xD;
It woz several hundred   i&#xD;
Kristofur aat a yun jaiant by re      tm o m&#xD;
biant b       ydms naekai ae nim ov Samunkl&#xD;
He    Lo hv   sincre kuntri ov ci Oksidentalz-&#xD;
Fi    o  o i lecalp  ente,  bii!n  a  disendant  ov&#xD;
Friga, ae godes ov liburt' lH1 eldsdt, ov&#xD;
dima, woz a luvli kriczrh    eldet dbit, Fi-n&#xD;
- . .ur, uz' ekstrordmnari bati 'i&#xD;
in infansi, encanted 61 bih6ldTrz  A  '   u, hun&#xD;
f6m spred rd  i ailand, and ako  z 91  ad up, her&#xD;
mdst distant landz. And cae Blak Dragun fikst hiz&#xD;
aiz upon hur, and hwen hi sb hur bft hg ditid&#xD;
tu mdk hur hiz braid.&#xD;
Samunkl woz ae mdstest&#xD;
Samuni WO  crcm~stekstensjv landholdur on are&#xD;
western ailand, and hi fainaliens bym .andhddr o&#xD;
61 dz ric trakts ndn az ee Yunaited Okents In&#xD;
ordur tu enkurej ldbururz tuuseteon Oid   n&#xD;
aloud ae kutvtrbuo           eo      iz landz hi&#xD;
aodcckultiy~tur z tu ok uipai acem Wic laout rent, su-&#xD;
p6rtin himself on ce   npi  emn wiat hi wo-&#xD;
tu aknmuldt bai trid wia foren u6unz. It woz&#xD;
undurstud, houevur, cat in kdso  worz or   woz&#xD;
erjensi, ai oknpanis ov ae soil ov w r cenrsim-&#xD;
burdnz ovh otr.9                   er ae nesesari&#xD;
budz ov aec kuntri.&#xD;
But are kinz in  uom ovcc Noran kuntriz w,,&#xD;
displizd at ae liburaliti ov Samun  For    ei&#xD;
It iz not gud (at ae pipi   d b' -d     o e  d&#xD;
rents; ais egzanpl wil wurk u  1irfed romsped&#xD;
diskontent amun our subjekts. sAnd     wilkipre&#xD;
Blulia spdk tu Monirkia, cre godes hum hi wnuriptv&#xD;
and gi bed him send vur and kolekt cc rents him.&#xD;
self. For, sed gi, udz pipi went out fe r r 6n&#xD;
kindom, and aerfdr addr   '           omyuon&#xD;
ki~du, an  ccr~r (andryir subjekts stil. S6 hj&#xD;
gent dvur hiz mesenjurz andyr shz taksst  az&#xD;
tsgaaerurz, az9&#xD;
&#xD;
advaizd him. But ae pip1 rifnzd abr dimandz and-&#xD;
diklerd acd wud p6 n6 rent, tribyut or kustum tu&#xD;
ac kil ov ae Buianz. Gen hi sent vur hiz Arniiz&#xD;
tu kontend wia aem in b'atl and tu vankwig and&#xD;
subdn em. But ad met wia dizastur and kud not&#xD;
akompli9 cae kipz dizair.&#xD;
And Samunkl sumund ae cffs and hedz ov ae&#xD;
pip1 tu a grdt kounsil. And ae 6bid ae kbl and&#xD;
hosted and kdm tugeacur in ful numburz, and sat in&#xD;
kounsil meni ddz. And a sed, Wi wil kast of ae&#xD;
kinz y6k, and mdk us kinz ov our dn; and Mon-&#xD;
rkia gal hi dip6zd from hur kwinli dignity aridout&#xD;
ai entair Oksident; and in hur sted wi wil ciz ac&#xD;
jenti Fridima and kroun hur purpecual kwin, and&#xD;
9i aal bi ae godes around huz traikulurd banur Wi&#xD;
wil rali our woryurz.  S6 a komnnd wic hur&#xD;
faur, and apointed a de hlwen hi gud brie hur out&#xD;
tu aen, aat ad mait dd hur homej. And on ae&#xD;
fdra de ov aeinuna ov Julius gi kdm bif6r aem&#xD;
wia blugin kountenans and lining on hur fuaurz irm;&#xD;
and acr kround hur wia a g6ldn kroun, and led hur&#xD;
fdra bifdr l ae pip, and ae pipl routed and klapt&#xD;
acr handz, and kraid, Fridima forever ! And ce&#xD;
kounsil orddnd aat i anivursari ov aat de gud evur&#xD;
after hi keyt az a holide, and i kold korondgun de,;&#xD;
and aat bl carr kinz gud tdk an da tu protekt, defend&#xD;
and prizerv ai onur and snpremnasi ov Fridima, and&#xD;
aat huevur konspaird agenst hur gud sufur dea.&#xD;
But alas ! ai our ov traiunf iz ofn ai our ov&#xD;
peril, and ais ae jent1 Fridima afturwurdz lernd u&#xD;
hur sor. In ae kounsil aat 96d hru aiz onurz er&#xD;
&#xD;
13)&#xD;
&#xD;
ffupvs LlUvarbao&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="14-15" xml:id="VAC5911-00000008"/>&#xD;
14                            -&#xD;
wer mesenjurz from Sunland, m  wr rT     .ai&#xD;
but a    n      o    unn-d       er Drag'nianz,&#xD;
butae'm~dn6  l~i inbihifov aer pains fat hei&#xD;
gud ger in ue government ov aekuntri. On ahi&#xD;
riturn bm ae Dragun cido ae biknt. On bn&#xD;
unmaindful ov hiz interests and hado ie   men&#xD;
g n hzhamd611not 1vn men-&#xD;
kbnd hi knknded t6 wen e nejkst grdt kounsil woz&#xD;
kld hs konkluded t prizent himself, alon wi hi?&#xD;
deleg~it ;s, and kle~m hiz sit az wun ov aeciof pro&#xD;
praiitari lordz and raitful o ants of ac  pro&#xD;
ailand. But ae Normen werlpa to admit him u&#xD;
a kounsil ov htnanz a hoeur, aloud him tu spi&#xD;
and prizent hiz kIdnz.H oford hu join wi  k c&#xD;
in forming a grand h' -and k  ntu ad    wu p   m l&#xD;
hiz fdrsez wia adz o  Samunkl, atne disposal ov oa&#xD;
kinz hDi gud bi cozen tu nl, a e  is oi i  a&#xD;
protekgun and dife.    ut r hl wud konsent tu a&#xD;
ydnyun dnli on sertin kondi unz.wui object ov ae&#xD;
waili d1d dimun woz tu obtn guz  un ove r'ae&#xD;
i propdzd fat if ad wud giv hur tu him  riia.j&#xD;
hi wud divers hiz former   u      nrim tm m&#xD;
hi had bin sd lon yunaitedspouz Monakitum,&#xD;
and Fridima gud bi hiz l'in an onnali kvded,&#xD;
waif, sd lop az rivurz ran or gan rd rAh w  id&#xD;
ad had lon konsulteunz and       i     bfr als&#xD;
kud from ae grdt kuvenant hwic woz t, bi ao pt'-&#xD;
pecual lb ov ae relm.  Ue Dwgianz diar pur-&#xD;
it gud kontdn an akt ov bitro a baindin  istar&#xD;
and Fridima in purpecual bondz. Samunkl and ae&#xD;
Normen wer gokt at ais propdzal; and yet ad wei&#xD;
so dizairus ov ae Dragunz asistans in abr wo-i'.&#xD;
agenst Mondrkia aat ad did not der tu s6 n . CI&#xD;
&#xD;
aerf6r aloud ac kuvenant tu bi ritn obsknrli, s6 az&#xD;
tu i kdpabl ov difurent inturpietdeunz; and tu ais&#xD;
do ae mining ov sum parts iz disputed. It apirz,&#xD;
houevur, tu hay bin jenurali admited aat ai instru-&#xD;
ment gdv ae Blak Dragun a rait tu partisipet in ae&#xD;
guvurnment, and aat ae frdmurz kontemple'ted a&#xD;
ynyun bitwin him and Fridira. QI probably h6pt&#xD;
aat hi wud cnj hiz nicur, or at list hiz habits, az&#xD;
wun ov ai artiklz provided aat hi gud, after a gort&#xD;
p'riud, diskontinyu hiz trafik via ae Kugan-selurz&#xD;
and bring n6 mdr unhapi viktimz akros ae woturz.&#xD;
H-fou it hapnd aat ae 9rdd Samunkl ud hav giva&#xD;
hiz konsent tu ais unacural alaians haz ever bin a&#xD;
misturi. Bai sum it iz sed aat hi did not undur-&#xD;
stand ae necur and import ov ae kuvenant ford;&#xD;
bai uaurz aat hi must hay bin pirgali insdn, or pur-&#xD;
haps stnpifaid wia intoksikstin drugz; vaurz still&#xD;
mente'n aat hi woz braibd bai ae grdt advantejez&#xD;
tu bi diraivd from a lig wia ae Dragun.  lou-&#xD;
ever ais m' bi, it iz p4n hi woz never hirtili in&#xD;
fdvur ov ai alaians ; and az taim r6ld on, ae prospekt&#xD;
ov giving up hiz doter tu a embrds ov a monstur s6&#xD;
pred upon hiz spirits aat hiz brou woz furod wia pr-&#xD;
matnr rinklz. Az for ae caild, 9i wud start wia&#xD;
horur hwenevur ae kontemplsted ycnyun woz aladed&#xD;
tu, and beriin hur fds in hur handz imidietli rug out&#xD;
ov sait.&#xD;
&#xD;
15&#xD;
&#xD;
gRagillys All-ItA ba.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="16-17" xml:id="VAC5911-00000009"/>&#xD;
17&#xD;
&#xD;
CAPTUf RIII.&#xD;
&#xD;
ItJJJIMA, bin ov ae Ionjivian ris, did not&#xD;
gro up tu iwurmanhud rapidli laik mortalz.&#xD;
Hur ydi ekstended ard ae rdnz ov several&#xD;
ov (i erli kinz, wia hdm gi woz a grit fi&#xD;
vurit. (64 wer kerful tu mdk nd alajun tu&#xD;
hur unhapi bitroaal, probabli hdpin aat co&#xD;
Dragun wud dai bifdr ae nupgalz   ud b'&#xD;
konsumdted. Anyuali, on korondgun d, ae damzel&#xD;
whi hur mddnz rest in wait apird bifdr (e pipl and&#xD;
marct tu ae tempi ov liburti, amid i aklamsgnz ov&#xD;
ae multitadz, ha str6d hur paua wia rdzez, and huz&#xD;
admiri9un ov hur luvir ndcur and jenti dispozigun&#xD;
had nboundz&#xD;
But als holidd woz an ofens tu ae Blak Dragun,&#xD;
hu, az oft az it riturnd, sat mudi and unsdgal in hZ&#xD;
pales, meditdtin on (e minz bai hwic hi rmait brinr&#xD;
hiz fcur braid intu proper subjekun, and puni9&#xD;
ae Fridomanz hid wer fosturin hur vanity bai air&#xD;
pl zez, and hli, hi grddli suspekted, wer bent on&#xD;
br6kin up ae mac and snaci from  hiz pozegun&#xD;
i object o hiz dizair.&#xD;
Ge Dragn woz akustumd tu noc vvuri korons-&#xD;
eun dO upon hiz spir-handl. Aftur hi had mdd haf&#xD;
a hundred nocez hi bigan tu urj upon (Xe rdnin&#xD;
biganto n J upn ae ''ni&#xD;
&#xD;
kin biz klsm for Fridima, dimandig aat. gi gud at&#xD;
list i pldst undur ristrent, and insted ov wond-&#xD;
urin about at her plejur, bi komited tu ae gardian-&#xD;
ip ov tuturz hd wud trin hur tu dosiliti and sub-&#xD;
inign, and wud tic hur, abuv bl ainz els, gat ae&#xD;
Blak Dragun woz tu bi hur mAstur.    Ge kin hu&#xD;
guvurnd at aat taim wud not lisn tu ae prop6zal; but&#xD;
hiz rdn woz port, and ae kinz hd fol6 him wer m6r&#xD;
fsvurabl tu ce IDragun, and promist him gat hi gud&#xD;
hay b1 hi askt.  Gen ae skdli 61d monstr, faind-&#xD;
i gat hi had ae kinz upon hiz said, bigan tugo&#xD;
out m6r and mn6r ov hiz ditestabi ndcur. Hi kom-&#xD;
enst mdkin oksjunal vizits tu ae hous ov Samunkl,&#xD;
fraitnin pdr Fridima olm6st tu distrakgun, augi&#xD;
hur wia a maligus lir and 96in hur hiz horid tia.&#xD;
On wun or td okdjunz hi sizd hur bai ae her ov&#xD;
hur hed,.and wud hav dragd hur of tu biz 6n h6m&#xD;
wikout mersi, but for i outkrai rdzd bai ae neburz&#xD;
and tounzf6k, hd luvd Fridima az ae luvd aer on&#xD;
laivz.&#xD;
And non ae Dragun turned hiz venjens upon aiz&#xD;
kaind-hdrted pipi; for hwen eni o aem venourd&#xD;
wiain hiz boundariz hi wud koz gem to bi apri-&#xD;
hended and plist upon ae rak, in order tu asurten&#xD;
hiweaur is had eni akwi'ntans wix Fridima; and if'&#xD;
aCd bitrid ae list simpaai wia hur or hur frendz, ae&#xD;
torcur woz kontinyud until as6 daid. Sumtaimz (Xe&#xD;
wer plunjd undur wotur and held abr until h if&#xD;
sufoksted, aen rszd and plunjd agen, and ais ripit-&#xD;
ed s6 az tu msk Xaem sufcr ae panz ov a duzn&#xD;
deas; sumtaimz as wer konfaind in 16Dsum dun-&#xD;
13&#xD;
&#xD;
AT1t nts mub rbnc.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="18-19" xml:id="VAC5911-00000010"/>&#xD;
18&#xD;
junz til as wasted aw'i -&#xD;
ae fdvaitmddofd sa          ungur and diziz; but&#xD;
cr fvuri t mod of Cistrojin "acm w oz baij Ibm&#xD;
Qem Up kwaietli on (re nirest tr   s ha  i o&#xD;
ee Friddnianz went on unti ot S      1sland  of&#xD;
wiecr e horibi and   pno                 oz dfildl&#xD;
korpsez.. Travelurz, hien  al steno o  dikdin&#xD;
ded upon triz alo   er"  o s ae bodiz suspen-&#xD;
rizol1n tnevrz tu ae r'said, wud ofh turn bak,&#xD;
rizlvn leur to ateint a jumrni to  rtknr  gn&#xD;
But e Dragun woz wel pi       tuaat k ntri agcen.&#xD;
Fridsniansand hi snuft up afitid r az if it wor&#xD;
rc swvit smelin dr o fiv a burnt sazkh ifi wer&#xD;
s6 tdld hiz ministurz praivetli rat hfwen hi ha&#xD;
brbt h6m Liz norcrurn braid hi watOh e  hr oad&#xD;
deli in hiz karij tu v      '1wdtkhrout&#xD;
d~  inLizkarJ tu vu~ hur jibeted fr'endadh&#xD;
wud let hur n6 cat if -f   bd frendz, and hi&#xD;
cud cer ae sem fit.    9monstrns gi&#xD;
Rip6rts o   criz horurz riot  . irz&#xD;
and med hur kin   e kldsur t hurz norurid ma,&#xD;
Several K~ugan wimin hn had eskr nrctrn      r.&#xD;
ov ae  lak Dragun found        s wpt ae forecurz&#xD;
house . briin aer infants Wiae we Fm        faurz&#xD;
lent  e hd1 stdri oy  c Blakaguzrom naemi&#xD;
Hur tender htirt woz redi tu buraunz   keltiz.&#xD;
ae litl Kugan babz tu hur bzm, a        n giklaspt&#xD;
aem tirz and kisez.     -pdz t      gourin upon&#xD;
hi gud start on a krus;d fPpod  tu r  daura&#xD;
storm hiz kas], and klhaesta         lkDragun,&#xD;
k1tr o  ae kaptivz  n  im if nesesari for ae res-&#xD;
ofrd to akampan'i i and deliket az gi woz, 9&#xD;
ofurdto aumpai him  on a is des put ekp"l&#xD;
Cun. But hur fdaur aided     s fresurt fekspedi-&#xD;
nes, and tdId hur cat  ' wd norl bri howrd-&#xD;
91  ud not dali brim horef&#xD;
&#xD;
I I&#xD;
&#xD;
F_&#xD;
x&#xD;
$&#xD;
4 ,&#xD;
n4.&#xD;
..'$&#xD;
f&#xD;
&#xD;
19&#xD;
&#xD;
intu trubi but him als6; aat ae Blak Dragun woz&#xD;
ae mdst pourful prins in ae land, and nekst tu&#xD;
ae kin himself. Hi tdld hur ols6 aat hi woz ol-&#xD;
redi in fir ov hiz laif, bikbz hi had not givn hur&#xD;
in marij hwen dimanded. (en Fridima trembld&#xD;
from hed tu fut, and hur ciks and lips gr wait&#xD;
wica suprest im69un; for 9i so at hur fdaur, wia ol&#xD;
hiz pour and grdtnes, had nd strena or kurej tu re-&#xD;
zist eni demand hwic ae Blak Dragun mait mdk,&#xD;
and at hi wud probabli, if drivn tu ekstremiti,&#xD;
sakrifaiz ivn a doter tu sdv hiz n laif. S6 gi sist&#xD;
tu urj him, but mentali rizolvd aat hwotevur mait&#xD;
hapn gi wud kast hur lot wia ae pdr Kuans, and&#xD;
aat adc ud hensf 6ra bi her pipl.&#xD;
Ce friends and ndburz nou 96d abr strou sim-&#xD;
paui for Fridima, and som ov aem     b6dli "pro-&#xD;
nounst it a 94m uat ae gmdt Samunkl gud akt s6&#xD;
kouardli a part. But ae g6ld-wurgipurz, and crc&#xD;
waiz men ov ae 1b, and ae s61-dokturz on hiz juj-&#xD;
ment hi rilaid, advaizd. him tu bi kb9Us, and en-&#xD;
devur tu ristrdn hiz impecuus caild, and on n6&#xD;
akount alou eni m6r Kuganz tu entur hiz hous.&#xD;
Faindin hiz dbtur fikst in hur purpus, hi bigan tu&#xD;
gr6 m6r and m6r unizi, for hi woz rizolvd not tu&#xD;
giv hur up agenst hur vil. Hi aerf6r divaizd vd-&#xD;
rius ekspidients tu sikrit and protekt hur ; but&#xD;
ae kin ov ai Oksident and ae grit jujez ov. ea&#xD;
kindum, hd wer in akord wia ae Dragun, disaided&#xD;
aat ce prinses must bi givn up, akordiu tu ac&#xD;
bond ov bitroaal hwich htir f iaur had konfest aat&#xD;
hi saind. It woz not 1o bif6r nnz kdm aat mies-&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="20-21" xml:id="VAC5911-00000011"/>&#xD;
20&#xD;
enjurz from  e Blak Draginwer oeo.&#xD;
tu sikur Fridima and konve hur tore     ard&#xD;
hur aknolejd rmistur- Hur far hae abOd ov&#xD;
sors left but tu send hur    -       nou nr&#xD;
hevi. hart hi kbld hiz family tsuir for    a&#xD;
ferwel, and t6ld hiz Wipin dt ugeatU for a hosti&#xD;
tekt hur nd longmsr; tat      t no fiai for hur&#xD;
a; aip hvrsel on      e   rvdens ov God and&#xD;
a ins  az  ae  kaind h r ed  '  m&#xD;
hur bai re w.  S6 hwen p hadi1 mbrt endur&#xD;
kist hur, and. had put intu hr hdl embrdst and&#xD;
iz for hur. jurni, gi stred f6-an uz a fu nesesa-&#xD;
grimej, trustin in a 'woeful aronide penlu  pil&#xD;
wd, but wie hart alittin poien       ugaid her&#xD;
wS  it w i h itpalpipti  at  evuri  steiai  v a  1aintep,  for  fir&#xD;
1 emisariz o r e Dragun malt bi upon hur trk&#xD;
le mesenjurz, fdlin tu diskjvpo hur trak.&#xD;
turned h6m and rildtd tu iev hDr     ntrt, nou&#xD;
vencurz, and ae manur in hwic Fridnia hades-&#xD;
kdpt. Ii woz faris in hiz reFj at rde madn f  hs&#xD;
obstinasi; and are informdun (tat 9a   in for hr &#xD;
dund bai hur nacural protect a  ndg had bin6 ban-&#xD;
but ue kivz and de forests, simd a   nid   hdm a&#xD;
stimulus ov a nn aktiviti for  t aprm    him ae&#xD;
hiz victim. Hi forawia diturrnind trseren eoy&#xD;
nuk and kornur hwer ae panting 1Vitu meretev r&#xD;
found geltur- So koiq            .j i   athar&#xD;
found ezkr. S'   - -i'-tugea(ur (ae lordz and lddiz&#xD;
, hiz fain aibblz 51      -&#xD;
eksaitment l,   ,ae hwall gedin wiQ&#xD;
Shi swor a damnab         a&#xD;
mna had dilbure1.oa aat sins Frid.&#xD;
mahad disbrdedti and skornfuli rijekted him, hi&#xD;
wil upon hur, and ewdputhturtuw        h   hiz&#xD;
puthrto   ee hairdest&#xD;
&#xD;
minial lebur, until hur plump and rdzi form gud&#xD;
bi wsted tu ae veri b6nz; and aen for a worm ir&#xD;
hi wud ard cut hur skeleton tu hwaitn in ae opn&#xD;
fild, alone wia ae kairkasez ov ae Kuanz and Fri-&#xD;
ddnianz aat wer rotii in ac sun and blicin in (e&#xD;
dfz and rdn. A klangur ov apinz, laik ae cirz ov&#xD;
pandim6nium, ra  ard  (e pales  hl az hi ut rd  als-&#xD;
horid oa.&#xD;
And nou komenst ae grand hunt for ai inosent&#xD;
and haples Fridima. A aouzand horsmen mount-&#xD;
ed upon flit stidz, wia bludhoundz in aer tren,&#xD;
wen started of tu skour ae mountinz and velz ov&#xD;
Norland.  gryi. sulur and winter, in sprintaimi&#xD;
and harvest, ae tramp ov abr stidz , and ae houlin&#xD;
ov ae dogz sent terur tu ae harts ov ae pisful in-&#xD;
habitants. Fridima woz nevur sdf, 6 Cae kaind&#xD;
pezants did bl ac kud tu protekt hur. But 91 aot&#xD;
not ov hrself aldn. Dsli and naitli gi sot out ae&#xD;
pdr   Kaganz  hd  wer  flti i  from  (r  tormenturz, di-&#xD;
rektin o(em tu Cae houzez and vilejez hwer .9i had&#xD;
bin bifrended, and kerfuli pointin out tu aem ae&#xD;
p61an stir, bai fol6in hwic as wud ric Sn6land,&#xD;
a biturli k6ld kuntri, inaksesibl tu aIe Ku9an-&#xD;
hunturz.&#xD;
&#xD;
21'&#xD;
&#xD;
1u9nlys Valporba.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="22-23" xml:id="VAC5911-00000012"/>&#xD;
23&#xD;
&#xD;
CAPTUI IV.&#xD;
&#xD;
RAVELIN     aru ae waildz ov    Norland,&#xD;
hur tender limz eksp6zd tu ae sndz ov&#xD;
winter and ae rdnz ov sumnur, ofn wiaout&#xD;
a geltur in ce sivirest stormz, it woz eks-&#xD;
pekted aat ae fril Fridima, if not kapcurd&#xD;
bai hur enemiz, wud at Lena sink undur ac&#xD;
haddips 9i had tu endar. But tu cai amndz-&#xD;
ment ov bl, ae mdr sivir hur ekspdjur and sufur-&#xD;
inz, ae stronger and helhiur 9i gru, and s6 luvli&#xD;
in form and ficur aat ae pip1 bl bilivd hur a godes&#xD;
endoud witi imortaliti. Meni ols6, hirin hur ndbl&#xD;
wurdz in bihaf ov ae dispaizd Kuganz, diklerd&#xD;
aemselvz redi tu fol6 hur, ivn tu ae Dragunz kasi,&#xD;
for cre purpus ov resknin hiz mizurabl kaptivz.&#xD;
(e Dragonianz, siin hou ae prinses had gend&#xD;
ai afekunz ov cie multitadz, aplaid tu ae kin for&#xD;
a lb tu punig wia dea 1 ha gud hsrbur or konsil&#xD;
hur.   Gen ae kin brot ae matur bifdr ae grdt&#xD;
kounsil, and it woz agrd cat ae hdl kuntri gud&#xD;
join in ce sere aftur Fridima, and hdevur rifnzd&#xD;
tu point out hr haidin plisez, or tu asist in apri-&#xD;
hendin hur, gud bi sivirli punigt.&#xD;
&#xD;
woz non ridnist tarue grdtest struts; bl hfrd&#xD;
ta giv hur a naits lojin or a krm ov bred. In&#xD;
hur ekstremiti 9i wondurd fair out intu ae grit&#xD;
wildurnes ov ae west, and faindin a log kabin sat&#xD;
doun bif6r it in a stdt ov komplit egzhbscun. It&#xD;
woz okfipaid bai an 61d man huz nim woz Osa-&#xD;
mi, ae faur ov siks sunz.   HiI woz ov a stern&#xD;
kountenans and had a ruf grizli bird, and hwen&#xD;
hi kem out tu ask Fridima hur biznes, gi s6 trem-&#xD;
bid wia fir cat gi°kud not utur a wurd. Glen ai&#xD;
61d man, hf i1ad a kaindli hart, sp6k tu hur ten-&#xD;
d'urli, and invaited 'hur intu hiz kabin, hwer hi&#xD;
t6ld hur .,gi mait hay a h6m az lon az 9 c6z tu&#xD;
std, for hi so 'iat gi woz in distres. Aftur 91 had&#xD;
wormd herself bai ic fair, hi priperd a frugal mil,&#xD;
are best hiz hous afdrded. I-Iavin nou gsnd kon-&#xD;
fidens, Fridima tdld him hd 9 woz, and hwai gi&#xD;
had kum, and ov bi hur wondurinz in, ae waild&#xD;
and dizmal forests wia ae fnjitiv Kuganz. Hwail&#xD;
ac wer tbkin ai 61d manz f6r sunz, hd livd wia&#xD;
him, kdm in from ar wurk, and lisnd tu hur std-&#xD;
ri. 016 wer encanted wia ae fain silver tdnz ov&#xD;
hur vois, and ae wd in hwic gi pled ae koz ov ae&#xD;
pur dispaizd Kuganz drd f6ra bl abr simpaaiz. 016&#xD;
admaird ae piriti and upraitnes ov hur sentiments,&#xD;
and hur lofti and self-sakrifaizin benevolens.  Old&#xD;
Osami pursivd aat aC wer dipli drinking in hur&#xD;
spirit, but hi sat kwaietli and sed not a wurd. Az&#xD;
ai ivnin wdr aws hi rdz from   hiz cr and tuk&#xD;
doun a nnl hunting raifi aat hul in (le rum. Fridi-&#xD;
ma n6tist a strdnj fair in hiz ai, and hiz ditermind&#xD;
&#xD;
'R " OUT a g&#xD;
C:P-l             , ab&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="24-25" xml:id="VAC5911-00000013"/>&#xD;
24             Wapms         b&#xD;
luk olmdst fraitnd hur, ad gi n n from hiz aptrans&#xD;
aat hi' woz medittin no hirm tu hur. Aftur bur-&#xD;
niim hiz raifl and putim hiz kirtrijez in ordur, hi&#xD;
tdld Fridima aat sins hur faaur had fold tu akt&#xD;
ae part ov a protektur, az hi woz bound tu dii&#xD;
and had sent hur out intu ae k6ld wurld, hi wud&#xD;
himself adopt hur az hiz on caild, and wud asnlm&#xD;
ae rait and ae risponsibiliti ov a rent tu difend&#xD;
hur agenst bl aat wud dd hur hirm. (le brua-&#xD;
urz wormli risponded, and aedrd hur aat '  cud&#xD;
evur bi trited bai aem az a dir sistur.&#xD;
And nou, mal sunz, sed ai 61d man, yd had&#xD;
betur get yur wepnz in redines for faitin. Gis&#xD;
wurld iz ful ov tok and sinpaai, but tok and&#xD;
simpaai nevur yet protekted ae helples. If yd in-&#xD;
tend tu dilivur ais hunted lam from  hur persiku-&#xD;
turz, yu must bi priperd tu di it at ace risk ov&#xD;
yur laivz. Blud iz ae pfuaihiur ordsnd tu klenz&#xD;
ae stdnz ov ais bad wurld. Si yd not oat ae land&#xD;
iz ful oF leprusi?  It wil rikwair sumain m6r aan&#xD;
wotur tu wog it out. Ai am an d1d man, and mai&#xD;
laif iz not wura muc. Yu, mai sunz, ar yun ; ddu&#xD;
az yd laik ; but az for mi, ai gal set maiself agenst&#xD;
ae foul monster cuat iz wurkin b1 ais miscif. Ai&#xD;
wil mek mai ws intu hiz fortres; ai wil enter hiz&#xD;
pales; ai wil stand at hiz bedsaid; God helping -?,&#xD;
ai wil send a gaft oat gal win its wd tu hiz hirt;&#xD;
ai wil opn ae d6rz ov hiz dunjunz, and nok of ac&#xD;
feturz ov hiz priznurz. And ae boiz sed ad wud&#xD;
go wia him.   Gen Osami rict up hiz hand and&#xD;
tuk doun from   ae 9elf a Buk, hwic t6ld ov ae&#xD;
&#xD;
gage  Wahrha.25&#xD;
Blak Dragun, and ov ae Red Dragun hiz fdaur,&#xD;
and hou ae word agenst ac Lord, and hou ae juj-.&#xD;
ments ov hevn gud kum doun upon aem in fficur&#xD;
taimz. Aftur ridim a hwail hi fel upon hiz niz, az&#xD;
hiz kustum woz, and prd ae grit Olff.aur aat hi&#xD;
wud protekt Fridima, and dilivur ae Kuganz for&#xD;
hur sek, and aat hi wud bre'k ae pour ov ae Blak&#xD;
Dragun, and bani him from Norland and Sunland,&#xD;
and from 01 ae grin spots ov kriegun, and sil Lim&#xD;
up in t6fet fast and forever.&#xD;
Hwen Fridima so intu huz handz 9i had fbln,&#xD;
and hwot a hai and n6bl neur ae stern dld man&#xD;
pozest, and felt hur h6ps ov hapines and sikciriti&#xD;
wuns m6r rivaiv, hur hirt arobd waildli, for ae&#xD;
joi woz tu grit fo hur, and 91 burst intu a flud&#xD;
ov tirz. Di not bi eksaited, sed Osami; kompdz&#xD;
ydrself, trust in God, and al vil bi wel. S6 gi&#xD;
draid up hur tirz, and hwen ae had 61 bidn hur&#xD;
a kaind gud-nait gi ritaird tu rest. Qi sun fel in-&#xD;
tu a swit slumber, and drimd ov hapi sinz in a&#xD;
wurid hwer 61 ai inhabitants luvd Ic uaur az brua-&#xD;
urz.&#xD;
Osami imidietli bigan tu mek prepareunz for&#xD;
invedin ae dominyunz ov ae Blak Dragun. In-&#xD;
spaird wia hiz nn aidia, hi vizited 61 hiz 61d frendz&#xD;
and endevurd tu rouz aem tu a komun efurt for&#xD;
ae distrukgun ov ae monsterr. Meni ov acm abt&#xD;
hiz sm woz a gud wun, but disapriivd ov ae minz.&#xD;
In ae furst pl6s ae abt it prizumcuus for a fu in-&#xD;
divijualz tu get up a krussd agenst sue a venur-&#xD;
abl antediluvian, hd woz ikwal and perhaps mdr&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="26-27" xml:id="VAC5911-00000014"/>&#xD;
aan ikwal in pour and prestij tu ae suvurin him-&#xD;
self. Sekundli, if eni ain woz tu bi dun, it gud&#xD;
bi dun bai ae kin ov ace kuntri; and az hi woz at&#xD;
pis and amiti wiaae Dragun, it wud bi triznus&#xD;
for eni ov ae komun pip1 tu run kountur tu hiz&#xD;
egzampl, or atemt tu eksiknt justis wiaout hiz or-&#xD;
dur.  It woz jenurali admited aat abstraktli ae&#xD;
Dragun had n6 rait tu opres and maltrit Ge Ku-&#xD;
ganz; but az ion az hi did not medl wia ae Nor-&#xD;
men and Norwimin, it woz dimd haili impolitik tu&#xD;
stur up hiz r ia bai inturfirin in bihaf ov ae reced&#xD;
and helples krfcurz he had ae misforcun tu fbli&#xD;
under hiz pour. S6 e t6ld Osami pldnli aat ae&#xD;
wud hav nuain tu did wiau hiz skimz; m6st ov aem,&#xD;
indid, abt aat hi woz krezi, or wud sun bikum&#xD;
s6. A fa pipl, hi sb hwot a worm   and jenurus&#xD;
hirt hi had, and hon wilin hi woz tu sakrifaiz&#xD;
himself tu help aem aat had n6 helpur, enkurejd&#xD;
him in hiz undurtikin, and gdv him muni tu bai&#xD;
wepnz, longuturz and gortguturz, and 9irp lansez&#xD;
wia hwic ae Kuganz mait difend aemselvz agenst&#xD;
aer opresurz.&#xD;
Mintaim ae gret prinsez and lordz ov ae IDrag6.-&#xD;
nianz, hiring Gat Fridima had tdkn refdij wiQ a wudz.&#xD;
man ov ae west, sent f6ra aer emisariz in gret nuh-&#xD;
burz tu sere hur out and brie hur tu Ge pales in&#xD;
cenz, for ae Dragun had nou givn up ai aidia ov&#xD;
mdkin hur hiz waif, and woz 6nli bent upon distroiin&#xD;
(p&#xD;
hur and hur frendz. Hiz bandits wer ordurd tu&#xD;
plunder and 1' west ae nu kuntri, and kil of ae&#xD;
Friddnianz az fast az a kud. Gret numburz wer&#xD;
&#xD;
got and j'beted, stdr-houzez emtid, and vilejez&#xD;
burnt, ardin ae hdl kuntri intu konsturneun. (Ie&#xD;
sunz ov Osami wer tekn priznurz, aer Armz pin-&#xD;
yund bihaind aem  wia aoniz aat kut tu ae b6n,&#xD;
and in ais kondigun ae wer fasnd tu ae Drag6ni-&#xD;
anz' horse, and med tu run Wia aem  az ae gal-&#xD;
upt awe in ae burning hit tdrdz Sunland.   Wun&#xD;
ov Gemf bikem  a meniak from   ae hitin ov hiz&#xD;
bren; anuaur woz kild bai a wait devl-pricur, hd&#xD;
abt it gret merit tu ofur him az a sakrifaiz tu hiz&#xD;
god.&#xD;
At lena Osami, having komplited     hiz  arenj-&#xD;
ments, and faird ann bai ae birbdrian krdeltiz in-&#xD;
flikted on hiz sunz and neburz, ardz sudenli and&#xD;
tuk hiz dipircur for Sunland, akumpanid bai anri&#xD;
ov hiz sunz and hiz suninlb, and a duzn trusti&#xD;
woryurz.  dIe kem   upon ae Dragunz stronh6ld&#xD;
bai nait, genin admigun wiaout difikulti. Kerfuli&#xD;
filin aer we, ae enturd ar apartment nir ae pales,&#xD;
hwic woz ful ov fairdrmz and grit gunz. and&#xD;
poudur, furst mekin priznurz ov ae women hd&#xD;
stud gird at ae d6r. From    ls rum ae h6pt tu&#xD;
faind a pasej intu ae Dragunz bedcedmbur, in&#xD;
hwic kes de' wud sun bi ebl tu fini9 him. But in&#xD;
ais ekspekteun ae wer disapointed, and hwen ae&#xD;
morning bigan tu dbn ae found aer entrans had bin&#xD;
diskuvurd. Ule niz fi- laik laitnin ard ae pales&#xD;
and ardout bl Sunland, and raidurz wer huriin&#xD;
tu and fr6, bi waild az wia ai eksaitment ov batl.&#xD;
Hwen ae Blak Dragun herd ae tumult and woz t6ld&#xD;
ae koz, hi r6rd wia fari and. lagt hiz tel agenst&#xD;
&#xD;
26                  kilapps LR" 4thx.&#xD;
&#xD;
27&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="28-29" xml:id="VAC5911-00000015"/>&#xD;
28               na&#xD;
ae pales wblz til as guk az if rer bad bin an era-&#xD;
kwek. Oe aundur ov hiz rdrin ek6d ivn tu ie&#xD;
distant hilz ov Noriand, .kozin ai inhabitants tu&#xD;
kwdk wia terur and    haid (emselvz wiin  abr&#xD;
houzez. le Dragun olso kdm fdra ov hiz pales&#xD;
and 96d himself in bl hiz jaigantik propdrgunz,&#xD;
hiz form touring aloft tu ae rijun ov e stirz, dsrk&#xD;
nin ae sun az a kloud, and ardin a glmi 9ad6&#xD;
dvur ae h61 land. Pir Fridima sat krouci, solitary&#xD;
and  trembling, in a mountin kiv; nun derin tu&#xD;
minister tu hur wonts, or inkwair after hur wel-&#xD;
fer, or ivn pronouns hur ndm.&#xD;
And nou ae guvurnurz and re jenuralz and kap&#xD;
tinz ov Suialand, wik an drmi ov horsmen aid&#xD;
futmen, bigan tu gaaur from   bl kworturz -and&#xD;
ad envairund Osami and hiz kumpanyunz, lidt ft&#xD;
brdvli for Qer laivz, but wer at last dvurpourd. e&#xD;
sunz ov aii d1d hired wer sldn, and hi himself woz&#xD;
kapcurd, wended    and blidin, and dragd tu  e&#xD;
kounsil-hous for egzamind un. And   e guvurnur&#xD;
sed tu him, Ai no bl about ydr vilani; ai wont&#xD;
n6 informdgun on aat point; but tel me, ndv, hai&#xD;
sent yua hiaur?  Yu hay kum at ai instigdgun ov&#xD;
Samunkl; t iz ov nd yds tu dinai it. Konfes,&#xD;
and ai wil giv yd a for traial. len Osami, grdnir'&#xD;
wia pdn, turnd Liz gdri hed and mikli riplaid,&#xD;
Mai dfd iz mai dn; ai hay had nd kounsel or ad'&#xD;
vais from SamunkI. Unless yi wil juj mi akordin&#xD;
tu justis, ai wig nd traial; if y  dr ditermind tu&#xD;
hay mai ubld, kil mi at wuns, for ai am  redi tu&#xD;
dai. de gud .Buk telz mi ai gud ddi tu  aurrz az&#xD;
&#xD;
29&#xD;
&#xD;
ai wud hav% uaurz dd tu mi; and in siin tu pluk&#xD;
ae kaptivz  from  ae tiau o  ae Dragun, ai hav&#xD;
dun n6 m6r aan ai gud wig sum kind dilivurur&#xD;
tu du for mi in similar surkumstansez.&#xD;
Gen ae guvurnur, hii woz a Waizman, sed&#xD;
wiain himself, Ai must not sitm tu kondem   ais&#xD;
man for hdtin ae Dragun and bifrendin ae Kug-&#xD;
anz, lest it gud knrit for him simpauaizurz ivn&#xD;
amun ourselvz; but ai wil trai him for kiin and&#xD;
murdurin ae s6ljurz aat wer sent agenst him.&#xD;
S6 ae held a kdrt, and brat 6yurz and witnesez,&#xD;
and mdd a grdt pardd ov justis and ligaliti, and&#xD;
fainali ajujd him tu dea.   Glen ad t6ld him hi&#xD;
must hav ae s61-dokturz tu konvert and klenz&#xD;
him, s6 aat hwen hi daid hi mait not fol intu ai&#xD;
evurlastin flsmz. But Osami wud nqt hirken tu&#xD;
aer advais, and hi riturnd for ansur (at hi wud&#xD;
giv- m6r for oe prer ov a pur Kugan muaur aan&#xD;
for bl ae prarz and katekizmz ov ol ae s61-dokturz&#xD;
ae Blak Dragun had in hiz emploi.&#xD;
At lena ae irtur woz led fdra tu dai lhwail&#xD;
a grdt irmi ov s6ljurz and horsmen wer paredod&#xD;
around him  tu witnes ae spektakl and   traiumf&#xD;
dvur Liz fdt.  And as hull him    up bitwin ae&#xD;
hevnz and ai era, and woct him until hi Woz ded.&#xD;
But n6 sunur had ae spirit eskdpt from  ae bodi&#xD;
can it spred abrod in ai atmosfir, fil ne windz&#xD;
wik strinj hwispurz, and flitin hir and aer, laik&#xD;
a g6st, ard bl 0ae land. It disturbd ae lordz and&#xD;
prinsez ov ae Dragunz k6rt in abr midnait drimz;&#xD;
and ae yun men and wimin ov Korland bigan tu&#xD;
&#xD;
95 A&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="30-31" xml:id="VAC5911-00000016"/>&#xD;
30&#xD;
&#xD;
bria a fregor and pfirur er, and tu fil nu inpulsez,&#xD;
and tu yern aftur ae 1o g-luvd and banigt Fridi-&#xD;
ma. Wiain ti yfrz from Osamiz dea, ae pipi had&#xD;
jenurali kum  tu ae konvikgun 'at hi woz yet&#xD;
huvurin .dvur ae: kuntri, in ac 94p ov a girdian&#xD;
dnjel; xaat insted ov ritairin difited from  ae kon-&#xD;
teAt wia ae Blak Dragun, hi had joind ai irmi&#xD;
ov ae Lord; aat hiz napsak woz stil strapt upon&#xD;
hiz bak, and hiz s61 mlrciji on.&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
CAPTUf RV.&#xD;
&#xD;
URSfVIN aat ae afekgunz ov ae Normen&#xD;
wer inseparabli twaind around ae jenti&#xD;
Fridima, ae Drag6nianz bigan tu koisult&#xD;
hou dd mait brik up ae kindum, and form&#xD;
a nn guvurnment ov hwie ae lBlak Drag-&#xD;
un gud hay ae s61 pozegun. Old Publik&#xD;
Funlk9unari, hd had lon - bin kin ov ae&#xD;
Yunaited Oksident, and hd had ofurd td hundred&#xD;
and fifti silvurlinz for ae kap9ur ov Osami, woz&#xD;
about tu end hiz ren, and aer wer glimi apri-&#xD;
hengunz aat hiz suksesur wud not bi s6 frendli tu&#xD;
ae Blak Dragon az hi had bin. iwen ae taim&#xD;
kim for apointin a nn rdlur, aer woz grdt eksait-&#xD;
ment ard ae land. And on a set de ae virius&#xD;
traibz asembld, ae Drag6nianz, and ae Dem6kri-&#xD;
anz, and ae Frid6nianz, and ae Publikanz, and&#xD;
ai Iradikdturz, and ae Konservaturz, and ae&#xD;
multitndz ov ae pipl bda in Norland and Sun-&#xD;
land, t witnes ae kastin ov ae lots. And meni&#xD;
ov aem  sat up wocin bi nait, hwail ae siurz and&#xD;
Zgurz konsulted ai 6menz. And hwen ae nornin&#xD;
woz kum, bih6ld ai er woz ful ov fblin livz, hwic&#xD;
ae wind had bldn fair and waid dvvr ae kuntri.&#xD;
And hwen ae pipi had pikt acm up, and eg-&#xD;
&#xD;
Txiut  Thibx.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="32-33" xml:id="VAC5911-00000017"/>&#xD;
32&#xD;
&#xD;
,mM  nv s11 aI r bm~&#xD;
&#xD;
zanaind aem kerfuli, as found ritn upon aem  ae&#xD;
nom  ov MAGNUS MAHARBA. S6 ad nu Gat&#xD;
ais woz ae ndm ov Ger nekst kin.&#xD;
Glen woz aer grdt kom69un in Ge pales ov ae&#xD;
Dragun, and ae lordz and prinsez and lddiz ov&#xD;
hiz houshold wer field wia indignsgun, for ae had&#xD;
herd ov Magnus Mahdrba, aat hi woz an onest&#xD;
man, and wun Gat luvd justis and ekwiti, and&#xD;
hens ad inferd aat hi must bi an enemi ov aer&#xD;
mistur.  ed had olsd' herd it rip6rted Gat Fridi..&#xD;
ma, dlrin hur travel, had spent a nait at hiz&#xD;
hous, and instild intu hiz maind hur fanatikal&#xD;
planz for letin his ae Kuganz, and living ae Drag-&#xD;
un tu dai ov stdrvdgun. S6 ae effs and n6blz as-&#xD;
embld and drd p ae cdrtur ov a nn kindum for&#xD;
ae suport and difens ov abr bgust patron and biz&#xD;
projeni, and for ai ekstengun ov hiz and abr gldri,&#xD;
influens and pour dvur l Oae landz and siz, and&#xD;
for ai ekstermindgun ov aer enemiz bai fair and&#xD;
s6rd. And ad coz Prins Jefur tu bi aer kin, and&#xD;
hiz cif ninisturz wer Lord Sepulkur, and Lord&#xD;
Judas, and Munimungur, and Ndvimaladi, huz ofis&#xD;
it woz tu mik desoldt ae siz and tu beri in dip&#xD;
woturz ae ips ov Samunkl. And for hiz jen-r-&#xD;
alz hi had Grdtbrag, and Pretigdrd, and St6ni-&#xD;
jon, and St6nijak, and B6ldrobin. And ad rizd&#xD;
a grit drmi and tuk pozegun ov ae stronholdz and&#xD;
kaslz, and sized meni gips and gunz, bisaidz Gdz&#xD;
hwic had bin .sfkretli givn aem bai ae servants ov&#xD;
Publik Funk9unari.&#xD;
Nou hwen ae lordz and kounselurz ov ai Oksi-&#xD;
&#xD;
33&#xD;
dentalz hd wer asembld in   parliment herd aiz&#xD;
ainz, a  wer fild wia alarm. And ad sed amui&#xD;
aemselvz, Wi must bai bl minz pasifai ae Dragun,&#xD;
and giv him hwotevur hi dimandz, uaurwaiz wi&#xD;
gal bav wor and bludged, and our hapi land wil&#xD;
bikum a land ov straif and tumult, laik ai enent&#xD;
kindumz ov ai orient. Aftur muc angri dibst,&#xD;
sum biin in fsvur ov ae Dragun and sum agenst&#xD;
him, ad agrid tu mdk a triti ov purpecual pis and&#xD;
amiti on aiz kondigunz, ne'mli, aat hiz majesti ae&#xD;
Dragun woz tu bi rekognaizd az suvuren ov ae&#xD;
kuntri konjointli wia ae rsnin kin ; but hi woz not&#xD;
tu strec hiz drmz or fit, or ae 9ad6 ov hiz oaoriti,&#xD;
dvur eni ov ae nn western landz aat had bin&#xD;
purcest bai Samuukl; sekundli, aat Fridima gud bi&#xD;
givu him tu waif akordin tu ai orijinal agriment;&#xD;
lastli, aat Sarnunkl and ge Normen gud entur intu&#xD;
a solem - kuvenant wiG ae Dragun aat ad wud&#xD;
not molest him in ae focur, nor spi'k ov him  dis-&#xD;
rispektfuli az ad had dun; and wud undur nd sur-&#xD;
kumstansez alou eni flaiin Kugan tu tdk refntj in&#xD;
abr bordurz; and aat ais kuvenant gud never bi&#xD;
olturd, hwail sun, men and stdrz 96n in ae hevnz,&#xD;
or hwail mountinz, siz and rivurz mrkt ae divi-&#xD;
junz ov ai era. S6 as sent out ae dikri nora, soua,&#xD;
ist and west, aat bl ae land mait konfurm it.&#xD;
But it woz non td1 it; for ae Blak Dragun,&#xD;
siin Ge kouardis and konsturnsgon ov ae kin and&#xD;
hiz kounsil, bigan tu strec himself m6r and m6r.,&#xD;
and diklerd aat hi wud aksept ov  rain les aan&#xD;
undivaided swd from 69un tu 69un strdt akros Ge&#xD;
c&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="34-35" xml:id="VAC5911-00000018"/>&#xD;
kontinent, and from hwer ae noraurn laiun 94ks&#xD;
hiz sndi men tu hwer ae suaurn aligtr sunz&#xD;
himself on ae sandi 96r ov ae Grdt Bd sn. lie&#xD;
Normen ols6 wer disphzd wia ae nA kuvenant&#xD;
and rifazd tu konfurm it. And ae pourful Sam-&#xD;
unkl bigan tn 96 hiz spirit, and tu dinai aat hi&#xD;
had ever promist hiz dhtur in marj tu ae Drag-&#xD;
un; for hiz hart smdt him  hwen hi herd ov ae&#xD;
krdel sufurinz tu hwie Fridima had bin ekspdzd&#xD;
in hur wondurinz, and bi riprdct himself for ac&#xD;
kouardli part hi had . akted in sending' hur of in-&#xD;
sted ov manfuli standing up and protektin hur wia&#xD;
ae brbni muslz ov hiz strong arm.     At last hi&#xD;
went tu ai aturniz and tu ai dngents aat wer&#xD;
skild in ae lb, and dizaird aem  tu egzamin ae&#xD;
pdiroments ov bitroaal bai hwic it woz klimd aat&#xD;
hiz dotur had bin konsaind in wedlok tu ae snski&#xD;
monster. Aftur dilijent sere and kerful disaifurin&#xD;
ov ae maniuskripts, ae libyurz giv aer opinyun aat&#xD;
nd evidens ov a bitroaal -egzisted, and aat ae dok-&#xD;
iments rilaid on tu prav it had n6 valid berin&#xD;
on ae kis. (len sed Samunkl, God forgiv mi&#xD;
aat ai hav akted laik a fil; Fridima gal riturn,&#xD;
and ai wil defend hur, 'if nid bi, wia mai laif.&#xD;
Hwen ae taim kdm for Magnus Mahirba tu as-&#xD;
end ae ardn, bi ai 6menz wer unpropigus.    (le&#xD;
skai lourd, ae kloudz got fdra laitninz, aundurz&#xD;
mutur 1, vaipurz and ratlsndks kdm bisia from  aer&#xD;
denz, and ae hai priest, aat woz tu p6r on hiz lied&#xD;
ai anointing oil, woz a dirk daiabolikal Drag6nian.&#xD;
Nou Magnus Mahnirba woz ov a kwaiet and pis-&#xD;
&#xD;
ful temper; hi luvd evuri bodi, and sot ae gud ov&#xD;
bl men, and hiz gritest ker woz aat hi mait nevur&#xD;
injur an enemi, but wia ivnhanded j stis trit frend&#xD;
and f6 alaik. N6 kin had evur bif6r held ae skdiz&#xD;
ov justis wia s6 impirgal a hand. In hiz hrt hi&#xD;
hited ae Blak Dragun; but inaznuc az hi had bin&#xD;
konstitted kin dvur b6a gud and bad, hi woz ri-&#xD;
zolvd aat bad and gud gud ikwali .er hiz protek-&#xD;
gon. Hi had lernt from ae prists and sol-dok-&#xD;
turz aat hwen ai Olmaiti fagund abr planet wia&#xD;
hiz fingurz, and r6ld it out from ae depas ov&#xD;
aur, a m6ltn and fair bbl, ivn aen hi ordsnd it&#xD;
tu bi ae facur habitigun ov ae Blak Dragun, and&#xD;
pridestind aat kinz and prinsez gud du him onur,&#xD;
and gud protekt him, and gud alou him a ser-&#xD;
tin p6r9un ov abr rds for hiz workmen, and for&#xD;
hiz wud and wotur kaniurz, and for hiz medser-&#xD;
vants, and for mercandaiz, and for sakrifaiz on&#xD;
hiz olturz, and for hwotevur purpusez hi mait&#xD;
find it konvinyent tu ydz aem. But ai Iradike-&#xD;
turz tdld ae kin aat ae s61-dokturz wer ron; aat&#xD;
ae Dragun woz a yuzurpur and an outlo; aat hi&#xD;
woz not a kricur ov God but ov ae devl, and&#xD;
aat it wud bi rait tu kil him and aio out biz&#xD;
kirkas tu blie in ae rdnz ov hevn wia ae karkas-&#xD;
ez ov ae pur inosents hum  hi had murdurd.   ie&#xD;
kin lent a wilin ir tu aiz opinyunz, for hi abhord&#xD;
opregun ; and ola6 hi abt it wud bi ron for him&#xD;
tu tsk ae laif ov wun ov Godz kricurz, ovur him&#xD;
hi had bin plist az a rdlur, yet hi sikretli wigt&#xD;
at God himself, if hi disaprdvd ov ac Dragunz&#xD;
&#xD;
r-&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="36-37" xml:id="VAC5911-00000019"/>&#xD;
36&#xD;
&#xD;
dtinz, wud send doun a aundurb6lt ti distroi him&#xD;
and aius riliv ae land ov its foulest and worst en-&#xD;
emi.&#xD;
iwen Magnus Mahdrba woz anointed kin, hi&#xD;
stud up on ae arn and mdd a sp'c tu ae p pl,&#xD;
akordi tu oae kustum ov ae kuntri, s6 aat bl mait&#xD;
understand ae prinsiplz ov hiz guvurnment and&#xD;
hwot woz tu bi ae manur ov hiz rdl. HiI told em&#xD;
hi wud not alou Norland and Sunland tit bi di..&#xD;
vaided, for hi had tdkn hiz da tu prizerv aem in&#xD;
yinyun az wun kuntri; yet hi wud grant ae&#xD;
Drag6nianz evuri induljens aat woz posibl. Olad&#xD;
ae Blak Dragun woz ofensiv tu ae Normen, hiz&#xD;
raits gud bi rispekted; and if eni ov hiz kaptivz&#xD;
eskspt, ad gud bi hunted up and rist6rd tu him;&#xD;
and ae pipl ov Sunland gud bi left tu manej abr&#xD;
dn aferz az ae s  fit, provaided ad wud not siz&#xD;
ae forts and kaslz bilonin tu ae kin, nor inturfir&#xD;
wia ae gips and trddin ov Samunkl.&#xD;
Gus kaindli did ae  n  kin endevur tu ald ai&#xD;
iritseun ov ae Drag6nianz, but t n6 purpus. (1&#xD;
ansurd him bak wia skorn aat hi woz n6 kin ov&#xD;
aerz; aat ad had not edzn, nor wud as aksept&#xD;
him; aat ad had provaided a guvurnment for,&#xD;
aemselvz; and az for ae kinz pour tu enf  rs a&#xD;
yiinyun bitwin aem  and ae Normen, ad difaid&#xD;
him. And ad gaaurd ar flits and Armiz and set&#xD;
aem in batl ard agenst ae kinz garisunz, for ad&#xD;
wer impdgent tu bigin ae wor.&#xD;
&#xD;
CAPTUR VI.&#xD;
&#xD;
TONIPAIL kasl, on ai isturn k6st ov&#xD;
Sunland, woz wun ov ae kinz stronholdz&#xD;
bilt bai Samunk1 at grit ekspens, az a ssf.&#xD;
gird agenst foren invidurz. It stud at ae&#xD;
moua ov a 1 ur, and woz girded bai ae&#xD;
servants ov Samunkl, hd had ordurz tu ads&#xD;
mit n6 viziturz nor alone eni veselz tu pas&#xD;
wiaout ae kinz purmigUn. And ae DragOn sent&#xD;
a mesenjr In ae kaptin ov ae garisun, siin, Giv&#xD;
mi ae ki ov ae kasi, ([at mai woryurz md entur&#xD;
in and oknpai it, for it iz bilt upon mai terituri&#xD;
and aerf6r bilonz tx mi. And 41e kaptin and as&#xD;
aat wer wia him rifazd,- for -a sed, Wi must&#xD;
obs ai ordurz ov our kin, and wiaout hiz purmi--&#xD;
gun wi kan giv admitans t n6 wun. And Prins&#xD;
Jefur sed, Non iz our taim; let us storm ae kasi,&#xD;
and s6 brie on wor, and Gen wil ol ae pipl ov&#xD;
Sunland bi yunaited az wun man, and wi wil fair&#xD;
abr hirts agenst ae tairant Mahirba, and wil gd&#xD;
out agenst him in batl, and wil 6vurard and dis-&#xD;
troi him, and wil entur hiz pales and rl ae h61&#xD;
land.  And hi gsy 4e komand, and Dnk Preti-&#xD;
gird surounded ae kasl, and bumbirded it wk&#xD;
hiz artiluri, and ard upon it gelz and kombus-&#xD;
&#xD;
CTR  x b.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="38-39" xml:id="VAC5911-00000020"/>&#xD;
tiblz, setin it on fair, and filia it Wia sm6k and&#xD;
fldmz. And hi drov out ae men aat wer set tu&#xD;
gird it, and tdr doun Ge kinz banur and put in its&#xD;
plds ae banur ov ae ratlsndk and Dragun. And&#xD;
ae touted and san, and mdd meri dvur abr vikturi.&#xD;
And hwen Magnus Mahirba sb hwot woz dun,&#xD;
hi sent wurd tu Samunkl, and bad him g6 ar ae&#xD;
land and kolekt arf skdr and fiftin nouzand wor-&#xD;
yurz tu fait for abr kin and kuntri, and to rikuv,&#xD;
yr ae forts and kaslz aat had bin kapeurd. (len&#xD;
woz Samunkl glad, for hi %ad 1o bin impdcent&#xD;
tu avenj ai insults ov ae Drag6nianz, and had bin&#xD;
angri wia ae kin ' for hiz ekstrIm  forberans. i&#xD;
had ols6 t6ld hiz frendz praivetli aat Fiaur Mag-&#xD;
nus gud not ristrdn him muc longur, for if hi kud&#xD;
not obtain ridres uaurwaiz, hi wud tdk ae l5 intu&#xD;
hiz 6n handz. Az sun az hi risivd ae kinz man-&#xD;
ddt tu sumun ae woryurz, hi rdz up in hest tu&#xD;
eksiknt ae komigun. And aer woz trampin tii and&#xD;
fr6, and mesenjtrz huriin dvur p14n and mountain,&#xD;
and ae er woz alaiv wia ae sound ov musturin"r&#xD;
futsteps and ae ratlin and burnigin ov wepnz.&#xD;
And Samunkl konsulted wia ae ric men ov G6-&#xD;
aam, and hi kounseld aem ti 6pn ae selurz hwern&#xD;
as kept abr trejurz, and bria out ae g6ld ant woz&#xD;
hidn bihaind aer wblz, and giv it inta ae hand&#xD;
ov ae kinz ofisurz for purcesin wepnz, and for&#xD;
bildin gips, and for k16ain and fidin ae woryurz.&#xD;
And as ansurd him fsvurabli, and promist tu giv&#xD;
ae kin l1 aat hi nided.&#xD;
Nou ae siti ov G6aam woz a Edbelaitig siti,&#xD;
&#xD;
v 8               Li 1u J1Yu  li44arb r.&#xD;
&#xD;
and ae langwej ov ae pipl diskordant. And meni&#xD;
ov Gem wer Drag6nianz, hd apird in ae garb ov&#xD;
Dem6krianz, rizembiin (em s6 kl6sli aat ae komun&#xD;
1ip kud skersli tel ae diferens. Cie mercantz&#xD;
and marinurz wer jenurali frendz ov ae Dragun,&#xD;
bikbz abr weld woz msd bai trafikin in ae skdlz&#xD;
hwic fel from hiz bodi, for hi 9ed hiz skdlz evuri&#xD;
yir, and ad wer ov a fain and bntiful tekscur, and&#xD;
suseptibi ov a grit varaieti ov kulur and polig,&#xD;
and hwen mannfakcurd intu r6bz and vestments&#xD;
wer muse admaird and sbt aftur bai ae mercants&#xD;
ov foren kuntriz. (le Dragun had nou put a stop&#xD;
tu ais trafik; meni, aerf6r, hd had priviusli advo-&#xD;
ksted hiz kbz, sudenli turnd agenst him, diklerin&#xD;
aat ad had olwez dislaikt him in aer harts, and&#xD;
aat hensf6ra ad abjdrd and rinounst him forever.&#xD;
(11d fn went s6 fdr az tu se it woz not fit aat&#xD;
sue a monster gud liv. (Le anr waiz -men ov G6-&#xD;
aam, at hiz lips ae pipi wer akustumd tu tik&#xD;
advais, and hdz ndmz wer Taimservitur, Triban-&#xD;
osofur and Hrlikin, had until nou bin divaided&#xD;
in kounsel. Wun rekomnended jentines and for-&#xD;
brans tdrdz ae Dragun; anvaur woz wili ae&#xD;
monster and- bi aat ltvd him gud dipirt and bi&#xD;
gon, and form a pandim6nium for aemselvz, sue&#xD;
az as dcz; hwail ae aurd rifazd tu giv advais&#xD;
Iaur wd, not n6in1 hweaur Kin Magnus or Prins&#xD;
Jefur wud prdv ae stronger.    But hwen ad so'&#xD;
ae ki1z flag t6rn doun, and ae s6ljurz ov Sam-&#xD;
unkl faird upon and drivn out ov abr kasi, and&#xD;
ae ratlsndks traiumfin 6vur its ruinz, aiz ari waiz&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="40-41" xml:id="VAC5911-00000021"/>&#xD;
jj&#xD;
[  i&#xD;
t f&#xD;
$'8 I   i&#xD;
i,  t&#xD;
a . i&#xD;
73  t t&#xD;
(; l t&#xD;
11j&#xD;
I.&#xD;
'j , 3&#xD;
;i ('&#xD;
111&#xD;
i r&#xD;
j&#xD;
(i&#xD;
t&#xD;
&#xD;
! ' 1&#xD;
f  _&#xD;
k&#xD;
k&#xD;
f&#xD;
,&#xD;
f&#xD;
&#xD;
40&#xD;
&#xD;
men stud up wia yunaited vois and bad&#xD;
kum forward at ae kbl ov abr kin, and wo out&#xD;
ae stdn on Qer banur wic ae blud ov adz aat had&#xD;
insulted it. And  re mulitd rut wi   wun&#xD;
pois intu c  kounsil gr6, and ae cif woryurz,&#xD;
and ai d1d men, and ae mercants, and ae lyurz&#xD;
and spiricual dokturz harangd aem aer, and egz-&#xD;
horted gem tu fait for aer olturz and inherit&#xD;
and ae kuvenant ov er fdaurz. And ae grv ri-&#xD;
zounded wiif gouts, and traikulurd banurz wer hua&#xD;
upon evuri tri, and ae pipl lifted up  er hn&#xD;
t6rd hevn and tuk a solem da -at u wudialn&#xD;
nd .Dragun kindum  tu bi establigt upon aer soi&#xD;
And ue guvurnur ov ae siti, hiz nevi woz Rotn&#xD;
wud, a cif ov ae Drag6nianz, woz  er- and hie&#xD;
the multitad diskuvurd him ae krouded around&#xD;
him and aretnd him, and tdld him iat hi ols'&#xD;
rdz hiz vois for hiz kin and kuntri, or els bi&#xD;
kounted for a trdtur. S6 as kompeld him tu&#xD;
mount ae vinigur barel and gout for Magnus 1\o u&#xD;
hirba and Samjnkl.&#xD;
And ae grdt drmi ov 'Samunkl woz gaaurd&#xD;
akordin tu ee kinz komandment and ad komenst&#xD;
abr mirc intu Sunland. But ae jenuralz wer k&#xD;
eund tu dil jentli wia ae lordz and prinsez ov ae&#xD;
Drag6nianz, and on n6 akount tu msk wor upon&#xD;
ae I)ragun himself, but dnli tu 96 him ho&#xD;
potent hi woz tu kontend wie ae f6rsez ov i&#xD;
kin, and aus fraitn him intu gud bih6vyr i&#xD;
kud not bi wun bai kaindnes. And hwen Dctk&#xD;
Botlh6ldur and Dnk Miklmak1 enturd intu ae&#xD;
&#xD;
41&#xD;
&#xD;
prag6nian kuntri, as f rst ov bl i9id ar prokla-&#xD;
iunz, enjoinin upon aer folourz and 01 ae pipi&#xD;
tu onur and rispekt ai oaoriti ov ae Blak Dragun,&#xD;
and wornill ae Kaganz aat if as imprivd ai opor-&#xD;
tniti ov aer misturz distres tu raiz agenst him,&#xD;
s wud bi krugt wis an aiurn hand. But hwail&#xD;
aeeifs ov ae Normen wer s6 tender ov ae Drag-&#xD;
n, and s6 kerful tu injur hiz lordz and nobimnen&#xD;
az lit1 az posibl, ae Drag6nianz fot wi a(e ut-&#xD;
m6st strena and ftari, 91n fsvr niaur ta hai nor&#xD;
16.  Hwen ae kil so aat bl ae smbl batlz wer&#xD;
gdix agenst him, and cat insted ov bin imprest&#xD;
wia a h6lsum  dred ov hiz pour, ae Dragonianz&#xD;
wer dnli ae m6r imb6ldnd, hi kbld for Dulk Diit-&#xD;
wel, and bad him komens ae wor in ernest. And&#xD;
hi sent him wia td sk6r and ten ifjunz ov stalwura&#xD;
woryrz, ordurin him   tu mdk an 6vurhwelmin&#xD;
asolt on ia sentral Drag6nian armi, and aftur di..&#xD;
fitin tu pursue aem ivn tu ae gdts ov Riemantoun,&#xD;
aer kapital.  len Diak DUitwel krost ovur ae&#xD;
Bounarimirk rivur and enturd Vurjinland. Af-&#xD;
tur mrein toddz hi km   tu a smbl strim kold&#xD;
BulskamIpur, on ai uaur said ov hwic le ac Dra-&#xD;
g6nianz stronli fortifaid, and redi for an atak.&#xD;
And ae Normen advanst and fht a em an dez&#xD;
and ari naits, but kud not disloj em, for aer cifs&#xD;
wer 61d woryurz, auruli skild in aer airt, and (fe&#xD;
wsrili kept tu aer intrencments and wud not fait&#xD;
on ai 6pn field. But on ac f6ra de ae market out&#xD;
and joind bati, and f t wia despurdeun; and aer&#xD;
woz a grdt slotur. And hwen ae sun woz goit&#xD;
&#xD;
2YU.5 c tl"aI, rb&#xD;
l1w&#xD;
&#xD;
Txtwt&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="42-43" xml:id="VAC5911-00000022"/>&#xD;
(VVvI&#xD;
.nms v t~ta&#xD;
&#xD;
doun, and ae Normen wer fdnt and wi'ri, rd so &#xD;
spektur nomd Pan, and ad trembld wia: grdt fir-&#xD;
And hwen a fa ov aem bigan tu flai, e terur spread&#xD;
amun ae rest, and ad lukt ais we and aat, and 16&#xD;
ae spektur woz kids upon Gem. And Gs gdv a&#xD;
krai, and aru awe aer gunz and napsaks, and aban-&#xD;
dund er wagunz and kanun, and ran az if ai ermt&#xD;
wer klivin asunder bihaind aem.; ad pzd niujr&#xD;
tu it or drink til ad got bak tu ae royal siti. But&#xD;
aer enemiz did not pursn Gem, for ae abt it woz&#xD;
a ruz.  And ae nekst mornin ad sent fora Qer&#xD;
skouts tu egzanin ae batl field, and tu faind hwer&#xD;
ae Normen wer. And hwen ae had fuli secret ae&#xD;
rajun around, and so Gat ai drni ov Samunkl had&#xD;
indfd gon bak, living Ge r6dsaidz str6n w gdr-&#xD;
nents and wepnz huridli kast awe, ar kurej ri-&#xD;
vaivd, and ae routed and danst, and prokldmd a&#xD;
grdt vikturi, and bl Sunland woz field Wi   SOnz&#xD;
and festiviti.&#xD;
And ae gaaurd aer sien and winded and bed&#xD;
ae ded. But meni ov ae Normen wer left abuv&#xD;
ground, and hwen ae fie9 had diked and fhon&#xD;
of, ae karid ae bdnz tu aer tents, and man.&#xD;
fakcurd aem inta drir.kin kups, and finger rinz&#xD;
and nekle'sez, and bl manur ov kurius ornaments&#xD;
tu prizent tu aer waivz and swfthairts, az' tdknz&#xD;
ov Ger valur, ; and tu han up az tr6fiz in aer&#xD;
kolejez and muziumz, alone wia ae skin ov Osamiz&#xD;
sun, and ae skalps and skeletunz ov   raurz aat&#xD;
had bin sakrifaizd in onur oV ver god.&#xD;
&#xD;
CAPTIUR VII&#xD;
&#xD;
ORTIFAID and konfounded at ai un-&#xD;
lukt for dizastur ov Bulskampi', ae kin&#xD;
a  hiz lordz and hiz parliament bigan&#xD;
tn doubt hwebgur ae ud b iA to fraitn&#xD;
SD    nf out ov hiz insolent bai kilin&#xD;
of ara6rgn ov hiz servants and adhir-&#xD;
t  and hweaur it WUvd not i betr tu&#xD;
ents,kti  on" ontrhimself. But&#xD;
m~ek wor direktli upont ae inonstur islf    u&#xD;
e kiw sed, Let us dui  justli, and let us sper hiz&#xD;
laif if psebl. Al hav tkn an da tu prizerv him,&#xD;
akriifib s en ent stacuts; yet notwiastan&#xD;
diakord m a  oblig eu n  tu  ae  k ntri  iz  gr tur.  It&#xD;
iz ae fiziounz daiti tu sv hiz pdent wi hiz limz&#xD;
entair if hi kan; but if hi faindlz ais imposih, aen&#xD;
hi iz justifaid in kutin of a lim tu siv ae manz&#xD;
laif.  6 wil ai du wia ae Dragun; hwen it hi-&#xD;
kumz sertin aat ai kanot sv him waout endin-&#xD;
-urin ae kindum, ai wil liv him tu hiz fst, and hiz&#xD;
vaiolens gal kom doun upon hiz n hed, and ai&#xD;
a1 bi giltles ov hiz hlud. Gden sed ae kinz koun-&#xD;
selurz  Let a part ov ae Dragunz pour hi tikn&#xD;
awz, and let sum ov L'z andz hi konfiske'ted, and&#xD;
&#xD;
42&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="44-45" xml:id="VAC5911-00000023"/>&#xD;
44&#xD;
&#xD;
let az meni Kuganz az dir fdrst tu help him in hiz&#xD;
'wikd wr h rifstfrom ifer bondoj,' and hi in..&#xD;
waited tu tsk geltur undur ao stri banur, and fr-&#xD;
evur aftur let cem bi fri from anservis and oor-&#xD;
iti ov Qcr krdel mdistur  Gl  al servia  Dar-&#xD;
gun in a tondur spot, and      il b     ad,&#xD;
andwilhi onpol  tus~for pis on sue termz&#xD;
az wi md diktdt. And (re kin   g.v      set,&#xD;
and adi rdt e dikri, and it woz rikzor kon&#xD;
Qe stacuts ov ae reim.oamu&#xD;
Sun aftur ais, wun ov ae kinz cift&#xD;
woz Dnk Frimantl, durin hiz zmircez in az west,&#xD;
iskuvurd wun ov ae Dragonz lon    rmz"okstend..&#xD;
ed out intu io nn kuntri and grasping a stek hwi&#xD;
hi' had planted aer az a sain ov hiz tbfu l pone vn.&#xD;
And Frimantl tuk hiz staf and hd      pozegand&#xD;
h6ld on ce jaigantik po, and boundiste, and t t&#xD;
stdk, and gdv ordurz tu hiz ofisrz    t t ue&#xD;
brain s6rdz and aksez and naivz, and kut it of.&#xD;
Gen ue Dragon hould wi' a bitur    d mutitlo.&#xD;
entabl houl, (at r ct ivn tu oe ale an  fo upon&#xD;
ai irzor ae kin. An-shadfen                pon&#xD;
i.               And hwen ae kin had in1 wv.d&#xD;
and lernt e kbz, hi sent a mesen-ur t  ik Fir.&#xD;
mantle, and ribalkt him, and ordurd hi u nklFr..e&#xD;
Dragunz arm, and in nd waiz tuse it roe&#xD;
hiz bodi, az cie Wiind mait piv fdtal, and even hi&#xD;
wud bi gilti ov ae Dragunz blud   B3 nmnhi&#xD;
wed not Is ie bandz, for hi rigdrded   rianti&#xD;
sue a nonstur az nd murder. lN   r      ouOV&#xD;
rispekt tu oe kinz ordurz, hi lete pe   ot az&#xD;
it woz, until Daik Huntsman woz sent z kut&#xD;
&#xD;
i&#xD;
w&#xD;
prC&#xD;
E&#xD;
A&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
r6ps and giv' ai 61d reprobit anuar cans for hiz&#xD;
Bt b1  e kinz kaindnes bad n6 oefekt upon ae&#xD;
ranfor hi woz az proud and impirius az ev-&#xD;
ur. Glen ae kin kbld for faiv hundred lijunz ov&#xD;
oryuz, in adignl tu a6z hi oredi had, and h1&#xD;
t yk  t  hundred  1 juz  ov  are  br."vo t,  and  plest&#xD;
Da k Mikmak1 at crer hed, and ordurd aem tu&#xD;
'"c valyantli but wir li, and t6k pozeoun ov ai&#xD;
enemiz kapital.  And   uk Mikmak1 sed tuae&#xD;
kin, Ai mst trn and tic (Lem bif6r ai kan lid&#xD;
aem tu mit e Drag6nianz, lest Id g4d not bi d1&#xD;
wstd       'rp ej ov bati, and gud bi put&#xD;
tu wi l. stand ae garejo&#xD;
tu konfajul az at Bulskampur, and wi bi agen&#xD;
brot tu 96m.&#xD;
And ie mnxui in ae kiz kofurz bigan tu gro&#xD;
skant, and  e g6ld sist tu f6 from  bihand ae&#xD;
wolz ov G6aam, and from ae vblts - ov Bruarsit&#xD;
nd Bivztoun, and Rickrg6, and ae rivur banks&#xD;
hwer ae kinz ofisurz had dig4 s6 suksesfulh yi1-&#xD;
ded no mor.   Len Magnus Mahirba med hiz&#xD;
n   Lu hiz ministers and waiz men, and&#xD;
wonits nont&#xD;
ased, Woz not mi in dn9ent taim obtsnd from&#xD;
1e moa ov a f11  And tu hum   gudiae k.luk&#xD;
for silver and g6ld but tu Lord Grinfi, hum hi&#xD;
haz appointed tu bi dvur -hiz trejuri?  And ae&#xD;
grdt kounsil past a dikri at e lord, trejurur gud&#xD;
bi rikwaird tu riplenig ae egzh bsted costs, and aat&#xD;
hi gud bi purmited tu mangyfakcur mum   out ov&#xD;
hwotevur matfrialz hi abt m6st konvinyent, and&#xD;
at eni substans stampt and koind in (Le trejur&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="46-47" xml:id="VAC5911-00000024"/>&#xD;
46                 Ma      alta&#xD;
nilz 9ud bi kounted for ae trd koin and kurensi&#xD;
ov ae reim. And Lord Grinfig multiplaid hiz&#xD;
z, and kast aeri i61d kldaz and daivurz linen&#xD;
and kotn fabriks, and aer k'm  out btiful soft&#xD;
muni, stampt wia imejez ov ae kin and hz lordz&#xD;
and ilustrted wia b1 manur ov strdn' and k^ rius&#xD;
divaisez. And ae kulur ov it woz grin, laik a&#xD;
kulur ov ae dgun.   And hwen ae kin so it lii&#xD;
woz wel satisfaid, and Samunkl tuk it and sur-&#xD;
klltd it aru ae kuntri, and ae pipi were dilait-.&#xD;
ed, and yuzd it for trafik and for ae piment&#xD;
ov tribut and kustumz, and nd longer komphihd&#xD;
ov aer burdnz.1&#xD;
Lord Siwordur woz ols6 wun ov ae cif minis-&#xD;
turz ov ae reim, and hi woz apointed tu woe ae&#xD;
kinz and kuntriz biyond ae siz, ad&#xD;
d' 'an' o tupivent aer&#xD;
sendin ovur veselz and rend urin asistans tn ae&#xD;
Dragun.   And Lord Dipwotur had cir oy ae&#xD;
tips ov Samunkl, and hi sent aem tu gr ae i-&#xD;
irn  kost  ov  Sunland,  and  t  fao inri isilz  ..-&#xD;
on ae Dragonianz, and tu draiv aem out ov aer&#xD;
sitiz, and tu ritdk ae fortresez ov Samunkl hwir&#xD;
had bin stdln from him. And ae veselz skourd&#xD;
alone ae 96r and went around tu ae soua ov Sun-&#xD;
land; and enturin intu ae Grdt 'sn ad past on'&#xD;
and ke'm tu ae moua ov Faaurwotur rivur, on&#xD;
ae bank ov hwic 14 ae gret siti F'vuropo-  A&#xD;
Dk   Botlhldur  went up     ivrps      And&#xD;
stored ae fortresez and tuk ae ti , and &#xD;
in ae nm ov Kin Magnus Mahdrba. And hi rld&#xD;
ai enemiz ov ae kin wia igur, b6a. Hise9 ad.&#xD;
&#xD;
47&#xD;
&#xD;
-but hi gvrnd ae pip1 raicusli, and diliv-&#xD;
Kuanz out ov ac handz ov aer opresourz.&#xD;
iwall ae gips wer aus nmkini konkwests on&#xD;
n  6r Dnk Miklmakl mend i     ae ro-&#xD;
yal sitir erfuli trdnin hiz ti hundred lijunz, s6 aat&#xD;
yen ae spsi    6pnd hi mait mdv am forward&#xD;
t   erdn sicinantopn.Az sun az ae Wintur had past&#xD;
e l rdrd him tu mk hest and bi gon, and&#xD;
old hi  aat sins hi woz afrd tu lid hiz wor-&#xD;
yurz bai ae we ov BulskampUr, hwer ae had si&#xD;
ae spektur, hi mait tesk  cm around bai 9ip ta&#xD;
{ i1st ov ai enemiz siti and mirc from aens bai&#xD;
ai     and i     'zi rd.  S6 ad tuk  ip and landed&#xD;
ona rtaurn zr-ov Vurjinland, and mirct t6rd&#xD;
ac Dragunz stronh6ld. And hwen Dak Mikimaki&#xD;
a                  sit, and biheld ae spairz ov&#xD;
had kom   nir tu ae sta&#xD;
p   and ae fortifikigunz bihaind hwi ace&#xD;
eragn had intrenct himself, and ae vast rmiz&#xD;
aat wer gaaurd around ae pl~      o  t    ies&#xD;
kud  dforz ov ee horsez and ac&#xD;
w                 uvin in ae distans, and aI opn&#xD;
rourz OV aa gret black gunz, iz hdrt sunk wiain&#xD;
him, and ac joints ov hiz niz bikim les and hiz&#xD;
totrrin. And hi kbld for a spid, and sed&#xD;
tu hiz woryurz, lwot yd si mi dd, aat dd yi ols.&#xD;
And hi bigan tu dig in ai era, and tu kast p&#xD;
- ,         w    hi hadatnasf-&#xD;
a bank bif6r him, and hwen -      atwoz   si-&#xD;
gent depa, hi sat doun in it,o andw e    ikud&#xD;
protekted  agenst eni misi1 hwic ai e&#xD;
hurl at him. And as" b1 did s6; and hiz woryrz&#xD;
dug for ,emselvz kumfurtahl h6lz in    hwie ae&#xD;
&#xD;
; ,_' ;.&#xD;
_ --&#xD;
r , ,&#xD;
i, , t,".&#xD;
t ,&#xD;
y(&#xD;
F'  j&#xD;
&#xD;
Ilys Lqathbao&#xD;
4 , as,&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="48-49" xml:id="VAC5911-00000025"/>&#xD;
48              Tatnvs Tr axe&#xD;
mait kronc and bi sikar. And as wer wel plizd&#xD;
for a taim, but ae soil woz swompi, and aer haid.-&#xD;
i1 plesez biksm damp and unh6lsum, and as were&#xD;
atakt wia fivurz and rdmatizmz, and ar bigan tu&#xD;
perig bai hundredz in a de.   And hwenevur a&#xD;
woryur daid, ar kuvurd him up in hiz h61 and&#xD;
smudd ai era abuv him, az it woz bif6r ae digin.&#xD;
And Dnk Miklmakl ardz on a klir mornin and&#xD;
lukt dvr ae pldn, and ld, ae ground woz b1 bi.&#xD;
kumin smrar and level, and in sum p16sez skiers a&#xD;
singl dpn h61 woz tu bi sin. Gen hi pursivd aat&#xD;
if hi rimdnd a fa wiks longer, ae meddz wud bi&#xD;
ristdrd tu crabr orijinal buti and stilnes, and bi&#xD;
grinur and grasiur aan evur, and hi wud hay ak-&#xD;
ompli~t nuain eksept ae berial ov hiz woryurz bi-&#xD;
nfar adm. And hwen hi abt on ai ansur hi gud&#xD;
mik tu ae kin, and hon hf kud akount for ae los&#xD;
or hiz drmi, hi woz filed wi ae mdst gldmi antisi-&#xD;
peunz.&#xD;
And non ai enemiz horsmen bigan tu. kroud&#xD;
around him mdr kldsli, galupin in hiz rir evuri&#xD;
nait and -uretni tu kut of hiz ritrit. Glen hi so&#xD;
aat hi must iaur fait or flai. At last hi rimem-&#xD;
burd having herd ov a fain river hwio 14 about&#xD;
f6r dsz jurni tu ae soua, and after konsultir hiz&#xD;
cif kaptins, hi ditermind tu mire akros ae swomps&#xD;
ana morasez tu faind it. Ge h61 lrmi woz akor-&#xD;
dini put in mdgun, and plunjd b6ldli intu ae bogs&#xD;
and fenz, hwer ae' sun bikem envelupt in kloud&#xD;
and mist, and in dens forests kuvurd wia hanin&#xD;
mos, ard hwic ae sun kud seldom  penetrit. .Ce&#xD;
&#xD;
= r                   '49&#xD;
b6 herd teribi houlinz bai nait, and spektorz and&#xD;
goblins wer porpecuali fiitin akros aer paz, and&#xD;
6z cat wer' sik and fibl wer tormented du&#xD;
horibi aprihen9n aat Ae ud be left bihaned t&#xD;
bi a prd for ce waild bists and monsturz ov e&#xD;
)&#xD;
Az sn az ae Drag6nianz so aat e Normen&#xD;
had enturd ce swomps d6 klapt uer handz for joi,&#xD;
and rIgt aftur Dem, and dvurtuk  em, an  a&#xD;
rem bif6r and bihaind, and planted   aeian  s&#xD;
ages ce, and fbt   em de aftur de, anduost&#xD;
aem wi aer kavari, and kut doun and bucurdr&#xD;
grt nmburz. But ae trps ov Samun    t     nr&#xD;
ground brdvli, and hurid bak (ter pirsnarzn&#xD;
and agent wi' firful slbtur. And despur9eUg gti&#xD;
furrmnes  tu cIbr  harts  and c nj  rt  in t  t&#xD;
and s6 grd s6 akustmd tu fait aat           ud&#xD;
from kumbat wih man, goblin      imn self, if hi&#xD;
hay fot e Red Dragun ov              ktTriz fetoni&#xD;
had kum in ar pia. And ae rot aer ike    on&#xD;
3 e Painz and ai Oksandnd swept    zi a i four&#xD;
wi a aunduri tramp az ov konkururz in l ov&#xD;
o   lr gdri. But as left bihaind  er m&#xD;
abr best  and  bravest,  hd  164  aemselz  d   tu.&#xD;
dai in maim fenz or wer migld w&#xD;
amU!~cehp     ov seen.&#xD;
amo.aehips of.si(- -        fromm a(e0swomps&#xD;
And on ae sevna de    imej            bntiful&#xD;
an(  forests,  and  bh6ld,  ae  bai k  o a  biinfon&#xD;
rvur wer bif6r aem. And DhkM i 'n       ie on&#xD;
horsbak r6d on bif6r ae rest, and r ci&#xD;
furst, hi found abr a worb6t ov Samankl, n&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="50-51" xml:id="VAC5911-00000026"/>&#xD;
50&#xD;
&#xD;
hwic hi enturd and woz sdf. And uaur pips and&#xD;
b6ts wer prokfnrd, and ae remnant ov ae great 'r-&#xD;
mil enturd intu aem and riturnd tu ae royal siti.&#xD;
And Dak Miklmakli prizented aem   bif r ae kin&#xD;
and tdld him ov ae kurej and galantri as had dis-&#xD;
pled, and ov ae vikturiz a' had wun.. But hwen&#xD;
Magnus Mahdrba lukt upon nem and so hou abr&#xD;
ranks wer aind, hi woz muc displizd, and hi wept&#xD;
for grif and 94m aat hiz woryurz had bin sakri-&#xD;
faizd, and yet ai objekt for hwic hi sent Qem&#xD;
had not bin akompligt.&#xD;
&#xD;
CAP TUIR VIII.&#xD;
&#xD;
WIEN   Samo1 herd ov ais free dizastur&#xD;
and sh e aturd lijunz riturnif from Vur-&#xD;
S inland, hz indignigtn woz arouzd, an&#xD;
histnd tu ne pales hail hiz hart woz yet&#xD;
hot, and hwen hi had f6rst hiz we intu&#xD;
kinz prezens, hi arrest hun and sed,6&#xD;
i kiMagnus Mahirba, wer ya not anoint-&#xD;
ed ~lu an  of 6yr is p-pi for nu"  pzotek9un&#xD;
ed rd ler and cif dvor aihut.a       p  tkin&#xD;
and~~ fo2 rgu  ,And lion iz it (Eat yu i rmek&#xD;
and for der gnd -                    - .  p yr&#xD;
aiz holokosts tu an infernal Dragon, giviu up teir&#xD;
uekts t  bi sakrifaizd bai aouzandz and tcnt&#xD;
Sau                hundred nouzand in a yir,&#xD;
oaouranalon austo kil ae vail kricur at haz&#xD;
instigated ail krael wor, an  iz            , tt&#xD;
i      az wel az ae laivz ov hiz pipI-&#xD;
Ad hnzn lait at wy  hav sent DAk Milmakl,&#xD;
And houiz i a ouanz and an 61d and intimet&#xD;
01~~~ enmiovun9to beri ae soljurlz si&#xD;
akwdntans ov ne Dragun, n   beut, jand   ain6bl&#xD;
hav givn yd in swomps and nirgez an fgre&#xD;
gris z?  And hwai iz not ae trJnpt .blnefo n&#xD;
nu sumun aem intu oe ratks ov ae    or-&#xD;
yvrz, tu  faith for  air kim adA h  i ni tr  n&#xD;
not atroi and kurejus tit&#xD;
&#xD;
i  i&#xD;
(li(f&#xD;
&#xD;
Lakolivs&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="52-53" xml:id="VAC5911-00000027"/>&#xD;
53&#xD;
&#xD;
52&#xD;
&#xD;
ful, and hay ad not meni taimz rilist ae fit ov ao&#xD;
kinz servants from ae jinz and traps of acr ene-.&#xD;
miz ?  And hwai gud a    Dragun bi aloud itu&#xD;
grand ar fdsez and brdk aer b6nz and divour&#xD;
aem ? Ar ae not fle9 and blud laik oursclvz&#xD;
Ha   ad not hinan filinz ? DD  e not laf hwen&#xD;
ad dr mer, and wip hwen Gd rin sad? Du Gd not&#xD;
sufur hwen a   dr stirvd?  iDd not    er backs&#xD;
smart hwen ae hwip terz aer skin? Du Ger bod-&#xD;
iz burn wiaout pan? Hon iz it aat a kin li luv&#xD;
justis and ekwiti haz n6 piti for ae sordz ov GI'Z&#xD;
inosents? Had ae kin but prokhkmd ae Dragun a&#xD;
monster and an, outlb, hven hi furst bigan GO&#xD;
wor, and kbld out ae Kuganz tu avenj Genselvz&#xD;
ov aer opresur, our trublz wud hay lon sins end-&#xD;
ed; a cmonstur wud hay bin sldn, and ae widdz&#xD;
and orfanz, hdiz huzbandz and fdaurz ai purswdded&#xD;
ta entur ais konfikt, wud not nou bi filing mai&#xD;
irz wie aer wdlipz and riprdoez.  lwai gud ae&#xD;
kin kontinyu tn 96 kaindnes tu ae Blak Dragun?&#xD;
Dd yd stil purpus tu giv mai dbtur Fridima tu&#xD;
hz unacural embros ?  Wil yd sik for uaur rek-&#xD;
ordz ov bitroaal, sins it iz found aat ai dod kuv-&#xD;
enant givz ae Dragun n6 kidm?&#xD;
(Ten Magnus Mahdrba, h   sb aat Samunkl woz&#xD;
gritli eksaited, ansurd him  mikli and sed, Ri-&#xD;
membur, gud fend, aat yd ydrself hav aknolejd&#xD;
ydr promis tu giv ydr dbtur in  arij tu ae Blak&#xD;
Dragun ; yd hay ripitedli averd aat ais woz yiir&#xD;
undurstandin ov ae kuvenant ; yd hay sent out&#xD;
yair servants tu hunt up ae fcjitivz and riturn uem&#xD;
&#xD;
tu bondej; ydi hay erfuli ped taksez anditribnt&#xD;
for suportin ae Dragun and hav gerd in h  pand&#xD;
its, and non wil yd disavou yur on wur z&#xD;
rip ndist  y tr  oblgig *knZo             en&#xD;
(en Samukl kulurd dip, for hiz&#xD;
kondemd him, and hi kud not ansur atwurd.&#xD;
de kin kontinyuld, Yu se it iz rons tu opiesae&#xD;
Kuganz and tu ekstort from aem -bbur Wjout&#xD;
wjez. (is iz just hwot ai hay olwez ot ,Dbute&#xD;
s61doktrz tel mi it iz rait, and iat ae Dragun&#xD;
woz mid bai 'e Kristur for s veri purpus, and&#xD;
at ule sskred bucks konfurm it beyond kwescu.&#xD;
And   hwen ai maislf si aat God haz aloud ie&#xD;
Dragun tu egzist forsoodine jee and still  is&#xD;
himin ~ii,  i m. led Pto(lout h weaur hi hits&#xD;
i    ba,  iuc az  ai   for  if  it had  bin' left&#xD;
ae kiiur azt aca ad        rutou        d 0&#xD;
tu mi, a1 wud hay put him    out ov  ne w   an&#xD;
ag6.  But ai hv n6 pour vur ae Pragun, an&#xD;
 hwot         wud  it  avl if  ai  9ud  se iz o n    ruanz &#xD;
tr nou dilivurd, yur dunjun   'nkt yir Qudnz&#xD;
.  =tn bnokn.? Wud amal seis ss mekit so .()ud ai&#xD;
no hbr'laik e fu s Bulfatul' h  atact hiz ani-&#xD;
not bilak    efmstit                 u stop ae&#xD;
mal tu a pepur kait and sent it up    to&#xD;
komet?   Ai kanot ivn send a mesenjur touRio-&#xD;
mantoun; mai soljurz hay bin traing for a yir&#xD;
and kanot get abrn; hou am   ai  u  nori  iKur-&#xD;
anz and tel  em ae ar riist rom&#xD;
ier opresurz              ifadadbisaa&#xD;
But Samukl woz not satisfaid, and i'sed G&#xD;
mait az wel stop faitine if (i a anil ditek  P&#xD;
rimn  in frend9p wi       Draguna      ijt&#xD;
&#xD;
tht&#xD;
&#xD;
,            l  rb .&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="54-55" xml:id="VAC5911-00000028"/>&#xD;
54&#xD;
&#xD;
frend9ip ov ae Kuganz. And hi went aws doun.&#xD;
kast and hevihi'ted, displzd wi f e ki1 for hiz&#xD;
kongiengusnes, and kursia ae dd fat hi had ever&#xD;
bin dept bai bad  advaizurz tu entur intu pdrt-&#xD;
nurgip wia d1d SkdIi.&#xD;
Hwen Saniunkl woz gon, ife kin bigan tu ri-,&#xD;
flekt biturli on ae kondigen ov hiz kuntri, and&#xD;
Qe mizrniz ae Elak Dragun had brut upon it, and&#xD;
hi inkwaird wicin himself; Iz it rait iat bl mai&#xD;
subjckts gud perii for ae sik ov wun, and iat&#xD;
wun ae mdst htfcul ov bl, a tairant and an ene.&#xD;
mi, hiiz distrukgun wud, beyond dispnt, bi a pub-&#xD;
ilk benefit? Am ai not ddin ron tu Samunki and&#xD;
Fridima, and tu fae pip1 ov ae land, bai sakrifaiz-&#xD;
in aem at ae grain' ov ais bludi M6lok ? Duz not&#xD;
mai da tu protekt l ai inhabitants rikwair i at ai&#xD;
gud punig a6z hii injur 'ae rest?  If ae Dragun&#xD;
iz entaitld tu mai protekgun, iz hi not olsd laiabl&#xD;
tu penaltiz for hiz roburiz and hiz murdurz and&#xD;
hiz ribelyunz ?&#xD;
And ae kin kud not slip ifat nait for ae multi-&#xD;
tnd ov abts iat priest on hiz memuri, and for piti&#xD;
ov ae reced Fridinla, huz kraiz for protekgun hi&#xD;
had sd l6n disrig6rded; and hi nou bigan tu i-&#xD;
prdc himself for havin koldli turnd hur aws,&#xD;
hwen hi gud hav cerigt hur az hiz best frond.&#xD;
Aftur rivolvin ae matur in hiz brdn for a ion&#xD;
taim, hi fainali konklnded iat hi wud indulj ae&#xD;
Blak Dragun in hiz wswurdnes n6 longer; fat&#xD;
hi wud apoint him a dd for ripentans and rekon-&#xD;
sihegun, and after iat if hi gud persist in hiz&#xD;
&#xD;
t        ' f&#xD;
I J,&#xD;
&#xD;
R"Tupne b*p it.&#xD;
&#xD;
55&#xD;
wiked and wontioln wor, hi wnd 19   a    r  o&#xD;
hiz ekspul91 from ae er n      Sforcelirind,  v&#xD;
hi had set up hiz ooriti, a me&#xD;
bi ifO 11 aifat tWgr hiz bo-udmien.!"&#xD;
b    d ae Kgnf a er iz Onkm ae kin ar6z erl1,&#xD;
And hen   e mo kioz,        t hiz abts tu&#xD;
an1 entrd inu rhz klozet,   adon, ofri  a fri&#xD;
raitin in  e form  ov .a p11iz adhentS, and setin&#xD;
Lim a taim Pu diziat fr om nin himt and bikumd&#xD;
rekonsaild tu Sam U:  and worndi   hi  kl  hiz&#xD;
if hi 9gud stil log: rifCz. Ad hei    blt hi&#xD;
lordz tagea r for counsel, and ot agensht hif&#xD;
had ritn. And nnl vof e    sd   fit gens itefor&#xD;
i s   Io at ie kiz rezolageIn  voat fst. tu mt r&#xD;
01s6 glad  at ife Dragn    oz rr l r ti mwoIz&#xD;
diizerts. eon sed Lord Siwoud  tor hi Wz&#xD;
waiz and fir-sii, and undrs't  trpsz nt  dfk&#xD;
ii ofrr and wornil hwie i     Pi soSo   taim k&#xD;
tu ife IBlak IDragn ar gdbe kin s   nor&#xD;
-0        For ai irmiz ov  -kn   nondiz&#xD;
bpkronp19     Pags-a   kptinlz and horsmlen ar&#xD;
bak, an  e Drlin t iOgts ov o capital,&#xD;
spread don ts O6h 1vn tu  e melted laik waks.&#xD;
And hn hirtsfi v  Pip1 aretnin iz spred abrbod,&#xD;
Ana men Ole na it  eiz aelast krai ov disper,&#xD;
bl m   en lseit iLo'   z   'inz    n  i   i&#xD;
for hi iz sobad bai ife Drag~anz and help hot&#xD;
ekstremiti hi inks tu Ie K9aZ dizar tuap prok&#xD;
ifat hi kerz for ue K~uganz oro diir te won-~&#xD;
"em, niar haz hi emi rispet  elftignories an-i&#xD;
d erin  and   reed  F idi a,  wil s k rn s  an d&#xD;
konst1rn him.  6 ao ngnz        k     u&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="56-57" xml:id="VAC5911-00000029"/>&#xD;
ae pip! ov Sunland wil traiumf dvur us and mo-k&#xD;
ohir impotent, and gr6 boldur in fait aan bifdr.&#xD;
Raaur let a3 kin wdt for a ndr ospiguz sizn; and&#xD;
let our jenuralz r61 bak ae taid ov wor intu ac&#xD;
enemiz kuntri, and let our invinsibl hdsts agen&#xD;
stand bif6r Ricmantoun.  Hwen ais advantej iz&#xD;
gdnd, let ae kin i911 hiz proklameun aud hz&#xD;
worni, and orddn liburti tu ae kaptivz, and o1 GO&#xD;
Kuganz wil rug tu join us and ae Dragun rds&#xD;
gal kwdk ardout b1 Sunland, and ten az konkr-.&#xD;
urz wi wil priskraib ae kondigunz ov pis. And&#xD;
e kiCt sed, (Iis kounsel iz gad; wi vil wet for&#xD;
ae betur taim.&#xD;
&#xD;
CAPT1JI-tIgo&#xD;
&#xD;
B3RINS JEFUR        and ae Dragun wer nou&#xD;
in kl6s konsultd9un, and hwen c so Ge&#xD;
diskumficaUr ov ae Normen, and hou    e&#xD;
 had gaard around aer kapital in terur, ad&#xD;
14d Gr planz for invidin and konkuri  .&#xD;
Norland. And (d sent of B61drobin in&#xD;
ndst, and ordurd him tu 1 wist de tounz&#xD;
and sitiz, and siz ae silver and g6ld, and ae floks&#xD;
d herdz, and evuri ain upon hwiobiz woryurz&#xD;
an    ,     hadz.  And biin eksidin.i puft up&#xD;
kud leaer hanz. ud&#xD;
16ri Prins Jefur gdv ordurz aat .e 9ud&#xD;
tk 1kaptiv liagnus Mahirba himself, and brim him&#xD;
. c      at i mait 96 him tuaeP GODragun.&#xD;
inhwail ae kin, pursivini ,e ddnjur ov livi an&#xD;
'p  6d bai hwie hiz enemiz mait advans tu ata&#xD;
opnad  al,. tordzRieman-&#xD;
GO capital, had sent of anuau armi  rd    m&#xD;
e    bp  GO ,    v B3ulskampur, tu draiv bak ae&#xD;
t oun bai ae wde          -     e   apdrnpn&#xD;
hbti h6sts  at wer   i    ver      apidrunand&#xD;
Rapidnokmi rnyurz, and araeGOa    ov GO 9aini-&#xD;
d6r. And hi divaided d Airmi intu band and&#xD;
-.o ,vur Gem  Daks Pontif and    Dditwel and&#xD;
Stronbr and    aur brev jenuralz. -An-d&#xD;
sed it woz bail ninz fitin Gat aO Pontif gud bi&#xD;
&#xD;
'1&#xD;
&#xD;
t , }&#xD;
t-&#xD;
f'&#xD;
«,&#xD;
°:&#xD;
,.,&#xD;
(&#xD;
l&#xD;
-,&#xD;
&#xD;
1&#xD;
a                           '&#xD;
!.&#xD;
,ti&#xD;
,&#xD;
,&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="58-59" xml:id="VAC5911-00000030"/>&#xD;
abuv ae rest, s6 hi gdv him ae cif komand. But&#xD;
Dik Pontif woz a yun woryur, and ae dldur cIfs&#xD;
wer jelus, and displizd Gat a stripling gud bi phdst&#xD;
6ver aem.&#xD;
Andehwen hi riot ae Rapidnokin rivur hi as-&#xD;
embld. hiz woryurz and harand aem, and tdld aem&#xD;
aer wud bi no mor dizasturz, for as had met abr&#xD;
last difit and med abr last ritrit, and nou aer'&#xD;
brouz wer tu bi kround wig ae caplets ov vikturi.&#xD;
So hi spred out hiz dirmi aloe ae river bank tu&#xD;
prevent ae Drag6nianz from krosini, but ae kdm&#xD;
on in swormz laik.l6kusts, and hwail hi woz gdr-&#xD;
din wun spot ae dagt dvur in anuaur. And hwen&#xD;
hi so hou grdtli aer numburz eksided hiz 6n, hi&#xD;
bikem alsrmd, and sent and bisbt ,Duk Miklnakl&#xD;
tu giv him m6r woryurz, and fid for hiz men&#xD;
and horsez. But Dnrk Miklmaki sed hi gud hay&#xD;
n6n betur aan tu g6 aat wd, and nou hi mait get&#xD;
himself bak az hi kud.&#xD;
Cen Dk Pontif so Gat hi woz in an ivl kis,&#xD;
and hi gaaurd hiz woryurz around hini, t     " skdr&#xD;
and ten lijunz, and fot ae sekund grdt batl ov&#xD;
Buiskampur agenst an ovurhwelmin multitud ov&#xD;
Drag6nianz.  And ,Duk Stroubir stud aluf and&#xD;
wud not help him in hiz ekstremiti; but Dntk&#xD;
Dditwel, and Dnck Heneman, and Horntosur, and&#xD;
Qarpsikl, and aeu aur daks and kaptinz fot val-&#xD;
yantli, and kept up ae fait seven dsz.  For do&#xD;
sed, WI .must non ritriv ae dizasturz aat bifel us&#xD;
last yir bai .rizn ov ae spektur. -But hwen ad bi-&#xD;
held .Ge k6horts ov ae'Drag6nianz multiplaiin, and&#xD;
&#xD;
o     bai tenz and hundredz ov aouzandz,&#xD;
and s ae touring pmz ov B6ldrobin, and ae&#xD;
majestik straidz ov Lon step, and herd GOundur-&#xD;
majeo  St6ni-aks kavalri, ad persivd abr kds woz&#xD;
h e And gaauri up ae remnants ov ae bro-&#xD;
ke  biiz, (YO m~d a~r we' bak, az best 6 u,&#xD;
and bituk aemselvz for eltur tu  e stronh61dz on&#xD;
ae ks ov Ge Boundarimirk.&#xD;
e oaik   ar  aftur  ae  kinz  armi ru t e   lijnz  ov&#xD;
't"njk and Lonstep, wirl3B6ldrobin bihaind aem.&#xD;
Stimjae Qaini dir vali and 6vur ae Boundariirk&#xD;
rivur ae swept laik a hwurlwind. And ten aouz-&#xD;
ndov aeO  orland woryurz wer kipi gird in ae&#xD;
ov ae Hdrpurz, and a wer harpin and siniii&#xD;
a    in      ov Samunk1 and Fridima, and ov&#xD;
Osapi AOmairtur, for (at woz ae spot hwer hi&#xD;
fcl. And ae Drag6nianz surounded aem, and tuk&#xD;
t'v and had aem hal abr hirps on Ge&#xD;
aem kpi,-      '  d&#xD;
wi16z and sin no mor.&#xD;
And6zeand s woz s6rli purpiekst and sik at bhirt,&#xD;
a  hi went intu hiz klozet and gut ae d6r, and&#xD;
'd t  ae God ov hevn, and voud a vou, sein,&#xD;
If God wil but giv mi rilif ais w ns, aen wil ai&#xD;
no1gur dile' but wil apoint ae Dragun hiz de ,&#xD;
and aftur al iu him spe's for ripentans, ai wil&#xD;
pdokfem  ad iri ov outlri agenst him, and i gal&#xD;
bi ekstermindted and distroid, and hun up az a&#xD;
spektakl in ae sait ovf bl ndunz.&#xD;
And ae kin woz in a grie't strd't, for hi had n6&#xD;
-    l    n mhi kud rilai tu lid hiz woryurz at&#xD;
sue a kitikal tain. For Dk Mikimaklhad ri-&#xD;
&#xD;
C S&#xD;
,''    #&#xD;
t  jr&#xD;
I 1     '&#xD;
1C    'r&#xD;
,  -  c?&#xD;
1_ a&#xD;
fjy}1&#xD;
£      ' {;'&#xD;
;    s" ,&#xD;
,&#xD;
,  -.".&#xD;
,'-&#xD;
.&#xD;
,f&#xD;
T  :sr&#xD;
.fi'&#xD;
}      w" .&#xD;
f-=   \ y;"=&#xD;
,rtL&#xD;
Y,'r  '  - Y a&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="60-61" xml:id="VAC5911-00000031"/>&#xD;
60&#xD;
&#xD;
jTacrn  t jd~&#xD;
&#xD;
turud in dizonur from Riemantoun, and bisaidz&#xD;
aat, hi woz vei tender ov ae Drag6nianz, and&#xD;
had wornd are kin not tu me'k wor upon   0&#xD;
Dragunz n royal person, but 6nli tu terifai him&#xD;
sumhwot bai draivin bak hiz drmiz. Nor woz ae&#xD;
kin wilin tu entrust ae komand -tu Dks Pontif&#xD;
and Dditwel, hd had olredi bin traid and found&#xD;
une'bl tu kop wia ae derin proves ov B6Idrobin.&#xD;
So hi kBld hiz kounselrz, Lord Siwordr, and&#xD;
Lord Blerintrump, and Lord Stampon at woz (e0&#xD;
kinz armi-skraib. Glen sed Lord Stampon, WI&#xD;
must hav a ncioff; but ai uaurz priferd Dulyk&#xD;
Miklnakl, for as sed, Hi iz a Dim6krian, and if&#xD;
W dismis him b oae Demdkrianz wil dizert &#xD;
kin, and aen wil it bi wurs wi    us aan it iz&#xD;
nou. And ae kin sed, Rait; it iz not waiz tu&#xD;
swop horsez in ae - midi ov a strim. S6 DnkA&#xD;
Mikimakl woz sent forward wic a gret drni, and&#xD;
hi enkounturd ae Dragdnianz in (e susurn mount-&#xD;
inz ov Midlland, and set in ard agenst [em&#xD;
Horntosur wic hz lijunz, and Frankman and Bur-&#xD;
ninbrand, and as me'd a gre't slbtur ov i inv dd&#xD;
urz, and cist aem up ae saidz ov ae mountinz,&#xD;
and dvur ae roki krests, and doun intu ae vali&#xD;
bihaind uem, hwer woz a smrbl rivur kold Antit-.&#xD;
urz krik. Gen Bdldrobin krost e strim, and tuk&#xD;
pozegun o vae hilz. (at 14 in ae form ov a kres-&#xD;
ent on ae western bank, and priperd for a grat&#xD;
bati.  And ae kinz drmi enkampt on ai isturn&#xD;
said, and ldd aemselvz doun tu rest for .ae fnail,&#xD;
sein, Tumoro is ae d ov wor, hwic iz Wddenz.&#xD;
&#xD;
4&#xD;
&#xD;
61&#xD;
And hiwen e ai-dpnur bigan tu klaim dvur il&#xD;
srhilz      e woryurz rouzd from  abr slurmburz&#xD;
andrkomenst e fait. And ae batl wakst firfuli&#xD;
bludi and kontinud b de.  On ae nora Horn-&#xD;
tosur rddJ laik a madnd bul, and swept doun ne&#xD;
 wi hiz artileri; but hi woz at lena&#xD;
wrgnidand meni ov hiz kaptinz kild. And&#xD;
wen Dk Sumunur sb it hi sumund hiz band ov&#xD;
veturanz and rest forward t fll up ae vikant&#xD;
ranks and h61d. fast ae ground (at had bin wan.&#xD;
.No. hwen ae nnntaid woz past, ae Drag6nian kol&#xD;
u r"'d t6rd ae sona, and Qer ad fel upon Burn-&#xD;
ilbrandp hd woz krosin ie rivur on a stdn brij&#xD;
in ordur tu kut of abr ritrit. Hir id fht til ae&#xD;
sun went doun and ae kinz traps rested on aer&#xD;
sekti tu rinn ae bati on e moro. But&#xD;
oame mo6 . bat1 kdm, for B6ldrobin had dis-&#xD;
n ard    o Glen  sed Burninbrand  and  lorntosur,&#xD;
Nou iz our taim tu bi up and after em; but&#xD;
Dctk Mikimaki sed, N6, wi dr not dbl; for ie&#xD;
sn stron and ad wil lid us intu an&#xD;
Dagonias6 hi let aem dipirt in kwaiet. And&#xD;
a ru and went tu br 6n kuntri, and ip6rt-&#xD;
d u  rains Jefr and ae Dragon ae misforcunz&#xD;
bifbin aem&#xD;
Hathbwn Magnus Maharba sb at hiz prr woz&#xD;
ansurd and eat God had giv him ae viktun&#xD;
ansr hiz enemiz, hi rimembbrd hiz vou iat hi&#xD;
had luz    ad hi sent for hiz skraibz and kozd&#xD;
em u kopi ae raitin hi had ritn, eat it mait&#xD;
bi skaturd amen (e pipl.    And hi sed wifi&#xD;
&#xD;
r&#xD;
I&#xD;
f      f  f'&#xD;
E&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="62-63" xml:id="VAC5911-00000032"/>&#xD;
62&#xD;
&#xD;
o,&#xD;
&#xD;
CAPTUR X.&#xD;
&#xD;
himself, Non wil ai _divaid mai enemiz, ad ai wil&#xD;
ofur a riword tu adz aat gal forsik ae Blak Dragun&#xD;
and riturn untu mi, and. hwen ai hay bai ais minz&#xD;
rfkuvurd a pdrgun ov acm, ai kan izili suban ae&#xD;
rimendur. S6S hi kbzd ae raitin tu bi waizli and&#xD;
kerfuli wurded, promisin tu ae pipl ov a le pro-&#xD;
vinsez aat gud rinouns and abjdr ae stpremasi&#xD;
ov ae Dragun, and in t6kn ov abr obidiens send&#xD;
up aer mesenjurz tu ae grdt kounsil, aat ao past&#xD;
9ud bi forgivn, and ad gud bi aloud tu mdk aer&#xD;
on guvurnment, and tu manej aer 6n afers az&#xD;
afdrtaim. And if ad non submited ad gTd bi pur-&#xD;
mited tu ritin aer helots in scrvis ; or if as wid&#xD;
konsent tu rilis aem for a ransum, aen h   wud&#xD;
prokur from ae grdt kouinsil ae prais at hwic ad&#xD;
gud bi valynd, and after aat ae kaptivz gd g6 fri,&#xD;
and hi wud transport acm tu-abr dngent kntri or tu&#xD;
sum uaur hapi kMaim. But for ae Dragun and adz&#xD;
hu kontinyzid tu fait hiz batiz, and tu kil ae s6-l&#xD;
jurz ov Samunkl, aftur ae pirid ov wen hundred&#xD;
dez, hwio wud termindt on ai first d .ov ae Gdt-&#xD;
muna ov ae nekst nl yir, aar gud bi nd pdrdn, and&#xD;
lae helots aat servd aem gud bi set fri wIaout a&#xD;
ransom, and gud bi at liburti tu g6 hwer ad pzd,&#xD;
and ae kmz armiz gud not ristdr aem tu aer opres-&#xD;
urz, but gud protekt and difend aem  in abr fri-&#xD;
dum; and aus ae pour and gri ov ae Dragun&#xD;
wud bi brat tu an end, and hi wud pei and bi-&#xD;
kum ekstirkt, for hiz praid and for hiz trzn, and&#xD;
for hiz kaim hwic hi had kornited in ribelin agent&#xD;
ai oaoriti and gvurnment ov ae kin.&#xD;
&#xD;
AMUNKL and hiz dbtr wer non sumund&#xD;
_t aepales. And ae kin 96d aem ae rait-&#xD;
had ritn; and hi sed tu Samunk1,&#xD;
ricdima cal n6 longur bi a fajitiv and a&#xD;
vagabond ; hensfdra ci gal abaid in may&#xD;
pales az a dotr.  For ae Blak Dragun&#xD;
haz kild and distroid our pipl, and haz&#xD;
edur  himself uriwurai ov protekgn; nevur-&#xD;
aeles, it wud not hi rait to dip6z and bani9 him&#xD;
waeoLt givin him  a ffr oporthuniti for ripentans&#xD;
a uekonsili9Un. Ai hav aerf6r given him a hun-&#xD;
ed dz ov griS; let bl uinz rimin az ad wer til ae&#xD;
taim  i  ast, and  aen  ai wil igu  mai dikri and  di-&#xD;
tai him from   hiz prinsli stt.  And for Fridi-&#xD;
az sdk ai wil ransom ae Kuganz from aer bon-&#xD;
e'p and ai wit purees for aem  sum hapi a11and&#xD;
hwiaur as m6 bitdk aemselvz and bi no mor op-&#xD;
r   nd ae tendr hdrt ov ydr jentl dbtur gal&#xD;
hi '6 lo gr esft and t6rn wia ae kraiz and ae&#xD;
sufurinz ov ai linosent.&#xD;
Glen sed Samunld, Ie wurd ov -ae kin iz&#xD;
ud; but sup6z ae Dragun gud aksept .yur ofur,&#xD;
e nd ae provinsez and pip1 send up ger mesenjurz&#xD;
.fdr ai 6pniii ov ae Gstmuna, gal aen b       bi&#xD;
&#xD;
,   !&#xD;
, ; .&#xD;
,  ,&#xD;
 ,-  Ei&#xD;
s ij1  ''&#xD;
!f  = G&#xD;
,Ij  ,&#xD;
;' '!&#xD;
i   ; f jy&#xD;
t     i&#xD;
',',;(&#xD;
i     '&#xD;
'f ,i&#xD;
, 'i i1&#xD;
1    jt&#xD;
I}li&#xD;
1   '  I'&#xD;
1   ''  f&#xD;
&#xD;
rrr Yi&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="64-65" xml:id="VAC5911-00000033"/>&#xD;
*&#xD;
&#xD;
64&#xD;
&#xD;
ristdra az bifdr 2cl?  1&#xD;
binskriazd fr Qal ae laivz ov mai sdijurz hav&#xD;
bifrended     for nt? .? al ae Kuganz hd har'&#xD;
bifrended Gem  and Ist aer fit from ae snerz, hi&#xD;
agei riturdnd  Fod? -a1 ai engent kuvenant&#xD;
hidiivadd, anFimn b yunaited for laif tu aat&#xD;
Daun a1dnistur ? For nd, 6 kip1, aat ae Blak&#xD;
Dragun a anevuri risiv ae hand ov mai dbtur&#xD;
in marj; and moi pan aat, aftur hwot haz hap-&#xD;
nd si and 91 kanot liv upon ae sim continent;&#xD;
and stil furaur, az mai nim iz Samunkl, and. az&#xD;
Ge ilud ov a jaiant res fidz are mai vanz, ais&#xD;
karm iaz hunt him from  96r tu 961, til hiz kir-&#xD;
ksi bnwd faiv uouzand facumz dip in ae solt&#xD;
ei, alon h'G ac hundred aouzand hiwaitnin skel-&#xD;
etuns ov hizrnizurabl viktimz not yet kuvurd hal&#xD;
Gi ensepulkur~in iz!r&#xD;
Stop, stop, sed Magnus M   -ahirba, yd  r td muc&#xD;
e e  u      a n at wi must dd justli, and ob-&#xD;
zerv ae kuvenant ov Ge fdaurz. Ai hav hut vei&#xD;
iti hop Gat G ndblz and prinsez ov Ge Dragun&#xD;
wii aksept mai ofur. Purhaps ai gal not suksfd&#xD;
i       pip  O  a simgl provins.  But if ad dud&#xD;
.n at mai invite9un, aer rats must bi rispekt-&#xD;
ed. Anud aftr ad hav submited tu mai oaoriti,&#xD;
iDragU stbjl vig tu onur and supdrt ae Blak&#xD;
Drgu, suekt uGO ae lz ov ae kuntri, wi kan..&#xD;
ai ga   Ge m tobanig him from  aer midst.  But&#xD;
gi 9aemdu lma    os' tu purswed Gem, and wil&#xD;
giv aem Aolmst eni fevur Ge ask if ac wil aban-&#xD;
dun him.   Az tu givn up Fridima tu a     Drag-&#xD;
un,    hi gnd insist upon liz klim, liv Gat tu mi-&#xD;
&#xD;
65&#xD;
&#xD;
-&#xD;
Ai wil endevur tu pasifai him wia a ransm.&#xD;
Trubl not ydrself and Fridima vii yusles firz ov&#xD;
hwot wil probabli nevur hapn. If it gud unfor-&#xD;
cunetli bikum nesesari tu yunait Fridima, in ak-&#xD;
ordans wia ai original bond, tu wn for h    m 91&#xD;
haz n6 afekun, ai vil tdk kar aat 9i iz trited&#xD;
wia evuri rispekt. Qi gal never, hwail 4i liv, bi&#xD;
f6rst tu okpai ae pozieun ov a animal.   And&#xD;
Si cal bi aloud tu spend ae grdtur porgun ov&#xD;
evuri yin on hur fsvurit noraurn hilz. Yir do-&#xD;
tr, ai am   9   ir, wil olwez bi redi, az ai am,&#xD;
tu mndk a sakrifaiz ov hur 6n praivet filnz hwen&#xD;
nesesari for ae salvseun ov hur kuntri.&#xD;
(Ien Fridima kud n6 longer kontin herself, and&#xD;
gi bigan tu krai and sob biturli. Klinin kl6sli&#xD;
tu hur fdaur and 1ini hurzhed upon hiz 96ldur,&#xD;
9i trembid in evuri lin, az an aspen 1ff tremnblz,&#xD;
in ae id.   And hwen oi had prtli rikuvurd&#xD;
mue wi sod,    Hiwot iz ais cat ae kin haz dun?&#xD;
orsa  kin haz put mai laif in jepurdi, and&#xD;
mai enemiz wil nou araiz and kombain for mai&#xD;
distruken, and wi aat r flaturin wurdz ae wl&#xD;
disiv ae kin, .and az sun az as hav med aer pis&#xD;
wia him  a  wil persikut mi m6r aan evr, and&#xD;
aC pir inosent Kuganz wil bi trodn tu ae dust,&#xD;
and hunted and kild upon ae mountinz and in ac&#xD;
valiz, and in ae kdvz hwer as hav hid aemselvz.&#xD;
6 hou kan ai endur tu witnes ae sufurinz ov is&#xD;
kaind afek9unet pipi 3 For as ar tu mi az dn&#xD;
bruaurz and sisturz, and eksept dilivurans bi grant-&#xD;
Sed aem, let ae kin no agfiredli aat ai gal dal&#xD;
E&#xD;
&#xD;
i&#xD;
,+&#xD;
il ¢'&#xD;
&#xD;
Pl 1&#xD;
.a&#xD;
.&#xD;
&#xD;
M: ariz Abliii,&#xD;
&#xD;
Tu nir            rb i.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="66-67" xml:id="VAC5911-00000034"/>&#xD;
66         3, snAlbigrbr                                                                       6&#xD;
&#xD;
wia aem, and mai prezens gal nevur mdr bi a&#xD;
trubl t Oae kin or tu hiz pipl, and mai ndm&#xD;
gal peri and bi forgotn from   amun ai inhabit-&#xD;
ants ov acis land. And gi run hur handz for ae&#xD;
bitur grif and augwig ov hur sol.,&#xD;
([en Ge kin woz trubld, and hi wept, and sod&#xD;
tu hur faur, Kumfurt ae mddn, and pasifai hur,&#xD;
and dout not aat bl wil yet bi wel. 86 ad bid&#xD;
hur drain hur tirz, and hur fdar tdld hur hi woz&#xD;
preti cur ae Drag6nianz wud rijekt ae kinz pro-&#xD;
pozal. Hur taint ov trail wud bi but for a fib&#xD;
wiks, and aen hur sordz wud, l bi dvur, ae&#xD;
Blak Dragun wud perig. and sink tu oblivion, e&#xD;
kaptivz bi dilivurd from  abr bondz, and  b1 (re&#xD;
pip! wud hdl hur az ac hapi kwin ov a nn and&#xD;
betur dj. But Fridima kud not hug up hun krai-&#xD;
in, and gi bis&amp;amp;t ce kin at hi wud let hur ritair&#xD;
tu ae forests and komp6z herself, and rim'n abr&#xD;
til ae hundred dsz wer past. Ta ais ae kin wuid&#xD;
not konsent, for hi sed, Qi wil ldz hur rizn if left&#xD;
aldn wia cis anzaieti prdin upon hur. Hi fird os6&#xD;
at 91 mait in a rag mdment .esksp from ae kuntri&#xD;
and flai tu sum uvor land, and s6 fulfil ae wurd gi1&#xD;
had sp6kn, at hi and hiz pip1 ud si hur n6&#xD;
m6r. Hi kept hur aerfdr in ae pales, kerfuli woct&#xD;
and gdrded, and hi gdv hur ae best rdm, and&#xD;
invaited hur faur and frendz tu vizit bur evuri&#xD;
dd, aat ad mait sua and .enkurej hr. Notwia-&#xD;
standin 61 aer efortz tu mdk hur hapi, as kud not&#xD;
rist6r hur tu hur nacural bwoiansi. For Fridima&#xD;
felt aat 9i woz a priznur, and ait gi woz atil in&#xD;
&#xD;
ddn'ur ov a fit wors aan dee, and Gat abr woz n.&#xD;
sevtinti ov rilif for ae kaptivz 6vur hnz bondej 91&#xD;
n6rnd. Ofn in ce nait gi wud wik from stArtii&#xD;
drimz h      r hirt arobin konvulsivli. And evuri de&#xD;
9 lisnd wia intens interest tu Ge rdnorz, hweaur&#xD;
ov ps or wor, Gat ksm from Sunland, hopim,&#xD;
yet skersli deri tu biliv, aat e iDragun wud pur-&#xD;
ist in hiz foli til hiz dd ov grds woz past. Sum-&#xD;
taimz, hwen wbk   in ci e pales groundz, 91 wud&#xD;
rifiekt biturli on Ge kondukt ov ae kin, sem wat&#xD;
hi woz unjust, and Gat hi had n6 rait tu ofur ae&#xD;
Kuranz az a braib ta win bak ae Drag6nianz.&#xD;
i ud not understand ai old kuvenantz, nor ae&#xD;
kinz ekspaldel ov cen; for ei sed if ae kuve-&#xD;
nants wer for uph6ldiU inj ustis ad wer an abhor&#xD;
ens tu ae God ov hevn, az muc az ad wer tu hur.&#xD;
Anld furar, 1 did not biliv a robur kud akwair&#xD;
Ge rait to rob bai mekim a kuvenant wia eni bodi&#xD;
eksept  ae P  .ati tu bi robd; and it woz not pr-&#xD;
tended Gat GO Kuganz had enturd intu eni ov e&#xD;
kuvenants kw6l      Oted1ai ae kinin justifike'n ov ae&#xD;
Dragunz onoriti tu opres. Az for herself, 91 dimd&#xD;
it a gr6s outrj for her fdair or .eni wun els tu&#xD;
mik kuvenants and alaiansez for her agenst hur&#xD;
wil, and e kbld upon  1 Oae wined dnjelz tn 1lnd&#xD;
Gr pinyunz and her hur tu sum uaur sfir, if ger&#xD;
g;d evur bi an atemt tu f6rs hur intu ae DragUz&#xD;
iz.-&#xD;
hwen Ge Dragonianz herd ov xe kinz ofr&#xD;
=    and aretnin ad diraided aem and sed, Wi hay but&#xD;
Sh6d on and bi furm a lid lopgur:, and ±e v1k-&#xD;
&#xD;
4'&#xD;
&#xD;
66V&#xD;
&#xD;
67&#xD;
&#xD;
r&#xD;
, v,, 0  W  R, a " axb-.,Yo&#xD;
, Pt"  It    Q&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="68-69" xml:id="VAC5911-00000035"/>&#xD;
68&#xD;
&#xD;
Bluguinvz   2   jidrn.                                                                                                6&#xD;
&#xD;
turi iz ourz. And ae kin agen sent for hiz ofisurz&#xD;
and bad aem put aer drmiz in md9un, and m'rc&#xD;
direktli agenst ae kapital and pales ov ae Dragun.&#xD;
And Dak Burninbrand woz komigund tau lid ae&#xD;
wd. And hven hi had rict e --idnokin rivur&#xD;
and krost ovur tu i uaur said, hi so bif6r him&#xD;
a hai hil and around it a grit and strop wol.&#xD;
And hwen hi drdi nfr, it bikim a wbl ov fair,&#xD;
and belct fdra gourz ov dea-dflin inisilz amun hi&#xD;
woryurz.  And meni ov uem     fel ded upon ao&#xD;
plin, and as ritrited wens and agen bif6r ."e fair&#xD;
run.   And Horntosur begd ov Burninbrand aat&#xD;
hi wud kip awe' from ae wb1, for hi woz fraitnd&#xD;
at ae numburz ov ae sldn. But Burninbrand wud&#xD;
not lisn, for hi sed ae must gin pozegun or ae&#xD;
hil, kost hwot it mait.  S6 hi we'vd aloft hiz f-&#xD;
mig brand in aie presens of hiz h61 Lrmi for ae&#xD;
surd taim, and ad rugt forward, and ae Drag6.&#xD;
nianz mdd aem doun az bifdr, and paild ae phdn&#xD;
wia ae ded and daiin, ivn ten nouzand men. And&#xD;
Burninbrand had yet f6r skdr and ten aouzand&#xD;
woryurz left ; and after ae sun went doun hi&#xD;
gaaurd hiz diks and cifs in kounsil, and tdld,&#xD;
aem aat hwen ae mornin br6k ae must dag ae&#xD;
remnant ov ver 'rmi wuns m6r upon ae wbl, if&#xD;
peradvencur ae' mait te'k it. And bl ae cifs bigan&#xD;
tu murmur, for ad' sed, Hwai gud wi ipit Gis&#xD;
foli, and bit out ae brenz ov ae kiiz s6ljurz.&#xD;
bai aroir  aem  agenst ae wol, hwen wi kanot&#xD;
ric ae Dragonianz aat dr bihaind it? CGen Dak&#xD;
Burninbrand s6 aat hiz sup6rturz had bl fdld him,&#xD;
&#xD;
.  -- id  adorderd ai Armi&#xD;
and hi woz haili displizd, and  o      e ri&#xD;
tu bi awidrbn tu te noraurn bank ov nae ivur,&#xD;
And abr woz grdt we'lig and lamenteUl hadfout&#xD;
Norland for ae ten aouzand woryurz iat had foin&#xD;
.r  . '  And hwen    e IDragun sb it&#xD;
-bifor ae fairs wo -'    dbkmm.         iemn&#xD;
higind from i tu. Iin', and bike'm mor ditei'mind&#xD;
hi ridafom1rta      kin or risiv hiz of-&#xD;
aan evur not tu submit tu oe&#xD;
urd pcrdn.'rodn aat had bin&#xD;
PDjrin ace h61 tarnt ov prob6e.f  athd    i&#xD;
Daria  e h61  a, of P  (,)miz of ae kin&#xD;
givn to Ge Bflak Prgun    G0~m vG&#xD;
giv    t tu     wu s bif r abr enemiz.  For a&#xD;
E    er put.u geivoae vois or risiv ae mesejez by&#xD;
kud no lot gui' hirG  ~So   il    Omsjzo&#xD;
Fkidilna, and ge  pour ov hur nem az a wocwurd&#xD;
Fridiost.  And sum ov ae profets aat wer ov ai&#xD;
woz lost.  Adsmo         epa         i aem for&#xD;
Iradikiturz sed Gat God w z    .grui wil ov ae&#xD;
ofurin tu pCSres ai alaianz and glail   ov GO&#xD;
Dragun wiG Ge toil and tziz and arsez oe tig&#xD;
Kuganz, and Gat Gas' in neer be b1 tukon-&#xD;
agenst aen, and Gat ae wud wnevuro  al  tu  rdz&#xD;
kun Gai. enemy nlz until Fnidima woz aloude   i'&#xD;
h  r  banr  en i  ie nd  for  ae  protek9un  ov  bl&#xD;
her  ban uf  6v uAor  b e 4  l  ba it n   ae   an&#xD;
A nd in bt an  R zikrov.  h ' had  bin  sent  t  w oo&#xD;
And Dm      o    rekRzk tbrao- beyond ae Ajur khfs&#xD;
}:1 ae muvments tov           lavat+e yrud&#xD;
and Aligdtur mounte1lz, rizolvd vitria Go yin s&#xD;
not pas wiaout e gliriov sum vikterfor Hais-&#xD;
tdria  tn  rikond  in  hun  daia  a r  abrrf ,rtga sku r&#xD;
tuger hz andz a w      skaturd ab'od,  wskr&#xD;
and  ten  ijunz,  and  m crt tn fiIuiunzburo,  hw r&#xD;
Gr.tbag  and  B a 6k  'b n a  fiftijnz  ov iD ag-&#xD;
nian woryurz had Piet aver tents and but &amp;amp;'k.&#xD;
&#xD;
4   r,&#xD;
e&#xD;
i      i&#xD;
1    ; , ;&#xD;
s    l     I&#xD;
'   999   t&#xD;
;    ,&#xD;
'  j&#xD;
f   i&#xD;
, a  f&#xD;
f&#xD;
s, ,&#xD;
. .&#xD;
I&#xD;
'&#xD;
_  ;&#xD;
'&#xD;
Vii',, ,&#xD;
7±&#xD;
s..t&#xD;
&#xD;
69&#xD;
&#xD;
'  g&#xD;
t   3 ,!&#xD;
1'i&#xD;
iii i+ '&#xD;
.  i;&#xD;
{&#xD;
;,&#xD;
'     t,&#xD;
&#xD;
' ql&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="70-71" xml:id="VAC5911-00000036"/>&#xD;
70&#xD;
&#xD;
cenz, and had sat doun tu it and drink, and tu&#xD;
rdk aemselvz kumfurtabl for ace winter. And&#xD;
hwen ad herd aat Rdzikroun woz advansin ad rdz&#xD;
up in hest, and kdm out tu giv him bati on ae&#xD;
banks ov ae St6nifork rivur. And hwen aurti diz&#xD;
ov ae Ddziembur muna had past, and ai djed yir,&#xD;
sik and sad-hirted, having ldd himself doun tu dai,&#xD;
uif6lded hiz mantle tu tik wun mdr sordful Ink at&#xD;
ae morning sun, aen ae ti Armiz bigan abr dedli&#xD;
fre. And ae Drag6nianz rust upon Rdzikroun in&#xD;
aer fari, and hi kud not stand bif6r aem, and as6&#xD;
swept doun hiz hjunz bai hundredz and uouzandz,&#xD;
lvn fair aouzand men ; and ad tuk td uouzand&#xD;
kaptivz and twenti gret gunz. ([en Rdzikroun fel&#xD;
bak tu ae plis hi okcapaid at ai 6pnin ov ae fait,&#xD;
and aer hi held fast .hiz ground, and gaaurd hiz&#xD;
woryurz around him, and bad aem tik hirt wuns&#xD;
mor, and rimembur .aat ae darkest our woz just&#xD;
bifdr ae brdkin don.&#xD;
And s6 it prvd; for ae veri nekst ds ae skiJ&#xD;
ov batl turnd, and ae garlandz ov vikturi blos-&#xD;
and on ae brou ov Rdzikroun.     And hi turnd&#xD;
upon 'hiz enemiz, and ad fled bif6r him, and hi&#xD;
cest aem tu. ar kamps, and drdv aem souawurd&#xD;
wia a gr Wt -sibtur.&#xD;
&#xD;
it'&#xD;
&#xD;
CAPTrU]RXL&#xD;
&#xD;
ORDZ ai end ov ae hundred dez Fridi-&#xD;
ma gru m6r and mdr eksaitabl, and hur&#xD;
mecual wocigr    for ac slaitest hwispur&#xD;
prpeuawbr ov h6p had givn hur a won&#xD;
cik and a fivurd puls.  Ge ddz wer ker-&#xD;
fuli kounted, and at leia 9f bigan tu&#xD;
kount ae ourz, On ne last d6 hur a-&#xD;
.eti wozs6intens aat 91wud stlt at ae ruslin&#xD;
wo fansii aat mesenjurz had kum from ae&#xD;
Ilak Dragun.   Fainali, hwe'n gi s  e sun g6&#xD;
Ba       klz its lrinand bludgot ai binia ac&#xD;
down  and  kl z is, i&#xD;
silkn f-ie -    e twailait, and hwen ae not rugt&#xD;
upon hr brn aat ne lo  aguni woz vur, and aat&#xD;
hur destiny woz sf, e91 braik f6ra into a konvul-&#xD;
iv  detm and swnd aw. lwen    91 had rikuvurd&#xD;
iv grknd hrseif surrounded bai hur faaur and&#xD;
rend, hf had kum tu kongraculet hur upon hur&#xD;
gud forcun, and ae dilivurans ov ae kaptivz from&#xD;
aer prizn-hous. And bl aat simpaaaizd wia hur,&#xD;
in tounz and sitiz, gaaurd tugeaur tu woo ai out-&#xD;
g6in ov ae melankoli yfr, and tu prd for ae hapi&#xD;
entrans ov a betur dj.&#xD;
But ae nait woz drk and ghimi, and strenj&#xD;
noizes wer herd, and hwisliiz in ae er, and a&#xD;
&#xD;
Thiw5 Utlatfirba.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="72-73" xml:id="VAC5911-00000037"/>&#xD;
72                   I3Th nv 0    l liirn.                                                                                                        7&#xD;
&#xD;
flapin ov winz, az ov dimonz enrijd bikoz er&#xD;
taim woz gort. And ae gldm rested upon ae land&#xD;
til midnait. And hwen ae Gstmuna hwic 6pnd&#xD;
intu ae n . fra bigan tu turn upon its hinjez, and&#xD;
ae grdt belz in ae tourz komenst aer ri-in, aer&#xD;
kem a soft hwait lait aat spred its rddians dv'r&#xD;
ae skai, and'9dn in at ae winddz, and wia it a&#xD;
swit meludi az ov distant worblinz, and bl gat&#xD;
herd it sed, It iz ae sound ov ae kumin Ira! CIS&#xD;
dnjelz dr sinin aer dld son ov Pis on era and&#xD;
gud wil tu men ! And ae burdz in abr boui-z&#xD;
nbt ae mornin had kum; and ae ti bigan tu&#xD;
worbl melddiusli; and soft gdlz kdm   up from&#xD;
Sunland, laik ae ge'lz ov Arabi, Idn wig diligus&#xD;
perfnmz. And bl ae pipl bigan tu sin, and Fridi-&#xD;
ma san, and ae ourz glaided bai bifdr as wer&#xD;
awer, and ae nornin brdk.&#xD;
And az ae de advanst ae pi'pl weted in ankgus&#xD;
ekspektdgun for ae kinz dikri hwic hi had prom-&#xD;
ist, and ad sed, Iz not ais (e de for Iiburitin ae&#xD;
kaptivz? And iz not ae dd ov grds for ae Drag-&#xD;
un past ?  Iz not hiz duim tu bi pronounst cis&#xD;
ds? And sum sed, Magnus Mahairba never yet&#xD;
brdk hiz word; uaurz sed, Hi der not banig ae&#xD;
Dragun or dipraiv him ov hiz servants ; uaurz, aat&#xD;
it wud not bi just; uaurz stil, aat- it wud bi bi-&#xD;
yond ae kinz pour tu kari sue a dikri intu eks-&#xD;
ikigcun.&#xD;
Glen ae kin gaaurd hiz ministurz and skraibz,&#xD;
and sed, Yi nd (re wornia aat haz bin givn; and&#xD;
nou ae wurd gat haz bin sp6kn must bi akom-&#xD;
&#xD;
S&#xD;
i&#xD;
y&#xD;
&#xD;
pligt.  S6 hi inkwaird hon meni provinsez~ Qer&#xD;
wer cat had sent nd mesenjurz tu 0ae grdt koun-&#xD;
sil. And a ansurd him, Ten. And hi kbzd a er&#xD;
nmz tu bi inserted in de .dikri hwic hi had pri-&#xD;
prd. And ae form ov a0 raitin woz als :&#xD;
Hweraz ae Blak Dragun, added bai triznabl and&#xD;
wiked kounselirz, haz mdd wor agenst hiz kin&#xD;
and kuntri, and aerbai forfeited bl rait tu protek-&#xD;
gun ;&#xD;
And hweraz a pokl149eun haz bin mdd giving&#xD;
wornin and taim for ripentans, and ofurin pardn&#xD;
tu bi pipl and provinsez in iirmz, on kondigun ov&#xD;
acir submigun wiain (ae pfried ov wun hundred&#xD;
dde, hwic hundred dsz hav ekspaird ;&#xD;
Nou, oerfdr, ai, Magnus Mahairba, kin ov ae&#xD;
Yunaited Oksident, di public and dikler  at bl&#xD;
persunz held kapti  wihin ae foldin provinsez,&#xD;
tu wit: Vrjinland, Tora and Soua Karulurz, Gor-&#xD;
jusand, Flouriglddz, Ailandbimi, Fiaurwotur, Ark-&#xD;
njel, Lnisland, and Tdkusin, dr hensfdra and gal&#xD;
forever bi Fri; and aer fridum  gal bi mentdnd&#xD;
bai ae nagunal dirmi and nevi; and ad gal bi em-&#xD;
ploid tu garisun f6rts and tu serve a.r kuntri, and&#xD;
i tu 16bur for wjez hwerevur a enz; and (d gal&#xD;
hay (e rait ov self difens if assld bai aer enemiz.&#xD;
And ae lordz and kounselurs ov ae kin aprtvd&#xD;
ce dikri.  And ae mimstor aat woz 6vur iae&#xD;
 kinz trejuri sod, Let it bi aded aat uis akt iz&#xD;
=    pe1rformd in ce nem  ov justis, and dedikdted tu&#xD;
Olmaiti God.   And ae kin konsented. And hi&#xD;
saind (1e dikri, hi and Lord  Siwordur, and ad&#xD;
&#xD;
72&#xD;
&#xD;
73&#xD;
&#xD;
rn&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="74-75" xml:id="VAC5911-00000038"/>&#xD;
74            (a~iuvs   JJritr.                                                                                      7&#xD;
&#xD;
slid it wia ae grdt sIl and sent it fora tu bi&#xD;
publigt arnout 61 ae land.&#xD;
Glen ae kin kbld Fridima and tdld hur aat hi&#xD;
had fulfild his pronis, and aat gi gud nevur m6r&#xD;
bi trubld or persiknted bai ae Blak Dragrn, but&#xD;
gud bi at liburti tu rdm at hur plejur ard ae hdl&#xD;
kuntri, Sunland. az wel az Norland, and tu risiv&#xD;
ae luv and homej ov ai inhabitants and ae grdt-&#xD;
ful wanks ov ae liburdted Kuganz, and cat hur&#xD;
ndm gud bi linskraibd on b1 ae ki1z banurz. il&#xD;
aded ols6 ae h6p aat gi mait wun do bikum kwin&#xD;
ov 61 ne'unz.   Glen Magnus Mahirba tuk hur&#xD;
hand and kist it, and begd hur forgivnes for&#xD;
hwotevur ron hi mait hav dun hur. And gi kist&#xD;
ae kin on b6a elks, and ae kin wept.  For Fri-&#xD;
dlma biin ov hevnli orijin aer woz a kurent ov&#xD;
silescal ilektrisiti aat fidd from hur lips az "ad tuet&#xD;
ae kinz elk, penetrdtin hiz h61 frdm  and kindlit&#xD;
in hiz brest ae sm  fldm ov impirgal benevolens&#xD;
tu 61 ppl1 wia hwic 91 herself woz inspaird. And&#xD;
ae kin bikdm  az a nu man, and hi felt winin&#xD;
himself aat hi had nou risivd ae tre royal anoint-&#xD;
in, and from aat our hi woz evur redi and wilii&#xD;
tu 16 doun hiz laif for ai objekt ov hiz div6gun.&#xD;
And hiz lordz, wun after anuaur, tuk ae hand&#xD;
ov Fridima and kist it. And as akumpanid hur&#xD;
out intu ae strits ov ae siti, and a gout laik ae&#xD;
sound ovmaiti aundurinz grited hur az 91 mdvd&#xD;
aloe. And ae pipl strdd rdzez in hur paa, and&#xD;
ae Kuganz gaaurd around hur, and arei aemselvz&#xD;
at hur fit, and wept for ekses ov joi.&#xD;
&#xD;
And mdst warbtful it woz tu si hou ae h61&#xD;
Oksid1.t braitud wi dilait az ai ekdz ov ae sl es-&#xD;
cl  ^zik l6ted awd on Qe winz ov ae wind tu&#xD;
cie distant mountenz, and ard ae valiz and for-&#xD;
ests, and hwer (e rijoisin rivurz went por  ctr&#xD;
kristal fiudz intu ce si. And i evurgrinz 6pnd&#xD;
abr brancez lIny.li tu ae glz aat kist (rem az as&#xD;
went past; and    ai aisiklz aat hun  around ce&#xD;
waitnd top ov Meunt  geik sofnd intu tirz ov&#xD;
tendurnes; and b1 alone ae Roki krest cat ovr-.&#xD;
luks ce Pisful Si, ii iglz wer out on poized wi-n,&#xD;
survsin ae nnu batiz ov ae wurld biniac aem; and&#xD;
ae kloudz hun out abr luvliest banurz ov red,&#xD;
hwait and bla l 6vur rae skai; and of 69unz sent&#xD;
of aer worm  kurents tu melt ae aisborgz, and tu&#xD;
swip around ci ailandz and aeC Grdt Orient, and&#xD;
tu r61 up ar wdvz dvur ae B6Arbarus gorz ov Ku-&#xD;
oa, and ac burning sand o Ofur,- and Ler grin, del-&#xD;
taz ov ace Flouri Land, and tu wog out e fut-&#xD;
prints and ae blodstdnz hwic (. Blak Dragun and&#xD;
Liz fiaur had left bihaind em  in evuri kntni&#xD;
hwhr ad had had car habiti9u.&#xD;
&#xD;
75&#xD;
&#xD;
74&#xD;
&#xD;
3rurnv 5  ,'TIallftbae&#xD;
&#xD;
I{Ii;  ttxy JJ e;&#xD;
I j  { !  1   I&#xD;
i  I'1 1&#xD;
((  ( t&#xD;
C.i tjl&#xD;
t fi&#xD;
:it&#xD;
r;j "'&#xD;
R  r'   't&#xD;
r  ii,&#xD;
r&#xD;
F   li&#xD;
r&#xD;
t    i.&#xD;
its&#xD;
1&#xD;
E&#xD;
(C     t&#xD;
a t&#xD;
, ;   1&#xD;
R&#xD;
,y  +&#xD;
4',   s&#xD;
s    ,&#xD;
,F&#xD;
r    I,&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="76-77" xml:id="VAC5911-00000039"/>&#xD;
77&#xD;
&#xD;
CAPTUR XII.&#xD;
&#xD;
AGUR aan brdk de ared ov mai narativ&#xD;
in ai 1st, ni abt it betur tu bi sumhwot&#xD;
tdrdi in sizin de strin ov okurensez dat&#xD;
hapnd in ae west. Gat lain ai non tdk&#xD;
up.   Sun aftFr ae Dragoun komenst hiz&#xD;
wor, aer woz a maiti komdoun in ae&#xD;
granit hilz hwer ae Fiaurwotur haz hiz&#xD;
s6rsez, and in ae waid and fertil pldnz urd hvie&#xD;
ad fl6.  For ae Dragun had ur6n an aiurn cen&#xD;
akros ae canel ov komajnikden, and wud n6 lort-&#xD;
gur alou ae noraurn kandz and trddinbdts tu g6&#xD;
up and doun az afdrtairn. For ae brancez 6v ae&#xD;
Faaurwotur dr spred dvur ae sentral rIjun ov ii&#xD;
Oksident az ae brancez ov a tri spred ard al er ;&#xD;
and az ac bLurdz and skwurelz i aldrmd hwen ad&#xD;
si a serpent twainin around ae trunk bild aem,&#xD;
s6 wer ae dwelurz upon ae western woturz fild&#xD;
wia konsturneun hwen ad found ae Dragun woz&#xD;
arin hiz koilz akros aie grt rivur and baindi&#xD;
it wicu cdnz ov aiurn, aat hi mait mdk it a sliv&#xD;
and a bondman, fvn az hi had dun tu ae Kuganz.&#xD;
And ae pipi wer rouzd, and p6rd doun from abr&#xD;
hilz laik torents in de sprintaim, and adO sed&#xD;
HIwerevur our strimlets gd, aer wil wi g6, and&#xD;
&#xD;
1r al hi n6 enz Upon our woturz, from    ae&#xD;
douzand ldks, hwer our Minigiiturz hunt e waied-&#xD;
foul, tu ae G rdt Bdsn ov ae Miksinkan, hwer ac&#xD;
woturz mit and mingl wia as si.&#xD;
And aer dwelt anon ae hunturz a tuf and stub-&#xD;
urn woryur hnm ad klkd Granit, and hi woz&#xD;
Se            vaild b sts aat had bin kild in&#xD;
des moute   hwen hi herd ae tminult and mur-&#xD;
rin ov de pi,1. Az sun az ade t6ld him ov di&#xD;
insult tu oae F rwotor, hi sent and ofrd luiz&#xD;
servisez t Samunkl. And Samuenkl sp6k for him&#xD;
tu (e kin, and ae kii sent him a komigun tu&#xD;
kut a par doun ue Faourwotur and 6pn ae canel&#xD;
s6 dat dO gips ov ai Admirabl Ferigift, hwi  le&#xD;
in de Grdt B sn, mait hay a fri pasej up and&#xD;
doun de strinm.&#xD;
Gen Dfk Granit gaacrd a gr t h6st ov de il-&#xD;
anoirz, nd de Iaiav6z, and ae Waizkounselurz,&#xD;
and dO Miligagunorz, and ae Migniturz, and hi&#xD;
miret aem doun tu ae border ov Sunland, and&#xD;
da -prepardgu~nz tu advans upon Mumif6s and&#xD;
Wikedburg, ti gret sitis aat 1 l6eur doun on dO&#xD;
banks ov de FiaurwotUr. And aer kdm up from&#xD;
de sou a woryur aat wud not entur intu dO&#xD;
n kounselz ov de Drag6nianz, h"z ndm woz Qdr-&#xD;
man, and hi joind himself to de kiz armiz, and&#xD;
-      woz sent out tu faith bai ae said ov        ntk Gramt.&#xD;
And bikbz ov ae grdtnes ovae Ourdn aat rested&#xD;
tpon do gCldurz of diZ td cfftenz, ae spirits ov tu&#xD;
dld woryurz dat had left ae planet kem bak and&#xD;
enturd into aem, and pozest aem, and med aem&#xD;
&#xD;
Tg't                    -Tljirba*&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="78-79" xml:id="VAC5911-00000040"/>&#xD;
78&#xD;
strong for bat]. And ad km tu Gem in drfmz o&#xD;
ae nait, and infonzd intu em a p6rgun ov abr dn&#xD;
kwolitiz.  And hi aat tuk pozceun ov Dak Qir&#xD;
man woz wens a fdmus cif in ai Oksident, and&#xD;
woz kbld Tikumsi; hwail ae mentor aat inspirited&#xD;
Dak Granit woz an en cent hird bai ae nim ov&#xD;
Yulisz, aat formerly dwelt in ui Orient.&#xD;
And Dnk Granit biko-m   waiz and abgus and&#xD;
hi wud not miv doun ae FIaurwotur until hi&#xD;
had siknird al kntri on hiz left and raft, s6 aat ci&#xD;
enemi kud not kum in bihaind him. Nou aer weri&#xD;
td Isrj and veerikruked strfrmz aat rdz in aI Ali.&#xD;
getur mountenz, and ran up t6rdz Norland  az if&#xD;
Gs wigt tu entur ae pnrur rj unz hwer Fridima&#xD;
rizaided. And ae went windin alon said bai said,&#xD;
yer nir ic vaur, for a Ion distans, until ae ret a&#xD;
Haiurwotur rivur, ihwic biin a stronger strim dvur-&#xD;
pound aem and turned aem bak intu ae Fsiaur-&#xD;
wotur, nir Ge suaurnm6st point ov Norand, at a&#xD;
ples hwer purpecual kloudz ov fjipgan drknes&#xD;
obskur ae vijun ov ai inhabitants. And GO&#xD;
hui livd4 on GO banks ov aiz rivurz, hwenae pos&#xD;
hou lvinli ae' klun tugeaur in Ger k6rs, sed,  iz&#xD;
nr twin bruaurz; and ae kold aem Twin Siz  G&#xD;
noraurn strim woz ols6 n6n bai ae vlgar nern ov&#xD;
KInburground. And hwen Dnsk Granit p      osivd&#xD;
iat Ge Twinsi kuntri woz ae ki o oae F pcrwot&#xD;
ur vali, and so ae dlespuret efdr s Gat wnrwo-d&#xD;
bai ae Drag6nianz ti h6ld it for er bati&#xD;
hi ditermini aat hiz fUrst faitin  'd b' grnd&#xD;
hi sent up Raitfut, ae komandun o  hiz   s&#xD;
storm e stronhdldz ov ae Twinsi hwie I on hiz&#xD;
&#xD;
79&#xD;
&#xD;
j1W5 x jtb~r.&#xD;
&#xD;
rait. Aftur aiz had bin tskn, Duk Granit mniva&#xD;
forward on e left tu Oe Kumburground, and sur-&#xD;
ounded e kasl ov Dbnip.sun, hwer a grd't armi&#xD;
ov Drag6niaIZ wer gaaurd.  And ae Drag6nian&#xD;
komander, i Dnk Flaiinaff, assd tu fait, but ac nor-&#xD;
uEn mountenlrz dvurpourd him, and n1ounte  iz&#xD;
bulwurks, and kut doan ae b6ldest of' hiz woi-&#xD;
yurz, and piest aem s6rli til naitf bl. And hwen&#xD;
Fla.inaff so Gat e bati had gon agenst him, and&#xD;
aat hi and hiz jenz mst bikum kaptivz on ao&#xD;
mord, hi ot ov b1 hiz aefts and hiz roburiz hwic&#xD;
hi had komited, and hi woz eafr'd ta surendu&#xD;
himself tuo ae kn, lest hi 9ud bi. trutdlaik a SMa'-&#xD;
efaktur az hi woz, and bi hun up bai Oaenek. S&#xD;
hi kbld hiz leftenant, and ge'v him iz plimz and&#xD;
hiz epolets, and plst him in hiz sted, and in-&#xD;
strukted him  hwot tu d  on ae mord.    And&#xD;
hwen hi had put 61 ai in ord     am, hizrz up and&#xD;
tak hiz Pild undur liz arm, and fled, and iAdhiz&#xD;
eskep in ae deirknes ov ae nait, and woz herd&#xD;
ov n6 m6r.&#xD;
=        And GO nest d6 woz ac de ov ae Sun, hwic&#xD;
woz a sdkred de, and hwen ae mornia broke and&#xD;
, Dbinsn kas1 began tu ghitr in ae gdn lai, G&#xD;
leftenant hsnd t me'k hiz submigun, and tu -di-&#xD;
ivr intu ae handz ov e viktur 61 hiz woryrz&#xD;
aat rimsnd alaiv. And as kounted ae number ov&#xD;
ae kaptivz and found aem tu b urtin uouzand&#xD;
men.&#xD;
Gen ae Granit DOak turned hiz fd s agen tu ae&#xD;
west, and tuk up hiz lain ov marc for ae Fiaur-&#xD;
&#xD;
+ t&#xD;
.   ,&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="80-81" xml:id="VAC5911-00000041"/>&#xD;
80&#xD;
&#xD;
wotur. But hwen hi had krost ae Twinsf hi&#xD;
found Duk Pretigrd   w i  a grdt armi in hiz&#xD;
furnt, nir a tempi (tat woz ndn  az ae Sailent&#xD;
Cure. And aeta trinrmiz joiiid bati, and ad foto&#xD;
aril t diz, hwie wer (Le ddz ov ae Sun and M0n,&#xD;
and aen rested, bikbz ae pkds woz s6 aikli kuvurd&#xD;
wi pailz ov ded and daii n aat ad kud n6 longer&#xD;
mvu dvur ae ground. And a kounted ae sldnp&#xD;
and wdnded ov ae kinz drmi and found ae nun..&#xD;
bur woz twais ten aouzand ; but ae Drag6nian&#xD;
ded wer td nimurus tu kount.   And Pretigird&#xD;
sent and bisbt Prins Jefur  at hi wud giv him&#xD;
m6r woryurz, lest ae Granit Dik gud s z upon&#xD;
ae Faurwotur, and ae grdt vali bi forever lost.&#xD;
And grdt numburz wer sent on tu sukur him ;&#xD;
and hi gaaurd (em around ae Korinaian kolumz&#xD;
aat stud bai ae rdsaid on ae wd tu Mumifrs.&#xD;
But Dnk Granit went forward and disperst aem;&#xD;
and hi prest on to Mumifds and tuk it. And hi&#xD;
brdk ae cdn aat had bin street akros ae Faur-&#xD;
wotur, and distroid ae Dragunz wotur-ramz aat&#xD;
wer swimin up and doun ae rivur, and butin at&#xD;
evuri m(n aat kem in aer wd. len hi mdvd doun&#xD;
ae rivur tu atak ae Wiked siti. And hi found it&#xD;
woz bilt hai and strop,and terest up from (10&#xD;
wotur baturiz tu a sumit, and its wblz wer ful&#xD;
ov dirk h6lz arl hwie bl manur ov burnin gelz&#xD;
and aiurn bblz wer gourd upon ae gip(s aatemt-&#xD;
ed tu pas, and upon evuri enemi aat vencurd nai.&#xD;
And wun ov ae kin z ofisurz sed, Let us mk a&#xD;
nu r6d for ae- Fdaaurwotur, (at hi md 116 tu (10&#xD;
,7&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
r ' ? " t rtr i 4jithx.&#xD;
&#xD;
fi!&#xD;
&#xD;
aga     and m -,   ita&#xD;
s bai a str t canel, at a distant from  sit a&#xD;
bi n6 longur difaild bai kontakt wi its polbut e&#xD;
soil. 56 ad dug a na care br od anJd  ut n t&#xD;
FacurwotUr woz 61d    and  slkgi, an d   n&#xD;
cinj hiz k6rs tu akomodst ae nn-agld n    u&#xD;
fur ov frendz or foz.&#xD;
e nuX ira ov Fridima woz non nea at hanf&#xD;
but D"k Granit, laik Rdzikron, woz impkent for&#xD;
sm  vikturi bif r  ai  61d  yir  ud  z  S o i   ad&#xD;
Dik Qrman, in hnm     h  rozd ontdens, and&#xD;
sent him  doun  ie strim  wiabovW kedurg, and&#xD;
rmi on al isturn 96r pust au AndDkidrman&#xD;
mik an atak from                         .ne norf. hi  oz ordrAnd&#xD;
went and fktd a landing azhi woz ordurdp  And&#xD;
ari dsz bif6r ie na yr hi led hiz twips up o&#xD;
(et wolz ov e siti, and an aouzand ov  z  w at&#xD;
yurz wer smitn doun bai 410 fai ebizui Gat&#xD;
swept dvur and around (em.- -And t gvnaid&#xD;
hwer (s trod woz soft and mairi, and atndyntaid&#xD;
ue skaiz p6rd doun aer rni oir and l1b&#xD;
wnded and dain sunk intu ae mai and      hwe&#xD;
nait in pitiful helplesn0  an nizur. Ansktprgu&#xD;
ae morning woz kmu,   -k      h- ask   e   hic&#xD;
tu beri hiz ded and bri. awhdiz wrorde  ast&#xD;
woz granted. And hwenp hi ha     aformd e l-&#xD;
sad ofisez for hiz fbln kumradz, h  onrd rhiz&#xD;
idnX ov hiz woryurz, and pl6st (elnmn rhid&#xD;
veselz and brbt aerm bak to   amp&#xD;
at Milkinpenz.                        divaiz na&#xD;
Aftur ais fdlyur hk Granit bigan t    e aints&#xD;
skimz for disloji. ae DIragonianz&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="82-83" xml:id="VAC5911-00000042"/>&#xD;
hwerin as trusted. And hi sent out hiz gips and&#xD;
hiz pafaindurz tu penetrdet ae lks and somps&#xD;
and Roundabout bdyuz on ae rait hand and on ae&#xD;
left, if purcans ad mait find a wd for hiz gips and&#xD;
armi wiaout pasin undur ae wblz ov ae siti, but&#xD;
Qe kud faind nun. And hwven hi so aat ae Get.&#xD;
muna had kum    and gon, and ae kiil m unt ov&#xD;
Febrifnlj had ols6 past aw, and ae Md'ren imna&#xD;
woz non fdr advanst, hi ditermind tu send hiz&#xD;
wor gips strit doun ae strim and run gem past ae&#xD;
siti under kuvur ov a dark nait, hwail hi wia hiz&#xD;
dirmi msrct doun bai a surkniitus r d on ae west.&#xD;
And (e gips and galiz wer ist from abr mdrinz,&#xD;
and -havin put out abr laits, ad drifted sldli bai&#xD;
ae frounin batiments, and wer not diskuvurd til&#xD;
ae wer olndst biyond re.  Gen ac Drag6nian2&#xD;
laited up abr fair, and hwen d s caat (le gipac&#xD;
had gon bai, arr hiltops rizounded wit rej, and ac&#xD;
spit out after aei strinz ov brimstdn and fair,&#xD;
but bl tu nd purpus. And Dak Granit brot hiz d r,&#xD;
mi around in sdfti, and havin rijoind hiz veselz hi&#xD;
krost dvur and kdm in bihaind ae siti and bisi'jd&#xD;
it. And hi ardd hiz gunz agent it, bda from 'ae&#xD;
land said and from ae wotur, and rand upon it a&#xD;
storm  ov fair bai do and bai nait.  Aid Da~k&#xD;
Pepurkorn, hil stud wocin upon ae wblz, woz in-&#xD;
dignant, and hi priperd tu difend himself ta&#xD;
last.&#xD;
&#xD;
CA PTUR XIII.&#xD;
&#xD;
IN MAGNUS had nou plst DaTk Smua-&#xD;
anik$ in cirj og ae l6ur rijunz ov cre&#xD;
lFiurwotur, and Ferigift and      poP&#xD;
wer dvUr ae gips. And bikbz Hlorntosur&#xD;
w oz brv and derin, and woz n{iUr tim&#xD;
urus laik Mikraki nor infleksibl laikour-&#xD;
ninibrand, hi apointed him t hi kud ot&#xD;
o     n istr Armi, and t6ld him tn i i  kudrot&#xD;
pk sum ov e feurz from cre krest oveBdrohiz&#xD;
i len Iorntosur put himself at re h    f6r&#xD;
.         ad hi sent of DIak St6niman wi&#xD;
wnoho ra"men tu raid nrd Vurjinlad, and to&#xD;
Snz doun ce brijez, and tu let leis ae canelz ov&#xD;
wotor-fludz, and tu dag around   e wl hi&#xD;
e moU    and crus distract hiz enemiz, lwail hi&#xD;
Riacmantoun, a    s     min front And on ae&#xD;
w  hiz h61 kdrmi Rass(a em i  rne-     t at&#xD;
sekun  d ov ce Meri mi;n ae tuarmz met&#xD;
sekln    -v and a had a hot and bludi bati ov&#xD;
Cten d zy O  ce furst ad ov ae fait sum ov aet i&#xD;
s6ljurz bikdn konfizd, and s sPetur  a himself&#xD;
talui  a.lu  zc6fe     hk1C3udisilplest himself&#xD;
in flr   ut azaed I -' bId. wi won hand .and&#xD;
in ar pa, brandiin  i u   And hi dr6v crem&#xD;
ha adcr6 gtentr in ai uar.n e aundurin lijunz&#xD;
' ba, adEa tornd agen upon(e&#xD;
&#xD;
p 4  {''7&#xD;
jij;jI&#xD;
f; f,&#xD;
,iE&#xD;
.7&#xD;
1 k&#xD;
a&#xD;
&#xD;
'u a,'&#xD;
i  ti  ,'&#xD;
'  i&#xD;
,4 '&#xD;
#&#xD;
t fi '&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
'i ;;&#xD;
ii i,&#xD;
I'&#xD;
'&#xD;
f,&#xD;
',.&#xD;
!&#xD;
S.&#xD;
i  {&#xD;
Yi&#xD;
s&#xD;
.&#xD;
i  ! i&#xD;
f''&#xD;
't '&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="84-85" xml:id="VAC5911-00000043"/>&#xD;
84             B~p     Saah-&#xD;
ov St6nijak, and fot til ae sun went doun, and&#xD;
gcn ue batl went on bai munlait. And a silescal&#xD;
wocur aat woz lukin out from bihaind ae silver&#xD;
lainin ov a kloud, lwen hi so upon ae banurz&#xD;
ov Horntosur ae nm ov ae gud Fridima, and&#xD;
pursivd aat hur kbz woz in ddnjur, stept doun&#xD;
upon ae pldn hwer ae fait woz aikest, and urd&#xD;
a vdl 6vur (i aiz ov ae men aat fold Stdnijak-&#xD;
And ad kud not si ie fis ov abr lidur distinkt-.&#xD;
i, and hi apird, tu aem laik a Friddnian, and ad&#xD;
leveld aer longturz and p6rd ar fair upon him,&#xD;
and hi fel doun and daid.     Oe nekst morning&#xD;
Bdldrobin rind ae batl, and hurld hiz koluinz&#xD;
fotriusli agenst ae. Frid6nian ranks. But Horn-&#xD;
tosur put forward ae Beriin Dnk and ae Burnin&#xD;
Da ck tu rizist him, and a dvuerkdm him, and kuv-&#xD;
urd ae ground wia hiz ded. And B"eriin bD c&#xD;
himself woz slin. And aer fel ov ae Dragnianz&#xD;
(tin aouzand men ; and  ov ae Friddnianz fiftin&#xD;
aouzand.&#xD;
And Horntosur woz trubld bikbz hi kud not&#xD;
hir ae huf bits ov St6nimanz horsez, for as wer&#xD;
nou far awd; and hi sed, Peradvencur hi haz met&#xD;
wia dizastur.  And hwail hi weted and tisd tii&#xD;
kac ai eko ov hiz trampin, ae kloudz ddrknd and&#xD;
a gret storm ov rdn fel from ae skai, and ae&#xD;
Rapidrun and Rapidnokin rivurz kdm aundurin&#xD;
doun from  ae mountenz, on hiz rait and hiz left,&#xD;
and aretnd tu engulf him in abr torents. And&#xD;
hwen hi so ac fludz aat wer raizin around him, hi&#xD;
fird aat hiz lain ov ritrit wud bi kut of; s6 hi&#xD;
&#xD;
-jadra hiz drmi, and ad riturnd dripig and doun-&#xD;
kast tu Fo1nmoua and rested aer.&#xD;
Prins Jefur woz non ildted, and hi tuk counsel&#xD;
"     Dragun and sed, ([is iz ae taim for us tu&#xD;
vi our strenna for ae koronen de ov Fridima&#xD;
z at hand, and  e Normen Ar priperin to sele-&#xD;
brt it wi pomp and rijoisin sue az woz nevur&#xD;
For cd hav ripndiited our alaians forever,&#xD;
n hav olredi idd aer planz for mariin Fridim&#xD;
P rins kwoliti, hd aspairz tu re suvurenti&#xD;
ov aIOrient, and hwen ae ynyun iz efekted ce&#xD;
tuge u  riei    cr   wurild.  But let  us  pul  out  ce&#xD;
tuge from undur iniz fain erkaslz, and put a stop&#xD;
ti arz - korondgun ddz, and turn Qbr holidz and&#xD;
-c-e inoz intu m6rnful wlinz and bitur tirz.&#xD;
For ioisr wel bl tu send our armiz intu Nor-&#xD;
land and wi wil tdk pozegnf ov   abr kin and hiz&#xD;
kanptal and ae sitiz and tounz and stronh6ldz gal&#xD;
lapi ,  dts at our apr6c, and bl ce g6ld and sil-&#xD;
ur ov re land gal bi ourz.    For Pins Jefur&#xD;
had s kret events in Bruursiti and G6aam, and&#xD;
s rt tounz, hd stud wdtin tu 6pn ae gdts;&#xD;
ad olso dnjurns serpents, klad K6braz, tu hi let&#xD;
is upon  e pip1 ov ic siti az fast az ae Drag6-&#xD;
nian 4rmi kdm on.&#xD;
And  e Dragun apruvd ov Prins Jefurz plan,&#xD;
nd c sent ordurz ta B6ldrobin, tu pres forward,&#xD;
and cr wud giv him az meni sdljurz az hi nd-&#xD;
ed And wc6 ggacrd    ar f6rsez from  ai ist and&#xD;
west, and cre woryurz wer laik l6kusts for mul-&#xD;
titad, and abr gado dirknd ae land.     And ae&#xD;
&#xD;
j ~&#xD;
&#xD;
f "&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="86-87" xml:id="VAC5911-00000044"/>&#xD;
,r atx~  Thaj  xdbn.&#xD;
&#xD;
tuk up cer lain ov mire fbr ae kinz pales, but&#xD;
Horntosur stud in aer paa and prevented iem-.&#xD;
So ae dru. of trd  e west, and went bai wd ov&#xD;
e mountenz ard ae Lafingap and      9ainind'r-&#xD;
And ae krost ae Boundarimiark rivur and enturd&#xD;
intu (e Penwud valiz, plundurin and distroiin az&#xD;
ae went.&#xD;
And ae Normen sh (at ae taim ov aer sdr&#xD;
traial woz kum; for if ae kud not bit bak ae&#xD;
viktdrius lijunz ov Sunland ac must bikum (er&#xD;
bondmen and serv aem forever. And e Pen-&#xD;
wudianz sent in hst for helpurz tu  b  i rijun&#xD;
round about; and ae kin kbld upon ae rdilrz ov&#xD;
(e provinsez tu lend Qer dd and r61 bak ae tail&#xD;
ov invdjun.  And hi sent of ordurz tu hiz ips&#xD;
and woryurz aat wer upon ai isturn 96r tu sn&#xD;
up are rivurz  and atak ae Dragun in hiz rir.&#xD;
Glen Jefur woz grdtli alkrmd and sent of in hest&#xD;
tu kl bak B6ldrobin, but it woz tdi l6, for hi&#xD;
woz nou far up in the Pen wud hilz.&#xD;
And sevn dz bif6r korondun ds ce kin sent&#xD;
for Dnk Huniwotur, and gdv him kormand ov&#xD;
i arrmiz, and cirjd him tu miv wdrili and tu&#xD;
brin B6ldrobin intu hiz sner, and bai nd minz&#xD;
sufur him  tu eskdp and riturn tu hiz mistur.&#xD;
And DCtk Huniwotur pursivd aat te strugi wud&#xD;
bi despuret and bludi; and hi silekted "e val ov&#xD;
Deusburg  for hiz batl filed, and  mir ald hiz&#xD;
h6sts on Sepulkur hil, soua ov Cae siti, and iV&#xD;
ordurz tu hiz cffs aat if (e' -seni woryur turn&#xD;
hiz bak tu ae fd, ae penalti gud hi instantorna&#xD;
&#xD;
And Boldrobin, si (Xe p14s hi had silekted, mid&#xD;
hiz wd tu  e ssm spot, and tk pozegn ov (est&#xD;
hilz on 1e nor, and ai 6kn rijez on (e wst,&#xD;
li - vn lead/z  ardi a  klasik  ibuti ovur  ae  pisful&#xD;
hdz ivnn 9 aiur hi brbt biz infantri, and hiz&#xD;
ve.li and hiz   rtllri, a hundred and fifti great&#xD;
g  n,  d field ae wudz wi, hiz worlaik ar.&#xD;
And on ae furst de ov (e muna Jdius (e ati&#xD;
Fan.For B6ldrobinf woz a kgs tu    i    hi&#xD;
big d  p  ov  luniwotur had ol kum up;i so&#xD;
hosted and put forward Dnk Erlistrt, h    e&#xD;
-1e upon (e Frid6nian bandz aat wer n a&#xD;
vans ov re rest, and kapeurd about ar aouzand&#xD;
en.    Ule nest dd  e kontest woz rinu  wi&#xD;
men.       fi   and ae kanun p6rd    er aurn&#xD;
storl grun e Round tops and Granit spurz ov&#xD;
storpk  hil and tar ard ae wudi aikets ov ae&#xD;
Wulvz' mounten ; and ai nrtluri ov  e -Normen&#xD;
pdld and splintrd  i .dncent Oks binma 11vc ae&#xD;
nhad tdkn 9eltur.            And ae d&#xD;
6robinhd had led   Xe asolt Upon Sepulkur&#xD;
hl, riturnd tu aer cif hwen (e sun went ou,&#xD;
lt and tu risiv ordurz for (e morn.&#xD;
to kons  . (at -(Xe nest dd wud hi (e turn&#xD;
point ov vittoi or difft, and az cis bati went&#xD;
p(inXd bilv  wud turn e forcun ov ae wor. And&#xD;
about midnait (e Blak Dragun, having her&#xD;
Cati    and biin rouzd tu an unwanted pic ov&#xD;
eksaitment, left hiz pales and glaided alone  (Xe&#xD;
saimen X nt ui hi riot ae kamp ov hiz&#xD;
s ienso; and  iinfzd inta ai ofisurz and s01-&#xD;
&#xD;
86&#xD;
&#xD;
i&#xD;
&#xD;
87&#xD;
&#xD;
41&#xD;
&#xD;
iit&#xD;
&#xD;
C   r r   C '    i "&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="88-89" xml:id="VAC5911-00000045"/>&#xD;
jurz b1 ae vairus ov hiz necur, and miglin wie&#xD;
ac ranks hi brifrd upon an hiz poiznus and in..-&#xD;
toadar nzbrea, until aer aiz glisnd laik dimunz&#xD;
fanirA   n    arobd Wi ae hit ov an unerali&#xD;
fair. And aaet dnin vpr at got from hiz nlos-&#xD;
trilz fil  ae tent hwi           an   hiz dks&#xD;
.edri.kin   vain, inspairin aem  Wia ae lust&#xD;
ov venjans.  And Daik Yelwel rdzd hiz hand&#xD;
and svor wia a bludi a aat on ae mor hi&#xD;
wud kut iz we intu ae hirt ov ae Frid6nian&#xD;
.            1mi or intu ai infernal rjunz. And ae rest ap&#xD;
d him and routed dmen.&#xD;
Wia a  d~n  v dc e despuret strugi Wvuns&#xD;
mrl bigan.  And B6ldrobin     ektd Yewwnst&#xD;
atak and brk ae rait win o  ae Frid6nian irmi&#xD;
and aus priper ae wd for ai dvurhwelin asolt&#xD;
hwie hi had rizervd for      r&#xD;
did not suksid, and after hi uouzand ov Yez yer-&#xD;
yurz had bin smitn d oun tu ae ground hi si-&#xD;
enli gaapurd up ae remnant and wiadrd. .     e&#xD;
langur ov bat[ nou s'st and 61 woz kam  and&#xD;
kwaiet az a sumur si. But Bdldrobin woz sikret-&#xD;
li konvin hiz grdt gunz around are ae forest from&#xD;
ae nora tu ae west, hwer hi ekspekted tu mek&#xD;
hiz vikturi 9pr. And ae Xormen wer jo      n&#xD;
lait ov hart, for ad had nd at o ae teril stand&#xD;
aat woz tu fbl upon aem er ae dd kldzd. And&#xD;
ae gaaurd around aer kamp fair, and brekfasted,&#xD;
and sat doun upon ae gras, and med aemselvz&#xD;
meri, and san soz. And ae wurda h '       suz&#xD;
wer aiz:&#xD;
&#xD;
Osami'z a s6ljr in ai semi ov ae Lord,&#xD;
1Hz s61 iz martin on.&#xD;
Osamiz napsak iz strapt upon hiz bak,&#xD;
Hiz s6l iz marci on.&#xD;
Osamiz musket gdz fairin awd,&#xD;
Hiz s61 iz marc on.&#xD;
Osamiz pet lamz wil mit him on ae wd,&#xD;
Az ad g6 mirein on.&#xD;
Nonu arfcirz for Samukl and Fridima,&#xD;
Az wi g6 mircin on.&#xD;
(Ie soxnz had daid awd, and ae midd4 ourz went&#xD;
pisfuli bai, ontil ae belz in ae tourz ov Deasburg&#xD;
strUk a', henlsudenli ai 6kn hilz wer 01 aflem,&#xD;
adkot a1, hg1 igan tu skrim ardi ai r, and ae&#xD;
fild wia flain nisilz hrin dea&#xD;
h601 atmosfir woz           --NT&#xD;
on abr wilnz and swipin ard ae kamp ov ae   of&#xD;
men.   And ad started up in terry, and aer ol-&#xD;
la and rokt binia ai dvurhwelmin tempest&#xD;
omz i'                     Undo aedgiiovfhd&#xD;
from hwie ar woz    6 eskp.udura        t ov h&#xD;
aat fli hai above hz lied, IDnk Iailand woz sin ka-&#xD;
ririn akros ae vali, fol6d kl6sli bai Lonstep and&#xD;
ae hevi batalyynz ov Dak Stedidrm. And hwen&#xD;
ad had riot ae fut ov Sepulkur hil, aer woz a l&#xD;
in ae fairin, and 16, ae Drag6nianz wer asendin&#xD;
ae hilsaid and advansin wia flaiin banurz tu ae&#xD;
cAj. At ais instant a gadd simd tu pas dvur ae&#xD;
sin, and 'ae Normen lukt up and sb a tourii&#xD;
&#xD;
}a&#xD;
&#xD;
Osamiz bodi laiz mn61durnin Qo grey',&#xD;
1hz s61 iz mrci     on.&#xD;
&#xD;
88&#xD;
&#xD;
89&#xD;
&#xD;
R T&#xD;
-laffUt'S A' Talifirba.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="90-91" xml:id="VAC5911-00000046"/>&#xD;
90&#xD;
&#xD;
form, wi a dim outlain, havi ai apiras ov a&#xD;
ain lait kloud, and 94pt aftur ae similitad ov a&#xD;
man, but ov kolosal magnitid. Its fit apid u&#xD;
rest upon ae ngeunz kapital, hwail its hed eksten.&#xD;
ded up intu ae bln skai, and woz surounded wia&#xD;
a hdlo ov wundrus bati. Don its brost fldd a ion&#xD;
silvuri bird. Its ]on and bdni rait arm, ari hwic&#xD;
ae suez rez 96n fibli, woz street out tdrdz aoa&#xD;
nora, and held in its grasp (e rizemblans ov a&#xD;
s6ljurz musket, from ai end ov hwie fidd a zigzag&#xD;
strim ov ilektrisiti, pointin dounwurdz, laik a be&#xD;
yunet, in ae direkgun ov ae Drag6nian h6st. (e&#xD;
et arm ekstended far aws tu ae sonaw rest, point-&#xD;
in wia a Ion p6l, skersli dizernab], tdrdz ae lofti&#xD;
spairz ov ae Wiked siti qat 16 on ae banks ov  e&#xD;
Faaurwotur. For a moment ae sdlj urz stud g'zi'&#xD;
in wundur at ais _strinj spektakl; aen taooren&#xD;
raid out simultdniusli,  It iz  e gdst ov Osami,&#xD;
wia hiz musket and hiz paik"! And ce wurd fla&#xD;
from rank tu rank, and sun a gout for Osami and&#xD;
Fridima tor rae welkin laik ae burstin ov a aouz-&#xD;
and aundurz.   And ae hirts ov ae woryorz gru&#xD;
furm az adamant, and ai flektrik kurent ran alone&#xD;
caer nervz, hirdnin crem intu still. And as fist ev-&#xD;
uri man hiz b6yunet, in laik manur az s had sin&#xD;
upon ace skai, and dagt agenst abr enemiz wia a&#xD;
fnn aat numnkud rizista&#xD;
fari rat nuain kud rizist.  Doun went hors and&#xD;
raidur ; doun went arrmz and banurz.  (lIe Lunz&#xD;
ov Stedirm wvurd for a moment, and cen drop&#xD;
on cer iz, hwail ae vikturz swept dvur aem, and&#xD;
r6ld ard rae vali az ce surjez ov ci 69un r61 hwea&#xD;
&#xD;
I&#xD;
&#xD;
taid and tempest boa pres aemi on. And B6ldrob-&#xD;
in, hwen hi sb ae magnitnd ov hiz -dizastur, hisnd&#xD;
and got him up intu ae mountenz, and gaaurd ae&#xD;
remnants ov hiz Armi, and slun: awd wia hiz mas-&#xD;
tur ae Dragun tu ae pl4s from hwens ad6 kdm.&#xD;
And ae sdm d- Duk Pepurkorn kdm out from&#xD;
as wblz. ov Wikebrg, and prizented himself tu&#xD;
Dak Granit. And hi gdv him    ae ki ov ae siti,&#xD;
and surendurd hiz woryurz, aurti aouzand in&#xD;
number, and ti. hundred grdt, gunz wia -hwic tu&#xD;
salt ae stiri banur ov Fridima on ae korondgun&#xD;
noro.&#xD;
&#xD;
91&#xD;
&#xD;
f&#xD;
1   1 f&#xD;
}&#xD;
&#xD;
00&#xD;
&#xD;
N'Taglivs TP4,rho&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="92-93" xml:id="VAC5911-00000047"/>&#xD;
93&#xD;
&#xD;
t~ft bu&#xD;
&#xD;
CAPTUR XIV.&#xD;
&#xD;
LOURIN and ghtmi, ae Blak Dragun ri-&#xD;
enturd hiz pales and sumund Prins Jefur.&#xD;
And   hi tdld him ov b ae dizasturz raat&#xD;
a had bifbln aer kbz, and hou hi had sin e&#xD;
gdst ov Osami, and had found a silescal&#xD;
wordurz huvurin round ce "banurz ov Fri-&#xD;
dima, and aat hi dind it ydsles tu kari&#xD;
on (e wor in hirnan waiz eni longer. Hi cen&#xD;
propozd  tu telegraf tu hiz four, hi livd in&#xD;
ai uaur planet aat woz l6ur doun, and rikwest&#xD;
him  u giv aem dd. But for ais purpus it wud&#xD;
bi nesesari aat Prins Jefur gud giv himself up&#xD;
and olsd hiz principal ciftenz, tu bi entairli und-r&#xD;
huz fdaurz kontr6l, and to alou e mesenjurs ov&#xD;
hiz faur tu entur into aem and mik nem ai in-&#xD;
struments ov  abr wil, tm wurk out abr objects in&#xD;
aer dn we. And bl cre instruments hwid hiz fi-&#xD;
aur mait ydz tu kari out hiz purpusez must band&#xD;
gemselvz bai a frm    obligegun nevur tu diz-&#xD;
ert or rinouns hiz servis, but tu obs him in b1&#xD;
ains and olwez. And Prins Jefur kounseld wict&#xD;
Lord Judas and hiz uaur advaizurz, ha wer at&#xD;
furst du tu baind aemselvz, but fainali konsent-&#xD;
e. (len cre sent a telegram tu ae Red Dragun&#xD;
&#xD;
P1&#xD;
&#xD;
-       ov 10 sikret wairz cat yu-&#xD;
ov Tofet, baiimnz     Ad    e.rto     ae Red&#xD;
"atel i10ti planets.  And ae0.hairt ov o    e&#xD;
halted ae tupae,.g                    esfrn&#xD;
a oz nvd wi kompagun for ae sufuri.    .&#xD;
Do h    v   and hi sent of spidili a lijun ov ma-&#xD;
hgnant spirits t rendur tu ai eradw ehu'z ae se&#xD;
vis ad asstanS ca6 nided. And (16 kinbiat&#xD;
vis and asis             -   Jef. and hiz min-&#xD;
and  wer  introdist  t 1 Prins  Jefulte  and  adn jd&#xD;
istrz;andhaen (16 had konsulted, and   rnd&#xD;
Cer panztu  ncual satisfakgn, as ivaided cem-&#xD;
ivr plantu b   , and went out tu silekt abr in-&#xD;
stleit. bAnd, itwoz agrid aat sum ov aerm&#xD;
stuments.inu    G6aamaits, and inogurdt a pan-&#xD;
gud enter intu ae siti; uarz wer tu vizit foren&#xD;
intriz and aur up dd menz kl iz and bl sorts&#xD;
onplngz and poiznz and bri. am 6vur and&#xD;
ovpleg ad  distroi i inhabitants ov ae land;&#xD;
skar  abrod tu  n   (n 1  woturz  and  burn  ae  siti;&#xD;
aauz swer tu     rosid ti Sndland, and fdniii&#xD;
and se nbwer tposrz ov pis, kari on ae wor&#xD;
S emsenz ov spaiz and murdururz hd kud strain&#xD;
b   inz o   n   cre m6st despuret ov aeo  wer&#xD;
pioided.   nfenal maginz bay hwic a   mait&#xD;
pitrovaice ki min   ales and hiz kounselurz in&#xD;
cro beifbu z pe cif ov aiz woz Gaif bks, a&#xD;
drbeacnburz.  a f  r 63 ndurtuk t b16 up ae&#xD;
diimen h- in a formoBla  hiz daiaboikal kontraiv&#xD;
panienbut fBld; hi had nou gr6n waizur in hiz&#xD;
ansez,but fdld;  u tu train hiz hand VulS nd.r.&#xD;
kraft and woz ankge9US t  ae  A m-    oworfer&#xD;
Ue furst ekshibigoa ov   he   a sdn o v or&#xD;
i Gab  dsnon hwic  a skwd n ov&#xD;
fiSpirits med caer disent about ae midov    o&#xD;
I~l spn&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="94-95" xml:id="VAC5911-00000048"/>&#xD;
94&#xD;
&#xD;
ATITh J~ir.&#xD;
&#xD;
mtnrr J'lins.  And (1 siti wozsw&#xD;
K6braz bisin out asi venun;     snd  ei od wig&#xD;
Grnailurz wer bitn bai (erand    z     w&#xD;
gem, and az aa:t wer b~it&#xD;
went mad, and ran hiarr and hi.ar, burnir houz-&#xD;
ezand stonn ae wocurz ov ae siti. And hwen&#xD;
ever  e so -eni ov ae Ku anz cga&#xD;
stdnd crem  wi st6nz, andgb tem   wicasklu&#xD;
and hun tem up in are strits, and hakt and hnd&#xD;
aem in pisez and burnd (em. And te cif rilr,&#xD;
huz nemin woz Gudsmr, spsk kainkdli tu ie di.&#xD;
momiaks and krmfurted aem; and crd routed for&#xD;
Gudsimur and iB6ldrobin, and for Prins Jefur and&#xD;
ae Dragun, and cer goutinz and raiutinz izo nna..&#xD;
ed arinu ae siti for Iri dez.  And hwen ce kinz&#xD;
ofisurz wer awer ox it, crd sent cer irmed bandz&#xD;
tu asist ae wocurz, and   '6 s^ an       e&#xD;
. , ae sU and disperst aec&#xD;
men intu hdm ae find had ent            .&#xD;
ented, and r"1cikverd&#xD;
ae siti, cat it mait agen bikum a sif abdd for&#xD;
hnman inhabitants.&#xD;
And cd eat km    up from ale Iar planet brot&#xD;
wia cem   paturnz ov ae priznz and tenplhouzez&#xD;
in Helha, her      e Rd D- -&#xD;
n elham, h wercRedlragun rizaided. And&#xD;
aer woz a femus tempi rat stud on ae 96r kold&#xD;
Nstrond, aat iz bai interpretieun Deastrand, cec&#xD;
wlz ox hwic wer bilt ov adrz.   ee fsez ov  lz&#xD;
serpents wer turnd inward, and from acbr mouaz&#xD;
i9ud strimz or poizn, formin a nivr' cat Ildd ard&#xD;
ae vast strukcur.  Kwin Hela woz tie&#xD;
. .a      ,   ."oz                 eBodes aat&#xD;
pnizaided ovur it, and woct ae priznurz sent tu&#xD;
hur for sif kipig,  le ardh upon hwic gi sat woz&#xD;
angwie ; hur tdbl woz famin; hur atendants wer&#xD;
&#xD;
i&#xD;
' j&#xD;
p pj }'&#xD;
ii    (&#xD;
I&#xD;
it&#xD;
$+&#xD;
irr&#xD;
{,' )&#xD;
;1 ail&#xD;
fa&#xD;
t)&#xD;
Y&#xD;
&#xD;
;T 17&#xD;
&#xD;
pad  hur bed woz lines; 91&#xD;
Ekslivid and gastli p1, and hur veriluks in-&#xD;
-o            An    ered Dragon hadgi.&#xD;
spaird horur.  Ande hd                    hiz&#xD;
strikt crj tu.  Rufwild and Wurstovrkt ov hi&#xD;
m6st skilfil d inunz, (lat  e gu -oir 6 fAr ias&#xD;
a temptin Sunland on ae sem plan, sf&#xD;
prktikab, wio hwot matirialz (6 lkud faid in&#xD;
ae kontri, aad aat (s gud f1 it wif riievnri&#xD;
ov hunt won hundred wer tu b sa&#xD;
d-.WrtV                         after konsult-&#xD;
And i Rufwind and Wurstovbl, aft     rminutd&#xD;
in win Prins Jefur, silekted from  ti r   ttr&#xD;
Drag6nianz 1at wer admirable adaptedt ier pua-&#xD;
us, wun ov him  woz a jenural an     dizu and&#xD;
fizigun. And jae tuk pozegun ov asr bodiz and&#xD;
- -n fazd aemselvz mitu    ezne       .&#xD;
spirits, andiv~              t     e sm uil.&#xD;
o lnd  zest bikdm  wun an  a       . --&#xD;
pozesr u  po           rcnts under Prins&#xD;
And cdoed  aer  furst  eksper  e  d  ie  pa&#xD;
.6      ,- at Riemntoun, hwer          . fited up&#xD;
LibcitiP~l nd lu'urhous, and fild     ge v&#xD;
timz for sakrifaiz.  But hwen a sa     for  i&#xD;
had zamfl"ie'idil~ iwozi disatisfaid, forh&#xD;
frhad ez amind u  ll e ..do -unz for (Le&#xD;
s   ad wer skersli ikwal tu ce    njn rin&#xD;
ucanz hiwic wer blt bai aer on pip -diet Prins&#xD;
Jefur advaizd wib (e dimnlz,   s ov Deastrim,&#xD;
pls1 kbld Dedmansvil, on ce baasim og Deielaz&#xD;
hwer s abt ad kud prods a    taksi  ound,&#xD;
l6 Rufwid                arkt o.t hiz g&#xD;
6n pales.                 kolek tedob l a  dr&#xD;
and dr    hiz dedlain, and  o   bi  i aUi&#xD;
and ratlsnskst hi kud fand, ad - wod   sp in&#xD;
tuae 10 l, wic a cbr fesez lukin inwurd, s  cat&#xD;
&#xD;
95&#xD;
&#xD;
'  1&#xD;
!  4 .&#xD;
,;&#xD;
ii&#xD;
1t  _&#xD;
i,&#xD;
e&#xD;
.E   '&#xD;
'i&#xD;
,.&#xD;
H&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="96-97" xml:id="VAC5911-00000049"/>&#xD;
00   t1fl jri f x&#xD;
&#xD;
ad mait pdr aer venum  upon Ge recez kongrigs-&#xD;
ted wiain.  And hi had houndz Laik ae houndz&#xD;
ov Hela birkin round about, redi tu siz and tar&#xD;
eni aat gud atempt tu eskip.   And hwen Ruf-&#xD;
wind had komplited ae wbl, hi lukt upon it wia&#xD;
a dilaited kounteians, and laft for joi, and sed&#xD;
hi wud bi ov mur serves tu Prins Jefur aan 61&#xD;
ai drmiz ov B6ldrobin. And a kbt aurti aouz-&#xD;
and Frid6nianz and dr6v aem inta Gi enkldjur,&#xD;
and Rufwind    stript aem  ov aer k]dain, and&#xD;
Wurstovol, he woz a   doktur, tuk cirj ov aer&#xD;
fad and medisin.   S6 hi gdv aen stdrvyd'rn for&#xD;
aer mit, and poizn for aer drink. And Ge poizn&#xD;
went doun intu aer bled, and field aem wia pntrid&#xD;
sorz, and ae l rotin in fila and vermin until ae&#xD;
steno spred dvur ae h61 rIjun, and woz b6rn on&#xD;
ae windz til it riot ae noraurn hilz and enturd ae&#xD;
nostrilz ov Samunkl.   And Wurstovol mingidn&#xD;
wia hiz. medisinz sum sikret cirm, bai hvi hi&#xD;
drd out ae fie9 from  under ae skin ov hiz priz.&#xD;
nurz, s6 aat ae b6nz hun lusli az in a bag, and&#xD;
as mivd and toturd in a manor aat woz hor-&#xD;
ibl tu bih6ld. And ae doktur wud msk ae skel&#xD;
etunz get up and dans bif6r him for hiz aniiz-&#xD;
ment, and hwen ae kud not raiz hi wud aretn&#xD;
aem  Wia nu torments until ae did. And ae pdr&#xD;
krieurz bikim dilirius, and ae fbt wiG ic uaur,&#xD;
and dizaird tu dai, but kud not, for Wurstovbl&#xD;
woz kerful tu prizerv aer laivz until  e taim for&#xD;
sakrifaizin Gan  tu hiz mAstur.  (e number Gat hi&#xD;
sakrifaizd woz fiftin aouzand, and a uaur fiftin&#xD;
&#xD;
00&#xD;
&#xD;
touzand hi kept alaiv az subjekts for hiz eksperi-&#xD;
ments.&#xD;
en      .mnZat went intu Sndland tuk poz-&#xD;
And aedimon  aat  el 6bra, and naor ser-&#xD;
egnn ov Sandadur and        k  ,an umsri sto&#xD;
pentainl nicurs,  ad  e sent of Grinhilz and tu&#xD;
brik 6pn  fe g61d voltz    i  ae  nditu kapeur&#xD;
burn ae siti ov G6aam wi fair,a         and tu&#xD;
Rickdrg6 and Baisntoun   and Swainasiti, ad&#xD;
ht a paa ard Ge midst ov Kin. Magns' donin&#xD;
yunz and. sever ae west from       sut . iand. a&#xD;
h6st ov rfanz wer sturd up aru siondulan,&#xD;
adt apointed  Vandalihamr, and  Swipendulum,&#xD;
and Lonk6bra for aer lid g, a  aturit wtr&#xD;
ov  Arrez, and  ltra swein and touring wurdzb&#xD;
and imajind Gat WIG abr n tabe    a Drag6nian&#xD;
bl tu dip6z ae kin and estb9&#xD;
.aatihiz,       ud bi purpeCual.&#xD;
ainasti hdz ren      and b iz kounselurz and ae&#xD;
And hwen    e k and.G biud and kirnej, and&#xD;
Waiz men ov ae lnds1a             -b aizand&#xD;
GO blak  undur-loudz garndciftenz oBia&#xD;
pursivd os6 Gat Ge prinsez anwifenDinoianz&#xD;
and .Galia wer in sikret  ge wivz and&#xD;
and hwen ad herd e wh    z ovi   Dedmandi&#xD;
nufarz ov a6Z aat wer pent upd ini edarbr-&#xD;
Gd wer filed wiG biturnes an  gron iy ae bur-&#xD;
dnz  nd rsposibilitiz.  And. wun ov GOwai&#xD;
anz and risponsiiii.-        kla Tribnnosofvr,&#xD;
men ov G6aam hi aat woz       ldku,&#xD;
rdt tu ue kin and t61d him G1t ae ppIs in&#xD;
on"gr endnr Ger soroz, and ;,lat hi must in sum&#xD;
w6 endevur tu mdk pis WiG     e Dragn  bf6r it&#xD;
gud bi wurs wie aem aan it woz.        IGr&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="98-99" xml:id="VAC5911-00000050"/>&#xD;
98              &amp;amp;   m   W  sh.&#xD;
advaizd ae ki a at bai wd ov 96in ae Dragun dr"&#xD;
onor andnsekt  hgd b-1d'&#xD;
onur and rispekt, hi    ud bu1d for him   a bri'&#xD;
kuvurdi wig6ld, and invait him tu wbk awe&#xD;
upon it, and pas ovur tu sum uaur 96r; and&#xD;
hadgon ovur, ae brij    ud bi brdkn&#xD;
up, and ae g6ld givn tu him bai wdt,, akordin&#xD;
tu ae royal standard, twenti aouzand gekelz twenty&#xD;
aouzand taimz told. But ae  ,ropozal fd   ti&#xD;
-     epropozl    d dt uin-&#xD;
dikot a spot hwer ai uaur end ov "e brij mait&#xD;
rest, and ae ki  nn aat ae Blak Dragun woz to&#xD;
sagecus tu mare of intu ae si wiaout bn gir&#xD;
ov obtenin a solid futin in sum u     -ur - j i&#xD;
said; hi a't0ae Dragun had kost ae kuntri enuf&#xD;
olredi, wiaout ofurin him  eni furaur bountiz.&#xD;
And Sandador and hiz asdcidts, hd wer ful or&#xD;
sutlti, rdt t tae Tribinosofur tu intursid for gen,&#xD;
and proknr aem an bdiens wia ae kin.    And ad;&#xD;
invaited him tu vizit aem in Sndland tu help for-&#xD;
wurd ae wurk ov pis and kompromaiz, s6 aat bl&#xD;
mait bi harmonius agen az bif6r; for as nn aat&#xD;
bun an onest man hi. woz unsuspigus ov gail in&#xD;
vaurz, and aerf6r wud bi ae m6r izili entangld&#xD;
in aer snerz. For biin ankgus aat evuri ain in ae&#xD;
ydnivers gud bi gud and plezant, and ful ov bin-&#xD;
evolens laik himself, hi woz Ida tu billy aat ivl&#xD;
egzisted in eni wurld eksept hwer hi sh it wia&#xD;
hiz aiz; and hi kud not bi purswdded ait fa&#xD;
Blak Dragun had a fdaur, or at      aer woz eni&#xD;
Red Dragun, hii livd in a l6ur sfir and sent out&#xD;
hiz emisariz on erandz ov miscif. Hi aerf6r did&#xD;
not hezitdt ti aksejt ae invitsgun oy ae daiaboli-&#xD;
&#xD;
99&#xD;
an;, and  ia  ld kz purmi un went tI vizit em.&#xD;
E, 5pzii   -our ov ae0 n6gunz agoni woz nai,&#xD;
hd sited   eiselvz on ae brink ovf ae Naiagoni&#xD;
katarakt, and wer dilaitin aernselvz wia gezia up-&#xD;
on its iejezov distruk9un. And hwen ae so ae&#xD;
Tibinmoofejez opr     smaild upon him  agra-&#xD;
i  b    a   p  lizd  wia  a r  smi a  wurdz.  B t&#xD;
b.1,and h1 woz pai&#xD;
1.r;i woz ankus for him, firing lest hi mait&#xD;
ae ki.o.ngu          r     ,    .&#xD;
,     -   and bikum  a viktim tu aer dplisiti.&#xD;
b hi  sent  a  mesenj tur  to ut an  end  tu ae  kon-&#xD;
f iurens,   and  e losofur  riturnd  in  sfti  t u hiz&#xD;
h6m. And hi kontinyud tu dd ae kin gud se'-&#xD;
-s, and h'  pok  u tae1 ipl wurdz ov wizdum,&#xD;
and  enkurejda sp e m b histro n  for  a e wor,  un-&#xD;
il  (Le nBlak Drag un   ud  konsent  t u  kwit  a 0&#xD;
kuntri.&#xD;
Bti ha Blak ragon 9&#xD;
But -e v, and    Fridima had md     p ar&#xD;
B    n  t e  huteur  distres  m ait  bitaid,  n6  fur-&#xD;
auaz at hor evkompromaiz ud bi ofurd tu&#xD;
a  BakDagun, nor wud ad furnig a singl sil-&#xD;
u'o Bi1la  D oun. bri'  ae  mortifikdun  ov  hiz  di-&#xD;
vocur, o tubild a monyument for hiz grSV.&#xD;
p reur, or 1tu&#xD;
&#xD;
i&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="100-101" xml:id="VAC5911-00000051"/>&#xD;
CAPTURE. XV.&#xD;
&#xD;
101&#xD;
&#xD;
ITE RMIND at last tu krug out eafov&#xD;
ae Dragun and waip him from   ae fs o'v&#xD;
ae planet or dai in ae atemt, Kir Mag-&#xD;
nus adrest himself tu ae wor in ernest.&#xD;
And amun bl hiz jenuralz hi found nun&#xD;
ikwal tu Dak Granit; for olad aer ver&#xD;
ni loftier and mdr majestik woryurz&#xD;
in biz servis, and adz hd kud fait betur in ae&#xD;
beginning ov a bad, ier woz nd wun h stud s6&#xD;
irekt in ai end. For hi woz laik a rok in ai&#xD;
ocun aat Inks blae freur and ferur fr ae sur.&#xD;
ez aat swfp dvur it, And ae kin sent for lhim t&#xD;
kum and fait B6ldrobin, hnm   hiz uaur jenuralz&#xD;
had aloud tu slip rdi aar fingurz and eskdp af.&#xD;
tur as had konkurd him twais.&#xD;
But bif6r hi left ae rijunz ov ae Fdaurwotur,&#xD;
Dnuk Granit kli'rd ie canel ov ae Twinsi bd ce we'&#xD;
up tu ac mountenz; and hi drdy ae Drag6nianz&#xD;
out ov QaddinUk, and cst aem up tu  e top ov&#xD;
ie LukdvUr mounten, hwer as difaid him tu roc&#xD;
aem. And Horntosur woz sent tu asdl acm and&#xD;
draiv aem doun. And hi went up and fot aem&#xD;
on ae sumit, for it woz abuv at kioudz; and aer&#xD;
hi iund Grs tbrag, and hi 8truk him wig ae tip&#xD;
ov hiz horn and test him doun ae presipisez.&#xD;
&#xD;
And hi went rolin 6vur and dvur until at last hi&#xD;
fel intu Cte Cikenmokin bruk, hwic served tu kill&#xD;
hiz drdur sumhwot, and tu diminig hiz brag and&#xD;
blustur. And Brskin~brij woz wia him, and hi ol-&#xD;
s6 br6k doun and fel intu ae strim.   And D"Ik&#xD;
Granit left Qirman and Horntosur tu luk aftur&#xD;
ae br6kn fragments ov Grdtbragz 4rmi hwail hi&#xD;
went tu si fae kin.&#xD;
And ae kin risivd him wia onur, and med him&#xD;
cif kapten ov bl hiz armiz, 1st, -west, nora and&#xD;
soua; and hi kbld upon Samunkl for faiv hundred&#xD;
zjnz m6r ov freg woryurz. -And hi i9ud hiz&#xD;
StToIenz ta ae Kuganz,  bidin aem rali ndur ae&#xD;
Frid6nian flag, and fait for aemselvz and for aer&#xD;
kuntri. And ad kdm bai hundredz and bai aouz-&#xD;
andz, hwerever ae kinz invitsgnu riot aem, and&#xD;
gurli joind ae ranks ov aer dilivururz.  And ae&#xD;
grt gunz ov Samunkl bigan tu aundur and laitu&#xD;
bl round ae horaizun. And Datk Kilmdr wdvd hiz&#xD;
simitur alone ai isturn k6st, and Dlgrin, a sun ov&#xD;
ai 69un, woz sent wia gips and fltin tourz tu ed&#xD;
him in rikuvurin St6nipail kasl, and in ae kapeur&#xD;
ov C(irlztoun, ae orijinal den hwer ae rat1sneks&#xD;
wer hact;. And as sent intu ae siti abr f;miri mes-&#xD;
enjurz and abr swonpstnjelz, and baturd doun ac&#xD;
wolz ov St6nipail and m°d it a rain, but ae d:rd&#xD;
not entur it for fir ov ae serpent :aat wer kon-&#xD;
sild amun ae rocks and rubig.&#xD;
And hwen ae spring 6pnd, Dik Granit tuk up&#xD;
ae gantlet aat B6ldrobin had ardn doun, and miret&#xD;
alone. e lain ov advans aat Dditwel and Miklmaki,&#xD;
&#xD;
im%  tttts Diz, ui tl"b&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="102-103" xml:id="VAC5911-00000052"/>&#xD;
102&#xD;
&#xD;
g         al 1otba.                           103&#xD;
&#xD;
Burninbrand, Horntosur and Huniwvotur had bin&#xD;
undb1 tu foId. And hi tuk ae lain in hiz hand&#xD;
and t6Id ne ki1 hi gud not let g6 until hi riotni&#xD;
end ov it, if it tuk him b1 smurnr. And h i &#xD;
ted Fridima tu akumpani ai drmi- s       W&#xD;
alor win nem.    And hwen hi had hum    tu  e&#xD;
Waild wudz nat 1s beyond n Rapidrun rivur, h&#xD;
found ne wudz filed wia ae woryurz o, Bd1dobi,&#xD;
a  nu  and  mait  irmi, hwie nr  ldur  d 'md  in&#xD;
sibl. And ns fhird upon ne Friddnianz    im - s&#xD;
and iket, and cirjd upon lem, and fot   i  for&#xD;
tu dez. And cr wer sln and wdnded     s    r s&#xD;
about ten aouzand men. And at nait no     aid&#xD;
nianz ritaird from nae Waildwudz tu noe rago..z&#xD;
hwer ner wer fain spots of 6pn plaekonvinyont&#xD;
for faitirn.  And   ae   i drmz agen joined bati,&#xD;
and fbt for siks ddz lOngur. AndagIn omd   satl&#xD;
and proues, and 6 no sikret help e  I  hiz ki&#xD;
render him, Bddrobin woz nbl tu        nk&#xD;
furmnesDtrPr al ntok&#xD;
frmnes ov hiz antagonist. And Dpr ,esrokit&#xD;
onwurd, and krost ne Cikenominws swomps&#xD;
sat doun win hiz drmi t  bis'o     wonmps, and&#xD;
emo, in Jaik manur az hi hd bis      dd&#xD;
konkurd Wik~edborg.                   1sjd and&#xD;
konurrd&#xD;
And Fridima woz impd9ent, and    sd&#xD;
go intu ne hirt ov Sunland, and k    u no ,  e.i&#xD;
ganz tu fait for us, and Wi wil h   o   se Kur&#xD;
vikturi, and gal not hay tu beri sda ei oivr&#xD;
fanurz sdljurz, for it siknz mi tu Si no  ir&#xD;
.And aftur konsidurin hr nrik west for a da  a&#xD;
nait hi ford hiz plan and sent hur Wi ande s&#xD;
&#xD;
ct&#xD;
&#xD;
,.&#xD;
-&#xD;
.r&#xD;
.;&#xD;
Y&#xD;
J&#xD;
&#xD;
i&#xD;
&#xD;
kort tu Dak Qirman, hi woz faitih St6nijon in&#xD;
e Gorjsland, and direkted him tu asist hur, and&#xD;
tu risiv and enkurej bl ae Kuganz 9i mait brig&#xD;
him. And Qdrman klosli skriitinaizd hur kriden-&#xD;
galz, for hi woz afrid gi wud giv him trubl. But&#xD;
hwen hi sb hur kwinli b'rin, and hou majestik-&#xD;
all si unfurld ae traikulurd banur, and hou cc&#xD;
woryurz routed az gi past bif6r aem, hiz admir-&#xD;
gn woz kindld, and hi ofcrd t go hwerevur 9i&#xD;
wud point ae wd. Gen Fridima kast hur ai t6rd&#xD;
i isturn si, and 9i t6ld him at hi must kut a&#xD;
swo ard nae hdl breda ov ae Dragunz domin-&#xD;
ynz, and ber glad taidi  ov dilivrans tu ae&#xD;
wstiW skeletunz in Dedmanzvil, and swip alon ai&#xD;
69un 96r til hi kud join handz wia hiz fel6 wor-&#xD;
yrz at Riemantooun. And Dulk Qarman sed, It&#xD;
is wel; ae did iz a despuret wun, but it gal bi&#xD;
dn. And hi lifted himself up tu i okdjun, and&#xD;
hi tk a hundred aouzand woryurz in hiz tren&#xD;
and bigan hiz mare. And hi went dver ae moun-&#xD;
ten rijez, draivin ae lijunz ov St6nijon bifdr him,&#xD;
and rae ground guk binia ae trod of hiz woryurz&#xD;
az if an erakwek had bin pasin. And Dik B9-&#xD;
up6lk  ae grit Drag6nian s6ldoktur, met em am-&#xD;
u   nae Painz ov  no mounted, and abr hi woz slen.&#xD;
And hwen Stdnijon kud n6 longer stad in bat,&#xD;
Dk Naithud, a furius and despuoet voryur, gn&#xD;
naitli armor, kdm out tu mit aem, and bar abr en-&#xD;
trans intu ae Gdtsiti. And bi fbt ari batlz and&#xD;
voz diskumfited, and aer fel ov hiz w oryurz twen-&#xD;
ti aouzand men.   And hi fel bak gagr ind an&#xD;
&#xD;
F+   t&#xD;
i   .Cd&#xD;
£   f&#xD;
a:&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="104-105" xml:id="VAC5911-00000053"/>&#xD;
104&#xD;
krestfbln, and left ae spdus phnz ov Goijusland&#xD;
tu ae mersi ov ae konkurur. And hwen Dnk Qur-&#xD;
man had past ardi ae Gdtsiti, hi kut asunder h-&#xD;
lainz ov konekgun wi   ae west, and spred hiz&#xD;
Winz for ai 69un. And ai igi skrind  an  Frid1&#xD;
ma tuk hur pids in ae van, and gi put on hu&#xD;
garment ov red, wait and bln     and a lroun&#xD;
wvoz upon hur hed, and ae drurmz and trumpets&#xD;
struk up abr viktdrius anaemz bai hur said.  nd&#xD;
ie rdd gi travel woz-bijemd wie budz and blos&#xD;
umz, and hwerevur gi advencurd tu put  e s61 ov&#xD;
hur fut upon ce ground, fre9 blhmin rdzez spra&#xD;
up binfa it;- and ae sprig flourz ov  e noiurn&#xD;
prdriz spontiniusli burst fora dvur bl ae savanaz ov&#xD;
Goriusland. And c(e Kuganz kdm ont tu mit hur&#xD;
wia sonz and dansez; wict uer waivz and litl wunz&#xD;
ae krouded around hur tu kis ae frinjez ov hur&#xD;
star-spangld rdb; and niaur arts nor entrtiz kud&#xD;
turn aem bak from foldin hur. And hwen ae Dra-&#xD;
g6nianz sb e kroun aat woz upon hur hed,&#xD;
trembld and prunk from hur gdz; and aer dnks&#xD;
and prinsez kud not faind a single woryur aat der&#xD;
opoz ae marc ov ae viktdrius armi s6 Ion az ci&#xD;
woz at its hed.  And   -e vaiuri&#xD;
.           e   apuriwbiz ovDed-&#xD;
mansvil fel doun, and Wurstovbl and hiz women&#xD;
fled haur and aiaur tu sik for haidin plsez hwer&#xD;
ae mait not mit ae glans ov hur ai.&#xD;
And hwen Dak     iirman bigan tu nir ci Iden,&#xD;
and ae sound ov hiz trumpeturz rdld alon ce Sa-&#xD;
vanaz aat 14 on ae kdst, Dik ILirdihud, hd' stud&#xD;
sentinel in aat kwortur, lost hiz fortitna and hz&#xD;
&#xD;
Owan Us  alsb.105&#xD;
h"irdnes, and hiz nervz grd limp and lakes laik a&#xD;
wumanz; and hi gaaurd up hiz ijnz bal nait,&#xD;
and fled for refj tu Curlztoun. But ae muzik&#xD;
and tranpin ov ae Frid6nian rmi fol6d him aia-&#xD;
r os6l; s6 hi set fair tu ae siti and ran for hiz&#xD;
aif. And Fridima enturd ae siti and wokt ariu ae&#xD;
strits, and aic men ov Curlztoun grdi jenti and kem&#xD;
out tu salt hur; and hwen as sb hur ad6 bik m&#xD;
kaptivsted wia hr luvlines, and tuk an o6 aat&#xD;
adi wud wurgip ae Dragun n6 m6r.&#xD;
And lwen   e Dragun so aat Dak Granit had&#xD;
kl6sli at him up on wun said, and at Qiirman&#xD;
and Fridima wer presin him hard on ai uaur, and&#xD;
wud sdn kut of hiz 6nli lain ov ritrit, hi bigan&#xD;
tu prsiv aat hiz our woz at lena kum. And hi&#xD;
r6ld and raiad in agoni, and ae purspiregon gugt&#xD;
out from  binia hz glosi skslz, and hi kud get&#xD;
n6 slip at naits, and hi had spazrnz and kontor-&#xD;
gnz aat wer dredful tu bih6ld. (len Jefur and&#xD;
B6ldrobin, siin hou ace gldri ov aer aidul woz 1d-&#xD;
parted, konklinded tui liv him tu hiz fdt and Ink&#xD;
6n1i tu ae srfti ov aenselvz and ae r armiz. And&#xD;
it woz disaided aat B6ldrobin gud go out and giv&#xD;
bal tu Dak Grant, and if diffted a6 wud eaen&#xD;
abandun e pales and kapital, and mek aer we&#xD;
souaward ard ae mountenz.   S6 B6ldrobin went&#xD;
  out tu Iacet bruk, and a'er hi met hiz konkur-&#xD;
urz, and ad6 m6d doun hiz woryurz and rod bak&#xD;
and fora an1  &amp;amp;r ranks and slotura aem  wia a&#xD;
grdQt slotu .  And Da'k IHailand woz shin, and&#xD;
Yelwel woz surounded and tdkn. And B6idrobm&#xD;
&#xD;
I.&#xD;
&#xD;
Kj&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="106-107" xml:id="VAC5911-00000054"/>&#xD;
10&#xD;
&#xD;
turned hiz fds tu e mountenz, but ae kavalri ov&#xD;
Flit9erif wer on hiz trak, and hi kud turn  niar&#xD;
tu ae rait hand nor tu ae left.'" And hwen hi sb&#xD;
ai advansin Armi ov Dck Granit kldziu around&#xD;
him, hiz joujment and hiz rizu riturnd, and hi rdzd&#xD;
ue hwait banur and went out tu mit biz advur-&#xD;
sari. And hi tuk of hiz helmet and -plnmz, and&#xD;
mid hiz salut6gun and prizented Liz wepn tu Dtak&#xD;
Grant; and Dik Granit tuk him   bai ae hand,&#xD;
and ae hacet woz berid.&#xD;
And ter stil rimdnd Dnk St6niion and fort&#xD;
aouzand Drag6nian woryurz wocin o eo banks ov&#xD;
ae Firful rivur for cii aprde ov Qirrnan and Fridi.&#xD;
ma.   And hiri ov ae dizastur of B6ldrobin hi&#xD;
turnd himself tu flai, but Dntk Qrman stud in&#xD;
hiz paa; and hwen hi so aer woz nd eskdp, hi ol-&#xD;
s6 aridi doun hiz hacet at re fit ov ae konkurur,&#xD;
and ad bernd it aer. And ae sdij rz ov (e ti tr..&#xD;
miz agen bikdm bruLaurz, and danst tugeaur binia&#xD;
ae kin!z nn banur, intu ae tekscur ov hwic  e ndmr&#xD;
ov Fridima had bin inw6vn.&#xD;
And ae Dragun, hwen bi found aat B6ldrobin&#xD;
and Stdnijon had fors6kn him, bit hiz forced and&#xD;
lagt himself wir hiz til; and hiz atendants fled,&#xD;
ainkin hi wud sting himself tu dea laik a skorpiun.&#xD;
And hi disapird from hiz pales in ae nait, glaid-&#xD;
ii of intu (1e wudz tu haid himself, and hi rfturnd&#xD;
tu hdid hiz kdrt aer nd mdr. And ace kin went&#xD;
doun tu si hwot had bikum ov him, and hi found&#xD;
hiz pales emti. And hi egzamind Te dunjunz and&#xD;
cenz and ae instruments ov torcur hwic ae grizli&#xD;
&#xD;
iangagtha.               107&#xD;
tairant had left bihaind him; and hi 6pnd ac&#xD;
gdts ov fe Liburtipenz and lundurhouzez and hrot&#xD;
out, ae kaptivz.&#xD;
Nor woz Prins Jefur ta bi found at liz o&#xD;
habits9un; for on ae d hwen B6ldrobin prizen-&#xD;
ted himself tu Dfak Granit, hwic woz a h6li de, hi&#xD;
herd ae taidilz az hi sat wurgipin in a Drago-&#xD;
nian temp1, and hi rdz up hestili and fled. And&#xD;
hi went swift11 t6rd ie suaurn si, hopin tu fair&#xD;
som Bulian vesel in hwic tu mdk hiz eskep. But&#xD;
hi woz hemd in bai ae s6ljurz ov ae kin aat wer&#xD;
evuri hwer skourin ae kuntri. And hwen hi pur-&#xD;
sivd ae kds hi woz in, and had kum tu oa end&#xD;
ov hiz wits, and nl not hwot fertur t  u,  i&#xD;
rszd wun last and pitius prer tu ae fiur ov  e&#xD;
Blak Dragun ldz servant hi had bin; and   i od&#xD;
disivur kompagundted him, and o'njd him intu a&#xD;
wuman, and kiad hur wi( fimsl aparel, s6 at 91&#xD;
mait not bi n6n. But hi neglekted tu rimnv hr&#xD;
sandalz, hwic wer strop and servisabi, and hwick9&#xD;
9t tu ritin. And wun morning az gi woz wo..ki&#xD;
out wis hur miikpil upon hur arm, gi s at e&#xD;
gras woz dni, and rdzin hur dres t kip it from&#xD;
etin wet, hur sandalz wer diskuvuid bai sum&#xD;
s6jurz at wer pasin at wd. And (e aprihen-&#xD;
ded hur and bid hur konfes tu Qem hu 91 wo&#xD;
And gi wud not ansur, but t6ld aem d t t1&#xD;
bi a9d tu msk wor upon wimin. And ae s61-&#xD;
jurz wud lisn tu n6 entritiz, but i spait ov hur&#xD;
struglz karid hut of tu Qer ofisurz, bai h o&#xD;
durz gi woz lojd in a prizn.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="108-109" xml:id="VAC5911-00000055"/>&#xD;
CAPTUR XVI&#xD;
&#xD;
ae Dragdnian drmiz wer nou disban-&#xD;
ded, and ae konflikt tu b outward apir.&#xD;
akld,yet ae dfmunz stil lingrd tu&#xD;
kari out aer findi9 malevolens, and wer di-&#xD;
terinmd not tu yid az lon az aer woz a&#xD;
sing instrument left tu dd aor bidi. And&#xD;
Gaifoks, ae mdst krafti and derin ov aem&#xD;
,entur  intua Rua aat woz nir a aiatur, not&#xD;
far from  ae pales, and abr hi dd hiz planz for&#xD;
ae kinz distruk9un. For hi had brt up wia him&#xD;
from i ;naur planet an ard, hdz point had bin&#xD;
pt in ae wotr ov dea, and its gaft woz wind&#xD;
tia easfer ov sertenti. And hi sbt oportniti&#xD;
konsulted  iagenst ac bod ov ae kil. And hl&#xD;
stedwi      ai   aur emisariz or Prins Jefur,&#xD;
at wer in Norland and Sndland, and adz aat&#xD;
wer in Midiland, nir hto  croalei.     Adh&#xD;
sil ektd     -    n   tu  royal siti-   And hi&#xD;
tirekted foQ his kowurkurz .Pourfulpan  and H6s-&#xD;
io, and Mrat and Caildharuld and Sekundr&#xD;
d, and Mudpilz, and Lrfinf'nd. And Qirat in-&#xD;
vaited acn naitli tu bankwet in a sp6gus kavurn&#xD;
And a   kir z pales, hwbr  e Dragun WOz sikrited.&#xD;
aer e konkokted helbroa and fed ae Drag&#xD;
tn, and nurit hiz h                    e    r&#xD;
bi  ops cat hi mait yethlirl&#xD;
&#xD;
109&#xD;
&#xD;
Magnus Mah'rba from hiz r6n and get pozegun&#xD;
ov ae kindum.    And as mdd for aemseivz eks-&#xD;
p16siv maginz and misilz ov dea, and 9drpnd a'-r&#xD;
dagurz, and asaind to i aktur hiz pdrt In ae dra-&#xD;
ma ad wer about tu pu4 orm. For as purpust tu&#xD;
distroi ae kin and hiz lordz and Dnk Grani t bl at&#xD;
ae sdm moment, s6 aat ad mait rug intu ae pales&#xD;
amid ae konfijun and konsturndeun ov ae pip,&#xD;
and fiks ae Dragon s6 furmli upon ae ur6n uat hi&#xD;
kud not bi displdst.&#xD;
And hwail ai enemiz ov ae kin wer plotin hiz&#xD;
distrukgun, wun ov ae hevnli wocurz kdm tu him&#xD;
in a vijun ov ao nait, and punted on hiz brin, az&#xD;
hi woz slipin, a dizmal pikcur ov blud and hor-&#xD;
urz; and hwenl hi aw6k ae pikeur woz stil kir&#xD;
and distinkt. And in ae mornin hiz frendz kdI&#xD;
tu vizit him, and ad so aat hiz fds woz psl, and&#xD;
ac form  ov hiz vizej disturbd. And hi t6ld aem&#xD;
hiz drfm, and hon hi had sin an 69un ov biud,&#xD;
and himself swimin abrin.   And ae wocur aat&#xD;
had pnted ae drim had hwispurd in hiz Ir aat ac&#xD;
grdt drama woz tu kldz at ai end ov f6r yIrz&#xD;
from ae taim it bigan ; and aat ai 69un ov blud&#xD;
woz in rikwaital ov ae ronz .-dun tu a  IKuganz;&#xD;
and aat for evuri drop dron bai ae lag aer must&#xD;
bi anuaur dron bai ae sdrd; and hwotevur woz&#xD;
wontin tu mdk ae rekompens perfekt must bi kan-&#xD;
seld bai ae blud ov a kostli sakrifaiz. And ae&#xD;
kinz advaizurz went out and konsulted tugeaur&#xD;
raivetli, and sot tu understand ae drim, but ad&#xD;
kud faind nun aat woz dbl tu divain ai interprete-&#xD;
&#xD;
r I4&#xD;
i&#xD;
i       '+i&#xD;
c l1&#xD;
i&#xD;
7&#xD;
.&#xD;
'ii&#xD;
$, ri,&#xD;
S /&#xD;
',&#xD;
tl&#xD;
°ii i&#xD;
i&#xD;
'  F i&#xD;
{&#xD;
iii&#xD;
'i it  1&#xD;
i 'I,;&#xD;
&#xD;
P&#xD;
6&#xD;
fl1Y&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="110-111" xml:id="VAC5911-00000056"/>&#xD;
lit          lgrns R~hh.&#xD;
9un.   Yet a dimd it cc hrja'&#xD;
r6 pldst a stroll gird aroundareinjles hal  an&#xD;
prikbgun, and anuaur   tu woe pal     i  wd eru&#xD;
And ad kompnted rae taim    ov f' yf z  pro -&#xD;
komensment ov ae wor, he        r  iz from ag&#xD;
tdrn doun from  Stdnipail kas  and cr fouag wo&#xD;
pfriud wud end on ce fortin  v     ae ound ae&#xD;
hwie voz e     ov Gudsakrifaiz. And (sed, Let&#xD;
us mik it a glad and joiful d, and a   d forLt &#xD;
selebrigun ov pis and vikturi, and fora d  fori&#xD;
ov banurz, and for drdgunz r , and  formi ngun in&#xD;
peradvencur ae 9ad' wil          ummegunz ; and&#xD;
mind. And cd krdvd    i pas of from ac     un-&#xD;
furl ai Old banur from  prmin ov    iitui kan&#xD;
on ai aniversari ov its furstdio  Ad cri ki&#xD;
woz plizd, and gdv komand t    h   r n    , an&#xD;
on ce ivnin ov Gudsakrifaiz d'i wcry"rzpand&#xD;
banur wuns mdr wivd dv"r cre     e    rparngoldv&#xD;
and ae kanun p6rd f'ru c r je rmorekaso,.&#xD;
And go dm  vnina aer joifiul salnt.&#xD;
And r   rmwvnide rkiin woz sitin in a pIdhous,&#xD;
hw c6hdpursweded hi"m to go crat hi mat;c&#xD;
of ae burdn ov hiz kerz   Andg jut a car  t 96kr&#xD;
ae ganz arond Stdn' A'  d Just az arr y&#xD;
crce grdt arud GStnipail kasi prokldmd ce k1dzi1&#xD;
ov cre gret dr" ima, (4aif' sks and i urr fnnzl&#xD;
asisted him hdstd'-s"ndai vaTr dcim unzlhd&#xD;
akisnd  sim  Asted tu perform cer pirts in ce kon-&#xD;
hwb~sr  k  nhd cr6 rkept stelaili intu cre pldh oJus&#xD;
nrcrckin    had en turd, and az  hiind fbrwurd.&#xD;
unsuspektnl   u ozerv     aktin ov ce pldurz, ai-&#xD;
a   ant o  pointed wcr dea and wid Wa ce fe--&#xD;
acn  h  fe   ti struk- him inac bak ov hiz hed,&#xD;
ndhftl u a for unkongus.   And Gaifbks&#xD;
&#xD;
111&#xD;
&#xD;
sprang p from  bihaind ae kin, flurigin hiz dagur&#xD;
and goutin in ci frz ov b rae pipl aat hi had sldn&#xD;
a tairant. And hi lipt upon e stj, and out at&#xD;
c d6r, and woz gon. And acr sm our ov ae&#xD;
nait Pourfulpdn enturd ae csmbur ov Lord Siwor-&#xD;
dur, hd woz laiin on a sik bed, and hi sm6t him&#xD;
and wud hav kild him, but ae silescal gardianz&#xD;
ard ir gildz dvur him and worded of ae bl6z.&#xD;
And ac kinz servants rimiivd him tu a praivet&#xD;
crmbur and ldd him doun tu dai. And hiz lordz&#xD;
and ar cat luvd him, and Fridima, stud around&#xD;
hiz bed, and \voct him until are morning. And bi-&#xD;
,koz hiz vaitaliti woz strop, ae kin lingurd in hiz&#xD;
daiin, and ae bodi and spirit strgld in abr n-&#xD;
klspin. And hwen ae sunlait lukt in at ae win-&#xD;
d6, ae wiri arobi n sist; and ae kin. gv up hiz&#xD;
g6st, and it bikCm disentangld from its atacments,&#xD;
and fl6ted upward tu dwel wia ai imortalz. And&#xD;
Fridima put hur lips tu ae kinz k1d, and kist hiz&#xD;
k6ld fds, and gi sed, Alas, alas, rat aou gudst dai&#xD;
for; mi! For if aou hadst not pitid ais sordful&#xD;
caild, and. tskn hur pdrt hwen aer woz nun els&#xD;
at kud dilivur hur, ou maitest stil hay livd,&#xD;
pourful and onurd amun ne kinz ov ai era, and&#xD;
mai pur ndm  wud hav perigt from   cre memuri&#xD;
ov men. Andi i kuvurd hur fds, and p6rd for a&#xD;
hur angwig in a torent ov tirz.&#xD;
And a vois ov wdiin went up from    ae royal&#xD;
siti, and it spred and inknist in volyum az it&#xD;
r6ld 6vur are land. And b ae gg sitiz wer sud-&#xD;
enli drdpt in ge wfdz ov m6rnin ; and ae sun&#xD;
&#xD;
1tgituyai r 5tto&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="112-113" xml:id="VAC5911-00000057"/>&#xD;
112&#xD;
&#xD;
gr edark and ghmiz ; and ae wordurz ov e skai&#xD;
street Qer kloudz ov k rep o11 r  iur  vci s&#xD;
and west ; and a pbl woz spred- vura      m I snounten&#xD;
tops and dvur ae loli vz, and  1 oe triz ovmounten.&#xD;
est wer frinjd wia fanirial taslz; and men sp6 " not&#xD;
for horur, arnd evri puls pbzd in its bitin az if&#xD;
e krak ov ddm   had sounded from  a klr skai.&#xD;
And hwen ae terur had abated a krai or ven&#xD;
jans ardz on ai br, and ae Blak Drag    h    "erde'&#xD;
in hiz haidin pies. And h' at wuns komprihen&#xD;
ded aat Qer woz nd den s6 dirk, ns omprihenp&#xD;
n6 mounten s6 hai, az tu giv him a kwaiet rest-&#xD;
in pies on ce planet hwer hi hadkdunaist&#xD;
S6 hi put on diirknes for hiz kuvurin     d&#xD;
out ov hiz h61, and grikt a waild rik t sumun&#xD;
dimunz aat gud akumpani him on hiz diprue&#xD;
And hi rdzd up hiz lofti form, and spred h. pin-&#xD;
yunz for ae h6m ov hiz farur; and ae m6ldpm'&#xD;
oblivion setld on hiz winz az ae disaird b&#xD;
cre aundurkloudz aat skurted biz dounwvrd we'.&#xD;
And Samunkl sent out hunturz tu sere for e&#xD;
men aat had enturtdnd ae dimunz, and had bin&#xD;
abr instruments in ce murder ov re kin. And hwen&#xD;
ed had kot aem, as hand (aem u    tu dai in vnc&#xD;
sat oi a0 mrnin and angri hevnz. But ud kud&#xD;
not kil crc di'munz aat had instigated (1iZ rece&#xD;
for ad had gon out ov ae men andtabandund cez&#xD;
tu cer fdt, az sun az as had n6 furar servisfor&#xD;
cem tu perform.&#xD;
Nou cer woz in a(at kuntri a masiv and lofti&#xD;
kolum, on hwie it woz ce wunt ov Histdria tu&#xD;
&#xD;
113&#xD;
&#xD;
B&#xD;
s,&#xD;
.n-&#xD;
.i&#xD;
a&#xD;
,U&#xD;
i&#xD;
1-&#xD;
sue{&#xD;
t,-&#xD;
4-&#xD;
3 Yr&#xD;
Sf&#xD;
I:&#xD;
A;J&#xD;
7&#xD;
F&#xD;
g11&#xD;
F&#xD;
&#xD;
rikord ae nemz ov dipdrted hirdz and stdtsmen,&#xD;
and  l ae grdt and gud aat wer dizervi ov ri&#xD;
membrans. It woz piramidal in form, and vast&#xD;
in dimengunz, and ae kloudz rested on its sumit.&#xD;
And after ae multitndz had riturnd from veii ae&#xD;
kinz korps, ad gaaurd around ae monyument tu&#xD;
witnes ai inskraibin ov hiz ndm.  And IHist6ria&#xD;
tuk hur longest ladur, and set it up agent ae&#xD;
said ov ae kolum, and (e woct hur az 91 asen-&#xD;
ded; and Fridima klaimd up aftur hur tu si hwer&#xD;
9i wud put ae0 nm ov hur fsvurit. And hwail&#xD;
9 woz pasin dvur ae spot hwer ae ndmz wer&#xD;
m6st aikli ritn, ae pipl gezd intently, ekspekti&#xD;
evuri moment aat 9i wud stop and bigin. But 91&#xD;
went on and on, until 9i had left ae vast kroud&#xD;
ov stdtsmen and woryurz binia hur fit.  And9ci&#xD;
past ae ion lain ov kinz, Kin Adam and Kim Jef-&#xD;
ur, and Kin Andrd, and Kim Adam     ben Adam,&#xD;
hd bifrended Fridima in hur caildhud, and Osami&#xD;
ae mirtur, and  1 ae filanaropists and marturz aat&#xD;
had givn abr laivz- tu ae welfer ov aer res.  And&#xD;
hwen ae pipT's aat 91 still kept asendim, ae gev&#xD;
a loud gout, for ad een undurstud aat it woz a grdt&#xD;
and n6bl kin at had past awe' from  amun crem.&#xD;
Nou aer woz ritn, flr up and distinkt from are rest,&#xD;
just undur ae kloudz, a single ndm, in larj karakturz,&#xD;
yet skersli vizibl for ae distans ; ce nem woz&#xD;
PATER       PATRIAE.&#xD;
And ac woct Histdria as 91 fikst hur ai upon ae&#xD;
spot; and Fridima kl6sli fol6d hur.  And hwen&#xD;
gi had riet ae plis, gi tuk from hur gurdi an ai-&#xD;
&#xD;
,i cjn " 1&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="114-115 (Index) " xml:id="VAC5911-00000058"/>&#xD;
urn stail, and pdst hur hand on ae rok tu rait&#xD;
just binia ae solitari ndm. And hwail ae multitnd&#xD;
wer goutinp, and bifdr ac rok woz pfrst, Fridifma&#xD;
sp6k and sed, Mai sister, dd yd rimembur ae f'r&#xD;
milyunz ov liburdted Kuganz? And Histdria drop&#xD;
hur aiz, and rimsnd for a rn6ment in ab, aen&#xD;
stept upon ae nekst round, and pkdsin bur fingurz&#xD;
just 6vur ai inent leturz, bigan  i gkrve r&#xD;
.big an t             kr       ok&#xD;
wia a klir bold strdk. And bl ae pipl wer amdzd&#xD;
and konfounded, for it woz a fikst buffov of ae&#xD;
men ov ai Oksident aat n6 neni kud ever bi ritn&#xD;
abuv aat ov ae fiaur ov hiz kuntri.  But hwen&#xD;
Historia wisdrd hur hand, and ad so ae nor ov&#xD;
M AGNUS MAHARBA,&#xD;
and nu aat it woz ritn for bl taim, in karakturz&#xD;
enduring az al iternal hilz, aer mainds wer ilamin.-&#xD;
eted, and ae so wia nu aiz, and abr goutinz wer&#xD;
cejd tu tirz ov glad and wunduria imdgun, and&#xD;
ae klaspt aer handz in prbr, and gdv aanks tu ace&#xD;
God ov hevn aat hi had aloud iem t    Ink upon&#xD;
oV's ov6 n6bl a kin and mrtur, ae dilivurur&#xD;
nd svyur ov hiz kuntri.&#xD;
And Samunkl and bl ae pip1 embdimd ae bodi&#xD;
ov Kin Magnus Mahirba, and Id it in a tam;&#xD;
and hiz memuri ae embaimd in aer afekgunz. And&#xD;
ae nigunz ov ai Orient m6rnd and lamented him;&#xD;
and ae Viktdrius kwin ov Bulia tact ae barp ofv&#xD;
sord ; and a kbold him bai ae nim ov Mahirba&#xD;
ae Gud. And Kin Andrd ae Sekund rand in hiz&#xD;
sted.&#xD;
&#xD;
INDEKS&#xD;
Or Proper Nenz okovri    in   is Wvrc.&#xD;
&#xD;
ADAM I., sekund kin ov ae&#xD;
Oksident, psj 113.&#xD;
Adam ben Adam, sun ovae&#xD;
former, 17, 113.&#xD;
Ailandbmi, a provins, 73.&#xD;
Aligitur mountenz, 69.&#xD;
Andrkia, a malevolent jfn..&#xD;
yus, I- .&#xD;
Andi I., sev3a k n ov Ge&#xD;
Qksident, 113.&#xD;
Andre II., sevntina kin usk-&#xD;
s;dz Magnus Mahirba, 114.&#xD;
Ant iturz krik, batl ov, 60.&#xD;
Arabi, an oriental kuntri, 72.&#xD;
Ajur klifs, s6 kbld from aer&#xD;
skaii ha, 69.&#xD;
Arkinjel, a swompi proving&#xD;
or ae Faaurwotur, 73.&#xD;
Baisntoun, a p14s femus for&#xD;
bufal6z,'97.&#xD;
BIrbarus 96r, ae noraurnkdst&#xD;
ov Kn a, 75.&#xD;
Berlin k, fel at Calenjurz-&#xD;
vi,84.&#xD;
11up1k, D  nian dlik and&#xD;
soldloktur, 103.\&#xD;
BIevztoun, a liturari s ti, from&#xD;
Bos, ae klasik rut ov Bo-&#xD;
vis, 45.&#xD;
Black Dragun, hiz orijin, 6;&#xD;
krosez GaeStormi oun, 8;&#xD;
persi:ftts Frldima, 17&#xD;
mdks wor on ae -kin~, 37;&#xD;
aplaiz tvuoiz fduur for'help,&#xD;
92;asinks tu oblivion, 112.&#xD;
&#xD;
Bkerintrrmp, lord ov ae naz-&#xD;
kariurz, 60.&#xD;
Bludisikl, dfk, a bludi ripur&#xD;
at Deasburg; hiz proves at&#xD;
Calenjurzvil, 83.&#xD;
Botlh6ldur, dak, hiz rigur, 46.&#xD;
Boundaritmrk rivur, separe-&#xD;
tin Midiland from Vuijin-&#xD;
land, 41.&#xD;
B6ldrobin, Drag6nian  duk,&#xD;
invddz Norland twais, 59,&#xD;
86 ; yildz tu Granit, 106.&#xD;
BrSkinbrij, veri unsif; brdk&#xD;
doun under ae tred ov&#xD;
Horntosur, 101.&#xD;
Bruaursiti, kapital ov Pen-&#xD;
wud, 45.&#xD;
Bultaitur, an oriental monark,&#xD;
yen 6jed, 53.&#xD;
Bulia, an ailand ov Nora, 97.&#xD;
Bulskampur, a smblstrim nd-&#xD;
ted for speturz, 41.&#xD;
Bic, pozest bai ae spirit ov&#xD;
Gaifoks, 108.&#xD;
Burning dk, hiz proves, 84.&#xD;
Burninbrand, dok, brz Ge&#xD;
torch ov won akros ac stou&#xD;
brij, 61; ataks ae fain&#xD;
wol, 68.&#xD;
Caildharu ld,wia Gaif bks, 108.&#xD;
Calenjurzvil, gr&amp;amp;dt batltild, 83.&#xD;
Cikenniokin bruk, 101.&#xD;
Cikenominsrivur, 102.&#xD;
Curztoun, a 9varus sit&#xD;
meni serpents aer,101.&#xD;
&#xD;
114                     t              I'n i r1J&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="118 (Index) -119 (Index) " xml:id="VAC5911-00000059"/>&#xD;
18&#xD;
&#xD;
on ze Twns, 100.&#xD;
a trait rivur and&#xD;
nin a pasej for ae&#xD;
anz tu invid Nora&#xD;
&#xD;
land, 59.&#xD;
C rpsik1, dik, a Tiatonik ri&#xD;
pur, hiz wepn pur stil, 58&#xD;
Cfrat, fisted (e dimunz. 108&#xD;
kdt and hut. 112: Yunra&#xD;
eskept.&#xD;
Qise,, a vaipuri traib ov fern-&#xD;
mmi daiabolianz, 46*.&#xD;
Qirmanduk, uts a swoa&#xD;
ard Gorjusland, 103.&#xD;
&#xD;
Daiab6lianz, risiv ger inspir&#xD;
egun from ae Red Dragun&#xD;
ae hand ov a toi daiabdii&#xD;
an anoints Kin -Magnus, 35&#xD;
Dedmanzvil, horurs ov, 95.&#xD;
Demigod    lonivianz  o01&#xD;
mikst blud, 11.&#xD;
fen 6krianz, an ekstensiv&#xD;
traih, 31.&#xD;
Dearsbung, batl ov, 86.&#xD;
Deastrand, or Nastrond, 94.&#xD;
Deastrim, a poizn bruk at&#xD;
Dedmanzvil, 95.&#xD;
Dim6nianz, men pozest bal&#xD;
dimunz, 97.&#xD;
Dimunz, a h61 lijun kdm up&#xD;
at wuns, 93.&#xD;
Dipwotur, lord, drinks from&#xD;
Ge welsprinz, 46.&#xD;
Daninsun, a strop6kasl, 79.&#xD;
Doziembur muna, ae last ov&#xD;
ae yir, 70.&#xD;
Dragonianz, frenclz ov ae&#xD;
Dragun, '31.&#xD;
Dragun, fsaur and sun, si Red&#xD;
and Blak Dragun.&#xD;
Dulgrin, ndval dik, suksesur&#xD;
ov Daipomp, 101.&#xD;
Dditwel, dak, did not dd az&#xD;
wel az woz ekspekted, 41.&#xD;
alpomp, neval dik, 83.&#xD;
&#xD;
gIundurhous, den at Ricman&#xD;
toun, 95.&#xD;
lErlistrt, Drag6nian cak, 87.&#xD;
$gaick, haiest and hwaitest&#xD;
mounten dvurlukin Ge Stor-.&#xD;
mi si, 75.&#xD;
&#xD;
t Fsaurwotur, rivur and prov-&#xD;
ins, 76; koruptli ritn Mrs.,&#xD;
az if it ever feminin&#xD;
Febrif j muna, gud agent ff-&#xD;
vurz, 82.&#xD;
Ferigift. nival dak, 77,&#xD;
Firful rivur, 106.&#xD;
. Fivuropolis, a sikli siti at ae&#xD;
moua ov ae Fsaurwotur 46&#xD;
Flaiinff. a grdt robur, mid a&#xD;
lord bai Publik Funk una.&#xD;
ri, 79.&#xD;
Flitcerif, dik, a frius raider&#xD;
and galant faitrjr, 106.&#xD;
Flouigdz,a marci peninga-&#xD;
la in Sunland, 73.&#xD;
Flouriland, or silescal empair,&#xD;
a kuntri in ue f&amp;amp;r Orient, 75.&#xD;
Folnnoua, nir ae Rapidnok-.&#xD;
in, 85.&#xD;
Frankman, dak, 70.&#xD;
Fridima, ov silescal pirentej,&#xD;
12; per ikted bai ae Dra-&#xD;
gun, 17; faindz Osanmi, 23;&#xD;
ei kisez ae kin, 74; hedz ae&#xD;
ariimi,102 ; biwilz  e kinz&#xD;
deg, 111.&#xD;
Friddnianz, 18, 31.&#xD;
Friga, an oneent godes, 12.&#xD;
Frim antl, diak, ae grdt pac&#xD;
opnur, atemts to kil ac Dra-&#xD;
gun wiaout ordurz, 44.&#xD;
&#xD;
Gaifoks, an   old  ieprob6t,&#xD;
kuniz bak tu era wiG an in-&#xD;
fernal ard, 93, 108.&#xD;
Galia, a worlaik kindum in&#xD;
Nora, 97.&#xD;
&#xD;
G dt munaH, 6pnz 6nli for ae&#xD;
ni 'yir, 72.&#xD;
Gtsiti, 'Curman 6pnz it, 104.&#xD;
Gorjusland, hlosumz at ae ap-&#xD;
rdc ov Fridima, 104.&#xD;
G6iam, a Bsbelaitic siti, 39.&#xD;
Granit, dtk, uncinz ae Fa-&#xD;
'urwotur, 80; tiks Wiked-&#xD;
burg, 91; konkurz B6ld-&#xD;
robin, 106.&#xD;
Granit spur, nir Deasburg, 87.&#xD;
Grdtbrag, Dragonman dlik, 32;&#xD;
rutG trled bai a ukur, 100.&#xD;
Grdt Bisin ov ae Miksinkan,&#xD;
34,77.&#xD;
Grdt Orient, isturn said ov ae&#xD;
planet, inkladz Nora and&#xD;
Kura, 7.&#xD;
Grnfi, or Simunfie, lord&#xD;
trejurur, mc'ks a nu sort ov&#xD;
mnuli, 45.&#xD;
Grfnhilz, noraurn proving, 97.&#xD;
Gudsaklifaiz dd, ae sikred&#xD;
Fraide, 110.d&#xD;
Gudsimur, but not a gud&#xD;
dour, 94.&#xD;
&#xD;
Hcet bruk, beriin ae tome-&#xD;
hb  aler 105.&#xD;
Iaiawdz,  an   enturpraizii&#xD;
traib ov -noraurlurz, 77.&#xD;
Hailand, a Dragoniaal woryur&#xD;
from  e hilz, 89.&#xD;
Halurwotur, a rivur divaid.,&#xD;
Norland and Sunland, 78.&#xD;
Htrdihud, dak ov Jefur, 104.&#xD;
Hidrpurz valid, a krosia on ae&#xD;
Boundarimsrk rivur, 59.,&#xD;
Hela, kwin oF ae l6ur ri-.&#xD;
junz, 94.&#xD;
Hnelamnhur h6m, 94.&#xD;
Jlencman, c~Ifk, 58.&#xD;
HEstiroa, pozest ov a dimun,&#xD;
108.&#xD;
Hilanoiurz, ae traib tu hwic&#xD;
Kin Magnus bilod, 77.&#xD;
&#xD;
His t6ria, kips ae rekurd ov 'ie&#xD;
djez, 113.&#xD;
Hi;ee, sne'ki ndcurz, a veri&#xD;
ekstensiv traib, 46.&#xD;
forntosur, dak, lks atsae&#xD;
Dragonianz, 60, 83, 100.&#xD;
Huniwotur, duak. diits B6ld-&#xD;
robi a at De asburg, 86.&#xD;
Wait, devipricur, wdlid and&#xD;
kild Osanius sun, 27.&#xD;
Hwaitnd top, haiest pik on&#xD;
'Ai isturn kost, 75.&#xD;
Ijipt, a dark rjun in Norland,&#xD;
78.&#xD;
lkwoliti, an oriental prins,&#xD;
kept for ae m6st part in&#xD;
strikt konfainment, 85.&#xD;
Iradikdturz,  aer  strongest&#xD;
Garisun woz stigund     in&#xD;
BIvztoun,31.&#xD;
&#xD;
Jefur, aurd lain ov ae Yunait-&#xD;
ed Oksident, 113.      ,&#xD;
Jefur,0prins, GODrag6nian ii-&#xD;
dun, 32; cinjd tu a wun-&#xD;
an, 107.&#xD;
Jddas, Drag6nian lord, mem-&#xD;
bur ov an old fanilh, bitrid&#xD;
hiz kuntri for silvur, 32.&#xD;
Julius, muna ov, 13.&#xD;
Kapital siti, a grdt woein pl6s&#xD;
for klenzit ae naeunal gar--&#xD;
m ents, 5 7.&#xD;
1inmor, dir, 101.&#xD;
K161k6bra, a dimnian, 97.&#xD;
Konservaturz, 31.&#xD;
Korinaian kolunz, 80.&#xD;
Koroneeun dd, 13.&#xD;
K6braz, huded serpents, frur&#xD;
in apirans than ratlsndks,&#xD;
but ikwali dan urus, 94&#xD;
Kristofur, a grit navigetur, 7,&#xD;
Kumbuiground rivur, 78.&#xD;
Kuga, ae suaurn kworter oa&#xD;
ae planet, 7.&#xD;
&#xD;
.i&#xD;
L&#xD;
t,&#xD;
a&#xD;
u.&#xD;
F&#xD;
.7&#xD;
t',1Sy&#xD;
Ry(&#xD;
S&#xD;
p&#xD;
&#xD;
-r&#xD;
3.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="120 (Index) -121 (Index) " xml:id="VAC5911-00000060"/>&#xD;
120&#xD;
&#xD;
L.Ingap, an 6 pin in cai Ai&#xD;
nmuntenz, fir Laifurzvil, 8&#xD;
Libertipen, a l6asum dunju&#xD;
at Ricmantoun, 95.&#xD;
Lank6bra, 97.&#xD;
Lo stepiDrag6nian diak, 5&#xD;
Luu~6vur mounten, 6vtrrha;'&#xD;
Le (addinidk, 100..&#xD;
Liiland, 7W.&#xD;
Magnus Maharba, sikstin&#xD;
kin ov (re Yunaited Oksi&#xD;
dent ;  oultRbz re Blal&#xD;
Dragun, 73; iz mrturd&#xD;
11(1.&#xD;
Marein munar 82.&#xD;
enmunr, ae muna        o'r&#xD;
lourz, 83.&#xD;
Midland, a provins laiin on&#xD;
(re Boundari r rk, 60.&#xD;
.ikimakl, dfk, marces t6rdz&#xD;
Riemantoun, 47; faits ae&#xD;
batil ov Antiturz krik, 60.&#xD;
Miksinkan, a grit kuntri ov&#xD;
mikst rdsez soua ov Sun-&#xD;
land, 77.&#xD;
Miligagunurz, pipi ov Miliga-&#xD;
gun, 77.&#xD;
Milkipenz, a kampig ground,&#xD;
81.&#xD;
Minis iturz, a traib ov hunt-&#xD;
urz, 77.&#xD;
Monarkia, an oriental lonjiv-&#xD;
ian, 11.&#xD;
Mudpilz, a dim6nian doktor,&#xD;
108.&#xD;
Muaurzbur6, 69.&#xD;
Mumifds, on ae Fdaurwotor,&#xD;
77.&#xD;
Munimungur, kipur ovfae&#xD;
Draguuz g6ldcest, 32.&#xD;
Mainz de, 80.&#xD;
Naiagoni, a terik katarakt&#xD;
on are bordurA ov Sndland,&#xD;
99.&#xD;
&#xD;
-u- Naitoud, a ftrlus Drag6nian,&#xD;
6G.  armdl az a nait, 1c:0.&#xD;
n  Ndstrond, rein ov He'a, 94,&#xD;
Nevirnaladi, kolm9unur ov&#xD;
pairat tips, 32.&#xD;
9. Nora, orijinal haiv ov cre Nor-&#xD;
1z    men, 7.&#xD;
Norland, a kuntri setid bat a&#xD;
koloni ov  pilgrirnz from&#xD;
Nora, 21.&#xD;
a Nora Karolurz, 73.&#xD;
SOksident, crc gret westura&#xD;
kwortur ov cr planet, 7.&#xD;
Osarni, harburz Fridlima, 23;&#xD;
iz sten, 29; riapirz at Deas-&#xD;
burg, 90.&#xD;
Ofur, te g6ldn 96r ov ai 6ri..&#xD;
ent, 75.&#xD;
Oknrij, or kiasik mountenz,&#xD;
ontie west ov Deasburg, 87.&#xD;
Opm'il muna, unbaindin ov&#xD;
tie strinz, 110&#xD;
drient, isturn kwortur ov ca&#xD;
planet, 7.&#xD;
Pain hilz, 103.&#xD;
Painz and Oks, sevnv ic, 49.&#xD;
Pan, spektur, fraitnz ae Nor-&#xD;
men, 42.&#xD;
Paler Patriae, fiaur ov hiz&#xD;
kuntri, hiz fdrn riccz tu ae&#xD;
kloudz, 113.&#xD;
Penwud, a larj forest in Nor..&#xD;
land, 86.&#xD;
Pepurkorn, Drag6nian dak,&#xD;
82, 91.&#xD;
P116, duk, fled bai nait win&#xD;
Flainaif, 79.&#xD;
Pisful si, west oV cre Oksi-&#xD;
dent, 75.&#xD;
Pontif, duk, 57.&#xD;
Pourfnlp6n, ataks Lord Si-&#xD;
wordur in biz bed, 111.&#xD;
Pretigiird, Drag6nian  dik,&#xD;
32, 37.&#xD;
&#xD;
}&#xD;
r'&#xD;
5 _i&#xD;
a&#xD;
,,.&#xD;
:.;&#xD;
&#xD;
(&#xD;
121&#xD;
&#xD;
Fub ikaiz, an ekstensiv traib  S&#xD;
cv.Nprinen1, 31.&#xD;
Publik ~ Fkgnari, fiftina&#xD;
Raitfut, a grdt n aval koman-&#xD;
dur, 78&#xD;
Rapidnokin rivur, 58R     i-&#xD;
Rapiaron, soua ov ae IRapid-&#xD;
flokin, 102.c&#xD;
Ratisiels0, giv wornim hif6r&#xD;
ad straik, hwic ae K6braz&#xD;
dui not, 34.&#xD;
Rickrg6, meni gips' kdrg6&#xD;
-  u 16dn  a r,  97.&#xD;
Ricmantoun, a ric siti, hed&#xD;
kworturz ov ae Dragun,&#xD;
47, 95.&#xD;
Rokrkest, or western moun-1&#xD;
tenz, 75.&#xD;
Rotnwud, guvurnur ov Go-&#xD;
aam, 40.&#xD;
Roundabout bdyu, 82.&#xD;
Round top, sona ov Sepul-&#xD;
kur hi, 87.^&#xD;
R6zikrouln, duk, faits at Mcc..&#xD;
urzburd, 69.&#xD;
Rufwind, fonndur ov Ded-&#xD;
manzvl1, 95.&#xD;
Salient cure, bati nir it, 80.&#xD;
Samunkl, a pourful jaiant and&#xD;
extensive landholdur, 12 ;&#xD;
lust nz hiz kini, 38;, bik~umz&#xD;
an Iraciketor, 51; embimz&#xD;
ae kinz bodi, 114.&#xD;
Sandadur, a serpent ov ere&#xD;
wrst kaind, 97.&#xD;
Savanaz, on a eor ov Gorjus-&#xD;
land, 104.&#xD;
Sekundirnuld, pozest ov ace&#xD;
senm spirit az Benedikt,r108.&#xD;
Sepulkur, a Drag6man lord,&#xD;
32.&#xD;
Sepulkur hil, nir Deasburg,&#xD;
86.&#xD;
&#xD;
iwordur, lord, a waiz man&#xD;
55; ase1d bal cae dfmul z,&#xD;
111.&#xD;
)mdabakS, dik, 83.&#xD;
ndland, noraurn sekun ofv&#xD;
cie Grit Oksideflt, 21.&#xD;
Soua Karolurz, a pivS, 73.&#xD;
Spotwfldz, gret bati ov, 102.&#xD;
Starnpon, lord, rmi skraib,&#xD;
60.&#xD;
Stedirm, Drag6ian dik, 89.&#xD;
Storm oun, or isttnf, 8,&#xD;
Stonifork rivur, 70.&#xD;
Stunijak, bravest ov cie kav-&#xD;
alirz, 59 ; hiz dea, 84.&#xD;
St-nijol, yildz tu gCrman,&#xD;
106.&#xD;
St inan, duk, 83, 84.&#xD;
St6mpail kasl, blt ov roks&#xD;
kast intu ae si, nir Curlz-&#xD;
toun, 37.&#xD;
Strounir, dnk 68&#xD;
Sutrn, mounted in Midliand,&#xD;
a grntbai aar, 60.&#xD;
Sumunr, dk, 61.b      r&#xD;
Sunland, kolonaizd bai Dra-&#xD;
gSnianz 9.&#xD;
Sunz de, ae sekred de, 79.&#xD;
Swainsiti, a gret pkds for kil-&#xD;
in hogz, 97&#xD;
Swi~ipeld~lLltf, a ko'bra, 97.&#xD;
Taimseritur, won ov ae waiz&#xD;
man ov G6aam, 39.&#xD;
Teusin, a provins, 73.&#xD;
TikumSi, old cif'ten, riturnz&#xD;
t1 help Q rman, 78.&#xD;
Tiran, a ripulsiv, dvurbarin&#xD;
lonjivian, 11.&#xD;
T~fet, ae neaur planet, 25, 92.&#xD;
TribanosofUr, a waiz man ov&#xD;
G6aam, 39 ; prop6zez a g6ld&#xD;
brij for ae Dragun, 97; iz&#xD;
entaist intu Sndland, but&#xD;
eskeps, 98.&#xD;
&#xD;
<pb  n="122 (Index) " xml:id="VAC5911-00000061"/>&#xD;
Twinsi, a trim and provins Wikedburg, tc'kn bai Granit&#xD;
in Sunland, 76.            on koroneun de, 91.&#xD;
Wddenz d, f6ra de ov ae&#xD;
Vandalliamur, c6zn cif ov ae  wik, 60.&#xD;
K6braz, 97.              Wurstovol, doktur, hiz med-&#xD;
Viktd6rius kwin  ov  Bulia,  isinz wars aan dea, 96.&#xD;
m6rnz for Magnus Mahar- Wulvz' mounten, 87.&#xD;
&#xD;
ba, 114.&#xD;
Vurjinland, 61d dominyun ov&#xD;
ae Drag6nianz, 41.&#xD;
Waildwudz, bat1 ov, 102.&#xD;
Waizkounselurz, a larj traib&#xD;
in ae norawest, 77.&#xD;
&#xD;
Yelwel, Drag6nian dak, 68,&#xD;
105.&#xD;
Yulisez, neent woryur, 78.&#xD;
Yunaited Oksident, ae prin-&#xD;
sipal kindum ov ae western&#xD;
ailand, 34, 73.&#xD;
&#xD;
P. 6 1. 3 respektivli for rispektivli&#xD;
9 14 kindums for kindumz&#xD;
17   1 haf for hdf&#xD;
20   1 hwich for hwic&#xD;
21 14 mountinz for mountenz&#xD;
40   3  harangd for harand&#xD;
44 11 sun for sun&#xD;
56   3 ospieuz for ospigus&#xD;
61 6 artileri for grtiluri&#xD;
62  11  afars for aferz&#xD;
87 19 encent for ingent&#xD;
118   7 pir for pr&#xD;
&#xD;
122&#xD;
&#xD;
x&#xD;
k&#xD;
I&#xD;
.1&#xD;
&#xD;
Unlks&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD;  &#xD; &#xD;
            </p> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>