<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC5696">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Sentinel at the Pass </title>
            <author>Baer, Warren.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC5696</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-0177</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                    participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sentinel at the Pass</title>
                  <author>Baer, Warren.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>106 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>S.l. </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1873">1873</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2000-09-25">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="Christina Dulude, Indiana University" when="2001-06-01">Finished TEI encoding and proofreading</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-06-03">Finished final editing</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-04-09">Converted document from SGML to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-04-09">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC5696-00000001"/>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>THE Sentinel at the Pass.</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">A NOVEL.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>BY <docAuthor>WARREN BAER.</docAuthor> AUTHOR OF "CARMINE," "CHAMPAGNE CHARLIE," ETC. ETC.</byline>
            <docEdition>Entered, according to Act of Congress, in the year 1873, by WARREN BAER, in the Office of the Librarian of Congress, at Washington. The right to dramatize reserved to the author.</docEdition>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>GALVESTON:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>PRINTED AT THE "NEWS" STREAM JOB OFFICE.</publisher>
            </docImprint>
            <docDate when="1873">1873.</docDate>
         </titlePage>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="" xml:id="VAC5696-00000002"/>
            <head>To Judge R.D. JOHNSON,</head>
            <p>This volume is respectfully dedicated, in testimony of the author's respect for him as a gentleman of culture, a man of generosity, and a Judge of unblemished integrity. Long may he live to receive, as he now does, the respect of his fellow-citizens, among whom he passed a life of honor and usefulness.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>WARREN BAER.</signed>
               <dateline>GALVESTON.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The sentinel at the Pass</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Sentinel at the Pass.</head>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>Chapter I.</head>
                  <p>AN hour past noon, and hardly so late, either, for the sun's rays were still disagreeably warm, though his disk was veiled by a gossamer haze of purple lustre, an atmospheric phenomenon peculiar to the plains of Arizona, a country but little known, when our narrative begins. So now we have the hour, next let us fix the location: It is the west entrance of the far-famed Apache Pass. Have you ever read of or been told by emigrants of this winding passage through this lone mountain? No matter now, you will read of it, you will see it almost pictured to your mind's eye, you will almost hear the savage whoop of the Apaches ring through the desolate walls of jagged rocks and narrow, level sand bed. There is a profound stillness pervading the overhanging atmosphere, the very rocks seem to whisper "caution," as you pass along with hesitating steps, and your heart seems to beat with a trembling sensation in every pulsation of your very soul. You seem to breathe freer, you feel as though your life had been given back to you as you emerge from either entrance of the Pass, and a voice seems to hang over you shouting in demoniac whispers "beware, beware, there's murder in the air, the home of the Apache is the abode of death. The white man who tarries here will find no grave, the buzzard shall devour his flesh, the wolf shall <choice>
                        <sic>knaw</sic>
                        <corr>gnaw</corr>
                     </choice> his bones and the raven croak his funeral knell." Then be up and away ere the lurking savage, with unseen weapon has spotted the sand with your steaming blood, and your death gasp faintly gives back the exultant whoop of the treacherous foe. And what chief of brutal instincts rules over this extended area of plain and mountain. The hunter, the trapper and the immigrant will answer you in a whisper, "Mangos Colorado, or bloody sleeve, great chief of the Apache nation," than whom no man is dreaded more, for he is without mercy to his enemy, and that enemy he deemed the white man, especially the American emigrants. Well then, to return to the hour and place, the west entrance of the Pass, you will find there the troopers from Fort Buchanan under immediate command of Col. H. Why are they there? It is to guard the passages and the stage which<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC5696-00000003"/> travelled the Butterfield route across the plains bringing the mails from California to the eastern States. Only six passengers occupied the six seats in the light coach, or wagon if you will, sometimes four and oftener six mules dragging at a slow jog the frail conveyance, the narrow wheels of which cut deep into the gritty sand. At any other hour of the day the stage could have been seen afar off, but the hazy atmosphere of noon rendered all objects obscure even at the distance of a league. The stage which was expected on this occasion was thought not to be far off, and the anxious eyes of the troops and officers were frequently cast in the direction in which it was expected to arrive. At last the delay of its arrival became distressingly tedious, and a trooper was sent up to one of the rocks upon the hillside to see if he could discover any sign of its approach, but scarcely had he begun ascending the hill, when the sentinel on guard at the farther end of the line shouted out with all his strength of voice, "Corporal of the Guard—the stage, the stage, we see the dust of its track." Immediately there was a great commotion in camp, and in a few moments through the sultry air could be seen a dark spot like uplifting smoke, which seemed to hang for an instant above the plain and then as suddenly disappear. As the hour wore away the advancing object became more distinct until, finally, the body of the coach and the mules became visible and soon thereafter Wash. Elrick, the fearless driver of the stage, drew up his sweating mules beside the Colonel's tent.</p>
                  <p>"Well done, Elrick; you have made capital time," exclaimed Col. H, grasping the driver's hand with much warmth of pressure; "you see I was watching for you, but it was hardly necessary, as Mangos was at the Fort a few days ago, and we held a parley, and peace for the present now holds between us."</p>
                  <p>"He must have been hard pushed," replied Elrick, taking off his buckskin glove, "he's got some devilment in his head, you'd better believe it."</p>
                  <p>"That's to be supposed," replied the Colonel, "for he's going on a thieving expedition into Mexico. As my troopers might give some of his tribes trouble during his absence he thought the better way was to leave no enemy in the rear who could annoy his women, children and old men. But enough of the scamp, I suppose the treaty will last until he returns with his booty; at all events, you all are safe this trip. But whom have we here?"</p>
                  <p>"Oh, I forgot to introduce you. Col. H, this is Sir Harry Bart," replied Elrick, "who, with his daughter, is traveling home by land in order to see the country and take a glance at Pike's Peak, Chimney Rock, and Pilot Knob."</p>
                  <p>After shaking the knight warmly by the hand and receiving an introduction to his daughter, and apologizing for not having any refreshments on hand suitable to serve the occasion, the Colonel invited Sir Harry to alight and stretch his limbs, remarking "but I would not advise you to tarry long, as I desire you to get through the Pass before sunset, though, no doubt Elrick will see to that. The fact is I never enter that dungeon, as I style it, that I do not feel in a hurry to get through. It seems the longest three miles I ever traveled in my life."</p>
                  <p>"Is the road rough and rocky?" inquired Sir Harry.</p>
                  <p>"Oh, no," replied tire Colonel "only sandy. But then it is so gloomy and confoundedly peculiar in its dusky shadows and acute windings and turnings. Do you know that an army of ten thousand troops could block the way against fifty regiments?"</p>
                  <p>"Well, then, I shall hasten to experience this romantic sensation of terror," rejoined Sir Harry; "so let's move on, Elrick, unless," he added, with a gracious smile at his daughter, "Lutella should prevail on some of your gallant troopers to see us through the Pass."</p>
                  <p>"Not for the world," replied the daughter. "It would show cowardice upon our part, and be doubting the assurances of the Colonel, whose words and diplomacy should convince us of our safety. Mr. Elrick, what say you?" she added, as smilingly she bowed towards the driver.</p>
                  <p>"I don't say there's any particular danger, miss; but then you know this is a wild, treacherous country, and I'll bet five to one that if we had eyes that could see around rocks and through bushes, some of the imps, who inhabit this region, would be discovered looking at us now from that hill-side; but, after the Colonel's word of safety to us, I think we can venture."</p>
                  <p>"Elrick may prove right," replied the Colonel; "there are always lurking foes around us and any action upon our part importing distrust of Mangos' promises would be made known and an excuse offered him for breaking the treaty."</p>
                  <p>"Well argued," Sir Harry replied, "and I really suppose there is not the least danger; but I have listened so attentively to Elrick's account of the horrible butchery and treachery of the Apache, that my imagination may have become affected by the recital of their ferocious deeds of blood."</p>
                  <p>"It's too true," replied the driver. "When we leave the mouth of the Pass, at the other end, I'll show you the head-boards that mark the graves of a murdered train. Men, women and children were murdered there, and the young women carried off. I helped to bury them, and it was a<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC5696-00000004"/> shocking sight, too; it makes my very heart sick to think about it now."</p>
                  <p>"That will do," ordered the Colonel; "you would frighten the soul of a very Hector. Lieutenant Ward will furnish you an escort."</p>
                  <p>"I beg of you, Colonel, not to do so. Elrick, you must cease your fiendish stories to my father. Are we not six true and trusty warriors, armed to the teeth?" and here the daughter glanced at the three miners who sat upon the middle seat of the stage, impatiently waiting the starting of the mules.</p>
                  <p>"All our work for the last three years is with us in the coach," replied the stouter of the three miners from California, "and it's not likely that we would risk our fifty dollar slugs, if we thought there was any real danger, when we could be afforded protection by troops; and if a little dust should be stirred around us by the red skins, it's not likely that we would remain idle, and let Elrick do all the fighting. So let's push on. While that escort is getting ready, we could be half through the pass."</p>
                  <p>"I'm glad you approve my decision in this matter, gentlemen," replied Lutella. "I always endeavor to stimulate courage, and not dampen it with tears of fright. So good bye, gentlemen," she added, waiving her hand forward. "Elrick, to the charge!"</p>
                  <p>"So be it," said Elrick; and then the mules were whirled into the track towards the western opening of the Pass.</p>
                  <p>"Youth is ever over-confident," replied the Knight. "I trust all may be well."</p>
                  <p>"In my heart I almost know it," replied the Colonel, as he held the Englishman's hand in his own warm grasp.</p>
                  <p>"Farewell, gentlemen," again exclaimed the daughter, as she gracefully bowed to the officers, who stood silently observing the proud-spirited girl, seated in the rear of the stage.</p>
                  <p>"You know the signal, Elrick, remarked the Colonel. "Should you spy any Indians, turn your mules and drive for the Pass, and fire as you come. We shall remain here for an hour. The fact is they are all south of the Pass, and if any attack was intended it will come from this quarter, and it is from this cause I prefer to remain where I am."</p>
                  <p>"All right; I see through it now," replied Elrick; "and now get up you lazy cusses," and then added, "you lazy devils are more afraid of an Indian than any of us, so get along lively, you hussies," and here the whip-lash was lustily applied, and the young and insecurely broken-in mules started off at a slow trot; and then turning to Sir Harry, he added, "the Colonel's right; the Indians are all south or gone, and that's why he remains where he's at."</p>
                  <p>"And you think so, seriously," replied his companion.</p>
                  <p>"Sure of it; but just let me touch up that oft-hand leader; he's lazing now, but just let him smell one of them greasy Indians, and Goliah could not hold him."</p>
                  <p>"So, then, we would be assured of safety in flight," said the Englishman.</p>
                  <p>"Why, sir, he'd run his hoofs clean off his legs," said Elrick. "We once crossed a fresh trail of 'em, and it took the whole stage to hold him. However," he concluded, "we'll make the opening before good sun down, and then we'll have fair travelling until we reach the next station, only seven miles ahead."</p>
                  <p>As they entered the Pass, the mountain sloped gradually down towards the plain; but as they proceeded, bold rocks projected above the road, while here and there stunted patches of chapparel fringed the edges of the declivity, until midway between the two entrances the mountain summits shot up into bold, irregular peaks, and then gradually sloped off towards the eastern opening of the Pass. High up amid the rocks, the mountain goat, or the harmless antelope were seen grazing at intervals along the knolls of the hills, or nearer down the decline, were moving, in single file along some narrow trail, in search of greener or fresher grass. Sir Harry occupied the seat next the driver. He carried his rifle across his knees, ready for immediate service, while, revolvers in hand, the miners eagerly watched, at every turn of the road, for the upspringing of some hidden foe.</p>
                  <p>"Truly this is a lonesome drive," remarked Sir Harry. "I never felt so oppressed in my life. I cannot account for it. I am utterly demoralized; do, pray, Elrick, touch up the mules and make them strike a trot."</p>
                  <p>"I'd like to oblige you, Sir Harry; but really can't do it. The sand is too deep here, besides, my animals are tender-footed and their hoofs are worn to the quick. On good roads I'll put 'em through at a dashing gait. Patience is a virtue, Sir Harry. Only half an hour, and I'll put you where you'll see day light once again." As Elrick concluded his speech a merrily gay voice broke upon the stillness of the air, startling and enlivening the hearts of the depressed travelers.</p>
                  <p>"You've got a treasure in that girl, Sir Harry; her voice sounds as sweet and cheering to me now as a band of music," exclaimed Elrick.</p>
                  <p>"Yes, yes," rejoined the father; "and that's what makes me so apprehensive now for our safety. It's the song of Robin Hood's last appeal to his lady-love. It's a pretty air, but out of place here; though in peaceful abodes, a great favorite of mine."</p>
                  <pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC5696-00000005"/>
                  <p>"Be that as it may," replied the driver, "I could listen to that voice all day." At that moment some fragment of rocks came rolling down the ragged sides of the steep ascent, blocking up the way.</p>
                  <p>"Some old goat displaced some loose rock above," remarked Elrick. "It don't take a rock long to reach from the summit up there to the bottom. Ho, there! let's get out and move the pieces from our track. <emph>Come men, let's move lightly</emph>."</p>
                  <p>"Are you certain it was not hurled at us by some hidden Indian?" asked the Englishman.</p>
                  <p>"No indeed; he'd not be guilty of such a fault. Why, man, they never disturb even a stick in their way when they move. They want to see and not be seen," replied Elrick.</p>
                  <p>The rocks were soon rolled to the side of the road when Elrick continued: "When we get to near the head of the Pass, I'll show you the Sentinel of the Pass—a large horned mountain goat who ever seems waiting for us to greet him with a crack or so from our Sharpe's rifles. I never pass below him that I do not make my bow to him with a whistling bullet from my rifle."</p>
                  <p>"And, Mr. Driver, let me ask you if you do not consider yourself a poor shot since after practising so often you have not yet wounded the inquisitive sentinel?" asked the daughter.</p>
                  <p>"I almost confess it with shame," replied Elrick, "but the fact is he's a knowing old fellow for though a stout one of his kind, and his horns a good mark upon which to draw a dead, square bead line, yet, at the very moment I pull the trigger, he seems to fall behind the rock, and there's a shot lost."</p>
                  <p>"I think I can reach him if he gives me a chance," replied Sir Harry.</p>
                  <p>"We shall certainly find him there," replied Elrick, "for we never pass here that I don't find the old fellow guarding the Pass with his inquisitive black eyes, and thus they conversed until, reaching the opening, Elrick halted his mules and springing from his seat, followed by the Knight, pointed up the mountain to a square flat rock which projected in an over-hanging position, angular shaped towards the top, and exclaimed, "there Sir Harry, behold our game," and sure enough, there stood the goat upon his rocky throne, calmly surveying all surrounding objects and especially the stage.</p>
                  <p>"Let's fire at him together," said the Englishman.</p>
                  <p>"No, that would be foul, Sir Harry. In fact, I am so accustomed to meet him that absolutely he seems like an old acquaintance, and I should be loth to kill him. It would seem like wounding an old associate in my travels, so I only now shoot at him to make him jump from the rock."</p>
                  <p>"Do not shoot at him, father; he is doing us no harm, and his presence here may indicate that all is safe and no enemy, else it would not show its form so boldly."</p>
                  <p>"As to his killing the old fellow, I've no fear of that feat being done around here; so let drive, Sir Harry, that your daughter can boast that she has seen the large horned mountain goat leap from his native rock," said Elrick.</p>
                  <p>Sir Harry raised his rifle to his shoulder and taking deliberate aim, fired.</p>
                  <p>"Confound the fellow!" he exclaimed, with an impatient shrug of his shoulders. "Would you believe it, that just as I pulled the trigger, the creature jumped behind the rock."</p>
                  <p>"He's served me so often before," replied Elrick. "He's a sly one, depend on it, Sir Harry."</p>
                  <p>"I'd like to get another shot at him," said Sir Harry; "I'd show him a trick at firing."</p>
                  <p>"I'm sorry you wasted your powder at it at all," exclaimed his daughter. "Here we have just passed through a dangerous portion of our route, and upon emerging from the dark and dreary channel of our way, and are welcomed to sunlight and freedom by a harmless goat, which is watching our egress from the Pass, when you strive to do him an injury. For my part, when I first espied him perched up there, I felt assured of our safety, for I thought that had the Indians been near, he would not have shown himself, and who knows but his presence there may in some way be connected with our safety!"</p>
                  <p>"There may be something in that," replied Elrick, "for I always feel lighter in spirits when I see him up there—the old Sentinel at the Pass."</p>
                  <p>Sir Harry was a well-made man; not over tall, yet his limbs were set firmly to his body, and his manners, though extremely polite, were slightly reserved; too much cramped with a species of formality, an indefinable restraint in his movements, as though he wished to convey the impression that though friendly in his actions, nothing in his bearing should be construed into familiarity. His eyes were dark blue, nose slightly Roman, chin broad, and in the compression of his lips, we could well discern firmness and decision of character. His daughter, an only child, he had watched from infancy with more than a parent's fondness—a devotion, an isolated anxiety so complete as almost to be oblivious to all other surrounding objects or existences. His wife, a beautiful woman, had early taken her departure from this world of fraud, misery and corruption, and left the girl to sustain him in his affliction for her loss. Lutella, who much resembled her in form and features, returned his affection and parental love with all the ardor and<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC5696-00000006"/> concentrated warmth of her existence. What would all the splendid scenery of nature, its gorgeous sky, its shining rivers, its vast oceans, flowery plains and stupendous mountains be to her without his presence? Her youthful heart had never yet been impressed with the image of a mortal that could, even during a moment of idleness, mar the image of her father. She lived, breathed and thought only for her parent, so his being was the essential whole of her existence. When her father was dead the family name would die with him; "but then," she soliloquized, "his proud, manly spirit shall live in me. I shall be as my father was in mind; I shall embalm his memory in my spirit, in my soul, and there shall be neither place nor room for another form, another image in the living tomb of my heart." Of such intent, material and purpose was Lutella; but already the fates were working the scroll of futurity in her life, and the lights and shadows which illumined the changing vista of the coming years, were gathering and thickening across the pathway which she was to follow.</p>
                  <p>The goat was no longer seen from his rocky point of observation, and the dark shadow of the mountain cast its lengthening outlines across the plain, as the travelers left the Pass behind them.</p>
                  <p>"These sunsets," said Elrick, "always feel to me as though music was melting in the air around me. I always, somehow or other, seem to think of home. There's nothing like it in any of the States. I've sometimes seen the air yellow and then red and purple, and yet not a cloud was visible. Within the space of twenty minutes all things would wear the color of the atmosphere. I don't believe it ever rains in this latitude; one can sleep as well in the air, on the ground here, as in a bed in the east. All is dry as a mummy. It's most too long before sundown to witness the beautiful colors that entrance me," he continued; "but we shall witness this beautiful sky before night sets in, and, Miss Lutella I know will admire it to perfection. But look!" he added, uneasily, and standing up erect in his seat, while he grasped his rifle and fixed his gaze toward the North, and added, "Stand to your guns, all! This means something, unless it's wolves chasing a wounded deer." At that moment two large black-tailed bucks, with heads erect and nostrils spread, dashed, with desperate haste across the road, several hundred yards in front of the stage. "I thought so; it is Indians; we must retrace our steps," and he wheeled the mules around and urged them towards the mouth of the Pass.</p>
                  <p>"There are only a few of them," said Lutella. "What fine horses they ride, and only look at the spears they carry."</p>
                  <p>The stage had only reached the entrance to the Pass, when down upon them came some twenty Indians, with a few stragglers in the rear.</p>
                  <p>"Don't shoot!" said Elrick, "unless they begin the fight."</p>
                  <p>"See, they are laughing," said Lutella.</p>
                  <p>"Laughing devils!" exclaimed Elrick. "Their very stink will frighten the mules!" and so it did; for the animals commenced snorting and rearing in their traces as the Indians passed them, sending a few arrows into the top of the stage as they glided by; when Sir Harry exclaimed, as he sprang from his seat, "A fair field and plenty of room!" and then began firing at the retreating horsemen.</p>
                  <p>"Look!" said Lutella; "there's some three others coming."</p>
                  <p>But the mules, frightened to a pitch of desperation, heeled around again into the direct road to the nearest station, and now became unmanageable.</p>
                  <p>"Get in, Sir Harry quick! Let the devils go."</p>
                  <p>But Sir Harry heeded not or heard not the voice of the driver, and he fired at the approaching horsemen when the hindmost horseman flung his body behind the neck of his horse for shelter from bullets from either rifle or pistol, let slip an arrow from his bow beneath his horse's neck, and with such swift and fatal aim as to pierce the Knight in his left chest, the Apache brave dashing off with unabated speed after his companions. When the arrow struck the Knight, his form waved and twisted together for an instant, and then went down with a leap upon the sand. At that moment the mules started away with the stage, their fright rendering their strength beyond control. Seeing there was no probability of checking the maddened animals, and that every moment bore her further from her wounded and perhaps dying parent, Lutella flung herself from the rear of the stage, alighting on her hands and knees upon the sandy road, and then careless or thoughtless of bruises to limb or body, she hastened, with all the speed of which she was possessed, in search of her father's body. Sir Harry had dragged his body, in a crawling position from off the road, and there at the very base of the mountain, amid a thin spread of chapparel, had laid his body down to die, and so perished a gallant soldier, a courteous gentleman, and one, too, whom his sovereign deemed worthy of knighthood. His honors were his own and would perish with him. A bloody froth was oozing from his lips, and the pallor of death was settled on his brow and cheeks, and he was lying on his back, when Lutella reached the spot where he was dying. For an instant the panting and reddened child, seeing the expiring parent motionless, unnerved, stupefied, stood with a<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC5696-00000007"/> vacant stare, gazing first at the heavens above and then at the corpse at her feet. Was she herself dead? Had her spirit passed from earth, and, awakening from death was it wandering in lands assigned to another sphere of existence? Was this state of being the agony attending upon a new creation of existence? No no! Reason resumes its sway, as with a sudden flash of consciousness she flings herself upon the unconscious form of her parent, and her soul starts into life anew, with a shriek so ringing and piercing as to be echoed back by the hills above her. "Father! father! awake—arise. Your Lutella calls! No, father, you cannot be dead! Oh, God! in mercy have pity on me. Take me from the world—crush me, heaven! Here on this body let me die! Sir, Harry Bart, oh, speak to your daughter! And you are dead, and I murdered you—took, stole, robbed you of your precious life, refusing the escort! Oh! God! is this destiny? What will become of me? My God! have mercy upon my soul! Oh, hateful demon—cursed savage! Oh, fatal arrow! What shall I do? What will become of me? Oh, father! father! get up! Stir but a single limb, that I may know you still live!"</p>
                  <p>Exhausted by her paroxysms of grief, she kissed the cold lips of the corpse, and then sank insensible beside the body of the late Sir Harry Bart.</p>
                  <p>The sun was low in the heavens; already the beetle began buzzing through the air, and the bat darted, with irregular flight, around the mountain's base. The atmosphere was already quivering beneath the weight of gathering night when stealthily creeping from behind rock and shrub, the form of an Indian was seen to glide with noiseless motion towards the dead body and the entranced daughter. It was he who did the deed of blood, and he now returned to rob and scalp the dead. He carried his long and sharp-bladed knife between his teeth. His movements were as silent as the uncoiling of the serpent's folds and his eye glistened with the gleam of the tiger, when in the act of springing on its prey. When he had approached sufficiently near as to almost reach them with his hand, he rested for a moment, and with a searching glance, gazed cautiously around to mark that no one watched over the bodies of the insensible and the slain. He then drew nearer and was in the very act of scalping the corpse of the late Sir Harry Bart, when up rose from behind him a large pair of horns, as though they had sprung up out of the very earth, and the next moment his knife was struck from his hand and he himself hurled several yards from the bodies he intended to disfigure and mutilate. At the sudden approach of so unnatural an apparition as a walking goat, with human hands and nose, the savage quickly withdrew, leaving his knife laying at the feet of Big Horn, as we shall call him, who, after a few moment's consideration, lifted the body of the insensible girl from off the corpse, and then kneeling upon one knee and raising the young girl's head from its prostrate position, and placing it upon his knee, said:</p>
                  <p>"Take that, you hideous grave-sucker," exclaimed Big Horn, as knife in hand, he rushed towards the prostrate form of the Indian, intending to follow up his advantage with all the haste possible; but the savage was too wide awake to his own safety to offer the least resistance, so quickly regaining his feet, he darted off amid the rocks and their patches of chapparel, and was soon lost to view.</p>
                  <p>"Both dead!" observed the Sentinel, as he began scrutinizing the two bodies near his feet, with a sympathizing voice and pitying look. "I knew how it would be. A small escort would have saved them. Elrick should not have turned back. I recognize this gentleman," said he. "His are the features of an Englishman. A full-formed man was he, and no doubt a brave one. Had he known the tricks of these hounds as well as I do, he never would have left the shelter of the stage. They appear to be people of quality, and English, too, judging from their dress and features. The bodies must be buried. I only wish Lying Pat was here; he may not be far off, as I often spy him dodging around the mouth of the Pass. Now, what is to be done? To go up to Dr. Keating's and return, would take up too much time. Well, Pat, it's true, is a monstrous liar and a big thief, but he has a good heart in him, though hypocrite he be. I shall call him at all events," and here the Mountain Sentinel gave forth three shrill shouts, but no answering reply greeted his anxious ears, save a deep groan of anguish which issued from the lips of the girl whose head had been pressed close to the breast of her lifeless parent.</p>
                  <p>"In God's name, one of them is alive!" he exclaimed, as he lifted the body of the girl in his arms, and felt her warm breath upon his cheek. "Speak to me!" he gasped, as his startled soul seemed convulsed with a joyous excitement, and then hastily drawing the cork from his canteen, said: "Drink, if only to sip, dear lady." He added, as he pressed the canteen to her lips, "There's virtue in this brandy from the Fort, if I could only get her to taste it." Finding the girl still almost insensible, he poured the spirits across her brow, and even into her mouth, when the girl opened her eyes and in soft accents asked:</p>
                  <p>"Where am I? What am I doing here? Release me from your arms, whoever you be!"</p>
                  <pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC5696-00000008"/>
                  <p>"I obey your orders with pleasure," he said, as he gently seated her upon the ground. "I am glad to see that you have revived from your fainting fit, Miss. I will carry you to a place of safety if you will only permit me to do so."</p>
                  <p>"Do you know," she replied, "that I have been dead! yes, dead! and will ever remain so while in this world. If I cannot weep now, it is because my heart has lost its moisture; my soul is not in my blood. The flesh shall cling to my frame, but my spirit will have naught to do with it—only as the bars of its prison. Did you know Sir Harry?" she asked, as her eyes still rested upon the lifeless form. "He was my father once; his body is fixed to the world now."</p>
                  <p>"This will never do, Miss; the night air will chill you; the savage will be upon us," said the Sentinel.</p>
                  <p>"What do you propose to do with me?" she asked with a vacant stare.</p>
                  <p>"Carry you to our tent, where you will be welcome, and attended to."</p>
                  <p>"And that body?" she asked.</p>
                  <p>"Bury it where it fell," said Big Horn.</p>
                  <p>"No, no; promise me you will return and bring it to where you carry me and give it Christian burial, and I will not only go with you, but reward you. Otherwise I will scratch a grave in this sand with my hands, and both of us lie therein forever."</p>
                  <p>Big Horn began reasoning upon the subject. She answered:</p>
                  <p>"It is useless to decide for me. I have determined upon this question."</p>
                  <p>"Well," said Big Horn, "I'll promise you, though it will prove a difficult job; but let us make haste; if the body's to be moved the sooner we reach the tent the better."</p>
                  <p>"Stop a moment," she said as she bent over the corpse and lifted the stiffening hand to her lips and kissed it. Then taking off from the finger the signet ring, she turned toward her attendant and in a firm voice said:</p>
                  <p>"I confide in your honor; let us go; lead the way, I will follow." But the attempt was futile on her part. Her body seemed deprived of all strength of motion. Upon seeing which, the Sentinel, urged by the necessity of the case, clasped her in his sinewy arms, and with a resolute mind and firm stride, ascended the mountain's sandy and rocky slope, directing his course towards the South where he knew he would strike a trail leading to the Doctor's tent, or shanty, as Lying Pat honorably designated the office of the Indian Doctor, Keating. The sun was just setting. The purple haze or glow of which Elrick, the driver, had so feelingly spoken, now began gathering in thickness athwart the heavens. A shower of colored rays appeared to fall from the tops of the mountains into the plains below, filling the air with a mysterious glow; in which one almost imagined he could behold the fairies sporting and dancing in the fading sunbeams. The full moon came up from behind the eastern hills, flooding the plains and vallies with her splendor. The fall blaze of her glory struck the rocky slope of the Pass at point blank range. The Knight's body was fully exposed to view, and a most profound silence oppressed the air with a weighty gloom, when against the hill-side some brush and sticks were, most mysteriously moved. Unless you had been very near and closely observing, and the twilight very lustrous, you would not have detected any appearance of change in the sticks and brushes. Presently a queer looking bunch of fur was observed to protrude from a hole in the side of the hill and then as suddenly disappear, and then it was seen again until it became stationary above ground and fixed and motionless as one of the rocks by which in part it was sheltered. Fox, bare, or badger it might be, but it could not be any of the midnight rovers in search of food, and, besides, the eyes of the creature were fixed upon the dead body of Sir Harry, whose sight should never again behold the light of day or the darkness of night. But a shadow becomes visible; it approaches the body; it is evidently not a beast of prey; but a human form, stealthily moving, gliding on hands and knees and resting for inspection of the position at every motion of the advance. Like the serpent, it dragged its slow length along noiseless, but not unnoticed. Like the panther, which, after killing its prey, hastily covers the carcass with leaves or earth, when disturbed by some unexpected intruder upon its feast, and then retires and lies concealed until all danger is passed, and then again ventures to return and enjoy its food in quiet, so came back the Indian when he knew the Sentinel of the Pass had left the spot of the late bloody encounter. With a leap he sprang upon the body, and was rifling the corpse of its clothes preparatory to scalping its head, when the shadow on the hill-side seemed to grow up suddenly from out the hole and the brush, bow and arrow quickly appeared in its hands an instant thereafter, and the Indian, who was tearing the coat from the body of poor Sir Harry, sprang to his feet and giving vent to a murderous cry of agony, darted down the hill-side and was soon lost to view. The figure resumed its first position and only again was to be observed the bushy head of hair, as motionless and unnoticeable as ever. A few moments thereafter<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC5696-00000009"/> the form of a man was seen to glide out of the hole and drew towards the body, drawing himself cautiously along upon knees and elbows.</p>
                  <p>"It's Lying Pat that's put a stitch in his dirty pants behind. It was a pretty sight to witness his dancing over the rocks, and hear his musical whoop fading in the distance. He must have reached Crow Springs by this time. Man, sure, and here's a bundle of papers he's torn from the dead man's breast-pocket. Who knows but there's a fortune wrapped up in this little pile of letters. I'll just stow them away in my chamber, and as by the soul of my aunt Timotherea, who was a perfect soul as she was, but very poor in the sole of her foot—I hear that rolicking scamp of a Sentinel coming, with the mustang, to take up the dead body of the stranger I'll just lay quiet and keep my own secrets. It's every man's duty to be honest, but first be honest to yourself. Often practice it upon yourself and you'll soon learn how to be honest to other people. Come along, myself and papers, we'll meditate, and the overrate we'll soon underrate." A moment more and Lying Pat had slipped into his hole. It's well he did so, if Pat wished to avoid detection, for two horsemen leading a riderless pony trotted down the mountain. Upon reaching the place where the body was lying, they hastily dismounted and flung the corpse across the back of the pack pony; then dextrously making it fast with a lariet, they returned in a gallop in the direction from which they came.</p>
                  <p>"I wonder what's become of Lying Pat to-day?" observed Big Horn to his companion, as they rode away with the body.</p>
                  <p>"I can't say," replied the other man. "He's perhaps in some hole in the ground, and he'll swear to you that he has discovered a gold mine."</p>
                  <p>And so closed up the day's doings; the package of its events was sealed, directed and mailed by the hand of Death; the messenger was Time, and destination Futurity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
                  <p>EXCEPT in the immediate beds of the Gila and Colorado rivers, the country in the Territory of Arizona becomes a dreary waste, destitute of water or vegetation. It is true that in the vallies of Tucson, Tomacaori, Santa Cruz, Messilla, and the Piemos settlement, on the Gila, and San Benadino ranche, are fertile patches of land, where settlers and Indians manage to procure an ample subsistence at an expenditure of very little labor; but here the efforts of the husbandman must cease, as the nature of the surrounding soil is most uninviting to the eye of the farmer and immigrant. The face of the country wears the appearance of a desert, surrounded by hills. Here, almost in the centre of the great inland basin which divides the Gulf of Mexico from the Gulf of California, are located the Apache nation; but the tribe claims dominion and relationship to all the country and all tribes inhabiting the land in the vicinity of the Colorado and Gila rivers.</p>
                  <p>"All gone to Doctor Keating's tent," remarked Pat as he once more emerged from the hole of his cave under ground. He then covered up the aperture with a layer of sticks, and throwing a bush over these, he took his departure, following up the mountain in the direction the horsemen had taken.</p>
                  <p>"What will Doctor Keating say, all the way from Edinburgh college? Plastering up wounds and pulling out teeth for his savage patrons, of beautiful limbs and wholesome breath. I'd rather plaster up their breather. Why, if I had my way, I'd cage the whole of them and send them to the mountains of Ireland to get civilized. What admiration old Mangos and Delgadite would excite at Donnybrook Fair, if surrounded with a dozen or so of his gut-eating crowd. I think cologne would be in demand and the belles of Killarny could well employ their time in making breeches for these heathens. Begora, but this is a fine night," continued Pat, when an hour's walk had brought him higher up towards the summit of the mountain. "It's a beautiful world, after all, if we could only see it as we'd like it. It's a big mirror of a moon to look at it now as I stand. A lake of quicksilver, bordered around with mountains of gold. You can't see such silver nights any where else. All countries have some beauties of their own; that moon is for this land, and no other, and be dad, I be sure of it; and if they don't believe it, let them come and see. And now it strikes me I shall advise Dr. Keating to open a medical school and send to the States for students," and Pat cast himself upon the ground and began laughing. "Say, did ever a hare fly from a coyote quicker than that thieving rascal from the body when that arrow stitched up a rent in his breeches? Be dad, I'll be sure to find him at Dr. Keating's who'll be charging him a pony to cut out the arrow-head." At that moment a figure, with noiseless step advanced to where Pat was lying on his back, laughing.</p>
                  <p>"Get up," spoke the intruder. "The Doctor has been fearing you had died in one of your caves, and we were going to dig the mountain down to find your treasures hid away."</p>
                  <pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC5696-00000010"/>
                  <p>"And where, Crooks, would you put the dirt?" replied the Irishman. "I suppose you'd put it in the hole out of which you took the mountain."</p>
                  <p>"You'd better make your appearance soon; the Doctor wants to use the plaster which you put away and none of us can find," said Crooks.</p>
                  <p>"And is it one of the young copper bloods he wishes to plaster up, Mr. Stiff-neck? I'm sure I could tell the exact spot where the brave was pricked with a thorn."</p>
                  <p>"He was not gagged by a thorn. He says be was hit with an arrow by accident. One of his companions made a misshot," replied Mr. Crook-neck; "but you bad better come along and not let the Doctor lose his fee."</p>
                  <p>"I suppose that two braves were playing leap-frog in the grass," said Pat.</p>
                  <p>"Very likely," replied Crook-neck, "or anything else you please, only come along. Though you make out you are crazy to all others, yet to me it's otherwise. Yon are not the least bit of a fool; so come along, or I'll expose you to the Indians."</p>
                  <p>"I'll go with you," replied Pat, "for I want my supper. There's a difference, though, between us, Mr. Crook-neck; you have observed that I'm not a fool, and I have discovered that you are one. You needn't be swearing so," continued Pat. "Are you not this Dr. Keating's fool? Don't he swear at you? Don't you act the part of a slave to him, and don't you tremble when he talks cross to you? If he frowns, you cringe before him; you fear this Doctor more than the frog does the snake. If it was me he had to deal with, I'd paddle his quarters with his pestle."</p>
                  <p>"You're a boastful fool, and can lie like any trooper at the Fort," replied Crook-neck, "and now get up, or not one mouthfull of food of my cooking shall you eat this night."</p>
                  <p>"Pardon me Mr. Crook-neck. I spoke never a word to you. It was the spirit of my uncle who at times takes possession of my body, and pays no rent for the use of it, and brings some drug, with him that puts my soul to sleep, and then he becomes uproarious and meddlesome, and my poor carcass has to answer for his villainous performances. He once lost myself a fortune; for my rich aunt, who was fond of me, was grossly insulted by him, while he was taking advantage of my weakness, so when she was dying, says she:</p>
                  <p>"'Pat, you are a clever youth, and can get along well in the world. You've got such a blarney in your speech that you'll never require a cent of my money to help you along through the streets of Dublin, and I therefore leave you my blessing. I felt worse than if I had been kicked by the Doctor's mule.'"</p>
                  <p>"And how do you manage to get rid of this spiritual wag?" asked his listener.</p>
                  <p>"Stand on my head for an hour. I think the old fellow must have died with a rush of blood to the head, for he don't seem to like the position. And anyhow I think he was fond of snuff, for he sneezes himself out of my mouth, and my pallet has the taste of sulphur for a week or so after he's gone."</p>
                  <p>"Do you know there's no such a liar living as you are? A natural born and bred liar," said Crooks, "and not a crumb of my bread shall you eat this night," and then he started for the tent, and was quickly followed by Lying Pat.</p>
                  <p>Some ten minutes walk brought the two disputants to Dr. Keating's shop, residence or office, just as you please to call it. It was not a camp, for it was planked up tight in front with short, thin pieces of wood of irregular shape, which the Doctor had induced the natives to bring to him from the Fort. Between these slips of boards mud had been plastered with such care and thickness as to keep out both rain and sunshine. Two natural walls of granite rock extended up from the sides and rear of his abode to the height of ten or more feet. Musquit poles had been placed across this chasm and the interstices or cracks in the roof had been filled in with short and light branches from the same kind of trees. This roof kept off the sun's rays, if it did permit the rain to force its way to his floor; but it gained so seldom and in such small showers as to prove little injurious to either his health or comfort.</p>
                  <p>This office, was divided into two apartments. The front room being the one in which be received his Indian patients, for it was here that Mangos sent his braves when wounded in battle, to be attended, their wounds were dressed by Dr. Keating, and here, too, he pulled out the teeth of the child as well as the warrior. This Dr. Keating was certainly a great man among the Indians, for, he was a useful man and rendered them alleviating services in the hour of distress. Of drugs and medicines he professed to know nothing. So long as he confined his efforts to surgery and dentistry, he was all right and secure in his position; but to have dealt out medicine to heal the sick was hazardous, for he would have labored under the imputation of killing the brave or squaw, in case the patient died while under his treatment, or else been viewed as as impostor and unworthy to live among the tribe. A few chairs, a stool or so, a looking glass, and a large dentist chair was all the furniture in his front room. Two mattresses rolled up in the corner of his room constituted his sleeping arrangements. In his second apartment was a feather bed and bedstead, table, chairs and book stand, with books properly arranged<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC5696-00000011"/> ranged, and even to bowl and pitcher; his claims to comfort extended no further. Where these detached pieces of furniture were procured, or at what price, the Indian alone could tell. Most generally the emigrant trains were the store-houses from whence they obtained their plunder. But it mattered not to the Doctor; his wants were to be supplied at all hazards, and the Indians knew it. They considered him a friend to all the Indians, and as be spoke the Spanish language fluently they could readily comprehend each other. He had no difficulty in communicating all his ideas, whether as to game or furniture. The Doctor indulged them in many of their foolish tastes; but there was one rule strictly enforced in regard to his premises, that when he had drawn a tooth or dressed a wound, the Indian was not permitted to remain near his office, and with thankful hearts they generally obeyed him. In a few brief words we will close a description of his life among them, and he must of necessity treat them kindly, and render himself essential to their comfort, in relieving their pains, or by being liberal to their chiefs when in actual want. All these considerations of policy rendered him a great man among them, and one with whom they would be loth to part.</p>
                  <p>The inner room was occupied every night by himself, for the Doctor was never absent, night or day, when he could possibly help it. In this room was seated the Doctor when Big Horn arrived with Lutella. An Indian had, but a few moments before, brought him a package of letters and newspapers from, Elrick, who had cast them out of the stage at a certain place upon the road-side. An Indian had been sent early that morning to await the arrival of the mail. It may be as well, while we have an opportunity, to take a glance at the Doctor as he sat, arrayed in a faded night-gown, opening the letters and newspapers placed upon the table beside him. Now, then, we have before us Dr. Keating, his countenance denoting a mixture of the Irish and Scotch nationalities. The nose was thin and Italian shaped, the lips thin, but very impressive, the forehead high and towering, the eyes of a bluish gray, the expression of his face was classical when excited, and hypocritical when in repose. His figure was of good size, rather slim, and his carriage was extremely graceful, if not commanding. But if Dr. Keating had been attentively watched for a few moments, a nervous tremor would occasionally have been seen to pervade his whole body. One newspaper only was opened while the Doctor was completing the perusal of his lengthy correspondence, when the Sentinel at the Pass hurriedly entered the office, and without a moment's hesitation or delay, deliberately placed Lutella's form upon the Doctor's bed.</p>
                  <p>"I've brought you, Doctor," said he in almost breathless accents, "I've brought you a patient worth preserving; see to it that you bestow on her all your skill, and delay not a moment. She has fainted twice in my arms while bearing her body up the mountain. Do what you can for her instantly, for when you hear the history of her great loss—the bloody murder at the foot of the hill—I know your sympathy will be excited to the highest pitch of wonder and pity."</p>
                  <p>"I know it all," said the Doctor. "Crook-neck, the sneak, saw it all and told me the whole story. I think the man was to blame. The Indians were chasing some deer and were following the main army on their way to Mexico, when to show their dexterity with their bows, they shot a few random arrows into the top of the stage, when some great man, or great fool, jumped from his seat and rashly let drive with his Sharpe's rifle. You, perhaps, as well as Crook-neck, know the sequel."</p>
                  <p>"In substance it is substantially correct," replied Lutella's protector. "But the girl had nothing to do with the affair, and must, therefore, be most honorably protected. Say you not so, Doctor?"</p>
                  <p>"Do you know her name? But wait a moment Big Horn," added Keating, "You are sweating like one of those buffalo bulls after a hard day's drive. I should judge you had a pretty hard walk of it. Why, man, I'll venture to say that there is not a muscle in you that is not strained. Come, let me refresh your strength and courage." He then unlocked a sailor's chest and taking a bottle of brandy from one corner of it, he handed it to the Sentinel of the Pass, who, after having satisfied his thirst, passed it to the Doctor, who, having done likewise, placed the bottle on the table.</p>
                  <p>"I asked you for the girl's name," said the Doctor.</p>
                  <p>"I have forgotten it," replied Big Horn; "but it's cut in the stock of the rifle of the murdered man. I hid it away in the bushes."</p>
                  <p>"Then it will be gone before day to-morrow morning if you did not hide it well, for Crook-neck or Pat will steal it."</p>
                  <p>"I promised the girl to bring up the body here and to bury it in her presence, and you can see it and identify it, perhaps."</p>
                  <p>"That's a good idea," said the Doctor after a few moments given to thought. "Crook-neck and you can soon gallop down with an extra horse and bring up the corpse."</p>
                  <p>"It is best," replied the Sentinel, "but you'd better give the girl some attention."</p>
                  <p>"No, no, let her sleep, I'll see her after an hour or so, she's only worn out with excitement, fatigue and grief. She's<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC5696-00000012"/> in comfortable quarters, what more could she desire? Do you know who was in command of the squad who shot the stranger?"</p>
                  <p>"Yes," replied the young man, "It was Delgadite."</p>
                  <p>"I never liked the dirty scoundrel," replied the Doctor, "he has the worst face of any one of his tribe. I believe even Mangos is afraid of him. Have you met the Irishman? I want him to visit the Fort for me, my supply of powder is nearly exhausted."</p>
                  <p>"I can replenish your stock," said the Sentinel.</p>
                  <p>"It's not exactly that," replied the Doctor, "but I may have a friend or so to serve. Besides, my supply of candles is giving out, and to be without plenty of light would drive me mad, indeed. Now you and Crook-neck had better bring up the body."</p>
                  <p>When the clatter of the horses' feet assured him of the departure of the Sentinel and his companion, the Doctor took his candle and returned to the room in which Lutella was lying. Her short, quick breathing denoted that the girl, though asleep, was in a most wretched and restless condition of mind. The grey traveling dress which enclosed her form was spotted in front with darker stains of crimson blood, while the green veil which was tied around her neck, and even her kid gloves, gave evidence of their close contact with human gore. The Doctor quietly removed the veil and gloves; he next brought water, basin and towel, and after softly turning her upon her back, with her face fully exposed to view, he bathed her brow and washed the blood from her cheeks and lips. After performing this ablutory service to his young patient, and having <choice>
                        <sic>releaved</sic>
                        <corr>relieved</corr>
                     </choice> his hand of towel and basin, when an idea seemed to strike him, for, bringing a light, he once more hurried to the bed, and intently gazing upon the features of the sleeping girl. His body reeled from the bed. He had seen that countenance or its counterpart somewhere upon this broad earth. "I shall await until to-morrow for further disclosures," he said.</p>
                  <p>The Doctor resumed the perusal of the letters and papers, some of which he left unopened upon the table. After hurriedly glancing at some of the letters which seemed of no importance, be seemed to scrutinize the foreign post-mark of one which had escaped his attention in the first instance. After breaking the seal, he glanced at the closely-written pages, and soliloquized as follows:</p>
                  <p>"What could have moved my sister to take a house in Liverpool? My father dead! Mother! Only my sister living. Only a small estate out of the accumulation of half a century. Replenish the coffers of the family by marrying some wealthy lady. Well, my anxious sister, that's sooner proposed than accomplished. It is true I might fall heir to the Knight's estate were there no offspring intervening, and Sir Harry being a widower and not very far advanced in years of dotage. Still there are chances in my favor. Only one, child. Sir Harry's fond of travelling. Only a life interest in the estate, which, at his death falls to his oldest child in fee simple. Well, Sir Harry was my father's brother, and, of course, having only one child, my sister is told by her solicitor that, in case anything should happen Alfred Keating, your humble servant would fall heir to a large share of the movable, barring a will in somebody else's favor, and the entailed estate."</p>
                  <p>The noise of advancing horses broke the chain of his soliloquizing, and hastening from the office be met Crooks and the Sentinel returning with the corpse.</p>
                  <p>"Where shall we place it?" asked the Sentinel.</p>
                  <p>"Here," replied the Doctor. "Bring it in here, into the office."</p>
                  <p>"And the girl?" asked the Sentinel. "Is she still asleep?"</p>
                  <p>"She is still asleep, soundly sleeping," replied the Doctor.</p>
                  <p>"I'm glad of it," replied Crooks, "for I don't like to hear people cry their screaming noise. The fact is, I don't much like to handle dead people, any how. All the time we were bringing this man's body up the mountain, I felt as if his ghost was following behind his horse to see where we intended to bury his body."</p>
                  <p>"Who gave you any right to think or speak about his spirit. You'll never have a ghost," sternly rejoined the Doctor. "It was seared out of you. Well, no matter," and poor Crooks shied off toward the tent without a word more that night; while in the full blaze of the mild moon's night splendor they untied the lariets with which the body was fastened to the horse, and then carried the remains of Sir Harry into the Office, placed it on a table and threw a blanket over it.</p>
                  <p>"Shall we bury it to-night?" asked the Doctor.</p>
                  <p>"Not to-night," replied the Sentinel. "I have promised to let her see the remains deposited in the earth."</p>
                  <p>"Well, then, we have got a spade here, and can dig the grave to-night while the girl is sleeping. Come, Crook-neck, get the spade and let's get to work."</p>
                  <p>Some fifty yards from the office a spot was selected, a grave measured off and the work began, the blade of the shovel dazzlingly reflecting the full splendor of the midnight moon. They worked in silence, supplying each other's places in the hole, until the work was completed. When the grave<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC5696-00000013"/> was deemed sufficiently deep, discussion was had between them as to the propriety of wrapping the body in a winding-sheet, or making a box. The Sentinel of the Pass objected to any other way except giving to the deceased a decent and Christian burial.</p>
                  <p>"It cannot be done here. I'll tell you what can be done though. We can sew the body up in an old piece of tarpaulin, and it will be preserved."</p>
                  <p>As the Doctor's word was law, all acquiesced.</p>
                  <p>"And the wolves will have it out in a night," replied Crooks.</p>
                  <p>"That's true," said the Doctor.</p>
                  <p>"We can guard against that," said the Sentinel. "We'll wrap the body in wolf-skins for an outer covering, singeing the hair first. There are several lying near the office, and the body will never be disturbed. I've seen it tried many a time."</p>
                  <p>"Let it be so then," replied the Doctor, "and at early dawn, we will dispose of the last of this rash Englishman. And now let's return to the office."</p>
                  <p>When all was quiet and still around the Doctor's abode, and when only could be heard the jarring strike of the grave-digger's shovel against imbedded rocks in the sterile soil upon the knoll, Lutella awoke to consciousness and to misery. From the small and narrow abode which she occupied, she distinctly saw, through the open door, the candle throwing its feeble glow of light around the gloomy room of the Doctor's mountain home. Her mind, confused by the strange and <choice>
                        <sic>wierd</sic>
                        <corr>weird</corr>
                     </choice> appearance of all objects by which she was surrounded, remained in a quiescent state for several minutes. Slowly but surely she began to collect her ideas, while, through the agency of memory, facts and objects began to arrange themselves with natural order and substantial impressions upon her sight and senses, until at last, with a sudden bound, she sprang from the bed with eyes expanded and all her senses rendered more acute by the dreadful silence that oppressed her existence, she moved with faltering step toward the candle. A mist seemed to settle in the room from floor to ceiling. "There! there!—I feel it, know it—there lies the body of my father!" she exclaimed, as she fixed her gaze upon the blanket which covered the corpse. "I can tell the demon of the curse which has wrought this ruin, that I, too, am a spirit demon for evil and destruction, and never shall it cease to follow his life, to pursue and torture unto death this fiend, this savage monster, whose pitiless weapon pierced the heart of as brave and gallant a gentleman and as loving a parent as ever trod the earth. Merciful Father in Heaven! may my spirit never rest contented until, from valley to mountain-top, from plain to ocean's shore, through torrents and across rivers and floods—never rest my soul, night or day, in storm or sunshine, until I avenge the blood this day shed in brutal treachery; or be the soul accursed who fails to follow where I lead, to bring this hellish beast to justice; and if he fail me not in the righting of this unholy wrong, then all of earthly things I possess, let him claim—all, and if he so will it, this hand and body."</p>
                  <p>Then taking the light, she slowly <choice>
                        <sic>appproached</sic>
                        <corr>approached</corr>
                     </choice> the table, and in accents slow in their utterance said: "Poor attendant on man's wants in darkness, lend me thy friendly glow. You show us our wants and our weaknesses less great than the sun; thou art most useful in his absence." She raised the edge of the blanket, and as though satisfied that her conjectures were right that the body of Sir Harry rested beneath its folds, she threw off the blanket from his face and gazed intently upon the countenance of the dead. She replaced the blanket, and kneeling beside the table devoted some minutes to prayer. Then arising, she again lifted the covering, and stooping, kissed the cold, broad brow thrice; and again she kissed it, and as the tears dimmed her vision, she lisped in long-drawn accents from the depths of her soul: "I but weaken my spirit and flesh by permitting my grief thus to toy with that which was, but now is no longer of life. Good night, father; farewell forever! Oh, who now will prove my friend—who supply the place of such a parent—on what arm shall I lean for support?" and she pressed her handkerchief to her eyes.</p>
                  <p>A shadow now flitted across the room, and a voice spoke as in response to her agonizing wail of woe:</p>
                  <p>"I am that friend; I am that protector. I rove fearless on these plains, over these mountains. I fear neither the savage, nor the wild beasts who inhabit this wilderness of sand. I can traverse the mountains by night, with the stars for my lamp, and the fords of the streams are known to me when the mountain mists descends upon our rivers."</p>
                  <p>"Who are you, and what is your name?" she interrupted. "I know you as one remembers some image he has seen in dreams. Speak, and tell me who and what you are?" she responded.</p>
                  <p>"I am styled the Sentinel at the Pass. The Doctor calls me Big Horn."</p>
                  <p>"There," she interrupted, "that will do. I remember all now. You are the mountain guide who rescued me while clinging to my father's body, and it was you, no doubt, who brought me to this place of safety. But do tell me your real name, that on my knees I may thank you for your mercy and<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC5696-00000014"/> your bravery." And she cast herself upon her knees beside the table, and said: "Oh, if your kind, true and noble heart could but hear me thank you—"</p>
                  <p>"Get up," in all kindness; "let me aid you," said the young man. "You will certainly exhaust your natural strength. You are more feeble than you imagine," and then raising the trembling form in his arms, he gently led her to the bed she had previously occupied. "I will sit beside you until the Doctor and the rest return."</p>
                  <p>"Thank you," she feebly replied. "Take your station and stand before me with the light." The young Sentinel did as he was bid, when she remarked: "I have seen that face before I left England. Yours is a manly countenance; you have some resemblance to my mother's family. Tell me, if you will really oblige me, your real name?"</p>
                  <p>"I have none," replied her protector. "I have eschewed civilization, and with it my family name. I surrendered it when I left home. It is now one of the heirlooms of the family."</p>
                  <p>"Well, I suppose I must rest content, but my head is very painful. Moisten my handkerchief and place it over my brow; —I think I am feverish."</p>
                  <p>The young man willingly complied with her request, and she sank into a quiet repose with her hand clasped in his.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
                  <p>There is as much of mystery as there is of reality in this world. The one develops itself without an effort, and the other is made manifest by our desires and strenuous attempts on our part to satisfy them. "How came I to meet this girl among these deserts and rocks? How came I here <choice>
                        <sic>at at</sic>
                        <corr>at</corr>
                     </choice> all? What spell deluded me to fly from the confines of civilization and tarry here in this wilderness, where the very heavens refuse fertility to the soil and rains to the parched and sandy plains? Alas! I fear there is more direction in this adventure than my finite mind can comprehend. Was this all intention upon the part of the great Deity, or was this meeting with the girl the mere result of chance? It is most singular, to say the least of it. Was it Fate, was it Destiny, that Sir Harry was to end his life, here in the very centre of the most blood-thirsty of the Indian race—to be shot down in daylight, in the presence of his only daughter. And I, why was made an instrument to witness his death and burial? It is all incomprehensible prehensible to me. And by what strange combination of circumstances was, this grieving girl made to witness the butchery of the very mortal who had brought her into life, nourished and protected her in infancy, and set the soul of his being in the adornment of her mind and body? And here she lies, a wretched miserable object of pity, away from friends and relatives, isolated from all that rendered her youthful years enjoyable from all those scenes sacred to home influences, which purify and ennoble the soul aspiring for a glorious immortality. I, too, had a home, surrounded with every comfort. Friends, relatives, luxuries—all, all were at my command to add to the enjoyment of life. And yet, all were forsaken, abandoned by myself, and all this given up—and here, clothed in the dress of a Nimrod, I wander, without an object in view, over hills where no springs afford water to the thirsty traveler, and where the famished wolf, in the very agony of his misery, howls forth to the burnished moon the complainings of his distress."</p>
                  <p>What would be the musings of any man similarly placed after a day's excitement like that through which the Sentinel had passed? The corpse of the courtly knight, with the broken arrow-head near the heart and a portion of the shaft protruding from the chest, the feverish hand of the young girl, with jeweled rings upon her fingers, clasped within his own, and the screech of the ground-owl upon the brush roof already chanting the funeral dirge. After a battle, the Sentinel would, without any remorse of conscience or pertuberation of spirit, wrap his blood-stained blanket around his chilled and wearied form, cast himself upon the gory field and close his eyes in profound slumber; and at early morn be ready at the first call of the bugle to renew the fight or join in the pursuit. But his present situation afforded no such stimulation to action. Sad thoughts of home, combined with a thrill of mysterious awe, seemed to pervade his senses, until with a shudder he started from his seat, and hurriedly leaving the tent, sought the refreshing dew of night to allay the nervous excitement of his mind. He had scarcely reached the open air when, the Doctor and Crook-Neck drew near.</p>
                  <p>"Go in," said the young man. "You will find the young girl asleep."</p>
                  <p>"And the corpse, too, I dare say," replied the Doctor. "The grave is all ready to receive it. Come, get ready the tarpaulin, and we will tie it round the form."</p>
                  <p>"So be it—all except the head, which we will leave uncovered until the young girl has seen it once more," replied the Sentinel.</p>
                  <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC5696-00000015"/>
                  <p>"It is but a reasonable request, Big Horn," said the Doctor. "So now all hands hurry to finish this unpleasant task."</p>
                  <p>The three stood around the table while the Doctor uncovered the face, Crook-Neck holding the light. As the glare of the candle's flame fell upon the features of the dead, the Doctor started back with a look of horror, and raising both hands above his head, exclaimed:</p>
                  <p>"Great God! it cannot be! Am I dreaming? It is indeed the face of Sir Harry Bart. Cover up the face again, my friend, and give me a few moments to recover my senses. I knew him well. What an end was his. 'Tis strange beyond all comprehension. He speaks to me dead, what he never dared to speak to me while living. He may have thought it, he may have suspected it, but never has spoken the sentence. No matter. I tell you what it is, men," he said as he turned his wild, glaring eyes upon his horror-stricken companions, "There is nothing like it in all animated nature; no, nothing like the accusing features of the dead. Get you to work men; I cannot touch that body. I will meet you at the grave at early sunrise; so do your parts manfully. These devilish tempting thoughts within me must be crushed out or I am lost!" saying which, the Doctor flung a blanket over his shoulders and left the office. Where he rested or where he roved, no one knew. But the two abiders by the dead body faithfully performed their sorrowful task, and when the first faint blush in the east announced the coming day, they awoke the girl from her slumber and bad her prepare for the funeral. Lutella's grief was excessive, and her step was faltering and unsteady as she followed the two men who bore the mortal remains of her parent to the grave. The Doctor was there leaning on the spade when they arrived.</p>
                  <p>"Put in the body; place it in carefully and fill in the dirt. I'll meet you at the office, and—I'll meet you at the office," he repeated. "I am not well; I'll have coffee when you return." No more he spoke, for with quickened step he hurried from the gloomy scene.</p>
                  <p>"Kind friends, let me say my last prayer <choice>
                        <sic>over over</sic>
                        <corr>over</corr>
                     </choice> my father's body; it was he who, while living, taught me to pray—let me not forget his holy lessons when he is no more."</p>
                  <p>Kneeling beside the grave, she prayed in a low whisper and with deep earnestness, and when her prayer was ended, she requested them to cover up the dust with rocks and sand.</p>
                  <p>"He will not rest here long," she said, "his remains will be removed to his native England, where he was born and should have died. Oh, my father, what cruel fate stamped your destiny to this sad end!"</p>
                  <p>True to his promise, when the work of filling up the grave was finished, they were cheered by seeing breakfast prepared; but nowhere could the table upon which the corpse had been placed be seen.</p>
                  <p>"Get ready the benches. Come, now, my sweet, grieving child," the Doctor added, "a cup of hot coffee will impart warmth to your body, and act as a soothing drink to your nerves. Now, pray, tell us by what name they called you when baptised?" imploringly asked the doctor.</p>
                  <p>"My name is Lutella," she replied; "I was named after my mother."</p>
                  <p>"A very pretty and classical name—the moon and stars combined; and your mother's family name, if you please, Miss?" he asked, in a careless way of questioning.</p>
                  <p>"Voiture, sir; it is of French extraction."</p>
                  <p>"And you are the only living child?"</p>
                  <p>"The only child born of my father's marriage with my mother."</p>
                  <p>"Have you any relations living?" he again inquired.</p>
                  <p>"I have some cousins and other distant relatives. My mother had no sisters; my mother's father was lost at sea. My father had a brother, but we heard he had traveled into foreign parts, and we believe he is dead."</p>
                  <p>"Did your father never get a letter from him?" he still went on to question her.</p>
                  <p>"I think not. I have heard from my mother that my uncle was a person of quick temper and hasty words. That he broke with my grandfather and cursed him, and for this cause my grandfather cut him off with a shilling in his will. He blamed my mother as the cause of this loss, and grossly insulted her, which my father would not endure, though he was his own brother, and he shut the door of his house against him, and forbade him ever to enter his doors again."</p>
                  <p>"Of course your uncle was much enraged by this want of feeling upon the part of his brother," he observed.</p>
                  <p>"When relations fall out," she added, "they are very bitter in their feelings against each other, and uncle swore vengeance against both of them, and to carry out his threat of vengeance, he bribed some bad man to steal me away when quite young, and the person being detected in the act, and my father having a suspicion as to who prompted it, promised the man not to prosecute him if he would tell the real criminal's name, and he did so and accused my uncle, who shortly after disappeared, and they have heard nothing of him since. I was then sent away, or rather hid away at school, until they thought all danger of being stolen was past."</p>
                  <pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC5696-00000016"/>
                  <p>"You never saw your uncle?" he asked with seeming indifference.</p>
                  <p>"I do not remember him. I may have seen him; but if I had, the time has been so long ago, and I was so young, I could not recollect him."</p>
                  <p>"Did they say he resembled your father?"</p>
                  <p>"Not at all," she replied. "My father took after my grandfather's family, and my uncle after my grandmother's."</p>
                  <p>"Come, now, let's have our breakfast. A good cup of coffee, and antelope chops and biscuit will strengthen us all."</p>
                  <p>The girl refused to eat, but drank freely of the coffee.</p>
                  <p>"Of course," observed the Doctor, "you will rest awhile with us, until you recover from your fatigue. We will make you as comfortable as possible."</p>
                  <p>"I will stay with you for a month or two," she replied. "I must watch nightly beside my father's grave until it shall lose its freshness. The wolves must never mangle his remains."</p>
                  <p>"And then?" asked the Doctor. At that moment the heavy trot of the trooper's war-horse, and the shaking clatter of the brass scabbards, ended all further questionings, and the next moment the Lieutenant of a squad of troopers swung himself, with a military curve, from his charger, and without an instant's delay, entered the Doctor's abode and said:</p>
                  <p>"So, Keating, a sad affair has happened near your quarters. Quick, man, tell us all about it, for we must follow the rascals. I hear Sir Harry Bart has been shot at the very door of the Pass, and we but a few miles distant. God! if my men had only been there."</p>
                  <p>"Sir Harry, or whoever else you may call him, was killed by that Apache chief, Dalgadite, and we buried him out yonder, about a hundred yards or so from where we stand."</p>
                  <p>"I do not think the killing was premeditated. This young man here," replied the Doctor, pointing to the Sentinel, "will explain to you all the circumstances concerning the affair."</p>
                  <p>"And will cheerfully do so," replied the Sentinel.</p>
                  <p>"Ah, Big Horn!" exclaimed the officer, grasping the young man's hand. "You once rendered me a great service, and I shall not soon forget it. Please let's hear the whole matter, briefly stated."</p>
                  <p>"Never mind that at present," replied the Sentinel; and he then told all he knew of the sad accident.</p>
                  <p>"And the girl, where is she?" asked the Lieutenant, in an off-hand way.</p>
                  <p>"Walk in and I will present her to you," replied the Doctor; "I thought it best to send to the Colonel for an escort to protect her to the Fort."</p>
                  <p>"And by Jupiter, she shall have it. Now please offer my services at once, and say that I am ready, I and my troopers, and will take it as a great favor, and protect her to the bitter end."</p>
                  <p>"I know, Lieutenant, your chivalrous nature; but she insists upon remaining here, to protect the grave of her father from the degradations of the wolves."</p>
                  <p>"It is impossible for her to remain in this comfortless abode, Doctor, tell her, with my compliments. Remain here! Why, it would be barbarous, she will certainly accept our services on this occasion."</p>
                  <p>"One would think so," replied the Doctor. "but you little know the race from which she sprung. I have heard of her family, and their peculiar traits of character; I could recite you instances of their fixedness of purpose—when they once resolve upon a course of action they are immovable."</p>
                  <p>At this moment Lutella made her appearance. When the troops arrived she had retired to the back apartment, and now thought it her duty to represent herself in person.</p>
                  <p>"I have heard your inquiry and generous offer," she spoke, bowing with great ease and simplicity of manner; "I am truly thankful for the interest taken in a poor isolated creature like myself. I can not go with you. Nay, do not speak," she entreated, as she saw the Lieutenant about to remonstrate. "Do not, pray, press me on this subject; believe me, without wishing to offend, that nothing can move me from this determination."</p>
                  <p>"Then I shall not urge it, and shall only protest at the injustice you do us, and state to you that the Colonel will be deeply mortified at your refusal," replied the Lieutenant.</p>
                  <p>"I do not refuse," she replied; "the time for accepting your generous offer has not yet arrived; the day may come when I may be thankful to accept your offer; for the present I must leave you. Convey to the Colonel every assurance of my thankful heart."</p>
                  <p>"One word more, Miss," entreated the officer; "what may be your name?"</p>
                  <p>"Lutella Bart. And now while opportunity avails I wish to thank all of you, and particularly that gentleman," she said, glancing at the Sentinel, "for the careful attention shown me on this trying occasion," she said, bowing, and then retired to her room.</p>
                  <p>"I tell you what, Doctor," said the Lieutenant, much excited, when they had left the office, "this will never do; I say it will never do. The Colonel will never stand it. Why, it would be a species of barbarity to permit her to suffer this<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC5696-00000017"/> rough usage, and alone here without a female companion. I will see to it, depend upon it; and blood spots still on her dress. It can not, must not be. Look to her, Doctor," he said with his right hand firmly grasping the hilt of his sword. "You know I have the name of being a hard rider, and swift to revenge an injury, but in an affair like this, if I had been born with a heart of stone or iron it would melt."</p>
                  <p>"I believe you," replied the Doctor, offering his hand. "The Indians call you Blood-Eater, but to me you have ever seemed an honest and high-minded soldier."</p>
                  <p>"Let them call me so," replied the officer, while his face flushed with anger. "I have seen nineteen of my men, when helpless in sleep, murdered with ghastly wounds from liver to throat. I have witnessed sights of horror, and deeds of blood inflicted upon the harmless immigrants that would make the sight of a demon recoil from the horrid spectacle. Go ask any of my brave troopers there if I have exaggerated in one jot or tittle the infamous crimes of this accursed nation."</p>
                  <p>"They are savages; remember that Lieutenant," observed the Doctor, "we must only expect to find savage instincts as an apology for their butchery of all strangers."</p>
                  <p>"I'll tell you what they are," said Crook-Neck, trying to straighten up his head, "in our country they would be styled felons, and they'd all be hung by the neck."</p>
                  <p>The Doctor gave the deformed such a withering look of rebuke as to make him retire into the office.</p>
                  <p>"I would not have such a hatred, scorn and loathing contempt for these people were it not for their skulking, sneaking and treacherous mode of warfare; they ever avoid an open fight when attacked, and steal upon their enemies and murder them in cold blood, granting no quarters—even the child at the breast is given to the knife. I would I could be more terrible in my wrath in fighting these devils. I shall see you again Doctor; look well to your charge. At any hour my forces are at your command." The lieutenant waved his hand in token of a friendly parting. In another moment he was in his saddle, leading his troops down the mountain side, towards the mouth of the Pass.</p>
                  <p>"I like the looks of those fellows," said the Doctor, "there's something bold in their very visages, and recklessness in their daring. How firm they sit in their saddles; there's solid weight there. Big Horn, admire those troopers, they are just the thing to rove through this infernal country. Did you not observe the arrow scars on their cheeks? and that Lieutenant is just the one to lead those chaps into a fight. There, see them descending the hill, how regularly they move, their carbines bines on their backs, all seem to move in a line; and Big Horn, go you and see to the child, while I speak a word to this friend of mine."</p>
                  <p>The Sentinel did as requested, when the Doctor spoke as follows to Crook-Neck: "You well may tremble you cowardly cur," he said as Crook-Neck stood beside him in a quivering fright. "Who authorized you to speak about hanging? Was it for this license of your tongue that when you were cut down from the gallows saw it for this you upbraided me, that with a false tube I kept the breath in your body and stiffened your neck with a braided rope, and when I secured your body from the hangman; aye, and paid for it, too, and then restored you to life, that you talk of hanging. Roll up that sleeve on your arm and call the officers of the law, and show them where I cut off the pieces of flesh to disfigure your face, or, rather, improve it. You remember that so changed your countenance that even your own cousin did not recognize you?"</p>
                  <p>"I wish you had have let me died," said Crook-Neck, while he cast himself upon his knees before his tyrant and tormentor.</p>
                  <p>"It had been better if I had done so, for all the use you have been to me," replied the Doctor. "I want no more talk about hanging, or I'll hand you over to the law."</p>
                  <p>"I did not bring myself to life; you did it, and they'd hold you to answer for it," said Crook-Neck.</p>
                  <p>"Pooh, you villain." said the other; "the law rewards its citizens for saving life. Now let me hear no more of such nonsense. Get up and behave yourself, or your daughter shall be cast out from school, and be a beggar on the streets, and never have one cent of the money."</p>
                  <p>The Doctor led the way to the brow of the hill, while Crook-Neck skulked on behind, brooding over his master's terrible threatenings. Dr. Keating was in trouble. The shadows of events grew taller and darker towards the sunset of life. Surrounded by comfort and luxuries, his youth was reared; he had borrowed from time, and the interest had accumulated, and the creditor was rapping at the door of his conscience for admission, and demanding payment of the interest, if not for the principal. There could be no refusal to pay now, the creditor ever cried for justice; he would be heard, and his claim must be paid, in part if not in full. Keating watched the file of troopers until their blue uniforms faded in the distance, and then turning his steps towards the office, he saw two Indians advancing, carrying between them one of the warriors of their tribe, apparently severely wounded. He entered his office and brought out a chair, and awaited their approach in silence. He received them with all the apparent<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC5696-00000018"/> friendliness which policy suggested. Upon an examination of the wound he discovered that the savage had received an arrow in his hip, and driven, too, with such force as to have passed through the flesh and project on the opposite side. The Doctor drew out the arrow, the head forward, and then washing the wound with turpentine, and tying a strong bandage round the leg, and telling his companion to take him home and keep the limb quiet, was about to enter his office, when another of his patients complained of the tooth-ache; quick as thought, in his capacity as dentist, the Doctor produced his forceps and making the complainant open his mouth, he ripped out a molar with all imaginable dexterity, while the other Indians cried "bravo, bravo."</p>
                  <p>After giving some directions for treating the wounded man, he dismissed the trio, but first asked the Indians by whom he was shot; to which the wounded warrior replied, "some one who was hid away in the grass, probably a thieving Piemos." To me this was a mystery in savage life, and might be sufficient cause to engender strife between the inhabitants of the Piemos village and the Arabs of the plains. Such an act against one of our citizens along the border of the Rio Grande would cause a commission to be sent by our Senate to inquire into such an act of treachery, but with the Indian, his only recourse was to apply the law of retaliation, and a Piemos <choice>
                        <sic>citisen</sic>
                        <corr>citizen</corr>
                     </choice> would surely fall beneath the arm of some kindred of the defunct warrior.</p>
                  <p>But was this arrow, by which the lying thief was so seriously wounded, sent from a Piemos' bow? Certainly it needed in part confirmation; yet the reader will entertain the suspicion that Pat had tried his skill with terrible effect upon "somebody's t'other end of nothing."</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
                  <p>As the day advanced in lightness, Lutella, accompanied by the Sentinel, visited her father's grave, and when there, with the assistance of her companion, who carried the spade, they rounded it of its sharp edges, and raised higher the mound of sand.</p>
                  <p>Has it never been observed with what eager haste, the dead are buried, and how anxious most people are to hasten from the grave, but it was different with the two young people, who had performed what they considered a sacred duty. They lingered for over an hour, conversing in low tones upon the surrounding scenery. Away to the west was seen long ranges of mountains, and lone hills or peaks ascending above the dreary waste. The sluggish Gila could be traced for many a mile as it moved with slow current towards the boisterous and treacherous Colorado, while to the east the broad stretch of plains extended to the opposite hills beyond.</p>
                  <p>"This air is so brilliant, soft and refreshing, I wish my dear parent could be here to enjoy it. It will prove a doleful day to many of his friends in England, for I can assure you," she added with much warmth of feeling, "he was very much admired and respected there, Mr. Sentinel."</p>
                  <p>"I do not doubt it," replied her companion, "only let us retire from the unpleasant sight this evening, we can renew our visit to-morrow."</p>
                  <p>"Be it so," she said, "I can not expect you to take the same interest in my loss as myself; but you have rendered me so many acts of kindness, I shall comply with your request. I presume it is unnecessary to apologize for these tears, they in part relieve my grief, for I tell you I am dreadfully unhappy."</p>
                  <p>And so ended their first visit to the grave. The day passed off without further fright or annoyances; the sun, though still lingering above the horizon, seemed robbed of more than half his splendor, a thick mist of a purple blue hanging round the tops of the mountains.</p>
                  <p>When the Sentinel and Lutella were on the eve of renewing their visit to the last resting place of a once dear parent, their ears were greeted with several shouts of advancing muleteers, and then came the crack of the whip and the jingle of the bell mule.</p>
                  <p>"Stick to your feet, my hearties; Pat, you lazy scamp, the Apaches will have your scalp yet, if you lag so far behind—come, tug away, you little cusses, or I'll not put shoes on you, nor rub your teeth with snow, if you don't hurry up," and often spoke and shouted the muleteer, as he neared the Doctor's office.</p>
                  <p>"Oh, I know that voice, 'tis Elrick's, the driver's; let me hasten to meet him," exclaimed Lutella, and she bounded from the door; and as Elrick and Pat halted the mules, she scarcely permitted the driver to alight before she grasped both his hands and started into tears.</p>
                  <p>"My dearest young lady," said the hardy and fearless driver of the plains, "how I grieved for you; it was a sad mishap, but we can't check up when Providence wills it so; we can only wait for time to wear off the rough points of our sorrow. That's not a bad man, Miss," said he, pointing to Pat; "he sent word to the troopers, and mounting one of the mustangs,<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC5696-00000019"/> brought us word at the station, ten miles away from here, and told us all of your misfortunes, and how you wanted clothing, took yours and Sir Harry's leather bags from the stage; got another driver in my place and here we are, as you see, all safe with the baggage, and I hope nothing's lost. I saw the danger when your father jumped from the coach, but couldn't hold the critters, they were so frightened, and when you flung yourself out my very heart froze like a big red ball of blood, but never could I hold 'em up for a second. If you want evidence of who was the rascals who shot your father, I can swear it was Delgadite, the very worst devil among the whole of the greasy cusses. But where's the Doctor?"</p>
                  <p>"Sleeping under his blankets, on the mattresses," replied the Sentinel.</p>
                  <p>"Well, you three, with that lazy Irishman—no, I'll take that back, we have stuck well together. The Doctor is as good, if not better, than any of you, and he is a good surgeon too, for he pulled a tooth for me with a fish-hook—I say let him sleep. If we had let the troops tended on us all this trouble would have been saved to us; not that it's a nuisance to bring the valises, only, I say, that they would have made the copper-skins quicken their gate a little; but no matter now, whatever our Great Master wills must not be talked about with irreverence, if we did, it would do no good, and be like throwing a glass of water on that desert down there and expecting it to spring out of the ground. Come, Pat, unstrap the mules; let's get the bags off and take 'em into the Doctor's office, that the young lady may get some clean clothes on; she'll feel better, poor child, when she gets some clean feathers on her."</p>
                  <p>At the end of this uncouth, yet friendly harangue by the driver, Pat unpacked the mules, and after larrietting them out, carried the valises into the back room of the office.</p>
                  <p>"Now go, fly my young lady and examine the baggage and write me a clean receipt; business is business, at all times, and I am not the man to be spoken of at the agent's office as one having been unfaithful in the discharge of his duty."</p>
                  <p>Lutella had followed Pat into the room, and the Sentinel and Elrick were soon busily engaged in conversation.</p>
                  <p>"Of course you'll rest your mules," said the Sentinel.</p>
                  <p>"Yes, until noon to-morrow, for they've beat the speed of the antelope on this drive. But look there," he said, for the Irishman, upon leaving the office, had cast himself upon the ground, and was soon snoring with lengthened drawings of forgetfulness. "Let him sleep on, he was up all night and nearly all day in the saddle. I was in my bed, but could not sleep for thinking of the fate of poor Sir Harry, and his child, and when the night had clearly passed, and Pat came to hand and told us the story, my mind grew distracted, and as quick as we could catch fresh mules we started off, and here we are. I'll tell you what, he's got as good a heart as ever God put into a Man, for he shed many tears when he told me how it all happened."</p>
                  <p>"Why, I did not see him," said the Sentinel, "he must have been hid away in the brush."</p>
                  <p>"Well, he was there of a certainty, for he knows it all. But we differ on one point, he don't like the Doctor, and I do, but he'll get over that hatred when he knows the Doctor better. And now let's see if we can't trump up a morsel of grub."</p>
                  <p>"We have biscuit, and coffee and cold antelope meat; will you walk in, Driver?"</p>
                  <p>"No, don't disturb the young lady," replied Elrick, "we can take it out here. The open air every time for me when 'taint wet round about, but I believe it never rains in this blasted territory. If I'd have my way, I'd wash it out from the face of the globe by letting the ocean run over it. I shall take my rifle to-morrow at daybreak and look up that big horned mountain goat. Do you know the old fellow waits for me every time I pass with the stage? I thought him a good omen, but now he's otherwise. I'll let drive at him in real earnest, and we'll have a good roast off his quarters if he comes within the reach of my rifle. He's a good dodger, but nothing can dodge powder and ball every time."</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
                  <p>The day had vanished, the great big-hearted moon, all aglow with swelling glory and expanding life and light, had, to all appearances, absorbed the sun and stars, and was climbing up the eastern horizon when, rifle in hand, accompanied by Lutella, the Sentinel left the office to guard the grave. The driver was lying in profound sleep; Pat was none the less oblivious to all transient objects, and thus silence reigned supreme around the office, when, from beneath his blankets, the Doctor drew his well-proportioned form and glanced around the apartment. He stood erect in silence for ten or twenty minutes, as though undecided what conclusion to arrive at, in completing his plan of action under the present circumstances. During the whole time from the arrival of the driver and Pat at his door, he lay stretched upon his bed, intently observing all that had transpired near him; had heard the whole account as related<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC5696-00000020"/> lated by Elrick concerning the flight of the mules, and Pat's subsequent arrival at the station, and their return with the valise; saw from beneath his covering the exact spot where they were placed, and now, when all around was quieted down to a dead silence, he prepared his mind and senses for immediate action in carrying out a set purpose, and that was to obtain all information connected with Sir Harry's personal and real estate at the time of his death. He left the abode, and cautiously moved among the sleepers, and then approaching near where a protecting rock hung near the office wall, be rested his elbow upon its point and steadfastly gazed upon the face of the moon for a few minutes, and then returning to his office he neared a corner of the room and dragged a sleeping body from beneath several hair pods used in packing the mules, and said:</p>
                  <p>"Get up, you are wanted; come, we'll freshen up; a glass or so will restore our sight. I only wish I had power to straighten your neck." The Doctor's 'slave,' as Pat called him, sprang instantly to his feet, when, from a leather flask, the Doctor poured their usual measure of drinks; and when he had replaced the flask beneath the blanket, the Doctor spoke as follows:</p>
                  <p>"Get near the watchers at the grave; it is probable they will not return before midnight, and see that you are not spied. I want you to observe <choice>
                        <sic>secresy</sic>
                        <corr>secrecy</corr>
                     </choice> and dispatch; if they attempt to return to the office, give me warning and detain them. You must do it; I must not be disturbed without notice."</p>
                  <p>"I will act as you want me to," replied Crook-Neck. "If they get here without your knowing of it, it will be over my dead body."</p>
                  <p>"Well then, let it be over your crooked body," replied the Doctor, as he hurried the obedient servant out at the door, then followed the gliding form of Crook-Neck until it became only a shadow in he moon blaze. He again entered the door and passed into the back apartment which had been assigned to Lutella for her sleeping room. Lighting his candle he took a close scrutiny of every nook and corner, and then observing the bloody dress hanging near the bed, he felt of the pocket, and finding the keys to the two valises he instantly opened that belonging to the girl and finding nothing but her clothing, a few trinkets, a few letters and her mother's photograph, which he instantly recognized from other circumstances, and from the almost exact resemblance it bore the daughter, and some old letters from friends in England, be closed the valise locked it and then sought to find out the contents of Sir Harry's.</p>
                  <p>"It's useless," he said, "to curse the dead, but portraits of an enemy are always vexatious, but a year so defaces their features," he spoke, and then soliloquized. "They are both gone, both gone, and the world will soon forget, both father and mother will soon fade from memory."</p>
                  <p>The Doctor unlocked the remaining valise and turned its contents upon the bed. A few traveling shirts, a pair of pants, and a light coat, a razor strop and other tricks of comfort, which usually attend the wants of travelers. When returning the contents to the valise, he espied a memorandum. Some portions of the writing were in a foreign hand, and pages were wholly filled with instructions to his daughter in case any mishap should befall him in his adventure, and then he read the very last writing in the book, to-wit: "You will find my most important papers relating to my personal affairs well secured in my inner coat pocket, the one next to the left breast. In case of accident, secure the coat at all hazards;" "and so I will and the memorandum too," said the Doctor, as he tore ont the leaf and carefully stowed it away in his pocket. "He must have had some amount of money, but unless the girl has it, some one, the Indian perhaps, has stolen it." He said no more, replaced the clothes in the two valises, and put the keys where he had found them. He went out to recall the watchman he had placed near the grave, to observe and watch the actions of he sentinel and Lutella. "What, what a life of misery has been mine. Am I ever to suffer this? the same womb bore us both, and the same parents guarded over our youth. Now this girl has been raised as I was, in plenty, with a luxurious home surrounding her. Were she my daughter, and had I the means I would not possibly deviate from the course of living marked out for her by the fashionable world; but the ah, bah," he added as his lips in scornful and derisive mocking, at his own reasoning, spat blood, for his passion had choaked him, and his teeth had vented his wrath upon the inner lining of his cheeks.</p>
                  <p>"Come here, Crook;" he exclaimed, as that worthy came swinging along in the moonlight, "you know I am a man of few words and quick perception. I want you to start at early dawn for the fort. You can take any of the mustangs you find larreted out, and you shall be rewarded beyond your own expectations."</p>
                  <p>"I am your man; anything to get out of this wild country. I know the way well, and my horse knows it too. I start before sunrise, and Doctor see that you fill the flask."</p>
                  <p>"Rely upon me as your friend in every particular," said his master.</p>
                  <pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC5696-00000021"/>
                  <p>"It's when the fit is coming on me, that I take it," said Crook-Neck.</p>
                  <p>"I am well aware of that. I'll have all things ready for you, so go and rest until daylight," said the Doctor as he entered his door.</p>
                  <p>"An hour after this adventure upon the part of the Doctor, he was seen sitting on a bench, with a candle stand placed beside him, while he was writing with great rapidity. His face was pale, his hand slightly tremulous, but his eye was deep-set in thought, and his brow shaded with the stamp of reflection. Having finished and sealed his letter, he once more sought his blankets, when Elrick entered, and stretching his stout, robust form to his full height, spoke: "I thought I saw a light within; ho, there, Doctor; gone to bed again I say to sleep; so good night," and the Doctor neither moved nor replied.</p>
                  <p>"They are at the grave," said Crook-Neck, who in spite of every effort had not been able to woo the Goddess of sleep. "She's a strong girl, Mr. Driver. She does not want the wolves to tear up the body of her father, and believe me they'd do it too, only they smell Big Horn's powder, who can drop a ball of lead when he wills it, just where it's most fatal. We were together once, when a wild cat passed us carrying a rabbit to its young, and the rabbit was alive, for they always bring any rabbit or squirrel alive to their young to teach them to kill it, or play with it, while the old one sets and looks to capture the game in case it tries to escape. Well, the cat was running by us, as I say, with the rabbit, when Big Horn says to me, 'I'll release that hare' and up with his rifle and let drive, as you do sometimes on your wild cattle, when the cat sprang into the air, and the rabbit cut dirt as fast as his legs could carry him off, and, further," continued Crook, "you'll do good service by going to the grave and stay there till daylight, and let the two poor sleepy creatures come home and rest. You'll see them sitting on the ground, at least so you'll find the young creature, the man is walking up and down keeping guard. But I want to tell you when you go there, to keep a sharp look out, for the wolves. You can't see their dusky forms. I'll warrant you there's plenty of 'em round watching for them sentinels to go to sleep, or leave the tomb, and if you are not careful they'll dig a hole to get at the body between your legs, if you were setting a-straddle of the grave. You look mighty sleepy now, so take care you don't keep your sleepers closed too long."</p>
                  <p>"Thank you, Crook, for your advice, but if they do creep on me while I sleep, let 'em look sharp when I wake up, for this bit of iron was never known to fail me," replied Elrick.</p>
                  <p>"But another thing I want to tell you before you start," said Crook. These wolves and Apaches go together in their hunting parties. They are the meanest sneakingest things in the world. When they smell plunder they remain as quiet as a mouse, and never show themselves, but always on the alert, and let your back be turned and they'll steal the boots off ye, nor give even a quarrel. And they work not only in silence, but take turns at pawing out holes, one being tired another sets to work. Now do as I tell you and you'll come out all right, but if you neglect my warnings you'll be fooled."</p>
                  <p>"I'm not of the sleepy kind, though I confess I feel more heavy than when I first took my snooze," said the driver as rifle in hand he wended his way toward the watchers of the night.</p>
                  <p>Shortly after his departure the Sentinel and his companion returned. Little was said by either party as they arrived at the entrance of the office. Crook-Neck presented her with a light, while the Sentinel cast himself beneath the blanket which the driver had just vacated, and was soon sleeping soundly. Now, what the driver said about being more inclined to doze than before his first repose was quickly verified, for scarcely had he seated himself upon the blanket which Lutella had but recently left, when his eye-lids grew weighty, his muscles relaxed, and his mind simmered into a state of forgetfulness. One by one the stars went out or were drunk up by the moon, and she herself spread her glare over the whole earth and faded into darkness, and his spirit was imprisoned in the goal of sleep. Old hunters say that wolves can tell when a human being sleeps, whenever they come near enough to wind their bodies. Be this as it may, for scarcely had the driver become unconscious of life, before several dark shadows issued from behind the rock, and with steady glaring eyes approached the grave, crouching low to the earth, they steadily crawled toward the grave, and there stood Sentinel over the weary sleeping form for some twenty minutes, and then in the most noiseless and energetic manner, began pawing a hole at the foot of the grave. They worked, one getting tired another of them instantly taking his place, until the miner's tail could be seen projecting from the hole, and then came a gnawing of the tarpaulan, when the unusual noise broke the spell, and the driver sprang to his feet and instantly discerning the state of the surroundings, grasped the tail of the wolf which was wagging out the hole, he dragged him from his under-ground work shop, and swinging the wolf's body in the air, as he tightened his<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC5696-00000022"/> grip upon his tail, he dashed the body hard upon the earth until the animal's heart nearly bursted out of its throat. In the mean time the others slunk away without a growl, or even a whine. You may well imagine that Elrick slept no more that night, and set manfully to work to repair the damage which his negligence had permitted the wolves to perform while sleeping on guard.</p>
                  <p>"I never saw in all my days of tugging it through life, such imps of darkness, and such scowling looks of fiendish hatred, as the two other fellows gave me when they retreated behind the rock. They have such a sneakish way of turning their heads as they trot along, and their eyes snap sparks of fire, and you can hear their gritting madness as they go until it gets the mastery over them. These cursed wolves are as cowardly as a young hare. I can have pity for all other beasts except these wolves; they are so remorseless upon the helpless," said the driver.</p>
                  <p>When daylight came he flung the animal's body across his shoulder, and when he reached the office, threw it down in front of the door, and without further remark, took his rifle and started off in search of the big horned goat, which had so often invited and avoided his shot when passing along with his stage. Lutella, when called out to view the dead grave-robber, felt a cold chill of horror creep over her as she gazed upon the body, for of all animals when dead the wolf presents the most loathing appearance. His eyes glare wildly fierce with a glassy, greenish lustre, and his half open jaws reveal rows of fanged pointed teeth, frothed with slime.</p>
                  <p>"How hideous," exclaimed the young girl as she gazed. "If such be the monsters that prey upon the human body after death, neither my own nor my father's body must rest long under this earth."</p>
                  <p>"The corpse will soon lose its life scent," replied the Doctor, "and then we will have nothing to fear. Confound that Irishman," he added "he was certainly here last night; was it not so, Big Horn?"</p>
                  <p>"Irishman, as you call him, is generally here at meal time. At all events, let's remove this carcass;" and the two men, each taking a half, dragged the body a hundred yards from the office, and there left it. When they were returning to the office, Doctor Keating inquired of the Sentinel if he felt disposed at some future day to visit England.</p>
                  <p>"I have entertained such a thought, and frequently of late," replied his companion.</p>
                  <p>"We'll talk of this matter hereafter," the Doctor added. "It's a singular girl, is it not?" he continued.</p>
                  <p>"Very courageous and determined; her resolution is beyond belief," replied the Sentinel.</p>
                  <p>"That is not so surprising," rejoined the Doctor, "considering the race from which she had her growth. You will perceive, if you examine closely, that though the head is small, it is finely developed, and the features every one of them, even to the eyelid, are finely and exactly chiseled out in bold relief. I am something of a connoisseur in beauty, and if you mark the whole form in prospective, you will see that the contour of the whole body corresponds with the direct angle of motion. There's many a curve in her limbs requiring expansion, and some angles to be polished in their roundings. She will never make a very tall woman, but like all women who have received proper training and culture in their youth, she will make a firm but graceful walker. Had Sir Harry lived, before he considered her education, he would have spent a small fortune in feeing teachers from the continent. What think you Big Horn; am I right, or am I too critical?"</p>
                  <p>"I'm not much of a judge," replied the Sentinel, "but what I most admire is that splendid grey eye of <choice>
                        <sic>her's</sic>
                        <corr>hers</corr>
                     </choice>; it looks into one's very heart."</p>
                  <p>"Well, my young friend, I know you are not much given to gossip, but I will say to you, that I saw her mother when I was a young man on a visit to a relation of mine, but whether this Sir Harry married her, or whether it was her sister I do not distinctly recollect, but both sisters were remarkably fine looking women, and I should not be surprised that when this girl Lutella grows up she does not rival either of them, both in aspect and grace. I've seen some very handsome women in the States, but the American character is not yet formed; they are so constantly receiving such accessions of the foreign element, as to engender such a mixing up of things as to render streaked most all their mouldings. Whereas the Romans all possessed Roman noses, so will the American be American. It will exhibit angles or curves assimilating to the Greek or Roman, but the real natives of the soil will add nothing to the race, either in features of the face or expression of countenance."</p>
                  <p>"I should like the eye of the Indian to be retained if I had the formation of the American head, for I do think it surpasses in black shining lustre that of all animals, be it human or otherwise," replied the Sentinel.</p>
                  <p>"There's something rank about its glare," replied the Doctor, "and cutting in its gleams, though I grant you it partakes of a milder type in the young squaws. But honestly, I have watched it at night by the camp fire, and imagined the pupil of the eye was glossed over by a metallic varnish. How many<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC5696-00000023"/> times I have watched the red men sitting round the camp fire after dressing their wounds or performing operations; they would never flinch when the knife was being applied, they seemed to laugh only to conceal their agony. The heart of the savage is grateful too, for I have known them to carry an antelope, which probably cost them many hour's watching to kill, for five miles, in order to reward my labors in their behalf. But here comes Lutella we must show her our dripping well; what say you, will you accompany us Big Horn?"</p>
                  <p>"Certainly," replied the young man, "she expressed a wish last night to visit it, and it's not very far off, but who comes here?"</p>
                  <p>Some four miles off an Indian horseman could be discerned walking his horse directly toward the <choice>
                        <sic>mounth</sic>
                        <corr>mouth</corr>
                     </choice> of the Pass.</p>
                  <p>"A black horse," said the Doctor; "he either brings here a wounded companion, or a deer or antelope to pay for the dressing of the wound of his relation. If such is the case it is Mutante, or Change of the Year. He is a fine, intelligent Indian, and the Colonel at the Fort has conceived a most favorable opinion of his honesty. Of course," he added, "there are among all classes of people to be found in all nations, individuals superior to others in mental and physical attributes, and Mutante is one of them; but in an hour or so we shall know of a certainty. Let's go and get the girl and then for the dripping well."</p>
                  <p>Lutella was called, and she willingly accepted the offer of accompanying them in their walk. A small traveling hat, plainly trimmed with a brown ribbon, shaded her from the evening sun, and over this was carelessly thrown a green gauze veil, and a tight fitting dress of gray barege, and gloves to match, completed her attire. The Sentinel wore his suit of goat skin and fur cap, while the Doctor was arrayed in his old morning gown of many figures and colors.</p>
                  <p>Descending a narrow path leading round some projecting rocks, a short walk brought them to a pile of organ-shaped rocks, from near the top of which, through a narrow crack, the water issued in large drops, falling in quick succession, and clear as crystal. Beneath the crack, to a distance of some twelve or more feet, was a large basin, which the dripping liquid had nearly filled.</p>
                  <p>"You see how the constant flowing of the water has worn away the hard rock upon which it has fallen, probably it has taken many billions of drops to accomplish the formation of this bowl, yet surely, steadily, year after year, the sap and liquid, flowing in minute globules, has, by the constant action of friction, scooped out this basin. I have sometimes been tempted to cut into the reservoir to obtain a larger supply of this cooling beverage, but upon reflection, thought I'd rest content, and let well enough alone. Think you, Lutella, was not I wise in deserting my venturesome undertaking?"</p>
                  <p>"Decidedly so; but why are you lingering in a savage state, in this dangerous and desolate abode; you appear to be a gentleman of wit and education?"</p>
                  <p>"I'll answer you," replied the Doctor, "Why are you here? Why is Big Horn here? why Pat or Crook Neck? I tell you Fate has blocked out each our destiny, on which Time is the moulder and fashioner."</p>
                  <p>"I will not argue with you in this way of thinking. I was taught differently. I think our reason and conscience should be our guide while we live," said the girl.</p>
                  <p>"Well," replied the Doctor, "I will not mar your training. You have but a short span of existence to measure backwards. The Fates have no voices, save through the teaching of experience. Be happy if you can; be more than your destiny you can not; but now let us taste of that which will afford us such cooling, healthful pleasure," and providing a glass tumbler, he added, "Drink of that element which delighteth all your senses; come to this corner of my fountain and catch the drops in your glass, and you will see your own image reflected in Nature's mirror, for this is Pat's looking-glass; he has spent many hours beside this chaste reflector of Nature."</p>
                  <p>"Here the Indians have often quenched their thirst I suppose?" said Lutella.</p>
                  <p>"Yes," replied the Doctor, "the last Indian I saw drink at this spring was Delgadite, as some call him, and several of his squaws."</p>
                  <p>"That monster, whose very name should be so terrible to me," exclaimed Lutella, "what a wretch he must be, indeed."</p>
                  <p>"You can form your own opinion of his character," interposed Sentinel. "At one of the stations, near the crossing of the Gila river, they stood in need of some men to guard the horses. These men were required to tend as guards to the mules, and upon the first appearance of danger to give the alarm, and drive them within the station walls. Through a Mexican boy Delgadite was informed of this fact, so disguising himself in all parts like a Mexican ranchero, he made application for the place of the keeper, was hired, and acted his part of a faithful herder to perfection. Two mornings after his being herder, the stage arrived at the station, the gates were found open, and the place deserted. Upon examination, the keepers, to the number of three, were found with their heads split open with an axe. They had evidently been killed in<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC5696-00000024"/> their beds while asleep, the mules driven off, and all the arms and ammunition taken away. A Mexican boy, hid away under some hay, shortly after the stage arrived, made his appearance, and gave a full history of the affair as above related. So you see, Miss Lutella, that he fully merits the evil name he has acquired in this country."</p>
                  <p>The Doctor now said, "Let us return to the office, as I see Mutante will speedily make his presence known at the door."</p>
                  <p>Nor did they anticipate the arrival many minutes, for the chief shortly made his appearance, carrying a large-sized fawn in front of his saddle, which he had killed on the plains, having hunted since daybreak for some deer or antelope meat to recompense his friend, the Doctor, for dressing the wound of his companion. Waving his hand in respectful salutation, a way of friendly greeting peculiar to the Apache nation, and which they borrowed from the Mexicans. He alighted from his horse, untied the larriet which held it to the pummel of his saddle, and then placed it on the ground near the feet of his benefactor, then clasping the Doctor in his arms, gave utterance to many warm expressions of gratitude. He spoke the Spanish language fluently, and his voice lacked that harsh, guttural tone, so rasping in sound to the Indian tongue. Having pressed the Doctor most lovingly to his breast, Sentinel submitted to like friendly embraces, and when the chief's eye caught sight of Lutella, he knelt upon one knee, and bowing his head, kissed the palm and back of his hand to her, lowered his hand, and regained his feet, and said: "White squaw come from fort; white squaw soldier's gall." Lutella passed quietly into the office, but the Indian's glance of admiration followed her until her form disappeared from view. He asked no further questions, for it is of the nature of the Indians neither to express surprise nor evince curiosity. Mutante was a fine specimen of his race. His form was as straight as an arrow, his limbs supple in their movements, with a form rather cast for active effort than deeds requiring great strength of muscle. His <choice>
                        <sic>featunes</sic>
                        <corr>features</corr>
                     </choice> were youthful and pleasant, and in expression, his hair was short in front, and hung a foot or more in length down his back, a narrow belt adorned his brow, fringed with a string of beads and pearls, shells hanging round his neck, a tight-fitting buckskin jacket, with sleeves reaching to the elbow, the breast of which was worked with beads and the feathers of the Mexican parrot. His pants were made after the style of the Greaser, open to the knee, with rows of silver buttons along the seams. Around his waist was tied an Indian officer's sash, upon his feet he wore braided moccasins, and around his wrists were silver bracelets, and rings of the same metal on his fingers gers. His arms consisted of a double-barreled shot gun, a knife which he carried hung to the sash, and bow and arrows, which were wrapped in the skin of a fox and tied behind the seat of his saddle. The horse he rode was a stout black pony, with bushy mane and tail, one end of the larriet serving as a bridle. Such was the warrior Mutante, as he presented himself before the Doctor's door. He was bold, yet cautious in war, generous to his comrades, polite to the belles of his tribes, and respectful to the aged. With the Doctor he had always been on intimate terms of friendship, and many is the fat antelope he's been instrumental in sending to the Doctor's table.</p>
                  <p>An Indian will seldom evince a weakness even in the presence of his equal, and no man ever understood better the nature of the Indian's character than the Doctor, who, suspecting the young warrior to be hungry, said: "Come, now, Big Horn, let's make ready this meat which Mutante has procured for us, and we will encourage him to future endeavors in our behalf, for our smoke-house is not over-stocked with game. I will make ready the fire, while you skin the deer and cut up the ribs."</p>
                  <p>"It shall be so," replied Sentinel, and removing the deer a few paces from the door, he soon removed the skin, and cut up the quarter. The fire being ready, each procured a sharp stick, and then sticking it through slices of meat hung it over the flame, scarcely heating it. Setting upon the ground around the fire and using their fingers in lieu of knives and forks, they soon satisfied their hunger, and hung up the remaining portion of the carcass to dry, there being no danger of its spoiling from exposure to the sun, the air being so tempered with dry heat. At this moment the robust form of Elrick, the driver, was seen hastening toward them exclaiming: "Hallo there, don't be in a hurry to hang up that meat or put out that fire; here's another hungry mortal, ready to fill up the inner man."</p>
                  <p>"Well, what luck," asked Sentinel, as he again stirred the fire and began chopping off more steaks for the driver.</p>
                  <p>"Tired enough; I have hunted the whole top of the hill for the goat, saw nothing of it or its sign, but came across a beautiful but still spring near a bank, with a cave near it.</p>
                  <p>"Do you know anything about that spring?" inquired the Doctor of Mutante, who began laughing, as he replied:</p>
                  <p>"It is lucky it was not the day of the virgins. It is the flower spring. On one of our feast days, five of our old women go with our young squaws who are fit to become mothers, and they dance and sing for three days, but no man must come near them until they are purified by the waters of the spring. I do not think that any one knows the exact form and ceremony<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC5696-00000025"/> but though a woman may mingle with then, yet wo be unto that man who ventures to approach the dancing ring, for the old squaws have birches near, and run at him with a rush, and if they catch him they tear his hair, and give him a most severe beating, and the young girls hide in the cave until the intruder has taken his departure."</p>
                  <p>"Now, boys, after this information, be wary else a severe flogging awaits any one who invades the premises of the fairies when the first flower of maidenhood blooms on the hill-sides," said the Doctor laughing. The whites lighted their pipes, but Mutante refused on the score that he was not yet old enough. The day was drawing to its close; already the blue purple mist began to suffuse the outlines of the distant mountains, and the prairie dog to scamper and chatter round his hole. Mutante sat upon the ground with his hands locked across his knees, his eyes being constantly fixed upon the Doctor's office. Upon observing this the Doctor took the young chief aside and related to him the story of Lutella's youth; <hi rend="i"/>her voyage across the water to San Francisco; her journey from there to the Pass; the attack upon the stage after the treaty; the death of her father, even taking the young woman to the grave where Sir Harry was buried, and then told him how she watched nightly over the grave to protect the body from the wolves.</p>
                  <p>Mutante never moved a muscle of his face, but the eye was reckless, and the gleaming glow of revenge in quivering flashes, illumined the whole expression of the countenance.</p>
                  <p>When the Doctor had finished his narrative the young Indian slowly regained his feet, exclaiming with compressed jaws, "Delgadite must die. Mangos will kill him; he has broken the treaty made at the Fort, and now while our brave men are gone with him to Mexico, the Captain at the Fort could kill our women and children, and say in excuse, that the Apaches broke the treaty and murdered his people. Mutante will watch to-night over the grave, and shoot the wolves with his arrows; but the wolves will not come, he likes not the smell of the Indian."</p>
                  <p>Now by what right the Doctor told this affair to the Indian, remains to be questioned. It could not be that he sought the death of Delgadite, for that chief was with Mangos in Chihuahua. He had some object in view more than indulging the Indian's idle curiosity, but as yet he himself had only partially formed his future plans of action regarding the girl, and that he might use the Indian to advantage, against any enemies at the Fort or among Mutante's tribe.</p>
                  <p>It was very evident to the least observant mind that things could not remain in the same quiet state in which they were found the day after the murder. Being a foreigner, and one knighted by his Queen, it was more than probable that as soon as the news should reach the English Consul in San Francisco, instant and energetic measures would be taken for the safety and return of the daughter, and the removal of the body to his native land. But there was a more determined, positive and decisive mind nearer at hand, and that was the presence at the Fort of Col. H. No officer was more intimately acquainted with the habits, number and location of the various tribes, and the Doctor felt assured that if he had any plans of interest or policy to carry out, he must begin instantly to work them into a shape and form that he could handle at will and without delay; so retiring early, beneath his blankets, he prepared his mind for alternate periods of dozing and waking, with good or bad intent, as his anticipations should determine. The Sentinel had drawn a bench in front of the office door, and beside Lutella watched the moon, as with gathering light, she rolled up above the mountain's horizon, away off to the East, as cold as the frozen North, and silent as the valley of death. Beasts of prey are prone to wander during the night, darkness being their mantle of concealment. To the Indian was given the bow and the arrow, being of little weight, easily repaired, and silent in sending home the messenger of death. The natives of our forests and plains live principally by hunting—by stealthy strides. He has to steal upon his game, and what he lacks in the available distance of his arms of warfare he supplies by art, treachery, and frequently by imitations of the animal of which he is in pursuit. After conversing for nearly two hours upon random subjects, and listening to the many incidents of stirring import which had befallen the Sentinel in the course of his adventurous life, Lutella proposed a walk to the grave. "I fear," she observed, "the Indian may have fallen asleep and the wolves make a second attempt to disturb the dead." The driver had long since sought repose in quiet slumber. Unnoticed they strolled towards the gloomy resting place of the dead.</p>
                  <p>"Hold!" said the Sentinel, as he pressed the young girl back with his left hand, and gazed intently towards several rocks some forty paces to the right of the path which they were following.</p>
                  <p>"Look!" he whispered; "do you see those glittering, sparkling spots to the right of the rocks; they are the glow of the wolves' eyes."</p>
                  <p>"But the grave is deserted!" she responded. "It is well we have so opportunely arrived, as they would have been digging in a short a time."</p>
                  <pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC5696-00000026"/>
                  <p>"Now look at that dark shadow creeping just beyond, in the rear of those eyes; wait, and observe it intently; you think it stationary, but it is moving nevertheless; but," said he, "not a word," and they both stood motionless, watching first the shadow beyond and the wolves' eyes in front. A minute or so elapsed, when the merest whirk of a sound struck their ears, then forward sprang a wolf, and rolling over and over on his back, began snapping at its side, and then with a low, whining cry, dragged itself off among the rocks.</p>
                  <p>"Come, let us hasten back," said Lutella, and she started with urgent haste towards the office door.</p>
                  <p>"You now perceive that the Indian seldom sleeps on guard," said the Sentinel. "I only wish I was as certain of salvation as I am that no wolf will disturb that grave this night."</p>
                  <p>"I shall now retire, but I know I will dream of those horrid Indians all night," said Lutella. "So in Heaven's name you must promise to watch my sleep, else I will stay awake all the night."</p>
                  <p>"No Indian ever enters this office," replied the Sentinel, "but the Doctor syringes his legs with oil of vitriol, and not suspecting from what quarter it comes, he is left dancing the Apache horn-pipe in a style equal to the excited cat before a storm. That outside door will be closed to-night, which will bar all entrance to wolf, Indian or Christian; so, my fair young lady, you can rest in safety for a night," he said as she passed into her own small but secure apartment. And so ended another day of her stay in the heart of the Apache nation.</p>
                  <p>A brisk southerly breeze fanned the morning's reddening aspect. Streaks of pale, purple-like braided bands of pearls and rubies, hung around its brow. Clouds were rolled before the wind close to the surface of the plain, and then climbing the sides of the ragged mountains, became lost behind their summits. These thin masses of vapor, when struck by the beams of the morning sun, reflects all the prismatic colors of the rainbow, and when they disappear before the advancing light of day, they leave upon hill and dale a refreshing shower of moisture cooling to the air and revivifying to shrub and plant. The days are warm and the nights correspondingly cool. This sudden transition of extreme temperature is caused by the intense rarification of a cloudless atmosphere and the high altitudes of the surrounding mountains and shelterless plains.</p>
                  <p>Wrapped in the folds of his faded morning gown, the Doctor issued from his office door, and with his arms folded behind his back, and apparently in deep thought, walked towards the grave. At that moment Mutante, already mounted and prepared to take his departure, rode up, and grasping the Doctor's hand and promising to see him again on the following week, left in a gallop, just as Lying Pat made his appearance. He wore his new flannel shirt, fox skin cap and buckskin pants.</p>
                  <p>"Well, Pat," said the Doctor, offering his hand, "You must have been on a visit to the moon."</p>
                  <p>"A worse place," replied Pat, in great seriousness of countenance; "I came here an hour ago, and told that mad-sick lover, Mutante—"</p>
                  <p>"Mad-sick lover!" repeated the Doctor in surprise.</p>
                  <p>"Yes, I repeat it; I have been sympathizing with Mr. Red Tender Heart for the last hour; he is desperately in love with your ward, and would have been hanging round your quarters annoying the girl to eternity, had it not been for a little ruse and a slight deception upon my part to get rid of him."</p>
                  <p>"Ruse on your part to get rid of him, and who gave you liberty to interfere with my guests?" interposed the Doctor, reddening with anger; "Am I not capable of managing my own affairs, and sending off my own friends in case I tire of them. In future keep away from my quarters, if you intend to act master here."</p>
                  <p>"The best of these red devils are but skunks," replied Pat, with a sullen reserve pictured on his visage, "I only told him that Mangos had fought a battle and lost many of his braves, and that a messenger was seeking him from the Gila to the Colorado."</p>
                  <p>"Which was a lie," said the Doctor, stamping his foot with great energy.</p>
                  <p>"Well, suppose it was," repeated Pat, "Haven't you more than once told me that I was the biggest liar living? Shall I not prove your words true; no friend of yours, who valued your honor, would make me out a truthful man; there's some difference, we Paddies think, between deceiving a Christian and a savage."</p>
                  <p>"I want none of your philosophy," replied the Doctor, "but where have you been straying, and did you see aught of Crook-Neck?"</p>
                  <p>"I have been at the fort, and while there, Crook-Neck came there with a letter from you to the Colonel, so the Colonel told me confidentially, when I dined with him."</p>
                  <p>"When you dined with him?" repeated the Doctor.</p>
                  <p>"Certainly, he was about to send the dispatches to Washington upon the state of the Territory, Indian depredations, and the temper of the tribes for war or peace."</p>
                  <pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC5696-00000027"/>
                  <p>"Pat," said he, confidentially, "I've a mind to let you be bearer of dispatches to President Buchanan, for there may be difficult problems to solve in these treaties with the various Indian nations hereabouts, which will require application, and I know of no one more capable of rendering this garrison more effective service in negotiating. Though most pressing in his requests, of course I declined, until I had consulted you."</p>
                  <p>"Consulted me," repeated the Doctor, "upon what subject?"</p>
                  <p>"Why, upon the propriety of accepting the high responsibility of the embassy."</p>
                  <p>"You may go to the devil," said the Doctor. "But what of Crook-Neck?"</p>
                  <p>"He's enlisted in the cavalry," replied Pat."</p>
                  <p>"Now I've caught you," exultingly exclaimed the man of drugs, "He's deformed, and they would not admit him to the service."</p>
                  <p>"Under ordinary rules they would not admit him, its true," replied Pat, "but in this blasted country, where the advance guard have to look around trees and rocks, the Colonel said he was just the man he wanted, for with his crooked neck he could look round corners, and keep an eye on the rear division of the column."</p>
                  <p>"I'll tell you what, if you speak such another lying syllable to me, and don't wake the driver, and hurry and get breakfast, you shall never come near my house again," said the Doctor.</p>
                  <p>"You asked me for some news, and if I gave you none, you'd swear I was concealing some secret, and now that I bring you a quantity, you threaten me with the loss of a home, let me be as easy as one can."</p>
                  <p>"Go, go, in God's name, and do as I bid you, or you'll make me as mad as the Indians say you are," and the Doctor continued his walk to the grave, and when there sat down upon a rock, and remained long in deep thought.</p>
                  <p>"It shouldn't be the likes of you sleeping on this time of day," said Pat, as he gave the lazy driver a lusty slap on the back, "come, now, be moving your limbs apart," he continued, as Elrick began yawning and stretching. "You'd better be looking after the mules at the station; everybody's been smashed to ruin, and all the mules stampeded."</p>
                  <p>"Indeed, then, it's time for me to be mounting and off," said Elrick. "Speak me kindly to Miss Bart, and tell the Doctor I'll see him in a day or so. Of course you'll aid me to catch the mules."</p>
                  <p>"Never fear, my boy, on that score," replied Pat; "but stay and take a morsel of this Indian's grub."</p>
                  <p>"No," said Elrick, "this is indeed bad news. Come along, quick, I must see for myself;" and so gathering up the saddle-traps, the driver led the way to where the mules were staked out, Pat giving a doleful relation of the sad event, as they hurriedly sought the mules. In about one half hour the Irishman returned, and as he took down the remaining portion of the deer to cook for breakfast, he muttered:</p>
                  <p>"Meat like this is rather scarce, and to have such loafers hanging around, devouring such excellent fodder, is inconsistent with self-preservation."</p>
                  <p>When he had got the chops frying in the pan, he called aloud; "Get up fair lady of the plains, Lutella, the rolls are baking, coffee made, and the Doctor saying his prayers for another Indian battle, that he may dress more wounds, and get another deer for a fee."</p>
                  <p>Lutella now made her appearance, and after giving Pat a kindly good morning, and inquiring if all was secure at the grave, and receiving assurance on that point, Pat asked in return; "Did a wounded Indian, with an arrow in his body, call to have the weapons cut out by the Doctor?"</p>
                  <p>"Yes, indeed," replied the young girl, "and that venison was brought as pay for the operation."</p>
                  <p>"The first operation was mine, the second the Doctor's, the third was the devil's, for he's dead, and they are burning his body," replied Pat.</p>
                  <p>"How do you know," said she, "how do you know all that's going on."</p>
                  <p>"Why, by my spies and agents," said Pat.</p>
                  <p>"I suppose it cost you many a shilling to bribe them?"</p>
                  <p>"You are right, Miss," he rejoined, "but having a very rich gold mine on the Gila, and many of the Piemos working for me, I find no <choice>
                        <sic>difficdlty</sic>
                        <corr>difficulty</corr>
                     </choice> in meeting my financial expenses."</p>
                  <p>"I tell you what," said the Doctor, who had approached unawares, "you are the most inconceivable liar that ever lived."</p>
                  <p>"That may be," replied Pat, "but my art has saved me from being driven from these parts, on a charge of being a wizzard. But be easy, for don't you hear the music of the instruments of battle, the clink of sword, and the jingle of spurs."</p>
                  <p>"I hear nothing," replied the Doctor, "but where's Big Horn and Mutante."</p>
                  <p>"Gone hunting," replied Pat. "One small baby of a deer cannot last your boarders a century. There's work, sir, ahead for all of us, and Big Horn, as you call him, will have to mount his charger for other sport than the timid antelope."</p>
                  <pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC5696-00000028"/>
                  <p>The Doctor gave the Irishman a searching look of inquiry, which Pat pretended not to notice, but resumed.</p>
                  <p>"I told you the troops were near at hand, Captain Whistler and Lieutenant Rooters, with their men, are coming up the hill."</p>
                  <p>"You had better return to your room, my child," said the Doctor to Lutella; "at the proper time your presence may be necessary."</p>
                  <p>Scarcely had the girl vacated her seat near the camp fire, when the officers, with a score of men, reined their cavalry before the door.</p>
                  <p>"You see we have not been tardy," exclaimed Capt. Whistler, as he dismounted and clasped the Doctor by the hand. "Lieutenant Rooters has told us about this unpleasant affair, and your letter requiring our presence, backed up by the Colonel's anxiety in this matter has not delayed us in hastening our advent."</p>
                  <p>"I regret I did not more fully explain my intentions in regard to this particular subject, when he so kindly paid us a visit a day or so ago, but we can only think of one thing at a time, and if you will both step aside with me for a few moments, we will talk the matter over to a full understanding of all the requirements of the case."</p>
                  <p>Acting upon the Doctor's suggestion, the three retired to some distance from the office, where an animated discussion ensued, and a definite course of action decided upon. They then returned to the office door and were formally introduced, by the Doctor, to the young lady.</p>
                  <p>"It has been deemed advisable, Miss Bart," said Captain Whistler, "that a change should take place <choice>
                        <sic>inyour</sic>
                        <corr>in your</corr>
                     </choice> present abode. It is necessary that you should visit the Fort for a few days, in order that certain papers should be certified to by the Colonel under your signature. This may be of great consequence to you in the identification of the body, manner, time and place, and cause of your father's death."</p>
                  <p>"Is it necessary that I should go instantly? Does it meet the approval of the Doctor?" asked Lutella, in much perplexity of mind. "What will become of my father's body."</p>
                  <p>"My word on it, the body shall be guarded over," said the Doctor.</p>
                  <p>"And Doctor, we can spare you a brace or so of troopers to assist in preventing its desecration," said Captain Whistler.</p>
                  <p>"Never fear," he quickly replied. "There are four of us to look after the grave, so now make ready. In a day or two you may return, and arrangements will be effected for sending you and your father's remains to California."</p>
                  <p>"We have brought with us an ambulance to the foot of the western mouth of the Pass," said Captain Whistler, "and you have only to walk to the foot of the hill to find your conveyance. We are strong enough to protect you against any scattering force, and the sooner you start the better."</p>
                  <p>Finding how complete she was in the hands of her protectors, Lutella submitted with as good a grace as possible, and handing what little baggage she possessed to the troopers, she set off on her journey, the officers having dismounted and walking by her side, the Doctor bringing up the rear. Lutella, when she fully understood the import of the movement made to the Fort, being no less than the first step towards sending her father's body to her native England, became eager for any change of location which facilitated the intended removal.</p>
                  <p>Pat insisted upon accompanying Lutella to the Fort, and so mounting one of his own mustangs, he followed in the rear of the ambulance, occasionally singing a song, or chasing an antelope which came within hailing distance of the cavalcade. The Doctor returned to his office, where he found Crook-Neck picking the bones of the deer.</p>
                  <p>"Thou art a good boy," said the Doctor, shaking him warmly by the hand. "And have done thy work manfully, only let us be true to ourselves and let the world sweat in its agony of vice and selfishness, and we, like Bacchus, can frolic on the feast of their follies and failures. But just now we are bothered, terribly bothered, if we can not find out where Big Horn rests to-night."</p>
                  <p>"Then we are unbothered at once, good Doctor, for I left him at the Fort."</p>
                  <p>"And why there? And has he, too, enlisted as that awful liar, Pat, said you had done?"</p>
                  <p>"He has picked up a job in the way of writing, and remains to give evidence in Sir Harry's murder."</p>
                  <p>"Then we are saved; for once we are befriended by fortune, for this very night, up out of that hole must come Sir Harry's corpse. Our fortune lies there in the breast pocket of his coat; not in money—bank notes—but papers of inheritance, for should anything happen to that girl, it will be well to possess those papers to establish a certain person s identity."</p>
                  <p>"I'll dig out the grave," replied Crook-Neck, "if you'll take out the body and examine it; but it will make me sick if I touch it. I shall tremble so I shall fall into the pit."</p>
                  <p>"Well, well," replied the Doctor, "only if I require help, you'll lend a hand though. You can shut your eyes, you know."</p>
                  <pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC5696-00000029"/>
                  <p>"Yes, of course," replied Crook-Neck; "but I've got a squeamish stomach."</p>
                  <p>"I see," rejoined the Doctor with a faint laugh. "Well put in; admirable hint; a most gentle insinuation. We will have the brandy ready at hand, and then for a stout heart and willing hands, and our fortune is achieved. Let midnight, then, be our watchword. Now take whatever you can find to eat, and then to bed to sleep, and then—well, do what the dead cannot do—eat some supper."</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
                  <p>It is midnight. The moon nearly overhead, with a clip taken off her rim, the air chilly, and the hills all around quiet, and Crook-Neck already digging out the earth from the grave; and there stands the Doctor animating his slave with encouraging remarks. Such the picture.</p>
                  <p>"Bravo!" be would exclaim. "Every shovel of dirt thrown out, Crook-Neck is worth a twenty pound note—a bully, bold, stout sexton are you, my man. Come now, my man, nerve up the system that supports the soul in this trying hour, and then pouring out a half glass of brandy he handed it to the laborer, who was sweating most freely from every pore of his skin; not that his work was so onerous as from its ghastly character.</p>
                  <p>"It's getting a little dark down here," said Crook-Neck.</p>
                  <p>"Ah, yes," replied the Doctor. "I'll go and get the lantern," and off he started in search of the light. If the Doctor had glanced around before his departure, be would have seen the same glaring eyes peeping from the rocks as on the two nights previous; but he failed to do so, and they continued to glow like coals of fire, and as soon as his form had vanished one of the owners of those glaring eyes crept, cautiously sneaking to the very edge of the hole in which Crook-Neck was intently at work, and when the fumes of the body ascended as it became more exposed, it struck the sensitive nostrils of the silent and half-famished watcher above, it raised its head to the moon, and with gaping jaws gave forth one loud, fiendish howl, and a howl, too, that only could issue from the slimy throat of a wolf, and which seemed to have been bellowed forth by the earth beneath Crook-Neck's feet, so startled him, that he flung the shovel from his grasp, and bounding from the hole, flew as fast as fear could propel his body towards the Doctor's office.</p>
                  <p>"What?" said the Doctor, who had heard the howl, "are we to be frightened by a villainous wolf? "go bring the gun, and come back, but before you go, let's take a drink," and drink they did, of something stronger than water, after which they were soon at their work again, and the body quickly uncovered. The tarpaulin had preserved the flesh from decay, and when they cut it open round the face and chest, little if any offensive odor was perceptible.</p>
                  <p>"Here, now, hold the light," said the Doctor, as he tore open the dead man's coat, and exposed the inner breast pockets to view. "By the power of roguery or chance they are not here," he exclaimed; "the papers are not here, they were dropped on the way, or the Indians stole them—probably now they are ashes, used to light his pipe or campfire. Blast their wolfish hearts, I wish all their souls were lumped together and buried in the grave. Take away the light while I cover over the body," and then, after straightening out the tarpaulin, they both filled up the grave, and silently awaited the approach of morn, when they betook themselves to their blankets and slept away the greater part of the day.</p>
                  <p>The subsequent events which transpired at the Doctor's office, until the flight of himself and all his boarders to a distant land, can be told in a few pages, where the sequel will show their arrival at their final place of destination. After the removal of Sir Harry's body to San Francisco, and thence to England, Lutella was again persuaded to visit the office near which her father's body had been buried, which event nearly cost her life, or worse, her slavery. Under pretence of enabling her to witness an Indian dance he invited the squaws and warriors of a neighboring camp to pass his office and encamp for the night near his spring; and while she was going to attend the dance, a little after dusk, the Doctor was tripped up, and Mutante, on a black horse, lifted her body from the ground with great rapidity, and placing it before him on his saddle, urged his horse to the path leading to the western entrance of the Pass. Here he was anticipated by Sentinel and Pat, who, suspecting something wrong on the part of the Chief and the Doctor had guarded the path. Miss Bart was rescued from his grasp, and the Chief, with his war-horse, were forced over a precipice. They guarded her room that night, and the troops arriving the next morning, she was escorted by the command to Fort Yuma, and from thence took the stage for San Francisco, and reached England by steamer. Lieutenant Rooter soon thereafter resigned his commission in the army, and followed her a month or so thereafter to England.</p>
                  <pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC5696-00000030"/>
                  <p>Elrick got another shot at the old Sentinel at the pass, and with such unerring aim as to nearly kill Sentinel, knocking the horns from his head, and in a subsequent visit to the rock, took them into his keeping. The Doctor was now doomed to be driven from his home by a terrible disease, for the small-pox breaking out among the neighboring tribes, they brought the victims of this fell disease in great numbers to his tent to be cured. No other recourse for saving his life was available but instant flight. So one morning he was missing, and Crook-Neck, in a letter stuck on a tree, near the door, informed Pat and Sentinel of their flight. Driven from their home by the same disease, the two friends resolved to reach San Francisco by the same route over which Lutella had sought refuge from barbarianism; they shouldered their rifles and started for Fort Yuma, which they reached, and there wrote to Elrick, and told him where he could find the goat which he supposed he had killed, and also learned where a letter could reach him.</p>
                  <p>On the way they were joined by Leoche, Pat's young squaw, who had dodged all his motions and tracked him on his way. She carried Pat's child all the way to Fort Yuma, and was of great service to the party in making their fire and preparing their food. Pat was anxious to leave her behind with her people, but Sentinel insisting so strong upon her accompanying them, that he was compelled to submit. They crossed the Colorado river near the Fort, and being well secured, they rested for a few days, and then crossing the desert lying between Tejon Pass, when they once more breathed the pure air of freedom.</p>
                  <p>As for Delgadite, he was taken by Mangos Colorado to Fort Buchanan, and shot by that Chief in the presence of the Colonel for violating the treaty.</p>
                  <p>[The sequel will explain the rest of the story.]</p>
                  <p>It may not be out of place to mention that in Fort Yuma they were joined in their journey by the veritable Mouse-Crow, who afforded them great amusement, and enlivened the trip with many a contest of dancing with Pat and Mrs. Dougherty. He will make his appearance in a foreign land ere we part with him.</p>
                  <p>It may be as well further to add that during the last part of their journey to the Fort, they were aided in their travel by accepting an offer to ride in one of the wagons composing the Government teams being drawn to the Fort by Brown, the wagon-master, and that some of the Indians attempted to kill Leoche rather than let her accompany the white man from her tribe. When they arrived at the Fort, Pat told the Sergeant that Sentinel was crazy, and he was taken to the guardhouse. How he was freed from his durance the sequel will show. They were followed by some of the Indians, and Sentinel's morning gown having been stolen by a soldier, the thief was shot by some unknown party, no doubt the same <choice>
                        <sic>Indiams</sic>
                        <corr>Indians</corr>
                     </choice> who had followed on their tracks to revenge the wrong of taking away Leoche, the squaw. As for Elrick, he accompanied Miss Bart to San Francisco.</p>
               </div>
               <closer>[END OF FIRST PART.]</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>H. REED &amp; CO., CISTERN BUILDERS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>H. REED &amp; Co</p>
                        <p>CISTERN BUILDERS GALVESTON, TEX.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>ESTABLISHED IN 1881</p>
                  <p>NEW SHOP—252 &amp; 254 TREMONT STREET. Office, 101 Church St., Opposite Old Stand. GALVESTON, TEXAS.</p>
                  <p>ALL WORK GUARANTEED OR NO PAY. Address, Post Office Box No. 1491.</p>
                  <p>Directions for Putting Up Cisterns When Shipped: Keep the side of bottom up that the Card is tacked on, and marked "UP" Let each joint of the bottom remain open ¼ inch to allow the staves to be placed all round—commencing with Nos. 1, 2 and 3, over the space on bottom corresponding; then place all staves in succession to their numbers. Drive the lowest hoop to within 3 1/2 inches of the bottom of the staves, and drive all the hoops very tight. Be careful to get the bevel of the hoops down. Paint well around the chimes inside when completed.</p>
                  <p>Let the Cistern Best on its Bottom, and not on the Staves.</p>
                  <closer>H. REED &amp; CO.</closer>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <pb n="60 (Advertisement) -61 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC5696-00000031"/>
                  <head>W.A. DUNKLIN &amp; CO., Commission Merchants, (HENDLEY'S BUILDING,) STRAND, GALVESTON.</head>
                  <p>PERSONAL ATTENTION GIVEN TO THE SALE OF Cotton and Produce, Filling Orders and RECEIVING AND FORWARDING GOODS.</p>
                  <p>LIBERAL ADVANCES ON PRODUCE IN HAND FOR SALE.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>WASHINGTON HOTEL, GALVESTON TEXAS.</head>
                  <p>JOHN SUMMERS (Late of the Exchange,) PROPRIETOR.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>JOSEPH LABADIE, 61 Market Street, Galveston, Texas.</head>
                  <head type="sub">(SIGN OF THE GOLDEN GUN.)</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sells fine London Twist Guns for $20; Colts' and other Deringers for $8 per pair; Powder $7 50 per keg; Shot $2 75 per bag; Percussion W. P. Caps 68 cents per 1000; Metallic Cartridge, Kentucky Rifles, $12 each; Bull-Dog Pistols $10; Winchester Rifles $40; Base Balls and Bats very cheap; Trout lines 100 feet long, with 2 hooks, block and sinker, only 25 cents; Red Fish lines do. 40 cents; Red Fish lines, do. 178 feet long, only 75 cents, and other goods in proportion, comprising an assortment found in no other store of the same kind in the United States. All orders by mail promptly attended to. Having facilities for the duplication of stock from the best makers, guarantee to sell cheaper than the cheapest. Give me a call.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>ADOLPH WAITZ, EDWARD COLLIER, Deutscher Advocat.</head>
                  <p>WAITZ &amp; COLLIER, Attorneys and Counselors at Law, OFFICE, POST OFFICE ST., COR TWENTIETH, GALVESTON, TEXAS.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>LAURENCE L. COHEN, SR., PORTRAIT PAINTER, HOUSTON, TEXAS.</head>
                  <p>Recipient of Gold Medal, Silver Medals, Silver Goblets, Cups, Diplomas, etc., from State and County Fairs. Special success in making Portraits of deceased parties from old and faded Photographs, Gems or Ambrotypes. Refers to all leading Galleries in Galveston, Bryan, Waco, Houston, Austin, etc.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <pb n="62 (Advertisement) -63 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC5696-00000032"/>
                  <head>F.A. SAWYER,</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Watches, Clocks, Diamonds, Jewelry &amp; Silver-Plated Ware, IN EVERY VARIETY. ENGRAVING AND WATCH REPAIRING NEATLY DONE.</p>
                  <p>No. 77 Main Street, HOUSTON, Texas.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>J. B. Sheldon DEALER IN STOVES &amp; TINWARE, NO. 69, EAST CHURCH STREET, GALVESTON, TEXAS. JOB WORK OF ALL KINDS Promptly Attended to.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>R. H. BAYLOR, Druggist And Chemist,</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Opera House Building, Galveston, Texas. Toilet Goods, Perfumery, FINE SOAPS, ETC., ETC. PRESCRIPTIONS CAREFULLY COMPOUNDED.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>S. LEAVECK,</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Frances Rubic 50326</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>Dealer in FINE JEWELRY, Watches, Clocks, Etc. 130 Market Street, Galveston, Tex. Perfect Spectacles a Specialty.&lt; Watches and Jewelry Carefully Repaired and Warranted.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>THE EQUITABLE Life Insurance Company OF NEW YORK,</head>
                  <p>Has 50,000 Policies in Force; Has $20,000,000 Assets; Annual Income, $8,500,000. Has done the largest amount of new business during the last four years of any Company in the world! Before insuring your life examine fully its terms, plans, etc. J. S. SULLIVAN, Manager for Texas, 114 Tremont Street, Galveston.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>GREGORY &amp; BARTLETT,</head>
                  <p>Eclipse Livery and Sale Stables, TREMONT STREET, GALVESTON, TEXAS. <figure/> Are always on hand to serve their customers with the finest Horses, Buggies and Carriages in the city. <figure/> Funerals attended to with Hearse and Carriages. Horses taken on Board.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>DR. J. G. GOODALL,</head>
                  <p>Nos. 209 and 211 MARKET STREET, GALVESTON, TEXAS, DEALER IN Drugs, Medicines, Chemicals, Brushes, Fine Soaps and Perfumery, And all articles usually kept on hand by DRUGGISTS. Physicians' Prescriptions Carefully Compounded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>L. F. PRICE,</head>
                  <p>(Late of LaGrange,) Lawyer, Real Estate Agent, BROKER AND CONVEYANCER, OFFICE—SECOND DOOR EAST OF THE OPERA HOUSE, GALVESTON, TEXAS.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <pb n="64 (Advertisement) -65 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC5696-00000033"/>
                  <head>B. O'MALLEY, ATTORNEY AT LAW,</head>
                  <p>Office, Cor. Main and Congress Streets, Van Alstyne's Building, HOUSTON, TEXAS. Will practice his Profession in the several Courts of Texas, and also the Federal Courts in Galveston and Austin, when called upon. Will examine and perfect Titles to Land, and will pay taxes for non-residents, and collect and remit immediately claims for non-residents, Etc., Etc., Etc.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>CAPITOL HOTEL,</head>
                  <p>(Late ENTERPRISE HOUSE,) E. L. BREMOND, PROPRIETOR, HOUSTON, TEXAS.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>DR. L. D. ESTABROOK, Dental Surgeon,</head>
                  <p>Tremont Street, near Cor. Church, GALVESTON, TEXAS.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>L. E. REYNOLDS, ARCHITECT,</head>
                  <p>No. 114 Tremont Street, Galveston, Texas. Plans and Designs for Public and Private Buildings. Attention given to Building in every Department. Public Patronage Respectfully Solicited.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>BRANCH OF E. A. TYLER, 115 CANAL STREET, NEW ORLEANS,</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>C. W. PESCAY &amp; CO. 81 Main Street, Houston, Texas. WATCHES, JEWELRY &amp; SILVERWARE. Watches and Jewelry Repaired.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>MADAME TRAHAN, Dress Maker,</head>
                  <p>165 Post Office St., bet. Twenty-First and Twenty-Second, GALVESTON, Texas.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>CAPT. D. DEHAVEN (Mississippi River.) J. H. MATHEWS (late of Mobile, Ala.)</head>
                  <p>DeHAVEN, MATHEWS &amp; CO., AUCTIONEERS, COMMISSION MERCHANTS AND GENERAL AGENTS, Congress Street, Opposite Post Office, W. B. OCHILTREE, Auctioneer. HOUSTON, TEXAS.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>P. H. MOSER, REAL ESTATE AGENT,</head>
                  <p>Two Doors East of the Post Office, GALVESTON, Texas. Has always a number of Houses for Sale Very Cheap. Titles Warranted.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <pb n="66 (Advertisement) -67 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC5696-00000034"/>
                  <head>T.E. Thompson, Dealer in WATCHES AND JEWELRY,</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>T.E. THOMPSON'S BUILDING</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>Corner Market and Tremont Streets, Galveston, Texas.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>MIKE BRANNAGAN. MAT. BULLOCK</head>
                  <p>BRANNAGAN &amp; BULLOCK, Carriages Nos 20, 21, 35 and 36. Stable, Bath Av., Near Market St.</p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>LIVERY STABLE</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>ORDERS Left at the Stable And the Office OF THE Exchange Hotel PROMPTLY ATTENDED TO.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>WARD, DEWEY &amp; CO.,</head>
                  <p>Lessees of State Penitentiary, MANUFACTURERS OF FURNITURE, Boots and Shoes, Domestics, Etc., SALES ROOMS, 24 MAIN ST., HOUSTON, TEXAS.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>CHAS. S. SHATTUCK,</head>
                  <p>IMPORTER AND DEALER IN FRENCH, GERMAN AND ENGLISH Fancy Goods, Glassware, China and Bar Fixtures. SOLE AGENT FOR TEXAS AND MEXICO FOR C. A. KLEEMAN'S Patent St. Germain Study Lamps, Chandeliers and Brackets, which we sell at New York Prices. THE IMPROVED STEAM COFFEE MAKER, For Steamboat, Steamship, Hotel, Restaurant and Family Use.</p>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>The following are some of the many advantages of this invention, which are considered indispensable by all lovers of good COFFEE. The principle of operation is extracting and filtering, thereby producing a saving of one-third material; and, as the apparatus is completely closed while in operation, all the aroma of the coffee is retained.</p>
                  <p>The coffee remains hot and pure until all used, owing to being surrounded with hot water.</p>
                  <p>And we would say to Captains and Owners of Steamboats and Steamships, and to Proprietors of Hotels and Restaurants, and to Families, that the COFFEE MAKER has performed its work beyond all expectations, enabling any one to use Java or Mocha Coffee at the same cost as when they have been using Rio with the old style coffee-pots.</p>
                  <p>A Trial, and Success will Crown your Efforts.</p>
                  <p>It was awarded the First Premiums at the Fourth Annual Louisiana State Fair, 1870; the International Fair held at Pittsburg, Pa., 1870; and at the St. Louis Fair, October, 1870.</p>
                  <p>The public are invited to call and examine this new and complete invention, at SHATTUCK'S Non-Explosive Solar Oil and Portable Gas Light Depot, COR. TREMONT AND MARKET STREETS, GALVESTON. TEXAS.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC5696-00000035"/>
               <head>THE SEQUEL.</head>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
                  <p>When Sentinel was brought before the Colonel, he fully explained to that dignitary the character of Pat; being that he was much given to jesting; that though thoroughly educated at college, and excessively indulged in his humorous inclinations of mind, which might have been expected otherwise from his family, his father being a parson, and a strict observer of the forms, and a rigid adherent of the doctrines of his church.</p>
                  <p>"The truth of your capacity to govern yourself, to the injury of no man in this garrison, can be easily ascertained, said the Colonel, and he then ordered the sergeant to bring to his presence, Pat the accuser, which was done. When the Colonel threw his glance at him he became furious. His eyes flashed with anger, and his chest seemed to expand with spasmodic throes of excited passion, while the countenance of the witness was all aglow with merry sparkles of half-concealed pleasantry.</p>
                  <p>"So you still continue to give annoyance in the world," said his examiner. "You were born a liar, and will die one, for know," said he, addressing the prisoner, "that this fool and mischief-maker came near involving us in a war with the Piemos tribe, one of the most industrious and civilized of these races, and to avoid such another attempt at deviltry, we order the sergeant to kick you from our presence, and order you never to darken with your shadow the walls of the Fort again. Sergeant do your duty promptly."</p>
                  <p>That officer, in obedience to the command of his superior, took Pat by the shoulders, and turning the prisoner's back toward him, preparatory to infliction of the punishment, received a backward kick from Pat, which sent him sprawling flat upon the floor, much to the merry-making of all present at the trial, and the safety of the Irishman, who fled with precipitate haste from the Fort. The sergeant being of a somewhat jocular disposition, regained his feet, brushed his knees, and was proceeding to pursue, when the Colonel recalled him, slyly observing "that it was lucky to get rid of such a crazy fool at so little expense."</p>
                  <p>"When the hunter was relieved he learned from the sergeant the reason of the Colonel's dislike to Pat, for," continued the soldier, "inasmuch as the Colonel is a bachelor, your friend, on all fool's day, went up to the Piemos village and told Antonio Azul, the chief, that the Colonel had sent him there to obtain from him four wives for the use of the Colonel, not very youthful and with their front teeth out, for which he would give in return ammunition and whisky. Old Azul called a council and they agreed to it, and four widows were sent to the Fort, with their front teeth knocked out. When presented to the Colonel, that worthy became greatly enraged that such an indignity should be thrust upon him, and the tribe, no less surprised and enraged, that they had been imposed upon, treated the emigrants passing near their village with every means of annoyance, and spite, and contempt within their power. The complaints of the emigrants reaching the Fort, caused the soldiers to retaliate, and thus a war was nearly created with this people." On the following day Pat was found quietly seated in the circle, around the breakfast table, with his squaw and her papoose near his side, nothing disturbed by the events of the previous day. The Sentinel was kindly dismissed by the Colonel, and they were permitted to avail themselves of the wagon driven by Brown across the desert, to return with some artisans, who were to reconstruct the fort building at Yuma.</p>
                  <p>The teamster, Brown, in obedience to orders, hitched up his team of six mules, and started on his way to Tejon Pass, and thence to Los Angelos, where he was to remain until the arrival of the artisans and carpenters, who were to return with him, to aid in the construction of new buildings at the Fort. On the day selected for his departure, the sun ascended over the eastern mountains as red and fiery as the lava streams when gliding down their sides during the darkness of night. The Colonel had kindly granted permission to Big Horn, and Pat and his squaw to accompany him in his journey. After parting with the Colonel and several officers of the garrison, they took their departure, not forgetting a barrel of water and hard tack, furnished by the quartermaster at the Post. The lazy Indians, in their variegated costumes, followed them for a distance, begging for tobacco and whisky, and then slunk away to renew their bathings in the river, or to play cards upon its banks. Brown, with his team, had to cross a sandy desert of some fifty miles, where neither wood nor water was to be had until he reached the mountain range beyond. As<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC5696-00000036"/> he entered on the first mile of his journey, he cracked his whip and with a stout heart said "that he would cross the sandy waste within twenty hours, and he would bet on it." So on he drove, with a merry whistle, the sand deepening in his course, as he proceeded, until he came to a sandy ridge where a few mesquit bushes afforded shelter to the watchful hare, when a black object sprang up erect upon its feet, and the sleek, greasy form of Crow presented itself to view.</p>
                  <p>"What are you doing here?" said Brown.</p>
                  <p>"You just see," said Crow, "that I am a deserter from the Indians, and had a suspicion that you all would be goin' to go to the gold mines of Californy. I thought I'd jest try my hand and take dis shadow somewhere nigh your wagon."</p>
                  <p>"Have you got any money to pay your passage?" asked Brown, with a quizical tone of voice.</p>
                  <p>"Yes, sar," replied Crow; "but inasmuch as it's bein' a government conveyance, a kind of public concarn belonging to de people, I guess you'll be light on dis individual, being as you see I'se de first disnaturalized citizen of my color." Saying which he pulled from his pocket a buckskin purse, well filled with fine river gold, and as Brown held out his hand for the passage money, he poured about an ounce into it.</p>
                  <p>"Get in," said Brown. "You are a citizen and must be protected, and I'll drink your health when we reach the mountain ahead."</p>
                  <p>Crow instantly sprang into the wagon, and, after shaking hands all around, produced a pipe and tobacco, and next begging a match, began relating what happened after the shooting of the Indian, by Big Horn. He said, in substance, that "the Indians who were in the company, suspected him of complicity with the whites, in giving them information about their attempt in kidnapping the squaw, and that he, in company with them, followed the wagons to the Fort for revenge; and that early one morning, seeing a man approach with Big Horn's wrapper on, they mistook him for that man and shot him in the back; whereupon dis child suspicioned dat dey might sarve him the same way, thought he'd just leave while the scalp was still stuck on his head."</p>
                  <p>"A narrow escape you made of it," said Brown, winking at Big Horn, "who knows but this Crow has been sent after you to pick you off in the dark?"</p>
                  <p>"No sar," said Crow, "I'll give up my life as de heaven's proof ob my sincerity ob my trufe. What, kill a white man for killin' an Indian! No sar, my conscience would smudder me in one night." Thereupon he surrendered his pistol and knife up to Brown.</p>
                  <p>"All right," said Brown, "I'll drink your health when we reach the mountains. But there's one question more, and then we'll deem ourselves safe: Where did you steal that purse of gold?"</p>
                  <p>"As for dat," said Crow, "dey give it to me to take care of while dey went swimmin' dis mornin'."</p>
                  <p>"They considered you very honest then. Where do they get it?" observed Pat.</p>
                  <p>"Dat's for some other darkey to say, I 'spose gamble for it," replied Crow."</p>
                  <p>"What do you intend to do with it?" said Brown.</p>
                  <p>"Do with it?" said Crow, looking as one in deep thought, and then answered, "Divide it 'mong us when we reach 'Frisco."</p>
                  <p>"Good intentions should be rigidly enforced, so hand it over, and I'll be banker for us all," replied the driver.</p>
                  <p>"Sartinly," replied Crow, and he once more brought forth the greasy buckskin bag and passed it to Brown, who kept it for the use of the company.</p>
                  <p>Towards noon, the rays of the sun grew intensely hot, and the tires of the wheels seemed to sink deeper into the sand; the mules began to slacken into a slow walk, while the sweat seemed to roll out from every pore of the heated skins of the tired animals.</p>
                  <p>Mrs. Dougherty became restless and excited. She glanced around at the horizon to every point of the compass. Her features changed from a lively expression to one of alarm and anxiety, and pulling Big Horn by the sleeve, she whirled her arm around in the air in every direction.</p>
                  <p>"What is it?" asked Big Horn, being able to detect no moving object in view. She then replied in Spanish, "We must camp quick, no dinner, all drink of water; the wind will come quick, the sand will follow; desert storm, choke us with sand," saying which she jumped from the wagon, and seized the lead mule by the bridle.</p>
                  <p>"I suspected it," said Brown, "all of you get out, unhitch, and tie fast the mules."</p>
                  <p>All immediately went to work to prepare for the coming sand storm. The mules were quickly fastened, the wheels taken off the wagon, the bed or body turned over for a shelter, and the mules larrieted to the wheels.</p>
                  <p>The young squaw brought water to each of them, and urged them to drink plenty of it. She told them to wrap up when the wind came to keep out the dust.</p>
                  <p>"I see nothing," said Pat, "to make all this fuss about; I<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC5696-00000037"/> believe you have both gone crazy. There's not a cloud visible, and not a breath of wind moving."</p>
                  <p>"Wait awhile; don't you see how restless the mules are, and how they are looking toward the northwest, and how the animals are striving to huddle together?" said his wife, who again gave water to the mules, and offered some to the men. "You will be much dry before to-morrow," she said. She then poured some water over herself and child.</p>
                  <p>"There," said Pat. "Indian like, she has spiled that new dress I bought for her at the Fort. This is decidedly a rich joke; the wind may blow again, but fools will never die."</p>
                  <p>Though the mules grew more restive, yet even Big Horn began to doubt the arrival of the coming storm, though the very heavens seemed filled with a great wave of silence and heat. Suddenly turning his glance toward the northwest, he seemed to trace in the distant space the formation of new mountain ranges, falling and rising in their heights, while a burning blast of air struck his face. "It will be here directly," said the Indian wife pointing to the gathering mountains of wind and dust. "Quick, come with me to the wagon, the wind will burn you, and the sand will cut and stifle you," and then with her blanket wrapped around herself and child, she sought safety beneath the wagon body.</p>
                  <p>Wave after wave of wind in quick succession lifted the light portions of dust from the earth, until mountains of dust at a nearer distance seemed to swell into existence in the very mid-air, when coming alarmed, Pat crawled beneath the wagon. Then went in Big Horn, but it being unpleasantly crowded, Crow and Brown only placed their bodies under shelter, leaving their legs exposed to the blast, which now began to strengthen in its fury, and thicken in its weight.</p>
                  <p>The storm of sand and dust continued until day-break on the following morning.</p>
                  <p>In other countries, these violent eruptions of the elements would be styled monsoons; they blast and scorch the land. Travelers are often blinded by them, being burning hot like the blast of a furnace. The finest silk cannot keep out the dust from throat and eyes. When the young squaw crawled out from beneath the wagon shelter, and announced the storm abating, the others followed her example, and a profound silence was observed until they were able to converse without choking, when Brown remarked, "Let us praise God for giving that poor Indian woman for saving our lives. In battle or in danger, hereafter, I shall protect the Indian squaws. This certainly was the last drying up place in creation."</p>
                  <p>When Pat and the others had finished getting the sand and dust from their eyes, ears, nose, and throat, he seemed seized with a momentary glow of affectionate gratitude, and most warmly embraced her, and he then swore "that as soon as a parson could be found, he would marry her for saving his life."</p>
                  <p>Even during the violent cowlings of the storm the agonized snorting of the mules could be heard within the wagon. Two or three of them were found standing with their tails to the blast, while the others were still lying with their backs to it, and were with difficulty placed upon their feet. They began coughing violently, and Brown almost despaired of their ever again being of any use in this world of sorrow and tribulation.</p>
                  <p>The squaw seemed most anxious for day light to arrive, for though the crystal atmosphere renders the starlight brilliant it was insufficient for the purposes she had in view.</p>
                  <p>"This all comes from Crow's stealing that purse. I move we kill him," said the teamster.</p>
                  <p>"Look ye here, Mr. Brown," replied Crow, placing his arms akimbow, "ef I was meant to be kilt right here, we'd all gone de long road togedder, and furder, you's got some ob dat vile stuff out de purse, in your pocket, and its my 'pinion dat when one gets such hebby trash in his pocket, its mighty apt to stick dar, without considerin' other people's right to it."</p>
                  <p>"Well," said Brown, winking at Sentinel, "As there's no high timber in these parts, we'll have to wait till we reach the woods," who replied,"I can't spare him yet, he'll prove valuable in the mine."</p>
                  <p>"Dar's whar I's gwine," said Crow."</p>
                  <p>During this colloquial display at wit on the part of the teamster they were all busily engaged in hitching up. The wheels were soon again placed on the wagon, and the word was given "all aboard," but they were delayed by two of the mules refusing to move in their traces.</p>
                  <p>"Here's a go," said Brown. "I believe that like us all, their lungs are full of sand and dust. No doubt you are in the same fix. I believe if I don't get water soon I shall dry up."</p>
                  <p>At last, after repeated lashing with the whip, the coughing: mules were made to move at a slow walk.</p>
                  <p>"Look," said Pat, "see where my good squaw is, some half mile from the wagon."</p>
                  <p>The squaw was seen plodding along at a slow walk, frequently stopping and stooping, and casting a level glance along the sandy surface of the desert. "Go Sentinel, see, she is beckoning to us," said Brown.</p>
                  <p>And off started Pat and Sentinel, and when they came up with her, she explained to them that the Indians have secret<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC5696-00000038"/> springs or sinks of water concealed in the deserts; that they never make them known to the white man, and if any Indian reveals them, he is styled an enemy to his tribe, and liable to be killed by any Indian knowing of his treachery. That near the sand hills just by, she knew one was hid away, but which one of the hills could not find out until after full sunrise; the vapor would be thicker over the spot where the water was than at any other place. Some of the sand hills covered a sand stone rock or ridge, and at the end of one of the ridges the spring could be found.</p>
                  <p>They waited with impatience the arrival of the wagons, when they all resolved to make a general hunt for the water, as it was evident that it would be doubtful if mule or man would survive if some assistance in the way of salt or fresh water could not be obtained. The tongues of the mules were hanging from their mouths, while several of them were dripping blood from their nostrils. A burning thirst had seized them all, and their sight grew dimmer every hour. Everywhere round the horizon appeared great rivers and lakes of water, and here and there springs seemed opening in the earth a few rods before them.</p>
                  <p>After they had continued their search for over an hour, they became more exhausted as the sun's rays grew more intensely warming, and they had almost yielded to achings of despair. The squaw, who had separated from the rest of the party, gave forth a joyful whoop, when they all started to their feet, and animated by the cheering sound, were soon beside her.</p>
                  <p>"Look there," she said, "you see that small mound of sand between us and the sun—look close, see the water coming through the earth like a fog. Go to the wagon and bring a spade and bucket."</p>
                  <p>Without speaking another word, Sentinel and Pat hurried to the wagon, and soon stood with the squaw above the spring, which Indian sagacity had discovered.</p>
                  <p>She now told Pat to go and get the rifles and some ammunition, "for," said she, "these springs are guarded by old Indians hid away behind these hills. and they may strive to kill us." But before Pat could lift his wearied limbs to comply with her request, she had again changed her position. When he returned with the rifles, she took one of the iron ramrods and probed the sand in different directions, and at various places, but the earth gave back neither jar nor sound. At last, requesting all of them to keep at a distance, she flung herself lengthwise upon the earth, and listened attentively for a while, then gazing at the sun, she quickly arose; and crawling along the ground with a slow movement, she stopped and plucked several blades of grass from the parched sand, and, after examining closely, thrust down the ramrod at the very edge of the mound, and the wood beneath gave back a resisting sound. She now knelt down, kissed the earth, and, still on her knees, raised her hands towards the sun and bowed three times to that great luminary of day. When the sand was removed, a wagon's hind-board was disclosed, covering a hole of two feet square in the soft sand-stone <choice>
                        <sic>stratta</sic>
                        <corr>strata</corr>
                     </choice> of rock. Upon examining the cave, Sentinel discovered a pier of human bones but not a drop of water.</p>
                  <p>"The spring is further back," said the squaw; "those are the bones of an Indian who betrayed the spring to a white man; the Indian was found out and was tied in the cave to a rock, with plenty of antelope meat, just close enough to the water to be constantly looking at it but not able to reach it. He died there, and those are his bones. Give me the bucket and follow," she said to Sentinel, as she disappeared down the aperture; then followed Sentinel, who soon passed up a bucket full of pure, deliciously cool and clear water. It would prove a vain attempt to describe the feelings of joy that were experienced by the thirsty and almost perishing travelers. Their very souls seemed to swell with gratitude at their deliverance from what seemed almost certain death. After they had partially quenched their thirst, being allowed by Sentinel to be cautious in the quantity of their drinks, they hastened towards Brown with a bucketful, but, before Crow had taken many steps towards the wagon, the mules had winded the contents of the bucket, and, defying all attempts upon the part of the stranger to check them, galloped off with the wagon to meet him, and came near running over the mouth of the cave, near which they stopped and began to nicker. They were taken out separately from their harness and watered, the others being held while each was supplied. The spring was examined by all, and proved a silent and confined reservoir of drippings from a ridge of sand-stone rock. The barrel was emptied of its sand, and the last tin-cup of water left in the spring taken out. Of course all these proceedings took several hours of their time. Sentinel had but then ascended from the hole when an arrow lifted the hair from his head and another killed the child that the wife carried in her arms. Instantly two rifles responded to the attack—one discharged by Pat and second by Crow-and two old Indians were seen stretched upon the sand. These two old guardians of the spring had lain hid behind the sand hills and, awaiting the opportunity when all were engaged in the intense excitement of watching the proceedings<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC5696-00000039"/> ceedings around the well, had stealthily crept towards the party, resolving to kill the traitress and the person who had visited the spring in her company. The mouth of the cave was closed, as they found it, Sentinel observing: "There are seven mounds here, seven days of the week; remember, boys, if ever you pass this way again, that it is the middle one, as the nose is supposed to be in the middle of the face."</p>
                  <p>All being made ready, the grain for the mules being placed in the wagon and the water barrel being also properly cared for, the wife, wrapping the lifeless body of her child in a blanket, she carried it in her arms, stating that, when they reached the timbered mountain, they would burn its body, while its spirit would await her coming in the other hunting grounds above. All parties, refreshed by their fortunate supply of water, and the mules fed, by the middle of the night they found themselves ascending one of the slopes of the Siera Madre; and, as they took a last midnight glance at the desert, with its tall cactus plants guarding its desolated wastes, a fire was built and the child's body reduced to ashes—the mother lighting the flames which were to render the corpse of her infant but dust!</p>
                  <p>After an encampment of pleasant repose, and when about to renew their journey, the return stage made its appearance, and Elrick sprung from the seat, and shook each one warmly by the hand.</p>
                  <p>"Must use a little haste," said he, while his face expressed the joy of their meeting, "I'm somewhat behind time; Miss Bart has sent you her address, Mr. Sentinel, and here's her card, and says she will be pleased to see you, should you visit England. I have also a letter for the Lieutenant; but she says it's only on business, so you needn't turn so pale, Mr. Sentinel. I shouldn't mind visiting England myself for such a treasure; and here, Mr. Pat, here's a little purse of gold for you, and her compliments and some request."</p>
                  <p>"Where will a letter reach you, Elrick?" said Sentinel.</p>
                  <p>"Direct to Fort Yuma. I'm going to visit the old abode, and get the horns and hide of that old goat," replied Elrick.</p>
                  <p>"You'll find them somewhere around," said Sentinel.</p>
                  <p>"I hope so," replied the driver; "as for Miss Bart, I surrendered her into the possession of the British Consul, who placed her on board of the steamer for England. So now you know all. You'll hear from me if you write," saying which he sprang into his seat, cracked his whip merrily, passed a word or so of general import to his passengers, and was soon descending into the desert with his train.</p>
                  <p>"No nobler and truer heart lives on earth," said Sentinel, as he waved his hand a fond adieu to the stage driver.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
                  <p>Some fifteen months had elapsed since we left Elrick and his passengers on the mountain slope, on their way to California, and we now present our characters upon a new stage of action in a foreign, but to most of them their native land. The great ocean of the east had been crossed, and they once more breathed the humid atmosphere of England. Not far in the country, some two leagues or more, perhaps, a stage road was observed leading to one of the principal cities of the county of L., and passed very near a small but substantial villa, belonging to Col. Lassing, a bachelor and a retired officer of the India army, whose years numbered some sixty summers or more. Some creeping vines, then in bloom, shaded the front of the villa from the ardent blaze of the noon-day sun, and a few stout oaks cast their shadows along the avenue leading to the outhouses, with a painted pump with an old iron arm, stood like a solitary sentinel guarding the premises. The master and owner of this solitary retreat was seated in an old cane rocking-chair in his conveniently furnished parlor before a slow fire in the hearth. The mahogany shelves which were stretched along the sides of the room were filled with maps and charts, and works on war, in a good state, of Morocco binding.</p>
                  <p>He was man possessing, to all appearances, a robust frame, aquiline nose, with a broad, firm chin, and piercing black eyes, but the hair along his temples was pearly white. Upon leaving his seat to reach a bell, placed on a table near the window, he revealed by his limping gait that one leg was shorter than its fellow. When the bell had summoned the waiter, he asked him in a mild tone of voice:</p>
                  <p>Is my soup ready?" and then added, in an impatient voice, "How comes it so late to-day, John?"</p>
                  <p>"Please you, sir," replied John, "the cook had such a strange dream last night that it's troubled her all day. She thought that old Squire Lassing cane into the hall, leading his absent son by the hand; and that his wife, who hangs over the dining room table, left the frame, and came down and took a seat by the table and invited them to eat salt with her."</p>
                  <p>"Too much ale, John," he replied, "tell the cook to put less froth in her beer, and she'll sleep sounder. Now go and look<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC5696-00000040"/> to the soup, John, and let there be no more hobgoblin dreams in her soup."</p>
                  <p>At that moment the stage coach drove up to the gate, announced by the shrill horn of the driver.</p>
                  <p>"Go quick, John, and see who comes. I'm sure there must be some mistake, John; I'm expecting no visitors."</p>
                  <p>After thus speaking, the old man resumed his seat before the fire.</p>
                  <p>"Does Col. Lassing reside here?" asked a young man as he leaped from the coach, and throwing wide the gate, confronted the waiter ere he had time to leave the avenue.</p>
                  <p>"May it please you, sir, yes; you will find him in the parlor on the right side of the hall; but please, I must first announce you, sir, it's the Colonel's orders."</p>
                  <p>"I'll answer for you this time" replied the young man; "see to my friends and their baggage." He then stepped lightly toward the villa, and flinging wide the doors behind him, suddenly stood in the presence of the Colonel.</p>
                  <p>"God bless you, uncle," he said, as he stooped and kissed him on both cheeks, who, surprised beyond measure, quickly arose to his feet, and fronting the unexpected intruder, exclaimed:</p>
                  <p>"Why, Fred, you here?" and lie drew the young man toward him and welcomed him with a warm embrace, "this is, indeed, the cook's dream verified," he said.</p>
                  <p>"I have a friend or so with me, uncle, are they welcome?" asked Frederick Lassing, in whom, no doubt, the reader will recognize Sentinel of Big Horn notoriety.</p>
                  <p>"Take the house and carry it to them, and all in it too, for I give it to you henceforth and forever," was the reply.</p>
                  <p>"That's the way the Lassing's talk," replied Fred, as he went to escort Pat and his wife to be introduced to his uncle.</p>
                  <p>Upon seeing Mrs. Dougherty, the Colonel seemed struck with admiration and surprise.</p>
                  <p>"This reminds me," he said, "of the lassies in India, where the sun's rays mellow without browning the complexion," and he then greeted them both with an honest and joyous welcome.</p>
                  <p>The girl had much improved since we heard of her last, being dressed in a gray traveling dress of a fine polished texture, well fitting and suitable to her complexion. Her fine head of hair was evenly parted in the middle, with ears adorned with a diamond set presented to her by Sentinel. Still, at times, her wild nature seemed to control her feelings in her restless motion of body and searching glances of suspicion through the open window. Now that they were all gathered around the Colonel's little fire, their feelings subsided by the pleasant aspect of surrounding comforts, and their anxious thoughts at rest, dinner was announced by John.</p>
                  <p>The Colonel was all aglow with excitement, and so agree ably pleased was he that he consumed most of the time in attending to the wants of his guests.</p>
                  <p>Pat had been warned to make no mention of Miss Bart's misfortune, and their startling connection with the sad events of her life; these were reserved for another occasion.</p>
                  <p>"Where did you first meet with your wife, Mr. Dougherty?" inquired the Colonel of Pat, "and what's her history?"</p>
                  <p>"Well," replied Pat, "I met he gathering berries along the banks of the Gila; fell in love with her; told her of my ardent feelings in Spanish; proposed and was accepted, and married on the first new moon, she looking then but fifteen years old. We brought her to San Francisco on our way home, and when we went to the mines and foolishly spent our money and wasted our time, we placed her with a Spanish and English teacher of languages, and this accounts for her speaking so many English words in her conversation."</p>
                  <p>"No doubt she can ride horseback?" observed the Colonel.</p>
                  <p>"Straddle or otherwise," replied Pat.</p>
                  <p>"Well, you shall both have a ride to-morrow and take a look at the country."</p>
                  <p>"I, me walk," rejoined the lady; "I, me climb fence; I, me go only, climb tree, 'lone."</p>
                  <p>"As you please," replied their host.</p>
                  <p>"I believe after dinner I'll gallop over and see my sister," observed Frederick.</p>
                  <p>"Take care for your heart, my young buck," rejoined the Colonel, "there is an old schoolmate of Lydia's sojourning with her, a daughter of the late Sir Harry Bart, who was reported to have been killed by the Indians. She tells some wonderful stories of her escape from them during the night. She's a very pretty girl, indeed, and would have made a very dignified one, too, had she been a trifle taller. They are cheek and soul friends."</p>
                  <p>It is said that the queen had, during his life, much appreciated his services to the State, and, upon hearing of the lady's sad story, she had her brought to the palace, and would willingly have made her one of her maids of honor. Like most men, who devote their services to their country, his estate only affords a thousand a year. "I think, from what I saw of her, that she is a fine-spirited girl. But you must spend the day with me; there will be plenty of entertainers at the Hall; your presence would scarcely avail to add to the pleasure of the evening."</p>
                  <pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC5696-00000041"/>
                  <p>"Then be it so," said Sentinel, "I shall cheerfully and gratefully do your bidding," and then, he added, "Who has the estates in hand?"</p>
                  <p>"Old Lowering, your father's ancient legal adviser. He will be glad to hear of your presence in the country. Your father made a will, but was unable to leave Lydia much of the goods of this worthless world; the estates, being in tail, were made in your favor. Of course," he added, "you got the money for which you drew when in San Francisco?"</p>
                  <p>"She sent it promptly," replied Sentinel.</p>
                  <p>"And it reached us when we were just from the mines, and not a dollar to buy a loaf of bread," added Pat.</p>
                  <p>"Yes, 'tis true," added Sentinel, "and Pat got drunk as soon as he got in rough water, the steamer only puffing gently through rough water."</p>
                  <p>"And you got so," replied Pat, "before leaving smooth water, begora!"</p>
                  <p>Sentinel retired early to bed that night, but the uncle, with Pat and his wife, remained until near daylight, so much was he interested in the wild stories of the Irishman's life. The morning after their arrival opened with great brilliance, the merry songsters of the grove enlivening the beautiful morn with their cheering notes of song. Mounting his horse, he passed through the lane and out at the gate leading to the turnpike road. As would be styled in this country, he walked his horse slowly along the road, when he was overtaken by two gentlemen riding black horses. It was evident they were people in high life. Both were graceful riders, and sat upon their saddles with firm yet careless ease.</p>
                  <p>Upon nearing him, he discovered the riders to be, one his schoolmate, the Count De Lesseps, the other the Lieutenant, whose life he had saved upon the plains. Little were they aware that the genteel-looking rider, whom they had just passed, was so nearly allied to Miss Lassing, whom they were going to join in a morning's ride, and afterwards to entertain at breakfast.</p>
                  <p>It may here be necessary to say a few words in explanation of the Lassing house, to which these gentlemen directed their horses. It had been the old Squire's residence for many years, and where Sentinel—or, in future, to be known as Frederick Lassing—was born. It was a roomy old edifice, built of brick, with piazzas running completely round it on the first and second floors. It stood a half mile from the road, with shade trees in front and rear. Flower-beds and hot-houses adorned the open space in front, and, as you neared the house, rows of box-wood lined the walks. Statuettes met the visitor on either side as he entered the hall, and paintings of fox or stag hunts, in gilded frames, decorated the walls. The furniture was carved and solid, while the library was filled with the <choice>
                        <sic>costiless</sic>
                        <corr>costliest</corr>
                     </choice> works on art and science. In this house resided Miss Lassing. and Miss Bart, with several other guests of quality. The old servants were retained in service, and the old nurse, who had attended Miss Lassing in her youthful days, might be called mistress of the house. Frederick's uncle, Lassing, occupied the adjoining farm, and the walk from his residence to the hall being but a short distance, he was a daily visitor at the Lassing house. Count De Lesseps and the Lieutenant were frequent and favorite guests at the house, and report had connected their names in marriage with these two ladies.</p>
                  <p>After seeing the gentlemen admitted to the grounds by the old porter at the gate, Frederick resolved to defer his visit to the house until a later hour in the day. So, taking another direction, he continued his ride; entered the park by another gate, where the foliage was so dense and the clustered vines were so thick as to screen his person from view. A winding path led to the keeper's cottage, where he arrived just in time to see the family at breakfast. He alighted, tying his horse to the limb of a short, stout willow, and then called the keeper to him. A long, slim individual made his appearance, when Frederick gave him his hand and said:</p>
                  <p>"Lawson, you have grown much grayer since we parted. Follow me to yon old log in the thicket. You recognize me, do you not?"</p>
                  <p>"Indeed I do," replied the man, taking off his hat and warmly returning the pressure of the youth's friendly grasp. "You have grown apace though, and you resemble the late Squire more than ever."</p>
                  <p>They retired to the log designated by Frederick, when, after conversing about many incidents which had taken place during the youth's absence, the keeper observed:</p>
                  <p>"Your father, on his dying bed, often asked for you, and, shortly after you left; regretted his harshness, which had driven you from his presence. Of course you could not help his hunting horse breaking his leg; but then, you know, it was his favorite animal. You disobeyed orders, which the Squire never permitted, even in a son."</p>
                  <p>"So it seems," replied Frederick, "but let these things go; let us change the subject. Who is this person alleged to be addressing my sister?"</p>
                  <p>"An American, an officer in the army. He came here some months ago. It appears he met Miss Bart, your sister's friend, Miss Bart, while traveling with the late Sir Harry, and being<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC5696-00000042"/> in England and of her arrival through the papers, called to see her in London, and then followed her to the house. But I don't think she ever took much of a liking to him, for I have known her to walk through the park alone with the dog old Rock, when he was among the company in the parlor. Miss Bart is a strange lady anyhow. They say she can speak the Indian language in America, and was present when her father was killed, and came near being made prisoner by them. Old Mr. Lowering, the lawyer of the estate, has complained of late at the extravagance here. But you know he is a very close man to deal with, and they say he has saved much money for the estate. See, there goes the gay party to ride—there goes the gay party on their morning ride," and he pointed to a dozen ladies and gentlemen, elegantly mounted, moving toward the Park gate.</p>
                  <p>"I will now breakfast with you, Lawson. Remember, I do not wish to be known by any of the family." The day passed smoothly along—the keeper and the young man visiting portions of the estate until toward night, when Frederick, leaving his horse in change of the keeper, moved toward the house, but finding it full of company, returned to his uncle's abode.</p>
                  <p>On the following day the two girls were seated in an harbor, indulging in an hour or so at chit-chat, when an object most fancifully-dressed, with flowing black hair, tied with a ribbon of red, hung down her back, a double band of pearls and shells around her neck, presented herself. Her dress was of a gaudy color, and scarcely reached to her knees, with stockings, of elegant red, and with moccasins beautifully braided with beads. Her figure was round and comely in shape, her eyes of sparkling black, with rows of sparkling white teeth. and lips of deep Vermillion color. Her fingers were decorated with two costly diamond rings, while several of silver were visible on the others. She carried a bunch of flowers which she bad gathered on her way through the grounds.</p>
                  <p>"What a strange, handsome creature we have here, said Miss Lassing, as Mrs. Dougherty approached them, and then bowing and laughing took a seat at their feet.</p>
                  <p>"It must be one of the gipsy women lately arrived in the neighborhood," said Miss Lassing, "who seeing us alone, has ventured to approach and tell our fortunes."</p>
                  <p>"Me Indian squaw," said the intruder, frowning, "me no gipsy."</p>
                  <p>"Where do you live or come from?" inquired Miss Bart.</p>
                  <p>"Over the big, big water, where the clouds and sun come from, and she pointed to the east, "way over much big water."</p>
                  <p>"She's an Indian squaw, probably connected with some show. I've seen many of her race, but I confess this to be a very pretty representative. I like her figure well," said Miss Bart.</p>
                  <p>"She certainly is a very singular and attractive person," replied her companion.</p>
                  <p>At this moment, the wild girl cast herself upon her knees, and folding her small hands over her glistening hair, and then intently gazing into Miss Bart's, face, suddenly exclaimed: "Lutella! Lutella!!" and as suddenly seizing the lady's hand, kissed it, who exclaimed: "What in all heavens does this mean; how did she know my name?"</p>
                  <p>She was about to question her, when Miss Lassing's favorite pony came to the arbor to greet the ladies, and the squaw sprang upon its back, straddle-wise, and, with a trick known only to the Indian women, made the pony start off into a rapid gallop, much to the surprise of the ladies, and anxious fears of safety for the pony. But they saw neither squaw nor pony that day any more.</p>
                  <p>The keeper was instantly sent for, and ordered to pursue, but neither he nor pony made their appearance till night, for the wild rider had ridden the horse to the Colonel's stable in spite of fence or hedge, where she was received by the Colonel and Frederick amid shouts of applause, but Mr. Dougherty was much troubled in mind, observing, "she would get him into trouble yet," for he, perceived she lost nothing of the Apache's passion for horse-stealing.</p>
                  <p>The keeper had tracked her course, and arriving at the Colonel's, was kindly invited by him to spend the day, and keep silent tongue.</p>
                  <p>"If you look sharp on your way to the house you'll find the places where she lifted the pony over," said Frederick Lassing.</p>
                  <p>"Surely," replied Lawson, "she must be one of those gipsies who charm objects to mount in the air, when the wife replied, "A very good horse—too much skin grease for Indian to ride—very good to eat—me cook him."</p>
                  <p>The Colonel nearly choked with laughter, while Lawson seemed stupefied with the extraordinary performance of the Indian rider.</p>
                  <p>"You keep me in perfect terror," sullenly remarked Pat, "what will my parents say to my being wedded to this bundle of barbarity? She, like the partridge and wild turkey, will always remain the same in her wildness, never to be tamed."</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC5696-00000043"/>
                  <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
                  <p>Love enters the soul through all our senses, a thrill of pleasure pervades all the system, which increases as we continue to behold the object of its adoration. Absence chills the fever which beauty has kindled in the heart, unless a selfishness keeps up the fire. There are some hearts whose remembrances endure to the utmost limits of existence, but not generally the attractive objects by which they are surrounded engage the thoughts and passions, to the exclusion of the dimly remembered past. Among the lost arts of the ancients was that of painting marble slabs with pictures, which suffused the whole mass with such intensity of coloring, that when one plate, or slab, was to be cut from the block, the picture was revealed in the marble with renewed lustre and freshness of beauty; and thus it is with the hearts of truth, time may waste away the scenes of the past, but as they fade from view, others equally enticing and beautiful, are revealed in all things resembling the first impressions of youth.</p>
                  <p>With Lutella, hers was a bold, firm nature; she loved the man who rescued her from the Apache chief. Yet, while she carried the secret within her breast, and treasured it with all the watchfulness that the miser does his gold, she worshiped the thought of the object of her passion, that had her life, been dissevered, both parts of it would have evinced alike the image of her love. With Frederick, his was more of a hopeful desire, being more of a wish than a passion; yet, eager to venture his existence to obtain the constant longings of his breast. It was on the same evening after his visit to the arbor that Lawson, in company with the young heir to the estate, returned to the keeper's house.</p>
                  <p>"You have sent for my sister," said Frederick to Mrs. Lawson; "of course you did not tell her for what purpose she was summoned." "I have kept your secret," said the wife; "and you may expect her in a few minutes, sir;" when shortly thereafter Miss Lassing was seated in the keeper's room.</p>
                  <p>She was a singularly fascinating girl, all Grecian in her face, neck and shoulders, with clear complexion, and low receding brow. Her eyes were black, with a mellow glance—rather thoughtful in their expression, if not kindly meditative. She scarcely had time to remove her shawl and bonnet, when Frederick, suddenly entering, thus spoke:</p>
                  <p>"Allow me to salute you with a brother's love," and before she had time to resist, he kissed her fervently upon her cheek. "Now, look at me well, and see if you behold the lineaments of any of the features of your race." Whereupon the young girl cast herself into his arms and wept. He led her from the room in silence, and walking slowly, conversing they parted for the night with an affectionate embrace, just as the Lieutenant and DeLesseps came view to meet her. She heeded them not, but sought the library by a secret path, so well known to her girlhood. Shortly after meeting with her brother and entrance to the library, she was joined by Lutella, who exclaimed:</p>
                  <p>"Your steps are as stealthy as a cat, and the Lieutenant is furious at your parting with a strange gentleman!"</p>
                  <p>"Oh yes, truly, Lutella, it was both fortunate and unfortunate. Why did you seek me?"</p>
                  <p>"Only that they persuaded me," replied Lutella; "that had I been aware of your intended meeting with your <foreign xml:lang="LAT">in cog.</foreign> lover, would have resisted their solicitations."</p>
                  <p>Miss Lassing smiled, and then replied, "Yes, he is very dear to me; I love him as my life. You shall meet with him before very long. I am persuaded you will approve of my conduct; and as for the Lieutenant, a little spell of jealousy will purify his liver. So let the matter drop, if you love me. Come, I'll read some letters to you while you can doze upon the sofa, Lutella. But mind, don't sleep too soundly."</p>
                  <p>Saying which, she lighted the wax candles upon the centre table, and began reading her correspondence to her friend, who was now reclining at full length upon the sofa, and who thus spoke: "I wish I had not seen that Indian girl; it brings back scenes of my life of the horrible Apache Pass."</p>
                  <p>Frederick, upon arrival at his uncle's house, began thinking over the occurrences of the day, and particularly that of his interview with his sister; and it occurred to him that their parting might have been observed by the parties who were approaching in the distance, and cause a kind of slander to float in the drawing-rooms of the fashionable; and knowing that he had bound his sister to secrecy, he hastily retraced his steps and entered the library room as a most startling event occurred. Miss Lassing had read Lutella into a restless repose, when she suddenly sprang from her reclining position, and wringing her hands as though in intense agony of mind, exclaimed "Sentinel, Sentinel, oh save me from Mutante, I am dying—stab, kill me—oh, wretched me! Let go of me; oh, Sentinel, where are you?" And she sent forth a scream so terrifically wild and piercing, as to bring the gentlemen who were walking before the house to her assistance, and all the servants in the house<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC5696-00000044"/> were alarmed. It was at this moment that Frederick entered. "Sentinel is here, Miss Lutella; Mutante is numbered with the dead!" Then folding her in his manly arms, added, "Attend her, Miss Lassing; the open air will revive her." And then passing through the small door by which he had entered the library, disappeared from view. "That is your new servant, Miss Lassing," said the Count DeLesseps.</p>
                  <p>"Yes, sir," said that lady, in reply, "ready to serve me on all occasions, and a very responsible one too."</p>
                  <p>"Then," said he, "I may take my departure."</p>
                  <p>"If you so will it, Count. But take my advice, leave not in anger."</p>
                  <p>Fearing to risk further remarks, in which they might give vent to some indiscreet remark, the gentlemen speedily took their departure, and the ladies again sought the library.</p>
                  <p>"What a horrid dream you must have had, Lutella," said her sympathising friend.</p>
                  <p>"Horrid; indeed it was most fiendish. I again passed through my capture by Mutante, of which I spoke to you on my first arrival; and once more, I thought, Sentinel saved me. Nay, I could swear he was present, and bore me in his arms away from the murderous wretch."</p>
                  <p>"You probably mistook my brother for him, for he was present and bore you into the open air," replied the sister.</p>
                  <p>"Well, how strange are our fancies! I could almost take my oath that it was Sentinel himself," Lutella responded.</p>
                  <p>Neither Lesseps nor the Lieutenant made their usual calls the next morning, and Miss Lassing's spirit grew sad within her.</p>
                  <p>It would be foreign to our object to minutely describe further proceedings at the Lassing House. We must now renew our intimacy with old acquaintances. Suffice it to say, that a proper explanation was given to the Lieutenant, in person, and he renewed his visits at the house. As for Frederick, business called him to London, and several weeks elapsed before his return. During his absence, Pat and his wife went to see his parents, but did not make a very long stay there, giving as a reason on his return, of his making his stay there so short, that the old folks were perfectly horrified, and that his two sisters scarcely noticed his wife, and would not introduce her into society; which want of breeding was unnoticed upon the part of his wife, but he was bound to resent it, and left them in disgust. The Colonel was much relieved when they got back, for he said that "it was the dullest time in his life while they were gone from him; and that though Pat let the lie out, there were many who fouled their souls by keeping the lie in."</p>
                  <p>Pat and Mrs. Dougherty did much to relieve him of the lies by shooting arrows, dancing, whooping, running races, and other amusements of the Apaches. Big Horn, as he always called Fred Lassing, soon joined them in their sports, which seemed to render his uncle thrice happy and joyous.</p>
                  <milestone n="*   *   *   *   *   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/>
                  <p>Though the streets of London had been befogged for several days past, yet on the morning of which we write, was one of unequalled brilliance. Out from an old antiquated looking building, in one of the by-streets, came a gentleman, neatly clothed in a suit of black clothes, softly closing the door behind him, and ever casting a furtive glance of observation along the street. His step was cautiously slow as he moved across the street to an apothecary's shop, which he was on the point of entering, when he was tapped rudely yet familiarly upon his shoulder, and a loud, manly voice rang out close to his ear, "Crooks, old boy, I've found you at last God bless you, I'm so glad to meet with you; but who straightened your neck for, you?"</p>
                  <p>"Ah, Elrick, it's you, indeed, embrace me," and he flung his arms around the driver's neck. When the first excesses of his joy were over, he stated that the Doctor was sick, and sent him for medicine.</p>
                  <p>"Remain here a moment, and after I get this prescription filled, I'll take you to the house to see him, as he was speaking about you last night."</p>
                  <p>A few moments' delays, and they both crossed the street, entered the house, and Elrick followed Crooks to the Doctor's room. The would-be master of all arts was seated in a rocking chair, made of curiously worked willow. A flowing morning gown, emblazoned with patterns of Egyptian designs, hung loosely from his emaciated form, as he with difficulty arose from his seat to greet his visitor.</p>
                  <p>"Have been longing to see you, Elrick, I have some questions to ask you," he feebly spoke, while his hand trembled as he pressed that of the driver's. "I have a question, I say, to ask you. Does Miss Bart still live?"</p>
                  <p>"I believe so," replied Elrick, "as I helped to save her."</p>
                  <p>"Pray be seated then, and tell me how she was saved," he asked as he slowly resumed his seat in his rocking chair.</p>
                  <p>Elrick then graphically described all he knew personally, and what he heard from Miss Bart of her capture and rescue by Sentinel.</p>
                  <p>"Pass me a glass of wine from that decanter," meekly asked<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC5696-00000045"/> the Doctor, when the driver had finished his narrative, "and then tell Crook-Neck to send his daughter to me," he added.</p>
                  <p>Elrick left the room after serving him with wine.</p>
                  <p>"And all this designed treachery for the paltry sum of one thousand a year. What a terrible thing it is to manage the human mind," he observed, as he gazed into the fire. "I do believe we are the various compound of matter and spirit of all the combinations of nature, and still," he added, "all this will dissolve and separate, and go into new formations of devilish creations. The girl saved—Mutante dead and rotten, stinking in his own carcass, and myself about to undergo dissolution, and nothing left me but vaporous dreams of past existence. What they have styled the beautiful of earth I have never experienced, never participated in; what is lovely in woman I have never admired. Philosophy I have tried to possess, and when I have traveled around the course of existence, I find myself at the starting point again. I find the measured secret of life to be but meditations upon the experience of our past life, a pyramid of regrets, an almost endless shadow of hideous misery of labor unawarded—of hopes crushed under the wheels of accident or chance—a life failing in its vigor at every sunset, and ending with a cipher."</p>
                  <p>At this moment of his soliloquy, Crook-Neck's daughter entered. She was a pretty looking brunette, very precisely dressed in a new calico dress, with raven locks of black hair, and sparkling eyes of the same color, though somewhat reserved in her manner.</p>
                  <p>"Be seated, pray you," said the Doctor, "I wish to speak to your heart. You saw the young man who summoned you to me?"</p>
                  <p>Ella Crook-Neck did as she was requested, and took a seat and gazed vacantly into the fire, and bowed her head in reply.</p>
                  <p>"I desire that lately returned Arizonian for your husband. You will find him as true as he is brave. But in case you do not make him love you, he will not marry you, for I desire leaving you both all the money I have saved for yourself and father in case he weds you. Now go, and leave me in quiet, I wish to prepare for this dissolving process now drawing to its close."</p>
                  <p>Ella took her departure in silence, joined her father and the stranger, and listened attentively to her father's statements concerning what had transpired between the Doctor and himself since they left Arizona.</p>
                  <p>"On the morning of our departure, we visited an Indian village, where we packed up our traps, he telling the Indians he was going to Medicine Mountain to procure more medicine, and get his instruments sharpened. Here he got a Mexican to join us. We had five mules, and so we started on our way, day after day, making but small progress, until reached Crow Springs, where we rested four weeks. The Doctor was dressed as a priest, with cossack, beads, and cross, and passed himself off as a padre. We next arrived at Tucson, when we visited the old Cathedral, where he preached a sermon to the Papagoe Indians. and promised them salvation to all who would show him where the Jesuits worked their mines. But the Indians, perhaps being jealous of intruders, refused to betray their nation. After this, we continued our tramp until reaching San Antonio, and after reaching Austin, came down the coast to Galveston, where we took ship for Liverpool. Upon reaching England, he looked up the banker where our funds were deposited, and then sought the industrial school, where my daughter received her education. Shortly after this, he became intimate with a celebrated chemist. One day upon his return home, he set a trap for flies, and after taking a number and confining them in a bottle, he made me stop up all the cracks in a small room with putty, even to the key-hole. He then let loose the flies and closed the door on me. Then through a hole bored in the pannel of the door, he put a kind of pop-gun and shot several pills against the opposite wall, there they stuck, which began to burn, and emit a horrible smell, which sickened me so in my stomach as made me fall on the floor and become insensible. He quickly opened the door, When my senses were instantly restored by the fresh air. After a time the flies recovered their vitality, when the Doctor hastily exclaimed: "You see I can extinguish life and restore its vitality."</p>
                  <p>"He next filed application in the court to claim the estate of the late Sir Harry Bart. I was compelled to go there to swear to her death. However, he did not push the matter very closely, when Miss Bart arrived in England and laid claim to be placed in possession. I don't know if he ever met her and never heard him speak of her any more."</p>
                  <p>"Well," replied Elrick, "he's a solid team for a mud-hole, but I want to tell you," he added, with a complacent smile, "that I found the horns and skin of the goat and brought them with me."</p>
                  <p>At that moment a rap was heard at the front door, and the next moment Crook-Neck led Fred Lassing into the room.</p>
                  <p>"There," said Crook-Neck, "is Elrick," and the two friends were instantly clasped in the arms of each other.</p>
                  <p>"I want to say to you," said Elrick, when he had time to speak, "I've brought the horns and skin with me. It was a<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC5696-00000046"/> suspicious trick you played me, but a very smart one; so we'll say no more about it, only I'll have to remind you of your promise, which was that I should masquerade some day with the horns upon my head."</p>
                  <p>"Be not alarmed, old fellow, we'll arrange that before long."</p>
                  <p>"You got my letter, I presume," said Crook-Neck.</p>
                  <p>"Yes, and am here as you requested, to consult on our affairs."</p>
                  <p>After an hour spent in conversation, and exacting a promise for them all to call on him at his uncle's as soon as convenient, and being reminded that Elrick had brought the horns with him, he took his departure for his estates.</p>
                  <p>On the following night Crook-Neck announced that the Doctor was sinking fast.</p>
                  <p>"I don't much like to leave him alone," he said. "I think he'll step out from his body before morning." On his return to the chamber of the sick man he told him to bring a chair near his bed and spoke; his voice had evidently changed, being husky, and his sentences shorter than usual.</p>
                  <p>"I want you," said the expiring invalid, "to prepare for our departure, you can do little good here any more—and you may be of great service to me in the next abode, after this life."</p>
                  <p>"I can't see it, Doctor," replied Crook-Neck, his face turning liver red, "I'm not ready yet, and I don't know the people or the laws there. They might try me again for the old offense and the passage may be a very difficult one to make, with many terrifying dangers on the road. I'd rather be excused."</p>
                  <p>When the Doctor replied: "Then you refuse to obey me in my last extremity, do you, you ungrateful murderer?" At this word, issued in a solemn tone by the Doctor, Crooks turned white and trembled, and thus replied:</p>
                  <p>"I am as guiltless as you are, unless I killed myself, and at your orders, and then you would be the murderer."</p>
                  <p>"I saved your life front the gallows, and taken care of your money for your daughter."</p>
                  <p>"And now you want to take both again," replied Crooks.</p>
                  <p>"Only the other day, by cutting a muscle, I straightened your neck for you, and now you refuse to do a small favor; base, base ingratitude!" the Doctor continued.</p>
                  <p>"And you call that a small favor," said Crooks.</p>
                  <p>"It's for your advantage as well as my own," replied the other. "You can attend me there."</p>
                  <p>"Yes," interrupted Crooks, "be your slave, and live in eternal fear and scare of your threats. We'll both be free in a short time—both by the hand of death, who will relieve me of a tyrant and you of a hideous life of treachery and crime. You'll no more find a victim in me for your experiments."</p>
                  <p>"Then you won't go with me," he replied, in a voice scarcely raised above a whisper, while his eyes changed from a glaze to a dim lustre. He seemed to rally after a short spell of coughing, when he asked to be raised from his pillow; and while Crooks bent over him to comply with his request, the Doctor spit a mouthful of some poison liquid into his face, but it only spattered upon his glass eye, which he soon cleaned off by washing his face with a tumbler of milk, which had been brought up to quench the invalid's thirst.</p>
                  <p>After this villainous attempt to extinguish Crooks' sight, the invalid seemed convulsed with cramps, and drawing up his legs and turning on his side, expired without a groan. Under his pillow was found a phial of deadly poison.</p>
                  <p>The corpse of the Doctor was decently buried, and his name seldom mentioned. Miss Bart was notified to attend his funeral, but was unwell at the time. In a note she requested that the body, at some future time, would be placed in the family vault, beside that of her father's.</p>
                  <p>Elrick became as one of Crooks' family, and being Ella's sole companion in her walks and visits to places of amusement, they became warmly attached to each other, and were married, when a visit to Fred's uncle was agreed upon. After which, by Elrick's pressing solicitation, they agreed to move to Texas.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
                  <p>Miss Lassing and Lutella Bart were seated at tea in the library about dusk one evening, when Miss Lassing observed, with a quisical smile:</p>
                  <p>"Lutella, why don't you strive to win my brother? I declare to you he's a noble fellow. Why the most adorable girl in the country would like to win his heart."</p>
                  <p>"What nonsense," responded the other, "you know I have only seen him at a distance. He gives us, poor girls, no chance."</p>
                  <p>"That's because you are engaged to the Count Lesseps," jokingly replied the other "and he says the Count is so jealous he is afraid he would <foreign xml:lang="FRA">duel</foreign> him to death."</p>
                  <p>"To be serious with you," replied Lutella, "the Count has proposed and will take no denial, but he pleads in vain," and<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC5696-00000047"/> the young girl seemed lost in thought for a few moments and gave vent to a gentle sigh.</p>
                  <p>"Ah, you are thinking of that Sentinel again," quietly responded the other. "I'll find out."</p>
                  <p>"Perhaps so," responded the other, and again she appeared engaged in silent reverie.</p>
                  <p>"My advice to you, Lutella, is to try and love the Count, and do not say nay the next time he proposes. He is very rich, and has few bad habits for a man in his station; or else take my brother, should he propose, for though he is richer than the Count, if that be an object, he is not so handsome. But, I tell you truly, he is a little fond of roving."</p>
                  <p>"Come now," said Lutella "let's talk of something more sensible;" and she left the table, and, taking a seat at the piano in the parlor, began singing some lively ballad of the olden time.</p>
                  <p>At this moment a quick and light step was heard on the piazza, when Miss Lassing, bounding from her seat, exclaimed:</p>
                  <p>"That's Fred! I will let you see him nearer this time."</p>
                  <p>He came to the door and was introduced to her, but the twilight of evening was so slimeringly dull that she could detect little more than the outlines of his features. After a few passing remarks, of how she enjoyed herself at Lassing, and the state of her health, he begged a private interview, and, with his sister, retired.</p>
                  <p>His object in seeing his sister was to arrange with her about a fancy country ball.</p>
                  <p>"A merry time we'll have of it," said he; "one of my old chums has arrived from the plains. Do not have it too crowded, and invite only the most intimate of your friends to be present. Now kiss me, and run tell your classmate of the anticipated fun ahead."</p>
                  <p>The Colonel made every preparation to receive this new accession to his household; and when Crook-Neck and Mrs. Elrick and her husband arrived, they found their visit had been expected, and all were anxious to receive them. As for Mrs. Dougherty, she gave them a full pressure of the Indian hug. The Colonel was much taken with Crook-Neck, whose history and sufferings had, in part, been related to him by Sentinel.</p>
                  <p>Fred came home shortly after the arrival of the Colonel's guests, and, after being welcomed by all, told them of the anticipated ball and how welcome they would be at the Lassing House, and how, after the ball, they could hold a council as to their future prospects in life.</p>
                  <p>"Three of us have decided that question already," replied Crooks. "My family are going straight to Texas in a few months. The fertile plains, timbered valleys, and beautiful streams of water, Elrick, has so thoroughly bewitched us as to render us all eager to visit this land of plenty—rich in all the agricultural wants of this age of progress and science, and where millions can find a home, leaving room for millions yet to come."</p>
                  <p>"Then Mr. and Mrs. Dougherty are one or two of your number," said the Irishman; "and Mrs. Dougherty can then straddle the mustang to perfection."</p>
                  <p>When this intention was made known to his wife, she clapped her hands with joy, and gave a whoop of satisfaction that nearly brought the plaster from the walls.</p>
                  <p>In vain Fred Lassing strove to oppose their intended trip to Texas. He offered every inducement within his power to prevent, but it proved of no avail, though the Colonel's genuine English hospitality—only to be found in England to such an extent—gave them an insight of what they might expect from one so rich and generous as Fred, yet they had resolved on it to a man. "If the Doctor was here, poor fellow, he would complete our Arizona circle," said Fred.</p>
                  <p>"An idea killed him; he could not again find the rock the ore of which could resist the power of the attraction of gravitation," said Crooks.</p>
                  <p>You have forgotten another precious person," said Elrick, "Miss Bart." "She is within hailing distance," rejoined the uncle; "but the matter of persons of which we speak, nothing must be said till after the ball," for they were coming in large numbers, dressed in every conceivable disguise that their whims could suggest or fancy call into display. The violinists had for an hour or more been playing the bow, and the maskers, warmed with the dance, when Crow strutted through the rooms, bowing to many and shaking hands with a few. His strut was admirable, his fiddle and bow being carried most gracefully under his arm. No one presumed he was a genuine darkey. Mr. and Mrs. Dougherty were very attractive in their Indian costumes, with their bows and arrows, and his Apache spurs, worked moccasins, and ornamented baskets, of the fruit of the prickly pear and wild berries The old Colonel, dressed in full uniform, talked with all he knew; and, accompanied by Crooks and Frederick in domino, seemed greatly pleased at the display. Miss Lassing remained uncovered most of the evening, and accompanied Lutella through the rooms, resting upon her arm, save when engaged in the dance. Frederick had danced with Lutella—and then they seated themselves near a window—</p>
                  <p>"Miss Bart," said he, "we are both dear to each other;<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC5696-00000048"/> I never had an opportunity before to relieve my passion of its truth. You are very near and dear."</p>
                  <milestone n="*   *   *   *   *   *   *   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/>
                  <p>Lassing House was beautifully lighted on a most exquisite evening in October. It was yet scarcely an hour past the dark of dusk when a gentleman walked near the gate opening at the main carriage way leading to the house. He occasionally stopped, and seemed absorbed in deep meditation. It was too early an hour for any but the most familiar guests to arrive, and Frederick Lassing, the young squire as he was called, was bracing his limbs and thinking over the past scenes of the last four years on the plains, and contrasting his then wild mode of life with the comforts and affluence which now surrounded him, when a dark shadow moved toward him in the person of a polished son of Africa, who bowing said:</p>
                  <p>"I say, sar, is you de master-boss ob dis house? I heard dar was to be a gatherin' for a smart shuffle, an' dis nigga's fiddle-player, all de way from ole Virginny—wants a job, and I'll gib you a spec'men ob dis chile's cat-gut if you be's in want ob a greased elbow."</p>
                  <p>"I am the owner," replied Frederick and then after a moment's hesitation added, "I may have use for you, so take a seat on that stone slab and play us a reel until the keeper yonder comes to light the lamps at this gate."</p>
                  <p>"How much you gwine to pay dis chile fur de night's work? You see, boss, widout 'fendin' 'ou, dis chile's got to eat, and wants de wuff ob his labor."</p>
                  <p>"Say five shillings an hour," said Frederick, and the darkey counted on his fingers, "Dat'll do, sar, much 'bliged," and after tuning his string, he struck off with the corn-husk reel and with such a dashing touch of the strings, that Frederick's legs fairly quivered under him. "You shall have six shillings an hour, keep on old music box," said Frederick, as he suddenly grasped the fiddler's hat and flung it upon the ground, and began dancing around it, when the master of the violin said grumly, "You done spil'd dis nigga's hair fur de 'cashun ob de party."</p>
                  <p>Lawson coming up with an attendant to light the gate lamps, he got a glimpse of the applicant, whose crisped locks of wool were puffed out above his ears sustained two broad laps of white of his collar. With all, the musician was quite respectfully dressed for a darkey.</p>
                  <p>"Follow me to the house, Mr. Crow," said Frederick, "and we'll see what good things are awaiting your arrival."</p>
                  <p>"So you knows dis darkey den. Truth, ain't you de feller dat made Irish Pat grease de board on de plains. I knows you is since I hear you laff."</p>
                  <p>But Frederick was too full of laugh to reply until after a spell, and he added, "oh you need not deny it, you broke de wagon board. The Irishman was too much for you that time. But how came you here?"</p>
                  <p>"I jined a troupe ob minstrels, and b'long to a travelin' show, and do de strings ebery udder nite at de village. I sees you's at home hereabouts." Lawson bowed to Crow as he passed. "I like to see sich respecks showed me," said Crow, "it shows I'm de equal ob any man in dis Queen's country."</p>
                  <p>Frederick was again seized with a gushing fit of laughter, which continued until they reached the house.</p>
                  <p>"Look here," said Crow, "any dogs about dis mound ob light? for if dar be, dis chile wants to know 'bout dem."</p>
                  <p>"Rest satisfied, Crow," replied his conductor, as he entered his private office, where they found Elrick and Pat playing at cards. "Here's Crow," said Frederick, "take care of him until I come," and he left.</p>
                  <p>Crow was thunder-struck. They shook hands time and again, but he pushed off, saying, "Gentlemen, spare dis nigga's collar; I's got to preform before de noblest ob dis country. Berry glad to see you, but don't be too familiar."</p>
                  <p>"What became of Brown?" asked Pat, "he got all your old dust."</p>
                  <p>"Maybe he didn't fool dis chile. Dis nigga had two bags; got de one which had shot in it. He went to Los Angelos, sold de Guv'ment teams and deserted wid de money."</p>
                  <p>"Remember, Crow, and you, gentlemen, that Crow is to be one of the guests to-night, and to be so respected," said Frederick.</p>
                  <p>"What's dat's you say, I's to be de ekal ob de great folks tendin' dis party?"</p>
                  <p>"It's a masque ball, and you are occasionally to pass through the rooms, and once or twice give us a cotillion or a reel. You are to speak to us."</p>
                  <p>"Give us your hand on dat," said Crow, "I've seen many such make believe people. Dey hide dar faces in de streets and camp meetin's. Me don't come here to see dem. Dis chile's nat'ral all de time, and looks like his mudder and fadder —good and true stock from ole Virginny."</p>
                  <p>Here a servant entered and handed Frederick a scrap of paper, on which was written but a line, "Dress in the queen of the roses. ELLA."</p>
                  <pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC5696-00000049"/>
                  <p>Leaving his friends, Frederick went to receive his guests. He was none <choice>
                        <sic>to</sic>
                        <corr>too</corr>
                     </choice> soon to welcome, with his sister, the neighboring guests, for they now began to arrive in rapid succession and in goodly numbers. Not many minutes thereafter the violinists began to tune their fiddles, and in half an hour the dance began. Pat, with his wife, were dressed in full Indian costume; Frederick and his uncle, in plain dominos, promenaded through the rooms, and the old gentleman exercised his wit and humorous propensities to their full intent. Mr. Crow occasionally made himself visible in his enormous shirt collars, smiling and shaking hands repeatedly with the maskers, who marveled at the art with which any white person could so transform himself into an African, for they had no conception that in this case he was anything but some person of fashion in disguise. His sister, in plain domino, escorted Lutella through the rooms, and, save when engaged in the dance, her sole companion. As Queen of the Roses, she seemed beautiful indeed, her graceful form, brilliant dress, and dignity of carriage, attracting marked attention. Frederick danced with her several sets, until finally they were seated, and he thus spoke: "We will be dearer and nearer acquaintances. Come with me on the piazza, and, let us catch a glimpse of the moonlight;" and as they seated themselves and viewed the charms, of Luna, he continued: "I am a friend, and have been more so; I would give my life to save you from harm."</p>
                  <p>"You may prove a false friend," she musingly replied.</p>
                  <p>"There can be no such a person as a false friend, Miss Queen of the Roses; the moment one proves false he ceases to be a friend."</p>
                  <p>"Who are you, sir?" asked the girl.</p>
                  <p>"I say again, your friend; and, above all, your devoted admirer, or worshiper, if you will."</p>
                  <p>"Mercy! what a lover you would make; were any girl to listen to your cunning speeches, her vanity would trouble her through life. Let us return to the dance."</p>
                  <p>"Listen but a moment, fair Queen of the Roses—this very night will make you, on this very night depends the happiness of both. May the gods defend us both."</p>
                  <p>"Indeed!" she replied; "then I must be prudent and circumspect. Come?" and they returned to the parlors just in time to see Elrick enter in a goat's mask. He wagged his tail with a string tied to it, smooth his goatee, gave a short whiffing snort, and then blaited several times.</p>
                  <p>"Why do yo tremble, and why so agitated, fair Queen, are you afraid of the goat?" But she answered, only saying, "Let me be seated, and bring a glass of water;" and as Elrick passed several times amid the dances, attracting unmeasured surprise and admiration, then sought the piazza, she quickly followed him, and plucking him by the sleeve, in all eagerness she said: "Tell me in all truth who and what you are. It is a necessity."</p>
                  <p>"Then, of course, good Queen, as necessity has no law, I am Elrick, the stage driver."</p>
                  <p>"And where is he, the Sentinel of the Rock?"</p>
                  <p>"Here, also; he has been with you dancing; you ought to have known him."</p>
                  <p>"Assist me, or I shall fall," she gasped.</p>
                  <p>"I am here ever ready to assist you," said Frederick, as he caught her in his arms and led her to a seat.</p>
                  <p>The dance went on apace, and Miss Lassing, after seeking Lutella through the rooms, at last found her weeping by the side of her brother, and led her privately to her chamber.</p>
                  <p>"Remember what I told you, fair Queen," said Frederick, "a painful surprise often ends in a joyous reunion."</p>
                  <p>And here occurred a most amusing scene in the ball-room—for Crow, thinking of his six shillings, and it being a late hour—and something might be expected of him in the way of a musical effort, took a seat amid the musicians, and after turning his "Saft Down," as he called her, struck up a regular old Virginia <choice>
                        <sic>real</sic>
                        <corr>reel</corr>
                     </choice> whereupon the goat, Indians and Frederick joined, and the other musicians falling into line, the maskers joined, being drawn away as by an electric shock, fell into the circle, and with such eagerness did all seem to enter into the report of the dance, that Crow, putting aside his "Saft Down," hastened to add his beautiful figure to the dancers, and with a cry of "swing the one you love the best," moved his flat foot with astonishing rapidity; and then followed a rival effort between him, and the Indian for mastery, when the dance became a confused medley. And so, the ball ended, much to the delight and satisfaction of all.</p>
                  <p>And here let us conclude our narrative, in stating the marriage of the Lieutenant and Miss Lassing, and that also on the same evening, at Lassing Hall, of Frederick Lassing with Miss Lutella Bart, in the presence of all her friends; and to make sure that Pat Dougherty would hold sacred his marriage vows, which Pat had announced and promised before a California Justice of the Peace, the marriage ceremony was performed in his case with all the solemn and impressive service of the established<pb n="98-99 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC5696-00000050"/> lished church. After gratulations of the festivities at the Lassing House, usual on such occasions, Crooks, Elrick and his wife, including Mr. Dougherty and his wife, took steamer for New York, on their way to Texas, where they all arrived in good health, and enlivened by joyous hopes for the future. They are now inhabitants of this great State, which will prove in the end the honored Star of Liberty in the flag of the Union.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <closer>[THE END.]</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="advertisement">
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>S. CONRADI, Watchmaker &amp; Jeweler,</head>
               <p>61 Main Street, Van Alstyne's Building, HOUSTON, TEXAS. Watches, Clocks and Jewelry CAREFULLY REPAIRED AND WARRANTED.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>Fourth Avenue Hotel,</head>
               <p>COR. MARKET AND TWENTY-SIXTH STREETS, GALVESTON, TEXAS. GATES &amp; PHILLIPS, Prop'rs. (Formerly from Montgomery, Ala.) <list>
                     <head>TERMS:</head>
                     <item>PER MONTH ..........$35 00 to $40 00</item>
                     <item>PER WEEK ............$8 00 to $10 00</item>
                     <item>BOARD AND LODGING PER DAY ........$2 50</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>GALVESTON FEMALE SEMINARY.</head>
               <p>THIS Institute will open on the first day of September, in the building on Avenue "I," formerly occupied by Mrs. Huffmaster.</p>
               <p>All Departments will be represented from the Primary to the Collegiate.</p>
               <p>A limited number of boarders will be received.</p>
               <p>Application will be made to the Legislature for power to confer Degrees.</p>
               <p>Applications should be addressed to: BOX 921 T. J GIRARDEAU, Principal.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>BLESSING &amp; BRO.,</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>174 Tremont Street, Galveston. STATE AGENTS FOR THE Celebrated Lock-Stitch Wilson Sewing Machines. These machines are fast taking the place of all others, because, while they are by FAR THE BEST MACHINE made, they are sold at a SMALL PROFIT, making the retail price from $15 to $50 less than their competitors. Every Machine WARRANTED. Send for Illustrated Price list. Address as above.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>BLESSING &amp; CO., PHOTOGRAPHERS,</head>
               <p>174 Tremont Street, Galveston,</p>
               <p>Have the best equipped gallery in the State. Do all styles of work pertaining to the Art. SATISFACTION GUARANTEED in every instance.</p>
               <p>Frames, Albums, Stereoscopic Views and Photographer's Supplies. YOUR PATRONAGE IS SOLICITED.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <pb n="100 (Advertisement) -101 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC5696-00000051"/>
               <head>W. H. ELIOT, DRUGGIST,</head>
               <p>PROPRIETOR OF DR. ELIOT'S CELEBRATED SOUTHERN REMEDIES, No. 45 Main Street, Houston, Texas.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>P. W. JOHNSON &amp; CO., Undertakers,</head>
               <p>No. 14 Market, between Bath Ave. and 26th Street, GALVESTON, TEXAS. ORDERS FILLED EITHER DAY OR NIGHT. A full supply of Burial Cases, Metallic, Mahogany, Walnut and Rosewood. A share of the public patronage is solicited.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>ST. CHARLES HOTEL,</head>
               <p>Near the Central Railroad Passenger Depot, Hempstead, Texas. L. P. AMSLER, Proprietor.</p>
               <p>This House has been recently opened and newly furnished throughout. Satisfaction guaranteed both as to Fare and Prices.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>WM. D. PELAN,</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>DEALER IN Stoves, Tinware, AND HOUSE FURNISHING GOODS, And Agent for the Patent Filter. MARKET Street, between 26th and 27th Roofing, Guttering and all kinds of Job Work promptly attended to.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>Head Quarters for Ladies' and Gents' Kid Gloves.</head>
               <p>D. WENAR, Faney &amp; Staple Dry Goods, LADIES' AND GENTS' FURNISHING GOODS, IN EVERY VARIETY AND STYLE, Cor. Market &amp; Twenty-Second Sts., GALVESTON, TEXAS.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>N. C. WHITE,</head>
               <p>Slate, Fire Brick, Hard Slabs, Tiling, Lighting Rods, &amp;c., FOR SALE AND MADE TO ORDER. MANTELS FURNISHED AND SET UP. No. 111 Avenue I, near Corner of Tremont Street, GALVESTON, TEXAS.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>H. S. BALDWIN, JEWELER,</head>
               <p>109 Centre Street, Galveston. REPAIRING DONE WITH NEATNESS AND DISPATCH, AT REASONABLE CHARGES.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>K. G. KIRKPATRICK,</head>
               <p>Attorney and Counselor at Law, Corner of 19th Street and Avenue H, GALVESTON.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <pb n="102 (Advertisement) -103 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC5696-00000052"/>
               <head>Mme. OTTILDIE KEATS,</head>
               <p>MANUFACTURER OF Every Description of Hair Work, SUCH AS WIGS, CURLS, BRAIDS, ETC. 117 Main Street, Houston.</p>
               <p>Particular attention given to the making of Hair Flowers and Hair Jewelry, etc. Will give further information through the mail, upon application.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>Daily News.</p>
                     <p>J. D. SAWYER, BOOK and News Dealer,</p>
                     <p>MARKET ST., Cor. 22, GALVESTON, TEXAS.</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>Subscriptions taken for all Papers and Periodicals in the United States, for six or twelve months.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>G. A. GIBBONS,</head>
               <p>MERCHANT, TAILOR, DEALER IN Gentlemen's Furnishing Goods AND GENERAL OUTFITTER, 76 MAIN STREET, HOUSTON, TEXAS.</p>
               <p>AGENT FOR THE SALE OF Jno. M. Davies &amp; Co.'s CUSTOM MADE SHIRTS, ETC., ETC.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>C. H. MOORE, Galveston. GEO. I. DOE, Boston.</head>
               <p>C. H. MOORE &amp; CO. Importers and Dealers in DOORS, WINDOWS, BLINDS, BUILDERS' HARDWARE, Etc., Market St., between 27th and 28th, GALVESTON, TEXAS.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>A TREATISE ON HERNIA,</head>
               <p>With a New and Safe Method for it Radical Cure, WITH ORIGINAL INSTRUCTIONS TO OPERATORS IN SURGERY, AND NEW SURGICAL INSTRUMENTS. Octavo, 240 pages, beautifully illustrated and electrotyped from original drawings by the author. GREENSVILLE DOWELL, M. D., Professor of Surgery, Galveston Med. College.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>JOHN W. POPE,</head>
               <p>Carpenter and Builder, Shop Cor. 22d Street and Avenue "H," GALVESTON, TEXAS. JOBBING PROMPTLY ATTENDED TO.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>HENRY McMAHON,</head>
               <p>News Dealer &amp; Book Seller, 212 TREMONT STREET, GALVESTON, TEXAS.</p>
               <p>P. S.—My business is newly established, and I respectfully solicit a liberal share of the public patronage.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <pb n="104 (Advertisement) -105 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC5696-00000053"/>
               <head>JNO. K. WILEY,</head>
               <p>(Successor to ALBERT BALL, JR.) WHOLESALE AND RETAIL DEALER IN Hats, Caps, Boots, Shoes, Furnishing Goods, Notions, Etc., 155 Market Street, Second Door East of Twenty-Second, GALVESTON, TEXAS.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>J. O. SCOTT,</head>
               <p>Architect and Builder, MARKET STREET, between 27th and 28th, (OVER C. H. MOORE &amp; Co.'s,) GALVESTON, TEXAS.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>J. E. GALLAHER. N. H. NELSON.</head>
               <p>GALLAHER &amp; NELSON, Book Sellers, Book Binders, AND NEWS DEALERS, No. 233 POST OFFICE STREET, GALVESTON, TEXAS.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>L. T. BOTTO &amp; BRO.,</head>
               <p>MANUFACTURERS OF Stick, Rock and Fancy Candies, AND WHOLESALE DEALERS IN FRUITS, NUTS, ETC., ETC. STRAND, GALVESTON, TEXAS.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>M. ROSENBAUM, Merchant Tailor,</head>
               <p>175 Tremont STREET, GALVESTON, TEXAS. Masquerade Costumes for Hire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>P. H. CARVILLE,</head>
               <p>Cooper and Cistern Maker, (OF OVER TWENTY YEARS' STANDING,) Barrels, Half Barrel and Kegs of all Kinds Made to Order, and all Work Guaranteed. Manufactory, 15 Mechanic Street, GALVESTON, TEXAS.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>A. BALDINGER &amp; SON,</head>
               <p>DEALERS IN CHINA, GLASS, EARTHEN, BRITANNIA &amp; SILVER PLATED WARE, Coal Oil Lamps and Fixtures, WOOD AND WILLOW WARE, TOYS AND FANCY ARTICLES, CORNER MECHANIC AND 22d STREETS. Galveston, Texas.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <pb n="106 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC5696-00000054"/>
               <head>J. W. BRADFORD, Agent,</head>
               <p>Corner of Church and Tremont Streets, GALVESTON, TEXAS,</p>
               <p>For the sale of Papers, Periodicals, and Books not to be had in any Book-Store or News Depot, but only from the Publishers or their Agents; also, for Steam Washers, and other Labor-Saving Machines, he has now the following:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>"OUR FIRESIDE FRIEND," <list>
                        <item>A Chicago Weekly of Eight Pages, (unsurpassed by any Family Paper among the Weeklies,) with which is given to every Subscriber a splendid Chromo 16x20 inches, in black walnut frame, and a chance in $40,000 cash and other Premiums for $4 per year—an offer unequalled by any Paper in the United States. The paper is now in its Third Year, with over 75,000 Subscribers.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>PICTORIAL FAMILY BIBLE, <list>
                        <item>Holman's Edition, containing the Old and New Testaments, Apocrypha, Concordance, <choice>
                              <sic>Pslams</sic>
                              <corr>Psalms</corr>
                           </choice> in metre, and complete Bible Dictionary, illustrated with nearly 400 Engravings, together with a History of the Books of the Bible, beautifully illustrated, and many Chronological and other Tables, all written to facilitate the study of the Word of God. Price $6 to $17.50, according to binding and contents.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>"THE ART OF MAKING MONEY." BY JAMES D. MILLS <list>
                        <item>A merchant of New York describing the road to fortune, specifying the best means of travel, and pointing out also the rocks and quagmires to be avoided. A rich merchant, after reading it, said: If he had its help when young, he would have been rich long before he was. Every young man needs it. Price $2.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>"PEOPLE'S PICTORIAL ATLAS." WILLIAMS' EDITION. <list>
                        <item>This is the latest and best edition of Atlas now offered to the public. It is a graphic and clear History and Geography combined, and brings down the History of all civilized Governments to prominent events of 1872. The 52 Maps are beautiful and unequalled, and are all new. Price $7.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>"THE SCIENCE OF A NEW LIFE." COWAN'S EDITION. <list>
                        <item>This is a work of rare merit—a mirror that holds up to one's gaze his own interior physical self, showing the beauty and harmony of every part, and also what wreck and ruin man can make of God's own work. The language is chaste, and the diction clear and convincing. Every human being, male and female, should have it. It has over 100 illustrations, and is printed in both German and English. It has been generally and well noticed by the first papers of the United States, and meets the approval of our best and wisest people. Price $3 to $4; and also, the</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>Steam Washer, or Woman's Friend. <list>
                        <item>This is a self-approved Labor-Saving Invention, so constructed as to make steam do, and much more thoroughly, the washing formerly, and yet by too many, done on the wash-board. Many families in Galveston now have them, and all testify to its excellence. See what W. Richardson, editor of the News, who has one also, says of it:</item>
                        <item>"We some time since gave a favorable notice of the Steam Washing Machine, for which Mr. J. W. Bradford is Agent. It will be seen that he has reduced the price to $8. We have now used this Washer for several months, and our longer experience with it only serves the more to recommend it. Our candid opinion is, that in any large family it will pay for itself every month, in the labor saved, and stilL more in the saving of the wear and tear by the common wash-board."</item>
                        <item>It is guaranteed, and the price, $8, will be refunded, if it fails to satisfy after being used as directed. A child can use it, and a half-hour's steaming washes a boiler full of clothes without rubbing, pounding, or straining the weakest fabric.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Further information in reference to the above given by letter or circular.</p>
               <p>Prompt attention given to every request or order.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>