<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC5795">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Intriguing for a Princess </title>
            <author>Bennett, Emerson, (1822-1905)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC5795</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-0276</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                    participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Intriguing for a princess</title>
                  <author>Bennett, Emerson, (1822-1905)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 p. l. 5-96 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>J.W. Bradley</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Philadelphia </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1859">1859</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
            <language ident="spa">Spanish</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="AEL Data" when="2003-01-21">Finished transcription and SGML encoding</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2003-02-27">Finished TEI conversion and final editing</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-04-22">Converted document from SGML to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-04-22">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n=" (Cover Title Page) " xml:id="VAC5795-00000001"/>
         <div type="half_title">
            <bibl>
               <title>BRADLEY'S RAILROAD LIBRARY.</title>
               <title>INTRIGUING FOR A PRINCESS.</title>
               <title type="sub">An Adventure with Mexican Banditti.</title>
               BY
               <author>EMERSON BENNETT.</author>
               <pubPlace>PHILADELPHIA:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>J. W. BRADLEY, 48 NORTH FOURTH ST.</publisher>
               <date>1859.</date>
            </bibl>
         </div>
         <pb n="Advertisement" xml:id="VAC5795-00000002"/>
         <div type="advertisement">
            
            <head>"TRUTH IS STRANGER THAN FICTION."</head>
            <head type="sub">SIXTEEN YEARS IN THE WILDS OF AFRICA.</head>
            <p>A Book of Thrilling Adventures and Hair-Breadth Escapes, more wonderful and intensely interesting than all the novels ever written.</p>
            <p>LIVINGSTONE'S TRAVELS AND RESEARCHES IN SOUTH AFRICA: INCLUDING A Sketch of Sixteen Years Residence in the Interior of Africa and a Journey from the Cape of Good Hope to <unclear>Loanda</unclear> on the West Coast, thence across the Continent, down the River Zambezi, to the Eastern Ocean FROM THE PERSONAL NARRATIVE OF DAVID LIVINGSTONE, LL.D., D.C.L., Fellow of the Faculty of Physicians and Surgeons, Glasgow: Corresponding Member of the Geographical and Historical Societies of New York Gold Medallist and Corresponding Member of the Royal Geographical Societies of London and Paris, &amp;c., &amp;c</p>
            <p>TO WHICH IS ADDED A HISTORICAL SKETCH OF DISCOVERIES IN AFRICA. Illustrated with numerous Engravings.</p>
            <p>Copies sent by Mail on receipt of the Price. $1.25.</p>
            <p>AGENTS and CANVASSERS wanted in all parts of the United States for this and other Popular and Saleable Books to whom the largest commission will be paid Send for our Catalogue and particulars of Agency.</p>
            <p>J. W. BRADLEY, PUBLISHER, 48 N. Fourth Street, Philadelphia.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i"/>N. B.—This is the only Cheap Edition of this work published. All other Books represented as republications of Dr Livingstone's work are spurious.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="(TitlePage)" xml:id="VAC5795-00000003"/>
         <titlePage>
            
            <titlePart>BRADLEY'S RAILROAD LIBRARY.</titlePart>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>INTRIGUING FOR A PRINCESS.</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">An Adventure with Mexican Banditti.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>BY <docAuthor>EMERSON BENNETT,</docAuthor> AUTHOR OF "PRAIRIE FLOWER," "REFUGEES," "PERILS OF THE BORDER," "CLARA MORELAND," "TRAITOR," "ARTIST'S BRIDE," "FORGED WILL," ETC. ETC.</byline>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>PHILADELPHIA:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>J. W. BRADLEY, 48 NORTH FOURTH ST.</publisher>
            </docImprint>
            <docDate when="1859">1859.</docDate>
            </titlePage>
            <pb n="5" xml:id="VAC5795-00000004"/>
         <div type="fly_title">
            <bibl>
               <edition>Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1859, by EMERSON BENNETT, in the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United States for the Eastern District of Pennsylvania.</edition>
               
                  <publisher>STEREOTYPED BY L. JOHNSON &amp; CO.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>PHILADELPHIA.</pubPlace>
                 
            </bibl>
         </div>
     
         <div type="preface">
            <head>PUBLISHER'S PREFACE.</head>
            <p>IN offering No. 3 of our Railroad Library to the public, we are quite sure that very many of our readers will thank us for giving them, in this form, one of the best tales of this distinguished author.</p>
            <p>The following, from a distinguished critic, so well expresses what we would say of Mr. Bennett, that we quote it in full:</p>
            <p>"We feel no hesitation in placing Mr. Bennett as foremost among our American writers. Of course we do not include metaphysics, nor history, nor philosophy, (although it must be confessed that his writings prove his perfect familiarity with each;) but we mean that he is the best writer, taken all in all, of any in this country, in the particular field of literature which he has chosen. There are doubtless many writers who excel him in some minor points; but, taken as a whole, his works are unrivalled on this side the Atlantic.</p>
            <p>"In all that he writes, there seems to be an irresistible charm, holding the reader spell-bound from the beginning to the end. That this gift is natural, and not acquired, we assume from reading some of his earlier productions. We well remember the eagerness with which the 'Prairie Flower' was sought after and devoured upon its first appearance in the West. Everybody<pb n="6-7 (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC5795-00000005"/> body read it; everybody talked about it; and for a time, not to have seen the 'Prairie Flower' was to acknowledge yourself guilty of unpardonable ignorance. Since then many other of his works have appeared, descriptive of Western and Southern life, with the characters drawn so faithfully, that one can hardly go on board a steamboat, or enter a hotel, without recognising some of the living shapes of his ideal heroes and heroines.</p>
            <p>"Of Mr. Bennett, personally, we know nothing, having never seen him, or even heard a person speak of him who has been honored with his acquaintance. But his reputation is the common property of all lovers of the noble maxims which he inculcates, the morality which he teaches, and the virtue which he adorns, in a style at once the purest and most fascinating. Under his glowing pen, vice is stripped of its gaudy coloring, and held up for abhorrence in all its haggard deformity; while virtue, humble and lowly, clothed in rags, is won from its timid retreat, and brought forth that the good in heart may do it homage."</p>
         </div>
         <div type="contents">
            <head>CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>CHAPTER I. The Beautiful Unknown <ref target="VAC5795-00000007" rend="right">9</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER II. Almost Magic <ref target="VAC5795-00000010" rend="right">16</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER III. The Story, and What Followed <ref target="VAC5795-00000014" rend="right">23</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER IV. Several Matters <ref target="VAC5795-00000020" rend="right">35</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER V. The Attack <ref target="VAC5795-00000024" rend="right">43</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER VI. The Hacienda <ref target="VAC5795-00000029" rend="right">53</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER VII. Almost a Murder <ref target="VAC5795-00000033" rend="right">61</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER VIII. In the Power of my Enemies <ref target="VAC5795-00000037" rend="right">71</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER IX. Return to Life <ref target="VAC5795-00000043" rend="right">82</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER X. "All's Well that Ends Well" <ref target="VAC5795-00000047" rend="right">89</ref>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Intriguing for a princess</head>
            <pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC5795-00000006"/>
            <head>Intriguing for a Princess.</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE BEAUTIFUL UNKNOWN.</head>
               <p>MY name is unknown to the world, and, were it not for the sake of conscience, I would not record it. As it is, however, permit me to introduce myself to your notice as Alden Burmond. As to where I was born, what is my age, personal appearance, and so forth, it is enough for my present purpose to say, that, at the time the events occurred of which I am about to give you a detailed account, I was in the very prime of life, unmarried, and not ill-looking. I had, during my earlier years, visited nearly every country on the habitable globe, and had passed through many scenes of peril, and been the hero of some thrilling adventures.</p>
               <p>So much for an introduction; now, then, for my story.</p>
               <p>The year 18—found me in Jalapa, in the interior of Mexico. My destination at this time was the city of Mexico; but having reached Jalapa one fine summer's<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC5795-00000007"/> day, when earth and sky were in their glory, I was so enchanted with the town, its inhabitants, (the female portion especially,) and the magnificent scenery around, that I lingered for more than a week beyond the period I had fixed upon for arriving at the Capital.</p>
               <p>Jalapa, I should remark, <foreign xml:lang="FRA">en passant</foreign>, is a beautiful place, and well calculated to make a most favorable impression upon one who has just passed through the pestilential atmosphere of Vera Cruz, where the vomito, during the hot, sickly season, decimates the population, and carries off unacclimated strangers almost to a man. Although situated in a bowl-like valley, surrounded by mountains, it has an elevation of over four thousand feet above the level of the sea, and therefore the air in the dry season is pure, and of a temperature to make one in love with himself and all around him. The town, with its luxuriant gardens, and flowers, and tropical trees, plants, and fruits, seems nestling, as if for protection, at the very foot of Mount Macultepec; while the lofty Orizaba, with its snow-capped peak, towering into the very skies, and shimmering in the bright sun, like a huge spire of silver, forms a point upon which the eye can rest with delight. On all sides save one, whence you have an enchanting view of the distant ocean, you are surrounded by mountains clothed with forests of eternal green. The city itself, containing some eighteen or twenty thousand inhabitants, is built in an irregular, picturesque style, not unlike some of the cities I have seen in Spain. The houses, from one to two stories in height, have long, grated windows overlooking the street, through the bars of which, as you pass along, you behold some of the most beautiful damsels to be found in any part of the world; for here is not only the "blue blood" of old Castile, but the blood of cross, which gives perfection to the human form and features.</p>
               <p>As I am writing for English readers, I shall take care to avoid Spanish terms as much as possible, that I may be more readily understood, which, I presume, is the desire of every writer who understands himself what he is writing about. Some books, remarks some shrewd observer, are written to amuse and instruct the reader, while others are evidently put forth to show how much the author knew. As I know but little, and am sensible of my ignorance, I shall take care not to make any display of my learning.</p>
               <p>Know, then, that I had been more than a week at one of the principal fondas, or hotels, of Jalapa, and had been daily rambling about the town and environs, and looking pleasantly at all the dark-eyed beauties that came within the range of my vision,—whether in the streets, in the vast gardens, or within their grated domicils,—when at last I met with the adventure I am going to relate.</p>
               <p>It was toward evening of the last day I had fixed for remaining in Jalapa, and I was sauntering through the Plaza Grande, or Great Square, for the last time, for I must take the diligencia before daylight the next morning<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC5795-00000008"/> ing for the Capital, when, stopping at a booth to purchase some fruit of an old woman, a lady brushed against me, in a manner that appeared something more than accidental. As I turned to observe her, she slightly put aside a thick veil, and I caught a glimpse of two soft, lustrous black eyes. She passed on without speaking or making any sign; but while I stood debating with myself, whether I might construe her actions into a wish to be followed or not, she looked back and made a slight motion with her hand. This decided me, for I rather prided myself on my gallantry, and the next minute I was at her side. She did not now raise her veil, nor make any sign that she was aware of my presence, and I thought perhaps I had committed a blunder. However, having a tongue at my command, and no person being within hearing, I was determined to know, and I addressed her in a low tone:</p>
               <p>"Has the Señorita any commands for me?"</p>
               <p>"Will the Señor Caballero fall back and meet me at the door of the Cathedral?" replied a sweet, silvery voice, that gave my heart a romantic leap.</p>
               <p>"Certainly," I answered, and immediately slackened my pace to let her pass on alone.</p>
               <p>She soon disappeared in the large Cathedral, which was near at hand, while I, wondering to what this singular introduction would lead, sauntered leisurely about for a few minutes, and then, carelessly ascending the steps of the church, leaned with an air of indifference against the main portal.</p>
               <p>In a few minutes the fair stranger appeared, coming from the body of the building; and, on perceiving me, she drew aside her veil, just long enough to give me a glimpse of the most beautiful features I had ever beheld.</p>
               <p>"Is the Señor Caballero as brave as he is handsome?" she inquired, dropping her veil.</p>
               <p>"In a good cause, Señorita," I replied, with a smile, "I hope my courage will not disgrace my beauty."</p>
               <p>"You jest, Señor," she rejoined, gravely.</p>
               <p>"Because you set the example, fair lady."</p>
               <p>"How, Señor?"</p>
               <p>"In asking if I am as brave as handsome—which I might be, and be no son of Mars."</p>
               <p>"You are not of Spanish extraction?" she said, inquiringly.</p>
               <p>"No, Señorita."</p>
               <p>"You are a foreigner, Señor?"</p>
               <p>"In this country, so please you."</p>
               <p>"Unmarried, Señor?"</p>
               <p>"I have that pleasure, at your service."</p>
               <p>"Could I ask a favor of you?"</p>
               <p>"A dozen, if you like."</p>
               <p>"Do not jest, Señor."</p>
               <p>"I never was more in earnest, fair lady."</p>
               <p>"My conduct must appear strange to you, Señor, and I have a strange request to prefer; but, if you will assist me, I trust I shall be able to repay you."</p>
               <pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC5795-00000009"/>
               <p>"Say on, Señorita."</p>
               <p>"Not here, nor now," she replied, again lifting her veil and glancing quickly around. "To-night, when the bell of this Cathedral strikes the hour of twelve, will you be standing by the booth where I first met you?"</p>
               <p>"I will."</p>
               <p>"Thanks, Señor: I know you will keep your word. Till then, adios."</p>
               <p>With this she turned back into the body of the Cathedral; while I, after remaining at the steps a few minutes, returned to my hotel, to acquaint the host with my new resolve to remain his guest for at least another day.</p>
               <p>After supper, I retired to my room and put my pistols in order; and then, lighting a fine cigar, I threw myself upon the bed, and ruminated upon my chances of becoming the hero of some romantic, remarkable, and mysterious adventure.</p>
               <p>When the clock struck eleven, I uncorked a bottle of excellent wine, and did justice to its contents; and I would advise any one who has a mysterious appointment to keep, in the solemn, witching hour of night, in a strange city, to do the same thing; for it strengthens the nerves like the sight of a row of policemen. Not knowing what would be required of me, nor how the affair in which I was about to engage might terminate, I sat down and wrote the particulars of my interview with the beautiful unknown on a sheet of paper, which I locked up in my portmanteau, so that, in case I never returned, a clew to my sudden disappearance would be found on searching my effects. This done, I stole softly down, and reached the booth in the Plaza Grande just as the great bell of the Cathedral pealed forth the midnight hour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC5795-00000010"/>
               <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
               <head type="sub">ALMOST MAGIC.</head>
               <p>SCARCELY had the bell done striking, when, from the dark corner of a building, a youthful page advanced to meet me.</p>
               <p>"Is this the Señor Caballero?" he inquired.</p>
               <p>"I was so addressed by a lady some hours ago," I replied.</p>
               <p>"Then follow me, Señor."</p>
               <p>"Whither?"</p>
               <p>"I may not say; but come, and you shall see."</p>
               <p>"How may I know that this adventure will not terminate with my life?"</p>
               <p>"If you have any fears, do not come," was the reply: "you were supposed to be brave."</p>
               <p>"But a brave man should be cautious; else is his courage little less than fool-hardiness," I rejoined, rather tartly.</p>
               <p>"All I can do to remove your fears, is to swear, by the holy cross, that no one with whom I am connected has designs upon your life or purse," said the page.</p>
               <p>"Well, lead on—I will follow."</p>
               <p>"Thanks, Señor."</p>
               <p>The page then set forward, at a quick walk, and, leaving the Plaza Grande by a broad street, or avenue, soon turned into a smaller street, and from this into another. Traversing this last some five minutes, he again turned into another, and presently halted by a gate, which he unlocked and opened.</p>
               <p>"Enter, Señor!" were the first words he spoke after quitting the Plaza Grande.</p>
               <p>I did as directed; but not, if truth must be told, without some unpleasant reflections. I had been in Paris, and London, and other great cities, and I knew that strangers were sometimes entrapped to their ruin; and might not this be a fiendish plot to murder me for my money? But then, again, this seemed improbable, from the fact that it was not in reason to suppose I would take money, or any thing of value, with me, when starting out on so mysterious a nocturnal adventure. But, whatever the end of the affair might be, it was now too late to be saved by repentance or regrets; for the page had entered and locked the door, and I found myself standing within some building, and in total darkness.</p>
               <p>"Give me your hand, Señor," said the page.</p>
               <p>I obeyed, and he led me forward, through a dark, narrow corridor, which had many a short turn, now to the right and now to the left, and which, to my impatient spirit, seemed to be endless. At last we reached a narrow, spiral stairway, and went round and round<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC5795-00000011"/> to the second story, where we came to a halt, still in total darkness.</p>
               <p>"One moment, Señor," said the page, attempting to withdraw his hand from mine, which now closed upon it like a vice.</p>
               <p>"Nay," said I, sternly, "you stir not again without me! I may have been foolish, in blindly trusting myself to your guidance; but I am not so foolish as to let you go till I know where I am."</p>
               <p>I felt his hand tremble; and this, for the first time, fairly awakened suspicion in my breast, that there might be some dark design upon my person.</p>
               <p>"Hark you!" I continued, in a low tone, but one that could have left no doubt on the mind of the hearer that I was in terrible earnest; "I am armed to the teeth; and the first sign of treachery I perceive, I shall blow out your brains."</p>
               <p>"Señor," answered the trembling page, "I swear to you, by the blood of my mistress, no harm is intended."</p>
               <p>"Very well, then—conduct me to her presence."</p>
               <p>"This way, then, Señor;" and taking two or three steps forward, we came to a wall, where the page touched a spring, and a door flew open, disclosing an apartment which I must pause to describe.</p>
               <p>The room was not large, but gorgeously furnished, and brilliantly lighted by a cluster of wax candles, set in a heavy chandelier of solid silver, which depended from the frescoed ceiling. The carpet, with its raised or basso-relievo flowers, of all the bright hues of the tropical clime, into which the foot, as it passed over, seemed to sink, was beautiful beyond description. A table of carved ivory occupied the centre of the apartment, and on it stood a salver, with a goblet and drinking cups of solid gold. The walls were a succession of paintings, relieved by a few marble statues in niches. There were a couple of ottomans, and two or three chairs, and a melodeon, a harp, and guitar, all the solid portions of which were composed of ivory, beautifully inlaid with costly gems. There were golden vases, filled with fresh-culled bouquets, which made the air heavy with perfume. There were mirrors in golden frames, so disposed as to multiply reflections of all the different objects, and make the apartment seem of vast dimensions. In short, it was a kind of fairy-palace; and, bursting so suddenly and brilliantly upon my long-blinded vision, I felt dazzled and bewildered, and for a moment fancied myself the sport of a dream.</p>
               <p>"If you will enter, Señor, and permit me to call la Doña Panola, you will not long be alone," said the page, arousing me from my revery.</p>
               <p>Feeling satisfied no treachery was intended, I at once released him, and entered the gorgeous apartment, when the door closed and fastened. I turned to look at it, and, to my surprise, discovered nothing but a large, beautiful painting—the scene an Italian landscape, with some pretty flower-girls in the foreground. I no longer felt any alarm, however; and, as no one was present, I amused myself in examining the paintings and statues,<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC5795-00000012"/> which were certainly fine specimens of art. I had just passed leisurely around the room, congratulating myself on my good fortune in becoming an object of attraction to a lady so refined, and beautiful, and wealthy, as the owner of all I saw must be, and was deeply wondering as to how this singular and romantic adventure would terminate, when, to my unbounded surprise, I found the fair unknown by my side. She had entered unheard and unperceived, and was standing by me, so silent and motionless, that my first impression was that she was a draped figure, which I had overlooked.</p>
               <p>"Welcome, Señor!" she said, with a smile; "you have kept your appointment, and are here. I thank you. Let us be seated."</p>
               <p>She led the way to a seat by the table, and I followed mechanically, feeling more bewildered than ever. Never had I beheld any being so exquisitely beautiful. Her sylph-like form might have served as a fairy-model for an artist; and her lovely features, when in repose, for the countenance of an angel. She was dressed in white, and, with the exception of diamond rings on her fingers, a single red rose on her bosom was her only ornament. Her skin was dark, but clear, and her features were brilliant with intellect and soul. Her raven ringlets fell in lavish profusion around her neck and shoulders, and her bright, black eyes were softened by long, drooping lashes. That she was high-minded, high-spirited, generous, and impulsive, could be seen in a single gleam of her eye; that she was eccentric, I had already had evidence in her manner of making my acquaintance; and that she was bold, daring, energetic, determined, and unconquerable, I soon discovered in her firm-set mouth, thin, compressed lips, and well-turned chin, as they were made to give forcible vitality to certain expressions, that flitted, like sunbeams and shadows, over her ever-changing countenance. Her age was evidently not far from eighteen years.</p>
               <p>"Señor Caballero," she resumed, as we seated ourselves on either side of the ivory table, with the massive gold salver, goblet and cups between us, "you think me a strange, wild being—do you not?"</p>
               <p>"I think your ladyship beautiful."</p>
               <p>"You flatter me, Señor, and address me as if I had rank."</p>
               <p>"Your page spoke of you as la Doña Panola."</p>
               <p>"Ah! that explains. Your name, Señor, if you please."</p>
               <p>"Alden Burmond, at your service."</p>
               <p>She lifted the golden goblet, and poured wine into the golden cups.</p>
               <p>"Señor Burmond," she said, taking up the cups, and handing one to me; "may there ever be peace between us!"</p>
               <p>"With all my heart!" I replied; and we both drank.</p>
               <p>"And now," she resumed, "we will to business. But first confess, Señor Burmond, that you think me the most singular being in the whole world!"</p>
               <p>"One of the most singular, certainly."</p>
               <pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC5795-00000013"/>
               <p>"I like your frankness, Señor Burmond, and I will as frankly own I am playing a part, which you shall soon comprehend, though not till I have mystified you a little more. You said you were unmarried?"</p>
               <p>"I did."</p>
               <p>"You have called me beautiful!"</p>
               <p>"I have."</p>
               <p>"You see I am wealthy?"</p>
               <p>"To all appearances."</p>
               <p>"And appearances are not false. I have rank."</p>
               <p>"I believe you."</p>
               <p>"I have intellect."</p>
               <p>"Of that I am certain."</p>
               <p>"Let me sum up, then. I have beauty, wealth, rank, and intellect."</p>
               <p>"I dare subscribe to all."</p>
               <p>"Well, then, to be brief, will you marry me?"</p>
               <p>"Marry you?" repeated I, in astonishment.</p>
               <p>"You are amazed; I anticipated as much; but, before you decide, you must hear my story."</p>
               <p>"With pleasure, your ladyship."</p>
               <p>And forthwith she began the following singular narrative.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE STORY, AND WHAT FOLLOWED.</head>
               <p>"MY name is Panola Francisca Mariana de Esperanza. I was born in Brazil, and am eighteen years of age. My father was the Emperor of Brazil, but my mother was not the Empress. She was of noble birth, however, and related to the present reigning family of Spain. At her death, which occurred three years ago, I inherited a fortune, and quitted the Convent of Santa Maria, where I was being educated; and, by the advice of the Emperor, my father, who foresaw trouble if I remained, I left the country in a secret manner, and sailed for Havana, where a cousin of my mother was then residing. The cause of the Emperor's desire that I should leave the country, was his fear of a revolution. My mother had three brothers, all of whom held important offices under the government; and, if report did not belie them, each was an adept in the courtier's art of intrigue. At the death of my mother, a paper was found, addressed to her, without date or signature, in which it was proposed, if she would give her sanction, to assassinate the Emperor, seize the reins of government, and, during the confusion which must ensue, proclaim her Queen Regent<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC5795-00000014"/> gent, and so, by an internal revolution, establish a new dynasty, with the succession of myself as Empress.</p>
               <p>"The author or authors of this treasonous paper were not positively known; nor was it known whether my mother favored the design or not; but it was inferred that she did, from the fact that the communication was not at once handed over to the Emperor, that he might be upon his guard. It was also inferred that my uncles were the grand conspirators; and two of them—Don Raphael, the Emperor's Private Secretary, and Don Fernando, the Captain of the Guard—were at once arrested and thrown into prison; but the other brother, Don Diego, Commanding General of the Interior Forces, managed to escape a couple of hours before the order for his apprehension reached his quarters, by getting on board a British frigate which was just weighing anchor.</p>
               <p>"Of Don Diego I wish now to speak more particularly. He landed at Havana before I did, and paid me a visit the same day I reached there—having learned, from the Spanish captain of the vessel which I sailed in from Rio Janeiro, that I had come out incognito. I had seen my uncle, Don Diego, several times, but had never exchanged a dozen words with him previous to this interview of his own seeking. In fact, he was a man I did not like. He was about forty years of age, tall, finely formed, with features that many would term handsome, though with an expression too stern, sinister, and intriguing, to suit my taste. Give me an open, manly countenance, even if homely in feature, in preference to any beauty that has no display of the nobler passions.</p>
               <p>"At the interview I allude to, my uncle made known to me his wishes and hopes; and said that but for the sudden death of my mother, he doubted not all would have been realized; though the only fact he could bring forward to show treason on her part toward the Emperor, was her retention of the treasonous paper, which he admitted was written at his instigation, but without the knowledge of his brothers, who, in so much at least, were guiltless of the crime of <foreign xml:lang="LAT">læsæ majestatis</foreign>. But it was possible my mother suspected the origin of the paper, and kept it concealed from the Emperor for the purpose of screening her brothers from his vengeance. At least I have endeavored to put this construction upon her secrecy in the matter; for I should be ten times more unhappy than I am, did I know she regarded with favor the fiendish plot of assassinating the father of her child.</p>
               <p>"Don Diego—let me drop the warmer title of uncle, for I abhor the man—Don Diego, I say, expressed himself delighted that I had left Brazil and stood on Spanish ground, where I would be safe till the way could be prepared for my ascent to the throne. He said he was at the head of a large party, who were ready to overthrow the reigning dynasty, and proclaim me Empress of Brazil the moment I should reach my majority; and, provided I would wed his son, Don Miguel, who was<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC5795-00000015"/> somewhat in the favor of the Spanish King, he doubted not the throne could be made secure to myself and heirs.</p>
               <p>"He was much surprised when I coolly informed him I was not in the least ambitious for the distinction he would confer on me; but, on the contrary, preferred to have my father reign, and his own son succeed him. He still thought he could mould me to his will; but found, after repeated trials, that my nature was not so plastic as he had imagined. He then proposed that I should marry his son, Don. Miguel; but this I vowed not to do; for, besides the fact that I did not at that time wish to marry any one, I too much disliked the father to think of the son with any other than feelings of repugnance. At this time I had not seen Don Miguel, and the ambitious father sent for him to come to Havana. We met; but the meeting did nothing to further Don Diego's wishes; on the contrary, I frankly told him that, sooner than wed his ignoble, crafty, treacherous son, whose character I had intuitively divined, I would enter a convent and don the black veil.</p>
               <p>"From that moment I date a series of persecutions, with which I will not trouble you. It seemed the design of Don Diego and his son to force me into a union which my soul abhorred; and, wearied out at last with their intrigues and importunities, I accepted the invitation of a friend, whose acquaintance I had formed in Havana, to come to this town, and here make my home. Arriving here, and liking the place, I purchased this dwelling, which formerly belonged to a nobleman; and, employing a dueña to superintend the establishment, I procured a few servants, and set up in a style to please my own fancy.</p>
               <p>"Being somewhat eccentric, and living in this manner, I was not the person to escape observation, and even censure; and probably I have been more talked about than any other resident of Jalapa during the same time. But this gave me no uneasiness; and but for the fact that my fame spread abroad, and my abode became known to Don Diego, I think I might have passed my days here pleasantly. But I am at present suffering renewed persecutions from both Don Diego and his crafty son, who came to this place about six months ago, and have not ceased to annoy me ever since—though careful to commit no overt act which might render them liable to prosecution. Much of the time they are away, and I think I have grounds for the suspicion that they are in some manner connected with a band of robbers who infest this part of the country. Yet I cannot say I think they are leagued with these outlaws merely for the sake of plunder, but rather for the purpose of collecting a force which may be transported to Brazil, as a nucleus around which to form an army of revolutionists, to carry out their own ambitious plans. Of late, Don Diego has made his boast that I shall soon be glad to marry his vile son;<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC5795-00000016"/> and, merely to foil him, I have resolved to marry another.</p>
               <p>"Thus, Señor Burmond, the matter stands at present. Both Don Diego and Don Miguel are now away, but I know not how soon they may return; and ere they return, it is my desire to place myself beyond their machinations, by becoming the wife of some honest man. As to yourself, I had seen you more than once ere I arrested your attention; and something led me to suppose I might get your assistance in this, to me, important affair; and, if you will consent to a private marriage, you shall be free to depart as soon as the ceremony shall have been performed, and I will place five thousand pistoles at your command. And let me add, that, in case you consent to this arrangement, it will be advisable for you to leave the country as soon as possible, for I do not think your life will be safe here twenty-four hours from the time the news reaches the ears of Don Diego and his son; but, with the exception that it will be beyond your legal right to wed another, you will be as free as now, and richer by five thousand pistoles. What say you, Señor?"</p>
               <p>"On my part, fair lady, you make this marriage a merely mercenary consideration," I replied.</p>
               <p>"True, Señor, and why should I not? On my part it will be a marriage of convenience or necessity, with some inconvenience to yourself, and without other benefits than the award."</p>
               <p>"But suppose, after marriage, I should prefer the wife to the pay?"</p>
               <p>"That would not please me, Señor, for I only want a husband in name. You see I am frank."</p>
               <p>"You would not like me for a life-partner, then?"</p>
               <p>"No, Señor Burmond; I would be as free after marriage as now; in fact, it is for freedom that I shall wed, if I wed at all."</p>
               <p>"But suppose I tell you I love you?"</p>
               <p>"Then you would say what, in all probability, would not be true; for how could you love one you now behold almost for the first time?"</p>
               <p>"But there is such a thing as love at first sight."</p>
               <p>"In romances, Señor."</p>
               <p>"In reality, your ladyship."</p>
               <p>"There may be, Señor Burmond; but not in this case, I think."</p>
               <p>"I am not so sure of that. There is something in your frank, off-hand manner, combined with your beauty, that fascinates me."</p>
               <p>For the first time, a warm glow suffused the features of my lovely Princess.</p>
               <p>"The conversation has taken a different turn than I expected," she said.</p>
               <p>"But I trust a not unpleasant one."</p>
               <p>"You embarrass me, Señor. Let us return to my first proposition. Will you, or will you not, marry me for the sum of five thousand pistoles?"</p>
               <p>"And for no other consideration, fair lady?"</p>
               <pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC5795-00000017"/>
               <p>"For no other, Señor Burmond."</p>
               <p>"I scarcely know what to reply," I answered. "True, I am single, and have no wife in view at present; but should I find my hands tied, there is no telling how soon I might be eager to be loosened of the bonds. While at liberty, we may not prize liberty; but take away our liberty, and imprisoned nature rebels and sighs for freedom. You are certain you would wish me to leave you at once, and never see you more?"</p>
               <p>"I am certain of nothing, Señor Burmond, but that I should wish to be left entirely free to do as I might see proper, and that it would not be safe for you to remain in Mexico."</p>
               <p>"But I have business at the Capital."</p>
               <p>"Imperative?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, your ladyship."</p>
               <p>"Could you not trust it to an agent?"</p>
               <p>"No! it requires my own presence there."</p>
               <p>"This is unfortunate."</p>
               <p>"Let it give your ladyship no uneasiness, for it will have no weight in my consideration of your proposition."</p>
               <p>"But it has weight with me, Señor. Suppose you consent to marry me, and, after the ceremony, set out for the Capital? Well, my marriage must be made public, for that is the whole object I have in view; being made public, Don Diego and his son would be among the first to hear of it; and should they learn my husband had gone to the Capital, what more natural than that they should follow for the purpose of taking his life?"</p>
               <p>"Granted, your ladyship," I replied; "but, having paid me for the risk and inconvenience of becoming your husband, with the desire of being rid of me at once, I cannot see why it need trouble you, even if I should be found and assassinated."</p>
               <p>"Ah! Señor Burmond; but you overlook that I should then be a widow."</p>
               <p>"But not a sorrowful widow, since you would care nothing for your husband."</p>
               <p>"You do not understand. Would I be any better off then than now?"</p>
               <p>"Ah! I see; you would then be in the market for Don Miguel!"</p>
               <p>"Exactly so; and the five thousand pistoles would be paid for nothing. Only during your life would I be fairly protected against the designs of these plotting conspirators."</p>
               <p>"Doña Panola, let me give you credit for a shrewd eye to business," I rejoined, rather coldly.</p>
               <p>"You seem hurt, Señor Burmond," she replied; "but you should not forget that, from the first, I have held up the whole affair simply as a business transaction, neither more nor less."</p>
               <p>"Very well, then, your highness, in a business manner I will consider your proposition. Let me see! Five thousand pistoles—eighteen thousand dollars—to take your ladyship for a wife, and not have you for a<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC5795-00000018"/> wife after all. It is a pretty sum, a very pretty sum, and I do not think I could make eighteen thousand dollars more easily; and, besides, there is something very novel in the affair, which rather pleases me. I have a mind to do it, my lady."</p>
               <p>"You will much oblige me, Señor Burmond," said the Princess, with a very winning smile.</p>
               <p>"If I could retain my wife, after getting her, I should certainly have no objection," I rejoined. "When would you wish the ceremony performed?"</p>
               <p>"Within the hour, Señor."</p>
               <p>"Indeed! That would be very sudden. How could you arrange it?"</p>
               <p>"All is arranged; the priest is in waiting."</p>
               <p>"You surprise me. I thought, among Catholics, it was necessary to publish the bans."</p>
               <p>"I have procured a dispensation from the Bishop. I did it to-day, after seeing you."</p>
               <p>"Then you thought I would accept your proposition?"</p>
               <p>"I thought it best to be prepared."</p>
               <p>"But I must visit the Capital; could you not await my return?"</p>
               <p>"It might then be too late, Señor. As I have told you, Don Diego and Don Miguel are both away, and now or never is my resolve."</p>
               <p>"And suppose I refuse?"</p>
               <p>"Then I must look for another."</p>
               <p>"But, I repeat, I must visit the Capital. Are you willing, fair Princess, to run your risk, if I run mine? I, you say, stand in danger of losing my life, which I do not greatly fear; you, of losing a husband in name, and five thousand pistoles."</p>
               <p>"As the case stands," she replied, "if I cannot change your purpose, I shall not let your resolution thwart my design."</p>
               <p>I thought rapidly and seriously for a few minutes, weighed my chances of ever wanting to marry another, against eighteen thousand dollars, and then rejoined:</p>
               <p>"I accept your proposition."</p>
               <p>"Thanks, Señor Burmond!" she said, gayly: "let us drink to our speedy union;" and she again filled the golden cups with wine.</p>
               <p>"And to our speedy and eternal separation, I suppose I should add!" I said, as I tossed off mine.</p>
               <p>She smiled, but made no response. Then she arose, offered me a ring, and said,</p>
               <p>"Are you ready?"</p>
               <p>"I am ready, fair Princess."</p>
               <p>She clapped her hands three times, and a concealed door flew open, disclosing a small apartment, lined with white silk, and having a small altar of rosewood in the centre, before which stood a priest, vested in white surplice and stole, with his attendants and four other persons grouped around, one of whom was the page already mentioned. We advanced to the altar, and the ceremony was performed according to the ritual of the<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC5795-00000019"/> Roman Catholic Church—a grave-looking gentleman, with white hair, giving away the bride.</p>
               <p>The ceremony over, I bade my new wife a brief adieu, and was conducted by the grave-looking gentleman and page to my hotel, where, on parting, I received five thousand pistoles in gold.</p>
               <p>When I reached my room again, the bell of the Cathedral was striking the hour of three.</p>
               <p>"Well," said I, as I threw myself on the bed, "this has been an eventful night, and one long to be remembered."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
               <head type="sub">SEVERAL MATTERS.</head>
               <p>IF a man can sleep soundly on the night before execution, certainly it is fair to presume a man may sleep soundly on the night of his marriage. The fact is, I did, and a fact is worth all the philosophy in the world. When I awoke, the sun was at least three hours above the horizon, and was shining as bright and clear as if nothing material had happened. At first I was disposed to consider the adventure of the past night a very curious dream; but no dream could bring such solid realities as lay before me, in the shape of five thousand pistoles. I rubbed my eyes, arose and felt of the gold, to be sure it was not a deceptive appearance. There it was—the real, substantial article—as certain as that I was a living human being; and I, who only the day before would have laughed at the idea of taking to myself a wife, was a married man!</p>
               <p>"Well," said I to myself, "this throws into the shade all the romances I have ever read."</p>
               <p>Here a mozo came to say that my breakfast had got cold three times, and his master feared I was ill.</p>
               <pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC5795-00000020"/>
               <p>"Tell your master I will give him evidence to the contrary, as soon as I get dressed," was my reply.</p>
               <p>Could I eat? Yes, I felt quite sharp-set. Marriage had not taken away my appetite; and this I thought a very favorable sign. I speedily dressed myself, and devoured my breakfast with rare gusto.</p>
               <p>"Secure me a seat in the next diligencia for the city of Mexico!" I said to mine host.</p>
               <p>"Si, Señor," he replied, with a bow. "One seat, or two?"</p>
               <p>"One. Why do you ask?"</p>
               <p>He smiled, and gave me a peculiar look.</p>
               <p>"Explain?" I said.</p>
               <p>"Does the lady remain?"</p>
               <p>"What lady?" I inquired, in surprise.</p>
               <p>"It is said, Señor, you were married last night."</p>
               <p>"Who says it?"</p>
               <p>"It is known all over town, Señor."</p>
               <p>"Who started the idle report?"</p>
               <p>"You can see it posted at the Cathedral, Señor."</p>
               <p>I hastened down to the Plaza Grande, and saw a group of persons collected around the portal of the Cathedral. As I drew near them, one whispered to another, and all turned and looked at me, and some smiled. There was a paper posted, and I read it. It was something like a certificate of my marriage with the Princess Panola, signed by the officiating priest.</p>
               <p>"My wife is in a hurry to make her marriage known," I thought, as I hastened back to the fonda, to escape inquisitive glances.</p>
               <p>"When does the next diligencia pass?" I inquired of mine host.</p>
               <p>"It will be along about daybreak, Señor."</p>
               <p>"Send my meals, and a bottle of wine, to my room. I shall remain there through the day."</p>
               <p>"Si, Señor."</p>
               <p>I repaired to my sleeping chamber, and did not quit it again that day. In the afternoon, the youthful page appeared, and brought the compliments of la Doña Panola, with an inquiry after my health.</p>
               <p>"Tell her I am as well as could be expected under the circumstances," I replied, and bowed him out.</p>
               <p>In the evening he came again, and brought me a sealed and perfumed note. It read as follows:</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <p>"Pardon me, dear husband, for making our marriage public so soon. It was thought necessary. If you are still resolved to go to the city, take the best care of yourself. Shall I confess it? I feel I have more at stake in your life than five thousand pistoles, and Don Diego and Don Miguel's persecutions.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>PANOLA."</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>"Aha!" thought I; "so you did not escape scathless, my beautiful Princess! Well, this beats romance and reason. Marry first and make love afterward."</p>
               <p>I returned by the page this written reply:</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <p>"My dear wife may rest assured that, having as much at stake in the life of the subscriber as any one<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC5795-00000021"/> can have, I will take as good care of it as lies in my power.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>ALDEN."</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>The next morning, just as the diligencia drove up to the door, the page again appeared, and handed me the following note:</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <p>"I am sorry you are leaving for the city of Mexico, dear husband; but if you return alive, it will afford me pleasure to see you.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>PANOLA."</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>I hastily penned this reply:</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <p>"Adios, my dear wife. If I do not return alive, I shall regret the pleasure of which my death will deprive me.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>ALDEN."</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>"There," said I, mentally, "I believe I have been as sententious and pointed as your ladyship; and now for the journey."</p>
               <p>As it was not safe to carry any large amount of money in the diligencia, on account of the robbers who infested the road between Jalapa and the Capital, I secured only a small sum about my person, and arranged with a company of muleteers to transport the remainder with the heavy luggage, taking only my portmanteau and some necessary articles of wearing apparel.</p>
               <p>As I left the town of Jalapa, my last reflections were, that I had entered it a bachelor, and was leaving it a married man, my wife no less than a Princess, and myself richer by at least eighteen thousand dollars. Who would not marry for eighteen thousand dollars?—especially a Princess?</p>
               <p>There were in the diligencia three passengers besides myself—an Englishman, a Mexican, and a female of mixed blood. The Englishman and myself at once entered into conversation, and maintained it between ourselves—the other two, who did not understand our native language, rarely venturing a remark. The day was clear and genial, the air wholesome, the road ascending, and the scenery picturesque—the whole united putting us in very good humor. We conversed on various subjects before touching upon that which, in this part of the country, seldom fails to become the theme of travellers—namely, robbers.</p>
               <p>"Are you armed?" at length inquired my travelling companion, whose name was Boswell.</p>
               <p>"I have a brace of pistols about my person," I replied.</p>
               <p>"Will you fight, if attacked?"</p>
               <p>"I generally do, sir."</p>
               <p>"I am rejoiced to find I have a companion who is not a coward," rejoined Boswell, "for one sees so few brave men in this country, that the sight refreshes one like a spring in a desert. If these vehicles always carried armed, determined men, the lazy, white-livered scoundrels, who live by robbing them, would soon be obliged to turn their attention to some more honest pursuit. As you are a stranger in this part of the country, friend Burmond, let me tell you an astonishing<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC5795-00000022"/> ing fact. The travellers over this route calculate on their fees to robbers as a part of their expenses, and prepare purses to be given away accordingly, instead of a proper distribution of powder and lead."</p>
               <p>"I have heard something of this."</p>
               <p>"And I know something of it, sir. I have travelled this road more than a dozen times, and have seen more cowardice displayed on the route than I ever saw elsewhere in the whole course of my life. What would you think, sir, of a whole diligencia of male passengers being quietly robbed by a single man?"</p>
               <p>"I should think they deserved to be tied up and whipped, and then dragged through a horse-pond!"</p>
               <p>"Well, such has been the case more times than we number years. When I first came to this country, I submitted to the custom of paying double fare—first, the fare of travel; secondly, the robbers' fare—till I got so vexed at this cowardly game, that I resolved, so far as I was concerned, to put an end to it. On my last downward trip, therefore, with only one passenger besides myself, and he a cowardly Mexican, on being stopped and politely requested, by the leader of a gang of four, to hand over my purse, I deliberately put a ball through the villain's head, which so alarmed the others that they took to their heels, and the diligencia proceeded without further molestation. But the scoundrels took their revenge, I understand, on the next Englishman who came this way, by shooting him without provocation. And what is more, should I be recognised through their spies—for they generally have spies at the different stoppages, to ascertain, previous to their attack, the number and character of the passengers—I say, should I be recognised by one of these spies, we shall either not be molested at all, or have rather a troublesome time of it; and this is why I am so glad to find myself supported by a brave companion."</p>
               <p>"How is it," I asked, "since this mode of robbery has become so systematized that travellers prepare themselves to be victimized; how is it that the government, knowing this, takes no means to render the main roads safe?"</p>
               <p>"Why, we seldom have one government for a longer time than it takes to get up a revolution; and, as each faction desires to be in the ascendant, neither likes to offend the gentlemen of the road, for fear of converting them into formidable enemies. One or two of our chief magistrates did try it, but found it very bad policy for themselves—for one was assassinated, and the other is now without power or influence, a forlorn prisoner in the Castle of Perote."</p>
               <p>"And probably my eccentric wife's uncle and cousin are linked with these dastardly cut-throats," was my next very natural reflection, which I did not think proper to utter aloud.</p>
               <p>The day passed off without any disturbance, and in the evening we rode into the village of Perote, and took lodgings at the principal posada. I considered this town dismal enough, for all the houses presented a blank<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC5795-00000023"/> wall of stone to the street, without window or door, the only entrance being through a kind of side gate, which opened into the patio, or court, upon which all the surrounding buildings fronted; the inhabitants thus tacitly acknowledging the insecurity of life and property by making each of their dwellings a sort of castle.</p>
               <p>Mr. Boswell and myself occupied the lower apartment; and before retiring for the night, we made a careful examination of our weapons. I had a brace of pistols, and he a brace of pistols and a hunting-knife. He was a large, strong, muscular man, about thirty-five years of age, just in the prime of manly strength; and as I was not a person at that time to be despised in an encounter, we congratulated ourselves on the probability of becoming unpleasant customers to any assailants.</p>
               <p>"We are now fairly in the robbers' country, friend Burmond," he said, as he undressed and threw himself upon the bed, "and to-morrow will probably tell the tale."</p>
               <p>By the time I had finished my reply, a loud snore attested how little reflection he had given to his words.</p>
               <p>Alas! the to-morrow told a sad tale of him, and—But let me not anticipate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE ATTACK.</head>
               <p>WE resumed our journey at an early hour in the morning, and daylight found us on the dangerous road. The first objects that arrested my attention were numerous little crosses that dotted the way on either side.</p>
               <p>"What mean these?" I inquired of my still dreamy companion.</p>
               <p>"Why, sir, as I told you last night, we have got within the territory of the robbers, and many of these crosses mark the places where travellers have from time to time been murdered."</p>
               <p>"Very pleasant and amusing," I said.</p>
               <p>"Yes," he replied, with a kind of shrug; "and unless we give cause for some of these to be erected for the death of a few ladrones, the point of the joke is, that our last stopping-place may be somewhere in this vicinity."</p>
               <p>We continued our journey for a couple of hours, without meeting with an incident more important than now and then a mounted Mexican dashing past us, of whom our driver generally inquired concerning the road, and, in every case but one, received for answer<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC5795-00000024"/> that it was fortunately free from robbers—the person who differed from the others, expressing his belief that a certain hollow, not far off, where the trees grew close and interlocked their branches, would be a troublesome place to pass without paying our fare anew.</p>
               <p>"Well," remarked Boswell, who overheard the conversation, "if the scoundrels get any thing out of me, it is my opinion that they will remember the event longer than I shall, for I am determined not to be robbed alive."</p>
               <p>We now kept a sharp look-out; and when we began to ascend the hill, which descended into the hollow alluded to, we quietly drew our pistols, to the great alarm of the other passengers, who begged us to make no resistance, but preserve our lives and theirs, by suffering ourselves to be robbed in a decent and gentlemanly manner—it being a well-known fact, that the ladrones seldom maltreat the travellers they rob, unless assailed by the latter. It is needless to say that the prayers of our companions were unheeded, for we had determined to act like men rather than cowards, and either carry our purses safely through, or sell our lives dearly. At length we reached the brow of the hill which rose above the dreaded hollow; and ordering the driver, on pain of death for disobedience, to dash forward and run his animals through the gloomy retreat, we settled ourselves into the best position for acting on the defensive, and anxiously awaited the result. Down the steep hill we went, at a speed which, at any other time, would have made us fearful for our safety, and soon found ourselves almost in darkness, so dense was the green foliage of the giant trees which lined the way, interlocked their branches, and excluded the genial rays of the sun. After reaching the hollow, our course lay down its bed for the distance of a quarter of a mile, and then the road turned sharp round a rocky projection, and began to rise somewhat abruptly. It was at this point we most feared an attack; for here the diligencia must either move slow, or run a fearful risk of upsetting and plunging down a precipice to the right; and here it was, just as the vehicle had turned the dangerous point, the order came for the driver to stop his animals.</p>
               <p>"Drive on, at all risks!" we shouted; and fearing us about as much as the ladrones, who began to gather in the road, the driver put whip to the beasts, and the diligencia went a few paces with a sudden jerk.</p>
               <p>The next moment there came the report of a pistol, the driver fell from his seat, and the animals, seized by the bit by strong men, were borne back almost upon their haunches, while our terrified travelling companions fell upon their knees and shrieked for mercy. One moment more, and the doors of the vehicle were torn open, several heads appeared, and a stentorian voice commanded us to throw ourselves upon our faces, and allow our purses to be taken.</p>
               <p>Boswell and myself replied simultaneously, not in words, but with our pistols, he firing to the left and I to the right. Each of us brought down our man; and<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC5795-00000025"/> with a yell of dismay, the robbers all suddenly disappeared.</p>
               <p>"There," said Boswell, coolly, his voice fairly drowned by the continued shriekings of our cowardly companions; "the scoundrels have made another exploit which they will not be likely to boast of, I'm thinking;" and then, pointing his discharged pistol at the party inside, he shouted in Spanish: "Stop your infernal howlings, or we'll serve you as we served your outside kindred."</p>
               <p>This threat terrified the party to silence, and I inquired:</p>
               <p>"What is to be done now? I fear our driver is killed."</p>
               <p>"In that case," he replied, "I will take his place, and drive to the next stage myself."</p>
               <p>"But we shall be shot down if we venture out of our fortress."</p>
               <p>"No fear of that," he rejoined, with a scornful laugh. "We will reload our pistols, and by that time there will not be one of the white-livered knaves within a mile of us."</p>
               <p>"I am not so sure of that. I am of the opinion they are now secreted in the adjoining wood, waiting to take us at more advantage than by a direct assault."</p>
               <p>"I will prove the contrary to you, my friend," said Boswell; and he proceeded to load his discharged pistol with great deliberation and care.</p>
               <p>This done, he opened the door to the left, and fearlessly lessly descended the steps, for the purpose of taking the place of the driver. He had just reached the ground, and I was in the act of following him, when a volley was fired from the thicket. Several balls pierced his manly breast; and staggering back, with a groan, he sunk down dead at my very feet. Seeing at a glance that he was beyond hope, I instantly sprung back into the diligencia, closed the door, and prepared myself for the attack, which I of course expected would be immediately renewed. After waiting for a few minutes in anxious suspense, and hearing no noise without, I cautiously looked through one of the windows, and discovered that the cowardly robbers were not disposed to again peril their precious lives by a bold assault. On the contrary, they seemed to prefer waiting till necessity should compel those within to venture forth, when they could be destroyed without danger to themselves.</p>
               <p>What was to be done? Oh! what would I not have given for three or four brave comrades to stand by me! How soon would we have changed the aspect of affairs! With that number, knowing, as I now did, the cowardly nature of these Mexican highwaymen, I would have ventured to assail a dozen, without fear of the result. But I was alone. Alone, and yet surrounded by cringing poltroons. Two Mexicans had entered the diligencia at Perote; and there were now, besides myself, three men, and the woman of mixed blood before mentioned. Did I say men? I should rather have said three animals bearing the human form; for there<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC5795-00000026"/> was not one manly quality in the breasts of either of these trembling bipeds, who, rolled up like balls in the bottom of the vehicle, were moaning, groaning, wringing their hands, and chattering half-intelligible prayers to the Holy Virgin, and all the other Saints in the calendar. Perilous as was my situation, with the almost certainty of being murdered sooner or later, such was my indignant contempt, excited by their cowardice, that I actually debated with myself whether I had not better make an effort to procure the driver's whip and spend the remainder of my earthly stay in giving them a well-deserved lashing. Had it been one of these contemptible creatures, instead of the brave Englishman, who had received the murderous fire of the ladrones, the would, I fancied, would have gained, rather than lost, by the departure of a craven spirit.</p>
               <p>But what was to be done? Under the circumstances, I knew it would be time thrown away to attempt to kindle a spark of courage in the breasts of my fellow-travellers; and after a few minutes of serious reflection, I determined, if possible, to save my own life, and leave them to their fate. I cautiously looked through the windows on all sides, and took every thing into consideration, before deciding on my plan. Boswell I knew was dead; the driver I believed to be so; and therefore there was not one human being I could rely on for the least assistance. Besides, the traces had been cut, and the animals were not to be seen, so that I had no hope of catching and mounting one of them, and making my escape in that manner. The diligencia was a fixture in the road, and the only hope of remaining in my comparatively safe position inside, was, that the mulada, which travelled over this route, might come along and frighten away the cut-throats.</p>
               <p>But there was no certainty that this would occur on that day, and the suspense was heart-sickening. I felt in a mood for action of some kind, and I was determined to have it, even if death itself should be the penalty. True, it was more than likely that the day would not pass without the appearance of some mounted traveller; but then, in all probability, he would be shot down without warning, or, seeing the state of affairs, take the alarm and fly; in either of which cases he would be of no assistance to me. And then, again, how long might it be before the robbers, suspecting the weak state of the garrison, might venture upon another assault?</p>
               <p>No! inaction, with such companions, was not to be borne. I could face death as well as another; but then it must be death in a struggle for life. I could not bear to think of sitting quietly down and being shot like a dog in cold blood.</p>
               <p>Through the window to the left, I could just see the covert, in which my enemies were concealed, with a covered mountain rising high and steep behind them. To the right was a precipice, which terminated in a thick bush-covered ravine. If I could reach that unharmed, perhaps I might effect my escape. It was a<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC5795-00000027"/> fearful alternative; for, from my position, I could not see whether this precipice could be descended in safety or not, and it might be that a plunge down its mural surface would end my existence. Better that, was my final conclusion, than being cooped up where I was, a prey to mental tortures; and uttering a short prayer, I resolved upon the trial.</p>
               <p>With the greatest caution I opened the door to the right, which had been closed after the attack, and looked up and down the road. All was clear; no robbers to be seen. With one pistol in my hand, and the other so disposed that I could seize and discharge it in an instant, I drew in my breath, and leaped from the carriage. The next moment I reached the edge of the precipice, and saw, to my horror, that, instead of sloping down, it fairly overhung the ravine. I looked up and down the road, and could see no way of descending except by a bold leap, which in all probability would be certain death, as the distance to the top of the dwarfish trees and bushes, which spread their foliage over the opposite bank near the rocky bed, could not be less than sixty feet.</p>
               <p>While I stood in momentary contemplation, several shots were fired at me from the thicket before mentioned, and one ball passed through my hat. That a "miss is as good as a mile," may be true in some things; but when it comes to a rifle-bullet, I, for one, have a decided preference for the greater distance; and would much rather, for the sake of my nerves, be missed by a mile than an inch. As the ladrones fired from the covert, four men, armed with long knives and carbines, leaped into the road, two on either side of me, at a distance beyond pistol-shot, and levelled their pieces for a deliberate aim. That all four would miss me, was not reasonable to suppose; and I knew, if wounded or crippled by their fire, I should certainly be put to death, sooner or later. There was a bare possibility that I might go down the precipice and survive; and hurriedly fixing my eye upon a point where the thickly clustering bushes seemed best calculated to break my descent without breaking my bones, I made a vigorous leap outward, and heard the balls, which were fired at me the same instant, whistle harmlessly over my head.</p>
               <p>Down I went with lightning velocity, and soon found myself buried in the very cluster of bushes at which I had aimed, considerably jarred, and quite out of breath, but without a bone broken or any serious injury. If ever I felt truly grateful for the preservation of my life, I did so at that moment; and as I lay on the ground, and looked up through the green, sheltering foliage, at the bright sun and serene sky, I felt my soul expand in adoration of that Great Being whose protecting arm had so signally preserved me in a moment of such terrible peril.</p>
               <p>As it was no part of my design to have the robbers suppose I had escaped with life, I lay perfectly still, and listened to every sound, with my eyes riveted on the<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC5795-00000028"/> brow of the precipice from which I had taken my fearful leap. I soon saw the parties who had last fired at me, peering down the ravine and heard with satisfaction one call to the other, and say that I should never give the gentlemen of the road any more trouble. Then they withdrew; and presently I heard more firing, followed by the cries of my cowardly companions, begging for mercy. For some time loud voices and harsh tones resounded; and then the mangled corpse of Boswell, stripped of his clothing, was hurriedly tumbled over the precipice, falling within a few feet of me. It was a horrible sight; and, oh! how my very blood leaped in my veins to avenge his death!</p>
               <p>Fearing that the bandits might find a way to descend into the ravine for the purpose of robbing me, whom they supposed to be dead, I thought it best to start off on a new adventure. And a very remarkable adventure I had, as the sequel will show.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE HACIENDA.</head>
               <p>I DID not think it safe, all things considered, to regain the road immediately; and so I went down the bed of the ravine for some quarter of a mile, and then turned up a sloping bank into a thick wood, which I supposed ran parallel with the highway. Under this impression, and also that I was shaping my course toward Puebla, I walked on for a couple of hours, without once thinking it necessary to ascertain whether my conjectures were right or not. But at length it occurred to me, that, if I were really going wrong, it might lead to serious consequences, and I immediately sought for the road. But where I expected to find it, it was not; and in making an eager, hurried search for it, I got bewildered and turned, and knew not which way to go.</p>
               <p>When a man has completely lost his way, and has become so turned as to see the sun rise in the south or west, and set in the north or east, I think the best thing for him to do, especially if far from human habitations, in a deep forest, is to close his eyes and wander around until he knows less of the locality than he did before; and then either climb a tree and sleep in the<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC5795-00000029"/> branches, or go to sleep on the ground beneath—the chances being that he will wake up and find himself all right; though, if not, I would advise him to believe that the sun really does rise in the east and set in the west, notwithstanding appearances; and that it is much more reasonable to suppose that his poor little brain has got an ugly twist, than that a mighty revolution has taken place in the universe.</p>
               <p>But though one may sometimes give good advice, as a doctor gives good physic, it does not always follow that one likes to take his own dose; and that mankind are in the habit of preaching what they do not practice, is every day exemplified. The fact is, I had got bewildered, and I saw the sun was wrong; but I knew the road I was searching for must be in a certain direction, and not far off; and I made eager haste to regain it ere the day should be too far advanced to enable me to reach Puebla before nightfall.</p>
               <p>For hours I hurried through the forest, without finding a road, a habitation, or seeing a human being; and at last, completely discouraged, I sat down upon a high rock, on elevated ground, and gloomily ran my eye over a wild, cheerless landscape. As I did so, I saw, afar in the distance, a thin wreath of smoke rising above a cluster of trees that seemed to have a small clearing around them; and weary and faint though I was—for I had not yet broken my fast, and the sun was now on the decline—I immediately started up, with feelings of elation, and set off toward the point which promised to bring me in contact with some of my species. Across a broad valley, two streams, and over many undulations, rising into hills and deepening into hollows—some open, almost barren, and uncultivated, and some covered with low, branching trees and dense chaparral—across, over, and through all these, I took my way; and at last, just as the sun was sinking in the northeast—for the sun, be it recollected, had been going the wrong way all day—I reached a miserable hut, made of reeds and flags, and found it tenanted by a Mexican Indian, his wife, and two half-grown, naked children, all of whom eyed me with suspicion and seemed alarmed at my presence.</p>
               <p>I could speak Spanish quite fluently; but their dialect appeared to be composed of some half a dozen languages; so that it was with great difficulty I could make myself understood; while I, in turn, could only understand them by signs.</p>
               <p>I made them comprehend that I was hungry and tired; and they gave me some tortillas and fruit, and pointed over the hill, uttering the words "casa," "grande," from which I inferred that they did not care to lodge me, but that I could get lodgings at a fine house at no great distance. I took out three Mexican dollars, and putting them in the hands of the master of the dwelling, made him understand that I wished him to be my guide to the hacienda; to which, after a consultation with his wife, he assented, and we set out forthwith.</p>
               <p>The sun had by this time set, and the stars were out<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC5795-00000030"/> in all their glory. It was a lovely night—not a cloud to be seen in the heavens; and after the heats of the day, the fragrant breeze felt cool and delicious as it fanned my feverish brow and temples. My guide led the way at a fast walk, and an hour's progress brought us within sight of the hacienda; when, pointing to it, and muttering something I did not understand, but probably a blessing, he kissed my hand and took his leave.</p>
               <p>I hurried to the gate of the hacienda and rapped loudly; and presently a mozo, or man-servant, appeared and said:</p>
               <p>"Who are you? and what do you want?"</p>
               <p>"I am a stranger in the country," I replied, "a weary, benighted traveller, and want lodgings for the night."</p>
               <p>"This is not a fonda."</p>
               <p>"But surely you will not refuse me a lodging for the night?"</p>
               <p>"I will ask my master, Don Juan."</p>
               <p>"Pray tell him I would speak with him."</p>
               <p>The mozo disappeared, closing the wicket-gate as he went, and left me standing without. In a few minutes the proprietor of the establishment opened the wicket, and thrusting a lighted torch outside, surveyed me by its light, while he kept all but his head and shoulders concealed from my view. He appeared to be between fifty and sixty years of age, and had a stern, commanding look. His skin was of a sickly yellow, and much wrinkled; and the deep seams in his face—lines of thought, care, trouble, and anxiety—together with his bald head, gray side-locks and eyebrows—all denoted one who had experienced much tempestuous weather on the voyage of life. He spoke in a positive tone, and with the air and command of one who had always been the lord and master of those about him.</p>
               <p>"Well, young man," was his first greeting, spoken quite harshly, "you requested to see Don Juan, and you see him What next?"</p>
               <p>"I am foot-sore and weary, and should be happy to lodge under your roof."</p>
               <p>"Who are you? and where are you going?"</p>
               <p>"I am a stranger in the country, travelling to the City of Mexico, where I have some business of importance."</p>
               <p>"Where did you land?"</p>
               <p>"At Vera Cruz."</p>
               <p>"Indeed! Why have you wandered from the National Road? Could you find no means of conveyance, and no place of entertainment, that you must come here begging lodgings?"</p>
               <p>"Sir!" I replied, indignantly, "I am no beggar. I expect to pay for all I get, except insolence; and I shall not accept too much of that without returning an equivalent!"</p>
               <p>"So, so! Got some fire, the lad has!" he muttered, in what I fancied was a tone of approval. And then to me: "But you have not told me why you left the National Road, and came so far out of your way! If your<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC5795-00000031"/> story is true, you certainly owe it to yourself to give me this explanation."</p>
               <p>"And am I far from the National Road?" I inquired.</p>
               <p>"Fifteen miles, at least."</p>
               <p>"Then have I lost my way indeed!" I rejoined; and I hastened to explain how it had happened.</p>
               <p>He listened attentively to my narration of the incidents of the day, keeping his dark, piercing eye, which still seemed to blaze with all the fires of youth, fixed full upon me, as if to read my very soul. When I had finished my story, he threw open the little gate, and said:</p>
               <p>"Come in."</p>
               <p>The hacienda of Don Juan Albertoz was one of the better class. It consisted of several buildings fronting upon an inner court or patio, the whole surrounded by a high, strong wall, built of adobes, or sundried bricks. A massive gate, containing a wicket, was the only opening through this wall; and the four corners were fortified by bastions, and little round towers, like pepper-boxes, with loopholes for musketry. The main dwelling, two stories in height, with a flat roof, occupied the entire front—the passage from the patio to the gate being through an arch in the centre. The other buildings were stables, granaries, and dwellings for the dependents of the household—one-half of the patio being used for yarding cattle, mules, and horses at night, which the defenceless state of the country rendered unsafe to leave outside of the walls.</p>
               <p>I was conducted by a side door in the arch into the general sitting-room of Don Juan's dwelling; where I found his family—consisting of a wife, two daughters, a daughter-in-law, and a very pretty grand-daughter, some fourteen years of age—seated around a table, partaking of a supper of game, fruit, vegetables, tortillas, and frijoles—the son, the husband of the daughter-in-law, and father of the grand-daughter, being away. The family was waited upon by three or four menials, and I was kindly invited to partake of the evening meal: I sat down near the head of the table, Don Juan doing the honors; and, notwithstanding I had eaten recently at the house of my guide, I was still in a condition to do justice to what was before me.</p>
               <p>After supper, at the request of Don Juan, I again narrated the incidents of the day. I noticed that the family looked very grave at my recital, and often exchanged glances; but being completely wearied out, and anxious for rest, I thought less of this then than I probably should have done at another time; and as soon as politeness would permit, I requested leave to retire for the night. Don Juan called a negro, and spoke a few words to him in an under-tone; and the latter, procuring a light, conducted me to a very comfortable apartment in the upper story. The room contained a bed, which, to one as fatigued as myself, looked very inviting; and my whole thoughts being centred in the<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC5795-00000032"/> enjoyment of sleep, I hastily threw off my clothes, put my pistols under my head, blew out the light, and, rolling myself in a blanket, was soon in a state of sweet forgetfulness.</p>
               <p>But I did not sleep comfortably all night, as the reader will soon perceive.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
               <head type="sub">ALMOST A MURDER.</head>
               <p>HOW long I slept soundly I do not know; but at length I awoke, feeling a great depression of spirits, accompanied with a dread of something terrible, not unlike a presentiment. At first I was inclined to believe it a touch of dyspepsia; and I sat up in bed, and chafed my stomach with my hands, hoping soon to find relief; but the symptoms growing worse instead of better, I got up and paced the floor, shuddering at every step, and fancying myself surrounded by demons.</p>
               <p>The apartment contained one window, which overlooked the patio; and approaching this, I stood for some time and gazed forth upon the night, for the stars were the only objects clearly perceptible. At length I fancied I heard muffled steps along the corridor which ran past my room, and for the first time a suspicion of something wrong about the dwelling flashed upon my brain. I recalled to mind the peculiar glances I had seen exchanged between the different members of the family during the recital of my adventures with the robbers, and the thought occurred to me that possibly I had taken refuge in a dwelling belonging to some of the<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC5795-00000033"/> accursed band; and with the thought I sprung to the bed and felt for my pistols, in order to be prepared for any emergency. Heavens! they were gone! Some one had entered my room during my sleep and abstracted them; and my blood fairly curdled at the reflection that I was now completely defenceless, and at the mercy of any cold-blooded assassin who might see proper to take my life.</p>
               <p>Never had I experienced such intense mental agony as at that moment. I had been through many perilous scenes, and had stared death in the face many times, yet always with my nerves braced for the worst; but now, having just awakened from a peaceful and tranquil sleep, half bewildered and prostrated with a shivering horror, I was completely unmanned, and trembled in every joint, and felt a cold, clammy perspiration pressing through all my pores. And to add to my enervating weight of terror—a terror rather caused by a sudden relaxation of the physical system, than by any proper fear I had of death—the muffled steps approached my door and paused, and all became silent, as if the person were listening for any sounds within.</p>
               <p>What was to be done? Should I fly to the window, and stand prepared to throw myself out and call for help? But then, if my death were meditated, what would that avail me? I should only be flying from the hands of one assassin to those of another! But then again, if all were resolved upon my death, which I could not believe, why this stealth in approaching an unarmed man? a man, too, supposed to be asleep? or rather, why had not the deed been done at the moment of securing my weapons, when I was wholly in the power of the midnight robber? No! it must be the bloody design of some one or few, acting without the knowledge or against the wishes of the many; and as I hurriedly came to this conclusion, I took a single step toward the window, determined to make a leap through it and call for help—a resource against instant death, even should it end in death at last.</p>
               <p>But how trivial a thing may change the current of our thoughts, our plans, and our fortunes! As I took that one step toward the window, the cautious opening of the door,—which I might have bolted, had the idea occurred to me a minute sooner,—the cautious opening of the door—I say, sent the blood through all my veins, with a thrill of indignation; and from a creeping, trembling coward, I suddenly felt myself become a man again; a man who, though unarmed, might prove no easy victim of a dastardly assassin! Yes! in that one moment I felt myself change, as it were, from a trembling hare to a mighty lion, and I could have beat myself for being so recently so base a poltroon! What! let a single assassin crawl upon me, with a fair warning of his approach, and tremble and seek to fly, like a puny child scared with a nursery tale, instead of manfully grappling with so cowardly a foe and giving him his deserts! For shame! for shame!</p>
               <p>But ere I should do the nocturnal intruder an irreparable<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC5795-00000034"/> parable injury, common justice required that I should first be certain he meant me harm; and to ascertain this, I dropped upon my hands and knees, and noiselessly crawled under the bed. The apartment was dark; and as my unwelcome visitor brought no light with him, and had not got fairly into the room before I disappeared, the action was not perceived. Slowly and cautiously the door opened, and as slowly and cautiously closed; and then I became certain of some one groping his way to the bed, with a cat-like step. I fairly held my breath, and listened to the faintest sound. He stopped at length, so near to me that I could reach his feet without changing my position; and then I could hear his hands moving carefully over the bed, as if feeling for my person. Apparently he found what he was searching for; for the next moment a blow descended, and a hissing sound came from his lips, barely articulating the words:</p>
               <p>"There! take that, you——villain!"</p>
               <p>This convinced me that he had wilfully struck at my life—though deceived by the blanket, which I had fortunately left rolled together, into the belief that I was under it. Longer forbearance, therefore, could not be a virtue, and instantly I seized him by the heels and jerked him down. As he fell, he shrieked loudly for help; and continued to shriek, till I had succeeded in throwing myself upon him, and grasping him by the throat, when I soon choked him into silence; and, under the excitement of the moment, I might have choked him to death, had not other actors suddenly appeared upon the scene.</p>
               <p>His cries alarmed the inmates of the dwelling; and amid the noise of several voices shouting to each other, the door was burst open, and Don Juan, in his night-gear, with a light in one hand and a stiletto in the other, followed by two or three trembling menials, entered the room. The old man's face was almost black with fury; and as he hurried toward me, perhaps with the intention of killing me on the spot, I thought it high time to prepare to defend myself, and not yield my life, even to such odds, without a manly struggle. I therefore sprung to my feet, and, seeing the large knife of my first assailant sticking through the blanket, I leaped upon the bed, seized it, and, wildly brandishing it over my head, shouted, in mad defiance:</p>
               <p>"Stand back, you villains! or I will cut my way through you!"</p>
               <p>Don Juan paused, irresolute, and the trembling menials, whose numbers were now augmenting, huddled themselves together near the door, much better prepared for flight than fight.</p>
               <p>"What is the meaning of all this?" demanded Don Juan.</p>
               <p>"Ask this midnight assassin!" said I, pointing to the still prostrate form of my nearly strangled foe; "and, if his guilty spirit still linger in its worthless tenement, perhaps he will explain! All I know is, that, having claimed honorable hospitality of you for the night,<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC5795-00000035"/> the laws of God and man have been barbarously outraged in an attempt to murder me while I was supposed to be asleep; and if you, sir, can justify such inhuman conduct, you are better qualified for the master-fiend of hell than an inhabitant of even this half-civilized country!"</p>
               <p>"Young man," replied the host, in a softened tone, "I pledge you my honor that this attempt upon your life was made without my knowledge."</p>
               <p>"I believe you," returned I, frankly; for I saw, at a <choice>
                     <sic>clance</sic>
                     <corr>glance</corr>
                  </choice>, he felt mortified and humbled.</p>
               <p>"It is a damning disgrace!" he added; "the more unpardonable in its vile features, that the attempt was made by the son of the host."</p>
               <p>"Your son!" cried I, in astonishment.</p>
               <p>"Yes," said he, with a quivering lip; "I will humble myself so much as to confess that that heap of mortality is bone of my bone and flesh of my flesh—but not animated by a single spark of my spirit,—no! the saints forbid!"</p>
               <p>As he spoke, he bent over the prostrate man, who was now struggling for breath, and, without touching him, held the light near his face.</p>
               <p>"He revives," said I.</p>
               <p>"Yes," he replied, gloomily; "but I can see that, had I been one moment later, you would have finished him."</p>
               <p>"Thank God, you came in time!" I rejoined.</p>
               <p>"I do not know that I can echo your sentiment," he muttered: "the craven-hearted villain deserved to die. Here!" calling to his servants—"come here, some of you, take up this dog, and bear him to his own apartment. I will settle with him to-morrow."</p>
               <p>He then got up, and turned his back upon his son, with an expression of indignant loathing, and so remained until the latter had been carried from the room. Then, putting down the light, he seated himself upon the bed, dropped his head upon his bosom, and gave way to his feelings in a manner that affected me deeply. I sincerely pitied the old gentleman, and I made the best attempt I could to console him.</p>
               <p>"I am sorry," I said, "that fortune led me to your hospitable roof; for, had I not come hither, this, that so much distresses you, would not have occurred. Perhaps your son was not in his right mind; for it seems to me no sane man would attempt to murder a peaceful guest without a motive. And if he was sane, and wanted my life, why did he not take it at the time he removed my pistols?"</p>
               <p>"What do you mean?" said Don Juan, looking up.</p>
               <p>"Why, your worship, when I went to bed, I placed my pistols under my head; and when I awoke, they were gone."</p>
               <p>"Are you sure?" he asked, quickly.</p>
               <p>"I could not find them, or I should certainly have made use of them. I will look again, however."</p>
               <p>"Do, Señor."</p>
               <pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC5795-00000036"/>
               <p>I took the light, and made a careful search for the weapons; but they were not to be seen.</p>
               <p>"And, by-the-by," I added, "I remember hearing your son say, as he struck this knife into what he supposed was my body, 'Take that, you——villain!' Now this evidently implied bitter feeling toward me personally, and yet I have no recollection of ever having seen his face before. He could not have been in his right mind, certainly."</p>
               <p>Don Juan made no reply to this; but, grasping my hand, he fixed his eye steadily upon me for some moments, and said:</p>
               <p>"You have a noble heart, Señor Burmond, and deserve better treatment than you have received. If you feel disposed to sleep, after what has occurred, I pledge you my sacred honor, and swear by the holy cross and all the saints, you shall not be molested or disturbed again! and to-morrow I will myself head an escort and guard you to Puebla. And then, let me entreat, in return, that you will never mention this disgraceful affair where it can do me injury."</p>
               <p>"You have my solemn promise, sir," I replied, "that I will only mention it to one person while in Mexico, and that person shall be bound to secrecy."</p>
               <p>"Thank you, Señor, and good night! I will leave this lamp with you, and you may let it burn, and fasten your door—though, I assure you, I shall keep guard outside myself."</p>
               <p>With this Don Juan went out; and for fear of accidents dents, I took the precaution to make the door fast, by double bolts, as I ought to have done in the first place. I then threw myself upon the bed; but it may readily be believed I slept no more that night, though it passed off without any further disturbance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC5795-00000037"/>
               <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
               <head type="sub">IN THE POWER OF MY ENEMIES.</head>
               <p>AT the first streak of day I opened the door of my apartment, and found Don Juan sitting in the corridor. His strongly marked features were pervaded by a stern, gloomy expression—an expression which boded ill to some one, though evidently not to me.</p>
               <p>"Here are your pistols," he said, rising and presenting them to me. "The caps have been removed, but they are still loaded."</p>
               <p>"Where did you find them?" was my natural inquiry.</p>
               <p>"Señor Burmond," he replied, "permit me to request, as a favor, that you will ask me no questions concerning this dark transaction; but rest assured the guilty parties shall not escape punishment. And pardon me, if I make still another request. As soon as you have broken your fast, will you permit me, with a safe escort, to set off with you for Puebla?"</p>
               <p>"I am at your command, sir, at any moment," I replied.</p>
               <p>"Come with me, then, and take breakfast: all is ready for our departure."</p>
               <p>I was conducted by the host to the same apartment where I had taken my supper the night previous; but none of the family were present. The table was set for two, and Don Juan and myself ate in silence. As soon as the meal was finished, I accompanied my host into the patio, and found eight horses saddled and bridled, and six armed Mexicans standing beside them, ready to mount.</p>
               <p>"You will find this an easy riding beast, Señor," said the host, handing me the bridle rein of a noble gray</p>
               <p>I took the hint, and was quickly in the saddle. Don Juan mounted and placed himself by my side; and the others, imitating his example, also mounted and paired off, so as to form a double file. A nod from the host, to a mozo in waiting, was sufficient command for the opening of the great gate; and, without a word being exchanged by any of the parties, we rode through the arch, and set off at an easy gallop.</p>
               <p>It is not my purpose to fatigue the reader with the detail of a wearisome day's ride. Suffice it, therefore, to say, that we reached the beautiful city of La Puebla about nightfall, and my guide conducted me to the "Fonda de las Diligencias," where we all took lodgings for the night—it being my intention to take passage the next morning for the city of Mexico. I soon learned that the news of the attack upon the diligencia, with the supposed murder of my companion and myself, had reached here early in the day, creating no little excitement and alarm; and when it became known that<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC5795-00000038"/> I was one of the two, and had miraculously effected my escape, it may readily be believed that I was the lion of the occasion. I was immediately surrounded by a crowd of persons, all eager to hear the story from my lips, and I gratified them by telling it as briefly as possible. But no sooner had I finished the exciting tale than a new party beset me, and I was obliged to repeat it. A third and still larger group appearing, to take the place of the second, I determined to escape a continuous repetition; and, by a little ruse, I managed to slip through the crowd and gain the street. It being a warm, pleasant night, and I feeling that a walk, till the hour of retiring, would be beneficial after my long ride, I at once set off on a ramble about the town.</p>
               <p>I had not proceeded more than half a dozen squares from my hotel, however, when, just as I was turning the corner of a large, fine street, two men, in the costume of military officers, accosted me politely, and inquired if I were not a stranger in Mexico.</p>
               <p>"I am not a citizen," I replied.</p>
               <p>"A foreign traveller, Señor?" inquired one. I nodded an affirmative.</p>
               <p>"You must pardon us then, Señor, if we request to see your passport."</p>
               <p>"I have it not with me, and I fear it is lost," I answered. "You have probably heard of the recent attack upon the diligencia between here and Perote, during which at least one passenger was murdered?"</p>
               <p>"We have heard something of it."</p>
               <p>"I was one of the passengers in the diligencia, and escaped by leaping down a precipice—leaving my portmanteau, which, among other things, contained my passport, in the vehicle. Whether the cowardly ladrones carried it off as booty or not, I do not know; but perhaps I may be able to learn by inquiring at the Fonda de las Diligencias; and if you consider the matter important, and will accompany me——"</p>
               <p>"This does not suit us," hastily interrupted the one who spoke for both. "If any traveller loses his passport, it is not our business to hunt it up for him."</p>
               <p>"Certainly not," I replied; "but in a case like this, where a traveller has been robbed, and one of his companions murdered, on the national highway, and all because your government is too weak or cowardly to protect the most public and most travelled road, it does not become the officers of such a government to be too haughty, exacting, or disobliging to one who has most cause for complaint!"</p>
               <p>"This is not to the point," replied the spokesman: "we do not know you; we do not know that you have been robbed; and unless you can produce your passport, you must come with us."</p>
               <p>"To what place do you wish to take me?"</p>
               <p>"To our quarters. You must see our captain, and he will decide upon your case."</p>
               <p>"First have the kindness to accompany me to my hotel, which is only a short distance."</p>
               <pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC5795-00000039"/>
               <p>"No! we cannot do that without permission of our captain, who is also near at hand."</p>
               <p>"Very well, then, if you are determined not to oblige me, conduct me to your captain."</p>
               <p>The exact spot where this occurred was not light by any means, and only some two or three individuals passed us while we were speaking; but I remembered afterward, that my military friends seemed quite uneasy, and kept a watchful eye upon every person in the vicinity. I remembered this afterward, I say, and so I must have noticed it at the time, though it did not excite suspicion of any thing wrong.</p>
               <p>To my surprise, I found myself hurried from the main street, into streets dark, narrow, and mostly deserted; and although they had said their quarters were near, it was some fifteen minutes before they reached their destination. They halted at last beside a solitary building, standing in a gloomy, unlighted part of the town. A single tap on the door caused it to be opened; and the moment I had crossed the threshold, it was closed. I was next led, unsuspectingly, into a small room on the right; where some half a dozen persons, springing upon me at once, pinioned my arms, threw me down, and forced a gag into my mouth. This was all done so suddenly as to prevent resistance; and I saw, too late, that I had been entrapped, and that my life would probably pay the penalty of an indiscriminate credulity.</p>
               <p>Having bound my arms, and deprived me of my weapons, the ruffians ordered me upon my feet; and then informed me, that if I would not call for help, or make any undue use of my voice, the gag should be taken from my mouth, as they wished me to reply to some important questions. I informed them, by a sign, that I would do as they required, and the gag was accordingly removed.</p>
               <p>I was now conducted into another apartment, where some ten or twelve armed men were in waiting, three of them being seated upon a slight elevation, with a desk in front of them, and the others standing about in various attitudes. The apartment had something the appearance of a modern court-room; and I began to entertain the opinion that I had been brought before a legal tribunal, and had nothing serious to fear; but I was soon undeceived.</p>
               <p>The elder of the three seated upon the bench, as for convenience I will term it, was a man turned of forty, and seemed to be about twenty years the senior of the younger. The resemblance between the two was sufficient to mark them as father and son; and the features of both were stern, with an expression of vindictiveness and treachery that denoted the absence of the nobler feelings of humanity. Both, however, seemed to be intellectual, which was more than could be said of the third party, who sat between them, and who might be characterized as sullen, obstinate, and brutal.</p>
               <p>As I was led up to the bench, facing these three judges,<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC5795-00000040"/> the elder fixed his black, snaky eyes keenly upon me, and said:</p>
               <p>"Your name is Alden Burmond?"</p>
               <p>I was surprised to find myself already known to persons I had never seen before, but I replied, respectfully:</p>
               <p>"So I am called, Señor."</p>
               <p>"Three nights ago, in the town of Jalapa, you were married to la Doña Panola Francisca Mariana de Esperanza?"</p>
               <p>The truth now flashed upon me at once, and I experienced some very singular and very unpleasant sensations; but I managed to keep these concealed, and replied boldly:</p>
               <p>"I was, Señor."</p>
               <p>"You knew, at the time, that she was the daughter of the Emperor of Brazil, and therefore a Princess?"</p>
               <p>"I believed she was all this, Señor."</p>
               <p>"You had heard of her uncle, Don Diego?"</p>
               <p>"I had heard his name mentioned."</p>
               <p>"Unfavorably mentioned, of course?"</p>
               <p>"I say nothing against him, Señor."</p>
               <p>"Well, you had heard mention of his son, Don Miguel?"</p>
               <p>"I do not deny it, Señor."</p>
               <p>"You knew that, for political reasons, it was the desire of the father that his son should marry his cousin, the Princess?"</p>
               <p>"I believed such to be the case, Señor."</p>
               <p>"Yet knowing all this," he continued, scowling fiercely "you deliberately resolved to marry the Princess, and frustrate his plans?"</p>
               <p>"For certain reasons, Señor, which shall be nameless," I replied, "I did marry one who called herself Panola, and whom at the time I believed to be suffering from unjust persecutions."</p>
               <p>"And what do you think you deserve for this?"</p>
               <p>"The respect of all honorable men."</p>
               <p>He exchanged a few words in whispers with his villainous colleagues, and then replied, with a still fiercer scowl:</p>
               <p>"We, who are the judges in this case, think differently, Alden Burmond. It is our opinion that you unfairly played for a large stake, and deserve to lose."</p>
               <p>"That such would be the opinion of Don Diego and Don Miguel, who have, it seems, constituted themselves my judges, I never had any reason to doubt," I replied, pointedly.</p>
               <p>"So then," he rejoined, "you know us?"</p>
               <p>I was not sure when I spoke, but his answer proved that I had correctly surmised: the base uncle and cousin of Panola were actually before me.</p>
               <p>"Remove the prisoner," continued Don Diego, starting up; and I was accordingly hurried from the apartment into the smaller one adjoining.</p>
               <p>Here, after being again gagged, I was compelled to remain for some time, in the most torturing suspense, with two villainous-looking fellows standing guard over<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC5795-00000041"/> me, both of whom, it was evident to me, would have been delighted at the reception of an order consigning me to death. I had no hope now that I should escape; but the mystery of the whole affair puzzled me, and drew off some of my thoughts from a more unpleasant contemplation.</p>
               <p>How had I been traced and marked so surely as to be arrested by pretended officers so soon after entering a strange city? Were any of the military guards in league with this gang of Diego's? and had they heard me relate my own story at the hotel, and suddenly adopted the stratagem of the passport to get me into their clutches? Was there any connection between this last affair and the attack on the diligencia? and was the attempt upon my life the night previous another link of the chain? Had Don Juan, my host of last night and my guide and protector of to-day, any inkling of what would befall me at Puebla? I could not believe he had: certainly he had not, unless nature had for once deceived me in human signs.</p>
               <p>While I was thus ruminating, the door opened, and Don Diego entered, followed by his son, and four men whose faces were concealed under masks. All drew up in a circle around me, and the two who had been in attendance upon me were ordered to retire. As they left the apartment, Don Diego removed the gag from my mouth, and said:</p>
               <p>"From what I have learned, it appears you possess a kind of charmed life; but I rather think the spell will soon be broken, and you will give evidence that you are only mortal."</p>
               <p>"You speak enigmatically," I replied.</p>
               <p>"I speak, fool, of the deaths you have escaped, and of the death you will not escape!"</p>
               <p>"All men that live have escaped all deaths of the universe; but, when they die, there is a death they do not escape."</p>
               <p>"Every fool knows that," he sneered.</p>
               <p>"Then I trust I am comprehended," said I.</p>
               <p>"You are insolent, knave!"</p>
               <p>"By what authority do you call me knave," I rejoined, "since I am only related to <emph>you</emph> by marriage?"</p>
               <p>On hearing this, Don Miguel, with whom I had not exchanged a word, stepped forward, and, with the flat of his hand, struck me on the side of the face.</p>
               <p>Strange as it may seem, that blow was undoubtedly the mysterious means by which my life was to be preserved; for, with a bound and a yell that would have done credit to a Bedlamite, I threw myself against him with such force as to knock him down; and, at the same time, using all my strength, now increased by rage, I snapped my bonds as if they had been threads.</p>
               <p>I scarcely need say that this work of a moment threw the party into confusion,—a confusion of which I took advantage, by using my fists with a skill, quickness, and force which they had probably never seen equalled. In fact, I doubt if I was wholly sane, but rather wildly mad, from anger and a desire for<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC5795-00000042"/> liberty. My brain felt giddy, my veins seemed swelled with heated blood, and my strength appeared to me the strength of a giant. I danced, I shouted, I yelled, and struck out, right and left, with a fury and a force that levelled every one who attempted to seize me.</p>
               <p>The noise attracted persons from the adjoining room; but I was so fortunate as to reach the opposite door, and dart through it, just as they entered; and ere they could understand, in the confusion, what had taken place, I was hurrying up a flight of stairs, that led I knew not whither. I gained the story above, unmolested, but heard the ruffians coming after me, and knew not which way to turn, or where to go, to save my life. There was a swinging lamp at the foot of the stairs I had ascended; and by its light I perceived another flight, which would probably lead to the flat roof of the building. Up the second flight, therefore, I bounded; and, to my inexpressible joy, reached the open air. Here I called for help, and rejoiced to think that my voice would reach other than my enemies; and that, if I died by their hands, my death would possibly not be unavenged; and at least I was determined not to die in the secret manner which would leave my foes at ease.</p>
               <p>I was now on the <foreign xml:lang="SPA">azotea</foreign>, or flat roof, peculiar to Spanish buildings; and, continually shouting for help, I ran to the front, determined, if closely pressed, to make a bold leap into the street. My cries were soon answered from different quarters, and I heard the alarm of the night-guard, and the noise of several persons running, apparently to my assistance.</p>
               <p>But at this moment I saw several dark figures spring upon the roof from below, heard several reports of firearms in quick succession, felt a strange sensation of dizziness and sickness, and then the blank of death—the death as of body and soul—succeeded.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC5795-00000043"/>
               <head>CHAPTER IX.</head>
               <head type="sub">RETURN TO LIFE.</head>
               <p>MY gradual return to consciousness is in my memory like a confused and irrational dream, in which I seemed struggling through a dark and misty cloud that enveloped me, with some fair, angelic being gliding before me and beckoning me on to a region of light and joy.</p>
               <p>At last I opened my eyes in a neat, well-ordered room, and found myself lying on a comfortable bed. I felt weak, and sore, and stiff, and it seemed as if I had hurt myself by a fall, though I could remember nothing that had occurred. I knew not where I was, nor could I conjecture; but the lovely spirit of my dream stood beside me, gazing upon me so anxiously, so tenderly, and so sadly, that I felt prompted to address her, though expecting to see her vanish at the first word I should utter.</p>
               <p>"Who are you, fair being?" said I, in my native tongue.</p>
               <p>"Alas! his mind still wanders, and he still speaks in a language I do not understand," she sighed.</p>
               <p>These words, uttered in Spanish, in a tone that seemed to vibrate on my soul, thrilled through my whole being, and awoke an indistinct remembrance of something strange, peculiar, and important, though too much like a dream to be a reality. I looked at the speaker, and saw that she was beautiful beyond my power of description; but the familiarity of her countenance I attributed to the fact that I had often seen it in my dreams. Yet why in my dreams, if this was a reality? Could it be that I was dreaming now? At the thought, I repeated my question, but this time in Spanish:</p>
               <p>"Who are you, fair being?"</p>
               <p>"Do you not know me, dear Alden?" she inquired, in return, speaking in low, silvery accents, and holding her breath for an answer, while her dark, lustrous eyes rested softly and sweetly on mine.</p>
               <p>"Know you?" said I, wonderingly; "know you, fair lady? That look, that voice, both tell me I should know you! and you have called me by name. But something has happened to me—something serious I fear—for my memory seems struggling with a blank, and I cannot bring up images of the past with sufficient distinctness to decide on what is real and what is ideal. That I have met you in my dreams, I feel certain; but did we ever meet otherwise till now?"</p>
               <p>"Run your memory back for a brief period," she said, hastily. "Do you remember Jalapa?"</p>
               <p>"Jalapa! Jalapa!" I mused: "I have certainly heard that name before."</p>
               <p>"And Panola,—you remember Panola?"</p>
               <pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC5795-00000044"/>
               <p>"Ha! stop! one moment! Panola! yes! Panola! Good heavens! what is this that rushes over my brain, and thrills through every nerve and fibre of my body? Am I awake and recalling what was not a mere dream? Yes! yes! Jalapa—Panola—my wife!" I cried, in a frenzy of excitement. "<emph>You</emph> are Panola! and <emph>you are my wife!</emph>"</p>
               <p>"Yes," she said, throwing her soft, white arms around my neck, "I am your wife, Panola; I claim you as my husband, and we will part no more."</p>
               <p>"But my brain is not clear yet," I continued: "something dark intervenes between our marriage and the present! Tell me what it is. I am still bewildered."</p>
               <p>She pressed her lips to mine, fervently, passionately, and then, bowing her head upon my bosom, wept.</p>
               <p>"I will tell you all," she said at length; "but not now—not to-day. You are too ill—too weak—too recently come up from the grave. Here! take this and sleep!"</p>
               <p>She poured some liquid into a spoon, and placed it to my lips. I took it mechanically, and soon found reality blending with fancy, and fancy disappearing in a cloud of forgetfulness.</p>
               <p>When I awoke again, it was night, and Panola was still patiently and affectionately watching by my side. I would have conversed with her, but she forbade it; and, conscious of a want of mental strength and will, I did as she desired, and slept again.</p>
               <p>The second day after this, I found myself strong enough to converse without doing me an injury; and at my urgent solicitation, Panola consented to answer my questions, and clear up some of the mystery that still enveloped me as a mist.</p>
               <p>"Where am I?" I inquired.</p>
               <p>"In La Puebla; in the Fonda de las Diligencias," was her answer.</p>
               <p>"These names sound familiarly; but I have no remembrance of coming here."</p>
               <p>"I think I can make all clear to you, dear husband," answered Panola. "You remember our marriage?"</p>
               <p>"Yes."</p>
               <p>"You remember setting out, the second morning after, in the diligencia for the city of Mexico?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, now I do."</p>
               <p>"You remember I warned you against enemies?"</p>
               <p>"Ay—even that."</p>
               <p>"You stopped the first night in Perote."</p>
               <p>"Let me see. Yes, that is clear."</p>
               <p>"The day following, the diligencia was attacked at Dark Hollow, and you made a narrow escape by leaping from a precipice."</p>
               <p>"Ha! yes! that awful scene, with the death of my comrade, grows clear in my memory."</p>
               <p>"You wandered far that day, and sought a night's hospitality at the hacienda of Don Juan Albertoz."</p>
               <p>"One moment. Don Juan Albertoz? Yes, you are right."</p>
               <pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC5795-00000045"/>
               <p>"There was an attempt made that night to assassinate you."</p>
               <p>"Ay, and I foiled the villain."</p>
               <p>"The next day the noble Don himself escorted you to this city."</p>
               <p>"Let me think! that is not quite so clear. One moment. There! yes, I have that."</p>
               <p>"You put up at this hotel, and told your story to many eager listeners, and then went out to escape the crowd."</p>
               <p>I reflected and assented.</p>
               <p>"Two men, apparently officers, accosted you, and required your passport. Not having it, you accompanied them, by their orders, to a lonely building. What took place there, I must not say; but——"</p>
               <p>"Ha! I have it now," I cried. "All is plain now. I remember the rest, till—till——"</p>
               <p>"Till you were shot down on the azotea," rejoined Panola, as I paused.</p>
               <p>"Was I then shot?" I inquired.</p>
               <p>"You were, and fell to the ground below, where the guard, coming to your rescue too late, picked you up for dead. I thought, or rather hoped, there might be signs of life, and had you conveyed to this hotel."</p>
               <p>"You!" I cried, in perfect amazement; "you had me conveyed hither? Were you then in the city?"</p>
               <p>"I was."</p>
               <p>"But how came you to be out with the guard?"</p>
               <p>"I was acting as guide to them."</p>
               <p>"Guide? You? Do explain! I am all bewilderment."</p>
               <p>Panola smiled, and kissed me.</p>
               <p>"Dear husband," she rejoined, mischievously, "let me put this explanation off till another day."</p>
               <p>"Not till another minute. I am dying of curiosity."</p>
               <p>"I thought only our sex was troubled with curiosity," she replied, with a laugh.</p>
               <p>"Go on! go on! I am eager—excited."</p>
               <p>"A soporific will calm your nerves."</p>
               <p>"Do not tantalize me, please, my angel."</p>
               <p>"Well, that endearing term has conquered," she said, with another light laugh—a laugh silvery and sweet, that made me happy to hear. "But I must begin at the beginning. Ha! I hear steps: it is the surgeon."</p>
               <p>She opened the door, and a man of venerable appearance entered. I was pleased to perceive he was a foreigner; and better still, to learn that he was an Englishman. He had formerly been in the navy, but for the last ten years a resident of Puebla.</p>
               <p>"A steady improvement, Mr. Burmond," he said, with a cheerful smile, as he took my hand, and seated himself by my side. "You owe your life to this lady; for never had patient a better nurse, and never man lived who had been nearer death's door."</p>
               <p>"What are my hurts, doctor?"</p>
               <p>"Being almost as numerous as your sins, I will only mention the principal ones. You received two bullets in your body, and fell twenty-five feet."</p>
               <pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC5795-00000046"/>
               <p>"Do you think me out of danger now?"</p>
               <p>"I think you will recover, gradually."</p>
               <p>"And how long have I been under your care, doctor?"</p>
               <p>"Two weeks to-day."</p>
               <p>"Good heavens!" I exclaimed. "Two weeks! Then have I been near death's door indeed!"</p>
               <p>After some further conversation, the surgeon took his leave, enjoining me to be careful, and not weary or exert myself in the least. The moment he had gone, I impatiently demanded Panola's story.</p>
               <p>"I will not gratify your curiosity on such bidding," she said, laughing.</p>
               <p>"What shall I say, then?"</p>
               <p>"What you please."</p>
               <p>"My dearest angel."</p>
               <p>"Well, that will do. And now I will allay your curiosity, and excite your vanity, by telling my story."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER X.</head>
               <head type="sub">"ALL'S WELL THAT ENDS WELL."</head>
               <p>"WHEN I first saw you in Jalapa," began Panola, "I did not fall in love with you; but I thought you a very proper man for my purpose, and I acted accordingly. After our marriage, my mind began to dwell on you with some pleasure—probably because you were absent—and I thought I should like to meet you again. On the impulse of the moment, (and I am rather a creature of impulse,) I addressed you a note, which was, I confess, a little tinctured with flattery. Your odd reply pleased me, for I am fond of originality; and the second note, and another answer, followed. I liked your careless, half-sarcastic, independent rejoinder; and being gone, my mind set up an ideal, and called it Alden Burmond. When one of our sex names her ideal after a human being, it is a sure sign that, sooner or later, she will fall in love with the original or real, especially if the latter keep out of her way long enough, and happen, as in this case, to encounter peril on her account.</p>
               <p>"Well, the day you left, Don Diego came to town, and, hearing of my marriage, sought an interview with me. I need not describe all that took place; but let it suffice<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC5795-00000047"/> that he swore a wicked oath that we should never meet again. I knew he would keep his oath, if possible; and as he left the city soon afterward, I feared the worst, and determined to follow him if I could. I got my page, who is about my size and build, to procure me a male suit; and, dressed in this, I set off on horseback, in the night, for Perote. I reached that place the next morning about sunrise, and made inquiries concerning the diligencia, the number of passengers it contained, and so forth. I knew from the description given that you were one of those passengers, and I determined to follow on and overtake you, and either persuade you to return, or share the danger with you. But I thought it best to hire a party of courageous fellows to accompany me, for I had heard some frightful stories of the road between Perote and Puebla, and in carrying out this design I was delayed some two or three hours.</p>
               <p>"At last, accompanied by four armed men, who had formerly been muleteers, and knew the route and its dangers, I left Perote, and endeavored to make up for lost time by riding fast. At Dark Hollow we found the diligencia standing in the road, deserted, and all around the evidences of a sanguinary fight. My heart sunk within me, for I feared you had been murdered, and search was made for your body. At the bottom of the precipice we found a naked corpse; but, thank Heaven! it was not yours.</p>
               <p>"We continued our search, beating about the bushes, and traversing the road for a considerable distance from the central point. At length we discovered a woman hid under a rock, and half dead with fright. From her we managed to learn that, after a desperate fight between the robbers and two of the passengers, the former had finally conquered; and while they were robbing the peacefully disposed, herself among the number, another armed party came up, and the ladrones fled. The second party offered no violence, but made particular inquiries concerning one of the passengers who had been killed, for she contended that both the foreigners had been killed by the ladrones. After this we made another search for your body; but not finding it, we came to the conclusion that it had been removed. Still hoping you might possibly have escaped—for I did not believe that Don Diego, who doubtless commanded the second party, would care to remove your body, it being sufficient for his purpose to be sure of your death—still hoping, I say, that you had, in some miraculous manner, escaped with life, I sent two of my fellows back to Perote, to watch for you and tell the news, while I, with the other two, rode on to Puebla. We reached Puebla in the night; and I was the first, the next morning, to spread the terrible intelligence, which was received with consternation.</p>
               <p>"Still retaining my disguise, I walked about the town, in no very enviable state of mind; and during my stroll, I passed the very building into which you were entrapped the following night. I do not know why, but, as I passed the door of that building, a shudder<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC5795-00000048"/> ran through my frame, and my blood felt chilled with horror. So unusual a circumstance caused me to notice it more particularly. Retiring some distance, I leaned against a tree; and while I stood thus, to my perfect amazement, and almost terror, I saw Don Diego and his son enter. Then I knew that that building, whatever else it might be, was a place for plot and intrigue, and perhaps conspiracy against the Mexican government; and I resolved to watch it narrowly, and, if I discovered any thing to warrant the proceeding, to make it known to the authorities. Don Diego had wronged me in many ways; I believed him, at heart, if not in deed, guilty of your death; and I felt myself justified in any lawful retaliation.</p>
               <p>"Not to prolong my story, let it suffice that I was hardly out of sight of that building all day; and I saw several persons enter and leave it at different times; though there never were more than two together, which led me to suppose they were afraid of exciting suspicion. At dark I repaired to this hotel, and had not been here long, when, to my utter astonishment and unbounded joy, I saw you enter with an armed party. I dared not make myself known to you then; but I got near you, and kept near you, and heard you tell your tale twice to an excited crowd. When you slipped away into the street, I followed you; and when you were stopped by those pretended officers, I was near enough to overhear a part of the conversation; and I actually passed you once while you stood talking, but took care not to excite suspicion by seeming to notice you or them.</p>
               <p>"I did not think they were what they pretended to be; and when they took you with them, I followed at a cautious distance, and saw you enter the dreaded building. Then I knew there was no time to be lost; and I flew to the head-quarters of the guard, and informed the captain that I could lead him to a band of conspirators, robbers, and murderers; and demanded, in the name of the government, that he should follow me at once. This was a bold proceeding, for I had no proof; but I cared not for the consequences, so that I might save your life. After some questioning and delay, he called out a part of his men and set off with me; but at the same time he threatened me with vengeance, should he find I had deceived him.</p>
               <p>"Before we got to the building, we heard your cries for help, but were not in time to save you. The sound of fire-arms quickened the guard to a run; and when we reached the building, we found you lying upon the ground, apparently dead, weltering in your blood. Citizens, hearing the alarm, came crowding up in all directions; and, procuring assistance from them, I had you conveyed to the hotel. Meantime, the guard forced an entrance into the building, and, meeting with resistance, fired upon the party inside. Don Diego and one other were killed, some four or five were wounded and taken prisoners, and the rest escaped."</p>
               <p>"And so," said I, "your villainous uncle is dead! It<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC5795-00000049"/> is wrong to rejoice at the death of even an enemy, but I am glad you are free from his persecutions. He certainly deserved his fate. What became of his equally villainous son?"</p>
               <p>"It is supposed he has escaped."</p>
               <p>"You will have nothing to fear from him, I think."</p>
               <p>"No," replied Panola; "he is too much of a coward; and besides, if in Mexico now, he will be likely to leave on the first opportunity."</p>
               <p>"This is, altogether, a very curiously tangled and romantic affair," said I. "Do you think Don Diego had any connection with the band of cut-throats that first attacked the diligencia?"</p>
               <p>"I judge not, if it be true that they fled on his approach; though they might have been frightened at the sound of horses' hoofs, and he have been one of them for all that. It is hard to say."</p>
               <p>"And the attempt upon my life at Don Juan's hacienda—how heard you of that?"</p>
               <p>"He himself informed me, and added that you appeared to have enemies in every quarter."</p>
               <p>"Did he hint that the person who tried to murder me was connected with the road-banditti?"</p>
               <p>"No; he only said that your life was attempted while under his roof and protection; and that, feeling the disgrace most keenly, he had tried to repair the injury in a slight degree, by escorting you hither."</p>
               <p>"And all this was two weeks ago?"</p>
               <p>"Yes."</p>
               <p>"It seems like a dream."</p>
               <p>"It was a terrible reality to me," sighed my companion.</p>
               <p>"And have you, dear Panola, been with me ever since that eventful night?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, my dear husband, I have scarcely left your side, and never for more than an hour at a time."</p>
               <p>"You are an angel indeed."</p>
               <p>"I am glad you think so, for you must not ask me to separate from you again."</p>
               <p>"And are you willing to cling to me through weal and through woe?"</p>
               <p>"Dear husband, I have a legal right to be ever with you henceforth; and when I add that I now love you, you will see how happy your consent to an undivided union will make me."</p>
               <p>"But I do not wish to remain in Mexico."</p>
               <p>"I have already ordered my property to be sold, and shall be rejoiced to leave Mexico with you and go wherever it is your pleasure."</p>
               <p>"Heaven bless the hour we met! and may we never part again, till we part to reunite in a better world!" said I, fervently.</p>
               <p>My lovely wife threw her arms around my neck and breathed a joyful "Amen!"</p>
               <p>Reader, you have my story, such as it is. I have nothing to add, save that I recovered in time, and in<pb n="96-97 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC5795-00000050"/> time left the country of Mexico, bearing my lovely wife with me. Where I fixed my home, and where I am now residing, I need not say. Sufficient for you, that I am surrounded with all the luxuries of wealth, amid the genial airs of a Southern clime; and that the sweet prattle of my children, and the silvery tones of love from the lips of my eccentric and still beautiful wife, render me supremely happy. The daughter of an Emperor—a Princess <foreign xml:lang="LAT">de jure</foreign>—is content to sink rank and title in domestic enjoyment, beneath the shadow of the stars and stripes, the ever-glorious banner of Freedom.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>THE END.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="advertisement">
            <head>J. W. BRADLEY'S LIST OF PUBLICATIONS.</head>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>Perils and Pleasures OF A HUNTER'S LIFE.</head>
               <head type="sub">WITH FINE COLORED PLATES.</head>
               <head type="sub">Large 12mo., 336 pages, $1.00.</head>
               <head>CONTENTS</head>
               <p>Baiting for an Alligator—Morning among the Rocky Mountains—Encounter with Shoshonees—A Grizzly Bear—Fight and Terrible Result—Fire on the Mountains—Narrow Escape—The Beaver Region—Trapping Beaver—A Journey and Hunt through New Mexico—Start for South America—Hunting in the Forests of Brazil—Hunting on the Pampas—A Hunting Expedition into the Interior of Africa—Chase of the Rhinoceros—Chase of an Elephant—The Roar of the Lion—Herds of Wild Elephants—Lions attacked by Bechuanas—Arrival in the Region of the Tiger and the Elephant—Our first Elephant Hunt in India—A Boa Constrictor—A Tiger—A Lion—Terrible Conflict—Elephant Catching—Hunting the Tiger with Elephants—Crossing the Pyrenees—Encounter with a Bear—A Pigeon Hunt on the Ohio—A Wild-Hog Hunt in Texas—Hunting the Black-tailed Deer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="i"/>Agents wanted in every part of the United States and British Provinces. Address,</p>
               <p>J. W. BRADLEY, Publisher, 48 N. Fourth street, Philadelphia.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <pb n="98 (Advertisement) -99 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC5795-00000051"/>
               <head>LIFE AND EXPLORATIONS OF DR. E. K. KANE,</head>
               <head type="sub">AND OTHER DISTINGUISHED AMERICAN EXPLORERS, INCLUDING LEDYARD, WILKES, PERRY, etc., etc.</head>
               <p>CONTAINING NARRATIVES OF THEIR RESEARCHES AND ADVENTURES IN REMOTE AND INTERESTING PORTIONS OF THE GLOBE.</p>
               <p>BY SAMUEL M. SMUCKER, A.M.</p>
               <p>Author of "Court and Reign of Catharine II.," "Emperor Nicholas I.," "Life of Alexander Hamilton," "Arctic Explorations and Discoveries," "Memoir of Thomas Jefferson," "Memorable Scenes in French History," etc.</p>
               <p>With a fine Mezzotint Portrait of Dr. Kane, in his Arctic Costume.</p>
               <p>This work brings within the reach of all the admirers of our great Explorers (of whom Dr. KANE, although last, is not least,) the most important matter contained in books costing ten times the amount.</p>
               <p>AGENTS and CANVASSERS by taking this book, with our new work of DR. LIVINGSTONE'S EXPLORATIONS IN AFRICA, can make more money in the same time than on any other books now published. Retail price, $1.00. Specimen copies sent by mail on receipt of the price.</p>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>NOTICES OF THE PRESS.</head>
                  <p>From the many favorable notices of "Smucker's Life of Dr. Kane and other American Explorers," we take the following:</p>
                  <p>The author has here given us a valuable addition to American Biographical literature.—<title>Godey's Lady's Book</title>.</p>
                  <p>A terse, useful and interesting work. It is a delightful volume.—<title>U. S. Jour</title>.</p>
                  <p>It will become a household volume.—<title>Chicago Tribune</title>.</p>
                  <p>The portrait of Dr. Kane contained in this volume is a splendid steel engraving, and may be relied upon as a correct likeness, as we ourselves have frequently seen the original, and find the resemblance most striking.—<title>Am. Free Press, Easton, Pa</title>.</p>
                  <p>Worthy of a place on any centre-table, or on the shelves of any library.—<title>Trenton Gazette</title>.</p>
                  <p>For family libraries, this book is just the thing.—<title>Arthur's Magazine</title>.</p>
                  <p>J. W. BRADLEY, Publisher, 48 N. Fourth street, Philadelphia.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>DR. LIVINGSTONE'S TRAVELS AND RESEARCHES OF SIXTEEN YEARS IN THE WILDS OF SOUTH AFRICA.</head>
               <p>This is a work of thrilling adventures and hair-breadth escapes among savage beasts and more savage men. Dr. Livingstone was alone and unaided by any white man, traveling with African attendants, among different tribes and nations, all strange to him, and many of them hostile, and altogether forming the most astonishing book of travels the world has ever seen. All our Agents acknowledge it is the most salable book published. The most liberal commission made to Agents, in small or large quantities.</p>
               <p>Copies sent by Mail, free, on receipt of the price, $1.25.</p>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>NOTICES OF THE PRESS.</head>
                  <p>It abounds in descriptions of strange and wonderful scenes, among a people and in a country entirely new to the civilized world; and altogether we regard it as one of the most interesting books issued within the past year.—<title>Daily Democrat, Patterson, New Jersey</title>.</p>
                  <p>The subjects treated of are new and strange, and take a deep hold upon popular feeling. The book is having a great run, and will be read by every reading man, woman and child, in this as well as other lands,—<title>Ashtabula (Ohio) Telegraph</title>.</p>
                  <p>Those of our readers who would have a delightful book for reading at any hour, will not be disappointed in this work.—<title>United States Journal</title>.</p>
                  <p>This interesting work should be in the hands of every one. Its interesting pages of adventures are full of instruction and amusement.—<title>Auburn American</title>.</p>
                  <p>With truth we can say, that seldom is presented to the reading public a work containing such a vast amount of solid instruction as the one in question. The volume is handsomely illustrated, and presents that <emph>unique</emph> appearance of exterior for which Mr. Bradley's publications are noted.—<title>Family Magazine</title>.</p>
                  <p>CAUTION.—The attention of the Publisher has been called to spurious editions of this work, put forth as "Narratives of Dr. Livingstone's Travels in Africa." Ours is the only cheap American edition of this great work published, and contains all the important matter of the English edition, which is sold at six dollars.</p>
                  <p>J. W. BRADLEY, Publisher, 48 N. Fourth street, Philadelphia.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <pb n="100 (Advertisement) -101 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC5795-00000052"/>
               <head>TEN NIGHTS IN A BAR-ROOM, AND What I Saw There.</head>
               <p>This powerfully-written work, one of the <emph>best</emph> by its <emph>popular Author</emph>, is meeting with immense sales,—ten thousand copies having been ordered within a month of publication. Young men wishing to <emph>do good</emph>, and at the same time to <emph>make money</emph>, will find a rare chance in selling this book. It is a large 12mo., of 240 pages, Illustrated with a beautiful Mezzotint Engraving, by Sartain; printed on fine white paper, and bound in the best <emph>English muslin, gilt back</emph>. Price $1.00.</p>
               <p>The following are a few of the many Notices of the Press.</p>
               <p>Its scenes are painfully graphic, and furnish thrilling arguments for the temperance cause.—<title>Norton's Literary Gazette</title>.</p>
               <p>Powerful and seasonable.—<title>N. Y. Independent</title>.</p>
               <p>Written in the author's most forcible and vigorous style.—<title>Lehigh Valley Times</title>.</p>
               <p>In the "Ten Nights in a Bar-Room," some of the consequences of tavern-keeping, the "sowing of the wind" and "reaping the whirlwind," are followed by a "fearful consummation," and the "closing scene," presenting pictures of fearful, thrilling interest.—<title>Am. Courier</title>.</p>
               <p>There is no exaggeration in these pages—they seem to have been filled up by actual observation.—<title>Philadelphia Sun</title>.</p>
               <p>We have read it with the most intense interest, and commend it as a work calculated to do an immense amount of good.—<title>Lancaster Express</title>.</p>
               <p>We wish that all lovers of bar-rooms and rum would read the book. It will pay them richly to do so.—<title>N. Y. Northern Blade</title>.</p>
               <p>It is sufficient commendation of this little volume to say that it is from the graphic pen of T. S. Arthur, whose works will be read and re-read long after he has passed away. He is as true to nature, as far as he attempts to explore it, as Shakspeare himself; and his works, consequently, have an immense popularity.—<title>New Haven Palladium</title>.</p>
               <p>There are many scenes unequaled for pathos and beauty. The death of little Mary can scarcely be surpassed.—<title>N. Y. Home Journal</title>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="i"/>Agents wanted in every part of the United States and British Provinces. Address,</p>
               <p>J. W. BRADLEY, Publisher, 48 N. Fourth street, Philadelphia.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>"LIVING AND LOVING."</head>
               <head type="sub">A Collection of Sketches.</head>
               <p>BY MISS V. P. TOWNSEND.</p>
               <p>Large 12mo., with fine steel Portrait of the Author. Bound in cloth, $1.00.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>CONTENTS.</head>
                  <item>Muriel.</item>
                  <item>To Arthur, Asleep.</item>
                  <item>The Memory Bells.</item>
                  <item>Mend the Breeches.</item>
                  <item>The Sunshine after the Rain.</item>
                  <item>My Picture.</item>
                  <item>Little Mercy is Dead.</item>
                  <item>The Old Letters.</item>
                  <item>The Fountain very Far Down.</item>
                  <item>The Rain in the Afternoon.</item>
                  <item>The Blossom in the Wilderness.</item>
                  <item>The Mistake.</item>
                  <item>October.</item>
                  <item>Twice Loving.</item>
                  <item>The Old Mirror.</item>
                  <item>The Country Graveyard.</item>
                  <item>Now.</item>
                  <item>The Door in the Heart.</item>
                  <item>My Step-Mother.</item>
                  <item>The Broken Threat.</item>
                  <item>Glimpses Inside the Cars.</item>
                  <item>The Old Stove.</item>
                  <item>The Old Rug.</item>
                  <item>The "Making-Up."</item>
                  <item>Next to Me.</item>
                  <item>"Only a Dollar."</item>
                  <item>The Temptation and the Triumph.</item>
                  <item>Extracts from a Valedictory Poem.</item>
                  <item>December.</item>
               </list>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>NOTICES OF THE PRESS.</head>
                  <p>We might say many things in favor of this delightful publication, but we deem it unnecessary. Husbands should buy it for their wives, lovers should buy it for their sweethearts, friends should buy it for their friends—a prettier or more entertaining gift could not be given—and everybody should buy it for themselves. It ought to be circulated throughout the land. It carries sunshine wherever it goes. One such book is worth more than all the "yellow-covered trash" ever published.—<title>Godey's Lady's Book</title>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="i"/>Agents wanted in every part of the United States and British Provinces. Address,</p>
                  <p>J. W. BRADLEY, Publisher, 48 N. Fourth street, Philadelphia</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <pb n="102 (Advertisement) -103 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC5795-00000053"/>
               <head>ARTHUR'S SKETCHES OF LIFE AND CHARACTER.</head>
               <p>An octavo volume of over 400 pages, beautifully illustrated, and bound in the best English muslin, gilt back, $2.00.</p>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>NOTICES OF THE PRESS.</head>
                  <p>The present volume, containing more than four hundred finely-printed octavo pages, is illustrated by splendid engravings, and made particularly valuable to those who like to "see the face of him they talk withal," by a correct likeness of the author, finely engraved on steel.—<title>Neal's Gazette</title>.</p>
                  <p>In the princely mansions of the Atlantic merchants, and in the rude log cabins of the backwoodsmen, the name of Arthur is equally known and cherished as the friend of virtue.—<title>Graham's Magazine</title>.</p>
                  <p>We would not exchange the copy of these sketches, with its story of "The Methodist Preacher," for any one of the gilt-edged and embossed Annuals which we have yet seen.—<title>Lady's National Magazine</title>.</p>
                  <p>The first story in the volume, entitled "The Methodist Preacher; or, Lights and Shadows in the Life of an Itinerant," is alone worth the price of the work.—<title>Evening Bulletin</title>.</p>
                  <p>It is emphatically a splendid work.—<title>Middletown Whig</title>.</p>
                  <p>Its worth and cheapness should place it in every persons hands who desire to read an interesting book.—<title>Odd Fellow, Boonsboro</title>'.</p>
                  <p>"The Methodist Preacher," "Seed-Time and Harvest," "Dyed in the Wool," are full of truth as well as instruction, and any one of them is worth the whole price of the volume.—<title>Lowell Day-Star, Rev. D. C. Eddy, Editor</title>.</p>
                  <p>There is a fascination about these sketches which so powerfully interests the reader, that few who commence one of them will part with it till it is concluded; and they will bear reading repeatedly.—<title>Norfolk and Portsmouth Herald</title>.</p>
                  <p>Those who have not perused these model stories have a rich feast in waiting, and we shall be happy if we can be instrumental in pointing them to it.—<title>Family Visitor, Madison, Geo</title>.</p>
                  <p>No library for family reading should be considered complete without this volume, which is as lively and entertaining in its character as it is salutary in its influence.—<title>N. Y. Tribune</title>.</p>
                  <p>The work is beautifully illustrated. Those who are at all acquainted with Arthur's writings need hardly be told that the present work is a prize to whoever possesses it.—<title>N. Y. Sun</title>.</p>
                  <p>We know no better book for the table of any family, whether regarded for its neat exterior or valuable contents.—<title>Vox Populi, Lowell</title>.</p>
                  <p>The name of the author is in itself a sufficient recommendation of the work.—<title>Lawrence Sentinel</title>.</p>
                  <p>J. W. BRADLEY, Publisher, 48 N. Fourth street, Philadelphia.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head type="sub">A BOOK OF STARTLING INTEREST.</head>
               <head>THE ANGEL AND THE DEMON</head>
               <head type="sub">BY T. S. ARTHUR.</head>
               <p>A handsome 12mo. volume, Price $1.00</p>
               <p>In this exciting story Mr. Arthur has taken hold of the reader's attention with a more than usually vigorous grasp, and keeps him absorbed to the end of the volume. The book is one of STARTLING INTEREST. Its lessons should be IN THE HEART OF EVERY MOTHER.</p>
               <p>Onward, with a power of demonstration that makes conviction a necessity, the author sweeps through his subject, fascinating at every step. In the union of THRILLING DRAMATIC INCIDENT, with moral lessons of the highest importance, this volume stands forth pre-eminent among the author's many fine productions.</p>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>NOTICES OF THE PRESS.</head>
                  <p>A story of much power, imbued with that excellent moral and religious spirit which pervades all his writings.—<title>N. Y. Chronicle</title>.</p>
                  <p>This volume is among his best productions, and worthy of a place on every centre-table.—<title>Clarion, Pa., Banner</title>.</p>
                  <p>This is a most fascinating book, one which the reader will find it quite hard to lay aside without reading to the last page.—<title>Albany, N. Y., Journal and Courier</title>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="i"/>Agents wanted in every part of the United States and British Provinces. Address,</p>
                  <p>J. W. BRADLEY, Publisher, 48 N. Fourth street, Philadelphia.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <pb n="104 (Advertisement) -105 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC5795-00000054"/>
               <head type="sub">"To the Pure all things are Pure."</head>
               <head>WOMAN AND HER DISEASES, FROM THE CRADLE TO THE GRAVE:</head>
               <p>Adapted exclusively to her Instruction in the Physiology of her System, and all the Diseases of her Critical Periods.</p>
               <p>BY EDWARD H. DIXON, M.D., Editor of "The Scalpel," Consulting and Operating Surgeon, author of a Treatise on the "Causes of the Early Decay of American Women," &amp;c., &amp;c., and formerly Physician to the New York Deaf and Dumb Asylum.</p>
               <p>Sent by Mail on receipt of the price, $1.00</p>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>NOTICES OF THE PRESS.</head>
                  <p>"WOMAN AND HER DISEASES, from the Cradle to the Grave, adapted exclusively to her Instruction in the Physiology of her System," etc. By Edward H. Dixon, M.D. This work, though pertaining to subjects, the discussion of which has hitherto been almost exclusively confined to the medical profession, contains not a line nor a word calculated to awaken impure emotion, but much to strengthen purposes of virtue, and at the same time to remove the ignorance which lies at the foundation of the prevailing licentiousness. It has received the highest commendation from men whose opinions have great weight with the friends of morality and religion.—<title>New York Tribune</title>.</p>
                  <p>The chapter on the consequences and treatment of self-abuse, is one of the most earnest appeals we have ever read, and we believe will save thousands from an untimely grave. That, on abortion, entitles Dr. Dixon to the thanks of every humane person in the community.—<title>Merchants' Ledger, N. Y.</title>
                  </p>
                  <p>The thanks of the public are due to Dr. Dixon, both for the matter and the manner of it. Every mother should read it, and then present its contents to her children.—<title>Anglo-American</title>.</p>
                  <p>Dr. Dixon has lent a deep interest to his work, and is doing good service by its publication.—<title>Boston Medical and Surgical Journal</title>.</p>
                  <p>We are sure we are doing a public benefit, by commending to universal notice this work, imparting as it does a vast deal of information of vital importance to every one. Medical and other journals of the highest repute in this country, have spoken of it in the most exalted terms, and earnestly recommend its introduction into every family.—<title>New Bedford Evening Bulletin</title>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="i"/>Agents wanted in every part of the United States and British Provinces. Address,</p>
                  <p>J. W. BRADLEY, Publisher, 48 N. Fourth street, Philadelphia.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>INDIA AND THE INDIAN MUTINY.</head>
               <head type="sub">COMPRISING A COMPLETE HISTORY OF HINDOOSTAN, FROM THE EARLIEST TIMES TO THE PRESENT DAY, WITH FULL PARTICULARS OF THE RECENT MUTINY IN INDIA.</head>
               <p>ILLUSTRATED WITH NUMEROUS ENGRAVINGS.</p>
               <p>BY HENRY FREDERICK MALCOLM.</p>
               <p>This work is now ready for Canvassers and Agents. It has been gotten up with great care, and may be relied on as COMPLETE and ACCURATE; making one of the most THRILLINGLY INTERESTING books published. It contains Illustrations of ALL THE GREAT BATTLES AND SIEGES, making a large 12mo. volume of about 450 pages, and is sold at the low price of $1.25.</p>
               <p>We make the largest discounts to Agents. Send for our list of books, including some of the most popular and salable books published.</p>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>NOTICES OF THE PRESS.</head>
                  <p>The tragical events of the war will not only be read with thrilling interest, but the history of India will be studied by all classes. The work before us is well calculated to impart the knowledge of India and the Rebellion, which is sought by those whose curiosity has been excited, as it gives, in one volume, a popular history of the country at different epochs.—<title>Rural New Yorker</title>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="i"/>Agents wanted in every part of the United States and British Provinces. Address,</p>
                  <p>J. W. BRADLEY, Publisher, 48 N. Fourth street, Philadelphia.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <pb n="106 (Advertisement) -107 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC5795-00000055"/>
               <head>THE Battle fields of the Revolution.</head>
               <p>COMPRISING Descriptions of the different Battles, Sieges, and other events of the War of Independence, interspersed with Characteristic Anecdotes.</p>
               <p>Illustrated with numerous Engravings, and a fine Mezzotint Frontispiece. By THOMAS Y. RHOADS. Large 12mo., 336 pages. Price $1.00.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>CONTENTS.</head>
                  <item>The Sergeant and the Indians.</item>
                  <item>Burning of the Gaspee.</item>
                  <item>The Great Tea Riot.</item>
                  <item>The First Prayer in Congress.</item>
                  <item>Battle of Lexington.</item>
                  <item>Fight at Concord Bridge.</item>
                  <item>Capture of Ticonderoga.</item>
                  <item>Battle of Bunker's Hill.</item>
                  <item>Attack on Quebec.</item>
                  <item>Attack on Sullivan's Island.</item>
                  <item>The Declaration of Independence.</item>
                  <item>Firmness of Washington.</item>
                  <item>Capture of General Lee.</item>
                  <item>Capture of General Prescott.</item>
                  <item>General Prescott Whipped.</item>
                  <item>Battle of Trenton.</item>
                  <item>Battle of Princeton.</item>
                  <item>General La Fayette.</item>
                  <item>Battle of Brandywine.</item>
                  <item>Battle of Germantown.</item>
                  <item>Battle of Red Bank</item>
                  <item>Burgoyne's Invasion—Battle of Bennington.</item>
                  <item>Heroic Exploit of Peter Francisco.</item>
                  <item>Andrew Jackson.</item>
                  <item>Siege of Yorktown—Surrender of Cornwallis.</item>
                  <item>George Rogers Clarke.</item>
                  <item>Death of Captain Biddle.</item>
                  <item>Patriotism of Mother Bailey.</item>
                  <item>The Dutchman and the Rake.</item>
                  <item>Simon Kenton.</item>
                  <item>The Murder of Miss McCrea.</item>
                  <item>Massacre at Wyoming.</item>
                  <item>Treason of Arnold.</item>
                  <item>Patriotism of Elizabeth Zane.</item>
                  <item>Stony Point.</item>
                  <item>John Paul Jones.</item>
                  <item>Battle of King's Mountain.</item>
                  <item>Burning of Colonel Crawford.</item>
                  <item>Battle of the Cowpens.</item>
                  <item>Baron Steuben.</item>
                  <item>Mrs. Bozarth.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="i"/>Agents wanted in every part of the United States and British Provinces. Address,</p>
               <p>J. W. BRADLEY, Publisher, 48 N. Fourth street, Philadelphia.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head type="sub">THE MASTER-SPIRIT OF THE AGE.</head>
               <head>THE PUBLIC AND PRIVATE HISTORY OF NAPOLEON THE THIRD:</head>
               <p>WITH Biographical Notices of his most Distinguished Ministers, Generals, and Favorites.</p>
               <p>BY SAMUEL M. SMUCKER, A.M.</p>
               <p>Author of "Court and Reign of Catharine II.," "Nicholas I., Emperor of Russia," "Life of Alexander Hamilton," etc., etc.</p>
               <p>This interesting and valuable work is embellished with splendid Steel Plates, done by Mr. Sartain in his best style, including</p>
               <p>The Emperor, The Empress, Queen Hortense, and the Countess Castiglione.</p>
               <p>The work contains over 400 pages of closely-printed matter, and has been prepared with much care from authentic sources, and furnishes a large amount of information in reference to the Emperor of the French, HIS COURT, AND FRANCE UNDER THE SECOND EMPIRE which is entirely new to American readers. This work is the only one, either in English or French, which boldly and accurately describes The Real Character, The Private Morals, The Public Policy, of Napoleon the Third.</p>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>NOTICES OF THE PRESS.</head>
                  <p>This is a very valuable contribution to the literature of the present time. An extraordinary amount of information is given in the present volume. Like all the other works of the graceful and fluent author, it must command a very large popularity.—<title>Philad'a Mercury</title>.</p>
                  <p>It is the most complete biography of the French Emperor yet published, and brings events down to the present time.—<title>Baltimore Republican</title>.</p>
                  <p>This book is well written, printed on good paper, is neatly bound, good size, and sold cheap.—<title>Valley Spirit, Chambersburg</title>.</p>
                  <p>This work does full and ample justice to the subject. It is a production of superior ability. Mr. Smucker is an accomplished writer. He is learned and accurate in his researches, and his style is polished and scholarlike, so that he produces works of sterling value and permanent interest.—<title>Phil. Dis</title>.</p>
                  <p>Copies sent by mail on receipt of the price, $1.25.</p>
                  <p>J. W. BRADLEY, Publisher, 48 N. Fourth street, Philadelphia.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <pb n="108-109 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC5795-00000056"/>
               <head type="sub">A BOOK OF STARTLING INTEREST.</head>
               <head>THE ANGEL AND THE DEMON.</head>
               <head type="sub">BY T. S. ARTHUR.</head>
               <p>A handsome 12mo. volume. Price $1.00.</p>
               <p>In this exciting story Mr. Arthur has taken hold of the reader's attention, with a more than usually vigorous grasp, and keeps him absorbed to the end of the volume. The book is one of STARTLING INTEREST. Its lessons should be in the HEART OF EVERY MOTHER. Onward with a power of demonstration that makes conviction a necessity, the author sweeps through his subject, fascinating at every step. In the union of THRILLING DRAMATIC INCIDENT, with moral lessons of the highest importance, this volume stands pre-eminent among the author's many line productions.</p>
               <div type="advertisement">
                  <head>NOTICES OF THE PRESS.</head>
                  <p>A story of much power, imbued with that excellent moral and religious spirit which pervades all his writings."—<title>N. Y. Chronicle</title>.</p>
                  <p>This volume is among his best productions, and worthy of a place on every centre-table."—<title>Clarton, Pa., Banner</title>.</p>
                  <p>This is a most fascinating book, one which the reader will find it quite hard to lay aside without reading to the last page.—<title>Albany, N. Y., Journal and Courier</title>.</p>
                  <p>Copies sent by Mail on receipt of the Price, $1.00.</p>
                  <p>AGENTS and CANVASSERS wanted in all parts of the United States for this and other Popular and Saleable Books, to whom the largest commission will be paid. Send for our Catalogue and particulars of Agency.</p>
                  <p>J. W. BRADLEY, PUBLISHER, 48 N. Fourth Street, Philadelphia.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <pb n="110 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC5795-00000057"/>
               <head>WE PUBLISH MOST OF T. S. ARTHUR'S NEW BOOKS.</head>
               <p>ALSO WORKS OF HISTORY, BIOGRAPHY, &amp;C. FOR WHICH WE WANT AGENTS AND CANVASSERS IN ALL PARTS OF THE UNITED STATES AND CANADA. OUR LIST IS SENT FREE.</p>
               <p>J. W. BRADLEY, Publisher, 48 North Fourth Street.</p>
               <p>PHILADELPHIA.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>