<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC5923">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Sandwiches </title>
            <author >Ward, Artemus, (1834-1867)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC5923</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >Sandwiches</title>
                  <author >Ward, Artemus, (1834-1867)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >[30] p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >G.W. Carleton</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[New York?] </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1870">1870</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2000-11-08">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="Pacific Data Conversion Corp." when="2002-01-02">Finished transcription and SGML encoding</change>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-04-22">Finished TEI conversion and final editing</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <front> 
         <titlePage xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="cover"> 
            <pb  n=" (Cover) " xml:id="VAC5923-00000001"/> 
            <docTitle> 
               <titlePart>Sandwiches</titlePart> 
            </docTitle> 
            <byline >By <docAuthor xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Artemus Ward.</docAuthor>
            </byline> 
            <docImprint>
               <publisher >CARLETOM PUBLISHER.</publisher> 
               <pubPlace>NEW YORK.</pubPlace>
            </docImprint> 
            <docEdition>25 Cts.</docEdition> 
            <pb  n="[2] (TitlePage) -3" xml:id="VAC5923-00000002"/> 
            <docEdition>Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1870, by G. W. CARLETON, in the Clerk's Office of the District Court for the  Southern District of New York.</docEdition> 
         </titlePage> 
      </front> 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Sandwiches</head> 
            <head>SANDWICHES.</head> 
            <div type="letter"> 
               <head>ONE OF MR. WARD'S BUSINESS LETTERS.</head> 
               <opener>
                  <salute>To the Editor of the -</salute>
               </opener> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>"As genial a feller as we ever met."</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <div type="letter"> 
                  <p>SIR-I'm movin along-slowly along-down tords your place. I want you should rite me a letter, sayin how is the show bizniss in your place. My show at present consists of three moral Bares, a Kangaroo (a amoozin little Raskal-t'would make you larf yerself to deth to see the little cuss jump up and squeal) wax figgers of G. Washington Gen. Tayler John Bunyan Capt. Kidd and Dr. Webster in the act of killin Dr. Parkman, besides several miscellanyus moral wax statoots of celebrated piruts &amp; murderers, &amp;c., ekalled by few &amp; exceld by none. Now Mr. Editor, scratch orf a few lines saying how is the show bizniss down to your place. I shall hav my hanbills dun at your offiss. Depend upon it. I want you should git my hanbills up in flamin stile. Also git up a tremenjus excitemunt in yr. paper 'bowt my onparaleld Show. We must fetch the public sumhow. We must wurk on their feelins. Cum the moral on 'em strong. If it's a temprance community tell 'em I sined the pledge fifteen minits arter Ise born, but on the contery of your peple take their tods, say Mister Ward is as Jenial a feller as we ever met, full of conwiviality, &amp; the life an sole of the Soshul Bored. Take, don't you? If you say anythin abowt my show say my snaiks is at harmliss as the new born Babe. What a interestin study it is to see a zewological animil like a snaik under perfeck subjecshun! My Kangaroo is the most larfable little cuss I ever saw. All for 15 cents. I am anxyus to skewer your infloounce. I repeet in regard to them hanbills that I shall git 'em struck arf up to your printing office. My perlitercal sentiments agree with yourn exackly. I know thay do, becawz I never saw a man whoos didn't.</p> 
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Respectively yures</salute> 
                     <signed>A. WARD.</signed>
                  </closer> 
               </div> 
               <div type="letter"> 
                  <p>P. S.-You scratch my back &amp; He scratch your back.</p> 
               </div> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <head>AMONG THE SHAKERS.</head> 
               <p>The Shakers is the strangest religious sex I ever met. I'd hearn tell of 'em and I'd seen 'em, with their broad brim'd hats and long wastid coats; but I'd never cum into immejit contack with 'em, and I'd sot 'em down as lackin intelleck, as I'd never seen 'em to my Show-leastways, if they cum they was disgised in white peple's close, so I didn't know 'em.</p> 
               <p>But in the Spring of 18-, I got swampt in the exterior of New York State, one dark and stormy night, when the winds Blue pityusly, and I was forced to tie up with the Shakers.</p> 
               <p>I was toilin threw the mud, when in the dim vister of the futer I obsarved the gleams of a taller candle. Tiein a hornet's nest to my off hoss's tail to kinder encourage him, I soon reached the place, I knockt at the door, which it was opened unto me by a tall, slick-faced, solum lookin individooal, who turn'd out to be a Elder.</p> 
               <p>"Mr. Shaker," sed I, "you see before you a Babe in the Woods, so to speak, and he axes shelter of you."</p> 
               <p>"Yay," sed the Shaker, and he led the way into the house, another Shaker bein sent to put my hosses and waggin under kiver.</p> 
               <p>A solum female, lookin sumwhat like a last year's bean-pole stuck into a long-meal bag, cum in and axed me was I athurst and did I hunger? to which I urbanely anserd "a few." She went orf and I endeverd to open a conversashun with the old man.</p> 
               <p>"Elder, I spect?" sed I.</p> 
               <p>"Yay," he sed.</p> 
               <p>"Helth's good, I reckon?"</p> 
               <p>"Yay."</p> 
               <p>"What's the wages of a Elder, when he understans his bizness-or do you devote your sarvices gratooitus?"</p> 
               <p>"Yay."</p> 
               <p>"Stormy night, sir,"</p> 
               <p>"Yay."</p> 
               <p>"If the storm continners there'll be a mess underfoot, hay?"</p> 
               <p>"Yay."</p> 
               <p>"It's onpleasant where there's a mess underfoot?"</p> 
               <p>"Yay."</p> 
               <p>"If I may be so bold, kind sir, what's the price of that pecooler kind of weskit you wear, incloodin trimmins?"</p> 
               <p>"Yay!"</p> 
               <p>I pawsd a minit, and then, thinkin I'd be faseshus with him and see how that would go, I slapt him on the shoulder, bust into a harty larf, and told him that as a <emph>yayer</emph> he had no livin ekal.</p> 
               <p>He jumpt up as if Bilin water had bin squirted into his ears, groaned, rolled his eyes up tords the sealin and sed, "You're a man of sin!" He then walkt out of the room.</p> 
               <p>Jest then the female in the meal bag stuck her hed into the room and statid that refreshments awaited the weary travler, and I sed if it was vittles she ment the weary travler was agreeable, and I follered her into the next room.</p> 
               <p>I sot down to the table and the female in the meal bag pored out sum tea. She sed nothin, and for five minutes the only live thing in that room was a old wooden clock, which tickt in a subdood and bashful manner in the corner. This dethly stillness made me oneasy, and I determined to talk to the female or bust. So sez I, "Marrige is agin your rules, I bleeve, marm?"</p> 
               <p>"Yay."</p> 
               <p>"The sexes liv strickly apart, I spect?"</p> 
               <p>"Yay."</p> 
               <p>"It's kinder singler," sez I, putting on my most sweetest look and speakin in a winnin voice, "that so fair a made as thou never got hitched to some likely feller." [N. B.-She was upaids of 40 and homely as a stump fence, but I thawt I'd tickil her.]</p> 
               <p>"I don't like men!" she sed, very short.</p> 
               <p>"Wall, I dunno," sez I, "they're a rayther important part of the populashun. I don't scacely see how we could git along without 'em."</p> 
               <p>"Us poor wimin folks would git along a grate deal better if there was no men!"</p> 
               <p>"You'll excoos me, marm, but I don't think that air would work. It wouldn't be regler."</p> 
               <p>"I'm fraid of men!" she sed.</p> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <p>"That's onnecessary, marm. <emph>You</emph> ain't in no danger. Don't fret yourself on that pint."</p> 
               <p>"Here we're shot out from the sinful world. Here all is peas. Here we air brothers and sisters. We don't marry and consekently we hav no domestic difficulties. Husbans don't abooze their wives-wives don't worrit their husbans. There's no children here to worrit us. Nothin to worrit us here. No wicked matrimony here. Would thow like to be a Shaker?"</p> 
               <p>"No," sez I, "it ain't my stile."</p> 
               <p>I had now histed in as big a load of pervishuns as I could carry comfortable, and, leanin back in my cheer, commenst pickin my teeth with a fork. The female went out, leavin me all alone with the clock. I hadn't sot that long before the Elder poked his hed in at the door. "You're a man of sin!" he sed, and groaned and went away.</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>Artemus among the Shakers. "Yay," they sed, and I yay'd.</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>Direckly thar cum in two young Shakeresses, as putty and slick lookin gals as I ever met. It is troo they was drest in meal bags like the old one I'd met previsly, and their shiny, silky har was hid from sight by long white caps, sich as I spose female Josts wear; but their eyes sparkled like diminds, their checks was like roses, and they was charmin enuf to make a man throw stuns at his granmother, if they axed him. They commenst clearin away the dishes, castin shy glances at me all the time. I got excited. I forgot Betsy Jane in my rapter, and sez I, -</p> 
               <p>"My pretty dears, how air you?"</p> 
               <p>"We air well," they solumly said.</p> 
               <p>"What's the old man?" sed I, in a soft voice.</p> 
               <p>"Of whom dost thou speak-Brother Uriah?"</p> 
               <p>"I mean the gay and festive cuss who calls me a man of sin. Shouldn't wonder if his name was Uriah."</p> 
               <p>"He has retired."</p> 
               <p>"Wall, my pretty dears," sez I, "let's have some fun. Let's play pass in the corner. What say?"</p> 
               <p>"Air you a Shaker, sir?" they axed.</p> 
               <p>"Wall, my pretty dears, I haven't arrayed my proud form in a long weskit yit, but if they was all like you perhaps I'd jine 'em. As it is, I'm a Shaker pro-temporary."</p> 
               <p>They was full of fun. I seed that at fust, only they was a little skeery. I tawt 'em Puss in the corner and sich like plase, and we had a nice time, keepin quiet of course so the old man shouldn't hear. When we broke up, sez I, "My pretty dears, ear I go you hav no objections, hav you, to a innersent kiss at partin?"</p> 
               <p>"Yay," they sed, and I <emph>yay'd</emph>.</p> 
               <p>I went up stairs to bed. I spose I'd bin snoozin half a hour when I was woke up by a noise at the door. I sot up in bed, leanin on my elbers and rubbin my eyes, and I saw the following picter: The Elder stood in the doorway, with a taller candle in his hand. He hadn't no wearin appeerel on except his night close, which fluttered in the breeze like a Seseshun flag. He sed, "You're a man of sin!" then groaned and went away.</p> 
               <p>I went to sleep agin, and drempt of runnin orf with the pretty little Shakeresses, mounted on my Californy Bar. I thawt the Bar insisted on steerin strate for my dooryard in Baldinsville, and that Betsy Jane cum out and giv us a warm recepshun with a panful of Bilin water. I was woke up arly by the Elder. He sed refreshments was reddy for me down stairs. Then sayin I was a man of sin, he went groanin away.</p> 
               <p>As I was goin threw the entry to the room where the vittles was, I cum across the Elder and the old female I'd met the night before, and what d'ye spose they was up to? Huggin and kissin like young lovers in their gushingist state. Sez I, "My Shaker frends, I reckon you'd better suspend the rules, and git marrid!"</p> 
               <p>"You must excoos Brother Uriah," sed the female; "he's subjeck to fits and hain't got no command over hisself when he's into 'em."</p> 
               <p>"Sartinly sez," I, "I've bin took that way myself frequent."</p> 
               <p>"You're a man of sin!" sed the Elder.</p> 
               <p>After breakfust my little Shaker frends cum in agin to clear away the dishes.</p> 
               <p>"My pretty dears," sez I, "shall we <emph>yay</emph> agin?</p> 
               <p>"Nay," they sed, and I <emph>nay'd</emph>.</p> 
               <p>The Shakers axed me to go to their meetin, as they was to hav sarvices that morning, so I put on a clean biled rag and went. The meetin house was as neat as a pin. The floor was white as chalk and smooth as glass. The Shakers was all on hand, in clean weskits and meal bags, ranged on the floor like milingtery companies, the mails on one side of the room and the females on tother. They commenst clappin their hands and singing and dancin. They danced kinder slow at fust, but as they got warmed up they shaved it down very brisk, I tell you. Elder Uriah, in particler, exhiberted a right smart chance of spryness in his legs, considerin his time of life, and as he cum a dubble shuffle near where I sot, I rewarded him with a approvin smile and sed: "Hunky boy! Go it, my gay and festiv cuss!"</p> 
               <p>The Shakers then danced and sung agin, and arter they was threw, one of 'em axed me what I thawt of it.</p> 
               <p>Sez I, "What duz it siggerfy?"</p> 
               <p>"What?" sez he.</p> 
               <p>"Why this jumpin up and singin! This long weskit bizniss, and this anty-matrimony idee? My frends, you air neat and tidy. Your lands is flowin with milk and honey. Your brooms is fine, and your apple sass is honest. When a man buys a kag of apple sass of you he don't find a grate many shavins under a few layers of sass-a little Game I'm sorry to say sum of my New Englan ancesters used to practiss. Your gardng seeds is fine, and if I should sow 'em on the rock of Gibralter probly I should raise a good mess of garding sass. You air honest in your dealins. You air quiet and dont distarb nobody. For all this I givs you credit. But your religion is small pertaters, I must say. You mope away your lives here in single retchidness, and as you air all by yourselves nothing ever conflicks with your pecooler idees, except when Human Nater busts out among you, as I understan she sumtimes do. [I giv Uriah a sly wink here, which made the old feller squirm like a speared Eel.] You wear long weskits and long faces, and lead a gloomy life indeed. No children's prattle is ever hearn around your harthstuns - you air in a dreary fog all the time, and you treat the jolly-sunshine of life as tho' it was a thief, driven it from your doors by them weskits, and meal bags, and pecooler noshuns of yourn. The gals among you, sum of which air as slick pieces of caliker as I ever sot eyes on, air syin to place their heds agin weskits which kiver honest, manly harts, while you old heds fool yerselves with the idee that they air fulfillin their mishun here, and air contented. Here you air, all pend up by yerselves, talkin about the sins of a world you don't know nothin of, Meanwhile said world continners to resolve round on her own axeltree once in every 24 hours, subjeck to the Constitution of the United States, and is a very plesant place of residence. It's a unnatral, on-reasonable and dismal life you're leadin here. So it strikes me. My Shaker frends, I now bid you a welcome adoo."</p> 
               <p>"A base exhibiter of depraved monkeys and onprincipled wax works!" sed Uriah.</p> 
               <p>"Hello, Uriah," sez I, "I'd most forgot you. Wall, look out for them fits of yourn, and don't catch cold and die in the flour of your youth and beauty." And I resoomed my jerney.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC5923-00000003"/> 
               <head>THE CRISIS.</head> 
               <note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WRIGHT2-0396-NOTE001" place="inline"
                     n="*">[This Oration was delivered before the commencement of the war.]</note> 
               <p>On returnin to my humsted in Baldinsville, Injianny, resuntly, my feller sitterzens extended a invite for me to norate to 'em on the Krysis. I excepted &amp; on larst Toosday nite I peared be4 a C of upturned faces in the Red Skool House. I spoke nearly as follers:</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>"Shall the Star Spangled Banner be cut up into dish-cloths?"</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>Baldinsvillins: <unclear>Hearto4</unclear>, as I hav numerously obsarved, I have abstrained from having any sentimunts or principles, my pollertics, like my religion, bein of a exceedin accommodatin character. But the fack can't be no longer disgised that a Krysis is onto us, &amp; I feel it's my dooty to accept your invite for one consecutive nite only. I spose the inflammertory individooals who assisted in projucing this Krysis know what good she will do, but I ain't 'shamed to state that I don't, scacely. But the Krysis is hear. She's bin hear for sevral weeks, &amp; Goodness nose how long she'll stay. But I venter to assert that she's rippin things. She's knockt trade into a cockt up hat and chaned Bizness of all kinds tighter nor I ever chaned any of my livin wild Beests. Alow me to hear dygress &amp; stait that my Beests at presnt is as harmless as the new-born Babe. Ladys &amp; gentlemen needn't hav no fears on that pint. To resoom- Altho I can't exactly see what good this Krysis can do, I can very quick say what the origernal cawz of her is. The origernal cawz is Our Afrikan Brother. I was into BARNIM'S Moozeum down to New York the other day &amp; saw that exsentric Etheopian, the What Is It. Sez I, "Mister What Is It, you folks air raisin thunder with this grate country. You're gettin to be ruther more numeris than interestin. It is a pity you coodent go orf sumwhares by yourselves, &amp; be a nation of What Is Its, tho' if you'll excoose me, I shoulden't care about marryin among you. No  dowt you're exceedin <unclear>charmin to </unclear>, but your stile of luvliness isn't adupted to this cold climit.' He larfed into my face which rather Riled me, as I had been perfeckly virtoous and respectable in my observashuns. So sez I, turnin a leetle red in the face I spect, "Do you hav the unblushin impoodents to say you folks haven't raised a big mess of thunder in this brite land, Mister What Is It?" He larfed agin, wusser nor be4, whareupon I up and sez, "Go home, Sir, to Afriky's burnin shores &amp; talk all the other What Is Its along with you. Don't think we can't spair your interestin picters. You What Is Its air on the pint of smashin up the gratest Guv'ment ever erected by man, &amp; you actooally hav the owdassity to larf about it. Go home, you low cuss!"</p> 
               <p>I was workt up to a high pitch, &amp; I proceeded to a Restorator &amp; cooled orf with some little fishes biled in ile-I b'leeve thay call 'em sardeens.</p> 
               <p>Feller Sitterzums, the Afrikan may be Our Brother. Sevral hily respectyble gentlemen, and sum talentid females tell us so, &amp; fur argyment's sake I might be injooced to grant it, tho' I don't beleeve it myself. But the Afrikan isn't our sister &amp; our wife &amp; our uncle. He isn't sevral of our brothers &amp; all our fust wife's relashuns. He isn't our grandfather, and our grate-grandfather, and our Aunt in the country. Scacely. &amp; yit numeris persons would have us think so. It's troo he runs Congress &amp; sevral other public grosserys, but then he ain't everybody &amp; everybody else likewise. [Notiss to bizness man of "Vanity Fair:" Extry charg fur this larst remark. It's a goak.-A. W.]</p> 
               <p>But we've got the Afrikan, or ruther he's got us, &amp; now what air we going to do about it? He's a orful noosanse. Praps he isn't to blame fur it. Praps he was creatid fur sum wise purpuss, like the measles and New Englan Rum, but it's mity hard to see it. At any rate he's no good here, &amp; as I statid to Mister What Is It, it's a pity he cooden't go orf sumwhares quietly by hisself, whare he cood wear red weskits &amp; speckled, neckties, and gratterfy his ambishun in varis interestin wase, without havin a eternal fuss kickt up about him.</p> 
               <p>Praps I'm bearin down too hard upon Cuffy Cum to think on it, I am. He wooden't be sich a infernal noosanse if white peple would let him alone. He mite indeed be interestin. And now I think of it, why can't the white peple let him alone. What's the good of continnerly stirrin him up with a ten-foot pole? He isn't the sweetest kind of Perfoomery when in a natral stait.</p> 
               <p>Feller Sitterzens, the Union's in danger. The black devil Disunion is trooly here, starein us all squarely in the face! We must drive him back. Shall we make a 2nd Mexico of ourselves? Shall we sell our birthrite for a mess of potash? Shall one brother put the knife to the throat of anuther brother? Shall we mix our whisky with each others' blud? Shall the star spangled Banner be cut up into dishcloths? Standin here in this here Skoolhouse upon my nativ shore, so to speak, I anser-Nary!</p> 
               <p>Oh you fellers who air raisin this row, and who in the fust place started it, I'm shamed of you. The showman blushes for you, from his boots to the topmost hair upon his wenerable hed.</p> 
               <p>Feller Sitterzens, I am in the Sheer &amp; Yeller leaf. I shall peg out I of these dase. But while I do stop here I shall stay in the Union. I know not what the supervizers of Baldinsville may conclude to do, but for one, I shall stand by the Stars &amp; Stripes. Under no circumstances whatsomever will I sesesh. Let every Stait in the Union sesesh &amp; let Palmetter flags flote thicker nor shirts on Square Baxter's close line, still will I stick to the good old flag. The country may go to the devil, but I won't! And next Summer wheh I start out on my campane with my Show, wharever I pitch my little tent, you shall see floatin prowdly from the centre pole thereof the Amerikan Flag, with nary a star wiped out, nary a stripe less, but the same old flag that has allers flotid thare ! &amp; the price of admishun will be the same it allers was-15 cents, children half price.</p> 
               <p>Feller Sitterzens, I am dun. Accordinly, havin wiped my massiv brough with Betsy Jane's bandaner, I squatted.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <p>In the Ortum of 18- my frend, the editor of the Baldinsville <title>Bugle</title> was obleged to leave perfeshernal dooties &amp; dig his taters, &amp; he axed me to edit for him doorin his absence. It didn't take me a grate while to slash out copy enuff from the xchanges for one issoo, and I thawt I'd ride up to the next town on a little Jaunt, to rest my Branes which had bin severely rackt by my mental efforts. (This is sorter Ironical.) So I went over to the Rale Rood and axed the Sooprintendent for a pars.</p> 
               <p>"<emph>You</emph> a editer?" he axed, evijently on the pint of snickerin.</p> 
               <p>"Yes Sir," sez I, "don't I look poor enuff?"</p> 
               <p>"Just about," sed he, "but our Road can't pars you."</p> 
               <p>"Can't, hay?"</p> 
               <p>"No Sir-it can't."</p> 
               <p>"Becauz," sez I, lookin him full in the face with a Eagle eye "<emph>it goes so darned slow it can't pars anybody!</emph>" Methinks I had him thar. It's the slowest Rale Road in the West. With a mortified air, he told me to git out of his offiss. I pittid him and went.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <head>THE WAR FEVER IN BALDINSVILLE.</head> 
               <p>As soon as I'd recooperated my physikil system, I went over into the village. The peasantry was glad to see me. The skoolmaster sed it was cheerin to see that gigantic intelleck among 'em onct more. That's what he called me. I like the skoolmaster, and allers send him tobacker when I'm off on a travelin campane. Besides, he is a very sensible man. Such men must be encouraged.</p> 
               <p>They don't git news very fast in Baldinsville, as nothing but a plank road runs in there twice a week, and that's very much out of repair. So my nabers wasn't much posted up in regard to the wars. 'Squire Baxter sed he'd voted the dimicratic ticket for going on forty year, and the war was a dam black republican lie. Jo. Stackpole, who kills hogs for the 'Squire, and has got a powerful muscle into his arms, sed he'd bet $5 he could lick the Crisis in a fair stand-up fight, if he wouldn't draw a knife on him. So it went-sum was for war, and sum was for peace. The skoolmaster, however, sed the Slave Oligarky must cower at the feet of the North ere a year had flowed by, or pass over his dead corpse. "Esto perpetua!" he added. "And sine qua non also!" sed I, sternly, wishing to make a impression onto the villagers. "Requiescat in pace!" sed the skoolmaster. "Too troo, too troo!" I anserd, "it's a scauderlus fact!"</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>Joc Stackpole says he can lick the Seceshers in a fair stand-up fight.</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>The newspapers got along at last, chock full of war, and the patriotic fever fairly bust out in Baldinsville. 'Squire Baxter sed he didn't b'lieve in Coercion, not one of 'em, and could prove by a file of <title>Eagles of Liberty</title> in his garrit, that it was all a Whig he, got up to raise the price of whisky, and destroy our other liberties. But the old 'Squire got putty riley, when he heard how the rebels was cuttin up, and he sed he reckoned he should skour up his old muskit, and do a little square fitin for the old Flag, which had allers bin on the ticket <emph>he'd</emph> voted, and he <unclear/> old to Bolt now. The 'Squire is all right at heart, but it takes longer for him to fill his venerable Biler with steam than it used to when he was young and frisky. As I previously informed you, I am Captin of the Baldinsville Company. I riz gradooally but majestically from drummer's Secretary to my present position. But I found the ranks wasn't full by no means, and commenced for to recroot. Havin notist a gineral desire on the part of young men who are into the Crisis to wear eppylits, I detarmined to have my company composed excloosively of officers, everybody to rank as Brigadeer-Gineral. The follerin was among the varis questions which I put to recroots:</p> 
               <p>"Do you know a masked battery from a hunk of gingerbread?"</p> 
               <p>"Do you know a eppylit from a piece of chalk?"</p> 
               <p>"If I trust you with a real gun, how many men of your own company do you speck you can manage to kill during the war?"</p> 
               <p>"Hav you ever heard of Gineral Price of Missouri, and can you avoid simler accidents in case of a battle?"</p> 
               <p>"Hav you ever had the measles, and, if so, how many?"</p> 
               <p>"How air you now?"</p> 
               <p>"Show me your tongue," &amp;c., &amp;c. Sum of the questions was sarcusstical.</p> 
               <p>The company filled up rapid, and last Sunday we went to the meetin house in full uniform. I had a seris time gittin into my military harness, as it was bilt for me many years ago; but I finally got inside of it, tho' it fitted me putty clost. Howsever, onct into it, I lookt fine-in fact, aw-inspirin. "Do you know me, Mrs. Ward?" sed I, walkin into the kitchen.</p> 
               <p>"Know you, you old fool? Of course I do."</p> 
               <p>I saw at once she did.</p> 
               <p>I started for the meetin house, and I'm afraid I tried to walk too strate, for I cum very near fallin over backards; and in attemptin to recover myself my sword got mixed up with my legs, and I fell in among a choice collection of young ladies, who was standin near the church door a-seein the sojer boys come up. My cockt hat fell off, and sumhow my coat tales got twisted round my neck. The young ladies put their handkerchers to their mouths and remarked, "To he," while my ancient female single friend, Sary Peasley, bust out into a loud larf. She excersised her mouth so vilently that her new false teeth fell out onto the ground.</p> 
               <p>"Miss Peaseley," sed I, gittin up and dustin myself, "you must be more careful with them store teeth of yourn, or you'll have to gum it agin!"</p> 
               <p>Methinks I had her.</p> 
               <p>I'd bin to work hard all the week, and I felt rather snoozy. I'm 'fraid I did git half asleep, for on hearin the minister ask, "Why was man made to mourn?" I sed, "I giv it up," havin a vague idee that it was a condrum. It was a onfortnit remark, for the whole meetin house lookt at me with mingled surprise and indignation. I was about risin to a pint of order, when it suddenly occurd to me whare I was, and I kept my seat, blushing like the red, red-rose-so to speak.</p> 
               <p>The next mornin I rose with the lark (N. B.-I don't sleep with the lark, tho'. A goak.)</p> 
               <p>My little dawter was execootin ballids, accompanyin herself with the Akordeon, and she wished me to linger and hear her sing. "Hark I hear a angel singin, an angel now is onto the wing."</p> 
               <p>"Let him fly, my child!" said I, abucklin on my armer, "I must forth to my Biz."</p> 
               <p>We air progressin pretty well with our drill. As all air commandin offissers, there aint no jealusy; and as we air all exceeding smart, 'taint worth while to try to outstrip each other. The idee of a company composed excloosively of Commanders-in-Chiefs, orrigernated, I spose I skurcely need say, in these Brane. Considered <emph>as</emph> a idee, I flatter myself it is putty hefty. We've got all the tackticks at our tongs' ends, but what we particly excel in is restin muskits.</p> 
               <p>We can rest muskits with anybody.</p> 
               <p>Our corpse will do its dooty. We go to the aid of Columby-we fight for the stars!</p> 
               <p>We'll be chopt into sassige meat before we'll exhibit our coat-tales to the foe.</p> 
               <p>We'll fight till there's nothin left of us but our little toes, and even they shall defiantly wiggle!</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <p>The propriety of introducing a sad story like the following, in a book intended to be rather cheerful in its character, may be questioned; but is so beautifully illustrates the firmness of woman when grief and despair <unclear>have</unclear> taken possession of "the chambers of her heart," that we cannot <unclear>refrain</unclear> from relating it: Lucy M- loved with all the ardor of a fond and faithful wife, and when he upon whom she had so confidingly <unclear>leaned</unclear> was stolen from her by death, her friends and companions said Lucy could go mad. Ah, how little they knew her!</p> 
               <p>Gazing for the last time upon the clay-cold features of her departed husband, this young widow-beautiful even in her grief: so ethereal to look upon, and yet so firm!-looking for the last time upon the dear, familiar face, now cold and still in death-Oh, looking for the last, last time-she rapidly put on her bonnet, and thus addressed the sobbing gentlemen who were to act as pall-bearers: "You pall-bearers just go into the buttery and get some rum, and we'll start this man right along!"</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC5923-00000004"/> 
               <head>A VISIT TO BRIGHAM YOUNG.</head> 
               <p>It is now goin on 2 (too) yeres, as I very well remember, since I crossed the Planes for Kaliforny, the Brite land of Jold. While crossin the Planes all so bold I fell in with sum noble red men of the forest (N. B. This is rote Sarcasticul. Injins is Pizin, whar ever found,) which thay Sed I was their Brother, &amp; wantid for to smoke the Calomel of Peace with me. Thay then stole my jerkt beef, blankits, etsettery, skalpt my orgin grinder &amp; scooted with a Wild Hoop. Durin the Cheaf's techin speech he sed he shood meet me in the Happy Huntin Grounds. If he duz thar will be a fite. But enuff of this ere. <hi rend="i"/>Reven Noose Muttons, as our skoolmaster, who has got Talent into him, cussycally obsarve.</p> 
               <p>I arrove at Salt Lake in doo time. At Camp Scott there was a lot of U. S. sojers, hosstensibly sent out thare to smash the mormons but really to eat Salt vittles &amp; play poker &amp; other beautiful but sumwhat onsartin games. I got acquainted with sum of the officers. Thay lookt putty scrumpshus in their Bloo coats with brass buttings onto um &amp; ware very talented drinkers, but so fur as fitin is consarned I'd willingly put my wax figgers agin the hull party.</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>"Oh stay, Sir, stay!" said a tawl gawnt femasle.</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>My desire was to exhibit my grate show in Salt Lake City, so I called on Brigham Yung, the grate mogull amung the mormins, and axed his permishun to pitch my tent and onfull my banner to the jentle breezis. He lookt at me in a austeer manner for a few minits, and sed:</p> 
               <p>"Do you bleeve in Solomon, Saint Paul, the immaculateness of the Mormin Church and the Latter-day Revelashuns?"</p> 
               <p>Sez I, "I'm on it!" I make it a pint to git along plesunt, tho I didn't know what under the Son the old feller was drivin at. He sed I mite show.</p> 
               <p>"You air a marrid man, Mister Yung, I bleeve?" sez I, preparin to rite him sum free parsis.</p> 
               <p>"I hev eighty wives, Mister Ward. I sertinly am married."</p> 
               <p>"How do you like it as far as you hev got?" sed I.</p> 
               <p>He sed "middlin," and axed me wouldn't I like to see his famerly, to which I replide that I wouldn't mind minglin with the fair Seek &amp; Barskin in the winnin smiles of his interestin wives. He accordinly tuk me to his Scareum. The house is powerful big &amp; in a exceedin large room was his wives &amp; children, which larst was squakin and hollerin enuff to take the roof rite orf the house. The wimin was of all sizes and ages. Sum was pretty &amp; sum was plane-sum was helthy and sum was on the Wayne-which is verses, tho sich was not my intentions, as I don't 'prove of puttin verses in Prose rittins, tho ef occashun requires I can Jerk a Poim ekal to any of them <title>Atlantic Munthly</title> fellers.</p> 
               <p>"My wives, Mister Ward," sed Yung.</p> 
               <p>"Your sarvant, marms," sed I as I sot down in a cheer which a redheded female brawt me.</p> 
               <p>"Besides these wives you see here, Mister Ward,' sed Yung, "I hav eighty more in varis parts of this consecrated land which air Sealed to me."</p> 
               <p>"Which?" sez I, gittin up &amp; starin at him.</p> 
               <p>"Sealed, Sir? sealed."</p> 
               <p>"Whare bowts?" sez I.</p> 
               <p>"I sed, Sir, that they was sealed!" He spoke in a tragedy voice.</p> 
               <p>"Will they probly continner on in that stile to any grate extent, Sir?" I axed.</p> 
               <p>"Sir," sed he turnin as red as a biled beet, "don't you know that the rules of our Church is that I, the Profit, may hev as meny wives as I wants?"</p> 
               <p>"Jes so," I sed. "You are old pie, ain't you?"</p> 
               <p>"Them as is Sealed to me-that is to say, to be mine when I wants um-air at present my sperretooul wives," said Mister Yung.</p> 
               <p>"Long may thay wave!" sez I, seein I shood git into a scrape ef I didn't look out.</p> 
               <p>In a privit conversashun with Brigham I learnt the follerin fax: It takes him six weeks to kiss his wives. He don't do it only onct a yere &amp; sez it is wuss nor cleanin house. He don't pretend to know his children thare is so many of um, tho they all know him. He sez about every child he meats calls him Par, &amp; he takes it for grantid it is so. His wives air very expensiv. Thay allers want suthin &amp; ef he don't buy it for um thay set the house in a uproar. He sez he don't have a minit's peace. His wives fite amung theirselves so much that he has bilt a fitin room for thare speshul benefit, &amp; when too of 'em get into a row he has em turnd loose into that place, whare the dispoot is settled accordin to the rules of the London prize ring. Sumtimes thay abooz hisself individooaly. Thay hev pulled the most of his hair out at the roots &amp; he wares meny a horrible scar upon his body, inflicted with mop-handles, broom sticks and sich. Occashunly they git mad &amp; scald him with bilin hot water. When he got eny waze cranky thay'd shut him up in a dark closit, previsly whippin him arter the stile of muthers when thare orfsprings git onruly. Sumtimes when he went in swimmin thay'd go to the banks of the Lake &amp; steal all his close, thereby compellin him to sneek home by a sircootius rowt, drest in the Skanderlus stile of the Greek Slaiv. "I find that the keers of a married life way hevy onto me," sed the Profit, "&amp; summes I wish I'd remaned singel." I left the Profit and startid for the tavern whare I put up to. On my way I was overtuk by a lurge krowd of Mormons, which they surroundid me &amp; statid that they were goin into the Show free.</p> 
               <p>"Wall," sez I, "ef I find a individooal who is goin round lettin folks into his show free, I'll let you know."</p> 
               <p>"We've had a Revelashun biddin us go into A. Ward's Show without payin nothin!" thay showtid.</p> 
               <p>"Yes," hollered a lot of femaile Mormonesses, ceasin me by the cote tales &amp; swingin me round very rapid, "we're all goin in free! So sez the Revelashun!"</p> 
               <p>"What's Old Revelashun got to do with my Show?" sez I, gittin putty rily. "Tell Mister Revelashun," sed I, "to mind his own bizness, subject only to the Konstitution of the Unitid States!"</p> 
               <p>"Oh now let us in," sed several femails, puttin thare arms rownd me in luvin stile. "Becum a Preest &amp; hav wives sealed to you."</p> 
               <p>"Not a Seal!" sez I, <unclear>startin</unclear> back in horror at the idee.</p> 
               <p>"Oh stay, Sir, stay," sed a tall gawnt femaile ore whoos hed 37 summirs must hev parsd, "stay &amp; I'll be your Jentle Gazelle."</p> 
               <p>"Not ef I know it you won't," sez I. "Awa you skanderlus femaile, awa! Go &amp; be a Nunnery!" That's what I sed, jes so.</p> 
               <p>"&amp; I," sed a fat chunky femaile, who must hev wade more than too hundred lbs., "I will be your sweet gidin Star!"</p> 
               <p>Sez I, "I'le bet two dollers and a half you won't!" Whare ear I may Rome He still be true 2 thee, Oh Betsy Jane! [N. B. Betsy Jane is my wife's Sir naime.)</p> 
               <p>"Wiltist thou not tarry hear in the Promist Land?"</p> 
               <p>"He see you all essenshally cussed be4 I wiltist!" roared I as mad as I cood be at thare infernul noncents. I girdid up my Lions and fled the Seen. I packt up my duds &amp; left Salt Lake, which is a 2nd Soddum &amp; Germorrer, inhabited by as theavin &amp; onprincipled a set of retchis as ever drew Breth in eny spot on the Globe.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <head>PICCOLOMINI.</head> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>Piccolomini in the Child of the Regiment.</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>GENTS-I arroved in Cleveland on Saturday P. M. from Baldinsville jest in time to fix myself up and put on a clean biled rag to attend Miss Picklehomony's grate musical sorry at the Melodeon. The krowds which pored into the hall augured well for the show bisnis, &amp; with cheerful sperrets I jined the euthoosiastic throng. I asked Mr. Strakhosh at the door if he parst the perfession, and he said not much he didn't, whereupon I bawt a preserved seat in the pit, &amp; obsarving to Mr. Strakhosh that he needn't put on so many French airs becawz he run with a big show, and that he'd better let his weskut out a few inches or perhaps he'd bust hisself some fine day, I went in and squatted down. It was a sad thawt to think that in all that vast aujience Scacely a Sole had the honor of my acquaintance. "&amp; this ere," sed I Bitturly, "is Fame! What sigerfy my wax figgers and livin wild beasts (which have no ekals) to these peple? What do thay care becawz a site of my Kangaroo is worth dubble the price of admission, and that my Snakes is as harmlis as the new born babe-all of which is strictly troo-?" I should have gone on ralein at Fortin and things sum more but jest then Signer Maccarony cum out and sung a hairey from sum opry or other. He had on his store close &amp; looked putty slick, I must say. Nobody didn't understand nothin abowt what he sed, and so they applaw-did him versiferusly. Then Signer Brignoly cum out and sung another hairey. He appeared to be in a pensiv Mood &amp; sung a Luv song I suppose, tho he may have been cussin the aujince all into a heep for aut I knewd. Then cum Mr. Maccarony agin &amp; Miss Picklehomony herself. Thay sang a Doit together.</p> 
               <p>Now you know, gents, that I don't admire opry music. But I like Miss Picklehomony's stile. I like her gate. She suits me. Thare has bin grater singers and there has bin more bootiful wimin, but no more fassinatin young female ever longed for a new gown or side to place her hed agin a vest pattern than Maria Picklehomony. Fassinatin peple is her best holt. She was born to make hash of men's buzzums &amp; other wimin mad becawz thay ain't Picklchomonies. Her face sparkles with amuzin cussedness &amp; about 200 (two hundred) little bit of funny devils air continually dancin champion jigs in her eyes, said eyes bem brite enuff to lite a pipe by. How I shood like to have little Maria out on my farm in Baldinsville, Injianny, whare she cood run in the tall grass, wrastle with the boys, cut up strong at parin bees, make up faces behind the minister's back, tie auction bills to the skoolmaster's coat-tales, set all the fellers crazy after her, &amp; holler &amp; kick up, &amp; go it just as much as she wanted to! But I diegress. Every time she cum canterin out I grew more and more delighted with her. When she bowed her hed I bowed mine. When she powtid her lips I powtid mine. When she larfed I larfed When she jerked her hed back and took a larfin survey of the aujience, sendin a broadside of sassy smiles in among em, I tried to unjint myself &amp; kollapse. When, in tellin how she drempt she lived in Marble Halls, she sed it tickled her more than all the rest to dream she loved her feller still the same, I made a effort to swaller myself; but when, in the next song, she looked strate at me &amp; called me her Dear, I wildly told the man next to me he mite hav my close as I shood never want 'em again no more in this world. [The <title>Plain Dealer</title> containin this communicashun is not to be sent to my famerly in Baldinsville under no circumstances whatsomever.]</p> 
               <p>In conclushun, Maria, I want you to do well. I know you air a nice gal at hart &amp; you must get a good husband. He must be a man of branes &amp; gumpshun &amp; a good pro-vider-a man who will luv you strong and long-a man who will luv you jest as much in your old age, when your voice is cracked like an old tea kittle &amp; you can't get 1 of your notes discounted at 50 per sent a month, as he will now, when you are young &amp; charmin &amp; full of music, sunshine &amp; fun. Don't many a snob, Maria. You ain't a Angel, Maria, &amp; I am glad of it, When I see angels in pettycoats I'm always sorry thay hain't got wings so they kin quietly fly off where thay will be appreshiated. You air a woman, &amp; a mity good one too. As for Maccarony, Brignolo, Mullenholler and them other fellers, they can take care of theirselves. Old Mac. kin make a comfortable livin choppin cord wood if his voice ever givs out, and Amodio looks as tho he mite succeed in conductin sum quiet toll gate, whare the vittles would be plenty &amp; the labor lite.</p> 
               <p>I am preparin for the Summer Campane. I shall stay in Cleveland a few days and probly you will hear from me again car I leave to once more becum a tosser on life's tempestuous billers, meanin the Show Bisnis.</p> 
               <closer>
                  <salute>Very Respectively Yours,</salute> 
                  <signed>ARTEMUS WARD.</signed>
               </closer> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <p>When I was in Nevada, I was called upon, shortly after my arrival, by an athletic scarlet-faced man, who politely said his name was Blare.</p> 
               <p>"I have a little bill against you, sir," he observed.</p> 
               <p>"A bill-what for?"</p> 
               <p>"For drinks."</p> 
               <p>"Drinks?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, sir-at my bar; I keep the well-known and highly-respected coffee-house down street."</p> 
               <p>"But, my dear sir, there is a mistake-I never drank at your bar."</p> 
               <p>"I know it, sir. That isn't the point. The point is this: I pay out my money for good liquors, and it is people's own fault if they don't drink them. There are liquors-do as you please about drinking them, <emph>but you must pay for them!</emph> Isn't that fair?"</p> 
               <p>His enormous body (which Puck wouldn't put a girdle round for forty dollars) shook gleefully while I read this eminently original bill.</p> 
               <p>Years ago Mr. Blaze was an agent of the California Stage Company. There was a formidable and well-organized opposition to the California Stage Company at that time, and Mr. Blaze rendered them such signal service in his capacity of agent that they were very sorry when he tendered his resignation.</p> 
               <p>"You are some sixteen hundred dollars behind in your accounts, Mr. Blaze," said the President, "but in view of your faithful and efficient services, we shall throw off eight hundred dollars of that amount."</p> 
               <p>Mr. Blaze seemed touched by this generosity. A tear stood in his eye, and his bosom throbbed audibly.</p> 
               <p>"You <emph>will</emph> throw off eight hundred dollars-you <emph>will?</emph>" he at last cried, seizing the President's hand and pressing it passionately to his lips.</p> 
               <p>"I will," returned the President.</p> 
               <p>"Well, sir," said Mr. Blaze, "I'm a gentleman; <emph>I am</emph>, you bet. And I won't allow no Stage Company to surpass me in politeness. <emph>I'll throw off the other eight hundred dollars, and we'll call it square!</emph> No gratitude, sir-no thanks: it is my duty."</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC5923-00000005"/> 
               <head>THE SHOW IS CONFISCATED.</head> 
               <p>You have perhaps wondered wharebouts I was for these many dase gone and past. Perchans you sposed I'd gone to the Tomb of the Cappylets, tho I don't know what those is. It's a popler noospaper frase.</p> 
               <p>Listen to my tail, and be silent that ye may here. I've been among the Seceshers, a earnin my daily peck by my legitimit perfeshun, and havn't had no time to weeld my facile quill for "the Grate Komick paper," if you'll allow me to kote from your truthful advertisement.</p> 
               <p>My success was skaly, and I likewise had a narrer scape of my life. If what I've bin threw is "Suthern hosspitality," 'bout which we've hearn so much, then I feel bound to obsarve that they made two much of me. They was altogether too lavish with their attenshuns.</p> 
               <p>I went amung the Seceshers with no feelins of annermosity. I went in my perfeshernal capacity. I was actooated by one of the most Loftiest desires which can swell the human Buzzum, viz:-to giv the peeple their money's worth, by showin them Sagashus Beests, and Wax Statoots, which I venter to say air onsurpast by any other statoots anywheres. I will not call that man who sez my statoots is humbugs a lier and a hoss thief, but bring him be4 me, and I'll wither him with one of my scornful frowns.</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>"I was ceased and tied to a stump."</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>But to proceed with my tail. In my travels threw the Sonny South I heared a heap of talk about Seceshon and bustin up the Union, but I didn't think it mounted to nothin. The politicians in all the villages was swearin that old Abe (sometimes called the Prahayrie flower) should'nt never be noggerated. They also made fools of theirselves in varis ways, but as they was used to that I didn't let it worry me much, and the Stars and Stripes continued to wave over my little tent. Moorover, I was a Son of Malty and a member of several other Temperance Societies, and my wife she was a Dawter of Malty, an I sposed these fax would secoor me the infloonz and pertectiun of all the fust families. Alas! I was dispinted. State arter State seceshed, and it growed hotter and hotter for the undersined. Things came to a climbmacks in a small town in Alabamy, where I was premtorally ordered to haul down the Stars &amp; Stripes. A deppytashun of red-faced men cum up to the door of my tent ware I was standin takin money (the arternoon exhibishun had commenst, an' my Italyun organist was jerkin his sole-stirrin chimes). "We air cum, Sir," said a milingtary man in a cockt hat, "upon a hi and holy mishun. The Southern Eagle is screamin threwout this sunny land - proudly and defiantly screamin, Sir!"</p> 
               <p>"What's the matter with him?" sez I, "don't his vittles sit well on his stummick?"</p> 
               <p>"That Eagle, Sir, will contioner to scream all over this Brite and tremenjus land!"</p> 
               <p>"Wall, let him <emph>scream</emph>. If your Eagle can amuse hisself by screamin, let him went!" The men anoyed me, for I was Bizzy makin change.</p> 
               <p>"We are cum, Sir, upon a matter of dooty -"</p> 
               <p>"You're right, Capting. It's every man's dooty to visit my show," sed I.</p> 
               <p>"We are cum -"</p> 
               <p>"And that's the reason you are here!" sez I, larfin one of my silvery larfs. I thawt if he wanted to goak I'd giv him sum of my sparkling eppygrams.</p> 
               <p>"Sir, you're inserlent. The plain question is, will you haul down the Star-Spangled Banner, and hist the Southern flag?"</p> 
               <p>"Nary hist!" Those was my reply.</p> 
               <p>"Your wax works and beests is then confiscated, &amp; you air arrested as a Spy!"</p> 
               <p>Sez I, "My fragrant roses of the Southern clime and Bloomin daffodils, what's the price of whisky in this town, and how many cubic feet of that seductive flooid can you individooally hold?"</p> 
               <p>They made no reply to that, but said my wax figgers was confiscated. I axed them if that was ginerally the stile among thieves in that country, to which they also made no reply, but sed I was arrested as a Spy, and must go to Montgomry in iuns. They was by this time jined by a large crowd of other Southern patrits, who commenst hollerin, "Hang the bald-headed aberlitionist, and bust up his immoral exhibition!" I was ceased and tied to a stump, and the crowd went for my tent-that water-proof pavilion, wherein instruction and amoosment had been so muchly combined, at 15 cents per head-and tore it all to pieces. Meanwhile dirty-faced boys was throwin stuns and empty beer bottles at my massiv brow, and takin other improper liberties with my person. Resistance was useless, for a variety of reasons, as I readily obsarved.</p> 
               <p>The Seseshers confisticated my statoots by smashin them to attums. They then went to my money box, and confisticated all the loose change therein contaned. They then went and bust in my cages, lettin all the animils loose, a small but helthy tiger among the rest. This tiger has an excentric way of tearin dogs to peaces, and I allers sposed from his gineral conduck that he'd hav no hesitashun in servin human beins in the same way if he could git at them. Excuse me if I was crooil, but I larfed boysterrusly when I see that tiger spring in among the people. "Go it, my sweet cuss!" I inardly exclaimed, "I forgive you for bitin off my left thum with all my heart! Rip 'em up like a bully tiger whose Lare has bin inwaded by Seceshers!"</p> 
               <p>I can't say for certain that the tiger serisly injured any of them, but as he was seen a few days after, sum miles distant, with a large and well-selected assortment of seats of trowsis in his mouth, and as he lookt as tho he'd bin havin sum vilent excercise, I rayther guess he did. You will therefore perceive that they didn't confisticate him much.</p> 
               <p>I was carrid to Montgomry in iuns and placed in durans vial. The jail was an ornery edifiss, but the table was librally supplied with Bakin and Cabbidge. This was a good variety, for when I didn't hanker after Bakin I could help myself to the cabbige.</p> 
               <p>I had nobody to talk to nor nothin to talk about, howsever, and I was very lonely, specially on the first day; so when the jailer parst my lonely sell I put the few stray hairs on the back part of my hed (I'm bald now, but thare was a time when I wore sweet auburn ringlets) into as dish-hevild as state a possible, &amp; rollin my eyes like a manyyuck, I cride, "Stay, jaler, stay! I am not mad but soon shall be if you don't bring me suthin to Talk!" He brung me sum noospapers, for which I thanked him kindly.</p> 
               <p>At larst I got a interview with Jefferson Davis, the President of the Southern Conthieveracy. He was quite perlite, and axed me to sit down and state my case. I did it, when he larfed and said his gallunt men had been a little 2 enthoosiastic in confisticatin my show.</p> 
               <p>"Yes," sez I, "they confisticated me too muchly. I had sum hosses confisticated in the same way onct, but the confisticaters air now poundin stun in the States Prison in Injinnapylus."</p> 
               <p>"Wall, wall, Mister Ward, you air at liberty to depart; you air friendly to the South, I know. Even now we have many frens in the North, who sympathise with us, and won't mingle with this fight."</p> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <p>"J. Davis, there's your grate mistaik. Many of us was your sincere frends, and thought certin parties amung us was fussin about you and meddlin with your consarns intirely too much. But, J. Davis, the minit you fire a gun at the piece of dry-goods called the Star-Spangled Banner, the North gits up and rises en massy, in defence of that banner. Not agin you as individooals,-not agin the South even-but to save the flag. We should indeed be weak in the knees, unsound in the heart, milk-white in the liver, and soft in the hed, if we stood quietly by and saw this glorus Govyment smashed to pieces, either by a furrm or a intestine foe. The gentle-harted mother hates to take her naughty child across her knee, but she knows it is her dooty to do it. So we shall hate to whip the naughty South, but we must do it if you don't make back tracks at onct, and we shall wallup you out of your boots! J. Davis, it is my decided opinion that the Sonny South is makin a egrejus mutton-hed of herself!"</p> 
               <p>"Go on, sir, you're safe enuff. You're too small powder for me!" sed the President of the Southern Conthieveracy.</p> 
               <p>"Wait till I go home and start out the Baldinsvill Mounted Hoss Cavalry! I'm Capting of that Corpse, I am, and, J. Davis, beware! Jefferson D., I now leave you! Farewell, my gay Saler Boy! Good by, my bold buccaneer! Pirut of the deep blue sea, adoo! adoo!"</p> 
               <p>My tower threw the Southern Conthieveracy on my way home was thrillin ennff for yeller covers. It will form the subjeck of my next. Betsy Jane and the progeny air well.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="section"> 
               <head>ON THE WING.</head> 
               <opener>
                  <salute>Gents of the Editoral Corpse:-</salute>
               </opener> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>"Don't Spear me agin, if you please."</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>Since I last rit you I've met with immense success a showin my show in varis places, particly at Detroit. I put up at Mr. Russel's tavern, a very good tavern too, but I am sorry to inform you that the clerks tried to cum a Gouge Game on me. I brandished my new sixteen dollar huntin-cased watch round considerable, &amp; as I was drest in my store clothes &amp; had a lot of sweet-scented wagon-grease on my hair, I am free to confess that I thought I lookt putty gay. It never once struck me that I lookt green. But up steps a clerk &amp; axes me hadn't I better put my watch in the Safe. "Sir," sez I, "that watch cost sixteen dollars! Yes Sir, every dollar of it! You can't cum it over me my boy! Not at all, Sir." I know'd what the clerk wanted. He wanted that watch himself. He wanted to make behave as tho he lockt it up in the safe, then he would set the house a fire and pretend as tho the watch was destroyed with the other property! But he caught a Tomarter when he got hold of me. From Detroit I go West'ard hoc. On the cars was a he-lookin female, with a green-cotton umbreller in one hand and a handful of Reform tracks the other. She sed every woman should have a Spear. Them as didn't demand their Spears, didn't know what was good for them. "What is my Spear?" she axed, addressin the people in the cars. "Is it to stay at home &amp; darn stockins &amp; be the ser-<emph>lave</emph> of a domineerin man? Or is it my Spear to vote &amp; speak &amp; show myself the ckal of man? Is there a sister in these keers that has her proper Spear?" Sayin which the eccentric female whirled her umbreller round several times, &amp; finally jabbed me in the weskit with at</p> 
               <p>"I hav no objecshuns to your goin into the Spear bizness," sez I, "but you'll please remember I ain't a pickeril. Don't Spear me agin, if you please." She sot down.</p> 
               <p>At Ann Arbor, bein seized with a sudden faintness, I called for a drop of suthin to 'drink. As I was stirrin the beverage up, a pale-faced man in gold spectacles laid his hand upon my shoulder, &amp; sed, "Look not upon the wine when it is red!"</p> 
               <p>Sez I, "this ain't wine. This is Old Rye."</p> 
               <p>"<emph>It stingeth like a Adder and biteth like a Sarpent!</emph>" sed the man.</p> 
               <p>"I guess not," sed I, "when you put sugar into it. That's the way I allers take mine."</p> 
               <p>"Have you sons grown up, Sir?" the man axed.</p> 
               <p>"Wall," I replide, as I put myself outside my beverage, "my son Artemus junior is goin on 18."</p> 
               <p>"Am't you afraid if you set him thus example he'll cum to a bad end?"</p> 
               <p>"He's cum to a waxed end already. He's learnin the shoe makin bizness," I replide. "I guess we can both on us git along without your assistance, Sir," I obsarved, as he was about to open his mouth agin.</p> 
               <p>"This is a cold world!" sed the man.</p> 
               <p>"That's so. But you'll get into a warmer one by and by if you don't mind your own bizness better." I was a little riled at the feller, because I never take anythin only when I'm onwell, I arter wards learned he was a temperance lecturer, and if he can injuce men to stop settin their inards on fire with the frightful licker which is retailed round the country, I shall hartly rejoice. Better give men. Prussick Assid to onct, than to pizen 'em to deth by degrees.</p> 
               <p>At Albion I met with overwhelmin success. The celebrated Albion Female Semenary is located here, &amp; there air over 300 young ladies in the Institushun, pretty enough to cat without seasonin or sass. The young ladies was very kind to me, volunteerin to pin my handbills onto the backs of their dresses. It was a  surblime site to see over 300 young ladies goin round with a advertisement of A. Ward's onparaleld show, conspickusly posted onto their dresses.</p> 
               <p>They've got a Panick up this way and refooze to take Western money. It never was worth much, and when western men who know what it is, refooze to take their own money it is about time other folks stopt handlin it. Banks are bustin every day, goin up higher nor any balloon of which we hav any record. These western bankers air a sweet &amp; luvly set of men. I wish I owned as good a house as some of 'em would break into!</p> 
               <p>Virtoo is its own reward.</p> 
               <closer>
                  <signed>A. WARD.</signed>
               </closer> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <p>The students of the Conneaut Academy gave a theatrical entertainment a few winters ago. They "executed" Julius Csar. Everything went off satisfactorily until Csar was killed in the market-place. The stage accomodations were limited, and Csar fell nearly under the stove, in which there was a roaring fire. And when Brutus said - <q>
                     <p>"People and Senators!-be not affrighted,"</p>
                  </q> he was amazed to see Csar rise upon his feet and nervously examine his scorched garments. "Lay down, you fool," shouted Brutus, wildly, "do you want to break up the whole thing!"-"No," returned Csar, in an excited manner, "I don't; I want to act out Gineral Csar in good style, but I ain't goin' to bile under that cussed old stove for nobody!" This stopped the play, and the students abandoned theatricals forthwith.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC5923-00000006"/> 
               <head>EDWIN FORREST AS OTHELLO.</head> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>"Fair Youth, do you know whot I'd do with you if you was my sun?"</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>Durin a recent visit to New York the undersined went to see Edwin Forrest. As I'm into the moral show bizness myself, I ginrally go to Barnum's moral Museum, where only moral peple air admitted, partickly on Wednesday arternoons. But this time I thot I'd go &amp; see Ed. Ed has been actin out on the stage for many years. There is varis 'pinions about his actin, Englishmen ginrally bleevin that he is far superior to Mister Macready; but on one pint all agree, and that is that Ed draws like a six ox team. Ed was actin at Niblo's Garding, which looks considerable more like a parster than a garding, but let that pars. I sot down in the pit, took out my spectacles &amp; commenced peroosin the evenin's bill. The awjince was all-fired large &amp; the boxes was full of the elitty of New York. Sevral opery glasses was leveld at me by Gothum's fairest darters, but I didn't let on as tho I noticed it, tho mebby I did take out my sixteen-dollar silver watch &amp; brandish it round more than was necessary. But the best of us has our weaknesses &amp; if a man has gewelry let him show it. As I was peroosin the bill a grave young man who sot near me, axed me if I'd ever seen Forrest dance the Essence of Old Virginny? "He's immense in that," sed the young man. "He also does a fair champion jig," the young man continnerd, "but his Big Thing is the Essence of Old Virginny." Sez I, "Fair youth, do you know what I'd do with you if you was my sun?"</p> 
               <p>"No," sez he.</p> 
               <p>"Wall," sez I, "I'd appint your funeral to-morrow arternoon &amp; the <emph>korps should be ready!</emph> Your too smart to live on this yearth." He didn't try any more of his capers on me. But another pussylanermuss individooul, in a red vest and patent lether boots, told me his name was Bill Astor &amp; axed me to lend him 50 cents till early in the mornin. I told him I'd probly send it round to him before he retired to his virtoous couch, but if I didn't he might look for it next fall, as soon as I cut my corn. The Orchestry was now fiddling with all their might, &amp; as the peple didn't understand anything about it they applaudid versifrussly. Presently, Old Ed Cum out. The play was Otheller or More of Veniss. Otheller was writ by Wm. Shakspeer. The scene is laid in Veniss. Otheller was a likely man &amp; was a ginral in the Veniss army. He cloped with Desdemony, a darter of the Hon. Mister Brabantio, who represented one of the back districks in the Veneshun legislater. Old Brabantio was as mad as thunder at this &amp; tore round considerable, but finally cooled down, tellin Otheller, howsever, that Desdemony had come it over her Par, and that he had better look out or she'd come it over him likewise. Mr. &amp; Mrs. Otheller git along very comfortable like for a spell. She is sweet-tempered and luvin-a nice, sensible feemale, never goin in for he-female conventions, green cotton umbrellers and pickled beats. Otheller is a good provider and thinks all the world of his wife. She has a lazy time of it, the hired girl doin all the cookin and washin. Desdemony, in fact, don't hav to git the water to wash her own hands with. But a low cuss named Iago, who I bleeve wants to git Otheller out of his snug government birth, now goes to work &amp; upsets the Otheller family in the most outrajus stile. Iago falls in with a braneless youth named Roderigo &amp; wins all his money at poker. (Iago allers played foul,) He thus got money enuff to carry out his onprincipled skeem. Mike Cassio, a Irish man, is selected as a tool by Iago. Mike was a clever feller &amp; orfficer in Otheller's army. He liked his tods too well, however, &amp; they floored him, as they have many other promisin young men. Iago injuces Mike to drink with him, Iago slyly throwin his whisky over his shoulder. Mike gits as drunk as a biled owl &amp; allows that he can lick a yard full of the Veneshun fancy before breakfast, without sweatin a hair. He meets Roderigo &amp; proceeds for to smash him. A feller named Montano undertakes to slap Cassio, when that infatooated person runs his sword into him. That miserable man, Iago, pretents to be very sorry to see Mike conduck hisself in this way, &amp; undertakes to smooth the thing over to Otheller, who rushes in with a drawn sword &amp; wants to know what's up. Iago cunninly tells his story, and Otheller tells Mike that he thinks a good deal of him but he can't train no more in his regiment. Desdemony sympathises with poor Mike &amp; interceeds for him with Otheller. Iago makes him bleeve she does this because she thinks more of Mike than she does of hisself. Otheller swallers Iago's lyin tail &amp; goes to makin a noosence of hisself ginrally. He worries poor Desdemony terrible by his vile insinuations &amp; finally smothers her to deth with a piller. Mrs. Iago cums in just as Otheller has finished the fowl deed and gives him fits right &amp; left, showin him that he has bin orfully gulled by her miserable cuss of a husband. Iago cums in, &amp; his wife commences rakin him down also, when he stabs her. Otheller jaws him a spell &amp; then cuts a small hole in his stummick with his sword. Iago pints to Desdemony's deth bed &amp; goes orf with a sardonic smile onto his countenance. Otheller tells the peple that he has dim the state sum service &amp; they know it; axes them to do as fair a thing as they can for him under the circumstances, &amp; kills hisself with a fish-knife, which is the most sensible thing he can do. This is a breef skedule of the synopsis of the play.</p> 
               <p>Edwin Forrest is a grate acter. I thot I saw Otheller before me all the time he was actin, and when the curtain fell, I found my spectacles was still mistened with salt-water, which had run from my eyes while poor Desdemony was dyin. Betsy Jane-Betsy Jane! let us pray that our domestic bliss may never be busted up by a Iago!</p> 
               <p>Edwin Forrest makes money acting out on the stage. He gits five-hundred dollars a nite &amp; his board &amp; washin. I wish I had such a Forrest in my Garding!</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <p>Several years ago Bill McCracken lived in Peru, Indiana. [We were in Peru several years ago, and it was a nice place we <emph>don't</emph> think.] Mr. McCracken was a screamer, and had whipped all the recognized fighting men on the Wabash. One day somebody told him that Jack Long, blacksmith at Logansport, said he would give him (McCracken) a protracted fit of sickness if he would just come down there and smell of his bones. The McCracken at once laid in a stock of provisions, consisting of whisky in glass and chickens in the shell, and started for Logansport. In a few days he was brought home in a bunged-up condition, on a cot-bed. One eye was gouged out, a portion of his nose was chawed off, his left arm was in a sling, his head was done up in old rag, and he was pretty badly off himself. He was set down in the village bar-room, and turning to the crowd he, in a feeble voice, said, hot tears bedewing his face the while, "Boys, you know Jack Long said if I'd come down to Loginsput he'd whale h-ll out of me; and, boys you know I didn't believe it, but I've been down thar and <emph>I found he would</emph>."</p> 
               <p>He recovered after a lapse of years and led a better life. As he said himself, he returned from Logansport a changed man.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <head>MOSES THE SASSY; OR THE DISGUISED DUKE.</head> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER I.</head> 
                  <head type="sub">ELIZY.</head> 
                  <p>My story opens in the classic presinks of Bostin In the parler of a bloated aristocratic mansion on Bacon street sits a luvly young lady, whose hair is cuvered ore with the frosts of between 17 Summers. She has just sot down to the piany, and is warblm the popler ballad called "Smells of the Notion," in which she tells how with pensiv thought, she wandered by a C beat shore. The sun is settin in its horizon, and its gorgus light pores in a golden meller fluid through the winders, and makes the young lady twict as beautiful nor what she was before, which is onnecessary. She is magnificently dressed up in a Berage basque, with poplin trimmins, More Antique, Ball Morals and 3 ply carpeting. Also, considerable gauze. Her dress contains 16 flounders and her shoes is red <unclear>morocker</unclear>, with gold spangles onto them. Presently she jumps up with a wild snort, and pressin her hands to her brow, she exclaims: "Methinks I see a voice!"</p> 
                  <p>
                     <figure> 
                        <head>"Oh that I should live to see myself a ded body!" screamed the unfortnet man.</head> 
                     </figure>
                  </p> 
                  <p>A noble youth of 27 summers enters. He is attired in a red shirt and black trowsis, which last air turned up over his boots; his hat, which it is a plug, being cockt on to one side of his classical hed. In sooth, he was a heroic look in person, with a fine shape. Grease, in its barmiest days near projuced a more hefty cavileer. Gazin upon him admirinly for a spell, Elizy (for that was her name) organized herself into a tabloo, and stated as follers.</p> 
                  <p>"Ha! do me eyes deceive me ear-sight? Is it some dreams? No, I reckon not! That frame! them store close! those nose! Yes, it is me own, me only Moses!"</p> 
                  <p>He (Moses) folded her to his hart, with the remark that he was "a hunkey boy."</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER II.</head> 
                  <head type="sub">WAS MOSES OF NOBLE BIRTH?</head> 
                  <p>Moses was foreman of Engine Co. No. 40. Forty's fellers had jus bin havin an annual re-union with Fifty's fellers, on the day I introjuce Moses to my readers, and Moses had his arms full of trofees, to wit: 4 scalps, 5 eyes, 3 fingers, 7 cars, (which he chawed off) and several half and quarter sections of noses. When the fair Elizy recovered from her delight at meetin Moses, she said:-"How hast the battle gonest? Tell me!"</p> 
                  <p>"We chawed 'em up-that's what we did!" said the bold Moses.</p> 
                  <p>"I thank the gods!" sed the fairy Elizy. "Thou did'st excellent well. And, Moses," she continnered, layin her hed confidinly agin his weskit, "dost know I sumtimes think thou istest of noble birth?"</p> 
                  <p>"No!" said he, wildly ketchin hold of hisself. "You don't say so!"</p> 
                  <p>"Indeed do I! Your dead grandfather's sperrit comest to me the tother night."</p> 
                  <p>"Oh no, I guess it's a mistake," sed Moses.</p> 
                  <p>"I'll bet two dollars and a quarter he did!" replied Elizy. "He said, 'Moses is a Disguised Juke!'"</p> 
                  <p>"You mean Duke," said Moses.</p> 
                  <p>"Dost not the actors all call it Juke!" said she.</p> 
                  <p>That settled the matter.</p> 
                  <p>"I hav thought of this thing afore," said Moses, abstractedly. "If it is so, then thus it must be! 2 B or not 2 B! Which! Sow, sow! But enuff. O life! life!-<emph>you're too many for me!</emph>" He tore out some of his pretty yeller hair, stampt on the floor sevril times, and was gone.</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER III.</head> 
                  <head type="sub">THE PIRUT FOILED.</head> 
                  <p>Sixteen long and weary years has elapst since the seens narrated in the last chapter took place. A noble ship the Sary Jane, is a sailin from France to Ameriky via the Wabash Canal. A pirut ship is in hot pursoot of the Sary. The pirut capting isn't a man of much principle and intends to kill all the people on bored the Sary and confiscate the wallerbles. The capting of the S. J. is on the pint of givin in, when a fine lookin feller in russet boots and a buffalo overcoat rushes forored and obsarves:</p> 
                  <p>"Old man! go down stairs! Retire to the starbud bulk-hed! I'll take charge of this Bote!"</p> 
                  <p>"Owdashus cuss!" yelled the capting, "away with thee or I shall do min-rer-der-r-r!"</p> 
                  <p>"Skurcely," obsarved the stranger, and he drew a diamond-hilted fish-knife and cut orf the capting's hed. He expired shortly, his last words bein, "we are governed too much."</p> 
                  <p>"People!" sed the stranger, "I'm the Juke d'Moses!"</p> 
                  <p>"Old hoss!" sed a passenger, "methinks thou art blowin!" whare-upon the Juke cut off his hed also.</p> 
                  <p>"Oh that I should live to see myself a ded body!" screamed the unfortnit man. "But don't print any verses about my deth in the newspapers, for if you do I'll haunt ye!"</p> 
                  <p>"People!" sed the Juke, "I alone can save you from yon bloody pirut! Ho! a peck of oats!" The oats was brought and the Juke, boldly mountin the jibpoop, throwed them onto the towpath. The pirut rapidly approached, chucklin with fiendish delight at the idee of increasin his ill-gotten gains. But the leadin hoss of the pirut ship stopt suddent on comin to the oats, and commenst for to devour them. In vain the piruts swore and throwd stones and bottles at the hoss-he wouldn't budge a inch. Meanwhile the Sary Jane, her hosses on the full jump, was fast leavin the pirut ship!</p> 
                  <p>"Onct agin do I escape deth!" sed the Juke between his clencht teeth, still on the jibpoop.</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER IV.</head> 
                  <head type="sub">THE WANDERER'S RETURN.</head> 
                  <p>The Juke was Moses the Sassy!</p> 
                  <p>Yes it was!</p> 
                  <p>He had bin to France and now he was home agin in Bostin, which gave birth to a Bunker Hill!! He had some trouble in gitting hisself acknowledged as Juke in France, as the Orleans Dienasty and Borebones were fernest him, but he finally conkered. Elizy knowd him right off, as one of his ears and a part of his nose had bin chawed off in his fights with opposition firemen durin boyhood's sunny hours. They lived to a green old age, beloved by all, both grate and small. Their children, of which they have numerous, often go up onto the Common and see the Fountain squirt.</p> 
                  <p>This is my 1st attempt at writin a Tail &amp; it is far from bein perfeck, but if I have indoosed folks to see that in 9 cases out of 10 they can either make Life as barren as the Dessert of Sarah, or as joyus as a flower garding, my objeck will have bin accomplished, and more too.</p> 
               </div> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC5923-00000007"/> 
               <head>INTERVIEW WITH PRESIDENT LINCOLN.</head> 
               <p>I hav no politics. Nary a one. I'm not in the bisiness. If I was I spose I should holler versiffrusly in the streets at nite and go home to Betsy Jane smellen of coal ile and gin, in the mornin. I should go to the Poles arly. I should stay there all day. I should see to it that my naburs was thar. I should git carriges to take the kripples, the infirm and the indignant thar. I should be on guard agin frauds and sich. I should be on the look out for the infamus lise of the enemy, got up jest be4 elecshun for perlitical effeck. When all was over and my candydate was elected. I should move heving &amp; arth-so to speak-until I got orfice, which it I didn't git a orfice I should turn round and abooze the Administration with all my mite and maine. But I'm not in the bisniss. I'm in a far more respectful bisniss nor what pollertics is. I wouldn't giv two cents to be a Congresser. The wuss insult I ever received was when sertin citizens of Baldinsville axed me to run fur the Legislater. Sez I, "My frends, dostest think I'd stoop to that there?" They turned as white as a sheet. I spoke in my most orfullest tones, &amp; they knowd I wasn't to be trifled with. They slunked out of site to onct.</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>An Interview with President Lincoln.</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>There4, havin no politics, I made bold to visit Old Abe at his humstid in Springfield. I found the old feller in his parler, surrounded by a perfeck swarm of orfice seekers. Knowin he had been capting of a flat boat on the roarin Mississippy I thought I'd address him in sailor lingo, so sez I "Old Abe, ahoy! Let out yer main-suls, reef hum the fore-castle &amp; throw yer jib-poop overboard! Shiver my timbers, my harty!" [N. B. This is ginuine mariner langwidge. I know, becawz I've seen sailor plays acted out by them New York theater fellers.] Old Abe look! up quite cross &amp; sez, "Send in yer petition by &amp; by. I can't possibly look at it now. Indeed, I can't. It's onpossible sir!"</p> 
               <p>"Mr. Linkin, who do you spect I air?" sed I.</p> 
               <p>"A orfice-seeker, to be sure!" sed he.</p> 
               <p>"Wall, sir," sed I, "you's never more mistaken in your life. You hain't gut a orfiss I'd take under no circumstances. I'm A. Ward. Wax figgers is my perfeshun. I'm the father of Twins, and they look like me-<emph>both of them</emph>. I cum to pay a frendly visit to the President cleck of the United States. If so be you wants to see me say so-if not say so, &amp; I'm orf like a jug handle."</p> 
               <p>"Mr. Ward, sit down. I am glad to see you, Sir."</p> 
               <p>"Repose in Abraham's Buzzum!" sed one of the orfice seekers, his idee bein to git orf a goak at my expense.</p> 
               <p>"Wall," sez I, "ef all you fellers repose in that there Buzzum thare'll be mity poor nussin for sum of you!" whereupon Old Abe buttoned his weskit clear up and blusht like a maidin of sweet 16. Jest at this pint of the conversation another swarm of orfice-seekers arrove &amp; cum pilin into the parler. Sum wanted post orfices, sum wanted collectorships, sum wantid furrin missions, and all wanted sumthin. I thought Old Abe would go crazy. He hadn't more than had time to shake hands with 'em before another tremenjis crowd cum porein onto his premises. His house and dooryard was now perfeckly overflowed with orfice seekers, all clameruss for a immejit interview with Old Abe. One man from Ohio, who had about seven inches of corn whiskey into him, mistook me for Old Abe and addrest me as "The Pra-hayrie Flower of the West!" Thinks I <emph>you</emph> want a offiss putty bad. Another man with a gold heded cane and a red nose told Old Abe he was "a seckind Washington &amp; the Pride of the Boundliss West."</p> 
               <p>Sez I, "Square, you wouldn't take a small post-offis if you could git it, would you?"</p> 
               <p>Sez he, "a patrit is abuv them things, sir!"</p> 
               <p>"There's a putty big crop of patrits this season, aint there Squire!" sez I, when <emph>another</emph> crowd of offiss seekers pored in. The house, door-yard, barn &amp; woodshed was now all full, and when <emph>another</emph> crowd cum I told 'em not to go away for want of room as the hog-pen was still empty. One patrit from a small town in Michygan went up on top the house, got into the chimney and slid down into the parler where Old Abe was endeverin to keep the hungry pack of orfice-seekers from chawin him up alive without benefit of clergy. The minit he reached the fire-place he jumpt up, brusht the soot out of his eyes, and yelled: "Don't make eny pintment at the Spunkville postoffiss till you've read my papers. All the respectful men in our town is signers to that there dockyment!"</p> 
               <p>"Good God!" cride Old Abe, "they cum upon me from the skize-down the chimneys, and from the bowels of the yearth!" He hadn't more'n got them words out of his deliket mouth before two fat offiss-seekers from Wisconsin, in endeverin to crawl atween his legs for the purpuss of applyin for the tollgateship at Milwawky, upsot the President cleck &amp; he would hev gone sprawlin into the fire-place if I hadn't caught him in these arms. But I hadn't more'n stood him up strate before another man cum crashin down the chimney, his head strikin me vilently agin the mards and prostratin my voluptoous form onto the floor. "Mr. Linkin," shoutld the infatooated being, "my papers is signed by every clergyman in our town, and likewise the skoolmaster!"</p> 
               <p>Sez I, "you egrejis ass," gittin up &amp; brushin the dust from my eyes, "I'll sign your papers with this bunch of bones, if you don't be a little more keerful how you make my bread basket a depot in the futer. How do you like that air perfumery?" sez I, shuving my fist under his nose. "Them's the kind of papers I'll giv you! Them's the paper's <emph>you</emph> want!"</p> 
               <p>"But I workt hard for the ticket; I toiled night and day! The patrit should be rewarded!"</p> 
               <p>"Virtoo," sed I, holdin' the infatooted man by the coat-collar, "virtoo, sir, is its own reward. Look at me!" He did look at me, and qualed be4 my gase. "The fact is," I continued, lookin round on the hungry crowd, "there is scarcely a offiss for every ile lamp carrid round durin' this campane. I wish thare was. I wish thare was furrin missions to be filled on varis lonely Islands where eppedmics rage incessantly, and if I was in Old Abe's place I'd send every mother's son of you to them. What air you here for?" I continnered, warmin up considerable, "can't you giv Abe a minit's peace? Don't you see he's worrid most to death! Go home, you miserable men, go home &amp; till the sile! Go to peddlin tinware-go to choppin wood-go to bilin' sope-stuff sassengers-black boots-git a clerkship on sum respectable manure cart-go found as original Swiss Bell Ringers-becum 'origenal and only' Campbell Minstrels-go to lecturin at 50 dollars a nite-imbark in the peanut bizniss-<emph>write for</emph> 
                  <title>the Ledger</title>-saw off your legs and go round givin concerts, with techin appeals to a charitable public, printed on your handbills - anything for a honest living, but don't come round here drivin Old Abe crazy by your outrajis cuttings up! Go home. Stand not upon the order of your goin, but go to onct! If in five minits from this time," sez I pullin' out my new sixteen dollar huntin cased watch and brandishin' it before their eyes, "Ef in five minits from this time a single sole of you remains on these here premises, I'll go out to my cage near by, and let my Boy Constructor loose! &amp; of he gits amung you, you'll think old Solferino has cum again<pb n=""/> and no mistake! Clear out you varmints!" You ought to hev seen them seamper, Mr. Fair. They run orf as the Satun hisself was arter them with a red hot ten-pronged pitchfork. In five minits the premises was clear.</p> 
               <p>"How kin I ever repay you, Mr. Ward, for your kindness?" sed Old Abe, advancin and shakin me warmly by the hand. "How kin I ever repay you, sir!"</p> 
               <p>"By givin the whole country a good, sound adminstration. By poerin' ile upon the troubled waturs, North and South. By pursooin' a patriotic, firm, and just course, and then if any State wants to secede, let 'em Sesesh!"</p> 
               <p>"How 'bout my Cabinit, Mister Ward?" sed Abe.</p> 
               <p>"Fill it up with Showmen, sir! Showmen is devoid of politics. They hain't got any principles! They know how to cater for the public. They know what the public wants, North &amp; South Showmen, sir, is honest men. Ef you doubt their literary ability, look at their posters, and see small bills! Ef you want a Cabinit as is a Cabinit fill it up with showmen, but don't call on me. The moral wax figger perfeshun musn't be permitted to go down while there's a drop of blood in these vains A. Linkin, I wish you well! Ef Powers or Walcutt wus to pick out a model for a beautiful man, I scarcely think they'd sculp you; but ef you do the fair thing by your country you'll make as putty a angel as any of us! A. Linkin, use the talents which Nature has put into you judishusly and firmly, and all will be well! A. Linkin, adoo!"</p> 
               <p>He shook me cordyully by the hand-we exchanged picters, so we could gaze upon each others' liniments when far away from one another-he at the hellum of the Ship of State, and I at the hellum of the show bizniss-admittance only 15 cents.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <head>ON "FORTS."</head> 
               <p>Every man has got a Fort. It's sum men's fort to do one thing, and sum other men's fort to do another, while there is numeris shiftliss critters goin round loose whose fort is not to do nothin.</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>Artemus rescood from the Kanawl.</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>Shakspeer rote good plase, but he wouldn't hav succeeded as a Washington correspondent of a New York daily paper. He lackt the rekesit fancy and imagginashun.</p> 
               <p>That's so!</p> 
               <p>Old George Washington's Fort was to not hev eny public man of the present day resemble him to eny alarmin extent. Whare bowts can George's ekal be fownd? I ask, &amp; boldly anser no whares, or eny whare else.</p> 
               <p>Old man Townsin's Fort, was to maik Sassyperiller. "Goy to the world! another life saived!"(Cotashun from Townsins advertisemunt.)</p> 
               <p>Cyrus Field's Fort is to lay submachine tellegraf under the boundin billers of the Oshun, and then hev it Bust.</p> 
               <p>Spaldin's Fort is to maik Prepared Gioo, which mends everything. Wonder of it will mend a sinner's wickid waze. (Impromptoo goak).</p> 
               <p>Zoary's Fort is to be a femaile circus feller.</p> 
               <p>My Fort is the grate moral show bizniss &amp; ritin choice famerly literatoor for the noospapers. That's what's the matter with <emph>me</emph>.</p> 
               <p>&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c. So I mite go on to a indefinite extent.</p> 
               <p>Twict I've endeverd to do things which thay wasn't my Fort. The fust time was when I undertuk to lick a owdashus cuss who cut a hole in my tent &amp; krawld threw. Sez I, "my jentle Sir go out or I shall fall unto you putty hevy." Sez he, "Wade in, Old wax figgers," whareupon I went for him, but he cawt me powerful on the hed &amp; knockt me threw the tent into a cow pastur. He pursood the attack &amp; flung me into a mud puddle. As I aroze &amp; rung out my drencht garmints I koncluded fitin wasn't my Fort. He now rize the kurtin upon Seen 2nd: It is rarely seldum that I seek consolation in the Flowin Bole. But in a sertin town in Injianny in the faul of 18-, my orgin grinder got sick with the fever &amp; died. I never felt so ashamed in my life, &amp; I thowt I'd hist in a few swallers of suthin strengthin. Konsequents was I histid in so much I dident zackly know whare bowts I was. I turnd my livin wild beests of Pray loose into the streets and spilt all my wax wurks. I then bet I could play hoss. So I bitched myself to a Kanawl bote, there bein two other hoases hitcht on also, one behind and another ahead of me. The driver hollerd for us to git up, and we did. But the hosses bein onused to sich a arrangement begun to kick &amp; squeal and rair up. Konsequents was I was kickt vilently in the stummick &amp; back, and presuntly I fownd myself in the Kanawl with the other hosses, kickin &amp; yellin like a tribe of Cusscaroorus avvijis. I was rescood, &amp; as I was bein carrid to the tavern on a hemlock Bored I sed in a feeble voise, "Boys, playin hoss isn't my Fort."</p> 
               <p>MORUL-Never don't do nothin which isn't your Fort, for ef you do you'll find yourself splashin round in the Kanawl, figgeratively speakin.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <p>We have no intention of making fun of serious matters in telling the following story: we merely relate a fact.</p> 
               <p>There is a rule at Oberlin College that no student shall board at any house where prayers are not regularly made each day. A certain man fitted up a boarding house and filled it with boarders, but forgot until the eleventh hour, the prayer proviso. Not being a praying man himself, he looked around for one who was. At length he found one-a meek young man from Trumbull County-who agreed to pay for his board in praying. For awhile all went smoothly, but the boarding-master furnished his table so poorly that the boarders began to grumble and to leave, and the other morning the praying boarder actually "struck"! Something like the following dialogue occurred at the table:</p> 
               <p>
                  <hi rend="i"/>Landlord-Will you pray, Mr. Mild?</p> 
               <p>
                  <hi rend="i"/>Mild-No, sir, I will not.</p> 
               <p>
                  <hi rend="i"/>Landlord-Why not, Mr. Mild?</p> 
               <p>
                  <hi rend="i"/>Mild-It don't pay, sir. I can't pray on such victuals as these. And unless you bind yourself in writing to set a better table than you have for the last three weeks, <emph>nary another prayer do you get out of me!</emph>
               </p> 
               <p>And that's the way the matter stood at latest advices.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC5923-00000008"/> 
               <head>JOY IN THE HOUSE OF WARD.</head> 
               <p>DEAR SIRS,-I take my pen in hand to inform you that I am in a state of grate bliss, and trust these lines will find you injoyin the same blessins. I'm reguvinated. I've found the immortal waters of yooth, so to speak, and am as limber and frisky as a two-year old steer, and in the futer them boys which sez to me "go up, old Bawld hed," will do so at the peril of their hazard, individooally. I'm very happy. My house is full of joy, and I have to git up nights and larf! Sumtimes I ax myself "is it not a dream?" &amp; suthin withinto me sez "it air;" but when I look at them sweet little critters and hear 'em squawk, I know it is a reality-2 realitys, I may say-and I feel gay.</p> 
               <p>I returned from the Summer Campane with my unparaleld show of wax works and livin wild Beests of Pray in the early part of this munth. The peple of Baldinsville met me cordully and I immejitly commenst restin myself with my famerly. The other nite while I was down to the tavurn tostin my shins agin the bar-room fire &amp; amuzin the krowd with sum of my adventurs, who shood cum in bare heded &amp; terrible excited but Bill Stokes, who sez, sez he, "Old Ward, thare's grate doins up to your house."</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>"Twins, marm," sez I, "twins!"</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>Sez I, "William, how so?"</p> 
               <p>Sez he, "Bust my gizzud, but its grate doins," &amp; then he larfed as if hee'd kill hisself.</p> 
               <p>Sez I, risin and puttin on a austeer look, "William, I woodunt be a fool if I had common cents."</p> 
               <p>But he kept on larfin till he was black in the face, when he fell over on to the bunk where the hostler sleeps, and in a still small voice sed, "Twins!" I ashure you gents that the grass didn't grow under my feet on my way home, &amp; I was follered by a enthooslastic throng of my feller sitterzens, who hurrard for Old Ward at the top of their voises. I found the house chock full of peple. Thare was Mis Square Baxter and her three grown up darters, lawyer Perkinses wife, Taberthy Ripley, young Eben Parsuns, Deakun Simmuns folks, the Skoolmaster, Doctor Jordin, etsettery, etsettery. Mis Ward was in the west room, which jines the kitchin. Mis Square Baxter was mixin suthin in a dipper before the kitchin fire, and a small army of female wimin were rushin wildly round the house with bottles of camfire, peaces of flannil, &amp;c. I never seed sich a hubbub in my natral born dase. I cood not stay in the west room only a minit, so strung up was my feelins, so I rusht out and ceased my dubbel barrild gun.</p> 
               <p>"What upon airth ales the man?" sez Taberthy Ripley. "Sakes alive, what air you doin?" &amp; she grabd me by the coat tales. "What's the matter with you?" she continnered.</p> 
               <p>"Twins, marm," sez I, "twins!"</p> 
               <p>"I know it," sez she, coverin her pretty face with her apun.</p> 
               <p>"Wall," sez I, "that's what's the matter with me!"</p> 
               <p>"Wall, put down that air gun, you pesky old fool," sed she.</p> 
               <p>"No, marm," sez I, "this is a Nashunal day. The glory of this here day isn't confined to Baldinsville by a darn site. On yonder woodshed," sed I, drawin myself up to my full hite and speakin in a show actin voice, "will I fire a Nashunal saloot!" sayin whitch I tared myself from her grasp and rusht to the top of the shed whare I blazed away until Square Baxter's hired man and my son Artemus Juneyer cum and took me down by mane force,</p> 
               <p>On return in to the Kitchin I found quite a lot of people seated bet the fire, a talkin the event over. They made room for me &amp; I sot down. "Quite a eppisode," sed Docter Jordin, litin his pipe with a red hot coal.</p> 
               <p>"Yes," sed I, "2 eppisodes, waying abowt 18 pounds jintly.</p> 
               <p>"A perfeck coop de tat," sed the skoolmaster.</p> 
               <p>"E pluribus unum, in proprietor persony," sed I, thinkin I'd let him know I understood furrin langwidges as well as he did, if I wasn't a skoolmaster.</p> 
               <p>"It is indeed a momentious event," sed young Eben Parsuns, who has been 2 quarters to the Akademy.</p> 
               <p>"I never heard twins called by that name afore," sed I, "but I spose its all rite."</p> 
               <p>"We shall soon have Wards enuff," sed the editer of the Baldinsville <title>Bugle of Liberty</title> who was lookin over a bundle of exchange papers in the corner, "to apply to the legislater for City Charter?"</p> 
               <p>"Good for you, old man!" sed I, "giv that air a conspickius place in the next <title>Bugle</title>."</p> 
               <p>"How redicklus," sed pretty Susan Fletcher, coverin her face with her knittin work &amp; larfin like all possest.</p> 
               <p>"Wall, for my part," sed Jane Maria Peasley who is the crossest old made in the world, "I think you all act like a peck of fools."</p> 
               <p>Sez I, Mis. Peasly, air you a parent?"</p> 
               <p>Sez she, "No, I aint."</p> 
               <p>Sez I, "Mis. Peasly, you never will be."</p> 
               <p>She left.</p> 
               <p>We sot there talkin &amp; larfin until "the switchin hour of nite, when grave yards yawn &amp; Josts troop 4th," as old Bill Shakespire aptlee obsarves in his dramy of John Sheppard, esq., or the Moral House Breaker, when we broke up &amp; disbursed.</p> 
               <p>Muther &amp; children is a doin well; &amp; as Resolushuns is the order of the day I will feel obleeged if you'll insurt the follerin -</p> 
               <p>Whereas, two Eppisodes has happined up to the unnersined's house, which is Twins; &amp; Whereas I like this stile, sade twins bein of the male perswashun &amp; both boys; there4 Be it</p> 
               <p>
                  <hi rend="i"/>Resolved, that to them nabers who did the fare thing by sade Eppisodes my hart felt thanks is doo.</p> 
               <p>
                  <hi rend="i"/>Resolved, that I do most hartily thank Engine Ko. No. 17 who, under the impreshun from the fuss at my house on that auspishus nite that thare was a konflagration goin on, kum galyantly to the spot, but kindly refrand frum squirtin.</p> 
               <p>
                  <hi rend="i"/>Resolved, that frum the Bottum of my Sole do I thank the Baldinsville brass band fur givin up the idea of Sarahnadin me, both on that great nine &amp; sinse.</p> 
               <p>
                  <hi rend="i"/>Resolved, that my thanks is doo several members of the Baldinsville meetin house who fur 3 whole dase hain't kalled me a sinful skoffer or intreeted me to mend my wicked wase and jine sade meetin house to onct.</p> 
               <p>
                  <hi rend="i"/>Resolved, that my Boozum teams with meny kind emoshuns towards the follerin individoouls, to whit namelee-Mis. Square Baxter, who Jenerusly refoozed to take a sent for a bottle of camfire; lawyer Perkinses wife who rit cum versis on the Eppisodes; the Editor of the Baldinsville <title>Bugle of Liberty</title>, who nobly assisted me in wollupin my Kangeroo, which sagashus little cuss seriusly disturbed the Eppisodes by his outrajus screetchins &amp; kickins up; Mis. Hirum Doolittle, who kindly furnisht sum cold vittles at a tryin time, when it wasunt konvenient to cook vittles at my house; and the Peasleys, Parsunses &amp; Watsunses fur there meny ax of kindness.</p> 
               <closer>
                  <salute>Trooly yures,</salute> 
                  <signed>ARTEMUS WARD.</signed>
               </closer> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <head>PERSONAL RECOLLECTIONS.</head> 
               <p>You'll be glad to learn that I've made a good impression onto the mind of the lan'lord of the Greenlion tavern. He made a speech about me last night. Risin' in the bar he spoke as follers, there bein over 20 individooals present: "This North American has been an inmate of my 'ouse over two weeks, yit he hasn't made no attempt to scalp any member of my family. He hasn't broke no cups or sassers, or furniture of any kind. (<emph>Hear, hear.</emph>) I find I can trust him with lited candles. He eats his wittles with a knife and a fork. Peple of this kind should be encurridged. I purpose 'is 'elth!" (<emph>Loud 'plaws.</emph>)</p> 
               <p>What could I do but modestly get up and express a fervint hope that the Atlantic Cable would bind the two countries still more closely together? The lan'lord said my speech was full of orig'nality, but his idee was the old stage coach was more safer, and he tho't peple would indors that opinion in doo time.</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>"Has my clothin' a Welchy appearance!"</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>I'm gettin' on exceedin' well in London. I see now, however, that I made a mistake in orderin' my close afore I left home. The trooth is the taler in our little villige owed me for a pig, and I didn't see any other way of gettin' my pay. Ten years ago these close would no doubt have been fash'n'ble, and perhaps they would be ekally sim'lar ten years hens. But now they're diff'rently. The taler said he know'd they was all right, because he had a brother in Wales who kept him informed about London fashins reg'lar. This was a infamous falsehood. But as the ballud says (which I heard a gen'l'man in a new soot of black close and white kid gloves sing t'other night), Never don't let us despise a Man because he wears a Raggid Coat! I don't know as we do, by the way, tho' we gen'relly get out of his way pretty rapid; prob'ly on account of the pity which tears our boosoms for his onhappy condition.</p> 
               <p>This last remark is a sirkastic and witherin' thrust at them blotid peple who live in gilded saloons. I tho't I'd explain my meanin' to you. I frekently have to explain the meanin' of my remarks. I know one man-and he's a man of varid 'complishments-who often reads my articles over 20 times afore he can make anything of 'em at all. Our skool-master to home says this is a pecoolerarity of geneyus. My wife says it is a pecoolerarity of infernal nonsens. She's a exceedin' practycal woman. I luv her muchly, however, and humer her little ways. It's a recklis falshood that she hepecks me, and the young man in our neighborhood who said to me one evenin', as I was mistenin' my diafram with a gentle cocktail at the villige tavun-who said to me in these very langwidge. "Go home, old man, onless you desires to have another teapot throwd at you by B. J.," probably regrets havin' said so. I said, "Betsy Jane is my wife's front name, gentle yooth, and I permits no person to alood to her as B. J. outside of the family circle, of which I am it principally myself. Your other observations I scorn and disgust, and I must polish you off." He was a able-bodied young man, and, remoovin' his coat, he inquired if I wanted to be ground to powder? I said, Yes: if there was a Powder-grindist handy, nothin' would 'ford me greater pleasure, when he struck me a painful blow into my right eye, causin' me to make a rapid retreat into the fire-place. I hadn't no idee that the enemy was so well organised. But I rallied and went for him, in a rayther vigris style for my time of life. His parents lived near by, and I will simply state 15 minits had only clapst after the first act, when he was carried home on a shutter. His mama met the sollum procession at the door, and after keerfully looking her offspring over, she said, "My son, I see how it is distinctually. You've been foolin' round a Trashin' Masheen. You went in at the place where they put the grain in, cum out with the straw, and you got up into the thingamyjig, and let the horses tred on you, didn't you, my son?" The pen of no livin Orthur could describe that disfortnit young man's sittywation more clearer. But I was sorry for him, and I went and nussed him till he got well. His reg'lar original father being absent to the war, I told him I'd be a father to him myself. He smilt a sickly smile, and said I'd aheady been wuss than two fathers to him.</p> 
               <p>I will here obsarve that fitin <unclear>or</unclear> be allus avided, excep in extreem cases. My principle is, if a man smites me on the right check, I'll turn my left to him, prob'bly; but if he insinooates that my gran'mother wasn't all right, I'll punch his hed. But fitin is mis'ble bizniss, gen'rally speakin, and whenever any enterprisin countryman of mine cums over here to scoop up a Briton in the prize ring I'm allus excessively tickled when he gets scooped hisself, which it is a sad fack has thus far been the case-my only sorrer bein' that t'other feller wasn't scooped likewise. It's diff'rently with scullin boats, which is a manly sport, and I can only explain Mr. Hamil's resunt defeat in this country on the grounds that he wasn't used to British water. I hope this explanation will be entirely satisfact'ry to all.</p> 
               <p>I'm a little sorry you've got politics over here, but I shall not diskuss 'em with nobody. Tear me to peaces with wild omnibus hosses, and I won't diskuss 'em. I've had quite enuff of 'em at home, thank you. I was at Birmingham t'other night, and went to the great meetin' for a few minits. I hadn't been in the hall long when a stern looken' artisan said to me,</p> 
               <p>"You ar from Wales?"</p> 
               <p>No, I told him I didn't think I was. A hidgyis tho't flasht over me. It was of that onprincipled taler, and I said, "Has my clothin' a Welchy appearance?"</p> 
               <p>"Not by no means," he answered, and then he said, "And what is your opinyin of the present crisis?"</p> 
               <p>I said, "I don't zackly know. Have you got it very bad?"</p> 
               <p>He replied, "Sir, it is sweepin' over England like the Cymoon of the Desert!"</p> 
               <p>"Wall," I said, "let it sweep!"</p> 
               <p>He ceased me by the arm and said, "Let us glance at hist'ry. It is now some two thousand years -"</p> 
               <p>"Is it, indeed?" I replied.</p> 
               <p>"Listen!" he fiercely cried; "it is only a little over two thousand years since -"</p> 
               <p>"Oh, bother!" I remarkt, "let us go out and git some beer."</p> 
               <p>"No, Sir. I want no gross and sensual beer. I'll not move from this spot till I can vote. Who ar you?"</p> 
               <p>I handed him my card, which in addition to my name, contains a clabrit description of my show. Now," I proudly said "you know me?"</p> 
               <p>"I sollumly swear," he sternly replied, "that I never heard of you or your show in my life!"</p> 
               <p>"And this man," I cried bitterly, "calls hisself a intelligent man, and thinks he orto be allowed to vote! What a holler mockery!"</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC5923-00000009"/> 
               <head>FOURTH OF JULY ORATION.</head> 
               <head type="sub">DELIVERED JULY 4TH, AT WEATHERSFIELD, CONNECTICUT, 1859.</head> 
               <note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WRIGHT2-0396-NOTE002" place="inline"
                     n="*">[I delivered the follerin, about two years ago, to a large and discriminating awjince I was 96 minits passin a given pint. I have revised the orasbun and added sum things which makes it approposser to the times than it otherwise would be. I have also corrected the grammers and punktooated it. I do my own punktooatin now days. The printers in VANITY FAIR offiss can't punktooate worth a cent.]</note> 
               <p>FELLER CITIZENS: I've been honored with an invite to norate before you to-day; and when I say that I skurcely feel ekal to the task, I'm sure you will believe me.</p> 
               <p>Weathersfield is justly celebrated for her onyins and patritism the world over, and to be axed to paws and address you on this, my fust perfeshernal tower threw New Englan, causes me to feel-to feel-I may say it causes me to <emph>feel</emph>. (Grate applaws. They thought this was one of my eccentricities, while the fact is I was stuck. This between you and I.)</p> 
               <p>I'm a plane man. I don't know nothing about no ded languages and am a little shaky on livin ones. There, expect no flowery talk from me. What I shall say will be to the pint, right strate out.</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>Mr. Ward delivering his great Fourth of July Oration.</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>I'm not a politician and my other habits air good. I've no enemys to reward, nor friends to sponge. But I'm a Union man. I luv the Union - it is a big thing-and it makes my hart bleed to see a lot of ornery peple a-movin heaven-no, not heaven, but the other place-and earth, to bust it up. Too much good blood was spilt in courtin and marryin that hily respectable female the Goddess of Liberty, to git a divorce from her now. My own State of Injianny is celebratid for unhitchin marrid people with neatness and dispatch, but you can't git a divorce from the Goddess up there. Not by no means. The old gal has behaved herself too well to cast her off now. I'm sorry the picters don't give her no shoes or stockins, but the band of stars upon her hed must continner to shine undimd, forever. I'me for the Union as she air, and whithered be the arm of every ornery cuss who attempts to bust her up. That's me. I hav sed! [It was a very sweaty day, and at this pint of the orashun a man fell down with sunstroke. I told the awjince that considerin the large number of putty gals prosent I was more fraid of a DAWTER STROKE. This was impromptoo, and seemed to amoose them very much.]</p> 
               <p>Feller Citizens-I hain't got time to notis the growth of Ameriky frum the time when the Mayflowers cum over in the Pilgrim and brawt Plymouth Rock with them, but every skool boy nose our career has been tremenjis. You will excuse me if I don't praise the erly settlers of the Kolonies. Peple which hung idiotic old wimmin for witches, burnt holes in Quakers' tongues and consined their feller critters to the tredmill and pillery on the slitest provocashun may hav bin very nice folks in their way, but I must confess I don't admire their stile, and will pass them by. I spose they ment well, and so, in the novel and techin langwidge of the nusepapers, "peas to their ashis." Thare was no diskount, however, on them brave men who fit, bled and died in the American Revolushun. We needn't be afraid of setting 'em up two steep. Like my show, they will stand any amount of prase. G. Washington was abowt the best man this world ever sot eyes on. He was a clear-heded, warm-harted, and stiddy-goin man. He never slopt over! The prevailin weakness of most men is to SLOP OVER! [Put them words in large letters-A. W.] They git filled up and slop. They Rush Things. They travel too much on the high presher principle. They git onto the fust poplar hobby-horse whitch trots along, not carin a sent whether the beest is even goin, clear sited and sound or spavined, blind and bawky. Of course they git throwed eventooally, if not sooner. When they see the multitood goin it blind they go Pel Mel with it, instid of exertin theirselves to set it right. They can't see that the crowd which is now bearin them triumfantly on its shoulders will soon diskiver its error and cast them into the hoss pond of Oblivyun, without the slitest hesitashun. Washington never slopt over. That wasn't George's stile. He luved his country dearly. He wasn't after the spiles. He was a human angil in a 3 kornered hat and knee britches, and we shan't see his like right away. My frends, we can't all be Washington's, but we kin all be patrits &amp; behave ourselves in a human and a Christian manner. When we see a brother goin down hill to Ruin let us not give him a push, but let us seeze rite hold of his coat-tails and draw him back to Morality.</p> 
               <p>Imagine G. Washington and P. Henry in the character of seseshers! As well fancy John Bunyan and Dr. Watts in spangled tites, doin the trapeze in a one-horse circus!</p> 
               <p>I tell you, feller-citizens, it would have been ten dollars in Jeff Davis's pocket if he'd never bin born!</p> 
               <p>Be shure and vote at leest once at all elecshuns. Buckle on yer Armer and go to the Poles. See two it that your naber is there. See that the kripples air provided with carriages. Go to the poles and stay all day. Bewair of the infamous lise whitch the Opposishun will be sartin to git up fur perlitical effek on the eve of eleckshun. To the poles! and when you git there vote jest as you darn please. This is a privilege we all persess, and it is <unclear>1</unclear> of the booties of this grate and free land.</p> 
               <p>I see mutch to admire in New Englan. Your gals in particklar air abowt as snug bilt peaces of Calliker as I ever saw. They air fully equal to the corn fed gals of Ohio and Injianny, and will make the bestest kind of wives. It sets my Buzzum on fire to look at 'cm.</p> 
               <q>
                  <lg type="quotation"> 
                     <l>He still, my sole, be still,</l> 
                     <l>&amp; you, Hart, stop cuttin up!</l> 
                  </lg>
               </q> 
               <p>I like your skool houses, your meetin houses, your enterprise, gumpshun &amp;c., but your favorit Bevridge I disgust. I allude to New England Rum. It is worse nor the korn whisky of Injianny, which eats threw stone jugs &amp; will turn the stummuck of the most shiftliss Hog. I seldom seek consolashun in the flowin Bole, but tother day I worrid down some of your Rum. The fust glass indused me to sware like a infooriated trooper. On takin the secund glass I was seezed with a desire to break winders, &amp; arter imbibin the third glass I knockt a small boy down, pickt his pocket of a New York <title>Ledger</title>, and wildly commenced readin Sylvanus Kobb's last Tail. Its drefful stuff - a sort of lickwid litenin, gut up under the pesonal supervishun of the devil-tears men's inards all to peaces and makes their noses blossum as the Lobster. Shun it as you would a wild hyeny with a fire brand tied to his tale, and while you air abowt it you will do a fust rate thing for yourself and everybody abowt you by shunnin all kinds of intoxicatin lickers. But unless your inards air cast iron, avoid New Englan's favorite Bevrige.</p> 
               <p>My frends, I'm dun. I tear myself away from you with tears in my eyes &amp; a pleasant oder of Onyins abowt my close. In the langwidge of Mister Catterline to the Rummuns, I go, but perhaps I shall cum back agin. Adoo, peple of Wethersfield. Be virtoous &amp; you'll be happy!</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <head>A WAR MEETING.</head> 
               <p>Our complaint just now is war meetins. They've bin havin 'em bad in varis parts of our cheerful Republic, and nat'rally we caught 'em here in Baldinsville. They broke out all over us.</p> 
               <p>Our big meetin came off the other night, and our old friend of the <title>Bugle</title> was elected Cheerman.</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>The Editor of "The Bugle" is interrupted by Betsy Jane and her female warriors.</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>The <title>Bugle-Horn of Liberty</title> is one of Baldinsville's most eminentest institootions. The advertisements are well written, and the deaths and marriages are conducted with signal ability. The editor, Mr. SLINKERS, is a polish'd, skarcastic writer. Folks in these parts will not soon forgit how he used up the <title>Eagle of Freedom</title>, a family journal published at Snootville, near here. The controversy was about a plank road. "The road may be, as our cotemporary says, a humbug; but <emph>our</emph> aunt isn't bald-heded, and <emph>we</emph> haven't got a one-eyed sister Sal! Wonder if the Editor of the <title>Eagle of Freedom</title> sees it?" This used up the <title>Eagle of Freedom</title> feller, because his aunt's head does present a skinn'd appearance, and his sister SARAH is very much one-eyed. For a genteel home thrust, Mr. SLINKERS has few ekals. He is a man of great pluck likewise. He has a fierce nostril, and I b'lieve, upon my soul, that if it wasn't absolootly necessary for him to remain here and announce in his paper, from week to week, that "our Gov'ment is about to take vig'rous measures to put down the rebellion"-I b'lieve, upon my soul, this illustris man would enlist as a Brigadier Gin'ral, and git his Bounty.</p> 
               <p>But to return to the war meetin. It was largely attended. The Editor of the <title>Bugle</title> arose and got up and said the fact could no longer be disguised that we were involved in a war. "Human gore," said he, "is flowin. All able-bodied men should seize a musket and march to the tented field. I repeat it, sir, to the tented field."</p> 
               <p>A voice-"Why don't you go yourself, you old blowhard?"</p> 
               <p>"I am identified, young man, with a Arkymedian leaver which moves the world," said the Editor, wiping his auburn brow with his left coat-tail: "I allude, young man, to the press. Terms, two dollars a year, invariably in advance. Job printing executed with neatness and dispatch!" And with this brilliant bust of clekance the editor introduced Mr. J. Brutus Hinkins, who is sufferin from an attack of College in a naberin place. Mr. Hinkins said Washington was not safe. Who can save our national capectle?</p> 
               <p>"DAN SETCHELL," I said. "He can do it afternoons. Let him plant his light and airy form onto the Long Bridge, make faces at the hirelin foe, and they'll skedaddle! Old SETCH can do it."</p> 
               <p>"I call the Napoleon of Showmen," said the Editor of the <title>Bugle</title>-"I call that Napoleonic man, whose life is adorned with so many noble virtues, and whose giant mind lights up this warlike scene-I call him to order."</p> 
               <p>I will remark in this connection, that the editor of the <title>Bugle</title> does my job printing.</p> 
               <p>"You," said Mr. Hinkins, "who live away from the busy haunts of men, do not comprehend the magnitood of the crisis. The busy haunts of men is where people comprehend this crisis. We who live in the busy haunts of men-that is to say, we dwell, as it were, in the busy haunts of men."</p> 
               <p>"I really trust that the gentl'man will not fail to say suthin about the busy haunts of men, before he sits down," said I.</p> 
               <p>"I claim the right to express my sentiments here, said Mr. Hinkins, in a slightly indignant tone, "and I shall brook no interruption, if I am a Softmore."</p> 
               <p>"You couldn't be <emph>more soft</emph>, my young friend," I observed, where-upon there was cries of "Order! order!"</p> 
               <p>"I regret I can't mingle in this strife personally," said the young man.</p> 
               <p>"You might inlist as a liberty-pole," said I in a silvery whisper.</p> 
               <p>"But," he added, "I have a voice, and that voice is for war." The young man then closed his speech with some strikin and original remarks in relation to the star-spangled banner. He was followed by the village minister, a very worthy man indeed, but whose sermons have a tendency to make people sleep pretty industriously.</p> 
               <p>"I am willin to inlist for one," he said.</p> 
               <p>"What's your weight, parson?" I asked.</p> 
               <p>"A hundred and sixty pounds," he said.</p> 
               <p>"Well, you can inlist as a hundred and sixty pounds of morphine, your dooty bein to stand in the hospitals arter a battle, and preach while the surgical operations is bein performed! Think how much you'd save the Gov'ment in morphine."</p> 
               <p>He didn't seem to see it; but he made a good speech, and the editor of the <title>Bugle</title> rose to read the resolutions, commencin as follers:</p> 
               <p>
                  <hi rend="i"/>Resolved, That we view with anxiety the fact that there is now a war goin on, and</p> 
               <p>
                  <hi rend="i"/>Resolved, That we believe Stonewall JACKSON sympathizes with the secession movement, and that we hope the nine-months men -</p> 
               <p>At this point he was interrupted by the sounds of silvery footsteps on the stairs, and a party of wimin, carryin guns and led by BETSY JANE, who brandish'd a loud and rattlin umbereller, burst into the room.</p> 
               <p>"Here," cried I, "are some nine-months wimin!"</p> 
               <p>"Mrs. WARD," said the editor of the <title>Bugle</title>-"Mrs. WARD, and ladies, what means this extrord'n'ry demonstration?"</p> 
               <p>"It means," said that remarkable female, "that you men air makin fools of yourselves. You air willin to talk and urge others to go to the wars, but you don't go to the wars yourselves. War meetins is very nice in their way, but they don't keep Stonewall JACKSON from comin over to Maryland and helpin himself to the fattest beef critters. What we want is more cider and less talk. We want you able-bodied men to stop speechifying, which don't mount to the wiggle of a sick cat's tail, and go to fitin; otherwise you can stay to home and take keer of the children, while we wimin will go to the wars!"</p> 
               <p>"Gentl'men," said I, "that's my wife! Go in, old Gal!" and I throw'd up my ancient white hat in perfeck rapters.</p> 
               <p>"Is this roll-book to be filled up with the names of men or wimin?" she cried.</p> 
               <p>"With men-with men!" Our quoty was made up that very night.</p> 
               <p>Still believin that the Goddess of Liberty is about as well sot up with as any young lady in distress could expect to be, I am</p> 
               <closer>
                  <salute>Yours more'n anybody else's,</salute> 
                  <signed>A. WARD.</signed>
               </closer> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC5923-00000010"/> 
               <head>POPULARITY.</head> 
               <p>What a queer thing is popularity. Bill Pug Nose of the "Plug-Uglies" acquires a world-wide reputation by smashing up the "champion of light weights," sets up a saloon upon it, and realizes the first month; while our Missionary, who collected two hundred blankets last August, and at that time saved a like number of little negroes in the West Indies from freezing, has received nothing but the yellow fever. Fiddlers, Prima-Donnas, Horse Operas, learned pigs, and five-legged calves travel through the country, reaping "golden opinions," while editors, inventors, professors, and humanitarians generally, are starving in garrets. Revivals of religion, summer resorts, and pleasure trips, are popular, while trade, commerce, and chloride of lime are decidedly NON EST. Popularity is a queer thing, very. If you don't believe us, try it.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <head>WOMAN'S RIGHTS.</head> 
               <p>I picht my tent in a small town in Injianny one day last seeson, &amp; while I was standin at the dore takin money a deppytashun of ladies came up and sed they wos members of the Bunkumville Female Moral Reformin &amp; Wimmin's Rite's Associashun, and thay axed me if they cood go in without payin.</p> 
               <p>"Not exactly," sez I, "but you can pay without goin in."</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>The Otoe Indian buries his tomahawk, and settles down to farming.</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>"Dew you know who we air?" said one of the wimin-a tall and feroshus lookin critter, with a blew kotton umbreller under her arm-"do you know who we air Sir?"</p> 
               <p>"My impreshun is," sed I, "from a kersery view, that you are females."</p> 
               <p>"We air, Sur," said the feroshus woman-"we belong to a Society whitch beleeves wimin has rites-which beleeves in razin her to her proper speer-whitch beleeves she is endowed with as much intelleck as man is-whitch beleeves she is trampled on and aboozed-&amp; who will resist henso4th &amp; forever the incroachments of proud &amp; domineering men."</p> 
               <p>Durin her discourse, the exsentric female grabed me by the coat-kollor &amp; was swinging her umbreller wildly over my hed.</p> 
               <p>"I hope, marm," sez I, starting back, "that your intensions is honorable? I'm a lone man hear in a strange place. Besides, I've a wife to hum."</p> 
               <p>"Yes," cried the female, "&amp; she's a slave! Doth she never dream of freedom-doth she never think of throwin of the yoke of tyrrinny &amp; thinkin &amp; votin for herself?-Doth she never think of these here things?"</p> 
               <p>"Not bein a natral born fool," sed I, by this time a little riled, "I kin safely say that she dothunt."</p> 
               <p>"O whot-whot!" screamed the female, swingin her umbreller in the air. O, what is the price that woman pays for her expeeriunce!"</p> 
               <p>"I don't know," sez I; "the price to my show is 15 cents pur individooal."</p> 
               <p>"&amp; can't our Sosiety go in free?" asked the female.</p> 
               <p>"Not if I know it." sed I.</p> 
               <p>"Crooil, crooil man!" she cried, &amp; bust into teers.</p> 
               <p>"Won't you let my darter in?" sed anuther of the exsentric wimin, taken me a feckshunitely by the hand. "O, please let my darter in - shee's a sweet gushin child of natur."</p> 
               <p>"Let her gush!" roared I, as mad as I cood stick at their tarnal nonsense; "let her gush!" Where upon they all sprung back with the simultanious observashun that I was a Beest.</p> 
               <p>"My female friends," sed I, "be4 you leeve, Ive a few remarks to remark; wa them well. The female woman is one of the greatest institooshuns of which this land can hoste. It's onpossible to get along without her. Had there bin no female wimin in the world, I should scarcely he here with my unpareleld show on this very occashun. She is good in sickness-good in wellness-good all the time, O, woman, woman!" I cried, my feelins worked up to a hi poctick pitch, "you air a angle when you behave yourself; but when you take off your proper appariel &amp; (mettyforically speaken)-get into panty-loons-when you desert your firesides, &amp; with your heds full of wimin's rites noshuns go round like roarin lyons, seekin whom you may devour someboddy-in short when you undertake to play the man, you play the devil and air an emfatic noosance. My female friends," I continnered, as they were indignantly departing "wa well what A. Ward has sed!"</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <head>SCANDALOUS DOINGS AT PITTSBURG.</head> 
               <p>Here in the Buzzum of my famerly I am enjoyin myself, at peas with awl mankind and the wimmin folks likewize. I go down to the village ockashunly and take a little old Rye fur the stummuck's sake but I avoyd spiritus lickers as a ginral thing. No man evir seen me intossikated but once, and that air happind in Pittsburg. A parsel of ornery cusses in that luvly sity bustid inter the hawl durin the nite and aboosed my wax works shaimful. I didnt obsarve the outrajus transacshuns ontil the next evening when the peple begun for to kongregate. Suddinly they kommensed fur to larf and holler in a boysterious stile. Sez I good peple what's up? Sez thay them's grate wax wurks, isn't they, old man. I immejitly looked up ter whare the wax works was and my blud biles as I think of the site which then met my Gase. I hope to be dodrabbertid if them afoursed raskals hadent gone and put a old kaved in hat onter George Washington's hed and shuved a short black klay pipe inter his mouth. His noze thay had painted red and his trowris legs thay had shuvd inside his butes. My wax figger of Napoleon Boneypart was likewise mawltreatid. His sword wus danglin tween his legs, his cockd hat was drawn klean down over his ize, and he was plased in a stoopin posishun lookin zactly as tho he was as drunk as a biled owl. Ginral Tayler was a standin on his bed and Wingfield Skotts koat tales ware pind over his hed and his trowsis ware kompleetely torn orf from hisself. My wax works representin the Lord's Last Supper was likewise aboozed. Three of the Postles ware under the table and two of um had on old tarpawlin hats and raggid pee jackits and ware smokin pipes. Judas Iskarriot had on a cocked hat and was apeerently drinkin, as a Bottle of whisky sot befour him. This ere specktercal was too much fur me. I klosed the show and then drowndid my sorrers in the flowin Bole.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <head>THE CENSUS.</head> 
               <p>The Sences taker in our town bein taken sick he deppertised me to go out for him one day, and as he was too ill to giv me informashun how to perceed, I was consekently compelled to go it blind. Sittin down by the road side I drawd up the follerin list of questions which I proposed to ax the peple I visited: <list> 
                     <item>Wat's your age?</item> 
                     <item>Whar was you born?</item> 
                     <item>Air you marrid, and if so how do you like it?</item> 
                     <item>How many children hav you, and do they sufficiently resemble you as to proclood the possibility of their belongin to any of your nabers?</item> 
                     <item>Did you ever hav the measels, and if so how many?</item> 
                     <item>Hav you a twin brother several years older than yourself?</item> 
                     <item>How many parents hav you?</item> 
                     <item>Do you read Watt's Hims regler?</item> 
                     <item>Do you use boughten tobacker?</item> 
                     <item>Wat's your fitin wate?</item> 
                     <item>Are you trubeld with biles?</item> 
                     <item>How does your meresham culler?</item> 
                     <item>State whether you air blind, deaf, idiotic or got the heaves?</item> 
                  </list>
               </p> 
               <p>Do you know any Opry singers, and if so how much do they owe you?</p> 
               <p>What's the average of virtoo on the Ery Canawl?</p> 
               <p>If 4 barrils of Emptins pored onto a barn floor will kiver it how many plase can Dion Bourcicault write in a year?</p> 
               <p>Is beans a regler article of diet in your family?</p> 
               <p>How many chickins hav you, on foot and in the shell?</p> 
               <p>Air you aware that Injianny whisky is used in New York shootin galrys instid of pistils, and that it shoots furthest?</p> 
               <p>Was you ever at Niagry Falls?</p> 
               <p>Was you ever in the Penitentiary?</p> 
               <p>State how much pork, impendin crysis, Dutch cheeze, popler suvrinty, standard poctry, childrens' strainer's, slave code, catnip, red flannel, ancient histry, pickled tomaters, ole junk, perfoomery, coal ile, liberty, hoop skirt, &amp;c., you hav on hand?</p> 
               <p>But it didnt work.</p> 
               <p>I got into a row at the fust house I stopt to, with some old maids. Disbeleven the ansers they giv in regard to their ages I endevered to open their mouths and look at their teeth, same as they do with hosses, but they floo into a vilent rage and tackled me with brooms and sich. Takin the senses requires experiunse, like any other bizniss.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <head>WAX FIGURES VS. SHAKSPEARE.</head> 
               <opener>
                  <dateline>ONTO THE WING-1859.</dateline> 
                  <salute>MR. EDITOR:</salute>
               </opener> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>"Home Guard Drill."</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>I take my Pen in hand to inform yu that I'm in good helth and trust these few lines will find yu injoyin the same blessins. I wood also state that I'm now on the summir kampane. As the poet sez - <q>
                     <lg type="quotation"> 
                        <l>ime erflote, ime erflote</l> 
                        <l>On the Swift rollin tied</l> 
                        <l>An the Rovir is free.</l> 
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p> 
               <p>Bizness is scacely middlin, but Sirs I manige to pay for my foode and raiment puncktooally and without no grumblin. The barked arrers of slandur has bin leviled at the undersined moren onct sins heze bin into the show bizness, but I make bold to say no man on this footstule kan troothfully say I ever ronged him or eny of his folks. I'm travelin with a tent, which is better nor hirin hauls. My show konsists of a serious of wax works, snakes, a panoramy kalled a Grand Movin Diarea of the War in the Crymear, komic songs and the Cangaroo, which larst little cuss continers to konduct hisself in the most outrajus stile. I started out with the idear of makin my show a grate Moral Entertainment, but I'm kompelled to sware so much at that air infernal Kangeroo that I'm frade this desire will be flustratid to some extent. And while speakin of morrality remines me that sum folks turn up their nosis at shows like mine, sayin they is low and not fit to be patrernized by peple of high degree. Sirs, I manetane that this is infernal nonsense. I manetane that wax figgers is more elevatin than awl the plays ever wroten. Take Shakespeer for instunse. Peple think heze grate things, but I kontend heze quite the reverse to the konrtary. What sort of sense is thare to King Leer who goze round cussin his darters, chawin hay and throwin straw at folks, and larfin like a silly old koot and makin a ass of hisself ginerally? Thare's Mrs. Macbeth-sheze a nise kind of woomon to have around, aint she, a puttin old Mack, her husband, up to slayin Dunkan with a cheeze knife, while heze payin a frendly visit to their house. O its hily morral, I spoze, when she larfs wildly and sex, "gin me the daggurs-He let his bowels out," or wurds to that effeck-I say, this is awl strictly propper I spoze? That Jack Fawlstarf is likewise a immoral old cuss, take him how ye may, and Hamlick is as crazy as a loon. Thare's Richurd the Three peple think heze grate things, but I look upon him in the lite of a monkster. He kills everybody he taks a noshun to in kold blud, and then goze to sleep in his tent. Bimeby he wakes up and yells for a hoss so he kan go orf and kill sum more peple. If he isn't a fit spesserman for the gallers then I shood like to know whare you find um. Thare's largo who is more ornery nor pizun. See how shamful he treated that hily respecterble injun gentlemun, Mister Otheller, makin him for to beleeve his wife was two thick with Casheo. Obsarve how largo got Casheo drunk as a biled owl on corn whiskey in order to karry out his sneekin desines. See how he wurks Mister Othellers feelins up so that he goze and makes poor Desdemony swaller a piller which cawses her deth. But I must stop.</p> 
               <closer>
                  <salute>Very Respectively, Yures,</salute> 
                  <signed>A. WARD, T. K.</signed>
               </closer> 
            </div> 
            <div type="section"> 
               <head>TOUCHING LETTER FROM A GORY MEMBER OF THE HOME GUARD.</head> 
               <opener>
                  <dateline>-BROADWAY, <date>Dec. 10, '61.</date>
                  </dateline> 
                  <salute>Dear Father and Mother:</salute>
               </opener> 
               <p>We are getting along very well. We mess at Delmonico's Do not repine for your son. Some must suffer for the glorious Stars and Stripes, and dear parents, why shouldn't I? Tell Mrs. Skuller that we do not need the blankets she so kindly sent to us, as we bunk at the St. Nicholas and Metropolitan. What our brave lads stand most in need of now, is Fruit cake and Waffles. Do not weep for me.</p> 
               <closer>
                  <signed>HENRY ADOLPHUS.</signed>
               </closer> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC5923-00000011"/> 
               <head>ARTEMUS WARD TO THE PRINCE OF WALES.</head> 
               <p>FRIEND WALES,-You remember me. I saw you in Canady a few years ago. I remember you too. I seldim forgit a person.</p> 
               <p>I hearn of your marrige to the Printcis Alexandry, &amp; ment ter writ you a congratoolatory letter at the time, but I've bin bildin a barn this summer, &amp; haint had no time to write letters to folks. Excoos me.</p> 
               <p>Numeris changes has tooken place since we met in the body politic. The body politic, in fack, is sick. I sumtimes think it has got biles, friend Wales.</p> 
               <p>In my country we've got a war, while your country, in conjunktion with Cap'n Sems of the <hi rend="i"/>Alobarmy, manetanes a nootral position!</p> 
               <p>I'm fraid I can't write goaks when I sit about it. Oh no, I guess not!</p> 
               <p>Yes, Sir, we've got a war, and the troo Patrit has to make sacrifisses, you bet.</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>The miserable man once played Hamlet, and expired to slow music (produced by himself, as there was no orchestra).</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>I have already given two cousins to the war, &amp; I stand reddy to sacrifiss my wife's brother ruther'n not see the rebelyin krusht. And if wuss cums to wuss I'll shed ev'ry drop of blood my able-bodid relations has got to prosekoot the war. I think sumbody oughter be prosekooted, &amp; it may as well be the war as anybody else. When I git a goakin fit onto me it's no use to try ter stop me.</p> 
               <p>You hearn about the draft, friend Wales, no doubt. It caused sum squirmin', but it was fairly conducted, I think, for it hit all classes. It is troo that Wendill Phillips, who is an American citizen of African scent, 'scaped, but so did Vallandiggum, who is Conservativ, and who wus resuntly sent South, tho' he would have bin sent to the Dry Tortoogas if Abe had sposed for a minit that the Tortoogusses would keep him.</p> 
               <p>We haint got any daily paper in our town, but we've got a female sewin' circle, which ansers the same purpuss, and we wasn't long in suspents as to who was drafted.</p> 
               <p>One young man who was drawd claimed to be exemp because he was the only son of a widow'd mother who supported him. A few able-bodid dead men was drafted, but whether their heirs will have to pay 3 hundrid dollars a peace for 'em is a question for Whitin', who 'pears to be tinkerin' up this draft bizzniss right smart. I hope he makes good wages.</p> 
               <p>I think most of the conscrips in this place will go. A few will go to Canady, stoppin on their way at Concord N.H., where I understan there is a Muslum of Harts.</p> 
               <p>You see I'm sassy, friend Wales, hittin all sides; but no offense is ment. You know I aint a politician, and never was. I vote for Mr. Union-that's the only candidate I've got. I claim, howsever, to have a well-balanced mind; tho' my idees of a well-balanced mind differs from the idees of a partner I once had, whose name it was Billson. Billson and me orjanized a strollin' dramatic company, &amp; we played. The Drunkard, or the Falling Saved, with a real drunkard. The play didn't take particularly, and says Billson to me, Let's giv 'em some immoral dramy. We had a large troop onto our hands, consistin' of eight tragedians and a bass drum, but I says, No, Billson; and then says I, Billson, you haint got a well-balanced mind. Says he, Yes, I have, old hoss-fly (he was a low cuss)-yes, I have. I have a mind, says he, that balances in any direction that the public rekires. That's wot I calls a well-balanced mind. I sold out and bid adoo to Billson. He is now an outcast in the State of Vermont. The miser'ble man once played Hamlet. There wasn't any orchestry, and wishin to expire to slow moosic, he died playin on a claironett himself, interspersed with hart-rendin groans, &amp; such is the world! Alars! alars! how onthankful we air to that Providence which kindly allows us to live and borrow money, and fail and do bizniss!</p> 
               <p>But to return to our subjeck. With our resunt grate triumps on the Mississippi, the Father of Waters (and them is waters no Father need feel 'shamed of-twig the wittikism?), and the cheerin look of things in other places, I reckon we shan't want any Muslum of Harts. And what upon airth do the people of Concord N. H., want a Muslum of Harts for? Haint you got the State House now? &amp; what more do you want?</p> 
               <p>But all this is furrin to the purpuss of this note, arter all. My objeck in now addressin' you is to giv you sum adwice, friend Wales, about managin your wife, a bizniss I've-had over thirty years' experience in.</p> 
               <p>You had a good weddin. The papers hav a good deal to say about "vikings" in connexion tharewith. Not knowing what that air is, and so I frankly tells you, my noble lord dook of the throne, I can't zackly say whether we had 'em or not. We was both very much flustrated. But I never injoyed myself better in my life.</p> 
               <p>Dowtless, your supper was ahead of our'n. As regards eatin' uses Baldinsville was allers shaky. But you can git a good meal in New York, &amp; cheap too. You can git half a mackril at Deimonico's or Mr. Mason Dory's for six dollars, and biled pertaters throwed in.</p> 
               <p>As I sed, I manige my wife without any particler trouble. When I fust commenst trainin' her I institooted a series of experiments, and them as didn't work I abanding'd. You'd better do similer. Your wife may objeck to gittin' up and bildin' the fire in the mornin' but if you commence with her at once you may be able to overkum this prejoodiss. I regret to obsarve that I didn't commence arly enuff. I wouldn't have you s'pose I was ever kicked out of bed. Not at all. I simply say, in regard to bildin' fires that I didn't commence arly enuff. It was a ruther cold mornin' when I fust proposed the idee to Betsy. It wasn't well received, and I found myself layin' on the floor putty suddent. I thought I git up and bild the fire myself.</p> 
               <p>Of course now you're marrid you can eat onions. <emph>I</emph> allus did, and if I know my own hart, I allus will. My daughter, who is goin' on 17 and is frisky, says they's disgustin. And speakin of my daughter reminds me that quite a number of young men have suddenly discovered that I'm a very entertainin' old feller, and they visit us frekently, specially on Sunday evenins. One young chap-a lawyer by habit-don't cum as much as he did. My wife's father lives with us. His intelleck totters a little, and he saves the papers containin' the proceedins of our State Legislater. The old <unclear>gentl'man</unclear> likes to read out loud, and he reads tol'ble well. He eats hash freely, which makes his voice clear; but as he onfortnitly has to spell the most of his words, I may say he reads slow. Wall, whenever this lawyer made his appearance I would set the old man a-readin the Legislativ' reports. I kept the young lawyer up one night till 12 o'clock, listenin to a lot of acts in regard to a draw-bridge away off in the east part of the State, havin' sent my daughter to bed at half past 8. He hasn't been there since, and I understan' he says I go round swindlin' the Public.</p> 
               <p>
                  <emph>I</emph> never attempted to reorganize my wife but once. I shall never attempt again. I'd bin to a public dinner, and had allowed myself to<pb n=""/> be betrayed into drinking several people's healths; and wishin' to make 'em as robust as possible, I continuerd drinkin' their healths until my own became affected. Consekens was, I presented myself at Betsy's bedside late at night with consid'ble licker concealed about my person. I had sumhow got perseshun of a hosswhip on my way home, and rememberin' sum cranky observations of Mrs. Ward's in the mornin' I snapt the whip putty lively, and, in a very loud woice, I said, "Betsy, you need reorganizin'! I have cum, Betsy," I continued-crackin' the whip over the bed-"I have cum to reorganize you! Ha-ave you per-ayed to-night?"</p> 
               <p>I dream'd that night that sumbody had laid a hosswhip over me sev'ril conseckootiv times; and when I woke up I found she had. I haint drank much of anythin' since, and if I ever have another reorganizin' job on hand I shall let it out.</p> 
               <p>My wife is 52 years old, and has allus sustaned a good character. She's a good cook. Her mother lived to a vener'ble age, and died while in the act of frying slap-jacks for the County Commissionerr. And may no rood hand pluk a flour from her toomstun! We haint got any picter of the old lady, because she'd never stand for her ambrotipe, and therefore I can't giv her likeness to the world through the meejum of the illusterated papers; but as she wasn't a brigadiergin'ral, particerly, I don't s'pose they'd publish it, anyhow.</p> 
               <p>There's varis ways of managin' a wife, friend Wales, but the best and only safe way is to let her do jist about as she wants to. I 'dopted that there plan sum time ago, and it works like a charm.</p> 
               <p>It may interest you to know that I'm prosperin' in a pecoonery pint of view. I make bout as much in the course of a year as a Cab'net offisser does, &amp; I understan' my bizniss a good deal better than sum of 'em do. Respecks to St. Gorge &amp; the Dragon.</p> 
               <closer>
                  <salute>"Ever be happy."</salute> 
                  <signed>A. WARD.</signed>
               </closer> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <head>"I AM HERE!"</head> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>The Boston man gets into a state of excitement with the mule-driver.</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>There is no mistake about that, and there is a good prospect of my staying here for some time to come. The snow is deep on the ground, and more is falling.</p> 
               <p>The doctor looks glum, and speaks of his ill-starred countryman, Sir J. Franklin, who went to the Arctic once too much.</p> 
               <p>"A good thing happened down here the other day," said a miner from New Hampshire to me. "A man of Boston dressin' went through there, and at one of the stations there wasn't any mules. Says the man who was fixed out to kill in his Boston dressin', 'Where's them mules?' Says the driver, 'Them mules is into the sage-brush. You go catch 'em - that's wot <emph>you</emph> do.' Says the man of Boston dressin', 'Oh no!' Says the Driver, 'Oh yes!' and he took his long coach whip and licked the man of Boston dressin' till he went and caught them mules. How does that strike you as a joke?"</p> 
               <p>It didn't strike me as much of a joke to pay a hundred and seventy-five dollars in gold fare, and then be horse-whipped by stage-drivers, for declining to chase mules. But people's ideas differ in regard to shrewdness-which "reminds me of a little story." Sitting in a New England country store one day I overheard the following dialogue between two brothers:</p> 
               <p>"Say, Bill, wot you done with that air sorrel mare of yourn?"</p> 
               <p>"Sold her," said William, with a smile of satisfaction.</p> 
               <p>"Wot 'd you git?"</p> 
               <p>"Hund'd an' fifty dollars, cash deown!"</p> 
               <p>"Show! Hund'd an' fifty for that kickin', spavin'd critter?-Who'd you sell her to?"</p> 
               <p>"Sold her to mother!"</p> 
               <p>"Wot!", exclaimed brother No, 1, "did you railly sell that kickin' spavin'd critter to mother? Wall, you <emph>air</emph> a shrewd one!"</p> 
               <p>A Sensation Arrival by the overland Stage of two Missouri girls. They are going to Nevada territory to join their father.</p> 
               <p>"This is the first Squar' meal we've had since we left Rocky Thompson's," said the eldest. Then addressing herself to me, she said:</p> 
               <p>"Air you the literary man?"</p> 
               <p>I politely replied that I was one of "them fellers."</p> 
               <p>"Wall, don't make fun of our clothes in the papers. We air going right straight through in these here clothes, <emph>we</emph> air! We ain't goin' to <emph>rag out</emph> till we get to Nevady! Pass them sassiges!"</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <p>We have read a great many stories of which Winchell, the great wit and mimic, was the hero, showing always how neatly and entirely he sold somebody. Any one who is familiar with Winchell's wonderful powers of mimicry cannot doubt that these stories are all substantially true. But there is one instance which we will relate, or perish in the attempt, where the jolly Winchell was himself sold. The other evening, while he was conversing with several gentlemen at one of the hotels, a dilapidated individual reeled into the room and halted in front of the stove, where he made wild and unsuccessful efforts to maintain a firm position. He evidently had spent the evening in marching torchlight processions of forty-rod whiskey down his throat, and at this particular time was decidedly and disreputably drunk. With a sly wink to the crowd, as much as to say, "We'll have some fun with this individual," Winchell assumed a solemn face, and in a ghostly voice said to one of the company:</p> 
               <p>"The poor fellow we were speaking of is dead!"</p> 
               <p>"No?" said the individual addressed.</p> 
               <p>"Yes," said Winchell. "You know both of his eyes were gouged out, his nose was chawed off, and both of his arms were torn out at the roots. Of course he couldn't recover."</p> 
               <p>This was all said for the benefit of the drunken man, who was standing, or trying to stand, within a few feet of Winchell, but he took no sort of notice of it and was apparently ignorant of the celebrated delineator's presence. Again Winchell endeavored to attract his attention, but utterly failed as before. In a few moments the drunken man staggered out of the room.</p> 
               <p>"I can generally have a little fun with a drunken man," said Winchell, "but it is no go in this case.</p> 
               <p>"I suppose you know what ails the man who just went out?" said the "gentlemanly host."</p> 
               <p>"I perceive he is alarmingly inebriated," said Winchell; "does anything else all him?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes," said the host,-"HE'S DEAF AND DUMB!"</p> 
               <p>This was true. There was a "larf," and Winchell subsided.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC5923-00000012"/> 
               <head>THINGS IN NEW YORK.</head> 
               <p>The stoodent and connyseer must have noticed and admired in varis parts of the United States of America, large yeller hanbills, which not only air gems of art in theirselves, but they troothfully sit forth the attractions of my show-a show let me here obsarve that contains many livin', wild animils, every one of which has got a Beautiful Moral.</p> 
               <p>Them hanbils is sculpt in New York.</p> 
               <p>&amp; I annooly repair here to git some more on 'um;</p> 
               <p>&amp; bein' here, I tho't I'd issoo a Address to the public on matters and things.</p> 
               <p>Since last I meyandered these streets, I have been all over the Pacific Slopes and Utah. I cum back now, with my virtoo unimpared, but I've got to git some new clothes.</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>An objeck who says he wont go to the war.</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>Many changes has taken place, even durin' my short absence, &amp; sum on um is Sollum to contempulate. The house in Varick street, where I used to Board, is bein' torn down. That house, which was rendered memoriable by my livin' into it, is "parsin' away! parsin' away!" But some of the timbers will be made into canes, which will be sold to my admirers at the low price of one dollar each. Thus is changes goin' on continerly. In the New World it is wat-in the Old World Empires is totterin' &amp; Dysentaries is crumblin'. These canes is cheap at a dollar.</p> 
               <p>Sammy Booth, Duane street, sculps my hanbils, &amp; he's a artist. He studid in Rome-State of New York.</p> 
               <p>I'm here to read the proof-sheets of my hanbils as fast as they're sculpt. You have to watch these ere printers pretty close, for they're just as apt to spel a wurd rong as anyhow.</p> 
               <p>But I have time to look round sum &amp; how do I find things? I return to the Atlantic States after a absence of ten months, &amp; what State do I find the country in? Why I don't know what State I find it in. Suffice it to say, that I do not find it in the State of New Jersey.</p> 
               <p>I find some things that is cheerin', partic'ly the resolve on the part of the wimin of America to stop wearin' furrin' goods.</p> 
               <p>I never meddle with my wife's things. She may wear muslin from Greenland's icy mountins, and bombazeen from Injy's coral strands, if she wants to; but I'm glad to state that that superior woman has peeled off all her furrin clothes and jumpt into fabrics of domestic manufactur.</p> 
               <p>But, says sum folks, if you stop importin' things you stop the revenoo. That's all right. We can stand it if the Revenoo can. On the same principle young men should continer to get drunk on French brandy and to smoke their livers as dry as a corn-cob with Cuby cigars because 4-sooth if they don't, it will hurt the Revenoo! This talk 'bout the Revenoo is of the bosh, boshy. One thing is tol'bly certin-if we don't send gold out of the dountry we shall have the consolation of knowing that it is in the country. So I say great credit is doo the wimin for this patriotic move-and to tell the trooth, the wimin generally know what they're 'bout. Of all the blossins they're the soothinist. If there'd never bin any wimin, where would my children be to-day?</p> 
               <p>But I hope this move will lead to other moves that air just as much needed, one of which is a general and therrer curtainment of expenses all round. The fact is we air gettin' ter'bly extravagant, &amp; onless we paws in our mad career in less than two years the Goddess of Liberty will be seen dodgin' into a Pawn Broker's shop with the other gown done up in a bundle, even if she don't have to Spout the gold stars in her head-band. Let us all take hold jintly, and live and dress centsibly, like our forefathers, who know'd moren we do, if they warnt quite so honest! (Suttle goaketh.)</p> 
               <p>At a special Congressional 'lection in my district the other day I delib'ritly voted for Henry Clay. I admit that Henry is dead, but inasmuch as we don't seem to have a live statesman in our National Congress, let us by all means have a first-class corpse.</p> 
               <p>Them who think that a cane made from the timbers of the house I once boarded in is essenshal to their happiness, should not delay about sendin' the money right on for one. And now, with a genuine hurrar for the wimin who air goin' to abandin furren goods, and another for the patrotic everywheres, I'll leave public matters and indulge in a little pleasant family-gosip.</p> 
               <p>It was II, P. M., when I reached my homestid and knockt a healthy knock on the door thereof.</p> 
               <p>A nightcap thrusted itself out of the front chamber winder. (It was my Betsy's nightcap.) And a voice said:</p> 
               <p>"Who is it?"</p> 
               <p>"It is a man!" I answered in a gruff vois.</p> 
               <p>"I don't b'lieve it!" she sed.</p> 
               <p>"Then come down and search me," I replied.</p> 
               <p>Then resumin' my nat'ral voice, I said, "It is your own A. W., Betsy! Sweet lady, wake! Ever of thou!"</p> 
               <p>"Oh," she said, "it's you, is it? I thought I smelt something."</p> 
               <p>But the old girl was glad to see me.</p> 
               <p>In the mornin' I found that my family were entertainin' a artist from Philadelphy, who was there paintin' some startlin' water-falls and mountins, and I morin suspected he had a hankerin' for my oldest dauter.</p> 
               <p>"Mr. Skimmerhorn, father," sed my dauter.</p> 
               <p>"Glad to see you, Sir!" I replied, in a hospittle vois. "Glad to see you."</p> 
               <p>"He is an artist, father," sed my child.</p> 
               <p>"A whichist?"</p> 
               <p>"An artist. A painter."</p> 
               <p>"And glazier?" I askt. "Air you a painter and glazier, sir?"</p> 
               <p>My dauter and wife was mad, but I couldn't help it, I felt in a comikil mood.</p> 
               <p>"It is a wonder to me, Sir," said the artist, "considerin' what a wide-spread reputation you heve, that some of our Eastern managers don't secure you."</p> 
               <p>"It's a wonder to me," said I to my wife, "that somebody don't secure him with a chain."</p> 
               <p>My reported capture by the North American savijis of Utah, led my wide circle of friends and creditors to think that I had bid adoo to earthly things and was a angel playin' on a golden harp. Hents my rival home was onexpected.</p> 
               <p>A few days after my return I was shown a young man, who says he'll be Dam if he goes to the war. He was sittin' on a barrel, &amp; was indeed a Loathsum objeck.</p> 
               <p>Last Sunday I heard Parson Batkins preach, and the good old man preached well, too, tho his prayer was ruther lengthy. The Editor of the <title>Bugle</title>, who was with me, said that prayer would make fifteen squares, solid nonparil."</p> 
               <closer>
                  <signed>A. WARD.</signed>
               </closer> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <head>AGRICULTURE.</head> 
               <argument> 
                  <p>The Barclay County Agricultural Society having seriously invited the author of this volume to address them on the occasion of their next annual Fair, he wrote the President of that Society as follows:</p> 
               </argument> 
               <opener>
                  <dateline>NEW YORK, June 12, 1865.</dateline> 
                  <salute>DEAR SIR: -</salute>
               </opener> 
               <p>I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 5th inst., in which you invite me to deliver an address before your excellent agricultural society.</p> 
               <p>I feel flattered, and think I will come.</p> 
               <p>I have been an honest old farmer for some four years.</p> 
               <p>My farm is in the interior of Maine. Unfortunately my lands are eleven miles from the railroad. Eleven miles is quite a distance to haul immense quantities of wheat, corn, rye, and oats; but as I hav'n't any to haul, I do not, after all, suffer much on that account.</p> 
               <p>My farm is more especially a grass farm.</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>Artemus finds it pleasant strolling about his farm with his dressing-gown and cigar.</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>My neighbors told me so at first, and as an evidence that they were sincere in that opinion, they turned their cows on to it the moment I went off "lecturing."</p> 
               <p>These cows are now quite fat. I take pride in these cows, in fact, and am glad I own a grass farm.</p> 
               <p>Two years ago I tried sheep-raising.</p> 
               <p>I bought fifty lambs, and turned them loose on my broad and beautiful acres.</p> 
               <p>It was pleasant on bright mornings to stroll leisurely out on to the farm in my dressing-gown, with a cigar in my mouth, and watch those innocent little lambs as they danced gaily o'er the hill-side. Watching their saucy capers reminded me of caper sauce, and it occurred to me I should have some very fine eating when they grew up to be "muttons."</p> 
               <p>I wrote to my old friend, Mr. Dexter H. Follett, of Boston, for two shepherd dogs Mr. F. is not an honest old farmer himself, but I thought he knew about shepherd dogs. He kindly forsook far more important business to accommodate, and the dogs came forthwith. They were splendid creatures-snuff-colored, hazel-eyed, long-tailed, and shapely-jawed.</p> 
               <p>We led them proudly to the fields.</p> 
               <p>"Turn them in, Mr. Perkins," I said.</p> 
               <p>Eli turned them in.</p> 
               <p>They went in at once, and killed twenty of my best lambs in about four minutes and a half.</p> 
               <p>My friend had made a trifling mistake in the breed of these dogs.</p> 
               <p>These dogs were not partial to sheep.</p> 
               <p>Eli Perkins was astonished, and observed:</p> 
               <p>"Waal! <emph>did</emph> you ever?" I certainly never had.</p> 
               <p>There were pools of blood on the greensward, and fragments of wool and raw lamb chops lay round in confused heaps.</p> 
               <p>The dogs would have been sent to Boston that night, had they not rather suddenly died that afternoon of a throat-distemper. It wasn't a swelling of the throat. It wasn't diphtheria. It was a violent opening of the throat, extending from ear to ear.</p> 
               <p>Thus closed their life-stories. Thus ended their interesting tails.</p> 
               <p>I failed as a raiser of lambs. As a sheepist, I was not a success.</p> 
               <p>Last summer Mr. Perkins said, "I think we'd better cut some grass this season, sir."</p> 
               <p>We cut some grass.</p> 
               <p>We hired four honest farmers to assist us, and I led them gaily to the meadows.</p> 
               <p>I was going to mow myself.</p> 
               <p>I saw the sturdy peasants go round once ere I dipped my flashing scythe into the tall green grass.</p> 
               <p>"Are you ready?" said E. Perkins.</p> 
               <p>"I am here!"</p> 
               <p>"Then follow us!"</p> 
               <p>I followed them.</p> 
               <p>Followed them rather too closely, evidently, for a white-haired old man, who immediately followed Mr. Perkins, called upon us to halt. Then in a low firm voice he said to his son, who was just ahead of me, "John, change places with me. I hain't got long to live, anyhow. Yonder berriyn' ground will soon have these old bones, and it's no matter whether I'm carried there with one leg off and ter'ble gashes in the other or not! But you, John-<emph>you</emph> are young."</p> 
               <p>The old man changed places with his son. A smile of calm resignation lit up his wrinkled face, as he said, "Now, sir, I am ready!"</p> 
               <p>"What mean you, old man?" I said.</p> 
               <p>"I mean that if you continner to bran'ish that blade as you have been bran'ishin' it, you'll slash h- out of some of us before we're a hour-older!"</p> 
               <p>There was some reason mingled with this white-haired old peasant's profanity. It was true that I had twice escaped mowing off his son's legs, and his father was perhaps naturally alarmed.</p> 
               <p>I went and sat down under a tree. "I never know'd a literary man in my life," I overheard the old man say, "that know'd anything."</p> 
               <p>Mr. Perkins was not as valuable to me this season as I had fancied he might be. Every afternoon he disappeared from the field regularly, and remained about some two hours. He said it was a headache. He inherited it from his mother. His mother was often taken in that way, and suffered a great deal.</p> 
               <p>At the end of the two hours Mr. Perkins would reappear with his head neatly done up in a large wet rag, and say he "felt better."</p> 
               <p>One afternoon it so happened that I soon followed the invalid to the house, and as I neared the porch I heard a female voice energetically observe, "You stop!" It was the voice of the hired girl, and she added, "I'll holler for Mr. Brown!"</p> 
               <p>"Oh, no, Nancy," I heard the invalid E. Perkins soothingly say, "Mr. Brown knows I love you. Mr. Brown approves of it!"</p> 
               <p>This was pleasant for Mr. Brown!</p> 
               <p>I peered cautiously through the kitchen-blinds, and, however unnatural it may appear, the lips of Eli Perkins and my hired girl were very near together. She said, "You shan't do so," and he <emph>do-soed</emph>. She also said she would get right up and go away, and as an evidence that she was thoroughly in earnest about it, she remained where she was.</p> 
               <p>They are married, and Mr. Perkins is never troubled with headache.</p> 
               <p>My friend Mr. D. T. T. Moore, of the <title>Rural New Yorker</title>, thinks if I "keep on" I will get in the Poor House in about two years.</p> 
               <p>If you think the honest farmers of Barclay Co. want me, I will come.</p> 
               <closer>
                  <salute>Truly Yours,</salute> 
                  <signed>CHARLES F. BROWNE.</signed>
               </closer> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC5923-00000013"/> 
               <head>A MORMON ROMANCE.-REGINALD GLOVERSON.</head> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER I.-THE MORMON'S DEPARTURE.</head> 
                  <p>The morning on which Reginald Gloverson was to leave Great Salt Lake City with a mule-train, dawned beautifully.</p> 
                  <p>Reginald Gloverson was a young and thrifty Mormon, with an interesting family of twenty young and handsome wives. His unions had never been blessed with children. As often as once a year he used to go to Omaha, in Nebraska, with a mule-train for goods; but although he had performed the rather perilous journey many times with entire safety, his heart was strangely sad on this particular morning, and filled with gloomy forebodings.</p> 
                  <p>The time for his departure had arrived. The high-spirited mules were at the door, impatiently champing their bits. The Mormon stood sadly among his weeping wives.</p> 
                  <p>
                     <figure> 
                        <head>"I knew when my Reginald staggered into the dooryard that he was on the Die."</head> 
                     </figure>
                  </p> 
                  <p>"Dearest ones," he said, "I am singularly sad at heart this morning; but do not let this depress you. The journey is a perilous one, but - pshaw I have always come back safely heretofore, and why should I fear? Besides, I know that every night, as I lay down on the broad starlit prairie, your bright faces will come to me in my dreams, and make my slumbers sweet and gentle. You, Emily, with your mild blue eyes; and you, Henrietta, with your splendid black hair; and you, Nelly, with your hair so brightly, beautifully golden; and you, Mollie, with your cheeks so downy; and you, Betsey, with your wine-red lips, far more delicious, though, than any wine I ever tasted-and you, Maria, with your winsome voice; and you, Susan, with your-with your-that is to say, Susan, with your-and the other thirteen of you, each so good and beautiful, will come to me in sweet dreams, will you not, Dearestists?"</p> 
                  <p>"Our own," they lovingly chimed, "we will!"</p> 
                  <p>"And so farewell!" cried Reginald. "Come to my arms, my own!" he said, "that is, as many of you as can do it conveniently at once, for I must away."</p> 
                  <p>He folded several of them to his throbbing breast, and drove sadly away.</p> 
                  <p>But he had not gone far when the trace of the off-hind mule became unhitched. Dismounting, he essayed to adjust the trace; but ere he had fairly commenced the task, the mule, a singularly refractory animal - snorted wildly, and kicked Reginald frightfully in the stomach. He arose with difficulty, and tottered feebly towards his mother's house, which was near by, falling dead in her yard, with the remark, "Dear Mother, I've come home to die!"</p> 
                  <p>"So I see," she said; "where's the mules!"</p> 
                  <p>Alas I Reginald Gloverson could give no answer. In vain the heart-stricken mother threw herself upon his inanimate form, crying, "Oh, my son-my son I only tell me where the mules are, and then you may die if you want to."</p> 
                  <p>In vain-in vain! Reginald had passed on.</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER II.-FUNERAL TRAPPINGS.</head> 
                  <p>The mules were never found.</p> 
                  <p>Reginald's heart-broken mother took the body home to her unfortunate son's widows. But before her arrival she indiscreetly sent a boy to Bust the news gently to the afflicted wives, which he did by informing them, in a hoarse whisper, that their "old man had gone in."</p> 
                  <p>The wives felt very badly indeed.</p> 
                  <p>"He was devoted to me," sobbed Emily.</p> 
                  <p>"And to me," said Maria.</p> 
                  <p>"Yes," said Emily, "he thought considerably of you, but not so much as he did of me."</p> 
                  <p>"I say he did!"</p> 
                  <p>"And I say he didn't!"</p> 
                  <p>"He did!"</p> 
                  <p>"He didn't!"</p> 
                  <p>"Don't look at <emph>me</emph>, with your squint eyes!"</p> 
                  <p>"Don't shake your red head at <emph>me!</emph>"</p> 
                  <p>"Sisters!" said the black-haired Henrietta, "cease this unseemly wrangling. I, as his first wife, shall strew flowers on his grave."</p> 
                  <p>"No you <emph>won't</emph>," said Susan. "I, as his last wife, shall strew flowers on his grave. It's <emph>my</emph> business to strew!"</p> 
                  <p>"You shan't, so there!" said Hearietta.</p> 
                  <p>"You bet I will!" said Susan, with a tear-suffused cheek.</p> 
                  <p>"Well, as for me," said the practical Betsy, "I ain't on the Strew, much, but I shall ride at the head of the funeral procession!"</p> 
                  <p>"Not if I've been introduced to myself, you won't," said the golden-haired Nelly; "that's my position. You bet your bonnet strings it is."</p> 
                  <p>"Children," said Reginald's mother, "you must do some crying, you know, on the day of the funeral; and how many pocket-handkerchers will it take to go round? Betsy, you and Nelly ought to make one do between you."</p> 
                  <p>"I'll tear her eyes out if she perpetuates a sob on my handkercher!" said Nelly.</p> 
                  <p>"Dear daughters-in-law," said Reginald's mother, "how unseemly is this anger. Mules is five hundred dollars a span, and every identical mule my poor boy had has been gobbled up by the red man. I knew when my Reginald staggered into the door-yard that he was on the Die, but if I'd only thunk to ask him about them mules ere his gentle spirit took flight, it would have been four thousand dollars in <emph>our</emph> pockets, and <emph>no</emph> mistake! Excuse those real tears, but you've never felt a parent's feelins."</p> 
                  <p>"It's an oversight," sobbed Maria. "Don't blame us!"</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER III.-DUST TO DUST.</head> 
                  <p>The funeral passed off in a very pleasant manner, nothing occurring to mar the harmony of the occasion. By a happy thought of Reginald's mother the wives walked to the grave twenty abreast, which rendered that part of the ceremony thoroughly impartial.</p> 
                  <p>That night the twenty wives with heavy hearts, sought their twenty respective couches. But no Reginald occupied those twenty respective couches-Reginald would nevermore linger all night in blissful repose in those twenty respective couches-Reginald's head would nevermore press the twenty respective pillows of those twenty respective couches-never, nevermore!</p> 
                  <pb n=""/> 
                  <p>In another house, not many leagues from the House of Mourning, a gray-haired woman was weeping passionately. "He died," she cried, "he died without sigerfyin, in any respect, where them mules went to!"</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER IV.-MARRIED AGAIN.</head> 
                  <p>Two years elapse between the third and fourth chapters.</p> 
                  <p>A manly Mormon, one evening, as the sun was preparing to set among a select apartment of gold and crimson clouds in the western horizon - although for that matter the sun has a right to "set" where it wants to, and so, I may add, has a hen-a manly Mormon, I say, tapped gently at the door of the mansion of the late Reginald Gloverson.</p> 
                  <p>The door was opened by Mrs. Susan Gloverson.</p> 
                  <p>"Is this the house of the widow Gloverson?"-the Mormon asked.</p> 
                  <p>"It is," said Susan.</p> 
                  <p>"And how many is there of she?" inquired the Mormon.</p> 
                  <p>"There is about twenty of her, including me," returned Susan.</p> 
                  <p>"Can I see her?"</p> 
                  <p>"You can."</p> 
                  <p>"Madam," he softly said, addressing the twenty disconsolate widows, "I have seen part of you before! And although I have already twenty-five wives, whom I respect and tenderly care for, I can truly say that I never felt love's holy thrill till I saw thee! Be mine-be mine!" he enthusiastically cried, "and we will show the world a striking illustration of the beauty and truth of the noble lines, only a good deal more so- <q>
                        <lg type="quotation"> 
                           <l>'Twenty-one souls with a single thought,</l> 
                           <l>Twenty-one hearts that beat as one!'"</l> 
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                  </p> 
                  <p>They were united, they were!</p> 
               </div> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <head>THE NOBLE RED MAN</head> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>Lo! The poor Red man and a "pretty waiter girl."</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>The red man of the forest was form'ly a very respectful person. Justice to the noble aboorygine warrants me in sayin' that orrigernerly he was a majestic cuss.</p> 
               <p>At the time CHRIS, arrove on these shores (I allood to CHRIS. COLUMBUS) the savajis was virtoous and happy. They were innocent of secession, rum, draw-poker, and sinfulness gin'rally. They didn't discuss the slavery question as a custom, They had no Congress, faro banks, delirium tremens, or Associated Press. Their habits was consequently good. Late suppers, dyspepsy, gas companies, thieves, ward politicians, pretty waiter-girls, and and other metropolitan refinements, were unknown among them. No savage in good standing would take postage-stamps. You couldn't have bo't a coon skin with a barrel of 'em. The female Aboorygine never died of consumption, because she didn't tie her waist up in whale-bone things; but in loose and flow-in' garments she bounded, with naked feet, over hills and plains like the wild and frisky antelope. It was a onlucky moment for us when CHRIS. sot his foot onto these 'ere shores. It would have been better for us of the present day if the injins had given him a warm meal and sent him home ore the ragin' billers. For the savages owned the country, and COLUMBUS was a fillibuster. CORTEZ, PIZARRO, and WALKER were one-horse fillibusters-COLUMBUS was a four-horse team fillibuster, and a large yaller, dog under the waggin. I say, in view of the mess we're makin' of things, it would have been better for us if COLUMBUS had staid to home. It would have been better for the show bisniss. The circulation of VANITY FAIR would be larger, and the proprietors would all have boozum pins! Yes, sir, and perhaps a ten-pin alley.</p> 
               <p>By which I don't wish to be understood as intimatin' that the scalpin' wretches who are in the injin bisniss at the present day are of any account, or calculated to make home happy, specially the Sioxes of Minnesoty, who desarve to be murdered in the first degree, and if POPE will only stay in St. Paul and not go near 'em <emph>himself</emph>, I reckon they will be.</p> 
               <p>A MAN in Buffalo-an entire stranger to us-sends us a quarter-column puff of his business, with the cool request that we "copy as editorial, and oblige." If he does not eventually subside into a highway robber it won't be for lack of the necessary impudence.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <head>BUSTS.</head> 
               <p>There are in this city several Italian gentlemen engaged in the bust business. They have peculiarities and eccentricities. They are swarthy-faced, wear slouched caps and drab pea-jackets, and smoke bad cigars. They make busts of Webster, Clay, Bonaparte, Douglas, and other great men, living and dead. The Italian buster comes upon you solemnly and cautiously. "Buy Napo-leon?" he will say, and you may probably answer "not a buy." "How much giv-ee?" he asks, and perhaps you will ask him how much he wants. "Nine dollar," he will answer always. We are sure of it. We have observed this peculiarity in the busters frequently. No matter how large or small the bust may be, the first price is invariably "nine dollar." If you decline paying this price, as you undoubtedly will if you are right in your head, he again asks, "how much giv-ee?" By way of a joke you say "a dollar," when the buster retreats indignantly to the door, saying in a low, wild voice, "O dam!" With his hand upon the door-latch, he turns and once more asks, "how much giv-ee?" You repeat the previous offer, when he mutters, "O ha!" then coming pleasantly towards you, he speaks thus: "Say! how much giv-ee?" Again you say a dollar, and he cries, "take 'um, take 'um!" - thus falling eight dollars on his original price.</p> 
               <p>Very eccentric is the Italian buster, and sometimes he calls his busts by wrong names. We bought Webster (he called him Web-STAR) of him the other day, and were astonished when he called upon us the next day with another bust of Webster, exactly like the one we had purchased of him, and asked us if we didn't want to buy "Cole, the wife-pizener!" We endeavored to rebuke the depraved buster, but our utterance was choked, and we could only gaze upon him in speechless astonishment and indignation.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC5923-00000014"/> 
               <head>THE ISTHMUS.</head> 
               <p>On the ninth day we reach Aspinwall in the Republic of Grenada. The President of New Grenada is a Central American named Mosquero. I was told that he derived quite a portion of his income by carrying passengers' valises and things from the steamer to the hotels in Aspinwall. It was an infamous falsehood. Fancy A. Lincoln carrying carpet-bags and things! and indeed I should rather trust him with them than Mosquero, because the former gentleman, as I think some one has before observed, is "honest."</p> 
               <p>I intrust my bag to a speckled native, who confidentially gives me to understand that he is the only strictly honest person in Aspinwall. The rest, he says, are niggers-which the colored people of the Isthmus regard as about as scathing a thing as they can say of one another.</p> 
               <p>I examine the New Grenadian flag, which waves from the chamber-window of a refreshment saloon. It is of simple design. You can make one.</p> 
               <p>Take half of a cotton shirt, that has been worn two months, and dip it in molasses of the Day and Martin brand. Then let the flies gambol over it for a few days, and you have it. It is an emblem of Sweet Liberty.</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>An inebrated Colifornia miner desires to be an angel, and with the angels stand.</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>At the Howard House the man of sin rubbeth the hair of the horse to the bowels of the cat, and our girls are waving their lily-white hoofs in the dazzling waltz.</p> 
               <p>We have a quardille, in which an English person slips up and jams his massive brow against my stomach. He apologizes, and I say, "all right, my lord." I subsequently ascertained that he superintended the shipping of coals for the British steamers, and owned fighting cocks.</p> 
               <p>The ball stops suddenly.</p> 
               <p>Great excitement. One of our passengers intoxicated and riotous in the street. Openly and avowedly desires the entire Republic of New Grenada to "come on."</p> 
               <p>In case they do come on, agrees to make it lively for them. Is quieted down at last, and marched off to prison, by a squad of Grenadian troops. Is musical as he passes the hotel, and smiling sweetly upon the ladies and children on the balcony, expresses a distinct desire to be an Angel, and with the Angels stand. After which he leaps nimbly into the air, and imitates the war-cry of the red man.</p> 
               <p>The natives amass wealth by carrying valises, &amp;c., then squander it for liquor. My native comes to me as I sit on the veranda of the Howard House smoking a cigar, and solicits the job of taking my things to the cars next morning. He is intoxicated, and has been fighting, to the palpable detriment of his wearing apparel; for he has only a pair of tattered pantaloons and a very small quantity of shirt left.</p> 
               <p>We go to bed. Eight of us are assigned to a small den upstairs, with only two lame apologies for beds.</p> 
               <p>Mosquitoes and even rats annoy us fearfully. One bold rat gnaws at the feet of a young Englishman in the party. This was more than the young Englishman could stand, and rising from his bed he asked us if New Grenada wasn't a Republic? We said it was. "I thought so," he said. "Of course I mean no disrespect to the United States of America in the remark, but I think I prefer a bloated monarchy!" He smiled sadly: then handing his purse and his mother's photograph to another English person, he whispered softly, "If I am eaten up, give them to Me mother-tell her I died like a true Briton, with no faith whatever in the success of a republican form of government!" And then he crept back to bed again.</p> 
               <p>We start at seven the next morning for Panama.</p> 
               <p>My native comes bright and early to transport my carpet sack to the railway station. His clothes have suffered still more during the night, for he comes to me now dressed only in a small rag and one boot.</p> 
               <p>At last we are off. "Adios, Americanos!" the natives cry; to which I pleasantly reply, "<hi rend="i"/>Adous! and long may it be before you have a chance to Do us again."</p> 
               <p>The cars are comfortable on the Panama railway, and the country through which we pass is very beautiful. But it will not do to trust it much, because it breeds fevers and other unpleasant disorders at all seasons of the year. Like a girl we most all have known, the Isthmus is fair but false.</p> 
               <p>There are mud huts all along the route, and half-naked savages gaze patronizingly upon us from their doorways. An elderly lady in spectacles appears to be much scandalized by the scant dress of these people, and wants to know why the Select Men don't put a stop to it. From this, and a remark she incidentally makes about her son who has invented a washing machine which will wash, wring, and dry a shirt in ten minutes, I infer that she is from the hills of old New England, like the Hutchinson family.</p> 
               <p>The Central American is lazy. The only exercise he ever takes is to occasionally produce a Revolution. When his feet begin to swell and there are premonitory symptoms of gout, he "revolushes" a spell, and then serenely returns to his cigarette and hammock under the palm trees.</p> 
               <p>These Central American Republics are queer concerns. I do not of course pecisely know what a last year's calf's ideas of immortal glory may be, but probably they are about as lucid as those of a Central American in regard to a republican form of government.</p> 
               <p>And yet I am told they are a kindly people in the main. I never met but one of them-a Costa-Rican on board the Ariel. He lay sick with fever, and I went to him and took his hot hand gently in mine. I shall never forget his look of gratitude. And the next day he borrowed five dollars of me, shedding tears as he put it in his pocket.</p> 
               <p>At Panama we lose several of our passengers, and among them three Peruvian ladies, who go to Lima, the city of volcanic irruptions and veiled black-eyed beauties.</p> 
               <p>The Seoritas who leave us at Panama are splendid creatures. They learned me Spanish, and in the soft moonlight we walked on deck and talked of the land of Pizarro. (You know old Piz conquered Peru! and although he was not educated at West Point, he had still some military talent.) I feel as though I had lost all my relations, including my grandmother and the cooking stove, when these gay young Seoritas go away. They do not go to Peru on a Peruvian bark, but on an English steamer.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <head>AT THE TOMB OF SHAKSPEARE.</head> 
               <p>MR. PUNCH, MY DEAR SIR,-I've been lingerin by the Tomb of the lamentid Shakespeare.</p> 
               <p>It is a success.</p> 
               <p>I do not hes'tate to pronounce it as such.</p> 
               <p>You may make any use of this opinion that you see fit. If you think its publication will subswerve the cause of litteratoor, you may publicate it.</p> 
               <p>I told my wife Betsy when I left home that I should go to the birth-place of the orthur of <title>Otheller</title> and other Plays. She said that as long as I kept out of Newgate she didn't care where I went. "But," I said, "don't you know he was the greatest Poit that ever lived? Not one of these common poits, like that young idyit who writes verses to our daughter, about the Roses as growses, and the Breezes as blowses-but a Boss Poit-also a philosopher, also a man who knew a great deal about everything."</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>Artemus Ward visits the Tomb of Shakspeare, and makes a slight mistake.</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>She was packing my things at the time, and the only answer she made was to ask me if I was goin to carry both of my red flannel night caps.</p> 
               <p>Yes. I've been to Stratford onto the Avon, the Birthplace of Shakspeare. Mr. S. is now no more. He's been dead over three hundred (300) years. The peple of his native town are justly proud of him. They cherish his mem'ry, and them as sell picturs of his birth-place, &amp;c., make it prof'tible cherisin it. Almost everybody buys a pictur to put into their Albiom.</p> 
               <p>As I stood gazing on the spot where Shakspeare is s'posed to have fell down on the ice and hurt hisself when a boy (this spot cannot be bought-the town authorities say it shall never be taken from Stratford), I wondered if three hundred years hence picturs of <emph>my</emph> birthplace will be in demand? Will the peple of my native town be proud of me in three hundred years? I guess they won't short of that time because they say the fat man weighing 1000 pounds which I exhibited there was stuffed out with pillers and cushions, which he said one very hot day in July, "Oh bother, I can't stand this," and commenced pullin the pillers out from under his weskit, and heavin 'em at the audience. I never saw a man lose flesh so fast in my life. The audience said I was a pretty man to come chiselin my own townsmen in that way. I said, "Do not be angry, feller-citizens. I exhibited him simply as a work of art. I simply wished to show you that a man could grow fat without the aid of cod-liver oil." But they wouldn't listen to me.</p> 
               <p>"And this," I said, as I stood in the old church-yard at Stratford, beside a Tombstone, "this marks the spot where lies William W. Shakspeare. Alars! and this is the spot where -"</p> 
               <p>"You've got the wrong grave," said a man-a worthy villager: "Shakspeare is buried inside the church."</p> 
               <p>"Oh," I said, "a boy told me this was it." The boy larfed and put the shillin I'd given him into his left eye in a inglorious manner, and commenced moving backwards towards the street.</p> 
               <p>I pursood and captered him, and after talking to him a spell in a skarcastic stile, I let him went.</p> 
               <p>The old church was damp and chill. It was rainin. The only persons there when I entered was a fine bluff old gentleman who was talking in a excited manner to a fashnibly dressed young man. "No, Ernest Montresser," the old gentleman said, "it is idle to pursoo this subject no further. You can never marry my daughter. You were seen last Monday in Piccaddly without a umbreller! I said then, as I say now, any young man as venturs out in a uncertain climit like this without a umbreller, lacks foresight, caution, strength of mind and stability; and he is not a proper person to intrust a daughter's happiness to."</p> 
               <p>I slapt the old gentleman on the shoulder, and I said, "You're right! You're one of those kind of men, you are -"</p> 
               <p>He wheeled suddenly round, and in a indignant voice, said, "Go way-go way! This is a privit intervoo."</p> 
               <p>I didn't stop to enrich the old gentleman's mind with my conversation. I sort of inferred that he wasn't inclined to listen to me, and so I went on. But he was right about the umbreller. I'm really delighted with this grand old country, <emph>Mr. Punch</emph>, but you must admit that it does rain rayther numerously here. Whether this is owing to a monerkal form of gov'ment or not, I leave all canded and onprejudiced persons to say.</p> 
               <p>William Shakspeare was born in Stratford in 1564. All the commentaters, Shaksperien scholars, etsetry, are agreed on this, which is about the only thing they are agreed on in regard to him, except that his mantle hasn't fallen onto any poet or dramatist hard enough to hurt said poet or dramatist <emph>much</emph>. And there is no doubt if these commentaters and persons continner investigatin Shakspeare's career, we shall not, in doo time, know anything about it at all. When a mere lad little William attended the Grammer School, because, as he said, the Grammer School wouldn't attend him. This remarkable remark, comin from one so young and inexperunced, set peple to thinkin there might be somethin in this lad. He subsequently wrote <title>Hamlet</title> and <title>George Barnwell</title>. When his kind teacher went to London so accept a position in the offices of the Metropolitan Railway, little William was chosen by his fellow pupils to deliver a farewell address. "Go on, Sir," he said, "in a glorus career. Be like a eagle, and soar, and the soarer you get the more we shall all be gratified! That's so."</p> 
               <p>I returned to the hotel. Meetin a young married couple, they asked me if I could direct them to the hotel which Washington Irving used to keep?</p> 
               <p>"I've understood that he was onsuccessful as a lan'lord." said the lady.</p> 
               <p>"We've understood," said the young man, "that he busted up."</p> 
               <p>A very nice old town is Stratford, and a capital inn is the Red Horse. Every admirer of the great S. must go there once certinly; and to say one isn't a admirer of him is equv'lent to sayin one has jest about brains enough to become a efficient tinker.</p> 
               <p>I guess I'm through, and so I lay down the pen, which is more mightier than the sword, but which I'm fraid would stand a rayther slim chance beside the needle gun.</p> 
               <closer>
                  <salute>Adoo! adoo!</salute> 
                  <signed>ARTEMUS WARD.</signed>
               </closer> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC5923-00000015"/> 
               <head>HORACE GREELEY'S RIDE TO PLACERVILLE.</head> 
               <p>When Mr. Greeley was in California ovations awaited him at every town. He had written powerful leaders in the <title>Tribune</title> in favor of the Pacific Railroad, which had greatly endeared him to the citizens of the Golden State. And therefore they made much of him when he went to see them.</p> 
               <p>At one town the enthusiastic populace tore his celebrated white coat to pleces, and carried the pieces home to remember him by.</p> 
               <p>The citizens of Placerville prepared to fte the great journalist, and an extra coach, with extra relays of horses, was chartered of the California Stage Company to carry him from Folsom to Placerville-distance, forty miles. The extra was in some way delayed, and did not leave Folsom until late in the afternoon. Mr. Greeley was to be fted at 7 o'clock that evening by the citizens of Placerville, and it was altogether necessary that he should be there by that hour. So the Stage Company said to Henry Monk, the driven of the extra, "Henry, this great man must be there by 7 to-night." And Henry answered, "The great man shall be there."</p> 
               <p>The roads were in an awful state, and during the first few miles out of Fulsom slow progress was made.</p> 
               <p>"Sir," said Mr. Greeley, "are you aware that I <emph>must</emph> be at Placerville at 7 o'clock to-night?"</p> 
               <p>"I've got my orders!" laconically returned Henry Monk.</p> 
               <p>Still the coach dragged slowly forward.</p> 
               <p>"Sir," said Mr. Greeley, "this is not a trifling matter. I <emph>must</emph> be there at 7!"</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>Horace Greeley's gay and festive adventures on the overland route from California.</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>Again came the answer, "I've got my orders!"</p> 
               <p>But the speed was not increased, and Mr. Greeley chafed away another half hour; when, as he was again about to remonstrate with the driver, the horses suddenly started into a furious run, and all sorts of encouraging yells filled the air from the throat of Henry Monk.</p> 
               <p>"That is right, my good fellow!" cried Mr. Greeley. "I'll give you ten dollars when we get to Placerville. Now we <emph>are</emph> going!"</p> 
               <p>They were indeed, and at a terrible speed.</p> 
               <p>Crack, crack! went the whip, and again "that voice" split the air. "Git up! Hi yi! G'long! Yip-yip!"</p> 
               <p>And on they tore, over stones and ruts, up hill and down, at a rate of speed never before achieved by stage horses.</p> 
               <p>Mr. Greeley, who had been bouncing from one end of the coach to the other like an India-rubber ball, managed to get his head out of the window, when he said:</p> 
               <p>"Do-on't-on't-on't you-u-u think we-e-e-e shall get there by seven if we do-on't-on't go so fast?"</p> 
               <p>"I've got my orders!" that was all Henry Monk said. And on tore the coach.</p> 
               <p>It was becoming serious. Already the journalist was extremely sore from the terrible jolting, and again his head "might have been seen" at the window.</p> 
               <p>"Sir," he said, "I don't care-care-<emph>air</emph>, if we <emph>don't</emph> get there at seven!"</p> 
               <p>"I have got my orders!" Fresh horses. Forward again, faster than before. Over rocks and stumps, on one of which the coach narrowly escaped turning a summerset.</p> 
               <p>"See here!" shrieked Mr. Greeley, "I don't care if we don't get there at all!"</p> 
               <p>"I've got my orders! I work for the Californy Stage Company, <emph>I</emph> do. That's wot I <emph>work</emph> for. They said, 'git this man through by seving.' An' this man's goin through. You bet! Gerlong! Whoo-ep!"</p> 
               <p>Another frightful jolt, and Mr. Greeley's bald head suddenly found its way through the roof of the coach, amidst the crash of small timbers and the ripping of strong canvas.</p> 
               <p>"Stop, you - maniac!" he roared.</p> 
               <p>Again answered Henry Monk:</p> 
               <p>"I've got my orders! <emph>Keep your seat, Horace!</emph>"</p> 
               <p>At Mud Springs, a village a few miles from Placerville, they met a large delegation of the citizens of Placerville, who had come out to meet the celebrated editor, and escort him into town. There was a military company, a brass band, and a six-horse wagon-load of beautiful damsels in milk-white dresses, representing all the States in the Union. It was nearly dark now, but the delegation were amply provided with torches, and bonfires blazed all along the road to Placerville.</p> 
               <p>The citizens met the coach in the outskirts of Mud Springs, and Mr. Monk reined in his foam-covered steeds.</p> 
               <p>"Is Mr. Greeley aboard?" asked the chairman of the committee.</p> 
               <p>"<emph>He was, a few miles back!</emph>" said Mr. Monk; "yes," he added, after looking down through the hole which the fearful jolting had made in the coach-roof-"yes, I can see him! He is there!"</p> 
               <p>"Mr. Greeley," said the Chairman of the Committee, presenting himself at the window of the coach, "Mr. Greeley, sir! We are come to most cordially welcome you, sir-why, God bless me, sir, you are bleeding at the nose!"</p> 
               <p>"I've got my orders!" cried Mr. Monk. "My orders is as follers: Git him there by seving! It wants a quarter to seving. Stand out of the way!"</p> 
               <p>"But, sir," exclaimed the Committee-man, seizing the off leader by the reins-"Mr. Monk, we are come to escort him into town! Look at the procession, sir, and the brass band, and the people, and the young women, sir!"</p> 
               <p>"<emph>I've got my orders!</emph>" screamed Mr. Monk. "My order's don't say nothin' about no brass hands and young women. My orders says, 'git him there by seving!' Let go them lines! Clear the way there! Whoo-ep! KEEP YOUR SEAT, HORACE!" and the coach dashed wildly through the procession, upsetting a portion of the brass band, and violently grazing the wagon which contained the beautiful young women in white.</p> 
               <p>Years hence gray-haired men, who were little boys in this procession, will tell their grandchildren how this stage tore through Mud Springs, and how Horace Greeley's bald head ever and anon showed itself, like a wild apparition, above the coach-roof.</p> 
               <p>Mr. Monk was on time. There is a tradition that Mr. Greeley was very indignant for awhile; then he laughed, and finally presented Mr. Monk with a bran new suit of clothes.</p> 
               <p>Mr. Monk himself is still in the employ of the California Stage Company, and is rather fond of relating a story that has made him famous all over the Pacific coast. But he says he yields to no man in his admiration for Horace Greeley.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <p>The other evening we enlivened a railroad car with our brilliant presence. The conductor came in. The following were a few of the questions put to him: One old fellow, who was wrapped up in a horse blanket and who apparently had about two pounds of pigtail in his mouth, wanted to know "What pint of compass the keers was travelin' in?" An old lady, wanted to know what time the 8 o'clock train left Rock Island for "Dubu-kue?" A carroty-haired young man wanted to know if "free omyibuses" run from the cars to the taverns in Toledo? A tall, razor-faced individual, desired to know if "conductin" paid as well eout West as it did deoun in his country; and a portly, close-shaven man, asked the price of corner lots in Omaha. These and many other absurd questions, the conductor answered calmly and in a resigned manner.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <head>AMONG THE FREE LOVERS.</head> 
               <note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WRIGHT2-0396-NOTE003" place="inline"
                     n="*">Some queer people, calling themselves "Free Lovers," and possessing very original ideas about life and morality, established themselves at Berlin Heights, in Ohio, a few years since. Public opinion was resistlesaly against them, however, and the association was soon disbanded.</note> 
               <p>Some years ago I pitched my tent and onfurled my banner to the breeze, in Berlin Hites, Ohio. I had hearn that Berlin Hites was ockepied by a extensive seck called Free Levers, who beleeved in affinertys and sich, goin back on their domestic ties without no hesitation whatsomever. They was likewise spirit rappers and high presher reformers on gineral principles. If I can improve these ere misgided peple by showin them my onparalleld show at the usual low price of admitants, methunk, I shall not hav lived in vane! But bitterly did I cuss the day I ever sot foot in the retchid place. I sot up my tent in a field near the Love Cure, as they called it, and bimeby the free lovers begun for to congregate around the door. A ornreer set I have never sawn. The men's faces was all covered with hare and they lookt half-starved to deth. They didn't wear no weskuts for the purpuss (as they sed) of allowin the free air of hevun to blow on to their boozums. Their pockets was filled with tracks and pamphlits and they was bare-footed. They sed the Postles didn't wear boots, &amp; why should they? That was their stile of argyment. The wimin was wuss than the men. They wore trowsis, short gownds, straw hats with green ribbons, and all carried bloo cotton umbrellers.</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>Horace Greeley's gay and festive adventures on the overland route from California.</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>Presently a perfeckly orful lookin female presented herself at the door. Her gownd was skanderlusly short and her trowsis was shamful to behold.</p> 
               <p>She eyed me over very sharp, and then startin back she sed, in a wild voice:</p> 
               <p>"Ah, can it be?"</p> 
               <p>"Which?" sed I.</p> 
               <p>"Yes, 'tis troo, O 'tis troo!"</p> 
               <p>"15 cents, marm," I anserd.</p> 
               <p>She bust out a cryin &amp; sed:</p> 
               <p>"And so I hav found you at larst-at larst, O at larst!"</p> 
               <p>"Yes," I anserd, "you have found me at larst, and you would have found me at fust, if you had cum sooner."</p> 
               <p>She grabed me vilently by the coat collar, and brandishin her umbreller wildly round, exclaimed:</p> 
               <p>"Air you a man?"</p> 
               <p>Sez I, "I think I air, but if you doubt it, you can address Mrs. A. Ward, Baldinsville, Injianny, postage pade, &amp; she will probly giv you the desired informashun."</p> 
               <p>Then thou ist what the cold world calls marrid?"</p> 
               <p>"Madam, I istest!"</p> 
               <p>The exsentric female then clutched me franticly by the arm and hollerd:</p> 
               <p>"You air mine, O you air mine!"</p> 
               <p>"Scarcely," I sed, endeverin to git loose from her. But she clung to me and sed:</p> 
               <p>"You air my Affinerty!"</p> 
               <p>"What upon airth is that?" I shouted.</p> 
               <p>"Dost thou not know?"</p> 
               <p>"No, I dostent!"</p> 
               <p>"Listin man, &amp; I'll tell ye!" sed the strange female; for years I hav yearned for thee. I knowd thou wast in the world, sumwhares, tho I didn't know whare. My hart sed he would cum and I took courage. He <emph>has</emph> cum-he's here-you air him-you air my Affinerty! O 'tis too mutch! too mutch!" and she sobbed agin.</p> 
               <p>"Yes," I anserd, "I think it is a darn site too mutch!"</p> 
               <p>"Hast thou not yearned for me?" she yelled, ringin her hands like a female play acter.</p> 
               <p>"Not a yearn!" I bellerd at the top of my voice, throwin her away from me.</p> 
               <p>The free lovers who was standin round obsarvin the scene commenst for to holler "shame!" "beast," etsettery, etsettery.</p> 
               <p>I was very mutch riled, and fortifyin myself with a spare tent stake, I addrest them as follers: "You pussylanermus critters, go away from me and take this retchid woman with you. I'm alaw-abidin man, and bleeve in good, old-fashioned institutions. I am marrid &amp; my orfsprings resemble me if I am a showman! I think your Affinity bizniss is cussed noncents, besides bein outrajusly wicked. Why don't you behave desunt like other folks? Go to work and earn a honist livin and not stay round here in this lazy, shiftless way, pizenin' the moral atmosphere with your pestifrous idees! You wimin folks go back to your lawful husbands if you've got any, and take orf them skanderlous gownds and trowsis, and dress respectful like other wimin. You men folks, cut orf them pirattercal whiskers, burn up them infurnel pamplits, put sum weskuts on, go to work choppin wood, splittin fence rales, or tillin the sile. I pored 4th my indignashun in this way till I got out of breth, when I stopt.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <head>HIGH-HANDED OUTRAGE IN UTICA.</head> 
               <p>In the Faul of 1856, I showed my show in Utiky, a trooly grate sitty in the State of New York.</p> 
               <p>The people gave me a cordyal recepshun. The press was loud in her prases.</p> 
               <p>I day as I was givin a descripshun of my Beests and Snaiks in my usual flowry stile, what was my shorn &amp; disgust to see a big burly feller walk up to the cage containin my wax figgers of the Lord's Last Supper, and cease Judas Iscarrot by the feet and drag him out on the ground. He then commenced fur to pound him as hard as he cood.</p> 
               <p>"What under the son are you abowt?" cried I.</p> 
               <p>Sez he, "What did you bring this pussylanermus cuss here fur?" &amp; he hit the wax figger another tremenjis blow on the hed.</p> 
               <p>Sez I, "You egrejus ass, that air's a wax figger-a representashun of the false 'Postle."</p> 
               <p>Sez he, "That's all very well fur you to say but I tell you, old man, that Judas Iscarrot can't show hisself in Utiky with impunerty by a darn site!" with which observashun he kaved in Judassis hed. The young man belonged to I of the first famerlies in Utiky. I sood him, and the Joory brawt in a verdick of Arson in the 3d degree.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <p>DULL.-It is a scandalous fact that this city is desperately and fearfully barren of incident. No "dem'd, moist, unpleasant bodies" are fished up out of the river; no ambitious young female runs off with her "feller;" no stabbings, gougings, or fisticuffs occur; no eminent merchant suspends; no banker or railroad man defaults; and not even a dog fight disturbs the rigid and corpse-like quiet of the city. We want a murder. We insist upon having a murder. A manslaughter wont do. It must be murder, premeditated, foul, and unnatural. It must be a luscious murder, abounding in soul-harrowing incidents. Some "man in human shape" must chop the heads of his entire family off with a meat-axe, or insert a butcher-knife ingeniously under their fifth ribs. Let murder be done. Bring on your murderers.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC5923-00000016"/> 
               <head>SCIENCE AND NATURAL HISTORY.</head> 
               <p>MR. PUNCH, MY DEAR SIR,-I was a little disappointed in not receiven a invitation to jine in the meetins of the Social Science Congress.</p> 
               <p>I don't exackly see how they go on without me.</p> 
               <p>I hope it wasn't the intentions of the Sciencers to exclood me from their deliberations.</p> 
               <p>Let it pars. I do not repine. Let us remember Homer. Twenty cities claim Homer dead, thro' which the livin Mr. Homer couldn't have got trusted for a sandwhich and a glass of bitter beer, or words to that effeck.</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>Natural History.-Sudden and unexpected playfulness of the Bear.</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>But perhaps it was a oversight. Certinly I have been hospitably rec'd in this country. Hospitality has been pored all over me. At Liverpool I was asked to walk all over the docks, which are nine miles long; and I don't remember a instance since my 'rival in London of my gettin into a cab without a briton comin and perlitely shuttin the door for me, and then extendin his open hand to'ards me, in the most frenly manner possible. Doos he not, by this simple yit touchin gesture, welcum me to England? Doesn't he? Oh yes-I guess he doesn't he. And it's quite right among two great countries which speak the same langwidge, except as regards H's. And I've been allowed to walk round all the streets. Even at Buckingham Pallis, I told a guard I wanted to walk round there, and he said I could walk round there. I ascertained subsequent that he referred to the sidewalk instid of the Pallis-but I couldn't doubt his hospital feelins.</p> 
               <p>I prepared a Essy on Animals to read before the Social Science meetins. It is a subject I may troothfully say, I have successfully wrastled with. I tackled it when only nineteen years old.</p> 
               <p>In case I had read the Essy to the Social Sciencers, I had intended it should be the closin attraction. I had intended it should finish the proceedins. I think it would have finished them. I understand animals better than any other class of human creatures. I have a very animal mind, and I've been identified with 'em doorin my entire perfecsional career as a showman, more especial bears, wolves, leopards and serpunts.</p> 
               <p>The leopard is as lively a annual as I ever came into contack with. It is troo he cannot change his spots, but you can change 'em for him with a paint-brush, as I once did in the case of a leopard who wasn't nat'rally spotted in a attractive manner. In exhibition him I used to stir him up in his cage with a protracted pole, and for the purpuss of makin him yell and kick up in a leopardy manner, I used to casionally whack him over the head. This would make the children inside the booth scream with fright, which would make fathers of families outside the booth very anxious to come in-because there is a large class of parents who have a uncontrollable passion for takin their children to places were they will stand a chance of being frightened to death.</p> 
               <p>One day I whacked this leopard more than ushil, which elissited a remonstrance from a tall gentleman with spectacles, who said, "My good man, do not beat the poor caged animal. Rather fondle him."</p> 
               <p>"I'll fondle him with a club," I anserd, hitting him another whack.</p> 
               <p>"I prithy desist," said the gentleman; "stand aside, and see the effeck of kindness. I understand the idiosyncracies of these creeturs <unclear>better</unclear> than you do." With that he went up to the cage, and thrustin his face in between the iron bars, he said, soothinly," Come hither, pretty creetur." The pretty creetur come-hithered rayther speedy, and seized the gentleman by the whiskers, which he tore off about enuff to stuff a small cushion with.</p> 
               <p>He said, "You vagabone, I'll have you indicted for exhibition <unclear>dangerous</unclear> and immoral animals."</p> 
               <p>I replied, "Gentle Sir, there isn't a animal here that hasn't a beautiful moral, but you mustn't fondle 'em, You mustn't meddle with their idiotsyncracies."</p> 
               <p>The gentleman was a dramatic cricket, and he wrote a article for a paper, in which he said my entertainment was a decided failure.</p> 
               <p>As regards Bears, you can teach 'em to do interesting things, but they're onreliable. I had a very large grizzly bear once, who would dance, and larf, and lay down, and bow his head in grief, and give a mournful wale, etsetry. But he often annoyed me. It will be remembered that on the occasion of the first battle of Bull Run, it suddenly occured to the Fed'ral soldiers that they had business in Washington which ought not to be neglected, and they all started for that beautiful and romantic city, maintainin a rate of speed durin the entire distance that would have done credit to the celebrated French steed <hi rend="i"/>Gladiateur. Very nat'rally our Gov'ment was deeply grieved at this defeat; and I said to my bear, shortly after, as I was givin a exhibition in Ohio-I said, "Brewin, are you not sorry the National arms has sustained a defeat?" His business was to wale dismal, and bow his head down, the band (a barrel orgin and a wiolin) playing slow and melancholly moosic. What did the grizzly old cuss do, however, but commence darncin and larfin in the most joyous manner. I had a narrer escape from being imprisoned for disloyalty. I will relate another incident in the carreer of this retchid Bear. I <unclear>used</unclear> to present what I called in the bills a beautiful living Picture-showing the Bear's fondness for his Master: in which I'd lay down on a piece of carpeting, and the Bear would come and lay down beside me, restin his right paw on my breast, the Band playing "<title>Home, Sweet Home,</title>" very soft and slow. 'Altho' I say it, it was a tucbin thing to see. I've seen Tax-Collectors weep over that performance.</p> 
               <p>Well, one day I said, "Ladies and Gentlemen, we will now show you the Bear's fondess for his master," and I went and laid down. "I tho't I observad a pecooliar expression into his eyes, as he rolled clumsily to'ard me, but I didn't dream of the scene which follered. He laid down, and put his paw on my breast, "Affection of the bear for his Master," I repeated. "You see the Monarch of the Western Wilds in a subjugated state. Fierce as these animals natrally are, we now see that they have hearts, and can love. This Bear, the largest in the world, and measurin seventeen feet round the body, loves me as a mer-ther loves her che-ild!" But what was my horror when the grizzly and infamous Bear threw his other paw <emph>under</emph> me, and riz with me to his feet. Then claspin me in a close embrace he waltzed up and down the platform in a frightful manner, I yellin with fear and anguish. To make matters wuss, a low scurrilus young man in the audiens hollered out, "Playfulness of the Bear! Quick moosic!" I jest 'scaped with my life.</p> 
               <closer>
                  <salute>Very respectively yours,</salute> 
                  <signed>ARTEMUS WARD.</signed>
               </closer> 
            </div> 
            <div type="section"> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <head>IS INTRODUCED TO THE CLUB.</head> 
               <p>MR. PUNCH, MY DEAR SIR,-It is seldim that the Commercial relations between Great Britain and the United States is mard by Games.</p> 
               <p>It is Commerce, after all, which will keep the two countries friendly toards each other rather than statesmen.</p> 
               <p>I come of a very clever famly.</p> 
               <p>The Wards is a very clever famly, indeed.</p> 
               <p>I believe we are descendid from the Puritins, who nobly fled from a land of despitism to a land of freedim, where they could not only enjoy their own religion, but prevent everybody else from enjoyin <emph>his</emph>.</p> 
               <p>As I was walkin along Regent street, amoosin myself by stickin my penknife into the calves of the footmen who stood waitin by the swell-coaches (not one of whom howled with angwish), I was accosted by a man of about thirty-five summers, who said, "I have seen that face somewheres afore!"</p> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>"Young woman, I'm not your Saler boy. Far different."</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <p>He was a little shabby in his wearin appard. His coat was one of those black, shiny garments, which you can always tell have been burnished by adversity; but he was very gentlemanly.</p> 
               <p>"Was it in the Crimea, comrade? Yes, it was. It was at the stormin of Sebastopol, where I had a narrow escape from death, that we met!"</p> 
               <p>I said, "No, I wasn't at Sebastopol, I escaped a fatal wound by not bein there. It was a healthy old fortress," I added.</p> 
               <p>"It was. But it fell. It came down with a crash."</p> 
               <p>"And plucky boys they was who brought her down," I added; "and hurrah for 'em!"</p> 
               <p>The man graspt me warmly by the hand, and said he had been in America, Upper Canada, Africa, Asia Minor, and other towns, and he'd never met a man he liked as much as he did me. "Let us," he added, "let us to the shrine of Bachus!" And he dragged me into a public house. I was determined to pay, so I said, "Mr. Bachus, giv this gen'l'man what he calls for."</p> 
               <p>We conversed there in a very pleasant manner till my dinner-time arrove, when the agree'ble gentleman insisted that I should, dine with him. "We'll have a banquet, Sir, fit for the gods!"</p> 
               <p>I told him good plain vittles would soot me. If the gods wanted to have the dispepsy, they was welcome to it.</p> 
               <p>We had soop and fish, and a hot jint, and growsis, and wines of rare and costly vintige. We had ices, and we had froots from Greenland's icy mountins and Injy's coral strands; and when the sumptoous reparst was over, the agree'ble man said he'd unfortinitly left his pocket-book at home on the marble centre-table. "But, by Jove!" he said, "it <unclear>was</unclear> a feast fit for the gods!"</p> 
               <p>
                  <unclear>I said</unclear>, "Oh, never mind," and drew out my puss; tho I inardly <unclear>wishes the gods,</unclear> as the dinner was fit for 'em, was there to pay for it.</p> 
               <p>I <unclear>come</unclear> of a very clever famly.</p> 
               <p>The <unclear/> gentleman then said, "Now, I will show you our Club. It dates <unclear>back to</unclear> the time of William the Conqueror."</p> 
               <p>"Did Bill belong to it?" I inquired.</p> 
               <p>"He did."</p> 
               <p>"Wall," I said, "if Billy was one of 'em, I need no other endorsement as to its respectfulness, and I'll go with you, my gay trooper boy!" And we went off arm-in-arm.</p> 
               <p>On the way the agreeble man told me that the Club was called the Sloshers. He said I would notice that none of 'em appeared in evenin dress. He said it was agin the rools of the club. In fack, if any member appeared there in evenin dress he'd be instantly expeld. "And yit," he added, "there's geneyus there, and lorfty emotions, and intelleck, You'll be surprised at the quantities of intelleck you'll see there."</p> 
               <p>We reached the Sloshers in due time, and I must say they was a shaky-looking lot, and the public house where they convened was certingly none of the best.</p> 
               <p>The Sloshers crowded round me, and said I was welcome. "What a beautiful brestpin you've got," said one of 'em. "Permit me," and he took it out of my neckercher. "Isn't it luvly," he said, parsin it to another, who passed it to another. It was given me by my Aunt, on my promisin her I'd never swear profanely; and I never have, except on very special occasions. I see that beautiful boosum pin a parsin from one Slosher to another, and I'm reminded of them sad words of the poit, "parsin away! parsin away!" I never saw it no more. Then in comes a athletic female, who no sooner sees me than she utters a wild yell, and cries:</p> 
               <p>"At larst! at larst! My Wilyim, from the seas!"</p> 
               <p>I said, "Not at all, Marm. Not on no account. <emph>I</emph> have heard the boatswain pipe to quarters-but a voice in my heart didn't whisper Seu-zan! I've belayed the marlin-spikes on the upper jibpoop, but Seuzan's eye wasn't on me, much. Young woman, I am not you're Saler boy. Far different."</p> 
               <p>"Oh yes, you are! she howled, seizin me round the neck. "Oh, how I've lookt forwards to this meetin!"</p> 
               <p>"And you'll presently," I said, "have a opportunity of lookin backwards to it, because I'm on the point of leavin this institution."</p> 
               <p>I will here observe that I come of a very clever family. A very clever fam'ly, indeed.</p> 
               <p>"Where," I cried, as I struggled in vain to release myself from the eccentric female's claws, "where is the Capting-the man who was into the Crimea, amidst the cannon's thunder? I want him."</p> 
               <p>He came forward, and cried, "what do I see? Me Sister! me sweet Adelaide! and in teers!"</p> 
               <p>Somehow my coat was jerked off, the brest-pocket of which contained my pocket-book, and it parsed away like the brestpin. Then they sorter quietly hustled me into the street.</p> 
               <p>It was about 12 at night when I reached the Greenlion.</p> 
               <p>"Ha! ha! you sly old rascal, you've been up to larks!" said the lanlord, larfin loudly, and digging his fist into my ribs.</p> 
               <p>I said, "Bigsby, if you do that agin, I shall hit you! Much as I respect you and your excellent fam'ly, I shall disfigger your beneverlent countenance for life!"</p> 
               <p>"What has ruffled your spirits, friend?" said the lanlord.</p> 
               <p>"My spirits has been ruffled," I answered in a bittur voice, by a viper who was into the Crimea. What good was it," I cried, "for Sebastopol to fall down without enwelopin in its ruins that viper?"</p> 
               <closer>
                  <signed>ARTEMUS WARD.</signed>
               </closer> 
            </div> 
         </div>
      </body> 
      <back> 
         <div type="illustrations"> 
            <pb n="32 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC5923-00000017"/> 
            <p>
               <figure> 
                  <p>Artemus Ward at the Rink</p> 
               </figure>
            </p> 
         </div> 
      </back> 
   </text>
</TEI>