<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC5910">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Recollections of a Lazy Life </title>
            <author>Skinner, Mose, (fl. 1869-1885)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC5910</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-0383</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                    participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Recollections of a lazy life</title>
                  <author>Skinner, Mose, (fl. 1869-1885)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>S.l</pubPlace>
                  <date when="1869">1869</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2000-11-06">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="Caroline Lilyard, University of Minnesota" when="2001-07-31">Finished TEI encoding and proofreading</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-08-04">Finished final editing</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-04-22">Converted document from SGML to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-04-22">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n="[1]" xml:id="VAC5910-00000001"/>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>RECOLLECTIONS OF A LAZY LIFE.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>BY <docAuthor>MOSE SKINNER,</docAuthor> Author of "Mose Skinner's Grand Peace Jubilee."</byline>
            <epigraph>
               <cit>
                  <q>
                     <p>Some are born great; some achieve greatness; and some have greatness thrust upon them.</p>
                  </q>
                  <bibl>—WILLIAM SHAKESPEARE.</bibl>
               </cit>
            </epigraph>
            <epigraph>
               <cit>
                  <q>
                     <p>"That's just my case, exactly!"</p>
                  </q>
                  <bibl>—MOSE SKINNER.</bibl>
               </cit>
            </epigraph>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>BOSTON:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>PRINTED BY WARREN RICHARDSON. <address>
                     <addrLine>No. 11 Milk Street.</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </publisher>
            </docImprint>
            <docDate when="1869">1869.</docDate>
         </titlePage>
         <div type="advertisement">
            <pb n="Advertisement" xml:id="VAC5910-00000002"/>
            <head>WHITEN YOUR TEETH</head>
            <head type="sub">BY USING CHOATE'S OAK BARK AND ORRIS Tooth Paste.</head>
            <p>This preparation thoroughly Whitens the Teeth, Hardens the Gums, and Perfumes the Breath, without injury.</p>
            <p>M. MANDL, a celebrated French Dentist, discovered that the foul adhesive mucus, tartar, or greenish incrustation on the teeth, consists of the skeletons or dead remains of minute microscopic creatures or insects, united in one mass by decomposition; and that the mouth and teeth, when foul and dirty, contain millions of these insects. To avoid them, use CHOATE'S Oak Bark and Orris Tooth Paste, Prepared and for sale by HENRY A. CHOATE, DRUGGIST, Under Revere House, Boston. [Copyright secured.]</p>
         </div>
         <div type="advertisement">
            <head>CLOCK'S EXCELSIOR HAIR RESTORER</head>
            <p>Will positively restore grey hair to its original color, either black or brown; prevents it from falling off; cures all humors or eruptions on the scalp; makes the hair grow on bald heads when bald from disease; it is clean; does not gum the hair; is elegantly perfumed. Sold by all the Apothecaries.</p>
            <p>F. B. CLOCK, Chemist and Apothecary, Proprietor, CORNER OF CAMBRIDGE AND TEMPLE STS., BOSTON.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="advertisement">
            <head>MOSE SKINNER'S Grand Peace Jubilee and Jewsharp Oratorio</head>
            <p>Acknowledged to be the best Burlesque ever published. Is for sale by all News-Dealers. Price Ten Cents.</p>
            <p>Mr. Skinner would be happy to greet his numerous friends in the columns of the "TRUE FLAG," weekly but not weakly.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Recollections of a lazy life</head>
            <head>Recollections OF A LAZY LIFE.</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <p>I have received the following communication from the prominent capitalists and "interviewers" of the great city of Boston. I feel immensely tickled to find myself occupying such a proud position in the eyes of the community.</p>
               <p>"MOSE SKINNER, Esq.:</p>
               <p>Dear Sir: Will you favor us with some incidents of your remarkable and eventful career? We want you to. Such a production would add greatly to the high-toned literature of the day. To the aged, it would rekindle the smoldering fires of ambition; and all pious youth, in perusing it, would not only burn with fiery ardor but fairly sizzles to emulate the example of a man who to-day, sir, stands before the civilized world and New Jersey as the sole projector of the most sublime Peace Jubilee that ever sold for 10 cents. To a doting public, who, with a mother-in-law's solicitude, hath watched your guileless career, it would prove a tender memento, showing to what height a man may attain who commenced public life as editor of the <title>Slunkville Trombone</title>, assisted by a pair of shears and a linen duster, under the hallowed influence of an easy-chair and a spittoon."</p>
               <p>I immediately replied, thanking them for a series of backhanded compliments so touchingly conveyed, and asked<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC5910-00000003"/> them, in case I should die, what they would charge to write my epitaph. They replied, "We should be very happy to write your epitaph at the lowest market price. Let us know when you expect to slip your wind, and we will not only have the 'Gates Ajar,' but 'Wide Open.' And if you think it would facilitate your progress, we will have the Bars Let Down."</p>
               <p>Thus with pleasant jest do great minds often commune with one another.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>MY FIRST SQAWK OF INFANCY</head>
               <p>was emitted Anne Dominoe 1819. A sister of Anne's on her mother's side officiated as wet-nurse, and take it all in all it was quite a social gathering.</p>
               <p>I am of noble birth, through not exactly a Bourbon. Still I always liked Old Bourbon, and make it a point to treat him well. My family is older than Mr. Bourbon's. I claim a direct descent on my Uncle William's side with the estimable female who held the camphor bottle when Adam was born. Even now can be found, in the old ancestral castle on the Erie canal, the mouldy manuscript that tells how the Duke de Skinneur, with seventy-six unarmed men, held the town of Fischbolville, against a splendidly disciplined army of seventy-seven blood-thirsty manikins, receiving as a reward for his valor the paw of the lovely and accomplished Countess Brownn, a direct descendant of the Deddbeett Dynasty of Rottenbones.</p>
               <p>During infancy I was christened twice, to humor my mother, but it did'nt <emph>take</emph> neither time.</p>
               <p>As I emerged into artless childhood, I gained considerable notoriety as a crippler of bull-frogs, and a throwist of dead cats into neighboring wells. Or anon did I playfully rob a bird's nest of the only son of his mother, and she a widow. I will not refer to my once putting a litter of kittens into the stove oven, or a chaw of tobacco in the tea-pot; let these pass as the innocent outpouring of a childish nature. In the words of the immortal bard, <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>O! dase of my childhood,</l>
                        <l>I'm a thinkin' on ye now!"</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q> When <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>Through flowery vales,</l>
                        <l>With little pails,</l>
                        <l>A berrying I went,</l>
                        <l>With my little sister Min,—</l>
                        <l>And our little pails of tin,</l>
                        <l>For to put our berries in,</l>
                        <l>Me and Min, Me and Min.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Although this was eminently hunky, I never would'd I were a child again. No. To me "Childhood's happy hours" were a wretched fraud, and signified an exclusive diet of brimstone and molasses and castor oil, with a nourishing dessert of measles and whooping cough.</p>
               <p>Nothing occurred to mar my lamb-like existence till thirty-four. Winters had come and gone, when I fell in love with Tabitha Ripley, hired girl at Deacon Slipshod's. She was an artless creature of thirty-nine Summers ; and, as time developed her maiden charms and the golden charms of her bank-book also, I concluded I had better go for her, and I went.</p>
               <p>Our marriage, which the parson blessed for seventy-five cents, was in due season blessed by twins. I never was blessed with triplets, but had the fever and ague three Winters, to make up for it.</p>
               <p>After being married, I began to hanker for fame, and pine for popularity. Fame is smoke, but the smell of it is bunkum to the nostrils. Like the American eagle, I resolved to soar and soar until I could'nt get any soarer. I determined that the name of Moses Skinner should become a household word, and little children should cry for me. Knowing that a newspaper was lever to popularity to any<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC5910-00000004"/> man with money and without brains, I invested Tabitha's dowry in the <title>Slunkville Trombone</title>, a "Mirror of choice literature, polished sentiment, and cheerful anecdote, for the genteel home circle."</p>
               <p>The position of editor was one for which I had long hankered. Toward the easy-chair especially did my impulsive nature gush forth. There is something about an easy-chair strongly attractive to my sensitive organization. As an arduous laborer I do not excel. As a workist I am not a success.</p>
               <p>The public will remember the <title>Trombone</title>. The mere sound of that name will recall to mind in a startling blast my famous double-leaded editorial on the Alabama claims, which was criticised so severely by the <title>Hull Boomerang</title>, in an article headed, "Is Mr. Skinner right in his masterly collaring of this subject? or is he aint?"</p>
               <p>That editorial was a hefty boost up the ladder of fame, and honors were heaped upon me. I was allowed the freedom of Hull, with the privilege of strolling through the graveyard. I was also tendered a free pass to all the small pox hospitals in the country, with permission to kiss the female patients. How true it is that Fame wins favor!</p>
               <p>[I will here state that persons wishing my picture will find an excellent chromo-tin-type at the news-dealer who lives furtherest from my house. That even little children may be able to buy them, I have reduced the price to $1.00 each, or $13.00 a dozen.]</p>
               <p>Time passed on, and I will here remark that as a passer-on, Time is an eminent success.</p>
               <p>It was in the Spring of '61 that the huge carbuncle of civil war, which had been coming to a head for several years, burst upon us. We all know that J. Buchanan poulticed that carbuncle instead of lancing it, and as a natural result Boston was afflicted with a Peace Jubilee. The prominent part I took in crushing the rebellion is too well known to need comment in these memoirs. The name of Skinner was ever synonymous with gore. Who was it that with Spartan firmness sacrificed his brother-in-law and two of his wife's cousins, in order that the Nation might live? Mose Skinner. Who blessed his step-son and bid him go, when the clarion notes of $500 bounty thrilled the heart of every true patriot? Mose Skinner, Esq. </p>
               <p>At a veteran reception in Slunkville, in 1864, I drove the team containing the gallant band who so nobly defended Fort Warren, during three of the bloodiest months of the war. Will it be considered egotistical if I also state that I was president of a band of heroic souls called "A committee for evading the draft," and that the name of Mose Skinner was first on the list of exempts? Said Mr. Stanton in his letter to our provost marshal, "In case of another draft, I shall rely upon the cheerful graveyard called Slunkville for a full quota of exempts, led by that veteran white-livered subterfuge, Mose Skinner."</p>
               <p>Thus it always was. A Skinner was never known to quail in danger's stormy hour. My grandfather boldly faced death during the Revolution. He was sutler's clerk, and often speaks of an interview he had with Gen. Washington. He asked the General if he should n't hold his horse a little while, and he told him to get out of the way. This cheerful ancestor of mine is at present 117 years old, his towering intellect yet unshaken. He has not the slightest intention of disposing of his mortal coil, but gaily trundles his hoop, stones bull-frogs, and chews slippery-elm, with all the vigor of boyhood's sunny hours. It is a pleasant sight to watch him as he gaily chats with the village maidens, while the modest blush of youth suffuses his brow. I should also add that he can easily walk forty miles without spectacles, and eagerly bounds o'er a ten-acre lot at the cheerful sound of the dinner bell.</p>
               <p>The Spring of '62 saw me prostrated with my first great<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC5910-00000005"/> sorrow. Like a thunderbolt descending from the cloudless heavens, did colic descend upon my wife Tabitha, laying her flat in less than forty winks. O! the agony of that hour, when I watched with a husband's solicitude, she and the colic having it nip and tuck, both determined to fight it out on that line, and both equally determined to wear the belt. The result was, the colic finally collared her and walked off with her. She passed away peacefully and resignedly, merely observing to her heart-broken husband, "Mose, I'm off; good-bye; life is a conundrum,—I give it up!"</p>
               <p>Utterly crushed, and weak as an infant, I crawled to her bureau drawer, and convulsively seizing her bank-book, I wept like a child.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>'Twas sweet and balmy Spring time,</l>
                     <l>The hunkiest time of year,</l>
                     <l>When the April showers bring forth May flowers,</l>
                     <l>'T was then we laid her away, away,</l>
                     <l>About the middle of May, of May.</l>
                     <l>O Tabitha, you died too soon!</l>
                     <l>Why did n't you wait till June, till June!</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>[N. B. An eminent artist, in alluding to those chromo-tin-types of mine, says, "As gems of artistic skill they are unsurpassed. No family should be without one. A picture gallery destitute of Mose Skinner's chromo-tin-type, is a miserable failure." Price $1.00 each, or $13 a dozen.—The well-known modesty of Mr. S. alone prevents him from taking his place with the Nine Muses, as we understand he had a very tempting offer to that effect.] Comment is unnecessary. *   *   *   *</p>
               <p>Thus my wife died. No more would those loving hands pull off my boots and part my back hair as only a true wife can. No more would those willing feet replenish coal-hod and water-pail. No more would she arise mid the tempestuous storms of winter, and gaily hie herself away to build the fire, without disturbing the slumbers of the man who doted on her so artlessly. Her memory is embalmed in my heart of hearts. I wanted to embalm her body, but I found I could embalm her memory cheaper.</p>
               <p>I procured of Eli Mudgett, a neighbor of mine, a very pretty gravestone. His wife was consumptive, and he had kept it on hand for several years, in expectation of her death. But she rallied that Spring, and his hopes were dashed. Never shall I forget this poor man's grief when I asked him to part with this gravestone. "Take it, Skinner," said he, "take it, and may you never know what it is to have your soul racked with disappointment, as mine has been!" and he burst into a flood of tears. His spirit was indeed utterly crushed.</p>
               <p>I had the following epitaph engraved upon the stone:—</p>
               <q>
                  <p>To the memory of<lb/> TABITHA,<lb/> Wife of Mose Skinner, Esq., the gentlemanly editor of<lb/> the Trombone.<lb/> A kind Mother and exemplary Wife.<lb/> Terms $2.00 a year, invariably in advance.<lb/> Office over Hanson's Grocery, up two flights,<lb/> Knock hard.<lb/>
                     <q>
                        <lg type="quotation">
                           <l>"We shall miss thee, mother;</l>
                           <l>We shall miss thee, mother."</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q> Job Printing solicited.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Thus did my lacerated spirit cry out in its agony, even as Rachel weeping for her children. But one ray of light penetrated the despair of my soul. The undertaker took his pay in job printing, and the sexton owed me a little account I should n't have got in any other way.</p>
               <milestone n="*   *   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/>
               <p>Why should we repine at the mysterious ways of Providence and vicinity?</p>
               <p>I here pause to drop a silent tear to the memory of Tabitha Ripley that was. She was an eminently pious<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC5910-00000006"/> woman, and could fry the best piece of tripe I ever slung under my vest. Her picked-up dinners were a perfect success, and she always doted on Foreign Missions.</p>
               <p>I did not, however, allow myself to pine away to any great extent. In the person of Matilda Baxter, a gushing coquette of forty-seven Autumns, did I perceive a salve for my lacerated heart-strings. As soon, therefore, as I could smother my anguish and change my underclothing, to Matilda B.'s did I hie myself away, on the sweet wings of love. Never shall I forget our betrothal.</p>
               <p>It was a calm, still night in June, and all Nature had been hushed into repose by a judicious use of Mrs. Winslow's soothing syrup. Matilda and I were walking pensively among the garden sauce back of her house, and I was repeating those touching lines by Johnny Bunyan:— <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"Two beets with but a single head,</l>
                        <l>Two cabbages with one."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Around us the frolicsome June bug gaily waltzed, and the cheerful hum of the mosquito added pathos to the scene; while in the adjacent mill-pond the guileless bull-frog performed a select anthem to departing day. Afar off in the western horizon the sun was setting, which he did in his usual hunky style, without bursting 'ary button off his trousers. Nothing disturbed the solemn stillness but the gentle heaving of her bosom, and the gentle heaving of a small boy in the woodshed, who had been smoking a cheroot. I was trying to imagine, with the pure affection of youth, how many stamps she had laid away, while she was heaving an elegant assortment of sighs, varying from a small to a large size.</p>
               <p>The ecstatic rapture which steeped my soul in bliss o'er-came me, and seizing Matilda by her waterfall, I imprinted the pure kiss of betrothal behind her left ear.</p>
               <p>She gazed at me in silent rapture, and while the lovelight light gleamed with dewy softness from those liquid orbs upraised to mine, she said—</p>
               <p>"Skinner, have you taken a bath lately?"</p>
               <p>She continued, "You don't amount to shucks. If you mean getting spliced, out with it. Come, set the day, my ancient fraud, my festive bald-headed daffadowndally."</p>
               <p>Thus with honeyed words of love did we beguile the time.</p>
               <p>We were married in church; my children as chief mourners occupying front seats. There were no cards, except a game of euchre to see who should sleep the front side of the bed. We took a short bridal tour; she went to Hingham to see her Aunt Abigail, and I came to Boston to buy a new set of type for the <title>Trombone</title>. It was about the time that all was so quiet on the Potomac, but that day Boston was in a fever of excitement, because it was hinted in official circles that the commanding general would move as soon as his rent became due, though he hated to leave Mason and Dixon's line, it was so handy to hang the clothes on, on washing days.</p>
               <p>On returning to my domicil in Slunkville, my wife addressed me in the following chaste language:—</p>
               <p>"Skinner, I am now boss of this chebang, and I really hope, for your mother's sake, that I shan't be obliged to use the mop-handle over your head more than twice a day, and once Sundays."</p>
               <p>Another eccentricity of hers is planting her feet in the small of my back after I have retired for the night, and whirling me playfully across the room. The first overture of this kind occurred one very cold morning; when I suggested the propriety of her getting up and building the fire. If my memory serves me right, and I think it does, I built the fire myself that A. M., and I have made a point to do it ever since. If there is any thing I dote on, it is rising with the lark and building the fire. [N. B. This is not a joke.]</p>
               <pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC5910-00000007"/>
               <p>The Spring of 1865 will long be remembered. Mr. Bob Lee, of the Southern Confederacy, annoyed at the conduct of U. Grant, P. Sheridan, and other filibusters, offered to meet Grant under a sour apple tree to discuss affairs, recuss scenes, and cuss results connected with the war. That little talk ended in R. Lee taking the Confederacy and gracefully shoving it up the spout, at the same time expressing a desire to go home, become an honest farmer, and raise milk for the Boston market, weeping bitterly because he had n't a tintype of Wendell Phillips. Then our brave boys came marching home from Canada, and the Legislature passed an act, kindly allowing our crippled veterans to grind their hand-organs on the corners of our streets during the Winter season. Great preparations were made in Slunkville to receive the returning braves. The town was thoroughly aroused, and a veteran reception of gigantic magnitude was projected, consisting of fireworks, decorations, and a <choice>
                     <sic>sumptous</sic>
                     <corr>sumptuous</corr>
                  </choice> repast by that eminent caterer, the Overseer of the Poor. Members of Congress and New York pickpockets were invited. A delegation of Slunkville landlords, who were always in favor of a vigorous prosecution of the war, were to receive the veterans by raising their rent, and all those who had lost a leg or an arm were considerately allowed twenty-four hours to leave the town. Ice water was also furnished the veterans at the low price of $1.00 a glass. The decorations were both tasty and elegant. In front of the <title>Trombone</title> office was a beautiful transparency representing the provost marshal making out exempt papers, and the inscription: "The heart of Slunkville this day throbs with pride. Terms $2.00 a year, invariably in advance." In front of Squire Parsons' was the motto: "The Onion—shall it be presarved?" In the window of the Union store were the words, "Awl hale, worthy suns of patriotic sires. Our Sprooce Beer is still 2 cts. a Glass, notwithstandin the Enormous Pressure brot to Bare against us by Blowtid Capitalists."</p>
               <p>At the close of the festivities I was called upon by the schoolmaster for a speech. He said: "Will the massive intellect whose genius lights up this warlike scene favor us with a few of his sparkling and caustic remarks? I allude to Mr. Skinner, the file leader of the American Press."</p>
               <p>This schoolmaster evidently has talents. I said—</p>
               <p>"Fellow citizens: this is indeed a momentous event. When out forefathers landed in America, and picked Mayflowers off Puritan Rock, they didn't dream of such a momentous event as this. No. As a momentous event it is far ahead of anything they ever dreamed of." [<hi rend="i"/>A voice, "Can't you say something about momentous event, afore you set down, old Shears?"] I continued, "In view, then, of an event so momentous, let us adjourn to Spooner's tavern and moisten our diaphragms." [This proved to be the most telling point in my speech, and was received with a perfect outburst of enthusiasm.]</p>
               <p>But enough. The proceedings of that day have passed into history.</p>
               <p>About this time my wife was elected president of a Woman's Rights Society, and commenced giving lectures.—Her most able production was entitled "Is man a loathsome beast?" in which she proved that if there wasn't any men, there wouldn't be an broken hearts, or any false calves. The first time she delivered this lecture it had such an effect upon the female portion of the audience, that they passed a resolution to smother every male infant immediately after birth; then they marched home, dressed in men's clothes, and went out on the Common and played leap-frog and pitched coppers, in imitation of their liege lords and masters. My wife is a whole Sorosis, and ought to be allowed to Vote, for I am confident she would throw aside all party quibbles, and vote for the handsomest man. She is not, you see, a common woman. Will etiquette allow me to call her a fancy breed?—one of those rare plants that bloom only<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC5910-00000008"/> once in a hundred years, and then make us feel bad because it is n't once in two hundred.   *   *   *   *</p>
               <p>In the Fall of '66 my business affairs were decidedly bilious. My assistant editor, Sniffins, from living exclusively on the mixture known as bean-hash, was reduced to a frightfully mixed condition. During a revival in Slunkville he put all the converts in the lists of births, simply because they were born again; and put the deaths under the head of "Turf matters." He used to get home late at night, put his pants to bed and hang himself over the back of a chair. When Artemus Ward was in town with his great show, Sniffins tried to elope with the wax figure of Mrs. Cunningham, and purloined a pair of rubbers that adorned the feet of Judas Iscariot. He used to go out on the Common, and stump any boy under twelve to lick him in a fair stand-up fight. And he got so lazy that if he was obliged to get up at eleven A. M. he complained bitterly of being broken of his rest. But he was the smartest eater I ever knew. At the Agricultural Fair that Fall he ate the entire collation provided for five hundred persons, and then complained of a gnawing at his stomach. He had a notion one spell that he wanted to join the church, but the minister did n't want him, and told him there was n't any vacancy; but he said he was bound to join something, so he joined the engine company. On one occasion he donned his wife's flannel petticoat and went through the streets singing the popular air, "I want to be an angel, and with the angels board." After which he proceeded to the minister's study and offered to supply the pulpit, or discuss the constitutionality of the ten commandments.</p>
               <p>At a spiritual circle once held in Slunkville, this wretched man deliberately walked up to the medium, and struck her a severe blow, upsetting her in a scandalous manner, and the only explanation he could offer for this dastardly outrage was that he had been sick, and the doctor had told him he didn't live steady enough. "In fact," said Dr. Squilbob, "you go too much to extremes; and if you ever expect to get well, you must strike a happy medium." Sniffins thought this medium appeared to be happy, and so he struck her. Yet there was talent in the family. His father was the most finished hand-organ player I ever listened to; and his aunt Hannah could cure a boil dreadful quick. At one time there was considerable gossip about his father, owing to a little incident which occurred in the family. He playfully murdered his wife and mother-in-law, threw them into a well, and run off with his brother's wife. Aside from this, he was as genial a person as I ever met, and could put down his even tumbler of Old Rye without a murmur.</p>
               <p>The reason I have not described in glowing terms a mammoth flag raising in Slunkville in the Spring of '62, is because we never had any. A man named Slobbs suggested a flag raising. "No matter about any flag," said he; "let's a hoist Mose Skinner, for he combines most beautifully the national colors. H e's <emph>red</emph> nosed, <emph>white</emph> livered, and <emph>blue</emph> all the time."</p>
               <p>The next issue of the <title>Trombone</title> contained Slobbs' obituary notice, done up in my hunkiest style, which had the effect of ridding Slunkville of his carcase. He was seen to enter the Eastern Railroad depot and deliberately buy a ticket for Lynn, and that was the last of him.</p>
               <milestone n="" unit="typography"/>
               <p>Taking into consideration the flatulency of my business and the perfect cussedness of Slunkville generally, I determined to leave those classic shades. The opportunity presented itself in the Fall of '68, when I was called upon by the directors of the DEAD-BEAT MUTUAL LIFE INSURANCE COMPANY, to assume the presidency of that popular institution. I print their letter of request, and also their brilliant soul-stirring Prospectus, that the public may see that there's no humbug in the honor they would do me.</p>
               <pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC5910-00000009"/>
               <q>
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <opener>
                              <dateline>
                                 <date>Boston, Fall of '68.</date>
                              </dateline>
                              <address>
                                 <addrLine>MOSE SKINNER, Esq., Slunkville, Vt.</addrLine>
                              </address>
                           </opener>
                           <p>Dear Sir:—We the undersigned, representing the philanthropic interest of Boston, have recently organized a mammoth Life Insurance Company, which will excel in its ramifications every other known company. Esteeming your well-known philanthropy and acknowledged talent, we unanimously elected you President of our Co.,—feeling assured that in your hands it will find one worthy of its noble purposes. Presuming on your acceptance, we have taken the liberty of using your name in the following:</p>
                           <p>Prospectus of the Dead-Beat Life Insurance Company.</p>
                           <list>
                              <item>Cash Assets, $300,000,000. Liabilities, $1.39.</item>
                              <item>President, MOSE SKINNER, Esq.</item>
                              <item>Vice President, MOSE SKINNER.</item>
                              <item>Treasurer, M. SKINNER.</item>
                              <item>Directors <list>
                                    <item>O. FLEECEEM, Esq.</item>
                                    <item>WILL.  ROBEM,</item>
                                    <item>Hon. D. FAULTER,</item>
                                    <item>CLEEN M. OUT,</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                           <p>This gigantic Company, representing as it does many prominent Philanthropists of New England, offers rare inducements to those wishing to insure their lives against the ravages of disease and matrimony. Although yet in its infancy, it hopes, by strict attention to business, to merit a share of public condemnation.</p>
                           <p>The object of our Company is not to make money. O no. We have a loftier object in view than the gathering of coupons. It is a well-known fact that Death on his velocipede is going his rounds, and unceremoniously entering our families and removing the husbands and fathers thereof, without regard to age or sex. Our object is to relieve death of its sting, and make it purely a question of greenbacks; and if the widow wants to marry again, the Company furnishes her with a husband. This is a purely protective measure, and prevents the funds of the Company from being scattered. We also give a Free Lunch to all the policy-holders once a month, which takes place at the nearest almshouse, and is a truly convivial occasion.</p>
                           <p>We have secured the services of that able philanthropist, MOSE SKINNER, Esq., as general dragger-in of patrons. He will carry with him a demijohn of chloroform, and administer the same to such persons as he may select, under the subterfuge of a free drink, and while the victim is unconscious, he will be dragged into our office and insured. This is much superior to the style now in vogue, of sending out agents to waylay the victim at street corners and offices, and by a constant diarrhea of words reducing him to a state of imbecility, in which condition he is induced to take out a policy.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <head>A Few Facts to be Considered.</head>
                           <p>If any man who is in the habit of smoking one cigar a day, will smoke only half a cigar a day and deposit the rest of the money in the Dead-Beat Mutual Life Insurance. Co., he will die a millionaire.</p>
                           <p>The proceeds of one oyster-stew a week for an average lifetime, will enable a man's descendants to live on Commonwealth Avenue with a colored coachman.</p>
                           <p>The proceeds of a ham sandwich and a glass of lager beer daily, during a considerable length of time, will enable all future generations bearing your name to be steeped in luxury.</p>
                           <list>
                              <head>5 REASONS WHY I SHOULD INSURE IN THE DEAD-BEAT MUTUAL LIFE INSURANCE COMPANY.</head>
                              <item>1st. Because it is a good thing.</item>
                              <item>2d. Because it is the best thing I can do.</item>
                              <item>3d. Because I shall double my money in a very short time.</item>
                              <item>4th. Because I shall quadruple my money in just twice the time that it takes to double it.</item>
                              <item>5th. If I put my money into the hands of these noble minded Directors, I shall not squander it for clothes and house rent.</item>
                           </list>
                           <p>Any person wishing to join the Dead-Beat Mutual Life Insurance Company, can do so without undergoing any embarrassing scrutiny. We simply ask a candidate the following questions, which are both simple and chaste:</p>
                           <p>1st. Are you married or a single bachelor? If the latter, how many children have you?</p>
                           <pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC5910-00000010"/>
                           <p>2d. Are your children mostly boys and girls?</p>
                           <p>3d. Are you in favor of annexation to Boston?— and if so, how much of this happy and united country would you annex?</p>
                           <p>4th. Do you think the Peace Jubilee promoted peace and harmony throughout the land?—or only harmony in St. James' Park?</p>
                           <p>5th. Do you think that the whale that swallowed Jonah was dyspeptic simply because Jonah laid hard on his stomach?</p>
                           <p>6th. Do you think that "Gates Ajar" has anything to do with Open Bars?</p>
                           <p>Any person answering in the affirmative to all these questions, will be admitted to membership in the Dd Bt Mu. Life Ins. Co.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="part">
                           <head>THE DANGERS OF DELAY.</head>
                           <p>
                              <hi rend="i"/>Michael Rooney, laborer, thought of getting his life insured; called at our office for the purpose, but concluded he would just ask his wife about it first. On his way home from a "wake" that evening, he fell over a policeman who was asleep in his doorway. Mr. Rooney's legs were fractured, and he died in great agony exclaiming, "O be jabers, why did n't I gone an' done it!"—meaning, of course got his life insured.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi rend="i"/>Mr. Jones, merchant, decided to insure with us. Went home to dinner in at great hurry that day, so as to get down to our office as soon as possible. Wife sick, and laid her false teeth on the table; cook got the teeth and tried to chew slippery elm with them, broke them, and one tooth fell into the, soup. Mr. Jones took his soup, did n't see the tooth, tooth stuck in his throat, and he suffocated instantly. Family left in indigent circumstances. Wife ca n't go shopping but six times a week. Eldest son commenced wandering in his mind, finally became idiotic. Is now a clerk in a dry goods store. Sad case.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi rend="i"/>Mr. Loony Tick expected to run for Congress in the 5th District, and of course would have to get his life insured. On his way to our office attacked by roughs. Did n't run for Congress, but run for his life instead. Had a fight and got stabbed—died soon after; family saved the mortification of having a member of Congress to answer for.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>I decided to accept the honors so handsomely offered, as I saw in perspective a glorious opportunity for following the illustrious example of many philanthropic gentlemen who went into office poor and went out rich.</p>
               <milestone n="——" unit="typography"/>
               <p>As soon as it was generally known that I was to leave Slunkville, the excitement was intense. The grocer and butcher, expressed their grief in a touching memorial of several pages, commenting "Mose Skinner, Dr.," and ending with "pleas kall and settle at wonst." The good deacon said he should miss those little brass buttons my boys used to drop in the contribution-box. The sexton, a white-haired old man, came to me with tears in his eyes, and said he had long fondly hoped to plant me in yonder quiet churchyard, but now this boon was denied him. The engine company brought out their machine and squirted for half an hour in front of my office, directing the stream into my window, with the playful remark that they wanted to keep me from spoiling.</p>
               <p>The citizens generally were aroused, and proposed a grand impromptu meeting, in the town-hall, to express their resignation at my departure. To attempt to describe that affair would be impossible. The halt, the maimed, the blind, the idiotic and bedridden, all, all, were there. Old Cynthia Benson, who hadn't been off her bed for thirty years, "vowed to man" she would see Mose Skinner off, if she had to go in a wheelbarrow, which proved to be the case, her son Joel on this occasion winning many laurels as an eminent wheelist.</p>
               <p>As I entered the broad aisle escorted by the constable, the choir, which were stationed in the gallery, struck up the soul-stirring stanzas, <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"How pleased and blest are we</l>
                        <l>To see Mose Skinner flee."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC5910-00000011"/>
               <p>Over the rostrum was a beautiful transparency, representing me in the act of taking the stage, and the words, "We are resigned."</p>
               <p>The schoolmaster was the first speaker. He said it was with sorrowful joy that he noted the departure of one of Slunkville's solid men—183 pounds avoirdupois—the file leader of stove-huggers, the champion rester of America. In fitting terms he congratulated Boston on the acquisition of this brilliant carbuncle of genius. In conclusion, he hoped I would revisit those scenes where my editorial labors had been so eminently successful. (<hi rend="i"/>A voice. "I hope so, too, for he aint paid for that piece of tripe he bought of me the other day.")</p>
               <p>Parson Twitchell spoke next. He felt not only resigned at my departure, he said, but in fact quite cheerful. Looking at it in the light of a dispensation of Providence, it was one of Providence's most gratifying dispensations. He had known me long and intimately, and he could truly say that to any one accustomed to lending money, I would prove a firm friend. No one encouraged free lectures more than I did, or slept sounder when the contribution box was passed around. It was but justice to say that, as a tranquil slumberer during service, I knocked the spots out of any of his congregation. Who calls at meal-times more regularly than Mr. Skinner? Who is more ready to borrow our bottom dollar? His wife and family have long looked to him as their mainstay and support, and will probably keep on looking for a good while longer. They never had a want untold. They simply asked him for anything they wanted, and rather than disappoint them, he would let them keep on asking all their lives. He closed by offering me letters of mark to all the hotels, and the run of the Public Garden, with the privilege of looking at the Ether monument, or lounging on the bridge.</p>
               <p>His speech was a most finished production, and occupied about sixty-two minutes in passing any given point, and I gave him a point to start with. It was most affecting, and at its close there was scarcely a dry seat in the house.</p>
               <p>At this juncture cries of "Skinner," "speech," "hi, hi," &amp;c., rent the air, and as I arose, the enthusiasm of that vast assembly found vent in a perfect outburst of applause. I spoke as follows:—</p>
               <p>"My friends, what can I say on this momentous occasion?—What truths can I utter? (<hi rend="i"/>A voice—"Say you're a cussed fraud.") Oh! would I were a Webster, or a Clay, that I might do justice to this occasion. (<hi rend="i"/>A voice. "If this occasion was a square meal, you'd do justice to it.") The kind evidences of affection which I everywhere see almost unman me, and I feel as though I could not leave you, that my departure is a hideous dream. (<hi rend="i"/>A voice. "It will be a hideous nightmare if you stay.") My friends, how shall I best bid you adieu?" (<hi rend="i"/>A voice. "Take a dose of arsenic.")</p>
               <p>Thus, under a cloak of mirthful jest, did these honest villagers conceal their grief.</p>
               <p>At the close of the meeting the scene baffles description. All of that vast assembly wished me God-speed and quick about it, and earnestly hoped that no accident would occur to oblige my return to Slunkville. Little children gathered around me with tears in their eyes, and said I was their papa, and I was so overcome with emotion that I couldn't deny it, which caused a large red-headed female to exclaim, "God forbid that he should be anybody's pa, unless they want to die on a gallus, a-dancin' on nothin'!"</p>
               <milestone n="——" unit="typography"/>
               <p>I had some difficulty in finding a house in Boston with the right kind of a landlord. My object was to find a tenement where the parties were not inquisitive—about their rent.<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC5910-00000012"/> After a great deal of trouble, I finally got the refusal of a house, but I kept getting a refusal every time I went, so I left in disgust, hired a small attic in Chelsea, and took my meals at the South End, till my family arrived, then I let my wife look round a little. Of course these little family matters are, between you and I.</p>
               <p>I like Boston. It is a cheerful hamlet. Shakespeare was smart, but he never produced a cheerful Hamlet.</p>
               <p>In order to preserve my family circle intact, I brought my children with me, of which I have about what is considered sufficient punishment for a man of sin. Two of my sons are fast rising into a proud eminence in their profession, and bid fair to chalk their initials high up on the ladder of fame. They are dry-goods clerks.</p>
               <p>My youngest boy is a very smart, bright boy, and I am told that he resembles me more than any one of the children. He is studying with a civil engineer at present, and I asked his boss the other night how he was getting along. He said the last time be saw him he was going to dinner—he was getting along first-rate then. He added that my boy would never make a civil engineer, but might make a very uncivil one. He laughed as though he had said something funny.</p>
               <p>My daughters are fine specimens of the robust bean-fed female woman. They play the piano, of course. They might as well go into a nunnery at once, if they couldn't. I have got a very pretty piano, with the Æolian attachment, also a sheriff's attachment. My daughters have no attachment, but there is a South Boston flat who persists in abusing a guitar under their window, accompanying said guitar with the tune, "My heart pants for thee, gentle maiden," though what his heart has got to do with his pants, is more'n I know. The other night be played till one A. M. without stopping once, so I put my head out of the window and tried to reason gently with him. "Go home, gentle youth," said I, "go home and let it pant." He said this was a cold world. "Yes," said I "but you'll find a warmer one very sudden, if you don't leave; and perhaps a bucket of boiling hot water may assist you in realizing the joys of your future existence." I was a little riled at the young monkey, and if I said anything I was sorry for, I am ready to be forgiven.</p>
               <p>Any one who thinks their happiness depends on owning one of those pictures of mine, should go for their bottom dollar at once, and secure "the shadow ere the substance fades."</p>
               <milestone n="——" unit="typography"/>
               <p>N. B. If anybody wants to present me a gold-headed Cane, they can do so at once, without any hesitation. I should n't take it badly if a cottage at Newport was given me.</p>
               <p>N. B. No. 2. My wife wants a moire antique dress. The one she has is more antique than the fashion, and she won't wear it. She is n't a large person, and I think she could get along with 43 yards. She will trim it with festoons of shambry gauze and toil de Lynn, scolloped.</p>
               <p>I've been thinking all Summer about getting a white hat with a black band, but I don't see how I can afford it, as I've been at considerable expense lately in putting a new handle on my coal-hod. I suppose such a one as I want would cost about $17.20.</p>
               <p>I am a good deal like Grant,—I am very diffident about accepting presents.</p>
               <p>WANTED—A young man of pious ancestry, of thorough classical attainments, perfectly familiar with Greek, Latin, and Hebrew, to take care of seven horses, a female cow, and a nightmare. In his spare time he would be allowed the privilege of shaking the door-mat. Salary no object.</p>
               <p>Apply to the</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Public's obedient servant,</salute>
                  <signed>MOSE SKINNER</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="advertisement">
            <pb n="24 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC5910-00000013"/>
            <head>METCALF'S STENCIL ROOMS.</head>
            <p>Name Stencils for Marking Clothing, and Business Stencils for MERCHANTS &amp; MANUFACTURERS</p>
            <p>"Made to order in every style, and at the shortest notice.</p>
            <p>STENCIL TOOLS AND STOCK in great variety.</p>
            <p>L. S. METCALF, 101 Union St., Boston.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="advertisement">
            <head>NICE PRINTING!</head>
            <p>CARDS, CIRCULARS, BILLHEADS, &amp;c. DONE PROMPTLY, AT THE USUAL PRICES, BY WARREN RICHARDSON, 11 Milk Street, Boston.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="advertisement">
            <head>GLYCERINE POMADE,</head>
            <head type="sub">For Dressing and Promoting the Growth of the HAIR.</head>
            <p>Composed of Glycerine, the sweet principle of Oils, solidified; is not susceptible of becoming rancid or sticky,—its undrying, glossy properties, render it the most soothing and softening application known for the Hair, when prepared as in CLOCK'S GLYCERINE POMADE, sold by Apothecaries generally, and at the Proprietor's, corner of Temple &amp; Cambridge Streets, Boston.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>