<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC5558">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Aleck and Pete, or, 'The Hand of the Diligent Maketh Rich' </title>
            <author >Anonymous</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC5558</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >Aleck and Pete, or, 'The hand of the diligent maketh rich'</title>
                  <author >Anonymous</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >16 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >S.W. Book and Publishing Co.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>St. Louis </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1870">1870</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2000-08-18">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="Jennifer Riley, Indiana University" when="2000-11-03">Finished markup</change>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2000-11-08">Finished final editing</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <front> 
         <titlePage xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="cover"> 
            <pb  n=" (Cover) " xml:id="VAC5558-00000001"/> 
            <docTitle> 
               <titlePart>ALECK AND PETE;</titlePart> 
               <titlePart type="sub">OR, THE HAND OF THE Diligent Maketh Rich.</titlePart> 
            </docTitle> 
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>SAINT LOUIS:</pubPlace> 
               <publisher >SOUTHWESTERN BOOK AND PUBLISHING COMP'Y. <address> 
                     <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">510 AND 512 WASHINGTON AVENUE</addrLine> 
                  </address>
               </publisher> 
               <docDate>1870.</docDate>
            </docImprint> 
         </titlePage> 
         <titlePage xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
            <pb  n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC5558-00000002"/> 
            <docTitle> 
               <titlePart>ALECK AND PETE;</titlePart> 
               <titlePart type="sub">OR, The Hand of the Diligent Maketh Rich.</titlePart> 
            </docTitle> 
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>SAINT LOUIS:</pubPlace> 
               <publisher >S.W. BOOK AND PUBLISHING CO., 510 WASHINGTON AV.</publisher> 
               <docDate>1870.</docDate>
            </docImprint> 
            <pb  n="" xml:id="VAC5558-00000003"/> 
            <docEdition>Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1870, by the S.W. BOOK AND PUBLISHING CO., In the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United States for the Eastern District of Missouri.</docEdition> 
         </titlePage> 
      </front> 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Aleck and Pete, or, 'The hand of the diligent maketh rich'</head> 
            <pb n=""/> 
            <head>ALECK AND PETE,</head> 
            <head type="sub">OR, 'The Hand of the Diligent Maketh Rich'</head> 
            <div type="text"> 
               <p>"How are you, Aleck?"</p> 
               <p>"How are you, Pete?"</p> 
               <p>These exclamations came at the same moment from two young men who met in the Hall of the Southern Hotel. The latter had just turned from the register where he had been looking over the arrivals; the former from reading the flaming playbills  which decorated the side of the hall.</p> 
               <p>Alexander H. and Peter M. had been fellow-salesmen and room-mates for three or four years, during which time a warmer and more enduring friendship had grown up between them than often characterizes those who are not united by the ties of kindred. What their surnames were is not important  to our story. The short and familiar ones they applied to each other will answer our purpose. A hearty hand shaking followed the meeting of the old and fast friends.</p> 
               <pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC5558-00000004"/> 
               <p>"Where have you been, and how have you got on these two or three years," said Pete "since I last saw you? Starting for California, wasn't it?"</p> 
               <p>"No," replied Aleck, "for Montana-though I went to California afterward. And instead of two or three, it is nearer six years since I left here."</p> 
               <p>"Six years!" exclaimed Pete. "I had no idea it was so long. But 'time speeds unnoticed when he treads on flowers' is for once truth as well as poetry. But what have you been doing, old fellow,  anyhow? Made a beginning at least for a fortune,  I hope?"</p> 
               <p>"Not by a long shot, Pete. If your path has been through flowers, mine has been through thorns, I tell you. They have not left me a stitch of pants but what I have on, and a scanty invoice of upper rigging. And as to a fortune, I shall think myself rich if I get something to do to pay expenses till next spring, when I'll go to Oregon or Alaska, or somewhere. And now, tell me how <emph>you</emph> have got along these hard times? Had better luck than I've had, I hope?"</p> 
               <p>"I've no great cause to complain, Aleck. But I have a long story to tell you, and have not time for it this morning. Where can I see you this afternoon to have a long chat over old times."</p> 
               <p>"Suppose you call here and take supper with me; after that we will go the theatre to see Collins<pb n=""/> in "Arrah na Pogue;" then stay the night with me-that will be like old times, sure enough."</p> 
               <p>"Can't do it, Aleck, for several reasons. In the first place, my wife"-</p> 
               <p>"Your wife!" shouted Aleck. "You married?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, truly. Why not? But I'll tell you all about it this afternoon. And as to going to the theatre, I'm obliged to you for the invitation; but I haven't been in one for five years, and won't be for five more, if I know myself."</p> 
               <p>"The thunder you haven't!" exclaimed Aleck. "What's come over you? Well, come and take a drink, anyhow. I feel as if I needed something to sustain me under this awful news of your having fallen into matrimony."</p> 
               <p>"Excuse me, Aleck, but I have not 'smiled' for five years, neither."</p> 
               <p>"You're making up for the privation now, Pete, for you're as smiling and looking "as happy as a big sunflower." Well, have a cigar, at least."</p> 
               <p>"Thankee, Aleck. I've quit smoking and chewing, too."</p> 
               <p>"Whew!" whistled Aleck as he stepped back two paces and eyed his old friend from head to foot with looks of wonder and incredulity. "Given up theatres,  and drinks, and cigars, and stuck to it for five years! See here, Pete, have you turned Methodist parson? Where are you going to hold forth next Sunday?"</p> 
               <pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC5558-00000005"/> 
               <p>"No, Aleck!" said Pete, gravely. "I'm at my old business of salesman, at the old place. I'm no preacher-at least of theology-though I do  sometimes 'exhort' a little on kindred topics. I'll give you a specimen this evening from the text, 'The hand of the diligent maketh rich.' So, till 4 P.M.,  good-bye."</p> 
               <p>They parted, the one going down to his place of business on Second street, the other sauntering into the bar-room, where, somehow, he omitted his usual brandy cock-tail, contenting himself with a cigar. He followed Pete down town to look up his old acquaintances, and to try to procure a situation. At the appointed time and place the pair met again and went up to Aleck's room to converse an hour or so about the past, present and future.</p> 
               <p>"Now, Aleck" said Pete, throwing himself into a cushioned chair, "let me renew my question of this morning. How have you got on these five years-where have you been and what have you been doing?"</p> 
               <p>"I've been in almost every State and Territory between here and the Pacific, besides some in Mexico.  Sometimes I made a little money, then again lost it. At last, finding no good opening in California,  I packed up last week at San Francisco for this my old stamping ground, which after all seems to offer as many advantages as any other in the Union. I want a situation. What chance do you<pb n=""/> think there is for a boy of my size? In fact, I must make something soon, for I haven't money enough in my pocket to keep the blue devils a month longer from dancing a jig there. Its a short yarn, Aleck-I make it so in order to hear how you've done in the meantime. Got along pretty well, it seems to me-all but the marrying, which I don't more than half believe. Well, if you are married, I'm crazy to see the divinity who tempted you to bow your neck to the yoke matrimonial. Where are you boarding? I'm bound to make you an early visit. She was rich, of course?"</p> 
               <p>"No, Aleck, she was poor, like myself. You shall see her this evening. We are keeping house at Carondlelet."</p> 
               <p>"Poor and keeping house!" exclaimed Aleck. "Come, come, Pete, you're drawing the long-bow a little too strong."</p> 
               <p>"You shall see for yourself. We'll go down on the 5.40 train; you'll take supper with us and see my establishment. I'm sorry my house is not large enough to admit of my <choice>
                     <sic>accomodating</sic>
                     <corr>accommodating</corr>
                  </choice> you for the night. But you can come back on the 9.15 train and get to the hotel by early bed-time."</p> 
               <p>"Thankee, Pete, I'll go with pleasure. But do tell me what has wrought this transformation in your character and habits, which seems to me little short of a miracle?"</p> 
               <p>"No miracle at all," said Pete, "nor luck neither.<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC5558-00000006"/> It was simply the result of attention to the text I quoted this morning, 'The hand of the diligent maketh rich.' We parted," he continued, "five years ago last spring-you going to Montana and I remaining reluctantly in my old situation. I was lonely for a while, I tell you I was, for we had  been room-mates and cronies for over three years. I tried to find some good fellow to fill your place, for I could not well afford to keep that big room alone. Studying this over for some days, I began to review the kind of life we had led, and I was not long in arriving at the conclusion that"-</p> 
               <p>"That your late chum," broke in Aleck, "was one of the most prudent, moral, and every way exemplary young men in St. Louis; fit to be President of the Young Men's Christian Association?"</p> 
               <p>"No, Aleck, I concluded that you and I had been the greatest ninnies, the most exemplary asses that ever carried off the blue ribbands at a donkey show."</p> 
               <p>"Complimentary-very," said Aleck. "But how so?"</p> 
               <p>"We were getting twelve hundred dollars a year when you left, I believe?" said Pete.</p> 
               <p>"Yes, you twelve hundred, I a hundred more, for I had been a year longer in the house," said Aleck.</p> 
               <p>"How much did we <emph>save</emph> out of our salaries?" asked Pete.</p> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <p>"Save!" replied Aleck. "Not a dollar that I know of. At least I didn't. In truth, I had to leave with some little bills unpaid, till I remitted you for them-you recollect?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes. Now, Aleck, what became of our money?"</p> 
               <p>"Why, we spent it, of course," replied Aleck. "What else is money for?"</p> 
               <p>"True, but were we not fools to spend it all, and the way we did? to waste so much on things we could well have dispensed with-indeed what often injured us? How much did we spend, each of us, on cigars and tobacco alone?"</p> 
               <p>"Let me see," said Aleck, studying. "A quarter or so a day-say two dollars a week."</p> 
               <p>"And how much for drinks?"</p> 
               <p>"We were very temperate, you know. Not more than two or three a day. Put it another two dollars  a week."</p> 
               <p>How much for theater tickets and consequent hack-hire, gloves, bouquets, suppers, etc.?"</p> 
               <p>"Not over an average of-let me see," said Aleck, puzzled. "Rather hard to calculate. Big item. Put them down at an average of three-fifty a week."</p> 
               <p>"And billiards?" continued Pete.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, a mere trifle; not over a dollar and a half a week."</p> 
               <p>"Your figures, Aleck, are not above the mark, and yet the amount, in the aggregate, if we had only stopped to foot it up, would have alarmed us. Look<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC5558-00000007"/> at it. Cigars and tobacco, two dollars; drinks, two dollars; theaters, etc., three and a half; billiards, a dollar and a half. Nine dollars a week! <emph>Four hundred  and sixty-eight dollars a year!</emph> More than a third of our income."</p> 
               <p>"Your array of figures looks serious, certainly," said Aleck. "But what would you have a young fellow do? Save like a miser and live like a hermit?"</p> 
               <p>"No, not if he is content to remain a poor devil all his life. But if he is poor and wants to rise, to acquire property, to become a self-supporting, respectable man, he has no means to effect his object but to be economical as well as industrious-he must <emph>save a part</emph> of his earnings, and persevere in this course for years. In this way a majority of our rich men began life; it is the only sure way to success. Those who rise by speculation, who become rich suddenly, are the exceptions, not the rule. Industry and economy will win fifty times where speculation does once. Such, Aleck, were my reflections as I sat one Sunday morning at our window, a week after you left. I had spent nearly all my earnings. I had not saved more than enough to pay my expenses for a month, if I had chanced to be sick for that time. I had no idea of remaining  in a subordinate position all my life, and yet I had not even begun to lay up a fund to begin business  on. In short, I had acted like an ass! For a moment I felt disheartened, but I recovered hope<pb n=""/> and determined to turn over a new leaf-to be wiser in future, and to begin that very moment. I pitched my half smoked cigar out of the window, resolving to never touch another. I abandoned drinks, also, forthwith, and theaters and billiards. They and a few other superfluities had cost me over five hundred dollars a year. I determined to save that sum in future."</p> 
               <p>"And you really stuck to it, Pete?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, I did, though I suffered a sort of martyrdom  for two or three months."</p> 
               <p>"Which was hardest to quit?" asked Aleck.</p> 
               <p>"Cigars and tobacco," replied Pete; "the others were comparatively easy. For two months or more I feared I would have to take to them again. I was almost unfitted for attending to business. In fact, a medical friend advised me to use them moderately,  fearing bad results to my health. But I stuck to my resolve and came off conqueror. In two years from that time I had saved over eleven  hundred dollars. I married then, and spent most of my savings for furniture to begin house-keeping on. The senior partners of our house thought I had acted rashly in marrying. But when I explained  the whole to Mr. C-, who, you know, with all his stern exacting ways, has the kindest heart in the world for young men who are striving to rise as he did-when I told him of my abstinences, my savings, my style of house-keeping and plans for the future, he instantly approved of the whole, and generously ordered an increase of two hundred dollars  a year to my salary. The same increase, he told me, should be made yearly as long as I kept on in the same track. It is three years since I married,  and I have never regretted the adventure. I have found it as easy to save as before. Indeed, our savings have increased. But come, Aleck, I see it is time for us to start for the depot. You shall<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC5558-00000008"/> see for yourself how I am fixed, and then laugh at  or pity me, as you will."</p> 
               <p>Aleck turned to the mirror, made some improvement  in his toilet, and accompanied his friend to the cars. After a few minutes' ride they were at the handsome suburban town of Carondelet. A short walk brought them near Mr. M's. house, a  small, two-story cottage, with white-curtained windows,  trim fences, shrubbery, vines, everything suited to such a residence; the whole betokening comfort, taste and industrious care. A pretty two-year old boy toddled down the path with outspread  arms and face beaming with delight to meet his expected father. Aleck had not time to recover  from the pleasant surprise at finding that it was  Pete's son and his own namesake, when he was introduced to Mrs. M., who was awaiting their  arrival and holding the gate open to admit the party. He was received with the courtesy due to an esteemed friend of her husband. Though something  of a connoisseur in the matter of female costume,  Aleck failed to note anything about that of his new acquaintance, except that it was very neat and lady-like. Her face commanded instant respect as well as admiration, while her figure and movements  were the very personification of grace and  dignity. "What a lucky fellow Pete is," thought  he as they entered the small but pretty parlor, "to  possess such a wife, and son, and home, if," he added, "he is only able to keep up such an establishment."</p> 
               <p>While Mrs. M. was making some additions to the supper table the two friends walked out into the garden, which, like the house, showed evidences of skill, taste, and much labor. A large vine hung  full of clusters of grapes, and a few pear and peach trees were bending under their loads of luscious fruit. Flowers, too, were not wanting to lend<pb n=""/> beauty to utility. The gravel walks were level, smooth and clean, the borders neatly trimmed.</p> 
               <p>"You keep a gardener, I suppose?" said Aleck, inquiringly.</p> 
               <p>"Yes, or rather the gardener keeps me-at work. My wife and I do all the work; the heavier and rougher parts, of course, fall to my share."</p> 
               <p>"Indeed! But when do you find time for this work?"</p> 
               <p>"Of mornings and evenings-an hour, a half, or even a few minutes, on my part. My wife often spends some hours at it when the weather is very fine. It helps to keep her in good health; besides, our vegetables and fruits add much to our table, which, from the time of the violets in spring till that of the chrysanthemums of autumn, is never set without a bouquet to adorn it."</p> 
               <p>The supper bell tinkled and they went in, Mr. M. bearing in his hand a basket of choice fruit to serve for a dessert. The repast need not be described;  it was all a husband returning from daily toil could ask or expect from the hands of a loving wife. Aleck thought he had never tasted one so delicious. Its flavor was, no doubt, hightened by the air of contentment, purity and love which threw a charm over the entire household. The minutes sped rapidly while the two friends conversed about the events of the last five years. Nine o'clock was at hand and Aleck prepared to depart for the city. Mrs. M. joined her husband in inviting him to come down to see them often. Arrived at the depot they had a few minutes to spare before the train would come up.</p> 
               <p>"You must be thinking of beginning business for yourself soon?" inquired Aleck of Pete.</p> 
               <p>"No," he replied, "times are too unsettled. Most of those who are in business would as lief be out. Profits are small, expenses high, and currency<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC5558-00000009"/> deranged. I prefer a good salary for a while longer. Besides, I hold it to be a man's first duty to provide for his wife, or child, or parent. I have, therefore, invested most of my savings in such a way that if I were to die to-night my family would be moderately but surely provided for."</p> 
               <p>"How did you invest?" asked Aleck.</p> 
               <p>"By securing a policy of life insurance, which I did, for five thousand dollars, on the ten-payment fifteen-year endowment plan. And I must say that no act of my life ever gave me greater or more permanent satisfaction. It gives me but little trouble to pay the premiums yearly. I have to make only ten of them. If I live fifteen years I will receive, from <emph>eight</emph> to <emph>ten</emph> thousand dollars. If I am taken ill, dangerously so, the reflection that my beloved ones are provided for, will add to my peace of mind and help to restore me to health. And if, through some extraordinary chance or Providence, I become bankrupt, the law preserves my life insurance from seizure by rapacious creditors.  My wife and child would secure it amid the wreck to save them from poverty."</p> 
               <p>"I've heard a great deal lately about life insurance,"  said Aleck, "but confess I had a prejudice against it, though for no very definite reason. Perhaps  it was because it looked like a very serious matter; something like making a will, or buying a lot in a <choice>
                     <sic>cemetry</sic>
                     <corr>cemetery</corr>
                  </choice>, or getting married. But your approval gives me a better opinion of it, and induces me to believe that it is not, as I thought, one of the humbugs brought out so frequently of late to diddle us out of our money."</p> 
               <p>"No, Aleck, it is neither a novelty nor a humbug.  Life insurance companies have been in operation  for many years in Europe and have been regarded with great favor by the public. It was  introduced into this country more than thirty years<pb n=""/> ago, but remained almost dormant until within the last few years. Since then, say since the year 1860, it has increased with wonderful rapidity. It is even said that its operations have quadrupled in the last four years. The amount of the policies held in this country now is estimated at two thousand millions of dollars, and the work is not more than fairly started."</p> 
               <p>"It is this very rapidity of increase and this magnitude  which excited my fears," interrupted Aleck.</p> 
               <p>"You may dismiss that fear," said Pete. "The principles on which life insurance is built are so unfailing and so perfectly understood now that the best judges of finance and business in general have decided that there is no mode whatever in which money can be invested that presents greater assurance  of permanence and safety. In fact, it has been declared on undoubted authority that "<hi rend="i"/>there is nothing  in the commercial world which approaches even remotely the security of a well established and prudently  managed life insurance company."</p> 
               <p>"I give it up, Pete," replied Aleck. "I will dismiss  my prejudices against life insurance companies,  and will probably follow your example in securing a policy as soon as I have a little spare cash. But the first thing with me now is to secure this; I am nearly out of money, and must get something  to do right away. And you must help me to find a situation."</p> 
               <p>"Come around in the morning," said Pete, "and I'll see what can be done for you. And now, Aleck, as the train is coming up to the depot, I have only time to ask you what you think of my doings since you went away? Which are you ready to do-to laugh at or pity me?"</p> 
               <p>"Laugh at or pity you!" exclaimed Aleck. "No; from the bottom of my soul I <emph>envy</emph> you, though I<pb n="16" xml:id="VAC5558-00000010"/> would, if I could, double your prosperity and happiness.  You richly deserve them. You have acted like a man of sense, and I like a d-ogoned fool. You have employed your last five years in laying the foundation of a fortune. I have wasted mine in thoughtless dissipation."</p> 
               <p>"Never despair," said Pete, kindly. "It is never too late to reform. You have sowed your wild oats; now resolve to use the talents Heaven has given you for a better purpose. Have courage; determine to conquer your evil habits and you'll me out right side up yet."</p> 
               <p>"Pete, old fellow," said Aleck, as he pressed his  friend's hand nervously and tried to conceal his troubled feelings, "Pete, old fellow, you have this day taught me the best lesson I ever learned in my life. I'm going, like you, to turn over a new leaf, and to follow your example. I'll settle right down here in St. Louis, from this day forth and forever. I'll forswear and abjure cigars, tobacco, drinks, theaters,  billiards, cards, fast horses, et cetera, et cetera.  I'll work as hard and save as closely as ever you did. And I'll copy you in securing, with the first surplus cash I have, a life insurance policy for the benefit of my old mother. God forgive me for neglecting her so long." Here his voice grew thick, and his friend, with a kindly pressure of the hand, interposed.</p> 
               <p>"Your head and heart are all right again, Aleck. Have courage, stick to your resolves, and all will go well with you in future."</p> 
               <p>"Stick to them!" exclaimed Aleck. "I'll do it or die trying. If I don't I wish I may be teetotally and eternally-"</p> 
               <p>"Toot, toot," whistled the locomotive, "all aboard," shouted the conductor; the train was in motion, Aleck sprang on the platform, and was whirled away up to the city.</p> 
            </div> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>