<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC5690">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >The Emigrant's Mother </title>
            <author >Babcock, Rufus (1798-1875)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC5690</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >The emigrant's mother</title>
                  <author >Babcock, Rufus (1798-1875)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >144 p. [2] leaves of plates </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >Sheldon</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1871">1871</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="ita">Italian</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2000-09-23">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-04-26">Finished TEI encoding, proofreading, and final editing.</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <front> 
         <div type="illustrations"> 
            <pb n="Illustration (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC5690-00000001"/> 
            <p>
               <figure> 
                  <head>"Frightful was the spectacle as he turned to look back for his companion."</head> 
               </figure>
            </p> 
         </div> 
         <titlePage xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
            <docTitle> 
               <titlePart>THE EMIGRANT'S MOTHER:</titlePart> 
               <titlePart type="sub">A True Story of the last Fifty Years, FOR THE OLD AND THE YOUNG.</titlePart> 
            </docTitle> 
            <epigraph > 
               <q>
                  <lg type="stanza"> 
                     <l>"The good old paths are good enough for me;</l> 
                     <l>The fathers walked to heaven in them, and we,</l> 
                     <l>By following meekly where they trod, may reach</l> 
                     <l>The home they found."</l> 
                  </lg>
               </q> 
            </epigraph> 
            <byline >WITH A PREFATORY AUTHENTICATION, BY <docAuthor xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">RUFUS BABCOCK, D.D.</docAuthor>
            </byline> 
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>NEW YORK:</pubPlace> 
               <publisher >SHELDON &amp; COMPANY, PUBLISHERS, <address> 
                     <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">498 &amp; 500 BROADWAY.</addrLine> 
                  </address>
               </publisher>
            </docImprint> 
            <docDate>1871.</docDate> 
            <pb  n="" xml:id="VAC5690-00000002"/> 
            <docEdition>Entered, according to Act of Congress, in the year 1871 by SHELDON, BLAKEMAN &amp; CO. In the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United States for the Southern District of New York.</docEdition> 
         </titlePage> 
         <div type="dedication"> 
            <pb n=""/> 
            <p>TO REV. BARNAS SEARS, D. D.,<lb/> PRESIDENT OF BROWN UNIVERSITY, PROVIDENCE, RHODE ISLAND,<lb/> AND<lb/> REV. JESSE HARTWELL, D. D.,<lb/> PRESIDENT OF MOUNT LEBANON UNIVERSITY, LOUISIANA,<lb/> WHO, REARED AMID THE HILLS, IN THE VICINITY OF THE SCENE OF THE<lb/> LABORS OF THE PASTOR OF BROOKDALE, AND INTIMATELY ACQUAINTED<lb/> WITH SEVERAL OF THE CHARACTERS AND INCIDENTS<lb/> HERE CHRONICLED; LONG DEVOTED TO THE EDUCATION OF<lb/> THE YOUNG; AND NOW NOBLY FILLING SPHERES OF<lb/> IMPORTANT USEFULNESS, IN TRAINING THE RISING<lb/> MINISTRY, IN WIDELY SUNDERED PORTIONS OF<lb/> OUR BELOVED COUNTRY, THIS LITTLE VOLUME<lb/> IS RESPECTFULLY INSCRIBED, INDICATING<lb/> AS IT DOES THE MIGHTY INFLUENCE<lb/> OF MOTHERS IN THE GREAT<lb/> WORK TO WHICH THEIR LIVES<lb/> ARE SO WORTHILY<lb/> CONSECRATED.</p> 
         </div> 
         <div type="preface"> 
            <pb n="" xml:id="VAC5690-00000003"/> 
            <epigraph> 
               <cit> 
                  <q>
                     <lg type="para"> 
                        <l>"Penates! I will not quit,</l> 
                        <l>To mingle with the crowd, your calm abodes,</l> 
                        <l>Where by the evening hearth Contentment sits</l> 
                        <l>And hears the cricket chirp; where Love delights</l> 
                        <l>To dwell, and on your altars lays his torch,</l> 
                        <l>That burns with no extinguishable flame.</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <milestone n="*   *   *   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/>
                     <lg type="para"> 
                        <l>"Household deities!</l> 
                        <l>Then only shall be Happiness on earth,</l> 
                        <l>When man shall feel your sacred power, and love</l> 
                        <l>Your tranquil joys."</l> 
                     </lg>
                  </q> 
                  <bibl>SOUTHEY'S HYMN TO THE PENATES.</bibl> 
               </cit> 
            </epigraph> 
            <pb n=""/> 
            <head>PREFATORY AUTHENTICATION.</head> 
            <p>SEVERAL years since, a considerable portion of the sheets comprising the following story were shown to me: but circumstances needless to be explained, then prevented its completion. My recollections of it were awakened afresh quite recently, while perusing extensive manuscripts of a somewhat kindred character-developing the mighty influence of a mind of different order, trained, like the heroine of this tale, in New England principles and habits, and bearing them thence to the far West, to be the seminal elements of far, wider diffusion, and in a more genial soil, for the cultivation of what is indispensable to our country's welfare and honor. This coincidence prompted in me the desire that this true story should be given to the public, and the author was now enabled to complete it.</p> 
            <pb n="vi-vii" xml:id="VAC5690-00000004"/> 
            <p>But his earnest wish-for reasons important to himself-was to send forth this <foreign xml:lang="FRA">historiette</foreign> anonymously: and as fictions, and tales assuming only to be "founded on fact," with a large measure of imaginative embellishment, so much abound, it has been thought requisite for some responsible name to give assurance to the truthfulness of what is here written. I have been appealed to for this service, as one who-as well as the distinguished individuals to whom the little volume is inscribed-has the requisite knowledge, from the close proximity of my birth-place to the opening scenes here depicted, and from having visited more than once, in my wanderings, the western home also of the Emigrant's Mother-just to prefix, as I now do most willingly and conscientiously, my assurance of the entire truthfulness of the following statements. Only a change in a few of the names of persons and places has been made to secure the <foreign xml:lang="ITA">incognito</foreign>. The slight appearance of romance, if such there be, in the story, has not been sought for or contrived, but was only the conjunction, under God's favoring<pb n=""/> providence, of events adapted to awaken gratitude and call forth praise to the ALL-WISE DISPOSER.</p> 
            <p>A word more in reference to the title of this story. The word "Emigrant" now, almost exclusively, is applied to designate one who has come from another country. Not such was its principal use forty years since. Then, when a larger number and a more valuable quality of the influx into our western States were accustomed to come from New England and New York, rather than from Europe, this was the common term applied to them, and this use of it is here preserved. As to the importance to our beloved country of the large infusion of the industry, economy, and enterprise of those reared in hardship and privation on the comparatively sterile hills of the eastern States, brought early into the vast and fertile plains of the West, carrying with them intelligence, and in many instances the love of order, morals, religion and social progress, with its needful safeguards, there can be, I presume, no question among those who have carefully and without prejudice studied the mighty<pb n="viii" xml:id="VAC5690-00000005"/> problem now so rapidly, and, on the whole, so auspiciously developing in our national progress.</p> 
            <p>In this aspect the following story, besides the beautiful simplicity of early manners among the humbler classes which it pictures to the life, as they were known to exist half a century ago, has also a lesson of instruction of a higher kind, for the reflective reader who loves to gather up the teachings of God's good providence in the affairs of families and communities, which in the aggregate swell into the magnitude of nations, and command the attentive interest and profound study of the philosophical historian.</p> 
            <closer>
               <signed>R. B.</signed> 
               <dateline>PATERSON, N. J., December 1st, 1858.</dateline>
            </closer> 
            <pb n=""/> 
         </div> 
      </front> 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The emigrant's mother</head> 
            <pb n="8 (Illustration) -9" xml:id="VAC5690-00000006"/> 
            <head>
               <figure> 
                  <head>THE FAMILY GROUP. Page 8.</head> 
               </figure>
            </head> 
            <pb n=""/> 
            <head>THE EMIGRANT'S MOTHER</head> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <head>PART I.</head> 
               <epigraph> 
                  <q>
                     <p>"The brief and simple annals of the poor."</p>
                  </q> 
               </epigraph> 
               <p>
                  <hi rend="i"/>IN the closing years of the last century, Diantha Jones, the principal subject of this narrative, was found in the ambiguous station of a servant and a companion in the family of an humble Christian pastor. His residence was in one of the newly settled townships of New England. The members of his flock were few, scattered and poor; quite unable to afford him an adequate support. But his was no mercenary regard; he felt rather, toward all the members of that little community,<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC5690-00000007"/> the affection of a father. That small church had been gathered by his evangelical labors; and though other and more inviting fields often tempted him to leave, yet he steadfastly resisted the allurement, and seemed resolved-as they had been his first charge-so would he abide with. and serve them, till death should release him, or age and infirmities disqualify him for his official duties.</p> 
               <p>The family of the pastor consisted of a wife in very poor health, and three sons. The eldest of these was a vigorous young man nearly seventeen years old, whose daily toil assisted largely in their support. The second, seven years younger, was beginning to render some assistance, and the youngest, little Reuben, was still a nursling of less than twelve months. Under such circumstances it may be easily understood how important an event in their domestic history<pb n=""/> tory was the arrival of Mrs. Diantha Jones; or, as the children, by a large contraction, soon accustomed themselves to call her, "Miss Ana." This name gradually almost supplanted the other, and became the familiar and not disrespectful appellation by which she was known in the family and throughout the immediate neighborhood.</p> 
               <p>She was now a widow, about thirty years of age, of middle size and quiet demeanor. She had known more of hardship and sorrow from her earliest years, than of the enjoyments of this life. An orphan child, she had been committed to those whose tender mercies were cruel, and was at length snatched from the experience of severities which must ere long have proved fatal to her, by the interposition of some of her relatives. She had not been fortunate in her marriage; but after a few years her<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC5690-00000008"/> husband left her and went to sea, and she never heard from or saw him afterward. Thus left, with an infant son entirely destitute, she was enabled to put her trust in the Lord, whose gracious promise to the widow and the fatherless, she failed not to experience. After having struggled on for some years, thus lonely and dependent, till she had reared up her little boy to an age when it was practicable to engage him for the remainder of his minority to a respectable farmer in a neighboring township, she found a place for herself, as above related, in the family of the worthy pastor at Brookdale.</p> 
               <p>It may be readily understood, however, that the situation of Mrs. Jones was not enviable. The inadequate income of the family with which she resided, and the ill health of the mistress of it, threw no small burdens upon her.</p> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <p>In the early period, when our narrative commences, most of the families of moderate circumstances, in that vicinity, were accustomed to prepare almost their entire clothing by a species of industry which was indeed <emph>domestic manufacture</emph>. The wool and the flax from which their cloth was made, had to be carded, and spun and woven by hand, and to her the family soon came to look for the performance of nearly all the processes of this entire service, in addition to the usual toils of the kitchen and the dairy. From the early dawn of day, to the close of the evening, she was engaged in almost unremitted but varying service. This was rendered more tolerable because she had long been accustomed to it. She was also conscious of being useful, and that the value of her services were gratefully appreciated.  More than all, she was treated with uniform kindness and respect<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC5690-00000009"/> spect. Here too she regularly enjoyed religious privileges to which before she had been a stranger. With the close of Saturday evening her toils ended; and the Sabbath's holy rest enabled her always to visit the house of God, and experience the refreshing influence of the worship and the pious instruction there enjoyed. She always shared also the delights of social religious exercises; sending up from the domestic altar the morning and the evening sacrifice, accompanied with the devout reading of a portion of the sacred Scriptures. For such privileges she had often sighed; and now that Providence had in these respects favored her, she wisely regarded her daily labors, heavy and constant as they certainly were, to be no more than she should expect in the otherwise favored position which she occupied.</p> 
               <p>To follow through a single day's routine<pb n=""/> tine of her "service at all work," may furnish a better idea of the nature and amount of this toil, than could otherwise be gained.</p> 
               <p>Rising with the lark, she assisted the boys in milking the cows, then arranged the milk either for butter or for cheese-making ere she prepared breakfast for the family. After this repast, and the invariable season of family worship, there followed the regular work of the season, carding and spinning, or weaving, which was of course subject to such interruptions as the preparation of dinner brought along with it. When this principal meal had been dispatched, and the incidental clearing away had been attended to, she would return for a few hours to the regular work, before it was time to get supper. After this frugal meal, and the evening <hi rend="i"/>chores<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WRIGHT2-0171-NOTE001" n="*"
                        place="foot">
                     <p >A significant New England word, embracing a variety of small work and cares, held subordinate to the principal labor.</p>
                  </note> had been attended to,<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC5690-00000010"/> there remained some little interval, varying with the seasons of the year in its length, before the hour of evening prayer and repose: this was busily occupied with the needle, either in making or mending the clothes of the family. It is true the pastor's wife rendered such aid in some of these services as her infirm health allowed. But enough remained each day to fill up all the moments, and tax to the fullest power of effort and endurance the faithful Miss Ana. True, her severe toils were the more tolerable to her, because she was surrounded and associated with those who were necessarily alike industrious; and we all bear our own hard service more easily, when those around us cheerfully submit to the same.</p> 
               <p>A small farm, of rugged, repulsive aspect<pb n=""/> pect, but not unproductive, was occupied by the pastor. So much of his labor as could be spared from his professional duties, with that of his sons, and a little occasional assistance from some of his considerate and kind-hearted parishioners, enabled him to clear and till these acres, which in turn yielded their various products. These assisted him to live on, from year to year, exercising a frugal, but generous hospitality, and providing for the necessary wants of his family. The sons were accustomed to labor on the farm as soon as their age enabled them to be useful, during the summer season, and in the winter they enjoyed the benefit of that glory of New England, even in its earliest days, THE COMMON SCHOOL.</p> 
               <p>When they were toiling over their evening lessons, interrupted as they often would be by the intrusion of company<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC5690-00000011"/> pany into the common sitting-room of the family, where, for economy's sake, but one fire was kept up, or when some duty or errand for the family sent them away for an hour, and they had to make up the task by fagging later than usual, the good widow Jones would cheer them by a kind word or a considerate suggestion of their superior youthful advantages to those which fell to her lot. She was "sure she would willingly deprive herself of accustomed sleep, could she thereby secure such schooling and such good learning as they were now attaining." Very well, too, did she know how to mingle a little commendation with her counsel. If a neighbor had spoken well of the pastor's sons, at just the right time and place where this stimulus and comfort was most <choice>
                     <sic>necessay</sic>
                     <corr>necessary</corr>
                  </choice>, she could hint it to them in a sort of enigmatical inuendo which enhanced its interest and value.<pb n=""/> Did the teacher, who, in those days of primitive simplicity, boarded around with the parents of the scholars, drop a word of praise in regard to the fidelity, the studiousness, the success of these boys in their studies, this, too, was laid up with provident carefulness by Miss Ada, that she might repeat it to them just they they were beginning to get discouraged with some very difficult problem, or to grow drowsy from long and late detention at their studies. How earnestly, too, she seemed to help them all in her power by relieving them of such services as she could "somehow" find time to perform, though out of her usual line. Was an unusual amount of fuel to be brought in before a storm, she put on her red hood and mittens and aided them sooner to accomplish it. Was a weak and dying lamb to be nursed, and fed, and warmed<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC5690-00000012"/> for the night by the kitchen fireside, she would take the care off their hands.</p> 
               <p>Nor were other and less direct aids wanting on her part to assure them of her lively interest in their respectability and progress. No matter at what cost of toil and pains on her part, their clothes were always clean and ready for use at the required season, and if in their straitened circumstances they could not put on a new suit to attend school, as often as some of the wealthier neighbors' children, how sedulous were her endeavors, and how full of nice plans and schemes did she appear, in order that the old suits should look almost as well. Other boys would sometimes be late at school, in the short dark mornings of winter. But her care would never allow hers to be detained. They were called in time, if otherwise they did not wake; and the breakfast was ready for<pb n=""/> them in due season. To these little helps, she was wont to say, "our boys did not know how much they owed," in getting on so well that both the older ones taught school themselves, with credit and success, too, before they were "out of their teens." As she saw them rising in the world, after they left their father's house, her kindly eye and loving heart followed them, and often she seemed to be thinking with gratitude, that she, in her humble way, had contributed to their advancement.</p> 
               <p>Look in upon that family group, on one of the long autumnal evenings, when all are gathered around the cheerful hearth. On each side of the candlestand sit the father and the mother of the family in patriarchal precedence. He is reading aloud one of the earliest numbers of a religious magazine, recently received, full of interesting accounts of<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC5690-00000013"/> missionary labors, sufferings, and discoveries in India and South Africa; together with some journals of pioneer evangelical labors in our frontier wilderness settlements. Some of these "traveling preachers" are his personal friends-his much-loved ministerial brethren; and as they recount hardships, toils, successes in their Master's cause, the unbidden tear often gathers in his upturned eye. He pauses to add some word of personal explanation, and with his companion and faithful Mrs. Jones he exchanges a few words; or, if "the boys" seek for any additional information on the topics thus introduced, he delights to minister to the solution of their queries, or wisely guides their thoughts into some profitable and interesting channel. Their hands, meanwhile, are perhaps busied with some humble, but useful service. The ripe apples or golden pumpkins are freed<pb n=""/> from skin and cores, and nicely sliced for drying; or the earliest ripened ears of corn, as yet scarcely dry enough for threshing, are skillfully shelled, that the new kernels may be coarsely ground into the grateful hominy; or the tanned skins of the wild animals they have trapped, are cut and braided into whips, or sewed into mittens, both for their own use and to be exchanged at the country store for such little articles as they may desire. Their mother meanwhile busily plies her knitting needles, for the production of mittens or stockings of another material, and little Reuben seated in the corner, by a large pile of faggots, consisting of the knots or roots of the turpentine-tree, throws them at regular intervals upon the fire, to give bright light for his own kind nurse, "Mits Ana," as he lispingly calls her, while she cards the wool for the next day's spinning. Great is his<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC5690-00000014"/> joy, that making himself useful in this way, and keeping very quiet, he is allowed to sit up an hour later than usual, and that ever and anon he gets an approving smile both from nurse and mother, as his faggot-light sheds around the large kitchen unusual brilliancy. But his eyes begin to grow heavy, and his pile of light-wood is nearly exhausted; the clock that "ticks against the wall," tells the hour of retiring; the good father for the last half hour has laid aside his book, and vigorously assists his boys to earlier complete their tasks. So that all is now "put up." Together they bow down for the evening prayer, and each with cheerful, contented heart, seeks the quiet pillow.</p> 
               <p>Winter, with its snow-drifts and sleigh-rides, its careering storms without, and <choice>
                     <sic>it</sic>
                     <corr>its</corr>
                  </choice> nuts, and apples, and other comforts within, has passed away.</p> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <p>Smiling spring is changing into summer. Near half a score of years have passed away since the opening scenes of our little story. The pastor's eldest son is married and settled on a farm of his own. The remainder of the inmates hold their former places, though the younger ones have grown apace.</p> 
               <p>Mrs. Jones is evidently expecting some event of unusual interest. Her little cap and apron are not only of faultless cleanliness, as usual, but they now seem adjusted with more than ordinary care. For whom is she now "looking out?" The suspense is soon relieved. There rides up to the door and dismounts, a fine, tall youth-half way between a boy and a man. It is her own, her only son, Ammon, who by consent of the worthy farmer to whom he had been apprenticed, comes regularly at this season of the year, after the toil of planting has been<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC5690-00000015"/> completed, to spend some days with this loving but rarely seen mother. If he were very sick at any time, she knows that "word of it" would soon be brought to her, when in a few hours she could hasten to his side. But otherwise-so important does she regard it not to leave those who so much need her daily help-that she satisfies herself with this annual visit. Just in proportion as it was waited for long, there was concentrated on it an intensity of interest not easily conceived by those whose domestic enjoyment is more widely and uniformly diffused. Beloved as she was by all the family, and specially the younger portion of it, they could readily enter into and sympathize with her joy on these occasions. Nor was the affection altogether disinterested. Young Ammon was of a noble, generous nature, and if his education had been less thorough and extensive than that of the<pb n=""/> pastor's sons, his disposition was so amiable, his whole bearing so conciliatory, intrepid, and yet so discreet-his power in athletic exercises and his skill in the sports and pastimes befitting his years, were all adapted to make him the decided favorite, and to fix on him a large share of the universal regard whenever he appeared at Brookdale.</p> 
               <p>In age he was midway between the pastor's younger sons, and for reasons readily understood he was most associated with Reuben. To the latter this annual coming of Miss Ana's son was an occasion, which, in the monotony of his quiet life and few associates, was most welcome. They could ride and walk, could labor and play, could talk and sleep together. Ammon's vigorous arm would soon help Reuben to accomplish his task-and then to the mountain or to the forest; or, with rude but effective fishing-rods, they would<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC5690-00000016"/> betake themselves to angling in the adjacent river. Once, when a powerful rain had suddenly swollen this stream to turbid violence, sweeping before it every obstruction, and in its rapid rush unsetting the pathway of their course, they attempted to cross the fiercely-rolling billows on a bare and trembling tree-trunk which stretched from shore to shore.</p> 
               <p>Ammon led the way, and scarcely reached the opposite bank, when frightful was the spectacle which presented itself as he turned to look back for his companion. His less steady nerves had failed him at the trial, and midway over what threatened to become his watery grave, his progress had been arrested-the dizzy swimming brain had fairly incapacitated him to take a single step either backward or forward, and each moment the slippery trembling log threatened to fail his foot-hold and precipitate him amid<pb n=""/> rocks and yeasty foaming waters beneath. The cries of Reuben were imploring; and in defiance of all peril to himself, Ammon hastened back, and seizing his trembling comrade, bore him with incredible difficulty across the dangerous pass. Fears of the parental chiding for such desperate risk incurred, sealed their lips from all disclosure of this adventure. But it did not prevent their joining with unwonted fervency in the good pastor's prayer that night, when he thanked our heavenly Father for his kind, preserving care, guarding each one of them from all perils and dangers through the day. As they retired to their chamber both almost sobbed out the overflowing of their gratitude, and both, with a tenderness and considerateness unusual for their years, spoke of the painfully different scene which that night would have been witnessed in that dwelling, had but another<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC5690-00000017"/> hair's breadth of increased difficulty prevented the final rescue. Did the younger carry forward his thought, and, in anticipation of what had been so nearly fatal to him, did he ask, <q>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"Where, <emph>where</emph> would then my spirit be?</l> 
                        <l>
                           <emph>How</emph> should I spend Eternity?"</l> 
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p> 
               <p>When God, by what we call <emph>accident</emph>, brings death so near to us, how stupid it is, not to take a thought of what must follow death!</p> 
               <p>Suggestions of this timely character were often addressed by Mrs. Jones to both of these youth. Indeed, since religion with her was the principal thing, there were never wanting fit occasions for her to utter its momentous lessons. Her Bible was her daily counselor, her choicest friend. If you had looked in upon her, as she sat at her loom, you would have seen the book of her choice<pb n=""/> opened before her, and many of its golden truths did she thus treasure up in her memory. If the little folks called in to see her on their way to school, to ask for a drink of water, or hear her tell them a pretty story, she would reward them with the privilege of reading to her a Psalm or a chapter out of her own Bible.</p> 
               <p>But especially were her prayerful solicitudes drawn forth for this son of her love, and for young Reuben, to whom, as a kind of foster-mother, she felt the sincerest affection. Many were the tears and prayers which she and the good pastor's wife mingled together for the salvation of their children. But their good sense induced them rather to give the cheerful aspect of this matter to those who were awakening in their bosoms so tender and deep a solicitude. As it was not religion, but the want of it in these children, that made their parents sad, so<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC5690-00000018"/> it would have been the greatest perversion to have carried the impression to  their young minds, that religion only or  chiefly brought tears to their parents eyes, or sadness to their hearts.</p> 
               <p>Nor did God leave this family unplied  with other ministries, adapted to convince them of His parental corrections. Once and again severe illness visited both the sons that remained at home. The elder of them soon recovered, but Reuben was long confined to his sick-bed. His mother's strength soon failed her, in the attempt to nurse this youngest son, and thus was a double load thrown upon the patient and ever faithful Mrs. Jones. By night and by day, all labors and cares requisite for his comfort she cheerfully expended.</p> 
               <p>Alas! how few but by experience know the amount of such requisitions, and when they have passed by, how<pb n=""/> few adequately appreciate the obligation which they have conferred.</p> 
               <p>In this instance, perhaps there was not absolute ingratitude for such persevering and long-continued favors. Mrs. Jones was regularly paid her small stipend, and she was treated by all the family with a kindness and respect which seemed to evince the depth and sincerity of their acknowledgment for her humble but important services. But boys are apt to be thoughtless, and they soon forget the cares and toils expended on them, either in their health or sickness.</p> 
               <p>"Folly is bound up in the heart of a child," and how much, alas! of long-continued discipline is required for its expulsion. Nor is it less obviously true that "childhood and youth are vanity."  The heart, estranged from God, will early prompt the feet to turn aside from the ways of wisdom; and when gratitude to<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC5690-00000019"/> the great Giver of all good is habitually repressed, what marvel if it be withheld  from the instruments of His beneficence with whom we are daily connected?</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <head>PART II.</head> 
               <epigraph> 
                  <q>
                     <p>How unsearchable are God's judgments, and His ways past finding out."</p>
                  </q> 
               </epigraph> 
               <p>
                  <hi rend="i"/>TWELVE years had passed away since the beginning of our little history. The pastor's second son had just become of age, and, as an adventurer, had left the family circle. Reuben, now a dozen years old, though not a healthy, was an almost overgrown boy, from frequent and severe illness rather over-indulged, and not as yet able to do much in repaying the labors, cares and anxieties which he had occasioned. Like many an invalid child becoming more dear to parents and attendants by the extra watchfulness and toils which he had occasioned, he was<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC5690-00000020"/> scarcely less endeared to his unwearied attendant and nurse, Mrs. Jones. When she had once and again seen him raised up from the borders of the grave in answer to her fervent prayers, and had felt that her toils and vigils in his behalf had thus been amply recompensed, it only awakened in her heart a more intense desire that his young heart might yield to the demands of Heaven, and he no longer remain without a good hope through grace. Gently, yet earnestly and frequently, she endeavored to impress on his susceptible mind, the truths and obligations of religion. Sometimes he appeared to feel and heed her entreaties. Especially now that an unwonted affectionateness was manifested by her, in part occasioned by her son's just now coming of age, and setting forth almost immediately for a tour, and a season's labor in what was then deemed <emph>the far</emph>
                  <pb n=""/> 
                  <emph>West</emph>, it would be almost brutish in the boy to disregard the nearly maternal yearnings of her pious desire for his salvation. Still the waywardness of his youthful nature was becoming more and more manifest. He would sometimes seem to trifle with her most earnest remonstrances, and with teasing <choice>
                     <sic>supersciliousness</sic>
                     <corr>superciliousness</corr>
                  </choice>, rather than malicious ungodliness, he would not only ward off her religious appeals, but appear to turn them into ridicule.</p> 
               <p>The God against whose mercies he was thus hardening himself, now plied him with other influences. Partly for the improvement of his wife's health, the pastor was accustomed occasionally to take her with him in some of those official journeyings which led him for days away from his home. An excursion of this kind had just been planned, which both of them seemed to anticipate with<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC5690-00000021"/> unusual pleasure. An ordination, at which he was to officiate, some thirty miles from his home, was to be followed the succeeding day by another ecclesiastical convocation in a neighboring town, and they contrived for a whole week, a succession of delightful services, interspersed with gentle rides day after day. It happened, on the morning of their leaving home, and when the careful mother was desirous of making over the supervision of her boy to his Miss Ana, for the week, that more in mischievous frolic than with deliberate naughtiness, he turned the seriousness of them both into ridicule. His buoyant exuberance of spirits appeared for the time to defy control, and with a desperate pertinacity he seemed bent on the indulgence of his sportive levity. Even when his mother was entering her carriage, she once more called the gleeful boy to her side, to<pb n=""/> draw from him the assurances she wished in regard to his deference to Mrs. Jones while herself would be absent. But his waywardness even then, got the better of his usual filial deference, and repeating some heartless joke, he tripped away from her without the parting caress.</p> 
               <p>The second morning after her departure, at a very early hour, Mrs. Jones gently opened the door of his bed-room, and waked him by repeated, but cautious appeals. When his eyes were fairly open and turned on her, the sad, but unusually calm and studied aspect in which she stood gazing upon him, awakened first his curiosity and then a more painful emotion. Guardedly, and with great deliberation, she proceeded to inform him that during the dead hours of the night, while he had been wrapped in unconscious slumber, a neighbor had aroused<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC5690-00000022"/> her to communicate unwelcome tidings, which she thus related:</p> 
               <p>"His dear parents had met with a sad accident. They were hurrying from their first appointment in C--. When scarce a mile from the church, as they were descending a hill, the harness gave way (or had not been properly secured), the carriage ran upon the horse, and the frightened animal both ran and kicked violently, upsetting their carriage and seriously injuring them both. Your father was considerably bruised, but he was able to rise from the ground; and he found your mother"-here the faithful creature was fairly choked, and for a moment could not go on with her statement-"quite unable to rise, one of her limbs badly broken near to the body, and in most excruciating pain she was carried into the nearest house."</p> 
               <p>It was a sad morning to him. Unaccustomed<pb n=""/> customed to such affliction, to such severity of physical anguish in the person of her whom he loved best, it would have moved the most indifferent to witness the keenness of his sufferings. Very interesting was the spectacle of that true-hearted attendant, the faithful Mrs. Jones, striving to rise above the consideration of the sorrow which wrung her own heart, in order to minister the soothings which her Christian piety and large experience could suggest, to allay the intensity of his wild grief. "That mother, from whom he had <emph>thus</emph> parted, so soon and so dreadfully a sufferer! And was it for his sin that such an infliction had been laid on one of the gentlest and best of earth?" Such were some of his severe self-upbraidings. His faithful nurse, who knew how to minister to his mental suffering, as she often and long had to his bodily diseases, judiciously refrained<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC5690-00000023"/> at this time from all direct allusion to his misdeeds, and strove to turn his thoughts  to those high and general considerations of the wisdom and benevolence of God's  dealings, whose equity is undeniable,  even when clouds and darkness are round about Him.</p> 
               <p>Fortunate was it for Reuben that arrangements had immediately to be made  for his setting forth with his oldest brother and wife to visit these parents in their sad affliction. The incidents of preparing for this journey diverted his mind from too intensely poring over the occasion of it, and the next night they reached, together, the scene of the late disaster. Yonder by the road side still stood the broken carriage from which they had been thrown, near the rough rocks on which that much loved mother had fallen with so disastrous effect. They enter the neat but humble dwelling, and passing the ante-room<pb n=""/> room they reach the apartment where the chief sufferers are found. The father they find sitting up, with his head bound up, and still suffering from its contusions; and by his side, stretched on that low bed lies the mother, more severely stricken. The first sympathetic emotions occasioned by this meeting are over. Young Reuben begins to look around him with more composure. He learns one by one the pangs and sorrows which that fond parent has experienced. Especially on the second morning after his arrival, when the surgeon, as was his practice on each alternate day, removed the bandages from the broken limb and submitted it to the needful but intensely painful friction, deemed by him indispensable to prevent soreness or want of healthful circulation of the injured parts, the boy listened for the first time in his life to the outburst, from maternal lips, of<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC5690-00000024"/> those shrieks of bitter anguish which all her fortitude could not restrain. This, not for an instant merely, but continued for successive moments, which seemed to him like ages. As long as he could, he clung to her side, seemingly anxious to lighten by sharing her pains. But overcome by the scene, he hurried from the house, plunged into an adjacent grove, and even there, at a great distance, the groans and almost screams of his mother's agony still followed him, and pierced, not his ears only, but his very soul.</p> 
               <p>An hour afterward he returned. She was lying exhausted, but comparatively free from pain, upon her couch. She had wiped the tears from her eyes, and calling the loving boy to her side, she pressed his head to her bosom, and with the warmth of such love as a mother only can exercise, she seemed to reward him for the tenderness of his sympathy with her sufferings.</p> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <p>At a later hour, more probably for his gratification than her own, she allowed him to busy himself for some time, in striving to clear the matted tresses of her hair, and neatly complete the braids which platted it in more comely form. It was while alone with her in this filial service, that, with most gentle and winning sweetness, she inquired of him in regard to his treatment of his ever faithful Miss Ana. Was it the overwhelming tenderness and power of his own emotions which choked his utterance? Or did the same perverse spirit which produced his wrong conduct partially regain ascendency? so as to prevent his falling on her neck, and sobbing forth his penitent confession, as he had often on his knees done in secret, for the last four days. Or was the perverse spirit of <emph>delay</emph> whispering its delusive suggestions into his heart? "That when she should return to his now<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC5690-00000025"/> so desolate home, there would be a better time to convince her how truly and deeply he mourned over, how sincerely he repented of the light-hearted folly which had given them so much pain." Perhaps it was a combination of them all, which operated to prevent his using this last favorable opportunity to give joy to that mother's heart. Seeing that he hesitated to answer her inquiry, (and standing as he then did behind her, she could not discern the depth of his manifested feeling), she contented herself with the expression of her kind and earnest hope, that never would he again so trifle with the sacred and deep solicitude for his religious welfare, of one who, in her own feebleness, had been to him so nearly a mother: and others coming into the apartment, the topic was not again resumed. Alas, what would not, this inconsiderate boy have afterwards given for one moment's<pb n=""/> ment's opportunity to have assured that mother of his sorrow, and sought her willing and ready forgiveness.</p> 
               <p>After some four days passed at his mother's bed-side, Reuben returned again to his henceforth sad home. Three weeks had elapsed after the misfortune had befallen them. His father, once and again, had returned for the performance of his official duties: he was even now at his lonely home, and as all accounts of the speedy convalescence of his wife were favorable, he began to encourage himself and his now motherless household, that ere long he hoped to move back into her accustomed place, her who had not only been the light of his dwelling, but the joy and solace of all their hearts. The evening before, this had been the theme of his remark, ere he bowed down for prayer with the now broken circle.</p> 
               <p>In the morning, the pastor was early<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC5690-00000026"/> hurried from home, for some secular business in the opposite direction from that in which, at a later hour, he had hoped to set forth to visit his suffering companion. Reuben, Mrs. Jones, and some other casual inmates of the abode, were still in the breakfast room, when a stranger rode up, and inquiring if this was the residence of the Rev. Mr. --, received an affirmative answer, and immediately dismounted and entered the dwelling. His look was a sad and weary one, and his horse bore marks of rapid and long travel. When seated, he inquired very deliberately and emphatically for the minister, or either of his sons.</p> 
               <p>Young Reuben came forward, and received from the stranger an open letter, addressed to his father. Hastily he glanced over the lines, written and signed by the attending physician of his dear mother. They rather blindly intimated,<pb n=""/> than clearly revealed the astounding fact, that at a late hour the previous evening the pastor had experienced a great loss. A hasty perusal conveyed even to the mind of the child the overwhelming tidings. For a moment he gazed in silence on the messenger; then, calmly he asked, "does this mean that my mother is dead?" All eyes were fixed on him who alone could give the required information. He felt the painfulness of his duty, and for a moment his faltering tongue seemed unable to perform its office. But dashing a tear from his manly cheek, he embraced the dear boy in his arms, and falteringly said, "She will never thus clasp you more." That day, and the following one, the house was indeed a Bochim, a place of tears.</p> 
               <p>Then they brought her lifeless remains to her late cheerful dwelling. The widowed father saw all his now motherless<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC5690-00000027"/> children gathered there. Far and wide spread the mournful tidings, and through an extensive circle of loving hearts the pang of grief for her sudden loss was felt.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WRIGHT2-0171-NOTE002" n="*"
                        place="foot">
                     <p >She died of apoplexy, superinduced probably by her prostration, for so long a period, by that broken limb.</p>
                  </note>
               </p> 
               <p>Then came the mournful funeral. The late autumnal rains were sending down a copious flood-the withered leaves fell thick and fast, and through the bared branches of forests and fruit trees the sighing winds breathed their sad requiem. The holy man of God, the chief mourner's officiating brother, and one well able to sympathise with his sorrows, stood up from the sacred desk to proclaim, "I heard a voice from heaven saying unto me, Write, BLESSED ARE THE DEAD THAT DIE IN THE LORD."</p> 
               <p>Then despite the storm, a great throng gathered around the open coffin, to look for<pb n=""/> the last time on the remains of her they had loved so well. A truer mourner stood not among that multitude than weeping Mrs. Jones. For more than a dozen years she had been the inseparable companion of the deceased in all the varied circumstances of their condition through joy and sorrow. The power of that Christian spirit which both had experienced and were enabled to illustrate had made them one. In the different positions they occupied, each knew how to conduct and feel toward the other; for the golden rule was their welcome guide. There had been just those differences-not to say contrasts-in their temperaments, their mental and moral training, and their position in life, which made the one the fit complement of the other. What the one did not possess was found in the other, and the willing coalescence seemed to imply that they had felt themselves<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC5690-00000028"/> selves mutually dependent, mutually incomplete, but by union and co-operation with each other. When the bereaved family returned that evening to their henceforth more desolate dwelling, the widowed father and husband, by the soothing ministries of his official associates, had his heart lifted above the crushing sorrows of the hour, to fix itself on the glorious themes which, in like circumstances, he had proffered to those who were thus stricken. The sons, too, felt that the full tide of generous gushing sympathy from kindred and friends was warmly turned upon them. Reuben especially, as the only one at home and not yet risen to manhood, shared more largely than the rest in these soothing alleviations. But how few knew or cared to think of her sorrow, who felt, not less keenly than any other, the overwhelming, stunning blow<pb n=""/> which had fallen upon them all! Mrs. Jones, in the bustle of that scene, was to be called on by every body and for every thing, a kind of <foreign xml:lang="LAT">factotum</foreign>, who was expected to know and do whatever was required, and whatever no one else could.</p> 
               <p>Long, dismal, and comparatively cheerless was the winter which followed. By the pastor's desire his eldest son and wife came to live with him and his bereaved family. But so great was the contrast, to Mrs. Jones especially, between the friend she had lost, and the young, gay, pleasure-loving woman, who, notwithstanding the kindness of her heart, seemed to have no religious sympathies and principles in harmony with her own, that the void was in no degree filled. The words of christian hope and cheer which she had been accustomed to exchange with her who had now passed away, could no longer be fittingly uttered<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC5690-00000029"/> or their response listened to. She knew there was the same God and Father above, and to Him at least, in the privacy of her retirement, she loved to pour out her soul. At the family altar, too, the morning and evening offerings were constant and fervent. For poor, motherless Reuben she felt, if possible, a warmer and livelier religious concern than ever before, and many were the judicious efforts and friendly counsels with which she strove to turn his young heart into the ways of early piety, that he might not forget his sainted mother's God and Saviour. In the early days of his bereavement, she noticed with joy that his heart seemed more impressible, his conscience more tender, his will more disposed to bow to God's requirement. But youthful associates, the scenes of gayety and thoughtlessness which were soon brought in his way, and the proneness of the unrenewed<pb n=""/> renewed to relapse into more confirmed waywardness,- <q>
                     <lg type="quotation"> 
                        <l>"When disappointment mocks the roving heart,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Still of its own delusions weakly fond,</l> 
                        <l>And from forbidden pleasures loath to part,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Though shrinking oft beneath correction's keenest smart."-</l> 
                     </lg>
                  </q> was strikingly noticeable in the few months of his future progress.</p> 
               <p>Gradually, but on the whole rapidly and fearfully, she noticed the deterioration of his principles and practice. He was fast becoming a young man, and he no longer listened so patiently or heeded so carefully the counsels and cautions which pious lips and Christian hearts would gladly minister to him. He loved to debate, to argue; sometimes beginning this from the mere spirit of opposition, and to see if he could not confute the simple and pious with whom he was surrounded; and at others from the unholy bias of a heart reluctantly yielding to or<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC5690-00000030"/> else beginning to spurn the restraints with which he had hitherto felt himself encompassed.</p> 
               <p>In this transition state, how hard for one over-vain of the incipient smartness which he was now beginning to develop, and which the injudicious praised just enough to fan the embers to a flame,-how difficult did Mrs. Jones find it, when often she attempted to stem the tide of worldliness, and unholy compliance with sinful practices and corrupting amusements. He was now beginning to feel the full force of allurements to all the round of such youthful indulgences and pleasures. She, who knew so well how they had been regarded by that now sainted mother, and who felt continually the charge which those last audible accents had left on her ear, "to guard her youngest from all evil," was now struggling with the difficulties of her situation.<pb n=""/> Having no real authority, she could at most only persuade; and she was often made to feel, alas, how sadly, that folly is bound up in the heart of a child.</p> 
               <p>Should she reiterate her remonstrances with an unwelcome pertinacity, thus imperiling altogether her future influence? Or on the contrary should she timidly, and she feared unfaithfully withhold her counsel, just when the crisis of a first wrong decision was about to be consummated? With what deep solicitude did she often carry these doubts and perplexities before the throne of grace, and plead for that divine Wisdom which is alike profitable for this life and that which is to come. How great the relief she here found, even in the most trying emergencies. Did what she thought wrong, for the time prevail? undiscouraged by her apparent failure, she would strengthen her heart, and hope, by pleading still the<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC5690-00000031"/> promise and covenant of Him who has never said, Seek ye my face in vain. She knew that He had all hearts in His hand and could turn them as the rivers of water are turned. That all events, even those apparently the most untoward and discouraging, could yet be made under his wise subordination, to minister to the good of the subject of her petitions. She remembered sometimes with a cheering faith, how God dealt with the motherless Joseph--making the very means and instruments which apparently foretokened his ruin, the mysterious steps of his ultimate advancement and success.</p> 
               <p>It was evening at the pastor's dwelling-and as very often now happens, he is absent. His son's wife, now assuming the place of mistress of the household, with faithful Miss Ana for her helper, are together engaged in some of their usual toils, and Reuben, as he was often wont,<pb n=""/> was sitting by them. A country ball, or dancing party, had just been agreed on among his young associates, and he had been solicited to join in it. Without any real love for such amusements, for the enjoyment and participation in which his past staid and sober life had so little fitted him, there was on his part an unwillingness to be deemed singular, or to be so far separated from the blithesome and jocund companionship of his youthful associates. He dreaded to be singular, and many a time, the fear that he should be thought extra good and sober, because he was the parson's son, had induced him to put on airs, and utter words of bravado savoring of impiety and irreligion. Should he now evade his father's watchfulness, and stealthily hie away to the ball? This was the grave question he is secretly revolving, and by some means his sister-in-law has become aware of it. With<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC5690-00000032"/> her characteristic desire to please, more than to profit him, she introduces the theme for discussion among those three only, with a tacit understanding that her pious husband, and his father, the minister, should know nothing of what was there said. The evident purpose of this conversation, then and there, was to bring over, or silence "Widow Jones," as the young mistress called her, so that her opposition might no longer lie in the way to his attendance.</p> 
               <p>"What harm can there be in a little innocent dancing among young people?" said the young, gay sister-in-law. "I am sure I do not think young people should always act like old ones, and pretend to be sober and quiet when they do not feel like it."</p> 
               <p>Reuben chimed in most willingly, and stigmatized the scrupulosity which would refuse such indulgences to the young.<pb n=""/> For his part he could see no use in it. He wondered why the Christian people should so hate a little pleasurable indulgence.</p> 
               <p>The widow hesitated whether to say any thing; but as she could see by the inquiring looks of both her companions, that they desired to draw out some expression from her, and moreover feared that her silence would be taken for assent, she meekly remarked that there were pleasures more secure from excess and perversion, which afforded a higher and more permanent joy than dancing to the sound of the viol, which the Scripture seemed to forbid.</p> 
               <p>The pert boy thought this a good opportunity to evince his knowledge of Scripture as well as his powers of argumentation, and, with some superciliousness, he replied,-That he had read the Bible through, as she very well knew,<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC5690-00000033"/> and that he found more in favor of dancing than against it. He even took down his father's Concordance from the book shelf, and out of some two dozen places where the <hi rend="i"/>dance, or <hi rend="i"/>dances, or <hi rend="i"/>dancing were mentioned in all the Bible, he was very sure that two to one commended it. David, the man after God's own heart, and Solomon, the wisest man, and even the good father of the Prodigal Son, had all practiced or promoted it. He looked very self-complacent after this learned array, and said he should like to have Miss Ana, or any one else, show him the Scripture authority for prohibiting dancing.</p> 
               <p>She thought there was a great difference between David's dancing before the Lord as a religious duty, and such frolics of the young as tended to exclude God from their thoughts. And finally, she said that his deceased mother and herself<pb n=""/> self had often spoken of that Scripture declaration, "Whatsoever is not of faith is sin," as cutting up by the roots such levity as an immortal being, liable at any moment to be summoned into eternity, could not consistently engage in. Turning on him a look of utmost tenderness and kindness, she added, "that sainted mother has nobler employment now, and such she sought with many prayers and tears for you."</p> 
               <p>This testimony was not lost upon the often wayward boy. He knew that his reprover was right-that his mother had been right-that his father's desires for him, which for the last half hour he had been planning to contravene, were also right, and for this once, at least, his foolish thoughts of pleasure in the giddy mazes of the dance were abandoned. This was only a specimen of the manner in which this humble domestic, this<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC5690-00000034"/> real "help," as the New Englanders often call those assistants in their families whom they would not degrade by the name of <emph>servants</emph>, watched over the moral and religious interests of this now motherless boy.</p> 
               <p>Many months thus passed away, and then another change occurred in the pastor's family. He brought home a new wife for himself, a new mother for Reuben, and a new companion for Mrs. Jones. For weeks the two latter had been expecting this great event. Busy tongues had been not sparingly suggesting to the overgrown boy, "Well, you are to have a stepmother soon. She will make you know the difference between her and your own mother." "You need not expect much indulgence or kindness hereafter." These, with other intimations of the like character, just adapted to fill his mind with unwelcome, misleading prejudices<pb n=""/> judices, were plentifully urged on his attention. But in these unpropitious circumstances, how discreet and faithful was the part acted by this foster-mother of his early years. Instead of chiming in with such intimations as would alienate his regard, and even his filial affection from one who came to meet with difficulties and trials not a few, in her new and delicate position, Mrs. Jones seemed determined to see every thing in the new comer through the most favorable medium. She had ready excuses for any thing which seemed strange or wrong, and free and ready suggestions as to the advantages which he would derive from this new relationship.</p> 
               <p>Indeed, there was a demand for all these assiduous and kindly efforts on her part, to smooth the way for him properly to respect, and much more to love; one who, with many excellencies,<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC5690-00000035"/> was as unlike his own now sainted mother, as it is possible two good women could be. The one had been free and fond in all her intercourse with him, and all others who had just claims to her kindly regards. Her successor, on the contrary, was reserved, stately and chillingly cold in her manners. Somewhat exacting, too, he thought her, both towards himself and his revered father. Suffice it to say, her excellencies did not manifest themselves promptly. She might possibly have affection, but she did not show it. She might be amiable and good, but he thought the evidences of it did not appear. Many were the debates which he held with the good "Miss Ana," in which she strove to convince him, and not altogether in vain, that there was sterling worth, and a deep heart-full of kindness, even in that precise and stately formalism, which seemed<pb n=""/> to lock itself up, and repress all the outgushing of affection. Undemonstrative as were her ways, "depend on it, Reuben, you will find her a good mother, it you will prove yourself a good son." With such timely hints and assurances she was indeed performing for the youth an invaluable service.</p> 
               <p>In the mean time, the widow's heart was greatly exercised in regard to her only son's course, and her own. Ammon had visited the fertile regions west of the Alleghanies. For a considerable period he had labored there on good monthly wages, but with the laudable ambition so uniformly characterizing the young New Englander, he could no longer content himself without becoming the proprietor of a farm. He noticed that some of his neighbors at the East, who had removed to the virgin and productive soil of the Ohio valley and there purchased wild lands,<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC5690-00000036"/> and opened farms by their industry and enterprise, were rapidly becoming forehanded, and had the fair prospect of soon securing a reasonable independence for themselves and their families. No wonder that the example was contagious. The young man wrote to his mother, begging her approval and co-operation in his proposed enterprise. They could together secure a section of rich land; his vigorous arm could clear off the forests, fence the fields, and gather the bounteous harvests which were there yielded, and with youthful, enthusiastic ardor, he portrayed the picture of their happiness and success, when living together, she might be spared the severe toils for which, by and by, in declining years, her strength would prove inadequate.</p> 
               <p>All this she weighed with the prudent cautiousness for which she was so noted, but she also took into account the heavy<pb n=""/> 
                  <foreign xml:lang="LAT">per contra</foreign> balance of which he seemed unmindful. In that new country, would she not of necessity be cut off from her dearly loved religious privileges? Would not many social and moral privations also be experienced in thus leaving the home of her youth, and the friends of her love? She remembered that when Lot had preferred the well-watered and fruitful plain, it had involved himself and family in the corruption and peril of Sodom. The result of all her reflections induced her to appeal to her son to return and dwell among their own kindred in dear New England. And to make her proposition more welcome to him, she proffered him the handsome amount of all her hard earnings and careful savings, about five hundred dollars, to be invested by him in any way he thought best, if he would thus comply with her wishes.</p> 
               <pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC5690-00000037"/> 
               <p>The final decision was not made until after Ammon's return from the West. Then, mother and son, in many a long and anxious interview, endeavored duly to weigh all the counterbalancing considerations. Can it be doubted which scale would preponderate? A loving mother's heart could not long hold out against the enthusiastic ardor, which, even at that early day, the West, the mighty giant West could enkindle. Ingenuously, too, he frankly confessed there was another attraction for him towards the setting sun, in the person of a lovely young lady there, with whom he had already formed most endearing ties of betrothal, and she and her father's family were linked to that new and fruitful country. Of her he spoke to his mother as an enamored lover would be sure to speak, assuring her of a daughter's respect and love, and that it should be the sedulous<pb n=""/> endeavor of them both, to make her home with them as happy and peaceful as she could desire.</p> 
               <p>The die was cast, and the decision was soon and widely known. Very generally useful had widow Jones made herself for all these years in that community; nor could the kind-hearted neighbors think of parting with her, but with deep and sincere regret. But the keenest pang was felt in the family she had so long and faithfully served. Changed as that domestic circle was by the death of one and the removal of others, the tie that bound her to them was less strong than at earlier periods of her connection with them. She still revered the good pastor and his fervent prayers; she much respected the new wife he had brought home; but towards Reuben, whom she had nursed in infancy, and watched and cared for so anxiously in sickness and<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC5690-00000038"/> infirm health for so many years, and for whose spiritual welfare-especially since his mother's tragic exit-she had felt an interest so deep and prayerful, her regards were of the most tender and hallowed character. Should she leave him in person, she comforted herself with the thought that however widely they might be sundered, her prayers would still as perseveringly be offered in his behalf: and the God who hears and answers the petitions put up to Him in faith, she could not believe would disregard her own and the deceased mother's earnest cries for his salvation.</p> 
               <p>It was in the early spring of 1814, on a pleasant morning of the verdant year, the birds chanting forth their blithest notes, and all nature rejoicing in bright hope and vigor, that a double wagon of peculiar construction, and freighted with the choicest and most prized commodities,<pb n=""/> which would be of enhanced value in their distant home, stood at the humble door of the parsonage.  The hearty adieus, and the mutually implored "God bless you" of all had been uttered, and the vigorous hand of Ammon Jones with some difficulty held in the impatient and well-fed steeds which were then the only reliance for accomplishing what the locomotive now does for us with such vast increase of celerity and comfort; when his mother, turning last of all to Reuben, took the boy's hand, and with an emotion which seemed to pervade her whole frame, once more conjured him by all the sacred memories of the past, and by his known sense of duty, to seek the Lord in youth, to serve Him all his days, and to meet her and the departed in heaven. With convulsed and overpowering feelings they parted, not expecting to meet again on earth.</p> 
               <pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC5690-00000039"/> 
               <p>We will not here attempt the minute description of their experiences in that long journey-then usually occupying from twenty-four to thirty days-and now with incomparably greater ease accomplished in as many hours. No untoward event was experienced by them, except some slight break-down in the mud they encountered near Lake Erie, as they passed through Northern Pennsylvania.</p> 
               <p>They reached, at length, the EL DORADO of their hopes and aims. Kind neighbors gathered around them with interest, and helped them to rear the log-cabin which was to form their incipient home. A slight opening in the deep forest of huge and lofty trees had been made, the wheat crop, "got in" the last autumn,  was now springing up in rank luxuriance, the corn and the garden were planted, and in an almost incredibly<pb n=""/> short period, appeared in vigorous, thrifty growth, giving promise of ample recompense for their toil.</p> 
               <p>But there were other and less favorable experiences before them. Rapacious beasts of prey swarmed in the forest in such close proximity to their very door, that the howling of wolves, the growl of the surly bear; and the screech of the American panther were no unusual sounds in their ears even by day; while under the cover of night's darkness they held high carnival all around their humble dwelling. Woe to lambs, or calves, or poultry of any kind, not strongly defended against these nocturnal invaders. Many a time when these domestic animals had been, as was supposed, securely penned even adjoining their own cabin, the hungry wolves in droves would attempt pulling down the very walls of these sheds, to get at their victims, and<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC5690-00000040"/> with the utmost difficulty, even by the rifle of young Jones, could they be driven back to their lairs.</p> 
               <p>Nor, for the first years of their frontier life, were they entirely free from visits of more formidable foes. True, victories of Perry on the lake, and of General Harrison on land, had struck terror into the tribes of the tawny savages; but straggling bands, or wily scouts of these treacherous, and often drunken and ferocious red skins, were still prowling around the sparse settlements of the whites, exciting alarm where they did not commit depredation or murder. How far off, too, in any case of difficulty, were their nearest neighbors. A mile or two, through roads nearly impassible, on account of dense and tangled forests, and almost unfathomable mud, had often to be traversed to reach the nearest habitation. But, ere<pb n=""/> long, Ammon brought home his bride, fulfilling thus his promise to give a daughter to his fond mother, to cheer her heart in this wilderness life. And though they were far from the house of the Lord, and for years rarely could welcome the approach, or listen to the accents of the messengers of salvation, she remembered with satisfaction, that the God and Saviour we worship is not confined to dedicated sanctuaries. <q>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"Where'er we seek Him, He is found</l> 
                        <l>And every place is hallowed ground.</l> 
                        <l>For He, within no walls confined,</l> 
                        <l>Inhabiteth the humble mind."</l> 
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p> 
               <p>This humility, and the spirit of true and warm devotion, she habitually cherished. How unspeakable was her satisfaction, even in these far-off places of the wilderness, to hallow the Christian Sabbath, and sound forth in her sweet and<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC5690-00000041"/> trustful notes of praise, the honor of the divine Redeemer. The well-worn Bible, which, in former years she had so much read and prized, became now dearer to her than ever. And when at distant intervals, a pious neighbor, or some chance traveler who knew and loved the Lord, could pass an hour or a night beneath their humble roof, how like cold water to a thirsty soul, were the moments of converse with them on the themes dearest to her heart, and now, all the more prized because of their infrequency.</p> 
               <p>Cares, also, of another kind began to increase upon her. Children's children were speedily multiplied, bringing, indeed, no little augmentation to her toil and watchfulness by day and by night; but bringing, also, their own sweet and appropriate remuneration to a loving heart.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <head>PART III.</head> 
               <epigraph> 
                  <q>
                     <lg type="quotation"> 
                        <l>"There's a divinity that shapes our ends,</l> 
                        <l>Rough hew them as we may."</l> 
                     </lg>
                  </q> 
               </epigraph> 
               <p>
                  <hi rend="i"/>QUARTER of a century has passed since the events last chronicled in our little history occurred. Many of the individuals mentioned in this narrative, had finished their earthly course, and the simple incidents of our story had nearly faded from memory. Near the close of summer, in the year 1840, a middle aged man of thoughtful aspect, and in clerical dress, was seen very early in the morning entering the stage, whose destination-marked upon its panel-was the southern portion of one of our Western States. He has been spending the<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC5690-00000042"/> last few days as the welcome and honored guest among sundry families, who, years before, had taken their departure from his and their native town in far-off New England. Having had occasion to perform some official anniversary service at a distinguished university, which brought him nearer than ever before to the world-renowned cataract of Niagara, he hastened thither to fill his mind and heart with those ennobling emotions which the contemplation of God's handiwork rarely fails to inspire. Then the idea suddenly possessed him to wend his way still further West and look at the beloved neighbors and fellow-townsmen of his youth, in their new homes. Reaching them unexpectedly, and bringing large stores of treasured memories, and recent tidings of the dear ones they had left behind them, he became, not less for his own sake, than for these adjuncts of his visit,<pb n=""/> a highly-esteemed and warmly-welcomed guest. From house to house, from one new home to another, he was carried in a kind of princely state, witnessing, with wonder and delight, the progress which each household had made in subduing the wilderness, and spreading around them the sources of comfort, of affluence, and even of almost sumptuous gratification.</p> 
               <p>He wished to extend his tour a day's ride or two, to meet other loved objects of his former spiritual care, near the southern border of the State, and for this purpose, ere the sun had risen, he took his seat in the stage above-mentioned.</p> 
               <p>But many a day, opening auspiciously, is clouded soon with unexpected reverses. Our traveler, not unlikely, had indulged over-freely in the fine fruits which, in such abundance, the teeming fertility of this virgin soil had yielded, and in rapidly<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC5690-00000043"/> passing from one to another of these old neighbors, each had insisted that he must eat of their pears, and peaches, and melons, and the hot-house grapes, whose luscious clusters invited to a generous participation. Suffice it to say, the feverish unrest of the night followed him from the pillow to the stage; his whole frame seemed pervaded with the encroachments of severe disease. The reeling, dizzy brain, the fevered lip, the bloodshot eye, the nausea, and the writhings of spasmodic pain, all conspired to invest his situation with untold horrors. The stage became overcrowded, and the day, as it advanced, proved intensely warm. In the early part of it, while ascending the long hills, or when stopping for change of horses, our passenger attempted to walk forward, and, by vigorous exercise, to throw off, in healthy perspiration, the oppression, so unusual, which now encompassed and<pb n=""/> pervaded him. It was in vain. And equally futile were all endeavors, at the little hostleries where they from time to time stopped, to obtain any medicinal remedies adapted to his necessities. In this most unwelcome condition, each passing hour of endurance but adding to and rendering more intense his sufferings, the day was slowly advancing, till the meridian was considerably passed.  Bitter and desponding thoughts began to oppress his mind. Should he succumb to this attack, and, at some dwelling by the road-side, lay himself down to die, as the lamented Grimk, a few years earlier, and in the same vicinity had done?<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WRIGHT2-0171-NOTE003" n="*"
                        place="foot">
                     <p >T. S. GRIMK, one of the distinguished men of South Carolina, as a legislator, a reformer, a scholar; who, after delivering the discourse on American Education, before the Western Literary Institute, at Cincinnati, died of cholera at a house by the road-side, on his way to Columbus, October, 1834.</p>
                  </note> He thought of his pleasant and far-off<pb n="84" xml:id="VAC5690-00000044"/> home, of wife and children whom he might see no more, and again and again nerved himself, with all the power he could command, to resist these downward and fatal tendencies.  But each rally, each attempt to call up the reserved forces within him, became weaker and weaker; and revolting and painful as was the thought, he felt that he must yield and seek the friendly shelter of some dwelling ere insensibility should utterly prostrate him.  They were passing an unpretentious but somewhat ample house, and here he prevailed on the stageman to leave him, to live or die, as God should direct. His baggage was deposited by the gate-way, and with tottering steps he gained the door, explained his condition to the surprised inmates of the abode, and bespoke, as best he could, their compassionate hospitalities. They neither granted nor denied his request,<pb n=""/>
                  <pb n="Illustration-85" xml:id="VAC5690-00000045"/> 
                  <figure> 
                     <head>"And with tottering steps he gained the door." Page 85.</head> 
                  </figure>
                  <pb n=""/> but seemed considerately to regard his distressed circumstances, only the female members of the house being present; and the good house-wife saying she would send to the field for her husband to decide what should be done; while, in the meantime, the sick man was seeking to accommodate himself to the unwelcome delay.</p> 
               <p>At just this crisis of his fate, there entered the apartment, from an inner door, an aged and matronly looking woman, evidently a member of the household. A little below the medium height, of remarkably quiet demeanor, there was yet a steady persistence in all her bearing which at once indicated that she was no cipher in their domestic establishment. Briefly, the mistress of the mansion explained to "grandmother," as she respectfully called her, the condition of the suffering stranger, and his eyes<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC5690-00000046"/> imploringly met the old lady's for the first time. He thought there was wondrous depth and meaning in the gaze with which she now regarded him, and as in slow and carefully measured tones she uttered some inquiries for the further elucidation of his case, a sudden conviction seemed to flash upon the minds of both of them. For a moment only he hesitated. What he had thought, was, indeed, almost too good to be true, and yet as he scanned again those small, bright, twinkling eyes, that sedate form, that peculiar utterance, he could doubt no longer. It was, it must be, his own and early loved "Miss Ana." He rose with difficulty, and staggered to her side; he grasped the outstretched hands, while she, half bewildered, cried out, "Can this be Reuben?"</p> 
               <p>All uncertainties in regard to his reception were at an end in a moment.<pb n=""/> He found himself conducted to their best chamber, and at once surrounded by all the ministries of affectionate, devoted regard. In the midst of these arrangements Ammon's tall form appeared, as in his rough farming attire he had hurried to the house on the first summons. He was less altered in his aspect than his more wrinkled mother; and the sick man was very sure that he should have recognized this playmate of his youth under any circumstances. Esq. Jones, as he was now usually called, from having honorably filled a magistrate's office for years in that community, though himself a very unostentatious man, was now prodigal of his attentions. The best medical advice and aid attainable were at once procured, and all the members of the family vied with each other in rendering the prompt and efficient assistance which the circumstances<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC5690-00000047"/> ces demanded. Above all, the faithful nurse and attendant of his early years, this foster-mother, as he loved to call her, was most unremitting and earnest in her present devotedness to the sick man's necessities. She immediately took possession of the chamber nearest his own; she directed, or herself performed whatever her own skill in attendance on the sick had taught her was most conducive to his welfare. As she bathed his feet, or cooled his burning brow, or chafed his temples, or ministered to him the needful medicines prescribed, how vividly did it impress on both of them the remembrance of similar offices which she had performed for him in childhood, a third of a century ago. No language can adequately describe the persevering fidelity and womanly skill and tact of her attentions. Watching both by day and by night, and, with quiet efficiency,<pb n=""/> seeing that nothing was left uncared for, her noiseless step, her gentle hand and voice, and loving heart, anticipated his necessities, and soothed the perturbed and anxious spirit to repose. That upturned, heavenly countenance of hers, which seemed instinct with pious confidence in God, showed plainly where were all her trust and hope. But a few days elapsed before his case had reached and passed its crisis, and slowly he began to amend. Their mutual joy in this happy result was unutterable.  That family of his, whom he lately thought would see his face no more, would now scarcely hear of his danger e'er their anxieties would be relieved by the assurance of his decided convalescence.</p> 
               <p>These loving and long lost friends of his youth, also, would not, as they had feared, only find him to make for him an early grave, far from his kindred. No,<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC5690-00000048"/> by the good hand of his God and theirs, upon their earnest endeavors, he was to be restored to health and usefulness again, to reward their pious assiduities by pointing them to the divine and only efficient HEALER.</p> 
               <p>After a short time, his recovery became almost as rapid as had been his prostration. To Mrs. Jones and himself, those days of recovering mercy, when they could uninterruptedly sit for hours, side by side, and mutually rehearse the way in which the Lord had graciously led them, were indeed seasons of richest spiritual enjoyment, calling forth devout thanksgiving unto God. She told him ail the long and varied story of her removal to the wilderness, her privations and exposures, her vigils and toils. How grievously she had, for a time, mourned over the loss of religious associates and privileges, and how, one by one, the<pb n=""/> Saviour in whom she confided, had been pleased to supply one after another these deficiencies. The heralds of the Cross had been encouraged by her pious steadfastness and hopefulness, in part, at least, to set up their banners on that new field; and amid the log dwellings of the pioneers, as they gathered the little companies of those who feared and loved the Lord, and their voices went up to Him in praise and prayer, while the old forests around them re-echoed their songs of lofty cheer, God bowed His gracious heavens and came down, making the place of His feet glorious. She told how, even there, far away from any consecrated shrines of worship, in their rude and humble dwellings, or under the shade of the primeval trees, when they gathered for His worship, His Spirit came with sweet refreshing on the souls of the believers, and carried conviction, too, to<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC5690-00000049"/> the hearts of the unrenewed. There, and in such circumstances, she had years, before, seen her only son, and then his wife, and more lately some of their dear children, whom she had nursed with a mother's love, and strove to train in the way of piety, giving their hearts to the Redeemer.  These were her compensations for all her sacrifices, and were they not enough? With devout thankfulness she lifted her tear-dimmed eyes to heaven and said, "O yes, I can praise my God and Saviour forever, for these tokens of His infinite and unmerited love!"</p> 
               <p>Together that interesting family bowed morning and evening around their domestic altar, and joined the voices of young and old in the sweet hymns of praise for the divine goodness. As strength increased they walked out together. She, now nearly three-score and <pb n=""/> ten years of age, with her staff in her hand, would often pause to point out the localities around their pleasant home which had been made memorable by peculiar joys or sorrows. On the border of that wood, not very remote from their dwelling, her son had been almost killed by accident, when felling the giant trees of the forest. And there she had erected in her heart a monument of praise for God's deliverance of his invaluable life. Yonder, just over the hill, in a dwelling of one of the neighbors, where they had gathered for worship in former years, while she was sitting on the rude board-seats arranged for the assembly, her foot had been dreadfully crushed by the frail support of that seat giving way, and bringing down all its heavy load on, her unconsciously exposed limb. For days, weeks, yea months, the agony to her was indescribable; far greater than amputation<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC5690-00000050"/> tion would have caused; but patiently she bore all, and was rewarded, as she said, with a foot recovered, much better to her than none, or one of wood or cork.</p> 
               <p>A whole chapter or two might be interestingly filled with the gathering up of her incidental communications in those few days, supplemented and confirmed as they were, by what the kind-hearted grateful neighbors testified in her behalf, both as to her influence in her own family, or more widely in the little community around, where, for more than a quarter of a century, she had been a kind of moral and religious nucleus, around which the successive strata had gathered and formed themselves to the shape and spirit of her example. Modestly, and with becoming self-renunciation of all praise to herself, she spoke of the way in which God had led her all her days; and specially of<pb n=""/> the many lessons she had learned in that half a usual generation's length of years which she had passed under the roof of the pastor at Brookdale, as, under God, the means of her preparation for the important part which she had been forced to act on the new theater of her recent residence.</p> 
               <p>Recalling to Reuben's mind the books she had read in that little family library of the good pastor, the principles on which himself and his companion acted in rearing their own family, and as far as possible leading the neighbors and the entire community around them to be sober-minded, temperate in all things; industrious, frugal, and above all, God-fearing, and Christ-honoring, in heart and life, these <emph>these</emph>, said she with emphasis, have done so much to make my son's house happy and blessed, and to spread through the neighborhood of Bruceville the germs<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC5690-00000051"/> of order, success, and comfort. No wonder her influence there had become great. Having been planted there in the very beginning of the settlement, and for the most part having enjoyed uniform health, there was scarce a family in the whole vicinity to whom she had not hastened in their sickness, rendering them most welcome and important help, when no other could be procured. She loved the children whom she had nursed and cared for from their birth, and both children and their grateful parents remembered her great kindness to them in their hour of utmost need. Unostentatious, and never unduly assuming, she did not obtrude officiously her opinions or advice; but when the occasion demanded she was outspoken and decided; and her opinions on moral and religious, as well as domestic matters, were widely and greatly respected. "Why do you not ask Mother<pb n=""/> Jones?" became the common inquiry in all questions of importance, within her sphere. The commanding influence, and the blameless and highly honored character of her son, Esq. Jones, was enhanced by his connection with her; and then, in turn, it helped to add its own increment to her reputation. "See," said the neighbors, "what her pious consistency has wrought in making that family of his such patterns as they are!"</p> 
               <p>Not a judicious, upright decision did the magistrate give, in cases litigated before him, nor a successful effort did he volunteer as peace-maker among wrangling neighbors, but what reflected honor on his mother's influence.</p> 
               <p>It would have been passing strange, while Reuben had been gathering up all these testimonies in favor of one to whom he owed so much, if she, on her part, had failed to elicit from him, what his<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC5690-00000052"/> pious gratitude was prompt to acknowledge, what her forming influence had enabled him to accomplish. Little by little, she drew from him the main story of his life. How, the very next year after she had left him, so earnestly invoking on him, in the parting moment, the blessings which hers and his mother's prayers had sought for him, he had given his heart to God, and one year later, had been sent forth by his honored father's consent and aid, to prepare for usefulness as an ambassador of Christ. How, also, very early in his course of study, his begun career came near terminating by the death of his next older brother, who had just then finished his studies, and "with the ardor of a seraph" began to preach the gospel, only to find his course cut short by quick consumption, and in five months his body was laid in the grave. As this was attributed<pb n=""/> tributed to the deleterious influence of severe study on his before noble frame, great was the demur whether or not to arrest the course of young Reuben, even at the threshold, lest he should in the same way be sacrificed, and thus bring down the gray hairs of his father to a sorrowful grave. Then he told her how better counsels finally prevailed, helping him to complete his preparations; how God had graciously blessed his labors for near a score of years, in country and city churches where he had been pastor, enabling him to lead many hundreds to put on Christ in the pathway of discipleship; as she had herself done long before by his honored father's hand. Only two months before, his happiness had culminated in the conversion and addition to his church of his two eldest children. How, in fine, that father of his yet lived, between eighty and ninety years old,<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC5690-00000053"/> able, occasionally, to lead the flock he had cared for so long, and especially able, as all his acquaintances said, to lead with unsurpassed appropriateness and pathos their devotions on those funeral occasions when any of his associates in earlier years, like the withered leaves of autumn, fell before the driving blast. As these several reminiscences of their early years' connection were one by one rehearsed to her, the excellent woman would again and again exclaim, "O how wonderful has been God's goodness!" With some little remains of the womanly, perhaps laudable, pride of early years, she seemed to rejoice in all the tokens of public approval which had gathered around "this boy of her early care." His honor and renown, whenever he had reached the high places of the field and won a generous meed of public approbation, she traced, in part, at least,<pb n=""/> under the wonder-working providence and grace of God, to what she and his mother had done and sought for him.</p> 
               <p>Soon as he was possibly able to officiate, the neighbors were all notified to attend a lecture in the school house near Esq. Jones' residence. It was enough to be told that one so nearly a son of the honored mother of the settlement would there address them, to fill the room at an early hour; and from lips which she had so often moistened when parched in fever, she now heard the words of life and salvation. Nor was this all. The communion Sabbath of the little church was near at hand. Reuben's strength, as they all thought, was not fully enough recovered for him safely to set out on his homeward journey, and he must remain to gratify all their wishes by aiding their stated supply on that important occasion. When this was finally agreed on, the notices<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC5690-00000054"/> tices went forth very widely, over hillsides and valleys, over prairies and through incipient villages already springing up in that newly settled country.</p> 
               <p>The auspicious day at length arrived. Its bright sunlight spread over the lawn, and at an early hour the family were all astir for the needful preparation. The younger members on horseback, or on foot, or in humbler vehicles, took their way to the appointed place, while the carriage of Esq. Jones was filled by himself and wife, with his mother and the preacher. Long years had passed since they had rode to the house of God in company, and far the larger portion of the companions of their early years were with the dead. Scarcely could either of them realize that this was more than dream. The two miles which they traversed, furnished, at almost every step, some pleasant and grateful recollection,<pb n=""/> First, they passed for a considerable distance through the noble domain, the spacious fields of her son. Many of them he had reclaimed by hard and diligent toil from their native wildness, and the remainder he had annexed by purchase. As now they were covered over with his flocks and herds, or by the lofty and intensely verdant and dense-growing Indian corn, or showing the golden stubble whence the wheat-harvest had just been gathered, how natural that a sense of the divine goodness vouchsafed to them, should fill their glad hearts. Into all this joy their guest entered most cordially. The happy groups of young men and maidens whom they passed on the right hand and the left, all hieing to the sanctuary, appeared to look up to them with a very unusual interest. Their meaning glances of recognition seemed almost audibly to say, "This distinguished preacher, whom all<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC5690-00000055"/> are so eagerly pressing to hear, is only the result of Mother Jones' faithful, early training."</p> 
               <p>What then were her emotions when once and again she heard him, to the dense throng of the great congregation, preach that gospel, which so often and so far away she had heard from his father's pulpit. When, too, from his hand she received the symbols of her gracious Saviour's broken body and running blood, penetrated with holy gratitude, did not her heart, if not her lips, that day cry out, "Now let me depart in peace, O Lord, for my eyes have seen thy salvation?" Happy, thrice happy and blest was she, in being permitted thus to see the fruit of her prayers and early counsels made useful to her neighbors and friends.</p> 
               <p>The evening of that very day, after a leave-taking as tender, and solemn, and<pb n=""/> joyful, as their late meeting had been unexpected and opportune, one of the noble sons of Esq. Jones, took Reuben a few miles on his way to spend the night with other pious friends of the cause of Christ and of that dear family. This, too, had all been arranged by the considerate wisdom of this foster-mother, who, for good reasons, well understood by herself alone, had planned for one of her grandsons, this final privilege of a ride, and a confidential interview with one whom the whole family so much regarded. What was her motive for this sequestered intercourse between them? Why, this young man had but lately given his heart to the Saviour, and already felt-as none but his good grandmother knew-the intense longings of holy desire to give himself to the public service of the Lord. Will they not, said she to herself, find out by a kind of mutual<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC5690-00000056"/> tual instinct, this great theme of such transcendent interest and importance to the dear youth, and will not God bless to him the counsels of one whose own similar experience must have prepared him to sympathize with these youthful and hallowed aspirations? So, indeed, it fell out. As they rode on their way, in answer (who can doubt it?) to her prayers, this very topic was introduced: the timid ingenuousness of the young heart, warmly throbbing with love to the Saviour, in whom he had so recently believed, was laid open, little by little, to this recent stranger: and counsels adapted to his case were freely tendered and as gratefully received. On the young man's return to his home, not long were the two together, before he had told his honored grandmother all. How fully their recent guest had entered into and sympathized with all his own feelings of<pb n=""/> solicitude on the great question of his life-labor; and with what carefulness he had sought to guide his inexperienced feet in right and safe paths. Again did this good mother in Israel lift up her withered hands to heaven, and with tears of pious thankfulness exclaim, "This, too, is of the goodness of the Lord." "Was it for this," she asked, "that God, in part, at least, had brought him hither, that another might be helped on his way in taking up his cross and leaving all to follow Christ? So," thought she, "when, ere long, I lay down this silvered head of mine in the grave, another who has been dandled on my knees, and given to God's service in my early prayers for his consecration to this great work, may rise up and go forth in this or in heathen lands, to preach the unsearchable riches of Christ."</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC5690-00000057"/> 
               <head>PART IV.</head> 
               <epigraph> 
                  <q>
                     <lg type="quotation"> 
                        <l rend="ti-3">"Think you that raptured soul</l> 
                        <l>Now walking humbly in the golden streets</l> 
                        <l>Bearing the precious burden of a love</l> 
                        <l>Too great for utterance, or with hushed heart</l> 
                        <l>Drinking the music of the ransomed throng,</l> 
                        <l>Counts death an evil? No!"</l> 
                     </lg>
                  </q> 
               </epigraph> 
               <p>
                  <hi rend="i"/>IT pleased her heavenly Father to spare the honored life of widow Jones to the extreme old age of nearly eighty-five, or fifteen years after the events last recorded. And while little of startling interest occurred in that comparatively peaceful period, there was still such alternation in her varied and sometimes trying experiences, so much of the rich grace of the gospel did she share and exemplify, that we may profitably trace, very briefly, her subsequent career.</p> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <p>In the earlier portion of these declining years, she still insisted on taking her full share in the family cares and toils. It was indeed no longer necessary. Her son had been so prospered, and the children, even the youngest of them, were so fully grown, as no longer to make the large demand on her industry and watchfulness which they had formerly. But, "cleanliness and industry are next to godliness," was the motto which this good mother had early learned, and if rarely repeated by her lips, it had a significant enforcement in her daily life. From long and uniform practice these habits had become to her a second nature. And when that noble son and his wife would sometimes say to her, "Mother, why do you continue to rise so early, and insist on sharing still all the more burdensome toils and duties of the household?" he would quickly remark<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC5690-00000058"/> mark, "Somebody must do all this, and my comfort and happiness are rather increased than diminished by what I do."</p> 
               <p>Rising with the sun in summer, and long before his appearance in winter, she made her own apartment the neat and welcome place which it always appeared, and then would see to it that all the members of the family were assisted, so far as requisite, in their respective duties, so that in an orderly, quiet manner they might be ready for the breakfast and the season of family worship which immediately followed. Not a little of the happiness, and the mutual respect, and active good will of that numerous house. hold of parents, children and servants, were the direct result of this good order. They did not know its source-did not probably even surmise that what all the family so much enjoyed, what made this<pb n=""/> dwelling so welcome <emph>a home</emph> to the permanent or casual inmates,-was directly traceable to the steadfast fidelity in waiting on the Lord, which was there witnessed. And then again this steady, and orderly, and happy morning communion with God, was, more than they suspected, the result of her resolute carefulness that all should be ready in time for it; so that without; hurry or confusion, it might prove to every one of them the sweetest and most hallowed hour of the whole day.</p> 
               <p>That now venerable woman had known by painful contact in all her earlier years, how desolate and cheerless are the dwellings where God is not honored. She had felt the bitterness in body and soul of constant exposure to the fitful rule and wild disorder, the harsh dissonance and oft-recurring broils and outbursts of unholy passion, where master and mistress<pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC5690-00000059"/> have no fear of God nor love to the Saviour, no tender meltings of heart in bowing at the mercy seat, and no suitable considerateness of the wants and woes of orphan children parceled out among those whose tender mercies are cruel, and whose hard service is a bondage grievous as the Egyptian task-masters. The vindictive passion, the outbursts of violence, the harsh and causeless chidings, and the brutal blows under which her young frame had quivered and smarted, and her spirit often sank in almost hopeless despair, she still remembered; and as she thought of the happy years which succeeded under the roof of the pious pastor at Brookdale, where God was always honored, and the morning and evening incense went up from their domestic altar, she would inevitably draw the just conclusion, that surely God does, even in this life, pour out His indignation<pb n=""/> on the families that call not on His name while his rich blessing is on them that honor Him. She thought of the happiness resulting to parents and children together, when the words which God has taught us are treasured in our hearts, and taught diligently unto our children, talking of them when sitting in our houses, and when walking by the way, when we lie down, and when we rise up. Psalm xcii.</p> 
               <p>In the amusements and relaxations necessary for us, but which are so often perverted as to become scenes of disorder, breaking in most fatally on the regulations of a well-ordered family, she evinced her true knowledge of human nature, and the proper place to fix the limits of indulgence. She loved to witness, and even minister to the gleeful hilarity and joyousness of young hearts, full to repletion of the outbursting spirit<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC5690-00000060"/> of freedom. When the allotted tasks of toil or of study had been successfully completed, how sweet the smile that said from under that tidy cap, and out of those bright twinkling eyes and healthful lips, "Now go and enjoy yourselves." Well-regulated and properly limited mirthfulness, the happy, side-shaking laugh, the vigorous athletic sports, and specially the joyous songs of children and youth were sweet music to her old ears, and by cherishing a love for these sports and innocent pastimes of the young, in her own family and neighborhood, she helped to keep her own heart young also. "Wrinkles will come upon my face, age will thin and blanch my locks," said she, "but my care shall be, long as possible to keep the former from my heart, and let the sweet sunshine of loving kindness still encircle my brows." To this was it doubtless owing, in a very great degree,<pb n=""/> that all the children still loved and clung to her. It was one of their choicest treats to be allowed to sit in her room, to hear her stories, and look at the pictures she so carefully preserved, and hear her words of kind encouragement, or needed counsel.</p> 
               <p>One of the first abiding infirmities of her old age, was the loss of hearing. It was not sudden and total; but gradually, and, on the whole, pretty fast, she felt the loss of listening to the sweet and gentle tones of love in their natural utterances, and those who would make her hear them, were obliged to give unusual force and distinctness to their expressions. As this increased from year to year, she was soon unable to gather instruction from the ministrations of the sanctuary, and as the family was numerous, and all could not well go at once so great a distance, she, with that beautiful<pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC5690-00000061"/> considerateness which always characterized her, would insist on remaining at home, that her seat in the carriage, and then in the house of prayer, might be occupied by some who could more profit by these privileges. Greatly as she had always enjoyed the sound of a preached gospel, of the voice of public prayer and praise before, and unwelcome as must have been the privation of listening to the ordinary conversations of the loved ones in their family circle, it is not recollected that she ever, for one moment, either murmured or complained. The same genial smile irradiated her countenance, responding to each friendly look given her, and she seemed inclined all the more gratefully to prize her almost undimmed eyesight, and her powers of easy and quick locomotion. What a lesson to all! Instead of repining for the loss of something dear, but which<pb n=""/> God in wisdom has removed, to estimate more highly and justly the mercies still vouchsafed to us. The Bible and hymn book, with Baxter's Saints' Rest, and Burder's Sermons for the Aged, were now invested with new interest and attraction. As she read, very often would she be marking the passages which appeared to her most striking, and she would point them out for reading to the dear friends who came in, and loved to sit by her side, indicating how sweetly they had relished to her.</p> 
               <p>Among the rest of her visitors, her dear boy Reuben, as she loved to call him, though residing many hundred miles from her, made it in his way two or three times to visit her. He came always unexpected, unannounced; for the sake of the joyful surprise which he knew his entrance among them would awaken, and specially to the loving heart of this true<pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC5690-00000062"/> mother. His father and then his stepmother had died soon after his first visit to Bruceville, so that really there was no one on earth now seeming to him so truly his own parent as this loving foster-mother. He soon found, too, that by a slow and distinct utterance, his voice on rather a high key, would penetrate even her dull ears, so that for hours together they could carry on pleasant conversation. How naturally her mind, especially in his presence, was continually running back to the scenes, the characters and events of their early history! Many of her earnest inquiries after the welfare of early friends, more especially their religious welfare, he was enabled to answer to her great satisfaction, and this again called forth their united praise to God. He, too, could read her favorite books, and the choicest parts of them which she had specially marked for him,<pb n=""/> so that she could well understand, and thus they enjoyed them together, each finding their own satisfaction enhanced by this reflex influence of a common joy. Together they attempted singing some of the dear old hymns, such favorites with them both, and with others now passed into the skies, near half a century before. But her voice had become harsh and strong, as is the usual result of deafness, instead of evincing the musical sweetness of former days, and this exercise was not long persevered in. But in family worship she could hear his voice by kneeling just before him, and the satisfaction which this union of soul brought to both of them was unspeakable. The tears of holy gratitude would then dim her eye, and add new interest to all her features.</p> 
               <p>He had considerately brought for her gratification whatever he thought would<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC5690-00000063"/> be most acceptable to her. Not one of his gifts, even the most costly, did she so much prize, however, as the New Testament and Psalms printed specially for the aged, in type so large and fair, that, old as she was, it enabled her to dispense with spectacles in their perusal; so light,  too, in their thin, elastic covers, that her hand was never weary in holding them. Again and again would she press the  open books to her bosom, and in strong, loud utterances, cry out, "These, <emph>these</emph> are my treasures; and when you have to go away I can keep them and read them still. These words of Jesus and these Psalms of David! how marvelously rich they are in their teachings, and their comforts, too. I can well understand his meaning where he says, 'Thy words have I taken as a heritage forever, and they are the rejoicing of my heart.'"</p> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <p>Nor were they limited altogether to these indoor enjoyments. Her eye was still bright, her step was firm, and her health was excellent, and on a fine vernal morning or evening she loved to go forth leaning on the arm of her son, or Reuben, as with stalwart vigor they still loved to feel the pressure of such a burden. How sweet the perfume of the early flowers, how bright the verdure which carpeted the earth, how gorgeous the bloom of fruit trees in their exuberant blossoms! The garden, the lawn, the fields, covered over with flocks and herds, how did they all appeal to her heart, and they found there a ready response. She quoted no poetry, but she felt all and more than all that bards have sung, or the eloquent interpreters of nature have ever reached in their loftiest and most impassioned eulogies. Her own heavenly Father had made even His footstool<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC5690-00000064"/> thus resplendent. What then must be His throne! If such were the joys of her pilgrimage, what must be her home!</p> 
               <p>But other and sadder <choice>
                     <sic>ministeries</sic>
                     <corr>ministries</corr>
                  </choice> were also plied by the All-wise disposer to  loosen the ties which bound her to the world. One after another, half that precious family were called before her to that spirit world "where our best friends our kindred dwell, where God our Saviour reigns." First, two of the grandchildren, the loveliest and dearest, as doting parents are ever wont to think when death sets his mark on them, were removed. But grandmother said, "The great Proprietor came into His own enclosure and plucked for Himself-ah, why should he not?-the ripest sweetest fruits." With holy equanimity of soul she was enabled cheerfully to give them up to Him who had redeemed them.</p> 
               <p>Next came a sorer trial. The strong<pb n=""/> staff of her earthly support was also broken. That son, that only son, for whom and with whom she had so long lived, in the fullness of his manly strength and ripened wisdom, on whom the eye and heart, not of the family alone, but of the church, where, as an office-bearer, he was honored; of the community, where, as a good magistrate he so efficiently and widely promoted the public welfare, so confidingly vested, was now removed by death. It was no sudden fearful casualty smiting down their hope in a moment unexpected, but fatal disease fixed its tenacious grasp on him, nor would relax its hold. He felt that he must die, and ordering wisely and well all his earthly interests, he committed himself and the weeping, loving group around  him to the widow's God, the Father of the fatherless, and fell asleep in Jesus. The mother stood by, who had borne<pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC5690-00000065"/> him in her heart's core from his birth, and for near fifty years, amid all changes had clung to him so fondly, and with such exulting gratitude and joy. But she utters no complaint. Tears, not of bitterness, but of holy joy flowed freely, as looking up to Him whom she adored, she tremblingly cried, "Father, not as I will, but as Thou wilt. Father, Thy will be done! The cup which Thou givest me, shall I not drink it?" He, the great Healer, Comforter and Guide, bound up her bleeding heart, whispered His words of gracious promise to her faith, and led her unfalteringly towards her loved rest.</p> 
               <p>No long interval elapsed ere that same group gathered around the dying bed of her daughter-in-law, following so soon the husband of her love, to the spirit world. Again did this doubly bereaved family look to her, whose counsels, and examples, and prayers they had always enjoyed<pb n=""/> joyed, nor did they look in vain. She survived these great changes long enough to evince before them all, for their instruction and their comfort, too, how perfectly adapted is the religion of Christ for every exigency. Her heart was not congealed by all its desolating experiences. Her eye was not deadened to the scenes and claims around her. True, the heart did yearn more fondly for the complement of its full joy in other and brighter scenes, and the eye instinctively turned its gaze upward more fondly and frequently. Yet was she still the same loving, wise, and faithful friend to all these orphan children, which she had ever been, and nobly did their hearts reciprocate her love.</p> 
               <p>Once more did Reuben, now past his meridian, and full of pressing cares, find his way to greet her in what he feared might be her loneliness and desolation.<pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC5690-00000066"/> Just look once more upon the simple scene. It is a lovely morning of the earliest summer, and she has been for just a little while left sole mistress of the dwelling. The son who inherits the paternal mansion, and with it the blest privilege of caring for grandmother's welfare, had not yet brought home his lovely bride, and depended on a house-keeper, herself the mother of a dear babe which she brought with her. To-day they had left, for an hour or two, that babe under the faithful care of grandmother, while other avocations called them from home. She drew the cradle near the door, where she was sitting, with her back to the street entrance. Reuben had reached the premises unperceived by her. Seeing her well-known form, and her employment in hushing the little one, he passed the gate, and stood upon the threshold, his traveling-bag in hand.<pb n=""/> His shadow, in full and accurate outline with this accompaniment, fell on the floor before her, and scarcely looking up, in her loud peculiar voice she said, "They are all from home, you can have no trade to-day," supposing she was replying to a peddler soliciting the purchase of his trinkets. But still he stood there, as if immovably charmed and fastened to the spot, till again she repeated, in louder tones, her refusal of what she thought his importunate proffer. Still, as the shadow lingered, and she wondered that he did not leave, she rose and looked upon him, recognizing in full, the love that brought him to her side.</p> 
               <p>This ludicrous scene, at his entrance, gave both of them a hearty laugh, and prepared them, as one extreme leads to another, for the tender and mournful review of sad scenes which both had passed through since they had last met. "You<pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC5690-00000067"/> seem quite lonesome here, mother," said Reuben, in the loud tones requisite to make her hear. "Yes, yes," she responded, "they all think it very lonesome, but I am used to it; to me it is not unwelcome. My thoughts, my heart are no longer so much tied to the world. More easy I now find it to commune with God my Saviour, and think of the many mansions in His Father's house. He said He would go and prepare a place for His followers, and would come and receive them unto Himself, that where He is, they may be forever. I would not, indeed, be impatient, for it is good to wait the Lord's time, to do and suffer all His holy will. But I am so glad that the time of my departure is near. <q>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"'O who would live alway away from his God-</l> 
                        <l>Away from yon heaven, that blissful abode.</l> 
                        <l>Where rivers of pleasure flow o'er the bright plains,</l> 
                        <l>And the noontide of glory eternally reigns;</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <pb n=""/>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"'Where the saints of all ages in harmony meet,</l> 
                        <l>Their Saviour and brethren transported to greet;</l> 
                        <l>While anthems of rapture unceasingly roll,</l> 
                        <l>And the smile of the Lord is the feast of the soul!'"</l> 
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p> 
               <p>The slow loud utterance, by her, of these stanzas, seemed greatly to affect the heart of Reuben. Tears unconsciously, but plentifully were bedewing his cheeks, and her still quick and bright eyes detected them. Grasping his hand warmly, her inquiring look said, "Why should such a prospect make one weep?" Not unwillingly he told her that those words which she had just repeated awakened in his bosom the memory of their frequent utterance in the well known duet which his daughters played and sung together so often, and with such tender and hallowed joy, both to themselves and others. But God had taken the ripest to Himself-and the now lonely survivor, so often choking with fond, sad<pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC5690-00000068"/> recollections, when asked for this or other music she had been wont to give with such effect by the aid of the deceased, now answered with a sigh, "The sweet harmony is gone! and my lone notes are too mournful."</p> 
               <p>"Oh tell me," said Mother Jones with great earnestness, "tell me all about your stricken lamb-her life, her death, her last utterances ere she winged her way to Jesus' bosom." So earnest and persistent was her importunity, enforced as it was by the argument that not often could she at all hear the voices of those around her, while his was quite audible; and by the further assurance, that such rehearsals were now to her ear and heart more welcome than all others; "not sad, not gloomy," said she, "but rather inspiring, full of heartfelt joy," that refusal was impossible. Thus entreated, how could he deny any effort for her gratification<pb n=""/> cation? Drawing his seat very near to her, he gave the following</p> 
               <q>
                  <floatingText xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
                     <body > 
                        <div type="part"> 
                           <head>STORY OF EMILY.</head> 
                           <p>From earliest childhood, she had evinced unusual tenacity of purpose. Whatever she undertook, whether work or play, whether study or music, she gave her whole heart to it. Often so abstracted did she seem as to give no heed to passing occurrences. With this was combined what seemed stubbornness of temper. She had occasioned her parents and teachers more trouble, in this respect, than all their other children. Yet there was ever in her a nobleness, a conscientiousness, and an abhorrence of whatever was mean, dissembling, or allied to tricky artifice. Her truthfulness was always reliable, and to promises she had made, her fidelity was steadfast and unimpeachable. Without the versatility<pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC5690-00000069"/> which is often so charming, she had made uncommon progress in whatever she undertook. Her mastery of language, especially, was very unusual for her years.</p> 
                           <p>Before she was fourteen her mind became deeply exercised on personal religion. She was deeply and thoroughly convinced of her sinfulness in God's sight; and in the depth of contrition she loathed and abhorred herself. The public appeal which just then fell on her ear from a youthful ambassador of Christ, to "make one honest effort" to surrender her soul to Jesus, and trust Him entirely and forever, was blessed of the Holy Spirit. She yielded her young heart to the requirements of the gospel, and became a consistent disciple of the Saviour. It might be expected that religion, grafted on such a stock, would bear its noblest fruit. Lovely and blessed was the influence which she ever afterwards exerted.<pb n=""/> In the school among her fellow pupils, in the female prayer meeting, where those mature in age and piety marveled at the petitions they heard from her childlike lips, in the church of God and her Bible class, where her example and profiting were so noticeable, she evinced the power of that matchless grace of the Saviour which had made her its trophy. Ere long it pleased her heavenly Father to try her faith. She was laid on a sick bed, and for many days her life was nearly despaired of. How serene and unclouded, how firm and unshrinking was then her trust in the divine promises. Her heavenly serenity said loudly to all beholders, "Though He slay me, yet will I trust in Him." This scene of suffering occurred in the house of her maternal grandfather, where she was born; and very powerful and salutary seemed its influence on the rugged but noble nature of<pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC5690-00000070"/> that doting, kind-hearted old man. It pleased God, however, after the light had been flickering in the socket for several anxious days, to recover her to comfortable, but not robust health. In this state she visited among early friends, at a distance from her home, and here too her influence was blessed.</p> 
                           <p>Thus was she, for nearly four years, a growing, happy Christian. The light and joy of the home circle which she graced with heavenly sweetness, she was scarcely less beloved and honored wherever her unobtrusive pathway led her. Personal charms, all too winning, were developing themselves in her, combined with the nobler graces of heavenly origin. Once and again had her hand been sought, by those to whom she could not be entirely indifferent. But in full harmony with parental counsels, she said, "It is too early too decide in questions so momentous<pb n=""/> tous." A third appeal, having the advantage of almost daily intercourse, and enforced by the most solemn and earnest assurances that only by her influence the loving one might be led to the Saviour, she at length yielded to, and before completing her eighteenth year, in mid-winter of 1844, was married. How well she filled the important post of mistress of a family-how far she exceeded the fondest expectations of her friends in all the capability there evinced, need not be here described. Effectually and promptly had she won the hearts of her husband's kindred, in their commanding and dignified positions. Most of all was her unobtrusive piety still noticeable. Each morning in their dwelling, the Word of God was devoutly read together by the entire household; and at evening she and her husband bowed in prayer together in her chamber, making the apartment the hallowed<pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC5690-00000071"/> lowed threshold of heaven. How rare the combination of meekness and dignity which shone forth in all her deportment. The books she read, the letters and journal she wrote, the visits she received or returned, as well as all her daily intercourse with either friends or strangers, savored of her communion with the skies.</p> 
                           <p>Near mid-autumn, her father was required to set forth on a long and perilous journey through the entire western States, to occupy five months. The Sabbath evening before his departure, Emily spent with him in his own family circle. As usual they read, and sang, and prayed, her voice, a beautiful soprano, giving its richness to the favorite sacred airs in which they united. The beautiful sermon of Robert Hall, from the appropriate promise by the prophet Moses, Deut. xxxii. 25, <hi rend="i"/>Thy shoes shall be iron and brass; and as thy days, so shall thy<pb n=""/> 
                              <hi rend="i"/>strength be, was read and remarked on, more perhaps with reference to his anticipated perils in this journey, than to that of those he left behind him. She evinced the utmost cheerfulness; spoke freely and lovingly to that fond father of her great enjoyments in her new home, and poured into his willing ear the thrilling joys she still anticipated. There was just enough of pensive sadness, by the expected separation for so many weeks, to give keener and more chastened enjoyment to the hour, and he had never, perhaps, looked on that circle with a tenderer and more joyous heart.</p> 
                           <p>Before the next sunrise, he was on his way. One or two letters from home had met him on his wandering course, and little more than three weeks had elapsed after his departure, before one from his son-in-law, reaching him in middle Tennessee, told him of the premature accouchment<pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC5690-00000072"/> couchment of his daughter, and that mother and babe were then doing well. He responded at once, with fear and trembling, lest the daughter, and now a mother, should prove too frail for such an exigency. More than a week elapsed before he reached St. Louis, where his next letters were to reach him. With intensest impatience he broke the seal, to learn from the attending physician, that puerperal fever had supervened; in the not unusual delirium which ensued, most anxiously and repeatedly had the poor sufferer cried out for her father-her father. "Why do you not send for him, for certainly he would come to his dying Emily?"</p> 
                           <p>This, too, was accompanied by an intimation from the kind physician that nothing would so likely avail for her recovery as the soothing influence of that father's presence and prayers. This had<pb n=""/> been written some ten days already, and he was more than one thousand miles from her. How torturing the suspense! But the next day brought the dreaded tidings. The struggle was over, and the poor sufferer had departed. But her reason had been fully restored before the closing scene. When told that she was thought to be dying, after affectionate and pious counsels and adieus to those present, she left for the absent one this message, "When dear father comes, tell him not to grieve for his Emily. I shall soon meet him; perhaps I shall see him first." Then closing her eyes she whispered audibly and calmly, "I shall soon rest in the Saviour's bosom, and with the holy angels." A beloved Christian brother knelt by her dying bed, and breathed a fervent prayer. When in the conclusion he entreated the Father of mercies to sustain and comfort that stricken absent<pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC5690-00000073"/> father, whom the young sufferer had so tenderly loved, she clasped her hands and uttered a fervent "Amen!" This was her last word.</p> 
                        </div> 
                     </body> 
                  </floatingText>
               </q> 
               <p>When Reuben had completed the narrative, widow Jones exclaimed, "And I too can join in that amen! May my own departure, which now must be very near, be like that of this holy child of yours. What has the world to offer, comparable with such an exit, in prospect of the home, the bliss, the Saviour's embrace, which she realized?"</p> 
               <p>By a natural transition this led her to recapitulate many of the interesting incidents connected with the sickness and death of her own children, and children's children. These were widely varied, indeed, as must be expected; but all were strikingly evincive of the faithfulness of the Good Shepherd, who verifies to such<pb n=""/> His own precious promise, "I will never leave thee, nor forsake thee."</p> 
               <p>Oh how sinful and ungrateful would it be for me," she exclaimed, with earnestness, "to doubt His loving-kindness to me, after all which He has thus permitted me to witness and experience!" And then in the strong voice to which all had been accustomed to hear her in these latter years of imperfect hearing, she broke forth in singing the familiar stanza, <q>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"His love in times past forbids me to think</l> 
                        <l>He will leave me at last in trouble to sink;</l> 
                        <l>Each sweet Ebenezer I have in review,</l> 
                        <l>Confirms His good pleasure to help me quite through."</l> 
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p> 
               <p>Toward evening they walked forth a little distance from the dwelling, enjoying to the full the beauty of the vernal year. The clustering fruit trees were just scattering their fragrant and variously tinted blossoms, like snow flakes covering<pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC5690-00000074"/> the ground at their feet; and the sweet notes of the wild birds filled the air with their melody, while the honey bees hastening with their nectar sweets to their hives, sent forth a subdued hum not ungrateful to the ear. Leaning on Reuben's arm, she slowly led the way toward the resting place of the dead, but said with a cheerful smile, "I do not as was said of Mary, 'Go unto the grave to weep there.' No, thank God, I can rejoice rather. For the unslumbering eye of Him who watches over the dust of those who sleep in Jesus, will well perform its office till the archangel's voice shall call them from their sleep. Here beside my kindred would I too find a resting place for this poor old worn out frame. But my soul will fly away and join the redeemed in their white robes, and help them sing their new song of praise to our glorious Saviour."</p> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <p>And so, ere many months elapsed, she did. Her final illness was neither long nor painful. She welcomed, with thankfulness, the kindly ministries of her physician, and nurse, and grandchildren; she was remarkably quiet, evinced no impatience, and seemed to lie passive in the Lord's hands to be disposed of as He saw fit. But the eye, the heart were evidently above, and He whom she had waited for, came and received her into His own presence, to go no more out forever. There, in that humble cemetery, rest her remains with those of her son and other kindred; and those among survivors who knew her best, will most honor and revere her memory.</p> 
               <p>The condensed facts of our little history are completed, and they scarce need the formal pointing of their important lesson. Fully do they confirm<pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC5690-00000075"/> and illustrate the position, that not high rank or favored external circumstances are essential to true worth, or even to extensive usefulness. When many of the titled dignitaries of earth shall have passed to the oblivion they have merited, and others who have won brief plaudits by unworthy means, and have, as rapidly as they rose, sunk away to deserved forgetfulness, some, like this pious Emigrant's Mother, by well filling their humble stations, and honoring the Lord in all their ways, shall live in the hallowed memory of future generations, fulfilling thus the divine promise,</p> 
               <p>"<hi rend="i"/>Surely the righteous shall be in ever-lasting remembrance."</p> 
            </div> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>