<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC5561">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >The Angel of the Battle-field </title>
            <author >Bradshaw, Wesley (1837-1927)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC5561</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >The angel of the battle-field</title>
                  <author >Bradshaw, Wesley (1837-1927)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >96 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >American News Co.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1865">1865</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2000-11-08">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-01-07">Finished TEI encoding, proofreading and final editing.</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <front> 
         <titlePage xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
            <pb  n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC5561-00000001"/> 
            <docTitle> 
               <titlePart>THE ANGEL OF THE BATTLE-FIELD.</titlePart> 
               <titlePart type="sub">A TALE OF THE REBELLION.</titlePart> 
            </docTitle> 
            <byline >BY <docAuthor xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">WESLEY BRADSHAW,</docAuthor> AUTHOR OF "PAULINE OF THE POTOMAC," "VOLUNTEER ROLL Of HONOR," &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</byline> 
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>NEW YORK:</pubPlace> 
               <publisher >THE AMERICAN NEWS COMPANY, <address> 
                     <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">119 &amp; 121 NASSAU ST.</addrLine> 
                  </address>
               </publisher>
            </docImprint> 
            <docDate>1865</docDate> 
            <pb  n="4-5" xml:id="VAC5561-00000002"/> 
            <docEdition>Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1865, By THE AMERICAN NEWS COMPANY, in the Clerk's office of the District Court of the United States for the Southern District of New York.</docEdition> 
         </titlePage> 
      </front> 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The angel of the battle-field</head> 
            <pb n=""/> 
            <head>THE ANGEL OF THE BATTLE-FIELD.</head> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER I.</head> 
               <head type="sub">A HEROINE.</head> 
               <p>EIGHTY-SEVEN years ago the old bell in the tower of Independence Hall, Philadelphia, rang out a joyous pan for the birth of the American Republic. And many a time during the succeeding seven years did its clangor toll out, through summer breeze and winter blast, calling Americans to arm and meet the foeman. At the end of that time its iron tongue sang the requiem of Oppression and the Te Deum of Liberty, sweet, beautiful Liberty; and the warrior fathers of Seventy-Six returned in peace to their homes. Three millions of people were unshackled, and, laying aside the musket, they took hold of the plow, the helm, and the loom; and the new Republic was soon in the van of nations.</p> 
               <p>For the better portion of a century thereafter Peace and Prosperity reigned within her borders, and her flourishing cities and plenteous farms stretched from the Atlantic to the Pacific.</p> 
               <p>Suddenly, however, her life was imperiled. Hostile batteries, insidiously masked for twenty years, were trained upon the "Banner of the Stars." Chilled with horror, more than twenty-one millions of anxious ears were strained to catch the dull roar of traitor guns. The sullen and unwonted sound came at length rolling and echoing from Cumming's Point, and the lightning, on its swiftest pinions, bore the dire news that Freedom's meteor flag drooped amidst the sulphurous smoke that shrouded Sumter's battlements.</p> 
               <p>At the very moment the telegraphic dispatch reached Philadelphia, announcing that Beauregard had lit the fires of rebellion, a conflagration burst forth in the city, and the bell in the tower of Independence Hall tolled a general alarm, and was quickly followed by all the bells in the city. There was a strange significance about this coincidence which was noted at the time, and which increased the excitement, already so intense. Old men, middle-aged men, young men, and boys, with one accord, surged along through the streets of the city, shouting:</p> 
               <p>"Down with the traitors! Give us arms! give us arms! Forward! forward! Our dear old flag forever! Let us fight for it! Fight! ay, that's the word! Fight! fight!"</p> 
               <pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC5561-00000003"/> 
               <p>Chestnut street, from Third street westward, was the bed of a human torrent that rushed and swelled and eddied along with a violence which oftentimes seemed to threaten to crush in the banks of houses on either side and sweep turbulently on over the ruins. Once in a while a car or a carriage toiled through the mass, leaving a furrow behind it for a moment, but only a moment, for the seething, churning, whirling crowd flowed over and obliterated it instantly.</p> 
               <p>Down upon these billows of heads and shoulders and upturning faces looked two persons from a window of the Continental Hotel. The appearance of both distinguished them as Southerners.</p> 
               <p>One was a tall, aristocratic young man, elegantly attired, and possessed of a fine, handsome, and intellectual countenance. To some his attractiveness was enhanced by the long raven-hued hair, which, soft and silky, curled naturally almost down upon his shoulders.</p> 
               <p>The lady who stood beside him was slightly below the medium height, but of that peculiar dignity of carriage and mien which always seems to increase stature and to command general attention and deference.</p> 
               <p>As the two continued gazing down upon the crowd, some one in the latter, who had obtained an old American flag, unfurled it. The effect was electrical, and, like the roar of an ocean, a mighty cheer went up for the glorious and holy standard of our beloved land. Eleanor Poindexter, the young lady we have just referred to, waved her handkerchief and clapped her hands by turns, in the greatest apparent ecstasy. Her companion, however, not only manifested no pleasure, but scowled fiercely upon the scene below.</p> 
               <p>"I am astonished at you, Eleanor," he exclaimed, taking hold of Miss Poindexter's arm, and with no gentle grip. "You," he continued, as the young lady, in anger and surprise, turned toward him-"You, the daughter of a father whose very name is inseparable from the South, and whose life is devoted to her interests and honor!"</p> 
               <p>"Brother," replied Eleanor, her cheeks pale with offended dignity, and her voice quivering with emotion, "I am astonished at <emph>you</emph>! That glorious banner which is filling the thousands in the street with the wildest joy, and which, even as I speak, may be torn in shreds from its staff at Fort Sumter, is the only true emblem of real liberty. Yet you, the descendant of forefathers whose blood was shed on every field of the Revolution, now that that flag is insulted, attacked, destroyed, turn against it with the dastard foe! Shame on you!"</p> 
               <p>"Eleanor," answered Henry Poindexter, his anger increased, but as though regretting his rudeness to his sister, "I am sorry for my roughness, but you incensed me beyond control; and I warn you that if you make any further such demonstrations as you have just now made in favor of the cause which every true Southerner must hereafter detest, I will exercise the authority father has deputed to me and take you immediately home."</p> 
               <p>"Provided I consent, sir," quickly retorted the beautiful girl, her proud blood mounting to her cheeks and her eyes flashing fire. "Do you<pb n=""/> think," she continued, stepping back a pace and glancing at her brother with a sort of contempt, "that because father ordered you to attend me through our tour and afford me the protection due from any gentleman to a lady, he intended me to be your slave and obey your whims and commands?"</p> 
               <p>"Then, if you are so free and independent, Eleanor, I will alter my decision, and say that without you <emph>comply with my wishes</emph> I shall return home with you at once, and if you refuse to accompany me thither I will withdraw my protection from you and let you find your own way as best you can."</p> 
               <p>These remarks were uttered with an air and tone which were intended to be crushing in their effect. The speaker's surprise may, therefore, be imagined as his beautiful and heroic sister, drawing herself up with the utmost dignity, haughtily rejoined:</p> 
               <p>"<emph>You</emph> withdraw <emph>your</emph> protection indeed! I can dispense entirely with it; I do not need it! I can make my own way alone, sir, not only home, but to any part of the country to which I may see fit to go."</p> 
               <p>"To be insulted by Yankee <emph>gentlemen</emph>!" sneered Henry, laying great emphasis on the word "gentlemen."</p> 
               <p>"And, alas, to be unprotected by a Southern <emph>chevalier</emph>!" answered Eleanor, throwing the most biting irony into the last word, and glancing at her brother with that kind of a look which makes a general allusion at once personal.</p> 
               <p>Eleanor's sarcasm was received with applause by a group of ladies and gentlemen who had quickly gathered near her and her brother. This recalled her to the remembrance that her standing in society would not permit of her quarreling in the drawing-room of a public hotel without lowering herself, and therefore, bowing to her admirers, she said:</p> 
               <p>"I beg pardon, gentlemen and ladies, for having, in an unguarded moment, forgotten what is due to the laws of good-breeding, and thereby allowed myself to become angered. Come, brother," she added, turning to Henry, "let us go."</p> 
               <p>The latter did not answer, but, allowing his sister to slip her arm through his, walked from the apartment to their own private parlor. On entering the latter room, Eleanor cast herself upon a <foreign xml:lang="FRA">tete--tete</foreign>, and burst into a flood of tears. Henry guessed at the cause of his sister's grief, and seating himself beside her he passed his arm caressingly about her, and drawing her head upon his shoulder he kissed her repeatedly, saying, as he did so:</p> 
               <p>"Indeed, dear Eleanor, I am heartily ashamed of my rudeness in taking hold of you before all those persons in the drawing-room; will you forgive me and forget the offense? Come, now, say you will, there is a dear girl."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, dear brother," exclaimed Eleanor, looking up into his face, "I can easily forgive and forget that; but the exhibition on your part of hostility to your country, how can I forgive that? Tell me," she continued, in earnest tones, "that you were not yourself, dear Henry, when you manifested hatred to the flag and cause for which, in the darkest days of Seventy-Six, our ancestors gave their lives and fortunes?"</p> 
               <p>For a moment or two Poindexter<pb n="8-9 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC5561-00000004"/> remained silent, and then, dissimulating, for he knew well the determined and noble disposition of his sister, he replied:</p> 
               <p>"I confess it, Eleanor, I confess it! I was not exactly myself when I expressed myself so warmly on the all-absorbing topic of the day."</p> 
               <p>"And in future, Henry," resumed Eleanor, fixing her penetrating eyes upon her brother, "what course do you intend to pursue? for, depend upon it, there will now be but two sides-for the rightful government or against it; for the national flag or against it."</p> 
               <p>Henry Poindexter, in dissimulating in his previous reply to his sister, had thought thus to close the conversation, at least on that head. But from her look as she asked him the question about his future course he was convinced that his artifice had not served its intended purpose. He therefore determined to nip all inquiry in the bud by answering, in his naturally imperious tones:</p> 
               <p>"Eleanor, let me distinctly inform you that every true Southerner will choose the proper side in the contest that has just been so bravely and defiantly <choice>
                     <sic>inugurated</sic>
                     <corr>inaugurated</corr>
                  </choice> by General Beauregard in Charleston harbor. The South has determined to sever all further intercourse with the North, except as a foreign nation. The blow has been struck, and the battle remains to be fought."</p> 
               <p>"All of which means," said Eleanor, releasing herself from her brother's arm, "that the South has determined, causelessly, to destroy the Union, to trample under foot the American flag, and commence one of the most fearful civil wars that ever deluged the earth with blood and tears; and that you, as a true Southerner, will side with such an unholy cause."</p> 
               <p>"Your interpretation is a strong one, Eleanor. But let me assure you of one or two things: the South is resolved on gaining its independence at all hazards, and the Poindexters, to a man-your father, your uncles, and myself-are resolved to go with her. Consequently we spurn the established government, spurn its laws, its power, and its institutions!"</p> 
               <p>"And do you spurn its flag?" asked our heroine, in tones ominously quiet.</p> 
               <p>"Certainly!" was the unhesitating reply.</p> 
               <p>"Then," exclaimed the lovely girl, springing to her feet, "I spurn you! No longer are you a brother of mine when it becomes so easy a task for you to turn traitor! To-morrow I shall set out on my return home to ascertain whether your assertion about our father is true or only a base calumny!"</p> 
               <p>"Go you without my protection?" asked Henry.</p> 
               <p>"Without <emph>your</emph> protection?" repeated Eleanor, with the same irony in her manner as she had exhibited in the drawing-room. "Why," continued she, "if you do not curb your tongue, I shall be obliged to protect <emph>you</emph> ere long. Do you not hear the popular storm raging in the street below? Listen to it! Let its fearful voice sink deeply into your ears, and teach you discretion, if nothing else!"</p> 
               <p>"Ha, ha! The scum! the rabble!" exclaimed Poindexter <choice>
                     <sic>contemptously</sic>
                     <corr>contemptuously</corr>
                  </choice>. "Do you see these, and do you not know that I am an expert with both?" Henry drew forth a revolver and bowie-knife as he spoke, and grated his teeth in a manner that made his<pb n=""/> 
                  <figure> 
                     <head>"Quick, quick, Poindexter! escape with your sister! The mob has heard of us as secessionists!"</head> 
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC5561-00000005"/> sister's blood run cold, and seemed to court an encounter.</p> 
               <p>At this juncture some one came running along the hall, and, stopping at the door, knocked loudly. Then, without awaiting any reply, the summoner entered the parlor in which were Henry and Eleanor Poindexter. The unceremonious intruder was a friend who had accompanied Henry and his sister from the South, and his features were blanched to a chalky paleness as he exclaimed:</p> 
               <p>"Quick, quick, Poindexter! escape with your sister! The mob has heard of us as secessionists! There are ropes hanging on the lamp-posts in front, and before we know it we'll be strung up! You never saw such a frenzy in your life! Quick! bring your sister along, and we'll get out the back way, on George street."</p> 
               <p>As the new-comer ended his half-breathless exclamations, the uproar of the mob, which for a moment had lulled, broke forth afresh and with increased violence, and the parlor door being open it seemed for that reason to be much nearer than before. When his friend first rushed into the room, Poindexter became instantly perturbated, and now, as the increased clamor of the mob broke upon his ears. his nerves became so affected that he actually dropped his revolver, sprang toward the door, and called upon Eleanor to follow him, instead of bearing her forth in his arms like a brave man should have done. An exclamation from his companion, who, though rather cowardly, was not quite so far gone as Henry, restrained him on the threshold, and he turned back to assist Eleanor.</p> 
               <p>That heroic young lady had, however, in the mean time secured the dropped pistol, and as her brother advanced toward her she motioned him away, as, with the utmost coolness and most terrible sarcasm, she said:</p> 
               <p>"Thank you, Henry, you have kindly left me a weapon, and I do not, therefore, need your <emph>protection</emph>! Save yourself!"</p> 
               <p>The chivalrous brother, in the midst of his fear, was stung to the quick, and remained for a moment or so endeavoring to persuade Eleanor to accompany himself and friend to a place of safety. But, as she steadily and sternly refused, Henry took her advice, left her to protect herself, hurried down stairs with his friend, and valiantly escaped into George street in the rear of the hotel. With equal precipitancy the fugitives obtained a carriage and were driven some distance ere they breathed freely.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <head>CHAPTER II.</head> 
               <head type="sub">TWO MATTERS SETTLED.</head> 
               <p>UPON finding herself really deserted in peril by her brother, Eleanor Poindexter became fearful that some terrible fate was in store for her, but be it what it might, she determined to face it unflinchingly. So, calling her servant, a light mulatto girl, from the next room, she closed and locked all the doors and then calmly awaited coming events.</p> 
               <p>The noise of the excited populace continued without abatement to a late hour; but it came no nearer, and after Eleanor, in company with her her maid Rosa, had remained a long time, expecting momentarily to be at the mercy of the mob, she began to think that the friend who had brought the intelligence causing her brother's flight had been premature in his judgment. Her mind was, however, in a terrible state of suspense, and so unbearable did this become that our heroine resolved to go in person and ascertain whether or not there was any danger. In pursuance of this resolution she cast about her a shawl, and concealing the weapon so unceremoniously left her by her brother she unlocked the door leading to the hall and stepped boldly forth. Finding that the faithful Rosa was following close behind her, she said:</p> 
               <p>"Rosa, you stay here; I will go alone, for your presence, under the circumstances, might but serve to increase our danger."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, Miss Eleanor!" exclaimed Rosa, in earnest tones, and seeking as she spoke to restrain her mistress, "don't you go! Let me go, and you stay here! I'll come right straight back, and then if anything happens it'll only be me, you know! Now, Missey, let me go! You'll get hurt sartin, ef you go!"</p> 
               <p>Eleanor's education had always led her to the belief that a slave was incapable of showing any of those higher and admirable qualities of human nature which were thought to be exclusively attributes of the superior white race. Here, however, she had a most practical refutation of the hackneyed assertion. Our heroine's mind was one, however, not easily satisfied with any evidence that might be incomplete, and therefore, on the instant, now that the question was raised, she determined to put her servant to the test. Not that she feared to face danger herself, for she was as brave as she was beautiful; but she might never again have an opportunity so good as the present of satisfactorily settling for herself a mooted question.</p> 
               <p>"You are a noble girl, Rosa," she said, turning to her servant, "and you may go, as you desire it, but, above all things, do not become frightened, and if there is any real danger hurry back immediately, and we will then look to our escape."</p> 
               <p>"Yes, Miss Eleanor, I'll mind all that, God bless you!"</p> 
               <p>As she spoke Rosa bounded from the side of her young mistress, and<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC5561-00000006"/> went flying along the hall and down the stairway on her perilous mission. She was absent some fifteen or twenty minutes, and a shade of apprehension for her safety had just crossed our heroine's mind when she returned with light footsteps and a lighter heart. She scarcely entered the parlor, where Miss Poindexter was anxiously awaiting her, before she exclaimed, in joyous tones:</p> 
               <p>"Why, Missey, you'se been scared all for nuthin'. The people's not agoin' to hurt nobody. They'se only hurrahin' an' hollerin' for the 'Merican flag an' Major Anderson. I went right round through the middle of 'em, in the middle of the street, an' right round the corner ag'in through George's street, an' they didn't even say nuthin' to me!"</p> 
               <p>Though the words of Rosa relieved Eleanor from the dread of personal danger, they awakened at the same time within her the deepest chagrin for the cowardice of her brother Henry, who, without staying to ascertain what foundation there was for the report of his dastard friend, had fled with the latter on the first intimation of peril, and had deliberately left her to meet death or perhaps a worse fate, for History had recorded that mobs were capable of the most heinous crimes. However, she had now nothing to fear, and her mind, consequently, was left free to contemplate a matter the settlement of which the action of the slave girl had fixed.</p> 
               <p>Our heroine reasoned thus: "Rosa has been raised from her birth in bondage. She has been prohibited by law from being educated. She has been every day of her life taught to consider herself an inferior being; to consider herself as born and reared for the sole object of serving her superior white owners. In short, she has been taught to consider herself an intelligent brute-nothing more! Yet in spite of these disadvantages she has this very hour exhibited traits of character of which the most highly educated whites would justly be proud. What a contrast between her and my haughty, domineering brother, whom, at least until now, I had always looked upon as a hero."</p> 
               <p>"Rosa," said she to the slave, "what caused you to go down stairs in place of me; did you not suppose that you would be killed by the mob?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, Missey, I know'd all that, but I loved you to much to let you go. I'd sooner be killed twenty times over than have any hurt come to you, Miss Eleanor, God bless you!"</p> 
               <p>This reply was uttered in such earnest tones that it needed not the poor slave's gush of tears to stamp it as sincere.</p> 
               <p>"Rosa, would you like to be free?" asked Eleanor, as her own feelings began to well up within her.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, Miss Eleanor," exclaimed Rosa, with sparkling eyes, "'deed an' 'deed I would! Fur then I'd work very hard, and save up, and give Massa Poindexter all my money for mother, so that she'd be free too!"</p> 
               <p>"Slave, then, you shall be no longer!" said our beautiful heroine, in accents that showed she had forever swept from her mind prejudices and opinions which had been inculcated there by lifelong education and custom. "To-morrow I will have your manumission papers duly made out, and then I shall immediately return home. Hereafter, Rosa, I will pay you four dollars a week,<pb n=""/> and you must learn to depend on yourself."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, Miss Eleanor!" burst from the lips of the delighted Rosa, "God bless you! God bless you! and then I can save up, my wages an' buy my poor old mother, and she won't be a slave no more! Oh, God bless you, Miss Eleanor, God bless you, again!" And the poor, elated child of bondage, already freed from the degrading shackles, shed grateful tears on the lily hand of her young mistress, which she kissed over and over.</p> 
               <p>Ere proceeding further with our narrative we may state for the information of the reader that Miss Eleanor Poindexter had, at the time of which we write, been in possession for more than a year of a large plantation in Tennessee, bequeathed to her by her uncle Harrison Poindexter. All the slaves thereon, of which there were a hundred and seventy-five, the testator had devised to his brother Robert, our heroine's father, with the exception of Rosa, who was to accompany the plantation, and who consequently belonged to Eleanor. Harrison Poindexter's niece was past twenty-one when she became the possessor of her uncle's valuable estate, and, of course, was perfectly competent in law to attend to her own affairs. None could, therefore gainsay her legal right to strike the manacles from her slave Rosa, and thus make her a free agent.</p> 
               <p>The next day the first duty performed by Eleanor Poindexter was that of emancipating Rosa, and she was amply, thrice amply, repaid on beholding the extravagant joy of the latter when the magic document was placed in her hands. Our heroine next settled the hotel bill, and without waiting for the reappearance of her brother Henry set out on her return home. She left a letter for him, however, with the cashier, in which she simply stated her intentions, and extended to him some sisterly advice concerning courage and patriotism.</p> 
               <p>Before night fell she was nearly one hundred miles on her way to her father's home, the celebrated Palmetto Plantation, on the banks of the Savannah river. All along the road she met with the same excitement and confusion as she had left in Philadelphia. At every station anxious crowds would besiege the train and ask a thousand vain questions concerning the new and the impending war; and until she entered Southern territory she was everywhere greeted by the display of the national flag, or at least some makeshift for it, for the reader doubtless remembers what a sudden scarcity of bunting arose from the unprecedented demand for that material by the patriotic.</p> 
               <p>After passing through the most northern counties of Maryland, however, Eleanor lost sight altogether of the Stars and Stripes. As though swayed by one universal frenzy, the inhabitants now exhibited none but State flags, or nondescript banners, made by ambitious and inventive geniuses who hoped to see their various designs adopted as the grand standard for the opening rebellion. Though pained to the soul by this, Eleanor Poindexter was possessed of discretion enough to remain a silent spectator of the violent scenes by which she found herself continually surrounded.</p> 
               <p>Upon arriving in Richmond our<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC5561-00000007"/> heroine was surprised to find a telegraphic dispatch from her brother Henry awaiting her arrival. Henry was aware that she would most likely stop at a certain hotel there, and thither he had directed the dispatch. It must have passed her on the road not three hours before, as it had been received only that morning. It was a request that she should stop in Richmond until the next mail brought her a letter from Philadelphia. Eleanor promptly returned a message, inquiring of the cashier at the Continental Hotel, Philadelphia, whether Mr. Henry Poindexter was still there or had started home. An answer came in due time that <emph>he had hastily set out on his return!</emph> The same train, therefore, that would bring the letter referred to would bring also her dastard brother, and now she became fearful of him, for she knew him to be of a bitter and relentless temperament and he had manifested a most suspicious alacrity to overtake her and also to conceal his movement.</p> 
               <p>Originally our heroine had intended to stop a few days in Richmond to visit some relations residing in the city; but now she quickly altered her intention, and taking the next train south she hurried homeward, and succeeded in reaching Palmetto Plantation without being overtaken by her brother.</p> 
               <p>As might be expected her father was amazed upon beholding his daughter thus back full two months before he had expected her, and unaccompanied by her brother, to whom he had given the strictest injunctions to travel with and protect her. His amazement was increased, too, when he learned that Eleanor had journeyed all the way from Philadelphia attended only by Rosa; and the incensed father plied our heroine with a thousand varied questions, to all of which she replied simply and truthfully, seeking neither to conceal nor aggravate her brother's dastardly conduct. She wisely said nothing, however, respecting the telegram that reached her at Richmond, on account of her father's anger; and for the same reason, and also because Mr. Poindexter was an intensely pro-slavery man, she remained silent about Rosa's emancipation.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <head>CHAPTER III.</head> 
               <head type="sub">ELEANOR IN TROUBLE.</head> 
               <p>ON the afternoon on which our heroine reached home, her father was obliged to ride some distance across the country to attend to an important matter of business. Eleanor was exceedingly sorry for this, because she was fearful that each succeeding hour would bring her brother, and of him she had, since leaving Richmond, conceived an inexplicable yet terrible dread which all her efforts were unavailing to shake off. One fact, too, that added a degree of intensity to this dread was the absence of her mother, who was spending a few days at the house of a friend in Savannah. Eleanor's only hope rested on the continued non-arrival of Henry, and, to judge from the closeness of his pursuit, this was but frail.</p> 
               <p>The next day Henry's sister was sitting at the window of her chamber, from which an uninterrupted view of the country could be had for miles. As she sat thus, gazing forth upon the luxuriance of the scenery, she could not help thinking how soon it might be desolated should the war, which was now fairly opened, be carried to the bitter extremity.</p> 
               <p>"Oh," said she, in low tones of soliloquy, "how awful is the contemplation of such a future! Sword and fire will devastate fairer scenes than this. Sons, torn from dependent mothers, will be ruthlessly slaughtered! Husbands, dragged from their wives and little ones, will be tumbled lifeless into the yawning burying-trenches of distant battle-fields! Families now united and happy will then be broken up and scattered abroad, never to gather again around the same hearthstone! All the landmarks of society will be washed away in a deluge of blood! Such, such, alas! must be the result!"</p> 
               <p>Eleanor closed her eyes as though to shut out the scene of misery and desolation her fancy so vividly portrayed to her, and a shudder thrilled through her whole frame. Alas, how fearfully true has that picture of Eleanor's prophetic imagination become! Upon the Moloch-altar of Treason every family in the Confederate States has been forced to offer up its first-born, ay, and its youngest also. Such a repulsive scene, though as yet it had no existence in fact, was more than our tenderly-nurtured heroine could endure, and, starting up, she glanced far out over the country, upon which the bright sun was smiling so brightly, to dispel the delusion.</p> 
               <p>As she did so her quick eye caught sight of a person riding up the shaded avenue toward the mansion. A full view of the new-comer could only be had at certain intervals, where the trees forming the avenue were not so luxuriant in their foliage as usual, and through one of these Eleanor directed her anxious gaze. Whether actuated by the same curiosity as herself, our heroine knew not, but, directly in the interval through which she was gazing, the stranger slackened his animal's<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC5561-00000008"/> mal's pace in order to glance up at the casement of Miss Poindexter's room.</p> 
               <p>Those handsome upturned features, wreathed as they were in a meaning smile, were her brother's, and Eleanor grew faint at the discovery. Her feelings belonged to that class of emotions, inexplicable in themselves, but yet tenaciously holding their place when once possessing the mind; and, startling as it may appear, she actually found herself wishing for a weapon. It would, however, be an injustice on our part to fail to record the fact that our heroine most strenuously exerted herself to cast from her this repulsive feeling. But the more she endeavored to do so the deeper hold did it take upon her. For her to display it, however, would be to place herself on a level lower even than that occupied by Henry himself, and so she quickly resolved to face the latter.</p> 
               <p>In pursuance of this resolution, she descended promptly to the supper-room when the tea-bell rang, and took her place at the table, at which it became her duty to preside.</p> 
               <p>To her astonishment her brother did not present himself, and in consequence, besides herself, there were only Freddy and Mary Poindexter, a younger brother and sister, to keep her company. After the conclusion of the meal, she made inquiries concerning Henry, and learned that shortly after arriving home he had set forth to join his father. This intelligence, while it relieved our heroine of her anxiety in one point of view, served only to increase it in another. A mere desire to see his father could not have actuated Henry to a long, exhausting ride after just completing a forced journey, and there was no matter of sufficient importance to demand so speedy an interview, for Mr. Poindexter was to return the next day. The only interpretation, therefore, which presented itself to our heroine, as the correct one, was that her brother wished to say something to her father about the events that had caused her to so hastily return home. Yet why could he not await the coming of her father?</p> 
               <p>For once, in her life, Eleanor was obliged to acknowledge to herself an overweening curiosity as to the reason for her brother's extra journey. Until his return this curiosity, however, could not be satisfied, and so naught was left her but to conjecture, which in truth, we must add, she did not cease to do until the moment she beheld her father and brother coming up the avenue toward the house arm-in-arm. Upon Henry's features she noted the same half-satisfied, half-menacing smile that rested thereon the day previous, while upon her father's she noted a calm sternness more terrible than the fiercest frown.</p> 
               <p>"Eleanor," said Mr. Poindexter, scarcely parting his tightly compressed lips, and refusing the kiss which his loving daughter proffered him, "I wish to see you in the library immediately!"</p> 
               <p>Eleanor stood like one petrified, and gazed after her father and brother, as the two passed on to the apartment referred to, with emotions that neither pen nor pencil could truly depict.</p> 
               <p>Robert Poindexter had always loved his children dearly, and especially Eleanor, who, whenever he left home or returned, was always the first to receive his kiss. His strange conduct, therefore, on the present occasion was the more inexplicable, and<pb n=""/> was rendered more offensively personal to our heroine by the following incident: as he reached the hall-way that traversed the middle of the mansion, Freddy and Mary, his two youngest children, who had in playful glee concealed themselves here, bounded from their ambush with merry shouts of welcome and made him prisoner. Bending down he embraced and saluted each of them in a loving manner, and then releasing them, turned and somewhat impatiently beckoned Eleanor to follow him.</p> 
               <p>Already had the scalding tears, springing from our heroine's heaving bosom, begun to course down her cheeks, but the last gesture of her father, accompanied by that unparental expression of countenance, instantly dammed the torrent, which, thus suddenly arrested in its flow, chafed within fair Eleanor's breast like a tempestuous sea. Conscious of her innocence of any crime, and out to the heart by her father's uninquiring displeasure, the proud girl dashed away every tear from her bright eyes, and then hastened to obey the imperative order of her parent. Entering the library, she stepped with quiet dignity to the corner of a rosewood book-case, against which she partially leaned for support, while Mr. Poindexter closed and locked the door. Henry had gone to one of the windows, and stood thereat, looking carelessly out, or rather merely affecting to do so. He kept his face averted from his sister, which fact the latter was not slow to notice.</p> 
               <p>"Eleanor," commenced our heroine's father, coming forward and placing a chair near her, "be seated. I have something of importance to say to you. Here, Henry!" he continued, addressing his son, "sit you here by me."</p> 
               <p>Young Poindexter hastened to obey, but in taking the proffered seat, with a seemingly unintentional carelessness, moved it so that it would only partially face Eleanor.</p> 
               <p>"I thank you, papa," said the latter, in reply to her father, "but, with your pleasure, I prefer to stand where I am."</p> 
               <p>The paleness that overspread Eleanor's lovely features as she spoke, and the tremor in her tones, were not caused by fear, but by her wounded feelings. Her parent's treatment was a thorn driven into a tender heart, and each moment it rankled deeper and became more painful.</p> 
               <p>"I wish you to be seated, Eleanor," answered Mr. Poindexter, adding a fresh degree of sternness to his manner.</p> 
               <p>Eleanor bowed and stepped forward to the chair that was set for her. Instead, however, of immediately seating herself thereon she moved it from where it stood to a spot directly in front of her cowardly brother, who could not conceal his surprise, that found expression in a perceptible start.</p> 
               <p>Our heroine felt perfectly assured that she owed her harsh treatment by her father directly to her brother, and in the scene which was about to ensue she determined to have the dastard at least to face her.</p> 
               <p>"Eleanor," said Mr. Poindexter, fastening his eyes upon his daughter, "I have received an account of you from your brother Henry that has angered me beyond anything I have heard of for many a year, and from which you must satisfactorily clear yourself before you can again be instated in my favor."</p> 
               <pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC5561-00000009"/> 
               <p>Eleanor thought she partially suspected what the offense really was, and, as her conscience assured her that she was right, she felt calm, and perfectly convinced that she could prove the correctness of her conduct by the force of her argument. Little, however, did she dream of the snare that had been so adroitly set around and sprung upon her by Henry.</p> 
               <p>"Pray, dear papa," she therefore replied, "what have I done thus to incur such cutting, and, I may add, such undeserved treatment as you have just bestowed upon me without even asking a single question?"</p> 
               <p>"Can it be!" exclaimed Mr. Poindexter, in tones of impatient anger, "that you, Eleanor, whom I have had educated with such care, and nurtured so tenderly, should now, instead of confessing what you have done and asking my forgiveness, seek to prevaricate?"</p> 
               <p>"Your words astonish me, my dear papa!" exclaimed Eleanor, "I prevaricate! About what? Did I not inform you truthfully why I returned home after being deserted by Henry here, to whom, I do not doubt, I owe your displeasure?"</p> 
               <p>Mr. Poindexter silently regarded his daughter with apparent perplexity for a few moments, and then resumed:</p> 
               <p>"Eleanor, when I, at your reiterated desire sent you on your Northern tour with your brother Henry, I intended it to be one of pleasure in each other's companionship. You remember I told you, distinctly, that I did not wish you to form any permanent acquaintances in the North, most especially of the opposite sex, as I wished you at the proper time to wed some Southern gentleman, a man in whose breast love for the South and her institutions should be paramount. With this restriction I left you entirely free as to the person of your choice."</p> 
               <p>"And I did not disobey you, dear papa!" exclaimed our heroine, with a start, for she saw from her father's words and tones how fierce and uncontrollable his anger would become should he learn at the moment of her action in regard to Rosa. She saw, also, that her cowardly and vindictive brother had hatched up some tale against her for the sake of covering up his craven conduct in deserting her, or for some other and worse motive.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, my dear sister!" suddenly ejaculated Henry at this instant, with an air of hypocritical astonishment that would have deceived the shrewdest observer, "how can you say that and hope to be believed? Did you not on several occasions accompany Mr. Drayton, who is a well-known Philadelphia abolitionist, to various places of amusement and also out driving?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes," replied Eleanor, fixing her flashing eyes upon her brother, who quailed not, alas! in his villainy, "but you always knew of it. And, besides, he was so gentlemanly and courteous and attentive, while you were always away either at the club-house or the academy. But even if I did allow Mr. Drayton's visits I intended no permanent acquaintance with him, for, though I could enjoy his company as a passing friend, I could never, even with papa's permission, accept him as a suitor."</p> 
               <p>"Henry," said Mr. Poindexter, turning to his son, "as this is the first time you have seen your sister since your return, just narrate in full the<pb n=""/> account you gave me; and you, Eleanor, refute it if you can, which I hope you can and will."</p> 
               <p>"It pains me to do so," rejoined Henry, with a fresh display of hypocrisy, "but my duty to you, father, and to Eleanor herself, demands that I should-not to mention the utter necessity of my own vindication."</p> 
               <p>Our heroine's proud spirit was now fully roused, and a smile of scorn and disdain flitted upon her pale features as her brother proceeded. Yet, notwithstanding his outrageous falsifying, she retained her silence to the end of his narrative, in which he accused her of the most unbecoming conduct with Mr. Drayton, who, by a strange coincidence, had taken passage in the same train Southward as she had.</p> 
               <p>He plausibly accounted for his apparent desertion of Eleanor by saying that the mob had already started upstairs in search of him, and that, fearful if they reached the room he was in with her at the crisis that they would maltreat her on his account, he and his friend rushed down to meet the ruffians after leaving her his best weapon, the revolver, in case the ruse should prove unavailing. With naught but his bowie-knife he had hewed his way through the cut-throats, followed by his friend, and had succeeded in drawing them away in another direction. After flying and fighting for several squares, he and his friend were finally overtaken. In the confusion that ensued the latter was most likely killed, while he, slipping up a dark alley and leaping several fences, made his escape without much injury. He had been unable, owing to the excitement in the city, to return to the hotel for two whole days, and when he did he was horrified by finding that Eleanor and Mr. Drayton were gone.</p> 
               <p>He could not certainly ascertain that they went in company, or else he would have sought out Drayton to the ends of the earth and taken his heart's blood, but they certainly left the city in the same southward bound train.</p> 
               <p>He had then instantly telegraphed to Richmond, asking his sister, who could not yet have reached there, to wait for his arrival. Instead of complying, however, she had immediately hurried away. On the books of the hotel where she stopped he found Mr. Drayton's name entered <emph>as arriving on the selfsame</emph> day. This fact could be proved simply by referring to the book itself.</p> 
               <p>Such conduct he thought very unlady-like, besides being unsisterly. In conclusion, he begged of Eleanor to acknowledge her fault and seek her father's forgiveness. As for himself he had already forgiven her, for he loved her too deeply to do otherwise.</p> 
               <p>Several times during the recital of this base concoction our heroine, with the hot blood mounting to her temples, was on the point of starting to her feet and giving her vile brother the lie direct, but as many times she sank back, overcome and appalled by his heartless conduct. He had evidently, however, and somewhat to Eleanor's relief, heard nothing of Rosa's emancipation, for if he had he would most assuredly have imparted the fact to her father, whose already excessive wrath would in that case scarcely have retained bounds.</p> 
               <p>In his anxiety to convince his father of his sincerity and truthfulness Henry Poindexter rose from his chair<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC5561-00000010"/> as he concluded, And, stepping to Eleanor, actually took her hand, and was about to implore her, in language that he had well studied beforehand, to acknowledge her guilt and obtain her father's forgiveness. Instantly as she felt his touch, however, Eleanor sprang to her feet, and, pushing him away from her, eyed him with a look of the most contemptuous loathing and scorn, as she exclaimed in bitter accents:</p> 
               <p>"Away, foul, perjured man! Infamous creatures who, for no greater reasons than to cover up a cowardly act and his own neglect, would not hesitate to blast a sister's character; to tear asunder the ties of love which bind a father to his child; to bring the gray hairs of the one with sorrow to the grave, and crush the heart and reputation of the other beneath a load of infamy! Touch me not, hideous reptile! The puff-adder rather would I call brother than you! Away! touch me not!"</p> 
               <p>And the beautiful girl, almost insane with rage, sprang back several paces and stood gazing with burning eyes upon the brother, whom she well styled "hideous reptile."</p> 
               <p>Henry's calculations had included some such crisis as this, and he had accordingly schooled himself to meet it.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, father," he exclaimed, in broken accents well assumed, "Eleanor, I fear, has lost her reason! None other than a maniac would have conducted herself for the last few weeks as she has done! Alas, I fear that monster Drayton has thrown his blighting spell upon our dear, sweet Eleanor!"</p> 
               <p>Mr. Poindexter was a man of impulse rather than reason. The first casual glance at a matter, if it seemed to him at the time to be correct, would decide his opinion, and from that nothing could hardly shake him. Therefore he was overbearing and unreasonable. His son, knowing his exact disposition, had carefully prepared every point of his vile story, and imparted it to him with every art which deceit could suggest to carry his point. So complete was the statement, and so well hung too, that Mr. Poindexter had immediately credited it, formed his opinion at once, and condemned his daughter. This was why he repulsed her so sternly upon returning from his journey across the country. As a natural result, when what he chose to call her guilt was brought so decisively home to her, he expected her to fall upon her knees and beg his pardon. But a contrary result he never dreamed of, and consequently, when he beheld Eleanor's fierce repulse to her accuser, he concluded that she was guilty and sought to save herself by a display or anger.</p> 
               <p>Henry's deeply studied remark, however, touched a chord in his father's heart that partially thrilled with mercy toward Eleanor, and he instantly shifted half the culpability from her to Drayton. His duty, however, he thought was plainly indicated to him.</p> 
               <p>"What have you to say, Eleanor, to what you have heard?" asked he, in tones much softened as he saw his child's tearless, speechless anguish.</p> 
               <p>"That all Henry has uttered," replied our heroine, unfalteringly, "is a vile fabrication, built up for some sinister purpose of his own on one or two distorted and misrepresented facts! I call Heaven to witness its<pb n=""/> falsity! Beyond what you heard from me concerning Mr. Drayton, I know nothing! If he came south in the same train that I did, I am not aware of it! If he put up at the same hotel in Richmond, I never knew it. I never saw him there!"</p> 
               <p>"Did you not receive a telegram in Richmond from Henry?" asked Mr. Poindexter.</p> 
               <p>"I did," replied Eleanor, "but it asked me to wait for a letter, and not for him. In it he never mentioned his coming!"</p> 
               <p>"Why did you not tell <emph>me</emph> concerning it when you first saw me?"</p> 
               <p>"Because you were just leaving home, and there was consequently no time to do so. I say again that I answered truthfully all the questions you then asked me."</p> 
               <p>What rejoinder Mr. Poindexter would have made to his daughter, or what new hypocritical exclamation was ready on the lips of the villain Henry, it is alike impossible to say, for just at this moment the voice of Mrs. Poindexter, who had just returned home, was heard without, calling to her husband to open the door.</p> 
               <p>Eleanor's father drew the bolt, and the next moment our heroine's mother stood surveying the scene before her with astonishment. She had divested herself of her bonnet and traveling shawl, and held in her hand a paper which was rolled up.</p> 
               <p>"What may this mean?" she asked, handing the document to her husband, who was nearest, "have you been giving Eleanor permission to do this, Robert? And, by-the-by, why are you home so soon, Henry and Eleanor-you were to stay two months yet."</p> 
               <p>Had Mrs. Poindexter known what had just passed, she would never have added fuel to the flame by introducing the subject she thus so innocently did. But it was too late! She had sprung a fearful mine beneath the feet of Eleanor, whom she loved so dearly, from which the latter could not be rescued.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC5561-00000011"/> 
               <head>CHAPTER IV.</head> 
               <head type="sub">A STARTLING EXPOSURE.</head> 
               <p>MR. POINDEXTER, upon taking the paper from the hand of his wife, noticed before unrolling it its new appearance, as though it had just come from the lawyer's office. As may be supposed it was not long ere its contents were spread before his eager eyes, and in a moment he scanned their purport. Livid with rage did his countenance become, and striding to his daughter he seized her roughly by the arm, and, placing the document before her, hissingly exclaimed:</p> 
               <p>"See, base girl! this is one fruit of your association with that vile abolitionist Drayton, and what the next may be Heaven only knows! You emancipate and forever declare free your slave Rosa, believing that she has as much right to be free as yourself! Yes, yes! so she has, for you should be the inmate of a mad-house or a penitentiary! And you shall be till your aberrated reason comes back to you! You shall be!"</p> 
               <p>And the enraged father, crumpling up the deed of Rosa's emancipation, thrust it into his daughter's face, and shook her at the same time so fiercely as to loosen even the hold he had taken of her.</p> 
               <p>Without a word Eleanor, so brutally and senselessly used by her inconsiderate father, bounded across the space that separated her from her mother, and flinging one arm about the latter, said:</p> 
               <p>"Dearest mother, will you protect me from this violence until I can prove my innocence, or at least until my father can treat me somewhat better than a brute?"</p> 
               <p>"Silence!" thundered Mr. Poindexter, striding toward Eleanor, "you prove your innocence! You cannot, dare not attempt it! at least of this, base girl! Here is proof positive of your commission of a crime for which alone I would disown you forever! for which alone I ought to take your miserable existence!"</p> 
               <p>This fearfully harsh language, accompanied as it was by menacing gestures, was more than the poor, persecuted girl could endure, and, losing control of herself entirely, she tore herself loose from her mother's embracing arms, flung herself wildly upon her knees before her father, and, in a paroxysm of grief, exclaimed:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, my father, if your heart has become so hardened as to insult me thus, to condemn me of such heinous offenses as I never dreamed of, take my life! If you ought to take my miserable existence, here is my heart. Strike home! strike home! and with my dying breath I will proclaim my innocence of the charges laid against me by the reptile who calls himself my brother! He left me in the midst of danger to save himself; left me to death, or what other fate he did not wait to see! And you, my father, on whose strong arm I thought to lean for protection, you, without so much as hearing me in my own defense, threaten me with death! I fear you<pb n=""/> not! I fear no death! Strike here! Strike here, man! Here, father, plant your unjust vengeful steel!"</p> 
               <p>With these wildly spoken words our distracted heroine, striking her palpitating bosom, sank forward, with hysterical sobs, until her disheveled tresses lay about his feet.</p> 
               <p>In another moment her bewildered, yearning mother sprang to her, and, raising her upon her feet, said to her husband:</p> 
               <p>"For shame, Robert! Have you no heart? You have killed our Eleanor! Here, Henry," she continued, to her son, "come, take your sister's arm, and assist me to place her upon the sofa."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, no, no!" gasped Eleanor, in tones of horror, "do not let his hand come upon me! Sooner would I feel the hand of Satan himself! This is all his work! Oh, God! I am dying; forgive my enemies-my father-my brother!"</p> 
               <p>Nature was exhausted, and, with the meek words of forgiveness on her pale lips, Eleanor, thinking that she really was expiring, sank swooning upon the sofa to which her mother had just gotten her.</p> 
               <p>Robert Poindexter, as he beheld this sad result, and as the angelic words of his child rang in his ears asking the forgiveness of Heaven upon him, his feelings revolted, and he fell on her neck, and covered her cold, marble features with kisses, upbraiding himself and son the meanwhile for causing her death.</p> 
               <p>The vile Henry-whose real design has yet to be made known-conscious of the wicked part he had taken in the sad affair, stood aloof, and did not so much as place a finger upon his sister, fearful that if he did the act would recall the pure soul to the inanimate form to curse him. It was necessary, however, that the deceptive vail which he had drawn over his parent's perception should remain intact. With this object, therefore, he hastened away to obtain some restoratives, with which he soon returned. These were lavishly applied, and manifested their power by shortly bringing Eleanor back to consciousness.</p> 
               <p>When our heroine had fully recovered she turned to her father, and in reply to a question of his she said, in the tones of one whose determination was irrevocably taken:</p> 
               <p>"Father, I freely forgive you, but I can not longer stay beneath a roof where I can never again enjoy any peace of mind. I am my own mistress, a fact which both you and Henry seem to ignore, and I shall therefore use my undoubted rights."</p> 
               <p>Though deeply sorry for what he had done, Mr. Poindexter's ungovernable temper would not allow him to submit to opposition, or to be taken to task even by Eleanor, and in a moment his anger was rekindled. And as though fate had determined to bring on another and final crisis, Rosa, who had been absent on an errand for her mistress, came bounding into the library in search of her.</p> 
               <p>"Here, you insolent wench!" exclaimed Mr. Poindexter, "Stop, why didn't you tell me that your mistress had given you your freedom?"</p> 
               <p>"Because, Massa Poindexter," answered Rosa, somewhat taken aback, "you wasn't here. But I'ze agoin' to save up my wages an' buy my mother from you, Massa, so she'll be free, too."</p> 
               <p>"You are, are you," hissed Eleanor's<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC5561-00000012"/> father, in a fearful rage, "take that for your impudence;" and striking the inoffensive slave a heavy blow in the face, he sent her stumbling and reeling across the room.</p> 
               <p>Eleanor's temper, though slow to rouse, was not unlike her father's when it was roused, and this act of Mr. Poindexter stirred his daughter's very soul. Springing to her feet, she exclaimed:</p> 
               <p>"Father, do not repeat that! You had no legal right to strike Rosa, even when she was a slave! And now that I have made her free I myself even have no right to do so!"</p> 
               <p>"Free! free!" thundered the furious man, "I'll flay the wench within a hair's breadth of her life!"</p> 
               <p>As he spoke Eleanor's father seized a whip that chanced to be near at hand, and bounded toward Rosa with the intention of putting his threat into execution.</p> 
               <p>In an instant, however, and even as the upraised lash was about to descend, the passionate father was transfixed with horror. Over poor, crouching Rosa stood Eleanor Poindexter, her eyes burning with intense fire, her cheeks ashy pale, and her disordered tresses floating carelessly about her shoulders. In her hand she firmly held the revolver so incontinently dropped by her dastard brother in the Philadelphia hotel. The hammer of the weapon was thrown back, the nipple capped, the muzzle pressed hard against Eleanor's own bosom, and the lovely girl's finger firmly embracing the fatal trigger.</p> 
               <p>"One stroke," she said, in tones of frightful composure, between her compressed lips, "and as there is a God in heaven I die, forced to the act by your insane rage and injustice"!</p> 
               <p>The stern, self-devoting, and unyielding heroism of his daughter overcame Mr. Poindexter, when everything else failed, and as he stood trembling at her desperate and perilous situation-for a nervous twitch of her finger, no matter how slight, would end her existence-he admired her bravery.</p> 
               <p>Flinging from him the whip, he exclaimed: "Away with your weapon, Eleanor; you have conquered!"</p> 
               <p>Without another word he strode from the library to his own private room, where he shut himself up during the rest of the day, refusing entrance even to his wife.</p> 
               <p>Not until her father had entirely disappeared from sight did our heroine remove the deadly weapon with which she had in her excitement threatened her own life, and then, calmly restoring it to the concealment from which she had taken it, she bade Rosa to rise.</p> 
               <p>"Mother," she said, stooping and picking up the deed of emancipation that lay crushed and torn on the floor where her father had thrown it, "how came you to have possession of this document?"</p> 
               <p>"I found it,"' replied Mrs. Poindexter, "upon the dressing-bureau in my room. I could not tell what to make of it, I saw your signature, and still I thought it was nothing more than a joke on your part, until I noticed the legal seal stamped upon it. I immediately brought it down stairs, not aware even that you had returned, and imprudently enough brought about the terrible scene that has just been enacted. But, Eleanor, my dearest child, what is the matter? You carrying a deadly weapon! You must explain all to me, for everything<pb n=""/> is a mystery to me. This loathing, too, of your brother Henry, so unnatural-what means it all?"</p> 
               <p>"Come, my dear mother," replied Eleanor, passing her arm about Mrs. Poindexter and moving toward the door, "let us go to your room. I have much to impart to you; my heart is well-nigh broken. However, one moment, I must speak to Rosa! Rosa," continued the fair girl, leaving her mother just outside the door and returning to the still frightened mulattress, "did you give that book to Miss St. Aubyn?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, Miss Eleanor," replied Rosa, "an' as I was comin' back from there I met a genl'man, who poked this letter into my hand an' told me to give it to you right away."</p> 
               <p>Rosa spoke in so low a tone that Henry, who stood with his back toward her, could not hear what she said. And even had he been watching her he could not have detected her slipping a small white envelope to her mistress, so quickly and adroitly was the act performed.</p> 
               <p>"Very well, Rosa," answered Eleanor, taking the envelope and concealing it, "you can go down to the quarters now and see your mother."</p> 
               <p>"Thank you, Miss Eleanor," replied Rosa, quickly comprehending that the permission thus given was a partial order, and yet unable to perceive the reason for it. She knew that something terrible had occurred, but what it was she dared not inquire. So, courtesying to Eleanor, she hastened away to the quarters.</p> 
               <p>Our heroine was soon closeted with her mother, and in her maternal ear she poured forth the full burden of her sorrow. Mrs. Poindexter soothed her daughter, and assured her that if all the world should turn against her still would she love and cherish her.</p> 
               <p>"God in his infinite goodness bless you, dear mother!" wept Eleanor. "Your love, pure and holy, shines forth like a bright, beautiful star in the heavens where all else is so dark!"</p> 
               <p>"I have heard," said Mrs. Poindexter, after some further conversation, "from veritable sources, that Henry has become connected with bad characters. If it is so, Eleanor, and I fear it is, you must forgive him and help me to save him."</p> 
               <p>Our heroine gently shook her head, and kissing her mother said, as she turned to go to her own chamber:</p> 
               <p>"Forgive me, dearest mamma, perhaps I am rather too harsh, but I will seek repose and we will talk again to-morrow."</p> 
               <p>When Eleanor had gained the solitude of the neat little room, from whose window she had first witnessed the return of that brother who had laid such a deep, mysterious, and unaccountable plot against her, she opened the envelope that had been given to Rosa for her by the strange gentleman.</p> 
               <p>"Who can have sent it? What can it be about?" were questions that Eleanor asked herself as she unfolded the missive. To answer the first there was not even an initial, but to the second the following contents fully replied:</p> 
               <p>"MISS POINDEXTER-Your brother, Henry Poindexter, has conspired against you for the most vile and sinister purpose. Having become associated with certain bad men, he has involved himself in overwhelming debt. One of the villains, a neighbor of your father's, and a gambler, ay, worse, a <emph>murderer</emph>, James L.<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC5561-00000013"/> Santee, is Henry's principal creditor. In fact, I may say he is his only creditor, for, with the purpose of using your brother as a tool against you, he has purchased all the claims against the latter, or nearly all, and he has demanded, as a condition of release, that Henry shall influence your father to force you to an alliance with him. Your brother, dastard as he is, has consented to become the creature, the contemptible but powerful tool, of the vile Santee. You may disbelieve me, but as I hope for salvation I utter only the truth, and you will soon have proof of it.</p> 
               <p>"But fear nothing, I will protect you and warn you of every movement. Be discreet, be brave! I need not, however, urge you to bravery, for your heroic conduct, when your brother deserted you in such a cowardly manner at the Continental Hotel in Philadelphia, satisfies me that you are a true heroine.</p> 
               <p>"<emph>Above all things, keep this letter a secret even from your best friends</emph>. The snare is deeply laid for you, but again I say, 'fear not.'"---</p> 
               <p>"Do I dream, or am I bereft of reason?" murmured our heroine, after perusing the mysterious letter again and again, and pressing her hands to her temples. "My brother! oh, my brother!" she continued, in agonized tones, "who would have thought you capable of such infamy? Alas, this warning is too true! But who can the author be? Surely it cannot be that Drayton penned these lines? Stop, I have a note of his; I will compare the two!"</p> 
               <p>With trembling fingers, Eleanor ransacked some papers in her trunk, among which she presently discovered a note, that she had received from Mr. Drayton while in Philadelphia, excusing himself on one occasion from attending her to an exhibition on account of sudden indisposition; but unfortunately this had not been written by Drayton, but by an attendant, which fact was disclosed at the bottom of the billet by the line "<foreign xml:lang="LAT">per</foreign> J. C. E."</p> 
               <p>"It is preposterous, at any rate," soliloquised Eleanor, "to suppose Mr. Drayton, a man of such wealth and such refined literary culture should follow me home, and in a day learn all about a conspiracy which must have begun ere Henry and I left home. I was only introduced to him in Philadelphia. Why should I be so silly? The question, therefore, again arises, Who can be this mysterious friend who has discovered to me such a plot against my welfare and happiness? Heaven bless you, kind stranger, whoever you may be!"</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <head>CHAPTER V.</head> 
               <head type="sub">A GLIMPSE AT TWO VILLAINS.</head> 
               <p>AT the date of the opening of our life-narrative, the Southern rebellion was bursting into full and deadly bloom, and lading every pure breeze and air of Heaven with its noxious odor. Designing, wicked, and unscrupulous men were immeasurably gratified at the coming of a reign of blood and terror, for under a popular, delusive agitation, they foresaw their opportunities for giving full sway to their wickedness. Like buzzards they scented the smell of the contest from afar, and were impatient to fatten on the carrion feast.</p> 
               <p>To this class belonged James L. Santee and Henry Poindexter, the former, however, being by far the latter's superior, both in experience and abilities, although Henry was by no means unaccomplished in villainy.</p> 
               <p>Young Poindexter, naturally wayward and headstrong, had, several years before, fallen in with Santee, who, having purchased the plantation next to Robert Poindexter's, was admitted into the society of planters, and rated at half a million. The connection had resulted in Henry's ruin, and Santee soon conceived the diabolical plot of compelling his victim to crown his infamy by forcing or maneuvering a marriage between himself and the innocent, beautiful Eleanor Poindexter. It had taken Santee some time to arrange everything satisfactorily before he made the proposition to Henry, but, with consummate hypocrisy, he at last accomplished this, and finally brought Henry to the dilemma of choosing between his own and his sister's ruin, for a marriage with Santee could scarcely amount to more. He had well judged the character he was so adroitly manipulating, for no sooner was the difficulty presented to Henry, than he at once selected Eleanor as the victim in place of himself.</p> 
               <p>Instead of continuing the terrible story in our own words, however, we shall place before the reader a scene that occurred in a private room of Santee's palatial mansion, on the evening of the day on which the events narrated in tie last chapter took place.</p> 
               <p>An elegant inlaid card-table stood between the two occupants of the apartment-James L. Santee and Henry Poindexter-on which was the professional gambler's usual set-out, viz., a pack, of cards, some ivory counters, a decanter of spirits, and two richly cut glass goblets.</p> 
               <p>"Well, Harry, my boy," exclaimed Santee, in tones of rough pleasantry, "you're in deuced good luck to-night! All the aces three games hand running, which just rakes in a cool thousand for you! Spending money for a week or two, eh? I've had enough for to-night, so let's fill up and drink!"</p> 
               <p>The glasses jingled together, the rich liquor gurgled down the two worthy companions' throats, and Santee resumed:</p> 
               <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC5561-00000014"/> 
               <p>"Now, Harry, I'm ready to hear what progress you've made in the siege. I hope you did not have to beat another Continental retreat. By the by, Harry, that was rather bad. When Jenkins ran up stairs, frightened out of his wits, to tell you the mob was going to hang you, there was no demonstration whatever, except their infernal yelling and hooting for their dirty, drooping Stars and Stripes. I was in the bar-room at the time."</p> 
               <p>"Well," replied Poindexter, with a laugh, "you see I thought discretion was a good deal better than valor on that particular occasion, and so I left."</p> 
               <p>"But I ought to challenge you, Harry, for leaving our pearl behind, to be snapped up may be by that abolition <choice>
                     <sic>scroundrel</sic>
                     <corr>scoundrel</corr>
                  </choice> Drayton. He was dead in love with Eleanor, and I tell you what it is, if I had only got a chance at him some dark night, I would have slipped this into him."</p> 
               <p>The speaker displayed the hilt of a concealed bowie-knife.</p> 
               <p>"He's rather crazy, that Drayton," said Henry. "He's one of these literary geese who travel all about the country, cackling, and 'making notes,' as he calls it, upon the habits, and manners, and customs, and political tenets, and so forth and so on, of people."</p> 
               <p>"Yes, and he's a red-hot, infernal abolitionist, too!" added Santee, "and I'm no Southerner if I don't settle him quietly, if he ever happens in this vicinity!"</p> 
               <p>The concluding part of this sentence came piecemeal from between Santee's teeth, as he ground the latter together in mock rage.</p> 
               <p>"But what about the scene this afternoon?" continued the planter, "tell me that. I <emph>thought</emph> Eleanor would make a game fight of it!"</p> 
               <p>"Well, you see," answered young Poindexter, "when I got home I found I could do a good deal better than if I had overtaken Eleanor in Richmond, for father had gone over to Barrington's to settle about a lot of likely niggers. So off I went immediately after him, and had the good luck to find him in the exact humor. He was as mad as creation at first at my leaving Sis, but I explained it all to him, and then if I didn't stuff the governor, I'm a Yankee mudsill, that's all!"</p> 
               <p>"By the time I got half through I had him pretty well roused; but at the end of my yarn I had him jumping over his head; and I believe if he'd had Sis there at the moment he would have hung her instanter. And then I begged for her, but still advised him to make her ask his forgiveness, and then to make her marry a right-striped Southron, Mr. Santee, for instance, who had told me privately that he was deeply in love with Eleanor!"</p> 
               <p>"Bravo, my boy! bravo! bravissimo!" exclaimed Santee, with a hearty laugh of approval, and reaching across the table to slap the wicked brother upon the shoulder. "I feel inclined to write you a clearance for that ten thousand bond that I bought from Foster on your account. That was hard in you, Harry; but never mind, you'll see day through it yet, my boy. But go on, I feel interested in your narrative. The more I hear of Eleanor the more I desire her. Go on!"</p> 
               <p>"Well," obeyed young Poindexter, "I had the old man just worked up right, when we left Barrington's, and coming home he scowled and muttered all the way along. And didn't he bless Drayton and all the<pb n=""/> rest of the abolitionists! I knew there was a storm to break when we reached home; but I tell you what, Santee, I didn't expect the one that did come! Whew! Lord save me if I'd ever undertake such another task for double what I'm going to make by this; and it's only because I'm so bound up by your friendship that I don't leave this job half done. I tell you, Santee, honestly, I'm afraid we'll fail after all, for Eleanor's got more judgment and grit than most women have at twice her age!"</p> 
               <p>"Never say fail, my boy!" exclaimed the planter, in rallying accents. "Just go according to my instructions, and we'll make a full, clean crop; see if we don't. And then you know what depends on your success and failure!"</p> 
               <p>"Oh, I'll carry it through, even if I fail at last!" replied the heartless brother.</p> 
               <p>"That's the right way to speak, Harry! But go on, you did not finish your story, and I am anxious to hear the climax."</p> 
               <p>"When father and I went into the house," replied Poindexter, resuming the thread of his narrative, "the first one that came bounding forward to greet him-not poor me, for I was in her black books-was Eleanor. You ought to have seen the look the old man gave her, though, as he pushed her away from him, and jerked back his head to avoid her kiss. It would have made a good scene for an artist. And you ought to have heard his tone, as he ordered her into the library, to give an account of herself.</p> 
               <p>"I expected her to be frightened, but just as true as I'm here, she marched into the library as stiff as you please. Then came the tempest. She talked and raved, and denounced me; but then you know how father is, when he once gets an idea in his head, and I had taken good care to put the right idea there. I acted my part well, and had just got to the wind-up, when who should come rapping at the door but mother just returned from Savannah.</p> 
               <p>"That ruined everything!" interrupted Santee, as a shade of disappointment suddenly flitted across his sinister features.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, no, it was exactly the thing," said Henry gleefully. "When I saw her, I, like you, began to give up, for mother's the only one besides me who knows how to handle father. But she brought me good luck. It seems that, some day while in Philadelphia, Sis had gone and emancipated Rosa, the yellow waiting-maid, and had the paper regularly made out before a magistrate. The document, by some means or other, had been left on mother's bureau in her room. Rosa most likely left it there herself by some mistake. However, no matter how it got there, it got there, and mother innocently enough brought it down to father.</p> 
               <p>"As I said before, Santee, you know what father is. He was mad enough before, but when he saw this, he went up in the most approved style. Just at this moment, too, to help matters on, the wench herself came in, and father, snatching up a whip, was going to give her a flogging, when Eleanor sprang forward, and, drawing a revolver, stood over Rosa, and threatened father, if he struck the nigger, that she would shoot herself. And she was in earnest, for she pressed the pistol to her breast, and I saw the quick pulsations of her heart<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC5561-00000015"/> pushing the deadly muzzle back and forth.</p> 
               <p>"Father was more angry than I ever saw him before, but when he saw Sis do what she did he caved right in, and, throwing down the whip, left the library and I hav'nt seen anything of him since."</p> 
               <p>"Bless my soul!" exclaimed Santee, in tones of apparent ecstasy, "if Eleanor isn't a heroine it to adorn the pages of a first-class romance! Now, mark you, Harry, if I fail to get her, I'll come down on you as hard as I can. But if you succeed in getting her for me, I'll give you a full clearance and ten thousand dollars in hard cash besides."</p> 
               <p>"I will do the best I can, Santee," replied Henry Poindexter, "and you know I cannot do more. I do not see why Eleanor should not be Mrs. Santee as well as Mrs. Any-body-else. That's my candid opinion."</p> 
               <p>"Indeed, Harry," said Santee, with a leering, meaning smile, "you ought to have sufficient reason for thinking that she ought <emph>rather</emph> to be Mrs. Santee than Mrs. Any-body-else! But let me see!" he suddenly added, drawing forth his watch, "I'm half an hour behind time for an engagement I made this morning. Now, remember, Harry, don't lose your courage, and all will come out right. If anything now occurs, why, you can let me know of it immediately, and in the meantime, <foreign xml:lang="FRA">au revoir</foreign>."</p> 
               <p>Santee passed from the room, leaving Henry Poindexter, the heartless conspirator against a pure and innocent sister, to finish the glass of liquor he had just poured out for himself, and then to make his way home and slumber beneath the same roof with Eleanor.</p> 
               <p>Alas to what fearful turpitude can man sometimes descend! But to return to our heroine.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <head>CHAPTER VI.</head> 
               <head type="sub">A MYSTERIOUS FIGURE.</head> 
               <p>AFTER perusing several times the mysterious billet which contained the warning of the base intrigue against her by Santee and her brother, our heroine cast herself upon her couch and gave herself up to surmising. She asked herself how it could be possible that a crime so deadly an offense against the laws of nature so terrible, could even have been projected against one so innocent as herself. The fact, however, she could not doubt, and so all that was left to her was to marvel at Henry's turpitude. The setting sun found her musing thus painfully, and the evening star had climbed so high above the horizon as to slant its gentle rays down upon her pale face, ere she arose and bent her steps to the room of her mother to bid the latter good-night.</p> 
               <p>Mrs. Poindexter was alone and battled in tears when her daughter entered her chamber, and in a moment the <unclear>loving</unclear> girl, all forgetful of her own heavy troubles, wound her snowy arms about her mother's neck and cried:</p> 
               <p>"Why do you weep, dear mother?"</p> 
               <p>"I am mourning, my dear Eleanor," replied Mrs. Poindexter, "because I see in the future nothing but sorrow and distress, not alone in our country, but also in our own immediate family."</p> 
               <p>"Let us pray, mother," was the reverently uttered answer of our heroine, "that it may in both cases be averted."</p> 
               <p>"It is useless; Eleanor, useless," said Eleanor's mother, with a prophetic despair in her tones. "The bitter cup is already at our lips; we have had a sip of its contents, and it will not pass away until we swallow the last drop."</p> 
               <p>Whether it was that the fair girl participated in her mother's boding fears we shall not attempt to say, but the only reply she made to the last remark, was silently to press her mother closer to herself and nestle her cheek against hers.</p> 
               <p>A moment later the firm, heavy tread of Mr. Poindexter approached the chamber, and our heroine wishing to avoid a fresh interview with her violent-tempered father, exchanged a hurried kiss and "good-night" with her mother, and passed into an adjoining room. From thence, as the night was clear and beautiful, she made her way down stairs and out upon the piazza which ornamented three sides of the mansion.</p> 
               <p>As she emerged into the open air the light, cool breeze which was moving at the time greatly refreshed her, and caused her to lose a degree or two of that heaviness with which she had been so oppressed before leaving her chamber. The scene, too, spreading out before her was certainly most romantic, for the atmosphere was so fine that the gentle light that fell from the far-away stars was sufficient to make objects discernible at some distance; and yet so soft was this<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC5561-00000016"/> illumination that it filled the spectator with that dreamy, poetical pleasure that finds its cause alone in that wondrous blending of light and darkness which nature only can produce.</p> 
               <p>Drawing a rustic, antique stool into one corner of the piazza, Eleanor seated herself and directed her gaze across the lawn and through a clump of woods toward the quarters of the negroes. The latter were, as it happened, holding one of those peculiar prayer-meetings which have become a characteristic custom of their race. The wind also set in from that point of the compass, and owing to the solemn silence that reigned, our heroine could easily distinguish the tune, and oftentimes the words of the wild, sad hymn of devotion that her father's slaves were singing. She could distinguish, too, by the light of the flaring torches, whose rays flickered and flitted through the alleys of the intervening woodland, the various motions of the humble congregation. And as their weird but simple vesper song floated to her ears, her own disturbed spirit was soothed, and she felt almost happy.</p> 
               <p>She was absorbed, so much so, indeed, that she did not notice the approach of a tall figure that came gliding up the path until she was almost discovered. Quickly shrinking, however, into the deep shadow of a clustering vine that clambered luxuriantly about the corner pillar of the piazza, she succeeded in concealing her presence from the new-comer, whom, as he set foot upon the topmost step, she recognized at once as her brother Henry. She had previously judged that it was he, for none save the members of the family, or one or two of the most intimate neighbors, ever approached the house by the path referred to, which was a shorter way to reach the manor than the shaded avenue. He was just returning from the interview between himself and Santee, and seemed, from the slow, uncertain manner in which he walked, to be painfully thinking. Pausing, for a moment, on the piazza, before entering the house, he suddenly pressed one hand to his forehead, while the other still remained where it had been thrust into his breast, and exclaimed in a low, baited tone:</p> 
               <p>"Possessed of a devil! Yes; yes! it must be so! Oh, Santee!"</p> 
               <p>With these words hissingly uttered, Henry Poindexter strode into the mansion, and was lost to Eleanor's view.</p> 
               <p>Our heroine was astonished, she was amazed; and the anger that had been so justly excited within her against Henry, began to waver before a feeling of pity and forgiveness that his strange words awakened. She felt persuaded, although there was nothing in his exclamation to justify it, that he was already the victim of remorse for the harm he had worked toward her, and she experienced a pang of sorrow that she had shook her head when her mother asked her assistance in saving Henry. Alas! too angelic in her own nature even to conceive of wrong, she was incredulous enough to think that remorse must necessarily be succeeded by repentance. She resolved, therefore, on the spot, to go to Henry the next morning and conquer him into loving her again as a brother should. She even repeated over in her mind the words of affection that she would use to him.</p> 
               <p>Occupied with this idea she left<pb n=""/> the shadow of the clambering vine and stepped toward the same door by which Henry had gone in. As she did so she cast a passing glance out over the lawn, and was considerably startled by seeing at a little distance the figure of a man, who, at the same instant, seemed to have caught sight of her. In a moment he slipped up to a tree and disappeared behind it, nor did he leave his place of concealment until he heard our heroine shut to and secure the mansion door, when quickly gaining the road, he hurried away. By his strange action Eleanor was convinced that the mysterious intruder must have been following her brother, and yet for what purpose she could not surmise. Had his intention been one of assassination, he had, before reaching the house, ample opportunities which he did not improve. If he was a neighbor, he would have been accompanying instead of stealthily following Henry, and he would not, moreover, have sought such hasty concealment as he did when finding his presence observed.</p> 
               <p>Upon entering the house Eleanor rang for the porter, a stout, athletic negro, and, informing him of what she had seen, ordered him forth immediately to ascertain who the interloper was and what might be his business. Milo hesitated not a moment, but, hurrying from our heroine's presence, quickly procured a loaded gun and strode out, as he thought, for an adventure; but, much to his disappointment, he failed to find any one, and reluctantly returned to Eleanor with his report. Praising him for his alacrity and bravery, Milo's young mistress sought her chamber and prepared to pass the night. For several hours she found it impossible to sleep, but at last the soothing goddess gently enthralled her senses, and she sank into Nature's refreshing unconsciousness.</p> 
               <p>When she awoke she was surprised to find the sun well up in the heavens on his day's journey, and filling her airy room with his glorious beams. Springing quickly from her couch, Eleanor made haste to arrange her toilet, for the morning meal must have already been finished. While thus engaged a trampling of horses' hoofs struck upon her ears, and going to her lattice she opened it and looked forth.</p> 
               <p>A dozen or fourteen horsemen were just riding away down the avenue, among whom she recognized her father, her brother Henry, and their neighbor James Santee. These three were riding together in the rear of their companions, and Santee, looking up at that moment toward Eleanor's window, caught sight of our heroine ere she could withdraw. He smiled, inclined his head, and raised his cap with the easy grace of the perfectly accomplished gentleman. Eleanor could do no less than return the salutation, but she did so hastily and then immediately drew back. Scarcely had she done so when a gentle knock came to the chamber door, and, in response to her reply, she heard the voice of her maid, Rosa. Stepping forward she gave admittance to the latter, who, seizing her hand, kissed it affectionately, saying, as she did so:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, Missey Eleanor, I'se so glad you ain't sick! Missus Poindexter's gittin' right skeered 'bout you; 'deed she is! 'se been up two times 'fore dis time an' couldn't make you hyear,<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC5561-00000017"/> an' ef I hadn't 'a done it dis time yer mar waz a coming' up herse'f."</p> 
               <p>"Well, hasten down to mamma, Rosa," replied Eleanor, "and tell her that I will be with her immediately."</p> 
               <p>Rosa promptly obeyed, but she had hardly delivered her message ere the subject of Mrs. Poindexter's anxiety came tripping into the breakfast-room, and, embracing her mother, exclaimed:</p> 
               <p>"I am very sorry, mamma, that I should have kept you waiting, but indeed I did not fall asleep until nearly daylight, and I did not awaken until ten or twelve minutes ago."</p> 
               <p>"I thought such was the cause of your non-appearance, daughter," answered Eleanor's mother, caressing the lovely girl as she spoke; "and that is why I did not sooner become uneasy. But, come now, you must be ready for breakfast, for it is so much past the usual hour. Rosa, tell the cook to bring it in."</p> 
               <p>Only a few minutes elapsed ere a salver was brought in containing a small silver urn of fragrant Mocha, with the usual accompanying dishes and relishes. Mrs. Poindexter had already breakfasted, but, to please her daughter, she partook again, though very slightly. When the meal was finished, the two ladies retired to the cabinet, where they were soon deeply absorbed in conversation. It was the first opportunity they had had to converse since the exciting and almost tragic occurrence of the previous day, and that its bearing upon our narrative may be appreciated we shall record the essential points of it.</p> 
               <p>In answer to a request of Mrs. Poindexter, our heroine narrated fully everything that had taken place, from the moment of her altercation with Henry at the Continental Hotel in Philadelphia up to the mysterious event of the last evening.</p> 
               <p>A great portion of this detail, as the reader is already aware, she had yesterday imparted to her mother, but as she was much excited at that time the latter preferred to hear it again, now that her daughter was calm and collected.</p> 
               <p>"My dear Eleanor," said Mrs. Poindexter, after listening most attentively to the recital, "under the circumstances it behooves me to impart to you certain matters which have come to my ears from time to time of late. Ere proceeding, however, I feel it my duty to state that, for several years back, I have noticed at certain periods symptoms of insanity manifested by your brother Henry, and in no other manner can I account for his unnatural behavior toward you.</p> 
               <p>"Within a year, too, he has become connected with several bad characters about here, and I have reason to believe that he has committed himself in some way so as to place himself in the power of some of them. I feel well assured, also, that the principal of these villains is no other than James Santee, notwithstanding that he passes as such a high-toned, honorable man, and is held in such esteem by your father."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, my dear mother," exclaimed Eleanor, "I fear you may be doing Mr. Santee an injustice, although I must confess that sometimes, as I have looked attentively at his features, a feeling of repulse came over me. Yet this I have always set down to mere whim on my part, rather than to any good cause given therefor by<pb n=""/> him. Strangely enough, however, this peculiar, repulsive feeling to which I refer nearly always takes possession of me when he is making himself most agreeable."</p> 
               <p>"You must be aware, Eleanor," said Mrs. Poindexter, "that Santee wishes you for his wife!"</p> 
               <p>"I have for some time suspected such to be his object, mother; but I assure you such an event can never come to pass, for I do not, nor could not, love him, and I have resolved several times to frankly tell him so on the first opportunity he affords me."</p> 
               <p>"Then he has not as yet proposed to yourself?"</p> 
               <p>"Never has he breathed a syllable in that direction. Has he to any one else?"</p> 
               <p>"He has once or twice made overtures to your father, and I am sure he has favorably impressed the latter."</p> 
               <p>"You surprise me, dear mother!"</p> 
               <p>"Do you know, Eleanor," resumed Mrs. Poindexter after a short pause, "that he followed you the next day after you set out with Henry on your tour North?"</p> 
               <p>"No, I do not; I met him several times at the Continental Hotel in Philadelphia, and met him also in other cities, but never dreamed that he followed me thither. Mr. Jenkins-whose cowardice I can never forget-traveled with us to Philadelphia."</p> 
               <p>"Well, my dear, Santee not only followed you as I state, but he also endeavored, in company with Henry, to overtake you on your journey homeward. And it was he who dictated the telegraphic dispatch which you found waiting for you in Richmond. This I learned from your father, who had it from Henry himself. In this way, too, I heard of Mr. Drayton, who, it seems, made such a strong impression upon you, Eleanor. Who is he?"</p> 
               <p>"Mr. Drayton," replied our heroine, blushing somewhat at the unexpected mention of the name, "is a Northern gentleman, a native of Philadelphia. He is very wealthy and philanthropic, and spends nearly all his time traveling in different parts of the country. Why, mamma, he is as well acquainted with the region about here as you or I. His intellect and information are astonishing."</p> 
               <p>"Well, tell me, Eleanor, was it through his persuasion that you emancipated Rosa?" asked Mrs. Poindexter, half interruptingly.</p> 
               <p>"No, my dear mamma, no!" was the quick reply. "I emancipated Rosa from my own solemn conviction that she should be free; a conviction, as I have already told you, that was forced upon me in an instant, like the conversion of Saul on his way to Damascus. And, mother," continued our heroine in a deliberate tone, raising her eyes to heaven as she spoke, "if I possessed a thousand slaves, I would free them every one!"</p> 
               <p>"God prosper and bless you for those words, my daughter!" cried Mrs. Poindexter, impulsively, clasping our heroine to her bosom and imprinting a kiss upon her fair brow. "I would to God that every shackle had been loosed long, long ago, for then we would have been spared the fearful war which is about to ravish our land."</p> 
               <p>"I know," resumed Eleanor, sorrowfully, "that I have by my action deeply offended father, and that it<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC5561-00000018"/> may be turned to account by those who seek to destroy my happiness; but, mother, come what may, I am determined never to yield the position I have assumed. I believe it, I know it, to be my duty, and from it no earthly power shall swerve me!"</p> 
               <p>The conversation between Eleanor and her mother continued several hours, and ere its conclusion each had confided to the other the inmost secrets of her heart. For her mother's sake our heroine promised to forego the determination she had formed of quitting home, and, if possible, also to win her brother Henry from his wicked course. In her own mind, however, she felt that the first depended upon her father's future treatment, and that the second bordered on the impossible. From the revelations made by her mother she now looked upon Santee as a heartless monster; and by the very contrast afforded by him to Drayton we must not fail to record that the mere respect Miss Poindexter had hitherto entertained for the latter was deepened to a much stronger feeling.</p> 
               <p>After dinner Eleanor had her favorite horse saddled and rode over to visit Miss St. Aubyn, the daughter of a gentleman residing about a mile and a half from Palmetto Plantation. It will be remembered that Rosa was returning from Miss St. Aubyn's when met by the mysterious stranger who had given her the strange letter of warning for Eleanor.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <head>CHAPTER VII.</head> 
               <head type="sub">A STRANGE ADVENTURE.</head> 
               <p>OUR heroine had accomplished about half the distance between Palmetto Plantation and the St. Aubyn estate without meeting a human being. But, just as she reached a bridle-path that led down to the main road out of a stretch of timber land, she encountered a man riding slowly and with apparent caution toward her. As he caught sight of her he reined in his horse for a moment, as though to ascertain who she might be, or whether she was alone, and then came quickly forward. She did not, however, alter the pace of her own animal, and consequently she was a little distance beyond the end of the bridle-path ere the unknown rider came out of the woods upon the road. The next moment she heard her name repeated by the horseman, who in addition requested her to stop a moment as he wished to speak to her.</p> 
               <p>Eleanor immediately checked her spirited steed, brought him half way round, and held him in this position until the stranger approached close enough to speak. As the latter came up, our heroine scrutinized his countenance, or at least what she could see of it between the broad rim of his hat and a most luxuriant growth of wiry, red, or rather dark, sandy beard. The quick, furtive glances of his large, restless blue eyes impressed her unfavorably, and, gathering the reins more tightly in her hand, she held herself ready for an emergency. Carelessly as she attempted to do this act, it was noticed by the new-comer, who said:</p> 
               <p>"Fear nothing, Miss Poindexter; I merely stopped you to ask a question and a favor. Answer the one and grant the other, and I leave you immediately, with the assurance that our meeting was entirely unexpected and equally fortunate."</p> 
               <p>"I will do so, sir, if in my power," replied Eleanor, with composure and dignity."</p> 
               <p>"First, then, did you receive a note within a day or so from your maid, Rosa, given to her by gentleman on this road?"</p> 
               <p>"I did, sir," answered our heroine, somewhat startled that the forbidding-looking stranger should know of that matter.</p> 
               <p>"That is the question," continued her companion, who had respectfully ruined up his own hose some ten feet or so from Eleanor, "and now for the favor, or rather the two favors. Will you believe and profit by the contents of that note? and, also, will you promise not to mention to any living soul that you have seen a person of my description in this locality?"</p> 
               <p>"As to the first," answered Eleanor, "I could not do otherwise than believe, for of the truth of the mysterious note I had already had proof before receiving it. And as to the second, I see no objection to promising to do as you request."</p> 
               <p>The horseman started as our heroine<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC5561-00000019"/> ine made this reply, and a glance of surprise shot from his eyes when he heard his fair companion state her previous knowledge of the truth of the singular letter. But controlling himself in all instant, he added, as he cast furtive glances up and down the road:</p> 
               <p>"Will you positively assent to my last request, Miss Poindexter? My safety, and perhaps your own <emph>future</emph> safety, depends on your doing so."</p> 
               <p>"Certainly, sir, I will say nothing about having met a person of your description here, if my silence on the matter will be of service to you."</p> 
               <p>"Thank you, Miss Poindexter, it will be of service to me, and also to yourself. I shall place every dependence on your word. Good day!"</p> 
               <p>The look which accompanied this reply was more peculiar than any with which the unknown had yet regarded our heroine, and increased the feeling of uneasiness that had sprung up within her breast. This mysterious stranger was altogether unrecognized by Eleanor, and consequently she marveled the more that he was so familiar with her name, and she was on the point of inquiring who he was when he thus bade her a hasty good-day. As he gracefully wheeled his horse, he bowed to our heroine, and, riding into the timber, on the opposite side of the road to which he had come, quickly disappeared.</p> 
               <p>At first Eleanor thought of returning home, but remembering that there were several houses immediately on the roadside between where she now was and the St. Aubyn mansion, she put her noble animal to his speed and hastened forward. Yet the swift gait of her gallant Arabian was a snail's pace to the lightning-like progress of her own thoughts. A thousand surmises and a thousand suspicions flashed after each other through her mind, but all failed to illumine the mystery.</p> 
               <p>All at once, however, an idea struck her that she had the solution she sought. Santee was a man of the deepest plot; Jenkins she knew to be a sworn friend of Santee; and the mysterious man she had just encountered-who seemed so afraid of discovery-strongly, very strongly, resembled Jenkins. And that the stranger was disguised she had felt from the first moment she saw him. When, however, she examined this suspicion more deeply, it vanished, as had its predecessors, like the morning mist of summer before the rising sun. If the stranger was in league with Santee, he would scarcely have thus divulged the fact, at least to her, and yet, if he was not, what necessity was there for his unaccountable concealment?</p> 
               <p>So engrossing and so bewildering was this whirl of thought and counter-thought that our heroine, without knowing it, had actually passed her friend's mansion to the distance of a quarter of a mile before discovering her mistake. Smiling at herself, she turned back, and was soon after assisted from her horse by a younger son of Mr. St. Aubyn.</p> 
               <p>This was her first visit thither since her return from the North, and her welcome was exceedingly cordial. Of course the occurrences which had so lately taken place at Palmetto Plantation were entirely unknown to the St. Aubyns, and the latter were eager in their kind inquiries concerning the health of the Poindexters. Nellie St. Aubyn, who was a confidential<pb n=""/> dential companion of our heroine, was very particular in asking after Henry, who, owing to his marked and favorably-received attentions, had come to be regarded as the successful suitor for Nellie's hand and heart, each of which was a fortune in itself.</p> 
               <p>Independently of the promise she had given her mother, Eleanor, from her own natural goodness of heart, was inclined to conceal the base conduct of Henry toward herself. Yet so truthful was her heart that many times during the conversation which she held with the St. Aubyns she almost committed herself. However, by carefully wording her replies she avoided such a result, and without speaking a single untruth.</p> 
               <p>Eleanor's friends entreated her to remain to tea; but as she had said to her mother that she would be home soon she was compelled to decline the kind invitation, although she gladly accepted the proffer of Herbert's company to Palmetto Plantation. Her cavalier was soon ready, and both mounting their steeds, our heroine and Herbert were just waving their adieus to the St. Aubyns, when a cavalcade appeared over the ridge of an elevation in the road at a short distance.</p> 
               <p>Foremost among the approaching horsemen the quick eye of Eleanor discerned Santee, mounted on his large, gray courser, and closely followed by her brother Henry. These two together, with three or four companions, seeing that the St. Aubyns and their fair visitor had noticed them, dashed forward at a gallop and soon reached the mansion. It was evident that the whole party had been drinking, but still they retained a sufficient amount of reason to behave themselves in a gentlemanly manner toward the ladies. Henry was the only one who dismounted, and he did so that he might the more conveniently converse with Nellie St. Aubyn, who expressed the liveliest pleasure at seeing him, and naively informed him that she had been "cross-questioning Eleanor about him."</p> 
               <p>While the two lovers stood thus apart from the company, Santee, after lifting his cap to Eleanor and the other ladies, reined his horse close to Mr. St. Aubyn, and swinging himself gracefully half way down and out of his saddle, he grasped the hand of the latter, and said:</p> 
               <p>"Well, St. Aubyn, have you made up your mind to join us yet? We've been gathering up the neighbors all day, and we're going to have a strong meeting to-night at my place-all the influential men for thirty miles about. I suppose you've heard the confirmation of the glorious news about the secession of the 'Old Dominion?' She adds another star, and a brilliant one, too, to our Confederacy. You must come now, St. Aubyn, or you'll be stigmatized as a Unionist."</p> 
               <p>"No, Mr. Santee," replied Mr. St. Aubyn. "Indeed, I shall not join you. I do not, and cannot, approve of such a course. If the South is wronged she can be redressed much better in the Union than out of it, and, until I see much stronger reasons than I do at present, I cannot join you."</p> 
               <p>"Now, St. Aubyn," urged Santee, in a positive and yet conciliatory tone, "do give up your obstinacy. Why, with the feelings of the people worked up to such a pitch as they must very shortly be, your property, and even your life, will be in danger.<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC5561-00000020"/> Now, to show you to what a frenzy they are excited, these men whom you see coming up the road have collected all the national flags they could find and are going to burn them this very night."</p> 
               <p>"And instead of seeking to allay this unwarrantable excitement, this silly madness, you, Santee, and men who know better, have been encouraging it, and are still hounding it on. You sit there coolly, and tell me that at the meeting which is to be held to-night the damnable sacrilege of burning a number of national flags is to be permitted, aye, applauded by you! No, sir! sooner than lend my presence to such a meeting I would thrust my right hand into a cauldron of molten iron! The man, too, who would countenance such an act is a black-hearted traitor and a poltroon! There! you have my answer, once for all!"</p> 
               <p>Santee swung himself up again to an upright position in his saddle, and, shaking his finger slowly and malignantly at the patriotic St. Aubyn, rejoined, in a bitter undertone:</p> 
               <p>"You'll regret those words, St. Aubyn! You're a marked man; remember!"</p> 
               <p>He savagely twisted, rather than wheeled, his horse as he spoke, and, darting forward to meet Mr. Poindexter, who was close at hand with a dozen others, whispered something in his ear.</p> 
               <p>Our heroine's father immediately lowered his brows, and, riding forward, he thus addressed Herbert St. Aubyn, who still sat on his horse beside Eleanor:</p> 
               <p>"Your courtesy, young man, is not needed. I will accompany Miss Poindexter home myself!" Then, turning sharply on his daughter, he continued: "Eleanor, ride by my side."</p> 
               <p>"Very good, sir," haughtily replied Herbert St. Aubyn, stung to the quick by this intentional rudeness, and pulling his horse backward. Quickly recollecting himself, however, he smiled graciously at Eleanor, and raised his hat, which our heroine as graciously acknowledged.</p> 
               <p>Both Henry Poindexter and Nellie St. Aubyn noticed about the same moment that something of an unpleasant nature had occurred, and, parting with a hasty farewell, the former remounted and joined the cavalcade, while the latter retired with the rest of her family within doors.</p> 
               <p>Ten minutes later, even the stragglers of Santee's followers had passed by, and the solemn, holy quiet of evening drew on over the scene.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head> 
               <head type="sub">ELEANOR'S RESOLVE.</head> 
               <p>NEVER before in her whole life had Eleanor Poindexter seen her father under the influence of intoxicating liquor, and even now he had partaken just sufficiently to make him testy, and disposed to exhibit his temper, which, as is already known, was of the most unreasonable and ungovernable character. Well aware that, if she refused to obey him when he ordered her to ride beside him home, a scene would ensue more tragic than even that which had occurred the day previous in his library, Eleanor quietly did as he told her.</p> 
               <p>Santee rode on the side opposite to her father, so that she was between the two. All the way along the former did his best to please and entertain his fair though unwilling companion. Henry, her brother, as though conscience-stricken, did not come near his sister, but kept some distance back in the column, chatting pleasantly the while with his comrades.</p> 
               <p>Upon nearing Palmetto Plantation, Eleanor, making some gaily-spoken remark to her father, gave her steed the rein, and galloped forward to the mansion. On the piazza she found Rosa anxiously awaiting her arrival, for darkness was so close at hand that lights had been already lit.</p> 
               <p>"Rosa," said she, springing from her saddle, and giving the reins to her servant, "you must be my ostler to-night. Take Mehomet quickly to the North side of the barn, secure him there and return immediately. But do not on any account let my father see you. He is coming up the road with some friends. Be quick! When you fasten the horse and come back, watch me, and when you see me go toward the barn, you must mount the first horse you find and follow me to Mr. St. Aubyn's."</p> 
               <p>Rosa, though naturally enough much astonished, comprehended that there was necessity for the utmost despatch, and she accordingly hastened away with the words:</p> 
               <p>"I'll do jes' 'zactly what you sez, Missey Eleanor!"</p> 
               <p>Our heroine forthwith sought her mother, hurriedly informed her of the meeting that was to be held at Santee's, of the temper in which her father was, and of her own intention to return immediately to Mr. St. Aubyn's house, at least until the next day. She, also, in a few words, informed her mother of the strange meeting she had had in the afternoon with the mysterious horseman, and also of her suspicions in regard to him.</p> 
               <p>Mrs. Poindexter heartily approved of the resolve and begged her daughter not to delay her departure for fear that her father might come in.</p> 
               <p>A few minutes sufficed for Eleanor to bound up to her own room, change her riding-habit, and secure a few articles which she most highly prized. An unaccountable impulse caused her also to conceal in her pocket the<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC5561-00000021"/> loaded revolver that her brother had left in her possession in such an unknightly manner.</p> 
               <p>Hearing the tramp of the approaching horsemen, Eleanor glanced from her window and beheld the troop in its dark, shadowy outlines coming near, but still at a sufficient distance to allow her to bid her mother good night.</p> 
               <p>A moment more and she had gained the apartment in which she had left the latter; but Mrs. Poindexter had, in the meantime, descended to the supper room. Eleanor was tempted to hurry down a flight of stairs that was close at hand, and thus make sure her escape. But filial love instantly overcame the temptation, and she ran down to the supper room. Her mother was alone, waiting to receive her husband and his guests, and was much startled at seeing her daughter enter, for she believed her to be by this time fully on her journey.</p> 
               <p>"Oh! my dearest mother!" exclaimed our fair heroine, fondly embracing Mrs. Poindexter, "I could not leave until I bade you good night!"</p> 
               <p>"Good night, my Eleanor, good night? And God bless you! I will come over and see you in the morning. Now hasten away!"</p> 
               <p>Mrs. Poindexter, while making this reply, pressed several fervent kisses upon our heroine's lips and cast several fearful glances in the direction of the door by which she expected her husband to enter.</p> 
               <p>In an instant more Eleanor unclasped her arms and left her mother; thanking Heaven as she did so that the arrival of her father had been delayed. Scarcely had the assuring thought passed from her mind, however, before Mr. Poindexter, leaping from his saddle, strode across the piazza and entered the supper room, meeting his daughter face to face. Eleanor's heart sank within her, but swelled with unexpected pleasure as the following moment Mr. Poindexter, a smile wreathing his features, took her gently by the hand, and led her to a chair beside her mother's, at the head of the table, saying, as he did so:</p> 
               <p>"Come, my dear Eleanor, you must assist your mother to do the honors, for we have some visitors and we are already behind time."</p> 
               <p>Our heroine felt inclined to embrace her father, for his kind manner burst upon her as suddenly and as genially as the warm summer sun breaks its way to earth through the dark thunder storm. Mrs. Poindexter, also, was so overcome with the pleasing surprise that her voice trembled with gladness as she welcomed her husband home, and Eleanor to her side.</p> 
               <p>Ten gentlemen, who had been specially invited by Mr. Poindexter, entered the apartment after their host, and, at a word from him, proceeded to seat themselves at the well-filled board, after interchanging the customary civilities with the two ladies who presided.</p> 
               <p>The rest of the numerous company that had returned with our heroine's father and Santee, were entertained amongst the immediate neighbors, Santee supping by far the largest number of them.</p> 
               <p>During the casual conversation that ensued among Mr. Poindexter's guests, nothing was said at which our patriotic heroine could take exception, as all the gentlemen, moved apparently by the same motive, avoided allusions to politics, and conversed only<pb n=""/> on general topics in which the ladies could be interested. And to the end of the meal nothing occurred of any note except the following: As Eleanor once chanced to cast her eyes toward a side window that looked out upon the piazza, she was startled at beholding the visage of the unknown horseman whom she had encountered as she was going over to Mr. St. Aubyn's in the afternoon. The stealthy watcher raised a warning finger, as though to enjoin silence upon his discoverer, and then disappeared from the window like a fleeting apparition.</p> 
               <p>Eleanor's happiness was broken, for, though being unable to account for it, she felt that there was some mysterious connection between this singular man and the figure she had seen gliding across the lawn on the night her brother Henry had so nearly discovered her watching the prayer-meeting of her father's slaves. And, as naturally as a deduction could follow premises, the suspicion flashed upon her that this mysterious man was linked in some manner with, and guided by, Santee.</p> 
               <p>Upon the conclusion of supper, Mr. Poindexter's friends went out, remounted their horses, and waited for their host to join them before riding over to Santee's place. Here, as we have already stated, was to be held one of those violent meetings by which the traitorous leaders of the rebellion sought to lead captive the masses of the South, and yoke them to the bloody chariot whose pitiless wheels were already in motion. Mr. Poindexter was the last to rise, and, upon doing so, he stepped to his daughter and said, in tones still more pleasant than he had yet used:</p> 
               <p>"Come, Eleanor, my dear, I am going to take you with me. You are cast to-night for a rle of which you may well be proud. You have been unanimously selected on account of your grace and beauty."</p> 
               <p>"Pray, papa, what is the rle to which you allude? I may not be as good an actress thereof as you seem so confidently to believe I will."</p> 
               <p>Eleanor knew, or at least strongly suspected, of what character the meeting was to be, and though her reply was made in pleasant tones, still there was a touch of anxiety about the latter which all her efforts were unavailing to conceal.</p> 
               <p>"Ah, my dear," answered her father, "I may not inform you until you reach the stage. Come, mount your horse! Never mind about redressing; come along just as you are. There will be a grand affair."</p> 
               <p>Our heroine grew sick at heart as her father persisted in his request, for she dreaded that she was about to be subjected to a terrible ordeal. However, after a few moments' consideration, during which her mother urged her to go with her father, Eleanor said:</p> 
               <p>"Yes, my dear papa, I will accompany you with the utmost pleasure, and I will show you that the daughter of Robert Poindexter knows, and will truly perform her duty."</p> 
               <p>"Well said, my daughter!" exclaimed Eleanor's father, kissing his daughter's cheek-the first kiss he had given her since her departure for the North-"Let us be off," he continued, drawing her toward the door, "for the meeting will be opened before we get there."</p> 
               <p>Our heroine loosed herself a moment, and stepping back to where her<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC5561-00000022"/> mother was standing, she embraced the latter fondly, and whispered:</p> 
               <p>"Heaven bless you, dearest mother! good bye-perhaps for ever!"</p> 
               <p>The strange look which accompanied these scarcely audible words betokened the determination of an iron will, and caused Mrs. Poindexter's heart to throb with apprehension. Eleanor then turned and followed her father out on the piazza.</p> 
               <p>But here a fresh difficulty presented itself. Her horse, which ordinarily should have been hitched near-by, or else put up in the stable, was secured, as she had ordered, on the North side of the barn. With perfect calmness, however, Eleanor told her father that she had seen Mehomet going over toward the barn and that she would go and catch him herself. He would have detained her and sent a slave to bring the horse, which would have been the usual way, but Eleanor was gone like a fairy, and quickly disappeared in the surrounding gloom.</p> 
               <p>She soon reached the barn and was joined a moment or so later by Rosa, who had faithfully, and at no small risk, observed the minutest point of Eleanor's orders as far as consistent with the new circumstances.</p> 
               <p>"Rosa!" exclaimed our heroine, in a low, tremulous voice, "I feared you would make some mistake, but, thanks to your good judgment, you have done admirably. Yet your task is not ended. Get one of the horses out of the stable, ride over to Mr. St. Aubyn's, and tell him that I will come over as soon as possible. Tell him, too, that if I should be a little late he will oblige me by waiting up for me. Ask him, also, to allow you to remain til I come."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, Missy Eleanor! what's agoin' to happen? I'se nearly skeered to def 'bout you!"</p> 
               <p>"I cannot stop to explain now, Rosa," quickly replied Eleanor, "but do as I tell you, immediately!"</p> 
               <p>"'Deed I will, Miss Eleanor!"</p> 
               <p>Ere the mulatto had finished her reply, Eleanor vaulted into the saddle, and was riding back toward the mansion.</p> 
               <p>As Mehomet pranced proudly up with his fair burden, an exclamation of welcome burst from very lip of Mr. Poindexter's guests, and he and they, accompanied by our heroine, forthwith started for the meeting which was about taking place.</p> 
               <p>It was at no slow pace that they rode, and yet, upon arriving at the spot-a wide and beautiful field belonging to James Santee-in which were gathered more than a thousand people, impatient shouts were already being uttered for a speech.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <head>CHAPTER IX.</head> 
               <head type="sub">"HAIL! ALL HAIL, BRIGHT BANNER!"</head> 
               <p>THE field of which we speak was indeed a beautiful spot. Sloping on the side of a gentle acclivity, it was covered with rich, green grass, and surrounded by a deep woodland. Only a little imagination was required to suppose that it had once been an immense emerald, and that ages ago it had fallen from the sky, and, crushing down through the forest foliage, had imbedded itself in the earth, and lain hidden there ever since.</p> 
               <p>At the Western or highest side of this field, a large staging had been erected for speakers, and also for another purpose which the course of our narrative will develop. Flowers and flags were tastefully festooned and draped about it, the latter invariably being State flags only, and representing some one or other of the seceded States, or those which it was supposed would soon secede. The whole scene was rendered most brilliant by large fires, while strings of colored lights were fancifully distributed among the branches of the trees with which this natural amphitheatre was surrounded. The tableau, therefore, presented to Eleanor Poindexter, as she emerged from the moss grown aisles of the forest into the field, was indeed grand and impressive, and she involuntarily checked her horse that she might contemplate the scene at a distance.</p> 
               <p>As she did so, however, her father exclaimed, with a kind of joyous excitement:</p> 
               <p>"Do not tarry, Eleanor, my dear. Come, let us hurry through the throng and reach the stage."</p> 
               <p>After she recovered from the startle his exclamation had given her, our heroine pointed out to her father that it would be more advisable to ride around the outside of the meeting, and thus, without trouble or delay, gain the desired point. Mr. Poindexter adhered, however, to his own determination, and began to urge his own and his daughter's horse in among the spectators, who, giving way in all directions, sent up loud acclamations for our heroine, she being as well known to nearly all those present as was her father. This appeared to be exactly the result that Mr. Poindexter had wished; for, as the welcoming shouts broke forth, his cheeks flushed, his eyes brightened, and, as he rode along, he often made such remarks as these:</p> 
               <p>"Last, but not least, gentlemen! Ah! Mr. Mason, Beauty and Goodness, as well as Valor, are enlisted in our glorious cause."</p> 
               <p>But while Miss Poindexter's father was thus engaged, she herself rode alone beside him with ashen checks and drooping eyes (for on reaching the meeting her cavalier companions gradually mingled with the assembled spectators). Yet no word of remonstrance, none of complaint, parted her tightly compressed lips as her father thus made a show of her for a certain effect. She was<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC5561-00000023"/> pretty well assured in her own mind for what reason he had brought her hither, and she accordingly resolved on the course which she intended to pursue.</p> 
               <p>As she neared the stage she noticed particularly the absence of the national standard, and the peculiar selection of State flags. But she had not time to observe much more, ere her father, guiding her around the Southern end of the platform, led her to a roughly built inclosure, that had apparently been put up for the occasion.</p> 
               <p>Outside of the entrance thereto stood Santee and a select group of companions, among whom Eleanor noticed her brother Henry. The latter turned carelessly away, while Santee, springing forward, offered her his assistance to dismount. But, without a sign even of recognition to the man whom she now feared and hated, she leaped lightly to the ground, and turning to her father, who had also dismounted, asked him what he desired her to do.</p> 
               <p>"To step in here a moment with me, dearest Eleanor," replied Mr. Poindexter, throwing open the door of the inclosure, or cabin, if the layer of clap-boards, that served the place of a roof, could constitute it one. Still obedient, Eleanor entered as directed.</p> 
               <p>"Dearest Eleanor," resumed her father, closing the door after him as he spoke, and changing his former tone to one of more gravity, "this is the rle you are to play, and remember, on your proper performance thereof, depends my future regard for you. A crisis has arisen in the history of our land. The Southern States have determined to assert their freedom and declare their right to independence. Up to February 1st, seven States withdrew from the Union, and within a day past the glorious news has reached us that Virginia, the oldest and most influential State in the country, has forever sundered the ties that bound her to the old government. To celebrate these glorious events, and also to encourage and give proper aim to the struggles of our countrymen in this region, we have determined to have this splendid demonstration to-night. The whole affair has been arranged by Mr. Santee and a few noble friends, and will produce the most startling effect imaginable.</p> 
               <p>"By his, that is, their courtesy, you, Eleanor, have been selected, as I told you before, to play the most important rle. This I will explain to you fully, in order that you may better understand it. There will be eight speakers, one for each seceded State, and there will likewise be eight beautiful maidens, seven besides yourself. All the young ladies will be attired in a costume allegorical of Purity and Truth, and each of them will bear three flags, one the State flag, One the old national flag, and the other the new Confederate banner. The speeches will be made in the exact order of the secession of the State represented by the speaker, and at the conclusion of each speech, the young lady who personifies the genius of that State, will go to an altar, on which a fire will be burning, and, unfolding the old national flag from about the State flag, will fling the former into the flames. She will then reverently entwine the State banner with the new Confederate standard.</p> 
               <p>"You, my dearest Eleanor, will represent Virginia, the last and most<pb n=""/> powerful sister of the New Confederacy. And now you will retire to the next apartment, where the rest of the young ladies are doubtless waiting for you, and don your costume; but ere I leave you," continued Mr. Poindexter, taking his daughter's hand, "let me know that you fully and cheerfully consent to be thus distinguished, Eleanor."</p> 
               <p>"Have I not already obeyed you, father?" replied our heroine, in a smothered, husky voice.</p> 
               <p>"Yes, my dear, but I am still fearful, from Henry's report of you, and your own acts of late, that you might disobey my wish on this occasion."</p> 
               <p>"I will do my duty, father! As God above is my witness, I will not flinch!" said Eleanor in fervent tones, as a flush sprang to her hitherto pale cheeks and she stepped toward the door opening into the next room-for the little building of which we speak had been partitioned.</p> 
               <p>"Ha! that is how a daughter of Robert Poindexter <emph>should</emph> speak!" exclaimed our heroine's father, in tones of ecstasy, impulsively clasping Eleanor to his breast, "Good bye, daughter, until after the meeting is over, for the people, as you may hear, are becoming more and more impatient."</p> 
               <p>"Farewell, my father, farewell!"</p> 
               <p>Mr. Poindexter was making his exit as these words fell upon his ear, but their strangely mournful utterance instantly arrested his steps, and he turned to look upon his daughter. He caught a glimpse of her features, which had lost their blush, and were again ashy pale, and he heard her final farewell as she passed into the room beyond.</p> 
               <p>While this scene was passing within, another of equal interest was transpiring without. As Miss Poindexter had disappeared with her father, Santee drew two of his immediate companions aside, and thus addressed them.</p> 
               <p>"Well, Mason and Keit, what do you think of that wire pulling, eh? Poindexter's one of the most influential men about here, and with proper managing he will make one of our best advocates. He is very proud, vain, and sensitive, and so I tickled his vanity by proposing to him that his daughter should represent Virginia at the meeting to-night. She has just come home from the North, and the people knowing that, and seeing her thus taking sides with her father's cause, will be bound the more readily to that cause. You see we must enlist the women on our side, and not men only. I was very much afraid that the sweet dear would refuse, for she and her father have had a scene or two since she came home, on account of her getting in with some of those infernal abolitionists while in the North. But I guess the old man has taken the advice I gave him, and gained his authority over her again, with honey instead of vinegar."</p> 
               <p>"By the way, Santee," replied one of the latter's auditors; "are you not casting a net of your own in the direction of Miss Poindexter?"</p> 
               <p>"Well, perhaps I am," was the answer, given with a light laugh. "She's a fish worthy a good net and a better fishermen."</p> 
               <p>"<choice>
                     <sic>Epecially</sic>
                     <corr>Especially</corr>
                  </choice> the last!" chimed Keit, playfully digging Santee in the side with his thumb.</p> 
               <p>"Well, I do hope," resumed Santee, after some further irrelevant conversation<pb n="48-49 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC5561-00000024"/> sation, and speaking with a serious air, "that she'll play her part as I have arranged it; but I tell you what it is, it would not surprise me one whit to see her bounce out of there, pistol in hand, and in the highest kind of dudgeon."</p> 
               <p>"Hist!" exclaimed Mason, "the door's opening now!"</p> 
               <p>All three instantly fixed their eyes in the direction indicated, and Santee actually cut his lip between his teeth from very suspense. When he saw only Mr. Poindexter come out of the cabin, however, he gave a deep sigh of relief, and, springing forward, seized the hand of our heroine's father, and said:</p> 
               <p>"Now, Mr. Poindexter, isn't my advice the best? If, instead of smiling upon Eleanor, and coaxing her, when you went in to supper, you had stormed at and threatened her, you would not have had her here. You see she has a temperament high-strung and defiant."</p> 
               <p>"You were right, Santee, you were right! and I believe that, with a little kindness, I can persuade her even to undo her silly act in, regard to that wench, Rosa. At any rate I have accomplished this much-that she has promised me not to flinch from her duty to-night!"</p> 
               <p>"Good! good! better than good!" exclaimed Santee, rubbing and clapping his hands, while a gleam of delight suffused his sinister countenance. "But behold!" he continued, after a pause, "here come the nymphs now! They look like angels! Stand by with the matches, Ned!" he called to an assistant, who only awaited his order to discharge a flight of rockets, which was a signal for the commencement of the meeting.</p> 
               <p>The distance between the platform and the little building out of which the eight lovely girls had just issued was but short, and, by the time the latter had reached the stairs leading to the stage, the word was given by Santee. Instantly the heavily charged rockets screeched skyward, one after another, until all were discharged, by which moment the young ladies had reached the seats set apart for them. No pen can attempt properly to depict the wild and tumultuous excitement that followed. The ground itself trembled with the noise, and, during the uproar, the rest of the stage was filled with those who had been invited thereon.</p> 
               <p>When all was ready Santee stepped forward, and, with a motion of his hand, gained the silent attention of his audience. He stated the object of the meeting in that treasonable balderdash which was the common stock in trade of the vile leaders of the rebellion, and he ended by nominating Mr. Robert Poindexter for President, which, of course, was carried by acclamation. The usual long list of Vice-Presidents and Secretaries followed, and then commenced the real performance of the evening.</p> 
               <p>From the moment Eleanor Poindexter bade her exit from the cabin with her seven fair companions, three pairs of eyes were constantly riveted upon her. These anxiously gazing eyes belonged to her father, James Santee, and a tall man wearing a broad-rimmed hat, and a long, heavy reddish, wiry beard, which nearly concealed his face. The last mentioned stood alone in the shadow of a large tree, from which position he could see all that passed without being likely to attract much attention<pb n=""/> 
                  <figure> 
                     <head>Eleanor, disrobing herself instantly of the glorious standard of Liberty, waved it above her, and added: "<emph>Hail! all hail to thee, bright Banner! Mayest thou ever float above the Union, unharmed by foemen! unsullied by traitors!</emph>"-Page <choice>
                           <sic>51</sic>
                           <corr>52</corr>
                        </choice>.</head> 
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC5561-00000025"/> himself. To those who may be curious about this last pair of eyes, we will say that they were bright blue in color, large in size, and remarkably restless in movement. They were in short, the same eyes that had inspired our heroine with such a mysterious fear.</p> 
               <p>The eight young ladies who were to take such a conspicuous part in the proceedings of the meeting were attired in a uniform costume, consisting of a long, flowing robe of pure white, confined at the waist, with a belt of blue ribbon, and streamers, also blue. The bodice full, and of the same material as the skirt, was entirely plain, while the sleeves were wide and slit up on the outside to a point midway between the elbow and shoulder, thus displayed the arms, which were jeweled according to the taste of the fair owner. The headdress was a light, elegantly made tiarra of flowers mingled with tinsel. Rising from the middle front of each tiara was a star, also of tinsel and highly polished.</p> 
               <p>Though no taller than most of her companions, our heroine seemed to tower above them all like an empress, and right regal was her mien as she advanced with a firm step to the platform, carrying the flags already designated in either hand.</p> 
               <p>"Surely I am deceived!" said the man who stood alone in the shadow of the large tree, as he beheld our heroine going upon the stage.</p> 
               <p>If he added aught to these words, it was lost in the tumult that broke forth at that juncture.</p> 
               <p>The first speaker-he who represented South Carolina-was Colonel Keit, and when we have said that, there remains to us no necessity for recording even a synopsis of his fierce harangue. When he had finished, however, that part of the programme most impressive and most incendiary to the minds of the more ignorant portions of the spectators was initiated.</p> 
               <p>Prominently, in view of all, had been erected a sort of altar, upon the stage, and at a given signal by Santee, that master-spirit of evil, a sudden fire burst forth upon it, kindled by a pyrotechnic contrivance from beneath the platform. As the flames grew strong, Miss Ruffin, daughter of the man who fired the first traitor-ball at Fort Sumter, and who, therefore, was a fitting vice-genius of South Carolina, went to the altar and stood silently before it for a few moments. Then, assuming the supposed dignity of one of the ancient priestesses, she disengaged a Palmetto flag from about a Star Spangled Banner, about which it had been entwined, and, with a contemptuous manner, cast the latter into the fire, exclaiming as she did so:</p> 
               <p>"<emph>So perish the Old Union!</emph>"</p> 
               <p>Then, with the deepest expression of reverence, folding the Palmetto flag with the standard of the rebellion, she added:</p> 
               <p>"<emph>Hail! all Hail to the New Confederacy!</emph>"</p> 
               <p>Surely the madness that Heaven sends upon those whom it would destroy had seized the beholders of this impious idolatry, this horrid sacrifice to their Political Moloch, for the very welkin trembled for several minutes with the yells and shouts and screams of applause that greeted the offering.</p> 
               <p>But let us not tarry even upon the description of such a scene.</p> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <p>Six speeches, all much of the same tenor as Keit's, had been made, and six of the young ladies had, like Miss Ruffin, enacted their parts in the treasonable mummery. The President of the meeting had by this began to gaze oftener and more anxiously at his daughter, who seemed to be getting paler and paler as her turn approached.</p> 
               <p>Santee was to be the last speaker, and he, too, was eagerly watching his intended victim. He occupied a seat immediately behind Mr. Poindexter, and, bending forward his head, he whispered in the ear of the latter:</p> 
               <p>"I hope Eleanor will get through without breaking down, but I must say she looks rather nervous! Don't you think so?"</p> 
               <p>"Oh, no! She'll face it when it comes," answered our heroine's father. "You see I've got her to take the point, and she will go through for very shame. The success of the others will inspire her if nothing else will."</p> 
               <p>The seventh orator was a Texan judge, who roughly, but no doubt naturally, represented his State. His speech was short and brusque, and delivered in a manner rather unbecoming and vulgar for a judge.</p> 
               <p>The President announced, as the last speaker, "his <emph>patriotic</emph> friend, James L. Santee, Esq."</p> 
               <p>At the mention of his name our heroine started almost to her feet, and glanced about her as though longing for some avenue of escape. Her change of demeanor did not escape the eyes of either Santee or her father; but each believed it to be only the result of the near approach of the moment for her own performance.</p> 
               <p>As Santee opened his address, Eleanor looked over to where she had left her horse, and a thrill of something that was almost despair flashed through her, for, standing with his hand on Mehomet's bridle, was the mysterious horseman of the afternoon. But a strange gleam of determination came upon her countenance the next moment, and she turned and coolly answered some casual remark that one of the ladies addressed to her.</p> 
               <p>Santee was not long, and at the close of his speech, after alluding to the power, influence, and importance of Virginia, he paid a high-flown tribute to the fair Eleanor, which gained for her a compliment that none of her companions had received-a round of three deafening cheers. While these were still ringing, Santee took his seat.</p> 
               <p>The final moment had come at last, and, with the most intense anxiety, Mr. Poindexter and Santee eyed our heroine.</p> 
               <p>Not until perfect silence was restored did the latter stir from her seat, and then, rising with the utmost dignity, she advanced close to the altar. Here, instead of facing the latter as had done her companions, and hurrying through her part, she confronted the spectators. Gazing upon these a moment, she raised her eyes heavenward, and crossing her hands upon her breast, sank gradually down upon her knees to the platform.</p> 
               <p>So genuinely natural was this unlooked-for act that every breath was suspended, and those who sat upon the stage actually rose with one unconscious accord to their feet and leaned over toward the lovely girl, who looked more like an angel of light than a human being. Eleanor<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC5561-00000026"/> continued in this posture several minutes, her lips, the while, moving in silent prayer. She then arose, and as she did so a relief came upon the audience, which expressed itself in a low murmur or sigh, as it were of reverence and approbation.</p> 
               <p>"Noble Eleanor!" gasped her father to Santee, in a whisper of half stifled joy, and then, with the latter, he turned to witness his daughter's further performance.</p> 
               <p>The incomparable girl took her place before the altar, and, after a pause, began the usual unfolding of the flags. There was no hurry, for she alone, of all the eight maidens, was calm and really not <emph>acting</emph>. The State flag of Virginia was disentwined from around the Star Spangled Banner, and the next instant, <emph>twisted and wisped with the standard of the rebellion, it was cast loathingly into the flames</emph>.</p> 
               <p>With the act the imprisoned soul of our heroine burst the restraint that until now had confined it, and, as flashes of fire darted from Eleanor's eyes, and the bright blood rushed to her cheeks, the heroic girl cast about herself the "Banner of the Stars," the sacred banner for which Southern blood had often been shed, and in a voice that rang out as clearly as a bell:</p> 
               <p>"<emph>Perish! forever perish all treason! all traitors!</emph>"</p> 
               <p>Then, disrobing herself instantly of the glorious standard of Liberty, she waved it above her, and added:</p> 
               <p>"<emph>Hail! all hail to thee, bright Banner! Mayest thou ever float above the Union, unharmed by foemen! unsullied by traitors!</emph>"</p> 
               <p>The bursting of a tempest down from a soft Italian sky could not equal the effect that the act of our heroine produced.</p> 
               <p>First came a lull, as of death, and then, like some monstrous animal, stunned for a moment by a terrible blow, the spectators broke forth into bellowings of rage. Even highly bred gentlemen on the stage, who were wont to boast of their chivalry, rushed toward Eleanor, and whipped out their favorite bowie-knives to make her a sacrifice. But the imperious empress who had let loose the tempest was not one to cower from its fury.</p> 
               <p>Eleanor had merely slipped on her white robe over her own dress, in the pocket of which she had secreted Henry's revolver. In an instant this was in her grasp, and, inspired at the moment, like Samson of old, the glorious girl threw herself forward into the midst of her enemies.</p> 
               <p>"Back! back!" she cried, leveling her weapon now to the right, now to the left, and now in front of her, as occasion required.</p> 
               <p>In the excitement of the moment lay her advantage, and she pursued it successfully, for, strange as it may seem, she reached in safety her horse. Some friendly hand had already unhitched him. A moment more, and Eleanor was in the saddle, flying away through the forest at the top of Mehomet's speed, and at the imminent risk of being swept from his back by the pendent limbs and branches.</p> 
               <p>Once, as she was entering the woods, she cast a glance behind her, and noticed that the foremost and most eager of her pursuers was that same mysterious man whom she had seen standing beside her horse, and whom she now felt thoroughly convinced was an accomplice of Santee.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <head>CHAPTER X.</head> 
               <head type="sub">AN UNLOOKED-FOR REFUGE.</head> 
               <p>ELEANOR POINDEXTER, in directing her flight through the forest, well knew the peril with which the projecting limbs of trees threatened her, but there was no other choice left, except that of remaining to brave the fury of the mob. Besides, in taking the course she did, she reasoned that, in case of a pursuit on foot, she could soon distance the fleetest, and few mounted foes would care to even enter, let alone continue, the chase at a constant risk of their own lives. The wisdom of her action was proved by the result, for she had not galloped more than a quarter of a mile when she became satisfied that all save one of her pursuers had already ceased their efforts. Though in the darkness she could not see this solitary foe, she felt certain that he was no other than the mysterious being who had dogged her footsteps all the afternoon and evening.</p> 
               <p>Nearly a mile now stretches between Eleanor and her enraged enemies, and all this distance the heroic girl had ridden unharmed. But an undefined dread of the danger we have already mentioned induced her suddenly, almost involuntarily, to somewhat check her steed. And not a moment too soon did she do so, for the following instant she was swept from her horse by the latter running beneath a low-branched tree. Had she been going at her previous headlong speed, her death would have been as sudden as it must have been sure. As it was, her consciousness only lasted long enough to allow a single gasping word of prayer to pass her lips, and then the lovely and unfortunate girl fell heavily to the earth.</p> 
               <p>So intent had been Eleanor's pursuer upon her motions-which were rendered distinctly visible by reason of her white robe <note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WRIGHT2-0043-NOTE001" n="*"
                        place="foot">
                     <p >Any object that is white can be seen at a long distance, even on the darkest night. During the war this fact has been continually turned to a useful account. A white rag, tied around the cap or arm of soldiers, has served to keep the latter in the best order while making night attacks, on executing any night movement, or while on picket duty. A still more scientific application of the fact was made by the late Commodore Morris, we think, while passing the rebel batteries at Grand Gulf to assist the gallant Porter, Of Vicksburg fame. The passage was to be made after dark, and yet lights aboard of ships offered the best of marks for the vigilant rebel artillerists. But still it was necessary that there be light of <emph>some sort</emph> to enable a prompt and proper performance of their duties by the men. Here was indeed a serious difficulty, and one that promised much trouble. Suddenly, however, a thought struck the Commodore, and, sending for the hands, who had been engaged in lime-washing the hold, he ordered them up with their brushes and buckets. Much to the astonishment of all, the Commodore next ordered a good thick coat of the wash to be spread on the deck, inspecting the work himself. But astonishment was quickly turned to amazed delight, for, as fast as the lime went on, every thing on deck became visible, even, to a small picking rod. It is needless to add that lights were immediately dispensed with above deck on every vessel, and the whole fleet passed up without giving the rebels any other advantage than that of random firing.-W. B.</p>
                  </note> -and so close at<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC5561-00000027"/> at hand was he that her helpless limbs had scarcely settled themselves upon the couch afforded by the fallen leaves before he leaped from his horse and raised her inanimate form in his arms. No word did he utter which could mark the thoughts or emotions that were passing within his breast; but as he rose to his feet he turned half way round, and looked back in the direction of the meeting our heroine had so appropriately ended. He could see nothing; and the only sounds that reached him were faint hums, the thin apparitions of angry roars that were being sent up from a thousand throats.</p> 
               <p>After standing thus for a minute or so, the mysterious stranger gently placed Eleanor's head upon his right shoulder, and supported her easily with the same arm, thus leaving his left at liberty to lead his horse. Then, with as quick and yet noiseless a step as possible, he plunged on through the forest, changing his course almost at right angles to that in which he had come.</p> 
               <p>Half an hour's travel brought him to a small creek flowing into the Savannah river. As the water was shallow, he experienced no difficulty in fording it, and, on reaching the opposite bank, his course was again changed. His gait, also, now became more brisk, his fair and insensible burden apparently not impeding him at all. Perhaps it was a mile, or three quarters of a mile, distant from the stream that the stranger came to a ridge or swell of land, which seemed to stand out almost as abruptly from the surrounding surface as a grave mound in the midst of a level prairie. The length of the ridge was about ten or twelve rods, while its average breadth was seventy feet. It was covered with a dense and tangled thicket, interspersed with occasional trees.</p> 
               <p>The stranger, halting within a hundred feet of this mound, secured his horse to a sapling. Then going to a point midway along the side of the ridge, he parted the thick bushes and made his way slowly into the ticket. So knitted together were the masses of tough branches, tougher wires, and thorny creepers, that it was a task of no small labor and pain to penetrate a dozen feet into this natural network. At this distance, however, the bushes suddenly parted with extreme ease, and six feet further brought Eleanor's bearer to an opening in the ground, that was so artfully concealed as to defy detection.</p> 
               <p>Descending half a dozen steps, constructed simply of heavy logs, the singular unknown reclosed the entrance. Then groping his way along a passage whose depth permitted him to walk erectly, he soon emerged into a cave, or rather room, of extensive dimensions. A large and beautiful astral lamp depended from the middle of a huge roof beam, which, with a framework of others, supported the superincumbent earth of the ceiling. By the light thus afforded the stranger strode to where stood a handsome bedstead, and with the utmost tenderness, placed Eleanor who had begun to exhibit signs returning to consciousness, upon the richly appointed bed, which was of the softest<pb n=""/> down. Rising to his feet, he now contemplated the beautiful girl in silent admiration for a moment or so, and suddenly bending down snatched a kiss from her pale lips, and murmured some half inaudible words of endearment.</p> 
               <p>With this he turned away to an iron chest near at hand, from which he took a phial filled with the powerful extract of a rare oriental gum. Stepping back to the side of the couch on which Eleanor lay, he removed the stopper from the phial, and instantly applied the latter to the nostrils of his charge. This treatment he varied by pouring some of the precious liquid into the palm of his hand, and bathing with it the forehead and temples of the fair girl.</p> 
               <p>The efforts of Miss Poindexter's companion proved successful, and at the end of about ten minutes, Eleanor slowly opened her eyes and gazed about her. As she recognized the stranger, a shudder ran through her frame, and she murmured, in weak tones:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, God, protect me in this peril!"</p> 
               <p>With these words she clasped her hands, and with a strong effort she attempted to rise, but as yet her physical system was unequal to the task.</p> 
               <p>"God has protected you wonderfully, Eleanor, and will continue to do so," said our heroine's companion, in a soothing voice, but never ceasing his exertions to fully restore the life that had thus begun to flow again in its wonted channels.</p> 
               <p>Eleanor started at the language and tone of the stranger, so totally unexpected to her were both, and while he for a minute stopped bathing her forehead, she fixed her eyes upon his countenance, as though she hoped thereby to solve the mystery.</p> 
               <p>The broad-rimmed hat had been removed, revealing a high, intellectual forehead and thick chestnut locks, but the dark and heavy sandy beard was still sufficient concealment for the features, and so our heroine's scrutiny went unrewarded.</p> 
               <p>That strange fear of Santee and his wiles still clung to Eleanor and oppressed her. A glance or two about the apartment satisfied her that she was the occupant of no house, and as she smelled the damp, earthy odor which pervaded the atmosphere, she was at once convinced that she had been carried to a cave, and that, too, by the strange, inexplicable being who had made such an unfavorable impression upon her from the first moment she had encountered him, and who, also, had so recklessly followed her through the forest.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, sir!" she exclaimed, in a voice rendered broken, and yet stronger than before, by excitement and apprehension, "where am I? and by whom was I brought hither? and for what purpose?"</p> 
               <p>"You are, Miss Poindexter," replied the unknown, in assuring tones, "in the only place of real safety that you could find within a circuit of fifty miles, after the act you performed to-night. You were brought, hither by one who would give his life freely, for your security, and the purpose of bringing you here is to prevent the successful consummation of a diabolical plot against your happiness."</p> 
               <p>Eleanor, by the time her companion ceased speaking, had raised herself partially on her elbow, and, was gazing intently into his countenance. There was such a truthful, straight-forward<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC5561-00000028"/> forward manner about his utterance that very much of her suspicion of him fled, and she exclaimed, half musingly, half interrogatively:</p> 
               <p>"To save me from a diabolical plot! from James Santee?"</p> 
               <p>"To save you from James Santee, Miss Poindexter!" added the stranger, quickly, and with strong emphasis.</p> 
               <p>In an instant each event of her life, from her desertion by her brother Henry, in Philadelphia, up to the very moment that she had been struck from her flying steed, flashed before her like a lightning-painted panorama, and, with more of her suspicion in regard to the character of her companion dispelled, she resumed:</p> 
               <p>"And were you, sir, the author of the strange billet that was given to my maid Rosa a day or two ago?"</p> 
               <p>"I was."</p> 
               <p>"Well, sir," rejoined Eleanor, "you therein mentioned an incident that occurred in Philadelphia, which caused me at first to think that the writer was a Mr. Drayton, whom I had met in that city, and of whom I formed a very high opinion. I sought to settle the point by referring to a note that Mr. Drayton once sent me, but unfortunately the note had been written by a friend."</p> 
               <p>"Drayton! Drayton!" rejoined Eleanor's companion, in a musing, and, as our heroine fancied, somewhat envious tone, "I have heard of him. He has traveled in this part of the country, if I am not mistaken."</p> 
               <p>"He has," said Eleanor, "and to hear him converse you would think he had resided here from childhood."</p> 
               <p>To this the stranger made no answer, but after a pause he said:</p> 
               <p>"Miss Poindexter, I know not whether you have noticed the fact that you are not in a house, but a cave; a much safer refuge, however, than any house, at least in this, region. Your safety demands that you remain here for a time, but I shall not compel this course, in proof whereof I assure you that you are at liberty to leave this place whenever you choose. But for your own sake, and the sake of others to whom you are very dear, I do indeed hope that you will remain."</p> 
               <p>"You must be aware, kind sir," replied Eleanor, as the speaker paused for the purpose of giving his fair companion an opportunity to speak, "that though I owe you so deep a debt of gratitude for your noble aid, yet there exist certain proprieties-"</p> 
               <p>"Your pardon, Miss Poindexter!" interrupted the other, hastily, "I perceive what you would say, and acknowledge its truth and force. But let me pray of you to waive the demands of etiquette; at least for a time. Your stay here shall be made as comfortable as every luxury can make it, and if you desire it your maid Rosa shall bear you company. I will go and fetch her hither at the first opportunity."</p> 
               <p>Eleanor was utterly perplexed by the thousand varied emotions and thoughts that the earnest and anxious words of her companion awakened within her, and for several minutes she remained silent. At last she thus addressed the mysterious being beside her:</p> 
               <p>"Kind stranger, in the course of Providence we are often brought into situations where an error of our judgment may lead to terrible, even fatal consequences. In such a position I now find myself. I know you<pb n=""/> speak the truth when you say that there is no safety for me within fifty miles. I would even increase the distance. I am sure that had you intended to harm me-which, in truth, I must acknowledge to you that I suspected at first you did-you would scarcely offer me my liberty when just in your power. I am equally certain that were your intentions evil you would not offer me the company of my maid Rosa, and I therefore, kind friend, throw myself upon your generosity, your honor, and trust myself confidentially to your guidance."</p> 
               <p>"And I," answered the stranger, taking the hand our heroine offered him, "promise you, Miss Eleanor, that, as Heaven is my witness, I will keep my word, and that I will protect you, as I have said, with my life, if necessary. And now," he continued, in brisker tones, "I must be gone. It is a few minutes past twelve. I will return as soon after daylight as possible. Rosa is an early riser, is she not?"</p> 
               <p>"Oh, sir!" exclaimed Eleanor, neglecting to answer the question as she remembered the message she had sent to Mr. St. Aubyn, "if possible, grant me one favor?"</p> 
               <p>"As many as you like," replied the stranger.</p> 
               <p>"Before going to the traitor's gathering to-night," resumed Eleanor, "I was impressed that some such result as actually happened would occur, and I therefore sent Rosa over to Mr. St. Aubyn to request him to wait up for me, as I intended to take refuge with him. Rosa was also to remain with his permission at his house until my arrival. If, therefore, it is not too far from here, will you see him and tell him of my safety? for my dear mamma is to visit there to-morrow, and, if she find me not there to meet her, she will think some evil fate has befallen me."</p> 
               <p>"It is not very far," said Eleanor's mysterious companion, though our heroine gave him no directions, "and the carrier-dove would not speed thither more straight than I. If Rosa be there, I will bring her back long before daylight. But ere I go," continued the speaker, "I must insure you against becoming lonesome during my absence. In that book-case opposite you will find volumes on all subjects, and this closet, close at hand here, contains refreshment in plenty. This hand-lamp I will light and place upon that shelf. And as I know you are fond of music, you will find in yonder chest a flutina and lute, with whole quires of harmony and melody. There is, besides, a musical box set for eight airs, seven besides your glorious favorite, 'The Star Spangled Banner.'"</p> 
               <p>"Oh, then, indeed, time will not hang heavily on my hands!" smiled Eleanor.</p> 
               <p>"Then I will bid you farewell until my return!"</p> 
               <p>"Farewell, kind protector, and God take you in his holy keeping."</p> 
               <p>The next moment the strange host was gone from the sight of our heroine into the passage which led to the outside entrance of the cave.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC5561-00000029"/> 
               <head>CHAPTER XI.</head> 
               <head type="sub">ONE OF REBELLION'S FIRST FRUITS.</head> 
               <p>UPON emerging into the open air, the mysterious friend of Eleanor Poindexter-for his actions thus far entitled him to be called such-carefully concealed the mouth of the subterranean passage by which ingress was had to the cave. Then, stepping three paces to the right, the bushes parting, as we have elsewhere remarked, with the utmost ease, he seized a thick, wild grape vine, that sent several twining stems up along the trunk and into the foliage of a large tree. With an ease that showed previous practice, our strange friend using the tough, strong vine as a ladder made his way up into the tree.</p> 
               <p>Close to this tree stood several others, and through the foliage of each the grape vine passed, actually forming a safe and convenient bridge to a tree that stood on the outer edge of the thicket, through which Eleanor's preserver had previously passed. Here the vine had been deflected and rooted in the earth beneath, thus making a second natural ladder like the, one up into the tree in the thicket. The most consummate art had been exerted to make this whole work resemble nature's handicraft so closely as to deceive even the most inquisitive eyes. And most successfully had the object aimed at been attained, for the lines of vision from every portion of the forest had been so thoroughly intercepted by trees and vines that a person might, with impunity ascend, cross and descend the vine-ladder and bridge in broad daylight, no matter if a hundred pursuers were within as many yards. A fugitive might possibly be discovered by any one standing on the top of the ridge; but, as the latter was everywhere covered, as with a garment, by the impenetrable thicket, these, was absolutely no risk from this point.</p> 
               <p>As, however, a full account of this strange subterranean retreat will be recorded farther on in our narrative, we will at once follow the footsteps of the mysterious stranger.</p> 
               <p>Quickly finding his horse, he unfastened him, and with as much ease as though the sun were shining, led him to a bridle path. Then mounting the animal he rode away in a direction that soon brought him upon the main road. Once here the gallant steed was put at his best pace, and in a comparatively short time the singular friend, of our heroine was within sight of Mr. St. Aubyn's mansion, not that the soft starlight made it discernible, but because it was illumined by lurid flames, which were just bursting through the roof and sides of the barn that stood but a short distance behind it.</p> 
               <p>By the red and increasing glare the rider quickly distinguished also a mob of men, who, as the sparks and, cinders shot up from the consuming building, whooped and yelled with savage delight like so many<pb n=""/> wild Indians. Motives of prudence induced him to halt, and, as he did so he said:</p> 
               <p>"Santee's work, as certain as fate! St. Aubyn is noted as a Union man, and perhaps Santee knew or suspected that Eleanor would take refuge with him after breaking up that vile meeting. He has, therefore, instigated the infuriated mob to take vengeance on St. Aubyn, whom, however, he had already proscribed."</p> 
               <p>"Is that you, sah?" almost whispered a low voice coming from the clump of bushes against which the stranger's steed was standing.</p> 
               <p>"Who are you?" exclaimed the horseman, astonished at finding a human being in such close proximity, "who are you? Come out of that bush!"</p> 
               <p>"Oh, I's Rosa, sah! Rosa! Don't you knows me, sah? Don't you 'member I give a letter, sah, from you to Missey Eleanor? don't you 'member now, sah?"</p> 
               <p>With his second exclamation, the rider had quickly drawn a pistol, and, doubtless struck at that moment with the truth of the adage, that "delays are dangerous," Rosa hurriedly scrambled from her retreat, and presented herself before our mysterious friend, in order that he might recognize her.</p> 
               <p>"Ah, Rosa! it is you, eh?" replied the horseman, replacing his weapon, and speaking in milder tones than before. "But what are you doing here, Rosa? I thought Miss Eleanor sent you to stay at Mr. St. Aubyn's house?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, sah, so she did, but I'll 'splain everything in a minute. Oh sah! ef it hadn't 'a been fur lovin Missey Eleanor so much, I'd 'a been skeered to def, sah! I knows I would!"</p> 
               <p>"Well, Rosa, just be quiet a moment or two," said the stranger, perceiving that the mulatto was considerably nervous, "and then coolly tell me what you wish to. No harm shall befall you."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, sah! I'se not skeered fur mese'f! I'se skeered fur Missey Eleanor. She told me just after supper to come over hyear to Mr. St. Aubyn's, an' tell him she wuz 'a comin' over hyear herse'f, an' to set up fur her. I know'd there wuz somethin' wrong sah, an' I asked Missey Eleanor what's do matter. But she told me to mind what she said, and off she went. So, I come over hyear to Mr. St. Aubyn's, an' told him what Missey Eleanor said, an' he told me all right, an' told me to stay till Missey Eleanor come. But she didn't come, sah! an' we waited, an' waited, an' waited, till a little while ago, when de fust thing we heered all them men 'a comin' up de road. An' when they got to de house, they busted in de doors, an' hollered, an' hollered, sah, like a million debbils, sah! An' one man, Mister Santee, his name is, he run at Mr. Aubyn, sah, with a big knife, an' grabled him, an' told him Missey Eleanor wuz dar, an' ef he didn't give her up he'd kill him, an' burn everything up. An' some o' de other men, sah, they grabbed Miss Nellie Aubyn, a' hugged her, an' kissed her 'gainst her will, sah, 'cause she squealed murder an' they kep' on a' huggin' an' kissin' her, till Mister Henry Poindexter run in an' got her away, sah! An' when Mrs. Aubyn got down on her knees an' prayed to 'em not to 'buse an' 'sult Miss Nellie, they pulled off her wig, sah, an' hit her in de face with<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC5561-00000030"/> it, an' laffed at her, an' called her a d--d old Union woman, sah!</p> 
               <p>"Oh, sah! they cut up wicked, an' when Mister Aubyn an' de two young gen'lemen began to fight, why they jus' run on 'em, an' trampled 'em under their feet. Jus' then I thought mebbe Missey Eleanor 'll come an' git hurt without knowin' what's' agoin' on, an' I run out an' run froo de men outside de house, an' come across de field to here, 'cause Missey Eleanor 'll come dis way, an' I want to tell her to go back, sah."</p> 
               <p>"Are you sure, Rosa," asked the stranger, as the mulatto ended her awkward but vivid and truthful account, "that Mr. Santee was among those villains yonder?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, sah, jus' as sure as def!"</p> 
               <p>"Well, Rosa," resumed the horseman, "Miss Eleanor is safe, and I have come to take you to her. Would you not like to go to her?"</p> 
               <p>"Oh, sah, 'deed an 'deed I would! I'll run every step of de way after you, sah!"</p> 
               <p>"I will not let you do that, though, Rosa," replied the other, "so mount behind me and you shall ride to her."</p> 
               <p>Why no suspicion of the stranger's intentions arose in the mind of Rosa it would be impossible to say, but none did, and scarcely had the kind invitation been extended to her, ere, with the assistance of the rider, she was seated behind him.</p> 
               <p>The mysterious man then casting a look over at the work of riot and ruin, which seemed still to be going on, turned his horse's head back in the direction he had come, and set off at a trot. In due time he reached the point where the bridle path of the forest struck the main road, and here he halted.</p> 
               <p>"Rosa," said he, as he did so, "you must be blindfolded before you go any further, for the place in which your mistress is concealed must not be known even to her best friends."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, sah," pleaded the mulatto, "please don't! I wouldn't tell anybody ef I was roasted in fire! 'deed an' 'deed, sah, I wouldn't!"</p> 
               <p>Rosa's earnest solicitation, however, was unavailing. Her companion persisted in his demands, and threatened, in the most determined tones, to use force if she did not submit.</p> 
               <p>In an instant a terrible suspicion flashed upon the hitherto unsuspecting girl that the name of her beloved mistress had been used to deceive her, and that she was to be made the instrument of ill either to the former or herself. To conceive this idea was to think also of escape, and as, she had by this time dismounted she bounded away down the road. But she had not taken thirty steps ere she was grasped in the vice-like grip of the stranger, who, however, did not handle her roughly, nor lose his temper. He promptly prevented Rosa from making any outcry by thrusting a handkerchief into her mouth, which done he proceeded in an equally summary manner to bandage her eyes.</p> 
               <p>"Silly girl!" said he to his captive, as she struggled for her freedom, "I am not going to harm you! be still! you cannot escape!"</p> 
               <p>But with her shackles Rosa seemed also to have put off the craven characteristic of the slave, and, refusing to yield, she fought fiercely with her captor, who only conquered her at last by threatening to take her life if she did not submit. This threat, and the cold muzzle of a pistol pressed against her forehead, had the<pb n=""/> desired effect, and Rosa sullenly allowed the stranger to lead her back and place her in the saddle which he had vacated. In this manner he led her through the forest, until he came to the thicket-grown ridge, beneath which Eleanor Poindexter was entombed.</p> 
               <p>The mouth of the cave he reached in the same manner as when he bore our heroine thither, and a minute later Rosa, all gagged and blinded as she was, stood in the presence of Eleanor.</p> 
               <p>"Do not be alarmed, Miss Poindexter," said the stranger, addressing the latter, "Rosa is unharmed. She naturally enough suspected me of evil intentions, and I was obliged to use a little compulsion. She will quickly recover when she learnt that she is with friends. Rosa," he continued speaking to the mulatto, as he unbandaged her eyes, "here is your mistress."</p> 
               <p>As Rosa's sight was restored to her, her tongue was also loosed by the removal of the gag. The scene that ensued can only be imagined. Poor Rosa, overcome by mingled joy and surprise, wept and laughed by turns, and begged the strangers' pardon a dozen times for the trouble she had given him. This was readily granted, and in twenty minutes Rosa was happier than if she had been at home, for she now felt assured of the safety of "Missey Eleanor," as she affectionately called her mistress.</p> 
               <p>"Miss Eleanor," said the stranger, at length, "necessity forces me to absent myself at least for some hours from your presence. Ill has befallen your friends the St. Aubyns, through the malign influence of Santee. I may not tarry to give you any details, Rosa will do so. One promise you must make to me, however, ere I leave, and that is,that under no circumstances will you or Rosa attempt to leave this retreat while I am gone."</p> 
               <p>"That promise, kind friend, I willingly make," answered Eleanor, "on one condition."</p> 
               <p>"On what condition?" asked the stranger.</p> 
               <p>"That you will tell me the name of one to whom I owe such an overwhelming debt of gratitude."</p> 
               <p>The other drew forth a card, and, with a bow, placed it in Eleanor's hand.</p> 
               <p>"I shall never forget you, Mr. Iredell, while memory survives," said the fair and grateful girl, after glancing at the boldly penned autograph, and extending her hand to her hitherto, and even now, unknown friend.</p> 
               <p>The latter pressed the taper fingers and waxlike palm long and warmly before releasing them and taking his departure.</p> 
               <p>Once more he had crossed the airy bridge of grapevine and set off through the quiet, gloomy forest for the main road, and, while we leave Rosa to impart to Eleanor the terrible story of the St. Aubyn outrage, we shall again follow the mysterious Iredell.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC5561-00000031"/> 
               <head>CHAPTER XII.</head> 
               <head type="sub">THE ASSASSINATION.</head> 
               <p>IT yet lacked more than two hours of sunrise as Iredell rode up to the mansion of Mr. St. Aubyn, which, fortunately, owing to the wind setting in from the proper direction, escaped the fate of the barn. The latter was, by this time, a heap of dull red embers, and whose fitful flashes, as a fresh breeze awakened the smouldering demon, caused the shadow of the mansion to rush into the adjoining field as though unrecovered from its previous fright. How long since the mob had left, Mr. Iredell, of course, could not conjecture. He did not advance immediately to the house, but halted at the outer fence, or rather where the outer fence had stood, and listened for a sound that might betray the presence of any person. But the terrible silence that brooded over the scene was unbroken, except by the snapping and cracking of the remains of the fire, and after a pause of several minutes Iredell went forward, and, dismounting, tried the hall door. This was fastened on the inside, showing that some one was within. Whether the present inmates were members of the family, or some of the mob, however, was a matter the settling of which involved some risk. The risk Iredell promptly assumed, and knocking heavily with his knuckles, for the proper knocker had been torn away, he anxiously awaited a response. Thrice did he deliver his summons ere he got any reply, and then a trembling female voice exclaimed:</p> 
               <p>"For God's sake, do us no more harm!"</p> 
               <p>"I am a friend, Mrs. St. Aubyn!" instantly interrupted the traveler. "My name is Iredell. Do you not know my voice?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, yes!" replied the same trembling tones as before. "I will take down the bar."</p> 
               <p>A moment or so later the door was opened, and Iredell entered the mansion, whiled Mrs. St. Aubyn herself-for every servant had been driven away-replaced the bar.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, Mr. Iredell," said she, as she led her visitor into an adjoining parlor, "surely the wicked one himself must have been let loose in the land, and selected my family as his victims. Just before twelve o'clock several hundred maddened wretches, led on, or rather urged on, by James Santee, made a most murderous attack upon our house. They burned the barn and destroyed all they could lay hands on, as you can see for yourself. They vilely insulted both myself and daughter, and how they maltreated Mr. St. Aubyn and my two sons you shall judge. Here they are."</p> 
               <p>As Mrs. St. Aubyn concluded, she guided our friend to a bed, which had been pulled by the mob from one of the chambers to the parlor, and there half emptied of its contents.<pb n=""/> Upon it now lay Mr. St. Aubyn and his two sons, all three with their clothes torn, and their features cut, bruised, and bloody. They had all, too, been insensible up to within about five minutes, and consequently scarcely recognized Iredell.</p> 
               <p>The latter, with words of consolation and encouragement forthwith proceeded to render the victims all the surgical aid in his power, and in half an hour he had the satisfaction of seeing them so far recovered as to be able to converse with him and Mrs. St. Aubyn. From them he received an account of the late attack which was materially the same as that he had already received from Rosa; but there were one or two additional points which of course the latter could not have ascertained. The first was that the <hi rend="i"/>State Vigilance Committee, of which Santee was an officer, and the elder and younger Poindexter members, had, through Santee, warned the St. Aubyn's to leave the State within ten days, under pain of a still fiercer attack than the present one. And the second was that Nellie St. Aubyn had, after being rescued by Henry Poindexter from the insults of his companions, consented to go with him, as the mother understood, to take shelter with his father or Santee-which it was she did not know.</p> 
               <p>The heart-broken mother burst into tears, as she added:</p> 
               <p>"Ah, Mr. Iredell, my poor Nellie, I fear, is too deeply enamored of young Poindexter! But, perhaps I wrong her! She was not in her right senses!"</p> 
               <p>The lips of both the sons quivered, and their brows contracted, while Mr. St. Aubyn pressed his hands upon his face and groaned deeply as Mrs. St. Aubyn spoke.</p> 
               <p>Iredell remained in conversation with his afflicted friends until the sun began to rise, when, promising to see them soon again, and bidding them farewell, he took his departure.</p> 
               <p>It would be natural to suppose that our singular friend was weary, but, apparently indifferent to fatigue, he rode away in the direction of Palmetto Plantation, which in due time he reached. He was astonished as he neared it to see a servant at such an early hour tying up the shutters with crape, and, noticing a negro leaning against the fence, and looking long the road, he asked him what had occurred.</p> 
               <p>"Massa Poindexter waz stabbed froo do heart, sah, up at de meetin' las' night. Somebody, nobody seen who, jabbed a big knife into him an' dat wuz de end ob ole Massa, sah!"</p> 
               <p>"Assassinated!" exclaimed Iredell, in amazement.</p> 
               <p>"Dunno, sah, 'bout dat; but I knows Massa had a big knife jabbed into his heart froo an' froo de middle."</p> 
               <p>"Was his murderer seized?" asked Iredell.</p> 
               <p>"No, sah!" replied the black in a tone not very sorrowful, and Iredell, seeing that he was acquainted merely with the general fact, rode on.</p> 
               <p>Proceeding about half a mile he met a gentleman, mounted like himself, and whom he recognized as an intimate friend of Mr. Poindexter's, although almost a stranger to himself. Of him Iredell inquired into the particulars of the murder, but learned only that the affair was involved in an impenetrable mystery.</p> 
               <pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC5561-00000032"/> 
               <p>In a paroxysm of anger Mr. Poindexter had sprung toward his daughter Eleanor, after her unexpected action-which the narrator detailed very fully to his listener, supposing the latter to be utterly ignorant of it. In the excitement and jostling that ensued, some unknown person had driven a knife into the back of his victim, piercing his heart, and thereby causing his instant death. What motive could have induced the bloody act was as much a mystery as the deed itself, for, though so passionate and headstrong, Mr. Poindexter was courted as a friend, and often used to boast, that he had not an enemy in the world.</p> 
               <p>Iredell bade the gentleman good morning, and continued his journey. As he rode along he pondered deeply on the terrible homicide, and thought it passing strange that he should have heard nothing of it from the St. Aubyns. He could not rid himself of a suspicion that if Santee had not perpetrated the bloody act himself he was cognizant of who did. For it would have been natural to suppose that Santee, being the leader of the mob, would have added the murder of Mr. Poindexter to the supposed harboring of Eleanor as an incentive to his willing <foreign xml:lang="FRA">sans culottes</foreign>. But neither had he nor Henry Poindexter mentioned the occurrence while at the St. Aubyns. Henry, however, had not occupied a seat on the stage, but had been talking to friends in the body of the meeting when the tragedy took place, and, consequently, he might have started with the rest on their vengeful mission without being aware of his father's murder. The more Iredell thought upon the matter, the stronger became his conviction, in regard at least to the complicity of Santee.</p> 
               <p>Suddenly the question occurred to him, how should he break the sad news to Eleanor? for though her father had behaved so unfatherly toward her, yet the springs of filial love were too deeply heated in her heart to be choked or destroyed, even by a long series of wrongs. It was a duty, however, which, no matter how painful, he deemed he ought promptly to perform, and, trusting that when the moment came the proper language would come of itself, he rode on in a direction that brought him to the vicinity of the cave.</p> 
               <p>At the distance of a quarter of a mile from the latter, stood a neat and well kept cottage, deeply embayed, in fact almost concealed, in the midst of a clump of beautiful English Lindens that had been imported at a very heavy expense. To a little stable in the rear of this cottage Iredell straightway led his steed, which, in truth, sorely needed rest and feeding, and, after grooming him himself, he stepped into the cottage.</p> 
               <p>The old black dame whom our friend addressed as Polly, and who was alone in the kitchen-her husband being out in search of wild honey-seemed in no way surprised at the arrival of the owner of the cottage for such in fact was Iredell. On the contrary she proceeded, after wishing him good morning, to prepare a meal for him as methodically as though he had just come down from his chamber. While she was so engaged, he conversed pleasantly with her on casual topics, and when he had refreshed himself he took his rifle from its rack, and went out, saying as he did so:</p> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <p>"I am going on a little shooting <choice>
                     <sic>expidition</sic>
                     <corr>expedition</corr>
                  </choice>, Polly; if any one calls, tell them so. Do you understand?"</p> 
               <p>"De Lor' bres you, Mister Iredell, I understan' you!" replied the negress, who added in a low tone to herself, as the door closed upon the former, "dat dar man's de queerest man an' de best man what de good Lord ebber put on dis earf!"</p> 
               <p>By a roundabout way Iredell reached the cave, shooting as he went, several fine birds as an addition to the larder of his underground hotel.</p> 
               <p>He found Eleanor deeply engaged in the library to which he had directed her attention, while Rosa slept soundly upon a rough pallet, which had been improvised during his absence.</p> 
               <p>Our heroine's first question after greeting her kind friend, was in regard to the St. Aubyns, of whose sufferings Rosa had given her a most vivid account. She was deeply touched with sorrow when informed of the departure of Nellie St. Aubyn in the company of her brother Henry, and deplored her fair companion's lack of firmness and judgment. When, however, Iredell little by little broke to her the awful fate of her father, she found her own firmness unequal to the task of bearing herself up, and, burying her face in her hands, she grieved with that silent, internal grief, which is ten times more poignant than the sorrow that finds its expression in weeping and wringing of hands.</p> 
               <p>"Oh! Mr. Iredell," she moaned, after a long silence, "to think that my dear father should die so ignobly, and in such a cause!"</p> 
               <p>Tenderly did Iredell seek to console the afflicted girl, and at last succeeded, at least to the extent of obtaining her promise that, as much as possible, she would endeavor to regard her misfortune in the light of one of those inscrutable dispensations of an all-wise Providence, which, though apparently misfortunes at first, afterward became merciful blessings.</p> 
               <p>There was now however, another matter which assumed the utmost importance. It was that of Eleanor's future. After the barbarous usage of the St. Aubyns by Santee and his minions, she especially could expect no consideration whatever, and yet she could not remain in her present subterranean abode a great length of time.</p> 
               <p>For whole hours together did our heroine and Iredell, to whom she owed so much, canvass this subject, but no definite course of action was arrived at for more than a week. By this time, however, a plan, which Eleanor's strange friend originated, was set for execution.</p> 
               <p>Under his guidance and protection, she, accompanied by the faithful Rosa, was to make her way to Tennessee, in which State was the valuable plantation left to her by her uncle. This she was, if possible, to sell for cash, and then set out for the North, where she was to be joined by her mother, if Iredell could prevail on the latter to adopt such a course. Eleanor entertained not the slightest doubt of his success, for, besides the love which she knew her mother had for her, she was aware, also, that Mrs. Poindexter had always wished to reside in the North, but had invariably given way to the reverse inclination of her husband. So sure, indeed, was she that her mother<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC5561-00000033"/> would come, that she consented not to attempt to see her before starting on her journey, a proceeding which would have been attended with great risk to all concerned.</p> 
               <p>Every sun that now rose and set saw public matters becoming more and more stormy, and consequently the departure of our lovely heroine from her retreat was fixed at the earliest practicable date after the decision had been arrived at.</p> 
               <p>Accordingly, just past midnight, ten days subsequent to the eventful night that had witnessed her own glorious vindication of the national cause and banner, the murderous attack on the St. Aubyn family, and the tragic fate of her father, Eleanor Poindexter issued from her place of refuge, preceded by Iredell, and followed by Rosa. Though the latter had been blindfolded by Iredell, upon being brought hither, he had been so deeply impressed since then by her display of the noblest qualities of mind that he now dispensed with his previous precaution.</p> 
               <p>Three horses stood ready saddled outside the thicket, and, after a short delay, during which Iredell was readjusting the disturbed bushes, the trio mounted and rode away through the forest to the main road. Here the animals were given the rein, and ere day dawned they had carried their riders twenty miles on their way to Tennessee. A longer distance might have been accomplished, but Iredell at this point had a friend on whom he could depend, with whom he determined to rest until the next night.</p> 
               <p>In this manner he reached Atlanta, Georgia, in safety with his charge, and hero putting up the horses he took passage by railroad for Memphis, Tennessee. Eleanor's plantation lay some three or four miles above the latter city, immediately on the bank of the Mississippi.</p> 
               <p>Previous to reaching Chattanooga a difficulty occurred which almost proved fatal to the success of Iredell's plans; but, with consummate adroitness, he overcame it, and from that time out the journey was without any incident worthy of record. Great good fortune seemed to await our heroine at every turn, for when she arrived in Memphis she found that Mr. Lander, the owner of the plantation next to her own, was exceedingly anxious to purchase the latter. He offered a much larger price than he otherwise would have done if payment was allowed in Northern funds, which he was fearful-although he did not say so-would soon become worthless. Iredell, who conducted the transaction on behalf of his fair protege, shrewdly kept silent in regard to the intentions of Eleanor, and finally obtained a second additional sum before closing out the sale.</p> 
               <p>Mr. Lander congratulated himself hugely on his sharpness, while Mr. Iredell quietly enjoyed his own astuteness. His grateful client persistently endeavored-all the way from Memphis to Cairo, to which city he accompanied her-to gain his acceptance of a handsome sum, to cover the expenses he had necessarily been under. He as persistently refused, but at last, just as they were about to exchange farewells, he compromised the matter by asking our heroine for a small gold ring that she wore. Eleanor hesitated a moment, and then, slipping the ornament from her finger<pb n=""/> ger, she placed it upon one of his, saying, as she did so:</p> 
               <p>"That, Mr. Iredell, is a larger price than my fortune, but you are the more welcome to it on that account, and I am sure that when you see my dear mother and tell her how you obtained it, she will say the same. She gave it to me; my name is engraved within it."</p> 
               <p>The recipient would have returned so precious a memento, but Eleanor forbade it.</p> 
               <p>The train, which was to bear her preserver back to the South, was now nearly ready to start, and Eleanor, as she held his hand, did not seek to check the tears that trickled down her cheeks. At last, the final bell rang, and, as its clangor fell upon her ear, our heroine, with that innocence that is untrammeled by the restraints of etiquette, drew her friend toward her, and, tenderly imprinting a kiss upon his cheek, said, in trembling tones:</p> 
               <p>"Mr. Iredell, I kiss you for my dear mother; when you see her give it to her, and tell her I will await her in Philadelphia. God bless you, dear friend! God bless you! I hope we shall meet again."</p> 
               <p>"And God bless you, dear Eleanor!" was the response, made in a very husky voice.</p> 
               <p>The next moment the panting locomotive rushed away.</p> 
               <p>Eleanor Poindexter's simple and impressive act of affection was witnessed by a crowd of spectators, and a subdued murmur of applause ran from lip to lip.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC5561-00000034"/> 
               <head>CHAPTER XIII.</head> 
               <head>THE ANGEL'S MISSION.</head> 
               <p>SAD, sad, indeed, were the feelings that welled up within our heroine's bosom as she turned away from the depot to reach the hotel in which Mr. Iredell had succeeded in procuring rooms for her. The last six weeks afforded truly a dark and repulsive retrospect, while the future was, like the future of other mortals, a sea of uncertainty.</p> 
               <p>Such an uninviting town as Cairo possessed no attractions for Eleanor, and she, therefore, soon took passage for Philadelphia, in which city she was to await the appearance of her mother.</p> 
               <p>A month passed away, and as yet no tidings had reached our heroine, who fondly anticipated the pleasure of soon being joined by Mrs. Poindexter. Finally, at the expiration of six weeks, a letter arrived, which she noticed was directed in the handwriting of Mr. Iredell.</p> 
               <p>Impatiently she opened the missive which, however, she found had been already violated, most likely by some rebel post-office official.</p> 
               <p>Ere she read far, a sentence informed her of the sudden illness of her mother, who had been taken sick immediately after the burial of Mr. Poindexter. A succeeding sentence told her how her mother had rapidly grown worse, and further along was an account, couched in as gentle words as possible, of how the dear one had called for her Eleanor before she expired, and how she had prayed that Heaven might bless her exiled child.</p> 
               <p>Here was indeed a terrible blow! Never dreaming that death would interfere, and cut short a life so cherished, Eleanor, as we have elsewhere stated, had, at time of setting out for Memphis, foregone the risk and delight of a parting interview with her mother. And now she might commune with the loved one only when she had herself put off the garments of this life and passed on into the land of shadows.</p> 
               <p>The well-chosen words of consolation and endearment, that made the conclusion of the letter, softened somewhat the heart-breaking intelligence, and added a degree or two to the strength of a feeling for the author, which had already passed that of mere friendship.</p> 
               <p>"I gave your kiss, dearest Eleanor," ended the writer, "to your mother, as you desired me. I imprinted it upon her cold cheek as she reposed so stilly and softly in her shroud. Never performed I so holy a duty. But let me not dwell upon your bereavement longer than to point you to that Heavenly source from which alone flows the real balm for wounded hearts. I shall be unable to reach Philadelphia for some time yet, but I shall continue to hold you in the deepest reverence, and, allow me to add, affection.</p> 
               <p>"P. S.-Sealed in the inclosed paper<pb n=""/> I send you a long tress of soft brown hair, mixed, as you will see, with silvery strands. I need not tell you whose it is. I obtained from the lady who attended your mother <emph>double</emph> as much as I herewith send you; but fearing that, perhaps, in these troublous times, this letter might miscarry, or be lost, I retained one-half. I will preserve it carefully, and, when I see you again, will add it to what I now send, or, in case of loss, will replace the latter with it."</p> 
               <p>The little sealed paper referred to had not yet been opened by Eleanor in her eagerness to read the accompanying letter, but now she carefully, reverently broke the seal, and, taking out the sacred memento, pressed it to her lips. Then, wrapping it again in its envelope, she placed it next her heart, and murmured:</p> 
               <p>"God forever bless you, Mr. Iredell, for your tender forethought and solicitude."</p> 
               <p>Eleanor was now an orphan, and, in reality, nearly friendless, for, though the fact of her being a Southern refugee awakened for her the good wishes of the people among whom she found herself, yet she had no one to whom she could confide her sorrows, and from whom she could draw consolation, excepting poor, faithful Rosa. Yet a better or truer friend she could not have found, for, though uneducated, the latter continued to display all those finer qualities of mind which had originally caused Eleanor Poindexter to strike from her the degrading chains of the slave and make her free.</p> 
               <p>Being of an active temperament, our heroine could not endure idleness; and it was therefore her constant aim to find employment, not only for her head and heart, but also for her hands. Her philanthropic efforts were directed principally in behalf of the families of those noble men who had, in a vast number of instances, rushed to the battle's front ere they had time to attend properly to the wants of their dependent wives and children. The greater portion of the proceeds of her immense fortune she devoted to the great cause, and many hundred hearts were made thrice happy by her munificence.</p> 
               <p>Suddenly came the tidings of the first really great battle of the war-Bull's Run. After the first news thereof, every hour brought fresh and heart-rending accounts of the sufferings of the wounded Union heroes, many of whom had been left to the after-horrors of battle. Surgeons were lacking, nurses were not to be had, and urgent appeals came for both, and also for lint and bandages.</p> 
               <p>Not for a moment did Eleanor attempt to resist the inclination that arose within her to offer her services, and, ere she had finished perusing a graphic detail of a scene that had occurred in a hurriedly made hospital just beyond Centreville, she resolved to devote herself to the welfare of the sick and wounded soldiers in the field. There were thousands of women who would attend the city hospitals, but none would venture to the field, where danger and hardship lurked in every step.</p> 
               <p>"It is my solemn duty!" said Eleanor to herself, "and ere to-day's sun sets I will be on my way."</p> 
               <p>The rest of the morning, and part of the afternoon, our <choice>
                     <sic>heorine</sic>
                     <corr>heroine</corr>
                  </choice> spent in arranging her own affairs,and purchasing quantities of little articles that she<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC5561-00000035"/> judged would be most acceptable to the suffering soldiers.</p> 
               <p>With her precious freight, and accompanied by Rosa, who insisted, against all remonstrances, on going with her, Eleanor Poindexter, the child of such luxuriant affluence, set forth upon her mission of mercy and peril.</p> 
               <p>At Washington she experienced no delay in obtaining the necessary passes, and in due time she reached a point above Centreville, at which were the outer Union pickets. Like a ministering angel, she had, during her progress hither, distributed fully three-fourths of her supply of delicacies. Just before her arrival at the point referred to military necessities had compelled a contraction of the Federal lines. The order, therefore, had unfortunately been obeyed so promptly that a number of wounded men had been left behind in a wood about a mile west of Centreville. What rendered the matter more painful was that the helpless patients had received no attention for over twenty-four hours. No sooner did Eleanor hear this than she resolved to visit them at once, despite the peril she ran of being captured by the rebel cavalry.</p> 
               <p>Major Williams, the Federal commandant, had but awhile before asked vainly for volunteers to go to the relief of the wounded men, and he was about to order a company out for the duty at the time our heroine arrived. This fact he stated to her, in hopes that she would be dissuaded thereby from her own resolution; but after listening to him she said:</p> 
               <p>"Major, surely your men misunderstood you. Will you grant me permission to ask for volunteers?"</p> 
               <p>"As you choose," replied the officer, courteously; "but I fear you will have no success," he added.</p> 
               <p>"We shall see," said Eleanor in pleasant tones.</p> 
               <p>One regiment had been already drawn up for some duty or other, and, riding down its front, accompanied by his fair companion, Major Williams stated that Miss Poindexter had come all the way from Philadelphia in order that she might devote herself entirely to the wants of the sick and wounded soldiers.</p> 
               <p>"She intends," said he, "to go over to the hospital in the woods west of Centreville. She would like to have an escort; but, if she cannot obtain one, she says she will go by herself. Now, then, who will volunteer for the duty, or rather the pleasure?"</p> 
               <p>Scarcely had the Major ceased speaking, when, with single accord, every man stepped forward one pace, and, removing their caps, cheered wildly, and offered instantly to accompany the lovely young lady on her mission of mercy.</p> 
               <p>"I acknowledge myself vanquished, Miss Poindexter," said Major Williams, turning to Eleanor, "but I still wish you would be persuaded to remain here. You know not into what hands you will fall if you should be taken by the enemy."</p> 
               <p>"I place my trust in God, Major," answered Eleanor, with such simple, dignified faith, that the rough soldier was touched; and he sought no further to dissuade her.</p> 
               <p>One hundred and fifty men, partly from each company, were selected, and, forming about their beautiful charge and her indomitable servant, Rosa, they marched out, amidst the cheers of their companions, toward<pb n=""/> Centreville. The captain who led them-Stevens by name-had seen service in Mexico, and was as prudent as he was brave. He chanced, also, to be well acquainted with that region of country, a fact that enabled him to march by another road than the one generally used.</p> 
               <p>The hospital was reached without incident, and our heroine immediately proceeded to dispense her luxuries and kind words of consolation. Flitting from pallet to pallet-constructed of trees, branches and straw-and from stretcher to stretcher, she administered here a little jelly, there a gill of cordial; to one poor fellow a sip of wine, and to another a copious drink of water, for which he had been begging for hours.</p> 
               <p>Never before in her life had Eleanor witnessed so much horror accumulated, and on every pale or grimy face over which she bent she dropped her pitying tears. There were forty-five patients alive, and four dead. One wretched man, who, after having been shot through the body, had had his eyes ruthlessly thrust out with a bayonet, exclaimed, as she gave him a draught of water:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, God bless you! God bless you, dear lady! I wish I had my eyes again, only for a minute, that I might look up into your beautiful face, for I know you are as beautiful as you are good!"</p> 
               <p>A boy who was dying, as she pushed back his glossy curls and pressed her cool hand upon his burning brow, exclaimed, in the ecstacy of his delirium:</p> 
               <p>"I knew you would come, mother! I've been praying for you to come all day! Kiss me, mother!"</p> 
               <p>Instantly the request was granted, and with a satisfied smile upon his pallid features, the recipient expired.</p> 
               <p>On the next pallet lay a stalwart, bearded man, unable to speak by reason of a ball having completely cut out his tongue, and also wounded him through both jaws. He was also mortally wounded in the side. In his hand he clutched a pocket picture-case, on one side of which was photographed a fair young woman with a babe sleeping in her arms, and on the other side of which was written, in letters a little straggling, but plain:</p> 
               <p>"<hi rend="i"/>John Collins, Fire Zouaves, Mercer street, New York-his dear wife and baby."</p> 
               <p>He placed the case in Eleanor's hands, after pressing it to his lips, and made her to understand by motions that he would die happy if the picture were returned to his wife.</p> 
               <p>From several others Eleanor received cherished articles, love mementoes, charms, which, alas! had not charmed aside the bullet-pocket-books containing money, and farewell messages of affection to be delivered to mothers, fathers, wives, sisters, and sweethearts.</p> 
               <p>At last, amidst the reiterated blessings of her grateful patients, our heroine had accomplished all in her power. But this alone did not satisfy her. The wounded men were still in danger of capture, and she forthwith proposed to Captain Stevens that eighty or ninety of his men be detailed to bear their unfortunate comrades to a place of safety.</p> 
               <p>"That'll be a big job, Miss Poindexter," replied the Captain, "but we guess we'll run most any risk, after what you've done. Men," he continued, "the lady wants us to carry<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC5561-00000036"/> our comrades back into the lines. You'll do it, I know, to please her. I'll relieve you now and then, and the job'll come easier."</p> 
               <p>"We'll do it! We'll do anything she says!" answered the self same men who had before been too much afraid to volunteer for the very mission they were now accomplishing.</p> 
               <p>In as short a time as possible, the dead men were buried, and Eleanor's escort, bearing among them the surviving inmates of the hospital, set out on their return.</p> 
               <p>Half the distance was passed in safety, and all were congratulating themselves on a successful issue of their expedition, when a body of between seventy and eighty rebel cavalry came dashing after them.</p> 
               <p>To the undisciplined soldier, unable as he is to appreciate the safety that lies in a cool and determined use of his bayonet, nothing is more dreadful than a cavalry charge;<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WRIGHT2-0043-NOTE002" n="*"
                        place="foot">
                     <p >It is a well known fact that a thousand veteran infantry men can defy and laugh to scorn the fiercest onslaught of four times their number of the best cavalry that can be put in the field. The reader doubtless remembers the dread that the mere appearance of Stuart's rebel horsemen used to strike into the Union volunteers. But now, and for some time past, a picket of a few men, armed with the bayonet, will not only face, but actually defeat and even capture twice their number of Stuart's boldest riders-W. B.</p>
                  </note> and on the occasion to which we allude it is quite likely that, but for the timely and heroic action of Eleanor Poindexter, Captain Stevens would have found himself left entirely alone. Seeing the men wavering, our heroine checked her horse, and then urging him rearward along the files, she exclaimed:</p> 
               <p>"None but cowards will fly!"</p> 
               <p>These magic words, and their still more magic tones, instantly stopped the wavering, and Captain Stevens, taking quick advantage of the moment, thundered:</p> 
               <p>"Company, about face! shoulder arms!"</p> 
               <p>The men had been well drilled in "the manual," and came from a "shift" to a "shoulder" with precision.</p> 
               <p>"Front rank," quickly added the commander, "resist cavalry-rear rank, present-fire by rank, ready, aim-steady, now-wait for the word-steady-<emph>fire!</emph>"</p> 
               <p>The charging column of maddened steeds, infuriated by the spurs, and shouts, and yells of their riders, struck the gleaming line of bayonets. Those in front essayed to sheer off from the deadly and firmly held points, but they were pushed forward by those behind.</p> 
               <p>Each word of the latter part of Captain Stevens' command had been deliberately uttered, as his cool eye calculated the shortening distance of his foes, and the word "<emph>fire!</emph>" let loose a volley on the rebels, at such close quarters, that half a dozen saddles were cleared.</p> 
               <p>For an instant the rebel steeds were stunned, as it were, into a prancing, plunging herd. But so well trained were they, that a trumpet blast brought them to their ranks, whilst a second blare hurried them off in rapid yet orderly retreat.</p> 
               <p>At that time the rebels had not rid themselves of the unfortunate belief that a Southron, according to their arithmetic, was a fraction the superior in battle of four Union heroes, and consequently the seventy repulsed<pb n=""/> cavaliers only drew off to make a second attack.</p> 
               <p>This critical moment called forth Eleanor's good judgment as prominently as the other had her bravery, for turning to Rosa, she said:</p> 
               <p>"Rosa, you know the road we came along! Ride back to Major Williams and tell him we have been attacked, but are standing our ground! You are not afraid, are you?"</p> 
               <p>"No! no, Missy Eleanor, I'se not afraid! I sees what you want! You wants more sogers, an' a cann'n gun!"</p> 
               <p>Eleanor had no time to add a word before the mulatto was dashing back to the Union lines. She was a capital rider, and with both feet and whip she urged her animal to the top of his speed.</p> 
               <p>"Well, Miss Poindexter," exclaimed Captain Stevens, "you ought to be commissioned a general, and that yellow girl of yours ought to be put on your staff! She knows something. Be steady, now, men," continued the speaker, addressing the latter, "re-enforcements 'll soon be up now! Keep your lines steady, and the reb's 'll soon have to skedaddle!"</p> 
               <p>The enemy perceived the departure of the messenger, and well knowing what the result must soon be, they prepared for a second and fiercer charge than before, in hopes of capturing the escort and wounded ere help came. This charge was broken ere it had neared the serried Union bayonets, and an attempted flank movement was likewise foiled in a masterly manner.</p> 
               <p>Time was growing precious on both sides. Captain Stevens feared to retreat too much as his men might be thrown into disorder, and this was the exact object the rebels wished to accomplish.</p> 
               <p>Suddenly from a wooded knoll about a mile back a puff of smoke was seen, followed by a roar, and at the same instant a vengeful shell fell close to the rebel cavalry. Another and another of the screeching missiles sped over the heads of Eleanor's escort, and, awhile later, rising over a ridge in the road, came a full Union regiment at the double-quick.</p> 
               <p>The chivalrous would-be captors waited for no further demonstration, but leaving their killed and wounded in the hands of Captain Stevens, they galloped off. The piece of artillery a light twelve-pounder, thundered up, and being again speedily unlimbered, sent another shell or two after the fugitives to add wings to their flight.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC5561-00000037"/> 
               <head>CHAPTER XIV.</head> 
               <head type="sub">A HEROIC DEED.</head> 
               <p>MAJOR Williams had not expected that the detachment he sent out with Miss Poindexter would attempt to bring in all the wounded, and when, therefore, Rosa appeared in his camp with her urgent message, he the more promptly ordered out the force already mentioned. The rescuing regiment was accompanied by the faithful mulatto, who would sooner have perished than desert her mistress or have any harm befall her.</p> 
               <p>Not only was the praise of our heroine on the lips of all immediately concerned, but, Major Williams sent to the War Department a special and glowing account of her devoted and heroic conduct; and the sole reason why the public had not an opportunity of knowing of the services she rendered, was that her own modesty forbade any mention being made thereof.</p> 
               <p>General McClellan had now assumed command of the Army of the Potomac, and it was presently apparent that another battle would not take place soon unless forced on by the enemy, as the demoralized Union troops required a vast amount of reformation before they could be brought to any sort of excellence. Eleanor, therefore, after spending several days in the hospitals about Washington, went North for the purpose of fulfilling the hundreds of promises that sick and dying soldiers had obtained from her. Those that she could not perform in person she executed by letter, and the extent of her correspondence was such that during one week she expended nearly twenty dollars in postage stamps alone.</p> 
               <p>The season wore on, and certain significant movements rendered it evident that a collision must occur at a close date between the hosts of the Union and the legions of rebellion. Our heroine, therefore, immediately prepared to take the field, and her preparations were not completed too soon, for after a few comparatively unimportant skirmishes, in several of which Eleanor participated, came the battle of Edward's Ferry.</p> 
               <p>Many a sorrowing bosom heaves at the recollection of that conflict, for many a gallant soldier of the Union perished there uselessly on the banks and in the waves of the darkly flowing Potomac.</p> 
               <p>Fortunately for our heroine she did not get forward in time to cross the river, and consequently she escaped almost certain capture. However, she found opportunities more than sufficient for the full exercise of her self-sacrificing philanthropy on this side of the swollen river. And we cannot forbear recording, to the eternal disgrace of the Confederates, that they fired volley after volley across into the helpless wounded and dying, notwithstanding the fact that they saw Eleanor passing from one to another<pb n=""/> ther attended only by Rosa, and ministering to the unfortunate.</p> 
               <p>Thanks to a merciful Providence, the devoted girl escaped uninjured, as did also Rosa, who faced the whistling balls with as much coolness as her mistress. The latter had given her leave, if she chose, to remain in a place of safety, where she might, too, be equally as useful as in the more exposed position. But Rosa's invariable answer was:</p> 
               <p>"No, no, Missey Eleanor, I love you too much; 'sides, I wants to show you, so you'll see it fur you's'f, that a slave, when she's free, or even when she ain't free, ken have as much heart an' be as brave as a white pussun!"</p> 
               <p>It was during this bloody action at Edward's Ferry-better known as Ball's Bluff-that some wounded hero, experiencing the kindness of our heroine, and filled with gratitude, gave her the title of <hi rend="i"/>The Angel of the Battle-Field. In an instant the words passed from lip to lip, and thenceforth the gentle Eleanor was called Miss Eleanor, <hi rend="i"/>The Angel of the Battle-Field.</p> 
               <p>"Ah my dear old mother," wrote a gallant fellow of the lamented Baker's regiment, "you ought to have seen Miss Eleanor flying round among tho boys that got struck. I tell you, mother, when she came to Jim Carty and me, as we were lying in a little hollow, the rain pouring down on us in torrents, and the rebel bullets whizzing around us, I felt like I was home with you and Sis, and Jem cried, right out with gladness, and said he felt like he'd like to die for her. She unstrapped our knapsacks and put our blankets over us. We give her a new name to-day-'The Angel of the Battle-Field,' and she deserves it, don't you think so? I know I wouldn't have been here to-day if it hadn't been for her, and I want you to write her a pretty letter for me, and I want you to pray for her, too."</p> 
               <p>What an enviable title, and how gloriously did our heroine win it. Richard of Anjou wrote the names of Ascalon and Acre in blood, that he might attach "the Lion Heart" to his name; and Napoleon widowed and orphaned half of Europe for "a ten century" renown. But Eleanor Poindexter, the loyal lily of the South, by her sweet deeds of love and mercy has won a place in every heart that can cherish whatever is noble and truly great.</p> 
               <p>Eleanor was supremely happy in her hazardous labors, excepting those moments in which she thought of her younger brother and sister, left, as she knew they were, to no better influence nor guidance than Henry's. At the time she had received the letter from her mysterious friend, Iredell, in which was inclosed the tress of her mother's hair, she had written him a long reply, in which she begged of him to obtain, if possible, control of the two orphans and send them on to her at Philadelphia. Vainly she had waited for a reply, and just as vainly did she wait the coming of her brother and sister. She had long since arrived at the conclusion that either her letter had miscarried, or been destroyed by some vindictive rebel postmaster, or that Iredell himself had suddenly died.</p> 
               <p>What was her surprise, therefore, one day to receive a letter, via Richmond and Fortress Monroe, directed<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC5561-00000038"/> in the bold, clear chirography of Iredell. Like the first one, it had been violated. So unexpected was its reception that Eleanor's feelings mastered her for several minutes, and prevented her from opening it. Controlling herself, however, she removed the sheet of letter paper from its envelope, and spreading it open glanced at its contents. In an instant she noticed that the handwriting was different from that of the direction, and looking at the bottom she was almost stunned to see the signature of James L. Santee, immediately above which her eye as quickly caught the underscored words, "<emph>Your adoring lover, or your bitter enemy, as you may choose</emph>."</p> 
               <p>So totally overcome was the fair Eleanor, that she sat in her little tent without power to peruse the epistle. At length, however, summoning to her aid all her determination, she did so.</p> 
               <p>"Miss Poindexter," it began, "how I came into possession of this letter was by a very fortunate accident. I suppose you will call it by an opposite name. However, my dearest, we will not quarrel on that point. I expect that you will fret and fume the pretty flesh off your bones to know that I came across this letter of your dear friend Iredell, but I hope that it will not add too much to your anxiety when I tell you that Iredell will be properly attended to. He has long been looked on with suspicion, and now he will be <emph>fixed</emph>.</p> 
               <p>"Your dear, or, let me quote correctly, your 'loving friend', Iredell, had filled every side of a long foolscap sheet with information, and love and various other matters, which I admired so much as a curiosity that I retained it, and send you this in its place."</p> 
               <p>Here followed a semi-ironical, semi-obscene allusion to himself and Eleanor, which respect for the feelings of the latter has deterred us from recording. And the conclusion was such an incongruous mixture of rubbishing jargon that the belief forced itself upon the reader that the author must have been intoxicated when he wrote it.</p> 
               <p>Wonder, curiosity, sorrow and indignation took turns in the possession of our heroine's mind after she had perused the shameful document. Previous to her coming to the army this misfortune would have taken a terrible effect on Eleanor's mind, but it dwindled to small dimensions as she compared it with the misfortunes that she had witnessed befalling others for months past. So she resigned herself to Fate.</p> 
               <p>Time rolled on, and at last the Army of the Potomac prepared for a grand demonstration against the enemy, who had so impregnably intrenched themselves at Manassas. Whether, with one mighty effort, it was to hurl itself like a mailed giant on the rebel stronghold, or whether its strategic evolutions were to accomplish the desired result, had keen debated and settled by the solemn counsel of its leaders and high government officials. It was to strike a long distance in the rear, and, accordingly, the next announcement was that the Army had landed on the peninsula, and commenced its march toward the heart of the rebellion, Richmond.</p> 
               <p>Thither did Eleanor, attended as usual by the ever true and faithful Rosa, accompany the Union host, and soon enough did she find ample<pb n=""/> employment for those self-sacrificing exertions that had rendered her so beloved and respected by the soldiers.</p> 
               <p>The subject of the sufferings, both in battle and otherwise, of the Army of the Potomac, its splendid bravery and indomitable endurance, has been too often spoken of and written of to require any repetition here. Suffice it to say that, from the first conflict at Yorktown to the wasting carnage at Malvern Hill, the angelic Eleanor Poindexter was ever present, exercising her heavenly offices, despite every peril and horror by which she was surrounded. Surely she must have been under the special protection of God's good angels, for, beneath the darkest battle pall, and where the tempest of iron rained most pitilessly, she bound the gaping wound, or moistened the dying lip, or spoke sweet words of hope and consolation in the dulling ear, whilst shot and shell screeched and howled above and around her like demons from the eternal lake of fire.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER XV.</head> 
               <head type="sub">CAPTURED AT LAST.</head> 
               <p>WITH what anxious expectancy the national heart beat as the details of the sanguinary seven-days' battle came in is even yet fresh in our memories. It was known that McClellan was endeavoring to reach the James river, and it was also known that his flank was thus fully exposed to the consummate Lee and Jackson.</p> 
               <p>A flying march, then a halt, a hasty unlimbering of pieces, a mustering out of hundreds of souls, and another rapid march to the rear, were the bloody monotony of those dreadful seven days. Mothers, who lost your noble boys there, we weep with you indeed! Let us not, however, dwell upon the carnage, but, replacing the pall, leave the question of responsibility with that mighty commander whose decisions man may not gainsay.</p> 
               <p>Malvern Hill was the last point at which the rebels could possibly make a successful attack upon the Federal army before it reached the protection of the gunboats, and, here, as General McClellan had rightly conjectured, they made their final and most desperate attempt to overthrow the Army of the Potomac. So fearful was McClellan of anything going wrong, that he spent the whole night previous to the battle in personally disposing of his wearied but heroic legions. Glorious Kearney, stout old Heintzleman, Fighting Joe Hooker, and Unconquerable Sumner were all rightly placed and impatiently awaited the onslaught of the foe. Many a brave volunteer, as he rolled himself in his blanket that night and cast himself upon the green turf, gazed up at the far-away stars and thought how the self-same orbs, when they again reached the zenith, might twinkle down upon his own grave or corpse.</p> 
               <pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC5561-00000039"/> 
               <p>Dawn came at last, and with it came the battle, for as the first silvery rays glimmered up the eastern sky dark masses of rebels began to move and manuvre in front of the Union army. The latter had been formed in a semicircle, a plan afterward adopted in every detail by General Meade at Gettysburg, the arc presented to the enemy, and the chord free for rapid tactical evolutions.</p> 
               <p>Lee was stirring betimes, and scarcely had the sunlight illumined the hill-tops before his closely-massed artillery was belching shot and shell, cannister and grape, into the devoted Union lines. It was three o'clock in the afternoon, however, ere he got his gray-clad hordes properly positioned for the grand attack. At this crisis, as usual, there was an ominous lull in the firing, and during this lull the Federal commander wisely strengthened those points at which it was apparent the heaviest blows were to be struck.</p> 
               <p>These preparations were just concluded as the rebel cannon again burst forth in horrid harmony. Under cover of this fire a heavy column was hurled against the Federal army, at that moment the living Gibraltar of the Union.</p> 
               <p>The battle-field was open and hilly, or, more properly speaking, undulating; and as the rushing rebel column sank and rose into the troughs and over the billows of rich green grass, it looked like some fabulous monster hastening to a feast of blood.</p> 
               <p>On, on it comes, roaring, closer and closer. The artillery has ceased again, and the head of the monster is at the foot of the slope whose summit Franklin holds. The volleys of musketry hurtled into its body draws only its blood and rage; and, with a convulsive bound, it crushes its way into Franklin's <foreign xml:lang="FRA">corps d'armee</foreign>.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WRIGHT2-0043-NOTE003" n="*"
                        place="foot">
                     <p >The youthful appearance of Franklin's corps always attracted general notice, and it came at last to be called the "Boy Corps." When Harrison's Landing was reached, Franklin chanced to meet General Kearney.</p>
                     <p >"Well, Kearney," said he, taking the only hand of his companion-in-arms, "What do you think of my boys?"</p>
                     <p >"Boys! boys!" exclaimed the one-armed hero, in his characteristic, charging manner. "why, d-n it, Franklin, they're not boys! they're horses, air, regular horses!" W. B.</p>
                  </note>
               </p> 
               <p>The rock was splintered and toppled back with the impact of the blow, but, quivering in every atom, it rushed forward instantly, and pushed back the monster into the grassy waves at its feet. Again, collecting its energies, the reptile charged at Sumner, but failed as it had before. Its third attempt was made upon Hooker and Kearney, and how these heroes repulsed it, needs no comment. There was now but one untried point remaining, namely, the left wing, held by Porter's regulars, and, gathering up all its expiring powers, it precipitated its scarred body full upon these devoted men, and sought, with its gory claws to tear its way to a flanking position. How it failed, and how, breathless and bleeding, it was hurled back into the grassy sea over which it had come, and how it writhed its mangled body away to its retreat, scored and shattered at every movement by the gunboats, has passed into history.</p> 
               <p>During the battle, Eleanor Poindexter had got almost to the extreme left, and while the closing contest<pb n=""/> was raging, she was most unfortunately captured-as was also the faithful Rosa-during a fierce charge by the Twenty-first South Carolina Regiment. Several desperate attempts were made to recapture "The Angel of the Battle-field," but the foe were too fleet, and, therefore, secured the prize.</p> 
               <p>As Fate willed it, our heroine and Rosa, the mulatto, were taken by a squad of men who had been recruited from the very district in which Eleanor had lived nearly all her life. The consequence was that she was instantly recognized, and subjected to the jeers and ribald insults of her enraged captors, until a lieutenant came to her rescue.</p> 
               <p>"What are you about, you villains!" he exclaimed, dashing one and another of them aside. "I saw that lady giving a drink of water to two men of your own company, who were dying. One of them was my own brother, and the first man that insults her has got to fight me!"</p> 
               <p>"She's a renegade! she's a Southerner, and ought to be on the side of the South!" shouted several fierce voices, made husky by the dust of the battle.</p> 
               <p>"It's a lie! I don't believe a word of it!" retorted the officer. "She's an angel! I saw her myself all the time during the battle, and she was helping the wounded and comforting the dying, our own men as well as the Yankees, right under the heaviest fire of our pieces, and I don't want to hear any more about it!"</p> 
               <p>This rebel officer immediately detailed a strong guard, under whose protection he placed our heroine and her servant Rosa, with instructions where to report.</p> 
               <p>All that night Eleanor was obliged to pass just in the rear of the Confederate army, and, as may be supposed, sleep was put far from her. In the pitying kindness of her heart she offered to assist in the care of the wounded, but she was not allowed to do so. The next morning she and Rosa were taken to Richmond, where they were delivered into the hands of a Major Wharton. With a respect that becomes the more conspicuous from the fact of its being exceptional to the general rebel habit, Major Wharton selected, for the use of Eleanor and her servant, a small outhouse, separated entirely from the main building, where the ordinary prisoners were lodged. He lauded the object that had brought her to the battle-field, and apologized that circumstances did not permit him to treat her as well as he would like.</p> 
               <p>As our heroine was passing to the out-building spoken of, Rosa suddenly called her attention to a man who was standing at a little distance.</p> 
               <p>"There's Mister Santee, Missey Eleanor, jus' as sartin as def!"</p> 
               <p>A cold chill ran through our heroine's frame, and she quickly raised her eyes and glanced in the direction indicated. But quick as was her motion, she had not an opportunity of verifying or destroying Rosa's assertion, for the person whom Rosa had seen passed at the moment out of sight behind the corner of a fence. Eleanor paid no more attention to the matter, for she confidently believed that Rosa was mistaken.</p> 
               <p>Miss Poindexter had been too long schooled in hardship to waste time in useless repinings over her present situation, and sending out into the city she obtained, at exorbitant prices,<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC5561-00000040"/> various matters wherewith she and her unflinching servant might be rendered as comfortable as possible.</p> 
               <p>One soldier only was placed as a guard before the entrance to the little prison, and he, ignorant why his fair charge was a captive, and struck, too, with her beauty and gentle demeanor, endeavored, in a number of kindly ways, to gain her approbation.</p> 
               <p>"I've got some papers here, Miss," said he, in the evening, "and if you'll accept of them you're very welcome to them. They'll pass your time. I wish I had something better to read, but I haven't."</p> 
               <p>Eleanor quickly accepted the offer, with many thanks, and was soon after poring over the papers, one of which was a <title>Charleston Mercury</title> of a recent date. A paragraph, with the caption "A SAD FATALITY," caught her eye. It read thus:</p> 
               <p>"Jas. L. Santee, Esq., of Beaufort county, sends us the following statement in regard to the family of his friend and neighbor, Robert Poindexter, Esq., the proprietor of the celebrated Palmetto Plantation. At a political meeting held just after the secession of Virginia, on Mr. Santee's estate, Mr. Poindexter was mysteriously assassinated. The deed was committed by some unknown person, during an excitement caused by the action of Miss Eleanor Poindexter, who, in the very faces of the assembled multitude, audaciously waved and saluted the Yankee Stars and Stripes. She instantly fled, and, with the aid of an accomplice-at whom the finger of suspicion points as her father's murderer-reached Tennessee.</p> 
               <p>"There she sold a valuable plantation, which had been left to her by her uncle, and with the proceeds went to the North. She has never been heard of since, and it is quite likely that the infatuated girl at last fell a victim to the accomplice by whose assistance she got to Tennessee.</p> 
               <p>"Within a few days after the murder of Mr. Poindexter, his estimable lady was suddenly stricken down and died. A short time subsequent, Henry, the eldest son, took his remaining brother and sister down to Beaufort, in hopes that the invigorating pleasures of that fashionable resort would, in a measure, divert their minds from the grief which had fallen upon them. But, sad to relate, both these lovely children were drowned while enjoying a sail on the bay with their protector.</p> 
               <p>"This accumulation of trouble so weighed upon the mind of Henry that, within the past few days, he became a raving lunatic. Mr. Santee kindly took charge of him, but, by some means or other, he made his escape, since which time no clue to his whereabouts has been obtained, though a most vigorous search has been instituted. No doubt exists that the unfortunate man has committed suicide in some out of the way place which naught but chance will discover.</p> 
               <p>"Thus, within so short a time, one of the most wealthy and aristocratic families in the State, has been swept from existence. Eleanor, a beautiful, educated, and highly refined young lady, is still in the North, but whether living or dead is uncertain.</p> 
               <p>"Mr. Santee has administered to the estate of his late friend, and will charge himself with the proper management thereof until the truant Eleanor, or some other heir, comes forward."</p> 
               <pb n=""/> 
               <p>This was indeed a most fearful stroke to our heroine, and she was unable to repress the emotions that were awakened within her by the perusal of the paragraph quoted.</p> 
               <p>Terrible, also, were her suspicions in regard to the complicity of that dark-souled man, Santee, with the "sad fatality" spoken of by the <title>Mercury</title>. Had she been ignorant of the control that Santee had obtained over her brother Henry, and how he had attempted to make herself the victim thereof, she would not perhaps have thought as she did. But added to this knowledge, she had the testimony of her own dear mother as to his villainy, and the testimony of Iredell. And as Iredell's image came up before her, she was seized by another anxiety. The article in the <title>Mercury</title> had come from Santee, and the accomplice therein mentioned could be no other than her mysterious friend, who, she remembered, had experienced some peril near Chattanooga, the character of which, however, she had never heard. Could it be that Santee had followed him to Tennessee? Surely not, or he would have found an opportunity for revenge. Iredell's last letter, however, had fallen by accident into Santee's hands. And Santee, in the one that he sent to Eleanor in place of the original, boasted that, by it, Iredell had placed himself in his power, and that he would most certainly use this power. Had he done so? Alas! naught but a miracle could prevent him.</p> 
               <p>"What a demon is that awful man!" murmured our fair captive, shuddering, and involuntarily casting about her a glance of alarm.</p> 
               <p>The rest of the evening Eleanor endeavored to beguile by conversing with Rosa. She assured the latter that she would not permit the rebel authorities to seize her as a slave. But if, regardless of the deed of emancipation-which, by-the-by, Rosa had religiously preserved ever since Eleanor returned it to her-they proceeded to sell her, she would buy her at any price. Being reduced again to slavery had been Rosa's greatest fear in accompanying her mistress to the battle-field; but her love for, and gratitude to, the latter had induced her to brave even this peril.</p> 
               <p>At eleven o'clock the guard was changed, the place of the first-who was a well-bred kind of man-being taken by a sullen-looking fellow, who, Rosa declared, would prevent her sleeping all night. Eleanor endeavored to reason with her servant that discipline restrained even the worst men within certain well-defined limits, and consequently that nothing was to be feared from the new guard, who, unfortunately, was so unprepossessing in appearance. Rosa, however, would not be convinced, and persisted in remaining awake.</p> 
               <p>About one o'clock in the night a light footstep approached, and the next moment a voice was heard by Rosa conversing in low tones with the guard.</p> 
               <p>"Well, Major," said the sentinel, at length, "if you'll give me the thousand clear in my hand, and promise to see me out of the trouble of the escape, I'm at your service."</p> 
               <p>"I'll do so," replied the voice more audibly than hitherto, "there's your money, and I promise you the other."</p> 
               <p>"All right, Major," answered the<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC5561-00000041"/> guard, "now go ahead, and be quick about it."</p> 
               <p>The next instant, and even as Rosa gently awakened Eleanor, a knock came to the door which was then pushed softly back, giving entrance to a tall, manly figure, completely disguised in a Spanish mantle and broad felt hat.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER XVI.</head> 
               <head type="sub">THE RESCUE, AND THE STRANGE HORSEMAN.</head> 
               <p>UPON a broken table in one corner of the contracted room occupied by Eleanor and her faithful companion, there was a candle dimly burning, and this the mysterious stranger extinguished after raising his finger to caution silence upon the captives. The following moment his lips were close to our heroine's ear.</p> 
               <p>"Dearest Eleanor," he whispered in scarcely audible tones, "ever since your arrival in the city, I have been maturing a plan for your rescue. Now is the favorable moment for your escape. Everything is ready. I have bribed the guard, and it only remains for you, and also your servant, to follow me to a place of safety."</p> 
               <p>"First tell me," replied the fair prisoner, her voice tremulous with the suddenly awakened hope of escape, "to whom do I owe this act of kindness."</p> 
               <p>"My disguise must be perfect, indeed, dear Eleanor, or is it possible that you can have forgotten Iredell?"</p> 
               <p>These words were spoken in as low a tone as before, but there was a feeling thrown into their utterance that caused a thrill to run through Eleanor's whole being.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, my dear friend," replied she, taking the hand that her invisible rescuer had laid upon her arm, and pressing it warmly, "you must forgive me, but when you first came in you seemed to be at least two inches taller than you used to be, and not so broad."</p> 
               <p>"Nothing to forgive, dear Eleanor. You would have recognized me had it not been for my mantle. But let us not lose the precious moments. Come, all is ready-and your servant-what do you call her-she must not be left behind in the hands of her brutal <choice>
                     <sic>jailors</sic>
                     <corr>jailers</corr>
                  </choice>."</p> 
               <p>"Here's' me, sah," quickly, but softly, said Rosa, as she extended her hand through the gloom and placed it upon the arm of the speaker.</p> 
               <p>Eleanor knew well the value of dispatch, and whispering a word or two to her servant, she allowed her rescuer to lead her toward the door of the little prison. This he cautiously opened; and pushing his two companions back somewhat, he gazed out to see that the coast was clear.</p> 
               <p>"All goes well! Come!" whispered he.</p> 
               <p>The next moment the guard was passed, and the fugitives soon reached the wall inclosing the grounds attached to the building, used as<pb n=""/> quarters for Union prisoners. This was readily surmounted; owing to the skill and strength of the guide, and five minutes later saw the trio safely ensconced in a carriage that was driven rapidly toward the southern portion of the city.</p> 
               <p>When satisfied that there was no further peril of discovery, Eleanor could not longer forbear addressing her friend.</p> 
               <p>"Mr. Iredell," said she, "can you recall the contents of the last letter you sent me, that is, I suppose it to be the last. I received the first after it had been opened-by the rebel postmaster-but all I got of the second was the envelope."</p> 
               <p>"What mean you, dear Eleanor? I certainly sent you two letters."</p> 
               <p>"The first of which," replied Eleanor, "came to hand; but the second, most unfortunately, by some means or other, fell into the clutches of that vile man, Santee. He must hold some position in the rebel post-office. He removed your letter from the envelope, and sent a scurrilous and insulting note in the place of it."</p> 
               <p>"The villain!" exclaimed Eleanor's companion, interrupting her, and speaking from between his shut teeth. "But I have a copy of the letter, dear Eleanor, and I will let you read it. Better late than not at all."</p> 
               <p>"I feared," resumed our heroine, "that in it you had, perhaps, betrayed your whereabouts, or, at least, written something that might bring you into the power of Santee."</p> 
               <p>"Ah, calm all your fears on that point, dear Eleanor; my presence here with you at this moment is proof sufficient that he has, as yet, been unable to harm me, and of the future I will take good care. So pray dismiss all your apprehensions."</p> 
               <p>"I suppose, Mr. Iredell," rejoined Eleanor, "that you are aware of the sad fatality that has swept our family from existence, with the exception of myself."</p> 
               <p>"I have, indeed; but how came you to hear of it, dear Eleanor?"</p> 
               <p>"In the most unexpected manner. This very evening the soldier who was placed as guard over me, and who, I must add, was much of a gentleman, gave me several Southern newspapers, that time might not hang so heavily upon me. Almost the first article that struck my attention was one in the <title>Charleston Mercury</title>, headed 'A Sad Fatality.'"</p> 
               <p>"Really," interrupted our heroine's rescuer, "the ways of Providence are inscrutable. And, alas dear Eleanor, that sad paragraph was too true. I saw it. Your mother died soon after your father, and was followed by her two sons and your sweet sister."</p> 
               <p>"With this terrible fatality," said Eleanor solemnly, "I feel certain, too, that the black-hearted Santee has had a close connection."</p> 
               <p>"Not more certain than I do myself, dear Eleanor!" quickly added the other, with much emphasis. "But do not dwell," continued he, in soothing tones, "upon a subject that pains me because it grieves you."</p> 
               <p>"No, I will not think of it; or at least I will try not to. But I cannot always banish it, and when it rises before me I experience the most <choice>
                     <sic>unchristain</sic>
                     <corr>unchristian</corr>
                  </choice> feelings against Santee. I hope God will forgive him, for I cannot. No more, however, on that. Tell me, though, dear friend about<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC5561-00000042"/> the noble St. Aubyns; the account in your first letter was but meagre."</p> 
               <p>"Their history, dear Eleanor, is almost as painful as that of your own family. Three days after the attack that was made upon their mansion, on the night that you ended Santee's meeting in such an ungracious manner, the two sons determined to be revenged, and sought Santee for the purpose of shooting him. His good or evil genius protected him, however, and they failed in their attempt. After they fired at him he returned their shots, and one of the young men fell dead, while the other was so badly wounded that he died the same night.</p> 
               <p>"The old gentleman had ten days' notice given him by the State Vigilance Committee, of which Santee was a chief officer, to quit the State, or at any rate to leave the neighborhood in which he lived. So, after burying his two sons, he wisely took his wife and servants and went down to Savannah, where he is yet, I believe."</p> 
               <p>"And Nellie, the daughter, what of her, Mr. Iredell?" asked our heroine, with much concern.</p> 
               <p>"She went away with your brother Henry, on the night of the attack. He took her to Santee's mansion, and her wretched fate I need not inform you. Suffice it to say that she, like some others, has never been heard of, from that day to this, and never will."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, horrible! horrible!" exclaimed Eleanor, "and to think that my brother should allow himself to become the abject, wicked tool of such a demon as Santee!"</p> 
               <p>"Ah! my dear Eleanor, you were indeed fortunate to escape the monster, for you were to have been his grand prize. It was to secure you that he made a cat's paw of your brother. And though you eluded him once, he has recorded a vow to possess himself of you yet, and complete his vengeful designs."</p> 
               <p>"Sooner than which," replied Eleanor, in a solemn tone, "I would, with my own hand, part soul from body, and rejoin the dear ones from whom his machinations have separated me in this life."</p> 
               <p>Until this moment Rosa had maintained a respectful silence; but a thought entered her mind at the instant, and she asked:</p> 
               <p>"Please sah, Mister Iredell, 'scuse me, but, ain't Mister Santee in de city?"</p> 
               <p>"Rosa," quickly added Eleanor, reminded by the question of what had occurred as she was going to the little building assigned as her prison, "thought she saw Santee to-day, and called my attention at the time. But I concluded that she was mistaken, as I looked up instantly but could see no one that even resembled Santee."</p> 
               <p>"Rosa was right, dear Eleanor," replied our heroine's rescuer. "Santee is in the city. I came with him myself from Beaufort county. He holds a commission in the rebel army as major, and is here on some secret service. Not only is he here, but he knows that you are here. He was close by at the time you were taken from the main prison building and sent to the outhouse. I saw him watching you."</p> 
               <p>"Then, indeed, do I owe you a double debt of gratitude for this timely rescue!" answered. Eleanor, in sweet tones. "But," added she, quickly,<pb n=""/> "it makes me shudder to think what a fearful risk you ran for my sake, Mr. Iredell."</p> 
               <p>"I am fond of risks, dear Eleanor, but there was scarcely any in that. I merely assumed the name and rank of Santee himself, bribed the sentinel with a thousand dollars, and the rest you know as well as I."</p> 
               <p>"Do you not think that Santee, when he finds that I have fled, will institute a vigorous search?" asked Eleanor.</p> 
               <p>"I have not the slightest doubt of it, and I have made my preparations accordingly. I have secured apartments in the city here with a trusty friend. In these you and your servant must keep close until I return for you, which will be when I throw Santee off the track, and then we will make with all speed for Savannah. From thence we will reach the coast, and there be taken on board some Union man-of-war. This is our only course, for to attempt to reach the North by passing through the lines of the army would be to fall into Santee's hands certainly."</p> 
               <p>"Any way your judgment decides, dear friend," replied Eleanor, with gentle confidence.</p> 
               <p>"By-the-by, here we are at our destination," said Eleanor's companion, as the carriage drew up in front of a gloomy looking building, in which not a light was to be seen.</p> 
               <p>Not waiting for the driver to unfasten the door of the carriage out heroine's rescuer did it himself, and, stepping out, handed Eleanor up the front steps of the building, leaving Rosa to follow, which she was not slow in doing.</p> 
               <p>"All right, Billy!" said Iredell to the coachman, who, making some incoherent reply, drove away.</p> 
               <p>Admission was quickly given to the trio by a servant, who carried a candle, by the light of which Eleanor and her servant were shown to a handsomely furnished chamber. This chamber was on the second story, and communicated with a smaller apartment in the rear.</p> 
               <p>"Here, dear Eleanor," said Iredell, "you will be as safe as though you were in Paris. But do not attempt to leave your refuge, neither allow Rosa to do so, on any pretext, until I see you again. Whatever you wish all you need to do is ring this bell, and the servant will bestow upon you every attention. I would gladly remain and converse upon the events that have happened since you and I parted; but the most urgent necessity for my presence elsewhere prevents it. Believe me, however, I will, at the very earliest moment, return, like Noah's dove, to the ark. Farewell!"</p> 
               <p>"Farewell," replied Eleanor, extending her hand as he spoke, "farewell, and Heaven protect you, and keep you free from harm."</p> 
               <p>"Farewell," again said Iredell, as he took the proffered hand and pressed it to his lip.</p> 
               <p>The next moment he was gone.</p> 
               <p>During the succeeding two days our heroine saw nothing of her rescuer, but she scrupulously obeyed all his injunctions, and even went beyond them in many respects.</p> 
               <p>About the middle of the second night she was aroused from her slumber by a gentle knock at the door, and she heard the voice of her rescuer.</p> 
               <p>"Be ready in half an hour," said he, and then walked away.</p> 
               <p>Eleanor well knew what he meant;<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC5561-00000043"/> and springing up she hastily made preparations for her journey. These she completed, with the help of Rosa in less than fifteen minutes, and without waiting for the expiration of half an hour she rang the bell.</p> 
               <p>The signal was answered by Iredell, himself, cloaked and disguised exactly as he had been on the night of the escape.</p> 
               <p>"You are prompt, dear Eleanor," said he, remaining outside the threshold until our heroine should join him.</p> 
               <p>Eleanor did not fail to notice the act of gentlemanly courtesy, though, of course, she made no remark concerning it.</p> 
               <p>The same carriage that had brought our heroine to her present refuge now awaited her at the door, and stepping lightly into it she was soon speeding away in the direction of the Richmond and Charleston railroad depot. Arriving here she was placed aboard a train which was just about to start and ere sunrise many a mile lay between herself and Richmond.</p> 
               <p>Her rescuer, however, did not remain with her. About an hour previous to dawn he left, the car, of which she was (beside him and Rosa) the only occupant. Before going he said:</p> 
               <p>"I am playing a deep and hazardous game, Eleanor, and I must beg of you, as you value your own safety and mine, to second me at every turn."</p> 
               <p>"Instruct me fully, Mr. Iredell," replied Eleanor, "how I can do so properly, and I assure you you shall have no need of complaint."</p> 
               <p>"Well, then," was the answer, "I am acting the part of Santee. He is a secret agent of the rebel government. I have represented you and your servant as political prisoners, placed in my charge to Savannah, where you are to be imprisoned. Should the guard, therefore, at any time question you, you will reply accordingly, for I half think that a little suspicion may have been already raised in that direction. I will see you as often as convenient or necessary until we get to Savannah, when circumstances must determine our future course, especially should the plan of reaching the Union vessels fail.</p> 
               <p>"If we get that far," suggested Eleanor, "and any unseen peril should arise, do you not think we could reach the cave?"</p> 
               <p>"Ha! the cave!" exclaimed our heroine's rescuer, in a voice of surprise, and almost too loud for safety. Catching himself, however, he remained silent fully a minute, and then asked, in tones that struck Eleanor as rather peculiar:</p> 
               <p>"Do you think, dear Eleanor, that you could reach the cave by yourself?"</p> 
               <p>"I know I could not," was the reply, "for, as you are aware, I was insensible when you conveyed me thither, and when you led me from it the night was pitch dark. Indeed, Mr. Iredell, there are but two facts about it that I remember, one of which is the singular and delicious perfume that was exhaled by the shrubbery around, and the other of which is the unmerciful manner in which the thorns and briers lacerated my hands and arms."</p> 
               <p>"Which rudeness, under the circumstances, you excused, dear Eleanor," laughed Iredell. "But I must leave you," he continued, rising, and<pb n=""/> speaking in a more serious manner. "Remember what I have told you. Adieu!"</p> 
               <p>"Adieu!" replied Eleanor, "I will not forget."</p> 
               <p>Our heroine saw no more of Iredell, for whose safety she constantly and fervently prayed, until the next night, when he came to assure her that all was going well.</p> 
               <p>In this way (Iredell seeing Eleanor each night), Savannah was reached without discovery, much to Eleanor's joy, and Rosa's also. Here, however, our heroine's rescuer informed her that Santee was in hot pursuit.</p> 
               <p>"And so," added he, "there is naught left to us, dear Eleanor, but to seek, as you suggested, the refuge of the cave. Santee knows our object in coming to Savannah as well as we do, and, consequently, he would capture us the moment we reached the coast."</p> 
               <p>"As you will, dear friend, so long as no harm befalls <emph>you!</emph>" answered Eleanor, in anxious but prompt tones.</p> 
               <p>"It is not for myself that I fear, fair lady," replied the other, "but for you."</p> 
               <p>After some further conversation, during which several points of minor importance in the future programme of the fugitives were settled, the latter set off up the river.</p> 
               <p>It was with varied feelings that our heroine approached the home of her birth; a home in which she had spent the happiest and also the most sorrowful days of her life, and fain would she have turned aside to visit the familiar old homestead had circumstances allowed it. But Santee was on her track and that of her protector, and she hastened onward with the latter, after breathing a gentle prayer for the departed ones who lay sleeping so quietly in the grave.</p> 
               <p>Since leaving Richmond, Eleanor's rescuer had never once held a moment's intercourse with her during the day-time, but invariably at night. This struck our heroine as exceedingly strange, but, upon thinking over it, she concluded that he had some very good reason for so doing, and she therefore gave it no further consideration.</p> 
               <p>After leaving Savannah no incident worth recording occurred until the fugitives reached a point about three miles from Santee's mansion, and four and a half miles from Iredell's cave.</p> 
               <p>Here the light carriage in which Eleanor's rescuer was driving her was overtaken by a horseman, who must have turned into the main road from some by-lane just after the carriage had passed. At the moment that this rider came abreast of the vehicle a quaint remark of Rosa's caused Eleanor to laugh quite heartily. The former instantly checked his horse somewhat, as he seemed to recognize the voice, and then, pressing forward, he bent down from his saddle and peered in at the front of the carriage. The next moment, without speaking a word, he sheered off from the latter, and, dashing away, was soon lost in the darkness of the road beyond.</p> 
               <p>"That's a suspicious customer," whispered Eleanor's companion, after the horseman had disappeared, "and he may give us trouble. But if he does I am prepared."</p> 
               <p>The speaker, as he ceased, applied the whip vigorously to his animal, who was soon going at a heavy run, as though to overtake the lonely horseman in front.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC5561-00000044"/> 
               <head>CHAPTER <choice>
                     <sic>XVIII.</sic>
                     <corr>XVII.</corr>
                  </choice>
               </head> 
               <head type="sub">A SECOND AND TRAGIC RESCUE.</head> 
               <p>THE carriage in which Eleanor rode was fitted with an extra curtain in front, which, when drawn down, answered the double purpose of keeping the inmates dry, should it be raining, and protecting them, if need be, from curiosity. Though it was so dark, our heroine's companion after the strange rider had gone out of sight and sound, pulled down this curtain, and thus not only shut out all inquisitive gaze, but also cut off any view from the inside, for what reason the reader must judge by the sequel.</p> 
               <p>Presently the carriage was turned off the main road on to a smooth graveled path, arriving at the end of which it ceased to move. The driver immediately leaped from his seat to the broad porch of a mansion, and, unfastening the door, handed Eleanor and her servant out.</p> 
               <p>Our heroine could not conceal her surprise at being thus taken to an elegant building instead of to the cave to which she supposed she had been going all the while; and, laying her hand upon her companion's arm, she exclaimed:</p> 
               <p>"Why, Mr. Iredell, this is not the cave! Is it your residence?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes," quickly replied the other. "But hist! we are pursued! Silence! Come instantly into the house, dear Eleanor, or we are both lost!"</p> 
               <p>On the impulse, and ere she was really aware of it, Eleanor obeyed the exclamation, and followed her companion, the faithful Rosa keeping her close company. As the trio entered the hall of the mansion, which was in total darkness, Iredell stepped back and secured the door.</p> 
               <p>Within the next minute a gag was in the mouths of Eleanor and her servant, and a moment later a strong arm was about each, bearing them, as lightly as though they had been children, up a carpeted stairway. Up! up! up! higher and higher they were carried, until the topmost landing of the house was reached, when the captor, keeping his right arm pressed about Eleanor, seized Rosa with the same hand, so as to leave the other free. With the latter he unlocked and pushed back a door, and stepped through the opening thus made into a room that was more heavily carpeted than the stairs.</p> 
               <p>Both captives were loosed while the door was being quickly closed and fastened by the captor, who next lit a large lamp.</p> 
               <p>His previous exertions had caused him to drop his mantle, and as the rays of the light illumined his figure Eleanor noticed how different it was from Iredell's; but still she could not recognize him by the closest scrutiny she could make of his half concealed, half lit-up features as he bent over the lamp.</p> 
               <p>An opportunity for doing so, however, was not long delayed, for in a<pb n=""/> moment or two the strange man, turned to her, and, handing her a chair with the utmost politeness, requested her to be seated while he explained his conduct since first seeing her in Richmond.</p> 
               <p>Eleanor acceded mechanically, and sinking upon the proffered chair, prepared in silence to listen to what the other had to say. Rosa was much frightened, but, buoyed up by love and devotion to her mistress, she stood close behind the latter. Both prisoners, with one instinct, had removed the gags from their mouths the moment they found their hands at liberty.</p> 
               <p>"My darling Eleanor," commenced our heroine's captor, "I believe I told you, as we were coming along from Richmond, that I was playing a very deep game, did I not?"</p> 
               <p>"In truth you did, sir," replied Eleanor, "and, I must add, a very strange one!"</p> 
               <p>"Exactly so! Strange, no doubt, to you, sweet girl; and, when you learn all, you will say well played. But <choice>
                     <sic>al</sic>
                     <corr>all</corr>
                  </choice> in good season. Let me begin at the beginning, and by the time I have concluded I think I shall have proven my identity to you, and also explained one or two matters to your satisfaction-<emph>perhaps!</emph> And yet, why should I keep you in suspense, my angel? No, I will not! You remember that wench there telling you that she saw Mr. Santee, and calling your attention at the time to the fact?"</p> 
               <p>"I do!" was the reply.</p> 
               <p>"Well, as I told you once before, she <emph>was right!</emph> Santee was in Richmond at the time on secret service for the Confederate government. He saw you, determined to obtain possession of you, bribed the guard who was placed over you, took you from your prison, brought you to Savannah, brought you to the cave, and is here, your most devoted and rejoicing lover! Behold him, my sweetest!"</p> 
               <p>With these words the speaker removed in an instant a false wig and beard, and there, grinning sardonically, Eleanor beheld, not as she had supposed Mr. Iredell, but <emph>James L. Santee!</emph>
               </p> 
               <p>No word, nor no combination of words, can convey to the reader's mind the feelings that seized Eleanor Poindexter at this dreadful moment. Were it possible to imagine the despairing amazement that could possess a spirit which, after a long life of goodness and piety on earth, was given into the power of Satan while stepping across the very threshold of Heaven, it might be possible to imagine the despairing amazement that fell upon our heroine at the moment of which we write. No word burst from her ashen lips; no merciful swoon shut out the appalling reality of her situation; but she sat and gazed in helpless, stony composure upon her gloating master.</p> 
               <p>Rosa, too, clutching the chairback of her mistress, her eyes glassy and protruded, stared at Santee, and seemed turning into marble as she stared.</p> 
               <p>The silence was broken at length by Santee, who, still grinning maliciously upon his intended victim, said:</p> 
               <p>"Now for the explanation, sweetest dove. I had lost sight of you for a long, long time after you behaved so disloyally at my meeting, and had concluded that after you reached the North, you got in with that rascally Drayton. But Fortune smiled on me<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC5561-00000045"/> awhile since, and, one day as I was overhauling some suspected letters at the post office, I came across one directed to you. I opened it and found the choice epistle from that traitor Iredell, which I replaced, as you know, by a little note of my own. I hardly expected, then, ever to see you again, but lo! what a happy disappointment! Public business took me to Richmond, and there my delighted eyes lit upon you. My plan was soon formed. That letter of Iredell's posted me as to what I should say and do particularly, and the rest I trusted to my own genius, and you must own my work has been nicely done. Yet still it has cost me nearly two thousand dollars to get you here. I have not gone after Iredell yet, but I have him fixed so tightly that when I do he'll come like the coon to Captain Scott!"</p> 
               <p>"Oh! inhuman being! may God forgive you!" gasped Eleanor, recovering her speech.</p> 
               <p>"He'll have enough to do to do that!" replied the wicked, godless man. "But," added he, in altered tones, "I have no time to trifle! I will tell you the spring, the secret of all this. Your father grossly insulted me once, and I determined to be revenged on him, as I always do on anybody who questions my honor. I swore I'd follow him and his to the grave-ay, and further! I got your headstrong, foolish brother in my power, and I worked him to get you. It was my steel that ended your blustering father's career; your mother died suddenly after eating some delicious foreign fruit that I sent her. Your younger brother and sister were accidentally drowned in Beaufort Bay by Henry, to whom I had suggested that he would become sole heir to the estate by such an accident. After that, to turn suspicion away, he feigned madness, and I, good, kind friend, took charge of him. One night I lured him into the woods, and watching my opportunity slipped a noose about his neck. He died quite easy, and I tied him to a tree in such a manner that when he is found his suicide will awaken general pity. Then his sweetheart, or rather his wife, Nellie St. Aubyn, fell into my possession, as did also Palmetto Plantation. I soon got tired of Nellie, although she was really pretty, and I believe she's dying in the next chamber now."</p> 
               <p>"You, my love, are the last of the Poindexters. When you are gone I shall take full possession of Palmetto Plantation. You are a sweet lily that I have plucked with much trouble. Your fragrance I alone will enjoy, and when you wither, as you soon will, why of course you must give place to another. Ha! ha! revenge is a most delicious feast! Come, my love, let me embrace you!"</p> 
               <p>Fascinated with horror at the cool detail of his atrocious villainies, Eleanor had regarded Santee in silence. But his last words fully awoke her to the horrid peril that threatened herself, and, starting from her chair, she placed the latter between herself and her foe.</p> 
               <p>Santee took a step forward, but no more, for, as he raised his foot for the next, Rosa sprang upon him with the fury of a tigress, and, clutching him by the throat, almost bore him to the floor. Alas! however, the next moment a bowie-knife glittered above her, and flashed down into her bosom like the lightning bolt falls<pb n=""/> from heaven to earth. The faithful mulatto sank back with a wild shriek of despair; but, faithful to the last, stretched out her arms toward Eleanor, as though to reach and enfold her cherished mistress to her stricken heart.</p> 
               <p>"D--d, filthy worm! squirm there," hissed Santee, with the voice of an adder, and spurning dying Rosa with his foot as he spoke. "Now, Eleanor Poindexter," continued he, fiercely, turning upon the latter, "<emph>your</emph> doom has come! No escape for you now!"</p> 
               <p>Our heroine had often read in romances of pure and lovely women being in just such peril as she was now in. And she had read how valiant lovers or noble men had rescued them. Strange enough, too, she thought bitterly of the incongruity of fiction and reality.</p> 
               <p>No time was there to think more, however, for already were the lecherous arms almost about her. Springing back she whirled the chair aloft, and, with fire leaping from her eyes, exclaimed:</p> 
               <p>"Demon, back! Touch me not! I defy you! I challenge you, before the righteous God of heaven not to commit the sin you seek to commit."</p> 
               <p>"And, by the righteous God of heaven, I challenge you, infamous reptile, to mortal combat!" thundered the voice of a stalwart man, who, dashing in the door at this juncture, rushed upon Santee with a long, keen knife.</p> 
               <p>Santee, though taken at the disadvantage of an utter surprise, was cool, powerful, and well skilled in the use of the bowie knife; and, by a quick, movement, he caught his foeman's weapon on his own and passed aside a blow that otherwise had reached his life.</p> 
               <p>But the other was equally skilled, and much more powerful. Pausing only for a moment, he measured his distance, and then made two lightning-like, straight-forward, plunging thrusts.</p> 
               <p>"That for the liar and murderer!" he exclaimed, driving the steel into Santee's throat, "and that for the traitor and seducer!" planting the vengeful blade in the villain's heart.</p> 
               <p>Santee's death was so instantaneous that the groan he uttered ceased ere he reached the floor.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC5561-00000046"/> 
               <head>CHAPTER XVIII.</head> 
               <head>A PLEASANT DENOUEMENT.</head> 
               <p>WITHOUT waiting to deal a third blow, or even to cast another look at his dead adversary, the new-comer turned to Eleanor. The latter instantly recognized in her preserver her former protector, the <emph>real</emph> Iredell, and, uttering a cry of mingled joy and surprise, she cast herself into his arms.</p> 
               <p>At this moment a groan from Rosa called the attention of both to the poor, faithful unfortunate, who, to save her beloved mistress from a worse fate than death, had received a mortal wound. As Eleanor and Iredell kneeled beside her, Rosa took a hand of each, and faintly smiling, said in a low voice:</p> 
               <p>"God bres you, Missey Eleanor, I'se done gone; but de good Lord's sent his angels to take me away. He'll bress you, too, Mister Iredell, 'deed he will, fur savin' Missey Eleanor!"</p> 
               <p>With these words, the dying Rosa closed her eyes for about a minute, and remained very still. Then, opening them suddenly, she said to our heroine:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, Missey Eleanor, dere's one thing 'ud make me die happy, ef you'd only tell me you'd try an' do it some time."</p> 
               <p>"Tell me, Rosa!" exclaimed Eleanor, anxiously, as she saw that the expiring girl would soon be past speaking, "tell me what it is, and I promise you that I will do it if at all in my power."</p> 
               <p>"Dear Missey Eleanor," replied Rosa, in still weaker tones than before, "der's thirteen dollars in my pocket. Ef you'd put enough to it, an' git my old mother her 'mission paper."</p> 
               <p>"Your mother, Rosa," said Iredell, answering the dying servant, "has gone to Heaven. You will meet her there."</p> 
               <p>Poor Rosa heard him not, however, for, with the effort in behalf of her still enfettered mother, she passed to that great bar where no wickedly contrived laws of earth could shield the man of oppression and blood to whom she owed her death.</p> 
               <p>"It is well," continued Iredell, addressing Eleanor, "that she did not know what the end of her mother was. She, too, fell a victim to Santee, because, when accused of harboring her daughter, at the time the latter went away with you, she would not confess to your brother Henry that she knew where either of you were. She received, at Santee's suggestion, a fearful flogging, from the effects of which she soon after died."</p> 
               <p>"Surely! surely that horrible man must have been possessed of a devil!" shudderingly said Eleanor, glancing down at the body of Santee, who, with staring eyes, scowled darkly, stonily up at the ceiling.</p> 
               <p>"Then he has gone home at last," rejoined Iredell, "but come, dear Eleanor," he added quickly, "we<pb n=""/> must be leaving this locality ere any one returns. I will explain all when we reach a place of safety. Come."</p> 
               <p>Our heroine was cut to the heart that she could not bear poor, faithful Rosa's body to some place of sepulchre. This, however, was impossible, and she was obliged to leave the true-hearted servant sleeping beside her murderer.</p> 
               <p>As Eleanor and her preserver were about to hasten from the chamber of death, a partition door caught the attention of the former, and brought vividly to her mind the brutal words of Santee in regard to Nellie St. Aubyn dying in the next room. At Eleanor's earnest request, Iredell forced this door from its bolts and hinges. The apartment was pitchy dark. Iredell, therefore, stepped back to where stood the lamp that had been lit by Santee, and taking it up entered the unexplored chamber, accompanied by our heroine. Kneeling beside a bedstead, her face buried in her clasped hands upon the counterpane, was Nellie St. Aubyn. The intruders' footfalls disturbed her not, however, for several hours had elapsed since Death had mercifully freed her from her bondage of soul and body, as the corpse was nearly rigid and cold.</p> 
               <p>Silent with very horror, Eleanor permitted her protector to lead her down stairs; and in less than an hour more she was safely ensconced beneath the thicket-clad ridge that had once before afforded her a secure refuge.</p> 
               <p>Here, in their subterranean asylum, the two, without peril from eavesdroppers, could rehearse the strange events that had happened since they parted at Cairo. So deeply were they interested in each other's immediately past history that nearly the whole night was spent ere the mutual narratives where ended. Doubtless a detail of this conversation would prove highly interesting to the reader; but lack of space compels us to confine our record to such points as intimately concern facts we have hitherto stated.</p> 
               <p>"Really," exclaimed Iredell, as Eleanor concluded her narrative, "your story possesses more romance and adventure than the most thrilling romance I ever heard of, and, with your approval, I will add a point, or rather a surprise to it."</p> 
               <p>"With all my heart," replied our heroine, smiling graciously.</p> 
               <p>"Excuse me then, a moment or two," said Iredell, stepping into a small room from which he quickly reappeared.</p> 
               <p>"Mr. Drayton!" exclaimed Eleanor, almost swooning with amazement. "Am I dreaming, or is it all a reality?"</p> 
               <p>"All a reality, dearest Eleanor!" rejoined Drayton, for our heroine's companion was indeed no other than he. "But an explanation is due you," he continued, again seating himself close to his lovely charge, "and that you may thoroughly comprehend all, I will begin at the very commencement.</p> 
               <p>"I was left an orphan at the early age of four years, with a small income secured to me by my dear mother, whose deathbed I can even now distinctly remember. In charge of a friend I reached sixteen, at which time I entered the counting-room of a merchant on Delaware avenue. Seven years of constant and laborious attention to business made me the possessor of a moderate annual income<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC5561-00000047"/> come; but impaired my health to such an extent that relaxation became absolutely necessary. I resolved to travel throughout the country. That my journeyings might have another object as well as that of health, I determined to note closely and record the manners, habits, and customs of each State, its progress physically, morally, and politically.</p> 
               <p>"Thus was I engaged in this section of South Carolina, when, on one occasion, being benighted, I fell in with Mr. Iredell. He was a man of the rarest intellect, and very eccentric, so much so as to be accounted misanthropic, and even deranged. Our accidental acquaintance quickly ripened into the warmest friendship, or, with more truth, into love. In one respect, he and I were alike; neither of us had kith or kin. But while I was comparatively poor, he was wealthy. He asked me to become his adopted son, assuming his name in the State of South Carolina, but <emph>nowhere else</emph>, and inheriting his possessions when he died, if I should survive him. Eccentric enough, you will say, but, for this reason, the sooner accepted by me.</p> 
               <p>He then led me to this cave, which, by an accident, he had discovered long before, and which, as you see, he had finished most elegantly. Not the slightest alteration has been made since his demise. Removing hither from his cottage all his instruments and library, he spent the greater portion of his time here in solitary research of scientific and metaphysical subjects. It was here, too, that he narrated to me the whole narrative of his eventful life, which, however, I may never repeat to mortal ears.</p> 
               <p>"Several years we spent together in happiness, and then Death called my adopted father away to the duties of the other life. I had expected that on his deathbed he would seek to exact the most eccentric promises from me, but, to my great astonishment, he made but one request-that was, that six months of each twelve, for the five years subsequent to his decease, I should spend in this cave, while the other six I should spend exactly as I had been in the habit of doing before I fell in with him. After the expiration of the time named, I might guide myself according to my own pleasure. The five years were up a few days since. I had intended, when Mr. Iredell died to spend my whole life here, but my determination was altered by one single event."</p> 
               <p>"And pray, what was it?" asked Eleanor, with curiosity.</p> 
               <p>"It was my becoming acquainted with yourself, which, if you still remember, took place about the time of which I speak."</p> 
               <p>This answer was unexpected, and caused Eleanor suddenly to cast down her eyes and to become some what confused.</p> 
               <p>"And that," resumed Drayton, "was not the only result of that event. Shall I tell you what was the other?"</p> 
               <p>Eleanor smiled, without replying, and yet, by the very manner of her smile, gave the assent asked for. Drayton, therefore, continued.</p> 
               <p>"I became deeply interested in you, and finally fell deeply in love with you. I learned of Santee's wicked plot, and determined to thwart him, whether I should win your love or not. When you went North with your brothers I followed you, and when you returned, I returned<pb n=""/> turned also, but more cautiously than before, for the plotters against you had suspected me, and, consequently, were on their guard.</p> 
               <p>"I need hardly detail the subsequent events that happened. But may I ask of you something in return for my services? Man, you know, is a selfish being."</p> 
               <p>Another smile, this time accompanied by a gentle nod of the beautiful head was Eleanor's reply.</p> 
               <p>"Then, dearest Eleanor," resumed Drayton, growing so confidently bold as to pass his arm about our heroine, and draw her to him, "reward me with yourself. Let me call you my own through life, through eternity?"</p> 
               <p>"William, dearest William," said Eleanor, in tones wealthy with love and gratitude, "to no one could I more safely commit all I hold dear in life, here and hereafter, as to you who have so often shielded me from harm."</p> 
               <p>If the beautiful girl uttered other words, they were lost, as she allowed her head to sink forward on her lover's manly breast. But it was all sufficient, without other words, and the angels winged away to Heaven to record the vows of love and constancy that were then made between two pure and noble souls.</p> 
               <p>"But, dearest William," said Eleanor, looking up after the expiration of a few minutes, "you have not yet told me how you effected my rescue to-night, or even how you ascertained that I and poor Rosa were in Santee's clutches."</p> 
               <p>"True! true!" replied Drayton, "it was not through any ability of my own. Providence directed my course along the road you came, and as I overtook your carriage, I heard you laugh. I instantly knew your voice, and riding forward, I attempted to gain a sight of you, but the darkness prevented recognition. I saw that your driver was Santee, however, for I had seen him in that disguise before. Galloping ahead some distance, I turned aside, secured my horse, waited till the carriage came up, and then followed it afoot to prevent discovery.</p> 
               <p>"I was close by when you stopped out on Santee's porch. I heard you address him as Iredell, and I heard him reply about being pursued, so as to distract your suspicions. He little knew how truly he spoke! I was in the very act too, of effecting your rescue, when he hurried you and unfortunate, noble Rosa inside, and secured the door. To attack the massive portal, and thus inform Santee of my presence, might be fatal to you, so I controlled my passion until I could climb in at a second-story window. Rosa's scream was the first intimation I had of your exact whereabouts.</p> 
               <p>"Thank God I reached you in time for your salvation, and in time to mete out his just deserts to that wicked man, Santee, who was a fit pet of the vile tyranny that has so enslaved the people of the South. Truly the people of the South, while <choice>
                     <sic>triving</sic>
                     <corr>striving</corr>
                  </choice> to make the shackles of <choice>
                     <sic>theirs</sic>
                     <corr>their</corr>
                  </choice> miserable bondmen eternal, are riveting upon their own limbs irons, that, for centuries to come, will eat into their very souls. But it is the retributive justice of God!"</p> 
               <p>"Would to heaven!" exclaimed Eleanor, a glow suffusing her lovely features, "that I might take possession of Palmetto Plantation this very<pb n="96" xml:id="VAC5561-00000048"/> night. How soon would I fling to the breeze the starry banner of the Union, and how soon would I, with a single stroke of the pen, smite every soul-cankering fetter from every limb, whose only offense is that it is black. Heaven! yes, Heaven knows my heart!"</p> 
               <p>"Would Heaven you could, dearest, best Eleanor!" replied Drayton "but every slave, man, woman and child, has been removed from the plantation and sent to the rebel fortification."</p> 
               <p>"Above which," added Eleanor, in a solemn tone, "may the glorious flag of the free speedily float!"</p> 
               <p>"Amen! amen!" said Drayton.</p> 
               <p>Some further time was consumed by the betrothed lovers in arranging a plan to reach the North. One was finally settled upon, and set for execution the next night. To gather strength for the effort, each retired to slumber.</p> 
               <p>Night came, and, full of hope and anxiety, our lovers set forth on their perilous journey, both leaving their estates to their foes until the re-establishment over them once more of the power and authority of the United States. Not a syllable reached them, as they traveled their way, concerning the tragedy at Santee's palatial mansion, and they therefore concluded that it had not yet been discovered.</p> 
               <p>Providence must have specially guarded the fugitives, for, though several times almost captured, they at last reached the lines of the Federal army. Our heroine was instantly recognized, and received such a reception as must have gladdened her heart.</p> 
               <p>Both Eleanor and Drayton shared in the glories and perils of Antietam's bloody fray, and both shone brilliantly in that gallant contest for the holy cause. Drayton, who had made artillery a subject of study, rendered the most valuable services in that branch, and his was the honor of firing the last shell that scattered terror among the foes of the Union on that sanguinary field.</p> 
               <p>When, after the carnage had ended, he sought Eleanor, he found her bright, beautiful, heroic as ever, ministering to the wounded and dying.</p> 
               <p>"I now comprehend dearest Eleanor," said he, bending over her and fondly kissing her, "how you came to be called <hi rend="i"/>THE ANGEL OF THE BATTLE-FIELD!"</p> 
               <p>Other battles, more bloody than Antietam, have since been fought. President Lincoln and many a noble soldier of the Union have passed away, and the black cloud of treason which so long obscured the Sun of Liberty has passed away. But in the blue union of our glorious flag three <emph>new</emph> stars have appeared, rising from the blood of our noble soldiers and sailors. And, thank God, none of these stars, nor yet any of the others, shall ever pass away!</p> 
            </div> 
            <closer>THE END.</closer> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>