<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6132">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Queen Krinaleen's Plagues, or, How a Simple People were Destroyed </title>
            <author >Jonquil, (fl. 1871-1874)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC6132</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >Queen Krinaleen's plagues, or, How a simple people were destroyed</title>
                  <author >Jonquil, (fl. 1871-1874)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >151 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >American News Co.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1874">1874</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2004-02-03">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2006-02-05">Finished TEI conversion</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <front> 
         <titlePage xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
            <pb  n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6132-00000001"/> 
            <docTitle> 
               <titlePart>QUEEN KRINALEEN'S PLAGUES;</titlePart> 
               <titlePart type="sub">OR, How a Simple People were Destroyed.</titlePart> 
               <titlePart type="sub">A DISCOURSE IN THE TWENTY-SECOND CENTURY.</titlePart> 
            </docTitle> 
            <byline >BY "JONQUIL," AUTHOR OF "WAS SHE ENGAGED?"</byline> 
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>NEW YORK:</pubPlace> 
               <publisher >AMERICAN NEWS COMPANY.</publisher>
            </docImprint> 
            <docDate>1874.</docDate> 
            <pb  n="5" xml:id="VAC6132-00000002"/> 
            <docEdition>Entered, according to Act of Congress, in the year 1874, BY J. L. COLLINS. In the Office of the Librarian of Congress at Washington.</docEdition> 
         </titlePage> 
      </front> 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Queen Krinaleen's plagues, or, How a simple people were destroyed</head> 
            <div type="section"> 
                
               <head>QUEEN KRINALEEN'S PLAGUES.</head> 
               <p>IN introducing the subject for this evening's entertainment, I beg leave to explain that the people of the nineteenth century were different from those of our own generation.</p> 
               <p>On no other supposition would it be possible for you to comprehend the manners, morals, or aspirations of the creatures of whom I shall speak, or credit the story of the plagues of Queen Krinaleen.</p> 
               <p>Leaving their general habits and character to be depicted in the body of my tale, I shall merely say, in passing, that two hundred years ago people learned and taught by a system you would surely despise.</p> 
               <p>The authors, scholars, and scientific men of that feverish period wrote tediously long stories and essays, had them printed in<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC6132-00000003"/> books by thousands, and left to the public the trouble of procuring copies and reading them, instead of assembling the people before them, as we do, and giving them in natural speech the condensed essence of their reflections and researches.</p> 
               <p>But we are told by philosophers that the people of every generation are made to bear burdens for the benefit of posterity; and if those of that restless age had not borne the affliction of its literature, we could not be instructed by their history this evening.</p> 
               <p>Among the thousands of books which appeared under that time-worn license, was one remarkable for the new and startling theory it advanced. The author asserted, with earnestness and acuteness, that mankind had ascended from inferior animals, through various gradations of development.</p> 
               <p>"Our early progenitors," said he, "were hairy, awkward, and uncouth quadrupeds; but by an energy, and care for the development of their progeny, which their descendants have not inherited from them, they overcame the disadvantages of their lowly origin.</p> 
               <p>"By the constant use of their fore-paws in procuring food from the fruit-trees, the most active and industrious changed them into hands; and they gradually grew straight on their hind legs, so that they were eventually able to go erect upon them. This improvement upon nature, coupled with prudence in pairing, which led the most highly developed of both sexes to prefer each other, separated them by degrees from the lowest of their species, and enabled them to attain to the present noble mien and characteristics of man."</p> 
               <p>This book and its story had been long forgotten, but a copy having been preserved as an heir-loom by the descendants of the author, the theory of transformation was lately revived by one of them. You may, perhaps, remember that three years ago, Gibbon Darwin, Esq., gravely stated to his audience, that in the wild and distant land known to us as Amrika, a nation of people,<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6132-00000004"/> who had once ranked with the most powerful and civilized of the earth, had, by a retrograde development, returned to their normal condition-that of wild, hairy animals. His tale was said to be the result of personal observations, and, united with the learned theory of his ancestor, C.(Chimpanzee?) Darwin, each derived such support from the other, that the censors appointed by the audience to reward or punish him, as his efforts to entertain and instruct it proved successful or the reverse, made a favorable decision, and his ancestral name at once arose to its former distinction.</p> 
               <p>The gist of his lecture was that there had been at one time several races of men in this land, and each following its lowest propensities developed the animal nature that was in them, until they became as many different species of wild animals, according to their habits and dispositions.</p> 
               <p>One of these races, he explains, was, because of its diffident and servile disposition, called the Shy Knees. The people were at first accustomed to live together in great crowds; but as they developed the trait of economy to a heathenish extent, they excited the ire and contempt of their more prodigal and powerful neighbors. They were so often attacked, plundered, and bled, because of their plodding industry, that they soon became addicted to hiding in the thickets to escape the tax-collectors and the persecution of their aggressors. In a few years they ceased to live in houses, burrowing in the earth for shelter; and then ceased to walk upright as they were wont to do. The long queues of hair which they wore down their backs were broken off in their attempts to escape from their persecutors, and developed into short, stubby tails; their ears became prolongated by the frequent pullings received when recaptured, and they eventually became rabbits and hares, and run wild over the western part of the land to this day.</p> 
               <p>Another race, which he calls the Knee Gross, met a similar fate. They were addicted<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6132-00000005"/> dicted to eating and idleness, and by the constant use of their jaws, and the practice of sunning themselves on the banks of their rivers, their indolent and sensual instincts were developed until they became alligators, and they now swarm the coasts and banks along the southern portion of their land.</p> 
               <p>For the dominant and most enlightened race he, however, reserves the direst descent and doom. So numerous were they, that I wonder he can find room for them in that wide land, when he endows them with the unerring instincts and reproductive powers of the lower animals; but he does, and debases them in this ingenious way. Their women, he at first explains, had forgotten their dignified and responsible relations to their husbands, offspring and fellow-beings, and spent their time in gadding around the streets of their cities, dangling their useless hands before their breasts, and constantly widening towards their base until they looked more like kangaroos than human beings.</p> 
                
               <p>Their men, no longer smoothed and elevated by the softness and sympathy of their wives, became the eager slaves of greed, and gave themselves, bodies and souls, to the pursuit of wealth, as the only thing which could secure the toleration and respect, by satisfying the demands and extravagant habits, of their wives.</p> 
               <p>They soon lost their manly, honest, and generous expression, as well as all else which had distinguished them from brutes. The luxuriant hair which is one of the distinctive marks of the human head was lost at an early age, or only represented by a few straggling hairs to show what nature had intended them to be, and in what direction they themselves were tending. Their faces, which were once cheerful, oval, and full, soon became sharp, thin, and dissipated-looking by their constant care, and the practice of knavery; the insatiable greed of the wolf and the cunning of the fox, showing the direction in which they were moving. Their mouths and chins grew<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6132-00000006"/> into snouts; their eyes became wild and sunken, restless and piercing, instead of mild, truthful, and benevolent, as those of a man created in the image and likeness of God should be. Their backs became bent by constant application to business, without necessary rest or recreation, until they lost the erect mien their progenitors had, by different development, attained. These habits, together with tastes in sexual selection as foolish and debasing as those of their early ancestors were wise and ennobling, soon caused the whole race to degenerate. It was only those who had grown old and unmanly in the pursuit of wealth who could marry, and the females they selected were those whose highest duties were to advertise the wealth of their husbands, and to be household pets and ornaments.</p> 
               <p>So while the best people could not transmit their noble and humane qualities to posterity, those who were decrepit and debased were constantly reproducing a lower people, to transmit in their turn their worst characteristics to their offspring, until they had bowed the heads and the hands of the race to the ground, and at last became kangaroos. But Gibbon Darwin, Esq., confesses that the, kangaroo is not indigenous to that land, and, with the candor of his namesake, admits that it cannot be found there; yet here he is helped out of his dilemma by the Darwinian ingenuity.</p> 
               <p>He satisfied the inquiries of his audience by explaining that a deleterious taste in pairing having once been established in that unhappy race, as that of an elevating tendency was in their quadrumanous progenitors, the kangaroos continued in their selections and descent, giving preference to diminutiveness and deformity until they became little squirrels. This gives his theory plausibility, for he proves that in the northern part of the land the forests abound in squirrels, so large and plentiful that they are the main support of a tribe of savages called Kanucks, who cross over from their land<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6132-00000007"/> annually to hunt them for their fur and flesh.</p> 
               <p>This is the substance of his theory, and, absurd as it seems, the plaudits and remuneration which his audience awarded him entitle it to the attention of all our thinking men.</p> 
               <p>"If an enlightened and indulgent public," I thought, "can receive an ingenious tale with so much favor, it will certainly encourage the research and perseverance which discover and lay before it the truth."</p> 
               <p>There were evidences that Amrika had once been inhabited by a people whose progress in civilization entitled their memory to our respect, and I determined at once to set out and explore it. Their fate, their history and their origin, could not, I thought, be uninteresting, and their annihilation could not be so complete as to leave no trace of them where they once ruled and flourished as proudly as the empire of ancient Rome. I made a voyage of exploration to this -depopulated land, hoping to collect lect facts worthy of the favor of an audience; and these facts I desire to set before you this evening, leaving the result to your wisdom and goodness.</p> 
               <p>By skimming over the coasts of this land, and along the courses of its noblest rivers, I discovered the sites of its once proud cities. Yorick, Dell Fee, and Boasting, on the eastern coast; Sind Loo and Cheek Ego in the interior, and Sand Fresco on the western shore, were the most notable of them. In passing over the plains which lie between Sand Fresco and Sind Loo, the fan of my skiff struck a jutting rock one night, as I was crossing the peaked mountains which rise between the vast territories these two cities drew their supplies from; and while I was delayed for its repairs, I made observations which Gibbon Darwin, Esq., is welcome to use for his next public conversation. Besides the Jack Rabbits, which he says have taken the place of the Shy Knees, there is also an animal which I shall call the ground dog (though he resembles a<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6132-00000008"/> squirrel in appearance), which abounds in great numbers, and lives in villages like people. I also found undeniable proofs of the existence of a fourth race of men there, which was called the Poor Lo, and putting these facts together, my learned contemporary may find a fourth case of relapsing into quadrumana in support of his favorite theory.</p> 
               <p>In the bays and rivers of the southern coast I also saw the alligators which he said had succeeded the Knee Gross by gradual development.</p> 
               <p>After that I took advantage of the south winds, and crossed the wide continent from south to north, seeing everywhere beneath me the evidences of the pre-existence of a numerous and enterprising people. In the northern forests I saw the Kanucks going over from their villages in hunting parties, and, by the aid of our "Universal Sense Alphabet," learned from them with surprise that Gibbon Darwin's story was founded upon their traditions.</p> 
                
               <p>They confidently asserted to me that the forefathers of the squirrels were once the enemies and equals of their own. That they had been very cunning and powerful, had taken their fish from them with the aid of large water ships, and their substance by sharp trading; and they in turn retaliated now by killing and eating their helpless posterity. They related to me the history of an incursion their fathers had made to the chief cities of the Amrikites, and how they had found them deserted of life, while the woods were overflowing with squirrels. They said that they went every year when the animals were fat with the fruits of the forest to hunt them, eating some, and burning others, to appease the manes of their ancestors.</p> 
               <p>It was useless to seek for reliable information from a people so low in the grade of humanity as to talk of revenge. That they were still human upset Gibbon Darwin's theory, and that they had been suffered to exist on the borders of the extinct race was proof that it had been far more noble; and<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6132-00000009"/> I left these Kanucks to hunt the squirrel, while I sought among the ruins of the aforesaid cities the true facts concerning the fall and fate of their unfortunate inhabitants.</p> 
               <p>A severe winter prevented me from exploring the ruins with success, and the loneliness of my situation made it a solemn one to me. But when the snow had gone, and the winter winds had softened, everything awoke at the call of nature, and resumed its joyous life. The birds of many latitudes returned to their favorite haunts for feeding and breeding, and with vaunting notes and alluring antics courted the notice of their summer mates. They ascended the mighty rivers from the south, crossed the trackless plains, and met, without fear of the gun or the snare of the fowler, for courtship and selection in the pleasant valleys that once teemed with human life. Surely, thought I, nature is not at fault; its laws are immutable, and in obedience to them all things, vegetable and animal, will continue to enjoy and reproduce life. These animals have followed instinct, and they live here in peace; man must have trampled reason under foot, or nature would not have failed to propagate him, according to her original design!</p> 
               <p>My labors among the ruins of Yorick were rewarded during the summer, for I opened a catacomb of such books as those to which I have already referred, and at once gave myself up to the task of gleaning from them such information as respected the people who wrote them. They were stamped "A Stor Library," and an idea can be formed of the literary tastes and habits of the race when I assure you that not a greater proportion than one to one hundred of the many books there had one page of useful information in them. However, the books were well preserved, as the air had been excluded from them, and by cutting a page now and then from a valuable work, I was, in the course of a year, able to collect enough to supply all the links necessary for a connected account of the offenses and fate of this extinct people. It is not my intention to weary you with a history<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6132-00000010"/> tory of them, nor to tell you how they built their cities and became a nation. They have passed away with their arts and commerce, and we can be benefited only by knowing so much of them as shall teach us to avoid their doom.</p> 
               <p>Their beginning was, however, sufficiently remarkable and interesting to merit a few words before I proceed with the natural history of their decline and fall. They were called Amrikites, from the land they had lived in, which was known to our ancestors as Amrika; and were a hardy, intrepid people, proud of their descent and of the superior endowments of their own particular race.</p> 
               <p>Like the tradition of neas and his brother-Trojans fleeing for refuge from their own land, to seek a home wherever their ships should be driven to, and founding a new country in Italy, the forefathers of these people had fled from their own country for life and liberty, and landed on the desolate shores of an unknown land. Their home soon became an asylum for the oppressed of all lands; Briton, Celt, and Goth met and mingled there until they became one people, and had a common purpose, that of enjoying and maintaining their liberty.</p> 
               <p>Let me begin with them, then, at the height of their greatness; when they had just developed all the energy, bravery and devoted zeal man is capable of, in a long and terrible war among themselves. Their men, for years of incessant carnage, held the amassing of wealth, and their women the pursuit of frivolity and pleasure, subservient to the great and noble purpose of sustaining their armies and saving their country. The magnitude and boldness of their military enterprises, together with the vast resources they yearly developed, surprised the world and awed tyrants; and though boasting was a lamentable weakness of this people, a little might have been pardonable then, when their old enemies, the Newtrals and the Mezeers, could neither withhold their respect nor conceal their alarm.</p> 
               <p>This was the height to which, by the<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6132-00000011"/> simplicity of their habits and the justice of their laws, the descendants of the fugitive colonists arose; and I will now follow them in their fall and ruin.</p> 
               <p>I have said that, in the self-sacrificing spirit evinced by them during the time their liberties were in danger, they forgot everything except their duty to their country; but there were a few exceptions. There is in every community a class who will profit by a public calamity, and seek their own gain by preying on the vitals of their nation, when the attention of honest people is withdrawn from them and directed to the general danger and interests.</p> 
               <p>There were many such in this land, vultures and buzzards, who fattened on the corpses of the fallen, and by them were disseminated the seeds of disease and decay.</p> 
               <p>When the war was over, and these vampires found themselves wealthy, and multiplied in the land, they sought for opportunities of displaying their wealth, with the eagerness and ostentation of vulgarity. That their ignorance and lack of refinement might not be discovered in their speech, they hastened to foreign countries, where a strange tongue would cover their want of wit and wisdom, and a strange people ascribe their ill-bred and indecorous manners to their foreign birth, rather than to their previous condition. They regarded this as a double advantage, because when they returned to their own country the foreign airs they expected to import could again be used to cloak their natural coarseness, as people would say that their speech and manners had become corrupted by the countries through which they had traveled.</p> 
               <p>There was no land which afforded them the advantages they sought so much as the country of the Mezeers, and to that land they hastened, to hide their ignorance and display the fruits of their unscrupulous peculations.</p> 
               <p>It is not permitted in our enlightened age to speak evil of any people, living or<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6132-00000012"/> dead; but we must discriminate between speaking ill of people and condemning the evil that is in them or follows their actions, which is a duty we owe to virtue and to our fellow-men. With this premise I proceed.</p> 
               <p>The king who at this time reigned over the Mezeers was named Boursouffle, and was not indifferent to the benefits his people derived from the extravagance and ostentation of the strangers who visited his capital. But his own desires and interests were never forgotten in the good of his subjects; and he cherished a strong antipathy against the Amrikites, because their nation despised him, and had once thwarted his designs, and ignominously driven his proud army from a weak nation on their borders. Between his anxiety to be avenged, and his desire to enrich his capital, he became dejected and sick, for the Amrikites were wherever he went, and he was even by policy compelled to receive them civilly at his court.</p> 
               <p>When his queen, who was named Krinaleen, because of her beautiful hair, had learned the greatness of her husband's grief, she tried with all her native art and tact to amuse and arouse him. She caused her maids to arrange her hair in its most becoming style. She put on her most expensive jewels and gorgeous raiment, and when these failed to reach the depth of his sorrow she sent for her infant, the young Prince Chessapoe, and, arraying him after the manner of his grand-uncle, a great warrior, she brought him into the presence of his melancholy sire. This had the desired effect, for the king was aroused enough by the pattern of his uncle's breeches, coat, hat, and boots, to exclaim, "How shall I humble these barbarous Amrikites, who trample down my parks with their flat expansive feet, spit in my art galleries, and swarm my palaces with their wild inquisitive faces, and fill all my capital with loud boasts of what they have done to interfere with my plans and drive my armies from their coast?"</p> 
               <p>"Why should you be displeased with a<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6132-00000013"/> people who bring to your country the wealth of their own, and, though they are coarse and disgusting, come here only to admire all that we have and do, and seek to borrow some of our art and refinement of manners?" she asked, willing like a woman to overcome her prejudices for policy sake. But the king would not be mollified by her words; so he said,-</p> 
               <p>"I cannot suffer their insolence, nor permit them to revile me in the ears of my subjects, for all the benefits they bring to us; nor can I yet put them to death, because their nation would speedily avenge them. Give me advice, or I die." Now Queen Krinaleen, like most of the ladies who have luxuriant red hair, was a quick-witted, shrewd woman, and perceived at once how she could assist her husband and at the same time gratify her own tastes. So she said in her most soothing tones,-</p> 
               <p>"Be not sad because of the strength of their armies or the abundance of their wealth. They are a weak people, a race of snobs and apes, who have no taste or discrimination, but will readily imitate anything we do. "Wit is more than wealth, and art mightier than arms; let the conquest and destruction of them be left to my enchantments, and they shall soon be too weak and too mean to rail at or defy you, as they have done. I will prepare for them seven plagues greater than those of Egypt, and more productive of misery than the evils which flew out of Pandora's box; and when they shall take them back with them to their own country, their women shall sicken and die, and drive their husbands to bankruptcy and despair, so that they shall be soon a feeble-hearted nation, and unable to withstand your vengeance and your power. I will label these plagues with the cabalistic words, <foreign xml:lang="FRA">'Le Bon Ton,' 'La Mode Parisienne,' 'Les joujoux de la Demi-monde,' 'Le Jeu d' Eugnie,' 'L'Amour et l'Esprit,' 'La Crme de la Crme,'</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="FRA">'L'Email de Pompadour,'</foreign> and as they know but very little of our language, and nothing at all of our arts and<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6132-00000014"/> lives, they will in the barbarous dialect of their own country say they are 'Good Medicine,' and destroy themselves by their use. Their love of imitation will aid me, and I will lend myself a few hours each week to the work of displaying those cunningly-prepared plagues; and then let the lewd women of our capital, and the mistresses of our husbands, take them from me, and communicate them to the Amrikite women. So while I shall take antidotes for the poison, which they know not of, it shall destroy the great social evil of our land, and also the people of Amrika, who have defied and reviled you, and let your subjects revile you in the chief cities of their country."</p> 
               <p>This proposition did not give the king as much joy as his loving wife had a right to expect, because he loved his mistresses and did not wish them to be slain.</p> 
               <p>But he felt that his guilt made him weak before his wife's virtue, and as he had never hesitated to sacrifice everything to his own interests, he agreed to her plot.</p> 
                
               <p>So Queen Krinaleen assembled her magicians and counselors and astrologers, who were called in the language of the Mezeers the "Lesmodistes," "Lesorfevres" and "Lesmarchandsdesmodes," and asked them how the plagues could be made most fatal to the lewd women of their capital and the women of Amrika. They unanimously advised her to conceal them in "Soieries," a product of their country, which was so called because it gave sore eyes to all who looked at it in the shops of their capital, and especially to all who had more money than they earned, as was the case with those whom she sought to destroy. "Now the moment their vision once becomes troubled with Soieries," said they to her, "they will blindly take all the clothes and materials you infect, and when we make them very costly, they will be especially acceptable to the Amrikite women, who prize everything in proportion to the price we set on it."</p> 
               <p>Thus did these plagues, so destructive to the youth, beauty, and strength of the Amrikite<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6132-00000015"/> rikite people, originate with this royal couple, a model in their unity, for she, with all her woman's love of display and frivolity, was as wise as a serpent, while he, with his great armies, manifestoes, and military spectacles, was as harmless as a dove.</p> 
               <p>The queen did as her ministers advised, and they enriched themselves by their advice, because they supplied her with the material for the plagues, for it seemed that all but the hapless people for whom they were prepared were destined to be profited by them.</p> 
               <p>These plagues were now compounded with great care under the queen's supervision, and were on all fte days exhibited by her to the women of her capital, who sought to imitate her in everything but the virtues she practiced. When these creatures had, therefore, perceived that the queen had introduced new costumes into her court, they at once went to the Lesmodistes, who compounded them for her, and besought them to give the plagues to themselves, that they might also appear at their ftes, and ride in their carriages, looking as she did; for they foolishly supposed that the queen's natural beauty was derived from the plagues, while she only made them attractive by it. So the lewd women of the Mezeers went about exhibiting to all the first of those plagues; at first terrifying some by their strange garb and gait, and amusing others who had no pity for their debased and hapless condition. They mimicked people suffering from severe colic and cramps, for their backs were bowed down and their knees crooked forward, so that they could not stand or walk upright. They no longer seemed youthful, for their step lost its elasticity, their carriage its grace and suppleness, and they tottered about with backs bent as if bowed and stiffened with age, and loaded down with the tattered and abbreviated garments of a beggar. The virulence of the plague was the more evident by the chalky pallor and vermilion flush which had taken the place of the natural color of a healthy complexion, and by the<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6132-00000016"/> mania they had for all kinds of fantastic frippery, such as you know maniacs exhibit when they make their heads ghastly with rags and feathers, and tear their garments to shreds for the pleasure of seeing them dangle.</p> 
               <p>The women of Amrika were at this time in great numbers at the capital of the Mezeers, seeking for the excitement and notoriety a vain and empty mind always craves, and their attention was at once attracted by the strange and afflicted appearance of those creatures, who were infected and suffering, from the fevers and deformities of the plague.</p> 
               <p>As Queen Krinaleen had shrewdly observed, they were not well enough acquainted with the lives and manners of the Mezeers to discriminate between the women who were an honor and those who were a disgrace to their capital, but with a self-depreciation and abnegation entirely inconsistent with their vanity and pride of wealth, they believed all people were superior to themselves in taste and refinement, and foolishly deferred their own judgment and sense of propriety to every one who differed from them. They saw these women walking about the streets of the capital for amusement, like themselves, and, allured by their unusual mien and the attention they were attracting, they followed them into the shops where the Soieries were sold, as the Lesmodistes and their companions said they would. There they heard them speak of the "<foreign xml:lang="FRA">Le Bon Ton,</foreign>" while looking at the material; and, knowing only just enough of their language to interpret Bon as good, they "guessed," as was their habit, at the rest, and thought that "<foreign xml:lang="FRA">Le Bon Ton</foreign>" was high-toned or costly, and therefore the thing they most desired. So, while the men who sold the Soieries to those infected women knew their character, the Amrikite women were deluded by their speech and manners, and, believing themselves to be borrowing the outward form of taste and good-breeding from them, they caught the contagion with greater readiness.</p> 
               <pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6132-00000017"/> 
               <p>This is the way they introduced fatal and infectious diseases into their native land, for, as Queen Krinaleen had wittily remarked to her husband, they were a silly and unsophisticated people, who, while boasting of the superiority of their own wisdom and customs, were constantly borrowing and aping the manners and the follies of the nations they reviled.</p> 
               <p>Alas that the children of their fathers and mothers should barter the simplicity, virtue, and intelligence they inherited from their parents for such foul plagues as the enemies of their chastity and prosperity had prepared for them! But they thought themselves shrewd at bargains, and made the exchange.</p> 
               <p>It may be demanded by many of my auditors, what terrible infatuation had seized them, that they should sacrifice purity of manners, refinement, beauty, and health to the coarse, lascivious vagaries of the depraved women of the capital of the Mezeers, especially as a true woman's pride of virtue is so strong and deep-rooted that she is loth to have anything in common with those of her sex who bring reproach upon it, and is the first to discover and condemn the slightest deviation from it. I have already partly anticipated the question by saying they were not acquainted with the character of the creatures they imitated. They were in a strange land, and expected to see everything there so different from that with which they were familiar in their own country, that even vice was not recognized, because it was the same in appearance, only far more open and unblushing. Another explanation is, that although epidemics have their origin in the haunts of filth and wretchedness, they cannot be confined to them by any sanitary precautions we use, so long as people of every degree breathe the same atmosphere, and are of the same flesh and blood with each other. So the race was often subject to moral epidemics, which swept lands as completely as if education, refinement, or virtue could offer no opposition<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6132-00000018"/> tion to the contagions that undermined pure and healthy sentiments. This weakness of humanity made the line they drew between wisdom and folly and vice and virtue a very indistinct one, and hard for them to know on which side they were walking as long as they kept near it at all.</p> 
               <p>To-day we see Ophelia gentle, chaste, and discreet in the tragedy of Hamlet, which has descended to us from a good judge of human nature, and to-morrow behold her wandering about, with straws and flowers disfiguring the beauty of her head, and obscenity flowing from her raving lips. It serves to teach us that woman may to-day unblushingly do that which yesterday shocked her sense of decency and propriety when she saw another do it. Yet the outrage upon morals and good taste remains just the same. Vice does not become virtue nor does folly change into wisdom, as people seem to imagine when they turn from one to the other.</p> 
               <p>It was thus with the Amrikite women; virtuous as they were, they were soon attracted from their natural sense of chastity and decorum, and seemed desirous of resembling the wretched females who brought reproach upon their sex.</p> 
               <p>So well did they succeed, indeed, that they subjected themselves to many annoyances by being mistaken by the Mezeers, as they walked in the streets and gardens of the capital, for the unchaste creatures whose demeanor they were mimicking, and whose badges they were wearing.</p> 
               <p>As these women returned to their own country they brought the plague with them; made doubly loathsome by having taken it second-hand from those fallen creatures who took it from Queen Krinaleen. They walked about in their streets so deformed and crippled from it, that their heads and feet were at obtuse angles with each other, and all parts of their bodies so bedizened and disproportioned that the natural beauty of form and feature for which they had been before this celebrated was entirely lost.</p> 
               <pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC6132-00000019"/> 
               <p>Though differing from the creatures from whom they had taken the plague, they were, as before explained, of the same flesh and blood, and were susceptible to the same passions and feelings, and the same pleasure in dress and ornaments.</p> 
               <p>When their friends asked them concerning their strange clothes and behavior, the reply was: "It is 'Bong Tong;' we have learned it at Queen Krinaleen's Court, and intend to have it in our own country."</p> 
               <p>"But our country does not need a 'Bong Tong' in it if that kind of appearance is what you call it; we have much better features and forms here than Queen Krinaleen herself, and no thanks to her arts," said one young Amrikite damsel who had the bloom of health upon her cheek, and rejoiced in a well-balanced and joyous mind, and the name of Mary Jane.</p> 
               <p>"Well, we do not wish to be straight like you; it is not 'Bong Tong,'" was the reply of her returned friends; for it was a peculiarity of the plague that all who had it had no word or reason to answer besides "<foreign xml:lang="FRA">Le Bon Ton.</foreign>"</p> 
               <p>The philosophers and medicine-men of their country at once detected the plague, and warned them that the disease was fatal and would kill them; but their singular appearance was getting them the attention and notoriety they coveted, and they did not care whether it was fatal or not. At first those women who had not visited the land of the Mezeers condemned the indiscretion of those who brought the infection to their country, but hearing only "Bong Tong" in reply to all their reproofs, they soon caught it themselves, and before long nearly all the women in Yorick, Dell Fee, and Boasting were, in feet, backs, hands, and faces, as much crippled and discolored as the most infected among the lewd women of the capital of the Mezeers. To add to their forlorn aspect, they cut their hair over their foreheads, to give themselves the appearance of invalids just escaped from a hospital, and dangled their hands uselessly and awkwardly<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC6132-00000020"/> at their breasts, like the winglets of the penguin or great auk. There was a sudden and indignant cry raised by the wise all over the land at this wanton destruction of the beauty of which they were so justly proud; for their straight and graceful forms were destroyed by this detestable plague, and their modest and well-bred manners had been transformed to idiocy and indecency of behavior.</p> 
               <p>I am obliged to confess that their appearance with this plague gives Gibbon Darwin, Esq., a good foundation for his story; for they looked at this time as different as possible from that figure which we conceive for our mother Eve, as she was created for Adam, well-formed, healthy, and attractive. If, as all naturalists agree, the transmission of qualities from the mother's side is a law of human propagation, it must be admitted that the children of such deformed, sickly, and feeble invalids as the Amrikite women were after this plague had wasted their beauty and tainted their blood, could not be of that stuff which a country requires for its government, defense, and advancement. But it so happened that many of them never married, especially those who were prostrated by the plague in its severest form, for their energies were divided between seeking for antidotes to the evils of the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">Le Bon Ton,</foreign> and exhibiting and spreading it among their fellows.</p> 
               <p>The atmosphere of their homes was laden with a marcescent vapor, and until the sun rose to its zenith nothing but the sickly hue of the plague, and the waste it was making of their forms, was visible; but when the noonday sun had chased away these poisonous vapors, the victims of the plague came forth in the bright sunlight to exhibit the deformities it had brought upon them, in all their grotesqueness and caricature. By this means the most lively and ludicrous side of the picture was presented to the public; the most silly were enamored of it, while those who were of larger calibre found amusement in it, for they liked to laugh at something,<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6132-00000021"/> and thought this a subject for laughter and ridicule, rather than for loathing and condemnation.</p> 
               <p>The first plague having been spread among the Amrikites with so much ease, the Lesmodistes and their fellow-conspirators prepared others, under the patronage of Queen Krinaleen, to follow and hasten the destruction of the people. Everything which could impair health, subvert strength, conflict with nature, deform the members, mar grace and simplicity, pervert truth, and destroy confidence in the genuineness of anything that was developed and beautified by nature, was introduced into the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">Soieries,</foreign> for that became such a favorite article of display with the Amrikites, that they accepted anything which was ornamented with it.</p> 
               <p>The same plague, made chronic, until all the women of Amrika were affected, and the race had become too weak to resist the armies of King Boursouffle, might have done the work; but it would not have done it so quickly, nor afforded the Lesmodistes, the Lesorfevres, and the Lesmarchandsdesmodes so much profit and reward for their labors. The Amrikites were a changeable people, soon tiring of sensations and novelties, and always craving something new and exciting; and after the freshness of the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">Le Bon Ton</foreign> sensation had passed away, the plague might probably have expired with those who had destroyed themselves with it, and leave enough of untainted blood and unimpaired health behind to supply the loss of life and strength sustained by the country. To guard against this, and secure with all dispatch the enrichment of themselves and the destruction of the Amrikites, the Lesmodistes and their confederates persuaded Queen Krinaleen to allow them to change the name and vary the forms of the plagues as often as possible. So the next plague announced to the expectant victims was called <foreign xml:lang="FRA">La Mode Parisienne.</foreign> It was, like the other, however, first inoculated with the "sore eye" element, so that, becoming<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6132-00000022"/> blinded by that subtle poison, it would be received with less caution and hesitancy by the lavish Amrikites. Next it was given to the lewd women of the capital of the Mezeers, who always added virulence and contagion to Queen Krinaleen's plagues, and then agents were appointed in the cities of Yorick, Dell Fee, and Boasting, to facilitate the sale of the infected clothing they sent them; because they feared that if the Amrikites were compelled to come to their capital to purchase, they would discover the plot, by becoming acquainted with the effects of the plagues upon the miserable creatures the virtuous Queen Krinaleen had determined to exterminate from her capital. Therefore, they shrewdly agreed among themselves to give agents in Amrika a percentage of their profits, rather than risk losing all hope of gain by allowing the Amrikites to detect their villainy, and become alarmed at the malignity of the plagues.</p> 
               <p>Large ships were consigned to them, filled to their utmost capacity with clothing which had been previously infected, and then marked <foreign xml:lang="FRA">La Mode Parisienne,</foreign> so that the silly women of the Amrikite cities would think the name a respectable one, and receive the clothes without suspicion or fear. If the color or shape of the clothing betrayed that it had been already used and defiled by the lewd women of the Mezeers, the agents would insist that it was the only kind they had to give them, and they must take it or go naked, as there was nothing else for them to wear. To overcome their scruples, and make the plagues binding upon their consciences, they claimed that Queen Krinaleen had been by the Graces inspired with, and made prophetess of, a new religion called Fah Shun; and not having a prophetess in their own country, the Amrikite women blindly bowed down to this hideous idol. They cast before it reason, charity, health, comfort, and everything the agents of the Lesmodistes required of them, as cruelly as the worshipers of the<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC6132-00000023"/> monster Juggernaut used to cast their children under the wheels of his chariot.</p> 
               <p>No one justified it, no one could give one sound reason for doing it, as neither art, health, nor morals could be promoted by such a violation of reason, feelings, and taste; but each one blamed some one else for doing as the priests of this hideous idol commanded them.</p> 
               <p>Yet while they blamed, they imitated each other's example, because, not having courage to be true, they feared each other's scorn if they withheld any sacrifice from the bloody altar of the monster. Oh, the poor, devoted victims of Fah Shun! I could weep with the prophet for the slain of the daughters of that people, if their own folly had not invited and assisted in their destruction.</p> 
               <p>There was always in this people a strong propensity to clutch at strange doctrines; and carrying obedience to them to excess, and with the self-sacrifice which is a part of woman nature, they let their natural limbs and vitality waste, while giving all their attention to the false ones this plague offered. They became an insupportable burden to themselves, for there was no strength in the substitutes for flesh and blood which the religion commanded; and the more needful support became to them after the debilitating effect of this plague, the more difficult it became for them to procure it.</p> 
               <p>The support intended by nature for woman failed them even; for those who should have been their husbands hesitated before they burdened their youthful shoulders, and clogged their energetic movements, with the care of helpless and complaining invalids. No matter how healthy and vigorous they appeared before, no one could determine what they would be after marriage; for the poison of those plagues was in their system, and the bloom and fullness they were supposed to possess were often laid aside in the nuptial chamber, never to be resumed again. So you will<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC6132-00000024"/> readily perceive that much was already done by those two plagues towards the accomplishment of Queen Krinaleen's purpose.</p> 
               <p>Neither she nor her servants waited to see what would follow, however; but, now sure of their victims, a third plague was sent forth, more outrageous upon innocence and decency than any of the preceding ones. They labeled it "<foreign xml:lang="FRA">Les Joujoux de la Demimonde,</foreign>" and while the Lesmodistes and their agents recommended the clothes which were infected with it for promoting beauty and symmetry of person, they exceeded all that came before them in the grossness and indelicacy of their disproportions. The consequence was that those who had been deformed and wasted by the other plagues, presented, soon after assuming the costumes of the third one, a spectacle to the eye of the critical observer (and all had by this time become critics) that was ludicrous in the extreme, for the general inquiry was, "What fellowship have lank, skinny hands and necks with voluptuous busts and hips?"</p> 
                
               <p>Truly theirs was an age of startling wonders and transformations, for the sorceries and machinations of the Lesmodistes turned people to any form and feature they desired, as readily as the demons of ancient mythology changed their rivals to beasts or stones. But what most defies my penetration is, that since it is a trait of woman's character to have an innate and vehement desire to be beautiful, or to be considered so whether she is or not, she could adopt costumes and forms which tended only to make her ugly and deformed. Did she love the infected clothes and ornaments the Lesmodistes forced on her more than herself? And if so, what was there in them that made her prefer them to health, grace, and beauty?</p> 
               <p>Could they not see that the glances bestowed on their swollen proportions were not of admiration, but directed by the speculative spirit of the age, which was computing the cost of the curled hair and steel wire in them? The only plausible reason I can<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC6132-00000025"/> offer for such an unnatural phenomenon is, that the two first plagues had destroyed their fine sensibilities and perception, the offspring of the high civilization to which their race had attained; the "sore eyes" had made them blind to the contempt they incurred by their folly, and they were drifting back to barbarism by the debasing influences of the plagues on both body and mind. We know that savages everywhere have an ideal and standard for beauty, which is shocking and revolting to the refined. They make themselves hideous with paint, and fantastically ugly with gaudy-colored scarfs and feathers; but in each other's eyes they are objects of beauty and envy. They flatten their heads, split or compress their noses, blacken or knock out their teeth, gash their faces, stretch their lips and ears to the most disgusting proportions, to rival each other in beauty; their ideas are simply savage and barbarous, ours are more civilized and refined.</p> 
               <p>Among the books which I found in the ruins of Yorick, was one written by Captain Burton, a traveler, who was contemporary with this people. In it I read that the inhabitants of a portion of Africa, which he had visited, selected wives for their beauty by ranging all the marriageable women in a row, dressed up in front with military precision, and then picking out those whose posterior parts projected the farthest; as that was their ideal of beauty. Another traveler saw a belle who was celebrated throughout all her territory for her beauty, and so justly entitled to her fame, that when she sat upon the ground, she could not rise again until she had pushed herself along to some declivity, which assisted her to balance herself upon her feet by raising her enough to overcome her inconvenient posterior gravity. My point can be made now, when I state to you that the Amrikite women, having committed themselves to receive whatever monstrosities the Lesmodistes chose to conceive and bring forth to them, looked to them for counsel and into their<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC6132-00000026"/> books for directions concerning the plagues, with the same blind fatuity with which the Romans consulted their Sibylline books; and, by the advice of these unprincipled impostors, sought to establish the brutish African's standard of beauty among themselves.</p> 
               <p>The moment the third plague was sent among them, labeled <foreign xml:lang="FRA">Les Joujoux de la Demimonde,</foreign> the form of their women changed, as if by magic; and they developed behind, as if they expected to be chosen for their beauty like the African women. Alas for civilization, for modesty, and for morals, when the mothers of a coming generation are the victims of a plague so foul and lecherous!</p> 
               <p>This new deformity was called Pa-neer, by the Amrikites, however; I suppose because the daughters of the land found that Pa ne'er could be reconciled to such an enormity. Hung up in the windows of the agents of the "Lesmodistes," it resembled in shape the shell of a huge turtle, and the philosophers of the Amrikites first thought it was a life-boat their women carried suspended behind them, ready to float them incase they slipped from the bank of a river into the water. But at this time the plagues had so weakened the women, mentally and physically, they had not nerve enough left to go so near water, so that precaution would be a needless one; though some of my auditors may smile at the idea as associating so much posterior development with a fine nervous temperament.</p> 
               <p>I must also remark that when they affected the beauty of the Pa-neer, they also developed the back part of their heads in proportion, so that those who were learned in phrenology would see the consistency between the animal preponderance of the brain and the ambitious bulk of the Pa-neer.</p> 
               <p>If you think now that I have accounted for the willingness with which they became infected with the new plague, allow me to sustain my theory by explaining how they<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC6132-00000027"/> could so far recede from the advanced notions of civilization and religion, which at that time placed their country in the foremost rank of enlightened nations.</p> 
               <p>We are told that the priests of Somal, after overtaxing their mental capacity in learning to read the Koran, become unfit for anything that requires the exercise of judgment or common sense. What seems easy to our children so far exceeds the adult capacity of that weak-minded race, that in gaining a little learning the balance of the mind is lost. So these women over-balanced their foreheads, where the intellect is seated, by the enlargement of their animal propensities behind, and after expending their mental stores in the intricacies and trickeries of the plagues, they were incapable of sensible or natural discernment in making themselves attractive, for I admit their intentions were better than the means they used.</p> 
               <p>Their object was to win each other's admiration, no doubt, and they thought to do so by this plague, for they would not subject themselves to its burden for any beauty it gave them in their own eyes. Peacocks or turkey-cocks do not spread their tails for their own admiration, because they cannot conveniently look at them; they must have a spectator, even if that spectator should be only the most ill-bred of their barn-yard companions. So the Amrikite women were not tempted by selfish motives more than the desire to command admiration can be called selfish. They thought they were making themselves the objects of admiration and desire, and with martyr-like spirit they submitted to the tortures of the plagues for the good of others.</p> 
               <p>This was in obedience to a natural instinct, of course; but, unfortunately, they always tried to follow nature in the most unnatural way, and the benefits which were originally designed to flow from that amiable motive were not produced by their efforts. The only natural effect was a less beneficial one, an intensified rivalry of each<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC6132-00000028"/> other, which was expressed whenever they met by scornful looks and defiant gestures, similar to those interchanged by the males of the feathered race, when they contend for the admiration of their females with their odors, antics, and plumage.</p> 
               <p>The general result was, however, that which Queen Krinaleen had in view when she prepared the plagues for them. The men looked upon them as tainted and deformed, and could not be charmed by attitudes, developments, or odors which were contrary to nature, and offensive to their sense of taste and harmony. The beauty which sufficed and called forth the admiration of the debased African, could not satisfy the more refined requirements and elevated tastes of the enlightened Amrikite. If it had become the standard by which they had selected their wives, a race of barbarous bipeds might have blackened the country with their vile habits to this day, and leave no room for the theory of Gibbon Darwin, Esq.</p> 
                
               <p>A writer of the Mezeers who lived at this time, and was an observer of the effects of the plague in his own capital, had very justly remarked that the beauty of women is equaled in its diversity only by the impressions it produces upon men, and the effect it has upon their morals and manners. It makes them generous or selfish, pure or gross, and elevates or debases their natures, according to the emotions and sentiments it inspires.</p> 
               <p>In the most brutal and uncultivated minds, woman falls to the level of a female when her gentleness, modesty, and virtue do not deprecate the selfishness and combativeness of man, and then, like the female of any other animal, she is bullied and beaten by superior strength and energy. Barbarous nations and savage tribes had always so used woman; and casting away her gentle, unassuming manners and meek spirit, is equivalent in all lands to disarming herself, and challenging all that there is coarse, brutal, and selfish in the masculine<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC6132-00000029"/> culine nature, to enter the lists against her.</p> 
               <p>Underestimating the graces of simplicity, modesty, and gentle behavior, and overestimating the power of barbarous ornaments and unchaste customs, they made themselves dropsical, unclean, and gross; and defiled themselves from head to foot with a plague which could inspire nothing more than disgust in the minds of men who had far advanced in the fastidiousness of civilization.</p> 
               <p>As has been already intimated, their minds were affected by the tortures of their bodies, and therefore, while they regarded themselves with complacency, they could not perceive how the healthy and unafflicted despised them. The virtuous and refined people of the present day may indignantly condemn them, and say they were not fit to continue on the earth, since they sought to corrupt the morals of their race by the style of beauty they presented to the eye. And had their men admired them for the false charms they displayed, or selected them for the deformity of the Pa-neer, we could not regret their doom, as it is better for a people to perish from the face of the earth than retrograde from civilization and Christianity to the degradation of the Hottentot and the paganism of Fah Shun.</p> 
               <p>But let us in charity remember that all people act and speak in the delirium of fevers and other cerebral diseases, as differently from their sound and sober selves as possible. If the words and deeds of Philip drunk could be condemned and set aside by the better nature and judgment of Philip sober, so would the folly and crime of destroying themselves and their people by those plagues be repudiated by the well-meaning Amrikite women, if they had a moment's respite from the tortures and fevers heaped upon them.</p> 
               <p>But Queen Krinaleen and her agents knew this, and to prevent an abatement of their diseases, they kept sending poisons in new costumes all the time, to keep the fever and delirium at their height.</p> 
               <pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC6132-00000030"/> 
               <p>With a wisdom and shrewdness which would awake my warmest admiration, had they not been directed against health and innocence, she calculated the time to a day which each plague would retain its freshness and power with them, and then withdrew some of the features, that they might be replaced by those more novel to the eye.</p> 
               <p>While the optical disease was concealed in the Soieries, there could be no hope of the Amrikite women seeing whither their influences were tending, and if they could see themselves and their folly with impartial sight, those who had the plagues were too much wasted and weakened by them to be guided by reason, and make exertions for the recovery of their health and their moral and holy influence.</p> 
               <p>What could a woman do towards guiding her own steps or the feet of her fellow-creatures in the paths of usefulness and virtue, when her feet were so cramped that she was compelled to totter along on her toes, and her back so bent with disease that she squirmed rather than walked, and looked as if the cares and aches of a hundred years were crushing it? What grace of the heart could she cultivate and make attractive to others with the pressure of a life-boat and twenty other contrivances crowding her ribs against it, poisoning her blood by stagnation, and ready to cut her in two at the waist? What useful knowledge could she store in her head, when its level had been lost by the ambitious development behind it, and the plagues had made it necessary to poultice it with hornets' nests, bind it with coils of serpents, and scratch it with the claws and beaks of carnivorous birds?</p> 
               <p>With all these tiring her, tearing her, and torturing her, more than any disease we can conceive, could she listen to reason and try to make her life one of peacefulness, usefulness, and happiness? Could she constrain her husband to praise her at the gates of the city, and train her children to rise up and call her blessed? No, we must pity the<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC6132-00000031"/> unfortunate martyrs, for the sake of all they suffered: for they suffered a martyr's death without winning a martyr's crown. The pains and perplexities to which they were subjected were greater than those which have made the lives of a few thousand Christians honored on earth and rewarded with immortal glory in heaven, and yet because they did not suffer for principles or for the benefit of humanity, they are refused our sympathy and our praise! Ah, my auditors, it is the prosaic fashion of our days to think that the example of people should be remembered for what it is worth to posterity, but let us not forget how comparatively easy it is for us to do right when our clothes sit comfortably on us, our digestion is good, our bones are not preying upon our lungs and liver, and we are not suffering from the fevers and achings of debilitating plagues.</p> 
               <p>I will next call your attention to the nature and effects of the fourth plague, for to secure the complete degeneracy of the people of Amrika, enough of malignant disease was directed against them by the queen and her magicians to render them incapable of resistance to even the military genius and the army of her consort, who was harmless as the dove.</p> 
               <p>The fourth plague was called <foreign xml:lang="FRA">Le Jeu d'Eugnie,</foreign> and though communicated through the Lesmodistes and Lesorfevres to the women of Amrika, it was in turn transmitted by them to their husbands in a far more fatal form than they had received it themselves. Thus it has been through all ages: woman gives nothing as she receives it, for it must become either better or worse by passing through her hands. A pleasure, an affliction, or a simple statement must undergo some change which intensifies it one way or the other when she is the conductor. Humanity is, perhaps, the gainer by this arrangement in most cases, but in this plague it was a sufferer.</p> 
               <p>The resources of Queen Krinaleen were almost unlimited, as her subjects were industrious<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC6132-00000032"/> dustrious and submissive, and had rich vineyards and were skillful artificers.</p> 
               <p>To rival her, the loud and stubborn women of the Mezeers, whose feet never abode in their houses, taxed and robbed the king of the Mezeers and the men of his court all the more, so that for some time the simple people of their land were profited by the new plague.</p> 
               <p>But the queen soon quietly resigned this plague to the mistresses of her husband and his courtiers, and watched for the effect upon her own social enemies, and her husband's enemies, the Amrikites, while she continued to invent others.</p> 
               <p>In our language and day this plague would be simply described as a mania for extravagant expenditure and display, for it fell upon the victims in the form of an itch, which could not be soothed or allayed except by walking up and down on the streets of their cities, and turning in to soothe their hands by rubbing them with the silks and precious metals in the warehouses. This having a seemingly beneficial effect, they naturally desired to possess as much of the antidote as possible, and whenever they found materials which eased their hands by the power of friction, they purchased them, regardless of the cost.</p> 
               <p>But the more they resorted to this means of relieving themselves, the more incessant and imperative became the demands of their tickling and burning affection for a repetition of the treatment; because, like all cutaneous diseases, rubbing afforded only a temporary relief, while it increased the fever and irritation. Soon the ruling passion among the infected was that of walking and purchasing, or, in the phraseology of their cities, for "shopping" or "promenading." They did the former for the purpose of supplying themselves with cure for their own itch, and the latter to compare their cures with those of others who were afflicted in a similar manner.</p> 
               <p>Mistresses led the way and maids followed, until all those who had the plague in the<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC6132-00000033"/> land were in one whirlpool of excitement and rivalry.</p> 
               <p>This state of things, being considered at first a mere local disorder, was laughed at by the Amrikites, who thought it could never be attended by any serious consequences. Besides, it made the streets of their cities present a lively appearance, and those who traded in the wares the women purchased were enriched from the brisk trade they enjoyed by it. The husbands of those who were infected, too, were in good spirits because their wives were unusually affectionate and kind when they wanted money to make their purchases, which was almost every day. Thus it was the most insidious of all the plagues, because no one could foresee or suspect the evil that it was to bring upon their country.</p> 
               <p>But even husbands will become tired of affection when it is sold to them at a price they consider exorbitant, and they soon learned to regard the new plague as something too serious to be laughed at.</p> 
                
               <p>As the purchase mania increased each day with the itch and irritation of the plague, the husbands attempted to tighten their purse-strings; but this check was usually attended by hysterics, and public opinion, which was a strong current in their country, set against them and branded them as monsters for attempting to cut off the supply which was at the time, the sedative and irritant of this plague. Every man had a wife or daughters, who, like the daughters of the horse-leech, were crying More! more! all the time, and declaring they could not live if every remedy that every other woman in the land had tried was not procured for them also. In trying to soothe them and allay the plague the men sacrificed health, peace, honor, and principle, for in their efforts to save the lives of their wives and enjoy domestic quietness, they forgot every duty but that of procuring money with which to purchase remedies for the consuming and peace-destroying plague. They had no solace in their homes, for funds were wanted<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC6132-00000034"/> from some source to supply the plague, so they strove to overcome the difficulty by enlarging their warehouses, extending their commerce, increasing their labors, oppressing their dependants, and cheating their customers. But the more they labored to supply their wives and their daughters with remedies for the plague, the greater became their demand for them. The plague became incurable, and every sufferer became a plague in turn to those who labored to procure all the remedies, which had been tried in vain upon every other sufferer.</p> 
               <p>Soon it was perceived that it was not so harmless and amusing as was at first supposed, for while it was a source of profit to them by gaining for them the wealth of their fellows, they were none the richer for it, as it consumed more in their own families than it gathered to them from the families of their countrymen. It was then they felt the evil, in heart, and limb, and head, for nothing that disagrees with a man's health and prosperity is less than a great evil in his estimation, however pleasant it may affect him when he sees it in another. From laughing they turned to rage, they tore the hair from their heads, they raved and cursed, and slaved and burst, scattering misery and desolation all over their land, and covering themselves with shame and ruination. They had not the patience and buoyancy of the female temperament to sustain their vitality in this plague, and despair made it the more fatal to their overtaxed constitutions. But no one pitied them, nor expressed regret at their sickness and death. Their enemies were truly those of their own house, for so imperative and unrelenting was the demand for means of allaying the itch upon themselves, that the hands of the women may be said to have been at the hearts of their husbands, and their feet treading on their necks.</p> 
               <p>At last they made a united effort to free themselves from the tyranny and persecution of their wives. In their country, most men had hitherto allowed themselves to<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC6132-00000035"/> become possessed of the idea that religion was a sentiment adapted to woman, and becoming to her; and therefore delighted in boasting of their wives' piety and goodness, while they indulged themselves in a little grumbling and swearing when called upon to give the tithe necessary to the better maintenance of Christianity, which was at first the religion of their country. But when the worship of Fah Shun was introduced and found to be not only much more expensive than the religion of their ancestors, but also without any of the fruits of Christianity, they had no longer any hope of sharing in the blessings of their wives; so they determined to have a hope and solace for themselves.</p> 
               <p>The leading men of their country were consulted as to how they could best organize for protection against their wives and to counteract the new plague.</p> 
               <p>After much deliberation it was decided to "run" an opposition religion, because competition was a favorite principle of theirs; and they resolved that the name of this new religion should be called Doll Err, after the idol they made for their reverence.</p> 
               <p>This new idol was soon represented by duplicates, until they numbered as many millions as the gods of India, and were set up all over their land for worship. Their sons were trained up to believe it was an almighty power, and more to be esteemed than wisdom or honor, for the lives and examples of those who had been the miserable devotees of it were ever held up to them for emulation.</p> 
               <p>The biographies of misers and millionaires, whose hearts had become hard and shrunken by the meanness and selfishness of their aspirations, were text-books in their schools, and fathers used to smile approvingly when their sons showed a genius for cheating at marbles, or making sharp bargains in trading penknives, for that was the way, they were told, that Barr Numb, Jay Wrod, Gem Phisk, and other celebrities of their country, began the worship of Doll Err.</p> 
               <pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC6132-00000036"/> 
               <p>The brain and vital parts of the race had been touched at last, for, tainted on both sides, there was no hope that it could survive through many more generations. As long as the plagues were confined to the women there was hope, for all were not infected; and the men, being still vigorous and untainted, would naturally select the healthiest and best-formed of them for their wives, and leave an offspring to inherit their qualities, while the diseases and deformities of the others would die with themselves.</p> 
               <p>But now the men were also stricken: heart and brain paralyzed in all their true functions, to every feeling and to every sentiment that honors humanity, and gives life and character to a people. Their hands itched for gain, bribes, and rewards, their feet trod in all the avenues and by-lanes of treachery. They sought the offices and judgment-seats of the land, and made them shambles for the slaughter and sale of justice; their hands were turned against each other, except when they leagued to plunder their fellows, and prey upon their country. Physically and morally they were smitten by the plague; over-worked, they died of paralysis, or lived a race of invalids and monomaniacs. It was a matter of course with their wives and daughters, for it supplied them with their favorite antidotes, but with them it was a matter of life or death. It was itch with one sex, and scratch with the other; and scratching was the fatal part of this plague.</p> 
               <p>The disease settled on their stomachs and made them melancholy dyspeptics; on their livers, and turned their faces to yellow parchment. Their skin dried and wrinkled, and their hair became gray before they had lived half their days; their flesh withered, their bones crumbled, and they spent the other half of their life in hopeless suffering. They lost respect for themselves; they lost interest in their nation; they lost veneration for morality and truth, and they cared nothing for the prosperity of their race, so long as themselves and their lineal descendants<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC6132-00000037"/> ants were enriched. They went in and out among their fellows, a selfish, greedy, Godstricken people, with only one unavailable cure for all the aches and diseases they had brought upon themselves, only one barren consolation for all the peace they had lost, and one wretched substitute to their posterity for all the health and honor they had sacrificed, and that was Doll Err.</p> 
               <p>Distress and distrust was the habitual expression of every face; for it soon came that no man could be weighed in the balance of justice and not found wanting. The people knew not who to appoint for their rulers and treasurers, because the greed of the plague was so great, all were sure to betray the trust reposed in them. So in all their cities fraud and violence were eating up the prosperity and peace which characterized them when they lived in simplicity and purity. The temples and quays of Yorick, Dell Fee, and Boasting were now the marts of truth and honesty; people feared and shunned them, and would not venture from their own firesides, lest the plague and its evils should attaint and devour them.</p> 
               <p>My audience will bear in mind that all the plagues I have mentioned yet had been introduced to the Amrikites by means of the clothing infected especially for their destruction. There were many women, however, in Amrika who did not care for Queen Krinaleen's clothing, or for the filthy rags sent to their country by her agents, but rather preferred decent and untainted garments, not regarding the criticism and scorn of their foolish and frivolous sisters. Over these women, therefore, the enchantments of Queen Krinaleen and her magicians had no power; and, as she foresaw from the beginning that such would be the case, she sought other means to destroy those who despised her beauty and her artifice.</p> 
               <p>Now, there was no other way that her influence was felt by her contemporaries, except by the infected clothing which she<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC6132-00000038"/> invented. In this she was all-powerful: the silk-worm quaked in his cocoon, the whale shivered in his icy ocean, and the myriads who worshiped Fah Shun listened with silent awe when she gave her orders as to the amount of whalebone or other materials she wanted for compounding the plagues, and destroying the health and beauty of her sex. But while her enchantments ceased here, her husband also practiced enchantments and other evils in a different way and sphere; and upon him she called for aid when her ingenuity and the abominations of her creatures, the Lesmodistes, could not aid her.</p> 
               <p>To carry out her designs, and make the demoralization of the people of Amrika complete, King Boursouffle assembled his soothsayers, astrologers, and counselors, who were called Les Ecrivailleurs, Les Saltimbanques, and Les Polichinelles, in the language of the Mezeers; and he commanded them to invent plagues which would destroy all who should escape those the queen was preparing for their enemies. But they protested, with the gallantry of their nation, that none could withstand the enchantments and power of Queen Krinaleen, and that no one else could hope to succeed where she had failed.</p> 
               <p>This answer was displeasing to the king, however, and before they knew where they were he drove them from his presence in wrath; because they had enjoyed his patronage and protection by pretending to him that all things could be done by his power, and the word of his command. But the queen, who knew that they merely wished to flatter the king, called them to herself, and explained to them the nature of the women she wished them to deal with, and her reasons for fearing that the Lesmodistes, Lesorfevres, and Lesmarchandsdesmodes could not transfer her poisons to them. "They are in many respects similar to the troublesome subjects of the king whom you have enchanted by the poison <foreign xml:lang="FRA">L'Amour et l'Esprit,</foreign>" she said, "and as they are fond of books rather than costly jewels, and whimsical ideas rather than whimsical garments,<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC6132-00000039"/> they can be destroyed with their weaker sisters by sending infected books in the same ships which shall take the poisoned clothing of the Lesmodistes to their country." This gave them hope, and they begged to be allowed to come into King Boursouffle's presence again.</p> 
               <p>When he had permitted them, they said, "Your majesty knows that we possess all skill and cunning in devising ways to entertain and amuse people while we are morally and intellectually poisoning them.</p> 
               <p>"We have for many years been enchanting your subjects with pretty tales and spectacles of murders, suicides, adultery, and all kinds of treachery and lewdness, to keep them blind and forgetful of the real weakness and rottenness of our social and national status. By this means your majesty has been saved trouble in ruling them, and they have looked upon yourself and Queen Krinaleen as their benefactors; for people have come here from all lands to praise the grandeur and works of art you have purchased with their own money. Your majesty should not, therefore, be wrathy with us, for we can still serve you by our tricks and wit, and help to destroy your enemies, as well as keep your subjects in childish glee and submission."</p> 
               <p>The king was pleased at this courtly blarney, for he had no sooner driven them out than he was appalled at his rashness, as he knew how much of his power and his pleasures he owed to their cunning and co-operation.</p> 
               <p>When restored to the favor and patronage of King Boursouffle, they at once proceeded to poison anew all the books and spectacles they had before poisoned for the Mezeers.</p> 
               <p>They did not wait to invent anything new, but daubed the same matter over and over again, making it more nauseous and slimy than before, reproducing it under new names, and in new forms and colors, after the manner of the Lesmodistes in the poisoned clothing.</p> 
               <p>In a very short time the books were prepared, handsomely covered with yellow<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC6132-00000040"/> paper, and labeled <foreign xml:lang="FRA">L'Amour et l'Esprit,</foreign> so as to deceive the women of Amrika, who, with their usual credulity, would suppose that it was something very good, simply because they did not know what it meant.</p> 
               <p>The victims were cautioned against them, of course, but that only served to make them the more eager to get them; as, being daughters of Eve, they had a morbid presentiment that whatever their guardians were desirous of withholding was surely good for them to possess. Being also women of thought and mind, who had from the beginning mocked the silly worshipers of Fah Shun, and looked into books oftener than into their mirrors, they were jealous of the other sex, and thought that men did not like them to become possessed of those books, because they would learn from them what men were, and what they did.</p> 
               <p>Alas! the unhappy victims, they could not have anything that they would not turn to their own injury and destruction! Wealth, beauty, or intellect, whichever they had, made them presumptuous, vain, or arrogant, and wholly indifferent to truth, self-interest, or reason; and when they had neither, they fell a still easier prey to this plague, by seeking from it the solace which had been denied them by nature.</p> 
               <p>To begin with that part of the plague which acted on the weakest minds, and was compounded with especial regard to its destructiveness to the youth and innocence of the land, I beg leave to remark, first, that in the country of the Mezeers it had already been the bane and destroyer of their peace and happiness. It had been fatal to their social laws and prosperity, it had destroyed their confidence in the virtue and truth of their women, it had banished from their land that love of home and fireside security which has in all ages characterized a brave and virtuous people, and had made them the by-word among all contemporary nations for vagrancy and inconstancy. Its office was to reduce the people of Amrika to the same strait with<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC6132-00000041"/> themselves in this respect, for what is a people or a nation without social confidence and domestic virtues? What the biographies of their misers and millionaires had left undone, this finished for the youth and innocence of the country. True manliness was sapped at the very root, and the expanding mind filled with corrupt and cowardly sentiments, or with morbid and dreamy visions of ideal paramours and illicit loves.</p> 
               <p>This sickly enchantment soon became the bane of their land, for the women who were poisoned by it were transformed into visionary, useless, and languishing idlers; seeming to exist rather than live, for they aimed to be such useless sentimental creatures as the Mezeers painted in their books,-mere caricatures of women.</p> 
               <p>Seeing each other as described in the books of the Les Saltimbanques and their companions, the youth of both sexes became mutually distrustful, and, while pretending to be dying, or ready to die, for sheer love of each other, were ever on the watch to overmatch and betray, after the manner of the Mezeers. Love was changed to intrigue, and respect to contempt, by the teachings of these poisoned books. Moral and mental charms were esteemed useless for any desirable purpose after they had become infected; to chatter nonsense in ungrammatical language, repeat unmeaning phrases, and play easy waltzes, was considered all that was necessary to fit girls for the duties and graces of life. Retrograding from the wisdom and refinement of their ancestors, who did not overlook the weightier matters of education, they sought to go back to the habits of their earlier progenitors, who, as they were informed by the original Darwin, during long ages courted each other in vocal tones, and were subject to vague and indefinite emotions when moved by their beastly music. Therefore they vied with each other in learning to reproduce these emotions by squeaks and squalls, and thrumming with passionate fury upon some alluring instrument.</p> 
               <pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC6132-00000042"/> 
               <p>Taking their cue from the books of the Mezeers, which taught them that weak, contracted minds were preferable for the married state, inasmuch as they would be regarded more docile and confiding, they aimed to be silly, useless, and ignorant, and to avoid any word or deed which would betray a healthy sentiment or aspiration. Truly, here were reason and logic for those who sought to imitate animals!</p> 
               <p>Is the ass or the mule more docile and manageable than the noble and intelligent horse?</p> 
               <p>Is the ignorant and stubborn pig more easily led, or more faithful to its master, than the intelligent and sagacious dog?</p> 
               <p>I need not pause for an answer.</p> 
               <p>For those who had too much brain to be overcome by the above poisons, another ingredient was introduced by the Les Saltimbanques.</p> 
               <p>It was compounded of stronger fallacies, pretended independence of spirit, and a disposition to accept any doctrine which was opposed to revelation.</p> 
                
               <p>It first manifested itself upon women possessed of energy, and troubled with restless and unhappy dispositions; the good that was in them was easily perverted, and the evil made violent because the softer characteristics of their sex had not fully developed in them. As soon as the plague had come upon them, they became clamorous against nature for having made them women, and threatened to defeat her designs, if established laws and customs were not so amended as to recognize and fix their status as double-sexed. They became possessed of wandering and discordant spirits; they brawled and harangued in public places, and wrangled about new ideas and fancied oppression. They despoiled each other of their charms to prove that nature had mistaken their uses, and grasped at the accident of their being overlooked in the distribution of feminine gifts to establish their right to the peculiar qualifications and duties of the male.</p> 
               <p>They railed at domestic relations and conjugal<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC6132-00000043"/> jugal duties, because they lacked the graces of womanhood; they fretted because men could not suckle their young, and they denounced Scripture and science for intimating that such a feat was impossible.</p> 
               <p>They said that man, nature, and history had conspired against them, and they raved of reform and rebellion. They said that the sexes differed only as in lower animals; the same duties belonged to both; but while the lower animals remained as nature had made them, these changed sexes at will. They sometimes claimed the privileges of the male, while at other times those of the female, as best suited their inclination and convenience. It may be well to remark that their philosophers have tried, by philological analogy, to explain the cause of this remarkable insanity, which otherwise must be left unaccounted for among the many other singular phenomena of that violent plague.</p> 
               <p>In the language of the Mezeers, the gender of things was subject to no tangible rule, and to the most eccentric and unaccountable countable changes. Wheat, for instance, was masculine as a grain, but when it was ground into flour it became feminine, though there could be no good reason given for such a transformation. When that flour was made into bread, it was again of the masculine gender, and when the bread was toasted, it changed sexes once again and became feminine. Reading the literature of such a people would, therefore, lead those who had their minds deranged by this plague to imagine that they were passing through the same transitions, and subject to the same arbitrary changes. Indeed, when in the delirium of the disease, they often declared that their sex was the blind sport of accident, and should not be, therefore, considered to their disadvantage and prejudice. They quarreled with nature, law, custom, instinct, and inspiration,-in fact, with everything which recognized and appointed the distinct duties, functions, and attributes of the two sexes, and was inexorable in keeping them distinct.</p> 
               <pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC6132-00000044"/> 
               <p>In their wild tirades against divine, natural, and human laws, they carried with them all who were of weak understanding and unhappy temperament, as well as those who were willing to accept any theories that were new and startling, and opposed to their established customs and laws. Many others, who at first were not wholly in sympathy with those whom this plague attacked most violently, accepted many of their doctrines, and were abettors of the haranguers because of the novelty of their ideas and actions. They had no definite idea of what was to be the end of the plague, it took so many phases, and those most infected with it were so different from each other. But, hydra-headed, its evils became innumerable, and showed themselves in a hundred different forms. A legion of evil spirits appeared to have gained possession of them, for many of them professed to have communication with the spirits of the departed, and to be reforming society under their instructions. They called license liberty, modesty and virtue the enemies of progress, after the manner of the books the Mezeers had poisoned for them. Then, finding that many were in sympathy with them, their theories gradually culminated in doctrines which reduced them to the social condition of brutes. They demanded that marriage and other laws which confined natural inclinations, and restrained the free exercise of unlawful affections, should be abrogated, and that the law of caprice and lust should be the only one recognized in the land.</p> 
               <p>Free love and spiritual affinity were the terms they gave to their dissolute and demoralizing doctrines, and you can realize the fatal insidiousness of this plague, when I tell you that this scandalous and brazen demand for unbridled lasciviousness met with encouragement from many whose whole happiness and prosperity were guaranteed by the laws they sought to abolish as tyrannical. The brain fevers and heart burnings produced by this plague had so weakened the understanding of the most<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC6132-00000045"/> pliant, and inflamed the passions of others, that soon the most sedate in their country learned to regard it with indifference; and divorce was advocated and practiced with such unblushing freedom that the marital relation and obligation became a hideous mockery, a synonym for conjugal infidelity and social infelicity. They claimed a natural right to love as long and as frequently as it suited their inclination, and to repudiate their bonds whenever they tired of them, or encountered a stronger "affinity." This created distrust in the breasts of all who esteemed decency and morality as the conditions of social and national peace and security, and destroyed the virtue and sanctity of marriage. It gained adherents and ground despite of the beastly and debasing doctrines it inculcated, until at last, triumphing over virtue and reason, the wretched advocates of this ruinous system bore down all the opposition the few who remained untainted could offer, and succeeded in overthrowing all the laws and guards of the first rite heaven established upon earth for the benefit and advancement of mankind.</p> 
               <p>The acute student of human events will see at once that this people was doomed; for it is patent to all, that just before the downfall of the ancient Roman power, marriage was in the same way suffered to decline and lose the high repute and sacred place it held in the laws of that nation. So long as it was respected and observed by the people it had protected, the country did not want for embryo senators and soldiers to take the place of those who were called to pay their debt to nature or to their country; but when it was no longer the nurse of virtue and bravery, strength, harmony, and patriotism languished and died, and the nation fell before the fierce invader from the north. Some may wonder why the power of their laws was not invoked to check this plague, and restrain the wretches who made it dangerous to the welfare of society and their nation. My answer is, that they had a tradition in their country that their fathers had<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC6132-00000046"/> made a law which said <emph>there should be no law,</emph> and that in their zeal to administer this law and protect it against violation, they neglected to do anything for their own protection or safety. You smile at the paradox, and I do not wonder; but they called this the fundamental law of their land, and believed they were created to protect it, rather than that it was created for their own good and protection. Doubtless, their ancestors, who made some wise laws, had in view the welfare and protection of their posterity, but license and quibbling became such a passion with this people, that they interpolated and interpreted them, until they used them to defeat the object they were formed to accomplish.</p> 
               <p>The next plague of which I will give you an account was called <foreign xml:lang="FRA">La Crme de la Crme</foreign> by the people who introduced it, and also by those who were destroyed by it. I do not design that you should fall into the error of supposing that it was the sixth in order, or that the seven came one after another as I relate their effects to you; for they were all hurled with a fearful simultaneousness against the health and happiness of this devoted race, without waiting to see the effect of any single one of them. But not having seven tongues to call forth at the same time all your pity for this afflicted people and indignation at the malevolence of their destroyers, I must weaken the tale of their misfortunes by tracing one after another the broad paths of death and misery the plagues made in that once happy and populous land. Like the plague of <foreign xml:lang="FRA">Le Bon Ton,</foreign> this had been imported through that ignorant class of adventurers who went to foreign lands, and especially to the capital of the Mezeers, to display the wealth they had suddenly become possessed of, and received from them a foreign name to make it respectable and incomprehensible to their fellow-upstarts.</p> 
               <p>That the symptoms of this plague appeared first in this class of people is, however, certain; and they were similar to those of the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">Le Jeu d'Eugnie,</foreign> because they excited<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC6132-00000047"/> the people to a restless seeking for wants, and magnifying of them, as well as a disposition to substitute shams for reality, and hypocrisy for sincerity, in all their social relations.</p> 
               <p>There was, moreover, no other one of the plagues which became so desirable to all classes of this people as this one, because it was so utterly foreign to their clime, and inconsistent with the previous simplicity of their habits. Not to be a victim to this plague was considered by them equivalent to being a victim of the direst misfortune, and to be afflicted with it was to be, in their estimation, equal to being supremely blessed. In fact, it became such a standard of social merit and distinction, that those who could not become a victim to it felt that their lives and their husbands and children were of no value to them, because of the scorn of the daughters of the plague.</p> 
               <p>As it spread all over their land, peace, comfort and contentment fled before it; and the homes of the Amrikite people were made dreary and desolate by it, because, learning that in the language of the Mezeers, who sent them the other plagues, <foreign xml:lang="FRA">Maison</foreign> was the word for home, they foolishly supposed that a mason had more to do in making a home than contentment, fidelity, and love. Consequently, while they paid strict attention to the work of the mason, and had high walls of stone and brick built in imposing rows on their avenues, they neglected the more important means of making a true home of their masonry.</p> 
               <p>To be comfortable in self-respect or condition was a crime against their social laws; and to be outlawed by them was equal to being cut off from all earthly and eternal happiness. Therefore, to punish such as by reason of poverty, common sense, or some other social crime, were amenable to their laws, they made laws for the government of those who had the plague, which excluded all who could not pronounce every Shibboleth of their jargon from the happiness of their patronage and recognition.</p> 
               <pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC6132-00000048"/> 
               <p>"It shall not be lawful," said they, "for any one to ask us where we live, because living implies a state of existence and employment, which any animal, or any person so unfortunate as not to have the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">La Crme de la Crme,</foreign> may be in possession of; the query must be, 'Where do you reside?' so that we shall know the speaker is entitled to our respect and consideration.</p> 
               <p>"It shall not be lawful for any person to ask for admission at our doors, unless such person shall have first sent his card by a servant, with his age, income, the length of his lineage, and the income of his father and grandfathers written distinctly thereon; and if, after considering the matter attentively, we are confirmed in our suspicions that the petitioner is an impostor and has not the plague, it shall not be lawful for us to permit him to enter.</p> 
               <p>"It shall not be lawful for us to admit to the enjoyment and privileges of this plague any who do not live in mansions of the prescribed dimensions, material, and pattern, and have the doors marked with the emblems of the plague, so that we shall know the angel of peace and contentment has passed over them.</p> 
               <p>"It shall not be lawful for us to admit to our fellowship and supreme felicity any outside barbarians who do not contribute to the support of this plague a stupendous fortune, and evince for themselves and their children to the third and fourth generations, a disposition to submit to all the snubbing and indignities we shall be graciously pleased to subject them to, in remembrance of our serene goodness in communicating the blessings of the plague to them.</p> 
               <p>"It shall not be lawful for us to talk sense of any kind, or to take interest in it, but rather gabble of the amusements of Fah Shun, and imitate the manners in vogue at foreign courts, since we have none in our own country.</p> 
               <p>"It shall not be lawful for the wives and daughters of those who have not the plague to visit us, nor to address us, without our<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC6132-00000049"/> gracious permission; it shall not be lawful for our sons to many their daughters, nor for their sons to ask our daughters in marriage, that our blood may not lose its blue tint and purity by intermingling with them, etc."</p> 
               <p>But while they made these laws for mutual benefit they were themselves the victims of the evils of this plague. Contention about minor laws of their disease and superstition was constantly stirring up strife among them, and making them envious and jealous of each other. By building their houses higher than their fellows, and thus rendering the atmosphere more unfavorable to each other, they kept themselves in a constant fever and delirium; for instead of seeking a home more conducive to their health, they tried, rather, to annoy each other by overshadowing each other's dwellings, and increasing the virulence of the plague among themselves. Conscious in heart of the worthlessness of their own characters to their generation, they sought to divert the attention of their fellow-men from it by pointing to the wisdom and righteousness of their ancestors, and many of them caused the name "Noah" to be engraved upon their newly-made plate, to prove the nobility, length, and antiquity of their pedigree. The tendency of this plague, therefore, was to make them forgetful of their duty to their race and their country, and remain satisfied with what their forefather Noah had done by word and deed to save his own race from destruction.</p> 
               <p>Partaking of their parents' infection, the children also ignored their obligations to their country, and thought neither of the opportunities the present offered, nor of the wants of the future. The nation was, therefore, weakened rather than strengthened by their being a part of it, as a house is by old and rotten rafters in its roofing.</p> 
               <p>This was the object for which this plague had been sent among them, without doubt, for the king and queen of the Mezeers had learned the effect of this plague in the<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC6132-00000050"/> history of their own country, where, after several generations of luxury and profligacy, the interests of the rich and the poor had become so opposed to each other, that the latter, being greatly in the majority, rose up and slew the former, and then turned upon each other.</p> 
               <p>The evil of this plague was felt in another way, also; for when they had enacted a social law that only those who had it, or wealth to pour out for its sustenance, could marry, the young and healthy blood of the land was not allowed to infuse itself into the national life, and thereby counteract the dreadful influence of the plague upon the people. It was only those who had grown old and infirm with the plague who were allowed to marry, and those whom they had purchased with their wealth were women who loved the plague rather than their race. The wife was often married to perform the duties of a nurse, and she was taught from infancy that she must not object to such an aim and end so long as she could get the plague by it. By the observance of this law the plague was left free to prey upon the vitals of the nation; the honest and healthy failed to get mated, and left to their more successful and unscrupulous competitors the charms and accomplishments which could only be secured by wealth.</p> 
               <p>So from one generation to another, since those plagues began to trouble the land, disease, knavery, and cunning were increasing by the law of natural selection, which left those who remained poor and virtuous without means of securing wives and homes for the propagation of their healthy qualities and cultivation of their virtues, and also by the law of sexual selection, which led those of like constitutional unsoundness and mercenary dispositions to prefer each other, and transmit to their offspring their united baseness and coarseness of quality, mean and dishonest principles, and foul infectious plagues.</p> 
               <p>When once each sex set up a god for itself,<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC6132-00000051"/> the sympathy which had so far existed between them was at an end, the work of alienation was begun in earnest, and ever afterwards marriage between them became more rare, and lost the sanctity it possessed before the plagues.</p> 
               <p>But we will forget the hypocrisy and folly of the social laws of this people for a moment, and turn our attention to a law more natural and consistent with the human race.</p> 
               <p>I cannot but admire the laws of nature, which are so nicely and benevolently adjusted to our necessities, that many of the evils we bring upon ourselves by the violation of one law will be overcome by the interposition of another. We have seen that this plague had so tainted the blood of the people, and estranged the sexes from each other by the barrier it placed between them, that there was an unnatural restraint laid upon marriage. The women, however far they had strayed from nature and violated the laws of health and happiness, remained faithful and true to the desire to be mated; for those who were smitten of this plague still attempted to follow one of the most entertaining habits that naturalists have ever observed. I refer to the assembling of birds at their particular haunts when the pairing season approaches, and there parading their ornaments, chanting their love songs, and doing battle with each other according to their habits of selection.</p> 
               <p>The duty of putting forth these amorous efforts devolves upon the male, of course, because the gift of song, beauty of plumage, and courage for battle are his most highly developed characteristics. Enfeebled as the Amrikite women had become by this and the other plagues, they were not lacking in courage to do battle with each other for selection, or to take upon themselves the duties of marriage, as they understood them; and, as they felt that the gifts of beauty and song were theirs, in imitation of the birds whose plumage and notes they had previously counterfeited, they conceived the idea of<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC6132-00000052"/> resorting to this law of nature for remedy after all the other laws had been violated. When the summer approached they began their preparations for migrating to the places they had appointed for this purpose, and their parents and friends who were interested in their success prepared to go with them. Every effort was made beforehand to insure their success in these battles for the selection of mates, by securing for them all that could add to their beauty, accomplishments, and confidence in the approaching contest; and as wealth was regarded by all who were plagued by <foreign xml:lang="FRA">La Crme de la Crme</foreign> as the great charm that could win and accomplish all things, it was drawn from all sources, and accumulated by great personal privations, to be lavished on the females when the momentous contest approached.</p> 
               <p>These places of rendezvous were scattered all over the land for the accommodation of the combatants, but the most noted one was called Sorry-to-go; because however cheerless life had been in their mansions, the fathers of the unmated females were always sorry to leave their houses and their shops and for a season exile themselves from the few comforts they had, and from the worship of their idol Doll Err, and go to witness battles, parades, and rivalries they took no delight or interest in. But they were goaded to it like unwilling donkeys; for their wives and daughters had no respect for their prejudices, but compelled them to revisit the scenes of their own subjugation and attend a form of worship they despised, that their presence might, by their pompous and bullion airs, add weight to the charms of the combatants.</p> 
               <p>Once there, however, all that was required of them during this season was to browse on the lawns of Sorry-to-go, and serve as chief of the exchequer to those taking part in the contest and their allies.</p> 
               <p>The mothers of the unmated females were, from duty and inclination, more willing for the migration, for it reminded them of the battles for selection fought by themselves,<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC6132-00000053"/> and gave them opportunities of revenging several petty quarrels and jealousies which had remained unsettled from that time. Their presence was also useful and necessary to the success of their daughters, as they prompted them in attacks, covered their retreats when their weapons were shivered, and came to their rescue when their plumage and ornaments were defective, and the battle was going against them. But the great mistake they made was that they only followed nature partly, as the beauties they strove to excel each other in, and to excite and charm the senses of the males with, were all false and unnatural to them, being foolishly borrowed from animals which have no affinity with man.</p> 
               <p>Every bird of the forest and plain, from the little humming-bird to the ostrich, had been rifled for this display; the foul odors of beasts were distilled for their benefit; and even the whale had been despoiled of his ribs, that those of the contestants might be more gracefully curved, and they might be more shapely and irresistible in their alluring antics; but they neglected to display the charms most natural to themselves and most attractive to mankind,-simplicity, symmetry, modesty, health, and intelligence.</p> 
               <p>Another drawback to the success of this remarkable imitation of nature's untaught creatures, was the absence of marriageable young men from Sorry-to-go and other places of these amorous exhibitions.</p> 
               <p>Like many of the female birds, they coolly witnessed these exciting charms and diversions from a distant retreat, but kept aloof from the wooers, and, knowing that marriage was not permitted to them by their social laws, hid themselves in the dark solitudes of the forest during this season.</p> 
               <p>Indeed, none came to witness the contests besides the friends and relatives of the contestants, except idle loungers, who usually passed away the tedium of the summer months in such amusements and excitements as these scenes afforded them. They were called the old beaux of society, and, with a<pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC6132-00000054"/> critical and cynical eye, they beheld the battle of the Plagues, and fired the zeal and ardor of the poor combatants by pretending admiration they did not feel, and enjoyment in the gladiatorial sport.</p> 
               <p>So after the battling season was over the disappointed females returned unmated to their mansions, flagged and wearied, ruffled in plumage and temper, bedraggled and bespattered from the contest, wounded in heart and pride, and exhausted of both vitality and resources. Some did, however, succeed in attracting mates to themselves in these contests, but, unfortunately, not such as justified the efforts and the sacrifices it required to secure them. They were mostly lackeys, who had heard of the fame of these battles in a foreign land, and, borrowing the titles and the clothes of their masters for the occasion, they went thither to behold them.</p> 
               <p>As I have already told you, discrimination was the great want of the Amrikites; they mistook the affectation, punctiliousness ness, and critical impertinence of the servant for the manners of the master, did battle as zealously for the impostors as if they were men of true merit and breeding, and the most attractive and vigorous of the females secured them. The cheat was soon discovered, of course; but at this time marriage existed only in form of a civil compact, to be sundered at will, and there was not much harm done besides making a little social scandal, a few family animosities, and a little mortification at the result of their spirited contest.</p> 
               <p>I have now only one more of the plagues which were sent upon this people to speak of before giving you a summary account of their decline and final destruction. This plague was called <foreign xml:lang="FRA">L'Email de Pompadour</foreign> by the women of the Mezeers, and sent to those of Amrika under the pretense of being an elixir which would prevent the decay of beauty, and enable those who took it to enjoy a perpetual freedom from duty or care. To those who had the other plagues<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC6132-00000055"/> it was especially welcome, because it promised to relieve them from the pain and consequences of their folly; and it was said, by those who compounded it, to give them power over the minds of men, and get them the envy of their own sex, by keeping them always in the bloom and freshness of virgins.</p> 
               <p>These pretensions were enough to spread it among the women of the Amrikites; because, having made themselves sickly and prematurely old by the poisons of the other plagues, they would eagerly receive anything which could arrest their decay and enable them to devote themselves, while life prolonged its feeble light in them, to the pleasures of dress and rivalry. The real object for which it was sent to them, however, was to check the increase of the people, by making those who were the victims of its poison the fruitless shrubbery of their land, and the legalized mistresses of their husbands. It is the most difficult of all the plagues to describe, owing to the delicacy of its nature; and if I should use an indiscreet term in speaking of its evils, ascribe it to my indignation and zeal in depicting the wrongs of those innocents who could not speak for themselves.</p> 
               <p>Queen Krinaleen had one son, and only one, because her husband would remove her from his throne, according to the custom of his predecessors, if she did not give him an heir to it, and because if she had more than one son she could not spare time to make enchantments for his subjects, or to invent plagues for his enemies, and spread them among them. So we see that she was in all things a shrewd woman, a politic queen, and a dutiful wife. If her subjects imitated her in this, however, the land of the Mezeers would soon be depopulated; because two persons dying, and leaving only one to take their place, would, in the course of several generations, reduce the most populous country to a wilderness. With but few exceptions the Mezeers did not follow the example of their queen,<pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC6132-00000056"/> however, for they were a gay and careless people, and had neither a throne to secure to their line, nor enemies to destroy by the plague. But the lewd women of their capital, who were recognized as the transmitters of the plagues Queen Krinaleen invented in a doubly loathsome and mortal form, followed that part of her example which best suited their own calling and convenience. In other words, they wanted no sons for thrones, and therefore they removed that conservative principle from the plague which spared one son alive to Queen Krinaleen, and made it deadly to all the innocents before sending it to the Amirikite women. Now, as the other plagues had gradually reduced the moral, mental, and physical condition of those unfortunate women to such a low state, they welcomed this plague as much as all the others, destructive as it was of innocent life, and fatal to the strength and security of their country. The boldest of the Amrikite women justified this treason to their country, and violation of natural and divine law, on the grounds of the first law of nature-that of self-preservation. They maintained (when the real object of this plague had been discovered to them), with shameless disregard of their maternal instincts, that the higher breed of inferior animals destroyed by the instinct of self-preservation their offspring, if they found themselves subjected to danger or inconvenience during the period of gestation. They said they had at least the same rights to suit their own convenience that fancy dogs and pigeons had, and that though religion and society commended the martyrdom, they had an individual right to refuse to sacrifice health and beauty for the common good.</p> 
               <p>In other words, liberty to pursue frivolous pleasures, and the preservation of their complexions for purposes of rivalry, was a greater consideration to them than the privilege of training up an immortal soul to serve its race and live through eternity. Some who had wealth and a name they<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC6132-00000057"/> were desirous of transmitting to posterity, from motives of personal vanity, took the plague in its original form, and contented themselves with having a single heir, like Queen Krinaleen, saying that while one child was a luxury, two became an extravagance, and more yet a prodigality. The greater number, however, took this plague like all the others, at second-hand, and more deadly to the race than Queen Krinaleen had made it. They were too much occupied with the details and excitement of the other plagues, and too much given to the deceit and trickery connected with them, to have time to spare in training up children for the good and defense of the country.</p> 
               <p>Those who were prostrated and debilitated by the other plagues said their health would not permit them to undertake the responsibility training up families, and therefore took this plague to secure to themselves the enjoyments of their other wicked enchantments.</p> 
                
               <p>So the plague was spread, like all the others, throughout the whole land, and the women took more pride in being the untrammeled votaries of pleasure than the mothers of happy and virtuous families. This was more especially the case with the victims of <foreign xml:lang="FRA">La Crme de la Crme;</foreign> because wealth was esteemed so necessary to their existence, they feared to bring more people into the world lest there was not wealth enough in its mines and fields for their subsistence.</p> 
               <p>They pictured to themselves how happy Adam and Eve must have been with all the world before them, and only themselves to possess its treasures, as then there could be no fear of want before their eyes. So it was welcomed and justified like the other six plagues, as none of its victims held themselves amenable to reason or to moral law. No more ruthless destroyer of domestic happiness than this plague could there be invented, as Queen Krinaleen and her agents well knew.</p> 
               <pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC6132-00000058"/> 
               <p>With the tastes, desires, and pursuits of the two sexes growing more radically opposed to each other every year from childhood, until the difference between them amounted to positive antipathy, it was only by the triumph of a law of nature that they were brought together at maturity in the bond of love. That soon wore itself out when they had no mutual sympathies, and no desire to make their persons and minds agreeable to each other; and it was only by the tie of parental love that husband and wife were held together, while one was devoting heart, soul, and body to the service of Fah Shun, and the other engaged as devotedly in the worship of Doll Err. Taking their children from them was equal, therefore, to removing the only link which coupled such husbands and wives in harmony and unity, and taking away the every foundation upon which their nation was built.</p> 
               <p>Some may justify it as an act of mercy to the progeny, but that is ignoring their accountability to their Creator for having made the bodies he had given them so wholly the prey of those poisons that they could not transmit health to posterity. Many who foresaw the ultimate effect of this plague raised a cry of warning and alarm, but their efforts were unavailing: the victims of the evil became as loud in its praise as they did when the other evils were also exposed to them.</p> 
               <p>Thus this plague became a crying evil all over the land, and, like the death of the first-born in Egypt, the one that broke down the pride and strength of their mighty nation. No one could arrest its work, for, like the angel of death, it passed unseen at midnight over every house, and was only visible in the ruin and desolation it left wherever its sword was stretched. Deaths became so much more frequent than births that Death himself became alarmed at the future decay of his power, but there was no law in the land that could protect it against this plague, or punish the iniquity of the murderers.</p> 
               <pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC6132-00000059"/> 
               <p>The plague was essentially a work of darkness, and the argument that what never lived could not be killed was satisfactory to all whose moral instincts had become extinguished by the degrading worship of Fah Shun.</p> 
               <p>I have now described the nature of the plagues to you, and it only remains for me to explain how successfully they accomplished the ruin of this people, and excluded them from the history of the nations which have preserved their existence, and advanced with the progressive march of the last few centuries.</p> 
               <p>The first great step towards warping the judgment and trying the quality of the soul is to afflict the human body; and the physical poisons of the first three plagues most effectually performed this mission. By these great numbers of the women of Amrika had become so deformed, disfigured, and debilitated, they were no longer eligible to either marriage or maternity. Self-gratification and vanity of dress had become the only passions they were capable of developing, and their men not only despised the mean and mercenary motives which led most to seek the married state, but also withheld the merited respect and confidence from those who had to the last remained untainted by the insidious plagues, and had nobler feelings and had noble feelings and qualifications to brings into the partnership of life.</p> 
               <p>Then while the nation was struggling against the evils which so many of its mothers and daughters had brought upon it, a plague on the men, and the idolatry which unfortunately followed it, aimed a deadly blow at its life, and gave a taint to posterity on both sides; so that soon the race degenerated rapidly in strength, morality, and intelligence. By their social laws, no one besides those possessing immense wealth could marry; and as those who were most successful in the struggle for it had accumulated years and diseases with their money, posterity could hope for nothing from them. The most selfish, greedy, and<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC6132-00000060"/> evil passions of human nature were developed in the struggle, as they were the most constantly exercised; for, whatever watery moralists tell us to the contrary, wealth is not usually the reward of virtues and principles, nor should it be the expectation held out to our youth when we admonish them to be guided by them in their lives.</p> 
               <p>The people became weak-kneed, hollow-chested, and sharp-featured, without a sound physical or moral trait to transmit to their children, and by this means each generation sank lower and lower in the grade of humanity and civilization. No people or age has ever been able to advance, or even maintain the position it had inherited, under such disadvantages as this nation labored under. It is the law of marriage and selection that makes and unmakes our race; and whenever governments or societies make laws which deter the best and most virtuous from marriage, and invest the coarse-grained and selfish with the privilege of transmitting their qualities to posterity, you may safely prophesy darkness, degeneracy, and brutality for the coming ages. Humanity cannot afford to let its noblest representatives and finest material die without a posterity, or simply marry a calling or a mission, even though it may be a holier and loftier religion than those of Fah Shun and Doll Err. When the Christian Church tried it, there was a relapse into ignorance, debauchery, and barbarism, and the Dark Ages was the result, because it left to robbers and pirates and illiterate tyrants the duty of reproducing seed after their kind.</p> 
               <p>Next the plague of <foreign xml:lang="FRA">L'Amour et l'Esprit</foreign> spread over their land, like a dark pall of sin, and the license of their laws let them become so immoral and lost to law and virtue, that the nations with whom they held commercial intercourse were compelled, in self-defense, to keep their water-ships in quarantine, and prohibit the sale of their books and periodicals, which had become more infected and scurrilous than those of the Mezeers in a short time. Marriage had<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC6132-00000061"/> been succeeded by a sort of limited partnership that no decent person cared to enter into, because of the insecurity and irregularity of its relationship, and for this reason, also, posterity suffered and inherited nothing but the curses of their forefathers.</p> 
               <p>Then came the last plague, which deprived them of a posterity and the possibility of a reformation, and left the annihilation of their race only a question of time. They failed to perceive the danger, however, because when they sent forth to number their people and count their riches every decade of years, they forgot in their joy at the increase of their wealth, that their race was rapidly declining in physical and numerical strength. As I have already said, their land was always open to the exiles and homeless of other countries, and the apparent increase in their population was due to this steady tide of immigration.</p> 
               <p>Goths, Celts, and Scandinavians were constantly arriving with a numerous progeny, or with robust, prolific women, who were entirely free from the plagues. To them the Amrikites foolishly left the duty of propagating their race, and even of governing their nation, while they devoted all their time and strength to spreading and sustaining the plagues. They toiled and contended from year to year for wealth, only to waste it on these plagues, or pour it out on the altars of Fah Shun, and looked upon the people who came among them vigorous and untainted as lower and more brutal than themselves, because their habits were simple, and their love and care of offspring were natural. But we are all, whether men or monkeys, creatures of imitation, and as those people became acclimated, they lost the qualities they brought with them; and their children learned to think and do as the Amrikites taught them, by precept and example. Therefore the country had no other hope of maintaining the strength and existence of its population besides the arrival of fresh blood and vigor to supply the waste of the plagues; and because it was a wide land, and<pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC6132-00000062"/> rich in its resources, the presumption was that this would never fail it, and its own children might go on destroying themselves according to their inclinations.</p> 
               <p>But this source of strength and life was at last cut off, when the countries from which those people immigrated had cast off their surplus population, and could easily sustain all that were born on their own soils.</p> 
               <p>The nations with, whom the Amrikites had until this time held friendly intercourse traded with them no longer, nor visited their ports, as they feared the plagues might be transmitted to themselves; and after this little was known of their history or their fate, as it concerned no one but themselves.</p> 
               <p>They were shut out from all the world, and left without the healthy admixture of blood and vitality that had so far sustained them against the influences of a clime which was so unfavorable to preservation that their works of art and monuments have crumbled beneath it in one-tenth of the time it has required for the decay of those of Egypt or Greece. They did nothing, however, to avert their doom or drive the plagues from their unhappy land. Not one of the seven was arrested in its ravages while there was food in the country to supply it; but with fatal perseverance the women continued to destroy their health and vigor, and deform their persons, and the men, slaves to the folly of their women and their own greed, went on clutching, and cheating, and scratching from morning until night to sustain the plagues, and appease the gods each sex was zealously devoted to.</p> 
               <p>The wives and mothers of the land became fewer each year, as those who had remained true to their race and principles died from natural causes, and each generation was blessed with fewer of them, so that as time elapsed each man could mournfully say of himself, in a figurative sense, what the compassionate African woman once said literally of Mungo Park: <q>
                     <lg type="quotation"> 
                        <l>"He has no mother to bring him milk,</l> 
                        <l>No wife to grind his corn"</l> 
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p> 
               <pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC6132-00000063"/> 
               <p>Yet they did not even pity their hapless condition, but rather contentedly drew the lines closer and closer around their cities, as the rural population came in to supply the waste of the plagues, and they required less corn and milk from the earth for their sustenance each year.</p> 
               <p>The nation was at length reduced to such a feeble state, that even King Boursouffle need not fear to punish its inhabitants for the offenses of their ancestors; but, alas for human devices, himself and his armies, and Queen Krinaleen and her sorceries, and her heir, Prince Chessapoe, who had been enchanted with a baptism of fire, while his father stood sponsor, that he might by it be made invulnerable against his enemies, had long before this time gone the way of all earth.</p> 
               <p>The courtiers, who had cried with counterfeit admiration and loyalty "<foreign xml:lang="FRA">Vive l'Empereur!</foreign>" whenever he set up his gay-colored block army in gaudy rows, and showed to Les Saltimbanques, Les Ecrivailleurs, and Les Polichinelles, by wire-pulling evolutions upon a green platform, how his illustrious ancestor, with real soldiers, had crossed mountains, fought battles, and stormed cities, were also gone. Their laughter and their huzzas were heard no more in the Elysian Fields of their capital, as a wiser and a graver posterity had taken their place; for they had followed the king and queen to the far-off Elysium, where the shades of all kindly heroes find rest and pleasure.</p> 
               <p>As with Csar, whom King Boursouffle was, by himself, supposed to resemble in military and literary talents, the little good that was in them was interred with their bones, while the evil they did lived after them, and progressed while they were mouldering in their graves.</p> 
               <p>But my tale is not of them, and I will let them enjoy in peace whatever hospitalities and delights that land can afford them.</p> 
               <p>The ill-fated Amrikites are the people with whom I have to do, and I must hasten<pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC6132-00000064"/> to record the finale of the plagues, and the dying throes of their nationality. Ah, how shall I do it? How shall I, with words, conjure up to your view the weird, unearthly scenery of the last act of that solemn drama? How shall I paint for you the pale and thin-visaged Amrikites, the mere shadows of their ancestors, as they moved like yellow spectres about the streets of their cities, with a melancholy presentiment of their impending doom? Under what strange delusion did they labor, or rather by what strange power or fate were they spell-bound, that they were powerless to avert their doom? The fate of the mound-builders, who had inhabited that land before them, was known to them; could it have been that they felt that they were living in an enchanted land, where races of men sprung up, flourished, and decayed like the flowers of the field? Surely man can overcome fate; for the power that made him would not leave him helpless to a relentless destiny. The secret is this, alas! They despised spised that power, and became worshipers of the idols Fah Shun and Doll Err. Judging by their own sordid natures, they thought that judgment could be arrested by devoting to that power a tenth part of what they poured out upon the altars of their favorite idols. It may be incomprehensible to you how they could waste a tenth of their substance in the support of a form of worship that was not only diametrically opposed to their idols, but condemned their whole course from beginning to end. I confess it is a mystery to myself, much time as I have given to the study of their habits and the peculiar organization of their minds. They endowed colleges and seminaries for the express purpose of instructing their children in morals, and elevating their minds above the idolatry of the land, and then their social laws, habits, and maxims flatly denied the truth of all that was taught them in these colleges and seminaries; for Doll Err and Fah Shun were exalted at home as the great household idols.</p> 
               <pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC6132-00000065"/> 
               <p>Supposing themselves to be prompted by charity, they founded hospitals for the sick and afflicted, palaces for the impoverished, and asylums for the insane, and then feeling free to give full vent to their greed, and lust, and selfishness, they went on plundering their fellows, and driving them to madness and ruin, as if they feared that they would not have objects for their charity.</p> 
               <p>Under the delusion that they could be Christians and idolaters at the same time, they built churches, and even wasted a few hours each week, which might have been profitably devoted to greed, in listening to denunciations against their idols and their conduct, and exhortations to justice and truth. Not only did they patiently hear themselves condemned, but they paid without much murmuring for the favor of being told by faithful men how unholy was their greed, and how damning was their idolatry; and they consented for the time to all that was said in condemnation of their aims and lives.</p> 
                
               <p>Having done this much, with a sacrifice of feeling to duty that could command our admiration had they done it with more heart, and from motives of love rather than for form and custom sake, they then returned to their natural inclinations. They kindled their sacrificial fires, they poured out oblations to their idols Fah Shun and Doll Err, drying up and poisoning the life-blood within them by the heat and fumes of their molten metal. Alike indifferent to the welfare and health of their miserable bodies, and their charred and shrunken souls, they looked only at the glow of their blast-furnaces, and went on with their smelting, and rolling, and coining, and storing, scarcely stopping to bury those who were fallen by the plagues, or to consider how near they were to total extinction.</p> 
               <p>The high-soaring eagle, which could look up to the sun from its lofty eyre, had been at one time borne on the banners and impressed on the coins of the nation, typical of the courage and prowess of its<pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC6132-00000066"/> founders; but after the land had been smitten by the plagues, the pelican was substituted on their coins, surmounted with its characteristic motto,"I die for love of thee," for it had become the greatest ambition of the plague-smitten to have it recorded of them when they died, that they had left vast quantities of this coin behind them. Had it been possible for them to take it with them, it might have been different; but not being able, and having no heirs, to leave it behind was considered by them the next best thing they could do; and, therefore, the most pleasing thing that could be said of their memory was, that they had lived to possess it and died in its pursuit.</p> 
               <p>One by one the lesser towns became deserted and lost from the map of their country, for, blind to the fact that the plagues were destroying them, those of the most healthy districts thought that they could hope for life only by going to larger towns where the plagues were the most prevalent and destructive, so fatally had they become enamored of those evils.</p> 
               <p>The three despised and inferior races, Shy Knees, Knee Gross, and Poor Los, swift to imitate the worst traits of their superiors, were the first to disappear. Then the poorest of the Amrikites, for each year the line between them and the wealthy was drawn more distinctly, and their substance was taken from them.</p> 
               <p>Nothing could convince those who were left that they were not healthy and prosperous, so long as they had the means of supplying the rage of the plagues, for when their women followed the remains of those who had fallen to their graves, they dilated upon the merits of <foreign xml:lang="FRA">Le Bon Ton, La Mode Parisienne, Le Jeu d' Eugnie,</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="FRA">La Crme, de la Crme,</foreign> or extolled the wisdom and comeliness of their hideous and senseless idol Fah Shun. To the very end they seemed wholly unconscious of guilt in bringing such ruin and desolation on their cities.</p> 
               <p>Since they had introduced the last plague<pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC6132-00000067"/> among themselves, they had no sons to lean upon in their old age, or no daughters to comfort them when the fourth plague had taken away their husbands, if, indeed, the men with whom they lived could be called husbands after the plague <foreign xml:lang="FRA">L'Amour et l'Esprit</foreign> had destroyed the marriage rite, and made the relationship a mere temporary convenience. They walked their now almost deserted streets, seeking to attract attention to the ugliness and deformity they had brought upon themselves by still bearing the symbols and insignias of the plagues upon their persons. The poor, foolish, vain-minded, hysterical, barren creatures, what might they have done for the elevation and preservation of their nation had they been contented to lead useful, modest, and motherly lives, to guard their health and their innocence against the machinations of Queen Krinaleen and her emissaries, and of train up their children to be real men and women, with vigorous minds and bodies, and to love truth and honesty, their country and their God, instead of destroying some of them before their birth, and instilling deceit and cupidity in the tender minds of those they saved alive!</p> 
               <p>I fear I have already made my story longer than necessary, considering the short work these plagues made of the people of whom I speak. I do not mean to affirm, of course, that they died in one generation, or that in the lifetime of King Boursouffle and Queen Krinaleen they offered them the opportunity they sought when the plagues were sent out. On the contrary, the descent was so gradual that it was only the oldest people could see the difference between one generation and another. But, though slow, their doom was inevitable. "The mills of the gods grind slowly" is an old heathen proverb, but it was true of these modern idolaters, for Fah Shun and Doll Err ground them to powder in the course of time. Whether they died in the fever and delirium of the plagues, or, conscious of the approaching death of a once great nation,<pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC6132-00000068"/> they made a funeral pyre of their infected books and clothing, and then sang over it, in melancholy notes, the requiem of their former happiness, as the swan is said to sing to itself the sweetest song of all its life as its graceful career is ended, is a matter of conjecture.</p> 
               <p>It was fifty years ago, however, that their total extinction was first discovered, and their once busy and crowded cities were found to be gloomy, silent cities of the dead.</p> 
               <p>History so often nearly reproduces itself, that I have been obliged to draw parallels between the Amrikites and, the ancient Romans, because of the similarity of their beginning and decline. So in the end of my story there is one more event which will remind you of ancient history. You remember that in one corner of the Roman empire the Visigoths had been allowed to take refuge from the savage depredations of the Huns, and that afterwards, when Rome had become degenerated from its former strength and pre-eminence, and the Visigoths had become strong and bold by the protection and forbearance of the empire, they found a pretext for assaulting and destroying the power that had shielded and befriended them.</p> 
               <p>So in the northern part of the country of the Amrikites, a few tribes had taken refuge from the tyranny of the Newtrals and Mezeers, and had united under the common name of Kanucks. Though the Amrikites were a friendly and hospitable people, they never let these qualities interfere with their natural inclination to profit and peculation; for they would nobly entertain a traveler overnight, and sell him a spavined horse next morning. Well, they had nobly given shelter to this rude tribe in their realm, but they tried in many ways to make them pay for their entertainment. Among the various methods they had of doing this was that of levying upon the Kanucks for the fish that swarmed their coasts by lifting their lines and nets, and when they grumbled at that,<pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC6132-00000069"/> squarely denying that they had the right to catch the fish, since they were denizens of the lower waters and only went to their coasts for the purpose of breeding.</p> 
               <p>These questions of rights and privileges had been fished up from oblivion and buried in its depths a thousand times, and had entirely ceased to be resuscitated, when the Amrikites became too weak to have a marine existence. But the wicked never want for a provocation when they are tempted by their cupidity and the weakness of their neighbors. These Kanucks, since the plagues, which held a carnival of death in the Amrikite cities, had cut off all communication between their continent and other nations, had become semi-barbarous, and lived in their cold, unproductive country by hunting and fishing. They had become apprised of the fatal effects of the plagues among their neighbors, by fishing unmolested along their coasts; but still more by the long absence of the terrible eagle, which had, as far back as tradition could reach, periodically screamed in anger and defiance on their borders.</p> 
               <p>So one autumn, when a terrible tornado had swept along their coasts, tearing all their fishing-smacks from their moorings and dashing them to fragments, and game had also become scarce in their woods, they conceived the design of immigrating to the land of the Amrikites, and despoiling them of their stores and cities. To arouse the spirit of their people to such a bold and adventurous movement as they had never before dreamed of, and would not now, if hunger, or the certain prospect of it, had not goaded them to it, they sent out their most eloquent men to all their villages, to expatiate upon the wrongs their fathers had sustained from the fathers of the Amrikites, who lifted their fish from their lines and nets, and upon the necessity of seeking redress for them; even exciting them to superstitious frenzy, by saying that it was the spirits of their fathers which had enraged the sea against them, because they<pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC6132-00000070"/> had allowed them to remain so long unavenged. This brought nearly half of the whole tribe of Kanucks forward, and they assembled at a village called Gan Anock, situated on a river which divided their land from that of the Amrikites, and was called by the Kanucks Catarakee, but known in the books of the Amrikites as the Sand Laurens. Here they organized themselves for their incursion, sending their able-bodied men, who numbered two hundred thousand, forward to attack Yorick, Dell Fee, and Boasting, and following them more leisurely, with reserves and the non-combatants, who numbered nearly a million souls. They sustained themselves on their journey by parched corn and the game killed by hunting-parties, who were detached from the main body every day for that purpose. After a few weeks' advance, during which they realized more and more each day the temerity and peril of their undertaking, they approached the first town of importance on their route to Yorick. Thus far they had seen no signs of life, but they were distrustful of appearances, because of the proverbial cunning of the Amrikites. They halted, therefore, a few leagues from the town, for the ostensible purpose of determining by general council what terms they would dictate to the Amrikites, and in what manner they should conduct the assault.</p> 
               <p>But their real motive was to allow the Amrikites to become aware of their presence, and make overtures of peace to them.</p> 
               <p>As no sign of the Amrikites was visible, however, they sent forward a few men in the guise of emigrants, bending the points of their spears to shepherd's crooks, and driving a few domestic animals before them, for they knew that hospitality to strangers was their greatest virtue. Cautiously approaching the town, they found it depopulated and grass-grown, and were temporarily relieved of their fears. But as there was no spoil there, they hurried on now more confidently to Yorick. Here they sent ten men<pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC6132-00000071"/> in advance of them, with discretionary powers, as they were now so far from their own land that escape to it would be impossible if they were repulsed. So the pioneers came to the city, ready to disclaim all hostile intentions on the part of their tribe if they found the people prepared to resist them, or to exact the most degrading ransom if unprepared for defense. But they were astonished at finding no sign of life as they walked along the streets that once seemed to leap and shout with joy and exuberance of feeling, but would now echo to the sound of their footfalls, had not the grass grown up between the stones.</p> 
               <p>Right and left, wherever they turned, all was dismal, deserted, and desolate; the plagues had swept everything before them, and left no one alive to tell of the bitter end of their doom. All the afflicted people had toiled for was left behind them; the millions of wealth they were always ambitious of leaving were left, for the simple reason that they could not take them with them to the dark unknown world they had been hurried into by the plagues.</p> 
               <p>On every side monuments and gravestones were huddled together, blackened by the atmosphere, but still silent witnesses of the numbers that had lived, and the destructiveness of the plagues. The innocents that had died in infancy of the diseases they had inherited, and the mature who had destroyed themselves, were all together, testifying by the figures on their head-stones how brief had been their career, and how grievously they had sinned against themselves, their country, and their Creator.</p> 
               <p>The ten Kanucks returned to their people and reported that the Amrikites were extinct, and the land was theirs if they chose to possess it. This caused great rejoicing among them, and they encamped about the city, while they appointed men to collect and divide all that would be available for their support and shelter.</p> 
               <p>They could no more lodge in the city than in a cemetery, so solemn and deathlike<pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC6132-00000072"/> like was its appearance. They preferred to remain in the neighboring woods, and there rested themselves after their journey. When their hearts had been strengthened by the spoils and the stores of grain, salt-meat, and brandy the last of the inhabitants had left behind them, they sent part of their forces to Dell Fee and Boasting, to collect whatever could be found in those places also. The result was the same, and all that winter they had the remains of the wealth and stores of the Amrikites to subsist upon. Their markets and warehouses, banks and exchanges, colleges and churches, were all open to a foreign invader; the houses and acres they had robbed each other of were now in the possession of those who merely sought to preserve an existence, and that even the owners had denied to themselves. Spring came again, and, tired of the cities and fields they had risked their lives to obtain, the Kanucks sighed for the excitements of the sea and the chase. The air seemed oppressive and laden with poisonous ous vapors to them; the gloomy and deserted aspect of the dismal warehouses inspired them with superstitious awe and dread; and they feared that if the spirits of their own ancestors could enrage the sea against them, the ancestors of the Amrikites would cause an earthquake or an eruption, to punish them for their temerity in desecrating the sacred altars and happy homes of that once brave and virtuous people. They built themselves enough of sloops to transport all the metals and golden images of Doll Err, and other desirable plunder that remained, to their own country, therefore; and after loading and manning them, the main body took their journey back towards the Catarakee again. On their way they saw such abundance of game in the forests, and especially so many fat and frisky squirrels, they said in a jesting manner among themselves that the Amrikites had all turned into those creatures, as their activity and accumulative propensities reminded them of the traits of the extinct race.</p> 
               <pb n="146-147" xml:id="VAC6132-00000073"/> 
               <p>This soon became a common saying among them, and in after-years, when they related to their children the history of their incursion to the country of the Amrikites, the joke was repeated, and at length became one of their traditions.</p> 
               <p>This, ladies and gentlemen, is the true explanation of the astounding facts with which Gibbon Darwin, Esq., has startled you. A people has been lost by total extinction, as anything else subject to the laws of decay and reproduction would be lost, if it failed to reproduce itself.</p> 
               <p>Had it been possible for this people to degenerate into kangaroos and rabbits and squirrels, I grant they would have done it, for the whole tendency of their lives was that way; and their failure to do it proves how absurd the theory of Gibbon Darwin, Esq., is. The great battle of life and death, in which everything from man to the smallest herb, is engaged, does not depend so much in making a great show of strength or a successful charge on the field, as upon our steadiness and persistence in seizing everything which can make our position more tenable, and serve as a new basis of advancement, and upon our ability to maintain our ground against our antagonists and all the adverse influences which bear constantly against us. In this battle, a lily does not become a mushroom if unable to sustain itself in a soil that is more favorable to mushrooms; if it cannot hold its own and overcome the adversity of the mushrooms and the soil, it must die.</p> 
               <p>So it is with us, we must do or die; and so it was with the Amrikites in the great field on which they had fought and lost the battle for their existence. Though created in the image and likeness of God, and endowed with immortal minds, they were still of the earth, and subject to its laws in common with all other plants.</p> 
               <p>If the clime was such as tended to decay and destroy, after allowing races to develop and flourish to a certain extent, it did not justify them in giving up the battle which<pb n="148-149" xml:id="VAC6132-00000074"/> the weakest herb fights to the bitter end, much less in turning their hands upon themselves and assisting in their own destruction. They had a wide field, and thought they had it all to themselves, because the Aztecs and the Poor Los were gone, and instead of sending out shoots and creepers in every direction, to make their foothold in it more secure, and draw sufficient sap for their sustenance, they thought they could grow and flourish with only one root, or worse still, without a root at all.</p> 
               <p>Under the most favorable circumstances they were exposed to the waste and wear of time, but this waste had been made the more irreparable and fatal by their criminal folly in violating all the laws of health, happiness, and prosperity. They sinned against their race by wasting their youth, strength, and freshness on these debilitating plagues.</p> 
               <p>The Amrikite women, by destroying the symmetry of their forms with Queen Krinaleen's whalebone, and cutting off the supply of blood from their brains, limbs, and lungs, and letting the rude blast of the plagues nip and blight the human blossoms, subjected their race to the same penalty which an orchard pays when its trees are barked all round so that the sap is cut off from the branches.</p> 
               <p>Luxury with them became a necessity which kept the sexes apart, until they grew so unlike that marriage with each other was impossible, and the fondness and respect which they often pretended for each other became the great hypocrisy of their race.</p> 
               <p>When men and women have a common faith and purpose, any good granted to our world may be reasonably expected to result from the co-operation and sympathy; but separated by two forms and objects of worship, that of Fah Shun and that of Doll Err, the country became filled with false ideas of prosperity, and false and deleterious social axioms.</p> 
               <p>Fathers taught their sons to despise the<pb n="150-151" xml:id="VAC6132-00000075"/> superstition of their mothers and sisters, who worshiped and praised their idol as if there was no god but Fah Shun, and Queen Krinaleen was its prophetess; and mothers trained their daughters to look upon their fathers as hardened monsters, who refused to burn Doll Err's incense on the altar of Fah Shun.</p> 
               <p>There being no common ground on which they could meet as fellows and sympathize with each other, all kinds of devices were tried to secure to each sex immunity from the intrusion of the other, for however much the real object of their various social organizations were disguised and denied, it was to give them relief from each other's companionship, and opportunity to scoff at each other's tastes, pursuits, and aspirations.</p> 
               <p>Each sex looked upon itself with complacency, and upon the other as an enemy and an annoyance.</p> 
               <p>Natural feelings and affections had no longer a free channel, because of the obstructions, the teachings, and training of these setters-forth of false religions; and the misguided people not only called the curses of nature down upon them, but also, more terrible still, the wrath and vengeance of nature's God. <q>
                     <lg type="quotation"> 
                        <l>"Cursed be the social wants that sin against the strength of youth!</l> 
                        <l>Cursed be the social lies that warp us from the living truth!</l> 
                        <l>Cursed be the sickly forms that err from honest nature's rule!</l> 
                        <l>Cursed be the gold that gilds the straitened forehead of the fool!"</l> 
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p> 
               <closer>THE END.</closer> 
            </div> 
         </div>
      </body> 
      <back> 
         <div type="advertisement"> 
            <pb n="152-153 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC6132-00000076"/> 
             
            <head>WAS SHE ENGAGED?</head> 
            <head type="sub">BY "JONQUIL."</head> 
            <head type="sub">One Vol. 12mo. 339 Pages.</head> 
            <p>"WAS SHE ENGAGED?" is the title of Jonquil's last story, just in book form. The general method and minuteness of narrative reproduce Trollope in his own field,-that of society delineation; but the style is more piquant than that of Trollope, and, consequently, more readable and fascinating. The <foreign xml:lang="FRA">finesse</foreign> of Miss Rosy, and the clearness with which it is delineated, suggest the hand of a woman; while, again, the several heroes-for the story has several-are too thoroughly men to admit of the supposition that they are drawings from the portfolio of an <foreign xml:lang="FRA">artiste.</foreign>-<title>New York Home Journal.</title>
            </p> 
            <p>This entertaining love-story comes to us fresh from the pen and the press, in clear, readable type that would make a far less enticing work pleasurable. We feel assured that those who are fond of the purely emotional in character or literature will find ample entertainment from its pages. The story is written in the first person, and is a narrative vastly superior to a great mass of socalled novels. There is not a particle of rant from cover to cover. No passion is "torn to tatters." No impossible incidents are introduced, and yet the interest is maintained throughout. The pure, sweet character of Lucy, so well displayed against the more energetic but less poetical Rosamond; the sunlight and shadow<pb n="154 (Advertisement)" xml:id="VAC6132-00000077"/> of these two, enhanced by the dark and designing character of Sarah, combine to produce permanent impressions.-<title>Philadelphia Post.</title>
            </p> 
            <p>The scene of this novel is, of course, laid in the United States, for it is only here that the question which the title asks is ever left in doubt. The laxity of social intercourse here makes the question propounded by our author one of every-day occurrence. The public are not only puzzled to answer it, but very often the friends, relations, and even the parents, are no better informed. In the present volume, the very parties themselves seem to be in doubt on the subject, and it is only after considerable misapprehension as to their own feelings that the couples become sorted in accordance with their true sympathies.</p> 
            <p>A discussion of this momentous subject of engagement, from the point of view of the young people themselves, will enlist many readers and many comments. The title so fully expresses what the reader is to expect that it is unnecessary, and would be unfair, to state the result of the various flirtations. It would be answering the author's conundrum without giving his readers a chance to guess it.-<title>Philadelphia Age.</title>
            </p> 
            <p>A pleasant, bright, and sparkling story.-<title>Baltimore Gazette.</title>
            </p> 
            <p>Every one seems to be going for "Was She Engaged?"-<title>Boston Saturday Evening Gazette.</title>
            </p> 
            <p>FOR SALE BY BOOKSELLERS GENERALLY.</p> 
         </div> 
      </back> 
   </text>
</TEI>