<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
   xml:id="VAC6388">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Watching Spirits </title>
            <author>Ellet, E. F. (1818-1877)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC6388</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-0857</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                  copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction
                  project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                  University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is granted
                  to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                  contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                  educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                  inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University
                  Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
               Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Watching spirits</title>
                  <author>Ellet, E. F. (1818-1877)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>vi 182 p. [6] leaves of plates </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Scribner</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1851">1851</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
               Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
               website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and has
               been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
               Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2005-07-28">Finished OCR, rough
            encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2005-11-27">Finished TEI
            conversion</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-07-17">Converted document from SGML to TEI
            P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-07-17">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents
            and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n="Illustration" xml:id="VAC6388-00000001"/>
         <div type="frontis">
            
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6388-00000002"/>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>WATCHING SPIRITS.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>BY <docAuthor>MRS. ELLET,</docAuthor> AUTHOR OF "THE WOMEN OF THE AMERICAN
               REVOLUTION."</byline>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>NEW YORK:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>CHARLES SCRIBNER, 145 NASSAU STREET.</publisher>
            </docImprint>
            <docDate when="1851">1851.</docDate>
         </titlePage>
         <pb n="i" xml:id="VAC6388-00000003"/>
         <div type="fly_title">
            <bibl>
               <edition>Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1851, by CHARLES SCRIBNER,
                  In the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United States, for the Southern
                  District of New York.</edition>
               <publisher>C. W. BENEDICT, Stereotyper and Printer, 201 William Street.</publisher>
            </bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <p>TO<lb/> MISS CHAPIN,<lb/> (OF CANANDAIGUA, NEW YORK,)<lb/> As a Memorial of Esteem
               and Affection,<lb/> THIS VOLUME<lb/> IS INSCRIBED.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="ii-iii (List of Illustrations) " xml:id="VAC6388-00000004"/>
         <div type="illustrations">
            
            <head>ILLUSTRATIONS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>ABRAHAM AND THE THREE ANGELS, PAINTED BY AMICONI, ENGRAVED BY BUTLER.
                  Frontispiece </item>
               <item>HAGAR AND ISHMAEL, PAINTED BY OVERBECK, ENGRAVED BY BUTLER. <ref>21</ref>
               </item>
               <item>ABRAHAM AND THE THREE ANGELS, ILMAN &amp; SONS. <ref>46</ref>
               </item>
               <item>THE ANNUNCIATION, ILMAN &amp; SONS. <ref>89</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHRIST PRAYING IN THE GARDEN, PAINTED BY CORREGGIO, ENGRAVED BY HUMPHEYS.
                     <ref>118</ref>
               </item>
               <item>TOUCH ME NOT, PAINTED BY CORTONA, ENGRAVED BY HEMPHRYS. <ref>139</ref>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <pb n="iv-v (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC6388-00000005"/>
         <div type="contents">
            
            <head>CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>I. WATCHING SPIRITS, <ref target="VAC6388-00000007" rend="right">9</ref>
               </item>
               <item>II. THE MINISTRY OF ANGELS, <ref target="VAC6388-00000014" rend="right"
                     >21</ref>
               </item>
               <item>III. THE LESSONING OF ANGELS, <ref target="VAC6388-00000045" rend="right"
                     >78</ref>
               </item>
               <item>IV. ELECT ANGELS; OR ANGELIC RELATION TO THE WORK OF CHRIST, <ref
                     target="VAC6388-00000064" rend="right">113</ref>
               </item>
               <pb n="vi (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC6388-00000006"/>
               <item>V. DEPARTED SPIRITS, <ref target="VAC6388-00000078" rend="right">138</ref>
               </item>
               <item>VI. APOSTATE SPIRITS, <ref target="VAC6388-00000088" rend="right">154</ref>
               </item>
               <item>VII. CONCLUSION, <ref target="VAC6388-00000099" rend="right">176</ref>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Watching spirits</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>I. WATCHING SPIRITS.</head>
               <p>NO intelligent person questions the fact, evident indeed to our sight, that the
                  earth on which we live forms a very small portion of the creation of God. We
                  behold myriads of worlds sown thickly through space, and science discovers still
                  more of the immensity of the material system; while the volume of inspiration
                  teaches us, when we consider the heavens, to remember the insignificance of man.
                  But beyond the mere existence of those starry worlds shining in the spacious
                  firmament, and those systems whose laws are the study of science, it gives us
                  knowledge of nothing concerning them. We occupy a point in the universe isolated
                  from communication<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6388-00000007"/> nication with the
                  rest. The measureless distances that separate our planet from others, and the laws
                  of our being, place us in a state of as complete seclusion as if no other orders
                  of intelligent creatures existed. Yet we believe, and with reason, that the orbs
                  within our view are peopled with beings capable of love and obedience to the
                  Supreme Creator. While every part of this globe teems with life, it cannot be
                  supposed that the beauty and glory lavished on other works of the same Almighty
                  hand are unseen by creatures able to find their happiness in the contemplation.
                  The universal belief, too, in the existence of intelligent beings of a nature
                  different and superior to our own, is of itself a sufficient argument, since the
                  unaided intellect of man would never have reached such a conception It was
                  originally revealed to him with the idea of Deity, and though marred and defaced
                  by his sensual perceptions, could not be lost. Thus, in every age his fancy has
                  peopled the distant regions of space, as well as this earth, with creatures of
                  various intellectual ual capacities and moral natures, for the most part wearing a
                  form of etherealized matter. The gods of heathen mythology, the various races
                  created by popular superstition, <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"That had their haunts in dale or piny mountain,</l>
                        <l>Or forest by slow stream, or pebbly brook—"</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q> owe their origin to the cloudy and obscure knowledge derived from this
                  original revelation.</p>
               <p>There is a fitness apparent to reason in the circumstances of our earthly abode;
                  and not the least in its state of separation from the rest of the universe. The
                  moral system in which we are placed, as a fallen race destined to restoration
                  through faith, requires an isolation from other worlds peopled with sinless
                  creatures, and a limitation of vision, so that "the things eternal" may not be
                  evident to mortal sense. Man is thus shut up, in his narrow area of experience, to
                  a simple dependence on the testimony of God, having no further knowledge of the
                  divine government than is necessary for his submission and advantage<pb n="12-13"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000008"/> vantage. Faith is to him the only "evidence of
                  things unseen." Yet enough is revealed to teach him that he sustains mysterious
                  relations to other orders of creatures; that in the distant places of creation,
                  interest and sympathy are felt for him, and that a golden chain of union binds all
                  in harmony to the throne of Deity. It is therefore not irreverent or unprofitable
                  to consider the intimations given on this subject in the Book of Truth, to
                  meditate on our interests and duties in connection with it, and to ponder on the
                  disclosures thus vouchsafed of the grace and condescension of Him who created the
                  heavens and the earth, and makes it the happiness of all to obey his commandments.
                  The theme opens a noble field for reflection; one which the contents of volumes
                  would scarcely exhaust. It has been treated by other writers, able and
                  commissioned to dispense instruction. Gaston, in his "Concordance," has collected
                  a series of texts illustrative of the character of holy and fallen angels; Dwight
                  and Bishop Heber have each written a series of sermons on the subject; Chalmers'
                  Astronomical Discourses enter upon it, and the interesting work of "Charlotte
                  Elizabeth"—"Principalities and Powers"—is an elaborate treatise upon the nature,
                  attributes and character of the angelic creation. Briefly traversing the same
                  ground, the following essay may present, moreover, a few suggestive thoughts on
                  some important points which have been overlooked, or too hastily glanced at by
                  others.</p>
               <p>The account of the formation of man in Genesis, gives us reason to suppose that he
                  was made capable of communication with spiritual natures. "The Lord breathed into
                  his nostrils the breath of life;" he received direct from the Source of all
                  existence that principle which constituted him a living soul; which brought him
                  into brotherhood with angels and arch-angels, and into a filial relationship to
                  the Father of spirits. He was habitually conscious of the presence of Deity, and
                  enjoyed the exalted privilege of daily communion with his Maker. His soul, free<pb
                     n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6388-00000009"/> from every taint of sin, and wearing the
                  unobscured image of God, lived upon this ineffable communion. Whatever was its
                  nature, whether it took place directly or indirectly through a medium,—one thing
                  is certain,—it was perfect and unrestrained. It was the loving appeal of children
                  to a kind Parent, answered by larger expressions of bounteous love. The words
                  "they heard the voice of the Lord God walking in the garden in the cool of the
                  day"—open a wonderful extent of vision in regard to the primeval state of man,
                  thus privileged and exalted,—and of the condition of earth, thus highly honored as
                  the favorite resort of Him who had called its beauty into existence.</p>
               <p>It is apparent from the sacred record that these visits were some more evident
                  manifestation of the Deity than we may conceive of as communicated to the soul by
                  the most vivid perception of God's Omnipresence, and that it was not like the
                  indwelling of his Spirit with the Christian. The knowledge of his pervading
                  presence must have been continual tinual, whereas this manifestation was
                  occasional, though it may have been frequent. In man's state of innocence it was
                  doubtless the source of his highest happiness. It must have been something
                  external, and discernible by the senses; for when conscious of sin, Adam strove to
                  hide himself from it, and made excuse by pleading his nakedness. It does not
                  become us to indulge in conjectures on a matter concerning which it has not
                  pleased the Divine Spirit to give us information; but the fact of such a
                  manifestation, and the habitual familiar intercourse—as friend with friend—held
                  between God and man, shows the elevated position assigned him in the intelligent
                  creation, and strongly supports the conjecture that he was originally permitted to
                  communicate freely with other holy beings. The garden in which the Lord God walked
                  may well have been visited by the brightest of heaven's hierarchy, and the sons of
                  God who shouted for joy in the morning of creation, may be readily imagined to
                  have been allowed to rejoice in the loveliness of<pb n="16-17"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000010"/> earth, to delight the sinless pair with their
                  loving companionship, and encourage man to persevere in obedience through the
                  probation appointed him.</p>
               <p>The circumstances of the temptation, too, lead to the inference that to our first
                  parents a free and unreserved intercourse was allowed with beings of a higher
                  order. Man being pure and sinless in thought, it was necessary that the tempter
                  should assail him from without; for there was no ground within on which to build
                  the frame-work. Probably accustomed to spiritual communications addressed to their
                  senses, it caused little or no surprise to hear insidious words from the mouth of
                  the serpent. Andreini, in his "Adam"—the mystery which suggested to Milton the
                  idea of his great poem, makes the serpent explain the miracle of his possession of
                  speech by saying he had acquired the power in tasting the forbidden fruit; but
                  without indulging in poetic fancies, we may suppose it likely that Eve perceived
                  at once she was addressed by a spirit, speaking in the form of the animal. This
                  appears evident from her defence afterwards: "The serpent beguiled me:" not—I saw
                  the miraculous effect of the fruit on the serpent. She felt, when the mischief was
                  done, that she had been deceived by a malign power superior in intellect to
                  herself.</p>
               <p>With the fall of man his free and friendly intercourse with sinless beings no
                  doubt ceased. It was no longer a pleasure to them to visit earth, accursed on
                  account of sin; the thoughts and feelings of human beings were no longer in
                  harmony with theirs. Those swift-winged messengers of God, who in their capacity
                  to study and comprehend the works of creation and Providence, were accustomed to
                  pass to and fro through the vast and populous regions of space, visiting worlds
                  and comparing systems—turned away in sadness from the new creation, so lately the
                  scene of exultant joy and praise. Their natures shrank from contact with beings
                  tainted with moral evil, in whom the poison of sin was working unto death.
                  Thenceforward to all<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6388-00000011"/> eternity their
                  relations to man would have been only those of hostility, had not a new and
                  wondrous development of the purposes and attributes of God, a new evolution in the
                  history of creation, arrested their attention and fixed it with absorbing interest
                  upon the world they had deemed abandoned to evil. They were employed by the
                  Supreme in the execution of his sentence. When Adam and Eve were driven from the
                  garden, "cherubim and a flaming sword" were placed to keep the way of the tree of
                  life. They were sent also with messages of mercy from the throne of Divine
                  government to the province where the standard of rebellion had been erected.</p>
               <p>While those pure creatures, though ready in obedience to God's command to visit
                  earth, no longer sought companionship with man, and he was cut off from that
                  familiar intercourse with them which had been his privilege, it cannot be
                  questioned that man remained, and does still remain capable of receiving
                  communications from spiritual beings ings. Let not this be denied because none can
                  tell how it is accomplished. There is no more difficulty in supposing that they
                  communicate thoughts to men than that men do to each other. There are many means
                  by which this is done besides words:—as by pictures or letters; or by tones and
                  gestures, or significant silence, sometimes more expressive than language itself.
                  Each of these modes, so common among us, would be utterly inconceivable to any who
                  had never witnessed or practised them. How often does the play of feature, or the
                  habitual expression of the human countenance, disclose the character! and how
                  incapable would one who had never enjoyed the sense of sight, be of understanding
                  this method of discerning the thoughts and intents of the heart! It is therefore
                  irrational to doubt that another order of spirits may communicate thoughts to each
                  other, may understand ours, and impart suggestions, notwithstanding that these
                  must be done without the aid of the sense.</p>
               <pb n="20" xml:id="VAC6388-00000012"/>
               <p>We know that the Spirit of God communes with us, yet are we in no way conscious of
                  his agency: we cannot tell whence He cometh, nor whither He goeth. It is only by
                  "the fruits of the Spirit"—faith, love and joy, that we may mark the commencement
                  and progress of his blessed work.</p>
               <p>Those who believe that man may look forward after death to a higher sphere of
                  existence, admit the fact that there are other beings in the state to which he
                  aspires. Reason concludes also that a part of their happiness may consist in works
                  of love and mercy to us their inferiors, expressive of their gratitude to our
                  common Benefactor. Before pursuing this train of thought, let us briefly glance at
                  the view afforded us in Scripture of their nature and character.</p>
               <pb n="Illustration" xml:id="VAC6388-00000013"/>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="21" xml:id="VAC6388-00000014"/>
               <head>II. THE MINISTRY OF ANGELS.</head>
               <p>THE scriptures teach us that God employs as special agents or messengers, an order
                  of beings invested with eminent dignity and endowed with vast capacities. They
                  existed before the foundation of the earth, and rejoiced when the new system was
                  called into being, as at another manifestation of the power and goodness of the
                  Creator. They are called in the Bible by various names; each illustrative of the
                  qualities and privileges by which they are distinguished, or indicative of their
                  peculiar office. The title "sons of God" expresses a near and endeared relation to
                  the Deity; that of "morning stars,"—their majesty and splendor; that of<pb
                     n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6388-00000015"/> "cherubim and seraphim,"—the knowledge
                  and holiness that belong to them. In like manner, they are called "angels," to
                  indicate their habitual employment—performing the mission of the Most High; and
                  "princes, thrones, and dominions" in reference to the power and rule vested in
                  them. They are likened to fire for their purity, swiftness and strength. Their
                  numbers are countless. David saw twenty thousand chariots encamped around Mount
                  Zion; the Bible speaks of twelve legions who would have rushed, at Messiah's
                  command, upon his enemies; of a mighty array assembled at the hill of Dotham; of
                  thousands of thousands and ten thousand times ten thousand whom Daniel saw
                  standing before the Ancient of Days; and how vast the multitude which in
                  Apocalyptic vision St. John beheld standing on the sea of glass, and around the
                  throne of God and the Lamb! The noblest created attributes are theirs; they are
                  the most elevated and illustrious of all intelligent creatures, and to them are
                  entrusted the first offices in the Divine administration. Having every thought and
                  desire subordinate to God's will, inspired with an ardent zeal for His glory,
                  their delight is to perform His pleasure, and they find their chief joy in
                  fulfilling His commandments and hearkening to the voice of his word. They have
                  near access to their Maker; contemplate his character, and learn his attributes,
                  while their noblest end and aim are to glorify Him and their continual and
                  delightful occupation to praise his holy name for the wondrous works which He has
                  done.</p>
               <p>The power with which these bright and holy beings are endowed is great beyond our
                  conception. "They excel in strength." By this expression of the Psalmist we are
                  taught to believe them the mightiest of living creatures. This is proved by the
                  works assigned to them in the Bible. They stand in God's presence to execute his
                  commands; they concentrate in their minds the experience and wisdom of many
                  thousand years, send comprehensive glances through all the<pb n="24-25"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000016"/> kingdoms of nature, and understand as far as their
                  capacity enables them the ways of Providence. Their footsteps are planted in the
                  deep, and in the clouds they fulfil his word. Irresistible and terrible are they
                  in executing the judgments of Omnipotence upon rebellious man. A hostile army
                  laying siege to Jerusalem, is destroyed by the stroke of a single angelic
                  messenger, commissioned to fulfil the dread mandate. "Then the angel of the Lord
                  went forth, and smote in the camp of the Assyrians an hundred and four score and
                  five thousand: and when they arose early in the morning, behold, they were all
                  dead corpses. "By an angel the Lord smote the first born at midnight throughout
                  Egypt, when he passed through the midst to desolate the land, and suffered not the
                  destroyer to enter into the houses marked with the blood upon the lintel. So too
                  when David had sinned in numbering Israel and Judah, and the wrath of the Lord was
                  kindled—and the king, permitted to choose one of three things for his punishment,
                  had chosen "to fall into the hand of the Lord," an angel, commanded to inflict the
                  stroke of pestilence—"stretched out his hand upon Jerusalem to destroy it." "The
                  Lord repented him of the evil, and said to the angel that destroyed the people,
                  'It is enough; stay now thine hand.'" Then followed the sublime vision of the
                  avenger: "And David lifted up his eyes, and saw the angel of the Lord stand
                  between the earth and the heaven, having a drawn sword in his hand stretched out
                  over Jerusalem. Then David and the elders of Israel who were clothed in sackcloth
                  fell upon their faces." The appeal of David for mercy was answered by the angel
                  with a command that he should set up an altar, and call upon the Lord; and when he
                  had offered burnt offerings and peace offerings, and the answer had been given
                  from heaven by fire upon the altar, "the Lord commanded the angel, and he put up
                  his sword again into the sheath thereof."</p>
               <p>In the splendid picture here presented to the imagination—we know not which
                     most<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6388-00000017"/> to marvel at—the majesty of the
                  commissioned avenger seen in the act of smiting the city—or the mercy of Him who
                  "repented him of the evil," stayed the destroyer's hand, and directed the means by
                  which the wrath should be turned away. As an illustration of the power given to
                  the messengers of God, it is striking and impressive.</p>
               <p>Many other instances of angelic power are recorded in the Scriptures. When these
                  glorious creatures appear to rebuke or chastise sin, their aspect is terrible to
                  transgressors. For fear of the angel who rolled away the stone from the Redeemer's
                  sepulchre, "the keepers did shake, and became as dead men;" for "his countenance
                  was like lightning." The power of an angel closed the mouths of the hungry lions,
                  when Daniel was cast into the den. They are warriors, who were engaged in actual
                  conflict with the powers of darkness, when there was war in heaven, and Michael
                  and his angels fought against the dragon. Even Daniel, "the man greatly beloved,"
                  when he saw the vision of the angel, "his eyes as the appearance of lightning, and
                  his face as lamps of fire,"—while a great quaking fell upon the men who were with
                  him, so that they fled to hide themselves—was overpowered at the sight, and there
                  remained no strength in him. Manoah and his wife, when the angel that appeared
                  unto them ascended in the flame of the altar, fell on their faces to the ground:
                  and even the apostle to whom was revealed the vision of things to be, fell down to
                  worship before the feet of the angel whose office it was to show them. How grand
                  the idea given in his Revelation of the power and majesty of the angels sent forth
                  to execute the Divine will! The "strong angel proclaiming with a loud voice;"—the
                  "four angels standing on the four corners of the earth, holding the four
                  winds;"—the "angel ascending from the east, having the seal of the living God;"
                  the seven angels who sounded the seven trumpets; the "mighty angel come down from
                  heaven, clothed with a cloud, and a rainbow upon his head, and his face as it<pb
                     n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6388-00000018"/> were the sun, and his feet as pillars of
                  fire;" the angel he saw "come down from heaven having great power, and the earth
                  was lightened with his glory;" and he who came down "having the key of the
                  bottomless pit, and a great chain in his hand;" all visions emblematic of the
                  stupendous events brought about in the history of the Church—are well suited to
                  impress us with a lofty conception of the attributes of those chosen agents of the
                  Divine will. How sublime also the language of the Psalmist—"The chariots of God
                  are twenty thousand, even thousands of angels," and how exalted must be the nature
                  of those creatures whom the Almighty makes the instruments of his power and his
                  movements in his created universe!</p>
               <p>These potent warriors of heaven, whose lightning looks and flaming swords render
                  their aspect so powerful, are yet pre-eminent in beauty. All the perfect works of
                  the Creator are lovely, but the countenance of one of his holy angels must excel
                  all created ated objects, because the highest perfection of moral and intellectual
                  beauty is there combined; the attributes of majesty and grandeur are united with
                  the most attractive meekness, purity and grace. No thought of evil, no unruly
                  passion, has ever marred the serenity of an angel's face; immortal youth is his,
                  with all its gentle and winning qualities, as well as its undecaying vigor; and
                  basking in the unclouded effulgence of the Divine countenance, he reflects the
                  image of its benignant glory. Believing that the angels possess material bodies,
                  though spiritual and glorified, such as our grosser senses could not
                  apprehend,—and that the Creator who has lavished so much of loveliness on the
                  things of this earth, has put honor on them as the noblest of all his works, it is
                  impossible to conceive of any more captivating display of the perfect beauty which
                  is the fitting emblem and expression of their holiness; which should clothe the
                  favored beings who are nearest to God, and wear his likeness.</p>
               <pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6388-00000019"/>
               <p>In intellectual faculties and knowledge, the angels likewise are exalted above
                  other ranks of creatures. They drink from the Fountain of all light; they behold
                  continually the face of their Father, and offer unto him the praises echoed from
                  the uttermost limits of creation. Their mission to distant parts of the
                  universe—the ministry in which they are as a "flaming fire"—and the charge
                  entrusted to them—pre-suppose an extent of capacity and knowledge far beyond human
                  conception. Their wisdom is occasionally referred to in the Bible,—as where the
                  suppliant of Tekoah compares the wisdom of King David to that of an angel of God.
                  The very phrase—"his angels he charges with folly"—intended by a figure to express
                  the incomparable wisdom of Omniscience—shows that none more elevated in this
                  respect among finite beings could have been referred to; in the same manner as
                  Infinite purity is set forth by the poetical saying—"The heavens are not clean in
                  his sight."</p>
               <p>In holiness, too, these gifted and wondrous creatures excel. They burn with zeal
                  for the honor of God, and with love to his name. Spotless in purity, they abhor
                  all evil, and delight only in performing the Divine will; their whole nature and
                  character—their every action—bears the inscription—Holiness to the Lord. In his
                  service they engage in conflict with the infernal hosts and execute vengeance
                  against the enemies of his name; for his pleasure they encamp around them that
                  fear Him, bear them up in their hands, and are continually employed in the watch
                  and care of his saints. The fidelity and tenderness of their care, their loving
                  patience with wayward men, and the indignation they manifest against those evil
                  spirits who oppose themselves against God, attest their righteousness and their
                  holy detestation of whatever militates against the Divine purpose. With this
                  holiness, severe as its expression becomes when the Master they love is rebelled
                  against and insulted, mark their gentleness and meekness! They dare not bring
                  railing accusations even<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6388-00000020"/> against the
                  enemies of all virtue. They are far from pride in the splendor which invests them;
                  in all their ways they acknowledge entire dependence on their Maker; nor do they
                  act save in willing obedience to his commandments. Mark their humility of
                  bearing—their alacrity in serving beings inferior to them in nature and faculties,
                  and so debased by sin that the sight of them must be repulsive, were it possible
                  for these holy ones to feel repugnance towards any services to which they are
                  appointed. Mark, too, their compassion for human sorrow and their gracious
                  sympathy with man, for whose sake they are armed against the powers of darkness.
                  If philanthropy may be so pure and noble among men who have had the heavenly
                  principle implanted by faith in their hearts, how tender and fervent must it be in
                  the breasts of those who have no darkness nor corruption to check its
                  heaven-aspiring flame! The benevolence of an angel, it has been truly observed,
                  "may shoot over the mighty expanse of planets and systems, yet lavish tenderness
                  on each individual of their teeming population."</p>
               <p>As we gather ideas of the character and attributes of angels from the copious
                  notices of them in Scripture, what exalted views do we obtain of the future state
                  of believers, who, our Saviour has expressly declared, shall be "equal to the
                  angels." These morning stars, these principalities and powers in heavenly places,
                  are to be the companions throughout eternity, of those who have come out of great
                  tribulation; who have "washed their robes and made them white in the blood of the
                  Lamb." Man, originally, was made lower than the angels; he forfeited the promise
                  of life by the first covenant, but by the second Adam, those who attain to the
                  resurrection of life are permitted to enter heaven on terms of honor with the
                  highest there. A new song is put into the mouth of the redeemed, which is sweeter
                  than even the sound of the harps of seraphim and cherubim. The only rivalry which
                  can exist among the blest inhabitants<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6388-00000021"/> of
                  heaven, will be in rendering praise to God and the Lamb; and herein those to whom
                  much has been forgiven may well expect to lift the most exalted strains.</p>
               <p>The barrier to intercourse between man and angels must have remained forever
                  impassable, had he been left, as were superior beings who kept not their first
                  estate—in a state of revolt, and under the curse of the violated law. But a ransom
                  was provided: the Son of God became the propitiation for our sins; overtures of
                  reconciliation were made to the fallen race; and to those who by the precious
                  blood of our Lord and Savviour Jesus Christ, became "heirs of salvation"—the
                  angels of heaven were made "ministering spirits." "Sent forth to minister" to the
                  children of the new covenant, their work is done with sympathy, alacrity, and
                  love. They mark with attentive eye the concerns of earth, and rejoice in the grace
                  of God, which permits them to bear a part in the contest which is continually
                  going on with the Prince of this world, and the pow ers of evil. They joy in the
                  privilege of communicating blessings to the chosen of God who are yet in exile, of
                  whispering comfort to them in sorrow, of supporting them in temptation, and
                  finally, of bearing them away, when released by death, to their own abode of
                  perfect felicity.</p>
               <p>The testimonies of Scripture to the ministry of angels are numerous and explicit.
                  The happy beings described as partaking of the enjoyments of heaven are also
                  represented as battling with the dragon and his angels; bearing messages to
                  prophets, keeping guard over the servants of the Most High; as anxious witnesses
                  of the progress of Messiah's kingdom; as mingling in the converse of mortals, and
                  watching the believer in his pilgrimage. The question has been raised, by specious
                  reasoners who, acknowledging the general supervision and care of God, are
                  unwilling to believe in any special divine interposition in the case of particular
                  occurrences,—whether such expressions are not capable of a figurative<pb n="36-37"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000022"/> tive meaning; whether "by the angels who are said,
                  in Scripture, to encamp around the righteous, any thing more is intended than to
                  express in lively colors and imagery familiar to eastern eloquence the watchful
                  care and ready help of Providence; or at most those powers of the material world
                  which are wielded by the immediate and invisible sway of Him who "maketh the winds
                  his messengers"—and to whose call the lightnings answer. The famine, the
                  pestilence and the sword, are apostrophised and personified as his servants in the
                  same glowing flights of oratory; and his glory is said to be proclaimed, and his
                  praises sung, by 'the deep,' 'the mountains,' 'the cornfields,' and the 'morning
                  stars.' We know what is meant when Minerva reminds Achilles of that which his own
                  reason might well have suggested to him; and the prudence of Jacob, and the
                  blessing which the Almighty bestowed on his labors, might with equal propriety be
                  described as 'the angel' which led him by the way, and delivered him in all his
                  troubles. There are instances in the Apocalyptic visions where the mortal
                  protectors of the church, or the mortal invaders of the Roman empire are supposed
                  to be allegorically described as angels engaged in the execution of God's
                  judgments. The plagues and diseases which befel the Egyptians are spoken of by the
                  Psalmist as "evil angels among them;" and a very little extension of the same
                  principle may lead us to suppose that no more was meant by the words of Elisha (2d
                  Kings VI. 16.) than to express his confidence in that Divine protection which, in
                  fact, did not preserve him by the shields and spears of any celestial guards, but
                  by blinding the eyes and confusing the understanding of the Syrians sent to
                  surprise him."<ref rend="super" target="#note_001" xml:id="return_001">*</ref>
                  
               </p><note place="foot" xml:id="note_001">
                  
                  <p><ref target="#return_001">*</ref>Sermon by Bishop Heber.</p>
               </note>
               <p>"Why, indeed," it has been further asked, "should such intermediate agents be
                  employed by a God who is Omnipresent and Almighty? It is only the imperfection and
                  weakness of earthly monarchs which are disguised<pb n="38-39"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000023"/> guised by the flimsy veil of solemn and ceremonious
                  attendance, and which compel them to receive their information or accomplish their
                  designs through the eyes and hands of others. But how different is the case with
                  Him who beholds, embraces, pervades and sustains the universe; and how superfluous
                  does it seem, to crowd the court of heaven with these unmeaning pageants, whose
                  praises and homage can confer no honor on Him from whom all things are derived;
                  whose swiftness is idle with Him from whom nothing can escape, and whose fiery
                  chariots are but an empty show in His presence who needs but withhold his breath
                  to reduce his enemies to their original nothing! It is more reasonable, then,"
                  they tell us, "and more reverential towards the Almighty, to give an allegorical
                  interpretation to passages which are susceptible of it, rather than ascribe to Him
                  in reality, those appendages of a mortal king which, however they were adapted to
                  the prejudices of a wild and ignorant race, are inconsistent with the more
                  enlarged ideas Christians should entertain of his nature."</p>
               <p>These bold reasoners treat with as little ceremony the visions of angels, so
                  frequently recorded in the Sacred Volume. "They were condescensions," they tell
                  us, "to the prejudices and weaknesses of mankind; a part of those paraphernalia of
                  an earthly potentate, which it pleased God to assume in his intercourse with the
                  Jewish people, and no more to be received as real existences than the sapphire
                  pavement and crystal canopy of his throne, and the wheels full of eyes on which
                  Ezekiel beheld Him drawn by cherubim. In all these appearances there are many
                  things," they proceed, "which even the warmest advocates of the literal
                  interpretation must admit to be illusions only. Even if angels exist, there are
                  few who suppose that spirits are attired in such white and flowing robes as they
                  have presented to the eyes of mortals; that they are furnished, according to the
                  occupations in which they are engaged, with harps, or inkhorns, or
                     slaughter-weapons<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC6388-00000024"/> weapons; or that
                  they keep guard, in the array of ancient warriors, with chariots and horses of
                  material fire at the door of God's distinguished servants. But if these
                  circumstances are illusive, how much remains which is to be accounted real? Or
                  where is the difficulty in supposing that (as God avowedly condescends to the
                  imperfection of his creatures) the forms themselves, to which this attire belongs,
                  may be no more than splendid phantoms, employed by God to impress on the mind of
                  the beholder a sense of his power, his presence, or his protection; but phantoms
                  still, not real or intelligent personages, and without habitation or existence
                  except in the imagination of those whom God has been thus pleased to visit or
                  enlighten?"</p>
               <p>In this way, it has been suggested, the ancient Sadducees must have made their
                  denial of angels accord with the authority of the books of Moses. The same
                  opinions have been advanced by Dr. Priestley.</p>
               <p>The learned and reverend author quoted, says, in reply to such objections: "It is,
                  in the first place, allowed on all sides, that the allusions to angels as
                  existing, and the express or implicit assertions of their existence and agency,
                  are in the Sacred Volume extremely numerous and forcible. There are, indeed, not
                  much less than a hundred passages in the Old and New Testaments where angels are
                  spoken of as real and active creatures, and servants of the Most High, or where
                  they are actually described as having appeared to mortals, not in dreams or
                  prophetic visions, but openly, and to the waking eyes of many persons
                  together.</p>
               <p>"Now, of the texts which assert or imply their existence, there are many which
                  cannot, without the greatest violence to the propriety of language, be regarded as
                  rhetorical figures. When Daniel expressed his conviction that "God had sent his
                  angel to stop the lions' mouths"—is it likely that he would have said this to a
                  heathen sovereign, had he not believed in the reality of such a mission? When the
                  Psalmist speaks of man as<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6388-00000025"/> "made a little
                  lower than the angels," could he mean that a real existence is at all inferior to
                  a phantom? or a rational being to the accidents of the material world, however
                  figuratively described, or however providentially directed? Is it of a band of
                  shadows, a troop of rhetorical ornaments, that Christ is said to be made the head?
                  Or can "accidents" desire to look into the mysteries of the Gospel? Are they
                  nonentities to which, in the world to come, the righteous are to be made equal? Or
                  would Christ and his apostles, in describing the most solemn event in which the
                  human race can be interested, have so luxuriated in superfluous imagery as to
                  enumerate the angels among the agents concerned in the day of judgment, if the
                  belief in angels be an error? Let us pause before we thus degrade the Holy
                  Scriptures into one interminable allegory, or at least, place the controversy on a
                  proper footing, and if the doctrine in question be absurd or impossible, let us
                  abandon, as an imposture ture the religion which so authoritatively declares
                  it."</p>
               <p>A further argument is that we know, as far as we can trace the opinions of the
                  ancient Jews, the word angel or spirit must have had for them the same meaning as
                  now; and the evil growing out of such a mistake,—supposing the opinion to be
                  erroneous—was a most perilous one. Amidst the warnings against idolatry contained
                  in the Old Testament, would not the people have been guarded against the danger of
                  being led to worship "the host of heaven," by an assurance that no such host
                  existed, had such been the fact? "Was it not as easy for Elisha to express his
                  trust in the general providence and protection of God, as to employ expressions
                  obviously calculated to promote a popular error, and then to pray for a miracle by
                  which that error might be confirmed?"</p>
               <p>Nor is it repugnant to reason to believe that a Being infinitely wise and powerful
                  should employ the beings he has created,<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6388-00000026"/>
                  and require from them the fulfilment of his commands. We may see both good and
                  evil men made instruments in the daily dispensations of his Providence, which,
                  assuredly, He has power to carry on without their interference.</p>
               <p>Another question is proposed to such as suppose angelic apparitions to have been
                  illusions sent by God, and intended as proofs of his presence and protection. Is
                  not this very illusion—the writer asks—"God himself assuming a particular form,
                  declaring, in the likeness of a cloud, a fire, a man in long linen garments, or a
                  being with six wings and four faces, his power and his gracious pleasure? But
                  whence comes it then, that the persons thus described have spoken of themselves as
                  'sent' by God, as acting under his authority, as his servants, yea, and the
                  fellow-servants of them 'that have the testimony of Jesus?' 'See thou do it
                  not'—were the words of the angel when St. John bowed down before him: 'I am thy
                  fellow-servant: worship God.'"</p>
               <p>The particular instances of angelic ministration recorded in Scripture deserve
                  earnest consideration, being suggestive of solemn warning and instruction, and
                  teaching us how strict is their watch over individuals of our race.—Hagar, fleeing
                  from the face of her mistress, was found by an angel in the wilderness, and
                  directed to return, while a gracious promise was given that her seed should be
                  multiplied exceedingly, so that it should not be numbered for multitude. His
                  message was delivered in the name of the Lord, whose interposition the fugitive
                  acknowledged, expressing her consciousness of his presence and Omniscience in the
                  name given to Him who spoke to her.</p>
               <p>A remarkable picture is presented to our view in the visit of angels to Abraham.
                  The patriarch, sitting in his tent door in the heat of the day, received the three
                  approaching strangers with oriental respect and hospitality. He did not at first
                  sight, probably, perceive the real character of the mysterious visitors, but the
                  promise of a son revealed<pb n="46" xml:id="VAC6388-00000027"/> the heavenly
                  message and presence. Again, two angels, doubtless the same that had appeared to
                  Abraham, came to Sodom, to save the family of Lot from the destruction that was
                  about to descend on the cities of the plain. Well might he say to God, when led
                  forth by those celestial visitants—"Thou hast magnified thy mercy, which Thou hast
                  showed unto me in saving my life." How striking is this instance of angelic
                  interposition—in exhibiting the mercy of God, the obedience of his messengers and
                  their tender guardianship of the mortals they were commanded to succor! With
                  deliberate care, with earnest warning, they provide for, and hasten his departure,
                  laying hold upon his hand while he lingers, leading him and his family from the
                  city, and urging on him the necessity of instant flight. When Lot pleaded for the
                  small city in which he desired to take refuge, with what gracious condescension
                  was his petition granted! How mercifully was the storm of vengeance held<pb
                     n=" (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6388-00000028"/>
                  <figure/>
                  <pb n="47" xml:id="VAC6388-00000029"/> back, till he fled beyond its reach! "I
                  cannot do any thing till thou be come thither." The uplifted sword cannot fall—the
                  destroying arm must delay to strike, till the one family in a nation of sinners,
                  whose head feared the Lord, is saved from impending ruin. Such is the protecting
                  care and goodness of God, exercised towards the least of those who love Him and
                  keep his commandments.</p>
               <p>When Abraham sent his chief servant to seek a wife for his son among his kindred
                  in the ancient Mesopotamian settlement, the faithful patriarch expresses his
                  reliance on Divine protection for the success of the mission. "The Lord God of
                  Heaven—He shall send his angel before thee." He knew well the appointed work of
                  those ministering visitants, and conscious of his own duty to preserve integrity
                  of descent in the line of the Messiah, knew that the aid he required would be
                  sent. How beautiful is this expression of childlike confidence! In answer<pb
                     n="48-49" xml:id="VAC6388-00000030"/> to another instance of the same implicit
                  faith, an angel interposed to prevent the sacrifice of his son.</p>
               <p>The dream of Jacob, in which he beheld "a ladder set up on the earth, and the top
                  of it reached to heaven; and behold, the angels of God ascending and descending on
                  it"—is a striking representation of the ministry of celestial creatures, and of
                  the mode of communication between the holy inhabitants of heaven and a sinful
                  race. A door was opened in heaven; the dispensation was crowned by Divine
                  sanction; the Lord himself stood above the ladder, which typified the incarnation
                  and death of the Redeemer. Thus may Faith command both the visible and invisible
                  worlds, and see that in the remotest solitude <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"Millions of spiritual beings walk the earth</l>
                        <l>Unseen, both when we wake and when we sleep."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>In the Book of Daniel intimations are given, by which we are led to conclude that
                  a leader was appointed among the angelic hosts, to whom the Lord entrusted the
                  supervision pervision of affairs in the Church under the first dispensation. In
                  the tenth chapter and thirteenth verse, the angel who talks with the prophet,
                  speaks of "Michael, one of the chief princes;" and in the twenty-first verse,
                  calls him "Michael your prince." In the twelfth chapter he predicts the time when
                  "Michael shall stand up, the great prince which standeth for the children of thy
                  people." In the epistle of Jude, he is called "Michael the archangel." In the
                  Revelation, it is Michael who with his angels fights against the dragon, and
                  expels him forever from heaven. Under this mighty leader the armies of heaven, in
                  behalf of the inhabitants of earth, wage a conflict with the malignant hosts who
                  strive for our destruction. And now that we have revealed to us a more powerful
                  and glorious "Captain of our salvation," can we doubt that under Him the same
                  warriors are marshalled—engaged incessantly in the contest which is not to be
                  ended till Satan and his legions are cast out<pb n="50-51"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000031"/> from the world they have spoiled, and claim as
                  their lawful possession?</p>
               <p>As we trace the history of the Jewish church, the attendance of angels is so
                  frequently mentioned, that their appearance seems a matter of course in the
                  messages sent by the Divine Ruler to his people. In the journey through the
                  wilderness, the angel of God went with the pillar of the cloud before the camp of
                  Israel, and an angel was promised to go before the chosen people, to drive out the
                  nations in the land that was to be theirs. An angel intercepted the wicked prophet
                  Balaam, on his way to utter the curse so unexpectedly turned into a blessing. And
                  after the tribes were established in the promised land, the occasions were
                  frequent on which these heavenly messengers appeared to bring the Lord's message.
                  The first record is of the angel who came from Gilgal to Bochim, to remonstrate
                  with the children of Israel on their disobedience to the command given to make no
                  league with the inhabitants of the land, and to throw down their altars. Again,
                  when the people cried to the Lord in the distress brought upon them by their own
                  sins, an angel brought deliverance. "There came an angel of the Lord, and sat
                  under an oak which was in Ophrah, that pertained unto Joash the Abiezrite; and his
                  son Gideon threshed wheat by the wine-press, to hide it from the Midianites. And
                  the angel of the Lord appeared unto him, and said unto him, 'The Lord is with
                  thee, thou mighty man of valor.' And Gideon said unto him—'Oh my Lord, if the Lord
                  be with us, why then is all this befallen us!"—The gracious assurance of
                  protection is given with the command to go and save Israel from the hands of the
                  Midianites. "Surely I will be with thee"—was a sufficient pledge of success. "When
                  the heavenly nature of his visitor is proved by the rising of supernatural fire
                  out of the rock, to consume the flesh and cakes prepared by Gideon for the
                  supposed prophet, he is filled with consternation, and exclaims, "Alas, O Lord
                  God! for because<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC6388-00000032"/> I have seen an angel of
                  the Lord face to face!" Then it is that the voice of God himself bids the trembler
                  "fear not."</p>
               <p>Both in this instance and in that of Ma-noah and his wife, the discovery, made at
                  the departure of the visitor, of his heavenly nature, alarms those to whom the
                  message has been delivered. The advent of a messenger from Jehovah's presence
                  might well startle frail mortals conscious of their own unworthiness, and of the
                  exalted character of these his servants of the upper sanctuary. Even though
                  appearing in human form, there was something of awful majesty in their aspect,
                  surpassing humanity. The countenance of the "man of God" is described by Manoah's
                  wife as "very terrible," yet such that his holy character could not be mistaken.
                  It might have been the calm severity of spotless purity, fearful to the conscience
                  of a fallen being; the brightness of the spirit which, wearing no taint of earth,
                  could not be altogether obscured by mortal lineaments, and was too intense to be
                  gazed upon by human eyes. These visits of celestial beings were not so frequent as
                  to render their marvellous interference familiar in men's eyes; many years passed
                  between them, and each visitation was to announce some wonderful deliverance for
                  the perverse yet repentant nation.</p>
               <p>In the days of the kings, when the will of the Almighty was declared by his
                  prophets, the ministration of angels was of a different character. It was their
                  part to bring instruction and consolation to the seers who declared the divine
                  message to the chosen people, speaking "as they were moved by the Holy Ghost." How
                  touching, beyond the beauty of poetry or painting, is the picture of the angel
                  watching the slumber of Elijah under the juniper tree in the wilderness! Though
                  persecuted and forsaken of man, though driven out destitute and despairing, he is
                  an object of care to one far nobler than himself. Even his bodily wants are
                  provided for by his probably unseen attendant. "An angel touched him;" it was time
                  to awake from his sleep and take the<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC6388-00000033"/>
                  nourishment he needed; and lo, there is placed beside him a cruse of water, and a
                  cake is baked for him on the coals! Again he sinks into slumber, and again his
                  watchful friend arouses him, that he may have strength for the journey. Yet to
                  this favored prophet the appointed ministering spirit did not more willingly bring
                  succor, than others among the bright legions of heaven render service to every
                  suffering child of God.</p>
               <p>When the servant of Elisha, despairing at the sight of the host of Syria, cried
                  out in terror to his master, and at the prophet's prayer his eyes were opened, and
                  he saw the mountain of Dothan full of horses and chariots of fire, encompassing
                  the man of God—he beheld only what was actually there. The prophet prayed not that
                  an angelic host might be sent to reassure the young man; but that his eyes might
                  be opened, that he might see. Thus are the saints on earth encompassed with
                  heavenly guardians, and who knows, were he endowed with the faculty culty of
                  discernment, but that his eyes might open upon myriads thus employed for the
                  protection and service of "those who shall be heirs of salvation," so that he too
                  would say—"they that be with us are more than they that be with them." We may well
                  believe that the number of heavenly ones ready to help and serve God's human
                  servants, is far greater than those opposed to them—whether men or devils.</p>
               <p>The vision Isaiah had of the seraphim engaged in the worship of the Lord, and the
                  ministry of one of those winged and zealous creatures, in preparing him
                  symbolically for his prophetic office by touching his lips with a live coal from
                  off the altar, represents the angelic host as joining in the worship of their
                  "fellow servants who have the testimony of Jesus;" for it was of Him the prophet
                  spake, and his glory that he saw. Of the "cherubim" described by Ezekiel, a
                  graceful writer remarks: "It seems, so far as our dim faculties may penetrate the
                  mysterious veil, as though these were a peculiar order of angelic<pb n="56-57"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000034"/> creatures. The title is constantly given to those
                  appearances which the Lord instructed Moses to place at each end of the ark of the
                  testament, over the mercy seat of which they extended their wings: and who are
                  nowhere called by the general term of <hi rend="i"/>angels. Their station, we may
                  venture to think, is one of more immediate proximity to the throne of glory than
                  that of others; both from the position assigned to them in the material temple
                  which we are told was a figure of the true, or heavenly house of God, and from the
                  descriptions given by Ezekiel. Cherubim also were placed at the gate of the garden
                  of Eden, to wield the terrible sword of flame which barred all approach—keeping
                  the way to the tree of life. It is a most inviting field for the imagination to
                  rove in—these glimpses of the heavenly territory and its angelic inhabitants: but
                  imagination must not enter where we are humbly following the footsteps of
                  inspiration, to speak according to the word of the Lord—neither more nor less; and
                  we must be contented to believe, without expecting pecting fully to understand
                  what the prophet was enabled to convey of his own impressions of those things
                  which he beheld; so far, at least, as he makes distinct mention of beings whom we
                  are taught to consider as a part of the armies of heaven. Whether or not these
                  appearances were real, whether the angels are immaterial, invisible essences, and
                  therefore impossible to be seen by us in their natural state, and only clothed in
                  the semblance of something tangible for occasional revelation to man, or whether
                  the weakness of our powers, defiled and debilitated by original guilt, shuts them
                  out from our mortal ken, is a point that never will be fully cleared up until we
                  come to know even as we are known; but there is quite as much to be said for the
                  latter as for the former proposition."</p>
               <p>From the mysterious visions of Ezekiel much instruction pertaining to our subject
                  may be gained, though we cannot understand their full meaning. They were,
                  doubtless, glimpses into glorious realities, to be understood<pb n="58-59"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000035"/> stood when the veil of mortality shall be drawn
                  aside. This revelation furnishes another evidence of the existence of those holy
                  multitudes in our midst, employed, collectively and individually, in watchings and
                  labors for the good of the children of earth. Still more encouragingly is this
                  truth unfolded in the record of Daniel's prophetic visions. The outline of the
                  world's history was laid before him in the interpretation of the wonders that he
                  saw, with the grandeur of the final judgment; and in all the agency of spiritual
                  beings is conspicuous. "Thousand thousand ministered unto" the Ancient of days—and
                  "ten thousand times ten thousand stood before him." Some are introduced by name,
                  and others speak like familiar friends. It has been truly observed that "the
                  latter part of the book of Daniel brings us more into contact with the angels than
                  any that precede it; enabling us to form, as it were, an acquaintance with those
                  whom we humbly hope to associate with through eternity."</p>
               <p>From the lips of the prophets Haggai and Zechariah, it will be remembered, came
                  the message, in the name of the God of Israel, to Zerubbabel the governor, and
                  Joshua the high priest, at the termination of the seventy years' captivity,
                  calling upon them to delay no longer the building of the second temple. It was
                  promised that its glory should exceed the glory of the former house built by
                  Solomon in the height of his magnificence; a promise that referred, beyond doubt,
                  to the presence of Christ therein, since the latter temple had not the Shechinah
                  or visible Presence, the Urim and Thummim, the Ark and its contents, or the Sacred
                  Fire on the Altar; and the spirit of prophecy ceased to speak after its erection.
                  The message of exhortation, of warning and of promise, addressed by Zechariah
                  during the progress of this building, to the children of the captivity, describes
                  a glorious vision of angels. The man that stood among the myrtle trees, and the
                  angel that interceded for Jerusalem and the cities of Judah, against which the
                  Lord had had indignation for three score and<pb n="60-61"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000036"/> ten years, were deeply interested in the
                  restoration of the Jewish people. The angel being answered "with good and
                  comfortable words," turns joyfully to the prophet, and says—"Cry thou, saying,
                  Thus saith the Lord of hosts, I am jealous for Jerusalem and for Zion with a great
                  jealousy;"—and "I am returned to Jerusalem with mercies; my house shall be built
                  in it, saith the Lord of hosts." "The Lord shall yet comfort Zion, and shall yet
                  choose Jerusalem." Well might the spirit of the prophet be exalted with the great
                  promises he was instructed to utter, when, as with eagerness to bear the tidings
                  swiftly, another angel flew to meet the angel who talked with him, bidding him
                  "run" to communicate the glorious intelligence to the appointed messenger, of the
                  restoration of the holy city. These, and the visions that follow, exhibit the
                  burning zeal of the heavenly host for the fulfillment of the Divine word, and the
                  extension of the kingdom of their Master, and their sympathy in the trials and joy
                  of the church on earth. The contemplation of the prosperity of Zion, when the
                  Divine favor should be again risen upon her, causing her to shine like the sun in
                  the strength of the morning—fills the prophet's heart, and kindles his words, as
                  if his mouth had been touched with fire from the altar. The beauty of Zion as a
                  city of truth—the joy and gladness, and cheerful feasts to be held within those
                  walls, so lately a desolation and a mockery to the heathen, the blessing to be
                  poured out on the house of Judah, when the inhabitants of many cities, and many
                  people, and strong nations should come to seek the Lord of hosts in Jerusalem—such
                  is the burden of the word delivered—elevating the prophet with the spirit of joy
                  and gratitude and devotion, and exalting his language into the richest poetry. The
                  earnest sympathy of the bright creatures with whom he conversed on this great
                  theme, and of whom he sought instruction, sustains him while his eyes are opened
                  to the vision of a glory transcending all that had gone before: when<pb n="62-63"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000037"/> the kingdom of Him who was to be a priest upon his
                  throne should be set up, and his dominion should be from sea to sea, and from the
                  river to the ends of the earth; when the mountain of the Lord's house should be
                  established on the top of the mountain, and should be exalted above the hills; and
                  all people should flow unto it. These glimpses of a glory that should be revealed
                  in the latter day—the prophecies of the Redeemer's coming and kingdom, that break
                  with a sudden impulse from the seer's lips—are a key to the exultation and joy
                  manifested by the angels, who, seeing the approach of the day of redemption, and
                  the fulfillment of ancient prophecies, could understand what was beyond the
                  apprehension of the speaker himself. He could only exclaim, transported with the
                  wonders he discerned as through a glass, darkly—"How great is his goodness, and
                  how great is his beauty!"</p>
               <p>As if to indicate to after ages the source of the fountain which was to be opened
                  to the house of David, and come forth of the house of the Lord—in the midst of
                  these predictions opening a view of scenes in the far distant future, declaring
                  the termination of idolatry and false prophecy—is uttered the mysterious
                  denunciation, which, to the church in that age, and even to celestial listeners,
                  must have been both incomprehensible and appalling. It stands alone, unconnected
                  with aught that precedes or follows it, and unexplained by what has before been
                  spoken; it is as if the Spirit by whom Zechariah was moved, had suddenly descended
                  upon him with an influence and a power too vast for human apprehension—a sound
                  from heaven as of a rushing, mighty wind, impelling him to speak things concerning
                  which the angels who desired knowledge, were still unsatisfied. For as yet the
                  fulness of time was not come, and none could fathom the counsels of the Almighty,
                  when he said—"Awake, O sword, against my Shepherd, and against the man that is my
                  fellow, saith the Lord of hosts."</p>
               <p>With this dim perception of what was to come, is linked the intense interest shown
                     by<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC6388-00000038"/> the angels in the history of the
                  chosen nation, to whom were committed the oracles of God. During successive
                  generations they watched the development of the mighty plan of redemption
                  announced by the lips of Him who said—"The seed of the woman shall bruise the
                  serpent's head." Their faithful memory treasured every prophecy, and their
                  inviolable faith looked forward in confidence to its fulfillment in the coming of
                  Him who was "the desire of all nations," and who was to unfold to "principalities
                  and powers in heavenly places," such views of the Divine glory as the universe had
                  never before witnessed.</p>
               <p>Pursuant to this expectation, the angel who appears to Zacharias to announce the
                  birth of Messiah's forerunner, addresses him with the language of peculiar
                  encouragement. His words—"Fear not;" "Thou shalt have joy and gladness;" "I am
                  sent to speak unto thee, and to show thee these glad tidings"—significantly
                  express the import of the communication intrusted as a high privilege to one who
                  "stands in the presence of God;" that is—who is honored with peculiar dignity in
                  heaven. The ministrations of angels to our Saviour, will be considered in another
                  chapter. During the days of the apostles, their visits and ministry continued to
                  the church in Jerusalem. When the apostles were thrown into prison by the high
                  priest and Sadducees, "the angel of the Lord by night opened the prison doors and
                  brought them forth"—bidding them go and speak in the temple to the people. An
                  angel sent Philip towards the south, that the gospel might be extended by the
                  conversion of the Ethiopian. When Peter was imprisoned by Herod—while "prayer was
                  made without ceasing of the church unto God for him," "the angel of the Lord came
                  upon him, and a light shined in the prison," for his deliverance. When Herod
                  received divine honors, "the angel of the Lord smote him, because he gave not God
                  the glory." When Paul, on his voyage, was in peril of shipwreck, the angel of God
                  stood by him at night, to bid<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC6388-00000039"/> him be of
                  good courage, and promised him the lives of all who sailed with him. On the
                  occasion of the breaking down of the wall of partition between Jew and Gentile,
                  angelic ministry was employed. Even the disciples who had seen the Lord Jesus, had
                  never attained to so mighty a conception as this—that the blessings of the
                  religion they were appointed to disseminate, were to be free to all mankind; that
                  whosoever would might drink of the water of life freely; that God would pour out
                  upon the uncircumcised heathen the gift of the Holy Ghost. This important
                  revelation of the Divine will—a virtual abrogation of the ritual law established
                  so many ages before—was given with impressive accompaniments of supernatural
                  interposition. Angels descended from heaven to take away the vail which had
                  hitherto forbidden access to the most holy place; to proclaim that the Almighty is
                  no respecter of persons. The angel of God stood before Cornelius, called him
                  familiarly by name, and bade him "send men to Joppa, and call for one Simon, whose
                  surname is Peter;" while a mysterious vision revealed to the apostle as he prayed
                  upon the house-top, instructed him in his duty, and prepared the way for a full
                  discovery of God's gracious purpose. Thus were gathered the first fruits of the
                  harvest of the Gentiles.</p>
               <p>We have no further record, in particular instances, of the ministry of angels, and
                  have reason to conclude that their visible interposition ceased after the first
                  age of the Christian church. But that they continued, and do continue, to watch
                  its progress with loving interest, we cannot for a moment doubt. The instances we
                  have noticed imply that their observation and care were incessant, and of this
                  fact we are assured in several general passages. Paul tells the Corinthians the
                  apostles are made "a spectacle to angels." The manifold wisdom of God is said to
                  be made known to principalities and powers in heavenly places, "by the church"—by
                  her history, trials and sufferings, and the blessings vouchsafed to her. The words
                  of angelic<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC6388-00000040"/> gelic visitants to the
                  disciples, express not only full knowledge of all concerning them—but an abiding
                  sympathy of which they were but seldom permitted to receive the evidence. The
                  presence of invisible holy beings in places of worship is implied in the apostle's
                  direction, that the women should wear veils in the churches. The wise man, in
                  enjoining the payment of vows, says—"neither say thou before the angel, that it
                  was an error." Our Saviour frequently alludes to these unseen beings, and
                  describes them as interested witnesses of all that takes place or that shall
                  happen on earth. Luke xii. 8, 9, and ix. 26. Matthew xxv. 31, 32. When little
                  children are brought to Him He speaks of "their angels." His declaration that
                  "there is joy among the angels of God over one sinner that repenteth," would be
                  conclusive, were there no other passage of similar import, to prove their intimate
                  knowledge of what passes in this lower world, and their close observation of each
                  individual. Saint Paul says, "Are they not all ministering spirits, sent forth to
                  minister to them who shall be heirs of salvation?" thus declaring their
                  guardianship over the persons of believers, even previous to their regeneration.
                  We are told, moreover, that in the end of the world their open ministry shall be
                  employed. They are represented as the reapers of the great harvest, and the
                  executioners of God's judgment and vengeance. They shall gather together the elect
                  from the four winds, from one end of heaven to another; they shall attend the Lord
                  in his second advent from heaven, when he shall come "to be glorified in his
                  saints, and to be admired in them that believe." The Apocalyptic visions describe
                  their active employment, and the parables of our Lord declare their future agency
                  in the struggles and the triumphs of the church, and in the final conveying of the
                  righteous to their reward and the wicked to their punishment. In the magnificent
                  imagery by which in Scripture, the splendors of Christ's coming to reign on earth
                  are pictured, revealing glories that have never entered into<pb n="70-71"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000041"/> the heart of man to conceive, one prominent point
                  dwelt on, is the presence of "an innumerable company of angels." With what
                  ecstatic rapture will those zealous servants of God, who witnessed the ascent of
                  their incarnate King, throng the skies to attend Him when He shall visibly take
                  possession of his once revolted province, banishing his foes forever! How will the
                  song that proclaimed "peace on earth" at his birth, swell into exultation and
                  triumph, when the Prince of Peace shall take unto Himself his great power and
                  shall reign, and his will shall be done on earth as it is in heaven!</p>
               <p>Thus from the unquestionable testimony of Holy Writ, we are justified in the
                  inference that our planet, from its creation, has been visited by innumerable
                  multitudes of beings superior to us in intellectual capacity, and more ethereal in
                  their natural form—for we cannot, consistently with many acts attributed to them,
                  suppose them to be incorporeal spirits;—that these, perhaps congregated from
                  different worlds, have witnessed every transaction in which men have borne a part,
                  closely observing, not only the actions, but the character and disposition of each
                  individual of the human race; that they have seen with holy indignation all the
                  wicked deeds of the ungodly, and tenderly sympathized with the pure in heart
                  whenever suffering from the contact of an evil world; that they bear, moreover, a
                  commission from their King and ours, to take charge of individuals, to guard them
                  in dangers and through temptations; to fight against their invisible enemies,
                  administer comfort to them in affliction, and at the moment of death convey them
                  to everlasting habitations. We have a right to the inference that these blessed
                  creatures fill the air and the heavens about us, and walk the earth on every side;
                  that they are continually present, even in the most guarded solitude; that they
                  are fellow-worshippers with Christians in their places of religious service, and
                  spectators of the fervent devotion of Christ's people, or of their desecration of
                  the sacred place by wandering thoughts;<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC6388-00000042"/>
                  that not even the outward deportment and dress of those assembled escape their
                  attention; that they mourn over backslidings, and rejoice over every soul brought
                  to repentance, enrolling his name with thanksgiving as another stone in that
                  spiritual temple, which has been building through the ages of this world, and is
                  to stand forever. We have no reason to believe that their interest in the church
                  is a whit less lively than when they began to learn by her the mystery hid in God,
                  or that their visits to earth are less frequent—because they are no longer seen of
                  men—than before its soil was trodden by the feet of Immanuel; before Satan,
                  dispossessed of his boasted empire, like lightning fell from heaven. On the other
                  hand, it would be natural to suppose this planet an object of still deeper
                  interest to sinless beings—the nearer approached the closing of the present
                  dispensation, the nearer the time when He who purchased it with his blood, shall
                  enter upon its complete possession. Without presumption, we might imagine it a
                  place of resort continually to holy pilgrims from the remotest parts of the
                  universe, each eager to learn and to tell the story of man's redemption, to praise
                  the mercy of a forgiving God, and to wonder at the strange indifference of men to
                  the great salvation provided for them.</p>
               <p>How encouraging is this knowledge that, without a figure of speech, the angel of
                  the Lord encamps around each one who fears Him! We know not the precise nature or
                  manner of the "ministry" performed, but we know it is necessary for the safety of
                  the child of earth, and effectual to preserve him amidst dangers. Even external
                  perils are doubtless often averted by this celestial interposition, and
                  difficulties lightened or removed, which had perplexed and distressed the object
                  of their care; perhaps had been a stumbling-block in his way. Unconscious as he is
                  of this tender watchfulness, it is unremitting; and he will hereafter learn how
                  often he has been indebted to it. Against his unseen and spiritual enemies, they
                     watch<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC6388-00000043"/> with unceasing vigilance and
                  zealously contend; with him, and for him, they wrestle against principalities and
                  powers, and the rulers of the darkness of this world—the spirits that work in the
                  children of disobedience. With great comfort the believer can say, "They that be
                  with us are more than they that be with them." Though separated from all the
                  world, though environed by foes, he has on his side a vast preponderance of
                  numbers—his fellow-servants, whose example of fidelity, humility and zeal, should
                  sustain him amidst temptation, and the sense of whose companionship and sympathy
                  may cheer him in the loneliest hours of his earthly pilgrimage.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>"Ye stars that round the Sun of righteousness</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">In glorious order roll,</l>
                     <l>With harps forever strung, ready to bless</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">God for each rescued soul—</l>
                     <l>Ye eagle spirits, that build in light divine,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">Oh, think of us to day,</l>
                     <l>Faint warblers of this earth, that would combine</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">Our trembling notes with your accepted lay.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>"Your amaranth wreaths were earned; and homeward all,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">Flushed with victorious might,</l>
                     <l>Ye might have sped to keep high festival,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">And revel in the light;</l>
                     <l>But meeting us, weak worldlings, on our way,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">Tired ere the fight begun,</l>
                     <l>Ye turned to help us in the unequal fray,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">Remembering whose we were—how dearly won;</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>"Remembering Bethlehem, and that glorious night</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">When ye, who used to soar</l>
                     <l>Diverse along all space in fiery flight,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">Came thronging to adore</l>
                     <l>Your God new-born, and made a sinner's child;</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">As if the stars should leave</l>
                     <l>Their stations in the far ethereal wild,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">And round the sun a radiant circle weave.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>"Nor less your lay of triumph greeted fair</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">Our Champion and your King,</l>
                     <l>In that first strife, whence Satan in despair</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">Sunk down on scathed wing;</l>
                     <l>Alone He fasted, and alone He fought,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">But when his toils were o'er,</l>
                     <l>Ye to the sacred Hermit duteous brought</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">Banquet and hymn, your Eden's festal store.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>"Ye, too, when lowest in the abyss of woe</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">He plunged to save his sheep,</l>
                     <pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC6388-00000044"/>
                     <l>Were leaning from your golden thrones, to know</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">The secrets of that deep;</l>
                     <l>But clouds were on his sorrow; one alone</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">His agonizing call</l>
                     <l>Summoned from heaven, to still that bitterest groan,</l>
                     <l>And comfort Him, the Comforter of all.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>"Oh, highest favored of all spirits create,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">(If right of thee we deem,)</l>
                     <l>How didst thou glide on brightening wing elate,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">To meet the unclouded beam</l>
                     <l>Of Jesus from the couch of darkness rising!</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">How swelled thine anthem's sound,</l>
                     <l>With fear and mightier joy weak hearts surprising,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">'Your God is risen, and may not here be found.'</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>"Pass a few days, and this dull darkling globe</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">Must yield Him from her sight;</l>
                     <l>Brighter and brighter streams his glory-robe,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">And He is lost in light.</l>
                     <l>Then, when through yonder everlasting arch,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">Ye in innumerous choir.</l>
                     <l>Poured, heralding Messiah's conquering march,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">Lingered around his skirts two forms of fire;—</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>"With us they stayed, high warning to impart;</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">'The Christ shall come again</l>
                     <l>Even as He goes; with the same human heart,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">With the same godlike train.'</l>
                     <l>Oh, jealous God! how could a sinner dare</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">Think on that dreadful day,</l>
                     <l>But that with all thy wounds Thou wilt be there,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">And all our angel friends to bring Thee on thy way?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>"Since to our little ones is given such grace,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">That they who nearest stand</l>
                     <l>Alway to God in heaven, and see his face,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">Go forth at his command</l>
                     <l>To wait around our path in weal or wo,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">As erst upon our King,</l>
                     <l>Set thy baptismal seal upon our brow,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">And waft us heavenward with enfolding wing—</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>"Grant, Lord, that when around the expiring world</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">Our seraph guardians wait,</l>
                     <l>While on her death-bed, ere to ruin hurled,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">She owns thee, all too late—</l>
                     <l>They to their charge may turn, and thankful see</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">Thy mark upon us still;</l>
                     <l>Then all together rise, and reign with Thee,</l>
                     <l rend="ti-1">And all their holy joy o'er contrite hearts fulfil!"</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC6388-00000045"/>
               <head>III. THE LESSONING OF ANGELS.</head>
               <p>IT may be well now to consider angels as spectators of transactions in this world.
                  We may with reason suppose that a Creator infinitely wise and benevolent, would
                  not exclude his obedient and loving creatures from observation of the various
                  works of his hands. The vast number of systems in the universe, each perhaps
                  different from another, must afford sublime scope for study to the highest and
                  most penetrating intellect, and through succeeding ages, display still more and
                  more of the glorious attributes of Him who called them into being. If instruction
                  may be reaped from the careful study of the laws by which suns and planets are
                  governed, or the division into classes of their material products, how much deeper
                  must be the interest with which spiritual beings regard creatures nearly allied to
                  themselves, and in like manner responsible to the supreme Governor? How naturally
                  must this interest be enhanced when they behold these creatures in circumstances
                  of sorrow and extreme peril! "How fine a harmony there is," observes an eminent
                  writer, "between the law of sympathetic nature in heaven, and the most touching
                  exhibitions of it on the face of our world! When one of a numerous household
                  droops under the power of disease, is not that the one to whom all the tenderness
                  is turned, and who, in a manner, monopolizes the inquiries of his neighborhood,
                  and the care of his family?" "Conceive the universe to be one secure and rejoicing
                  family, and that this alienated world is the only strayed, or only captive member
                  belonging to it; and we shall cease to wonder that, from the first period of the
                  captivity of our species, down to the consummation of their history in time,<pb
                     n="80-81" xml:id="VAC6388-00000046"/> there should be such a movement in
                  heaven, or that angels should so often have sped their commissioned way on the
                  errand of our recovery." It is distinctly intimated in Scripture, "that, agreeably
                  to such laws of sympathy as are most familiar even to human observation, the very
                  wretchedness of our condition was fitted to concentrate upon us the feelings, the
                  attentions and the services of the celestials; to single us out for a time to the
                  gaze of their most earnest and unceasing contemplation—to draw forth all that was
                  kind and all that was tender within them, and just in proportion to the need and
                  the helplessness of us miserable exiles from the family of God, to multiply upon
                  us the regards, and call out in our behalf the fond and eager exertions of those
                  who had never wandered away from Him."</p>
               <p>The testimony of Scripture on this point admits no doubt. The apostle declares the
                  object of preaching "the unsearchable riches of Christ," to be not only that men
                  should see what is "the fellowship of the mystery which from the beginning of the
                  world hath been hid in God," but "to the intent that now unto the principalities
                  and powers in heavenly places, might be known by the church the manifold wisdom of
                  God." The cherubim that covered with their wings the mercy-seat above the ark in
                  the tabernacle of old—the representation of things invisible in the temple not
                  made with hands—were made to look with their faces one towards another, and
                  towards the mercy-seat;—an attitude strongly expressive of wonder and inquiry; and
                  Saint Peter, in speaking of the mysteries of the gospel, says—"which things the
                  angels desire to look into." From these and numerous other passages, we know that
                  the inhabitants of heaven are deeply interested in the concerns of earth; that
                  they have carefully noted its history from the beginning, and watched the actions
                  and sufferings of mortals; and that the glorious plan of man's redemption has
                  especially, in its august development through successive ages, occupied their most
                  profound attention, employed<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC6388-00000047"/> the whole of
                  their vast faculties, and called forth their most fervent ascriptions of "blessing
                  and honor, and glory, and power, unto Him that sitteth upon the throne, and unto
                  the Lamb forever and ever."</p>
               <p>The unfolding of this stupendous scheme, to which have tended all the
                  dispensations, judgments and mercies of Providence—on which converge all the rays
                  shed by revelation on the heavens above and the earth beneath—in which meet all
                  the lines stretching from point to point throughout the universe, was the object,
                  it cannot be doubted, for which this world was called into existence. We cannot
                  believe otherwise than that it was with an expectation—perhaps without the
                  knowledge how it was to be accomplished, yet still a confident expectation—of an
                  advance in the knowledge of the glory of God greater than any the preceding ages
                  of eternity had witnessed, that "the morning stars sang together, and all the sons
                  of God shouted for joy."</p>
               <p>Let us look more closely into the problem lem, and contemplate the wonders
                  revealed. "Behold, I show you a mystery," the solution of which engages angelic
                  intellect, and can be found only in the person of Him who was "God manifest in the
                  flesh."</p>
               <p>The law of God, to which every intelligent creature in the universe is made
                  subject, requires perfect obedience, under its terrible penalty—"cursed is every
                  one that continueth not in all things written in the book of the law to do them."
                  "All souls are mine," said the Creator; "and the soul that sinneth, it shall die."
                  From this dread sentence there is no escape. The angels who kept not their first
                  estate, found no place for repentance, but were driven forth from heaven as no
                  longer worthy the companionship of the sinless; meet only for the blackness of
                  darkness forever. With what anxious suspense—knowing all this—must the pure
                  inhabitants of heaven have watched the first stage in the history of earth; the
                  experiment—if we may so speak—on the human will, tried in the person of Adam, to
                  whose hands was committed<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC6388-00000048"/> mitted the
                  destiny of his posterity! How must those who now have joy over one sinner that
                  repenteth, have mourned the apparent failure of this experiment! They saw that man
                  had ruined himself; for in Adam the whole race fell. The world which angels hoped
                  would be the scene of God's glory, was to become the accursed abode of condemned
                  spirits, a theatre of triumph for the powers of evil. The wisdom of the highest
                  archangel could not discover a method whereby the guilty might escape the
                  punishment of disobedience. "What could the infinite Judge do, but honor his own
                  law by giving over the victim justice imperiously demanded? It was in this
                  interval of gloom, when the powers of hell were exultant at the advantage they had
                  gained—when, as we may believe without a figure of speech, the hosts of heaven
                  stood silent in mournful expectation, while all waited for the sentence that was
                  to consign the human race to hopeless perdition,—that the commandment came forth
                  from the most excellent glory—"Deliver liver him from going down to the pit; I
                  have found a ransom."</p>
               <p>How this deliverance was to be effected was the great mystery into which angels
                  desired to look. How could man who had fallen, become just with God? How could his
                  transgression be expiated, and how could he be clothed with a righteousness in
                  which he might be presented spotless before Him who is of purer eyes than to
                  behold iniquity? Should one of those bright legions undertake the work? No created
                  being could pay the debt, or sustain the weight of that wrath which, if not
                  intercepted, must sink a world to perdition. To expiate a single sin would have
                  required for man or angel, the years of eternity. For it is a common principle,
                  that the guilt of a transgression is estimated according to the obligation
                  violated, and the dignity of the person against whom it is committed. Thus an
                  infinite evil demanded an infinite satisfaction. And who, among all the multitudes
                  that stood before the throne, could render this?</p>
               <pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC6388-00000049"/>
               <p>The voice that said—"Lo, I come to do thy will,"—was that of One who in the
                  beginning was with God, and who was God; by whom, and for whom, all things were
                  created. He—the Lamb slain from the foundation of the world—assumed the burden of
                  human guilt, and undertook the restoration of man. In the eternal counsel and
                  purpose of God, the Son had become the surety of his people. In time past so
                  remote that thought fails to reach it, when as yet the angels were not, and the
                  heavens were not spread abroad, when the Father, the only begotten Son, in the
                  bosom of the Father, and the Eternal Spirit, were alone in their plenitude of
                  inconceivable, incommunicable blessedness,—then was "the counsel of peace" between
                  them; then was this favorite scheme of Deity already planned; then was the Son
                  commissioned to proceed forth from the Father, and the Holy Ghost commissioned by
                  the Son; each Person of the ever-blessed Trinity having his appointed work. The
                  Wisdom of God, who "was daily his delight light, rejoicing always before him,"
                  already "rejoiced in the habitable part of the earth," and had his delights with
                  that portion of the sons of men given Him from eternity, in due time, by the
                  righteousness in Him, to be made meet for his eternal complacency.</p>
               <p>Yet another part of the mystery is unfolded; "Forasmuch as the children were of
                  flesh and blood, He also must take part in the same." Even had it been in the
                  power of angel or archangel to render satisfaction to the violated majesty of law
                  by enduring the penalty—such a sacrifice could not have been accepted. It was man
                  who had sinned; man must pay the forfeit. Nay, it was not only the same nature
                  which had transgressed, that must suffer, but the victim must be lineally
                  descended from Adam, and partake of the hereditary infirmities of humanity, sin
                  alone excepted. It would have been easy for Omnipotence to create a human being of
                  sinless perfection, and to unite it with the Divine nature in the Person of
                  Christ; but such a being could not have been the Saviour<pb n="88"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000050"/> of the human race. He must own a like relationship
                  with his brethren to the common parent of the species. He must be born of a woman,
                  made under the law, and made in the likeness of <emph>sinful</emph> flesh. But
                  that the entail of guilt may be cut off—that He may be free from the taint of
                  Adam's transgression—it is ordained that He shall be born of a virgin. Behold,
                  then, the body prepared for Him who was to come! Without sin, pure and undefiled
                  before God, He is yet one of us; descended from Adam, calling Abraham his father,
                  and allied to us by the indissoluble tie of brotherhood; thus fitted to be our
                  representative, our substitute and exemplar. By his stripes we may be healed. His
                  soul may be made an offering for sin. He may work out, in his spotless and holy
                  life, a righteousness which we can call our own; He may offer an atonement which
                  will satisfy the uttermost claims of justice. For by the ineffable union of the
                  human and divine natures in the mysterious person of the Redeemer, the acts of one
                  may be properly<pb n="(Illustration)-89" xml:id="VAC6388-00000051"/>
                  <figure/> attributed to the other, and his sufferings as a man become invested
                  with an efficacy belonging to the dignity of the Godhead. Thus not only was divine
                  strength imparted, when He poured out his soul unto death, to bear the infinite
                  load of woe, but a divine virtue was communicated to his sufferings, that
                  henceforth all who believe on Him should not perish, but have everlasting
                  life.</p>
               <p>A spectacle which, beyond all others, called for the wonder of the hosts of
                  heaven, was the experience of the Redeemer in his sojourn on earth. Throughout
                  this, angels attended, either visibly, as ministers to Him, or invisibly as
                  witnesses. An angel sped from the court of heaven to a city of Galilee, to
                  announce to a meek virgin Messiah's birth. The angelic messenger who proclaimed to
                  the shepherds—"unto you is born this day, in the city of David, a Saviour, which
                  is Christ the Lord"—was attended by "a multitude of the heavenly host"—who praised
                  God and sang "Peace on earth—good will towards men." It was as if the
                  irrepressible praises<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC6388-00000052"/> which at that
                  august hour filled heaven, overflowed upon earth, bringing even into human view
                  "the glory of the Lord." The holy infant was under the watch and guardianship of
                  angels. One of them warned Joseph in a dream, to flee with the young child and his
                  mother from Herod's persecution into Egypt. "Be thou there until I bring thee
                  word"—was his injunction—showing that his mission and privilege was to watch over
                  the safety of his incarnate Lord, and that he would not leave to chance, or the
                  vigilance of earthly guardians, so sacred a charge! If on this occasion one was
                  permitted to become visible, we may be sure a countless host hovered around to
                  marvel at the sight of Him by whom all things consist, a fugitive from the wrath
                  and jealousy of a mortal prince! Through the years of childhood and youth—during
                  which the holy and harmless nature of Jesus, brought into contact with human guile
                  and cruelty, doubtless suffered much—unshielded as He was by wealth, position or
                  friends, from the "envy, hatred and malice" which virtue always meets from the
                  harsh world—angels invisibly attended Him, and marvelled at the mystery which
                  humbled Him to such a lot—for as yet the whole purpose of God was not made
                  manifest. They could gather, from the intimations of ancient prophecy, that
                  Messiah was to be a sufferer, and to be "cut off;" yet, probably,—as we know, from
                  the authority of Holy Writ, that the future is veiled to them,—the manner of that
                  stupendous sacrifice was to angelic conception incomprehensible. They could not
                  imagine such a crime as the immolation of the Lord of glory by those whom He had
                  stooped so low to save. If they knew that He was to become obedient unto death,
                  they perhaps expected that at the appointed time, He would ascend the sacrificial
                  altar, and offer up his human nature, like the victim appointed in the Levitical
                  law, by fire from heaven, in the sight of a world prostrate in abasement,
                  penitence, and unspeakable gratitude. They saw Him, however, even in the early<pb
                     n="92-93" xml:id="VAC6388-00000053"/> part of his career, proving the
                  mortifications of a lowly condition, the hardships of poverty, and the loneliness
                  of isolation from human sympathy. Who can tell how often sharp suspicion,
                  malignant slander, or brutal invective, pierced his guileless heart! Who can tell
                  how oft He suffered from the sin of those dearest to Him—the coldness or falsehood
                  of friends, the ingratitude of those whom He had benefitted—trials felt most
                  keenly by sensibilities never blunted by selfishness! Thus from every quarter the
                  shaft might enter his unprotected breast; at every step his celestial attendants
                  might know him "a man of sorrows and acquainted with grief."</p>
               <p>The baptism of Jesus, and his mysterious abode in the wilderness, where He
                  encountered the arch-tempter forty days, were witnessed by angels. We cannot
                  conceive them absent from that glorious scene in which the Father, by an audible
                  voice, bore testimony to the "beloved Son"—and the Spirit descended upon Him in a
                  visible form, emblematic atic of purity and peace. And in his strife with "our
                  adversary the devil," they looked on in amazement at the daring of the evil one,
                  and the depth of the humiliation endured for man. When this scene was ended,
                  "behold angels came and ministered to Him." For once, their zealous affection was
                  indulged by permission to bring succor to the holy Sufferer, to cheer Him by their
                  devotion, and pour out before Him their wondering adoration. Not often is it
                  recorded that they were thus privileged, for He was to drink the cup of human woe
                  unsustained. But "we know that Christ was 'seen of angels;' and we cannot believe
                  that ever, for one moment of time, were their regards withdrawn from Him." Most
                  earnest and adoring was their contemplation when the time came for the execution
                  of the mysterious sentence—"Awake, Oh, sword, against my Shepherd, and the man
                  that is my fellow;" when the sword of divine justice was called upon to slay and
                  spare not; to smite the Shepherd—and scatter the sheep who had followed Him.<pb
                     n="94-95" xml:id="VAC6388-00000054"/> In that dreadful night wherein He was
                  betrayed—the watching angels saw Him in every circumstance of those closing
                  scenes; when the sword pierced his soul in the treachery of one of the twelve; in
                  the carelessness of his disciples, who could not watch with him one hour; <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>The hour—none time hath numbered</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Wore ever pall so deep;</l>
                        <l>Earth 'neath the burden trembles,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">And heaven's bright myriads weep;</l>
                        <l>And cherubim and seraph</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Stand silent round the throne,</l>
                        <l>For He who reigns in heaven,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Spares not his only Son.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>They saw Him in the garden of Gethsemane, when his soul was "exceeding sorrowful,
                  even unto death;" when in the misgiving of human agony He thrice prayed that the
                  cup might pass from Him, yet submitted to drink it. One of their number was
                  commissioned to appear unto Him, "strengthening Him." With emotions no human
                  language could express, and which we may not in this mortal state comprehend, they
                  witnessed what followed; his arrest by the multitude that came out as against a
                  thief, with swords and staves, to take Him; the cowardly flight of the disciples
                  who had vowed never to forsake Him; the trial and condemnation; the spitting and
                  scourging; the mockery of his persecutors; the death upon the cross! They saw,
                  too, how deeply the sword pierced Him in that bitterest ingredient of the cup—the
                  infusion of the wrath of God poured out upon Him,—that terrible infliction from
                  the immediate hand of Deity, which but for the Redeemer's interposition, would
                  have crushed the whole race of mankind; that incomprehensible, supernatural
                  anguish which wrung from the lips of one whose human nature was strengthened with
                  all the powers of Divinity the exclamation—"My God—my God—why hast thou forsaken
                  me!" Who, even among angels, could fully understand the mysterious horror of that
                  mortal agony, upon which the sun was not permitted to look! or who can tell
                     that<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC6388-00000055"/> the darkness which overspread the
                  whole land was not a merciful veil to hide from all nature the terrors of that
                  hour, when "his visage was more marred than any man, and his form more than the
                  sons of men?"</p>
               <p>How awful the instruction conveyed to the watching spirits who beheld that
                  sacrifice! How terrible appeared the justice of God, who when He saw guilt imputed
                  to his beloved Son, spared Him not! How difficult the work of restoring the
                  sinner, in which the will of the Almighty, who made the heavens and the earth by
                  the word of the breath of his mouth, seemed not alone sufficient; which demanded
                  on the part of Deity, plan, labor, and sacrifice! for in such a work, had volition
                  only been employed, it is not irreverent to say Omnipotence might have spoken, and
                  it would <emph>not</emph> have been done; might have commanded, and it would
                     <emph>not</emph> have stood fast! That man might be saved it was necessary that
                  the energies of the Godhead should be tasked. The treasury of heaven must be
                  emptied for our ransom som. The Eternal Son must forsake the bosom of the Father,
                  strip himself of the glory that He had with Him before the world was, stoop to
                  take upon Himself the form of a servant, and become obedient unto death—even the
                  death of the cross—before the gift of eternal life could be bestowed on a fallen
                  race. He must be made sin for us, who knew no sin, before we could be made the
                  righteousness of God in Him.</p>
               <p>Nor was this most transcendent manifestation of love, by Him whose name and whose
                  being is Love—unwitnessed by apostate spirits. It was their hour, and the power of
                  darkness: <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>The hour of Hell's rejoicing,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">When mighty hordes, set free,</l>
                        <l>Proclaim o'er a world's ruin</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Infernal jubilee;</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And we cannot conceive them to have beheld unmoved the unutterable condescension
                  of our incarnate Saviour. When they sinned, they were instantly and forever
                     expelled<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC6388-00000056"/> pelled from the light of
                  God's presence. No mediator appeared to receive for them the stroke of justice
                  upon his own head; no bleeding Lamb of God offered up a propitiation for their
                  iniquity; no Spirit had been commissioned to put new hearts into their bosoms
                  filled with despair. Even though they understood not the height and depth of the
                  mercy of God, they could not but know, from the assurances Jesus had given to his
                  disciples, and from the sure promise of God which had been the theme of psalmist
                  and prophet through all the ages of the Jewish dispensation—that the tremendous
                  scene of the crucifixion was but the prelude to some wonderful triumph of divine
                  mercy; that the hour was at hand when the great prediction, "The seed of the woman
                  shall bruise the serpent's head," was to be accomplished. In the midst of their
                  exultation that human wickedness had reached so appalling a height, they must have
                  been thrilled with a foretaste of coming doom, and with terror in the prospect of
                  the promised resurrection, and the final expulsion of Satan from his ancient
                  domain.</p>
               <p>That most marvellous and glorious of human events—the resurrection of the Saviour,
                  was witnessed by angels, some of whom became visible to mortal eyes. The
                  appearance of the celestial messenger, with "countenance like lightning," who
                  descended from heaven while the earth quaked, and rolled back the stone from the
                  door of the sepulchre—striking senseless the keepers with the terror of his
                  presence—and of those who sat within the tomb, and announced to the wondering
                  women that their Master was risen, was an expression of the interest taken in the
                  scene by all the host of heaven. Eyes unsealed by faith might have seen the
                  regions of earth and air thronged by countless myriads, whose joy, when the rising
                  Son of God forsook the tomb, burst forth and filled heaven and earth with the
                  anthem of praise. The scene of our Lord's ascension was attended in like manner.
                  What imagination can picture the splendors of that august procession<pb
                     n="100-101" xml:id="VAC6388-00000057"/> cession—the escort of the Lord of glory
                  to his throne on high! when the eternal pillars of heaven were shaken by the
                  exulting song hymned by seraph harps—"Lift up your heads, O ye gates, and be ye
                  lift up, ye everlasting doors, and the King of glory shall come in!" Two of the
                  heavenly multitude remained to give consolation to his bereaved disciples.</p>
               <p>Another of the mysteries of redemption into which angels desire to look, is the
                  work of the Holy Spirit. It was not enough that Christ should expiate human guilt
                  by his death; it was not enough that a perfect righteousness should be provided,
                  in which man might be presented spotless before the presence of God's glory. The
                  Spirit that at the creation had moved upon the face of the formless deep, bringing
                  light out of darkness, was to move over a darkness deeper than ancient night—a
                  chaos wilder than that of the primitive elements. He was to produce a new moral
                  creation in the regeneration of the soul of man; to quicken the dead in sin —and
                  enable that which is born of God to overcome the world. Man's fallen nature is
                  governed by a principle of selfishness which shuts him out from the only
                  satisfying source of happiness; the Spirit takes away the heart of stone,
                  enlightens him in the knowledge of God, shows him the way of salvation through a
                  Mediator; unites him by faith to the Saviour, and enables him to exercise his new
                  faculties. The sinner seeks no longer his own gratification, but devotes himself
                  to the service of God, relying for acceptance on the merits of Christ. This new
                  birth, as it is termed in Scripture, is caused alone "by the will of God." No laws
                  that we know of govern his volitions. The emblem of the Spirit is the wind; of
                  which none can say whence it cometh nor whither it goeth. Other works of the Deity
                  are regulated by general laws; here his sovereignty is apparent; and none can say
                  unto Him "What doest Thou?"</p>
               <p>How interesting an object to the angels must be a redeemed sinner! They behold<pb
                     n="102-103" xml:id="VAC6388-00000058"/> him born in a state of estrangement
                  from his Maker, going astray from his birth, and following headlong the
                  propensities of his depraved nature. Reason and conscience warn him in vain; in
                  vain revelation speaks to him; he listens not to the voice of the charmer,
                  charming never so wisely. He is guilty, corrupt, miserable; but the abhorrence
                  with which holy beings would naturally regard him, is mingled with a strange
                  interest. Fallen as he is, he may yet be recovered. Though outcast and rebellious,
                  for him Christ died. Poor, and blind, and wretched, he may yet be an heir of
                  heaven, a joint heir with Christ. In bondage and darkness, he may yet be called to
                  light and liberty. Degraded now below the level of apostate spirits, he may yet be
                  placed on an equality with the highest of created beings; such is the manner of
                  love the Father hath bestowed upon those he hath given to his Son, that they too
                  should be called the sons of God. At the time appointed in the divine purpose, the
                  Holy Spirit arrests him in his course towards destruction. The rebel dies unto
                  sin, and being "risen with Christ," seeks henceforward those things which are
                  above, living a life of faith on the Son of God. Then commences the conflict which
                  can terminate only at death. "The flesh lusteth against the spirit and the spirit
                  against the flesh." When he would do good, evil is present with him. He finds
                  another law in his members, warring against the law in his mind, and is often
                  constrained to cry out with the apostle—"O wretched man that I am, who shall
                  deliver me from the body of this death?" But "greater is He that is with him than
                  he which is of the world." The principle of faith, implanted by grace, is still
                  triumphant; and he is enabled, having put on the whole armor of God, to withstand
                  in the evil day, and having done all, to stand. He wrestles against principalities
                  and powers—and spiritual wickedness in high places;—but is made a conqueror, and
                  more than conqueror through Him that loved him. Well may it be said<pb n="104-105"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000059"/> of those who are finally saved, "these are they who
                  came out of great tribulation." "A brave spirit," says Seneca, "in strife with
                  adversity, is a glorious spectacle, even for the gods." How much more so, when the
                  struggle is maintained, not with physical evil, but with the prince of this world
                  and the powers of darkness, and the subtle and desperate wickedness of the natural
                  heart; when the enemies of the soul are so powerful and malignant that the
                  interposition of Omnipotence is necessary to vanquish them! If the battle was
                  great, and the victory glorious, when the deities of heathen mythology descended
                  to mingle in the combat on the plains of Ilium, how much more when the true God of
                  the universe takes part! If the conflict in which the destinies of kingdoms were
                  involved was worthy the admiration of mankind, how much more that in which are
                  involved the destinies of an immortal soul!</p>
               <p>The conjunction between Christ and his people, on which is founded the equity of
                  his suffering in their stead, and of their being rewarded for his righteousness,
                  is another of the mysteries of godliness, plainly declared in Scripture. It is
                  represented always by the most intimate relations among men. Sometimes he is
                  called the Husband of the church; sometimes the relation is compared to that
                  existing between the head and the members, or the vine and its branches. The
                  reality of this union is constantly insisted on; and its necessity most strongly
                  inculcated. "Without me," says our Saviour, "ye can do nothing." "If a man abide
                  not in me, he is cast forth as a branch, and is withered." Believers are
                  collectively represented as one body, animated by one and the same spirit; Christ
                  is said to dwell in them by his Spirit, as a new principle of spiritual life. As
                  by natural life the soul is conscious of perceptions, desires and enjoyments, so
                  by virtue of this new life, it becomes susceptible of new desires, impressions and
                  enjoyments. The objects about which these new faculties are exercised, are far
                  superior to the objects that formerly interested it; for they<pb n="106-107"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000060"/> are divine and eternal. And what is more agreeable
                  to reason than to suppose the soul's relation to any object the more intimate, the
                  more noble and excellent the faculties engaged? What object more worthy of
                  contemplation than the perfections and works of an all-sufficient God? What
                  capacity of the creature more exalted than that of knowing, loving and enjoying
                  this Infinite Being, in whom all fulness of knowledge and bliss resides? This
                  chief and inmost capacity of the soul lies nearest its essence. While this is not
                  in exercise, the end of being is frustrated and happiness impossible; for the
                  fleeting joy temporal objects afford deserves not the name. When the believer
                  becomes united to Christ, he is quickened by life derived from the living Head.
                  Then does he experience what is expressively termed in Scripture "the life of
                  God." Imperfect though his perceptions may be, he has yet some conception of the
                  mysterious meaning of the Redeemer's prayer for his people:</p>
               <p>"That they all may be one—as thou, Father, art in me, and I in Thee, that they
                  also may be one in us."</p>
               <p>To those who object against the reality of such a union, that it is
                  incomprehensible, it may be answered that the union between the soul and body is
                  equally so. Who can tell how mind acts upon matter? yet the Scriptures teach us
                  that the believer depends as entirely on the Son of God for power to perform the
                  functions of spiritual life, as our physical frame upon the animating soul. "For
                  we are members of his body, of his flesh and of his bones," says the apostle. He
                  is also not only the exemplar, but the cause of our resurrection. "Because I live,
                  ye shall live also." Believers shall be raised from the dead, not, like the
                  wicked, by the mere power of God, but by virtue of that inextinguishable principle
                  of spiritual life derived from Christ, and implanted in them. "If the Spirit of
                  Him that raised up Jesus from the dead dwell in you, He that raised up Christ from
                  the dead shall also quicken<pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC6388-00000061"/> your mortal
                  bodies <emph>by his Spirit that dwelleth in you.</emph>"</p>
               <p>The objection that Christ is too distant from us for vital union, amounts to
                  nothing. In his divine nature he is ever continually present. By his quickening
                  Spirit uniting us to Himself, the actions of his human nature and ours become
                  reciprocally imputed. He assumes the guilt of our sins; we stand invested in his
                  immaculate righteousness. What closer relation can be conceived of than such an
                  one? Nor is this union contrary to the order of God's works, or the symmetry of
                  the universe. Is not the world made up of systems, the lesser constituting a part
                  of larger ones?—and is it unreasonable to conclude that the same harmonious
                  alliances may exist in the intellectual, as in the natural world?—What saith the
                  Scripture? "Ye also, as lively stones, are built up a spiritual house." "Built
                  upon the foundation of the apostles and prophets, Jesus Christ himself being the
                  chief corner-stone. In whom all the building, fitly framed together gether,
                  groweth unto a holy temple in the Lord." So also believers are called the
                  household and family of God; the assembly of the first born; the whole body—of
                  which Christ is the Head, communicating nourishment—"fitly joined together and
                  compacted by that which every joint supplieth; according to the effectual working
                  in the measure of every part, making increase of the body unto the edifying of
                  itself in love." (Eph. iv. 16.)</p>
               <p>Not only is there a natural and moral, but also a federal union between Christ and
                  his people. Adam was the federal head of the whole human race, and in him mankind
                  apostatized from God, and became outcast from his favor. The second Adam, the Lord
                  Jesus Christ, is the federal Head of his church. He is the representative and
                  surety of all who believe in Him; and it is <emph>in consequence</emph> of this
                  federal relation that the mystical union before spoken of takes place—when the
                  believer is actually, by faith, implanted in Him.</p>
               <pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC6388-00000062"/>
               <p>A lesson of vast importance may be drawn from what the Scriptures teach on this
                  subject. While "all Heaven is represented as stirred," shall men, who are chiefly
                  concerned in this great plan of restoration, be the only beings in the Creator's
                  universe, who regard it with indifference? Yet such is too surely the case. That
                  plan, with the Triune God, was, as we may well conceive, the favorite scheme in
                  the counsels of eternity—being the greatest evolution of the Divine character, the
                  brightest manifestation of the Divine perfections. For this purpose was Earth, the
                  theatre of events so mighty, called into existence; and for a series of ages was
                  Redemption made the subject of prophecies and providences. Angels behold these
                  things with adoring admiration, and desire to know more of them; devils toil to
                  frustrate the scheme, filled with astonishment and envy at beholding Him who
                  "spared not the angels that sinned," thus planning and accomplishing, at so vast
                  an expenditure, the restoration of man. How then shall we escape, if we neglect so
                  great salvation? If we reject the call and offers of mercy purchased by the
                  Redeemer's blood, there remains "no further sacrifice for sins." If, though
                  sensible of our ruined condition, we still cling to temporal vanities—what
                  stronger motives can be urged to win us from them? If fear of the wrath of God—if
                  the sight of his compassion and love—if gratitude for his unspeakable gift cannot
                  move us—if the dread of eternal misery or the hope of eternal life have no
                  effect—the treasury of heaven affords no other bribe to lure us—the armory of
                  heaven no keener weapon to pierce the stubborn heart. Then indeed, the hardness of
                  man's heart—the madness and folly of impenitent unbelievers, may be another ground
                  of wonder to the angels. Impenitent man incurs a guilt even deeper than that of
                  the fallen spirits; for lost as they are, they never despised the voice of mercy.
                  They never turned away from a Saviour, nor did despite to the Spirit of grace.</p>
               <pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC6388-00000063"/>
               <p>May we in time be made wise unto salvation, and taught to seek the gift of the
                  Spirit, which God hath promised to those who ask it——that He may enable us to
                  receive with earnestness—to believe with the whole heart—to know deeply and
                  practically those things which belong to our eternal peace!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>IV. ANGELIC RELATION TO THE WORK OF CHRIST.</head>
               <p>THE motives which impel the holy angels to the rendering of services to men, are
                  sufficiently obvious; the most ardent love to their Creator, and zeal for his
                  glory. In obedience to his will, no duty can be too lowly or too burdensome for
                  them to undertake with joyful alacrity. Nor can we wonder at their interest in the
                  inhabitants of earth. "The footsteps of God manifest in the flesh, have been upon
                  the narrow spot of ground we occupy; and small though our mansion be amid the orbs
                  and the systems of immensity, hither hath the King of glory bent his mysterious
                  way, and entered the tabernacle of men, and in the disguise of a<pb n="114-115"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000064"/> servant did He sojourn for years under the roof
                  which canopies our obscure and solitary world. Yes, it is but a twinkling atom in
                  the peopled infinity of worlds around it;—but look to the moral grandeur of the
                  transaction, and not to the material extent of the field on which it was executed;
                  and from the retirement of our dwelling-place, there may issue forth such a
                  display of the Godhead, as will circulate the glories of his name among all his
                  worshippers."</p>
               <p>Angelic faculties are enlarged to comprehend more of the startling sublimity of
                  that plan by which the sinner is rescued from death and delivered from the bondage
                  of corruption—than can enter into human conception. The passage of every redeemed
                  soul "from the deep pit and miry clay of sin to a throne with Christ," furnishes
                  them with a grander subject of meditation, and tunes their harps to loftier songs
                  of praise, than the brightest glories of the created universe. Yet we cannot
                  overlook the intimations given us in Scripture, of a marvellous interlinking
                  linking of their destiny with ours in this work of grace; of personal relations to
                  it sustained by them, which bind them on their own account, to adoring gratitude
                  in its contemplation. Such passages, says Dr. Chalmers, "present a faint opening
                  through which may be seen some few traces of a wider and a nobler dispensation.
                  They bring before us a dim transparency, on the other side of which the images of
                  an obscure magnificence dazzle indistinctly upon the eye, and tell us that in the
                  economy of redemption, there is a grandeur commensurate to all that is known of
                  the other works and purposes of the Eternal." It will not be a seeking of
                  knowledge withheld from us, to inquire into this mystery of Divine goodness
                  revealed in the Bible, interpreting the meaning of the chorus of praise with which
                  the bending hierarchy of heaven join redeemed spirits in the cry—"Worthy is the
                  Lamb that was slain!"</p>
               <p>An article of much ability and learning appeared a few years since in the
                     "Southern<pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC6388-00000065"/> Presbyterian Review,"
                  published in South Carolina, designed to prove from the Sacred volume, that the
                  atonement of Christ introduced into the moral government of God <emph>the
                     principle of grace,</emph> "which avails to the confirmation of beings who are
                  holy, as well as to the redemption of beings who are fallen." I shall quote freely
                  from this article, giving an abstract of its argument to show that not only those
                  of our race who are saved, but other orders of beings, stand on the platform of
                  divine grace, introduced to them as well as to us through the Redeemer's work. By
                  this, it is maintained, "the holy angels have been confirmed in their original
                  holiness and bliss against all possible defection."</p>
               <p>The first proof adduced is the application of the term "elect" by the apostle to
                  the holy angels. Paul's injunction to Timothy is,—"I charge thee before God and
                  the Lord Jesus Christ and the elect angels," &amp;c. If we understand the word in
                  the same meaning as when applied to man, it must signify that they are chosen in
                  the purpose of God to stand fast in holiness. "As, in the one case, the decree of
                  election respects the redemption and sanctification of a being who is sinful, so
                  in the other case, the decree of election respects the security and steadfastness
                  of a being already holy."—"The elect of mankind are chosen out from a race lost in
                  sin and righteously condemned;"—"the elect angels are those chosen from the whole
                  angelic race to abide the period of their probation, then to be confirmed against
                  all possible defection; and they stand opposed to and are discriminated from
                  another portion of the same race, who failed in accomplishing their probation, and
                  were at once adjudged to the damnation of the pit."</p>
               <p>In the book of Job, good angels are called "sons of God"—because, says Bishop
                  Davenant, "they are adopted as sons for Christ's sake;" for He is the only Son. He
                  cannot understand election, either of men or angels, to be out of Christ. Edwards
                  ascribes the preservation of the angels from falling at the<pb n="118"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000066"/> time of Satan's rebellion, to the grace of the Son
                  of God, then manifested; and regards the period of Christ's ascension into heaven
                  as that of their final confirmation. One thing is certain; the term "elect,"
                  applied to them, denotes them taken from a class to be recipients of some special
                  favor. Being thus chosen, their election implies that their everlasting holiness
                  and happiness is secured.</p>
               <p>Again—in proof of the angels' confirmation in holiness, it is alleged that "the
                  offices which they discharge, are scarcely consistent with a present probationary
                  state. They were with Christ when on Mount Sinai He set up the typical
                  dispensation of Moses; they appeared at sundry times as messengers of Christ to
                  his church below; they heralded his birth when He appeared in the fullness of time
                  as the babe of Bethlehem; they ministered to Him after his long temptation in the
                  wilderness, and strengthened Him when fainting in the garden of Gethsemane; they
                  watched about his sepulchre, when He was laid in Joseph's new tomb; they first
                     witnessed<pb n=" (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6388-00000067"/>
                  <figure/>
                  <pb n="119" xml:id="VAC6388-00000068"/> nessed his resurrection to his wondering
                  and amazed disciples; they will fill his train of glory, and place his throne in
                  the clouds when He shall descend upon the earth for judgment. It is the voice of
                  an angel which shall proclaim by the solemn name of the existing God the end of
                  time; it is the trump of an archangel which shall wake the nations of the dead;
                  the angels will go forth as reapers, gathering the righteous into heaven, and
                  casting the wicked into unquenchable fire; they are now, and will ever be, those
                  elect angels, around Christ's throne in Heaven, praising Him as the blessed
                  Mediator, worshipping Him as God and the Lamb forever. It seems scarcely possible
                  that they should be so fully identified with Christ in his work of patience and of
                  power upon the earth, if there existed still a doubt of their steadfastness as
                  holy beings: and if they cannot fall, it must be only because they are graciously
                  secured by the power of God, and not by any necessity of their own natures. One
                  certain fact, however, concludes our faith in<pb n="120-121"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000069"/> this matter, and will be found in the sequel to
                  meet all the exigencies of the argument. It is undeniable that the destiny of
                  angels as well as of men will be unalterably fixed at the day of judgment. 'Know
                  ye not,' says the apostle, 'that we shall judge angels?' An evil spirit once
                  challenged Christ, 'art thou come hither to torment us before the time?' And Jude
                  says explicitly, the rebel angels are 'reserved in everlasting chains, under
                  darkness, unto the judgment of the great day.' Here, then, is palpable proof that
                  on this day of destiny the condition of angels will be irrevocably fixed. If not
                  before, <emph>then</emph> their probation must cease; the rebellious forever
                  doomed, the holy forever established. Now as their offices discharged in the
                  resurrection and final judgment are viewed in connection with their manifest
                  confirmation, the same or similar functions discharged by them from the beginning,
                  are presumptive of that confirmation, as far back, at least, as the history of our
                  own race. We care not, however, to press these speculations tions, as the careful
                  reader will soon see that any limit, however distant, which is placed upon their
                  probation, as for instance at the day of judgment, will sustain the argument we
                  design to construct."</p>
               <p>Another proof of the angels' confirmation is their recapitulation in Christ. "In
                  that mediatorial dominion which is given to the Son, the angels are included:
                  'that in the dispensation of the fullness of time He might gather together in one
                  all things in Christ, both which are in heaven and which are on earth.' All the
                  orders of holy angels, then, are included in Him, and He is made Head over all.
                  But can this be, unless those thus included are confirmed beyond the risk of
                  apostasy? If none among men are united to Christ save those who are fully
                  justified thereby, and their salvation infallibly secured, surely none among
                  angels can be united to the same blessed Head save those who are confirmed thereby
                  and they made equally secure. It is this gathering all things in Christ, which
                  makes up the greatness of his<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC6388-00000070"/>
                  mediatorial glory; and the loss of one thus gathered, either human or angelic,
                  cannot be affirmed without blasphemy. It would destroy the integrity, mar the
                  beauty, and dash the glory of the mystical body; the Mediator would not be
                  perfect, because of the lost member; the mystical Christ would sit upon his throne
                  a deformed and mutilated object, to praise whom would be the bitterest irony, to
                  worship whom would be most insulting mockery."</p>
               <p>The question next arises—"If the holy angels are now confirmed in their primitive
                  integrity, or if they shall be thus confirmed at the period of the general
                  judgment, (for the fact and not the date of their confirmation is alone
                  important,) the question arises, upon what principle are they confirmed? How comes
                  their probation ever to cease? Why should not their happiness be conditioned to
                  all eternity upon their good behavior? It is obvious this confirmation can proceed
                  upon no principle of mere law. All that law does, and from its very nature all it
                  can do, is simply to point out the course of duty, and to enforce its teaching by
                  an adequate sanction. All its blessings are necessarily conditional, suspended
                  upon the obedience rendered. Four brief words exhaust its vocabulary;
                  keep—live—break—die. These words it must utter to all, and through all
                  existence.</p>
               <p>"Now the moment we introduce a limitation and say, up to this period I am liable
                  to disobey, but beyond it I am secured against every contingency, a new principle
                  is introduced, which is distinct from law; a principle of grace. While a being is
                  upon probation, which is a dispensation of law simply, his future state is
                  conditioned upon his obedience. In his confirmed state, it is conditioned upon
                  nothing but the good pleasure of God, who wills him to be thenceforward an
                  infallibly perfect being. In the one case his eternal condition is suspended upon
                  something within himself: in the other case, upon something as palpably without
                  him, and external to him: which we take to be, in their<pb n="124-125"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000071"/> scriptural meaning, the essential difference
                  between the terms grace and law—grace and works."</p>
               <p>The writer then suggests an inquiry how this principle of grace supervenes upon a
                  legal dispensation. "The right answer to this question, if it can be rendered,
                  will conduct us into the interior of the gospel plan, open to us the unfailing
                  wealth of that word <emph>grace</emph> in its evangelic meaning; reveal to us the
                  very heart of Christianity. It will lead us to that hidden chamber where God not
                  only unveils the splendor of his holiness, but also the glory of his love—to that
                  curtained sanctuary where the glorious majesty of God embosomed in his mercy—the
                  brilliancy of the one mellowed by the softer radiance of the other—is the
                  Shechinah of the Temple on high."</p>
               <p>He proceeds to show that the way in which the principle of grace is introduced
                  into the moral government of God, by which beings under this government are
                  emancipated from the penal terrors essential to law —is the work of Christ. His
                  work magnified the law, and on a principle of compensation, made room for the
                  exercise of grace. "If one allege that to confirm an angel by grace will relax
                  law, we answer, not so: because this grace is not granted arbitrarily, but upon
                  the ground of a high service which has been done to law for the express purpose of
                  introducing this grace. There are, however, manifestly three essential conditions
                  to such a work, in order to make out the compensation required. First, it must be
                  wrought by a being who is able to magnify the law, and make it honorable; so as to
                  compensate for the partial violence done in setting aside the penal portion of the
                  law. Secondly, it must be wrought by a being who is able to make a more glorious
                  revelation of God than the law can do; so as to compensate for the glory
                  intercepted in the loss of the penalty. Thirdly, it must be the work of a being
                  who is not bound to law on his own account; so that his work may be a ground of
                  merit. If these conditions are<pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC6388-00000072"/> met, all
                  will admit grace is not exercised at the expense of law." This work, which is a
                  true ground of merit, is performed by Christ, whose obedience does more homage to
                  the law than the obedience of all creatures; on this may grace be predicated, and
                  confirmation, which is above law, and is due to grace alone, may secure the angels
                  forever. "What is the conclusion forced upon us, but that a real connection
                  subsists between the atonement of Christ and the confirmation of elect angels?</p>
               <p>"To all this there is one plausible objection which may be urged: to wit, that
                  Christ did not assume angelic nature, and perform this work in their legal stead.
                  This, however, was not necessary in their case: had they been sinful, as men are,
                  then the Saviour's work must have been for them, as well as for us, strictly
                  vicarious. A sinful being has no righteousness, in which to be accepted with God.
                  He must therefore have a righteous substitute, and the obedience of this
                  substitute can become his only by a strict legal imputation. But these, as holy
                  beings, are already accepted: all they require is simply an act of sovereignty,
                  yet of grace, which shall secure their present state. The only difficulty in the
                  case, (of course the difficulty is not real, as to God, but only apparent as to
                  us,) is the introduction of a new principle of government, the engrafting grace
                  upon law. The moment the principle is introduced, God may, in the exercise of
                  sovereignty, apply it to what holy beings He may please: He may be sovereign in
                  applying it to holy beings, as we know He is in applying it to sinful beings. This
                  difficulty, as we have seen, is met through Christ, by his atonement. Grace is
                  manifestly introduced and made a principle of the divine administration. The
                  extension of this principle from one to another class of beings who are without
                  sin, as it does not affect the integrity either of his nature or of his
                  government, creates no embarrassment in our minds; but we freely submit it to 'the
                     good<pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC6388-00000073"/> pleasure of Him who worketh all
                  things after the counsel of his own will.'"<ref rend="super" target="#note_002" xml:id="return_002">*</ref></p>
               
               <note place="foot" xml:id="note_002">
                  
                  <p><ref target="#return_002">*</ref>"But that out of his eternal and infinite goodness and love, purposing to
                     become a Creator and to communicate to his creatures, He ordained in his
                     eternal counsel that one person of the Godhead should be united to one nature,
                     and to one particular of his creatures: that so, in the person of the Mediator,
                     the true ladder might be fixed, whereby God might descend to his creatures, and
                     his creatures might ascend to God: so that God, by the reconcilement of the
                     Mediator, turning his countenance towards his creatures, though not in equal
                     light and degree, made way unto the dispensation of his most holy and secret
                     will: whereby some of his creatures might stand, and keep their state, others
                     might possibly fall, and be restored: and others might fall, and not be
                     restored to their estate, but yet remain in being, though under wrath and
                     corruption: all with respect to the Mediator: which is the great mystery and
                     perfect centre of all God's ways with his creatures, and unto which all his
                     other works and wonders but serve and refer."—<title>Lord Bacon's Confession of
                        Faith.</title>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <p>Thus, it is argued, the redemption of man opens the way to the universal
                  introduction of grace. "For the grace thus introduced cannot be confined to the
                  province where it is wrought out; but as all worlds were created for God's glory,
                  and grace is the highest manifestation of that glory, the grace purchased by
                  Christ is at once engrafted upon the whole government of God. Its application to
                  holy beings is circumstantially different, but just as real and necessary to their
                  confirmation as it can be to the redemption and justification of sinful
                  beings."</p>
               <p>The article further maintains that the mediatorial dominion of Christ over the
                  angels, proves not only their confirmation, but proves that this confirmation
                  proceeds upon a gracious relation sustained to his work. "In Ephesians it is
                  written—that in the dispensation of the fullness of times he might gather into one
                  all things in Christ, both <emph>which are in heaven</emph> and which are on
                  earth.' Again in the same Epistle: 'when he raised Him from the dead and set Him
                  at his own right hand in the heavenly places, far above all principality and power
                  and might and dominion, and every name that is named, not only in this world but
                  also in that which is<pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC6388-00000074"/> to come; and hath
                  put all things under his feet, and gave Him to be the Head over all things to the
                  church, which is his body, the fullness of Him which filleth all in all.' In this
                  passage, the testimony is exceedingly full: the angels are clearly designated by
                  the terms principality, power, might and dominion; all these are put under
                  Christ's feet, that he may be Head over all to the church; and this church, which
                  is called his body, must include elect angels as well as elect men, since it is
                  the fullness of him which filleth all in all. Further on, we read: 'For this cause
                  I bow my knees to the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, of whom <emph>the whole
                     family in heaven and earth</emph> is named,' which surely sets forth the actual
                  incorporation into one body of redeemed sinners and elect angels, and their unity
                  as consisting in a common relation to Jesus Christ. In the Epistle to the Hebrews
                  the Apostle writes, 'thou hast put all things in subjection under his feet; for in
                  that he put all in subjection under him, he left nothing that is not put under
                  Him.' Again, the Apostle Peter writes: 'by the resurrection of Jesus Christ, who
                  is gone into heaven and is on the right hand of God; angels, principalities and
                  powers being made subject unto Him.' In the Epistle to the Philippians it is
                  written, 'God hath highly exalted Him and given Him a name which is above every
                  name, that at the name of Jesus every knee should bow, of things in heaven and
                  things in earth, and things under the earth." Lastly, in Colossians, it is
                  recorded: 'Having made peace through the blood of his cross, by Him to reconcile
                  all things unto Himself; by Him, I say, whether they be things on earth, or things
                  in heaven.' These passages clearly establish two facts: first, that Christ rules
                  and governs the angels; and secondly, that this dominion is not his essential
                  dominion which belongs to Him of right as one of the Persons of the Trinity, but
                  his mediatorial dominion, which He enjoys as God-man. Now, the question arises,
                  how obtains the Mediator this ascendency over the angels?<pb n="132-133"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000075"/> We easily comprehend how Christ is Head and King of
                  the saints, because He redeemed them. His mediatorial power over these is founded
                  strictly upon a mediatorial relation to them. But how is He the Head and King of
                  the angels, who, not being sinners, were not the objects of redemption?"</p>
               <p>The answer is,—that there exists a substantial relation between Christ and the
                  angels, in virtue of which He is crowned their Head. "Having, by his work of
                  obedience and suffering, introduced the principle of grace, God, in his
                  sovereignty, applies it to the confirmation of angels who are holy. The elect of
                  these, as well as the elect of men, are given to Christ, because He is the author
                  of the grace by which they both stand. He is made the Head of both: they enjoy
                  this grace because of their relation to Him; and upon this is erected the whole
                  structure of his mediatorial empire.</p>
               <p>"Our final argument for basing the confirmation of elect angels upon the grace
                  wrought out by Christ, is drawn from the worship which they render to him as
                  Mediator. In Hebrews, we have this record; 'when He bringeth in the first-begotten
                  into the world, He saith, let all the angels of God worship Him.' Evidently, this
                  worship is commanded to Him not merely as the Son, but as the Son Incarnate. In
                  the book of revelation, the rapt prophet describes his vision of the worship in
                  Heaven thus: 'and I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the
                  throne, and the beasts and the elders; and the number of them was ten thousand
                  times ten thousand and thousands of thousands; saying, with a loud voice, worthy
                  is the Lamb that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and
                  honor and glory and blessing: and every creature which is in heaven and on the
                  earth, and under the earth, and such as are in the sea, and all that are in them,
                  heard I saying, blessing and honor and glory and power, be unto Him that sitteth
                  upon the throne, and unto the Lamb forever.' What is the special foundation of
                  this special worship of the Mediator<pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC6388-00000076"/>
                  diator? Let it be observed that one of the main constituents of worship is a sense
                  of obligation. Worship, in its proper signification, is the religious homage to
                  one who is supreme, of a dependent creature; who, feeling his obligation, at the
                  same time delights in the being whom he serves and trusts. Angels and men worship
                  Jehovah, because He is supreme, and they are his creatures; this relation of
                  creatureship creates the obligation of worship. Now, if angels and men all worship
                  the Mediator, it is because He is supreme, and they are dependent upon Him. As
                  Mediator, redeemed sinners are dependent on Him for grace and holiness; hence, the
                  mediatorial relation is the ground of their mediatorial worship. If the angels do
                  not hold some analogous relation, being dependent equally for grace and the
                  security of their holiness, then it will become those who deny it to explain the
                  difficulty as to angelic worship of the Mediator.</p>
               <p>"The subject is not wholly speculative; for it suggests noble thoughts of God and
                  his government. How vast the scale on which He projects his plans! With what
                  variety of wisdom has He framed the universe, and interwoven principle with
                  principle, gold and silver threads, into the web of his government! How sublime,
                  and yet how lovely, is the work of Christ! Like the rainbow, spanning the
                  hemisphere, it reveals the perfections of God, as though prismatic, which,
                  combined, make up the great glory of the great God. Who can fail to adore that
                  Being who by his own pains and grief constructs upon the basis of an immutable
                  law, a platform of grace—the orchestra upon which "an innumerable company of
                  angels,' joined in concert with 'the general assembly and church of the
                  first-born,' cause the arches of heaven to reverberate with their glad
                  hosannas!</p>
               <p>"There is one matter, in connection with which the subject of this article may be
                  maturely pondered. We allude to the origin of moral evil. God certainly had power
                  to prevent the introduction of sin; it is an awful<pb n="136-137"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000077"/> ful blur upon the glory of creation; it occasions
                  the destruction of many, many thousands; how, then, came it to pass? Many able
                  divines have tried their strength at breaking the shell of this mystery. One thing
                  we learn from the preceding pages; that the introduction of sin is but a single
                  link, though important, in a chain which girdles the universe and lengthens out
                  through an illimitable eternity. In viewing the divine economy in its detached
                  parts, we are sometimes seriously posed by local difficulties in the system; but
                  in so far as we take in the scope of his government, these difficulties are
                  dwarfed, till they fall out of view. At least we learn that all our embarrassment
                  proceeds from ignorance; and that if more enlarged views even now relieve our
                  minds partially of pressure, when we reach a state of perfect knowledge, we shall
                  discover the entire symmetry of the divine administration. Let the Christian
                  reader especially reflect, that if the human race is chosen, as a burnished
                  reflector, to throw the light of divine grace upon the universe, it is the
                  privilege of each believer to be a point upon its polished surface. Let not a spot
                  dim his lustre; for no more solemn, yet animating reflection can suggest itself to
                  him than this, that in time and through eternity, he is an exponent of God's
                  matchless grace to a ravished universe."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="138" xml:id="VAC6388-00000078"/>
               <head>V. DEPARTED SPIRITS.</head>
               <p>IN connection with the subject of the watching and ministry on earth of those
                  bright spirits who surround the throne of God in perpetual worship, occurs a
                  question deeply interesting to every one of us. Have the spirits of the dead the
                  same privilege with those of a superior order? May those who have left this world
                  still linger around the scenes of their former joy or cares, and observe the
                  progress of human life? May they hover over those whom they loved, who cherished
                  them while living, and mourned them when taken away, with a knowledge of all that
                  concerns them, and with an interest unchilled by the hand of the great
                     destroyer<pb n=" (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6388-00000079"/>
                  <figure/>
                  <pb n="139" xml:id="VAC6388-00000080"/> stroyer? Or is the darkness of the grave a
                  veil between them and the living, which they cannot penetrate? When the breath is
                  expelled from the clay tenement, does the soul become suddenly unconscious of all
                  that previously employed its faculties, losing, in the new and higher life, all
                  perceptions which pertained to a previous existence? The inquiry opens a wide
                  field for speculation. We might ask, is it rational to believe that in a more
                  exalted state of being, the powers of the soul will be more circumscribed than in
                  the present? And does not the idea of retribution in a future life involve the
                  certainty, not only that the memory shall be unclouded, but that the perceptions
                  shall be quickened and the apprehension enlarged to a view of the bearings of past
                  occurrences on the present and the future in human affairs? Without venturing to
                  discuss the subject in a metaphysical point of view, let us, in all humility,
                  search into what it has seemed good to the Holy Spirit to reveal in the sure
                  word.</p>
               <p>The existence of the soul in a state of separation<pb n="140-141"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000081"/> ration from the body, is clearly revealed in
                  Scripture. "They all live unto God," is the declaration of our Saviour when
                  speaking of departed saints; and "the God of Abraham, of Isaac and of Jacob" "is
                  not the God of the dead, but of the living." "This day shalt thou be with me in
                  paradise," was his dying promise to the penitent thief. St. Paul had "a desire to
                  depart and be with Christ, which is far better" than to abide in the flesh;
                  "knowing that being absent from the body we are present with the Lord;" and that
                  when "our earthly house of this tabernacle is dissolved, we have a building of
                  God, a house not made with hands, eternal in the heavens."</p>
               <p>From these and other passages of like import, we know that the spirits of
                  justified persons abide with the Lord Jesus Christ. To them He has come, that He
                  might receive them to Himself; they are his special charge; to his keeping,
                  believers, like the martyr Stephen, commit their departing souls. And as He is
                  ever attended by his innumerable company pany of holy angels, it follows that
                  these are the companions of "the spirits of just men made perfect," for they are
                  named by the apostle with "the general assembly and church of the first-born,
                  which are written in heaven." The angel who communed with the Apostle John in the
                  Apocalypse, represents himself as the fellow-servant "of thy brethren the
                  prophets, and of them which keep the sayings of this book."</p>
               <p>In this lovely companionship, can we suppose that the knowledge of the manifold
                  wisdom of God acquired by angelic study of the history of the church on earth, is
                  denied to human spirits? that the dealings of Christ with his people, their
                  experiences, their struggles, their trials, and their triumphs, so instructive to
                  angels, are a closed book to them? Having seen so much, during their mortal
                  sojourn, of "the mystery which from the beginning of the world hath been hid in
                  God," is their eager desire to behold more clearly, met by a total blank—while
                  their elder brethren, to whom it is expressly said<pb n="142-143"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000082"/> they are made equal, may read the great lesson, and
                  day and night find themes for new ascriptions of praise? It is impossible to
                  believe that such is the case. Inasmuch as with "the voice of many angels round
                  about the throne" is blended the new song of those who are privileged to say—"Thou
                  wast slain, and hast redeemed us to God by thy blood out of every kindred and
                  tongue and people and nation; and has made us unto our God kings and priests; and
                  we shall reign on the earth"—we are warranted to believe that they are in no
                  respect inferior in privileges to the angels, and may, like them, visit the earth
                  to behold what the Lord doeth for his pleasure, among its inhabitants. How could
                  they "reign on the earth" without a full knowledge of all its affairs, or why
                  should they exult in such an anticipation, if at the stroke of death they had
                  suddenly become strangers to the militant church, and could no longer sympathise
                  in her dangers, nor rejoice in her victories? Nay more—if there is joy in heaven
                  among the angels over one sinner that repenteth—are the spirits of justified men
                  excluded from the joy—arising out of their interest in individuals—as well as
                  founded on love to Him who hath redeemed them, which must be so great an accession
                  to their happiness?</p>
               <p>In the Revelation, the holy apostles and prophets are called upon to rejoice, with
                  the inhabitants of heaven, over the destruction of mystical Babylon. In reference
                  to another remarkable passage, vi. 9—11, the author of "Principalities and Powers"
                  says—"How could the souls under the altar know that their blood was not yet
                  avenged on them that dwell on the earth? And why, if forever divorced from all the
                  ties of mortality, shonld they express impatience for the arrival of that time?
                  Assuredly not from any vengeful feeling; such is forbidden in just men in the
                  flesh, and cannot reside in the spirits of just men made perfect. Besides—the
                  generation on whom their blood was to be avenged, was probably not the same as the
                  generation who shed it. We can<pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC6388-00000083"/> only
                  understand it as expressing a fervent desire for the speedy arrival of that day of
                  vengeance which we know synchronizes with the year of the redeemed. Those souls
                  beheld and mourned over the desolate state of the Lord's still persecuted
                  church—the devoted little flock to which they also belonged; and knowing that He
                  would at once put all enemies under his feet, and exalt his church to glory and
                  everlasting peace, they pleaded for the hastening of that promised day."</p>
               <p>If this vision of the apostle may be said to be figurative, we cannot suppose it
                  calculated to lead to an erroneous inference. We might as well say that because
                  the phrase "Abraham's bosom" is figurative, we have no right to believe that the
                  beggar was really and truly carried by angels to the rest enjoyed by the
                  patriarch, the heavenly happiness represented so often under the emblem of a
                  feast. In this parable, the soul of the rich man is represented as having not lost
                  cognizance of earthly matters, since he knows that his brethren continue
                  impenitent.</p>
               <p>When the wicked Hebrew monarch, in despair of succor from heaven, went to the
                  woman at Endor, to search into the future by means of her divinations, he demanded
                  that she should bring up Samuel; and though the witch was evidently surprised at
                  the result of her incantations—it is declared that the visitant from the unseen
                  world was no other than the prophet. For a wise purpose he was commissioned to
                  appear and denounce the doom of Saul. His language does not imply ignorance of
                  what has befallen the monarch and his people. "And the Lord hath done unto him as
                  he spake by me; for the Lord hath rent the kingdom out of thine hand, and given it
                  to thy neighbor, even to David: because thou obeyedst not the voice of the Lord,
                  nor executedst his fierce wrath upon Amalek, therefore hath the Lord done this
                  thing unto thee this day." Then follows the dread assurance<pb n="146-147"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000084"/> of his coming fate. Who can read the scriptural
                  account of this mysterious transaction, and believe that Samuel was merely the
                  unconscious clod through whose lips flowed the words of prophecy—or a phantom
                  raised to terrify the superstitious king?</p>
               <p>The apostle, in the epistle to the Hebrews, exhorts his brethren to be "followers
                  of them who, through faith and patience, inherit the promises;" implying the
                  certainty that those who had been faithful to the end, had entered into the rest
                  prepared as their reward. The inheritance of the promises, however, for which they
                  had labored, waited and suffered, in the obedience of faith, could not be such,
                  without a remembrance of the promise given in the days of their sojourn on earth,
                  and shadowed forth in the religious services of their dispensation. Imperfect this
                  fruition of happiness must be, without a knowledge of the progress of the kingdom
                  appointed, in its own apportioned sphere; without the faculty of observing the
                  sure approach of the consummation of earthly things—when Messiah shall reign over
                  all the nations of the earth.</p>
               <p>The most remarkable incident recorded in the New Testament, from which we may draw
                  instruction pertaining to this subject, is the august scene that took place upon
                  the mount of transfiguration. There, while, as the Redeemer prayed, "the fashion
                  of his countenance was altered, and his raiment was white and glistering," "and
                  his face did shine as the sun"—there appeared to the wondering eyes of the
                  disciples two beings in human form, yet evidently more than mortal, for they
                  "appeared in glory," and were recognized as the great lawgiver and prophet of
                  Israel—Moses and Elias. The latter had indeed been taken to heaven in the body;
                  but Moses had died, and had been entombed, and cannot be supposed to have been
                  favored beyond the common lot of believers. We know not how it was that he came in
                  a form visible to Peter, and James, and John; but we cannot, for a moment,
                  question the fact that it was really Moses who stood on the<pb n="148-149"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000085"/> mount and talked with our Lord. The subject of the
                  conversation between these eminent servants of God and the incarnate Mediator, is
                  made known to be the same which doubtless occupied the attention of the angels;
                  which was the theme of expectation and marvel and praise to the universe of
                  sinless creatures; they "spake of his decease which He should accomplish at
                  Jerusalem." This is certainly conclusive proof that they were neither ignorant of,
                  nor indifferent to, the mighty event that was impending, nor to the interests of
                  mankind involved therein; that they were acquainted with the great plan of
                  redemption unfolded through a succession of ages, and by events that had occurred,
                  in great part, since their departure from this life; acquainted with the purpose
                  of the Son of God in submitting to the humiliation of wearing the likeness of
                  sinful flesh, and with the necessity that his life of obedience to the law should
                  be terminated by a sufferance of its penalty. His decease was that "which He
                  should accomplish," not as the other children of Adam fulfil their inevitable
                  destiny, but as the Conqueror over sin, the Captain of our salvation should put
                  the finishing stroke to his great and godlike work, through death destroying him
                  that had the power of death. From their evident possession of this knowledge, and
                  the privilege of revisiting this world, we may reasonably infer that the like
                  knowledge is conferred on all glorified saints, and that they too enjoy the
                  liberty of visiting, though not in visible form, their brethren who are yet in a
                  state of seclusion.</p>
               <p>Among the wonders that marked the finishing of Messiah's work, it is recorded that
                  after his resurrection, "many bodies of the saints which slept arose, and came out
                  of the graves," "and went into the holy city, and appeared unto many." Can we
                  suppose that the happy spirits returned to those bodies wholly uninformed of the
                  stupendous event, in celebration of which the bonds of their prison-house had been
                  loosed? Or supposing the "many" to whom they appeared<pb n="150-151"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000086"/> ed, more worthy of such an honor than others, can
                  we imagine them destitute of discernment and discrimination, or divorced entirely
                  from their relations to the humanity not yet admitted "within the vail"? Whether
                  the preference was caused by superior sanctity in the individuals favored with the
                  vision, or by peculiar relations sustained to the deceased, it in either case
                  supports our argument. And when the King of glory made his entrance through the
                  everlasting gates, were these risen saints, who doubtless ascended in his train,
                  ignorant of the occasion of the triumph that filled all heaven with joy and
                  hallelujahs of praise!</p>
               <p>Many obscure intimations scattered through the Hebrew Scriptures, allude to the
                  state of departed spirits. The fathers are spoken of as abiding "under the shadow
                  of the Almighty," in Him who is "the dwelling-place of his people" "through all
                  generations." They are said, observes an eminent writer, to "dwell in his
                  tabernacle," or "stand in his pavilion;" and they are "the expectants of Jehovah,"
                  continually "watching the movements of his hand." In the eleventh chapter of the
                  epistle to the Hebrews, the apostle describes those justified ones who had endured
                  trials and lived a life of obedience through faith—as waiting for those believers
                  who were yet to be gathered in, before they could receive the fullness of the
                  promise, and be made perfect. It was their part to look forward to the "better
                  thing" God had provided for the faithful in the latter days; and in their state of
                  release from the bondage and corruption of sin, they compass about the body of
                  Christians on earth as a great cloud of witnesses; the force of their combined
                  testimony to the truth being noted as an incentive to use the most earnest and
                  strenuous endeavors to win the same prize that crowned their course. From the
                  tenor of many passages in Scripture, we are therefore justified in believing that
                  the spirits of those who "sleep in Jesus" do watch over the elect in this world;
                  and that a true and indissoluble union exists between the members of Christ's<pb
                     n="152-153" xml:id="VAC6388-00000087"/> mystical body, both in heaven and upon
                  earth, so that those who have entered upon their inheritance cannot attain to the
                  perfection to which they are destined, until those who yet struggle with the
                  powers of evil have also been made "more than conquerors through Him that loved
                  them." The same truth shines in the apocalyptic visions—whenever the spirits of
                  the redeemed are mentioned as taking part with angels in their exultation at the
                  triumph of the church—the spouse of the Lamb, who is arraying herself in fine
                  linen—the righteousness of saints.</p>
               <p>We know nothing of the condition of the spirits of wicked men; but have no reason
                  to suppose they enjoy such high privileges. They are spoken of as "in prison;"
                  reserved to the judgment of the great day; and though it appears probable that
                  they are not altogether ignorant of occurrences on earth, they can have no such
                  interest as the other class in watching the progress of events. To them the
                  revolving of the cycle of time can bring but increase of woe; the coming of the
                  day of redemption will be the advent of the day of vengeance. We have no
                  scriptural ground for believing that they are permitted to join the legions of
                  Satan in active opposition to the diffusion of the gospel.</p>
               <p>How solemn and interesting are the reflections growing out of meditation on this
                  subject! With what intense sympathy and interest must the spirits of the blessed
                  dead contemplate the advance of their Christian friends in the path of obedience!
                  What encouragement to perseverance, when we know that we labor under the scrutiny
                  of so vast "a cloud of witnesses!" And what comfort may the mourner take to his
                  heart, in the thought that he is yet tenderly watched over by the loved and
                  lost—who now sustain to him a new relationship, more endearing than the closest
                  ties of kindred or friendship—being members of the same body, and having their
                  eternal glory and happiness bound up with his own in Him after whom the whole
                  family in heaven and earth is named!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="154-155" xml:id="VAC6388-00000088"/>
               <head>VI. APOSTATE SPIRITS.</head>
               <p>THE Bible informs us of the existence of a class of beings, fallen from their
                  original estate of purity and happiness, who are engaged in active rebellion
                  against their Maker, and are under an irreversible doom of condemnation. Their
                  relations to man are those of cruel and implacable hostility. While the glorious
                  exhibition of God's grace has borne its triumphs to the outskirts of the universe,
                  these proud and defiant spirits have maintained a keen and desperate opposition to
                  the accomplishment of his purposes. Says an eminent divine—"Nor can the record of
                  this wondrous history carry forward its narrative, without furnishing some
                  transient glimpses of a sublime and superior warfare, in which for the prize of a
                  spiritual dominion over our species, we may dimly perceive the contest of loftiest
                  talent, and all the designs of heaven in behalf of man, met at every point of
                  their evolution by the counter workings of a rival strength and a rival sagacity."
                  In this mighty and unceasing struggle, great principles are involved; on one side
                  zeal for the honor and supremacy of God, on the other the pride and malignity of
                  those who would uproot his government.</p>
               <p>It has been supposed by some learned divines that the chief of this apostate host,
                  while yet unfallen, was appointed to the superintendence of this earth at its
                  creation, and that jealousy of the new creature led him into rebellion. But this
                  is mere speculation, in which it is not profitable to indulge. It is not necessary
                  for us to know the date or the nature of the sin which cost Satan and his legions
                  their place in heaven; to know if any portion of God's wrath has been poured out
                  upon them, or if as yet they have only the<pb n="156-157"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000089"/> expectation of judgment. It behooves us, however,
                  to bear continually in mind the fact of, their existence and their concerted plans
                  and labors for our destruction; that we may be watchful, and "put on the whole
                  armor of God." "We know not if our rebellious world be the only stronghold which
                  Satan is possessed of, or if it be but the single post of an extended warfare that
                  is now going on between the powers of light and darkness. But be it the one or the
                  other, the parties are in array, and the spirit of the contest is in full energy,
                  and the honor of mighty combatants is at stake; and let us therefore cease to
                  wonder—that the ambition of loftier natures has here put forth all its desire and
                  all its strenuousness."</p>
               <p>Intimations are given in Scripture of a freedom of access even in heavenly places,
                  on the part of evil angels. Satan came among the sons of God, when they presented
                  themselves before the Lord. He had walked to and fro in the earth at his pleasure.
                  From the first temptation, evil spirits have striven for ascendency over human
                  hearts, and for the support of their master's kingdom. Satan claimed this world
                  when it received the curse of its Maker for man's sin, and maintained his
                  sovereignty, till the establishment of Messiah s empire gave an incurable wound to
                  his supremacy. When he found his infernal art over-matched by Divine wisdom, his
                  resistance to the progress of the gospel became violent and desperate. "We read of
                  a struggle which the Captain of our salvation had to sustain, when the lustre of
                  the Godhead lay obscured, and the strength of its Omnipotence was mysteriously
                  weighed down under the infirmities of our nature—how Satan singled Him out, and
                  dared Him to the combat of the wilderness—how all his wiles and all his influences
                  were resisted—how he left our Saviour in all the triumphs of unsubdued loyalty—how
                  the progress of this mighty achievement is marked by every character of a
                  conflict—how many of the Gospel miracles were so many direct infringements on the
                  power and empire of a great spiritual rebellion—how<pb n="158-159"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000090"/> the momentary advantages that were gotten over Him,
                  are ascribed to the agency of this infernal being, who entered the heart of Judas,
                  and tempted the disciple to betray his Master and Friend. We know that we are
                  treading on the confines of mystery. We cannot tell what the battle that He
                  fought. We cannot compute the terror or the strength of his enemies. We have not
                  been told how they stood in marshalled and hideous array against Him; nor can we
                  measure how great the firm daring of his soul, when He tasted that cup in all its
                  bitterness, which He prayed might pass away from Him."—"We cannot speak in our own
                  language, but we can say, in the language of the Bible, of the days and nights of
                  this great enterprise, that it was the season of the travail of his soul; that it
                  was the hour and the power of darkness; that the work of our redemption was a work
                  accompanied by the efforts, the violence, and the fury of a combat; by all the
                  arduousness of a battle in its progress and all the glories of a victory in its
                  termination; and after He called out that it was finished, after He was loosed
                  from the prison-house of the grave, after He had ascended up on high, He is said
                  to have made captivity captive; to have spoiled principalities and powers; to have
                  seen his pleasure upon his enemies, and to have made a show of them openly."<ref
                     rend="super" target="#note_003" xml:id="return_003">*</ref>
                  
               </p><note place="foot" xml:id="note_003">
                  
                  <p><ref target="#return_003">*</ref>Chalmers' Astronomical Discourses.</p>
               </note>
               <p>The struggle is not ended: Satan yet works in the children of disobedience,
                  walking about to seek whom he may devour; pursuing the windings of his dark
                  policy, plying his deep devices, and employing every art to entice and enthrall
                  men to their destruction. Scripture revelation on this point is full and explicit;
                  and in the warnings given to arouse us into watchfulness against invisible foes,
                  the most impressive figures of mysterious might and implacable malice are used.
                  The term "devil"—may include the whole army of spiritual adversaries, as a name
                  applicable to all, or as their leader is so called, and they being subject to the
                  will of a powerful and malignant prince and employed in the<pb n="160-161"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000091"/> execution of his plans, need not be named
                  individually. Whether the dominion exercised by their chief is in virtue of
                  superior faculties, in memory of the distinctions known in their first estate, or
                  but a temporary sway, for the purpose of having their united craft and violence
                  directed in the manner most effectual for the ruin of our race, we know not; but
                  it cannot be doubted that such an organized government does exist. We are
                  instructed that these spirits surround us unseen; that they are superior to us in
                  knowledge and intellectual faculties, and that it is in malignant envy of man that
                  their concerted efforts to pervert and destroy him are so unceasing.</p>
               <p>These facts, it is true, have been disputed by some who aim to appear "wise above
                  what is written." They have imagined Satan an allegorical name for whatever
                  opposes the progress of the heavenly kingdom; and have thought the apostle's
                  expressions should be interpreted of mortal enemies—"the Roman authorities, the
                  corrupt Rabbis bis, or the heathen priests." But any unprejudiced reader must
                  admit that this language of the Bible cannot be understood as metaphorical. The
                  terms applied could be appropriate only to evil spirits; nor could the acts
                  imputed to them be performed by mortals. They are said to believe and tremble;
                  their apostacy, and final punishment, are mentioned. The "wicked one" who beguiled
                  the first pair, who had the first murderer under his power, who aspired to tempt
                  the Son of God by the offer of worldly sovereignty, who is described as the
                  fountain of all evil, is represented not only as impeding the advance of truth on
                  earth, but as accusing the saints in the presence of the Most High. The popular
                  belief in the existence and agency of malevolent spirits, was confirmed by Christ
                  and his apostles. We are taught in the most sublimely comprehensive of all prayers
                  to pray daily for deliverance from the evil one—called also "the prince of the
                  power of the air"—"the great dragon," "the god of this world," and compared<pb
                     n="162-163" xml:id="VAC6388-00000092"/> in terrible fury to a "roaring lion."
                  We are directed to regard and fear Satan more than his human instruments of
                  wickedness: to remember whose counsels are designed to draw us from God.
                  Intimation is given of the vast number of these busy apostates, when we hear of
                  seven—or a whole legion, abiding in one human being. The incident recorded of the
                  entering of dispossessed spirits into the herd of swine, would be conclusive on
                  this subject, were there no other proof in Scripture of the reality of their
                  existence. This, therefore, cannot be questioned, though we are not enabled to
                  discover what degree of influence they are allowed to exercise, what power they
                  possess over the material frame of nature, or by what means they communicate with
                  the soul of man.</p>
               <p>When we are exhorted to be "not ignorant of Satan's devices," it behooves us to
                  consider attentively the record of his agency among men, contained in the Holy
                  Scriptures. It would require a volume to transcribe all the instances of this; we
                  shall therefore refer only to a few in which his interference is clearly
                  described. We may trace his malevolent working in the history of the chosen
                  nation, evident, where it is not plainly declared; as in the murmuring, rebellion
                  and idolatries of Israel, and in the hostility of the heathen tribes who opposed
                  their march to the promised land. The statutes given to the children of Israel
                  show that they were perfectly aware of his existence: they were forbidden to
                  sacrifice to devils, and the most severe penalties were denounced against those
                  who had dealings with familiar spirits. It is added that because of such
                  abominations the Lord had driven out the nations of Canaan; and we may clearly
                  infer that necromancy was widely practised. Thus were Satan's angels in intimate
                  intercourse with men, within the pale of the visible church, as well as in the
                  world lying in heathen darkness. It has been conjectured, with reason, that the
                  responses of the ancient oracles were given by diabolical interposition. The Book
                  of Job<pb n="164-165" xml:id="VAC6388-00000093"/> opens to us a view of mysteries
                  beyond our present capacity to understand, when Satan is represented as appearing
                  among the sons of God; coming from his abode—the earth, to receive permission to
                  afflict and tempt a righteous man. Other passages are equally remarkable: as where
                  Zechariah saw "Joshua, the high priest, standing before the angel of the Lord, and
                  Satan standing at his right hand to resist him:" where the angel who instructs
                  Daniel speaks of his contest with mysterious powers of evil under the name of
                  heathen princes; where Micaiah's vision describes the appearance, in presence of
                  the host of heaven, of one who volunteered to go forth and be a lying spirit in
                  the mouth of the prophets of Ahab; or where the devil is said to have disputed
                  with Michael, the archangel, about the body of Moses, it is supposed with the view
                  of making the place of his burial known to the people, that they might be tempted
                  to worship him.</p>
               <p>The evil spirit who planted dissension between Abimelech, the son of Gideon, and
                  the men of Shechem, after the murder of his brethren, came to his work by express
                  Divine permission; as did the one that troubled Saul, when the Spirit of the Lord
                  had departed from him. Such instances show the malice and the wrath even of wicked
                  spirits under the control of God, to work out his gracious purposes; and that they
                  cannot by a single step pass the limits He has prescribed to their power. It
                  pleased Him for a long time to suffer their abode in the midst of his chosen
                  people, inciting them to abominable transgressions, and reducing them almost to
                  the condition of the Gentile world enslaved under their cruel dominion. "They
                  sacrificed their sons and their daughters unto devils, and shed innocent blood,
                  even the blood of their sons and their daughters, whom they sacrificed unto the
                  idols of Canaan; and the land was polluted with blood." To such a depth of guilt
                  and wretchedness had diabolical cunning, cruelty and power sunk the nations who
                  had bowed under their yoke! In the pitiable waste, no<pb n="166-167"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000094"/> doubt there were individual instances in which
                  satanic interference wrought scenes of wickedness and woe deeper than the general
                  level. These fierce enemies of man, triumphant in malignity, had nearly succeeded
                  in trampling out all resemblance of the image in which he was created, and
                  assimilating him to themselves. But their triumpt was to be changed into terror
                  and discomfiture. The advent of the Incarnate Redeemer was a fearful overthrow to
                  "the prince of this world." Into the world Satan claimed as his own, in which he
                  and his agents rioted in their work of destruction, entered One whose mission was
                  "to save that which was lost." The fruit of many victories was to be snatched from
                  him who had the power of death. What marvel that unclean spirits evinced such fear
                  at the approach of the Deliverer, entreating to be spared, while at the same time
                  they acknowledged his irresistible power! "Let us alone"—cried the fiend commanded
                  to come forth from the victim he had possessed; "what have we to do with thee,
                  thou Jesus of Nazareth! art thou come to destroy us?" The devils permitted at that
                  time to enter into men became subject to the disciples through the name of their
                  Master, who revealed to them, in expressive imagery, the change that had taken
                  place: "I beheld Satan as lightning fall from heaven." But the evil one was
                  resolved not to relinquish his usurped dominion without a struggle, and he
                  ventured to contend with the Lord of all worlds for the possession of this his
                  revolted province. The most daring and desperate of his enterprises was his
                  assault during forty days in the wilderness, upon the Saviour Himself. He had seen
                  in the primitive garden how easily frail human nature might be led astray; he had
                  watched during the lapse of centuries the progress of human depravity; and in the
                  boldness of his malign nature he conceived the idea of cutting off every hope of
                  man at a single blow. He could not but be aware of the true dignity of Messiah's
                  person; the prophecies of former ages were well known<pb n="168-169"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000095"/> to him; he had heard the song of the angels at his
                  birth, and the testimony of the Father given at his baptism. Yet his presumption
                  even aspired to tempt the Lord of glory. To Him, by whom heaven and earth
                  subsisted, he made the proposition to fall down and worship his hateful self! In
                  view of this incredible height of daring, of this depth of wickedness, should we
                  not tremble for ourselves, exposed to his insidious snares; should we not marvel
                  at the condescension of the Redeemer, who stooped to such an indignity for our
                  sakes!</p>
               <p>"Then the devil leaveth Him," says the sacred record: but he departed not humbled
                  by discomfiture, not less bent on the frustration of the Divine purpose of mercy.
                  St. Luke says, "he departed for a season." Again, at the critical period of his
                  life, the Saviour said—"The prince of this world cometh." When He was betrayed
                  into the hands of sinners, the thick gloom that gathered around his soul is
                  described in his words—"This is your hour and the power of darkness." The full
                  import of these expressions we know not; but that a travail and anguish of soul
                  were implied, far beyond our knowledge or conception, cannot be doubted. Against
                  Him the fear and hate of the infernal host were especially directed; the slightest
                  victory over Him would have ensured their final triumph, and his assumption of the
                  inferior nature placed Him within the reach of their assaults. These, without
                  question, were more violent and deadly the nearer approached the dreadful hour of
                  his final suffering; and who may tell what presumptuous hopes may have flashed
                  into being in them, when they saw Him forsaken of God, and listened to the
                  orphaned cry that denoted the mysterious extremity of his woe!</p>
               <p>Has not experience, in every age of the world, confirmed the assertion of the word
                  of God, in respect to the subtlety, potency and machinations of the prince of
                  evil? Have we not seen, with our own eyes, his workings in the children of
                  disobedience! And<pb n="170-171" xml:id="VAC6388-00000096"/> is not every
                  Christian a daily sufferer from his crafty assaults, his laying hold of every
                  natural impulse and inclination of the heart, every faculty of the mind, every
                  circumstance in the condition, to disquiet, tempt and wound the soul! Is not every
                  follower of Jesus conscious that he needs the warning, "Be sober, be vigilant;
                  because your adversary the devil, as a roaring lion, walketh about, seeking whom
                  he may devour?" Is it not too evident that he "hath blinded the eyes of them which
                  believe not, lest the light of the glorious gospel of Christ, who is the image of
                  God, shall shine unto them;" that he cometh, "and taketh away the word out of
                  their hearts, lest they should believe and be saved"? This world is still the
                  arena of his struggles and his victories, and every step the pilgrim takes in his
                  journey towards the land of promise is fiercely disputed by enemies through whom
                  he cannot pass but as a conqueror. The air is populous around us; in our lonely
                  hours we are begirt by unseen foes, watchful for some unguarded point by which the
                  poisoned dart may enter the soul. But we may stand against the wiles of the devil
                  by putting on the whole armor of God. We have a sure refuge, within which the
                  adversary can have no advantage over us; a strong tower of defence; even the
                  shelter of that name to which all things in heaven and on earth and under the
                  earth do homage!</p>
               <p>The enemy who assaulted the Master, did not spare the servants. Besides the actual
                  possession of men who became victims incapable of resistance, and the infliction
                  in many cases of physical disease and infirmity, numerous instances are recorded
                  of the agency of Satan in suggesting wicked purposes, and prompting to evil
                  actions. In the New Testament, as in a map, his designs and plans are laid open so
                  that we may trace his working, and occasionally discern even the manner of his
                  operations. Thus we are told that he "entered into Judas;" an expression of
                  fearful meaning, denoting at the same time his determination to accomplish his<pb
                     n="172-173" xml:id="VAC6388-00000097"/> impious enterprise of frustrating the
                  Saviour's mission, and the awful power given him over those whom he can lead
                  captive at his will. The heart of the false disciple had long been an abiding
                  place for the arch-traitor, swept and garnished for his reception; but now in a
                  peculiar manner he "entered into" him; controlling every power of the man,
                  physical and intellectual, not, as he governed the possessed, by resistless force,
                  leaving them no moral responsibility—but by the sway of an acknowledged sovereign
                  over a willing subject. How awful the lesson, how salutary the warning, conveyed
                  in this portion of the sacred narrative!</p>
               <p>Satan "filled the hearts" of Ananias and Sapphira, "to lie unto the Holy Ghost."
                  He was entertained as a confederate with those who exercised "a spirit of
                  divination," and instigated Simon Magus and Elymas in their endeavors to injure
                  the gospel. His subordinates vexed and distressed those over whom they obtained
                  temporary power; whom they would have destroyed, had their ability extended so far
                  as to take away life. How affecting is the picture of their cruelty, in the
                  narrative of the boy who had "a dumb spirit;" of the demoniac among the tombs; the
                  daughter of the Syro-Phœnician woman; the woman whom Satan had bound eighteen
                  years; the man in the synagogue with an unclean spirit, and in many other
                  instances! The evil one had power also to afflict for a season the children of
                  God; and how eagerly did he snatch at opportunities to execute his machinations
                  against them! "Behold," said Christ to the church in Smyrna; "the devil shall cast
                  some of you into prison, that ye may be tried; and ye shall have tribulation ten
                  days." Peter fell under his power for a time, and how imminent the peril into
                  which he was led! His generous Master had warned him of his danger, and intimated
                  the agency at work to accomplish his destruction. "Simon, Simon, behold, Satan
                  hath desired to have you, that he may sift you as wheat." What a glimpse does this
                  passage afford into the contest<pb n="174-175" xml:id="VAC6388-00000098"/> waged
                  so mysteriously around and within us, between the powers of good and evil, and the
                  boldness of the latter, demanding as it were, the opportunity of testing the
                  fidelity of so zealous a servant! In this case, Infinite Wisdom saw good to permit
                  the trial; but its happy termination was ensured by the Saviour's intercession. "I
                  have prayed for thee—that thy faith fail not."</p>
               <p>"Surely in vain is the net spread in the sight of any bird." And we, in view of
                  the appalling revelation made to us of the power, the craft, the malice, and the
                  daring of the infernal host, with the close contact into which we are brought with
                  them during our mortal sojourn—may well be exhorted to "watch." They watch over us
                  for evil; let us "watch and pray, that we enter not into temptation." And while
                  remembering our own weakness, and the height and dignity from which these
                  apostates fell—we regard them with pity and horror, let us render humble thanks
                  that, to save us from becoming their prey, the Son of God abased Himself self to
                  endure their utmost violence. With the armor He has provided, and under his
                  banner, we need not shrink from the conflict, though wrestling with principalities
                  and powers, and spiritual wickedness in high places; for we strive not in our own
                  strength, and are amply furnished with the means of securing a triumph. Powerful
                  as Satan is, he flies from those who resist him, and faith enables the believer to
                  withstand his most terrific assaults. "Thanks be to God who giveth us the victory,
                  through our Lord Jesus Christ."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="176-177" xml:id="VAC6388-00000099"/>
               <head>VII. CONCLUSION.</head>
               <p>IN view of the interesting subject we have briefly considered, one truth must ever
                  be borne in mind. We may not depend for protection or assistance upon angelic
                  watchers. God alone is our refuge, help and strength. To Him alone must we betake
                  ourselves in earnest prayer for needed succor; from Him alone must we expect the
                  answer to our supplications. The ministerign spirits He sends forth are but
                  instruments in his hands for the working of his good pleasure. We must beware how
                  we ascribe to them properties which might serve as an excuse for putting them in
                  his place. We are warranted from Scripture to conclude that they have no knowledge
                  of the future, except what God has seen fit to reveal for special purposes. Nor
                  can we suppose them able to read our secret thoughts, though their exalted
                  faculties, acquaintance with past occurrences, and opportunities of observation,
                  may enable them to form accurate conclusions respecting the characters or motives
                  of action belonging to individuals. It would be daring impiety to attribute to
                  them omniscience, or any other attribute of the Deity. When our Lord tells us
                  there is joy among the angels over one sinner that repenteth. He likens it to the
                  rejoicing of friends and neighbors called together by one who has recovered what
                  he had lost. "<emph>Likewise</emph> I say unto you, there is joy, etc." They are
                  commissioned and "sent forth to minister" to such as shall be heirs of salvation;
                  and those who desire their companionship and aid must seek it not from them, but
                  Him whose messengers they are, and whose will they are swifter than the winds to
                  perform. In our warfare against the evil influences<pb n="178-179"
                     xml:id="VAC6388-00000100"/> continually surrounding us, in our struggles
                  against the rebellious thoughts suggested by their busy malignity, we must ask
                  help from Him who led captivity captive, and received gifts for men. For He has
                  given us an ally in whose presence the aggregate powers of the infernal host are
                  as nothing. Let Satan put forth his utmost strength to assail us; let temptation
                  and trial overwhelm us as many waters—deep calling unto deep—the soul of the
                  Christian may yet look up in confidence of victory; for not only does Jesus plead
                  his cause in heaven, but the Holy and Infinite SPIRIT, within his own breast,
                  "maketh intercession for him, with groanings which cannot be uttered." Our Divine
                  Saviour had in his mind that which transcended human thought or expression, when
                  He said to his disciples—"It is expedient for you that I go away." Unspeakable
                  indeed must the gift needs be, which could compensate to his bereaved friends for
                  the loss of the joy of his presence, and deeply must they have pondered over the
                  mysterious rious import of his words, to them incomprehensible, till, the economy
                  of the gospel dispensation being complete, on the day of Pentecost the sound came
                  like a rushing mighty wind, and cloven tongues sat upon each, and they were all
                  filled with the Holy Ghost. Mysterious expression—"filled with the Holy Ghost;"
                  having the Spirit, as a gift, poured out upon them; the Spirit of glory and of God
                  resting upon them; the Spirit giving them utterance! Wonderful dispensation,
                  introduced by the shedding of the precious blood of the Son of God, in which the
                  Holy Spirit comes down to dwell with men; to enter into the very hearts of the
                  dead in sin, and give them a new life; to abide with them in such a manner that it
                  may be said their "bodies are the temples of the Holy Ghost," "an habitation of
                  God through the Spirit." How sublime and awful, how far beyond mortal apprehension
                  is the thought that the soul of man may be the chosen abode of the Spirit of God!
                  "Know ye not," says the apostle, "that ye<pb n="180-181" xml:id="VAC6388-00000101"
                  /> are the temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you?" No created
                  spirit can enter into such intimate communion with another. The possessed of evil
                  spirits were unwilling subjects to their sway; the believer in whom the Eternal
                  Spirit dwells, must have all his powers brought into subjection unto the obedience
                  of Christ; his spiritual essence must be pervaded, permeated and possessed by the
                  love of holiness, and sin must be cast out as an abhorrent thing; for "if any man
                  defile the temple of God, him shall God destroy." We may not understand the manner
                  of this mysterious conjunction, but its blessed effects may be readily discerned
                  in "the fruits of the Spirit;" and how should we adore the greatness of the
                  Father's mercy, who hath bestowed on us such a manner of love! the ineffable grace
                  of the Son, who purchased the privilege for us at an inestimable price! the
                  wondrous condescension of the Spirit, who descends to take up his permanent abode
                  with us, continually helping our infirmities, when we know not even what we should
                  pray for as we ought! Mighty thought! that in our earnest supplications He mingles
                  his own all-prevailing intercession; that the humblest prayer rising on the wings
                  of faith is thus wafted, as in a bright cloud of incense, to the throne of
                  God!</p>
               <p>While we should regard it as a duty to ponder on the truth revealed in Scripture
                  for our good—that our world is populous with watching spirits, though unseen,
                  continually employed about the concerns of mortals, anxiously observant of every
                  part of our conduct, laboring for our ruin or our preservation, we should never
                  for a moment forget that we are environed by the presence of a Spirit Uncreate,
                  whose presence compasseth Infinity. Not only in his eternal Omnipresence is He
                  with us, but in a sense peculiar to his gracious manifestation through the
                  Redeemer's work. To believers Christ manifests Himself, as he doth not unto the
                  world. Let Christians then be diligent to "walk in the Spirit," and to show by
                  their good works<pb n="182" xml:id="VAC6388-00000102"/> and holy conversation that
                  their bodies are in truth "the members of Christ." Let them remember that they are
                  not only "bought with a price," but already taken possession of as a mansion of
                  grace, by Him who has purchased them, if so be that they have been truly called
                  according to the Divine purpose, and are accepted in the Beloved; and let them
                  earnestly take heed that by indwelling corruption, they "grieve not the Holy
                  Spirit of God," whereby they "are sealed unto the day of redemption."</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
