<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6533">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Ocean-Born </title>
            <author>Godman, Stuart Adair.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC6533</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-1010</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ocean-born</title>
                  <author>Godman, Stuart Adair.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>100 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Bunce</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1852">1852</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-05-03">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The ocean-born</head>
            <p>
               <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6533-00000001"/>  THE OCEAN-BORN: A TALE OF THE SOUTHERN SEASI  BY STUART ADAIR GODMAN, AUTHOB OP 'THE OPIUMSMUGGiER," &amp;C. &amp;C.  134 NASSAU STREET.  BU T E FND BRTHE PUB IUM, U XT-R C &amp;E ISE,   1    <pb n="0" xml:id="VAC6533-00000002"/>  'Entered according to Act ofCon'rsst J ne Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United Sthtes for tl e Southern District f New r   T     EE O CE AN-B OR N. CnAPTER I. "All was so still, so soft, in earth and air,  You scarce would start, to meet a spirit there'; Secure that nought of evil could delight To walk in such a scene, on such a night."-BYaOX. THE shades of night were just descending, and the sombre shadows of a cloudy, moonless evening were rapidly commingling into one huge outline, what, but an hour prior, had been a lovely tropical landscape. All was tran- quil, quiet, and seemingly enjoying that repose which the Omnipotent, in His wisdom, has made the business of the dark hours. The light land- breeze, as it came softly throughthe tree-tops and floated oceanward, sighed scarcely louder than an Eolian harp; the small waves, as they rippled on the smooth sand-beach, murmured with a drowsy, dreamy sound, as if they were moving unconsciously, like an infant in its slumbers; and the notes of the myriad insects, whose tiny voices arose from the foresis bosom, resembled strains 'of fairy harmony, sounding from some sweet spirit-land. Soothing and comforting would it have been to tthe disturbed soul, and care-worn heart, of any of Adam's toil-stricken sons, whose lot is cast amid ,the city's noisy, busy hum, could they have'been transported to that still spot, on Cuba's extreme eastern shore.    <pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6533-00000003"/> THEA OCEANr-BORN ; But even there, not long would they have been allowed sole possession of the pleasing scene; for, scarce had gloom usurped the place so lately gilded by the brilliant rays of the departed sun, ere, gliding in from seaward, like a phantom of the deep, came an exquisitely moulded, taut, heavily-sparred, full-rigged brig. Gracefully and rapidly she approached the land; and rounding-to, under the lee of a promontory that jutted far out into the water-a splash was heard, as her, anchor dropped--a slight, creaking noise, for a moment disturbed the quiet, as her sails were clewed up; and then, beautiful, motionless, and deathly silent, she floated as if she was, and had always been, as stationary, and as little subject to the will of man, as the high neck of land beyond her. Hour followed hour, and the silence that reigned on board the brig remained unbroken. The squareness of her yards, the loftiness bof her spars, the neatness of her rigging, all went to show that she contained a large and efficient crew; but no sound of bell, or other token, gave evidence that any one held ward or watch on her decks. But just at midnight, when it should have struck eight bells, a low whistle from a boatswain's call resounded; two seamen sprang over the hammocl- nettings into the starboard. quarter-boat, which was immediately settled away, and in a few seconds was, riding at the gangway. Eight stalwart sailors joined their companions, and taking their, places on the thwarts, in less than two minutes from the sound of the call, the cutter was manned with a crew of ten men and ready for ser vice. Some time elapsed, however, and still she remained unemployed; and her men were beginning to indulge in conversation, when the command of- "Silence in the boat, there!" uttered by a voice breathing authority En every tone, proved that the one for whom they were waiting was not far off Quickly the individual who had given the order came down-the side; and seating himself in the stern sheets assumed the tiller-ropes. The promptness with which his order had     een obeyed attested the aw with which the seamen regarded their superior; and the quick, stern mawn ner in which he asked-  Au' Ae ayou all rmed?" called forth a ready "Ay, ay, sir?'." Are your weapons in good orders Are your pistols loaded, and your cutlasses sharp ." he then asked. The crew again answered in the affiv- mative. Shove off, then    Oars  Let fall! Give way." were the commands     A TALE OF THE 6OUTHERN SEAS.         .  rapidly uttered, and as quickly obeyed; and pulling around the bows of the brig, the armed boat sped swiftly across;the cove.  Propelled by twenty strong and practiced arms,iit was but a little while until the boat arrived at the mouth of a small creek, or rather bayou, about half a mile to the westward of the brig. A slight motion of the steersman's' right hand, and the cutter shot into this bayou, up which, at the same rapid rate, she proceeded for a quarter of a mile. Dark, heavy masses of foliage, rising from the very surface of the water, prevented anything from being visible but their own dull outline, the black looking clouds that were scudding along on high, and the murky water. Not a word had been spoken on bhard of the cutter since she shoved off, mnd as she flitted through the shadows in tha dim light, the monotonous dick of her oars, as they turned -in the rolocks, had a ghoul-like, ominous sound, and she seemed, what she really was, a special messenger of the Evil One's bent on an errand of wickedness. Abruptly the direction of the boat's head was changed. "In oars 1 whispered the officer; and shooting through what appeared a cleft in the solid looking mass of mangrove bushes, the  cttter's bow: grated on the shore. Leaving the boat, the officer followed by eight of his men, in single file, immediately started at a quick pace on a small path :that led down to the waters edge; and with which he must have been very familiar or he could never have distinguished it in that dusky light, so indi;. tinct was it.  Leading through the thicket for a couple of hundred yards, the path opened on the edge of a large and tastefully-arranged garden, across which was seen the back part of a commodious and elegant dwelling. When arrived at the inclosure, the officer halted his men for a moment, and adopting a much kinder tone and manner than he had used during the ight, though they lost nothing in dignity or authority, he said- "Yon house, my men, contains a prideless treasure; tin it there is a jewel , -of surpassing value, upon whose possession I have set my heart. 'It is the mansion of Don Manuel Candido; and a pearl above all computation is his only daughter. To obtain her is the object -of this visit; and although' it is not a very fashionable hour to call upon a young lady, yet, as we are but rough sea-dogs, I hope she will pardon the intrusion." A peculiar chuckle, half laugh, half grunt, was uttered by the sailors, and the speaker continued-  The house, as you see, is'but of a single story. Tie windows, it is true,    <pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6533-00000004"/> 10 ,           THE OCEAN-BORN;  are barred with iron, but the grating across the one I wish to enter, if there is any potency in gold, we will find easily put aside. - The cwelling, contains, besides the servants, at least half a dozen gentlemen visitors and the old Don; so I commandyou, as yoU'fear my displeasure, to be as- silent as if you were in Davy Jones' locker. Follow me; keep quiet; and as you dread death, speak not above your breaths!        - Everything in and around the house was in deep repose. No fairy or good angel appeared watching over its inhabitants, to warn them of the hideous wrong with which they were threatened. No mental forebodings or warning dreams disturbed their slumbers; and peacefully, all unconscious of danger near, they slept; whilst the party from the brig crept stealthily, with panther-like tread, through the garden, to a window at the left corner of the mansion.                        . After the fashion of the Spaniards, the window was covered with iron bars, running through cross pieces of the same metal, reaching from below the lintel on the outside above the coping; and at the first glance it looked strong as a fortress. But slight effort was required from the three seamen who grasped it to wrench it from its place, and to show that the household had been tampered with, and that every bar had been cut. And in less time than we have' taken to tell it, there was no other protection between the occupants of the chamber and the rough, lawless men without, than the heavy white curtains which served to keep at bay the night air. Lightly stepping through the open window, which came nearly'to the ground, the officei of the cutter passed into the apartment; and there a picture of, such purity, innocence, and loveliness met his eyes, that, had not his heart been formed of stone, or been governed by passions that knew neither fear, pity, nor remorse, he would have turned and relinquished his fell purpose. -But when did man, influenced by his baser feelings, falter iin his efforts! Would that mortals were as strenuous in the paths of virtue. The room was a- large one, luxuriously furnished, and in the far corner, reclining on a low couch-which the rays from a small chamber-lamp on the thble brought out in strong-relief-slept one of the most beautiful of nature's most enchanting works-a young girl just passing into. womanhood. Her  oval face, perfeet in its outline, was resting upon an,arm that for symmetry and tapering beauty would have shamed Canova's masterpiece, whilst its snowy whiteness contrasted charmingly with the dark volumes of her rich, glossy, raven tresses, that were scattered over the pillow above it. Tranquilly she slumbered; and entranced, with his eyes riveted on .her-   A TALB OF THE SOUTHERN SEAS. face, first gazing at her ruby lips, and thin at her long silken eye-lashes, the bold intruder withi. the sanctuary of virtue, purity, and youth, stood for a time as if bereft of the power of motion. A slight movement of the beau- tiful sleeper recalled him to his senses, and stepping to the foot of the couch he laid his hand gently, but firmly, upon the shoulder of a mulatto girl who was sleeping on a rug near her mistress. As if the visit had not been unlooked for, the girl awoke w*ithout mani- festing surprise or alarm; and after listening to a few whispered words, she% and the man under whose influence she seemed, softly stole to the couch of ,the still unconscious lady. Dexterously the treacherous mulatto slipt a scarf across the lovely one's mouth, who, startled, awoke to find herself enveloped and pinioned in a coverlet, and being lifted in the strong grasp of a kidnapper. But a moment before she had been roaming in the enchanted paradise of youth's vision'realms, happyas an angel, her mind full of blissful imagin- ings; now she awakened'to find herself a captive in her father's house!- enclosed in the embrace of a stranger i--about to be carried she knew not where-she'dared not think for what 1I Even her trusted servant in league against her; and she unable to cry r that help she was aware was so near, and that she felt confident would be so readily afforded. The wild, the mournful; despairing, heart-broken glance she cast around was expressive of hopeless and   anguished feelings; and uttering a low, choking  nob, she swooned upon the shoulder of- him who was bearing her of    - "Thank the devil for that! she has fainted, and will neither struggle nor * cry," exclaimed in suppressed but exulting tone the bold man in whose arms she was.  "Come, Bonita, bear ahand, and  gather what you wish to carry off; we have no time to tarry." And stepping out on the ground as easily as if he had been all unburthened, the robber bore his prey swiftly toward his boat. Two of the men entering the Apartment he had just left, picked up a large trunk, and, followed by the mulatto, they, with their comrades, hurried after their leader; whilst the inmates of the dwelling continued to slumber in happy ignorance of the sorrow that awaited them in the morning. "Give way with a  will, men 1 A longs6troke, and a steady one. A hun. dred dollars apiece you shall havefor this night's work," said the officer as soon as. the boat was manned. And the bright streak of foam that soon flashed in her wake proved that her crew were doing their best, In a   brief space they neared the -brg.- A hail,--an answer; the lady  wae passed on board, and then below; :the mulatto followed; the officer X ,    ,    <pb n="12-13 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6533-00000005"/> THEE OCEAN-BORN;  then sprang up the side,. and took his place on. the quarter-deck; and as the cutter was rising fiom the water to its accustomed berth on the quarter, the  anchor was got, the tacks and sheets were hauled home, and with helm  a-port and yards braced up, the brig was standing with a stiff breeze rapidly, toward the Isle of Pines,; leaving the cove and its surroundings as calm, as quiet, and as lonesome as if it had never been the scene of aught ungentle er soul-troubling.  CHAPTER    II. -, Beauty's a doubtful good, a glass, aflower Lost, faded,' broken dead within an'hour,  And beauty, blemished once, forever s lost,  In spit' of physic, pantinng,pain nd cost.)-S-H'AKSPEIAR .  THE morning's sun was shining brightly on land nd ocean, and the brig  that had the evening before anchored in the- cove, was 'hurrying across the smooth sea, heading W. S. W., as if she were making toward the Spanish Many as are the gallant vessels that have been illumed by the tropic sun, never did its 'rays dart athwart a more sightly hull, handsomer spars, or neater top-hamper than belonged to the craft whose shadow it was now -.- U. et Basting on the water. In the dim night-light, when at anchor, the witchery of her model was unappreciable; but now, as her beauties stood revealed, she looked a perfect  sea-nymph; and as she gracefully rose with the long-rolling swell, and shaking the spray glittering like a shower of diamonds from her sharp bows,  sunk again into' her native element, she appeared a pure ocean-sprite, pos-  sessed of life and animation, gamboling in very exuberance of spirits. And  the muzzles of the heavy guns seen through the halt-ports, looked as if they would be used only in case of self-defence.' But appearances in vessels as in men, are ofttimes deceptive; and the  denizens of this world are too often found to be, sad as it is to acknowledge  "But appearances in vessels as in  en,  are ofttimes deceptive; and  th  *<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6533-00000006"/>   A TALE OF THE SOUTHERN SEAS.        '  15 it, bad in proportion to their beauty; and the splendid-looking brig was neither more nor less-than a pirate I Her crew, strong in numbers, stout of arm, bold of heart, and conscience- less, were renegades from every clime. Men of moir than a thousand crimes, and possessing but the single virtue of bravery, or, to name it more aptly, recklessness. True it is, they were faithful one to the other:. for this, in other men a virtue, they', however, deserve no praise; for against them was every man's hand, and theirs against the world; so that their existence and safety depended, and they knew it, altogether upon the integrity of each to each, and of the whole to their leader-who was their head, their mind, and upon whom  they depended for direction. And fit captain .for such a crew was he who commanded the brig. Gifted by nature lavishly with every quality, physical and mental, that would ,have rendered him an otna, ment to society, an honor to his family, a valuable citizen to his counntry, through mistaken kindness on the part of his guardians, in his'early youth, he had been allured to follow, without restraint or hindrance, the dictates of his own feelings. What wonder, then, that with an ardent temperament, quick parts, a handsome person, and reckless disposition, he' had listened to the voice of the syren that lureth .annually to destruction so many hundreds of the most promising youths of the nation. The commencement of his course toward the pit that is bottomless, was the same that has wrecked the prospects, anrid blasted the hopes of countless young men, born apparentlyiffor better things, fitted for nobler ends. First, vanity-and dress; then gambling and lewd company entangled and ensnared him; and then came pecuniary embarrassments; and then, as the downward path is ever swiftly travelled, a forgery, t Fear of discovery came nhxt-for pride is a feeling that ever, in strong natures, maintains the ascendency; and dreading lest he should be disgraced among his associates-not sorrowing for the crime, but fearing 'the consequences-he fled from the place of his nativity, the beautiful 'city of Savannah, to the West Indies. And now, whilst yet but in the first flush of manhood, scarce twenty-five, Frank Vincent was widely known and universally feared, as the daring'com- mander of the most dreaded pirate that had ever hat had ever harried the peaceful traders of the southern seas. - Even the, swift-sailing slavers, though near akin to pirates themselves, at al times kept a bright look-out for his brig. For the Fire-Fly never yet had met the craft she could not overhaul; and many a time, when other quarry was scarce, like the eagle after the fish-hawk, had    <pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6533-00000007"/> 16            THE OOEAN-BORN;      , she pounced upon some heavily-ladened Guineaman, relieved him of his living freight, and left him empty, cargoless, when almost arrived at port. Sucri was the Fire-Fly, her captain, and her crew; all, spite 0f many external beauties and material perfections, morally loathsome, dark, polluted. But, as if the Allwise in His mercy desired to leave naught so abandoned as to be deprived of all reason why it should be suffered to exist, even on board that brig, devoted as she was to rapine, robbery, and murder-the home of men careless of Heaven, honor, and virtue-who delighted in all sinfulness, in bright and glorious contrast to everything around, like a pearl. of price in a bed of mire, was one spirit, pure, unspotted, unpolluted, almost angelic in its innocence. It was the soul of the captive maiden, who,'the pvening before, had been so rudely hurried from the home of her childhood, and who now, with heart almiost bursting, was pent up in the Fire-Fly' cabin, CHAPTER IIL "She stands,as stands the stricken deer, Checked midway in the fearful chase, '  When bursts upon his eye and ear  The gaunt, gray robber, baying near Between it and its hiding-place- While still behind, with yell and blow, Sweeps like a storm the coming foe."--WHTTIER NOTHING was there in the cabin of the Fire-Fly to remind an occupant of the character of the brig. The apartment, it is true, was of unusual size for the; dimensions of the vessel, whose measurement barely reached two hun- dred tons; but that might be for the accommodation of passengers; whilst the splendor displayed in its fittings and furniture, could, without much  stretch of the imagination, be attributed to a desire to enhance their comfort  'Two large state-rooms occupied its after corners, which, like the bulkhead that divided it from what in a man-of-war would have been the ward-room, were enameled green and gold. The beams, heavily gilded, appeared solid   A TALE OF THE SOUTHERN SIFS.           17  bars of the precious metal; whilst plate-glass let in between them the whole length of the ceiling, reflected the brilliant hues of the rich emerald and gold-colored carpet that covered the floor. Pictures of sea-scenes, and of female heads,' that would have graced the cabinet of a connoisseur, hung around the sides, and were let in between the two large stern-windows that lighted the cabin. Across the transom stretched a broad, luxurious couch, covered with green silk-opposite to which, against the bulkhead, and on both sides of the door to the companion-way that led on deck, were chastely finished rose-wood beaufets, loaded with gold plate and chrystal. Books, too, and musical instruments were scattered about in profusion on lounges in various parts of the cabin, and on a round table that stood in its centre. And, more beautiful than any of the works of the limner's art that surrounded her, kneeling by the table, her arms resting upon it, and her head bent down until her forehead touched its cold marble-top, was she who had so unexpectedly and suddenly been installed mistress of this gorgeous apartment. Gold, however, is even heavier than baser metal; and though fetters composed of it may look brighter, they gall as deeply as those of rusty iron; and never was the spirit of captive in loathsome dungeon more  racked and oppressed than was the bosom of the fair tenantof that rich and    - costly prison.  Since she had recovered from the deep, almost deathly syncope, which the  first shock had thrown her into, and from which she did not awaken until the brig was farout at sea,.the kidnapped one had been constantly engaged in prayer. At first her appeals to the Virgin Mary, the saints, and to the Fatler of Light, were frantic, and uttered with maniacal fervor; but as if she found relief from the violence of her speech- and gesture, or, mayhap, from faith in the efficacy of her prayers, she gradually became more calm. Food and refreshment of all kinds she had sternly refused; and indignantly she, had ordered the girl Bonita, to whose falseness she attributed her misfor- tunes, from her presence, every time she came, and she had been -frequently   . to press her .to sleep or to eat. Long had Garcia been kneeling by the table, maintaining so rigidly the same attitude, that, had it not been for a nervous 'tremor that occasionally agitated her frame, and a low moan that escaped her lips, it would have been impossible to have persuaded a spectator that she. was not a faultless piece of sculpture, when a slight noise was heard at 'the door that led on deck. It was, however, unheeded by the maiden; and the door opening, Bonita softly entered the cabin, ahd walked toward her mistress.     <pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6533-00000008"/> 18     v      T T oOEcA-BORtN; When almost to the table, the mulatto paused; she was a woman of not more than thirty years of age, with straight hair and regular features, of a clear dark-olive complexion; and besides possessing an appearance of unusual intelligence for one of her class, she had a kind, open, frank-looking face, the expression of which was strangely at variance with the conduct she had been guilty of toward her too confiding mistress. As the servant gazed at the sweet being still prostrate by the table, and heard one of the plaintive, mournful sobs she uttered, the feelings of sorrow, of pity, of true compassionn that were at work in her heart, became visible on her dusky countenance, and tears began to trickle freely down her brown faee. Creeping slowly toward her kneeling lady, the girl addressed her in a voice naturally soft and sweet, but now rendered musical by the depth of her emotions, in the language of kindest endearment. Every term of qffection she could think of-and no tongue affords more beautiful terms by which to express love than the Spanish--she lavished upon her mistress in vain. Bonita, seeing her words all unheeded, drew still closer to the lady she had served so long, and, until lately, so faithfully; and the woman-feeling getting uppermost in her heart, forgetful of the difference in their stations and of 'her mistress's anger, laid her hand on the maiden's waist, and knelt by her side.  Though the words of the girl had produced no perceptible impression upon the lady, the .touch of her hand wrought an instantaneous change. No sooner had its weight been felt, than Garcia sprang to her feet, and step- ping back several paces with gleaming eyes, contempt and scorn lighting every feature, stood regarding the still crouching mulatto with a gaze as ,hard and pitiless as if the girls touch conveyed pestilence and death. Magnificent did Garcia look as thus she stood. Though young, seventeen summers having hardly passed over her, her form was fully developed, and her figure, faultless in its proportions, was above the average standard of woman. Her oval face, exquisitely shaped nose, dark, lustrously brilliant eyes, with long black lashes, her mouth, that looked as if it could express eVery emotion of her 'breast, her luxurious tresses, her classic head, all together rendered her a woman of surpassing beauty-one such as the Italian artists love to paint. And as she now stood, with every nerve tense, every feature of her intellectual and expressive face-brought into play, with confidence created by the necessity of self-reliance showing forth in her very attitude, she looked fit queen for a warlike people-charming and beau-   A TALE 01 THE SOOUTHRS SEAS.           19. / tiful enough to carry captive, and retain in bondage, the heart of athything mortal. 'Silently, for ar-biief space, the lady gazed at the mulatto, who remained crouched where she had first kneeled, her head sunk upon the floor, as if to depiecate the wrath of her incensed mistess.' But her presence seemed loathsome to the maiden, who exclaimed, in accents vehement and full- toned, Out, vile, treacherous slave! Begonel Leave mea Never let me see you more! Your presence will kill me!" "Oh! pity! pity! dear mistress;" sobbed the girl. "Pity! Pity you! For what?.-for betraying, for selling me! Me!- who have ever treated you with kindness! Leave me  Leave me! You are too base to bandy words with!" was the repry of the lady. "For the, love of the Blessed Virgin, have mercy on me, and pardon me 1 Indeed, dearest, sweetest mistress, I am not so guilty as I eem. I knew Iot what I was doing. Listen to me. Oh I turn not away from  me until you' have heard me; arid then, if I speak not the truth, drive me away forever ," exclaimed the mulatto, as, crawling across the cabin floor, she approached her mistress, and taking the hem of the lady's dress in her hands, sank at' her feet.  There is an eloquence in genuine feeling that seldom fails to produce con- viction; and the deep pathos of the girl's appeal-the sincere repentance she undoubtedly felt for the' part she had acted-for her looks, her voice, her position, were all too true to nature to be simulated-caused a re-action- in the feelings of her mistress. As a storm-cloud from before the sun, the dark and' angry expression flitted from Garcia's face, which resumed its habi- tual calm and mild appearance, as raising Bonita from the floor, she spoke to her in tones sad but kind. "Ever, until now, hast thou beeni true to me, Bonita. Since earliest childhood have you waited ,upon me affectionately, and faithfully performed. thy duties. And, oh! the blessed saints above know, that I would love bet-'  ter than words can th, to find thee still trustworthy; for sorely do I now need some one in whom I can confide." "Trust me then again; oh! mi vida, mi alma, and save your poor Bonita's heart from breaking. More than my own life, I love you, dearest mistress; and if you will only again place confidence in your slave, there is nothing a determined woman can do, that I will shrink from, to prove my    <pb n="20-21 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6533-00000009"/> 20      'THE OOEA      '-BO RN;  devotedness to you, my angel, and to show my repentance for the folly I have been guilty of."             -  "I will believe you, my poor girl, and forgive you; for I think your sor- :            ' row is now almost a match for mine. And now tell me frankly, Bonita, by what arts you were induced to lend yourself so thoroughly to my foul     ^! wronging."  And seemingly relieved to find that heir favorite servant was not leagued : . against her, and that she still had one friend, though an humble one, to  depend upon, the fair captive seated herself upon the cushioned transom,   ' whilst, Bonita, half sitting, half reclining at her feet commenced her expla- -  nation.      . "But once, cara niila, has your Bonita Feen absent from you since first            -        , -"             she nursed you, an infant, in these arms. It was, as you -reqaember, last t               b-.. c  winter, when I confined by, sickness, was pevented from accompanying you                                  n  . to your aunt's in Puerto Principe. Since your return home you have been  :                I         --  -;  as you never were before. In your sleep you have started and talked aloud,                   ;  and 'nightly called upon Henrico-a name I did not know. You were qui et in the daytime, and seemed sad, and almost ceased talking. And I thought e  -was I wrong?-that you had given your-heart to -some gallant you, had seen in the city." "Too, quick, and yetnot altogether wrng,-hast thoi been in thy guesi sg,            i girl," interupt,ed: the lady. the expressiqn of her countenance sudden ly,  changing'to a morse hopeful' air' as she continued, "Yet, surely jI nric can X n have had no hand in thus;hurrying me uasked and unattended, away, from.  my father and my home. Speak girl, quick!. Is it Hen;ico that hojlds us         , captive    .                       ,:                   ' "He told me, mistress, that be was so called. He also, said that you were :           : willing to go-that you were fearful your father would not. consent to his suit, and had agreed to; be stolen. It was '.very strange to me that you .  .    . .  - - AI. -  should have so suddenly allowed your love for your only parent to be so  i'      *  soon over-mastered by that for a stranger. But' the Seor spoke so kindly          areia pleads before Vincent for the life of her Father and his Companoa of you, -he talked so sweetly, he made me such handsome presents, that,        ' poor simpleton that I was, he coaxed me to believe him, and said it would' ' be but a matter of a day or two, and then your father would be, reconciled. And I, fool that I am, and knowing your. father's love for you, assisted to carry you from him."             ' -  "Oh, my father! my good, kind, indulgent father! ' What will become of you without your only child-your heart's idol i And what, oh! what     <pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6533-00000010"/>   A TAIS 'OF THE SOUTHERN SEAS.      '   23 will you think of her - affection, if you believe she has willingly left you," sobbed Garcia. "But tell me, Bonita," she instantly continued, " what man- ner of man is he in tvhose power we are  If it is Henrico-yet no, it cannot be-he would scorn to take such an advantage of a lady; but 'should 'it by any chance be he, no harm will reach us, for when he knows the sor- row and trouble he has caused, he will hasten to carry us back to my dear father." A noise on the companionway prevented the description the girl was about to commence, and the door quickly opening, the subject of their con- versation entered the cabin. Different, indeed, was the effect prqduced upon the mistress and the servant by the appearance of the captain. Thesgirl jumped toward him, exclaiming--  "Oh, Seior, Senior, are you not Hearico 8, Whilst Garcia, with horror and fear depicted in every lineament, shrieked, ' God in Heaven have pity upon me! I am lost, lost ;" aid overcome by the intensity of her feelings, she sank back upon the seat from which, at the opening of the door, she had arisen. As he stood by the table, in the centre of the cabin, there was nothing visible in the appearance of Frank Vincenit calculated to cause so much alarm in the breast of a woman. Tall, with a good figure, handsome face, and well-shaped head, covered with a profusion of brown, curly hair, and large deep-blue eyes, he had more the semblance of one likely; to gain favor in ladies' hearts,than to scare the rich blood in terror from their cheeks. And as he regarded the beautiful Spaniard with a smile on his lip, no one would have imagined that a form so fair to look upon, a face so seeming frank, could belong to one who had so hard a heart, so fierce a spirit, so unalterable a will,s belonged in verity to the pirate captain, in despite of his youth, and of the early moral instruction he had received. In a rich, deep, and fifnely-modulated voice, but with a slightly jeering tone, he addressed Garcia- "A bright good-morrow to you, lady fair. I hope you find the, poor accommodations I have to offer not altogether unbearable. And I have come to crave in person your pardon for the liberty I took, all unasked, of bringing you to share this my narrow home."     '     - To this salutation Garcia paid no attention, though the tears, which began to show through the fingers which covered her face, proved she was no un- concerned listener.   /  "What, my coy lady, not even a word, or a look, for a man who adores    <pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6533-00000011"/> 24           THE OCEAN-BORN; you-for one who will be your slave for life, if you will only render him one- half the love he tenders you? Speak, my shy one, speak; you have to do with one who has seen too much of woman's weeping to set it downfor more than it is worth, Come, lady, dry those needless tears-look up, and tell whether we are, to be friends, or whether you put me, at defiance."  The captain paused, as if he expected a reply, and Garcia, subduing her emotions by a strong effort, rose calmly to her feet, and looking steadily in the face of her interrogator, replied in a voice that, tremulous at first, be- came firm and decided, as with flashing eye and swelling bust, she answered, "Friends! Ay, such friendship you bear to me as the wolf does to the lamb; such love you have for me as has the hawk for the poor bird he swoops upon. Well dost thou know, base man, the feelings I entertain toward thee. At Principe I told you that I loved another, and besought you to trouble me no more with your hateful presence. And then, to show your love and your manhood, which, I take it, are about on a par, you stole ine from my father's house in the dea4 hour of the night. And now you offer me your love! Out upon you! Out upon you! Do you think so little of a Spanish maiden's spirit as to dream even that one could love such a thing as you are!-a' robber of unarmed men's houses! a kidnapper of defenceless woman! No! though all alone, unsupported, save by the Holy  Father above, the blessed saints, and the stout heart they have given me, here, in your own cabin, on board your own ship,'on the wide sea,-I defy you, sir captain, for death at least will not desert me." Quietly, without change of-feature, Vincent listened to. the impassioned accents and biting words of his captive. He had'spoken truly when he said he could not be moved by woman's tears; for the promptings of his own wilful breast was all that 'ever influenced him. In the same jeering tone that he had at first used, he continued- "Brave words, bravely spoken, my bright one. Right worthy are you to share a rover's home; and by all that I hold dear, and by all that I hate in this world and all others, share my lot thou shalt. I like the spirit you show-it suits me exactly; for' the fiercer the gale, the quicker it subsides. And now, my pretty one, one kiss I claim as my reward for hearkening to you so patiently." Suiting his action to his words, the pirate captain advanced to clasp Garcia in his arms. But, as he was about to touch her, she leaped past him, and rushing to the beaufet on the other side of the cabin, snatched from it a , . .s   A TALE OF THE S0UTHERN SEA.           2 massive gold goblet, armed with which she retreated to the farthest corner of the apartment.  A merry laugh burst from Vincent, as he saw the determined and lovely girl snatch the'goblet, and place herself in the corner, as if to resist him. "Surely, fair maid," he said, "you must hold my manhood at a cheap rate, indeed, to think that so slight a weapon in so weak a grasp, would scare me from such sweet lips as thine. Stop your nonsense, lay down your trinket, and force-me not to use violence to reach your lips; for a kiss I will have if it kills us both."  ":Keep off! keep off! Defile-me not by your touch!" was the reply of Garcia, as with uplifted hand she retained her position. The Pirate's outstretched arm was almost touching her, when, summoning her entire strength, the dauntless girl, with all her force thrown into the blow, struck him on the temple. Suddenly, as if stricken by a bullet, the captain dropped to the deck, whilst his blood spouted over the dress and person of the brave maiden, who, forgetful of her own position, and-of the provocation that led to the act, with her 'gentler instincts predominant, ex- claimed-  "Oh, Father! forgive me for the deed I have done ;" and stooped down to aid in distress him whom but a moment before she had been in terror of. The mulatto, who, during the dialogue between her mistress and Vincent, had seemed paralyzed by'fear, found her tongue as the pirate fell, and utter- ing shriek upon shriek, she hastened across the cabin to the assistance of the lady.                       ( The echo of the girl's first shriek had hardly died away, ere it produced an effect the very opposite of that desired; for, startled by the clamor, the officer of the watch looked into the cabin to see what was wrong, and per- ceiving the body of his commander lying on the fl6or, motionless and bathed in blood, he shouted--  "Fire-Fly's ahoy there i" as he jumped, and leaped at once down the com- paionway.  Scarcely had he reached his captain ere the crew came tumbling in hurried confusion down the stairs, as many at a time as its limits would allow, and in a moment the gorgeous cabin, that lately had not beeif tenanted save by- the fair Spanish lady, was crowded with truculent-looking tailors of all ages, nations, and 'colors, and onlyalike in the ferocity of their aspects and their readiness for deeds of blood.       .  A  murmurarose in the cabin as its rough and hardened occupants learned pnslan    <pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6533-00000012"/> 26            THE OOEAN-BORN; the situation of their leader; and as some of them picked up the captain and carried him on deck, a fierce shout was raised by the rest of the semi- -demons of-- "Overboard with the hussies! To the sharks with the pair of them 1" and a rush was made toward Garcia and the mulatto. Retaining her presence of mind amid even the great and imminent dan- ger that now surrounded her, Garcia endeavored to speak to the rude throng. But their savage cries of- -  Blood for blood!" "Overboard with them!  "Blast them, clear them out 1" drowned her more feeble tones. One glance the Spanish maiden cast at Bonita, as, swooning, she saw her carried off in the grasp of a couple of swarthy wretches; and then, as she felt the coarse hands of their terrible associates press painfully upon her , shoulders, as they prepared to hurry her off, too, to consign her, as she well knew, to a sudden and violent dean and a watery grave, she also happily became unconscious. CHAPTER IV. "Fate is above us all; We struggle, but what matters our endeavor? Our doom is gone beyond our own recall; May we deny or mitigate it?-Never!"--Mss LANDON. SLIGHT, indeed, is the barrier that ofttimes stands between man and his apparent destiny; and the seeminglytrifling incidents or accidents that inter- pose to prevent the execution of intended designs, changing the events an, ticipated to those directly opposite our desires, proves that what too many class under the sweeping but unmeaning title of circumstances-a term which can only be attributed correctly to the care and watchfulness of an overruling Providence-has much more to do with the regulation and guid- ance of the daily affairs of life, than most of us are willing to admit. To our fnite comprehensions, it 'is true, that the cause of these interpositions is                  At . r oA TALE OF THE SOTHERN SEAS.  generally unfathomable; for often we observe men snatched, as it were, by a miracle, from evils of no very great magnitude, to be immediately after plunged into a darn sea of troubles, from which they never escape. ,But despite our boasted intellectual privileges, and our claimed superiority over all other dwellers on this mundane sphere, man, though made after the image of his Creator, and self-sufficient in his advantages over the brutes, and in his free agency, goes blundering through his few brief years, commit- ting crime upon crime, the slave of first one passion and then another, as years change his cravings; seeking always something that escapes his grasp, and fulfilling a destiny and a course that he never premeditated, so steadily and certainly as to clearly demonstrate the existence of some invisible and compelling power that guides where it listeth, for its own wise ends and pur- poses.  So it was with the pirate crew, as with shout and yell, and horrid blas- phemy, they hurried Garcia up the companionway, the fixed purpose of heaving her into the ocean reigning paramount in every heart-if such wretches, either at sea or ashore, can be said to possess hearts other than the muscle that bears that name-with their commander senseless, and incapable of preventing their fell design; out of reach of all human power, it seemed as if the Spanish maiden's fate was fixed-her destiny in life accomplished. And yet, when all appeared so certain, a thing most trivial in itself changed the current of events.  The ruffians who had carried the mulatto from the cabin, with a long and loud "yo heave ho!" were just about launching her over the lee gangway as the party who were bearing her mistress reached the deck. Treating the whole matter as a jest, these swore that the lady should still maintain the prerogative'of her rank, and precede the servant; and with a loud shout se of them sung out-- "Blast your eyes there, ye lubbers! Hold fast and belay! Our craft's to be launched first; she's the one that flies the broad pennant!" A severe blow on the side of the head, from the butt of a pistol, laid the speaker prostrate on the deck ere the words had fairly passed his lips; and his startled companions gave back on all sides so suddenly, as to leave the two seamen who carried Garcia alone in the centre of the deck, to face their recovered and infuriated commander, who, with' cheeks pale from loss of the blood that covered his clothes and streaked his face, and eyes gleaming with concentrated rage and tiger passions, looked the personification of some incarnate demon, who had just escaped from the regions below to assert- his.    <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6533-00000013"/> 28           THE OCEAN-BORN; supremacy in power and wickedness over the demon-mortals who manned the Fire-Fly. Grasping a cocked pistol in each hand, for half a minute the pirate cap- tain stood regarding his crew, seeking with eager gaze to find who it was that had dared to be the ringleader in what he thought an attempt to 4eprive him of his fair captive. But the men who had on many former occasions felt the force of their commander's wrath, and knew well the ferocity of his disposition when aroused, stood quietly, with downcast gaze, like truant school-boys confronted by their teacher. Those by the gangway had laid Bonita on the deck, and slunk away for'ard; whilst the two who supported Garcia, stood almost trembling with dread, within two paces of their captain, wishing to be rid of their dangerous burden, but afraid to move.          , "Ye hell-hounds! did ye think I was dead, and that the brig and all that's in it were yours 8" said the captain, in a low but clear voice, address- ing himself to the crew; and then turning quickly to the two seamen who stood near him, he fiercely asked, ( What's your purpose with that lady, you bloody rascals? How dared you lay your hands on her, or any thing ,else H have a fancy to? Speak, speak quick, or I blow your lubber brains out "I The nearest man, whose eyes were fixed upon the muzzle of the elevated pistol, answered, ' I beg your pardon, Captain Vincent. . meant no harm or disobedience, sir; nor did airy of us. We thought this lady had killed you, sir;, and, according to our law of blood for blood, we were about to throw her over- board;" "Take her to the cabin, sir. Bear her carefully; and a couple of you pic up that mulatto and bring her to-then carry her to her mistress. And, hark ye, lads, I'll forgive you all this time; but if ever you dare to lay your hands, nay, but a finger, ay, even a look, upon another lady of mine, I'll make :you wish you had seen the devil first,' said Vincent, as he walked toward the-main-hatch, down which he disappeared; whilst a loud huzza from the crew proclaimed their gratification at their captain's recovery, and their pleasure at 'having escaped punishment for their interference with his captve.   -I..    A TALE OF Tt  SOUTHERN  SEAS.        29 .                             , . - t            *      CHAPTER' V. "Is there no constancy in earthly things? No happiness in us but what must alter? No life without the heavy load of fortune . What miseries we are, and to ourselves! Even then, when full content sits by us, What daily sores and sorrows P--BEAUMONT AND FLETCHaR. HAVING endeavored to depict the situation of the fair Garcia, we will now return to the home from which she was so rudely and unexpectedly hurried. It was the morning after the night in which the most lovelyjand cherished inmate of that luxurious house had been removed from its precincts. Several gentlemen were in the large drawing-room, which looled forth'upon a wide piazza, up and down whose polished floor some two or three more cabelleroes were walking.- By the restless manner with which every now and then one or. the other of them would glance at his watch, or change his psitiofi, it could easily be seen that they were anxiously awaiting a summons to the matutinal meal, apparently already delayed beyond the usual hour. One, the eldest of the party, whose quick glancing eye, as he, from time to time, looked with a somewhat nervous glance toward the door, seemed even more troubled thari it his younger companions; but the expression on his countenance evinced4 deeper cast of anxiety than could have arisen from either slight vexations or the cravings of a keen appetite. He was a large and portly gentleman, who had-numbered some fifty-five or six years, of commanding appearance, and with an air of unmistakable breed- ing pervading his whole appearance. His large black eyes,'which still re- tained their brilliancy, and fine features, proved that in'his younger days he' must have been eminently handsome; and even now, though his head was thickly sprinkled with those telltales of time, silvery hairs, he would have been a dangerous rival to tnany a younger man, where ladies' smiles and favors were the prizes.    <pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6533-00000014"/> 30           THE OCEAN-BORN; After waiting some moments, this gentleman's anxiety overcame his patience, and taking up a small' hand-bell that was lying on the table, he loudly rang it; a servant quickly answered his summons, and inquired his wishes. "Where is your mistress Has she not yet made her appearance?" were the simple questions he asked; but the tone of voice in which they were put, betrayed considerable uneasiness. "I don't know, Sefnor; I have not seen Sefforita Garcia this morning," re- plied the boy. Go and find Bonita, then, and send her to me,' returned the gentleman -and the boy left the room. In a few moments, however, he returned and reported that Bonita had not yet left her mistress's chamber. With a rapidly increasing dread and anxiety, for which he could'not account, the old gentleman listened to the servant's answer. Leaving the drawing-room, he hastened to Garcia's room door, at which he knocked. At first he tapped gently, but no answer being made, he rapped louder-an ominous silence still reigned; and being now really alarmed, he called, Garcia! Bonita! Daughter!" in accents each time louder and more expres- sive of alarm. No reply was, however, returned to his numerous calls, and almost frantit with dread-it was Don Manuel, and his daughter was all in all to him-he dashed his foot against the door with such violence that the strong fastenings gave way, and he rushed into the chamber. Still was the fond father doomed to disappointment; for, as the reader knows, the sweet onewho had occupied that chamber was already far beyond the sound of her. parent's voice, else would she have quickly replied to the shrill and frantio shout he uttered, when he reached her couch and found it tenantless. Although the father's cry did not reach the ears of the one for whom it was intended, it was distinctly heard in the drawing-room, and on the piazza, and the gentlemen there, alarmed, came hurrying into the bed-chamber. The first one who entered was a gentleman of some twenty-five years of age; of a noble figure, and classical regularity of feature, upon whose face, and in whose' eye might be traced an anxiety almost as great as that exhibited  on the father's countenance, as hurrying toward Don Manuel he exclaimed- '   "In the name of Heaven, Seior, what ill has befallen you - Is the Sefforita Garcia ill " "Il, ill, Don Henrico," replied the old man, apparently bewildered, "'ill, ill, did you say Garcia was ill Take me to her, oh-! be quick, and take me to her-why did you keep it from me so long?"   A TALE OF THE SOUTHERN SEAS.          3 Becoming still more alarmed at the Don's reply, Ddn Henrico, for a momenta could scarcely think, until a touch from one of the group of gentle- men who were standing by in breathless expectation, biought him to his senses. "I did not say that Seforita Garcia was ill, Don Manuel; I asked if she were."                - What! don't you know where she is, Don Henrico? She is not here, the servants say she has not been out this morning; the door was locked- and look! the saints have mercy upon me, look I the grating has been re- moved from that window!" and as he spoke, the old Don hastened toward the window at which he pointed, and sprang through it into the garden, fol- lowed by Don Henrico, the rest of the gentlemen, and all the servants; for by this time the disappearance of their young mistress had become known throughout the house, and all the servants had collected in her room.  The poached ground, the broken shrubbery, the removal of the iron 'gat- ing, showed conclusively that violence had been used in the abduction of Garcia; and the broad path made by the cutter's crew as 'they passed through the garden to the boat, plainly pointed out the direetion they had taken. Headed by Don Manuel, the party of gentlemen, and iany of the servants, hurried to the water's edge, in hopes of finding further traces -pf the lost lady; but when they arrived at the bank, all that they could discover was the impression left in the soft mud by the cutter's bow. So soon as Don Manuel was convinced that his daughter had been' violently carried off, his whole manner changed; and from a nervous, fidgetty, anxious bearing, he became cool, collected, and determined-a deep and settled feel-. ing of revenge tsurped the place of the fearful forebodings of unknown ill that  had at first beset him-and he looked and acted liked the bold and gallant gentleman he was. Turning to Don Henrico he asked- "What think you of this, Sefor? Who is it that has dared to steal a noble Spanish lady from her father's house? Who, think you, is the man that has thus boldly set at defiance the wrath of a fatherrobbed of his only child- and that father a Spaniard and a soldier!" "Would to Heaven that I knew,' Don Manuel," replied Don Henrico, "right speedily would I make him pay the penalty his baseness merits. But the more I think of it, the more am I astonished, and at the greater loss am I to imagine who has dared 'to do you, and the laws oot the land and our honors, this wrong."     <pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6533-00000015"/> 32           THE OCEAN-BORN; "And you, gentlemen," asked Don Manuel of the others, "can you, from your knowledge of those who reside in the vicinity, throw any light on this fell outrage that will help a bereaved parent to recover his only child .?' But before any of the group had time to reply, a negro came running from the house; fear, intense fear, was depicted on etjryeature of his ebony face, and ere any one had time to ask him the cause of his hurry and alarm, he addressed his master in short sentences, and in an incoherent manner- "Oh, Seior! The saints protect us! We will all be murdered! The devil himself; the horned devil, the one the padres tell us about, has been here HSe was here last night. I saw him. Oh, master, take care of yourself " "Are you crazy or drunk, girrah!" interrupted Don Manuel,- who, m- patient to learn what the negro had to communicate, had attentively listened. to his broken sentences, without being able to make any thing out of them but the fact that the boy was much frightened. "Speak plain, and speak slow; nothing shall hurt you here. Tell us what it is that has scared you out of your wits, and where it was'you saw it; and speak to the purpose, for we have but little time to idle." More afraid of his master's anger than even the dread that affected his mind, the short tones of Don Manuel's voice brought the negro quickly to his 'senses, and in an intelligible and clear manner he told his master that, the night before, while he was fishing in the bay, a short distance up the coast, he had seen. a brig at anchor; prompted by curiosity, he had ap- proached her as nearly as he could on the shore, to see if he could make out what she came after-but that as he got nearly opposite to her, he recog- nized her to be a pirate that had captured a vessel in which he had been once coming up the coast, and as he was debating in his own mind whether or not he should return home and tell his master, he saw a boat full of armed men shove off from the brig, commanded by the captain; and he then be- came so much alarmed, that he ran into the woods and hid himself, and had not been able to muster up courage enough to leave his hiding place until then. "Has the brig gone?" hastily asked Don Manuel, when the boy came to this part of his narrative.  "Yes, master; she be clean gone." "Then a malison be on your coward heart, you black wretch, for not sooner telling us. Do you know your cowardice has enabled your mistress to be carried off?" And turning away from the boy, as if he was too much en-   A  AE O  TAL E OF TH THEN SEAS.       33 grossed with thoughts of his daughter to waste any upon him, Don Manuel spoke to Don Henrico and his companions. '"Yes, gentlemen, this negro's story solves the whole mystery. But, Heavens and earth! it is even worse that I could have imagined. My Garcia in the hands of that infamous pirate, Vincent I But her innocence and the saints will protect her--and if God shows favor to those that trust in him, we will end the career of that curse of the seas, that man without a heart, Frank Vincent!"  "To the death we'will follow you, Don Manuel," exclaimed with one voice Don Henrico aifd all the gentlemen of the party. "To the house, then, gentlemen; my thanks, you know, you have for your kindness-and when we recover my poor girl, and punish that worse than devil, my gratitude I'll prove for the gallant aid I will receive from you. But to the house to the house! time is, precious-every moment the dis- tance becomes greater between my Garcia and her home, and our plan has  yet to be matured." CHAPTER VI. "Oh! how this tyrant, doubt, torments my breast! My thoughts, like birds, who, frightened from their nest, Around the place where all was hushed before, Flutter, and hardly nestle any more."-OTWAY. FOR once fortune seemed to favor the cause of justice, though, as in many other cases, the means presented were those least expected. Whilst Don Manuel and his friends were proposing different means by which to obtain an armed vessel in the shortest possible time-some suggesting expresses to one port on the island, and some to another, in the hope of finding a man-of-war in harbor-word was brought to the mansion that the slayer Fairy had just touched on the coast a few miles from there, on some business with a neigh- boring planter. As soon as Don Manuel heard the intelligence, his eyes brightened, and a fierce gleam of satisfaction shot from them.    <pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6533-00000016"/> 34            T AtE OCEA-ORN; 3 ; "That is just the thing, gentlemen," he said.. "I will charter the brig, and-we will be able to right our wrong without troubling the government, and also learn this pirate that we can protect ourselves by our own means. "'But, Don Manuel," interrupted Don Henrico, "will not the captain of the slaver be afraid to risk his vessel against the notorious Fire-Fly? And, if he is not, is his brig heavy enough to encounter the freebooter's craft?" "I have had dealings, and am well acquainted with the captain of the slaver, and know him to be .a man entirely devoid of fear, whose sole end and aim is to accumulate money. In fact, he himself is almost a pirate; and he would like no better amusement than fighting the Fire-Fly, against which he has an ancient grudge, provided his pay-is sure. For that he is certain that I am responsible; and all that I am worth in the world I would cheerfully give to recover my precious Garcia. Oh, money!. money! what art thou worth when man has nothing but thee! And then, as to the' slaver's abili'ty-his brig is about the same size, and carries ubout the same number of guns as does the pirate. But, gentlemen, justice is on our side, and we will not be heretical enough even to dream of failure. Come, come, gentlemen," exclaimed the old man, " let us to horse; collect all the assist- ance we can as we go along, and then to sea, never to return alive until our duty and our end is accomplished." A few short hours afterward and a splendid-looking brig stood off from the coast, heading in the same direction the pirate had taken; for the free- booter's haunt was thought to be on the South American coast, and to that it was believed he would betake him.  The wind was both fresh and fair; and as the perfectly modelled vessel dashed high the spray, and rushed throughlthe water at the-rate of twelve knots an hour, the spirits of the bereaved father rose almost to ecstasy as he paced the deck, and imagined that in. a little while longer he would again clasp his beloved child in his arms. But between hopes and their realization there is a wide difference. .All that day and night, with every stitch of canvas spread that could be offered to the breeze, did the noble vessel speed on her way and yet nothing had been seen of the pirate's brig. The patience of the father was becoming exhausted, his feverish liopes were beginning rapidly to change almost to despair, and he would have had the direction of the brig's head changed. To this, however, the captain of the Fairy would not listen. He said "that their best chance was to keep the course they were then holding, and run until they made land, if they did not fall in with the blasted thief they   A TALE OF THE SOUTHERN SEAS.          35 were looking for before. If we make land," he continued, "which I don't think we will without meeting him, then we will head to the south'ard and run the coast down; and we will then certainly overhaul him, for he has a nest somewhere down the coast; and there, I am certain, he will strive to take the pretty bird he has stolen." Silenced ltut not re-assured by the captain's arguments, Don Manuel gave up his opposition, but hailed the look-out on the fore-to'gallant yard every five minutes, to know if'there was not a sail in sight. It had just struck four bells in the forenoon watch, and the old gentleman, almost, hopeless, was about hailing the yard, when the look-out cried- "Sail ho!" "Where away! where away!" burst from fifty eager voices, for Don Manuel's party numbered about sixty persins, besides the regular crew of the brig, and they all shared largely in the old Don's anxiety. "About two points on our larboard bow!" was the reply. "Can you make her out? How's she heading, and what sail does she carry?" were the questions quickly asked by the captain of the Fairy. "She's a square rigged brig, sir; standing to the south'ard, under nothingr but her to'sails, for'sail, and jib, sir," answered the seaman.  "Our man as sure as fate, Don Manuel," exclaimed the captain, as'hasten- ing forward he rapidly went up the fore-rigging with his glass, to take a closer look at the sail in sight. He had hardly brought his glass to bear upon the stranger ere he cried out in an excited and exulting voice-  "It is her! it is her! I know her by the steep of her masts-by the sharpness of her bows-by the squaieness of -her yards, and by her saucy rakehelly air. Great thundei! what a clinking slaver she'll make, when we capture her," he continued, as he gave a long and eager look at the beautiful proportions of the brig, which, lazily rising and falling with ,the swell of the sea, seemed bent upon no particular voyage-appeared a mere idler upon the ocean. A clear and ringing shout burst from those on deck when they heard the captain's confirmation of their hopes, that the vessel in sight was the one they were seeking. An extra pull was taken upon the halyards fore and aft; small sails, that could not possibly do any good, were rigged outside the cloud  of studding-sails which already covered the brig, so eager were her crew to get within reach of the pirate. A stern and determined calm settled upon Don Manuel and his party, as they silently looked to their swords and cut-    <pb n="36-37 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6533-00000017"/> 36            THE OOCI-BORN;  lasses, and loaded their pistols, preparatory to the desperate struggle they knew so soon awaited them. With her magazine open, her guns loaded, her crew at quarters, almost flying through the water, the Fairy hastened toward the object of her pur- suit. Soon she had approached within a mile and a half of her, and yet the pirate brig held carelessly on the same course she was heading when first discovered. Neither by making sail, altering her course, or by signal, did the freebooters give any sign that they were even cognizant of the existence of the craft that was rapidly approaching. Under the same light canvas she held on her way, as if she was either assured that nothing near her own ton- nage would interfere with her if they could avoid it, or else, that she was competent to anX emergency. The appareint confidence of the0pirate-for the captain of the Fairy had too correct a knowledge of the commanderof the Fire-Fly to think it care- 'lessness-had a perceptible effect. upon the movements pf 'the slaver. Her captain, fearing some: deep-laid scheme, took in his studding-sails and lighter canvas, and handing his top-gallant; sails, reduced his vessel to prqpe -trim  for fighting. To his surprise, however, and that of: his crew, even this clear expression of his determination. to engage,' produced no yisible, impression upon th- .:apparently inrpassab-le pirate, who, froa- anything they ,cduld, dis- voP  n in-his movements, seemed, even: yet, entirely jgnorant of the Fairy's; approach..                        .  .  .  To learn if such was the factf let us look at matters for a moment on'board the Fire-Fly.  Garcia pleading with the Plrate Captain to relinquish his miserable callng.    <pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC6533-00000018"/>   A TALE OT THE SOUTHERN SEAR.          39 CHAPTER VII. ' Alas I the breast that inly bleeds, Ha nought to fear from outward blow; Who falls from all he knows of bliss, Cares little into what abyss."-BYRON. WHLST many of the old saws, adages, and proverbs that are handed down from generation to generatidonby oral tradition, in those'benighted lands where the electric light diffused by the printing press has not yet pene- trated,t and by every variety of means through those favored countries vivi- fied by its presence--are substantially incorrect fin their doctrines, and tend only to keep in practice long since discovered falsities and ridiculous super- stitions; yet some few of these chips of thought from minds, that foiurished in the days lang syne, are replete with truth; and not one of , them is .more entitled to credence than that which admits no man to be so bad but that ' good still remains in him. It is true in regard to individuals; and we regret our experience of life prevents us from saying that they are few and far between; like the needle in the haystack, the good that is in them is not easily discovered. We are, however, charitable enough to believe, even in their cases, that hidden deep though it may be 'neath many a hard and animal feeling and demoniac sentiment, lurks-carefully put away, too good for daily use, as the peasant's wife cherishes her holyday attire-at least one ennobling trait, one humanizing principle. And we attribute its total Aon- appearance, its seeming absence, to the obtuseness of our perceptive facuRies, rather than imagine for a single moment that one who can, .by, even the outward semblance of form and feature, claim kindred with the pure and virtuous, should be more brutal than the brutes, more earthy than the du st  And Vincent, though he was pirate, murderer, desperado, by the welling up occasionally of some long-abandoned and almost forgotten honorable son- timent, which, struggling for vent through the superincumbent mass of un- - worthy passions that governed him and kept it smothered, would, for a space *  .             o     <pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC6533-00000019"/> THE OCUAN-BORN;  -evanescent, sometime' as the flash of the summer lightning, then, again, for a longer period, causing him, against his desire, to pause and reflect, even if it could not control his.eventual purpose--proved that within him still remained at least one little.spot not altogether hardened, a faint ray not quite extinguished of that Divine light which emanates from on high. So soon as Garcia recovered her senses and self-possession, unsettled by the near approach of the horrible death from which she had seen no possi- bility of escape, Vincent had sought another interview; and the lady's calm bearing, her eloquent, womanly appeals to his nobler nature, her prayers to be taken back to her parent, her defiance of his power, her contempt of, his advances, though so completely at his mercy, combined in producing an effect upon the captain's mind and heart, such as nothing before had ever effected; and he left her in a state of indecision and perplexity that to him was novel and unusual. Immediately upon reaching the deck,' after leaving the cabin, Vincent ordered sail to be taken in on the brig until she was reduced to the short canvas she was. carrying when discovered by the Fairy; for thelr was some- thing so congenial to the pirate captain's nature in the high' stern pride, the cool bravery, the entire self-confidence of the Spanish maiden, that, respect for the traits he could appreciate in her character, compelled him involun- tarily to entertain almost a feeling of veneration for the noble girl who, rising superior to the weaknesses of her sex, all undaunted by terrors enough to appal the bravest man, thus scornfully set him and his terrible authority at defiance. This sentiment of respect, mingled with pity, would, at inter- vals, become so powerful, that the pirate would almost gain his own consent to put his vessel about; and return the captive one, uninjured and in safety, to her father and her home. Then again, however, the remembrance of the lady's surpassing beauty would vividly present itself to his imagination; the fact, too, that she was entirely in his power-that no mortal influence could prevent him from compelling her submission to his wishes, would thrust itself upon his attention ; and the evil inclination, if it could not entirely overcome the better disposition, at least served to keep it completely in abey- ance; so that hour after hour passed, and he who generally acted from the impulse of a single thought, could neither obtain his own sanction to carry the captive lady back,' nor to make sail on his vessel, and take her forward to his haunt on shore. Thus was the captain of the Fire-Fly's mind occupied, as with irregular strides, now quick, now slow, indices of his state of feeling, he paced the   A TALE OF THE O SOUTHERN SEAS.   weather side of his quarter-deck. The alert look-out, on boaid the pirate, had reported "a sail in sight," as soon as the Fairy's royals showed above the horizon, and' even before the pirate had been seen by the look-outs of the slaver. Though the fact of a strange sail being in sight, and bearing down toward them, was duly reported by the officer of the watch to Vincent, he paid no attention to it, gave it no heed, and still continued his hasty walk and mental struggle. As we have seen, the Fairy steadily and rapidly advanced toward the pirate, whilst the officers and crew of the latter vessel, with eager eyes, were gazing, first in the direction of the daring craft, so rashly hurrying to meet them-as if unconscious of the dangers they were courting-and then, with wondering, though cautious glances, scanning the person of their dreaded commander. The astonishment of the freebooters was equally great as to the motives of the course pursued by each of the objects of their curiosity-both so directly the opposite of that they were accustomed to observe: for ordinarily all ves- sels used their best speed to give the Fire-Fly a wide berth, and her captain  had ever before been deeply interested in the fact of a strange sail being in sight.  No one, however, on board the pirate dared to intrude upon their captain, and supposing he had some premeditated purpose in his conduct, none were bold enough to take the liberty of reminding him  of the approach of the strange brig. Accidentally. looking up, when the Fairy was almost within gun-shot, Vin- cent for the first time became aware of the fact that there was a vessel even within sight; so engaged had he been with his own thoughts, that the reply made to the 'officer who had reported the vessel to him, was purely me-  chanical; neither the report nor the reply had made any impression upon his mind. Somewhat startled then was he, on casting his eyes to windward, to find a strange vessel, arimed to the teeth and full of men, almost within reach of him. Turning sharply around, he .sternly demanded of his first officer who was standing on the other side of' the deck: " What means this negligence, Mr. Leach I  Dearly shall you rue it unless your explanation proves satisfactory. I have no time to hearken to it now," he continued, interrupting le lieutenant as he was about commencing an explanation--" My glass! my glass ! we will punish the insolence of that bold gentleman coming down on us so fast, and theninq      into your dis-    <pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6533-00000020"/> 42            T 'E OOECA-BOBK ; erepascy.'  And seizing the telescope, Vincent took a long and steady look at the brig, which now hacdapproaehed within half a mile of the Fire-Fly. Something that surprised or pleased him had thepirate captain learned by  the aid of his glass, for an entirely different expression took possession of his countenance, as without uttering a word, half-handing, half-throwing the instru- ment to Leech, -he hurriedly left the deck, and in an instant after was con- fronting Garcia in the cabin. "Once more, and for the last time, lady, am I a suppliant before you," was Vincent's abrupt address to the Spanish maiden, as soon as he approached within a few feet of her. "I have offered you, what I have never tendered to woman before, what never female shall refuse again, my love I Love entire, complete, .without a rival or a sharer! I am free from all restraints and affec- tions that bind other men; I have neither home, country, kindred! Even ambition shall not divide your sway over me. You shall be my hope, my conscience, my deity, my every thing upon earth! Nay, even my soul, if there is such a thing, you shall sway to your lightest wish, if, as my wedded wife, too, not as my leman, if you will but grant me your heart! Or, I will not even ask so much for all I have to offer; if you will only grant me your hand and- act toward me as a wife, I will fulfill to the echo every word I have sp'oken! Say, will you again refuse me "  Immovable had Garcia sat whilst thepirate addressed her, and for a few - seconds after he ceased speaking she remained seated-then, quietly rising, i a low,.clear and even-toned voice, she answered: :"-Captain Vincent, you tell me that you love me; that you almost venerate, worship me! and yet, in the very face of your own assertions, you strive to compel me to do that which you know would be infinitely more horrible to  me than death and all its fearful accompaniments! Such love I cannot appreciate, neither can I accept it nor return it. I am but a woman--an unprotected womuan; seemingly completely in your power. Yet, if you have not-manliness enough in your nature to feel pity for my defencelessness,you will find that I am strong in my very weakness; beyond your chntrol by my extreme'hopelessness! And now you have my answer once more and for aye I To you, I will be nothing! Neither mistress norwife, now, nor never! And so do your worst, for I have that within me which places me beyond your reach, great as is your power over this vessel and its inmates." Stern looked the pirate, as with attentive ear he gathered each word and syllable uttered .by his captive; and, as she finished speaking, a gleam of such fierceness shot from his eye, as visibly foretold that the maiden's fortitude   A TAIML Or'THE   THE 8   AS.        48 would be put to the test; his voice, however, was pitched on even al softer  key than he generally-used, as he-replied-. - "Maiden, you have had your say, and have deemed it fit to slight my profe fered- love. You are bold, very bold, I grant, and think yoUrsblf strong enough to bear aught of earthly trouble that will be pressed upon you. You will, mayhap, and that ere many days are past, regret'the words you have just spoken! You seem to doubt it! But hearken, for I swear, and. mark well my oath, that you shall be my wedded wife I And that, too, by Jour own consent, voluntarily granted-now, I leave you. When next we meet, it will be to mairy you!"  And turning suddenly, Vincent lef the cabin as unceremoniously as he had entered it. --- . . * I , CHAPTER VH.: "Grinned horribly a ghastly smile, to hear His famine should be filled, and blessed his maw, Destined to that good hOUir."-MLTON. WHEN the Captain of the Fire-Fly again appeared on deck, and taking the trumpet from the officer on duty, assumed himself command of his vessel, all doubt as to what course he would pursue, in regard to the maiden from whom he had just parted, had vanished from his tnind. The tiny spark of huminn- ity, which still struggled for existence within him, again had been smothered 'by the torrent of his evil passions; and his subordinates felt, as they studied his countenance, that their commander was as supreme over them even'in their hardness of heart and wickedness as he was in intelligence and physical symmetry.  Vincent had been- absent from his post only a- few moments, but they had sufficed to bring the Fairy, which steadily advhnced, thdugh slowly, in conse quence of her/ diminished canvas, within long range of the rate brig; and the captain of the Fire-Fly had not-- issued an order, when the slaveiA bow - gun belched forth a cloud of heavy white smoke, and a well directed ball plunged into the water so near the freebooter, that it sent the briny drops ii "shower over her deck, and i-he person of her commander k,   -      <pb n="44-45 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6533-00000021"/> "           THE OCEAN-BORN; "The gentleman's in a hurry to open the dance, Mr. Leech," remarked Vincent, as he coolly wiped the spray from .his face, "and he seems acquainted with us too, for he sends his cold iron without wasting time with courtesies. But if luck holds, and 'it's said the devil takes care of his own, we will make him wish himself out of it in even a greater hurry." No order as to the movement or direction of' his vessel did the pirate even yet give; and the Fire-Fly, still heading to the south'ard, under the same sail as when first seen by her antagonist, gave no external manifestation of her captain's knowledge of the. existence of such a craft as the Fairy-though, steadily watching her as she neared him, he appeared busy plotting out the line of action he would adopt. Another: shot from. the slaver, now within range, which flew whistling over his head, and left a wide rent in the spanker. as it went hurtling through it on its course, recalled Vincent to the necessity of immediate action. And much to the satisfaction of his crew, who, crowded to windward, busy with conjectures:as to what they would be called upon to do first, were beginning to tire of their inactivity, he called out in a clear and ringing voice-  "All hands, make sail 1"- and- the seamen's wandering thoughts being brought back to their accustomed channels, by having something to occupy their hands, all their mentral energies' were immediately concentrated by en- deavoring to perform their mechanical. :duties thoroughly. "Loose top-gallant sails! Cast off themain-sail4 Cleat away the flying- jib! - Let fall, all--and .haul away!" were the oders :that, rapidly as they fell from Viicent's lips, were as speedily executed by the largeand well dis- ciplined crew of the pirate.                , , ' ' "Haul in'the lee-braces! .Keep her by. the wind, quarter-master!" next. commanded the freebooter; and in as short a time almost as we have taken to tell it, the Fire-Fly, with greatly accelerated speed, was dashing through the water on a line diagonal to that pursued by the Fairy, and directly athwart her course.  When first discovered by the Fairy the pirate was heading to the southward, and the wind being E. N. E. made it free for the Fire-Fly, whilst it was nearly dead astern for the slaver. So that though the pirate gained some advantage by the change of course, the Fairy yet retained the weather-guage of her. From the first discovery of the object of their search, intense excitement had taken possession of every person on. board the slaver; now, for the first time since she was launched, engaged in a laudable enterprise. The motives that caused this strong, stern, resolute feeling, though as different as the vai-     <pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC6533-00000022"/>   /               -     - A TALE OF THE SOUTHERN SEAS.           47 p. ous parties affected, yet served to produce the same result in each-a deep anxiety to test the strength of the formidable freebooter in sight, who seemed so cognizant of his might, confident of his ability to maintain his liberty, and so scornfully regardless of those who were hurrying on with the determina- tion of crushing his power. With Don Manuel and Don Henrico, an implacable hatred toward the cap- turer of Garcia, combined with all a father's affection for his only child, and an admirer's love for his mistress, rendered them impervious to doubt or dread as to the result of the approaching conflict. Their anxiety to engage at once, without heeding danger, or submitting to the delays incident. to ma- neuvering for an advantageous position, was so great that it had caused the captain of the Fairy much difficulty to prevent the'old Don from usurping the entire command of the brig.  Foster, the captain of the Fairy, was, when his interests were at stake, as brave as steel; nothing daunted, no danger caused him to swerve from his object where money was concerned. But having no other governing passion than the one absorbing lust for gold-which covered over and kept out of sight by a thousand schemes and pretexts, rules so many men-he was always cautious, habitually careful, when most excited. The amount he had at issue in the present crisis was a heavy one; the largest he had ever placed at the hazard of a single throw. If he were successful, he gained a great reward from Don Manuel, another frem the government, and a beautiful vessel, be- sides the honor, which, when it cost nothing, he appreciated. If he failed, he lost every thing. His position he clearly realized; and though he had no. disposition to shirk the trial, when the issue had to come, he felt every dispo- sition to act as cautiously and guardedly as circumstances would permit. The inexplicable apathy of the pirate was an enigma he could not solve; butfrom his knowledge of the character of the man who commanded the formidable craft, so peacefully rising and falling with the swell, within gun shot of a foe, he felt assured some deep laid scheme was concealed behind his apparent heedlessness. Don Manuel was for running the pirate brig right aboard, and thtis settle the matter, hana to hand, in the quickest possible time. The captain of the Fairy, however, was for lying-to, and engaging at long arms-length with the guns. The dispute between them was growing fast and furious, as to which policy they should adopt, when they were both surprised by seeing the brig,  which, a few seconds before, had been almost divested of sail, now covered with canvas, speeding toward the south'ard and eastward.    <pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC6533-00000023"/> 48            THE OOEAI-BORN', "He will escape  He will escape! Oh! my daughter! my daughter!" exclaimed Don Manuel, believing the pirate's object was to avoid a combat. Relieved on that score, by Foster, all the old gentleman's impatience and im- petuosity returned, and he swore that if the Fairy was not run within grap- pling distance of the pirate at once, he would blow Captain Foster's brains out there on his own quarter-deck. Maintaining his equanimity even under these trying circumstances, the cap- tain of the slaver strove to convince Don Manuel of the folly of such a course. But the Spaniard would not listen to reason or argument. "There, 'almost within my sight, is my daughter! a prisoner to a vile wretch, who, for what I know, or for aught I can do to prevent it, may be now heaping indignities upon her. And you, for fear of risking your paltry vessel, would have us backing and filling about here as if we were on a plea- sure party. Out upon such logic! Away with such reason! Be a man, Captain Foster; run us aboard the foul villains, and let our good arms, our -sthut hearts, and our just cause, battle for us, and we soon will have that infa- mous rascal and all his crew in our power," exclaimed Don Manuel-his anx- iety for his child's-safety, his fear that, despite all his exertions, he would not be in time to save his cherished daughter from dishonor, entirely perv'erting his judgment, and rendering him rash and headstrong as a child. Those who regard effects, with the clear, discerning eye of unbiased intel- lect, can readily discern errors attributable to the cause, but let their judg- ments, no matter how clear naturally, become subservient to their strongest and 'deepest feelings, and they will find that those things they most condemned in others they are eager to do themselves. So easy is it to bear the sorrows that afflict others, to underrate the misfortunes that afflict not ourselves. Don Manuel, under different circumstances, would greatly have blamed an- other for not listening to and heeding the reasons urged against the course he dictated, by the captain of the Fairy; yet now they' made no more impression upon his mind than would a bucket of water upon Sahara's thirsty plains, and he swore that it should be as he wished-or blood would come of it then. Looking around to take the noiseless suffrages of those on board as to the chances of resisting the Spaniard's command, Foster found, from the expres- sion of their countenances, that all his party would back Don Manuel's wishes; and as they were quite equal in numbers to the brig's crew, the probabilities of any benefit arising from a struggle were so slight that, contrary to his judg- ment and his inclination, the captain reluctantly consented to follow Don Manuel's plan; warning him and his party, even whilst agreeing, that it could   A TALE OF THE SO6TitN   gSEAS.       49 not result happily-reiterating that those who lived until morning would wish they had hearkened to his advice. Tle prophecy aid counsel of the seaman were alike unheeded by Don. Manuel, who only replied, "Run us aboard of the rascal, Captain Foster, and I'll take all the risk'" Thus compelled, the captain of the Fairy reluctantly ordered his helm a-starboard, and his lee-braces rounded-to; and in a few moments the slaver was again heading directly toward the Fire-Fly.  Vincent, who, so soon as Garcia had spurned his last overtures, had clearly and firmly determined upon the course he intended to pursue; and who, also, thanks to his glass, was aware of. the cause of the Fairy's pursuit, and of the names and purposes of many of the persons he had recognized upon' her deck, saw with scarcely controllable satisfaction this strange manceuvre of the slaver."  "By Neptune! Mr. Leech," he exclaimed to his lieutenant, "the dotards aboard that craft must think the Fire-Fly's turned into a Spanish gUar da-costa, ard is ready to run away, or be run into, as best suits their humor. Hell catch me, though, if they do not find themselves mistaken. Call the crew to quarters, sir! and man the larboard guns." These orders were almost superfluous; for the crew, confident that their comnmaider's object was not to run, and certain that a fight must shortly en- sue, had gone to quarters, and' were at their stations ere the call was made; and, as the pirate's guns were ever shotted, so soon as her magazine was opened she was ready to engage. Could one have looked upon that bright spot on the southern sea, with interests separate from the fate of the inmates of those two beautiful vessels,' how much of loveliness would his physical eyes have beheld, how much of loathsomeness would his mental vision have kenned. The sun, undim dld by a single cloud, was sending'his clear, glad rays, as if to nourish and cherish every thing in and on the placid sea, which, undis- turbed by waves, rolling in long, slow swells, reflected back again, seemingly with joy, the glittering light it had just received; and sole representatives of man, or his handiwork,'were the two brigs, which, as yet steadily careering on their courses, lent additional grandeur to the magnificent picture. But man, whcre'er he goes, no matter in what small force, carries with him the trail of the serpent, and in his wake he ever leaves sin, sorrow and death. The tranquillity of nature's surroundings, the placidity of ocean, the efful- gence of the king of day, were all unheeded by the mortals; who, with  -        'r    <pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC6533-00000024"/> 50           ThE OCEAN-BORN; thoughts centered upon the present, as' if it were the end, thought-but of carnage, conflict and revenge-and with all their speed were hastening to mar the beauty of the scene. Vincent, after glancing at his crew of bronzed and bearded outlaws, and seeing they were/all prepared, and but waited his beck to fulfil his utmost wishes, quietly turned to reconnoitre the movements of the Fairy. From the steadinesswith which the brig headed from him, from the silence of her men, and the absence of any of the customary civilities extended by men-of-war, , even when about to engage, the pirate felt assured that the object of the ap- proaching vessel must be to board him and end the struggle as soon as possible. i' The fools-the fools," he muttered; "not content with bearding the lion, they must thrust their heads into his very jaws. Well, I can take them easier so than otherwise; and, forsooth, my chance for capturing the old Don: alive is better thus-and I'll not baulk their wishes." By this time the Fairy was almost within musket shot of the pirate, coming do*n upon her, bows on, in a line so straight that, did not the Fire-Fly alter her position, she must be struck amidships. Of course, none of the guns of the slaver, except the bow ones, unless she yawed, could be brought to bear upon the pirate; and Don Manuel's anxiety was so intense to grapple with Vincent himself, hand-to-hand, that he would not permit thee captain of the Fairy, as le desired, to give the Fire-Fly a broadside before boarding, for fear of losing time. The silence on both vessels was so profound, and they had approached so near, that the creaking of the tiller-ropes could be heard from one to the other, and yet neither hail had been given nor gunfired. Suddenly Vincent sprang upon the weather arm-chest, bringing at least one-half his person above the hammock-netting, in full view of his pursuers, and shouted- "Hard down with the helm! Square away the main-topsail! Haul over the head-sheets 1 Steady so!" And as the nimble vessel, which worked like a pilot-boat, came up into the wind and lay-to, her bow pointing toward the stern of the Fairy, and her broadside bearing point blank upon the slaver- Fire!" in a ringing voice yelled the pirate captain, and the loud boom of his six larboard guns, as they sent their messengers of death into the devoted Fairy, replied fearfully to the volley of musketry that had greeted Vincent from the slaver's deck so soon as his person was visible over the netting. Far different was the effect produced by the two discharges; for the balls aimed at the pirate had gone singing harmlessly over his head and past his   A TALE 0F THE SOUTHERN SEAS.,          51 person, as if he were wound-proof, whi at every shot from the Fire-Fly's guns had worked a fearful havoc on board the Fairy. Fired, in fact, within fifty feet, even the wads from the pirate's guns had slain many of the slaver's crew; but Don Manuel, Don Henrico, and Captain Foster had escaped untouched; and, ere.. the smoke from the freebooter's cannon had fairly lifted from the Firy's deck, the vessels came together with' a heavy, grinding crash, and the grappling irons front each fell upon the other at the same time, whilst busy hands, with many plies of stout lanyard, lashed spar and spar in close embrace. "Kill the villains! No quarter to the pirates! Think of Garcia!" shouted Don Manuel, as, at the head of his own immediate friends, he strove to board the Fire-Fly from the Fairy's bow. "Down with the thieves! Overboard with the lubbers! Remember the reward!" was heard from the lips of Captain Foster, who, gallantly leading on his crew, strove to obtain a footing on the pirate's forecastle. "Into the sea with them! Into the sea with them.! Show yourselves, ye Fire-Flies!"Vincent cried in trumpet tones, as, at the head of half his men, -he opposed himself to Don Manuel's party, while Leech and the balance of the pirates were contending with the boarders on the bow. Chivalrously Don Manuel, Don Henrico, and their companions fought, nerved as their arms were by thoughts of her for whom they battled. But, notwithstanding they strove manfully, exposed their lives cheerfully, and rallied each other hopefully, yet all their efforts gained them no advantage;  and though now and again one would reach the pirate's deck, it was only to be driven back or thrust over into the ocean.  Vincent, though apparently cool and. collected, fought like a famished tiger. Every stroke of his cutlas left a gaping wound; yet the weapon always returned in time to meet the blows aimed at his person, and ward them harmless off. His men, too, seemed urged-on by a love for bloodshed, and struck with the ferocity of murderers and the vindictiveness of fiends; so that but a little time elapsed before nearly all the supporters of Don Manuel were forced, wounded and bleeding, back upon the Fairy's deck. The old Don, stoutly-seconded by Don Henrico, still held his own; and, side by side, their backs against the pirate's bulwark, Don Manuel and his friend were now, all unsupported, desperately fighting against most unequal odds. Quarter Vincent had offered, as his object was to capture, not slay them; 'but they both indignantly refused his protection, and replied to his offers of mercy with curses. ,    <pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC6533-00000025"/> 52            THEm oEAN-BORN; Determined to take them both alive, if such a thing was possible, Vincent urged his men to a rush, and charging down upon the two brave Spaniards, the pirates bore them to the deck by sheer force of numbers; but not until several of the ruffians had lost the numbers of their mess was the victory gained, for the gentlemen struggled whilst there was room to move a hand. After Don Manuel and Don Henrico were- overcome, it was but the work of a moment to disarm and bind them; and just as this was accomplished, a loud hurrah from the forecastle of the Fire-Fly informed Vincent that, his officer's party had also been successful. Captain Foster had done his best, had exerted himself to the utmost, and had been assisted handsomely by his crew. But the perfect indifference to danger manifested by the pirates, their entire recklessness of life, the sang froid with which they fought-as if it were a thing. of daily occurrence-, proved too much for his men; and when the captain of the Fairy fell, covered with gashes, all his followers that were able -immediately retreated to their own vessel. Such was the panic that seized upon the remnant of the Fairy's crew, when they found their leaders had been captured or killed, that, had it been in their power, they would at once have sought safety in flight. But so firmly had the vessels been fastened together at the commencement of the contest, that it was a work of no little time to separate them; and but feeble resistance they offered to the avalanche. of blood-stained, shouting devils, who, led on by Vincent and Leech, soon came sweeping across their eraft. "Quarter to all who throw down their arms and surrender!" were sounds that the Fairy's crew hailed with gratitude, as they were pealed forth by the pirate captain;. and the sharp ring of cutlas, pike and boarding-axe, as they were hastily cast away by hands afraid to. wield them, proved how pleased the slaver's men were to get off so easily. Deeply gratified was Vincent at the result of the conflict; he had been most desirous of getting possession of Don Manuel and Don Henrico; and both of them he had, unhurt, in his power. In far greater proportion was the pain experienced by Don Manuel upon finding that his rashness and headstrong obstinacy, which now he viewed in its proper light, had caused such deplorable results. Could he have done so, he would at once have ended his earthly troubles, by letting loose the flood- gates of his life. Even this was now beyond his control; for both his hands and feet were closely confined, and nothing but his mind, which he wished enthralled, was at liberty to act. The misery he suffered was indescribable-   A TALE OF THE SOUTHERN SEAS.           63 scarcely possible to imagine; for every deep and tender feeling of his nature as parent, soldier, man, was racked and tortured. Don Henrico, silently lying near his friend, in'like hapless situation, tram- meled with cords, suffered scarce less; but his heart was so moved by sym- pathy for the sorrows of his companion, that his own. troubles were nearly unheeded. Captain Foster, though his distress sprung from causes very different from those afflicting Don Manuel and Don Henrico, was also suffering exquisite anguish. He had lost his all! What more can man lose8 . To him wealth was everything, and his brig, his all, was gone forever; and he, even if. he escaped with life, would be pennyless. So much did these reflections worry the slaver captain, that even the pain of the many grievous wounds with which he was hacked, appeared light in comparison to his mental miseries. And thus it too often is in life; the happiness, the success of one, being built upon the ruin, the sorrow, and the painop others. But the end is not now, and transient joys are no evidence'of,/pbrmanent blips. The pirate's as well as the Fairy's crew had suffered severely, many of both having been killed and wounded; and busy, the balance of the day and all that night, were those who remained unhurt amongst the Fire-Fly's men in attending to their own and the slaver's maimed, in burying the, dead, in repairing the damage done by their shattering broadside to the Fairy, arid in removing from both vessels all traces of the sanguinary struggle. To the relief and astonishment of his prisoners, Vincent had caused them to be treated with the utmost kindness and consideration. Their wounded had received the same attentions that had been shown his own; their dead had been buried with the same parks of respect that had attended the com- mittal of his own killed to that great grave o seamen-the ocean. His'own men were even more s'prised at the conduct of the pirate captain than were his captives; but his commahnds had been imperative, and though the surly savages uttered many deep oaths as they stooped to assist the slaver's men to rise, or bore them below, Vincent's orders were in every case obeyed, if not with good will, at least with good faith. The prisoners, including Don Manuel, Don Henrico, and Captain Foster, were removed to the Fairy, on board of which vessel they were 'confined, with as much comfort to themselves as comported with their perfect security; and the brig and her freight was taken charge of by Leech, the first lieute- nant of the' Fire-Fly, and a large prize crew from the pirate. And when the sun arose the morning after the fight, its rays served-as -     f '                      A.    <pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC6533-00000026"/> 54            THEs ocEANI-BORBS; they had done thousands of times before, and will do times without number to come-to gild the pathway of successful might and remorseless vice, as it led in triumph and with pride, conquered right and vanquished virtue to its doom.. The brigs, too, as with snowy decks and canvas gently swelling to the summer breeze, they sailed lovingly together over the calm water, sub- ject to the same will, how much they looked as if they had accomplished some praiseworthy purpose, or were bent upon some generous errand! But such is life: that which is most fair to look upon seldom merits the meed its appearance so boldly challenges.  CHAPTER IX. "'Misfortune does not always wait on vice; Nor is success the constant guest of virtue.'-HAVARD. IT was the fifth day after the sea-fight. During all this time Garcia's situ- ation had beei of the most unpleasant character; one of all others the best calculated to break the spirit and subdue the constancy if it did not unsettle the-reason of the strongest nerved woman-a state of continued doubt, sus- pense, and dread, with yet nothing tangible or visible to struggle against and overcome. After Vincent left the cabin, and before the battle commenced, she and Bonita had been removed to the cabin-tier of the Fire-Fly, where, safe from danger, they remained during the contest. The noise of the conflict had reached them in wavy murmurs, indistinct, it is true, but still sufficiently plain to enable them to know that a struggle was pending; but with whom, or for what purpose--whether the pirate had attacked some peaceful merchantman, or whether it was-an avenger of blood striving to render justice to the free- booters, they were profoundly ignorant. Garcia hoped and prayed that the latter surmise might prove correct, and that she might be freed from her bondage, even by the swamping or blowing- up of the pirate-brig, and at the expense of her existence-for nothing, save religious scruples, prevented the maiden from courting the embraces of the great assuager of human woes; death, aside from the sin of self-murder, had   A TALE OF TBE SOUiTHiE    SEAS.    /   55 no terrors comparable to the fears she entertained for the other dangers that 'encompaqsed her.  No satisfaction, however, or alleviation,.did the-battle bring to theSpanish maiden; for so soon as it was over, she, with her servant, whose companion- ship was all the consolation she possessed, were re-conveyed to the cabin. /Here they found an unpleasant alteration; the light of day had been excluded by fastening in the dead-lights that closed the stern-windows, and a small lamp suspended from a beam overhead, whose faint rays only served to cast a melancholy, gloomy illumination through the apartment, in itself enough to depress one's spirits, was all the light allowed them. Bonita was forbidden to leave the cabin; their food was brought by an attendant, who, though courteous in his manners, never uttered a word; and thus, confined, ignorant of whither they were traveling, doubtful how long their security of person would last, trembling each moment for fear of violence, or that they would be separated from each other, the mistress and the servant had passed four tedious, tedious days and nights.  This dreadful monotony. was interrupted on the morning of the fifth day, by a knock on the door that'led to the deck; bidding the person enter-for it was an idle ceremony, the door being fastened on the outside-Garcia looked up with a sickening sensatioh, expecting to see Vincent enter, and be again tormented by his importunities. To her agreeable surprise, instead of the pirate-captain, it was Leech, his first officer, who sought:admittance. Respect- fully saluting the lady, he informed her "that it was Captain Vincent's order that she should accompany him."  It was folly to refuse; but still Garcia was so loth to leave the cabin which had afforded her a sort 'of negative protection, that she could not refrain from appealing to the lieutenant. "Oh! where am I to go?  Have pity upon me," she sobbed, -" and pro- tect me, if you are a man 1 Remember the mother that bore you, and for her sake, if not for mine, tell me what new grief is now in store for. me'l" Touched by the lady's loveliness and distress--for Leech, though an officer, was an illiterate man, and consequently had not that flinty obduracy of heart that belonged to Vincent, and is always attached to educated villany, he kindly answered,  "I, lady, intend you no' harmi;: where, or for what you are summoned I am not at liberty to say. My captain's commands are thatyou follow me; and it will be worse than useless for you to resist." ' Come, then, Bonita, let u% go. When the worst comes, this hideous an- , *    -   .  .    ^      -  ?    <pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC6533-00000027"/> 56            THE OCEAN-BORN; ticipation will have ended," said'Garcia, turning to the mulatto. But the offi- cer motioned the girl back, saying she could not accompany them, that she must remain behind. And now, feeling as if her last earthly stay had been removed, with a suffocating sense of undefined dread weighing heavily upon 'her breast, and the sobs and lamentations of Bonita ringing in her ears, the maiden, preceded by Leech, left the cabin.                 - On reaching the deck, Garcia was startled to find that, instead of being at sea, as she expected, the Fire-Fly was--at anchor in a small and completely land-locked bay. The familiar and luxurious tropical vegetation on the shores 'around, reminded her so forcibly of her lost home, that for a moment, and her heart fluttered wildly at the thought, she imagined that the pirate had relented of his cruelty, and intended returning her safe to her bereaved father. A closer look at the surrounding objects convinced her that the land in sight-' was one she never before had seen; the sloping banks, covered with magnifi- cent trees, some pendant with feathery foliage, others with broad, fan-like leaves-the birds that fluttered, chirped, and. sung joyously in their branches-- the houses, indistinctly seen 'mid the vines that covered them-;-the mirrored surface of the limpid water-,-the. symmetrical vessel that floated upon it near the Fire-Fly-the clear, blue heavens overhead-all imaged quiet and con- tent. But it was only the peace and happiness of nature and of nature's works; to Garcia it was an unfamiliar scene that held forth no hope of deliv- erance-and stupefied by the reaction of -her own emotions, she followed the footsteps of her conductor passively, scarce conscious she was possessed of life. So wo-begone did the maiden look that Leech's heart, hard as it was, moved with pity for her sufferings; and he handed her dowfi the side into the boat waiting for them tenderly, as if she had been an infant. When the boat landed at the nearest shore, supported by the officer, she accompanied him, heedless of where he led.          .     j Thusin/ a trance as it were-for nothing, so deadens the faclities, so be- numbs the mind,- so stagnates' life without stopping the breath, is hopeless grief-Garcia. was. conducted through the forest for nearly half a mile from the bay., -          .          , Leech, her only attendant,'had not addressed a word to her; and the fresh air, the exerise, the'beauty, though unheeded, and the stillness of every thing around' was beginning' t revive the lady, and call back once more her scattered -senses, when the path they were following turned abruptly to the right-and a scene so unexpected, so like a vision, so horrible to believe, was suddenly pre-   A- TALE OF THE SOUTE     SEAS.        57 sented to the maiden's view, that pausing with dilating eyes and gasping breath for .a sufficient space to convince her bewildered faculties that it was not some awful phantasy, but a shocking reality before her, without a groan, a sob or sound, heavily she sunk upon, the ground; and there: she lay, so still, so breathless, that it seemed as if the tyrant death for once had in pity stepped between a mortal and her miseries. No childish bughear was it that had produced so great an effect upon the strong nerves and bold heart of the brave Spanish girl, but a scene, such as angels look down-upon-with blush4s and regret, and fiends contemplate with gladsome glee; it was a tableaux, such as the arch-mocker himself would have been proud of-so diabolical was the malice it evinced, so great the skill displayed in making God's beauties of mind and- matter subservient to man's  fell purposes.                     . Where Garcia fell, the path she had pursued opened upon a natural am- phitheatre in the bosom  of the dense woods-an oval space, some hundred paces in its greatest length, covered with thick, short grass, closely'shut. in. by tall trees, as if to fence it off from aught impure. But man had founid his way there; and what seemed intended by Deity for a chapel, where creature could offer up orisons to Creator, with nothing to intercept his view,of the upper sphere but the imperfections of his' vision, was- now fitted up with all the appliances, was on the point of being converted into a huge slaughter-pen.. The victims were there, ready, waiting-and  they were men! The execu- tioner, too, w- there, ready, waiting-and,he also was man! Draw 6  *-: a  semi-circle, its centre facing .a small :hut placed just on the edge of tthe Fiie of trees, stood al the prisoners captured on board the Fairy. In the middle of the line,'suppoited on either hand by Don Henrico and Captain Foster, was Don Manuel; whilst the others of the crew, a sailor0 and civilian alternately, made up the balance of the fearful string. Their hands bound behind them, their legs fettered together, and a huge pirates-with a cocked ship's pistol in his hand, standing behind each captive, showed at a glance the stern object of the noiseless parade. - At the door of the hut$ and wherehe could command the varying features of each victim in the  circle, stood Vincent, in an attitude'as easy and non- chalant, and with a  face as smiling as if -he 'were gazing upon a holyday show, or some  harmless spectacle with which he had no connection.   The place where the Spanish maiden dropped, was in funl view of every person in that dread array; and though their own situations, standing as they were on the very line that divides time's brink from eternity, seemed-to leave    <pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC6533-00000028"/> 58            TE OOB!m-BORN; no room in their minds for thoughts foreign to their own plight, yet a thrillI an electric shock of pity for the sorrows of the girl, shivered along the line of doomed ones, causing it to bend and waver. like a ribbon in the wind. Prepared to meet their own fates with calmness, ejaculations of anger and mortification began to arise from the captives at their inability to render aid to female loveliness in distress; but the rough grasps of their guards, and the cold muzzles of the heavy pistols that were pressed against their heads soon reduced them all to silence, save Don Manuel. The father had been kept in complete ignorance as to the situation of his child. Whilst the daughter, until she saw him before her, bound and ready to be murdered, knew not that her parent was absent from his home. So deathly oppressive were the sensations that came upon the-Spaniard, when he first beheld his darling girl, that it required all the pride of his cha- racter and the remembrance that- his weakness would only afford additional triumph to his sneering foe, to prevent the old man from swooning. But by a strong effort he controlled his feelings enough to maintain his senses, and gave them vent by heaping revilings and taunts upon Vincent, "Devil " he exclaimed, addressing the pirate, "you have-destroyed my child's peace; now finish your fell work, by ending her life with her father's! or have you just brought her here that the cup of your fiendish malice may be full! that you may revel in the tears of a daughter witnessing a father's death, and feast your eyes with the torments of a father seeing before him as he dies, the wreck and dishonored remains of what was" his earthly bliss! Thief! liar! hell-hound!" he continued, "if you have a drop of manly blood in you, I challenge you to loose my hands! and with my feet in shackles, ll make you feel the force of a father's revenge 1"And wrought almost to madness by the poignancy of his emotions, and his desire to punish the au- thor of his wrongs-who stood in front-of him smilingly listening-Don Manuel struggled so powerfully to break'his bonds, that though he could not start the stout cord that bound him, he and' the seaman who was holding him came forcibly to the ground.  A glance from Vincent, and several sailors hurried from the shelter of the woods, and assisted their companion to place the old man, foaming at the mouth and grinding his teeth, again in an upright position. Leech, so soon as Garcia fainted, had taken her in his arms and bore her to the hut, where, by the use of brandy-the only stimulant within his reach-he had succeeded in ieviving her; and just as her father had regained his feet, she rushed past Vincent-who remained standing, apparently a mere *!, , j , * }   A TALE OF TEE GO1THEN SES.           59 spectator, in front of the cabin-and throwing herself upon Don Manuel's breast, her arms clasped tightly about his neck, she cried, "My father!t oh, my dear father! I Sam still your own daughter! your  own, own Garcia! I am pure, and all free from dishonor; and will ever so remain while life lasts!" (i Thank God for that, my child!" burst from Don Manuel. "Pirate i" he continued, addressing Vincent, " now do your worst; you can kill the parent and the child with th6esame bullet!" Instead of replying to Don Manuel, Vincent spoke to Garcia, saying, ' "Come, lady, if you have aught to say to that old man, speak it quickly, for his lease of life is of the shortest-he and his companions have but five minutes to live. I am getting tired of this nonsense, and have already Wasted more time than I have to lose." "Spare them 1 Oh: for pity's sake, spare them t What can their deaths benefit you?" plead the girl, as, leaving her father's neck, she hastened to the pirate-captain, and fell upon her knees at his feet. "For your soul's sake, save them I Think! you are- about to hurry them, unprepared, into the presence of the Great King, who, ere long, will judge your actions I Show them mercy, that you may receive it in your time of need r" -Lovely enough to move anything not harder than the hinges of the gates of hell, looked the Spanish maid, as, with colorless cheeks, lustrous eyes, and long, disheveled hair, she crouched upon the earth,her gaze riveted on, Vin- cent's face, in the vain hope of tracing upon his smooth, smiling, sneering features, some gleam of-pity.  But all unmoved was the pirate, as far as outward symptom evidenced, by either her beauty or her words, "For my sake, then, if not for your soul's sake, spare them!" continued Garcia, her anxiety for her father overcoming all other feelings. "You said that you loved me; prove it, by saving my father and his friends 1" A transient expression of gratification,tsuppressed almost as soon as exhib- ited, was visible on Vincents countenance as he answered, W "Why should I heed your supplicationslady t What was the answer you vouchsafed me when a pleader to you   Was my prayer granted! Why, then, should I hearken to yours  But I am not so hard-hearted as you think; it rests with you whether your father lives or dies. As my father-in-law I will spare his life, and give his comrades their freedom for his 'sake. No other thing shall save them. I have said it, and my purpose is fixed."'  /s A If ' ace - t e a, t        *    <pb n="60-61 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6533-00000029"/> 60           THE OOEA1-BOR; "My father! oh, my father  God strengthen me-what shall I do i" gasped the poor girl, shivering convulsively with excessive agitation. "' Make your choice quickly, lady; two minutes more, and I give the word to fire," continued the pirate, as he closely watched the effects of the mental struggle that was racking Garcia's fiame.  "Save them! save them t and do with me as you will!" exclaimed the noble girl; affection for her beloved father, and pity for his companions, causing her entirely to forget self and the sacrifice, worse than death, that she was making. "You will marry me here, now; and trust to my honor. to send your father and his friefids home 8" asked Vincent. "Yes yes! if you will-promise to save them," she replied. ," The priest! the priest!" shouted the piiate; ,and, accompanied by a couple of seamen, as if they had had him in waiting, a Spanish friar, the fruit of some former capture, appeared on the edge of the forest. Witlh trembling steps the padre approached, doubtful whether it was not to his own death he was being led. ,      .  -"Marry that lady and I, sir priest," said Vincent, as sodn as the church- man was'within speaking distance, "and your freedom shall be your. fee.". ' Time and again had' Don Manuel called to Garcia, and besought her to cease pleadi'g'with the pirate, but to let him slay them 'all.. So great, how- ever, was her anxiety to effect her oqbjedt and save his life, that she had not heard her'father's supplications.  " .      ' When the priest first appeared, the captives thought hecame to give them final absolution, preparatory to their execution; and he had half finished the  marriage ceremony before even Don Manuel suspected his. object. So soon as he did imagine the duty the priest was engaged in, the old Spaniard heaped execrations so loud and fierce upon his daughter's head for disgracing herself, even to save his life, that, had she heard them; the -maiden would have drawn back from the rash promise she had made. But she was as in a dream, a waking stupor, having but one-idea in the whole world, the hope of saving a dear life-arid she heard nor saw nothing--had' plighted her solemn vows to love, cherish, and obey the man before her, scarce con- scious she had spoken. Thus was the pirate's oath accomplished. There, as has' happened on many another spot, in the glare of day, in the bright sunlight,. in the face of, surrounding men, was singleness of heart, strength of purpose, woman's nobility, sacrificed upon the altar of filial affection. There, as is not seldom      , ;S       .. -Defeat bald Capture of the Pirate Captain by the Ooa-Bsrv  ^    <pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC6533-00000030"/> 62        A TALE OF THE SOUTHERN SEAS. witnessed by the chui'ch's blessing, was purity of ind, youthful innocence, and maiden loveliness, harnessed for life to dpravity of feeling, full-blown wickedness and hardened crime. And vice, armed in panoply of proof, added onre'more to his many victories over defenseless virtue. Two hours after the celebration of this inauspicious marriage, the slaver brig, dismantled /f her guns, deprived of every offensive and defensive weapon, and again under the charge of' Captain Foster, stood out to sea; and, as she rapidly disappeared, hard-indeed would it have been to have told in which breast lodged the heaviest heart-- in that of the father, who, com- pelled against his will to seek his luxurious home, yet forced to leave behind him, lost forever, the only charm that made life desirable; or in that of the daughter,who, to save a parent's life, had become a pirate's bride, with nothing t console or comfort her in the gloomy present, or more threatening future, but the consciousness of -her own rectitude.  Vincent of all the persons who had lately thronged the shores of that small bay, was the only one who felt a sentiment even akin to joy; and at what a fearful amount of suffering to innocent numbers had his gratification beenfputchased. What conqueror though, from Napoleon to the pettiest Indian chief, ever stopped to count the cost to others of the triumphs they enjoyed t '  HAPTER X. "Affliction isthe wholesome soil of virtue; Where patience, honor, sweet humanity. Calm fortitude take root and strongly flourish,"-MALLET. TIME, of all things known to man, is the only one whose movements ever can be relied upon, about whose progress there is neither uncertainty nor variableness; as he steadily glides on, he takes the same measured stride now that he started with at the commencement of his long journey, toward eter- nity, nothing accelerating his pace, nothing retarding the regular, ceaseless advance of his irresistible motion. To mortals, fanned by Time's wings as he .    .S s A a, w                              e    , *^e   THE OCEAX-BOIV;             63 flits along, his pace seems unequal; but the hour that passed so quickly and unheeded over the gladsome heart, was of the same 'duration, varied not a second's length from the one that appeared an age to the tortured breast. Happy for us that it is so, else would our woes crush us. But for our com- fort, the hand that bears the poison, carries also the antidote; and the old man with the scythe, whilst he places the bitter chalice to laughing lips on this side, smooths the troubled brow, and dries the fast-falling tears on that. Wearily, wearily had a year passed over Garcia since she became the pirate's bride. During all that time no word had she heard from her father or her friends. But patiently, uncomplainingly, without a murmur she had borne her fate-a Christian woman, though a freebooter's wife! The value of the sacrifice she had made she properly estimated; but though she had saved the lives'of her father and his friends at the expense of her all of earthly comfort, yet, with woman's angelic disinterestedness, so difficult for man to understand, in thinking of the boon she had gained for otheis, she regretted not the equivalent that obtained it. -Andinfluenced by that genuine religion which vaunteth not itself, but that really believes it benefits man nothing to gain the whole world, if thereby he loses his own soul; feeling that the past was irrevocable, the futuie uncertain, and the present all that was controllable, valiantly she strove to so act that if her happiness was blasted here, it would only be the more entire hereafter. Vincent loved his wife; but it. was, as man's love too often is, a selfish feeling. His heart had felt that aching void occasioned by the need of something lovable; cut off by his puriits from the virtuous, and- vitue's ways, he yet had remaining within him enough of his early sentim'ets to prevent his mental, inner longings from being satisfied by sensual gratifica- tions; and he was too bad himself, too thorogly acquainted with .tie depravity of humanity, when governed by naught higher than ambition, lust, or avarice, to entertain any emotion deeper than contempt for those libels upon their sex-the woman who would voluntarily have shared his lot. Garcia's greatness of soul, her gentle patience, her enduring fortitude, the pirate appreciated; and though he could not, or at least would not, under- stand or sympathize with the cause of her strength, he yet was a happier man foi her presence. A better man, too, he was since his marriage; for though a pirate still, his wife's tearless eloquence had prevailed upon him to ever spare the lives of those he robbed-and, save in actual conflict, since their captain's nuptials, the Fire-Fly's crew had not committed a murder. For her husband, the Spanish lady felt no love; he was kind,to her,    <pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC6533-00000031"/> "        A TALE OF TEE SOUTHEBRN SEAS. treated her tenderly, and saving he insisted always upon taking her-to sea - with him, and would not relinquish his terrible trade for her pleadings, he strove to gratify her slightest wish; but a stern sense of duty, a morality that looked higher than the technicalities of law, or the usages of every-day ' life for its definition, assumed with her the stead of affection; and governed ,by its dictates, she was, what many men are fortunate enough to possess, yet  undervalue until the treasure is lost, in the widest extent of its signification- a wife! When the piratercrew first learned their captain had married his captivei they looked upon it as a flaunting jest, that soon would pall upon him-and they passed it silently by. But when they found that, contrary to established custom, he intended to respect the vows he had idly spoken, and caused them to treat Garcia with the same courtesy exacted*by himself, they rebelled; and it required all Vincent's authority and determination to drive them into acquiescence with his will. When they became acquainted with the lady's character, a changertook place in the feelings of the pirates; the civilities that had been extorted from them by fear of their commander's ven- geance, were now proffered as free-will offerings. Were they wounded, Garcia soothed their pains by her soft words .and tender sympathies; if ill and suffering, -she assuaged their miseries'by gentle nursing and womanly attentions. And before she had been amongst them many months, so con- ciliating is the power of puit-y and kindness, that the most hardened wretch who trod the Fire-Fly's deck- would not have raised a finger to harm her- looked upon her as a guardian angel. Severe as were the trials which had already racked her heart, until she believed its sensibilities must be benumbed, Garcia knew that another griev- ous sorrow was yet in store for her. She was about to become a mother! And under what disheartening circumstances would she have to pass through that' dread ordeal entailed upon earth's daughters as penance for Eve's trans- gression. No kind friends surrounded her; no home-sympathies cheered her; no sister, mother, was there to comfort her; and except the affectionate atten. tions of the poor slave, Bonita, who by every effort that came within the scope of her ability, strove to obliterate from her mistress' mind the share she had- had in her troubles, Garcia, so far as her feelings were concerned, was now, in her time of dread and danger, alone on the heaving, angry ocean, with not 'even a Christian hand to close her eyes should death' claim her.     \       I , THE OOEAJBOBN;  f         65 Vincent, to gratify a whim that his child's firsthreath should be the salt air, lad put to sea when hiswife most desired to remain on shore; and now, just as the iady's full time was complete, as if to heap new terrors upon her head, the Fire-Fly was contending against a fierce gale, struggling with the huge waves of the rough Atlantic. Clouds, heavy and black, like death-palls,scudded- across the heavens; the howling wind whistled and sang fearfully, as, it rattled through the rigging; and the vessel trembled and quaked, and her timbers groaned mournfully as she'was tossed about by the strong waves; and thus, while the storm-king raged in his wildest might, was the Ocean-Born ushered into existence. There, amid the crash of elements, seething wateir under, around, tempes- tuous winds and cursing sailors overhead, was a ray of brightness and purity, direct from Deity, admitted into the cabip -of the pirate brig. And the'spirit of the mother, as she gazed upon her beauteous boy, ex- perienced a sensation of inexpressible relief; foi; though the vessel was in imminent danger, though the storm increased in violence, no terrors did it bring to her. - A fiesh and sparkling fount of joy had beeq openedwin her bosom; and she knew that if it were her Master's will that she and her innocent babe were to be summoned .hence,Ait would be no loss to, her, and the child's great gain; or if it were ordained that they yere yet to live, she' felt a foretaste of the pleasure 'she would find in teaching the soul that had been entrusted to her care, its proper duty, and anticipated the labor of love thaewould devolve upon her in shielding her pure Ione from temptations, in " warding off such miseries as she had suffered from the spirit of her dear Ocean-Born.  , /    <pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC6533-00000032"/> A TALE OF lTHE 'S OTHRN SEA.. -CHAPTER XI. "It often falls, in course of human life, That right long time is overborne of wrong, Through avarice, or power; or guile, or strife, That weakens her, and makes her party strong; But justice, though her doom she do prolong, Yet at the last she will her own cause right.7"-SPENSER IN life, stern, real, actual life, there is no such thing as an isolated feeling-- a sentiment complete within itself-self-produced, self-satisfied; nor an action that, in its conception or fruition, does not draw within the circle'of its con- sequences, those apparently beyond the limits of its influence, Could the dense veil thrown over man's mental nature by the crudities and opacities of his animal belongings be removed for an instant, he would behold the harmonious symmetry, the glorious beauty and regularity of that faultless chain of causes and effects, which; forged perfect in its completeness, no link wanting at the creation, reaches through all time, to be continued through- out all eternity. ' Observing things as .we now do, partially, by interrupted glimpses, never getting a glance at more than a small fragment, we persuade ourselves nevertheless, that what we are cognizant of is the whole; and like the antiquary, who from an imperfect brick, endeavors to picture forth the size, dimensions and uses of the edifice of which it formed a part, we, poor moles that we are, strive to square God's justice. by our appreciation of our own worthiness. Whilst assenting with our lips So the truths promulgated by the inspired volume, we act as if this present state of existence was not to be followed by another. Our deeds prove, talk as we may, that we prefer an almost infinitesimal'amount of happiness'here, to an all-sufficing share of be- atitude hereafter. Else would pot the countries so strangely miscalled Chris- tian, be the scenes of so many uncharitable acts, the abiding places of so many suffering, starving poor, the haunts of so much moral depravity and legalized rascality. Nor would the world at large, which has been making   such rapid progress in intellectual improvement, be yet not one jot-or tittle more advanced in moral rectitude than it was a thousand years ago. Don Manuel differed not from others, and his human nature rebelled fiercely against.the cross which it was his fate to bear. He thought it was an injus- tice that he, of all his neighbors, shoutlj  selected as the one to be punished. He asked himself what he had done to merit this severe affliction I Wherein he was worse than others ? Had he not always been honest? 'Attended church, been a good master and a good citizen ? And almost tempted tofor- swear his belief in Deity, he concentrated all his hopes, thoughts and aspira- tions upon the anticipation of revenge. The Fairy's voyage from the Pirate's haunt-a small island to the south- ward and westward of St. Thomas--so far as accidents of wind and water were concerned had been a prosperous one. But never men who had just escaped a sudden and fearful death, landed from vessel with less of thankful- ness and morel malignancy in their hearts, than did Don Manuel, Don Henri- co and Captain Foster, when, after a few days passage they once more found themselves at the old Spaniard's house. Captain Fosters greatest grief, arising from  the loss he had sustained by the seizure of his guns and arms by the pirate, and by his failure to secure the large reward that he fully expected to realize by the capture of the free- booters, was within the reach of consolation, though the petty disappointment he had met with seemed to harass him almost as much as the greater and more positive trouble that afflicted his companions, A check from Don Mal- uel on his banker in Havana, for the full amount of the money he had calcu- lated upon making, in addition to the value of the cannon he had been de- prived of, soon restored the captain to a state of comparative happiness. Money, that panacea to so many of the ills of life, and which though it is necessary to comfort, is yet unable to command it-could not soothe the an- guish that oppressed Don Manuel and Don Henrico.. Of lucre, they both possessed more than enough, and either of them would willingly have given all they had of this world's goods could they have restored the lost Garcia to her home.                              ' To Don Manuel, without his daughter, every thing, life itself, seemed value- less. She had been all in d11 to him. His' wealth, property, standing in so- ciety, had only beetidear to him because it enabledhbim to Render more com- fortable and happy his cherished and only child. Don Henrico loved  arcia with the enthusiastic abandonment of a noble nature, certain that the object which claimed its admiration was entirely wor-     <pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC6533-00000033"/> 68        A TALE OF TE SO STHEIN   EAS. thy of the precious heart-treasures lavished upon it. The maiden, it is true, had not given voice to her sentiments in words, but Henrico felt assured from- the language he had read in her speaking eyes, that nothing but the peculiar and unexpected situation in which she found herself prevented Garcia from doing justice to his devotion by returning his adoration. Little wonder then that the feelings of the lover, so rudely robbed of his mistress, were almost as poignant as those of the father so cruelly deprived of his daughter.. No time, however, did the gentlemen waste in useless and idle repinings; but accompanied by Captain Foster, whose services Dohi Manuel retained at'a heavy fee, they set off by express at once for the capital to lay their griev- ances before the captain-general of the island. This functionaly, touched by compassion for the father's visible distress, and by pity mingled with sincere admiration,foir his heroic child, immediately or- dered all the naval force at his disposal to sea forthwith; offering a generous bounty for the capture of the pirate's vessel, and a still more liberal reward if they succeeded in rescuing Garcia. The Spanish men-of-war, accompanied by Don Manuel, Don Henrico and Captain Foster, ransacked every island, bight and bayou in the West Indies; untiringly they cruized upon the open sea, along the Main, and in and out through every intricate passage in that labyrinth of islands ahd sand keys that lies between the tenth and thirtieth degrees of north latitude, for months without success; and though they boarded every thing, not smaller than a cockle shell, they came in sight of-not the slightest tidings even could they gather of the whereabouts of the Fire-Fly. Guided by Captain Foster, they easily discovered the island where the dreadful marriage had taken place; but nothing found they there save a few deserted houses to show that man had ever visited the spot before-no living soul was in the vicinity. In hopes that Vincent, lured by its'security from weather and curious eyes, would return to that land-locked bay; a vessel was stationed there to intercept him, but though she faithfully maintained her po- sition until hope became hopeless; nothing .did she ever see of the friebooter's craft. Thus, after months had passed without any intelligence having been gained of Vincent, his vessel, or the lost one, supposing the pirate had betaken his desperate craft to other waters, where his evil fame,was not so widely dissem- inated, the government in despair gave up the pursuit, and the men-of-war V.   THE OOEAN-BON;             69 returned to their usual employment of taking pleasure trips up and down the coast. Though government became weary of seeking for the marauder, not so Don Manuel. He swore that while life lasted, or until he either recovered his lost child or slew the destroyer of his and her happiness, he would never relinquish his search for the Fire-Fly. To enable him to carry his purpose into execution he purchased, and fitted out with small-arms of all kinds and twenty brass cannon, a beautiful clipper- built ship of four hundred tons burden-just twice the. size of the pirate's brig. IDon Henrico warmly approved of Don Manuel's plan; though the expense of the outfit was large, yet so great was the old man's wealth that it was not beyond his means, and it was only at the urgent solicitation of Don Henrico, and to ease his mind, that his friend permitted him to share the cost of the vessel that was dedicated to the recapture or revenge of Garcia. The Fairy, at Don Manuel's request, had been sold, and pleased to think he would at some time have the gratification of paying old scores off on Vin- cent, and making money at the same time, Captain Foster took command of the new ship-to make another, and he felt confident a more successful, pur- suit of the pirate brig. The Blood-Hound, so she had been significantly christened, was indeed a splendid specimen of marine architecture. Long, low, with bows sharp as a wedge, great breadth of beam just abreast and a little qbaft'the foremast, then tapering off until the width across her taffi'ail was scarce greater than a com- mon sized schooner; with tall raking masts, longesquare yards, taut rigging, and every thing about her, hull, lower-masts, yards, all painted black, she looked the beau ideal of a cruiser; and her appearance promised that if ever she was lucky enough to get within gun-shot of the Fire-Fly, that notorious craft's days would be numbered From the time the search for the pirate had been discontinued by the men- of-war, the Blood-Hound, with Don Manuel and Don Henrico both on board' had been continually at sea; going into port only when compelled by neces- sity to refit, provision or get information, and then immediately putting out again to resume her ceaseless, and as yet unprofitable task. But nothing is more obstinate and obdurate than an old nran's passion; and Don Manuel, though he had labored diligently, sought unweafiedly and unre- warded for more than six months with the Blood-Hound, felt- not the least disposition to give up his fixed purpose: nor the slightest inclination to falter *           e    <pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC6533-00000034"/> 70        A TALE OF THE SOUTHERN SEAS. in his object-but remained firm in his determination to die at sea, or to' accomplish his end. A week had elapsed since the terrific storm in which we lost sightof the Fire-Fly had swept over the ocean; and the Blood-Hound having again fruitlessly visited the island-haunt of the pirate, heading to the nor'ard and eastward, was standing out to sea on a cruise. Don Manuel intending to run across the Atlantic, and if unsuccessful in the passage, then to sail down the whole extent of the African coast. The weather was delightful; no trace remaining on the smooth water, or in the clear heavens, of the violent commotion both had exhibited but a short week before. The small wavelets that rippled around the gallant ship's cut- water, as she glided on, made a soft and pleasant harmony, that. accorded charmingly with the, balmy breeze and cloudless sky, and seemed attuned by failr fingers to win man from his mental miseries. But the harsh tones of Don Manuel's voice, as pacing the deck he conversed with Don Henrico, proved that nature's quietude touched no sympathetic chord in his troubled breast. "To think," said the old Don to his companion, that in this fair world, so sweet to look upon, there should be so much foul villanyi and to see, on shore as well as at sea, rascality so,often successful, so seldom punished, is enough to make a man who'really desires to do as he would be done by, wish that he had never been born. Here, for a year, has that double-dyed scoundrel, Vincent, escaped harmless; and has doubtless chuckled daily over his success. Whilst my angel child, who never had a thought that was not pure, who never harmed a worm intentionally, has been condemned on earth, before death, to the torments of a hell. Where is the justice, where the encourage- ment to do right, in this,?" "It passes our comprehension, Don Manuel," replied his friend, "but if we acknowledge the existence of a Supreme Ruler, we must believe that there is a wise purpose in it, though beyond our knowledge. It is yet to be seen whether the,punishment meted out to transgressors here will not fully equal their deserts. Time is short, but Eternity has no end-and until we pass from this life to a better one, all that we can do is to strive to act according to our consciences, and trust to God's mercy for eventual justice." "Easy to talk, easy to talk, Don Henrico ;" continued Don Manuel, "but do you feel it? Can you practice it? Methinks I have seen you as rebellious against Heaven's decrees as ever I have been." \ , t   THE OCEA-BORNS;             71' "Sail ho!" shouted by the look-out aloft, prevented Don Henrico's reply; and hastily snatching their glasses, as Captain Foster asked- "Where away?" they were all soon eagerly scrutinizing a dark object upon the sea, some five miles distant from the Blood-Hound, and on her lee bow f  "Can you make her out, Captain Foster " in the same breath asked Don Manuel and Don Henrico, as after a long and steady look at the stranger, they found themselves unable to distinguish her build or rig. "No, not yet; she seems to have two masts, but there is something odd about her top-hamper, that I can't make out. But I'll go aloft and take a better look;" and seizing his glass, the captain proceeded with all possible haste to the fore-topsail yard. He remained on his lofty perch some time befdre he was able to give any satisfactory answer to the repeated questions put to him by the impatient gentlemen. At last, when 'Don Manuel and Don Henrico were restless with anxiety and hope-for every vessel they. trusted might turn out to be the one they sought-Foster gave food for their / wildest delight by crying out in exulting tones: "Hurrah-! hurrah! By heavens, we're in luck! As sure as I'm a living man it is the Fire-Fly; and under jury masts at that. Now she can't escape; we 've got her at last; and gleefully the captainf descended the rigging and lit upon the deck with a bound and another huzza, which being echoed by the ship's company, a loud cheer rang over the water, pealed forth by two hundred throats. High hopes of speedy vengeance, and tender thoughts of again beholding  their beloved one, mingled together so confusedly in the minds of Don Manuel and Don Henrico, as almost to render them  frantic. Sail. was crowded on the Blood-Hound, and shortly from her deck was visible the splendidly proportioned hull of the Fire-Ely, as with nothinfg but two short jury masts, barely sufficient to support a foresail and mainsail, in place of her tall and tapering spars, like a wounded water-fowl, the pirate brig came lag- ging along on'her eourse.           .  The gale which had overtaken the pirate, and that had howled such a wild welcome, or presaged such a doleful doom to his child, had also nearly swamped his vessel.' All the seamanship, determination, and courage of the captain and the crew had it taken to save the Fire-Fly from being engulphed in the vast, grave-like chasms which the heaving waters had' continually opened around her, and into which the wind as it sobbed and moaned, and then roared hoarsely, seemed striving to force her never more to arise. At '.     <pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC6533-00000035"/> 72        A TALE OF TBE SOUTHERN SEAS. last, after the fury of the storm abated, spite of all their efforts, the bngo was mastless, nothing but a hull tossing on the vexed vortex: the water-elves had been" cheated, but the spirits of the air had seized their share. Having no dock-yard in which to refit, the pirates carried a large quantity of spare spars; but nearly all bf them had been washed overboard, and it was with much difficulty that Vipcent had been able to get up even the scant jury-poles he was under when discovered by the Blood-Hound. Don ManueFs vessel, in consequence of her greater altitude, had been seen by Vinicent long before they made out his docked and diminished spars. From the Blood-Hound's rig, the pirate knew she was an armed vessel, and he thought a regular cruiser. Seeing that the stranger sailed' three feet to the Fire-Fly's one,.he felt assured it was useless to attempt to avoid her, and so, doggedly determining to hold steadily on his comrse, and trust to wits that had freed him from many a former peril when force would/ not avail-but resolved in any event not to be captured-the pirate captain beheld, without trepidation,- the heavily armed and dangerous looking ship bearing down upon him under a press of canvas. As the Blood-Hound came up near enough for persons on her deck to be distinguished by the' glass, Vincent, to his surprise, recognized Don Manuel. When he first saw approaching him the man he had so shamefully injured, clothed with ample power to carry into execution the vengeance that must naturally b rankling in his bosom, the pirate-captain for a moment experienced 'that sickening sense, so hard to drive away, of the proximity and certainty of a punishment known to be richly deserved. But it was only for a few seconds' space that the pirate felt disturbed. Summoning to his assistance the subtle intelligence and remorseless will with which he was endowed, suppressing all his human sympathies and weaknesses, acting but through his mind, he saw that though his brig was crippled, and could neither successfully fight with, nor flee from the approaching ship-that yet if he was deteimined to do or die, even now, though the chances seemed so few, he would be enabled to escape harmless from Don Manuels wrath.  Small thought had those on board the Blood-Hound that by any thing short of a miracle, could Vincent or his crew now ward xoff the punishment they go long had merited-had so long escaped. Ranging up almost alongside the Fire-Fly, with' crew at quarters, ports opened and tompions out, the Blood-Hound appeared about to attack the brig at once, without a word. Just, however, ah the bows of the two vessels were almost parallel, Don Manuel,.in a loud and excited voice, hailed:   THE OOEANu BORN;             73 "Heave to and sunrender, you cut-throats! or wei'll sink you." "Sink, and' be blasted! Your daughter goes along. with us;"Vincent coolly replied to the hail-as, without making any motion toward obeying Don Manuel's command, or paying any attention to his threat, he kept on his way.' So staggered was Don Manuel by the recklessness of the pirate, and by the remenibrance of the fact that, though so near her, his daughter was still as completely in the pirate's power as if he had been on the ocean alone, that before he recovered" himself enough to speak the vessels had forged by each other, and the Blood-Hound had passed astern of the Fire Fly. Calling Don Henrico and Captain Foster to him, the old Don. consulted with them as to the course they had better adopt. They all entertained the keenest desire to capture Vincent, and punish him and his vile associates for the pain and misery they had caused Garcia and her friends, as well as for the thousand other crimes they had been guilty of. But how to attain their end, and at the same time save Garcia, was a question they could not solve; They knew Vincent to be fearless, and entirely unscrupulous; and they were certain he would murder the lady, and perhaps blow up his vessel, before he would be captured. It was therefore with strange emotions that they found themselves, having the physical strength and the inclination to punish the pirates, yet withheld by love for Garcia from carrying their wishes into execu- tion. 'Situated as they were, however, small choice remained to them; they either had to attack the pirates and vanquish them, with the certainty of sac- rificing the generous woman who had so 'nobly cast herself away to preserve their lives-and this they could not think of-or else make such terms as they best could with the pirate captain, and save the captive lady Putting the Blood-Hound about, Don Manuel was soon agai   within speaking distance of the Fire-Fly; and as the old man hailed, Vincent gath- ered from his tone and manner that the father realized the disadvantage un- ter which he labored-and the freebooter smiled as Don Manuel said, "Surrender on board the brig there! and we will give you honorable treatment, and a fair trial on shore i" "Much obliged to you for your kindness, Don Manuel ;" sneeringlyJ-an- swered Vincent, "But I am very well satisfied where I am, and would rather be jtdge of my own actions."  "Your blood and that of your men be upon your own head, then, you graceless wretch!" exclaimed Don Manuel, betrayed from his coolness by te sneering accents of the pirate; "stand by your guns,.my men 1"  .    <pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC6533-00000036"/> A TALE aF THE SOITHBRN 1 SEAS. A single sentence from Vincent, as he asked-- Have you forgotten your daughter ?" called the father back.to the actu- alities of his situation. " Where is she ! where is she, you heartless brute ? Let nIe see her I Is she safe and alive? How do I know you have not murdered her " rapidly asked the old man. "She is safe and alive, Don Manuel," replied the pirate, " and it depends alto- gether upon you, whether or pot she remains so. Let us, however, understand each other, and not behave like school-boys, quarreling when they dare not fight. You would, I know, like to liang me and my crew; and you have the force to capture us, if we would let ourselves be taken. So far so good; but, on the other hand, we have no fancy for hempen cravats-they are un- wholesome; and besides, I have possession of your child; and though I do not wish to harm her, yet, sooner than be taken-though she is my wife, and the mother of my child-I will blow her; and every living soul on board the brig, into eternity. Now take your choice-your daughter, and leave us; or else fire a gun, and see her and us flying hellwards P' "Give up my daughter, then, and her child. God pity her for having had to bear a child to such a wretch-! and we pledge our honors to leave you and your murderous gang, to find that fate some other day, your deeds will suielyi meet !" was Don Manuel's reply. '" You pledge your solemn honors, and swear by the crucifix, that you will offer us no molestation, and grant us a week's grace to make an offing, if I surrender my wife and child ?" inquired the pirate. "We d ! we do !" replied, in one voice, Don Manuel, Don Henrico, and Captain Foster. "Swear it !" said Vincent-and the oath was taken separately by each. "Now send your boat; but only four hands in her, and no officers," continued the pirate, as he saw Don Manuel and a full crew about to leap into the cutter. Only the specified- number remained in the boat, and with a few strokes they reached the Fire-Fly. Garcia, who was too feeble to walk, was soon carried from the cabin to the deck of the Fire-Fly-and grateful the lady felt to the Almighty for his goodness in permitting her to be rescued from the horrible life she had been leading. She could not, however, part from the father of her child, though he had caused her so much sorrow, without making one more effort to turn him from the fatal course he- was pursuing. Eloquent was the appeal she made to Vincent, "for his dhild's sake, if not for her, nor for his own, nor for   his soul's sake ;yet fo: the sake of his innocent child, to relinquish his miserable calling, and seek an honorable living-sc that his son would not have to blush, if ever he heard his father's name."  But it was in the presence of all his crew, in sight of his enemies; and whatever were the real sentiments of the pirate's heart-for he little relished parting with the lovely one and the .babe, about to leave him forever-he suppressed all manifestation' of feeling, and answered in his usual cold and sneering tone: "I take it, lady, were the whole truth known, there is but trifling difference between a pirate and many a man who bears a much more honest-sounding designation.  One does*his wickedness, if so you phrase it, openly, and bravely dares the penalty; whilst the other slyly performs his rascality-and oftimes glossing over the greater crimes with smooth and specious titles, if he is lucky and stays within the wide boundary of the law-that net spread by - grand rogues to snare petty ones-forsooth, he is an honest nan, and deserves a monument! But your friends, I see, are getting impatient; so give you good day, lady, and a pleasant voyage to you !                ' '      ' Aurd this was the parting greeting of the pirate to her whose young joys he had crushed in the bud; to her, whose morning of life and hope he had darkened by the storm-clouds of his passion. Soul-stirring, heart-touching were the greetings that the recovered one received when she xeached the Blood-Hound. Her father, in his thankfulness at having onced more regained his beloved child, almost forgot the hatred he bore toward the cause of her sorrows; and Don Henrico, absorbed in.gazing upon his dreaims-object, could scarcely persuade himself that the pensive, thoughtful woman he now looked upon, was the same Garcia he had  worshipped a year before.  Bonita's joy at getting back to her master, and free from the pirate brig, was beyond all restraint. By turns she cried, iaughed, shouted, danced from joy-hugging the.knees first of her master, and then stooping down by her mistress, the excess of her gratifidhtion seemed to have turned her head. But the senses of the affectionate - mulatto all returned, when her mistress, overcome by the tremendous excitement, pleasant though it was, required her assistance to reach the cabin. An hour after Garcia had been received on board, the Fire-Fly could barely be seen from the Blood-Hound's deck; and ere night the vessels-one seeking a peaceful harbor and bearing happy mortals to aninnocent home,   <pb n="76-77 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6533-00000037"/> A TALE OF THE SOUTHERN SEAS. the other, freighted with heartless, crime-stained men, intent on pillage-had entirely disappeared from each other's sight. The Blood-Hound's run-in was safe and speedy; and Garcia again found herself an occupant of the chamber from which, a short twelvemonth anterior, she had been so rudely kidnapped. As the lady noted the familiar objects that surrounded her-how thick and fast did the scenes she had passed through, since she had been torn from its shelter, throng upon her. A twelvemonth is but a little while, and yet how multitudinous the events that can and do occur within its limits. All about her Garcia saw was unchanged; the same-furniture-the same scenery, the                                                          t    e o  same sky visible through the window-and yet how different thelady knew herself to be, fivm what she was, when last she had cast'her eyes upon those silent mementoes of" the 'past  A short- twelvemonth, and  she had been a lovely- iden, to sorrow,'dread, regrets, a stranger; every thing in the present bright, every thingin the fnitui'e- brighter. Now, and the hour-hand of -time  had   iade bt hi a single', revolution, ohe was famuiliar with sorrow, was a wtomai and a. mother; the fuLure had become a- dread, a nd the' past she hid                                                                 ( rati r oveiY strougled through, Was too fulleof pa'eful memories to think of.   CHAPTER.                 X                                                                     - Our early days! How ften back                                                        ist of Gara and the Ocean-Born to the Cell of the Condmned I We turn on life's bewildering track To where, o'er hill and valley, plays The sunlight of our early days.haD. W. GALLAGHER. AWHILST the Ocean-Born remained an infant, Don Manuel manifested no affection for him, took no interest in his welfare; in fact, he strove to imagine  that it was not his grandchild, nor the son of his daughter; and had it not been for its mother's sake, the oldgentleman would have sent the pirate's child                                      i out of his sight, away from its mother and- himself; to' be nursed by stran- gel's. For the first yeai or two of its existence, Don Manuel could not sepa- , rate thoughts of the fatherfrom the presence of the child; and at times, the       <pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC6533-00000038"/> 78            THE OCEAN-BORN; loathing he entertained toward the character of the parent created in his breast almost a disgust for his helpless, innocent offspring. As time passed and rendered less vivid the old man's realization of the pi- rate's crimes, whilst it expanded his son from a tender bud of beauty and purity into a bright and'glorious boy of surpassing grace and promise,Don Manuel's feelings underwent a change. -In the lovely prattler that toddled after him, calling "Grandpa, grandpa!" turning up ohjosy mouth for a kiss, the old gentleman forgot Vincent, and only saw before him the child of his heart's-child, his only grandson-and he rendered to him the full share of affection that Garcia's son had claim to. And the mother, neither wife nor widow, what were her feelingstoward the child, for whose father she could neither entertain love nor respect, nor yet ha- tred; he who, though living, was to his wife and child as one dead; and whose memory, when dead, would only shame those near to him, if'it lived. Wide* reaching, all-sacrificing, deep-seated as a mother's love-that most perfect, most heaven-savoring sentiment that exists on earth-can be, was Garcia's love for her boy. She thought not of the father, but only saw in her child a seed of immortality, which, though it would germinate, wilt, and decay here, was to be placed in either the garden or the waste of hereafter,'as the culture it received from her should determine. Her own lopes of othei happiness in life than that of striving to perform her duties faithfully, had fled; and the only ray of gladness that penetrated the sanctuary of her inner woman-feel- ings, was theaffection of her son, and the trust that his life would be a happy one. When the Ocean-Born reached his sixth. year, accompanied by his mother, Don Manuel carried him to Puertd Principe; and there, in the cathedral, with all the pomp and ceremony the church could bestow, had him christen- ed Jhan Manchez. Before this event the pirate's child had only been called by pet names; but after, as if with the name that had been conferred by the priests sanction, every unpleasant association connected with his grandson's history had been removed from the old man's remembrance, he never spoke of him but as Juan. His affection, too, toward the boy grew more fervent; and Don Manuel centered all the high hopes of a parent's heart, that once he had expected Garcia's nuptials to fulfill, upon the advancement of her child. Desiring to leave a vicinity where the parentage of the young Juan was too well known, Don Manuel soon after the boy was christened removed to the neighborhood of Matanzas; and here, as no one knew of her fatal mar-   A TALE OF THE SOUTERN SEAS.           79 riage, by her father's advice, Garcia assumed the name of Manchez, and pass- ed for the widow of a Spanish officer. Every thing that money and affection could do was done to make Juan?s path- way through life a road strewn with flowers. But a destiny we can neither fathom nor control, warps our efforts to ends we aimed not at; and nor mo- ney, nor love, powerful levers though they be, can repress the workings, of our natural predilections, or charm from its willfulness the waywardness of youth. One trait there, was in the character of her son that much pained his gen- tle mother. It was the only thing in his disposition she desired to alter; otherwise he was all she could wish. His mind was brilliant, his person beau- tiful, his affections warm and tender, his principles good, and his sentiments generous, but within, there was a strong and ever active energy, that would not be satisfied with the commonplace routine of peaceful life. He craved ex- citement; when a mere child he loved to ride wild horses, to scale dangerous passes; and as he grew older, his whole mind was bent upon going t sea and becoming a sailor. Against this inclination the mother and the grandfather both used their most strenuous exertions. They pictured forth in glowing colors the perils and privations of a sea life; the terrors of the storms, the horrors of the calms, the dangers from wind and water. They spoke of the hardships, the sever- ance of fiiends, the absence of home and home-comforts; but the more argu-, ments they advanced to show why he had better remain on shore, the strong- er did Juan's anxiety become to gp to sea. He acted kindly in the matter though; hi did not say that go he would, but besought them so earnestly to gratify his wish, so ardently pleaded with his mother and his grandfather, that their judgments were conquered by their affections, and they reluctantly consented to the boy's request. They endeavored, however, to persua'de the lad to postpone entering the service until he was older; for when he coaxed them into acquiescence, the Ocean-Born was barely fourteen. But Juan computed time to come with youth's measure, and two years, or even one ahead, appeared to him an age; whilst to his mother and grandfather, who had lived long enough to know that years fly on eagles' pinions, and are gone almost before you can realize their presence, the thoughts of their pet leaving them, even after the expiration of four years, was painful. Having gained his first point, their assent on any terms, the boy knew that the same means continued, would prevail upon his doting relatives to comply with his other wish-to enter. the Spanish navy at once; the warrant he    <pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC6533-00000039"/> 80            THE OCEAN-BORN; r:eceived a few months after the completion of his fourteenth year, showed that Juan's calculations had been correct. With the blessings and prayers of his mother-never before separated from her child-and who saw him start: with many fearful forebodings, accom- panied by Don Manuel and Don Henrico, the Ocean-Born started for Havana, to commence his career upon that element where-though he was  ignorant of the fact-he was tossing when first he saw light. Don Henrico, of all those interested in Juan's welfare, was the only one who experienced no regret at the youth's departure from home. Having a natural sympathy for the service, in which he had passed many years, he thought Juan would be as well off at sea as if he were elsewhere; arid besides, Don Henrico believed his own ends would be advanced by the boy's absence. The love the Don had cherished for Garcia, before her seizure by the pirate, instead of diminishing or growing dull from age or rebuff, had increased in volume and deepened in intensity. Don Henrico's filrt passion for the lady had been more excited by her personal grace and symmetry, than by hel mental accomplishments. -The splendor of the casket had so attracted his attention, that he neglected to estimate the value of the rare gems it contained. Since Garcia's return to her father, closely had Henrico observed her conduct; and the fortitude, patience, and resignation with which she had borne' her trials, the unwavering sweetness of her disposition, her unwearying charity, 'the gentle dignity of her manners, her even enhanced beauty-for her sorrows had purified, not cankered her feelings, and etherialized he expression to almost angelic loveliness-so captivated Don Henrico, that he felt if before he had loved the maiden, he idolized the mother of the Ocean-Born; and though he knew  all the peculiarities of her position, lie strove by every art in his power to win her for himself. When Don Manuel removed to Matanzas, Don Henrico could not bear the separation from her who was his day-dream, his night-vision, and he also located there; and though for fourteen years he had been unsuccessfully endeavoring to persuade Garcia to marry him, yet, with a constancy. confirmed and strengthened by disappointment, with a hope that would not despair, he still looked forward to the blissful day whed he would be able to call her his own.    - Before and since her residence at Matanzas, many offers had the lovely lady received from cavaliers, high-born and wealthy-to all of whom she had returned a quiet refusal, without assigning any reasons for her conduct. 8 2 -,   A TALE OF THE SOVTHERN SEAS.          81 But to Don Henrico, who had known her so long, had loved her so faithfully, and toward whom her young heart, in its freshness, had experienced the filst and only yearnings it had ever felt for man, she was more communicative, though not less firm and positive in her denial. "In the first place, Don Henrico," she said, " the argument you urge, that my marriage with Vincent, so far as any claims he could have upon me are concerned, would in law be a nullity, is nothing-of no force. I am aware that the certainty of suffering the penalty his deeds would award, could he be captured, would prevent his ever seeking me. But my vows I plighted to him whilst he lived; and I regard that person as ignorant of the value and power of a moral obligation, who does not consider it binding, who does not hold it sacred under any and every circumstance. So that what you ask, even if no other obstacle intervened, is impossible." "Promise me, then, dearest lady, that when you are certain Vincent has passed away from life's turmoils, you will hearken to my supplication, and I never will again mention the subject, until you are at liberty to act," exclaimed Don Henrico, his spiritsanimated by the prospect of even distant success. But his anticipations of even eventual triumph were chilled, as Garcia continued, "Oh, Don Henrico,/you mistake me altogether; I thought the mention of one insurmountable barrier would satisfy you, and prevent the, necessity of my having to pain you by urging other reasons. Hearken to me, my kind and well-tried friend, with patience; and believe that I highly prize your disinterestedness, feel truly grateful for your kindness and sincerity; and only regret that I cannot conscientiously assent to your desires. Seek some other's love, Don Henrico; you are wise, have a name known' in the world, are wealthy; and ladies, bright and fair, and young, whose hearts have never been seared by misery's fire, whose' affections are fresh and strong, will be proud of your attentions, glad to wear your title, share your fortunes. But I -I can never love as your wife should love you; and though no one can esteem you more sincerely, bear for you a more perfect friendship, yet naught' more than a friend, a lasting and a true one,can I ever be to you, friend of my early days; and so, for the peace\of both, never let us recur to this painful matter again." Notwithstanding the absence of encouragement in her words, and though * her manners remained unchanged, Don Henripq persuaded himself that when her son was away from  her his assiduous attentions would produce an /            -         *    <pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC6533-00000040"/> 82            THE OCEAN-BORN; impression upon Garcia, and cause her to relent in favor of his suit. But it was the same with the lady after her boy' departure, as it had been before; and when, four years having elapsed, the handsome Lieutenant Manchez, a favored youth, promoted for gallant deeds performed, returned on a visit to his home, Don H-enrico felt that his courtship had not progressed an atom- was more hopeless than before. Still he would not relinquish what had now become the object of his life, determined, if he could not win the only woman he had ever seen who was all he conceived a woman should be, that he would complete his pilgrimage in solitude. Overjoyed were the mother and the grandfather, at. the safe return of their loved Ocean-Born, who had fulfilled, as he grew up, all the promises of his childhood. Combining the physical beauties of both his parents-the high intellectual forehead of his father, the -expressive and lustrous eye of his mother, the fair skin of the one and the delicate smoothness of the other, the grace and pliancy of motion of the Spaniard, with the stature, strength, and symmetry of the Anglo-Saxon, added to quick mental' parts and a kind heart, Juan was, indeed, a son well calculated to fill a mother's heart with pride. With the keenness of a wateh- ful parent's anxiety, Garcia criticised her son's every act and speech; and she was rejoiced to find that, thanks to God's blessing upon her careful- instruc- tions, the force of character, and power of will and energy, that, unrestrained, had caused his father's moral ruin, had only tended, being properly directed, to the child's advancement in honor and virtue. Feasted, feted, complimented by neighbors and acquaintances-for he was heir to great wealth, and on the road to official preferment-Juan spent several months at home before his furlough expired; and as his mother parted with her boy for the second time, though she knew that nothing in life was certain, that the temptationresisted to-day, may gain victory on the morrow, she was less troubled with anxiety for the future of her child, than ,she ever before had been . Had Juan been the son of a husband he himself/had chosen for his daughter, Don Manual could not have loved him more enthusiastically, been more proud of him; and every thing that his money or influence could do the old man did, to hasten his, grandson's steps on the road to rank and station.                  '     , 4' '                         -    A AtALE OF THE SOUTHERN SEAS.          83 CHAPTER XIII. If solid happiness we prize, Within our breast this jewel lies, And they are fools who rqam; The world has nothing to bestow; From our own selves our joys must flow, And that dear hut-our home."-COTTON. A FLOOD of bright light, from myriad waxen tapers, was streaming-through the nmany windows of a noble mansion near Matanzas. Brilliant though the illumination was, the effect produced by the effulgent beams of the full tropical moon, as sailing along the clear ether, it sent its rays of silvery sheen over the luxuriant garden; touching palm-tree, orange-flower, rose bush, with its glittering pencillings, and causing the dew-spangles, as they quivered on leaves moved by the soft wind, to sparkle like countless diamonds, was still more charming. Strains of harmonious sweetness, from skillfully fingered instruments, mingling with the. lightsome, merry laugh of joyous maidens and gleesome youths, floated on the night air. In the house, groups of lovely ladies. and chivalrous gentlemen-beautified mpre by the radiant expression of contenttnent and happiness, that showed from their eyes, and wreathed their lips in gladsome smiles, than lr the costly gems and, rich attire with which they were adorned, crowded the apartments. Whilst here and there was to be seen the venerable white head of some old man, or the thoughtful, placid face of some mature matron, who seemed watching over the welfare of the care-free ones surrounding them. It was a fete at the residence of Don Manuel, given in honor of the Ocean- Bornwho, at home once more after a three years' absence, had just attained his majority; and at the same time, thanks to his grandfather's exertions to* back his own deselvings, a captain's commission in the royal Spanish navy. Don Manuel, as he gazed fondly upon the young captain, andsaw him,    <pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC6533-00000041"/> A4            IBSTHE OCEAN-BORN; dressed in the full uniform of his new grade, the handsomest among tho handsome, the most joyous of the joyful, felt that the measure of his happiness was full, and the grandfather forgot that the past had ever caused him a pang -that the future could bring him a wo. As the loving glance of the mother followed the movements- of her son from place to' place, she experienced a complicated sensation-mournful, yet pleasant-gratified, at the same time anxious. More than delighted was Garcia at the behaviour of her child thus far in fife-in nothing was he blameable. But she remembered that every thing had been prosperous with him; his path had been freed, so far as mortal agency and watchful love could free it, from temptations and excitements, to wrong doing; and she wondered, whilst trusting in God's' mercy for the best, what would be her son's course, should disappointments, trials, and sorrows come upon him. No doubts of the unknown to-come troubled Juan, for those who have never suffered evil, never anticipate its advept; and the Ocean-Born, just at the only unadulteratedly happy period of life, with powers of enjoyment at their acme, unblunted by too frequent exercise, or dulled by accurately understanding the value of earthly joys, satisfied with himself, feeling all the dignity of manhood, without any of its cares, in the midst of those dearest to him-beauty, wit, light-heartedness around him, was the very personification of perfect contentment. The few years he had lived, had been composed of golden-hued months, that brought each a heavier tribute of satisfaction to his heart, without exacting fee or reward; and judging of the future by the past, as we naturally do, the young captain thought but of a continuance and increase of the happiness the days fled had furnished. Another reason, too, -had Juan for forgetting on this evening that earth was  not heaven-that pleasure was not everlasting. The love of his heart's flint love had been returned; and the beautiful maiden leaning upon his arm, had a short hour before, under *n almond-tree, in the dim moonlight, plighted to him her troth, and as his ravished ear drank in the most precious words man ever listens to, he thought the bright stars above were pledges of their purity; the fragrant perfume from blossom and bud, that encompassed them, a faint sampler of their sweetness. Fair, and coveted by many, was the prize Juan had drawn id lifes lottery; for Catalina Gonzales, the lady of his choice, was young, rich, lovely-the belle of Matanzas. Where graceful forms abounded, hers was remarkable for its elegance. In a land distinguished for the brilliancy of its daughters' eyes, Catalina's were unequalled in their brightness; and Juan,as he gazed upon Cativ wer une   A TALE OF THE SOUTHERN     SEAS.       85 her, invested her with every mental charm and moral perfection he could imagine, and believed that he had secured a talisman in her affection that would turn'from him harmless every pang that life could bring.   Various, however, are the aspects assumed by the same object, when viewed from different points; and the mother and the son, the woman and the lovel; as they scrutinized' Catalina's character, endeavoring to reach the invisible causes through the visible effects, arrived at conclusions concerning the lady widely at variance. When the ball had ended, and Juan, with all the frankness of a confiding child to a devoted parent, hastened to impart to his mother the secret .of his success and happiness, sure of receiving her sympathy; he was surprised to find her listen to his story without manifestation of pleasure, aid still more astonished was he, when she endeavored to persuade him that he was deceived in the value of the jewel he deemed so priceless. His mother told him-and woman ever is the surest judge of woman's motives-that the eye he thought so matchless was indebted for its fire to a powerful mind influenced by pride; that the charming figure which moved so gracefully, was the dwelling-place of a spirit energetic and indomitable, but also ruled and governed by a single passion-the same pride that lighted up her eyes. Garcia admitted that her sonts beloved was fair, was witty, accomplished; but she denied that Catalina possessed woman's greatest charm, most estimable characteristic-that gentle, tender, self-sacrificing disposition, without which half her beauties are blem- ished.                     " But the arguments of 'the mother had no weight with the son. Juan thought, as children are apt to think, that his parent was mistaken, did not do his chosen-one justice. His mother pleaded with him, and besought him to pause carefully, reflect solemnly, ere he entrusted the happiness of his whole life to the keeping of one she believed incompetent to the charge; yet the youth, though he replied respectfully and regretfully, retained unchanged his original opinions of Catalina. Seeing that'her son's determination could not be altered, Garcia offered no further opposition to his wishes, and assented, though not cheerfully, to his marriage; for she felt as she acquiesced, that now the evil from which sho had so strenuously striven to shield her son' would ere long overtake him; andsher heart trembled at the thought, though it was out of her power. to prevent consequences beyond her control. Juan,- though he- strove' to banssh the unwelcome thought from his mind had to acknowledge, in disagreeing with a motherneer before disobeyed, that his first griefhad come upon him,    <pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC6533-00000042"/> 86           THE OCEAN-BOM RN just, too, when he flattered himself that he had reached the culmination of his happiness. On the morrow, the gay smiles and pleasant words of his mistress drove from the Ocean-Born's remembrance the unpleasant feelings that had op- pressed him after leaving his mother-the thotght that one so lovely as Cat- ,alina could not but be all that was loveable. Ardently he plead with her to let him appoint an early day for the solemnization of their nuptials, which he desired to take place at the soonest practicable period. Overcome, apparently, by his importunities, with a seeming disinterestedness, that in Juan's eyes proved the sincerity of her attachment, the lady permitted. him to name the earlist day compatible with his duties-as soon as he returned from a cruise  he was obliged to start upon in a few days-and that would occupy six months. During this interval Catalina informed her lover that she designed paying her last maiden visit to her relatives in Porto Rico, so that they would both return home about the same time. Again the future assumed to the Ocean-Born its accustomed rosy tints; and with pledges of mutual fidelity, and vows of eternal constancy, sealed by a fervent kiss and a long embrace- it was beneath the tropics-the lovers parted. When Juan, for the third time, left his mother and his home, it was with the hope of being gone but a brief while, compared to his former absences; and with the expectation of being happier than he ever before had been upon his return. The sadness, s6 much graver than usual, that sat upon his mother's broW, when shebade hit, farewell, appeared causeless to her son; and as he laugh- ed cheerfully at her forebodings, and in his health, and youth, and joyousness, looked so free from care, Garcia almost chid hefself for, casting. a damper upon his hilarity. But after Juan had gone, the gloomy impressions, that appeared the shadow of some,. unseen but advancing misery, so weighed upon her spirits, so oppressed her, that a flood 'of tears burst uncontrollably from her eyes; and it required all Garcia's faith, great as that was, in the goodness and mercy of God, to restore her mind to its habitual state of patience and resignation.  '  Reaching Havana, the young captain, proud of his new ship as. a child of a fresh plaything, took command of his corvette; and with a fair wind and good weather, started in high spirits on a cruise along the Main and through the Windward Islands.    A TAJ 'OF TMt 80OUTMR    SAS.        87 CHAPTER XIV.       " "Will fortune never tome with both hands full,  But write her fair words still in foulest letters 8 She either gives a stomach,' and no food- Such are the poor in health; or else a feast, '     And takes away the stomach-such the rich,' ,.      That have abundance and enjoy it not i--SHAKsPEaRm. TaE Ocean-Born's first cruise as a commander was as fortunate as he could have desired; fine weather, a good vessel, and an orderly and efficient crew made it a mere pleasure trip to him. The .days he numbered, ay, even the hours sometimes he counted, that yet reared themselves a barrier between him and his anticipated wedding; but, when they seemed to lag, thoughts of the happiness that would accrue after their expiration hastened their flight. Heading homeward from the Windward Isles, Juan drew favorable auggries of the new voyage he was so soon to embark upon, from- the pleasant naturo of the one so speedily drawing to a close. How little guaranty is there, how- ever, in the joys of the past, or the pleasures of the present, for their continu- ance in the future.  The corvette, running down the north side of the islandi bound for Matan- zas,-was within a few days of her port, and the blue line of the Cuban shore, as it loomed up in the distance, caused Juan to feel as if his hopes had already reached their haven. His thoughts wandered away from things visible, and with all a lover's curiosity were endeavoring to imagine' the: greetings'ho would receive when he. met those he loved-what Catalina would say-how she would' look-and whether she would be as:glad to meet him as he would be to greet her-when he was called back from the ideal to the real, by the report of a vessel in sight, whose movements were unintelligible.  It was early morning, clear, with a stiff breeze 'from the npr'ard and east- ward,'and as it-was directly ahead of him, the corvette quickly made suffi- cient way to enable-Juan to get a distinct view of the-strange sail.  He made her out to be a fullrigged merchant ship, with all sail set; but the fact of her tending frst one way and then another-now all fulLon one tack, then all aback on the other-was something he could not readily account for. With much curiosity and some anxiety-for the course he was pursuing    <pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC6533-00000043"/> 88           THE OCEAN-BOR  his betrothed would necessarily have to follow, and he was not certain she Iha yet reached Matanzas-Juan watched the eccentric manceuvres of the ship, until, getting close enough to distinguish objects clearly, he saw that her braces were all loose and unrove-her yards flying about with the wind-and he knew that-she must be deserted. 'On nearing the ship, the young captain found his surmise to be correct, for only the mournful sound made by the heavy canvas, as it flapped against the masts, answered the hails from the corvette. Why a sound and seaworthy craft, in mild weather, near land, should be abandoned by,her crew, was an enigma Juan was so impatient to unravel, that calling away a cutter he has- tened to board the ship himself. As the boat approached the ship, dark purple lines, that savored of blood, were seen trickling from her scuppers- and staining her side; and urged on by fearful anticipations, Juan speedily climbed up the ladder that hung dangling at her gangway.  In the seven years he had passed at sea, Juan had seen many disagreeable sights, and taken part in several engagements-but when he got high enough to glance over the bulwarks, down upon that deserted vessel's deck, a scene so painfil, so much more awful than he expected, broke upon his vision, that it was with difficulty he prevented the sickness that came over him from causing iim to fall backward into the cutter he had just left. Blood-blood-blood-was every where, upon every thing; on the deck, on.'the bulwarks, on the combings of the hatches-which were open-and flowing sluggishly, in a clotted, oozy stream, along the scuppers-whose ori- fices its coagulum had closed. Death, too, was there in its most appalling shape-violent, sudden, unlooked-for death, that leavesits victim neither time to utter a prayer for forgiveness nor murmur-a petition for mercy. Men, or bodies that must have contained the souls of men-for the wounds that cov- ered the lifeless remains showed they had fought gallantly--were strewn from the forecastle to the tafferel. But the large pile of dead lying near the com- panion-way to the cabin-with heads crushed, arms lopped off-,all stark and stiff-showed that'there had taken place the last and most desperate strug- gle: and the Ocean-Born-as, followed by. his Amen, he leaped down on the planks, slippery with the ensanguined current that had floated so many brave Spirits into eternity-felt a sailor's sympathy for the fate of the murdered ones, for he knew they had been slain hy pirates. The vessel was an Ameicianh-the Petrel, of Boston-Juan conjectured outward-bound; and his anxiety was relieved concerning his betrothed-- though his compassion was excited to a .distressing degree by the sight of those so cruelly butchered. Carefully he examined every corpse on deck, in   A TALE :OP THE SOUTylER  SEASm.       89 the vain hope that the work of destruction might have been parelessly performed -that breath might yet remain in some of the wrecks of mortality around. But the pirates' brands had left him nothing to do-all were dead; and, with a heavy heart, the young captain descended into the cabin, to see if any liv- ing thing was there. As he and the two men who accompanied him were about stepping into the cabin, they were startled by a deep, fierce howl, so expressive of both rage and pain, that, sounding close by, It caused them to pause for a moment irresolutely on the threshold. But the large, black Newfoundland dog that had uttered the fearful noise-and who, poor fellow, with his back broken, was crouched in a corner, almost incapable of motion-so soon as Juan fairly entered the apartment, and before the captain had discovered him, changing his angry tone into a short, sharp yelp of pleasure, the dog dragged himself out into the middle of the floor, and Juan recognized, to his unspeakable horror, in the wounded animal, a faithful and favorite pet belonging to his mistress. So sudden was the shock, so miserable the thoughts that accompanied it, that the Ocean-Born staggered back as if a fiend had arisen in his path; and then, shouting "Catalina! Catalina!" he frantically commenced searching the state-rooms for his betrothed. A small hatchway opened into the cabin-floor -it, the pantries, every nook and corner he searched-but a small book with his mistress's name written in it, which served to confirm his worst fears, was all he could find that appertained to her he so loved. Catalina had been there; was now in the possession of pirates! and only prevented from losing his senses by remembering that she probably was yet living, that possibly he might save her, or at any rate avenge her, Juan rushed on deck. Thoughts of revenge, doubts, dreads, fears, usurped the place of the hopes and teeming visions of bliss that had been occupying his mind a brief hour before; and' he began to realize the uncertainty of life, and the fleeting nature of earthly joy. The Ocean-Born's second trouble had come upon him, and with a force and crushing power that rendered it singly equivalent to all the pleasures his happy life had afforded. Making his way back with all speed to his own vessel, anrd as quick as he reached it, taking a telescope and ascending to tie fore-royal yard--too anxious the duty should be well done to trust it to another-4he young captain took a close and keen survey of the ocean on every side, hopipg: tte pirates were yet in sight. Nothing, however, could he see bnt the hay line of the- horizon, where the blue clouds and the blue water appeared mingling together. Another sweep of the glass, more carefully made, discovered, far in the north-west, a small speck, visible for an instant and then, out of sight.    <pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC6533-00000044"/> THR  O0'm-BORET; ly eyes rendered supernaturally sharp by intense emotion, could have inguished that little spot on' the far off water; it might be a gull, or Usion-but riveting his gaze upon it for a moment, Juan was confident it a sail. Taking its bearings from tha compass at the topmast head, Ocean-Born descended to the deck a being influenced by feelings new to ai-determined, stern, almost savage.  An officer and crew he sent on board the Petrel, with orders to bury her td, and afterward take the vessel into Matanzas; and then, with sail piled. m sail, until her hull was scarcely pereeptible beneath the mountainof Lvas it was supporting, the corvette's bows, driving the foam in cataracts  bre them as they swiftly parted the water, were pointed in the direction of spot he had discerned on the distant horizon. Phough the wind freshened, and it was as much as they could do to carry ir loftier sails, and though the corvette traveled at a iate she never before I equaled, she moved so much more tardily than his desires, that to her- )tain his vessel appeared stationary in a calm. Incessantly was Juan's glass directed toward the quarter in which he had n that dark point, but hour after hour passed ere the speck was visible  n the deck. At last, the look-out aloft reported that he believed the ect of their pursuit was a schooner. In another hour the look-out's supposi- n was found to be correct; and what had at first appeared a speck, and then eeming cloud, was found to be a topsail sehooner-but still miles distant. Oh, how the Ocean-Born prayed for a gale, that would compel the craft in ht to shorten sail, so that his heavier vessel could carny on and come mup h her. But the wind, instead of increasing, rather decreased; arid it was rly sunset before the corvette gained enough upon the schooner to see that 3 was a heavily armed, low, long, rakish clipper, too. little like an honest 3sel to be any thing but a pirate. Juau's hopes began to rise again, as soon. as he was assured he had not lowed on the wrong scent, and that he had in view the reprobates who'held mistiess captive-only four or five miles -separated him from them; and ep and dire *as the vengeance he swore against them as soon as they came thin hit grasp. The powers of the air seemed adverse however to his wishes; and a,. the wenit down the wind also died away, until not a breath ruffled the surface the water. The sails of the corvette banged sluggishly against the nasts,. the vessel roiled with the 'waves, without moving her a foot; and there, cost within striking distance, the chaser and the chased :were riding up and wanwith the swell, without the one being able to approach the objectt -of   A TALE OF THE SOUTHERN SEAS.           91 her pursuit-or the-other having the power to widen the distance between herself and vengeance. Greatly was Juan chafed to find himself so baffled, when the pirates seemed in his very clutches. But his fears for Catalina's safety were too vivid, his dread of the schooner's escaping in the night too keen, to allow him to wait quietly until the wind should enable him to attack the pirates' vessel with the corvette, and he determined to attempt the capture of the schooner with his boats.  Stating his intention to his crew, he called for volunteers; and was. gratified to find every man in the ship anxious to accompany him.. Selecting one hundred and fifty of his best hands, as many as the seven boats belonging to the'corvette could carry,'about nine o'clock the little flotilla started on an expedition as dangerous as any man ever undertakes. The young captain's every feeling was so absorbed by sympathy with Catalina, that doubts as to the issue of the undertaking never entered his mind; and his men, influenced by their commander's confident bearing, rowed cheerily and fearlessly toward the pirates. There was no moon, but the night was cloudless, and/the'light from the countless stars was sufficient to enable Juan to make out the loom of the schooner, whenever he rose on a swell, and after an hour's pulling, the boats were almost upon her.             )  The Ocean-Born had'just been able to ascertain that the schooner's nettings were all triced up, when a heavy and well directed shot from the pirates, that splashed into the, sea just astern of his own boat, warned him that the schooner was not to be taken by surprise-that his approach had been discovered-and that he would have to board under fire from her guns, and in the face of her desperate crew, "Give way, men! Give 'way; with a will! Death or victory!" shouted the young captain, as, heading the attack, his own boat, closely followed by the others, was urged swiftly toward the pirate schooner, whose cannon were now pouring upon them a heavy and deadly shower of grape-shot and canister. So fatally aimed were tl;e freebooter's guns, thqt ere the assailants could reach the schooner's side, though the tough ashen oars quivered with the  force of the rowers, at least fifty of the corvette's men were disabled. But  nothing daunted by the fate of their comrades, emulating the conduct of their fearless leader, the rest of his party, with shout and imprecation, cut their way thiough the pirate's netting, and threw themselves upon his deck. Here they met, hand to hand, in deadly struggle, her savage and lawless  men. Whilst Juan, tending toward the: schooner's stern, came in contact with him whom, from his uniform, and skillfully wielded weapon-which&amp; as yet had found no equal in the fight-he supposed the captain of the pirates. '    <pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC6533-00000045"/> 92           THE OCEAN-BOBN;  Long and stubborn was the contest between the youthful, active leader of the boarders, and the somewhat aged, but iron-sinewed commander of the schooner. Both were cool and collected, and fought with a mental concen- tration of purpose, and unyielding determination of will, that distinguished their encounter from the conflicts around. Stroke answered strole-steel met steel-thrust and parry followed ,each other for some time with equal fortune-and it was doubtful with which would be the victory, when the sword of the pirate, as he raised it to guard his head, broke short off from the force of the Ocean-Born's blow, and ere he could draw from his girdle the pistol his hand immediately sought, Juan leaped upon him with the bound of a panther, and bore him, overpowered, backward to the deck. Outnumbered by the corvette's men,' the fall of their leader so disheart- ened the' pirates that they cried " quarter!' And the loud shout that rang throlgh the night-air for miles, acquainted those remaining on board he man- of-war with their friends' success.  As goon as the pirate captain was secured, Juan hurried into the schooner's cabin, in search of his mistress. To his great joy he there found her, safe and unharted-except by the almost mortal terror occasioned by the thrilling events she had witnessed during the last fifteen hours. Cordial and plenteous were the expressions of affection and gratitude -that Catalina lavished upon the Ocean-Born, and as .he. hearkened to them and gazed upon the beauteous face and sparkling eyes of the fair speaker, he felt that the gratification of knowing he had been the means of saving her from pain, wa, mode than compensation for all the miseries he had suffered on her account*, The black gloom-fog which had overspread his mental horizon vanished like morning mist, and the young captain's future, brightened by the rising sun of hope, assumed again its former rosy hues, and, appeared joyous as ever. The wind, springing up about midnight, enabled the vessels to appioach each other, and all the schooner's crew were -transferred to the man-of-war, upon whose berth-deck, carefully manacled and guarded, they were placed, until they could be delivered up to the authorities on shore, for trial. and condemnation. The morning after the engagement, as the corvette, accompanied by her prize, hastened toward Matasnzas, the young captain's emotions were as rapturous as youth, gratified ambition and successful love could form in a warm and generous bosom; and the fondness with which Catalina listened to the images he drew of their future, showed how proud the lady was to possess so gallant a lover.                   . The merchantman sent in by Juan reached Matanzas ere he did. So that the citizens, when they saw the lofty corvette coming into harbor, followed by the rakish schooner, knew at once that it was the pirate and her capturer.   A TALE OF THE SOLTHEBN STAS.          93 Salvo after salvo of artillery pealed forth, and loud rang the bells of the city, to do honor to their young captain's triumph; whilst the gunsiof the corvette boomed out an acknowledgment of the compliment. But the Ocean-Born felt, as, stepping ashore from his gig-accompanied by Catalina- the shouts and hurras of the multitude rang in his ears, that a word of encouragement from the fair being by his side, or a glance of approval from the gentle mother who nursed him, was worth more than all the clangor of a hundremobs. Leaving Catalina at the residence of her father, without tarrying to receive the thanks with which the ]ady's, relatives would have loaded him, Juan proceeded at once to the residence -of Don Manuel, a few miles in the country-to greet his mother and grandfather. Arrived at home, beholding the gratification beaming on the face of the old gentleman, and the tenderi true love in the eyes of his dear mother- hearkening to the praises and congratulations of those he knew to be pure, disinterested and devotedly fond, Juan feltas great an amount of contentment and- happiness as man on earth can ever know. But then-for our sorrows ever draw near to'us, deep hidden in our joys-- when his every wish seemed gratified-his mistress resdued, his love returned -his mother and grandfather, well-and happy-his ambition more than satisfied--then, when to imagine a woe was nearly impossible, a huge avalanche of trouble was just ready to fall upon the head of the Ocean-Born with overwhelming force. -He that had borne prosperity so well-could he withstand adversity     - CHAPTER XV. "Adversity, sage, iuseful guest, Severe instructor, but the best, It is from thee alone we know Justly to value things below."-'SOM ERVILLE. JUAN never passed happier hours than those he spent at home the day he returned from his first cruise as captain. In the society of his mother, grand- father, and that old and tried friend, Don Henrico-who had hastened to congratulate the young hero as soon as he learned of his i'eturn-the moments flew by as moments can only fly to those blessed withihealth, hope and happiness. But life's duties ever step in to prevent life's joys from satiat- ing, and the young captain, much against his inclination, was compelled to    <pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC6533-00000046"/> TH '00E BOEtA;- leave his peaceful retreat early 'on the following day, to hand over to the civil authorities the pirate prisoners, who were yet on board theacorvette. Accompanied by Don Manuel, Juan proceeded to town--stopped a few moments at the home of Catalina-where his grandfather remained-and then went on board of his vessel, to discharge the stern task of transferring fifty'of' his fellow-creatures to the hands of those who would lead them first to prison, and then to execution. As the prisoners were paraded on deck, preparatory to being sent on shore, the young captain felt sonmuch pity for their situations that he was ashamed of his own tender-heartedness. He knew them to be guilty-oh, how guilty --of crimes without number. But an he looked and saw them men-living, breathing men, and most of them in the very prime of manhood-it seemed to hinm that it would be more in accordance with the spirit of the Great Law Book-which civilized governments pretend to take for theirguide-for a Christian people to give the poor wretches, who had been unable to restrain their lawless passions and animal appetites, an opportunity of repenting of their crimes-whilst restrained so that their influence could not be prejudicial to society-instead of thus rudely snapping the thread of their existence, and ushering them all unrepentant, unprepared, uncalled for, into the awful pres- ence of the Supreme Judge. It may be that the interest Juan felt in the leader of the bucaneers caused him to sympathize more than he otherwise would with the rest of his band. Something there was very different in the bearing of the pirate captain from' the manner and carriage of any of his crew, He was a fine-looking man, perhaps not more than forty-six or forty-seven years of age; but constant exposure to external and internal storms-those mental tornadoes that ravage man's frame as the material hurricanes do nature's works-had furrowed his brow and bleached his hair until he appeared sixty. His eyes, piercing, clear, undaunted, retained all the fire of youth, only-they had a cold, hard, fixed look, as if they were merely windows to the mind, through which the heart never gazed. A sneering expression, too, was upon the freebooter's countenance-as if he viewed his own and his crew's situation as a thing of no unexpected occurrence, that had to be, and it therefore was useless to Waste an emotion about it. To the Ocean-Born, the captain of the pirates appeared to be a man intelligent, brave and fearless; yet the feelings he entertained toward him were of curiosity mingled with respect, more than of pity. For :the pirate acted as one who was governed by an intellect keen, shrewd' and subtle-but 'devoid of soul; too indifferent to the present, too callous of the future, too intelligently evil, to exact pity-yet too basely wicked, too free from human dreads and sympathies, to command admiration.   A TALE Ol, tRE SOUTHERN SEAS.                    96 But Juan's duty was peremptory; and sending the prisoners to the quay, they were received by a large military escort, and, surrounded by a throng of shouting rabble, were marched off to prison. Whilst the populace, wi'h that strange perversity that makes man rejoice over his fellow's sins and misfor- tunes, appeared more gratified at the sight of a half hundred of their brother  wretches hand-cuffed, and on their way to felon's cells, than if it had been some holy procession, commemorative of noble deeds. The pirates and their guard had not left the quay many minutes, when a small boat, bearing a single passenger, put out from the landing and was rowed rapidly toward the corvette. The passenger was Don Manuel, who, as soon as the wherry reached the man-of-war, and he had received permission, hurried on board-an4 inquiied for the captain.  Something there was of. excitement' visible in the old man's face, that showed strong feelings were agitating his breast, and Juan, alarmed at the troubled expression of his grandfather, as he met him at the cabin-door, inquired anxiously-                         .  "Are you ill, my dear sir ?  Has any misfortune befallen you ?  Walk in -walk in !" " Heaven have mercy. upon you, my poor boy !" exclaimed the old gentle- man, as soon as he recovered composure enough to speak-" your life has been bright, and I, in my folly, thought that its future promised more happi- ness than-" " Has any accident happened-my mother . Is Catalina well ?" interrupted Juan, his voice tremulousawjth agitation. "Both are well, my child." "What then, my grandfather, can have disturbed you so strangely ?  Tell me quickly; I am a man, and hope I have fortitude enough to bear anything but the loss of those I love," replied Juan, as, with pale face and eager eyes, he waited for Don Manuel to answer. But the old gentleman, instead of speaking,'sat down upon a sofa, and leaning his face upon his hands, pressed his eyes, as if striving to shut from his sight some disagreeable spectacle. Whilst his grandson, burning with impatience, yet having too much veneration for his grandfather to hurry him to impart the fearful intelligence, stood nervously waiting. After the lapse of some moments the old man, inotioning the Ocean-Born to a seat by his side, said: "My dear, dear boy, you have been deceived regarding your birth and parentage. It was done with the best intentions, but between parents and children candor is the only thing that never -reacts painfully, and the truth, with all its stunning force, must now be told The leader of that pirate     <pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC6533-00000047"/> 96            THE OCEAN-BORN;  crew, who has just been consigned to prison, is your mother's lawful husband -your own father!" "Great God! It cannot, cannot be!" shrieked Juan, as he sprang to his feet-and then seizing his grandfather's .hand he continued: "Oh! say that there may be some mistake! That there is hope, even a single ray, that it is not so! lMy father! A pirate! consigned to prison and a felon's death -by his son's hand, too  It cannot, cannot, be! It is too horrible to believe!" Soothed by his grandfather, Juan again sat by his side; and fixedly, with- out moving, he listened, whilst the old man narrated the history of his mother's early trials and sufferings-her abduction-her marriage-her rescue. Though twenty-two years had elapsedieince he had seen the author of his daughter's wrongs, Don Manuel said that he no- sooner beheld the leader of the pirates, as they conveyed him through the street,. than he recognized in him the Vincent of former days, the blighter of his early hopes, returned to mar his present peace., Link by link had Juan followed the narrative, expecting to discover some flaw that would enable' him to entertain a doubt of its authenticity. But when his grandfather had finished, so complete was the story in all its parts -r-so miserably clear and connected in its details, that the Ocean-Born felt its truth in all its terror. Habit maintains its ascendancy when reason swerves, and Juan, influenced by the teachings of his mother, though his heart seemed bursting, his brain on fire, said to his grandfather-     . X "Let us pray for grace to bear this grievous trial; for of myself I hae not strength-its weight has crushed me." And there,- in the cabin of the corvette, the youth, just entering upon the threshold, and the old man, just ready to' leave life's theatre, bowed them- selves before the only Power who can strengthen man's weakness, and asked for fortitude to bear a sorrow that the young, fresh heart, and the old, sear'ed one, alike found too great for their endurance. Aftei' their supplication, both arose externally calm; but deep grief accom- plishes in seconds what time's slower hand requires years to perform-and though Juan appeared tranquil, his feelings had become almost as old as his grandfather's-gray hairs were visible amid his locks, that in the morning would have rivaled the raven's wing for glossy blackness-life never again would seem to him. as it had in days of yore-the kaleidoscope of youth had been removed, and the Ocean-Born saw that life was real, stern and sorrowful. / The excitement consequent upon the painful task he had to perform, com- bined with the. sympathy he felt for his grandson and daughter,.was more   A TALE OF, THE SOUTHERN SEASo.      '      ' than the feeble frame of Don Manuel-now past his seventieth yearr-could bear ; and Juan, when he reached home and- led the old man' to his chamber, feared that the grief which oppressed his grandfather would be more than his frail body could react against. Hastening to his mother, the Ocean-Born unfolded to her' the fearful faets he had learned; and Garcia's heart bled for her boy when she found that all the efforts she had made had not prevented "the sins of the father from being visited upon the child ;" that the sorrows she had hoped to shield him from had found her son, spite of her maternal watchfulness. But with all a mother's love, all a Christian's trust in G6d's goodness, she strove to- comfort her boy, and to persuade him that whatever is, is directed by the 'All-Wise for just and salutary purposes, though we may not be able to lperceive it. 'After a long interview with his mothei, Juan felt easier, if not happier; and the mother and the son determined to visit, that same evening, in his prison, the father and husband so unworthy such a wife and child. The young captain's influence prevented -his mother and himself from find- ing any difficulty in gaining admission to the pirate's cell; and Vincent, con- fined in a small, dank dungeon, chained .to a heavy iron bar, beheld and recognized her whom long years before he had so rudely torn from her home, so savagely compelled to marry him; and,- as in, days gone by, a soothing influence, emanating as it were from her presence, softened the almost ada- amantine glide in which  his feelings were encased-and whilst Garcia remained, the pirate was lost'in the man. ,The Oceaf-Born, what a lesson did he learn, as there, in that small den, he, for the first time, beheld his' parents together. The perpendicular cold stone walls, the rough, unyielding rock floor, the hard the ceiling of the cell, reminded him  of the world and its charities, as man finds them, when, unaided by living friends without, or those never-failing friends, good princi-- ples within, he comes in contact with either. His- mother, as the light from the torch fell upon her placid features, and eyes full of teuderness and sor- row, but showing forth the purity of the soul behind them, weak in her sex's fraiiy, but strong in her hbart's integrity, was a living exemplification ofwhat God's -race will do for man's weakness. * And his father, as there he stood with strong energies, vigorous intellect, immense muscular power, all rendered unavailing by lfetters voluntarily forged by himself, was a proof of the help- lessness of man's might, unaided by Divine right. The gratitude'Juan felt at having one parent so reproachless,'sonmewhat tempered the mibery, he experienced at possessing another sowcensurable; but the thought of his having been; however unintentionally, the means of bring, ing that crime-blackened father to the gallows, was awful.    <pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC6533-00000048"/> fl- utI OOIEAt-N-BOR, N Vincent, when he learned the object of their visit, was grateful for the motives that prompted their effort, but begged both Garcia and Juan not to' endeavor to have his life spared, "I am tired of life," he said  "I have been weary of it for years. But now, when I see what I might have enjoyed; when I look at you, Garcia, and feel that some such angel as yourself might have lovedme for my own sake; when I look at that youth, whom I will not disgrace by calling son, and think, that had I acted as I should have acted, as I was taught to act, I, might,'in the face of the world, have had such a child to call me father; and then know how I am situated, hdw acted-life disgusts mej I long to get rid of it I- When I think how much I have abused my advantages, hov sinned against my fellows and myself, I am anxious to leave a world where naught blesses me, where I have blessed no one." "No no!" Vincent continued, as Garcia was about to speak, :' speak not of me, nor for me; else the world, with its thousand ears, may learn some hint of your own and that gallant youth's connection with the felon-and you be disgraced forever." "We care not what the world says," spoke Garcia and 'Juan together; "we desire to gain you time to repent and make your peace with your Maker, ere you are summoned to the final tribunal," "I am too old to repent," replied the pirate. "My life, lived to the utmost, would hardly suffice to name the crimes I am guilty of, much less repent of them. No, leave me, and tell me not of mercyznor of pardon-I don't deserve it, and I don't expect it. Already I feel the pangs of hell, in knowing the loss I sustain, in being the husband of such a-wife, the father of such a song yet neither daring to claim the regard of the one, nor the respect of the other! Before you came, I thought no more of death than of a long sleep. But now, oh ! terror ! terror ! I dread to die, realizing the sins I have committed; and hate to live, aware of the joys I have cast from me. There- fore, leave me; else will I be unmanned and turn craven; and think no more of me, save in your prayers." Finding their longer stay only rendered the unhappy man more miserable, Garcia and the Ocean-Born.withdrew, leaving the pirate alone, but tot solitary; for his brain was teeming; his bell appeared to him crowded with the ghosts of the tbhongs he had murdered, who seemed jeering him, as he stood chained and manacled. Despite' his request, the. mother and the son used their utmost exertions to have Vincent pardoned, or at least to have his sentence mitigated' to imprisonment, But all their influence and eloquence was in vain; and the     pirate-captain was condemned to death. They also sought Vincent's permis- sion to visit him again, but could not obtain his consent-so that Juan, to know him, saw his'father but once. Those wlo saw the pirates executed, said, of all the erew, lte leader seemed most hardened, most careless of death. .So long does pride, with a strong grasp, maintain the mastery over every other sentiment, in those who have submitted to his dominion-and Vincent, smothering his better feelings, had died without a prayer or confession, apparently without compunction. On the same day that Vincent was hurried from life's stage, Don Manuel, who had been ill from the first discovery of.the pirate's identity-also died; but a far different death-one full of hope and Christian confidence. To Juan, his grandfather's removal seemed the very capstone 'of his miseries; he who so lately had nothing but happiness in anticipation, nw believed that the measure of his sorrow was full, that there was no room  for  another blow-but he was mistaken.     The breatl had hardly left Don Manuel when a servant brought the Ocean-Born a note; a glance assured him it was from Catalina; hastily breaking it open, in the expectation of finding it a ray of light on his horizon of gloom-7it only proved the crowning stroke of his misery. She whom he so worshipped, whose affections he had calcu- lated upon retaining if all else left him; she whose love. was to be to him a talisman-also had deserted him; and coldly stated in a note, that "'in obedience to her father's commands, she. rust relinquish .all acquaifitance and communication with his father's son."  Garcia had solved Catalina's character aright-pride, all pride. Now, indeed, did the Ocean-Born sink under the weight of his woes.  Iis father a pirate-a condemned and executed felon; his mistress false; the friends th'at had treated him most cordially, now-barely speaking-for it had leaked out' he was the pirate's son; .and the Christian world is ever halsher towards misfortune than to crime. Juan, hurled from the heights of human happiness to the depths of human misery-as innocent of the causes that led to the one as he was free from the agencies that produced the other-had not strength to meet. the shock; and a brain fever supervening, hi. life promised to last but a little, while longer than. his happiness.  But one great blessing was yet possessed by the stricken youth-his mother yet remained to him; by her kind nursing the physical malady was stayed in its progress; and when the Ocean-Born recovered his bodily strength, thanks to that mother's holy teachings, fervent prayers, he had also regained his mental courage.     <pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC6533-00000049"/> 1LVU           THEE OOEAN-BOREr; ' -      CHAPTER XVI.  "Virtue may be assailed, but never hurt; ' ,  Surprised by unjust force, but not efnthralled Yet even that. which mischief meant most harm,            , Shall in the happy trial prove most glory.7-MLTON.  .        "  IN a large and comfortable, but staid and sober-looking house, situated in one of the most private and quiet streetsin the city of Puerto Principe, there is now living an elderly lady, who, though never mixing in fashionable society,'is. universally known by the inhabitants of the town as the good Seiora Manchez. Those of her own class, for she is rich, respect her for the practice of those virtues which, though they themselves scarce imitate, yet  command their admiration; whilst the poor and distressed, who ever find in the lady a soother of their mental miseries, and a kind reliever of their'  physical wants, regard the Seiora as a saint worthy of canonization. Indeed, except the lady's own son, a priest, whose fervid eloquence and active charity, '  self-denial, and earnestness in the great work of salvation, is the wonder of the community; no one in thatsection is so-generally beloved as the sweet,. placid, benevolent lady of that staid and sober-looking house.  Few visitors are habitually received at the quiet mansion--for its mistress thinks time too precious to waste in idle gossiping; but the privileged, gray- haired mulatto ever greets with a smile a handsome old bachelor, whom she' titles Don Henrico, when he makes his regular. weekly call; and the hearty,  cordia manner -with which the gentleman salutes the seivant, "Bonita, my old girl, how are you?", is cause sufficient for her smiling welcome. At rare intervals, too, a bluff, sea-faring sort of person, whom the. black styles Captain Foster, pays a long visit to the. lady of the house ;'but the Seiora's constant companion, when his duties call him not away, is the priest, her son.  'Between the two there seems to exist a, bond stronger and more perfect than commonly subsists between mother and son-and so there is-the fellowship of suffering, sorrow, and trials passed .through and overcome in addition to their natural ties. The lady-it is Oarcia-and the priest is the Ocean Born, who, having learned the certainty of only disappointment here, have found. pure happiness in making things-temporal subservient to things eternal, and look forward with hope for their certain reward on that happy day when 'they both will be heaven-born!        -       </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
