<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6379">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Censoria Lictoria, or, What I Think of You </title>
            <author>Elemjay, Louise.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC6379</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-0848</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Censoria lictoria, or, What I think of you</title>
                  <author>Elemjay, Louise.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>84 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>New York  J.F. Trow</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York  J.F. Trow</pubPlace>
                  <date when="1855">1855</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-03-13">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Censoria lictoria, or, What I think of you</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6379-00000001"/>  CENSORIA LICTORIA; OR   WHAT I THNK OF YOU FROM THE NOTES AND MNUTES OF MSS BETSEY TROTWOOD'S OFFICIAL TOUR. BY "OUISE ELEMJAY,  "AUTHOR OF "ETTERS AND MSCELLANIES. The CENSOR'S role, the Roman Cato played, And rod and axe in LICTOR's hands obeyed. [PUBLISHED FOR THE AUTHOR. NEW YORK:. JOHN F. TROW, PRINTER, 49 ANN STREET.  1855.      <pb n="0" xml:id="VAC6379-00000002"/> * E . .INGSLEY, FOR THE AUT ENTER5), according to Act of Congress, in the year 1855 M. KINGSLEY, FOR THE AUTHOR In the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United States for the Southern District of New York. JOHN F. TROW, PRINTER, "Ann Street.   TO ONE WHOSE EPISTOLARY TALENTS FEAR NO OOMPETLTION, WHOSE MAGNANIMTY RESIGNS A PERSONAL PATRON TO PUBLIC WANT,- WILKINS MCAWBER; WHOSE GRANDISONIAN ELOQUENCE, MORE EVEN THAN HS OWN SUCCESSFUL EMGRATION, GAVE  TO  OCCIDENTAL    HUMANITY    ITS PRESENT CENSOR; THESE, HER OFFICIAL AND ANTE-OFFICIAL RECORDS, ABSTRACTED, AS USUAL, BY THE CONFIDENTIAL SECRETARY, ARE NOW  BY HS ADMRING AND HUMBLE DISCIPLE, THE HONORABBLE SECRETARY, AFORESAID.    <pb n="0 (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC6379-00000003"/>  CONTENTS. PAGE PREAMBILAR PERORATION ..............................   7 KENTUCKY .. ........ ........ ......................... " WHO'S TO WEAR THE HATS? ....................      12 REPORT OF A SELF-INSTALLED COMMTTEE ................. 15 THE DARK HOUR ....................................... 19 THE ALL-SEEING E E ................................... 20 TO MY WILL-O-'WISP DAUGHTER, FANNY FEERN............... 20 FILIAL ................... .... ..................... . 21 AN INVALID'S SOLILOQUY ..................... .... .... 23 To A BRIDE..    .....................23 "OGIC AND DEFERENOE ............................     24 NEW LORDS, NEW LAWS ................................ 26 DID YOU EVER ? ........................................ 26 THE ENGLISH IS A STRONG LANGUAGE ..................... 27 "WHY DON'T THE STATE OF MARYAND PUT HM (Rev. Mr. S.) IN PETTICOATS?" ........... . e . ........-.....   381 a. ALABAMA                       82 'WOMAN'S SPHERE. .................................... . 83 HARLESTON ..........                    4 M ]EMORIAL TO THRTY-THRD CONGRES... ................    44    <pb n="6 (Table of Contents) -7" xml:id="VAC6379-00000004"/> 6            CONTENTS. PAGE CLEVER AUTHORESS ................R...................   45 NUMBER ONE AND, NUMBER Two .......................    47 PROMSING PATRON ................................     59 "AY SERMON TO PRIEST AND PRELATE ..................... 59 CHARITY .. ......................  ............****   61 NEW  BROOM  ........................... .. ......... . 62 WHAT A BOO: MGHT BE GOOD FOR...7....................   7 CAP FOR HEADS THAT FIT ..............................   68 PUFFS AND PUFFERS.....  ........   ......   ..... 68  " MRS. GRUNDY AND EASTERN EDITOR TO SOUTHERN AUTHOR.. 71  SOUTHERN AUTHOR TO MRS. GRUNDY...................... 71 VALENTINE FOR THE LOUISVILLE JOURNAL................ 72 - ETHCS AND HUMANITY. .........................      79  ............................. 80  Ll ; FRBOM ON HGH .............................2.. . 82  ONLY A SLIGHT DIFFERENCE................ .............  83 I    *       .i . I         ' 4*   PREAMBILAR PERORATION. --------- SOME inconsiderate people may expect we are going to apologize for making free with Miss Betsey's bureau de police at this -particular stage of her career; and some few hardened old fogies, whose organs of veneration for modern manners; morals and tendencies, sadly need developing, might not care a bawhee, if we were to cast some such innuendo reflection on the honor and honesty of Young America's precedent-makers; but thanks to those "emancipated" souls, who have from time to time pyac- tically maintained, in the teeth of vulgar prejudice, that all right in matters of interest lies not in the g great heads that conceive, but the light-fingered hands that hold, or execute, we know better. EVERY THNG FOR ALL (that can get it), that'p our Uncle Sam's motto; but how is said ALL to get it, if any body's got any right to keep any thing back that any body else wants? It's clearly a conspiracy against the peace and dignity of 11 his "FREE AND ENLIGHTENED," for when people want a thing, they want it; trust a traitor to put his own papers in apple-pie order, and see    <pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6379-00000005"/> 8      PREAMBILAR PERORATION. if he don't slip out, or burn up the very ones you want: and, besides, what good will it do a man going on a trip to-day, if Mr. Dick and the missing papers should turn up to-morrow? W on't he have to be picked up next da, and acquit the engine on the morrow? Of course he will, and the fact is, he ought to have had these, and more besides, long ago; and would, too, if our su- perfluous, but well-meaning, hard-working Master Mel' hadn't been intercepted, and somewhat crippled, by the senseless kickings and cavortings of one of those old : "bdggars on horseback," that never can be easy to ride on their way, witho:r; iding down every' thing else. However, he'll find the ingenious operation of "biting off his own nose to spite his face," pleasant and profit- able, perhaps, some day; and the unlucky ad inter, with his gallant, but ill-omened name, has rotated now, and we've taken abundant precautions that there's to be . ' no more of that." Miss BETSEY may chafe at having  to buy another new veil, but knows very well we've got all her records in such "a fix," that nobody else ever could decipher ten consecutive words; a simple and effi-  cacious plan for "holding on," that we should take  great pleasure in recommending to other secretaries and office-holders, only that most of them, it is believed, practise upon it already. True, it has this little incon-  venience, we can't always make it out ourselves; and  when one line's contumacious, another has to go down.  This rather amalgamates styles; and one of the parties ..: being forestalled in his designs, may take advantage of it, to pretend our version isn't genuine ; but if any body  doubts it, let him come and see if we haven't got his   ......... 9rJJ Ja: IuATION.    9 first drafts, and others, too, belonging apparently to no particular person or place, but evidently smuggled in by some supernumerary scion, or candidate on trial. It is extremely mortifying, though, that we can't tell all inquiring minds a great deal more about our clief's private history than she knows herself she never did like being catechised, you knqw, but from all that we can learn, worthy Mr. Micawher, with a disinterest- edness above all praise, directed her attention to this continent about the time of the last presidential elec- tion, and persuaded her to be on hand in case "any thing should turn up." Accordingly, we find her here soon after all Bonnetdom went "a-crabbing ; "and it was hoped, the sight of her " respectable bever  ight arrest its course before it goack to Mrs. Eve's fig-leaf; but, unfortunately, a due regard for personal safety, and great horror of having to set her clogs in every predecessor's footsteps, compelled her, not only to muffle it in a double veil of deep-blue mystery, but even forego b ts "insane tilt," and her own patronymic, in order to escape being torn limb from limb by those peer- less jackals, apes, and other ' varmints," always on the look-out for some foreign lion! The election--mch to " glorification" discomfiture turned up FRANK PIERCE; and much to the credit of his sagacity, and Mr. Micawher's forecast, Mss BET- SY's unique talents were soon put in requisition. Fortunately, the official duties chimed in admirably with her own inclination to see what nobody else goes to see, and knowing that thimngs are to names as nothing to me, she continues up to this very day passing up and    <pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6379-00000006"/> 10      PREXMBILAR PERORATION. down (for the most part very quietly), under her ob- scure cognate; catching morals and manners without their holiday hats and "Sabba-dy" cloaks on, " takin' notes," and dispensing meed and dreed, "all fearlessly and free," where the first inkling of her distinguished name would bring whole troops of Philistines, if not Bar- num's show-case, down upon her to " put her through" the grand paces, as they did Samson of old; bury her ' five-fathom deep" in hoodwink and "flummery," her especial abomination; and, what is worse, deprive  Mrs. Grundy, " and all the rest of mankind," of the great pleasure of knowing what she really does think of the "chief estates" and little-greats in Uncle Sam's and St. Picayune's guessing, gasing, reeling, scrambling, nomadic, stampeding jurisdictions. LoUISE ELEMJAY, Sec. NEW YORK, Dec. 20th, 1854.   CEISORIA LICTORIA. KENTUCKY. Kentucky's slopes are green and fair, Kentucky's hearts are warm and brave And living gems of beauty rare Crown crest and cliff and woodland wave; And deep-toned notes of sympathy-. Vorthy the land of sacred dust-- Have cheered a heart whose prayer shall be God guard thee well, and thou--thy trust! Dwo   SARINGs, August 1st, 1852. Alas, alas! that blood should dye thy honored shore, Htome of the noble, beautiful and true--AsHMORE t 1854.                 L. E. "-1:ETUC          Y    <pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6379-00000007"/> 12       FAMLY PArERS AND ,-, "WHO'S TO WEAR THE HATS?" "WRo?"Why, you, to be sure! Who else do'you  suppose? None of your figure-heads over my top-gal- lant rigging, I thank you!"Take your hat? -not I. The clumsy, ill-conditioned, "shocking bad" old tar- paulin, keep it yourself! "But just to oblige." And haven't I obliged, I should like to know, till I've taken on more freight from  Messrs. Cotton-Bale, Dry-Goods &amp; Co., than I can make good headway under in fair weather-want to see me swamped, don't you? "Make such capital ballast " Glad to hear it-put it right on-don't know any body that needs it more. "Won't wear the things-hateful, ridiculous!"-" ' Stove-pipe hats,"' eh! Think to get rid of them, doh't you? No use. Hats were made to wear--somebody's got to wear them, and I. shan't. "Stupid, ugly, ill-contrived, un"mnageable things! Then who but you should wear them?   Great, awkward, stiff, intole-knle bores!." Don't see but they fit you very well. "But that's only because, ma'am,  you're use' to seeing us thgether." Don't often see you without, that's a fact. Wonder if you sleep in them- expect you can't-dare say that's the very reason now you've fallen out with them. "So 'hard and hot and heavy '-ruin your beautiful bonnet, ma'am, if they should happen to fall on it." Can't help it, none of your blarney-want to throw them away, and ruin all the hatters in the world, don't you? Shan't allow it, I tell you!   OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS.       13 "If you would only listen to reason!" Will, when I think there's any chance of hearing it. "Oh, then, you see, madam, such a constant pressure on the region of the brain "-don't fill up the vacancy-of course not -anybody can see that. "'But it might produce torpor, or inflammation." "Naught's never in danger "-got on your grand- mothefs double-wrapper now-want to poke your head into her nightcap too. Can't have it; distinctions must be kept up, else how should we know which was which? O Oh, just as easy, ma'anm "-Just as easy, I don't doubt, as you could have told, a year or two ago, what sort of pedal annexations ladies did have, if they had been cruel enough to s ove them into pantalets like children or squaws; or break the whalebones and straitlaces of pious, per pateti - d Mrs. Roundhead, and fall back into the costume of her worthy neighbor, good, quiet, stay-at-home Mrs. Knickerbocker ;---eking ! it out with some sort of mufflers in compliment to the 't' quaint, though rather irreverent sneers, of her classic ;; historian. No, no-don't forget old friends and past kindness-my turn now-bound to keep you (far as in me lies) from making yourself ridiculous; so just make yourself easy with whabt you have got, and never say CAPS to me again. "But they are so much lighter and more comforta- ble?"Can't have them, I tell you, without the bells- don't dream of abandoning you to your own discretion in matters of such vital importance. Yield the head- gear, you'll be after my parasol and bib-and-tucker next.    <pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6379-00000008"/> L I act is, I believe I have seen you with the latter already (though it mighlt be only the skirt of an infant's robe you had tucked u nder your vest when you couldn't get a decent shirt-bosom), and no doubt butyod distin yourelf as Aistress of Robes and older of the Gir- d   he" to a whlte hare of ballet dancers but do you  suppose I'm going to look at'any such frights? "Oh tht's all  habit, if you were only once used to the "--But I'm not used to them, and I don 't want to be used to then , and I'm not going to be used to them i Haven't I got used to the hats, and do you sup- pose I'm going the trouble all over again? "But ATis are so heavy and unhealthy i       : What if they are, haven't you got used to them? "If you'd only consider"--And who ever knew you to consider any thing but how to curl a moustache, flourish a rattan, and twirl an opera-glass? Consider,' in- deed-set you up to consider! "But if you please, ma'am"-I tell you I don't please, I don't mean to please, and what's more,I never will please, so shut -up with your fool-whim, put on your hat, and go about your business, or sit down and dress  this French doll, you exquisite little man-milliner you i BETSEY TROTWOOD.   REPORT Of the sef-installed Committee of THE TRANSCENDENTAL PHLAN- THROPY-EXPOETATION SOCIETY, prospectively convened, to take into consideration the spirit-stirring humanity appeal of the Ladies of Great Britain to the Ladies of America: MOST ELEVATED TRANSCENDENTALS: Your Committee having met, according to appoint- ment, in the Hall of Imagination, resolved itself into the most fitting exponent of super-empyrean benevo- lence, and agreed that our benevolence always intensi- fies most and flourishes best when its object is in any "- body's reach but our own, did proceed to resolve as follows : First-That whereas, facts and figures do materially impede the march of Transcendental Progress, it is here- by RESOLVED to disclaim, repudiate, and refuse to recog- nize as belonging to the human species, any specimen of the genus homo who shall decline to aid and abet, to the extent of his ability, in dethroning Statistics, Official Investigations, Parliamentary Reports and Scien- tific Demonstrations from their usurped supremacy over the mind of man; and install in their place the very reliable lucubrations of that profoundly erudite, incon- testably matter-of-fact and  pre-eminently veracious class of historians, commonly known as novelists or romancers. Second-That in consideration of the important services rendered by these disinterested though ill-used evangelists of "Liberty, Fraternity, and Equality," it is RESOLVED to request and advise all publishers to issue    <pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6379-00000009"/> 16 i      FAMLY pAPERS AND  their works hereafter, not from "love of filthy lucre," but "' free gratis," for the good of the race: and other sympathy-mongers to combine and endow a 6ollege of  criticism, with a capital of fifty millions, and authority to award premiumns of from five to fifty thousand per annum, to the more meritorious of these High Priests  of Utopian Theology.                  ' Third-Be it also RESOLVED, That your commander- in-chief for the Home Department be instructed to de- spatch suitable officers into the Interior, with orders to make full and impartial investigation into all the griev- ances, moral and physical, said to exist not only in the obscure streets, dens, lanes and alleys of the populous cities, but also in the mining, anufacturing, and agri- cultural districts of England, Scotland, and Ireland, and the adjacent Province of France, and suggest the most expeditious mode of redressing the same; and the Sec- retary for Foreign Affairs authorized and otherwise em- powered to invite the distinguished Charles Dickens and Eugene Sue to lecture iour humane and intelligent coun- trymen on the enormities perpetrated, without their privity or concurrence, in the Schools, Factories, Work- houses, Hospitals, garrets and cellars of Paris and Lon- don, End designate such of our eminent citizens as are, in their opinion, the most proper persons to interfere promptly and efficiently in the premises. Fourth--Being seriously apprehensive that a certain .. ultramundane region denominated Herschel is miserably deficient in light if not heat, this Coloinittee do most unhesitatingly RESOLVE to pettiiow Congress immediately : for a grant of five hundred millions to erect and furnish   US'J'1UkJLAi U SJU DU . lJl -I1JD. L f Observatories through which all sympathizers can exam- ine critically into the state of that planet and the. solar system generally; and also to charter forthwith THE GRAND CONCENTRIC UNIVERSE GAS COMPANY, with full power to lay pipes, establish reservoirs, contract for moonshine, levy subscriptions, and appropriate the right of way throughout the entire extent of those ulterior dependencies; Government being allowed to purchase one-half the whole stock in advance, at a premium of ten per cent., on condition that it give the President and Board of Directors carte blanche as to amount, and pledge itself to legalize and sustain all their acts and ordinances ab initio. Fifth-Having observed with extreme pleasure the affectionate interest which enlightened denizens of our Territory of Great Britain evince in all our domestic concerns, this Committee do unanimously RESOLVE that the said Territory is now worthy to be, and hereby is, elevated by brevet, to the rank and dignity of a Sove- reign Independent State, with all the rights, privileges, and immunities, present and prospective, appertaining to any other member, oriental or occidental, now, or hereafter to be admitted into this grand confederacy; in ratification whereof this Committee tenders in behalf of society, the right hand of fellowship and fraterniza- tion to the right honorable and well-beloved transatlantic sisters and, confreres, so nobly ambitious of competing with us the honor of re-organizing the whole social and material system. And, finally-Be it resolved that this Committee do now adjourn, repair to the Pantheon of all Abstractions,    <pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6379-00000010"/> 18 -FAMLY PAPERS AND submit these resolutions, and ask to be discharged from further service. FANCY TOPLOFTICAL, Chairman. The foregoing Resolutions having been duly present- ed and passed by acclamation-the House previously resolving itself into Committe of the Whole for their reception-it was further RESOLVED, 1st, That the Com- mittee be discharged with many thanks for its prompt and harmonious action, and very able and lucid exposi- ' tion of the precise views and objects of this Society; and, 2d, That copies of these and the aforesaid resolu- tions be immediately transmitted to agents and coadju- tors in all parts of our jurisdiction; and the Pulpit and Press, without distinction of sect or party, be invited and required, under penalty of our displeasure, to give them and the principles therein so luminously embodied,  all the sanction, advocacy, and dissemination which their own intrinsic merit, and the exigency of the case, so im- periously demand. By order of the Board, SERAPHNA ST. CERULEAN, Pres. TRANSCENDENTIA RANT, Corresponding Sec. and Amanuensis Extraordinary. Attested Copy. LUNATIUS VISIONNAIRE, Recorder. Capital hit, that of yours, Mr. Dick, getting me the first copy. Keep an eye on their proceedings; but re-   B .l         e 1OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS. 19 member what ompany you are in, and mind your king , Charles' Ilead pn o   , and mind your king Charles' head. "Shouldn' wond&amp;r if Mrs. President had the Veiled Prophet's vow!" Like enough BETSEY TOTWOOD. THE DARK HOUR. "I am clean forgotten as a dead man out of mind; I am become like a broken OH my spirit's chord hath lost its tone Hope's sparkling sands are running low And the weary days, the long, the lone Nor cares, alas, how soon they go! Yet the Southern heart is warm and true As the seraph sheen on wing of light; And like moon-kiss soft on honey-dew, Just such is its smile of gentle light: But the stranger's heart is dark with woe, And the minstrel harp is all unstrung  For unheeded falls that music's flow That falters on a stammering tongue. "A SUPERNUMERAIRE.    <pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6379-00000011"/> 20       FAMLY- PAPERS AN U "THE ALL-SEEING EYE." THou God seest! Man may fail And crush the bruised reed till it break, Its quivering harpstring's dying wail For passion's lurid tempest take; 'But TIou GOD SEEST all the soul ; Its crushing wrong, its dark despair Is mirrored in thy open scroll,-- A juster judgment waits us there!  TO MY WILL-O'-WISP DAUGtHTER, FANNY FERN. FANNY, my child, your mother does know you are out, but means to let you have your own way, without any fuss, as all reasonable, well-behaved parents should, when they know they can't help themselves.  But my dear, why don't you strike all round when you get the "cat" in your hand, instead of stopping short with a few ill-bred editors, whose mothers, poor silly things, never taught them the first principles of civilization. I don't half like such invidious distilc- tions. There's the whole tribe of "Itching Earsnow, just listen at them, when they happen to pounce on a su'spected contributor, or get a real live author by te :, button  One would think they'd bought him instead of his book or article, and ten to one if they didnt  of bi^ book or ta StfSS^^^I   )orrow that. And yet what a sweet howl they'd set up, f, after carefully folding down the page of a letter, you, should deliberately turn it up and read every mortal syllable before their face and eyes: You might as well be at an Irish wake ; they wouldn't stick to call you 'an unlicked cub," and your respectable parentess a sihe bear." Hurting people's feelings, I take to be the main ob- ject of " blowing them up," and when they'haven't any to hurt, it's labor lost; and 'twould break your dear little heart to see your venerable mother fatigue herself to no purpose; but couldn't you, honey, just give them a little oil of Lash? Do now, that's a good child ; and much oblige your dutiful manmma, FRANCES FERN, Sen. January, 1853. FILIAL. "OH, annoyed are you'?  Well, I told you so, with all your old frumpery notiwns about decorum, and delicacy and urbanity, just fit to rusticate with Chinese mandarins and Dutch burgomasters in some old land- scape garden. And good enough for you, too; you never would learn to clear a brush fence and dash through a nettle patch properly!"  Hush, Fanny, hush  That isn't the civil chat for a model mamma who knows her place and conducts to sensibly!"Give 'em a little oil of Lash?" To be sure she can, or she's no half-sister of mine; and if she    <pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6379-00000012"/> 22       FAMLY PAPERS AND won't, I will. Any thing to oblige you, ma'am, so long as it chimes in with my own humor, and you keep quiet and treat your children respectfully; so walk up here, every man, woman and child of you, and see if you don't catch it. You're a pretty looking set, now : hold up. your head you omadhoun there! It isn't enough, is it, that every guessing, prying, keyhole editor in the land must be bragging that Mr. SO-AND-SO, "the inevitable Mr. So- and-so," shook him by the paw, or walked into his sanc- tum, but you must infest the high seas to waylay and capture-all innocent fugitives from notoriety? Who gave you "Letters of Marque," I should like to know, that you've any right to board a strange craft, and or- der the captain to stand and deliver "a full and par- ticular" of his own private history; with that of the crew and all other cargo? "Haven't got any, eh?" Thought as much-and, harkee, Mr. Scout, and you, too, Captain Itemizer Longhow, my wife's cousin, Sour- krout Snapdragon, Esq., says he's kin to old Judge Lynch, and thinks an unhung spy, unlicensed priva- teer, and poacher at lrge, little better than PUBLIC NUISANCES! And here are you, too, modest Mrs. Dotell, with your old aunt, Eve Whatdoes! Have you ever a Bible between you, with a word in it about Busybodies, and don't you feel ashamed of yourselves now? No, you don't-you haven't got sense of propriety enough to feel ashamedat any thing! It won't be long before the whole tribe of you'll be popping into my store, just to buy a shawl or borrow a calico dress, and then coolly   OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS.  expect me to furnish you a whole suit of underclothes, of the choicest superfine, from that down, free gratis! You'd better, you had. CRAB' THE SECOND. AN  INVALID'S SOLILOQUY. "I had no place to flee unto, and no man cared for my soul 1" "JUDGE NOT," some chain the willing footstep stays, Thy brother's heart, perhaps, is vexed with care  A sister knows not of the bitter days That thought sits brooding o'er its lone despair. "FE, HEAT, how should they know how cold is DEATH, How fiercely gasps the encoffined mind To catch once more the gush of living breath? Lone, doubting heart, think better of thy kind! Think yet again, oh thou of little faith, He lives, who ne'er forsakes, though all forget ; "OVE, STRENGTH and TRUTH is pledged!  His bow "thus saith, Serene and high, spans all the darkness yet. --j,;        LA SUPERNUMERAIRE. TO A  BRIDE. MRS. J. L. M., OF LOUISIANA. GOD bless the beautiful and young, ,  God bless the weay, sad, and old;    <pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6379-00000013"/> 24       FAMLY PAPERS AND I will not shame my poet's tongue By envy of thy double gold. Thy spirit's wealth is rich and rare, Thy life's young rose hath known no mould, And worthy thou of fate so fair: God keep thy heart from growing old! L. L. "OGIC AND   DEFERENCE. "MY GRANDMOTHER!"  Well, what?" "Noth- ing, you old quiz, I didn't mean you, you know I didn't," says my eldest hope, " but heie's this newspaper, throw- ing up that crazy tomboy of a New York gal that went gallivantin in her brother's Sundays (more fool he not to wear 'em himself), and telling the' prim spinsters and strong-minded matrons' they didn't know 'what it was all a comin' to' when they were talking short skirts and 'woman's rights.'--Isn't it awful?" "Yes, very," replies my sensible mamma, " and that isn't half-there's been a whole book printed about some Yankee she Debby that went a soldiering in the Revo- lutionary war, and got discharged, dnd married and pen- sioned ; and more, too, about one Joan of Arc, that they pretend went philandering up and down dressed in mail, and fighting on horseback more like a born fury than a decent, honest, Christian woman; and got burned at last as a witch for her pains!-You see they never do come to any good."      OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS.        25 "Hold on there, old 'un, you're coming it a leete - too strong, that 'ere all happened before Bloomer and ? Convention were born " C That doesn't make a bit o' difference, sonny; it's all owing to Mrs. Pantalets and Miss Strongminded. And that isn't the worst either, for ever since their dis- graceful outhreak passed with impunity, some other ri- diculous creatures-ambitious snips of tailors or clothiers no doubt-have been suspected of unlawful designs upon the heads of community; and now it seems some bar- barous wretch has got this poor editor's 'hat,' and you : see yourself there isn't a particle of brains left!" "MY EYE, no there isn't," says Crab' the third, chucking down his gourd-case with a decided 'you don't get my brains, see if you do' air; "but do you know, old Specs, I wonder you and all the old fogies don't take up for Miss Convention and Mrs. Fillibuster!" "I take up for them? I!" Yes, you; why not?  They're the exact reverse of that swaggering, lying 'sack-imbibing old varlet, Jack Falstaff!" "So they are, boy, so they are, for he was 'not only -witty himself, but the cause of wit in others!' Enough said." Right smart boy, that, my son Crab'--if his granny doesn't spoil him!    <pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6379-00000014"/> '9       XJ . 3L..U J. J. Z CX. J lo .o .. X  m u, ' it NEW  LORDS, NEW   LAWS. MISS BETSEY'S INAUGURAL, March 4th, 1853. INKHORNS, POUNDTEXTS, COMPOSITIONSTICKS: ATTENTION, all of you  Try and keep quiet, and walk a chalk, will you? I've got something else to do besides following you up all the while to keep you from making perfect sillies of yourselves; but just let me catch you playing the fool with your "little go," stirring up, and perverting President Pierce's twenty-six battal- ions any where in this republic of letters, and see if I'm not down upon you with rod and lictor! BETSEY TROTWOOD, Censor. DID YOU EVER? No, I never! I really am ashamed of you-you, I mean, Mr. Editor-.-you, who sit on a three-legged stool; you, to whom 'the people look up, to talk such  bad grammar, and confound genders after this fashion! Don't you actually know any better, or do you suppose your paper unfit for ladies' eyes, that you are always : talking about your "readers," and say never a word about theb readeresses? Try and mend your ways, will you, and oblige this : present writeress.                 .  BETSEY TROTWOOD, Censor.   THE ENGLISH IS A STRONG LANGUAGE. STRONG," no mistake about that!-strong, I should rather think it was, to be identified at this present, after all the hauling and pulling, and twisting and screwing, to make it "walk round about the truth," till there's scarce a word with an inkling of its original signification left! Here's WOMAN now, once it meant a companion "meet" for man, when man was made in the image of his Maker; now, a poor vulgar creature made (for other people's convenience) out of the refuse clay, unfit for the crystal and china wares of creation. Then, when this " woman" was lawfully married, she was the wife of her husband. "And isn't she now, pray?" Not a bit of it, sir! She's nothing in the world but his lady; that is, some sort of feminine appendage-it may be his sister, his neighbor, his cousin, or it may be something else, not altpgether so presentable; so you'd better keep your eyes open, and make your own inferences-I can't help you, though it's evidently some incumbrance between him and the rest of the baggage. And LADY, too ;-old writers tell us it comes from lafdy, a contraction of laf, a loaf, and day, which signi- fied a loaf-giver; that is, a domestic sort of personage rather given to benevolence and hospitality. Now, it means a bundle of intense selfishness done up in "a mighty void of sense," and moulded by fashion into a walking advertisement of more millinery, gewgaws, and other dry goods-no matter whose or how come by- than any small craft could make good sail ,under, if she !.A    <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6379-00000015"/> 28       FAMLY PAPERS AND hadn't shipped more airs than would float a balloon. And then GENTLEMAN! Time was when that meant "a man without fear and without reproach," now it means-shades of all the Bayards, what does it mean? Well I don't wish to be too critical, and the EInglish certainly is a strong language and a copious, but it strikes me it can't quite come up to that defi- nition!          i  Here Miss Betsey-you've heard of my aunt BET- SEY TROTWOOD, the new CENSOR, haven't you?-gave an "insane tilt" of her beaver at my bundle of rods and fainted, just as one ofthe new specimens bawled out the name of another changeling, CHARITY, in excuse for fagging a young girl to death, whose father he had swindled out of his last dollar, and into a drunkard's grave. I know it's no manner of use this " tickling a r7zi- nocerous with straws," and have my doubts about the propriety of casting "pearls before swine ;" but sup- pose I must do her bidding, or be reformed out of office, and lose all the reward of my uncommon filial piety ; so, do you know, sir, that of two inspired apostles, one gives the definition of that word synthetically and senten- tiously as LOVE, and the other goes into the analysis more elaborately? Of course you don't, and it's a won- der to me that some enterprising colporteur, or getter- up of pious young story-books for grown-up old children, don't think of interspersing a few texts of Scripture in the Price Current, for the benefit of those who never read any thing else; but neither of them ever dreams of confounding it with throwing ("by order of the   ,- d@.    OFFICIAL 'DOCUMENTS.      29 board") a dog's bone with a dog's treatment, at some audacious wretch who brings his misery "between the wind and your nobility," and then chanting loud paeans to your own munificence, and caustic invectives on his ingratitude. Ingratitude, indeed! And what for should he be grateful? That you have pelted off a nuisance with dirty coppers and more bitter words, more to relieve your own eyes than his necessities? Don't he know, as well as you, how easily you can poke your hands into ' your own pockets, say, "so many appeals to charity," and "pass over on the other side," when they are only reported to you? To be sure he does; and don't he know, too, that this very " so many," is generally proof fositive that you never respond to any? None better; and here you swell up, as if the world never saw the like of such magnanimity, because you take in an orphan child, as well if not better born than your i own, and their equal, or superior, it may be, in every thing but present position; or (when you can't help it) patronize in some sort an unfortunate acquaintance, that you were once proud, perhaps, in your very heart's core, to call your "friend," make her the bond slave of all your wills, exact ever after the labor of a Hercules, the patience of Job, the meekness of Moses, the devotion of a martyr, the love of a seraph, and the servility of a toady; and then feel amazed beyond measure if she isn't willing, ever after, to go to perdition, if necessary, to save you and yours from " dying of a rose in aromatic pain." MONSTROUS, isn't it, this "black ingratitude of    <pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6379-00000016"/> 1-i 30       FAMLY PAPERS AND human nature" (certes if it exists), and altogether inex- plicable? Not quite! Did you never reflect, that "man is of three natures, reguiring all for charity," that no one feels specially thankful for what he has paid for, over and overt and that this very proscribed ingrate feels in his secret soul that you have taken your pay drop by drop out of his heart's blood to the very last farthing, and ten times over, in the pleasure of trampling down, in your coldness, your passion or your pride, all the in- dependence of his nature-scoffing, sneering, deriding and ignoring all the finer feelings of his being? And he has paid you, for "a man's self-respect is worth more to him than money, and evil is the charity that hum- bleth and maketh man less happy!" Once I saw a lady engage some domestic "finery," and wear it too, despite her own excellent taste, lest the ingenious manufacturer should consider the purchase a mere pretext for bestowing a few dollars which she herself but ill could spare ; and that was charity, but yours-go to, you don't even understand its first princi- ples, never take the word in your mouth again till you know what it means! You have not given "to diligence as to an equal," and the extorted pittance is deadly aconite to the soul! CRABTREE AP CRAB', 1st Lictor   : Of4COFFICIAL DOCUMENTS.           31 " 'WHY DON'T THE STATE OF MARYAND PUT -HM (Rev. Mr. S.) IN PETTICOATS.?" SURE enough, why don't it? I am afraid flannels and domestics must be scarce, and my own stock is getting rather low ; but inasmuch as he "that hath two coats" is enjoined to "give to him that hath none"I'll try and squeeze out one rather than he and his brethren, lay and clerical, who figure on the opposite side, shouldn't be properly attired. But why in the name of common sense-if she isn't defunct-can't they see, that when the third gender goes about to raise a fuss, "kick up a row," and "ele- vate the ancient Henry" generally, there's no way like letting it alone very severely," if they want it to go home and mind its own business, if it's got any, and leave them to do the talking; which it never will so long as they keep it before the public in so many point- less jests and pithless invectives, evincing nothing half so clearly as a hearty good will to be witty and sarcastic if they only could. Well, there's a vast deal of weakness and wicked- ness stirring, no doubt; but it strikes me a Highland seer would have thought of turning his own coat before making so many mislicks; yet here they all are, and never a man of them dreaming that he's only playing showman and  second fiddle" to this fillibustering lutsu and keeping it in countenance, by showing the world that there can be something a little more ridiculous i Here, you "young Harry," lay that flattering unc-    <pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6379-00000017"/> FAMLY PAPERS AND tion on the pulpit and press, or never say "copy" to me again. me - agaBETSEY TROTWOOD, Censor. ALABAMA.  RESPECTFULLY INSCRIBED TO THE CITIZENS OF MOBILE AND MONTGOMERY. BRIGHT land of "sweet waters,' how falls on the soul,  All frozen and chilled in the Crescent's cold glare,  X The balm of thy love ; and till life's latest goal  Be thy sons ever brave, thy daughters most fair.  Oh, Love is the light on the seraph's bright wing,   ; So dear to the eye that is glazing in death; In music Love steeps every cherub-harp's string,  And LOVE, holy love, is God's essence, he saith! On the heart Genius flings his glory and pall, Love bathes all its folds, and what splendor so rare?  So, land of ' sweet waters" the minstrel her all,  Breathes o'er the6 this moment, in blessing and prayer.  L L. L.  ^ 1853.        -                 i * SWEET WATERS, until some "pestilent researcher into antiquity"  translated it "here we rest."'  25  4   WOMAN'S SPHERE. Respectfully dedicated to those astute savans who never discover, "that in order to live WETLL, people must live," nor that some women wight possibly chance to miss the whole, sole and uni- versal MSSION, if they should happen to starve to death before- hand, or after they get out of practice. "To tell the hundreds and thousands of women struggling, in some form, for sub- sistence, that their MssIro is, 'to make good wives and mothers,' is simply to insult them most stupidly I "--GREELEY. "A certain age, which is the most uncertain thing of all.'-BraoN. No, that it isn't! Stick to poetry, my lord ; you've a rather respectable "knack   of rhyming,' but don't shine here, that's certain. There's WOMAN'S SPHERE, now as much taller in the way of dubiousness, as metaphys- ics is head and shoulders over mathematics. Why, I tell you, man, it could give odds, carry weight and beat all hollow, at the very first clip, any other will-o'-wisp ever seen this side Adam's fall!  Hundreds upon hun- dreds have been doing their best to come up with it ever since the hue and cry was first started ; but it's no more use than diving for the philosopher's stone in a boiling caldron of patriotism. They might just as well have been hunting for-pshaw, "a needle in a haystack" is no  sort of comparison-for-for-a fanatic's reason a patron's memory, a client's gratitude, an office-seeker's modesty, or any other inconceivable " phe-no-me-na!" Here Crab', speechmaking's your forte; I'm    out of breath, speak my speech! "Certainly, ma'am!   You mean to say that they, that is, those I'm talking about, didn't, to be sure, look for it on stumps, or in the pulpit, the bar, conventions    <pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6379-00000018"/> 34       FAMLY PAPERS AND and such like museums and menageries, not even Uncle Sam's over in Washington there; because, being in the main honest, sensible, 'law-abiding' citizens, they knew, of course, it wasn't to be found in any such unlikely, outlandish, rowdy-like, ridiculous places, though it can't be denied that some of them, editors, teachers and doc- tors for instance, did pry into others nearly as conspic- uous, improper and disreputable; but, as was said be- fore, not the first one of them ever got possession." The Mrs. Delicacys-sweet, gentle, retiring, lady- like, or poor sickly creatures--led off. And if any body could have found it, you'd have thought they might, for they couldn't, or wouldn't, or didn't look for it in any thing so masculine as 'business,' whether able to fee one set of agents for doing it, and another for overseeing them or not ; and any gentlemen of their acquaintance would, you know, ' attend to it with a great deal of pleasure,' if they only had time and didn't happen to forget it ; but what with smoking cigars, 'cussing' and discussing politics, icing brandy-smashers, and trying to raise poles to the height of human folly, they were one and all 'so desperately hurried and worried,' that really i  'they did wish women would quit making such rag- It  babies of themselves, take their own proper sphere and fill it, and not torment them to death with their ever- lasting importunity " "How absurd, just as if it made the slightest differ- ence whether their affairs were attended to now or some time after the day of judgment; but then, poor creatures, I suppose they can't help thinking it does,  sometimes, so it's rather a pity, but what they might."   OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS.       35  Don't be so sarcastic, Mr. Dick, one old quiz like Crab' here is enough for any family!" One too many, perhaps." "Quite likely, but go on, Ap!" "Well, they missed it, you see, and their cousins, the Mrs. Easys, who slipped quietly down from parlor to kitchen, from house to pig-stye, and as fast as real es- tate disappeared put the more personal property in its place, didn't do a bit better; for as soon as it was discover- ed that every individual piece had the kind of flaw called "a mouth," some men thought, and thought pretty loud too, that a woman's legitimate sphere didn't consist in lumbering up the world with rubbish that couldn't even be turned over to the sheriff; or thrown in with other live stock to eke out 'a capital speculation.' Mrs. Hold-her-own, Lookout, and Mind-her-own-busi- ness, agreed with them-wouldn't even look for it in the nest of that old goose, whose custom it was to lay golden eggs, be picked, plucked, starved, and otherwise "done to death," to enable her lord and master to cut a dash and astonish all out-doors-had no faith in their " ins- sion" to enrich the family circle with half a dozen loafers, and as many more walking brandy bottles or milliners' shops, apiece-didn't worship St. Griselda, ad- mire "water lots," paper cities, and other ingenious in- ventions, for enabling keen-sighted fiscal operators to see quite through their own property and their wives' too; nor believe, most religiously, in loving their neighbors a great deal better than themselves! Of course nobody expected them to find it; and every righteous usurer, gambler, or rumseller, unjustly defrauded of his three or    <pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6379-00000019"/> 36       FAMLY PAPERS AND four hundred per cent. ; every disinterested c friend of the family," choused out of some " smashing business" by stupid prejudice against new scrip and absurd love of old parchment; every charitable, public-spirited law-  yer, trustee and guardian, unfortunately interdicted from building hospitals, churches and colleges, at the expense of his client or ward; every ill-used tenant, forced by legal hocus-pocus to balk some "capital fel  low" of a landlord of champagne frolics, oyster suppers,  dice and other condiments of the back saloon, when he could just as well furnish him a trifling advance at a  slight discount of fifty or sixty per cent. as not, was,  you may be sure, utterly and instinctively shocked and disgusted with such insolence, meanness, unnatural sus- picion, revolting selfishness, and most shameless and un-  feminine intervention!     ,  The world had got to a pretty pass,-it had indeed, if all good-fellowship, inventive genius, the interests of  commerce, scientific demonstration, individual and joint-  stock enterprise were to be held in check by silly woman's  caprice! What should she know of banking and tra-  ding and splendid operations, altogether above her ken?  What right had she to go "mixing herself up with men's business" find out that her confidential friend had got her last dollar invested in his own name, and make him refund before they, his sworn chums, choice spirits,  and honorable creditors, could get hold of it? It was A infamous, indeed it was!  If woman hadn't sense  enough to consult her true interest, confine herself to her  own sphere, and see only through man's optics, it was time somebody taught her that it was! They, for their r   OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS.       37 part, didn't see what law was made for, if it couldn't protect men's rights a little better; and long and loud they bewailed their own hard fate, and sobbed "our sufferings is intolerable!"But when one Biddy O'Niver- fail slipped into a vulgar "hell," pounced on her own silver spoons and made off with the dollars "scraped to- gither Jist to pay the rint, buy the wee bit o' coal, and the darlint's shoes," then didn't they use strong lan- guage, Oh, but did'nt they? It took three full hours before they could find a sheet of paper strong enough to hold it, and four "good men and true," sworn to make her a public example and de- fend all henpecked husbandry from such high-handed outrage in future, to carry it and her effigy up to the pillory; but as ill-luck would have it, the "old un" (who is always on hand to help his own, I think) had one of his regular "limbs" articled there, and what did the sneering little imp-knowing he couldn't look inno- cent if he tried--do, the moment he set his eyes on left my bed," but stick his arms akimbo and ask if my uncle" took in lodgers, and when he came to "and board," screw himself up into a most diabolical twist, and hint that she "might have been scrouged out from under the doggery table?"Consequently the "Old boss" (I don't mean the very oldest one), after administering, as was proper, a sharp box on the place where young Impudence's jaw had been, and ascertain- ing that the other culprit wouldn't be like to go security for his (the printer's) fee, concluded that such "low personalities" vere beneath the notice of first class papers like his; though he kindly volunteered to make    <pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC6379-00000020"/> 38       FAMLY PAPERS AND '%/ the piffair a sort of standing, unwritten text for all the grave homilies, reprimands, affectionate appeals, fatherly admonitions and 4' grand palavers" which he and other argus-eyed might from time to time see fit to bestow on the  sex at large, irrespective of rank or class. So in the  long run Biddy got off just as scot-free as any of the balance, and rather amused, if the truth must be told, at the witty little squibs, jests and jibes eliminated. "A very good wit" they all had ; it hurt nobody, but good does sometimes come out of evil; thousands who never   I would have found time to make any exploring expedi- tions themselves, have in consequence been vastly en- lightened as to the precise whereabouts and cosmogUy,;yl of WOMBANS SPHERE. The very sight of a chart or guide-book throws all the Mrs. Mops and Miss Brooms into perfect ecstasies. "The quiet and the shade is wzoman's sphere, (oh, isn't that so nice and refreshing this warm    weather?) the care of her in'nt offspring,  er first and holiest duty!  (That's rather bad, as I haven't any  "young ideas" to shoot, and yours are all grown up and out of the way ; but never mind, I dare say they'll have a gen- eral distribution of bables after a while.) She must re- tire from public life (to be sure we will, and glad of the chance), itsfierce struggles, angry strife, and sordid cares ; its noise an glare are not for her ; (now doesn't that sound so sensible and refined?) it must ever grieve her BEST FRIENDS to see her mingling in the loud- mouthed, hardhanded strife of that unholy arena!" "Dear, dear, how it must worry your poor father and husband, Carrie, for us to sit up all night writing their   OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS.       39 sermons and editorials, when they've overdone them- selves a little, eating and drinking for -the good of hu- manity!" "Well, I must say I am sick and tired playing du- enna to silks and domestics that will form improper, de- grading alliances with the vulgar scum in spite of me, making a 'a perfect figure' of myself, hunting patterns all over town, but never knew before but what brother Charlie and my Edward took it all very patiently, if the collar'only happened to fit. " "And only to think what my dear departed J ohn must have suffered, seeing me go to" market every morn- ing, and how like a saint he always bore it too! If it hadn't have been for asking- him for money now and then, I don't suppose I ever should have found it out. Maggie dear, if ever you get married, always remember, child, to have the zoicker basket brought' up with the patent leathers!" "Why mlother, how you tallf! I don't expect even Boots would have me now, a great shameless, brazen- faced Amazon in public life, that's disgraced herself, performing at that vulgar theatre in A BO Hall! If I had only gone to the Opera now -- but I'm sure, I never meant to scandalize all my BEST FRIENDS." '"And sister Harriet and I never dreamed how it hurt all their feelings, for us to look after the crop and mind the shop; while Mr. Dragonistooth was dispensing mountain dew to his thirsty followers, demonstrating the origin of trade-winds in Bunkum, and the-feasibility of superseding steam and Gulf Stream  by thYU great motive power, and Mr. Drygoods, gone up with Mr. <pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC6379-00000021"/> 40       FAMLY PAPERS AND Tripod and Rev. Dr. Decorum to the Observatory, to help Professor Tirewoman and President Count-the- skirts, take the attitude, latitude, and longitude, of Miss Virgo's drapery." No indade, madam, but of coorse it did; for they takes it so hard to see even the likes of me, trudging through rain and shine, to gather up the bit sewing, or carry home the week's washing, that they always blocks up the way, and crowds us off into the gutter if they possibly can!" "Yes, but that's all over, Kate,-there's to be no more toil, and mud, and dust for us now; no parents are ever more to bring daughters into the world and leave them to shift for themselves ; no father dare to die without first providing them at least one husband and two children apiece; no helpless young mother to be left with herself and family to provide for; no selfish, monopolizing spouse, dream of making his exit before looking up a successor; no stupid, obstinate, domineer- ing, or worthless, unprincipled incumbrance, to force the weaker vessel to breast life's surges alone, or with some ignorant, reckless, gambling, drunken pilot at the helm; no faithless young lover to take himself off and leave his intended to wear the willow; no true-hearted one to wing his flight to a brighter sphere and bequeathe her the cypress! There's to be no more picking and choos- ing, taking one perhaps three or four times, and leaving another without any owner; an old maid or bachelor, is henceforth to be a thing Barnum couldn't find. Strict embargoes are everywhere to be enforced, and no wicked traitor to manifest destiny, presume to abduct himself i                 .            O I   OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS       41 from his present abiding place so long as a single unap- propriated, marriageable female remains. Uncle Sam is to make it his special duty to keep p a corps de reserve, to supply all accidental losses and deficiencies preserve the balance of numbers between is nephews and nieces, and see that no careless, inefficient or im provident wife lacks her full quota of 'little angels;' no disconsolate widow, pining, unafilanced or con tuma. ious, man-contemning ' old forlornity' stands 'all the day idle,' or shirks out under any pretext 'hatever from woman's uniform  uneceptional  ission. In short, there's nothing more for us to do, but expand our i own graces in the serene atmosphere of domestic life smile on our husbands, and nurse infant seraphs with folded wings, until they get highl enough to draw maps of Woman's Sphere, on pulpit cushions and three-legged stools, and sketch designs for that monumen we are going to build to the inventors of the same." Well, and thin, bless their dear souls, it won't be Kathleen O'Do-or-die that'll be withholding this con- thribution to that same;" but just at this identical oment ther  e came a sound "so full of woe," that every one knew instinctively it must be the summons from some ill-boding old raven, or ominous "Scrich owl  pretty birds of wisdom they are), which having elected iself Purveyor-eneral to the wants, moral social, con- ?8 o tal, and intellectual, of 3essi  o cialr co.- jlgal, and iof Messieurs Backwoods and Risinb.-generati. .  long before young Backwoods and what theneration knew any thing where they were or "they wanted, now called for a draft of 'Twenty Thousand, educationisis, immediately; and intimated    <pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6379-00000022"/> 42       FAMLY PAPERS AND pretty clearly that "FIFTY must be had," and the con- script renewed " every three years." Mothers wept, daughters fainted, and even ancient spinsters folded their hands in blank despair! A few gallant spirits, however, with that calm steady light in the eye, that you would follow any where, to the van of a forlorn hope, flung themselves into the breach, declar- ing they would die at their posts sooner than be dragged one inch from WOMAN'S SPHERE.  A few more loyal subjects rallied at length, and memorialized the CONSER- VATORS; setting forth the extreme hardships of the case, the imperious tone, and despotic nature of the Ukase, and imploring them " to raise the siege and put their disciples in immediate and inalienable enjoyment of their own loved ideal!" A majority seemed to think some sort of transmigration or pilgrimage still inter- vened; but Mrs. Masterly-Inactivity sat quietly down, vowing " that if they chose to bring it round, it was all very well, but for her part, she shouldn't budge a soli- tary foot," and Mrs. Speak-her-mind, gave it as her opinion, "that it wasn't to be found this side Mahomet's Paradise, unless it lay in doing every thing that each and every individual man in the whole 5rsal world, didn't care about doing himself!" There was nothing left for it then, but to send a full delegation of the most illustrious Discoverers, Topog- raphers, Censors, Legislators, and accomplished Man- Milliners, to wait on the Houris, and demand immediate possession; and in case they declined yielding the in- cumbency of WOMAN'S SPHERE, to do the next best thing-secure such a full and particular description,   ;H         OOFFICIAL DOCUMENTS.        4 43 portrait and pattern of the same, as should be perfectly adaptable to all persons, places, times, and emel encesg. -not omitting, in mean time, to deploy a sufficient force from their own supernumeraries, to cover all vul- r nerable points, from thie daring and insidious attacks of those seditious amphibiae (c neither fish, flesh, fowl, nor good red herrminge"), bent on slipping themselves into half-and-halfls, fbrthe etrovn       eit if foiled in their nefarious attempts to level boundaries. But why didn't the strOngrninded in hats and 'tights' cespatch them  at one  had' they  paper bullets' enough?"per Humph! i why yes--no.-Te    ct is, the mis- chievous monkejys were so unprecedenedtly thick-skulled they wouldn't &amp;lnow when they were killed! What would you advise, Mi. Dick, in such premises W  t "Have they committed any overt acts of hostility recently?" , ' Oh yes, any amount of 'high falutin,' fillibuster a'ys 'p/tyJfoUr-ptowrtyi sm,' and one of the Argus-eyes says: 'Strongminded woman is putting herself through a course of political ethics' (must have good eye to find them), 'medical lectures, and newspaper essays '" i "oh, she$ is              '* Oh, she is, is she? Well then, let them mind their own business, talk less nonsense, set better exam- ples, pass better laws, make better prescriptions write ? bette articles and  , dvebetter customs, and she'd have lessoccsion. That's my opinion!" "Blessyou, Mr. Dick, your common sense is ad- BETSEy TROTWOOD, Censor, f .Per CRAETn A, O14.t' 18t       ,.    <pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6379-00000023"/> "       FAMLY PAPERS AND CHARLESTON.  I may not look upon thy quaint and gallant face, But rightly art thou named, fair ey of the Sun; First CHARLES in virtue, Secon in thy grace, Iight regal is thy tone, and princely is thy ton. "A SUPERN UMERAIRE. MEMORIAL To the ffonorable the Senate and House of Representatives of the United States, in Thirty-Third Congress assemnled. "EGISLATORS:- The undersigned, your memorialists, respectfully represent, that the Magnetic Telegraph having become a special Humbug, and the Post-Office Department a most especial nuisance, public weal now requires that the same be instantly and utterly abolished, from and after such day and date as private enterprise and inge- nuity shall have devised ways and means for transmit- ting letters and other papers in a trifle lesstime, thanit stakes foot passengers to make the trip in proper person; --and, in the mean time, that the Executive be request- ed to issue Proclamation, so peremptorily and effectually restraining the great excess of animal speed, that no traveller shall hereafter presume to deliver himself, more than a whole month earlier than a public functionary can, letters andQ-ther missives started on the same day    and date for and from the same place and point; and also comprising stringent enactments, exacting transmis- sion of thirty-three and a third per cent. of all despatches paid for in advance, and securing to individual and com- mercial interests, a pro rata of ten per cent. to every ninety per cent. allowed to Bunkum, and your Memorial- ists will ever pray. BETSEY TROTWOOD, Censor. CRABTREE AP CRAB, 1st Lictor. "AWRENCE MELVILLE, Sec.  "ADY LACKLAND, Siupernumeraire. CLEVER AUTHORESS. CLEVER the mischief! What do you mean, you double-faced satyr, by this blowing hot and cold in the very same breath? And what has my niece, Lady Lackland done, I should like to know, that she should is be stigmatized " authoress?" She doesn't go unwashed and unkempt, her belong- ings are no dirtier than other folks, nobody ever saw "Life greasy nightcaps deck her head," what business have you, then, to "soft-soap" her this way? She don't patter about slipshod, clatter about in hat and boots, nor lounge about in fantastic, tatterdemalion, woe-be-gone old wrapper from morning till night-never takes a pen for a soup-ladle, makes chocolate in a coal- cuttle, salts tea out of an inkstand, cuts muttonchops with a pearl folder, flutes ruffles on a gridiron, or mis-    <pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC6379-00000024"/> "       FAMLY PAPERS AND takes, by any possible chance, your best sock (instead of vest) for a pudding-bag-can tell apple dumplings from n sourkrout, dutch cheese from cabbage heads, raw, and other greens in unsophisticated state-never needs  Spanish flies for inky fingers, or has to hunt all day and Mn borrow a broom to-morrow, "to sweep the cobwebs from 7 the sky,"-knows a thimble by sight, darning-needle  K by personal lacquaintance-has more "premeditated c: poverty" than "accidents of the day" about the heels i of her stockings-keeps her "little Jellybys" no worse  off than their neighbors, her marital's buttons and  strings in good condition as most conjugals-his satrap-o ship never grumbles (more than becomes a philosopher) about the dust on his coat, and the mud in his cofiee, nor vows-oftener than is needful for the preservation of " discipline,"--that his shirt collars " never do fit," ; and that's more than your wife can say of you and yours;  and now, what right have you, you corduroy simpleton- ess, to infamize her, one of President Pierce's subjects  and my officials, with such an epithet as " authoress?" It's libellous I know, it's actionable I believe, and  if ever I find a gentleman " as is a gentleman," that ever slept with a law book under his head, and isn't besotted past compos, lest some high-stepping she-male should toddle into those platid absurdities of that in- tensely Statesprison-looking toggery of his, I'll have you  prosecuted for defamation. "Authoress," you ninnified quintessimal of all ancient sillyism, it's a reflection on your respectable parentess, and it's a wonder she don't see you are out, and be after you with a gong-ette! Ah, here she comes   zV X .*A DJu U. jUMaENTS.   47 -"Oh Jamie, Jarnie, bairn, weel a day that 'er ye should think to gang out by yer lone self, when ye ken wed enough, ye born natul al, that it's oure and often I've tellt ye, ye had na the gumption to last over night t Come haim, Jamie."  Yes, you'd better, or you'll be apt to get Lictor- ized. BETSEY TROTWOOD, Censor.   f NUMBER ONE AND NUMBER TWO. FIRST-CLASS HOTELS. NUMBER ONE neat, comfortable conveyance from steamboat and depot, free gratis. NUMBER Two, fare ex- tra (and discretionary with your surly captor), in a fbrlorn dirty old omnibus, that tells you the moment you are seated, and have time to look 'round, how completely you were 'sold" by that dealer in irony, who Mserted Number Two, to be "one of the first hotels in the country." Number One, handsome reception-room, where you can sit or recline at your ease, till the presiding genius comprehends intuitively where you and your belongings can be bestowed most entirely to your own satisfaction. Number Two, sit in the public gangway, or stand and hold up the banisters till somebody comes and shuffles you off into the first vacant space. Number One, ROOMS airy, good-sized, faultlessly clean, and not en- tirely cut off from all communication with the out-door    <pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC6379-00000025"/> 48       FAMLY PAPERS AND world; Number Two, not very diminutive, but rather calculated to show off your accomplishments in the art of packing baggage in the smallest possible compass,  and commanding a charming surveillance of the sayings and doings, gymnastics and callo-thumpion rehearsals! of the whole kitchen menage.  X Number One, CHAIRS, half dozen, rosewood and ma- ;: hogany, spring-seat and cane-bottom; Number Two,  one Windsor, two cane-bottom, all very common. Num-  ber One, CARPET good, good of its kind, and in good  preservation-not the slightest occasion for a score of t Secession and Woman's Right newspapers to interdict  an unholy alliance offensive and retentive between it  and the soles of your shoes. Number Two, medium Scotch, judging from remoter parts, the more contiguous being so patriotically attached to the soil of their coun- try, that, like other patriots, their precise stripe and  color is a little dubious. Mem. Fine thing, my Aunt Betsey's lost her specs, and off to the rescue of Mr. Dick, who was entrapped, poor man, while lying in a collapse after his great effort in the long closing speech on the Woman's Right ques- tion, and forcibly inducted, SHE THNKS, into the chair of Befoggery in the Transmundane, Cosmopolite, Hybrid- ity Institute, by some sur loi, sub terre, kidnapping, manifestation kelpies; though, my own opinion is, that he's been regularly burked, for not finding the NEW- LIGHT rapped out of empty heads, tilting chairs, and tipping tables ;-but don't we know somebody else, this side California, that would be, apt to say, "wash" it, or send it on a short pleasure-trip at the stern o a   I   ^    OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS.       49 steamer, and see it come back, much reduced in specific gravity, but more improved in elasticity and general sa- lubrity? Well, I reckon!  Number One, FIREPLAe   larble, closed (supposing it to be summer), with highly polished fancy network, cast-iron grating, showing a background of spotless white; Number Two, hearth-brick painted red, fire- place plastered and whitewashed very fairly, and fur- nished with two green-footed andirons, supposed to be brass, and a pair, done up one in white, the other in newspaper. Mem. Convenient place to sweep other papers, and all sorts of trash-saves labor! Number One, MOSQUITO-BARS, best lace, exquisitely white, tent style, suspended per centre, its graceful folds spread out at night without any hint of yours, and thrown back by day overhead of low French lounge bed- stead, where you can get on anid off just as easy as not. Number Two, scrapped and patched, cross-barred, and lace, very yellow fixtures (unless you understand "the hang" of the things, and can get them down yourself), over apparently new, but very suspiciously worm-eaten "testers" and regular turned post, high old-fashioned bedstead. If young, hale and active, you can take a flying leap, and light somewhere near the middle; if not, just shove a trunk or two alongside, and you'll climb up after a while, may be. Number One, CouNTERPANE, finest Marseilles, changed once a week, if you stay so long; sheets and pillow- slips twice ditto, and oftener, if a drop of tea, or speck of any kind, happens to bedim their spotless sheen. Mattress, new and fresh, double-spring, and very best 3    <pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC6379-00000026"/> 50       FAMLY PAPERS AND quality, that nothing but a guilty conscience could pos- sibly make lie hard, if you should try by any fair means twenty-three hours out of twenty-four; and all made to fit the bedstead and each other so exactly, you can't get them out of sorts and " all up in a mess," do what you will. Oh, you may haul and pull, and twist and screw, and turn and tumble, it's no use, there they are. Num- ber Two, old dimity " cover" basted, darned, dirty and dingy; sheets, &amp;c., common cotton, the same dark- colored white, only "a little more so;" setting you right off, if the least bit metaphysical, speculating on the probable prices of soap and water, and how many one dozen ironings are equivalent to any one washing, in that " first-class" establishment. Bed, about as elastic as the " soft side of a plank ;" but if wise, and not feel- ing about as amiable as a porcupine at bay, you won't carry your investigations into other people's domestic concerns much further; indeed, there's no occasion to look. Pillows, twenty by nine inches, or thereabouts, but not very peripatetic, considering how much they have already outgrown their cases, their excursions (and those of their adjuncts) being generally bounded by big trunk on one side, and bureau on the other; unless mosquitoes are " very bad," in which case Betty or Bridget will probably find them somewhere about the room, or just out of the window. Number One, CENTRE-TABLE mahogany, with hand- some cover and Bible; wardrobe, side-table, bureau and Sits swashstand rosewood dike bedstead); the latter with marble-tops (Italian), to match hearth and mantel-piece. Furniture of washstand, &amp;c., &amp;c., all complete, double   OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS.       51 sets; wares, china i, fne and white, full complement, made to order, and nothing wanting. Number Two wardrobe and centre-table among the missing; bedstead sycamore; bureau mahogany face, and respectable glass, X t otherwise very ordinary, and much neglected. Wash- g stand and side-table common deal, painted divers colors, g to correspond with every thing, where nothing looks like g any thing else, nor any two like each other. Furniture of washstand, one hard, dark towel per diem, with nearly half a set of common white- and motley delf, minus a top here, bottom there, and handle somewhere else,--looking, for all the world, like trophies won in the grand scramble, after a general smash-up in some old -;a crockery concern. Side-table, rather hors du combat, and shoved back out of the way into a dark corner; but if you want to eat, or write, just help that choice collec- tion to emigrate; put one foot into the soap-stand (there's no cover, nor soap bigger than a wafer, to hurt or hinder), the other into the washbowl, and make yourself comfortable. They are quite clean now, you know, though I'm afraid you don't read your Bible as much as you should, or you'd remember, that "evil communications corrupt good manners," and not suffer that little finger-brush of yours to scrape acquaintance with all the coarse wedgewood and dirty stone-china in the country. Don't tell me there isn't any; haven't you got one of your own, I should like to know? And, be- sides, what right have you to go about compromising the dignity of the toga, by enacting the "old woman," who got so much dirt by sweeping up once a year, that I' V'VrUUUIL    <pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC6379-00000027"/> 52       FAMLY PAPERS AND she wondered "what upon airth people did do with it all when they'cleaned up every day?"  N. B. If the establishments were large, and yielded, in proportion as much dust, dirt, lint and feathers, as I've seen on and under some tables, beds and bureaus  lately (I don't mean yours now, Number Two), I sus-  pect they must have to employ a special train for its transportation ; but that's a mere speculation. Number -Two, wheel round, turn a crank on the wall, and it's just as certain as " manifest destiny," that somebody 'll come up before you've half a chance to for-  get what you wanted, looking so neat and cheerful, po-  lite, and perfectly respectful, that you can't possibly  speak cross, or feel ill-natured, if you want to ever so  much. Number Two, pretty fair cord and tassel, where  you are welcome to exercise your patience and muscles  all day, if you like-though I don't know so well about  that, either, for when Paddy and Sukey can't stand ' that confounded bell" any longer, it's a chance if some greasy, slatternly, blubber-lipped darky, or raw Celt- innocent of Anglo-Saxon as a Shanghai of high Latin- doesn't come up looking shillalahs and vinegar-cruets at- you, as much as to say, I'll tache ye better manners, sir, nor to be ringing me up any more, disthurbing the swatest nap, or the natest reel in the world ;" and I reckon you won't, if you can help it. - But a word to you, Number One. People like to look at pretty pic- tures, you know, and how do you know but they some- times ring oftener than they would, if you didn't keep some uncommonly good-looking ones about? Verbum   ........... Ju  sap-Number Two, you see, understands this matter rather better. Number One FARE} every luxury that sea and land, capital and skill, can command; got up in every con- ceivable style but a bad or indifferent one, as if to prove that it's not high living, but gormandizing,--not rich cooking, but bad cooking, that makes people sick. For desserts, the whole science of pastry and confectionery illustrated. Prelude, fresh bills of fare three times a day; accompaniment, music to aid digestion. Numbeir Two, half-boiled edibles for the vegetarian, raw enough to cook, and come again; huge masses of fish, flesh and fowl for the carnivorous, with lobsters, shrimps (and, for aught I know, toads, frogs, snails, centipedes, and other fresh-water reptiles) yesterday, to-day, and to-morrow by way of variety. Dessert, sugar and lard-lard, su- gar, and rice, slightly disguised with flour, and other va- riations. Music (about six hours every day), knife-and- fork prelude, plate-rattle chorus and gong interlude; and tin-pans and callothumpions hide your diminished heads, you can't shine again after that gong! Bill of Fare (once a day if you insist), a regular veteran in small type epaulettes, and gmost magnificent pen-flour- ishing ",contiuations," that mean exactly what they don't say; so if you fancy Irish potatoes, invaluable in a state of siege, where lead and bullets are exhausted, just mark  green peas," or ' corn "-underscore " broiled chicken, and you'll probably get a huge chunk of black- looking meat, swimming in a whole plate-no, saucer, full of beef, or mutton tallow, but not so much as a little finger-napkin to bless yourself withal.    <pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC6379-00000028"/> 54       FAMLY PAPERS AND Comparisons may be "odorous," as Mrs. Malaprop says, and somewhat lengthy too, but it takes a first-rate artist to bring a "full length" before every mind's eye with one or two pen-and-ink dashes; so you see, Number Two, that if I hadn't gone into " specialty- pleas" like, you'd have lost all the beauty of contrast, and never known for certain whether it was yourself, or somebody else, that had the honor of sitting. And now, to show that I'm not playing censor, and putting on. airs, like other subs, because my'superior's out of the way; and have, after all, just as much " sneaking kind- ness" for you left, as could reasonably be expected from one of that flayed-alive, and barbecued set of mortals, called travellers,-I'm going, with a laudable zeal for your improvement, to put you in a way of seeing what's what, with your own eyes.  Just make up a wallet-I paid you enough for no value received, the fractions being about right, the units all extra, to help along considerable-then take up a line of march " straight for California;" but don't go as ifshot out of a catapult, that isn't the way to learn any thng, and sea water is, I take it, about as salt one side of e Isthmus as the other; and some people along the coastfancy that " some things can be done as well as others." You'll'find several nice settlements, or places where nice settlements 5ught to be; one, in particular, promises to be a right .smart little village, when Lake Erie gets turned upside down into the Gulf of Mexico: but if you don't find Number One there, just go on till you do-when you come to the right place, any body can tell you which it is.   v - J' lVlaliA JUkU U JIYMUIN '1. i .  Should the unaccustomed quiet and apparent leisure get rather alarming, and you begin to feel some misgiv- ings about remaining any longer in that enchanted castle, where every thing must be done by magic, or some invisible troops of fairies, it's all done so quick, noiselessly, and well, go right off to head magician, and make " a clean breast" of it. Having nothing in the world to fear from your rivalry, he won't mind enlight- ening you, till you can forget more in the next half hour than you ever knew before in all your life; or taking you round to see what sort of fairies' he does operate with. When you have digested all that, just "possum it" a day or two-no, that won't be necessary either- just think of going back to Number Two, and if that doesn't lay you up for a good week, you are a man of some nerve-that's all! And, then, won't 'that attend- ant, who knows exactly what you want quite as well, if not a little better, than you do yourself, bring you every thing you ask for, and some others, which he thinks you ought to want, and would want, if you could only see them instead of the bill? Of course he will; and that elegant tea and-dinner-service, with its superior cutlery, plate, china, and English glass, doesn't it look refresh- ing? Certainly; and those fine waiters, too-too fine not to be covered afresh three times a day with the finest and glossiest of damask; and those peerless napkins, looking so like incarnate light, or woven snow-wreaths- stop! you don't presume to think of laying your unholy, earth-worm fingers on that visible purity, without first breathing a sigh for some similar lustration to reach your own sin-soiled, wor-worn spirit! If you do, you are a    <pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC6379-00000029"/> sinner "past praying for,"/' I fear; but 'Number One doesn't know that, and won't he call up to see you-see if you will have a physician, or any thing else ; send up his compliments to know how you are, with books and papers to amuse you--the paragraphs all marked that he thinks will specially interest you-and bring up agreeable company to entertain you ? To be sure he will-no kind of doubt of it; ask if there is any thing else he can do for you--do it, too; collect information, and let you know when it is done, without waiting for you to inquire; give you his advice (and it's a better article than you get every day free gratis) ; and all this time do you ever catch him look- ing icebergs, thunderbolts, and percussion-caps, till you expect every moment to hear, " Confound your impu- dence !" (or some other wicked words,) " do you suppose I've got nothing else to do, but look after you and your affairs ?"  No, you don't-you would really suppose he thought it was his business how his guests enjoyed themselves-his special pleasure to supply your want of tact and judgment; and a pretty heavy surplus capital he must have to make up for some people's deficiencies, as I happen to know ! Well, you feel better, now, don't you ? Yes, I see you do ; and when you see how much one kindly heart and master-spirit can perform, you feel very much like breaking every glass that reflects a flurried, petulant, im- patient face, giving Paddy a clean shirt, Sukey and Sambo at least one pound of soap and a bucket of wa- ter apiece, and starting all those coarse, odd, black- looking old saucers, that you use for plates, with that    common, dirty-handled broken-tined cutlery, and the rest of that "tag-rag and bobtail" dining and bedroom furniture (that in the parlor will do a while longer if you'll only have the piano tuned), off to some beggars' jauction--of course you do, and won't forget those young alf-breed, Japan and sheet-iron waiters either  Then ere's that a.eT ere's that antique gem of the kind, the one you know that-ahem, it's an ugly word, and as you are going to reform-you mean to, don't you ?--why I won't say it though how you ever did get off scot  r e with such a treasure, I'm sure I  can't divine; but you'll send it right back to the plain of Shinar, won't you ? The one I mean that was made out of Mrs. Noah's two old worn-out dustpans, spliced togetherin the middle. And not a bad idea that of the maker, nicking off the four orners to give it somewhat of an octagonal air, though tits a pity his "sodder" all "give out," so that he had to leave them   all standing "every which way fbr Sun- day," it gives it such a  reckless, " torn-down " appear- ance; or if you don't like to "acknowledge the corn% " and think Mr. Layard won't    care, just hand it  over to me, and I'll do my best to get it to the World's Fair.. spite of all the Barnums in  existence. But don't let P. G. have it, whatever you do, for he'd be certain to label it '  Master Tubal-Cain's first specimen, made out of is. Eve's camp-kettle (though we all know it's a much more modern  affair), put it   il a I lase and give it an alligator, cobra, rattlesnake, and boa con- strictor, for a  guard of honor to  keep it safe out of reach of all the antiquaries in the  world; and you know I  go against hum  bugging the public, and do n't even approve 3      <pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC6379-00000030"/> of your calling yours " a first class hotel," when (" faith of honest man") I did'nt see any thing "first class" there, unless it was the PRICEs-and they were about up to the very tallest-and that magnificent old cock- roach, and really I shouldn't wonder if he was Grand Patriarch of the whole tribe! ' STEAMBOATS anit sea-sarpints," why, what's the matter now? I'm sure I haven't said ani thing par- ticular-not even told what a city with a beautiful name you live in! Don't flare up so, man o' live, you might  pitch into a collapse or on to a snag ; and, besides, what sort of behavior is this, when I'm talking to you in such a fatherly kind of way? Don't you know " it hurts me a great deal worse than it does you, and it's allfor your own good, and you'll thank mefor it some day," as Mrs. Doctor Birch used to tell her hopeful progeny, when taking them through a course of the tallest kind of sprouts; and for which good service not the first one of the ungrateful little wretches ever has thanked her to this day, that ever I could learn? But don't you imitate their naughty example, for if you don't go right home and strike your colors down to  R half-mast, or run up your accommodations to high-     io water mark about the quickest, all the world will know  th you have a great deal more impudence and less ignorance  w] than I give you credit for! CRABTREE AP CRAB', Ist Lictor.     Sh   FAMILY PAPERS AND   OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS.             59 PROMISING PATRON. SAYS Maecenas the little, I'm very profound, Though to shallow-pate Euclid I do condescend, But with. foot in the clouds, caivut vast on the ground, This sublimity mnia, need never unbend  !  As PATRON I'll call and subscribe though--provided Stultissmrna femince will Aave the said call-- Not now, but some day when the thing is decided Past doubt-ten dimes isn't mucd, but my heart is so small ! LADY LACKLAND, 2d Lictor. LAY SERMON TO PRIEST -AND PRELATE. BY LADY LACKLAND, SECOND LICTOR. lI was sick, and ye visited me."-MATT. xsv. 86. HAS' your Reverence the Doctor or Pastor, your Right Reverence the Bishop, done this ; or has he, in the opin- ion of the impartial, sullied the purity of his lawn with the stain of worldliness, by acting to the grief of those whom God hath wounded ?" Should a Christian  man return evil for good? Should a gentleman insult, either by neglect 'or overt indignity, a  lady, and his equal ?-one never accus- tomed, from birth, education, or life-long association, to weigh the dictate of conscience in the balance of  expe- diency; and, consequently, little qualified-despite some  <pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC6379-00000031"/> 60       FAMLY PAPERS AND. reverses that would have crushed a- parvenu spirit back to its plebeian level-to tolerate moral cowardice in posi- tions which might (if they do not) enable the incum- bent to act promptly and rightly, without first consult- ing a rent-roll or barometer of caste. Should a man of the world, knowing the world's maxim, nemo me impune lacessit, and himself, evi- dently, "a man of like weakness and passions with others," venture, while adopting, unconsciously per- haps, her brief clerical portrait, and accepting her gift, to turn round and smite the giver too rudely on the one cheek, in the presumptuous hope that she alone of all the world would, by the grace of God, evince "that meek and quiet spirit which turns the other also?" Should a humane man-aware that though "the spirit of a man may sustain his infirmity, yet a wounded spirit who can bear?"-do this, when the naturally keen susceptibilities of the woman had become morbidly sensitive by severe and long protracted mental and' physical torture? Should a prudent man, a mere denizen of earth, "earthy," and no Ithuriel seated on a sunbeam, hold himself more scathless from a wo- man's pen, than did Napoleon in his hour of prime? Should a politic, worldly-wise man, even, so wantonly dissipate that "odor of superior sanctity,'" that prestige of an unction from on high, on which his social as well as sacerdotal supremacy, so preeminently rests? Above all, should the disciple esteem himself so much "wiser than his Master, or greater than his Lord," that he can venture to offend his " little ones," that he can contemn the plain ritual of his instructions, pro-   OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS.       61 " claiming what is that religion "which is pure and nde filed before God and the Father "-that he can dare to say, I wil not, when the Great Shepherd says," FED MY SHEEP?"  And, finally, is it meet that "le, by whose stripes we are healed," should be again stricken and wounded in the house of his friends-that o 6E whose kingdom "is not of this world," should be thus publicly mocked an insulted by his own "Ambassadors flaunting the livery of "the god of this world" in his face, vaunting his maxims and outstripping his own votaries in the race, till the profane world itself is shocked, and turns round to inquire, not "what do ye more," but "why do ye WORSE than others?" CHARITY. Latest style and most orthodox pattern for pious .Aifs. Plutus to read a New Publication thirogh, decline the purchase, and in- suit the author with the offer, of "DONATIONS! A HORSEXAN comes with boot and spur, My lord returns him thanks with speed: "And wherefore so, most noble sir?" "Because you did not bring your steed i" A reason good, why I should thank This opera-going a-per i She read, tis true, but to be frank, She did not steal--the type and paper   ! LADY LACKLAND, 2d Lictor.    <pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC6379-00000032"/> 2     FAMLY PAPERS AND  o2                 - P. S. "How honest grows the city queen, (So Crab', a saucy South, maintains) Bodies she used to take, I ween, But now she only takes the brains!" NEW  BROOM.. SUCH c dus t! Needn't think to throw it in my eyes though; don't put her glamour on me, I'll promise, if she has got " the evil eye!" iy poor aunt BETbEY i ifh woul has e hought ith?  wI on't believe it any how!--No, there never was any room unde  r that old beaver for "a bee in the bonnet,"-she' bewiched her, that's certain     t-ow shoul you  I see you don't believe it-how should you? Youm- lAv   caught her aiyou-7er w     he, never   haven't caught her agai-her with Uncle Sam's cor- mission in her pocet,and        incumbetter or wiser he ever ade, for never were such another ffice an incubent so exactly fitted to each other, going about to disgrace herself and me, by onsorting with--you on't knowhow it hurts me to expose my venerated reltive but the truth must come--with a poetizer  Oh, you may shake your head, but it's no use; I'd wag mine all day if it would do any good, or drive off this new wif of hers, the impuent mix, to set plain, straightforward words all a crbin-cruikshnkin de- cent 1English into cloggerel--and then bring me in, "art and part," to such atrocities i May rhyming seize me, if I don't believe it was this very harp-y herself me,^^^   OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS.        63 that set the brother ghouls, elves, and jackals, on the trail of poor lost Mr. Dick, and " between you and me and the gate post," haven't a doubt she made way with my respected aunt's excellent old specs, lest she should put a stop-to her own infamous proceedings! Now, not a purse-proud old dotard can presume to make a fool of himself, but he's down in a proclamation, and up in a pillory-not a supercilious editor ignore the difference between not being prepared and "not being called upon," not a son of a decimal refuse a lady a trivial act of common civility, and keep her waiting in the hot sun "bothering" about a few fractions of percentage till she faints outright,-not a " lord spirit- ual" or a "lord temporal," nor even a fancied aiob (and  pitiful snob), the veriest scum thrown up by the seeth- ing elements of society, can neglect the amenities or outrage the humanities; but she's down upon him with a sermon or squib, just as if our respectable firm was nothing more than a regular varse factory, where they turned out poetry to order! And such po-e-try, ye gods, only listen I "A new-fledged author does her utmost to be civil, (Most people worship still the Spirit of all EviD, Yet you're 'not called upon to praise or blame,' you say I And were you to be rude, sir chivalry, I pray?" There's Scripture measure for you, and again- "'A rose by any other name would smell as sweet'- It might, if one could trust his own especial nose; But Shakspeare, dear, that does not prove it right or meet, To call each dry, old, crabbed stick, by name of RosE!" L          #    <pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC6379-00000033"/> "       FAMLY PAPERS AND No more it don't, and how edifying that must be to all innate intelligences who " don't care to read any more" (and never did read any before), though I've  known people that liked to hear something new occa- sionally; but isn't this rich? "'My Lady Lackland 's gong deranged, they say! ' A quiz, you may be sure, what proof, I pray? 'Too much, alas! the case is very plain-  She thought to find a gentlemnan in WAYNE!' " "Rich," of course it is; but you see she's got no more conscience than a corporation dittle enough, for that matter, to set up half a dozen of them; it's my be- lief), so if a word happens to suit rhyme, or measure, down it goes ; and if it chances to mystify the reader, so much the better, for she's taken up an absurd crotchet, that facts belong to the public, names to the owners, asm if the first mother's son could ever relish the most ill- natured epigram ever seen, if it didn't take off his own particular; so you'll have to find out by your learning whose particular withers are wrung, or whether "Ken- tucky " means, Khamschadtka or Kham-Tartary in this PROCLAMATION EXTRAORDINARY. '"Ho!" fair sister States, Kentucky sends greeting, And fopling of fifty or sixty, with care; He "lives upon Love," (and other good eating, For the boy-god himself couldn't dine upon air); But the urchin slipped off, a bride was his aim, And he didn't count less than three strings to his bow, To "half court" each lass, "' then choose " was the game, And he's out-but, sonny, your mother does know!   OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS.         6 And fair-play's a jewel, so lest some mistake Cause belleood to fll by the shaft of your bo I've ordered a lirnner some charcoal to take, And sketch7, my flne lark, your full portrait below. Full length of one who guzzled, whi abusing good honest milk as "  chalk, gugar and water," and boasted that he could marry any girl in Kentucky. An ancient Adonis, and sleek-looking calf, Needs chalk, &amp;c., just to relish his tea: Hle's able to buy, but too stingy by half, So--- a penny, please sir, pray give it to me!" Ye kind-hearted landlords, just grant him his prayer, But don't board him a day unless he'll agree To pay without grumbling at least double fare, For you'll have to fork over good rations for three. The belles of Kentuck all worship this star, Though he dyes hisgray hair, as most ev'ry one knows; Yet still he consents to wed " on the squar' " So look to your blinds, there he eavesdropping goes. Such charms must attract; so he writes himself down, And dreams of a wife, not that beauty should dare To think and to say that this ", man about town" as ears very long, and heart of hardware. -Done at ahe oi stam Done at the oZd stamping-ground, under our hand and seal. IENTIUOKIANA. After that  state secretarysi   no co mmon mortal ould have comproised dignity by ever looking at any hing short of a president, nabob, or governor at the ary lowest; but listen : "A Yankee So-so and STUFFEDrOG of dimensions (Both de you may know in 'high life below stairs,')    <pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC6379-00000034"/> "      -FAMLY PAPERS AND Talk loud of their 'big men,' with knowing pretensions, And look, like two little ones-putting on airs "! She's clearly not "canny,' and what does she next but get  DEATH AND DECIMAL IN A QUANDARY. "'I'm puzzled,' says Death, what to do with his soul, Or the Gripe-all's career had long since been run;' Why the petrified heart might fatten a ghoul, And for soul-bless your life he never had one! "But his dimes, oh, his dimes! how shall I contrive, For the son of a gnome won't budge fromlis ore?' Place a mint over Styx and in he will dive, Charge Charon a fee, and win a fip more! ' "The plan's very good, but frien Plutus maintains That he never-will trust that ortal alive- With nothing but brass in the locale of brains- Who with gods and with men such bargains would drive!" " "Of Queen City, then, let Sir Saveall beware, ' Or she'll use him up quite-bones, bristles, and all, For he's very well ' smoked' (though tough), and with care His parchment will serve-any purpose that's small." Oh, a very vigilant and impartial officer is she, 'past a doubt, nothing too high for her impudence or low for her notice ; but I'm not going to be gibbeted in rhyme, or hung in hexameters or Hexhamheaths, whichever it is, because I don't know father from son! And if she wants introduction to one Captain Scalplock, just let her offer to string "long-winded" into metre, or come  scouting about down in '. the nation" here, whe{ I'm studying the art of slow torture under the illustrious old co,   OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS  sache ePIYESPLINTgESle" ti the benefit of insolent old gaberlunjies, eSinglly  atling out BREVIT, with their mouths all full of supererogaw tion, as if/heir readers would ever know the thing by sight, or the fee-simple of all palaver beloned t thngem; and other people were bound to talk out of their dic- ionaries, and had never a grammar of their own, or any right to put wit in fie columns because the can stupidity in six             ey can put If so very anxious to see the myth, why don't they look into the 9retort where some feolfor-hispains distils their atoms of idea from infinky of v i? -paiDo tlsey expect a candidate for the first honors of bush-figl to march up one line of "ordinary'" and down another enfilade a whole chevaux-de-fise of critics, nd brino against a blank wall of incomPrelensi ility ;  ouldn't dod,3 the  a ca of mpreiensibility. just as if he couldn't dodg  e thn,        scatr  dodge o theoaell as encyclopcedias, turn their fianks, spike their guns, rifle their storesvd scatter 'eir munitlons of war, whenever he choose? dIf t  , do, they've . issedothats all I CRABTREE AP CRAB', 1t Lictor.  no sort of use, for If never do read!" ite likey, Sir Coattail,: of genus called flish ; "The race of men is almos extinc  tails walking behind a moutae the ma orifr    <pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC6379-00000035"/> 68       FAMLY PAPERS AND But then your sweet self is the subject I need, To witness how well I can lay on the lash :  So bide a wee now, and I'll presently show  How great were the use in your situation; For books, it is proved, as all men should know, Are "elements" good of CIV-IL-I-ZA-TION " "ADY LACKLAND, 2d Lictor. CAP FOR HEADS THAT FIT.  "SPONTANEOUS PRODUCTIONS," says Cheatem to Niel, "Men may take for their need, as onward they pass " ' Thin, holy St. Patrick, this country, I feel, Has PLANTS rather rare of that very same class, That grow without culture in wild-field and wood-- Since books and umbrellas 'tis no harm to steal, They come up, in coorse, for the commonwealth's good!" LADY LACKLAND, 2d Lictor. PUFFS AND PUFFERS.             BLANK, BLANK.                    1( HAVING examined this work a la critic, that is, felt S of the paper, looked at the type, title-page, finale and b  binding, our opinion is, that another of the "green 'uns"  has given us a book, which any one may purchase that as likes, though we don't choose to read.       8 q Xl   OFFICIAL DOCUMEN1T  ow thiat's very like what I call swindling Do you know, sir, that that very  book cost the author cash, if not brains? And what rig  osh ha e you Scissor Snip pings, Esq., more than any other m ,  cisso r opria the same without some sort   ma    to apro so of the quivalent, p riate the poor wretch went bootlaent? Are you se the poohur reto bent botless and napless, if not old and hungry, to bed, in order to pay you that tri- bute? Who told you the lady wasn'y peer of the Poudes that her wedd-      wast Peer of the poettha  t her wedding ring gilt the offering to your hand? U You might have been hoaxed I Suppose now you haadn't, after all, such an un te rig  the homage, Without giving so much even as a nod of receipt irn return? Just imagine, my lord premier or lady patroness, naming you to brilliant beauty as 3Lr. the auccomllished gull, who silently accepts the charity of author's rains, or tells a tantalized public they lie on iis table, delighted heiress rei    they ke very well they did'nt lien the c rown of h is hat "-onlye think of itl!      crots  of his fat l! And you, too, you irreclaimable Softwill ever rebel? How long mst you be trod like the Torm before you can turned p o  b  e trod likef tho Upon Power?  "How long ill you hell Humbug of Tripod shovel clods on your vn cflin? How long will you Plunge in his Balaam oround, whence no light flashes up from the fathom. s duncedepths? There's enough of you, in all con- ence; if you'd only stand up for your rightsy refuse to hung befbrc you are tried, and buried before you are you might get justice and queid bero uo, as well other folks. You BRAVs Sq  s  te you, as te ll    <pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC6379-00000036"/> 70        FAMLY PAPERS AND Here, Lady Lack', come smoke me the moths that t' ,' - put out the fibres of these delicate, spiritual, spiritless little gossamer wings.  Crab', the haughty old svage, vows he won't hunt any such pitiful pests. "Old Tomahawk's right, better blood he should draw, The meanness of theirs would infect the north star; The game in this chase is beneath an old squaw, Toad, magpie or crawfish weie nobler by far!  'Tis an insect of Tripods Humboldt wouldn't class, So authors come on, this task must be ours; The defaulter's there, right in front of the glass, With 'line' and fair promise-his critique, ye powers, No man ever saw, though the swindler don't fail To boast and to hide all his quiddam honore- (If 'tis honor and wit, don't grudge the 'black mail,' For man, I am sure, never needed it more.) No diamond of genius can Tinseltop prize, Gilt and vellum he'll have, whatever befall; The helpless and poor UTppertenny espies, And sponges with pleasure a largtpe'from all ... A " i: But one Conscientious, well knowing no bays Could survive, in the germ, his flattering line, Don't sully its leaf with the breath of his praise, That siine of the worm on the statue so fine! 1 " Bravo, Lady Lack'! High time these old   censors" were censorized!-had it all their own way a long time-" sauce for thye goose, sauce for the gander,"'- "Poor rule that won't work both ways"--never mind the hornets. BETSEY TROTWOOD, Censor.   OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS. MRS. GRUNDY AND EASTERN EDITOR TO SOUTHERN AUTHOR. Buy southern born thought! That were treasonindeed, To rebel in arms, "aid and comfort, " at least If you'd only die off perhaps rwe ight  read Pelf's good for us Pubs, and ALL masters down East, You vassals don't know, when 'twill do to be Pleased; But starve as you ought, and for genius is fit, Prestissimo then, how your work will be seized Some Yankee goose quill givin gracious permit ed In mean time regmemeraciou s Permit. In m ean time remeber, if still you will write That never a courtier his fortunes did mend Who wilfully stood in his own very light, Daring farther than king, his bow shaft to send! SOUTHERN AUTHOR TO MRS. GRUNDY. My charming old woman, I ear what you say For croaking lord Tripods don't heed them at all; Though they'd do very well to keep out of way, The sandst place always for things that are small; But stand by for once, and see "tTefahc play,., If you value t  heir ads as much as "the tin,"-.. Now Tripod, my dear, don't set up a squawl You've kept us all out, for many a day; "ADY  IACLAND, 2d Lictor.    <pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC6379-00000037"/> 72       FAMLY PAPERS AND VALENTINE FOR THE LOUISVILLE JOURNAL. (LOST' OR MISLAID BY ORIGINAL CONSIGNEE.) MR. EDITOR:- If that sectarian clapperclawing in the Louisville papers is " a free fight, count me in for a few licks ;" and if your readers see more impiety in Saladin's scimetar than Richard's battleaxe, or any one fails to see that a man may occasionally write en infidel, for the better edification of belligerent orthodoxy, without being a regular Turk, or wqrse Christian than his neighbors, then much joy may he have of his stupidity-it's a very happifying agency-my far-famed models, the distin- guished Braves, Hurl-the-tomahawk, and Light-the- splinters, never could have victimized him-let him thank God and take courage, for he has abundant rea- son, Yours, CRABTREE AP CRAB', 1st. Lictor, And heir-apparent to that beautiful old scatter-gun of the accomplished chief, MSS-THE-TARGET. COIoKASAw BLUFFS, Feb. 14th, 1854. MR. PRENTICE:  I'm astonished at you! Have you never seen my Aunt Betsey's Inaugural? If not, so much the worse for you, the law expects every man to know it (except the lawyers), but here it is    OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS.       73 !.73 "CrNKHoRN S POUNDTEXTS, 0OMPOSITIONSTIOKS:  ATo    a ofyou Tr and keep quiet, and walk a chalk, willsyou? Ive got something else to do besides following you up all the while to keep you from making perfect sillies of yourselves  but just let me catch you playing the fool with your little-go,' stirring up, and perverting President Pierces twenty-six battalions any where in this republic of letters, and see if I'm not down upon you with rod and lictor ' "March 4th, 18537."  'BETSEY TROTWOOD, Censor. Well now you see what authority you're indicted under, and nerdn't go to putting on that innodent, don't know nothin', haven't done not/din' sort of look, unless you want to be taught after the manner ofthe men of Succoth "with the briers and thorns of the wilderness" for you know well enough you have! But what has come over you? Is there such a "nil- dew in the lapse of a'few miserable years" that you can't be the same genial, whole-hearted, magnanimous soul you used to be? Once, when some hungry "vally- d- y m," underscullion or out-door sub of a by-gone dynasty, cried lustily for "more pap in behalf of his arinihing wife and children, then who but you was the very first man to come forward, declaring that although constitutionally and teetotally opposed to that kitchen et and the whole menage, you could not and would not harden your heart against such pathetic eals to charity; and forthwith set up a contributionb , and reported "a brass button, rusty nail, and pew er ap- poon" as the result ofyour humane exertions?  -and "oh what a fall is there my countrymen "I'm ctually afraid to trust you with this little bit to '    <pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC6379-00000038"/> 74       FAMLY PAPERS AND bridle king Solomon long since prescribed.; though if long ears would only bray any where else it wouldnt  much signify; but here in the newspaper, your news- paper that has in the main set them a much better example, it's a little too bad, indeed our sufferings is intolerable 1" Without wishing to broach any new heresy, or flatter you in the least, I must say, that all things considered, newspapers are, I think, rather an item in modern liter- ature, and on the whole I like some of them. Am, in short, a good deal indebted to one or two for my exten- sive knowledge of men and things in general-at least that is my impression, though if any man chooses to be contentious, I don't wish to' be too positive, if the know- ing ones insist that I might have risen to be first Lictor, been just as wise, and written quite as well without ever having seen one, perhaps I might, they ought to know best; still newspapers are good to read and light cigars, and I am good to read and smoke them. I don't pre- tend to explain the cause of that either-perhaps I haven't got the time, perhaps I should be off skylarkino at something else if I had-I've known people to do the like before-but time was, when, by edging carefully round the grand achievements, I could even venture to look into a religious (beg pardon) sectarian paper of a Sunday without catching the Polemics, wiach I take to be one of the worst distempers that can iffect any com- munity; now if I can take a bird's eye peep at yours of a week day, without being seduced into castigating other people's faults instead of mending my own, it's as * No allusion to the Ward trials.--SO. 'V   OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS.       75 much. And here you begin to get an inkling of my grievance and your misdemeanor, but only an inkling, mind you, I'm too much in a hurry (witness my speed) for any thing else ; a fact I mention for your encourage- ment, because you might, you know, get uneasy lest I was about to " speak my speech" and be off. No, no, "mine ancient," it's out of fashion now, and " with all your faults I love you still" too well for that; and besides it takes my aunt Betsey, who hasn't the advantage of being a half-breed and knowing how to shoot all round the tree, and from every leaf and thorn of a crabtree chapporal, to do those sort of things. I hold it a useless waste of raw material when the value of an article (I'll take this one out in advertising) is measured by the yard; but honestly and soberly, we poor sinners do have hard measure dealt out to us every way. If we don't go to church, or trouble ourselves about such things at all then we are a set of hardened repro- bates or graceless allios; if we do, it's as like as not only to see our betters do the devotions, hear that their Maker is going to take them to heaven in spite of them- selves, and send us to perdition because we can't get there in spite of him, for all of which we are exhorted to love him very ddarly, and praise him devotly, be- cause he has made us to hate him most cordially and be punished everlastingly. And then these judges elect -quite enamored with the prospect of sitting on our cases hereafter, and as much incensed at seeing their meaning evoked from general expansion into visual    <pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC6379-00000039"/> 76       FAMLY PAPERS AND angle,-must needs practice sentencing and tormenting us before the time. They have humbugged us out of our Almanac, banned the dance, outlawed the theatre, confiscated the decanter, and stolen our novels, and all this we have borne; but when it comes to laying violent hands on our newspaper, the secular newspaper, then we say hands off! We don't presume to lay our ungodly fingers on your righteous columns, we don't need to be told that flippancy can't answer, nothing short of acri- mony can pass muster there, we are cast out of the synagogue, but this curbstone IS OURS! And now we say to you, keep out of our "broad road" if you don't want to be bespattered-don't rub your lawn against our sackcloth and then smite us if you get defiled, don't reflect your thoughts and acts boih on our sensorium, and then turn black in the face, if we show them up daguerreotyped in words; for verily we of the :' profane" are shocked at your insolent, all-patronizing, lord-para- mount airs, of having religions made to order, as if the Almighty had nothing else to do but match his ethics to your politics! Above all, don't bring any more of yoAr " brotherly love " to our market,-we know exactly what it's worth, for we've seen enough of it, we have. I' you fancy these amiable little family bickerings, why 'can't you amuse yourselves among yourselves, without tampering with our especial? If made over to you in fee-simple, he could only teach, never learn you, how to wield a polished, knightly lance ; but does mortal man suppose his readers could be " sold " by that little gem of a " pious fraud" of yours? That transparent effort   OFFICIAL DOCUMEfNTS.      " to throw on a rival church, the odium of denying an un- popular dogma, in the face of evidence enough. per contra to sink a ship? Did true man ever so blacken the fair fame of his own beloved, with the reflected stain of' such gratuitous and most mendacious poltroonery? Of course not; hurra then, for the valiant volunteer, the gallant little brave who undertakes to run the gauntlet, encoiled in rope enough to tie him hand and foot, and throw him to the Choctaws! But oh, Mr. Prentice, Mr. Prentice!" call you this, a backing of your friends,"--is this the way you suffer them to write themselves down? I'm afraid you've been contaminating your fingers with their "Cvile bribes," -yet no,-yQu surely haven't fallen quite so low as all that, at least I shall never offer you any such base in- dignity, for if you haven't taken final leave of all dis- cernment, as well as human sympathy, you must see it would be putting the change in the wrong pocket this time; if you have, remember the sad doom of one Sam my Houston, and  "consider yourself REPRI- MANDED t" But why didn't you let me know you were in want of stupid articles? If ever you get out again, just tele- graph down our way, and it shall' go hard, but I'll send you a whole dozen of my best opaque, rather than you should lack a foil to your'wit, or I the pleasure of see- ing it flash and glitter through thee clear obscure. Theirs are no use; you know yourelf 'twould be more than your life is worth, to dare draw that two-edged sword of yours on one of them; but do pray tell me, what is to become of the poor children who have, it seems, got a    <pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC6379-00000040"/> 78       FAMLY PAPERS AND most unpopular-odox Sunday School book that is read- able without threat or promise (whose munificent fulfil- ment they'd be apt to remember ever after as often as they thought upon nothing), and was ever so lucky a man, as the Reverend Author? To be sure the smell of so much ecclesiastical pitch does rather make a poor old fogy of a red skin sigh for the " good old times." "TALK, talk," he says, " no good, PINE SPLINTERS bery much good ; but I'm resolved what I'll do-I'll turn author too!" Taleit's nothing, tact is all-it's only "to hold on like grim death" to 'my share of the family papers and official documents, steaLthe balance, give the whole some rickety-cranky, outlandish- impudent title, throw in a few rounds of grape and canister at somebody's particu- lar Ism, get some of its great guns to fulminate me into notoriety, and my fortune's made ;-provided I don't make a mistake and " wake up the wrong passenger!" In that case I shall have to explain to all the Allissimas Sanctissimas, prifately, that it's a mere ruse de guerre, or complimentary salute in disguise; and when  the "lesser lights" comprehend, that it is, in fact, a tacit admission of their potency, they can't in conscience be very implacable at a little financiering blunder, when all the world must know, that if practice had the small- pox principle never need be ip danger, or in other words, that "religion is one thing, ahd business another." CRABTREE AP CRAB', 1st Lictor.   OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS.       9 ETHCS AND HUMANITy    . j Translated into doggerel for AMf .enpckO Socratee. and other kindred Sirits' by LADY LAOKLAND, 2d Lictor. DoN'T writhe any more, don't offer t rise, Such efforts are shocking to good Christian eyes i They must pain you, I'm sure, why don't you desist? If once out of sight, you'd be happily missed; And consider, 'tis sinful to struggle again, Say layman and priest, the kind-hearted men, For since you are killed, you had much better die; Indeed, you might yet if you only would try. It's your duty I'm sure-the Potters-field's nigh So quit all this breathing, and stark and stiff lie 'Not die till gour time?"-,that is very malign, For to feelings like mine, exquisitely fine, 'Tis distressing to hear how sadly you sigh, And my eye's getting dim--nov don't make me cry, But "look to the Lord," and soar up on high. Quick, quick!Ientreat, should the callous come by, They'd care very little, above or below, Bu send you right off-where they're like to go  What an angel we are, just dropped from the sky, And how saintly we talk, says Cynic close by; But should fortune yet make some turn in her wheel, Compelling the heartless in their turn to feel, And sleep in an alms'house, or matches to cry, Perhaps they would think it less sinful to try, And if human I keep, will endeavor to buy.   August 1854.   <pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC6379-00000041"/> i i NOTE PER SEC. They have churches and sermons in Paragon town, On the pathway to heav'n to pay many tolls; But sure there was error in placing them down For both must be needless in absence of souls. HYBRIDS NOT MASONS. Suca mystics, such mystics ! as some I have seen, "Ancient Henry" must pass in his lodge I ween  If a poor fainting wretch is struggling to stand, The pocket they know is the place for the hand; If he needs any hell, why just let him call, And they'll stand out of reach, and leave him to fall; When down in the ditch, he'll tumble no lower, And boot-toes can show him the " other side" shore ! If St. John were to vow he had a good claim, They'd vow to St. John that it was a great shame, And Archangel Gabriel his book needn't touch- Several entries of his mightn't please overmuch ! True Mystics have souls, the Hybrids have none Worth seeking at all when the grand race is run. In Hybrid's own town the former are rare; For genius or justice, the last do not care, And of Masonry's self large draughts it would take Those nominals there half human to make; A Millerite tract is the height of their ken, And juleps, gauds, cords, suit Fanny Fern's men.   OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS.          81 " Once there was an old woman," the parrots all cry- (The myth, it is thought, was the ghost of a lie,) And their " yarns" of false claims are true as Jack's bean Impostors, I'm certain, were never so green. Fine TALK they may make" says the world standing by, " But for BROThERLY LO    it's ' all in my eye ;' So since Mrs. Grundy h acts "wide awake," And watches each turn of te brilliat opaque, With demi-surmise, that its secrc consists In donningl the armor and shunning the lists, They'd do well to see that its credit's-at etake, And some little to show, for appearance's sake; For broad m)'stic mantle must trail in the dust, When its ancient folds screen the fljse to their trust ! : LADY LACKLAND, 2d Lictor.   * No allusion, perhtls, to enlightened casuists, who consider it a Christian duty to outrage and vilify stupid impostors who cannot see how funds solemnly pledged to a specific lpurpose can be lhonestly reappropriated, or absorbed without leave or license, be the exi- gence what it may, if left per force of the merest casualty tempo- rarily accessible; and none of course to retrospective legislation and other ingenious expedients for ignoring claims, and neglecting if not insulting claimants even when seeking merely l" aid and comn- - fort," not alms. But if dignified officials, like Miss Betsey Trot- wood's LICTOI) can't behave magnanimously, like king Lion when he saw whlat it was that was braying after him, but must needs descend to personalities, and defining positions like any Uncle Sani's  mouthpiece; or feel bound by tenure of office. to expose injustice and castigate insignificance for tlie good of the i)nblic and the honor of their livery, then we insist thlat the thing shall be fairly understood, and no unwarrantable pretensions based on that hono- rary condescension hereafter. And so, by Lady Lackland's leave,    <pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC6379-00000042"/> 82        FAMLY PAPERS AND  LIGHT FROM ON HIGH. ON SEEING A FAIR SOFT LOCK OF HAIR, TAKEN FOR A WIDOWEl) MOTHER FROM THE GRAVE OF AN ONLY SON, THIRTEEN MONTIS1 BURIED. SHE missed it, oh, she'd missed it long, That buried lock of youth's bright hair; It came, a glory, joy, and song, A waving light on summer air; But orange groves wore deeper night, For deatl had1 deck'd him in its wave, Yet woman's love, and sorrow's might, Have won this trophy from the grave. -Oh thing of human life and breath, Oh waving plume from angel's brow, Type of the life that knows not death, Light of two worlds is on thee now ! Gushes of song from seral)h chords, Redeeming love are echoing here; And thoughts too fine for mortal words Are floating round the spirit's ear. we. aroe ot going to have any seven cities set together by the ears, for  is nettle wreath she's liThg down for all whom it may concern to scramble after,-no, not if we have to toss it over in plain prose to line Sundries in Covington, Kentucky. They in turn must not begrudge a leaf or so of chaplet, to such other "individuals" as Imay exist, and feel unjustly overlooked or set aside in the disposition of those touching souvonirs.-NOTE per Sec.   Oh human love, oh Christian faith, How bright ye blend in woman's tear; "MY SON-my son !" that mourner saith, " I've found the lost, they. buried here. " My lost is found ! All pitying one, That mortal pang is laid to rest; Past is all doubt, my son, my son, I see thee on thy Saviour's breast !' God cheer thee, mother, thou hast given A gem to light a holier shrine; And earth has many stars of Heaven That need such guiding hand as thine. L. L. ONLY A SLIGHT DIFFERENCE. A BEDSTEAD of iron had PROCRUSTES of old, And limbs stretched, or lopped, till they fitted, I'm told  PROCRUSTES the Modern, quite civilized grown, In GOTHAM sets up his "r2espectable" throne;- Not honor or Truth will he have for its base, But choice Ptunicfcith-the classic old grace. No axes has he, gold is vastly more nice To hack and to hew human souls in his vise; Racks, gauntlets and drills must be very fine sport, For never had despot so loyal a court ! No step of a freeman, his chaplains dare take, Calls, Sunday by proxy, they do dare to make;    <pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC6379-00000043"/> ) 84       FAMLY PAPERS AND , Pattern-subjects are they, worth sketching for fame- E 't If the artist sketch well, they'll know by his name. King's So-So you'll findc1n abundance of tools- They're lying all round in the liv'ry of fools- He breathes on the heart, and they smile pn his knife, Improves in its turn, ev'ry comfort from-'life, Or sigh o'er life's victims, their sorrows and sin, , (When they're quite out of reach, or wear a black skin,) And mourn o'er the heathen, their blindness and -% wrongs- ' " , If the heathen comes in, they pick up the tongs. Ten commandments engraved on tables of stone,   Less incumbent they hold than etiquette's one, And Death mean to distance, by dashing on "fast"- L ::, AVERNUS is nothing, ELYSIUM means CASTE! Nobility knows itself noble; but hard Its spuriac struggles to show it, by card ; , And if summoned to heav'n, would lackey send in To see if 'twere all "point device" to a pin- ; ] Like people, like priest, "Sword" conquers the whole, And stretches the conscience, and lopps off the soul. "ADY LACKLAND, 2d Lictor.  * Gold is the old man's sword, and how they do hack and hew withal!-Old Novel. S           THE END. xsf %,; -    ANALYSIS, GRAMMAR AND RHETORIC CONDENSED, IN MERCY TO UNFORTUNATE SUFFERERS, COMPELLED TO TEACH AND STUDY GRAMMsA A VAST DEAL TOO MUCH.  BY 3- i 3i. t. 3., AUTHOR OF "LETERS AND MSCELLANIES." IN PRESS. Extracts of Testimonials.  . .It is clear in definition; bringing to the minds of young pupils the most difficult rules of grammar, thus saving MucH time and labor to both pupil and teacher; and at the same time, sufficiently Com- prehensive, to include all that is necessary to a good practical under- standing of the English language.--PHLp and MARTHA J. EOKLES, Pres. &amp; Vice-Pres. of Sharon Female College, Madison, Miss . .  The compiler does not profess "to add any thing new to the. sciepce, but only to make it more brief, and less irksome, though in- cluding extra and much needed elementary and collateral information; and what she has attempted I think she has well accomplished-her easy colloquial style rendering that attractive which has hithertd been so extremely repulsive, especially-to-the younger class of pupils.- JOSEPH H. EATON, LL. D., Pres. Union University, Murfreesboro, Tenn. After concurring fully wit Pres. Eaton's remarks, I would add that I consider it one of the very few elementary works, really adapted to the wants and capacities of the youthful mind; and containing, as it does mnultum et idoneum inparvo,' I augur for it an early. adoption, and extensive circulation.-F. C. Cossrrr D. D., Ex. Pres. Cumberland Uni- versity, Lebanon, Tenn  Without specifying its peculiarities, I would cordially recommend it to public patronage.- WM. J. WALLER, LL D., Pres. Episcopal College (temporarily suspended), Shelbyville, Ky. Will do my best to introduce it.-REv. R. M. KING, A. M., Pres. Cane Hill College (C. P.) Ark. Shall adopt it without fail. . . .  hallbe gratified to have the opportunity.-MRs. J. A. TEEs, and REV . D. T. STUART, A. M., Prin- cipals of Kentucky Female Seminaries, the former having 223 pupils at the close of her fifty-ninth Session, June, 1854. "I miss nothing that young ladies usually learn from two books of twicte the size  and find much not contained in either."-Verbal critique by, a highly successful Ex-Teacher. * 170 pp. 18mo. in larger typ' than usual.    <pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC6379-00000044"/> "ETTERS AND MSCELLANIES. (SECOwD EDITION-OUT OF PRINT.) Instructieand amug.        Exceedingly sprightly, and full of good. sense.    Lady of strong and exuberant thought. ... . . Scarce fail to be read with pleasure and profit. Shall review this work at large ....  Predict for it a ready and ex- tensive sale.-Louisville Journal. An ornament to our literature. ..    Full of amusing inci-  dent and sprightly remarks ..    Poetic genius of a high order  of merit. When it appears, give it a more extended review.-Kentucky  Statesman. ,  Subject of Temperance Reform, among other things, treated in- an original and most masterly manner.-Org. Temp. Ref. '* Full of genius and good taste, and will, I am sure, sell well.- Rev. Robert Morris, author of "Lights and Shadows of Free Masonry."  * This is a genuine BOOK-a lady-like book, with a lady-like spirit. You will find something in it that you don't see every day-sundry clear, ringing words, that take the atmosphere by a sort of surprise,  and not a few hard hits. It is free, bold, independent in intellectual quality, and, withal, truthful to the sex in those affections that acconl- pany the outgoing of their thoughts, and throw a higher grace thai )eauty around their images. It has another and tenderer interest-the interest of sorrow. calamities, such as seldom overtake our frail nature and crush out its lope and strength, have fallen on its gifted author.-With all manly nearts, this would insure its prompt patrdnage; but when real merit of an unusual degree is allied with an appeal to our sympathies, no one should fail to lend a helping hand for its success.-Montgomery (Ala.) Journal.                         , Possesses much merit, racy and humurous sketches by an original and keen observer.-Flag of the Union, (Jackson) Miss. One of the best of its class, rare and valuable. . . Ask for it a perusal by all lovers of good reading .... Quite suggestive. -. . . . Very spirited .   ... Neatly printed and.-uniquely written, one of the books that will repay perusal.-Vicksburg Whig, Yazoo City, Natchez, Baton Rouge, and Mobile papers. We commend this very interesting work. Fluent, racy, quaint, and poetical, it cannot fail to entertain and instruct. The book is well worth the price, and the purchaser will bestow a benefit at once upon himself and another who needs, and deserves, and will duly appreciate it.-Nashville Whig. A book of real merit, written in an exceedingly sprightly style, and calculated to do good in, besides pleasing,' every circle of Southern readers.  And we do think it would be rather outre on the part of any Ken- tuckian or Southerner to withhold the reward due to Southern litera- ture.-Ky. Yeoman. * Stars indicate VOLUNTEER critiques, Editorial MS. and verbal. si     a        .   ADVERTISEMENTS. Something out of the common, with a style just as peculiarly the author's own as anything to be found in the works of Lawrence Sterne. -Telegraph, (Murfreesboro, Tenn.) * Wants nothing but abuse to make it exceedingly popular. It is a capital work. . . .  Interesting as a biography, fascinat- ing as a novel; but not to be fully appreciated either by those who never read one, or never read anything else ..   The man who sees nothing special in this, would if left to his own unguided taste, pronounce Addison a dunce, Washington Iriing-a bore, and Ik Marvel nowhere-let his mother look well to his outgoings. ... A book. for the library-we shall put ours on the shelf with Irving-to bead read and read again by all who enjoy a "silent laugh," or thrilling' pathos ....    Cannot fail to command the sympathy and admira-' tion of all men of letters for its talented and suffering authoress.-Flag and other South-western Authorities.-Publishers making private sale of Eastern consignments. A very clever production, and we feel a decided interest in the suc- cess of the writer. It is made up of letters and sketches, running through a period of some twenty years. The style is easy, graceful and sprightly throughout. A passage or two of some of the earlier effu- sions may perhaps be considered slightly irreverent, but probably was not so intended. The whole work proves itself the emanation of culti- vated intellect, sparkling fancy, keen and close observation upon men and things. Sarcasms, sharp and pungent, abound in its pages, and many of the foibles and meannesses of life are lashed with an unspar- ing hand, while here and there dashes of humor alternate with passa- ges of gentle affection or touching sorrow. A sub-tone of sadness and suffering pervades the whole, and, without extraneous aid, it would not be difficult to infer that she has suffered more than enough to crush a less determined spirit.-Franlkfort Commonwealth. * I expected to find it similar in character to many of the works that are now-a-days brought to public notice, in various ways-a sort of badly printed, badly arranged rehash of ideas, either obsolete or famil- iar to every schoolboy. But, sir, I did not know the gem I was buying. I can truly say, that no half-day's reading ever gave me more pleasure than that spent over the above-named book. The style is fresh, free, and frank-playful, witty, sarcastic and grave-law, politics and reli- gion, morality and ethics, disquisition and description, are all dished up in proper turn, in the most 'delightful style that a sprightly, intelligent, "Leen visioned" woman could write. I write the above without her cognizance, but those who patronize the lady, will find the book worth treble the price; in fact, one forgets, under the fascinating influence of its pages, all notions of common "gelt" and cent-per-cent.- Corres- pondent Kentuckian. "I always take great pleasure in expressing that high opinion of your literary power and promise which the perusal of your recent publication has enabled me so earnestly to form."-Fitz Green Halleck.    </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
