<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6162">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Leaves from a Bachelor's Book of Life </title>
            <author>Copcutt, Francis</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC6162</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-0631</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                    participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Leaves from a bachelor's book of life</title>
                  <author>Copcutt, Francis</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>250 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>S.A. Rollo</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                  <date when="1860">1860</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2004-12-01">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2004-12-15">Finished TEI conversion</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-06-23">Converted document from SGML to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-06-23">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6162-00000001"/>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>LEAVES FROM A BACHELOR'S BOOK OF LIFE.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>BY <docAuthor>FRANCIS COPCUTT.</docAuthor>
            </byline>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>New York:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>PUBLISHED BY S. A. ROLLO, <address>
                     <addrLine>169 AND 170 FULTON STREET,</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>OPPOSITE ST. PAUL'S CHURCH.</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </publisher>
            </docImprint>
            <docDate when="1860">1860.</docDate>
         </titlePage>
         <pb n="3 (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC6162-00000002"/>
         <div type="fly_title">
            <bibl>
               <edition>Entered, according to Act of Congress, in the year 1860, by Francis Copcutt, In the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United States for the Southern District of New York.</edition>
               <publisher>DAVIES &amp; KENT, STEREOTYPERS AND ELECTROTYPERS, 113 Nassau Street, N. Y.</publisher>
            </bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="contents">
            <head>Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>The Raven. <ref target="VAC6162-00000003" rend="right">7</ref>
               </item>
               <item>Seeking Dinner Under Difficulties. <ref target="VAC6162-00000026" rend="right">51</ref>
               </item>
               <item>Charlotte May. <ref target="VAC6162-00000041" rend="right">81</ref>
               </item>
               <item>The Admiralty Papers. <ref target="VAC6162-00000052" rend="right">105</ref>
               </item>
               <item>A Day in the Dead Letter Office. <ref target="VAC6162-00000067" rend="right">133</ref>
               </item>
               <item>"Fire! Fire!" <ref target="VAC6162-00000101" rend="right">203</ref>
               </item>
               <item>Edith. <ref target="VAC6162-00000113" rend="right">225</ref>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Leaves from a bachelor's book of life</head>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="[4]" xml:id="VAC6162-00000003"/>
               <head>THE RAVEN.</head>
               <pb n="[6]" xml:id="VAC6162-00000004"/>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Raven.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <l>"For ye know not what a day or an hour may bring forth."</l>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>"MOTHER! mother!"</p>
                  <p>"Well, my child."</p>
                  <p>"Mother, I—— May I stay at home, to-day, mother?"</p>
                  <p>"Are you ill, Marie?"</p>
                  <p>"No, mother."</p>
                  <p>"Then why stay at home, my dear child, when all is prepared? Why avoid an excursion to which you have been looking forward with so much interest? Even now our friends must be waiting for us. What has so saddened you, my own Marie?"</p>
                  <pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6162-00000005"/>
                  <p>Mrs. Chapelle, as she spoke, placed her arm round the neck of her beautiful daughter, and kissed her pale forehead.</p>
                  <p>"I—I was awakened—"</p>
                  <p>She hesitated, her large eyes filled with tears, and she hid her face in her mother's bosom.</p>
                  <p>"I was awakened, mother, at daybreak, this morning, by a loud, hoarse cry, seemingly at my very ear; it said, 'Beware! beware!'—at least I thought so. Springing up, startled as if a thunderbolt had struck the house, I looked round the room, but could distinguish nothing in the gloom. Thinking it the deception of a wild dream, I lay down again, but in a little while the cry was repeated, louder, harsher than before. Aroused by the startling sound, I sprang out of bed, my heart beating wildly with terror, and there, on the sill of the open window, stood a large raven, black as night, and croaking as if the fiend himself had given it utterance. I moved forward; it turned its wicked black eye full upon me, winked, croaked, and flew away. That's all, mother. If I go to-day, I fear I shall never come back again. Don't laugh at me; indeed I can not help it; but—but, mother, I <emph>will</emph> go; I will shake off these silly forebodings: let us forget it."</p>
                  <p>"The resolution is well formed. Do so. The ALMIGHTY FATHER has taught the raven his notes, as well as the nightingale or your own canary, and there is music in each, but prophecy in neither, love."</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6162-00000006"/>
                  <p>THE curtain was up.</p>
                  <p>The act had commenced.</p>
                  <p>The sun had drawn up the curtain from before the scene—the curtain of darkness, studded with stars, and hidden it high in the proscenium. On the mighty stage were visible the Rideau Canal, with its hill of granite locks, the magnificent masonry of man; the everlasting mountains and huge rocks, the magnificent masonry of God; while between them rolled the beautiful Ottawa, from its source seven hundred miles away in the ice region; and in the foreground, foaming, hissing, surging, the "cataract of real water" dashed on, on the way to its ocean tomb, and sent up everlastingly its cloud of foam and spray toward heaven, like a white-winged messenger to the Mercyseat.</p>
                  <p>Its dome was the huge vault of blue ether, frescoed with clouds, where the sun-lamp hung, and flooded with light the actors, the scenes, and the audience. The birds and winds and the deep-toned somber bass of the roaring fall made its orchestra. The foot-lights were dancing rainbows, created by every movement of the sun-lit spray, and in the background were the Indian and bear-peopled forests, which reach to the Polar seas. Above and beyond all, for those who had eyes to see and ears to hear, echoes of the sphere-melodies might be caught, and glimpses of that heaven and hell of which our world-play of "Life" is but the emblem—the mirror held up to <emph>that</emph> nature.</p>
                  <p>In a few hours the "drop" will fall over this act of a day: in a few days the play will close, the curtain of doom descend, and all the lights be put out. Then, with a smile or a shudder, as we have applauded or performed well or ill, we shall look back from the measureless existence beyond the grave to the mimic scene.</p>
                  <p>Surrounded by all this, and standing on the suspension-bridge that hangs over the Ottawa, graceful and aerial as an inverted rainbow shorn of its colors, and harnessed for man's use, stood a party gazing at the cataract, as gay a one as the sun shone upon that day, in all the world-wide theater.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6162-00000007"/>
                  <p>THE sylph-like "Meta Bell," graceful as the white foam and spray; the "President," with fifty winters on his shoulders, and fifty summers in his heart, and a vivacity never tiring, that made an atmosphere about him; the "Editor," with "fusion" for his friends and confusion for his enemies, and whose "columns" were a stone of stumbling and a rock of offense to his opponents; "Lord Cate," the practical; "Lady Cate," the ideal; "Diana," the improvisatrice; "Marie," with the musical laugh and gazelle eyes; "Contractor Thorne" and his beautiful bride; the "Fast Man," whose affection for his pretty friends, pale sherry, and puns was perennial; and a dozen others, all "merry as a marriage bell," had left their offices, boudoirs, hearth-stones, cares, and native land, to wile away a few days with nature in the far north.</p>
                  <p>Crossing the broad St. Lawrence, they had been whirled away by the iron horse, whose neck is indeed clothed with thunder, and who laughs at the shaking of the spear, across the Canadas, between primeval forests and half-cleared fields, where the wheat had sprung up, and was trying, after a most vain and melancholy fashion, to bring forth fruit a hundred-fold; by log cabins that would frighten the romance of the school girl's cottage love from her fanciful brain, and past horses that seemed "fast" indeed where they stood beyond the power of moving, and whose flesh-less bodies showed "points" enough to satisfy the fastidious perceptions of a Long-Island horseman.</p>
                  <p>They had gazed from the "Barracks" at "Ottawa City" upon the beautiful scene where the ALMIGHTY has so visibly made his mark: had gone under the Rideau Falls, where the thin rocks hang overhead like a huge shelf, whence the waters fall like a lace curtain, graceful and white, and make a chamber fit for the bridal of a water-nymph. From the "Lake des Chats" they had seen the forest-home of the wolf, the bear, and the Indian, reaching thence onward to Hudson Bay and the ice regions. In the little Aylmer village, the last home of civilized life, they had danced "till broad daylight," and at the witching hour of night had startled the little place from its propriety<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6162-00000008"/> with their fireworks and music. Now they were returning toward their homes, and standing face to face with the "Chaudiere," the mighty cataract of the Ottawa, the "hell of waters," the "smoke of whose burning" ascends evermore toward that ALMIGHTY power which gave it its force, its beauty, and its awe. Mirth, wit, sentiment, humor had been never-tiring companions on their route; but now they were hushed into silence before the scene, where the water in wild wrath boiled, roared, and dashed, and where quietly the beautiful rainbow hung over it in the white spray:</p>
                  <p>"Like a child smiling on a battle-field, or a flag of truce amid its horrors," said Diana.</p>
                  <p>"Or," said Meta Bell, "like the smile of a woman at a bridal, where her lover is married to another."</p>
                  <p>"Ah! Meta, have you suffered?"</p>
                  <p>"No, not <emph>yet;</emph> but the fall and rainbow seemed to emblem the raging bitterness that fiction and imagination have taught me might lie under such a smile."</p>
                  <p>"Or," said the President, "like an insurance policy in your hand, when a conflagration, like a destroying angel, is consuming your property."</p>
                  <p>"Good," cried the Fast Man, "and certainly new; or like the moon shining on the 'smash-up' of an express train, or the gas on a 'form' knocked into 'pi;' but a truce to your similes. Look! look!"</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6162-00000009"/>
                  <p>THE Ottawa, which empties into the St. Lawrence at Montreal, takes its rise beyond Grand Lake, some eight hundred miles away in the far north, and, of course, is a river of considerable magnitude, in places several miles wide. It contains many rapids and falls, the principal of which are at Bytown, now called Ottawa City, where the river, confined within a rocky channel of half a mile in width, rushes on one hand over rocks and through chasms that seem to have been the work of earthquakes, and on the other, the main body of the river falls a distance of some eighty feet, in a sort of circular basin, the form having given it its old name of "La Chaudiere," and from this boiler or caldron a column of spray rises, similar to Niagara. It is a most grand, picturesque, and beautiful fall.</p>
                  <p>The valley of the Upper Ottawa being the best timber land of the province, and timber being, indeed, its only produce, the government has been at much expense and trouble in erecting works to facilitate its transportation to market. The principal of these works is at Ottawa City, where an immense dam has been erected to preserve the rafts from the cataract; and by the side of this cataract, between a rock island and the main shore, a race-way, chute, or slide is formed, which consists of two rapids and three artificial falls, overcoming, in the distance of about half a mile, the entire height of the main fall. On each side of this chute, and for some distance above it, is a double line of string-pieces, formed of huge floating logs, flattened on the upper side, and chained together at the ends. Between these the rafts, or rather sections of rafts, called "drams," are rushed down the falls, from the upper to the lower river, and it was one of them, on its seemingly fearful passage, that had attracted the attention of the party.</p>
                  <p>The Fast Man at once suggested that it would be an amusing and interesting finale to the excursion if they should make a "voyage" down the falls on one of these drams. The idea was received with acclamations by most, and the timid ones were re-assured by the President, who had already been down on one, and assured them of its perfect safety: so the wagons<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6162-00000010"/> were again in requisition, spirits rose with a new excitement, rapidly as mercury in the sunshine, and after a pleasant little drive by the river-side to where the rafts were congregated, one was selected, the raftsman bribed into good humor, and the party, all sunshine and happiness, passed on board. The rope, composed of a hickory sapling, was loosened, and the odd oblong log-boat floated out into the stream, when the President, looking round to see if all were there, cried: "Lady Cate, is your husband aboard?"</p>
                  <p>"<emph>Probably,</emph>" said the lady, quietly; "I saw him run through a pine saw-mill a little while ago."</p>
                  <p>"Ah! Lady Cate, they must have "wise saws" indeed in that mill to turn out such a board."</p>
                  <p>"The proof of which," said the Fast Man, "I suppose is, that they cut him on his first introduction; but see! he is there, hurrying down to the river; a run on the bank, by the way, Mr. President, and I'm first teller."</p>
                  <p>"Then pay out the rope and check the raft," said the President.</p>
                  <p>The raftsman opened his eye (he had but one), apparently in a vain effort to comprehend the drift of the conversation, then turned to attend to that of the raft, as Lord Cate sprang on board. He had lingered behind, gathering wild flowers for the bride, and wild mint to flavor some refreshments, the materials for which the Fast Man had been careful to transfer from the wagons to the raft.</p>
                  <p>The raftsman, their captain, was evidently a plant from the outskirts, if not beyond the pale of civilization. His face was bronzed with extreme heat, cold, and exposure. He wore a skin cap, surmounted by a fine sable marten-tail, well patched corduroy pants, and flannel shirt, a shoe on one foot, an Indian moccasin on the other, and chewed tobacco incessantly. That must have been a thirsty fish that could swallow the water within yards of him. He seemed in the main good-natured, listened with curious wonder to the conversation, and appeared to be not a little <emph>dashed</emph> at the strange and unusual passenger-list he had taken on board.</p>
                  <p>The raft moved on.</p>
                  <p>"Lady Cate," said the Fast Man, "a glass of pale sherry with you, old as your grandfather, and bright as your fancies."</p>
                  <pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6162-00000011"/>
                  <p>"Wine with such a scene and such a day! No! See the trees in their living green, on those summits embracing the clouds; the wild flowers on the banks, spreading their beauties for almost no one to see, unless it be indeed the angels; and the balmy air, too; the day seems to me as if it had been made for paradise, and was lingering here a few hours on its way home."</p>
                  <p>"Bravo!" cried the Fast Man; "the weather returns its compliments for having something unusual said about it. Diana, a glass of sherry, pale as your thoughtful forehead, and exhilarating as your poetry."</p>
                  <p>Diana withdrew her eyes from the sky, at which she had been looking, and shook her head.</p>
                  <p>"What are you thinking of, Diana?" said Marie.</p>
                  <p>"Thinking of, dear girl!—that those little white clouds are like flags of truce, held out by the angels, to bring us to a parley, that they may try and persuade us to leave our sin-war against the HOLIEST, and be one again with our KING, our FATHER, and our GOD."</p>
                  <p>The tears stood in Marie's eyes, and she leaned her head upon Diana's arm.</p>
                  <p>"Marie," said Diana, "you have been the gayest of our party, and, if I divine rightly, the saddest, too. Your merry, echoing, musical laugh has had something in it of strange and weird, that at times has almost made me shudder. It has seemed to me, if I may use the paradox, a beautiful falsehood. Am I not right, Marie? So sad, and at your age! What weighs on your spirits? Why, Marie crying! turn, love, or they will see it. Does the descent of the falls terrify you?"</p>
                  <p>Marie wept quietly a few moments, then looked up, and said:</p>
                  <p>"At my age! Ah, Diana! the clouds look darkest in spring, they are contrasted with such glowing sunlight: in winter we look for them as a matter of course. No, I am not alarmed at the descent, and would not leave the raft if I could. It is an undefined terror that has hung over me ever since we left home, and darkens my sky where, indeed, there are no clouds visible—no cause for the darkness that I can <emph>see!</emph>"</p>
                  <p>The President here suggested that some one should write an account of the excursion after they reached home, and offered to help the historian by keeping a 'log' himself.</p>
                  <p>The raftsman said he didn't care who kept a log, if<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6162-00000012"/> he were only paid for it; and opened his eye wider and took a double quid, when he saw the smiles his observation excited.</p>
                  <p>"Our Fast friend is very literally making 'a log'-book," said the President, pointing to where he was cutting names and dates on a stick of timber; "but Diana will do it better than any of us. Diana, will you not write an account of our trip?"</p>
                  <p>"No, I would not write a line about such an excursion; its sayings and doings are too like the children's soap-bubbles in the sunlight; beautifully round and rainbow-tinted, perhaps; but attempt to remove them for other's inspection or admiration, and they vanish into thin air;" and she resumed her seat by Marie's side.</p>
                  <p>They had now reached a point where the channel made by the string-pieces narrowed, where the current began to be more rapid, and where, beyond the dam, the falls could be seen, and the mass of water gliding over the edge of the rocks, then dashing into the wild, foaming chaos, and in the bright sunshine, the spray seemed like a column of snow supporting the rainbow arch.</p>
                  <p>Diana sat on a log, gazing at the scene for a time in silence; then, as was her wont when deeply moved by the beautiful, she began to rhyme out her thoughts, while all listened to the deep tones of her sweet voice, and the Editor, drawing out a card, penciled her words in shorthand: <q>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l rend="ti-1">"Thou'rt beautiful as is the wile</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">Of infancy, or its first smile</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">In mother's eyes; its earliest word,</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">When by maternal car 'tis heard.</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">As hope in a young bride, who ne'er</l>
                           <l>Has dreamed of any but a path of flowers, 'La Chaudière.'</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l rend="ti-1">"As graceful as the forms we see</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">Of angels in dream imagery,</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">When we're alone with GOD and night,</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">As she through whom the infinite</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">Of love was first revealed, Compare</l>
                           <l>All graceful things with thee, and thou art first, 'La Chaudière.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l rend="ti-1">"But dreadful, too, as is the sight</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">Of armies in their fearful fight,</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">As when the lightning's lurid glare</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">Flashes its thunder through the air,</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">The very home of flends seems there.</l>
                           <l>Are those not groans within thy vortex wild, 'La Chaudière?'</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l rend="ti-1">"How like our world, with passion rife,</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">Filled with war, quarreling, murder, strife,</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">With heaven above, around, before us,</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">And GOD'S own smile of mercy o'er us,</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">Is thy fell chaos, demon's lair,</l>
                           <l>While o'er it calmly hang thy spray and bow, 'La Chandière.'"</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6162-00000013"/>
                  <p>Diana's improvising was cut short at this moment by some apparent commotion in the distance, near the slide, and a bare-footed Canadian came running along the string-pieces, crying out, "Stop! stop! there's a raft fast in the chute!"</p>
                  <p>The raft of our party was steered by two rough oars some twenty feet long, one at each end. The raftsman cried to those who had hold of them to work in toward the string-pieces—a task of some difficulty, however, as the current had begun to move quite rapidly. The raftsman sprang to the side as it approached, and with his hickory withe caught a fastening, and brought the raft up with a jerk that nearly threw those who were standing from their feet.</p>
                  <p>"All our trunks checked," said the Fast Man, "although we have no baggage. Have a care, Meta; have a care, Mr. Editor, how you venture on those string-pieces; 'log-rolling,' you know, is dangerous; you will be overboard."</p>
                  <p>"We shall all be over-bored," said Lady Cate, "if you don't cease punning."</p>
                  <p>"Take the beam out of your own fair eye, lady."</p>
                  <p>"I hope we shall not be fastened here long," said Lord Cate; "for since we sat down to breakfast, saints and sinners, seven hours have passed; tied here, we lose our dinners. Such scenery's superb, but satisfying to no one single soul with hunger dying."</p>
                  <p>"'Angels and ministers of grace!' rhymes from Lord Cate," cried Contractor Thorne.</p>
                  <p>"And as full of hisses as a Gorgon's head, or our Psyche at Aylmer, when she was brandishing the torch of Tisiphone," suggested his bride-wife.</p>
                  <p>"That means," said Lord Cate, "I suppose, Marie firing off Roman candles."</p>
                  <p>"By the way," said the Editor, "what a defect it is in our language the oft-recurring sound of the 'S.' Have you never noticed in the Episcopal service what a hiss will spread through the house at certain parts of it?"</p>
                  <p>"That is when they don't like the performances," the Fast Man observed.</p>
                  <p>"Diana," continued the Editor, "can you not make us some lines without an S in them?" His request was repeated by a dozen others.</p>
                  <p>Diana turned from Marie's side, and, with her usual frank, ready good-nature, after looking down for some<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6162-00000014"/> time, and contracting her brows, as if she was thinking with an effort, said slowly: <q>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>"Girl of the dazzling eye,</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">Wild and free,</l>
                           <l>To the greenwood away we'll fly;</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">Come, love, with me.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>"Leave from thy gentle heart</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">Care, pain, and woe,</l>
                           <l>And away to the meadow green</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">And valley we'll go.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>"Thy voice will be echoed</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">By each warbling bird,</l>
                           <l>And the melody, lingering,</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">Through the valley be heard;</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>"No pain will haunt thee there,</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">Alone, but not lonely;</l>
                           <l>I will bear all thy care,</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">Mine, and mine only.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>"Oh! come to the wild wood,</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">Come, love, away;</l>
                           <l>There make the day, holy, love.</l>
                           <l rend="ti-1">And night like the day.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>"Why bear the burden, love—"</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>"Oh! indeed I can't go on. Seeking for words without an S cramps my imagination like a vice," said Diana, drawing a long breath of relief.</p>
                  <p>"It is not necessary," said the President, amid the applause that followed; "you have succeeded. How clear, ringing, and musical the words sound!"</p>
                  <p>"Oh!" said the bride, "if I had Diana's talent, I would ask for no higher earthly boon."</p>
                  <p>"He that sinneth in one is guilty of all; thou shalt not covet. Have a care, Mrs. Thorne, or you will break the decalogue."</p>
                  <p>"Break the deck-a-log," said the raftsman, glad at last to hear something he understood, and observing Mrs. Thorne getting up on a piece of timber that lay across the raft, "I should like to see any one break that deck-'log. It's the only sort of deck that will stand going down the slide;" and another mass of tobacco was hid in his capacious mouth.</p>
                  <p>The Contractor hid his face, the President smiled, the others laughed, all but the Fast Man, who fairly roared, while the raftsman retired to the end of the raft, looking as if he thought that he had a highly improper passenger-list aboard; but, not wishing to anger him, the President took a large tumbler full of antique sherry, and presented it; he drank it at a draught.</p>
                  <p>"How do you like that?"</p>
                  <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6162-00000015"/>
                  <p>"Well enough, but too weak," said he, shaking his head.</p>
                  <p>His palate had been educated with apple-rum and rye-whisky from the cradle, and the Fast Man sighed as he thought of the twenty years that wine had lain in the cellar, to be so appreciated.</p>
                  <p>"Too late to call spirits from that vasty deep," said the President.</p>
                  <p>A beckoning and waving of hats in the distance told them that the chute was free. The raftsman undid the wooden rope, and the raft, feeling the impulse of the bubbling water, moved rapidly down the stream, going faster and faster each moment, until the first of the falls was but a few yards distant, roaring and bubbling in very respectable imitation of its prototype that they were leaving behind.</p>
                  <p>All the voyagers were now gathered on the upper logs, as the water would rush through on the lower ones, and drench, if it did not wash over, any unfortunate below. Some were sitting with their feet on the same level, like a row of squirrels, others standing, some bold, some timid, all excited, all gay.</p>
                  <p>"Now comes on the tug of war," said the President dent, standing in front, and holding Lady Cate by the hand, ready, to take the brunt of the battle. The Editor stood next, with his arm round a form of nonpareil type of timid humanity, and was trying to re-assure it. Blue-eyed Thorne said she was almost frightened at the new <foreign xml:lang="FRA">rôle</foreign> she was performing, and Meta held her so that it might not be a roll into the water. The Contractor said: "Another moment, and we shoot down the slide;" and the Fast Man observed that "it ought to be shot down, for it was foaming at the mouth and dangerous," then cried out, "Two to one on 2.40! hold hard or she'll break up!" and in his enthusiasm he took up a bottle of sherry, broke it over the "decalogue," and said, "O Bacchus! pray back us in our perilous descent!" while Diana sprang up, and stood at her full height, her great eyes dilating with excitement at the scene, her arms gracefully extended, and a smile on her lips.</p>
                  <p>It was strange to see how her moods of feeling seemed almost to <emph>flash</emph> from one to another. The changes were so quick and complete, from repose to excitement, from grave to gay, from serious to fanciful, that those that did not know the warm and ever-living<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6162-00000016"/> sun-heart behind these many-colored clouds sometimes thought her fickle.</p>
                  <p>Thus she stood for a moment, then, with a light, elastic tone, said: <q>
                        <lg type="quotation">
                           <l>"GAY as the butterfly floats on the air;</l>
                           <l>Swift as the tigress springs out from her lair</l>
                           <l>Gay as the light-beams come heralding day;</l>
                           <l>Swift as the charger to battle away;</l>
                           <l>Gay as float on the white clouds in the sky;</l>
                           <l>Swift as the proud eagle springs up on high;</l>
                           <l>Down on a mountain of water we float;</l>
                           <l>Down like an avalanche rushes our boat;</l>
                           <l>Down like the deluge we pass through the foam,</l>
                           <l>Down toward the ocean, the sea-monster's home;</l>
                           <l>Down like the flash from where thunderbolis hide,</l>
                           <l>Down—"</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>"Like a raft on a government slide," said Lord Cate. "Have a care, Diana, or your 'fine frenzy' will 'roll' you overboard;" and he caught both her hands and held her tightly.</p>
                  <p>While this was passing, and they were all speaking at once, the raft had moved on faster, faster, balancing itself seemingly for a moment on the edge of the fall, preparatory to the spring, and then down it went with a rush which almost took away their breath. The ends of the logs buried themselves in the boiling foam, the waves rolled wildly through on the timber below, and the spray, sparkling, hissing, flashing, scattered itself, like millions of diamonds, over the voyagers. The next moment the raft recovered itself, rose to the surface, and, with its merry crew, whose laughter awoke the echoes, passed swiftly as the winds down the rapids.</p>
                  <p>On, faster and faster, they rushed. The huge patriarchs of the woods beneath them were tossed along like feathers on the mad water.</p>
                  <p>The second fall was near, and all were bracing themselves for another plunge, when one of the long oars, hung at the side of the raft, was caught at one end in the water, and, swinging round as if it were on a pivot, passed over the heads of those who were sitting, but struck the Editor and two others, all of whom fell in confusion to the lower layer of logs, just as the raft plunged down the second fall, and the waves came rioting through.</p>
                  <p>"The Editor's form knocked into pi and distributed over the logs!" cried the Fast Man, as they rose from their plunge, both laughing with those who were making merry over their mishap, while the raft<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6162-00000017"/> bounded, with a fleetness almost fearful, down the second rapid.</p>
                  <p>"Now for the last fall, the highest and deepest of all!" cried the President. "Sit down, every one, in the center, and hold—"</p>
                  <p>"<emph>Keep back! keep back! to the other side!</emph> QUICK, <emph>for your</emph> LIVES!" almost screamed the raftsman, springing over himself at the same time to the right of the raft at a single bound.</p>
                  <p>Where the other raft had been wedged in, a little while before, the chain which fastened the ends of the string-pieces together had become displaced, and the end of a huge log, some three feet in diameter and sixty feet long, protruded into the stream.</p>
                  <p>The warning came too late. The third fall was before them, and almost before any one even attempted to move over, the crash came. Like an avalanche upon a cottage, a locomotive against a rock, they crushed together. The hickory withes that bound them were snapped asunder like threads, and with reports like rifle-shots. One half of the raft was knocked to pieces, and the logs thrown about for a moment as if they had been children's baubles, then the whole mass, chaos-like, rushed down into the vortex.</p>
                  <p>The President, knocked into the water, held for a moment to a log, then was dragged by the force of the current into the foam. The Editor, feeling the log on which he stood forced from under him, closed his eyes as he fell into the mad waters, and to what seemed certain destruction. Two others clung to a piece of timber, it rolled over, and they went down together. Marie, sitting on the side of a great log, absorbed in her own thoughts and feelings, had not even heard the cry, and was thrown head foremost into the "hell of waters!"</p>
                  <p>As her daughter disappeared, Mrs. Chapelle sprang up to the top of the raft, and stood there as if struck to stone, rigid as marble, one arm stretched at her side, and the fingers closed so tightly that the nails entered the flesh, the other extended and pointing to the foam where Marie had gone down. Her eyes, distended frightfully, seemed to be gazing on vacancy, and there went up to heaven, and echoed back from the hill-tops and rocks, a wild scream of mortal anguish, long, shrill, piercing the soul in its<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6162-00000018"/> agony, uttering an infinite of woe. The most terrified lost their fears in listening, and tried with their hands to shut out the sickening sound. It died away on the air, then rose again, each scream shriller, wilder than before, as if the earth had opened, and the voices of the doomed came up from their torment.</p>
                  <p>Down into the waves raft, logs, and bodies were hurled, and the next moment they were on the still waters of the lower river beyond the falls.</p>
                  <p>The President and his friends rose to the surface at different points, and all were swimming apparently unharmed.</p>
                  <p>"Marie! Marie! Marie! she's lost!" cried those on the uninjured part of the raft. The swimmers balanced themselves in the water, and looked around for the lost one, while others who could swim threw off parts of their dress, ready to plunge toward any place where she might appear.</p>
                  <p>A few moments of intense suspense and terror, made awful by Mrs. Chapelle's screams, passed, and nothing appeared; then the President was seen to catch at something below the surface, and the next moment to dive under; he re-appeared with Marie in his arms. Logs and oars were pushed forward; those who could swim plunged in to his relief; with his strong arm he divided the water; the raft was reached, they were drawn upon it, and Marie laid at her mother's feet, <emph>quite dead!</emph> She had struck her head as she went down, and probably died unconscious even of danger.</p>
                  <p>Pale and beautiful she lay there, with her head in Diana's lap, no distortion or mark of terror on her fair face, no answering murmur from her cold heart to the tears that were gushing from the eyes that bent over her, no word for those that were falling alike from the strong man and maiden, no eyes that could see the rough raftsman kneel, as he crossed himself and sobbed out a prayer, for which he could find no words, for the repose of her soul.</p>
                  <p>Mrs. Chapelle's muscles relaxed, and her screams ceased, when her child was placed before her, and she sank down to the log; but her eyes were still distended, glazed, staring, and she took no notice of the corpse, although her hand rested upon it. Those about her would almost have been glad of<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6162-00000019"/> her unconsciousness, had not a sob from time to time half uttered, and choking as it rose, told of the agony within.</p>
                  <p>The raft was moored to the shore, a rude litter formed, the poor girl placed upon it, and the gay party of pleasure, now a funeral procession, moved on in a silence broken only by sobs, and by the choking sound of Mrs. Chapelle's voice—the groans that were struggling for utterance in her breast. She walked by the side of the garment-body of her lost child, whose soul was even then before the judgment-seat, and so they passed on.</p>
                  <p>A rude coffin was hastily made, and the body placed therein. Flowers, sent from a neighboring conservatory, were laid about the form of her who had loved them so well. A few orange-blossoms that were among them Meta placed about her brow, saying, with motionless lips, "for her bridal with the HOLIEST," as, with eyes from which the tears were streaming, she looked up toward that home to which the soul of her friend had gone back again.</p>
                  <p>An entire car was appropriated to the party, the sad, the desolate, the dead, and they entered and took their places apart and silent. The coffin lay upon the seats, and Mrs. Chapelle sat at its head, but she took no notice of the casket whence her jewel had been stolen; there was no speculation in her eyes, she gazed on vacancy, and uttered no word.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC6162-00000020"/>
                  <p>THE sun sent its bright beams through the car from beyond the western mountains. The steam-whistle brought back fierce echoes from the hills. The bell rang its last warning, and the groaning, heaving monster of brass and iron rushed on, amid the same green forest-leaves and wild flowers, cottages and water-courses, where, so light-hearted and merry, they had passed a little while before—the same, yet dull, desolate, meaningless, or unnoticed.</p>
                  <p>Those who moved, moved stealthily, and shuddered as they passed the hard couch where Marie, her cares all over, her tasks all ended, her tears all dry, and her hopes and aspirations turned into the realities which they emblemed, lay calm as the depths of blue ether through which her soul had passed to its reckoning.</p>
                  <p>Diana sat apart, distant and silent, but her eyes were upon Mrs. Chapelle, and her heart yearned to offer consolation, to share in some greater degree her woe. Several times she started from her seat, but the glazed, vacant stare in those eyes, where despair was written so visibly, sent her back again. At last she rose, went to the coffin, and looked on Death flower-decked; and as she gazed, her soul expanded with thoughts beyond its reach, and she felt how near was the other world; how its inserutable mysteries surrounded her; how thin the death-vail between her soul and her GOD! Her heart swelled within her as if it would burst; and she fell on her knees before Mrs. Chapelle, saying: "Speak, dear friend, suffering mother, speak, and let us, too, share the despair that is killing you!" and she hid her face and her passionate burst of tears in the childless mother's lap: but there was no look fr om the stricken one, no word save her choking, half-uttered sobs; and so they passed on.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC6162-00000021"/>
                  <p>THE curtain of darkness descended, and hung there full of cloud-emblems and bright-glancing stars, bringing tidings to the weary soul from where the wicked cease from troubling, and hinting, with their silent eloquence, of peace perpetual to the saddened heart. Another act of a day was ended, another of the audience had gone home to her FATHER'S mansion.</p>
                  <p>So the play goes on, comic or serious, gay or sad, solemn or humorous, all ending in the tragedy of death: and in the fall of the curtain at the general doom, when players and applauders will be weighed by OMNISCIENCE, and the treasury of everlasting life opened to those who have played <emph>not</emph> to be seen of men—to those who have applauded as conscience dictated, and not because the multitude said, It is well, it is well!</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>WOODBINE, clematis, and roses hung about the verandah of the beautiful cottage that had been Marie's home; and beneath them, slowly and solemnly, the coffin and soulless form were borne and laid by the hearth-stone, where the household gods had been so rudely thrown down and broken for evermore.</p>
                  <p>The few friends who had accompanied Mrs. Chapelle home proffered their services, and sought to win her back to consciousness; but her nervous agitation at their presence was so apparent, the greater calm as one after another left, so visible, that they all retired, but near by watched with and over her through the long, weary night: beneath the stars, and among the flowers that Marie had tended and loved so well.</p>
                  <p>Mrs. Chapelle was alone with night, GOD, and the temple from which the immortal spirit that made it holy had departed. She stood for a few moments near Marie's coffin, after the last of her<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6162-00000022"/> friends had left. The same strange unconsciousness still possessed her. There was the same gaze on vacancy from her distended, burning, aching eyes, the same groan—sobs half-uttered were trying to burst their way from her heart, and choking her as they rose. She moved slowly across the room to where Marie's canary hung: it was dead! To where the drawings were that Marie had done so skillfully, and tore them slowly from their frames; bit by bit the fragments fell from her fingers to the ground. Then, with her hands pressed tightly on her chest, as if there was suffering there, she paced the floor again, still avoiding, as she moved, the door that led to Marie's chamber. Then she passed near a rose-bush full of flowers, from which Marie had gathered one to put in her hair as she left her home. Mrs. Chapelle broke a rose from its stem, held it a moment, and it fell from her fingers; another and another were gathered, and the flowers were scattered about the floor: then she broke the stem, and the flowerless bush bung over lifeless. Approaching the coffin, she touched the body of her child, took up some of the orange-blossonis that Meta had placed on her brow, held them before her eyes, and burst into a laugh, wild, weird, fearful, mocking, such as the Doomed might turn upon the HIGHEST, as he told them to "depart;" such as would make the strong man tremble and shrink with fear. The flowers fell from her fingers, and lay scattered about the corpse: the groanings that could not be uttered went on.</p>
                  <p>She turned toward the door of Marie's chamber: she touched it and shuddered, opened it and went in. She approached the window where the raven had stood: a tremor passed over her frame, a convulsive shuddering shook her body; her features worked fearfully, frightfully; she clasped her hands over her head, then over her breast, then stretched them up toward heaven and cried, as if the agony of a demon had burst from a human heart: "O GOD! kill me, or awaken me!"</p>
                  <p>A note, in Marie's handwriting, addressed to her mother, lay upon the dressing-table. Mrs. Chapelle took it, tore it open, and read:</p>
                  <pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6162-00000023"/>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText>
                        <body>
                           <div type="letter">
                              <p>"The warning, mother, weighs upon my soul. I may hereafter smile at it, but it presses on me now, and tells me that I shall never see my happy home again, nor my pictures, flowers, and all these memories of my little life. I have prayed to our FATHER that HE would spare me yet a little, that I might teach my heart to say, THY will be done: but no 'still small voice' answers, and all is dark. In this hour of gloom, my life comes back to me in fitful gleams; memories crowd in, and make me tremble. I have not, mother, could not love you as I should: I have been a too thankless child. Oh! if you have found me wayward, careless, selfish, forgive, forgive me! My heart yearns to feel your clasping arms, and to ask forgiveness at your feet. Now, when the handwriting seems to be upon the wall, my soul measures for the first time the height and depth of that love which has been like an atmosphere round me from my cradle. If the warning be a warning indeed, do not weep for me. If my life be cut off in the beginning, mother, do not mourn. Yet a little while, and we shall meet again at the mercy-seat of our FATHER and our GOD.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>MARIE."</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>As she read, her distended eyelids gradually resumed their natural shape, and tears fell from her eyes. As she finished, she looked up toward heaven, pressed the letter to her bosom and lips again and again, as if some living part of the lost one had returned, and the grief which had been killing her welled from her heart in floods of passionate tears: the fountains of the great deep were broken up. She sank to the floor, placed the precious note in her bosom, and hour after hour her surcharged heart relieved itself at her eyelids, as if the fountain of her tears were perennial and exhaustless. So she mourned on, her soul yearning to pierce the darkness that envelops the tomb, and join her idol beyond its mysteries, until it expanded within her, and she lost sight of her corporeal being; her inner consciousness became for the time her only life, and her body and senses, to her perception, ceased to have an existence. She looked up, and the ceiling of the room divided and disappeared; the walls about her fell away; a glory, light, clear, calm, filled the heavens and surrounded her; and in the bright light above, with her arms folded over her breast, her large eyes<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC6162-00000024"/> looking down on her mother, with calm, holy earnestness, floated Marie, in white drapery, that covered her form in its graceful folds. She looked at her mother long and silently, then floated up higher, higher, pointing with one hand toward the heaven to which she was ascending. The glory became brighter as she went up, and she disappeared in the "excess of light." Mrs. Chapelle's tears ceased as she gazed, she clasped her hands and held them up toward her child, cried: "Marie! Marie!" said, "The LORD gave, and the LORD hath taken away; blessed be the name of the LORD!" and fell upon the floor in a swoon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>DAYS, months, years rolled on, and added their mite to the eras, to be swallowed up in the measureless past; and Mrs. Chapelle, her hair all white, whitened in a single night, and lines of premature age in her fair, calm face, went on her way. She had learned that we may suffer and grow strong; her soul, had been taught that sorrow may be blessed, and that a divinity may be hidden therein. What there had been in her of severe and harsh had been softened; of pride, subdued; of thought and reflection, deepened; and of love of the world, annihilated. She rejoiced with few that rejoiced, but there were none too lowly to weep with when they wept: and when night came, as her knees were bent and her head was bowed before her GOD, she asked that the "little while" before she joined her child might be shortened, and tears fell as memory and imagination brought before her the angel-face that she had seen floating upward toward the heavens.</p>
                  <pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC6162-00000025"/>
                  <p>The years went on their way, and she felt less sad as the end of each approached. The mile-stones in her life-journey were left behind, some but marking the distance she had come, others with death's head and cross-bone sculpture, making her tremble: flowers grew near few of them; none were covered with garlands: and so she passed on toward her FATHER'S mansion, children loving, the poor blessing her: but she never smiled again.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>SEEKING DINNER UNDER DIFFICULTIES.</head>
               <pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC6162-00000026"/>
               <head>Seeking Dinner under Difficulties.</head>
               <p>AURORA and I loved each other, and we also loved Mrs. Jones, for she had made us acquainted: beside, Mrs. Jones was chatty, kind, and sensible; very <emph>sensible,</emph> for she never saw nor heard anything that we did not wish her to see nor hear; so we often met in Mrs. Jones' back parlor, without the fear of Aurora's father before our eyes, who disliked me exceedingly on account of some false facts which had reached his ears, and he wished me at the—no, not there, only at any part of the world I happened to have a liking for, except his house. But, alas for sublunary bliss! Mrs. Jones had an only son in Milwaukie, the son of a husband and <emph>first</emph> love (wonderful conjunction); and Mr. Jones, having made a<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC6162-00000027"/> "pile" out West, had sent for his mother, offering her a home in his house for life, in addition to the one she already occupied in his heart. So our dear friend sent for Mr. Leeds, who a few days afterward hung his red "banner on the outer wall," and "Going, going, gone," ringing out loudly and clearly from the loved abode, sounded in our ears as the sad knell of all our "tête-à-têtes."</p>
               <p>The following Friday Mrs. Jones was to leave town. So on Thursday Aurora told Ma that she would take an early walk in the morning, and break fast at "aunt's," and possibly not come back until dinner time; and she did take an early walk, but she breakfasted on board the "Alida," and as to returning to dinner, we shall see.</p>
               <p>Well, the captain cried, "All aboard!" "All ashore!" and our <emph>moving accident,</emph> as one may call an American steamer, sprang out from the wharf into the stream; and between the river-banks, covered with their June draperies of fresh emerald green, we wended our way toward West Point, with the intention of saying good-bye to Mrs. Jones there, and returning in the afternoon. Passing Cullock-houk, the High Torn, and so on (names unknown to gazetteers, but sacred to boyhood's memories of vacation weeks in the country), grave and gay by turns, we kept our place on the promenade deck until the boat reached West Point. Then came the hurried farewell, the tears from the weaker vessels, and the dash and foam and spray from the strong one. Handkerchiefs waved; Mrs. Jones' face grew less in the distance, and was soon lost to our sight forever.</p>
               <p>As an hour and a half would elapse before the down boat from Albany reached West Point to take us back again, we wandered about that paradise of beautiful walks, listening to the birds that were caroling their songs of love in the sunshine, to the cannon which the cadets were firing at the target across the bay, and to the music of our beating hearts; and in this atmosphere of affection and cannon-smoke, our souls shut out the memory of the past, the anticipation of the future, and reveled in the dreamy bliss of the hour.</p>
               <p>"Hark!" cried Aurora. Hark, indeed! It was the bell of the steamer as she approached the wharf, and we were half a mile away. Putting spurs to our will,<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC6162-00000028"/> we indulged in the luxury of a hard run, and succeeded in reaching one end of the wharf as the plank was hauled in from the other, and the "thing of life" dashed on her course, quite as indifferently as if no "Niobe, all tears" had been standing fifty yards off, praying for a place on her receding deck. There was no railroad then. Alas! poor Aurora; she turned her flushed face and tearful eyes upon me with a look of utter, hopeless despair, worthy of a more important cause; but it was not an unimportant one, however. The link which bound me to her father's indulgence was weak enough in itself; and keeping his darling and only daughter away all night, as now seemed inevitable, I felt would break a dozen such links. I should be forbidden the house, that was clear; and as to Aurora, poor girl, her fate was dreadful, for would she ever be allowed to go to her aunt's again to breakfast? No, decidedly not. It was a moment of intense and feverish thought; but I had had such fevers too often during a strange and eventful life to be dismayed now. I remember a very acute attack, some years ago, that came near being cured with cold water. It was on Lake St. Peter, when two steamers ran into each other in the middle of the night, and both sank, and I thought I was being drowned: a mistake, by the way, and an unfortunate one, too, perhaps, for Aurora; for, had I become a dinner for St. Peter's fishes, would she not have been home to her own in time?</p>
               <p>But now, clearly defined, yet leading to no mode of getting to New York, except in imagination, my head was crowded with all manner of race-horses, wagons, wings, rail-roads, balloons, steamers, rowboats—row-boats? A row-boat? It came paddling into my brain, and made fast to the long wharf of memory, and its freight was a dim twilight recollection of an old advertisement in the <title>Sun</title> newspaper. I went to the end of the wharf, and asked the gaping idlers who had been smiling at our "fix," "Whose boats are those?" But they all belonged to Captain this and Lientenant that, and could not be had. I felt angry and nonplused, and looked toward New York with "infinite longings," as the novels say, or as I have seen a child look through the glass of a confectioner's window, or a loafer<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC6162-00000029"/> through that of a Broadway broker's office; but "'T will never do to give it up so," I thought, and glancing from my wondering neighbors (who, perhaps, were speculating on my sanity in wishing, as they supposed, to row to New York), I saw, some distance out in the river, a man rowing down stream. Taking off my hat, I waved it for him to come back, and in a few minutes he was at the wharf.</p>
               <p>"Can you take two persons to Peekskill?"</p>
               <p>"Y-e-s."</p>
               <p>"For how much, and what time will it require?"</p>
               <p>"Two dollars; about three or four hours."</p>
               <p>"That's useless: how much will five dollars shorten the time?"</p>
               <p>"Well, I guess I could take you down for that consideration in about two hours."</p>
               <p>I beckoned Aurora, who had been watching my movements with eager curiosity; we descended to the boat, and again I suggested to our Charon that the only possible usefulness of the trip depended on his placing us in Peekskill at an early hour. We took our places in the well-cushioned stern-seat; the boat shot out into the stream; the two brawny arms before us pulled with right hearty good-will; and we were soon enjoying the breezes which fanned us from the brow of "St. Anthony's Nose."</p>
               <p>Aurora, too, with what sweet, confiding, and unbounded confidence she looked up in my face, asking no question about the route, only too happy, apparently, to be with me, and to be going toward New York, and her dinner. Yet there was a "fly in our pot of ointment," and we felt that "his eye was upon us." Through all that pleasant row, the look faded from our eyes half expressed; the sentence sunk to a whisper. O that some ingenious son of science would invent a mode of rowing to enable the oarsman to see <emph>where he is going,</emph> and nowhere else! We wished him at the—No, we wished him just where he was, with his strong, brawny arms to help us out of our difficulty. Slowly we wended our way at the foot of the lofty Highlands, which, from our little boat, seemed to tower twice as high as they do from the deck of a steamer.</p>
               <p>But this rowing over a route that you have been in the habit of passing at a speed of twenty miles an hour, oh! what interminable miles it does make!<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC6162-00000030"/> You look at a mountain, and then chat and dream away an hour, and look again, and seem to have hardly changed your relative position. Of course, to a certain extent, I was happy. I was with Aurora, and could look into her black, soul-lit eyes, and feel my own soul expand under their magnetism; and up to the everlasting hills, and see their summits in the heavens, and feel through them more linked to the eternal; but what was all this, when we <emph>must</emph> be home to dinner at five? Steadily, pull, pull, pull, and dip, dip, dip, the oars moved on, as if the boat were alive and had a pulse; mountain after mountain was left behind us, and now the last was on our right, like a giant guarding the paradise beyond, and on our left, Fort Independence: a glorious place, by the way, to while away one's summer leisure, where often, in the years gone by, we would leave the hotel as soon as we had breakfasted, with a little lunch-basket, books, needle-work, fishing-lines, and choice companions, and row off in our fairy boat to some mountain nook, and read, and chat, and dream away the hours; or in the shadow of a rock throw out our bait to tempt the fishes from their bath to our dinner-table. Even now the merry echoes of the song and laugh seem to ring in my ears. May you never have sadder hours, Mary, than when those echoes answered to your song of "The Mountain Maid."</p>
               <p>But those days have vanished into the eternity of the past, and the sere and yellow tinge begins to color the foliage of our life-tree.</p>
               <p>Farewell, Fort Independence! farewell, ye towering, heaven-piercing Highlands, at whose base, where plummet and steam-pump never sounded, is Kidd's vessel and <emph>untold</emph> treasures; farewell, enormous pump, enormous coffer-dam, enormous humbug, where rusty cannon were dropped in at night, to be drawn out the next day for the admiring eyes of weak-headed stock-holders; a long farewell to your <emph>acidulated</emph> grapeshot and sour ingots; no "pile" will ever bless your eyes from those "diggings;" farewell.</p>
               <p>Peekskill is in view; we approach, and in a few minutes more have paid and thanked our Charon, and are hurrying up the long wharf in search of knowledge under difficulties. We had been long on our way: three hours and ten minutes from wharf to wharf.</p>
               <pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC6162-00000031"/>
               <p>"Have you a carriage, horses, wagon, buggy, anything of the kind?"</p>
               <p>"Nothing."</p>
               <p>"Where can they be had?"</p>
               <p>"Up the village, about a mile."</p>
               <p>And such a mile up that steep hill! I had to take myself and help Aurora, who almost gave out before we had ascended half of it in the hot sunshine. At last we reached "Williams," out of breath, and beginning to be a little out of patience.</p>
               <p>"Have you a carriage, horses, wagon; anything of the kind?"</p>
               <p>"Nothing."</p>
               <p>Of course not; "my prophetic soul" knew that before I asked him.</p>
               <p>"Where can they be had?"</p>
               <p>And the place was described, up this street and down that, of course some distance back on the road we had just passed. I left Aurora and ran back, and fortunately found the proprietor sitting in one of his unwashed vehicles, while the smoke from a Virginia regalia curled about his head, the fumes from which made day hideous twenty feet around him.</p>
               <p>"Can you take two to Whitlockville by five o'clock?"</p>
               <p>"Where's that?"</p>
               <p>Where's that, indeed! A livery-stable keeper at Peekskill not know where Whitlockville was! I began to have serious misgivings about that advertisement, but answered: "Why, fourteen miles back of Peekskill, to be sure: it is the station of the Harlem Railroad, and the last train leaves at five."</p>
               <p>He had not changed his position, and now slowly pulled out his watch, and elevating it to the level of his eyes, said:</p>
               <p>"No, Sir-<emph>ee!</emph>"</p>
               <p>The emphasis on the final letters was a serious damper on my enthusiasm! it was the "unkindest cut of all;" and as to obtaining any cut, even a cold one, of that day's dinner in Fourteenth Street, all hope of it was growing "small by degrees and beautifully less." But I answered, drawing out my watch in opposition to his over-fast one: "It wants twenty-five minutes of four, neighbor, which leaves you an hour and a half nearly to drive fourteen miles; I have often done it in less time. It is absolutely<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC6162-00000032"/> necessary for us to be in New York to-day. We were too late for the boat at West Point, and have <emph>rowed</emph> all the way here to try and reach the cars. I will give you ten dollars to do it, or five if you get there too late."</p>
               <p>He gradually turned his head as I spoke, and as the last words left my lips the cigar left his. He sprang from his seat and ran into the stable, saying: "The browns can do it, if any team in the county can."</p>
               <p>I walked back to the hotel, and in about two minutes the "browns" were harnessed and at the door, with a good carriage, only too heavy, and a colored Jehu, who said he <emph>thought</emph> he knew where Whitlockville was. The "browns" were the best hack team I ever saw, well-bottomed, broad-chested, fresh, and full of spirit; and off we started, with just eighty minutes at our command.</p>
               <p>Reader, did you ever drive back of Peekskill? Shade of Macadam defend you if ever you do so! Such hills! such valleys! such a total want of a square foot of horizontal ground! Where can it be matched? Here you have to drive slowly, from the absolute inability of horseflesh to pull a carriage up at any other rate; there you must drive slowly, to keep from being dashed to pieces at the foot of a hill. And the road itself! one would think all the showers for a twelvemonth had rained cobble-stones and pebbles. We made, however, good speed under the circumstances—for a dollar-spur to Jehu made him risk our necks several times with a "perfect looseness." Now we were at the bottom of a valley that looked, from its shape, if nothing else, as if it might have been the wake of a clipper-ship, and the circle of vision took in a potato-patch and two trees; then, again, on some "bad eminence," or at least dangerous one, with the mountains, villages, and river spread out like a map about us, and beautiful as a garden; but on we went, seeing little of all this, and noting less, my watch and the "browns" being the alpha and omega of my interest.</p>
               <p>Jehu suddenly pulled up for an instant to wet the horses' mouths at a wayside trough, four miles from Peekskill, and I found that we had lost two minutes beside the time he should have done it in; but he<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC6162-00000033"/> said the roads beyond were better, so we started again in good spirits.</p>
               <p>The horses were warming up to their work, the roads a little less rugged, and barns, houses, and trees were left behind us in rapid succession. Nothing was uttered, and nothing heard, save the carriage, the ticking watch in my hand, and occasionally, from the stretched-out neck of some old goose, a prophetic hiss as we passed. Again we had made four miles, and now in good time, though still behind on the first heat. The day was shortening, the air less warm, and the delicious evening breeze was beginning to stir the branches; the road, too, for the most part was level—indeed, no part being steep enough to check our speed—and the "browns" went with a will, as if sixteen quarts of oats and side-dishes of fresh clover were waiting their coming. We regained the lost time, and by Jehu's land-marks had made fourteen miles ten minutes before the hour; still no Whitlockville appeared, and no railroad; not even a blacksmith's shop, tavern, or steeple could be seen in the dis tance to indicate a village. On we went, faster and faster, and on went the hands of that watch: eight minutes—five minutes; no Whitlockville; three—two—one.</p>
               <p>Suddenly, shrill, sharp, and distant, we heard the whistle of the locomotive echoing over the fields. This was too much. I sprang from my seat, snatched the reins and whip from Jehu, gave the "browns" a cut over the back, and madly they started off at a hard run; so hard, indeed, that I did not know whether I was driving them or they were running away with me. Stones flew, and clouds of dust arose; trees, fences, and fields seemed to fly past us; innocent flocks of wandering geese were dispersed from the even tenor of their ways, hissing defiance as we went on. One lady swine, who had chosen the middle of the road to give her interesting progeny their evening meal, jumped from her place, scolding in deep contralto, while the little ones ran in all directions, giving vent to their annoyance in the shrillest falsetto; all but one poor thing: the "browns" trod on its toes, and it lay on the road calling "Ma" at the "top of its register." Altogether<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC6162-00000034"/> gether, it was a bit of harmony equal to the Italian opera <emph>behind the scenes.</emph>
               </p>
               <p>On went the "browns," leaving huge spaces behind them at every jump. Another instant we had passed the spur of a hill, which hid our view, and the whole wide table-land was disclosed. Then <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>I KNEW by the smoke that so gracefully curl'd</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Round that swift locomotive, the cars were afar;</l>
                        <l>And I said, If there's peace to be found in this world,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Poor AURORA and I can but hope for it <emph>thar.</emph>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Aurora laughed outright at our ludicrous position, and the next moment was crying as heartily. Jehu looked at our departing bourne, blank and dollarless, and I had my hands full in attempting to pull up the "browns," who seemed wild with excitement: and when at last I stopped them, although covered with foam, and the blood rushing through their veins as if worked by a steam-engine, they pricked up their ears and pawed the ground, still anxious to try their mettle against that of the iron horse; but they had to say "fail," and turn back toward their home, while ours and our dinner grew colder and more distant at each step.</p>
               <p>Where Whitlockville <emph>is</emph> I don't know: whether it is at all, has never been settled in my geography; and we then felt equally indifferent whether it was a church, a tavern, and dwellings, or only four planks and a crossroad. Not so, however, with regard to the horses: they had made a splendid run of some sixteen or seventeen miles in eighty minutes; over a road, too, which made our carriage resemble twenty-four of "Halsted's dyspeptic chairs" rolled into one. It might cost them their lives; and we had nothing to rub them down with, but cobble-stones or a fence-rail. To let them stand was dangerous; watering or feeding out of the question; so we cast a sad, lingering look at the smoke hanging on the horizon, and slowly on a gentle walk turned back toward Peekskill.</p>
               <p>We had done all we could, and felt disposed to pass the night together without vain regret, because it had pleased Mercury and the "browns" to keep us from our separate homes in town. Beside, who can resist the influence of a June twilight in the country? Certainly not lovers; so our five minutes too late, home, and all our mishaps, were forgotten, or at least not spoken of.</p>
               <pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC6162-00000035"/>
               <p>The fragrance from the fields, the gentle breeze, the warm rays of the setting sun, stole over and about us, and lent their influence to calm our hearts and thoughts: while the repose of all around, even the geese without a hiss, and the four-footed <foreign xml:lang="FRA">mère de famille</foreign> sleeping at the road-side, tended to subdue our feelings from the restlessness of the late excitement, and make us enjoy the luxury of the passing hour. Beside, drivers differ from boatmen in the fact that they drive without facing their fares: and Jehu, with an intense abstraction that did him honor, kept his eyes and attention fixed on his colored companions in harness. Poor things! the traces of grief were in his eyes—the grief of traces in theirs; but I wiped them from one with the unearned fee, and as for the others, they were walking toward home at a two-mile-an-hour gait, to them doubtless very satisfactory: equally so to Aurora and myself; for the sun, shining directly in our faces from above the distant western hills, made it <emph>absolutely</emph> necessary to draw down the curtain between Jehu and ourselves, and we were quite alone.</p>
               <p>The sun at last sank behind the mountain peaks, but the curtain was forgotten. Gradually the stars came forth, and sprinkled the carpet of heaven with diamonds, hinting to the soul of the glory above, and making it long to join the angels in their abode of love and holiness. Gradually the twilight deepened into night; trees stretched out their arms as if they were weird spirits, and living things seemed to be whispering near in every rustle of a leaf, as the branches were swayed by the gentle breeze. Here stood a bleached and leafless tree, with its branches pointing toward heaven, as if it still dared the lightning which had scathed it; there a vista opened in the forest, to which the dim star-light only lent vastness and awe, and in which the imagination conjured up shapes which might rival Circe and her crew. No word passed between Aurora and myself; words would have marred that eloquence of silence, that delicious revery. But my hand pressed hers; my arm stole round her fair form; gently I drew her toward me, and gently her beautiful head rested upon my breast. The pulse beat no faster; the heart's blood under her head moved on in the even tenor of its way: but oh, what a depth of<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC6162-00000036"/> tenderness was there! It seemed as if life had been an unreal dream, and that I had awakened and stood face to face with the Infinite of Feeling. The past, with its loves and passions, which had seemed, as they occurred, to absorb my being, shrank into insignificance; the past, with all its suffering, was for given; the past, with all its disappointments, was forgotten, and the future unthought of. I thought I had loved Aurora before; now I knew it, and felt it in every fiber of my being; while "the heart, enlarged by its new sympathy with one, grew bountiful to all." Yet I had no distinct idea of all this, or of what I could do, dare, or suffer for her. It seemed as if our souls were but one, that there was no separate existence; and in the midst of this delicious dream, the lines passed through my mind: "Eye hath not seen, nor ear heard, neither have entered into the heart of man the things which GOD hath prepared for them that love HIM;" and yet, Heaven help us! we sin on and lose it all.</p>
               <p>It is a most beautiful characteristic of love, that the deeper, the more absorbing or profound it becomes, the more mere passion shrinks into the background ground: and yet all love between the sexes is founded in it. This fact has probably led to so many theories of "Platonic" love. Love bears the same relation to passion that flowers do to the earth: they spring from it, root themselves in it; but oh! how far separated from it are their beauty and perfume, and how soon are these lost if they are covered with the soil, or even planted too deeply in it! This passion-basis may exist without the absorbed lover's consciousness—less so as his affection is broader, deeper, holier; but still it rests there, a substratum on which the fair fabric is built, and its sweetest, most beautiful, or, if you please, <hi rend="i"/>Platonic form resembles the garden, <emph>where the flowers (of affection and sentiment) spring up in such luxuriance that they hide t'e earth in which they grow.</emph>
               </p>
               <p>The lights in Peekskill were twinkling in the distance; we had nearly approached the end of our ride. Aurora's head still occupied the same pillow, and her breathing was so regular that I thought she slept; but as we passed the lighted window of a cottage, I moved her gently, and her eyes were turned up toward mine with a look of such earnest<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC6162-00000037"/> depth, that I knew she had thought and felt with me during all that two hours of eloquent silence. I pressed her to my heart and whispered, "Mine, mine forever! HE before whom we are alone, and with whom we have been communing, be our witness!" And the tears fell from her eyes as she hid her face on my breast again.</p>
               <p>The carriage stopped at the hotel. After waiting a moment, I lifted the curtains. Poor Jehu! he was fast asleep on the box. The horses had taken their own time and road to reach home, and they had been nearly five hours about it, for the clock was striking ten. We had been fasting fifteen hours, and having awakened to a "realizing sense" of the wants which flesh is heir to, the half hour which it required to broil a chicken seemed interminable. At last supper was ready and dispatched, and I handed Aurora to the carriage again to drive down to the river. The sky in the mean time had become nearly hidden with clouds, and all was dark, dark: and as we began to descend that steep hill which overlooks the entrance to the Highlands, and Aurora saw the dark sky, the outlines of the darker mountains about us, and the still darker river flowing below, which seemed to realize the poet's suggestion, "in that lowest depth a lower deep," she trembled, and asked me where I was taking her, saying it seemed like the place she had so often dreamed of, where bad spirits go in blank, black despair.</p>
               <p>"Pandemonium with the fire put out," I suggested; and with a lecture for making light of so dark a subject, we reached the wharf. A boat was in waiting, and we were soon rowed out into the stream toward Caldwell's Landing. But Aurora's annoyances were not over yet. We had reached the middle of the river, when we saw one of the largest steamers dashing on its way in the darkness toward Albany; and Aurora, a little unnerved by the day's excitement, became suddenly frightened and uncontrollable, clinging to me and crying convulsively. No wonder, indeed; for there are few things more fearful than one of these steamers at night, with the lights dancing about her, the fire falling from the grates into the water, the roar of her furnaces, the dash and spray of her wheels, when one is in a rowboat, without knowing but that the next moment she<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC6162-00000038"/> may be upon you. No wonder, when the Indians first saw one, that they thought the Fiend had been let loose. But she passed on, and we resumed our way; landed at Caldwell's; went up to the hotel; were shown into the little old-fashioned parlor; sat down on two high-backed chairs; and in five minutes, bolt upright, were fast asleep.</p>
               <p>The last word of the katy-did had been spoken; the last wakeful cricket was still; every leaf rested on its native branch, as if it were carved there; no breeze nor zephyr stirred grass-blade or flower; the steam pump at Kidd's coffer-dam was quiet, and quietly the tide flowed in whence it had been pumped with such noisy labor all the long day; the current of the river stole by without a ripple; the old man waiting for the Albany boat nodded over his lantern on the distant wharf; and the stars sent their gentle glimmers through our casement, where there was no other light. Yet there we slept. A loving breast; a beautiful head, willing to be pillowed on it; lips that might make one forget eternity, and willing to be pressed; a waist whose outline the Graces might have envied; an arm that might encircle circle it unforbidden; yet there, in that witching hour of night and loneliness, we still slept on.</p>
               <p>"The boat's a comin', Mister."</p>
               <p>We started from our perpendicular couches, for a moment unconscious of our whereabouts: then Aurora blushed, but the next moment her silver laugh rang out with a gush of melody sweeter than The Lind's magic" "Ah! non giunge."</p>
               <p>"All aboard! all ashore!" and again we were moving toward home. But alas! well we knew that the spirit of that dinner had departed, and nothing but its bones remained.</p>
               <p>I secured a state-room for Aurora, and then took possession of my own berth, too stupid and tired to be equal to the task of removing boots or coat, and in a moment was asleep again.</p>
               <p>"Are you the gentleman I am looking for?"</p>
               <p>"Certainly! what is it?" said I, springing up.</p>
               <p>"A lady on deck wants you."</p>
               <pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC6162-00000039"/>
               <p>I hastened from the cabin, and found that we had arrived at New York. Aurora was waiting impatiently for me. In a few minutes we were driving up Broadway. Not even a late reveler was abroad; the last omnibus had gone to its short-lived rest; the city seemed deserted, dead. As we approached the house, lights were visible from the drawing-room, from the basement, from the upper windows: perhaps, after all, they were waiting dinner for us. In another minute we had rattled up to the door, which the mother opened as Aurora stepped from the carriage and sprang into her arms. While they were sobbing out their explanations, I passed on to the drawing-room, where the father was standing, stern, fixed, and silent; but that look was as eloquent as though it had been spoken in thunder, "Now, Sir, explain what is the meaning of all this?" And as concisely as I could, I related what had occurred, and the efforts I had made to reach home; and imagining the best time to leave would be when he found his darling restored safe and uninjured, and that he had not been played the fool with, I bowed and withdrew. He kept his eye on me to the last, but there was not a change of muscle in that rigid face—no word from the compressed lip. I pressed Aurora's hand as I passed out, and left the house: and so ended my day in the Highlands.</p>
               <p>"Is that all?"</p>
               <p>Yes, that is all: we <emph>lost</emph> our dinner.</p>
               <p>"But——"</p>
               <p>Ah, yes, my fair reader, I understand. Raise your eyes from what I am writing, and tell me what you see.</p>
               <p>"Why, a lady with a lap full of caps and lace and things, and a sweet Grecian face, as pure and smooth as if it had been cut from marble, and never ruffled by a care; and, oh! what a mass of dark silken hair is folded about it as gracefully and naturally as if it had bent to its place like the petals of a flower, without comb or brush. But she looks down at her work with an absorbing earnestness, as if she loved her lace and——</p>
               <pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC6162-00000040"/>
               <p>That will do; it is Aurora. Look again.</p>
               <p>"Oh, dear me! it's not caps and things; it moves; it's a real live baby, and it shakes its tiny head and puts up its little hand to pull away the things which have dropped on it, and smiles as it looks up to its mother's face, as if it had just left heaven to have its worth proved by an earthly trial, and did not know but that it was still <emph>at home.</emph>"</p>
               <p>That is "Aurora" also. Would you lose a dinner for such a one? I do not think Aurora would part with it for two dinners.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>CHARLOTTE MAY.</head>
               <pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC6162-00000041"/>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Charlotte May.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <lg type="quotation">
                           <l>"We are such stuff as dreams are made of.</l>
                           <l>And our little lives are rounded with a sleep."</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>"MOTHER," said Lottie May, "my head aches, and feels very, very warm. What can be the matter?"</p>
                  <p>"You are feverish, love, and require rest."</p>
                  <p>So Mrs. May gave her child some herb-tea, and placed her in her little bed.</p>
                  <p>In the night, the mother was awakened by a groan, and lay and listened half unconsciously for a few moments; then she heard the groan again.</p>
                  <p>"It's Lottie," she said to herself; and springing softly from her bed, for fear of disturbing the child, she stepped to the side of its bed and whispered:</p>
                  <p>"Lottie!"</p>
                  <pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC6162-00000042"/>
                  <p>"Is that you, mother?"</p>
                  <p>"What's the matter, Lottie?"</p>
                  <p>"My head hurts me a little, mother." Then she groaned again as she clasped her hot hands over her soft brown hair. "Will you give me some water, mother?"</p>
                  <p>Mrs. May's hand trembled so that she could hardly pour out the water; but Lottie could not lift herself up to drink it, and the mother held her; then she lit the gas.</p>
                  <p>"My GOD!" she exclaimed to herself, as she saw the red and purple cheeks, the large dark eyes, now larger than ever, and blood-shot; the vacant, wild look, and the little hands clasped tightly on the top of her head.</p>
                  <p>"Lottie! Lottie! Charlotte!" said Mrs. May; but Lottie did not answer for some moments; then she opened her eyes suddenly, more widely than ever, and said:</p>
                  <p>"Oh, mother! I've seen an angel, and its face was like yours; and there were two great wings, and glory all round it, mother; and it called, Lottie, Lottie, Lottie!"</p>
                  <p>Mrs. May trembled again, but she did not show it, or change her countenance before her child.</p>
                  <p>She rang the bell for her maid, and told her to call John, and send him for Dr. Mason immediately; then she bathed the little sufferer in cold water, and laid her on the bed again until the Doctor came.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC6162-00000043"/>
                  <p>"WHEN was she taken, Mrs. May?" said Dr. Mason.</p>
                  <p>"She went to bed feverish; I was awakened an hour ago by the child's groans, and found her so."</p>
                  <p>"What have you done?"</p>
                  <p>"Bathed her in cold water; that is all."</p>
                  <p>"All wrong," said the Doctor: and he felt her pulse, gave her some calomel, told Mrs. May to keep her very warm, and the windows closed, and went home again, wondering why people would get sick at night—he did so hate night-practice; or if they must be sick, why could they not wait until morning to be treated.</p>
                  <p>Lottie lay in an unquiet doze, and Mrs. May sat by her side all the long night. Oh, how her heart yearned for her child!—and she prayed silently that the flower might not be gathered from her: indeed, she never knew how much she loved her little idol until now, when the shadow of Death loomed up like a black cloud on the horizon of her imagination tion, at which she looked with sickening anxiety. Would it bring thunder, and lightning, and destruction, or pass on with but a genial shower, leaving fresh greenness and life in its path? Was it the <emph>shadow</emph> of Death, or did the all-devouring tyrant himself hover near? And she grasped the child's hand, as she thought of the angel's calling, "Lottie, Lottie, Lottie," as if she would so keep Heaven from taking away her treasure; and in the long night-watches it recurred again and again; and each time her heart ceased to beat; a feeling of dread and awe overpowered her; and a tremor passed over her frame like the feeling from sudden fright in the darkness: yet, apart from her child, there was no fear in that mother's heart; she felt that she could part with life itself to save her little one.</p>
                  <p>At last the long, weary, desolate night had gone, and the sun shone into the room fitfully as the clouds passed over it.</p>
                  <p>Lottie opened her eyes, and looked up at her mother, and at the sunshine, and put her arms round her mother's neck, and said, in a low, weak, gentle voice:</p>
                  <pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC6162-00000044"/>
                  <p>"What's the matter, mother? You look so sick! I'm not ill now, mother; my headache's gone." Then she looked up at the sun again, and said: "Mother, I'll get up now." The mother's heart beat wildly with hope as she spoke, but the child could not move.</p>
                  <p>"But, mother, I'm better, a great deal better; I'm only a little sick. Kiss me, mother. I saw you by my bed last night, but could n't speak then."</p>
                  <p>She breathed harder from the effort she had made, and lay perfectly still, except her large eyes, which followed every movement of her mother about the room.</p>
                  <p>Then Dr. Jones came, and shrugged his shoulders at what had been done, though he declined interfering; but Mrs. May insisted, and called in old Dr. Armour, the friend of her father's youth also; and the three doctors met and "consulted" about the poor girl.</p>
                  <p>And Lottie was sometimes worse, and at others better; and at times she knew no one, not even her poor mother. It almost broke her heart to see the child stare at her so vacantly, and say such strange things. Then her eyes would change, and she would look up in her mother's face and smile, and be again her own dear Lottie.</p>
                  <p>In this manner two solemn, sad, and weary days of hope deferred passed away, and Lottie grew weaker and weaker.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC6162-00000045"/>
                  <p>MRS. MAY sat by the side of her sleeping child hour after hour, and gazed at the shrunken hands and rough crimson cheeks, and listened to her deep breathing, every breath of which seemed like a groan. Oh, how freely would she have given her life to bring back the hue of health to those fevered cheeks! She took up her embroidery, to try and while away an hour of this torturing uncertainty; but the needle trembled in her hand, for the work itself was a seat for Lottie's little chair; she could not make a stitch. Then she took up her favorite author, but the letters seemed blurred; she could not distinguish a word. Then she tried to write, but the tears fell and mixed with the ink—emblem of her fast-coming black despair. Then she knelt by the couch of her child to pray, but she could not; her prayers were the "groanings which can not be uttered;" and she arose and went to the window, and looked up toward the sun, but there were clouds over the sky: it seemed as if there were clouds over the sunshine always now. In the street she saw Dr. Jones' and Dr. Mason's gigs approaching; but she left the room, for she began to lose faith in them, and went into the garden, where there was more air to breathe; she sometimes thought she would choke in the rooms, they seemed so small.</p>
                  <p>When she came back, Dr. Armour was there also.</p>
                  <p>"Dr. Armour," said Mrs. May, with an appealing yet firm look, "will my child die?"</p>
                  <p>"Heaven grant she may not!"</p>
                  <p>"Doctor, I have steeled my heart to bear even her death. <emph>Will my child die?</emph>" And her look became more firm and grave, but she held her hand tightly over her heart.</p>
                  <p>"I am not omniscient, Madam: your own feelings probably tell you as much as all my science can. <emph>I fear the worst.</emph>"</p>
                  <p>Mrs. May rose to her feet with a fixed and vacant stare, and moved slowly forward through the rooms. She had never yet in her heart thought that her child would die: woman-like, she had hoped against hope. For a moment she looked round vacantly;<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC6162-00000046"/> all the scenes of those three days of torture crowded to her brain: the blood-shot eyes, the red, furred cheeks, the breathing a succession of groans, the Doctor's words, his look; and then like a flash of lightning through her brain passed the words, "Lottie must die!" and she uttered a piercing scream, and fell senseless on the floor.</p>
                  <p>When she came to herself, she was on her bed, and Dr. Armour standing by her. Recollection returned, and she said, with an unnatural calmness which startled him:</p>
                  <p>"Doctor, is my child dead?"</p>
                  <p>"Not yet. But do not rise, Madam: you are too weak."</p>
                  <p>Mrs. May looked at him with a surprised look; then rose and went to her child's bedside. Lottie knew her mother; and when Mrs. May took her hand, she felt it pulled slightly, and bent down her head until her lips touched those of her child, and she felt them move a little to kiss her; then she tried to speak, but could not; and the mother stood by the side of the bed, with glazed eyes, in which were no tears, for she could not weep. Oh! how she wanted to weep, but could not, and her eyes burned her as she gazed at the dying girl!</p>
                  <p>The doctors stood round her in silence, for they knew that she was dying; the mother bent over her in silence, for she felt that she was dying; and the child gasped, and gasped, and a slight gurgle was heard in her throat, and she lifted her head suddenly, and said, with a faint voice, "Mother!" and fell back on the pillow, quite dead.</p>
                  <p>"GOD of mercy, help me to bear this!" said Mrs. May. "ALMIGHTY FATHER, help me to bear this!" and she fell on her knees and clasped her hands in agony.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC6162-00000047"/>
                  <p>THE doctors slowly and silently left the room, and went down stairs, and they stepped into the parlor to have a chat before they separated.</p>
                  <p>Mrs. May started suddenly from her kneeling position, and looked earnestly at her child, the last hope of her heart, the last link that bound her to the earth; and she hurriedly felt her feet, hands, heart, and put her ear down to the still, silent lips, then glided swiftly and noiselessly down stairs to the back parlor, where the folding-doors were ajar.</p>
                  <p>".  .  .  Lower down; the breathing showed that. I was afraid we were to be kept up all night."</p>
                  <p>"I think you gave her too much calomel, Mason."</p>
                  <p>"Not a bit, not a bit: she should have had more yesterday, instead of your arsenic."</p>
                  <p>"Well, well. Curious case."</p>
                  <p>"Very."</p>
                  <p>"Gentlemen," said the old gray-headed Dr. Armour, who had wept at the death-bed, and had not spoken before; "gentlemen, it is unprofessional for me to say so, and late in life to acknowledge it, but this is all wrong somewhere. The child should not have died, and I must..."</p>
                  <p>Mrs. May had been checked by the tone of indifference, almost of levity, of the first speakers; now she threw open the doors, and stood there, drawn to her full height, and with her earnest eyes dilating, with a look that made them shrink as if they had seen a specter: but she only said:</p>
                  <p>"Heaven help ye, gentlemen, in your extreme need. Dr. Armour, for GOD'S sake, come back and tell me if the child is dead!"</p>
                  <p>They returned, but the corpse was growing cold.</p>
                  <p>Mrs. May clasped her hands round its neck, bent her head over its face, tear after tear rolled down her cheeks, and there she sat through the long night, clinging to the garment that had held her Lottie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC6162-00000048"/>
                  <p>MRS. MAY sat by the little coffin that contained her child's form. She had grown much older in the two long, weary, solemn days that Lottie had been dead. She could look at the death-sleep, and the little hands crossed on the bosom, and the closed lids over those dark, expressive eyes, and place fresh roses, and geraniums, and heliotrope about the calm, life-like corpse, without weeping now; but there was a deep, fixed, almost stern expression of grief on her pale, classic face, which seemed to ask no sympathy, and was feeding on the springs of her own life. She could not pray yet. Often had she fallen on her knees since the little one's last faint cry of "Mother!" but no utterance followed, for her heart only asked in agony, why HE had taken away her Lottie. And thoughts high and deep passed through her mind, of time and space, and heaven and immortality, until imagination had wandered and lost itself in the dim confines which separate thought from the impenetrable mysteries which surround us, until all consciousness of time and space in her present life was lost; and then the question would recur, <emph>did</emph> HE take her away, or was she sent, uncalled from the earth, by unholy errors, by poisoning drugs? and she shrank from the question shuddering.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC6162-00000049"/>
                  <p>CARRIAGE after carriage drove up to the door, rooms were filled with friends and acquaintances of the mourner and the mourned, and a solemn-looking man opened the Bible, and read, "Suffer little children to come unto me, and forbid them not, for of such is the kingdom of heaven!" Then he said many beautiful things about the child, which he had known from its birth; but Mrs. May could not listen, and, sobbing out her anguish, left the room, for <emph>why</emph> had HE taken away her Lottie? After the ceremony was over, she returned, and stood by the coffin, and looked at her child for the last time. She thought of all her grace and repose, even among her little play-mates, and all her arch and winning ways, and hot tears fell on the cold form. Then they closed the coffin, and placed it in the carriage with Mrs. May alone; she would have it so. They drove slowly down Broadway, and Mrs. May was startled by the noise of carts and omnibuses. It seemed strange that they drove on so furiously while Lottie was carried by; and crowds of people lined the streets, all gay and unheeding. Mrs. May drew down the curtains, and hid them from her sight. They passed over the South Ferry, and so on to Greenwood; and between the beautiful sculptures and white monuments (standing over buried hopes, like the rainbow over the abyss of the cataract, or the fair face over a crushed heart), until they came to Lottie's grave. It was a sweet spot, on the southern side of a gentle rise that overlooked the Bay and Narrows, and caught the first smile of Day, as he rose from the horizon and bathed himself in light; and the last rays of the sun rested on its bosom, while the twilight lingered there when darkness had hidden all below. Lottie had often played on it, and told her mother which was <emph>her corner.</emph> Poor child! she little thought how soon she would take possession; indeed, she always said it with as happy a smile as if she had been immortal, and would never need an earthly resting-place.</p>
                  <p>Mrs. May remained in the carriage, and when<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC6162-00000050"/> they took the coffin toward the grave, there was again that fixed and glassy look, those tearless eyes. How she longed to keep even the corpse forever near her!</p>
                  <p>They lowered the little coffin into the grave, and, as the earth fell on the lid, said, "Dust to dust, ashes to ashes!" and a little mound marked the place where, down, down in the earth, the fair-haired girl awaited the final reckoning.</p>
                  <p>They came to Mrs. May as they passed out, but she waved them away, and one after another left, until she was quite alone. Then she descended from the carriage, and went to the grave; and the servant brought a basket of flowers, and wept as he retired, for they all loved Lottie; and Mrs. May bent over the grave, and scattered flowers about it, she felt so wholly desolate, now that they had taken away the last link, the body of her poor child. The sun went down, and the night came on, as she knelt there. Tree and leaf and insect, all were hushed as still as the grave beneath her; and she looked up to the heavens, and saw the stars, like tapers on the pall of darkness which shrouded her, and she gazed and gazed, and her heart longed for a revelation of her child's fate and her own in that mysterious sphere, and her heart was softened as she gazed. Then she bent over the grave again, and took a little flower and put it in her bosom, and thought of her child and its last faint "Mother!" and the tears came to her eyes, her bursting heart found vent, and she wept, oh, how long and passionately, as if existence itself were welling from her eyelids! Then she looked up again, and the sky seemed to have lost its darkness; and the stars dilated, and scemed to fill the heavens with glory; and her spirit became more rapt and exalted, as if spiritual influences were about her with which she could commune; and her lips were opened at last. She prayed long and earnestly to the FATHER who had taken her idol. She felt now too truly that it had been an <emph>idol,</emph> and she blessed HIS holy name, and knew <emph>why</emph> HE had taken her Lottie. Her mind became more exalted; a transcendent exaltation took possession of her soul, and it scemed to expand super-sensually, until it lost sight of earth and its earthly tenement, and rose to the feeling, the <emph>consciousness of the</emph> INFINITE. She<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC6162-00000051"/> seemed to have a dual existence, a being separate from her being; and looked down on herself, as she knelt at the grave, with an <emph>infinite pity.</emph> (Whether under the direct influence of the "inspiration of heaven," or the native powers of her soul drawn from their slumbers by surrounding circumstances, who shall tell?) And her soul expanded in its exaltation, until she felt herself a link between the Fountain of Holiness and the great Soul of Humanity; and while a feeling of deep love and pity for mankind took possession of her soul, their errors and weaknesses shrank into the back-ground; even her own sorrows became vague, undefined, distant, almost little.</p>
                  <p>This consciousness, this exaltation, vouchsafed to the best of us so rarely, from the low or groveling forever barred, may come sometimes perhaps to a mother at the birth of her first-born, oftener at its death. A revelation to great minds at the moment of their best conceptions; to others, at the moment of death, or when death suddenly becomes imminent and near, and fear does not paralyze the soul. Sometimes it comes with the fervid devotion of the worshiper shiper, filled with a holy and living faith; seldom, if ever, in mere religious ecstasy; this, the flash of the torch, soon out and lost; that, like the June sunshine, lighting all things, and drawing them from the earth to warmth and life. But it comes to none without leaving him better, wiser, stronger to endure and bear, and with deeper sympathies for the sufferings and errors of his kind.</p>
                  <p>Mrs. May knelt there, wrapped in her new existence, hour after hour, far into the night, until her servants were alarmed, and they came and accosted her; but she answered them calmly, and left the grave with a blessed peace in her heart; and they drove over the lonely road, and through the quiet and deserted streets, toward her desolate home, a sad, but a wiser, a better being; for her soul had known the <emph>divine</emph> depth, her heart had become the <emph>sanctuary</emph> of sorrow. GOD had taken away her loved ones for a time, but HE had given HIS own love in their place, and she wept no more.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC6162-00000052"/>
               <head>THE ADMIRALTY PAPERS.</head>
               <pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC6162-00000053"/>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Admiralty Papers.</head>
                  <p>"ALL aboard! All ashore! Throw off the bo'line! Haul in the plank! Quick there!" cried Captain A——, of the steamer S——. The short, sharp ring of the engine-bell was heard as the last words were uttered, while the noisy sailors, chattering and exclaiming in their odd Franco-Canadian <foreign xml:lang="FRA">patois;</foreign> rushed frantically about, as if their lives depended on noise and hurry. Horses were pawing on the quarter deck; pigs were squeaking; Irish, French, and English emigrants were running rapidly about, looking for lost luggage, lost wives, lost children, and amid all the confusion the engine heaved and groaned, as if a huge giant were confined at his labor there. The wheels moved round. The mass of wood and<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC6162-00000054"/> iron suddenly became as a thing of life and will, and in a few minutes the crowd, which had come to gaze or say farewell, and finally the city itself, were lost to view.</p>
                  <p>As the boat went on, the loud confusion gradually became order. Sailors clustered in groups and told of hairbreadth 'scapes by flood and—town. Immigrants who had not realized their golden dreams about this hemisphere were cursing it for their misfortunes or stupidity, and returning to their native land. The cabin-passengers were chatting in small groups, walking up and down the deck in the balmy air of a June twilight, or smoking on the forward deck, amid the sailors, horses, immigrants, and freight, with which that deck was nearly filled.</p>
                  <p>The night wore on. The moon, like an anxious mother, looked from time to time, between the cloud-curtains which hung over our couches, to see if her little ones rested well; and the stars sent their far-away good-night smiles. Then the cloud-curtains were drawn together, and all was dark.</p>
                  <p>Gradually the throng was lessened; and when the moon finally hid her fair face, only a few couples were left among the ghosts of chairs which held out their bodiless arms on the forsaken deck. As the whispered love-tale ended, or the last thought was shared, couple after couple disappeared, and I was left alone; but to a loneliness which was more society than the unsympathizing faces of a strange crowd. I listened for a time to the heaving and groaning of the steam monster below, as he turned the great wheels; watched the dark waves as they rolled on, lit up occasionally by a lurid glare from the furnace into fantastic and weird shapes, and then, as memories which had become specters, and hopes without fruition crowded too painfully upon me, I shrank from the scene; found a place upon some bales where the watch-lantern hung, drew a book from my pocket, and read with the hope that another's thoughts might change the dark current of my own.</p>
                  <p>An hour passed; the words grew less and less distinct; the book fell from my hands, and I was lost in the unconsciousness of a dreamless sleep.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC6162-00000055"/>
                  <p>THE lamp went out as I lay there, hour after hour, far into the night, when I was startled into wakefulness by a crash, as if the master-bolt of a thunder-storm had struck the boat; then a loud, tearing, crushing, crackling sound, as if a whirlwind were breaking the vessel to pieces, and down, down, down, I felt the boat sink with me. That the boiler had burst, blown out the bottom of the steamer, and that we were going down instantly, became a clearly defined fact to my consciousness. I felt a deep, a profound sinking sensation at the heart; a thought of a few loved ones far away, and their sorrow at my death, glanced throught my brain; then, thought, feeling, consciousness, all centred in myself again, and my own position of inevitable death. I seemed suddenly to become, and the perception was clearly defined, two separate existences, one lying there to die, the other a spiritual one, hovering just over, and looking down with such deep yearning pity at itself, or its counterpart, whose race was run.</p>
                  <p>How often I have tried to look into eternity, to die without dying, to know how the immortal and mortal would feel as they were about to part forever; what the whispers of the soul are to the dying who know that they die; to the condemned who know their hour! This yearning, or curiosity, has possessed me since early boyhood, until, seeking and seeking, I have climbed tall masts, and held by a slender rope as the ship rolled me sheer over the fighting waves. Mounted tall chimneys, and stood upright upon their tops. Clambered bold precipices, and stood with feet half over the chasm, when the slip of an inch would have sent me down—to the other world. But it would not do; an atmosphere of safety seemed to environ me, and Death kept in the background, and would not show his face, nor tell what are his monitions and first words to his chosen ones, when he embraces them. Now the experience had come, and it was no pleasant one; but, on the other hand, not very terrifying. It was curious, strange, and certainly<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC6162-00000056"/> differed from all that I had read or imagined that it would be.</p>
                  <p>During the second or two which these feelings occupied, I had not risen, nor stirred from my place on the bales. Now my eyes only moved; first looking toward the bow, then toward the stern—no fire, no steam, nothing appeared in the darkness, and I felt the boat checked in her sinking. Starting from my bale-bed. I ran forward, guided by the twinkling light of a watch-lantern hanging overhead, and there a scene presented itself, ludicrous, wild, and mysterious: horses kicking and jumping frantically; women and children screaming; Canadian sailors, more timid than children, crying, weeping, and embracing each other; boards, beams, and bulwarks broken and crushed, and freight scattered about or heaped up in wild confusion; but <emph>no cause,</emph> that I could see, for all the uproar. I asked and asked, but the Franco-Canadian gibberish was as intelligible as the chattering of a convention of monkeys. I climbed over the wreck of matter to the side, and looked, but all was dark; no star was visible, no dim light showed even the outline of a cloud—to the other side, but the same blackness of darkness only was visible.</p>
                  <p>Hastening back again through the length of the boat, I found that the deck had in the mean time become crowded with human beings of all sexes, all sizes, and in all possible toilets, except a complete one. Dressing-gowns, night-gowns, pants, shirts, anything that in their terror they could catch at as they rushed to the deck, and most of them shouting, screaming, crying, or running about in the wildest confusion, calling upon GOD and man to save them from they knew not what, to take them they knew not where. I pushed my way through the agitated mass, and, reaching the after-gangway, all was revealed at a glance.</p>
                  <p>In the middle of Lake St. Peter we had come into collision with another great steamer of over a thousand tons burthen, crushed in her bows, and there she lay some fifty yards away, her decks crowded with people; the faint outline of whose moving forms could be seen in the darkness, and the boat was so rapidly sinking, that her guards were already in the water. Trembling with excitement<pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC6162-00000057"/> ment and terror at the impending fate of so many human beings, I pressed through the surging crowd to the rail, and there lay a large Canadian <foreign xml:lang="FRA">bateau</foreign> from the other steamer, close under our guards.</p>
                  <p>Five miscreants, whom fear had made cowards, and who had forgotten that they were men, at the first hint of danger had sprung into this <foreign xml:lang="FRA">bateau,</foreign> which would have carried fifty persons safely, cut the rope, which held her to the sinking steamer, and, notwithstanding the cries, shouts, and curses which followed them, had paddled away from their companions and reached our boat at the moment I forced my passage to the gangway. There the excitement was intense; how could it well be otherwise, when hundreds were dying, as it were, within our very grasp? Two of the noble five had already sprung up on the guards, and were upon the deck; the others were forced back into the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">bateau,</foreign> as they attempted to climb, and with curses ringing in their ears, and threats that the water under them should be their grave if they refused, were forced off toward their sinking fellow-passengers.</p>
                  <p>Hark! the engine bell rings; the wheels move round; we will save them yet. How is this? The wheels move in the wrong direction. The white waves dash out toward the stern. We are going, but from them, alas! Quick as light, the thought flashed upon me—we are sinking also! I glanced through the cabin deck-lights; it was too true—the cabin-floor was already covered with water.</p>
                  <p>They, too, on the decks, saw that we moved, and not toward their huge coffin-boat, which death was lowering into the grave. Around them were the waves; no stars were visible, and "darkness was upon the face of the deep." And there went up from those wretches, who in a few minutes must meet an Almighty whom they had worshiped or denied—perhaps curses, shouts, cries, screams; but they came to us in no such shape; for, mixed together as they rose, the air was filled with one long, loud, deep-echoing, and unutterably awful <emph>deathwail.</emph> Losing sight of personal danger for the time, I went to the other side of the cabin and placed my hands over my ears, to shut out the sickening sound, and tried to close my soul to the contemplation of all the awful images which imagination created;<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC6162-00000058"/> but they would not keep away. Babes clinging to mothers struggling in the waves; old men going down with the death-gurgle in their throats; women shrill shrieking as the last wave went over them; the fierce encounter between those whom danger had made fiends for some final hope—a board, a bench, a chair—the death-grip as they sank and died together. All this, and the crowding thoughts which flash on and light up the distracted soul at such a time, and which few can conceive who have not lived through similar scenes, filled my mind as though it were a many-sided glass, and on the instant mirrored all things. Gradually the sounds grew less and less in the distance, fainter and fainter, as we fled for life, and the last lingering far-away echo, as it died on the still air, seemed strangely like the sad complaining tune of an Æolian harp. Then it was hushed, ended, and they were left alone with the darkness, their sinking vessel, and their GOD.</p>
                  <p>"Now came the fearful cries—"The pumps! the pumps!" "Throw overboard the freight!" and with good-will were they responded to. Bales, boxes, packages, and barrels were soon darkening our wake, and in a few minutes the deck was cleared of every movable thing, except pieces of board and other light materials, which would help us to float a little longer in the last extremity; for there were no life-preservers on board, and the two small boats would hardly hold a tenth of those who were perhaps awaiting their doom. The pumping with handpumps was as a drop in the ocean. But the loss of the deck-load had sensibly decreased our sinking speed. Still, by this time the cabin was half filled with water; and chairs, sofas, and tables, with lighted candles upon them, floated flat upon its surface.</p>
                  <p>The engines worked slower and slower. The people at the pumps crowded the forward deck. The rest of the passengers were moving about, restless, nervous, anxious, and, for the most part, silent, when suddenly cries were heard from below. Those about, crowded to the skylight, and there were a bald head, a pair of shoulders, and a pair of arms visible, while the person to whom they belonged was waddling, splashing, dashing through the water, toward the cabin stairs, and crying at the top of his voice:</p>
                  <p>"Capting! the boat 's a sinkin'!"</p>
                  <pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC6162-00000059"/>
                  <p>These should have been fearful words to all those whose lives were depending on the result; but I doubt if there were any there frightened enough not to laugh, or at least smile. It was a fat gentleman, who, the evening before, had been one of the merriest of the gay, and the uproar of our accident had had no effect upon his slumbers, which were not disturbed until the cold water reached his berth; then he sprang out, and, in a loud and most sepulchral voice, gave us the information above. Soon he emerged from below, his single garment clinging to his fat sides, and cried:</p>
                  <p>"What are you all about? The boat's a sinkin!"</p>
                  <p>We calmed the fat gentleman's fears, and suggested that he had made a somewhat hasty toilet; but it was too late to call boots, pants, or coat from that "vasty deep." One, however, lent him a pair of stockings, and another a shawl and handkerchief, of which he made an extempore coat and hat, and so remained upon the cold, wet deck; but, notwithstanding, his fun soon came again, and he succeeded in making some forget that their fellows were drowning a few miles away, and that we might, even then, be gliding over our own graves.</p>
                  <p>In the engine-room the scene was a busy one. They were crowding the furnaces with pitch pine, broken barrels, and any inflammable substances which they could collect, raising the steam to the last point of safety; and the frequent hissings, as the safety-valve opened, showed that they were even going beyond it. The engine labored fearfully; the wheels, deeper and deeper in the water, went more slowly, and seemed each minute as if they would end their weary labors forever.</p>
                  <p>"All right!" cried the Captain, who had been heaving the lead continuously; "all safe! We are in shallow water; go to the upper deck, and you will not even have your feet wet."</p>
                  <p>What a feeling of instant relief took possession of their hearts, and transformed them in an instant from a despairing, half-hopeless throng to a gay, laughing, merry, social company of friends! for every<pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC6162-00000060"/> one spoke to every one, and each had a joke or an experience to relate.</p>
                  <p>Still the engine labored on: the cabin was full of water; it covered the deck; we retreated to the promenade. The water reached the engine-room; slowly and gradually our speed lessened; faster and faster the boat settled in the water, which spirted and hissed as it entered the furnaces. A last effort, as if it were a sigh of relief that its work was done, and the engine stopped. The boat sank a few feet more, and then lay still, imbedded in the sand. But the promenade deck, with its crowd of the happy and the safe, was above the surface of the water.</p>
                  <p>The scene was strangely ludicrous; for the ladies' saloon on deck had been rifled of all its lace and damask hangings, its quilts, sheets, and blankets, and each person was enveloped in one or more of these extempore garments, looking, some like ghosts, and some like harlequins.</p>
                  <p>"A narrow escape, neighbor," said I to a sallow-faced man, with sandy whiskers, dressed in a light-colored corduroy coat, and generally with the appearance, as it struck me, of an English or Scotch emigrant farmer. I had recognized him as one of the three who had left the other boat, and their sinking companions in the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">bateau,</foreign> at the time of the accident. He was walking up and down the deck, seemingly in a very philosophical frame of mind. A short German pipe hung from his mouth, whence at short intervals little puffs of smoke issued, and curled round his brow on their way to the clouds. Perhaps, thought I, full of good-will to all the world at that moment—perhaps, if I heard his story, the act which seemed so cowardly and selfish may wear a different aspect. He was walking alone, for all seemed to shun him, so I stepped forward.</p>
                  <p>"A narrow escape, neighbor."</p>
                  <p>"Yes."</p>
                  <p>"May I trouble you for a light?"</p>
                  <p>"Yes."</p>
                  <pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC6162-00000061"/>
                  <p>"Thank you. You escaped from the other boat, did you not?"</p>
                  <p>"Yes."</p>
                  <p>"Saved your pipe, I see."</p>
                  <p>"Yes."</p>
                  <p>"Was it not possible to have brought off more of those people? Your <foreign xml:lang="FRA">bateau</foreign> seemed to me to be a very large one."</p>
                  <p>"I s'pose we could."</p>
                  <p>"Then why did you not?"</p>
                  <p>"Well, self-preservation's the first law of nature, you know. I feared they would jump in and swamp us. Do you think the steamer is lost? I had a wife and four children on board."</p>
                  <p>Saved his <emph>pipe,</emph> and left his <emph>wife and four children behind!</emph> Reader, did you ever walk on a country road, in the twilight, and see a snake coiled up on the dust before you, and where the next step would have brought your foot upon the wriggling mass? If you have, you can imagine my feelings, as I started back and seemed suddenly to shrink into about half the space I had occupied just before. My silence apparently induced him to go on, for I had certainly become a most orthodox listener; the only difficulty at that moment would have been to utter a word on any subject.</p>
                  <p>"But what is your opinion about it?" said he, with more emphasis; "indeed I should like to know. If she sinks, can't she be raised again? and if not, then the boxes, trunks, baggage, can't they be fished up or recovered in some way? For," and he brought his right fist down on his left palm, to give force to his words, "I have some Admiralty-papers on board, and they <emph>must</emph> be saved."</p>
                  <p>What could I answer to that? My answer was silence. I left him; and as he resumed his walk, with the puffs of tobacco-smoke curling gracefully round his red whiskers, pictures of a drowning woman and children, calling piteously and in vain for his help, filled my imagination with all their horror.</p>
                  <p>Observing that the Captain was manning one of our two small boats to return in search for the other steamer, I volunteered to take an oar.</p>
                  <pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC6162-00000062"/>
                  <p>The deck, lying close upon the surface of the water, and its living freight, were soon lost to view, as we left in the darkness, and rowed out upon the solemn, lonely, somber, cloud-curtained water. The Captain sat at the stern, silent, like the rest of us; the helm in one hand, a lantern in the other, and a pocket compass lay upon the seat at his side. On, on we rowed in the direction we had come. No star was visible; no beam from a lighthouse penetrated the murky atmosphere, and, except the measured dip of the oars, silence as well as darkness was upon the face of the deep; for the doubt seemed almost certainty that numbers of our fellow-beings had within the hour been buried in that water-cemetery, where no monumental marble would ever check the passerby, and recall to him the memory of those who, a little while before sleeping in peace, were now sleeping the sleep of death. On, on we rowed, but no sound was heard. On, on we pulled, but nothing loomed in the black distance to give us hope that Heaven had been merciful.</p>
                  <p>The Captain looked at his watch, at the compass, and peered into the dark, then shook his head, and changed our course. On, on we pulled in that direction; but no barrels, boxes, or pieces of a wreck were visible upon the waste of waters.</p>
                  <p>Again the Captain changed our course; again we bent to the oars; but, alas! the hope which had lent vigor to our arms had almost gone, and the thought was sickening that no one had been left of all that company to tell the tale of woe.</p>
                  <p>Again we changed our course; then began rowing in circles, increasing the size each time, as the compass indicated that we had made a circuit; and so two long, wearying, profitless hours passed on.</p>
                  <p>Suddenly the Captain sprang to his feet, looked out earnestly over the dark waves, cried, "A light ahead!" and again changed our course slightly. We bent to our oars with hearty good-will. Soon a dark mass, low upon the water, became visible, which, as we approached, individualized itself into human beings. They waved their only lantern, hailed us with a shout as we approached, and we answered with a cheer. We stopped at speaking distance, that we might learn the state of affairs, and also to avoid a<pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC6162-00000063"/> possible rush into our little boat, which would have swamped it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>THE D— was a larger and stronger steamer than our own, and stood higher from the water. To the latter fact we owed our comparative safety; for, striking under her guard, our bows crushed through her side, and the water came in with such force that it was with the utmost difficulty that the people who were in the cabin escaped to the deck, to which they rushed, tearing, crushing, screaming, and cursing, except a few, of whom he of the Admiralty-papers made one, who sprang from the cabin window to the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">bateau,</foreign> and so escaped. Another <foreign xml:lang="FRA">bateau</foreign> was upon the forward deck as freight; into this forty or fifty of the frightened throng crowded, and as the steamer sank from under it, floated off into the lake. Others rushed to the upper deck; some held by boxes, boards, bales, whatever would support them; others swam off into the darkness; others sank to rise no more, or for a few moments struggled upon the surface; and so, amid the cries, the screams, the agony, the life-struggle, the boat went down. Suddenly it stopped; the quick descent ceased; the terrified crowd stood trembling, hoping against hope. Yes, it was true; on some rock, sand-bank, or submerged island she was resting, and the deck a few inches above the water.</p>
                  <p>As the passengers became calm, cries and groans were heard from below. A hatchet was procured, but some insisted that the vessel floated in consequence of the confined air in the cabin, and wished the imprisoned ones to be left to their fate. Humanity, however, prevailed, and from holes cut in the deck, six women and two children were taken. They had climbed up on the berths, and were holding their heads against the ceiling, while their chins were in the water, which threatened every moment to become their grave. These had hardly been released when the vessel began to settle, lower, lower, lower. The water covered the deck, and the scene of terror and horror was again enacted; but she stayed her course, as the water rose to the<pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC6162-00000064"/> height of the chair-seats, thus remained, and thus we found them. All who could stand upon the chairs, or the seats which ran round the entire deck, were dry, and the others stood knee-deep in water. Nearly all of them with nothing on but the single garment or two with which they had retired for the night.</p>
                  <p>After parleying a little, and learning the state of affairs, the Captain threw out his line, and as we rowed round the wreck, sounded again and again. At the close of the circuit, we approached, and assured them of their safety. The assurance took from many a heart a load of anxiety and terror.</p>
                  <p>And who were among all these people? I noticed one poor woman particularly, as she sat knee-deep in the water. Three children were clinging to her. There was no cry, no sob, no tear; but her face was marked with despair, and told a sadder tale than cries, or sobs, or tears could have done.</p>
                  <p>"Have you lost anything?" I asked.</p>
                  <p>"GOD help me!" was her answer. I felt sure my conjecture was right.</p>
                  <p>"You have lost your husband?"</p>
                  <p>"GOD help me!" and she rocked to and fro, without looking up or noticing me.</p>
                  <p>"He had sandy whiskers, and a light-colored fustian coat?"</p>
                  <p>"Yes, yes!"</p>
                  <p>"He is safe on the other steamer."</p>
                  <p>A sharp, shrill cry escaped her; she sprang up, clutched me by the arm, stared in my face, with almost the intense, weird earnestness of a maniac, crying as she looked:</p>
                  <p>"And James?"</p>
                  <p>What she meant was only too clear; three children were about her, but the first-born "was not." The Book of Fate was closed for him, his life account was balanced, and "Well done, good and faithful servant," or, "Depart ye," had already rung its awful meaning in his ears.</p>
                  <p>I shook my head, and she sank to her seat again. It was the poor wife of the man who had lost his Admiralty-papers.</p>
                  <pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC6162-00000065"/>
                  <p>We left them as the dawn broke over the distant horizon, taking two sick women back with us. In a few hours a steamer would pass, and relieve them from their plight, which we could not do. As the sky became lighter with the coming sun, we saw, three miles away, the pipe-stack of the sunken steamer rising from the water, and toward that we rowed, taking with us the good tidings that so many were saved. I told the man-monster of his son's death, but he hardly seemed to notice it. Profounder thoughts were probably coursing through that poor brain.</p>
                  <p>The sun rose and looked down brightly upon the two huge warriors, lying apart and dead in their watery battle-field, and for a moment its beams lent a more cheerful aspect to the crowd of the waiting and weary, the faint and the sick. Its beams also fell upon him whose soul was so dark, and that seemed strange. Strange that about that being no somber shadow rested to hide him from the humanity which he had insulted by taking its form. The bridal-morn had come and gone, and in his poor heart had awakened no perception of a higher trust, a holier life. Little children had come to him, with their strange, helpless glances, and then their early prattle, but neither blessing nor blessed. His Admiralty-papers and his pipe were his god and his hearth-stone—the Penates before whom he worshiped there, silent and alone; for all by this time knew his story, and shrank from his touch.</p>
                  <p>Well, he went on his way, and I heard of him no more. He saw in this cloud-curtained, star-lighted Hall of Doom what his eyes brought with them the power of seeing. If we see more, and use our seeing unwisely, we may yet be accounted worse than he. In the pride of intellect and sentiment, we may forget their proper use and their High Source, as he in his stolidity forgot his humanity. We can all put on the outward and visible form of sanctity, use prayer-artillery to gain the heavens with, but if we have no charity ladder to scale the breach, fail as well as he, poor animal, to enter there.</p>
                  <p>As the day wore on, steamers came to our assistance, and we were soon going our several ways again, the day-star of hope still beckoning us onward.</p>
                  <p>How changed the scene, from the moon-lit one of the previous evening! Some were parentless,<pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC6162-00000066"/> some childless. Sorrow had come upon them as a thief in the night. Partly from loss of rest, partly from the reaction from intense excitement, most of them were gloomy and silent. A few recklessly joked of the past. A lesser few, with calm, bright countenances, thanked the High and Mighty ONE, who had saved them in their extreme need. From these the notes of a hymn of praise arose, their echoes dying away in the distance, as we left the huge grave of the lost behind us. In the depths of that grave lay buried something more precious than life, love, wife, children, or humanity. Something, the loss of which could make the sundering of the holiest mortal ties but a trifling misfortune in comparison. Something which could bring a nervous tremor to a being which had left its first-born to the Angel of Death without a sigh. And that was some Admiralty-papers. They and his boy lay uncoffined and unknelled in the same wide grave. They did not want for tears, however, to embalm their memory. Those were wept over by him; this, by her, for whom is no help, no succor, save in that Almighty who gave her a heart to love much, to suffer more.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A DAY IN THE DEAD-LETTER OFFICE.</head>
               <pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC6162-00000067"/>
               <head>A Day in the Dead-Letter Office.</head>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
                  <p>SHE lay in her coffin there, so beautiful, so calm, so holy, that it seemed as if she were uttering a silent prayer to her FATHER in heaven, and would open her eyes at its close. "Blessed are the dead that die in the LORD, for they rest from their labors," said the grave man who was speaking in subdued tones to the mourners; and no one could look upon that fair form, from which the spiritual essence had gone on its measureless journey toward the mercyseat, without faith that she at least had found rest. She had uttered no complaint during her few months' illness, and when her coming doom was gently announced by him who had ministered to her spiritual<pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC6162-00000068"/> welfare from her childhood, she only said, "It is well;" and when the parting came, she pressed her mother's hand, moved her lips slightly as her little brother's face was held for a moment near her own, and, in utter weariness of life, turned her head on her pillow, died, and made no sign; but there was the impress of a holy one left upon her face, as her spirit returned to GOD who gave it.</p>
                  <p>"O most merciful and ever-blessed REDEEMER," said the minister, as he, too, looked toward the heavens; and as the mourners bent their heads reverently, a little boy of some four or five summers came into the room, and, looking wistfully around, approached the satin and flower-decked couch where his sister was so calmly sleeping. Reaching with both his little hands to the side of the coffin, he drew himself up so that he could see his sister's face, and in an earnest but almost inaudible voice whispered; "Mary! Mary!" But Mary was too far off to her him, too preoccupied in her new home to answer. He sank quietly to the floor; then, taking up a flower which had fallen with him from the coffin, he rose, drew himself up again with a convulsive vulsive effort, held by one hand as he dropped the flower on her lips, and again whispered, "Mary!" but the same eloquent answer was returned. Loosening his hold, he stood for a few moments trembling at the side of the coffin;—the prayer for the dead and the dying went on;—again he drew himself up, but this time uttered no sound, only reached out a little hand and touched her cold face; in that touch he seemed to have received a revelation of death; for, uttering a shrill, sharp scream, he fell to the floor senseless. Taking him up, we carried him from the crowd of mourners, some of whom, having seen what occurred, were weeping; others, who had not, were frightened at what appeared to be a voice from the coffin itself.</p>
                  <p>In a chamber, alone and apart, sat the fair girl's mother, her hair all too soon mixed with white; snow in the summer months, it had fallen upon her head as she watched by the death-bed of her child. We placed the little boy in her arms, and, as she pressed him to her heart, she pointed to an open and crushed letter lying on the floor at her side. Her face was haggard; there were no tears in her<pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC6162-00000069"/> eyes; and she rocked to and fro with the movement with which despair sometimes tries to cheat the moment of some part of its bitterness. "Read! read! it came from the Dead-Letter Office, contained a trinket, and therefore was saved, the others are all destroyed: it has killed her."</p>
                  <p>We took up the crushed letter, smoothed it out and read. Affection warm as the sun which draws the cactus-flower to life, sentiments noble and holy, such as love draws from a good man, but, alas! <emph>mis-</emph> directed, as all the others probably were. In that week's bill of mortality the fair girl made one of the fifty-nine cases of consumption, but she died of a <emph>dead letter.</emph> And he came back in all the fullness of life, in the fullness of a manhood which love had made noble, and found for his embracing—a new-made grave.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <p>WHEN we were a youngster, and apotheosized by the first laying on of jacket and pants; when imagination was beginning to quarry blocks of fancy granite to build castles with, and life was uncovering her lens to give us a peep here and there into her wondrous panorama, we were sojourning at a neighboring town with a family whose head was postmaster of the place. We soon had the range of the post-office in consequence, and became a pet with the clerks, not to say a small butt, too, for them to sharpen their wits upon. One day one of the most solemn-looking of the set, but one who could hardly open his mouth to speak without making the others laugh, for which we thought them very wicked, was closing and locking a bag, whose sides were distended to the utmost with crammed-in material of some kind: a fat, rotund, aldermanie post-bag. We asked:</p>
                     <p>"What is that?"</p>
                     <pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC6162-00000070"/>
                     <p>"Dead letters," said the solemn clerk, lugubriously.</p>
                     <p>"<emph>Dead</emph> letters! How came they to die?"</p>
                     <p>"Some from neglect; some because they could n't find their way home; some died because the girls refused them."</p>
                     <p>Refused! We had heard our people talk about a man's being sick, because he was refused, and here were letters killed by it.</p>
                     <p>"Are they very dead?"</p>
                     <p>"Yes, dead as a 'subject' after he's 'biled' and his bones hung together with wires."</p>
                     <p>We did not understand that, nor why the clerks should laugh so.</p>
                     <p>"Where are they going?"</p>
                     <p>"To Washington."</p>
                     <p>"To be buried?"</p>
                     <p>"Yes; they have a big grave-yard there, and the President reads the funeral service over the poor things."</p>
                     <p>For years afterward it was a vivid picture in our imagination, the crowd, the grave, and the President—as large again as other men, a sort of demi-god—reading the funeral service over the dead, while curious head-stones dotted the ground, setting forth the causes why the poor letters were lying there. As we grew up, and these absurd notions faded, they left in their place a strong curiosity to see this noted foolscap Golgotha, and now when our fair young friend had yielded up her life, and had been tragically dead-lettered into eternity, we determined, on our first visit to Washington, to explore this mysterious place, if we could obtain any friend at court to guide us through its shades.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC6162-00000071"/>
                     <p>"WAITER, take away this Chateaux Margaux of "1828" ("figures" evidently do "lie" sometimes), and bring a julep. Tell James to make it, and that it is for us."</p>
                     <p>Ah! a master-piece of bar-room art, gratifying as the first kiss of her thou lovest most, or a sudden rise in stocks when one is a heavy holder. Cold as the bergs which overlook the "open sea," where the north pole bids defiance to the nation's daring; sparkling as the eyes which open to the sunlight of the bridal morning. Oldest of antique nectars, dating thy mysterious birth far away in the hidden past, where facts become mythic, and great men are transformed into gods or demi-gods, hail!</p>
                     <p>"Not known ten years ago!" some tyros assert. Why, America was in swaddling-clothes, nay, unknown, long centuries after it was a joy forever. Not known ten years ago? To us its antique flavor adds an aroma to its aroma, and gilds refined gold. Why, Circe, a pet maid of honor to Mrs. Neptune, a daughter of the Sun, and Miss Perse, is known to have used it long before many of our antiquities were dreamed of or created. Hear Milton make his hero eloquent: <q>
                           <lg type="quotation">
                              <l>"AND first behold this cordial JULEP here,</l>
                              <l>Which flames and dances in his crystal bounds</l>
                              <l>With spirits, and balm, and fragrant sirups mixed;</l>
                              <l>Not that Nepenthes (sherry cobbler, probably)</l>
                              <l rend="ti-3">which the wife of THONE</l>
                              <l>In Egypt gave to JOVE-born HELENA</l>
                              <l>Is of such power to stir up joy as this—</l>
                              <l>To life so friendly, and so cool to thirst."</l>
                           </lg>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>Bravo! the poet brings it as freshly and clearly before the mind's eye as the waiter does before our physical ones, and the mercury in that thermometer twenty feet away shrinks down, down toward its lair at the bare sight of the pyramid of ice where the delicious liquid whence it rises is sparklingly reflected, like rubies and brilliants in the sunlight.</p>
                     <p>Milton does not actually mention "mint," but he does balm, a species of it; besides, what he meant, is clear to the meanest capacity, for we all know that a <hi rend="i"/>julep is not a JULEP without mint. Not ten years<pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC6162-00000072"/> old? Look at its head, frosty with the snows of untold centuries.</p>
                     <p>This is the last day of a five weeks' sojourn in Washington, and it has been a day in the Dead-Letter Office, the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">entrée</foreign> obtained, all our efforts crowned with success, and the spoils, in the shape of selected letters, scattered about the table, where that glorious julep stands to welcome them once more to light and life. How strange and weird they look, these odd anachronisms, dead before their time, but born again. And now, dear reader, while we are at peace with gods and men, while the milk of human kindness is circulating in our soul, and the spirit of this mint-perfumed nectar is snatching for us a few moments from earth and its sorrows, we will lay the Dead-Letter Office before you as far as words can do it, and then from this mass of letters, this cream of our day's work, we will re-select and lay before you <foreign xml:lang="FRA">la crême de la crême.</foreign>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <foreign xml:lang="FRA">entrêe</foreign> to the Dead-Letter Office, like kissing, goes by favor; and it has cost us much trouble and many refusals before we could obtain it. We do not mean the mere permission to look into the rooms, and at the clerk-undertakers who are preparing the letters for burial; that any one can obtain for the asking: but the "touch not, taste not, handle not," make such a permission a mockery. What! In one's hunger, look at a choice dinner, while the attendants are throwing it to the dogs? Enter the holy of holies, unable to receive its spiritual influences? Look at the "open sea," and never reach the pole? No! The <foreign xml:lang="FRA">entrée</foreign> we wanted was the uncontrolled, unlimited, unchecked range of the office for a whole day, with full permission to read, copy, extract, or carry off any of the letter-corpses to which we took a fancy; and that permission we obtained.</p>
                     <p>The day broke gloriously, as if it had been made for good spirits, and was lingering here a few hours on its way to their spheres. The flowers laughed in the sunlight, and grass-blades sprang up from every cranny between the stones, to welcome their great sun-father, when at an early hour, under the auspices of Mr. Auditor Pratt, we wended our way toward the beautiful white marble palace post-office.</p>
                     <p>Having entered, we turned to the left along the<pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC6162-00000073"/> corridor, which extends some two or three hundred feet through the entire length of the building; passing on to the last door, it opened and closed behind us, and we were in the sanctuary of the dead, a letter Golgotha, though not merely a "place of skulls," for they (the letters) being dead, yet speak.</p>
                     <p>We bowed solemnly to the clerks as the Auditor introduced us, and when he retired, sat down, lost in a revery over the sad scene; for what a vast record of buried hopes, lost friends, broken friendships, and neglected love lay scattered about that cemetery! While dreaming thus, one of the clerks began whistling merrily; in an instant the spell was broken, and we went business-like to our task of dissecting some thousands of "subjects."</p>
                     <p>The Dead-Letter department of the General Post-Office at Washington is one of much importance; there all the letters and packages which are misdirected, refused, or miscarried, are sent, after being advertised for a certain time in the place to which they are addressed; and, strange as it may seem, several millions annually fail to reach their destination. These are received at stated times from the various branches all over the Union, and are placed on the long tables of the office, where numerous clerks are exclusively employed in opening them; if they contain nothing, they are thrown down unread, packed in large paper bags, and every three months taken to the common and burned by cart-loads.</p>
                     <p>Should the letters contain money or other valuables, they are laid on a side-table, and a recording clerk arranges them alphabetically in the boxes prepared for that purpose, and writes to the writer of the letter, stating that it has been received. If no answer is returned, after three years the contents, if money, is placed in the treasury, still subject to the owner's order, if he bring the requisite proofs. Every article received is kept and labeled, and in this way they collect gloves, rings, garters, books, locks of hair, pictures, likenesses, law-papers, and so on, and in money some thousands of dollars weekly. Title-deeds and other valuable papers, supposed to be lost, are often recovered there.</p>
                     <p>We entered on our task with maw omnivorous, devouring all things as they came, protests and<pb n="146-147" xml:id="VAC6162-00000074"/> protestations, deeds and misdeeds, bills and—cooings, proposals for marrying and proposals for building, hands for sale and "hands wanted," notes to pay and notes to answer, on, on, on, we read each document as it came, from the piety which unlocks the Heavens, to the sinning which fits us for Hades'; from the legerdemain of the heart to the ledger-domain of the counting-house. But this, of course, could not last; as the day advanced we gradually became more fastidious, more alive to outward signs of inward and spiritual graces: guessed the contents of a letter by reading a line: threw away all which had a taint of print: laid aside, half read, those that were eloquent or odd; and when the hour came for closing the office, from a huge mass which we had glanced at or read, we had selected a package of several hundred, and here they are before us, lenses through which we will give a few glimpses of the panorama of life, guides who will take us for a moment behind the scenes, so that in looking at others' follies or woes, we may for a time forget that we, too, are players.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
                  <p>IT will be as well, perhaps, to preface our second chapter with the remark that all the names of both persons and places have been carefully erased, and even the initials are fictitious, so that the owner or writer, of course, will be the only one able to locate his own, and thus lead, perhaps, to the healing of breaches and misunderstandings, should they or any of them once more reach the surprised eyes of those who created them. With us, the only question, of course, is, have they literary merit enough to make them worth printing, or are they odd enough to amuse?</p>
                  <p>The first we offer seems to have been sent as an accompaniment to a parcel of flowers. It has two post-marks; evidently, the person to whom it was addressed had left, and it had been forwarded to the wrong address. It has neither date nor signature, and is unique in its kind.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="148-149" xml:id="VAC6162-00000075"/>
                     <p>"FATHER and mother have been quarreling so long that it seems as if there would never be another spring-time in our house, and home is chilly, cold, sad, although it has an infinite sky for a dome, and the cloud-frescoed horizon for walls. Our poor mother's heart is congealed, and her face is of snowy paleness, or covered with rain-tears on account of his indifference, and he looks down upon us from his proud eminence, and holds out his hands full of sparkling beams, but there is no warmth in them; so we have left our chilly home, our mother's cold bosom, and our father's freezing smile, to ask shelter of you for the few hours we have to live. We have nothing to offer you for your love but a little perfume: will you love us? Place us at your side, fair lady, or let us nestle in your bosom; it will not be for long. HE who gave us our moment's beauty will soon take it to HIMSELF again, but HE will love you better for having loved us."</p>
                     <p>The next, as we take them somewhat at random, runs thus:</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <p>"MY DEAR F—: I send with this 'The Caxtons tons' and 'My Novel.' Do you remember my promise to do so, made as we were groping our way down in the everlasting and dense darkness of the Mammoth Cave, where, as we burned our blue-lights in the pits, domes, ruins, chasms, and arches, we seemed to be daring the fiends in their native home, while our merry laughter frightened them off to the black reaches of the distant cavern? For how could doomed spirits, steeped in despair, listen to the laughter of such happy mortals, and not shrink away? at least I saw none of their red eyes peering out from the dark places, nor their faces grinning defiance at us: did you?</p>
                                 <p>"Our black guide was a jewel, but you lost one of the good things he said by remaining behind at 'Coram's Dome.' Alfred took us, scrambling and climbing, to a place he called Vulcan's Forge, thence with the usual hazard of our necks, to a heap of rubbish, the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">débris</foreign> of fallen stalactites.</p>
                                 <p>"'This,' said he, 'is the ashes from Vulcan's forge.'</p>
                                 <p>"'Alfred,' I asked quietly, 'do you ever find any of the bolts here?'</p>
                                 <p>"'No, Sir; they're all gone to thunder!'</p>
                                 <pb n="150-151" xml:id="VAC6162-00000076"/>
                                 <p>"The ready answer, half-classic and half-Bowery, set us laughing merrily.</p>
                                 <p>"Do you remember the evening I left the cave? 'Angels and ministers of grace!' What a night! On horseback, too, and such a road! About two miles from the cave the blackness of darkness over-took me, and the rain came down in sheets, as if the windows of heaven were opened. I could see neither trees, fences, nor road; and as to seeing the guide, that was out of the question: I could only hear the clattering of his horse's hoofs on the rocks. Leaning back in the saddle, I held the reins tightly in my hand, gave the horse his head, struck him with the whip, and away we went on a gallop. Literally, I could not see the horse I was riding. On we went through the black space, through darkness that could almost be felt, and came up to my eyes so densely that it seemed as if I could put up my hand and push it away like a physical substance. Now dashing through water, now stumbling over rocks, we at last finished the nine miles, and reached Bell's in a decidedly damp state, changed my clothes, took the ninth seat in the passing stage, and talked abolition until daybreak, there, in the heart of Kentucky, to eight unknown passengers. No harm came of the ducking or the abolition.</p>
                                 <p>"How is merry, light-hearted, pretty Miss R——? It was very funny, when <emph>crawling</emph> through 'Bunyan's Way,' to see her lie down exhausted, and call for volunteers to <emph>roll</emph> her through. By the way, if Bunyan had had that trip to take with his burden on, he would never have reached the Celestial City.</p>
                                 <p>"You have a niche in that part of my memory, where the more sylph-like and graceful beings I have met most do congregate.</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <salute>"Fare thee well,</salute>
                                    <signed>C——"</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>This letter reminds us of an incident at the Mammoth Cave, in which a bride and groom suddenly became as chilled and cold as the most profound misogamist could desire. A bride of some seven days' standing, with her husband and five friends, two ladies and three gentlemen, put oil in their lamps, and descended to the cave for a day's frolic and exploration. Three miles from the entrance they came to the river, and seating themselves in a scow,<pb n="152-153" xml:id="VAC6162-00000077"/> began singing and awakening the echoes, while the guide "sculled" along over the still waters, where the blind fish, too much like ourselves, were swimming about, heedless of the light above. They approached the end of the rock-arched river, Where the huge cave opens again like a mammoth rail-road tunnel, and the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">débris</foreign> of fallen rocks made it look as if a grand "smash-up" had taken place there. By the side of the beach a little rock just out. The elastic, light-hearted, happy bride sprang to the side of the scow to jump first ashore. Two gentlemen, without sense to balance their gallantry, followed to help her, and the three stepping on the side at once, over went the boat, bride, guide, oil, lamps, and suite; attendant fair friends—and foul friends, to say nothing of fare and fowl for their subterranean lunch; a scream, a plunge, a momentary struggle for life, and there they all stood, waist-deep in water, madly clinging together, and the shrieking, screaming, crying, weeping, wailing, screeching made a chorus of woe which would be a fortune to Verdi, could he transfer it to his "lines" in more "pleasant places." Few people can imagine how exceedingly black the darkness is down there, six hundred feet in a perpendicular line below the sunlight, and beyond the reach of the thunder echoes; and our gay bridal party did not dare to move one step, but clung together, and screamed loud enough almost to make the rocks fall on them. Indeed, they could not tell where to move, and a step might send them into the unfathomable deeps together. A guide, left behind at the hotel, not liking his leisure, followed them into the cave about an hour after they started, in hope, probably, of some pickings by the wayside. He hurried on, reached the river, took another scow, and about ten minutes after their "plunge-bath" the light of his coming lamp, joyful as the first-born's smile to its youthful mother, as the free air to the long-imprisoned, shone upon them, and they were taken on board, without reaching the other side of that Jordan. They went on their winding way, songless and silent, but very thankful and <emph>very</emph> wet.</p>
                     <p>The next we fish up has a piscatory flavor, and seems to have been a Dutchman's handiwork:</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <p>"DEAR SIR You will pleas send me 9 shads for my<pb n="154-155" xml:id="VAC6162-00000078"/> window 2 feets 9 inch wide 6 feets long like I seen at your store by steamboat traveller for New heaven</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <salute>"Your Servant,</salute>
                                    <signed>D——."</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>"Nine shad for New Heaven" is good.</p>
                     <p>It seemed strange, and even sad, as we waded through the dead masses, to see how lonely they were. No connecting link between the thousands and tens of thousands of stray letters. Each a separate mischance, each perhaps a separate sorrow. No communion between them, no acquaintanceship. The following are the only two which we found during the day, or noticed as being at all connected. Names, addresses, post-marks all prove that the writer of each of these should have been the recipient of the other. Yet how different the tone.! Well, we have known honey-moons marred in the first days of their existence by quarrels; and as postmasters send their dead letters but once in three months, there was time enough for such a wild passion to wear itself out, and allow the letters to reach Washington on the same day.</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <p>"NOBLE, GENEROUS-HEARTED DARLING: I can not allow a longer time to elapse without in some way expressing my deep, earnest, heartfelt gratitude for the kind sympathy and assistance you have rendered me in my late trials. Oh! how coldly do words tell the inmost feeling of my heart. Yesterday morning I went out with M—, and being very tired on my return, lay down to sleep, when Somnus came and led me back to the happy days I spent with you. Again I visited C——, and felt the nervous tremor of your dear supporting arm. I gazed once more upon the yawning chasm and the giddy whirl of waters, looked down into the impenetrable depths of the black, cold, watery grave; and when my woman's timid nature made me shrink and shudder, lest by one false step I should be hurled into eternity, I looked at you, and in the eloquence of your fond eyes I felt secure from every pending ill, and then, unheard by all below, I murmured a fervent prayer to HIM who knows our every thought, to grant (if such be HIS almighty will) that love so all-absorbing and intense as mine might yet awaken in your bosom some feelings like my own. It was but a short echo of what had really been. No human soul could have<pb n="156-157" xml:id="VAC6162-00000079"/> guessed the maddened ecstasy with which I traced those glorious wonders of an Almighty hand. Pure as an infant's were the emotions which led me up through nature unto nature's GOD. And have my prayers been answered? Have I found in you that earthly guide and counselor which my weak and erring nature so much needed? Have I prayed and prayed aright? Yes, I feel, I know I have. My love for you is sanctioned by a wise, unerring BEING, and to you alone shall my fond heart be given. By every tie of nature and of love, I am yours. And now, dearest, let me tell you, that deeply as I lament the loss of that confidence which was previously placed in me by those from whom I am now estranged, I can never wish to retract one word or action which has placed me thus. All outward opposition draws me nearer to you; and with regard to others, <q>
                                       <lg type="quotation">
                                          <l>"'MAN may dismiss compassion from his heart,</l>
                                          <l>But GOD will never.'</l>
                                       </lg>
                                    </q> And you, most fondly loved one, do you regret the past? or does the assurance of my undying love, being the result of our late joys and sorrows, in any way repay you for the annoyances to which you have been subjected? Does not one fiber of your generous heart and nature thrill like my whole system at the remembrance that <q>
                                       <lg type="quotation">
                                          <l>"'THERE are moments of life which we never forget,</l>
                                          <l rend="ti-1">They heighten and brighten as time stenis away;</l>
                                          <l>They give a new charm to the happiest lot,</l>
                                          <l rend="ti-1">And they shine on the glow of the loveliest day.'</l>
                                       </lg>
                                    </q> I must now leave you, once more assuring you how infinitely the happiness you have afforded me surpasses the misery caused by the cold-hearted world. GOD bless you, dearest—and believe me ever</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <salute>"Your own to eternity,</salute>
                                    <signed>O——."</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <p>"YOUR present position, O——, of comparative independence, will enable me to write what for some time past I have wished to say; yet what I should not utter even now, if you were in the same dependent position. It is, that our acquaintance is at an end. Your own conscience answers why, and I have too much experience of your sex, you too little duplicity, for me to be ignorant of what that answer is.</p>
                                 <p>"With your life before we met, be it written or<pb n="158-159" xml:id="VAC6162-00000080"/> unwritten, I have nothing to do; but with the present I have, and the step you have taken during the past month, in your career toward no land of promise, I fear, must of course end our friendship in all its phases.</p>
                                 <p>"You are the first being who has stooped to deceive me so, and curiously enough, too, the one of all others who made the deepest protestations of eternal attachment. If I had placed much faith in them, I might now feel annoyed or angry; I feel neither, and look with curious wonder at this new leaf in my experience of the book of life.</p>
                                 <p>"But why, if you suspected (knew) this, you may say, place me near your friends? Because I knew of the gold there is among so much dross; the spiritual nature there is among so much sensual; and I hope you may yet break your passion-chains, or at least keep those facts which would damn you behind the scenes.</p>
                                 <p>"Wild and ungovernable as your passion is, drawing down will, reason, soul in its train, yet I know that there is something of the angel there, and for the rest I am one of the last who have the right to cast a stone at you. This episode in our existence, eventful and sad as it has been for the most part, has terminated, and nothing remains but to say farewell.</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <signed>G——."</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>The next has no address at all. The writer in her grief seems to have forgotten to direct her sad letter, and so it is here.</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <opener>
                                    <dateline>"18—.</dateline>
                                 </opener>
                                 <p>"DEAR W.:" Again I take up the sad thread of my daily anguish. All is over.</p>
                                 <p>"'I fear I can do no more,' said the doctor; 'my art is at fault; nature must restore her now, if she be restored.'</p>
                                 <p>"'But, doctor, there is life still. She opens her eyes; for Heaven's sake do something while there is life—while there is <emph>life,</emph> doctor. Oh, God! Oh, God! what shall I do?'</p>
                                 <p>"'Mother! mother! do you know me, mother?'</p>
                                 <p>"A faint whispered utterance said, 'Yes, bless you, yes.' They were the last words the recording angel had to write of her utterance, and her work was nearly done.</p>
                                 <pb n="160-161" xml:id="VAC6162-00000081"/>
                                 <p>"We had given her from hour to hour the appointed drugs, and from hour to hour she sank more rapidly. We had watched with unwearying care and sleepless eyes; and now hope deferred was turned into approaching despair, which sank into our souls as the blood left her cheeks, and her eyes and mouth closed. The feet and hands were becoming cold, the pulse went and came fitfully, and beat slowly, with a thread-like motion. The face wore a look of happy content, of profound peace. Almost a smile was diffused over her countenance, as if heaven were opening to her spiritual eyes, before life had left her earthly ones. A few slight movements of the pulse at long intervals, a slight tremor on the countenance, and calm and holy as the sleep of an infant, she yielded up her soul to the heavenly Father.</p>
                                 <p>"Sobs and groans about the bed told of the links which were broken, the hooks of steel rent asunder. The children were weeping for Rachael, and refused to be comforted, because she was not.</p>
                                 <p>"She had not only been a good House-Mother, but a Faith Mother, a Mother in GOD—a link between the holy of holies and the souls of all about her. A quiet, uncomplaining, and martyr-like spirit, she has borne the burden and heat of the day, and is at peace. She has sunk below the horizon, like the sun, taking the light with her, and left the heavens dark behind, where but few stars are visible. One has lost in her a friend; another, a guide; another, a companion; all a Mother, all save one, and he, feeble with age, sickness, and much grief, tottered about the bedside sobbing aloud, the helpless, hopeless, bitterest grief, the grief of age—of age which has lost the life-long partner of its existence. That bitter grief whose hope is only a memory, whose future a grave.</p>
                                 <milestone n="*   *   *   *   *   *   *   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/>
                                 <p>"Three long sad days have gone with their fellows to the eternity we leave behind us at every step. Three weary days have passed, and life with its necessities has gone on again. But her place is vacant at the board; her footfall unheard in the evening walk; her gentle voice hushed forever and ever, and over all things gloom and sadness rest like a pall.</p>
                                 <pb n="162-163" xml:id="VAC6162-00000082"/>
                                 <p>"She lay in her coffin, beautiful in death. Her white hair parted on her forehead. Her eyes and mouth so gently closed. Her face was clear and unwrinkled, and the half smile upon her face when she died, still rested there, as if Heaven had revealed itself to her in the flesh, and left its impress. They placed her on the bier, and friends and acquaintances followed slowly with the mourners to the little chamber in the earth, where the dust whence an angel had sprung to light and life was to remain until the ages should mingle it with its native dust again.</p>
                                 <p>"The insects were hushed in the noonday sun. The air was still as the blue heavens over it. Leaf and grass blade were motionless, all was still—.</p>
                                 <p>"'Dust to dust—ashes to ashes'—</p>
                                 <p>"The iron door closed, and it was ended!</p>
                                 <p>"All things had been done decently and in order; and the many went their way to sow, to reap, to bargain, to whirl on; but we returned to where the household gods had been thrown from their places and broken—to a home with its hearth-some made desolate—to a home with the same outward form, but from which GOD had taken the spiritual grace for evermore.</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <signed>E—."</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>Our next, taken at hazard, is from among the ecstasies. The old story, love, love, ever new and never ending.</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <p>DEAR N——: I am happy to hear that you were well enough to leave your room for a few hours on Friday, and I most sincerely hope your exertions did not injure you. I need not tell you that your silence—I might call it neglect—has stung me bitterly, especially now I know that others are thought of.' But why should I be surprised? The novelty of my devotion is past, the trouble I have occasioned you in your invalid state is doubtless irksome. I will not reproach you, that would be unjust; but I do regret most heartily that I was not wise enough to know that this would be. I have placed you above the general race of men; have looked at and thought of you not as one human being thinks of another, but as a something so infinitely superior, placed by Heaven in my way, that to nearly idolize you was not wrong. But now, without<pb n="164-165" xml:id="VAC6162-00000083"/> out provocation, you leave me in ignorance as to your health, or leave me to hear from others, which is still worse, and when I am with you, evidently portray dissatisfaction. GOD bless you! May she who supplants me in your affections love you but half as well as I have done, and you may be satisfied, for you will then possess more than man ordinarily receives from woman. I am as ever.</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <salute>"Your fondly attached,</salute>
                                    <signed>M—</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>"Poor child, may she "grow strong." To "suffer," is evidently her lot. But what changed scenes and circumstances if all these missives could have gone on their way, and without losing it!</p>
                     <p>The author of the following would not probably be very graciously received by the quilting sisters, could they see it:</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <p>"MY DEAR T—: There is to be a quilting at P—'s on Saturday. I am requested to invite you: be there.</p>
                                 <p>"'Pray (prey) on, sisters!' The carcass is there—let the eagles gather together.</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <salute>"Yours in Christianity,</salute>
                                    <signed>L—."</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>Our next is as warm as a June sun in Italy. How tantalizing these glances! This letter looms up like a little island in the ocean, the apex of a submerged mountain—of sentiment and passion:</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <p>"'To be,' of course, as you always were; and as to forgiving, my dear child! what have I to forgive? If you held a capital hand, threw away your best cards without taking a trick, and lost the game, it is your own forgiveness you want, not mine. But there is one point in your sweet, pretty letter—that—that—What had the thoughts 'Satan himself must have prompted on the night of the concert,' to do with the matter? And again, how could you be taught to believe that the only feeling I had for you was ten times worse than hate?' What teaching could have any effect after that confidence of mine? After you knew the secret which is so largely the key of what some people think my strange and mysterious character? Why, ladybird, after embraces, the memory of which must still linger on your lips, after resting your head on my breast, and listening to that tale of early love, when the crimson of your cheeks was visible between<pb n="166-167" xml:id="VAC6162-00000084"/> the fingers which were clasped over your face to hide the fever which was glowing there, as your eager ears drank in the words: after all that, could you have any 'teaching' about me? No! We were thenceforward on an equal footing, not only morally, as all men and women are, but in responsibility also. What my intentions were, can hardly be discussed, for I had none. The sails were up, and a delightful breeze was blowing, but I had left the helm, and hardly glanced ahead to see if the boat was making toward a bank of flowers or a whirlpool.</p>
                                 <p>"What the possibilities of our position were, unchecked and untrammeled as it was, is for our several judgments to decide. For my part, I <emph>did</emph> think it possible that some new memories, <q>
                                       <lg type="quotation">
                                          <l>"'WHICH, tasted once, last always, and disdain</l>
                                          <l>Time's iron pressure,'</l>
                                       </lg>
                                    </q> might have been created in you here, to color with their fire-light the foliage of your life-tree; but the RULER of your destiny willed it otherwise, or <emph>you</emph> willed it otherwise, and—it is well that it is well—all the bitterness I felt about our separation had gone before May, and at that early day I had determined not to see you again, if things remained as they were.</p>
                                 <p>"We are on the top-round of the ladder of physical existence; each year all that gives life to passion and coloring to sentiment will in both of us be, if not fading, at best stationary. Perhaps, when long years have gone by, when little ones are clinging round you to call you blessed, and I am feeling more bitterly than I can now the loneliness of the pathway that I have marked out for myself, perhaps we may meet again, and after looking the surprise which we shall feel at the change which will have come over the spirit of our physical existence, talk frankly of our fitful fever-dream, and not probably before.</p>
                                 <p>"When your heart is over-full, and wants a channel wherein to flow, write to me. When the sad hours come, as they will at any age, rid yourself of some part of their bitterness with my sympathy; and when the garden of life looks arid and blank, if you will let me know it, I will try and plant a few flower-seeds there, which may perhaps grow<pb n="168-169" xml:id="VAC6162-00000085"/> up into things of beauty, and if so, be 'a joy forever.'</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <signed>B—."</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>We doubt if that ended so, but, alas! the infinite chaos of the Dead-Letter Office gave us no farther echo, and we pass on.</p>
                     <p>We clip the following paragraph from eight pages of similar white-robed charity:</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <p>MY DEAR L—: G— has examined it, and it is not cotton, but real English thread lace—I told you so. Where does she get it? Her father is too poor to give it to her. I suppose it will be thread-lace shawls next, or even camel's hair. I watched behind the old elm for three hours yesterday, and saw them come home in the twilight, and his arm was about her waist, and when they reached the gate, <emph>she</emph> kissed HIM! What do you think of that? I know he's bad enough: I found that out when he used to pay me so much attention. S— says, perhaps they 're engaged. Engaged! He marry that simpleton! I <emph>do</emph> wish you would come this week, instead of next, and see for yourself." *   *   *   *   *   *   *   *</p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>Ah! my dear young lady, cultivate the humanities more and spleen less, or the mile-stones on the road to your father's mansion will never be hung with garlands, even if you do not altogether lose the way; and as to the "dry-goods," comfort yourself; all English "thread lace" is made from cotton, if that be any consolation; and, by the way, camel's hair shawls are made of goat's hair; black "threadlace shawls," from silk. The material in these things is of little moment, it is the laboring fingers of the sons and daughters of toil which give them their value; and you, doubt it not, would be surer of walking in robes not woven nor made with hands, were you to join the corps instead of employing your time in seeking or creating scandal.</p>
                     <p>Here is a crow-quill note from a lady fair. We must confess, that after wading through the dead-letter masses for an hour or two, we rather took to notes and letters of this outward seeming. The large-hand letters were business, business, business, to such a wearying extent, and when not so, men seem so little inclined to really put themselves into<pb n="170-171" xml:id="VAC6162-00000086"/> letters, that the feminine epistles took precedence to a certain extent, and the result proved, what is so often said and sung, that this sort of literature is peculiarly the field of our fair friends:</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <p>"I HAVE spent the Sabbath, dear stranger, in reading the book you so kindly sent me, and hardly know how to express my delight on reading the accompanying note.</p>
                                 <p>"I have thrown many kindly feelings, many earnest, warm affections forth upon the world, and have shed bitter tears over the coldness that has been returned to me. But I know there are seeds which remain long years in the bosom of the earth before they spring up and produce things of life and beauty. So hope does not forsake me; and in these days of patient 'waiting for the light,' such words as yours—good books—my sister's tenderness—are GOD'S best blessings to</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <signed>S—."</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>Here is one from a lady fair, the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">dénouement</foreign> of a three-volume novel in a line:</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <p>"DEAR P—: If you drop in here at 2 P.M., on Saturday, the 20th, you can see me married.</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <salute>"Very truly,</salute>
                                    <signed>W——."</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>Again we draw at random from our Golgotha as follows:</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <p>"SHALL I say in offering a few flowers simply, 'To R——, with the compliments of W——?' It is all that is necessary; still, perhaps it would be hardly doing justice to Miss R——'s apparently frank, open-hearted nature, or to myself, so I will add my thanks, not for the <emph>pleasure</emph> her acting has afforded me, but for some little inkling of a new revelation of life, and also ask her if it is forgetfulness or indifference which has kept her from 'advising me of her earliest leisure.' I confess that I had built some pleasant little air-castles, founded on my possible acquaintance with her; but they are vanishing, crumbling to their original quarries, and the builder imagination, has laid aside his tools and gone on his way, so that now I have to address even a few flowers to the actress, not, as I would prefer, to the woman. When I saw her last performance, a wish came into my head, or heart, or soul, or wherever the temple is in which wishes do their worshiping—may I repeat it? That when this mimie scene in which she is acting becomes real, and Death<pb n="172-173" xml:id="VAC6162-00000087"/> rolls up into the proscenium above the stars the mysterious curtain from before eternity, and discloses to her view those scenes where the orchestra is sphere-melodies and the stars sing together for joy; where angels cover the stage, and where the background is the silent eternities, may the sorrow and sadness of her little life be found to have so purified her soul, that the ALMIGHTY DIRECTOR will give her an everlasting engagement near HIS throne.</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <signed>"W—."</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>The next is a glimpse seemingly into a romance where the principals did not meet. Its sentiment and pathos deserve a better fate than a burning on the Common at Washington, and we hope its rescue from that may be the means of bringing it to the head and heart it was written for, and should interest and sway:</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <p>"As this is the last time a word will pass between us, will you do me the favor, perhaps the justice, to read a few matter-of-fact lines? Then the spirit shall vanish into air again—your phantom friend die and make no sign.</p>
                                 <p>"You have probably thought that it was a strange interest which I took in one whom I had never seen: I will explain. Long, long ago, when visiting E—, she was one day looking over her letterdrawers; I observed a large package of letters, and asked, 'From whom did you receive those?' She answered, 'From yourself.' I asked permission to read them, and received it. Taking them with me, I laid them aside for the moment, and one morning brought them out with a feeling akin to annoyance at having brought upon myself the task of reading a series of lady's letters, written, too, by a stranger, or least by one of whom I had only heard.</p>
                                 <p>"I opened the first—the next, and read, read, read, on to the last. Surprised, then spell-bound by their depth of graceful thought and sentiment, their infinite longings, their pervading tone of uncomplaining sadness, sweet and melancholy as those of an Æolian harp, and though written in the confidence and abandon of the tenderest friendship, containing no sentence that I would not be proud to have a loved sister utter.</p>
                                 <p>"Then those notes passed between us, and the<pb n="174-175" xml:id="VAC6162-00000088"/> last one (previous to—well, I will not recall it) said, 'I can not, dear S—, bring my mind to say farewell; you shall hear from me in various ways, through friends, and by the stories which I will send you from my pen, in which you will see more of my spirit.' This was the last I heard from you, directly or indirectly.</p>
                                 <p>"Days, weeks, months passed away, still the oracle was dumb in anger or indifference, the Penate silent; Hope had reared a fair fabric, but its foundation rested on a rainbow, and vanished with the light. And as silence and the months went by, the meteor of hope burst, the sun sank below the horizon, and the sweet dream passed away with the hour, while its memory lingered about the dreamer through the long wakefulness of years. For, to me, you have always been a being sanctified and set apart from all others; an image in my mind, created by your own words and my imagination, uncolored even by other influences.</p>
                                 <p>"At last Mr. A— went to your far-away home, and I took the opportunity of sending you a gentle reminder of my existence, with some hope of discovering if I had been in any way the cause of any part of the torture you suffered, or if your silence simply meant I must think of you no more: the rest you know. The note came back and lies before me, and with perception sharpened by surprise, I have read and re-read it, but find no word that a 'serf might not have said to an empress.'</p>
                                 <p>"In all this I think that the first shadow of a selfish thought never crossed my soul; and when there was a possibility of seeking you here, I half feared it, lest the spell which you had so unconsciously woven about me should be broken. Indeed, I had hardly formed in my mind a picture of the outward and visible form of one who had shown such a depth of inward and spiritual grace.</p>
                                 <p>"If it may be done, write me; but if you wish me to tear the household god from its niche, the flower from its nook in the garden of memory, you have but to send back the same cold, silent answer as before, and my actions hereafter shall prove that the silence is indeed more eloquent than words. Earnestly and sincerely</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <salute>"Your friend,</salute>
                                    <signed>S—."</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <pb n="176-177" xml:id="VAC6162-00000089"/>
                     <p>That letter deserves a better fate. We hope it may yet reach the eye for which it was written.</p>
                     <p>A day in the Dead-Letter Office clearly proves many things, and among them that there is much truth, as well as pure affection and passionate love yet in this "cold, false world."</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <p>"DEAR A—: I have not longed for your letters as they that watch for the morning, but I have each evening, for a week past, looked at the little letter-niche on my return home, and with disappointment to find it empty; but it has come at last, been read, and placed in my side-pocket, where it will wear out its little life within hearing of the ticking of that time-piece which the ALMIGHTY wound up and set going many years ago, and which in HIS own good time HE will stop, take its curious mechanism to pieces again, and transfer its mainspring to uses which eye hath not seen, nor ear heard, neither hath it entered into the heart of man to conceive.</p>
                                 <p>"My chamber is a sort of Santa Claus Hall. There is a little alderman on the table, bowing and smacking his lips, as if he enjoyed the concealed bonbons in his rotund body. There is a little teaset for the chubby fingers of a child-pet, to furnish refreshment for her doll; also, little tables, fans, etc., to say nothing of tokens for children of a larger growth, all waiting for the advent of the new year. And there between the toys my fancy sees such smiling faces peep out, and gentle voices whisper, It is more blessed to give than to receive. Then in the corner are some trifles selected and bought for my Kitten-sister, waiting also for the coming of the year to pay their homage, and see the light of the countenance of their new mistress. Will she accept them? Will they cheer her on her way? Will they make her look less sadly at the milestone she is just passing in her life-journey? With them go my wishes that the new year may be to her heart but a day of feasting and joy; that <emph>all</emph> years may be so, until finally she opens her eyes quietly, gently, without pain, and awakens from her life-dream—in heaven.</p>
                                 <p>"Mrs. Childs says she can have no idea of heaven without loving and giving; the first, in this world,<pb n="178-179" xml:id="VAC6162-00000090"/> is a luxury I have ceased even hoping for; but the last can not be taken away from me, unless my friend send back the trifles that I express to-day, which she will not, will she, although they do come from</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <signed>ALMOST A STRANGER?"</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>"Hark from the tombs a doleful sound"—read and weep:</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <p>"DEAR M—: I have selected a very desirable, pleasant spot in Cedar Grove Cemetery, and if you will be brisk about dying, so as to bring the thing about before some other young man intervenes and has a right to insist that you shall be in <emph>his</emph> lot, I should be most happy to have you rest your dear bones beneath the honeysuckles and roses which are to encircle the evergreens of 'No. 4, sec. 5', the figures which in all probability indicate the final resting-place of</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <salute>Yours,</salute>
                                    <signed>G—."</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>This letter reminds us of a scene in Broadway. Time, four o'clock; <foreign xml:lang="FRA">pavé</foreign> crowded, short and tall, grave and gay, lovely and unlovely; hardly a square foot of space not filled with the shreds and patches of our common humanity, as it flowed to right and left, up and down our avenue of palace-shops, when at a brisk trot two horses came gayly along, drawing a strong, empty <emph>hearse,</emph> on the top of which sat a drunken Irishman. Pat leaned and rolled from side to side, every moment seemingly on the point of falling off, and only showing his drunkenness more absurdly from his efforts to steady himself and keep upright. The jeers of the boys and the looks of the passing throng evidently crossed his <foreign xml:lang="FRA">amour propre,</foreign> when, making a grand effort to maintain his equipoise, and evidently mistaking or forgetting his vocation, he drew in his chin, an idiotic smile lighted up his face, and as he held up his finger and beckoned to the passers-by, he cried: "Ride down? ride down? ride down?" Some of the passing crowd laughed, some jeered, some stopped to look, but the most, with a shudder, passed on their way. He probably reached the South Ferry without a fare.</p>
                     <p>Here is another oasis amid the desert of dead-letters from which we glean:</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <p>"DEAR M—: How our hours fly away into the past eternity, and take us on to the mysterious one<pb n="180-181" xml:id="VAC6162-00000091"/> to which we are hastening! It seems but yesterday, and yet it is fourteen days since I pressed your fair hand under the midnight sky, and said farewell, there where the bright evening star was looking on from the dark heavens like a sleepless eye—a mild, calm, holy eye, of boundless intelligence. How often it guided me about your neighborhood, and to and from W— during the few happy weeks which I spent in the vicinity; and now its gentle and everlasting light, each time I look up to the floor of heaven, takes my thoughts back to your home, where, indeed, the promise was held good, that where two or three are gathered together, they shall be blessed.</p>
                                 <p>"With this I send you a book, that is, a series of oblong bits of paper full of typical marks, and inclosed in a cover; the outward form of a book—if it have the inward and spiritual grace of one I can not say. I bought it on the recommendation of a lady, who has worshiped silly and wicked gods enough to people 'Vanity Fair,' and fill all the niches in Pandemonium, that is, Madam Fame. Oh! for a patent intellectual sieve, or spiritual thrashing-machine machine, to save one's hours, and keep the soul from shrinking at the hills of chaff he must wade through to obtain a few 'wheaten grits.' I send you also some flowers, which can hardly be unacceptable, now that Nature has put off all her gay drapery, her fruit-jewels, her flower-robes, and retired for the night.</p>
                                 <p>"'You paint! Oh! it is useless denying it; your cheeks, with a certain angle of the light shining on them, show a metallic, glassy surface, proving the fact with mathematical certainty. I can see it further off than I can tell the color of your eyes, and others also notice and talk of it; besides, it is very unbecoming,' I said to a pretty woman at the opera, the other night.</p>
                                 <p>"After that exhibition of indomitable will, of reckless daring, of gigantic temerity, to say nothing of the consequences, I require repose—time to calm my nerves and prepare for action; therefore you must excuse me if for the present I decline telling you 'your faults.'</p>
                                 <p>"No, no! you must not expect my praise for having 'resolved to read the book,' or twenty like it.<pb n="182-183" xml:id="VAC6162-00000092"/> Wade neck-deep in physiological literature, and of the best; that will not take you out of the Herd of the Sensuous, no more than going to church and resolving to listen to a sermon will take you to where the wicked cease from troubling. I read it many years ago, and others, tried to act then too, but my affinity with the herd is not yet wholly destroyed. To reach physical, moral, or spiritual excellence or holiness requires courage, perseverance, self-denial enough, and only he who seeks one or all with his whole soul can tell how much. But he sees, also, at every step, that the way of the transgressor is still harder, that appetite and 'preference' are enemies only second in power to the evil one himself. Any attempt to lead a life sufficiently ideal to be in harmony with nature and her laws, will soon give the leader another proof that Jordan is—not to be navigated before a fire in an easy-chair.</p>
                                 <p>"And now good-bye. May your life be like the snow which surrounds you—pure, bright, and sparkling in the sunlight, and hiding under its calm, fair surface an untold wealth of fruit and flowers, of sentiment and thought, until it is taken up again quietly, unconsciously, and without pain to its native heaven."</p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>When we were a juvenile, and pocket-money began to wear such weighty proportions that the feat of walking on two feet began to be irksome, we determined in some degree to give up their use. Sallying forth, armed in the complete mail of our innocence—Cœlebs in search of a—horse, we invested six cents of the aforesaid in a twelfth sectional fraction of an omnibus, and in due time were set down before Tattersall's. We entered that pious and saintly place, where by no accident has a horse over eight years old or unsound ever been known to show his face.</p>
                     <p>Business had begun; bidding was active. A superb, as it looked to us, shining, beautiful blood bay was caracoling round the ring, under the saddle. Eighty was bid—eighty-five—ninety—going, going, going! We modestly bid ninety-one, but it was finally knocked down to another at one hundred and ten dollars, leaving us much chagrined at our loss, and not a little excited generally.</p>
                     <p>The next "lot" was a light bay, "sixteen and a<pb n="184-185" xml:id="VAC6162-00000093"/> half hands high, eight years old, and kind." That was all, modest and to the point. "How much for this superb saddle and road beast? Twenty-five! Thirty! Thirty-one!" It "hung fire." We looked round in surprise. Several sharp eyes cast sidelong glances at us. "Thirty-five," we bid boldly, looking with confidence at the twelve hundred pounds of horse-flesh; not three cents a pound!—"dog cheap." Thirty-six—seven—eight—nine. And the lot was finally knowcked down to us at forty-five dollars. We paid the bill, and led him out in triumph.</p>
                     <p>"Mister! that horse has been sold here every week for six months; HE <emph>won't go,</emph>" said a man, dressed in a carman's frock, to us, as we led our prize along the street, looking for another boy into whose hands to consign the halter. We inquired, and found the carman's synopsis of ancient history differing from most histories, in being perfectly true. Certainly the <emph>next</emph> week was not an exception. He brought twenty-nine dollars, and the sixteen lost were the most economically laid out of any dollars we ever parted with. Our eyes were opened. It was the apex of a huge, submerged mountain of<emph>honesty</emph> and <emph>frankness</emph> in horse-dealing. We have never been deceived since, and for the simplest of all simple reasons: we never buy a horse until we have tried him enough to know just what he is, paying for his use if he don't suit. If the owner won't submit to that, <emph>we don't trade.</emph>
                     </p>
                     <p>We commend our experience to the writer of the following letter, and would warmly recommend him to save his fees and costs, and send his horse—"eight years old and kind"—to Tattersall's.</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <opener>
                                    <dateline>"18—.</dateline>
                                 </opener>
                                 <p>"DEAR SIR: I left my business this spring, to live in the country, and of course bought a horse, one which I now hold, and have had him for a month. I bought him of D—, at L—. He warranted him sound, kind, and eight years old. He is the last two, but his nose bleeds going up hill, and he stumbles going down. The hair is coming out of his tail, and the horse doctor, who has been giving him physic ever since I have owned him, at a cost of fifteen dollars, thinks he has been foundered or something. Now I want to know if you consider that a sound horse legally. I want your professional opinion.<pb n="186-187" xml:id="VAC6162-00000094"/> I have written to his former owner, and he says that the horse was sound when sold, and that I must have misused him. I have n't used him at all. I can't. Please to write him, and say that if he don't do something, he will be sued. Also, write me your opinion on the matter.</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <salute>"Your obedient servant,</salute>
                                    <signed>G—."</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>Here is a section of a letter, otherwise unsuitable for publication, which contains a hint or two that may be useful to equestrians:</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <opener>
                                    <dateline>"18—.</dateline>
                                 </opener>
                                 <p>"DEAR R—: *  *  *  *  *  *  *  *  *  *  * Now for your question, on which side of the gentleman should you ride. Without doubt, on his <emph>right.</emph> I know that you will find, as you suggest, a majority against you in doing so; but my democracy is not so orthodox as it was in boyhood; indeed, I am sometimes inclined to think that 'the majority is always'—wrong. Or, to put it a little more strongly, <foreign xml:lang="LAT">'vox populi vox'—Diaboli.</foreign> At best, it is but a lame reason for doing or thinking in a certain way, that the majority do or think so.</p>
                                 <p>"One reason offered for avoiding the gentleman's right is, that he is apt to run against your feet, if on that side. I would offer to such gentleman the papa's advice to his boy, 'Never go near the water until you know how to swim.'</p>
                                 <p>"Another reason is given, that the lady shows to the best advantage if seen from the near side, and that with the gentleman on that side she is hidden. This is not so, only as regards her drapery. If she ride well, that fact can be judged of best and most critically from the off side.</p>
                                 <p>"Again, 'the English ladies ride on the gentleman's left.' Ah! there you probably have the real cause of our custom, in imitating them; but we imitate them in letter only, and not in spirit. The very reason for which they keep on the gentleman's left in England is the only one I have to offer for keeping on his right here, and it is that the gentleman may be kept between you and the passing vehicle, <abbr>i. e.,</abbr> between you and danger. This is the only question worth a moment's consideration. The English law for driving is, "Keep to the left;" the American law is, "Keep to the right." So, while the English lady keeps on<pb n="188-189" xml:id="VAC6162-00000095"/> the left of her escort, and thus places him between herself and danger, that is, the passing vehicle, an American lady should keep on his <emph>right</emph> for the <emph>same reason;</emph> but, instead of that, they imitate literally, and lose sight of the spirit. It reminds me of a funny fact in the esthetics of sheep. Place a stick in front of a flock: the first comers will jump over it; then withdraw your stick, and the rest will continue jumping over the place where the stick was.</p>
                                 <p>It has a very absurd appearance, when the way is crowded or narrow, to see the Amazon on the higher part of the street, brushing against the passing carts, carriages, and omnibuses, while her escort shrinks down toward the curb-stone, as if he were timid and protected. In open fields, or on country roads, of course there is no rule about it—with one exception, perhaps. In the June twilight, when Night is gently covering you with her vail, and the stars wink at you, and say they won't tell, then, if you want him to squeeze your hand, put his arm round your waist, kiss you, or any trifle of that kind, by all means keep on his left; <emph>he can get at you more easily.</emph> But in cities, parks, or where vehicles are passing, keep between your escort and the curbstone—that is, on his right.</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <salute>"Yours truly,</salute>
                                    <signed>G—."</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>It would be difficult to find in our hunting annals a more curious tale unfolded than the following:</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <opener>
                                    <dateline>"18—.</dateline>
                                 </opener>
                                 <p>"WELL, my dear boy, I have something to write about at last besides crops and clearings in this wild and picturesque place; and, as you will observe by the handwriting, with my wife for amanuensis, for although my brain is in working order, my hands and feet are in such a state, that it would be a feat to make use of them, to which I am not equal at present. The day after I wrote you last, being on a hunting excursion, I grew weary toward the middle of the day, and seeing a spring some fifty yards away, laid down my rifle and bag, and went to take the cold water-cure for my weariness. On raising my head and looking around, I was not a little startled to see a huge bear making toward my game-bag, from the woods she had just left. To reach my rifle before the bear reached me was out<pb n="190-191" xml:id="VAC6162-00000096"/> of the question, the bear was already nearer; so I took to my heels and the bear took to her paws after me, passing over the bag as too small game for her attention. After running about three hundred yards, I looked round and saw that that mode of escape from Mrs. Bruin's embraces was useless; so springing up the first tree, I began climbing, with the hope of reaching a secure place in the branches, where I might keep madam at bay, and wound—perhaps kill—her with my large pocket-knife; but she proved herself the better climber, and at the moment I clasped with hands and arms the lower limb of the tree, the bear caught one of my wellbooted feet in her mouth. Then came the 'tug of war,' and the loose leg and foot were desperately busy kicking the face of my antagonist, who grumbled loud and long at the manner in which I was marring her beauty. The battle lasted but a few moments, for, in her determination to 'preserve the game,' she loosened her hold of the tree, and a kick more desperate than the rest knocked her entirely free from it, when off she swung, still holding by my foot, and of course hanging by it, while I as desperately clung to the branch above, like a huge pendulum between heaven and earth—between time and eternity, my heart beating clock-like. Soon all power of struggling had gone, my sinews cracked and joints strained as if they were parting, and while the glad beams of the setting sun colored all things with a flood of holy light, I resigned myself to my fate, and fell—into a soliloquy. 'My wife didn't want me to go gunning on a Friday, she was sure something would happen.' I scolded her for her superstition; alas! it was prophecy. Little Nellie looked up from her doll, and said, 'Oh, pa! forbear.' Pa for Bear! That, too, was prophecy. As I passed the brewery, they told me they were brewing my beer, and would send it in a day or two. Bruin my bier! Alas, that, too was a prophecy, but I had no ears to hear.</p>
                                 <p>"I'll try poetry on him. 'Music has charms to tame a savage'—perhaps poetry will bring a beast to reason. <q>
                                       <lg type="quotation">
                                          <l>"DID wight e'er reach his heavenward goal</l>
                                          <l>With such a weight upon his sole,</l>
                                          <l>Achilles-like? Alas! I feel</l>
                                          <l>Only too mortal in my heel.</l>
                                          <l>Oh, Bear, forbear! I can not bear,</l>
                                          <l>This weight of "grease" thus hung in air.</l>
                                          <pb n="192-193" xml:id="VAC6162-00000097"/>
                                          <l>Only let go and fall alone—</l>
                                          <l>You will not break a single bone;</l>
                                          <l>By holding on, we both must fall;</l>
                                          <l>And then, 'tis likely, you 'll break all;</l>
                                          <l>For you'll fall 'neath my fourteen stone.</l>
                                          <l>Please, gentle Bear, go down alone.</l>
                                          <l>You save your life by letting go,</l>
                                          <l>And mine as well by doing so.</l>
                                          <l>But immortality atones</l>
                                          <l>To you should you break all your bones.</l>
                                          <l>Our Phalon will your praises spout</l>
                                          <l>Till the last 'grease' spot is sold out;</l>
                                          <l>Gunther will dress and sell your skin</l>
                                          <l>To wrap some sleighing lovers in</l>
                                          <l>But as for me, alas! once dead,</l>
                                          <l>My skin's not worth an ounce of lead.</l>
                                       </lg>
                                    </q>
                                 </p>
                                 <p>"That my poetry is not very 'good entertainment for man or beast,' I don't deny, but I doubt if Milton himself would have done better <emph>under the circumstances.</emph> However, it had no effect, and after hanging there for an hour and a half—perhaps by the watch it might have been five seconds, the mind is apt to exaggerate in a 'fix' of this kind—I let go and down we went, Bruin under, as I had warned the foolish beast. Well, her ribs went in with a crash, and her soul went out with a grunt. And I was occupied until twelve o'clock that night 'progressing' to the nearest house, one mile from the scene of my hunt. And now I am lying on the sofa, as flexible and elastic as a soft lump of putty, while dear G— is doing my spiriting with her pen.</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <salute>"Yours, as ever,</salute>
                                    <signed>M—."</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>We have a good deal of faith generally, and have tried to accept the facts set forth in that letter, but it is a sorry failure.</p>
                     <p>From the date, the commercial whirl wind of '57 seems to have dug this fortune-tomb, one among its myriad of victims.</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <opener>
                                    <dateline>"18—.</dateline>
                                 </opener>
                                 <p>"DEAR K—: Musing last night in a cosy corner of my lonely room, upon life, and more particularly upon that section of it just sinking below the horizon of time down into the ocean of the past. As the clock struck twelve, Santa Claus slipped quietly down the chimney, and, perching himself upon the mantel shelf, he nodded good-humoredly, a happy smile stole over his rubicund face, and, holding up his basket of samples, he asked me 'my intentions.' Alas! I could but shake my head. He looked surprised; the smile left his face; he slowly<pb n="194-195" xml:id="VAC6162-00000098"/> placed the basket upon his shoulder again, and I—awoke. New Year eve, and my rooms empty! New Year eve, and no tokens waiting for the morning sun to find their way to those who call me uncle, cousin, brother, friend. No, not even for yourself. How strange it seems to have been surrounded with all that money could purchase for so long, and then to be absolutely in want. For the ruin, as far as the past is concerned, is absolute and final. Do you know that I have actually known what it was to want bread? Yes, over and over again. It might have been had for the asking, but a sort of stoic pride made me leave it unasked until my head or hands had earned it. I am not sure but that it is all best as it is. I have willing hands, a stout heart, and am young enough to begin again. Still, my New Year will be sad enough; but over it hangs a fair rainbow, a halo of light, namely, your sympathy and help—. May the New Year milestone you are passing be hung with garlands; perhaps if I could see aright, I might find mine covered with them, but I can not yet. Good-bye.</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <signed>"S—."</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>Here is another wail from a maiden's heart.</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <opener>
                                    <dateline>"18—</dateline>
                                 </opener>
                                 <p>"MY OWN DEAR FRIEND: I have attempted to write you, and to write calmly, but I can not. Come to me once more—come the moment after receiving this—for Heaven's sake, come. It seems as though my very senses would leave me. Of all the suffering I have experienced or anticipated, I little dreamed I could ever be called upon to give you the proof of the unselfishness of my love for you that was given yesterday.</p>
                                 <p>"If you <emph>love</emph> her, and if you are <emph>confident</emph> she <emph>loves</emph> you, make her your wife; you will be happier, I feel that you will, and I will do all that I can to promote your happiness; though Heaven only can know how much I love you, and what is the extent of the agony I now endure.</p>
                                 <p>"Take her, make her your own, and I will try and take her to my heart, and love her for your sake. Oh, how I long to rest my weary head, but it can not be; I dare not ask for sympathy from any one. My mother looks at me quietly and anxiously; she does not know that her child's heart is broken.<pb n="196-197" xml:id="VAC6162-00000099"/> I could carse the chains which bind me. God keep my reason from giving way. Go! go! and leave me to my life-long desolation.</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <signed>A—."</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>We throw our hook for the last time, and bring up the following.</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText>
                           <body>
                              <div type="letter">
                                 <p>"WILL you ride on the fifth? If you are at leisure, I will place 'Dragon' at your disposal at about three o'clock. There is not much to be seen; the Sun is holding out his warm hands, trying to induce Nature to make love with him; but she is in her laboratory, making essences, distilling perfumes ready for a great gala day; and in her brown gloves and leather apron she will have nothing to do with his 'nonsense,' so we must take the buds and foliage in our own hearts; and as 'the eye sees whatever it brings with it the power of seeing,' perhaps our imagination will grant us perception enough to cover the scene with things of beauty. I send 'Blanche' for your inspection. 'Love me, love my dog.' If you give her a chance, she will kiss you, to that extent being less bashful than her master. I have <emph>heard</emph> that there is much poetry in a kiss; I fear hers will turn out all doggerel. Let G— see her, as she has expressed a desire to do so, and tell her that I wish I could put a portion of her headache on my shoulders; but, alas! headaches and heartaches we have to bear them, and alone, unto the bitter end."</p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>And so we close. Where the letters give an inkling of joys which are past, they are sorrowful to the soul; how much more so where suffering has given them birth; yet, next to dying the death of a good man, we should prefer that of a dead-letter. The postman knocks at the door under the designated number. "A letter for—Jones, Esq." "Do n't live here," answers the Irish "stick in-waiting." A pencil-mark is placed on the epistle, and, without even the scratch of a bare bodkin, it is <emph>dead,</emph> in due time to be forwarded to its tomb at Washington, there to be dissected and burned, where its ashes will lie until that day when all thoughts shall be revealed. It has gone to its long home; it has been launched into another world, amid flame and smoke, without a pang, without a regret for<pb n="198-199" xml:id="VAC6162-00000100"/> all the hopes or sorrows, joys or griefs, which gave it birth, or a single thought on the part of the loved, hated, or dunned Mr. Jones, from its not having lived to fulfill its destiny.</p>
                     <p>They have a profound interest, these dead-letters! They bring with them mystery, melancholy, and a brooding sadness; and we have to thank them for many a dreamy revery, as well as for incidents ludicrous and sorrowful. Their deaths, like others, often end friendship and love, and affection grows cold from fancied neglect. Who has lived many years in this sin-marred paradise, and not known the importance which may attach to a dead-letter? Anna S—, a blue-eyed sylph—now in heaven, let us hope, if there be one for the suicide—loved and was loved again. Her lover, in search of those smiles of fortune which would enable him to wed, went to the South. He wrote to her with love's own eloquence, but the letters miscarried, and reports reached her of his Southern gayety. Stung to the soul by his apparent neglect, she married another, and too late learned the madness of the act. Poor girl! she breathed chloroform and death together, and followed her letters to the grave.</p>
                     <p>And now the originals of these gleanings must go back to their tombs, from which we have snatched their spirits for the few years' immortality of print. We part with them regretfully, and would fain hand them over to those who have waited in vain for their coming, and watched as "they that watch for the morning," until "hope deferred made the heart sick" and faint, and the faith which was its best support, grew weak and doubting. But what we sympathize with is as a drop in the ocean. Day by day, this letter-maelstrom sucks in its hecatombs of victims, sad emblem of our own blundering, mistaken, or neglected lives. We have a hope, however, which they can neither claim nor share, and it is, that we shall be taken from our dead-letter office, printed in nonpareil type in the Book of Life, and placed in the library of heaven, for communion with the angels near the throne of the ALMIGHTY.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="200-201" xml:id="VAC6162-00000101"/>
               <head>"FIRE! FIRE!"</head>
               <pb n="202-203" xml:id="VAC6162-00000102"/>
               <head>"Fire! Fire!"</head>
               <p>JEREMIAH CASSANDER JONES, or, as we always called him Down-East, "Kasy," a six-feet-two cousin from New Hampshire, to whom I had been showing the "lions" about town for the previous week, expressed a desire to see the far-famed Bowery Theater before he left. The place was <foreign xml:lang="LAT">terra incognita</foreign> to myself, and as I had heard of, and wished to see, the arrangements for preventing its being for the fourth time destroyed by fire, I acceded; and that we might have a good opportunity of examining the hydraulies, we put ourselves and a dollar into the hands of the box-keeper, a half an hour before the curtain rose, and told him our wishes. He promptly took us over the building, and explained the mode<pb n="204-205" xml:id="VAC6162-00000103"/> of "throwing cold water" on any undue warmth that the house might exhibit.</p>
               <p>Connected with the large mains through which the Croton water passes down the Bowery is a six-inch pipe in front of the Theater; this pipe runs under ground to the inner wall which separates the boxes from the lobbies, and up through that, and hidden in it, to the gallery on the fourth tier; from this main, pipes of two inches diameter are led in every direction where they will be of use in case of fire; thus, two of them are carried from the upright pipe under the floor of the first tier to the front and lower edge of the boxes, where they separate and are carried round the entire circle, and being gilded and burnished, form in appearance a merely ornamental molding. At the distance of every few feet are brass apertures about one and a half inches long, just sufficient to give direction to the water, and having a one-inch bore. The jets on the sides of the house pointed toward the second tier on the opposite side, while those in the center of the circle pointed toward the orchestra and stage. The same arrangement was made in the second tier, and the pipes carried round just above the gas brackets, gilded, and with similar openings to those below, the side jets pointing toward the third tier opposite, and those in front toward the stage. The pipes round the third and fourth tiers were the same, only pointing in different directions; the center opening pointing toward the proscenium and private boxes, and those on the side pointing partly toward the dome and partly toward the door-openings opposite, at the back of the boxes. Each pipe, as it reached the end of the tier toward the stage, was turned round and carried to the lobby, where it ended, with an opening to play the entire length of the passage.</p>
               <p>We understood that a similar arrangement had been effected for the stage, fed by other apparatus from the back street; but we had no time to examine that before the play commenced.</p>
               <p>In the six-inch pipe in front of the theater was a huge stop-cock, the iron head of which protruded just above the sidewalk, and could be turned by a loose crank-handle, which was kept hung up just inside of the pit-door, so that in case of fire it could<pb n="206-207" xml:id="VAC6162-00000104"/> be had at a moment's warning. This stop-cock once turned, the house would be flooded. I have been thus particular, for the better understanding of the harrowing scenes about to be described.</p>
               <p>Having satisfied our curiosity, we sat down in the "dress circle;" a distinction arising probably from the fact that those occupying it generally had coats and hats on, while in other parts of the house, coats, hats, and vests were mostly dispensed with.</p>
               <p>The hour of performance being at hand, black spirits and white, blue spirits and gray, began to pour into the pit; some in red shirts, some in striped, some with suspenders, some without; but all noisy, and all in good-humor. In the boxes came pretty Jewesses from Chatham Street, pretty milliners from the Bowery, "Short Boys," "Huge-fisters," "Bowery Boys," Eastern "Young America," in all its glory of misshapen beards, greasy hair, and large cravats; and above all was the gallery, thronged with our "colored brethren," of all shades from whitey-brown to jet black.</p>
               <p>The orchestra began playing; the audience was silent, save the gentle cracking of peanut-shells. The music ceased, and the curtain rose, showing a favorite actor on the stage. A short, spasmodic burst of applause, peculiar to the place, consisting of cries, "cat-calls," whistling, etc., followed, and the play proceeded. It was the "Lady of Lyons," and the Claude Melnotte of the evening for a time went on swimmingly with his <foreign xml:lang="FRA">rôle.</foreign> Loaferdom in the pit was subdued and quiet, and the white handkerchiefs at the brown, black, and blue eyes in the boxes formed a sort of halo for his genius—his screaming, rousing, passion-run-mad love-making. Well, as the scene went on, he had married "Pauline," repented him of the trick, taken her to his mother's cottage, and confessed what a bad boy he had been; and as she stood sobbing, with her hands covering her face, he undertook to tell the history of his love: <q>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>ACTOR—</speaker>
                        <lg type="quotation">
                           <l>My father died, and I, the peasant born,</l>
                           <l>Was my own lord. Then did I seek to rise</l>
                           <l>From out the prison of my mean estate,</l>
                           <l>And with such jewels as the exploring mind</l>
                           <l>Brings from the caves of knowledge, buy my ransom</l>
                           <l>From those twin—twin!—twin?</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>PROMPTER—</speaker>
                        <lg type="quotation">
                           <l>*  *  *  buy my ransom</l>
                           <l>From those twin j—s, mind!</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>ACTOR—</speaker>
                        <lg type="quotation">
                           <l>*  *  *  buy my ransom</l>
                           <l>From those twin, twins?</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="208-209" xml:id="VAC6162-00000105"/>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>PROMPTER—</speaker>
                        <l>*  *  *  twin jailers of the aspiring mind.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>ACTOR—</speaker>
                        <lg type="quotation">
                           <l>*  *  those twin jailers of the aspiring mind.</l>
                           <l>Low birth and iron fortune. Thy bright image</l>
                           <l>Glassed in my soul, took all the hues of glory—glory!—glory!—glory?</l>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And the prompter cried "glory," and the actor cried "glory," but nothing came of it; the dream had departed: he struck his forehead, as if he would punish the bump of memory; then turned to the audience, and said: "Ladies and gentlemen, I beg to apologize for this sudden lapse of memory, which to me is entirely unaccountable." He then began the paragraph again, and went through it without a blunder. I felt, during these few moments, that purgatory would have been a relief; and I never saw a play for months afterward with any satisfaction, for at every hesitation of the actor I expected to hear something about the "twins" or "glory" spluttered out.</p>
               <p>"Kasy" was soon absorbed in the performance, and while his ears and those of the groundlings were being split, I will mention what was passing outside.</p>
               <p>"Jim, do you want a check?" said a red-shirted vagabond to a long, round-shouldered, overgrown boy.</p>
               <p>"Yes," said the latter, catching at the check, slipping it quietly into his pocket, and looking around to see who was watching him. The next moment he went to the pit entrance; but the door-keeper was too sharp for him, and turned him away with some indignity. Jim returned, brim-full of wrath, to his companions, venting curses against the whole establishment.</p>
               <p>"Jim," said one of them, in a deep whisper, "duck 'em!"</p>
               <p>"What!"</p>
               <p>"Duck 'em!"</p>
               <p>"How? what do you mean? sa-a-ay?"</p>
               <p>Drawing them closely round him, and glancing at the same time from side to side, to see that no one was near, he explained:</p>
               <p>"You see that square bit of iron in the walk? Well, turn that, and every one on 'em in the house<pb n="210-211" xml:id="VAC6162-00000106"/> will be ducked. It leads to pipes all over the place, to be set agoin' in case of fire. My brother Bill works in the theater, and he told me so.</p>
               <p>"How can we turn it?"</p>
               <p>"The crank is inside, over the pit-door. I'll take the check, and make a muss with the door-keeper, while you climb up and get it down."</p>
               <p>"Kasy," said I, "you must remain alone, if you wish to see the play out. With this heat, and tobacco, and gas atmosphere, I am becoming too unwell to remain."</p>
               <p>Kasy left his seat, and we sauntered out on the balcony in front of the theater. Looking over the railings, we saw several boys rush from the pit entrance, and hurriedly cross the street, followed by others, who joined them on the other side. After hesitating a moment, to see if they were pursued, they walked down to the corner, crossed the street again, and came up on our side, slowly and compactly, in a body.</p>
               <p>"They have got the crank!" said Kasy, in a hoarse whisper, grasping my arm.</p>
               <p>"What crank?"</p>
               <p>"Why, the crank he showed us in the pit, to turn on the water in case of fire."</p>
               <p>I looked, and saw the handle half hidden among them: then, with a sudden impulse, and a mutual wish to see the result of the mischief that was evidently brewing, we rushed across the balcony and lobby, down stairs as fast, and into our places in the first tier, too much absorbed in our anticipations to notice the hundred black looks from the surrounding throng.</p>
               <p>The rouged fellow on the stage was rushing to the wars. Pauline was screaming her loudest to arrest his steps. Fathers, mothers, and uncles were helping on the excitement with their cries and babblement, while cotton and cambric in the boxes were trying to assuage the grief of Bowery milliners, dressmakers, and pretty Jewesses.</p>
               <pb n="212-213" xml:id="VAC6162-00000107"/>
               <p>"Better save their handkerchiefs for toweling," said Kasy, as we pressed our hats tightly on our heads, and screwed our courage to the sticking point.</p>
               <p>"Brayvo! brayvo!" cried the coatless; and suddenly, amid the applause, there went over the whole house a rushing sound, like a cataract or a whirlwind, or the escape of steam from the valves of a dozen engines. The next moment, and from balcony, boxes, gallery, stage, there came hissing out innumerable streams of water, each playing toward a higher place on the opposite side of the house, crossing each other at all possible angles; breaking into millions of drops, sparkling in the gaslight like diamonds, or as if the goddesses on the dome were throwing down brilliants by the ton. For a moment the scene, filled with rainbows and sparkling, dazzling foam, rivaled our most gorgeous dreams, our wildest imaginings of a sea-nymph's palace: the next, the gas was extinguished, and all was utter darkness. Then from that dense and frightened mass of beings went up a wild and universal scream of terror and despair that made the huge dome tremble, and for the time drowned the roar of the rushing, hissing, maddened water. Another moment, and all the men, women, and children which crowded the house from pit to dome were drenched, as if they had been plunged into the current of the river. It was <q>
                     <l>"Water! water! everywhere."</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Yet the cry, the horror, the dread was nothing but "Fire! fire!" The house echoed it to the lobbies, the lobbies to the street, the street to the bells, and the bells to the city.</p>
               <p>The loafer cried to the loafer, "The Bowery's on fire again!" and off they ran toward their Temple of the Muses. The lawyer said to his antagonist, as he cannoned and held the black, "The Bowery's as on fire <emph>again!</emph>" and visions of insurance suits dawned upon his official mind. The insurance president said to the merchant, "The Bowery's on fire AGAIN!" and smiled, for the had long since ceased to take "risks" on that concern. The policeman said, as he was relieved, "The Bowery's on fire again!" and shrugged his shoulders as he left his beat. The fireman cried to the fireman, "The Bowery's on fire again!" and their "ha! ha!" rang along the streets<pb n="214-215" xml:id="VAC6162-00000108"/> as they rushed for the "machine." And the fire-bells, with huge clamor, cried to their fellows, "The Bowery's on fire again!" There was <q>
                     <l>"Fire! fire!" everywhere, but not a spark was seen.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>In the house itself a general rush was made by the drenched and saturated mass of human beings toward the doors, over seats, benches, partitions, and the bodies of those who had fallen, or were knocked down in the excitement, and bonnetless, skirtless, bleeding, and wet, the audience appeared in the lobbies. But a new terror awaited them, for as the gas still burned there, and the water was dashed along from the opened pipes, the impression seized them that the fire was in front, and many rushed back, screaming in utter despair. Some called upon Heaven for mercy. "Mother! Jane! John! Father!" mixed with wild cries, resounded from all sides, and still the blinding, deafening, roaring, rushing water poured down in foam and spray, like the whirlwind storm of the tropics.</p>
               <p>Kasy and I had hastened back <emph>to</emph> "see the fun," and we now felt as if we were half guilty of the whole catastrophe, and trembled at the scene. At first it required all our strength to keep our feet against the crush; but as that passed, and we recovered the use of our faculties, we ran among the people in the darkness and dashing water, and tried to explain, but it was like talking to maniacs.</p>
               <p>We then turned our attention to those who were trodden upon, but the furious water almost blinded us, and we had to grope about the boxes to find them.</p>
               <p>In the lobbies the scene was still more deplorable. Some of the gas-jets were still burning, and streams of water were playing in all directions. Every human being was drenched; and muslins, silks, and calicoes clung to the persons of the wearers, as if they had been bathing in the surf of the ocean. Hatless, dressless, coatless, bonnetless, they were screaming, swearing, pushing, crushing toward the street.</p>
               <p>Outside, the excitement was equally intense. The impression that the Bowery was on fire had spread around the neighborhood.</p>
               <p>Firemen were attaching their hose to the hydrants; and in a few moments, to add to the confusion, <emph>they</emph> also were playing into the darkness, where there<pb n="216-217" xml:id="VAC6162-00000109"/> was already water enough to extinguish a dozen actual fires; while the few persons who really knew, or guessed the cause, were looking in vain for the crank, or running about the neighborhood to awaken sleepy blacksmiths and plumbers!</p>
               <p>In the gallery the scene was horrible. At the first rush the narrow winding stair-case was choked up with human beings, piled, in all shapes and angles, up to the very ceiling; a suffocating, groaning, dying mass; while for those behind them there were no means of egress, save jumping into the pit, which was certain destruction. A rope was at length found that some carpenters had used in repairing the dome. This was tied to the railing, and the end lowered in the darkness, amid the blinding spray from two hundred water-jets. A man descended the rope; it did not reach the ground, and he fell, with a cry of agony. Two women followed, and as they reached the end, their screams were so piercing and shrill that Kasy and myself were attracted to the spot. He darted like a cat up the slender iron column, to try and <emph>feel</emph> what was the matter, while I stood on the front of the boxes; and so we helped them down. Kasy tied the end of the rope to the column, and the others got off at the different tiers as they descended, and so escaped by the main stair-case.</p>
               <p>The dreadful impression of fire was still kept up, for although the footlights were extinguished at once, the six perpendicular rows of gas-jets which light the scenes were not reached by the water; and these, shining on the stage-side of the spray, although they could not illuminate anything through the dense mass of water, shone just sufficiently to give an inkling, to the last, that the stage was on fire.</p>
               <p>The members of the orchestra, at the first alarm, sprang, some into the pit, some on the stage, and disappeared.</p>
               <p>In the stage-box we had noticed a white-cravated and white-bonneted group of three couples, whom we had taken for a bridal party. When the alarm was given, two of the ladies fainted, but recovered again as the water came dashing upon them. Then they opened the door, but the light led them to suppose that the lobby was on fire. Hurriedly closing it again, they sprang over the box upon the stage, the groomsmen and partners fortunately running to the<pb n="218-219" xml:id="VAC6162-00000110"/> rear, while the groom made a leap for the pit, but landed on the kettle-drum, through the top of which he crushed, and became wedged within its copper sides, unable to move. The bride, following his example, jumped also, crushing the base-viol, which partly broke her fall. Groping about in despair, over instruments, desks, and chairs, and finding a barrier on all sides, she became bewildered, and cowered down in a corner, where the orchestra partition screened her partially from the furious water, and, almost unconscious with terror, awaited her fate.</p>
               <p>The water, which had now been pouring from all points for some considerable time, at the rate of three hundred gallons a minute, had acquired considerable depth; indeed, soon after the bride had cowered in her corner, in despairing apathy, it had reached her chin and mouth, and began to choke her, before she was startled from her position; but she had then lost all knowledge of her whereabouts, or what was the matter, except that she was drowning and alone!—where, why, or how, were sealed mysteries. Again she made spasmodic efforts to free herself from what seemed a dreadful nightmare, and clung to the partition until the water again rose to her chin, then suddenly consciousness and memory returned, but with it no physical strength, except to cling to what she held by, and utter scream after scream, so loud and shrill, and embodying so much of the pain of a death-agony, that Kasy and I were attracted by it from our comparatively quiet neighborhood.</p>
               <p>We plunged into the pit, now full of water, and half swimming, half wading on the benches, when we could feel them, we soon reached the orchestra, where a slight glimmer penetrated from the sidescenes. Kasy was first there; but being on the left, he found the man wedged in the kettle-drum, and extricated him. Poor fellow! he had fainted, and was quite unconscious. Having waded down the center, where the screams still guided me, I came directly upon the bride, and recognized her at once as the occupant of the stage-box. Her beautiful black hair was floating upon the water, her head thrown back, and her black eyes almost starting from their sockets in terror. I had waded up to the orchestra partition, which was covered with<pb n="220-221" xml:id="VAC6162-00000111"/> water, and was planting my foot as firmly as possible to reach and secure her, when she turned and saw me.</p>
               <p>Poor thing! I was the first human being she had seen through all that condensed eternity, since she had tried to escape. With a wild and unnatural energy she sprang up toward me, and I caught her in my arms, while she clung to me as if it had been a death grapple, and wept, oh! how passionately! Her sense of loneliness, of utter desertion, had lent her position half its terrors, and the sight of a mere hodman, at that moment of despair, would have been a blessing. I believe, had I gently laid her down in the water then, she would have died without a struggle.</p>
               <p>But we were in real danger. In my excitement I had forgotten the stage, the nearest place of safety, and also that the pit ran under the boxes. The bride was utterly incapable of physical exertion, except to cling to me, and I had to bear her entire weight, with the water dashing from above, and beyond my depth between the benches.</p>
               <p>Plunging along from bench to bench, with one arm round her, one struggling in the water, I soon found my strength, which had in a great measure been spent in previous exertions, rapidly ebbing with every effort. Still I plunged on, and called, "Kasy! Kasy!" but no answer. I called to Heaven for help, but Heaven also was silent. I felt the unhappy being on my arm lean more heavily on me. I felt her cheeks, and they were cold. Giving another plunge more desperate than all, I lost my footing, and down we sank into the water.</p>
               <p>I felt a shudder pass over my companion's body; her head sank down and rested on my shoulder; her arms relaxed their convulsive hold. We were dying together. The water gurgled in my throat and choked me. My folly assumed huge proportions, and the misdeeds of a lifetime flashed upon my consciousness, and made me despair of mercy from its Fountain-head, toward which I was hastening for judgment.</p>
               <p>The poor girl, in the very flush of her new existence, with a husband's first kiss upon her cheek, was <emph>dead.</emph> She had sunk from my grasp, a cold, wet, soulless, inert mass, and I was breathing water and<pb n="222-223" xml:id="VAC6162-00000112"/> death together, when suddenly Kasy's strong hand grasped my hair, and—</p>
               <p>I opened my eyes in my shower-bath. The week before I had become a red-hot convert to hydropathy, and in my sleep had risen, and probably for the previous ten minutes had been enjoying the luxuries of an extra bath and the nightmare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>EDITH.</head>
               <pb n="224-225" xml:id="VAC6162-00000113"/>
               <head>Edith.</head>
               <p>HE entered unannounced, and his foot-fall made no noise on the soft carpet. He stood still a moment, for he saw before him the being who held his destiny in her hands.</p>
               <p>The rooms were separated by an arch and columns only; and Edith sat there, with a single gas-jet burning but dimly above her, and shedding, as it came through the ground-glass, a soft and moon-like light about the room, while it threw into shade the curtained and mirrored vistas beyond. Her dark eyes were bent on the carpet before her, but unconscious of their own gaze. The volume she had been reading had fallen unnoticed from her fingers to the floor; and her arm, hanging at her side, rivaled in whiteness the lace that but partially hid<pb n="226-227" xml:id="VAC6162-00000114"/> it from view. The other arm rested on the sofa, and her head leaned forward, and rested lightly on the ends of her taper fingers. There were no rings in those delicate ears; no bracelet on that graceful wrist; no ring on the slender fingers: and much I love to see beauty <emph>so</emph> adorned.</p>
               <p>A grave, almost sad, expression rested on her face. Her breath went and came, and her bosom rose and fell slowly: each respiration left her with a sigh, and the interval was so long, that it seemed as if she had ceased to breathe. Selwyn moved toward her, still unobserved. His heart beat faster as he approached; he breathed more heavily. A possible future without her! The thought weighed on him like an incubus, and he hesitated before opening the gate that might either lead him to a precipice or a paradise.</p>
               <p>"Edith!"</p>
               <p>The emotion with which her name was uttered lent a thrilling tone to that deep, low voice. She started, and looked up, and met his earnest gaze; but her eyes drooped again to the floor, and the warm blood came to her face and neck, then left them paler than before: but no word followed the glance, and they remained a few moments in silence.</p>
               <p>"Edith!</p>
               <p>"Ten years ago, a little black-eyed being, you flitted in my pathway for a moment, and then passed away, like a gleam of sunshine through the clouds of a troubled sky. The music of your merry laugh rang on my ear like the echo from silver bells. The playful archness of your ever-changing ways seemed to rob guile of its meaning; but there was at times in those sparkling eyes a look of earnestness beyond your years, that made the beholder pause and ask a blessing on your voyage of life. You were flowering into existence, and the many-colored petals of thought, of hope, of affection were opening to life; and the gardener, Imagination, took the plant, which gave promise of such beautiful flowers, and transplanted it into the most hallowed nook of what there is of garden in my being; and he tended, watered, and watched over it, taking here a leaf, there a branch, until he had made it a perfect unity. And the plant grew and grew; and, as it grew, it turned, like the statue of the ancient sculptor, into<pb n="228-229" xml:id="VAC6162-00000115"/> a new life, and it became one of the Penates, and its image was niched in the wall of my soul.</p>
               <p>"You came again, Edith, when the girl's form had rounded into womanhood; when the laugh had lost its merry echo, but was deepening to the heart. You came again, Edith, and I found my fancy had not over-painted, my imagination had not done justice to your being. Your earnest eyes gazed out upon the plastic world, and sought and recognized all things beautiful and good in nature, art, and sentiment; and thoughts of wondrous depth oft came, and flashed like lightning on the subject that we analyzed; and the quick play of weird and airy fancies, too, as if you sought to hide with flowers the fruit your soul-tree bore. Years have rolled by since then, Edith, and I have always met the same kind, frank, and genial welcoming; no more: no word, no act that hate itself could misconstrue; but, Edith, I have been awakened from this dream of friendship, and—O GOD! the all I cast upon the hazard of this die!</p>
               <p>"Edith! I love you!"</p>
               <p>Edith's eyes were still cast down. When he began speaking, her bosom heaved with a quickened motion, and, as he went on, she pressed her handkerchief and hands there, to hide the agitation that was mastering her; and as the last words left his lips, eloquent with the deep tone that passion had given them, the tears welled from her eyelids.</p>
               <p>They might be tears of pity only—<emph>might</emph> be tears of love.</p>
               <p>Selwyn bent to his knee before her, and taking her hand in his, said:</p>
               <p>"Edith, a word before my fate is sealed. I bring no <emph>selfish</emph> love to offer at this shrine. If in the deep recesses of your woman's heart <emph>another</emph> reigns supreme, or even—"</p>
               <p>She raised her eyes to his, and their gaze met in a long, earnest, deep, absorbing look, that joined their souls forever, and revealed the love she had cherished in her heart for years. He elasped her fair head, sobbing, to his breast; his arms were pressed around her form; his soul blessed her in silence; a psalm of thanksgiving went up to Heaven from his heart, and his warm lips pressed their first kiss upon her smooth, white brow.</p>
               <pb n="230-231" xml:id="VAC6162-00000116"/>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>"NOW, Peter, we are ready."</p>
                  <p>How proudly those beautiful bays arched their graceful necks, pricked up their ears, and pawed the crisp snow, as they shook into a merry jingle the circles of silver bells round their bodies, and depending from their heads in a graceful sweep beneath the martingales, impatiently waiting for the motion of the reins or the crack of the whip, as if "Peter" were a god, and they proud to do his bidding.</p>
                  <p>"All ready, Peter!"</p>
                  <p>And off they started; not suddenly, or with a jerk, but prancing and pawing their way, as if they, too, knew the freight of happy hearts they were drawing, and sympathized in their gladness.</p>
                  <p>And who were the happy beings behind our beautiful bays, to whom the present was like sunshine, the future without a cloud?—the present profound peace, the future without a sigh?—the present a garden of flowers, the future an immortality of fresh greenness and fruit?</p>
                  <p>Two were affianced hearts and affianced hands, and two in a few days were to stand near them at the altar, when the vows which had been for long years spoken in their heart of hearts before GOD were to be shaped into words before man.</p>
                  <p>First, there was Edith of the queenly brow and dark, earnest eye, with the ringing laugh, that came not often, but, when it did, it came from her heart, and found its echo in your own; it resembled the spring blossoms of the fruit-trees, which fill the eye with a sense of beauty; but they spring from roots which shoot down far into the earth. So it rang gayly on the ear; but your rougher nature was softened under its sweet influence, and you felt that its roots were in her soul.</p>
                  <p>Then there were Sidnie and Jenny, the chosen friends for her bridal; the first with a calm, gentle, serious face when in repose, which turned, as it became lighted with a smile (it seemed like magic), into as mischief-loving a countenance as the sun ever shone upon—the mischief that could not harm a<pb n="232-233" xml:id="VAC6162-00000117"/> worm, but would leave her face to make room for tears if it hurt the feelings of the meanest. And Jenny, the fair young Jenny, with the white brow and curling light-brown hair, and a neck that might send the sculptor to his studio to work—no need to <emph>dream</emph> of ideals now—the thoughtful, impulsive child of nature, weighing her words in serious moods, but, when the gayer ones came round, no lark's song could be more impulsive. The words came first, and as the after-thought showed the odd fancies that her words might paint, her blushes gave them color and relief. Oh, she was more lovable so than thousands who never say a thing amiss, and measure every word!</p>
                  <p>And Selwyn sat there, in the prime of his manhood, with the happy three: his bark had been tempest-tossed enough, and weathered many a gale of passion and ambition; but now the haven of rest was in view, the sails mostly furled, streamer flying, the music (of his beating heart) sounding from the quarter-deck. With him all was peace, calm assurance of his present and his future, the will, the strength to guide and protect the dark-eyed being at his side, the heart that overflowed with affection, that loved as it never had loved, as it never would again.</p>
                  <p>Our bays had left the town behind them, and were on the broad, smooth, white avenue; their slender limbs moving quick and regular as clock-work, their silver bells echoing so musically in the still, cold air; their heads not so erect now, their ears laid back: and on they went, with the speed of light, as if they had a human enthusiasm, and were earnest in their work. And dogs ran out from the wayside cottages, barking, jumping, and frolicking in the fresh, light snow; springing in and out between the hoofs of the horses, as if they were beings of air, and could not be harmed; frisking about in the snow-flakes, throwing them up, and barking again as they fell about their ears. The air was still as the sleep of a child, and exhilarating as the first glass of the foaming wine. The hoofs trod on the crisp snow, and the runners slid over it with a <emph>crunching</emph> sound.</p>
                  <p>All things were white; fences lay hidden under broad fields of snow, on which the sunlight shone, reflected, and sparkled; but it was like the grace of<pb n="234-235" xml:id="VAC6162-00000118"/> Heaven to some sinners' hearts—it lay there unmelted and the same.</p>
                  <p>The trees had vails of white snow-lace hanging about them, as if they were arrayed for the bridal with the coming spring.</p>
                  <p>And the happy hearts in our flying sleigh, what of them? Wit, humor, repartee flew from lip to lip, and from ear to ear, with all the <emph>sparkle</emph> of the scene about them, with all the <emph>warmth</emph> of the June sunshine; and white, and brown, and gray warm furs were around and upon them, and hanging from the sleigh in graceful folds; and great, odd, weird eyes stared out from the furs, as if the life had been taken from the animals with their skins, and retained in them.</p>
                  <p>Oh, they were gay and mirthful, and merry and arch; and they laughed and talked lightly of their love, with graceful words: but it was like the white foam on the ocean, covering unfathomed depths; like the myriad forms, the graceful beauty of the weed which rests lightly on the surface of the sea; like the airy forms of the fairy snow-flakes, covering a warm earth full of hidden flowers and fruit; like the mist seen from the mountains, hiding for a moment the profound depth of the green vale! On went our gallant bays, as if the goal were before them, covered with thousands to welcome their coming, and the race were for life.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="236-237" xml:id="VAC6162-00000119"/>
                  <p>SUDDEN and startling as the cry of "fire" in the still night, as the thunder-clap from a sunny sky, came the thrilling whistle of a locomotive, ringing over the fields with an unearthly echo: and, suddenly as a flash, the spirited bays sprang aside from the horrid sound. A moment the runner hung on the edge of the steep bank, where the snow hid some broken rocks; another moment, and they were all dashed from the sleigh. One of the horses fell, and brought the other struggling upon him. Peter was swung round through the air, but held on to the reins as if it were a death-gripe; and darting up from the place where he was thrown, he sprang to the horses' heads, and held them tightly, before they could rise and make off. Jenny was thrown down the entire bank, but her wrappings of fur and the snow saved her unhurt, and she sprang up toward Edith's prostrate form. Sidnie's head struck first, and for a moment she was unconscious, but the cold snow on her face revived her. Selwyn caught at the sides of the sleigh to keep himself from falling upon Edith: the wrench on his arm was a powerful one, but it brought him to the ground on his feet.</p>
                  <p>And Edith, poor Edith! she was thrown upon a rock that the snow had but slightly covered, and lay there inanimate and unconscious as the stone which had, perhaps, given her the death-blow. Selwyn sprang to her side, and snatched her up with the eagerness of terror, but the gentleness of a child. In a moment he had reached the bank, and enveloped the pale, breathless form in a fur-robe. Then he called to the driver of an empty sleigh that was passing, and cried:</p>
                  <p>"Here, driver, quick! here's gold, <emph>gold</emph>—quick! as you love HEAVEN, to —— Street!"</p>
                  <p>In a moment they were seated, and away again. Selwyn clasped the body of poor Edith to his breast, but a tremor shook the strong man, as if he were a child. He had shut his eyes as he placed the furs round her fair form, for fear he <emph>might</emph> see blood, though he did not dare to own the fear even to himself. He might have felt her pulse, to see if she<pb n="238-239" xml:id="VAC6162-00000120"/> lived. No, he could not do that; his soul clung to the uncertainty, to this agony of doubt, in preference to learning that which might unhinge his reason in despair.</p>
                  <p>Dead! Dead? The blackness of darkness seemed to be closing on him like the door of a dungeon, as he shrank back, appalled, from the frightful word.</p>
                  <p>"Faster! man, faster: for GOD'S sake, faster!"</p>
                  <p>The horses sprang into a run as they felt the lash on their backs. Houses, fields, snow-drifts flew past them, but the minutes seemed ages as they went on. Not a word was uttered; no one dared even to look at the other, lest the answering glance should be despair—<emph>death.</emph>
                  </p>
                  <p>The city is reached at last; spire after spire is left behind. All things make way for the furious career of the sleigh; all lookers-on think the horses are beyond control, and so they pass. Another minute, and, covered with foam, they are drawn up at the door.</p>
                  <p>Selwyn lifted the still, motionless form that rested on his breast, as if it had been a child's, and bore it up the steps. The door opened; he went on, and up again to the chamber, and, laying his precious burden gently on the bed, fell on his knees, and said, or rather groaned:</p>
                  <p>"Oh, GOD of Heaven! have mercy on—Oh, GOD! oh, GOD!"</p>
                  <p>And he placed his hands over his face and burning eyelids, buried them in the bed, and groaned aloud: <q>
                        <l>"The strong man in his agony."</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="240-241" xml:id="VAC6162-00000121"/>
                  <p>AN hour has passed: the surgeon is still at the bedside: two fractured ribs have been set, and <emph>life</emph> is there, but Edith has uttered no word, made no cry, no movement when the crushed bones were replaced, and she lay there pale and motionless, the faint, faint pulse the only indication of life. Selwyn stood over her with his arms folded, motionless and silent as the dead, but despair in the lines of his face.</p>
                  <p>Suddenly a faint flush passed over her cheeks; then she opened her eyes a moment, looked up in her lover's face with an earnest gaze, and said:</p>
                  <p>"Tell Peter not to drive so fast, please, dear Selwyn."</p>
                  <p>He fell on his knees and caught her hand, but the light had faded away again; the eyes were closed; she was motionless as marble, and as white; and so another hour of dreadful doubt passed on.</p>
                  <p>Again a deep flush colors her face, brow, neck, with an almost purple hue; her pulse beats with a bounding motion, as if it would burst; a groan of pain escapes her lips; it passes away, and she opens her eyes calmly as before, and her consciousness has all returned.</p>
                  <p>Then Selwyn knelt by the bedside, and took her white hand in his, and she looked in his face, with a fond but sad and melancholy smile, and said, in a weak, soft voice, almost a whisper:</p>
                  <p>"I remember all, dear Selwyn; are <emph>they</emph> hurt?"</p>
                  <p>"Oh!" she groaned again, as the bounding blood shot through her veins, and then left her paler, whiter than before.</p>
                  <p>Then she opened her eyes once more, with a look of such deep pity for <emph>him,</emph> and in a weak, whispering voice, said: "Be strong to bear, dear Selwyn: I am dying."</p>
                  <p>He knew it already in his heart, but the uttered words startled him with a shock of pain.</p>
                  <p>"GOD help us, Edith; but the surgeon is here, dear, <emph>dear</emph> Edith. How is it with you? Can he do nothing?"</p>
                  <p>"Nothing, Selwyn—nothing. I feel it here, thank<pb n="242-243" xml:id="VAC6162-00000122"/> GOD, without pain now, but bleeding deep down beyond his reach—Selwyn!"</p>
                  <p>Her eyes sought his with a look of holy, infinite love; a look that passed into his soul, and rested there, a sweet, sad light, that clung to him through life.</p>
                  <p>"Selwyn! <emph>Wednesday</emph> was to have been the day of our bridal, and—and—I shall be in heaven within the hour, Selwyn."</p>
                  <p>A shudder passed over his frame, but, with the effort of a giant, he subdued the outward and visible form of his agony, pressed the white hand to his lips, rose on his feet, and beckoned to the minister, who had been sent for with the surgeon, to approach. Then he drew out the ring that had been prepared for the "Wednesday," gave it to him, and pointed to Edith. He then raised her gently from the bed, and passed his arm round her slender waist. His right hand held hers, her pale head rested on his breast, and her eyes were turned up toward his with a look as if her soul was passing to his own.</p>
                  <p>The minister opened the book and said:</p>
                  <p>"Dearly beloved, we are gathered together here in the sight of GOD and before this company, to join together this man and this woman, in holy matrimony.</p>
                  <p>"I require and charge you both (as ye will answer at the dreadful day of judgment, when the secrets of all hearts shall be disclosed), that if either of you know any impediment why ye may not be lawfully joined together in matrimony, ye do now confess it."</p>
                  <p>Then the minister continued, and said:</p>
                  <p>"Selwyn, wilt thou have this woman to be thy wedded wife? Wilt thou love her, comfort her, honor and keep her in sickness and in health, and, forsaking all others, keep thee only unto her so long as ye both shall live?"</p>
                  <p>Those who were present sobbed aloud; tear after tear rolled down the cheeks of the minister; and Selwyn groaned, rather than said: "I will!"</p>
                  <p>Tears came to his eyes also, the first tears of his manhood; not tears of relief, such as well up from a woman's heart; no, they burned their way to his eyelids, and left a scorched and arid path.</p>
                  <p>The minister said again:</p>
                  <p>"Edith, wilt thou have this man to be thy wedded<pb n="244-245" xml:id="VAC6162-00000123"/> husband? Wilt thou obey him and serve him, love, honor, and keep him in sickness and in health, and forsaking all others, keep thee only unto him so long as ye both shall live?"</p>
                  <p>Edith's gaze was withdrawn from Selwyn's face: she looked at the minister, and closed her eyelids in token of approval. She could not speak.</p>
                  <p>Then the minister joined their hands together, placed his own upon them, and said, in solemn tone:</p>
                  <p>"What GOD hath joined together, let no man put asunder."</p>
                  <p>The fair head leaned more heavily against Selwyn's breast, and he bent down and kissed the pale, white brow of the soulless form before him.</p>
                  <p>Edith was dead!</p>
                  <p>Selwyn laid her on the bed again, and stood at her side. His soul seemed to leave him in maddened frenzy to seek his Edith; and yet to have left his body still with consciousness: he felt numbed and cold, and the blood gathered round his heart, but lent no heat to it; thick blackness appeared to be gathering about him, shutting out all things, coming nearer, nearer, and narrower, until it seemed as if it would crush him, and he wrestled as a strong man with a giant to throw it off; and as this nightmare of the soul passed away, and he opened his eyes again, there lay the cold, marble-like temple which had held his holy of holies, that GOD had closed forever.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="246-247" xml:id="VAC6162-00000124"/>
                  <p>LONG years have gone since then to the past ages. Little ones, who were prattling their nursery rhymes, now govern the nations. Trees, whose green foliage shaded the forest-grounds, rot in old ships on the ocean. Seeds, then springing from the earth, now east their broad shadow over the fields. Many, whose fame echoed from shore to shore, and in whose dreams Immortality had marked them for her own, lie unremembered beneath the sod. A few, who sank to unnoted, unhonored graves, now shed their light over the nations; and once more we look back and see that mankind had "entertained its angels unawares."</p>
                  <p>The gay young companions of the fatal ride listen to the prattle of little ones who cluster round grand-mamma's arm-chair. But most of those who made the moving, living, breathing "world" are where the lapse of time is unnoted and unknown: where the hour and the thousand years are alike.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>DO you see that old man, upon whose face three-score-and-ten has made its mark; whose hair is all white with the snows of the winter of age, but whose step is firm and quick, whose glance is earnest and absorbed, unheeding the crowd about him? Do you note the profound yet calm expression of sadness, of sorrow over his pale face; a sadness of the soul that seems to be part of his existence, and pervades him like an atmosphere? Do you see him turn at the importunity of that sick beggar, with a quick, penetrating glance, listen to her story, and walk away with her to her cold, wet, fireless <emph>home,</emph> that he may winnow true suffering from pretense, and aid accordingly? It is SELWYN—the lover of a quarter of a century past; the lover, husband, widower, in a breath.</p>
                  <p>"Twenty-five years ago!" There is the sound of a knell in the sentence. What is <emph>not buried</emph> in that lapse of time? The hopes, faiths, beliefs, expectations, as well as the living beings about us.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="248-249" xml:id="VAC6162-00000125"/>
                  <p>FAR away from the cemeteries where fashion has set her stamp, and death looks gay; far away from the graveyards which look so lonely and sad; far away from the noise or echo of man's busy life, deep in the far forest, rises, among the trees which shadow it, a white marble shaft, pointing to that heaven where the wife of a moment has gone.</p>
                  <p>There is nothing but "EDITH" on its smooth surface to tell its tale to the wandering beholder. Few ever see it but the venturing hunter: it comes upon him like a mysterious <emph>presence:</emph> he lays his gun on the grass, weaves his own tale of the strange monument, and the blithe, merry birds fly about unharmed by him for hours as he dreams. And every year, in the autumn time, when the day comes round that Edith first owned her love; when nature has put on her gayest attire to hide for an hour the gloom of her coming death; when the trees are all decked in their carnival hues, and scatter their bright leaves like smiles to the frolic winds before they enter on their long, cold Lent, their wintry fast, the old man kneels at the tomb of his Edith, and thanks GOD that he has tempered his judgments with mercy; and his heart swells with gratitude that, though it has been shut like the door of a vault to love, HE has opened it with sympathy for the sufferer, and has permitted him to be a comforter to the afflicted, a light to some who are groping in darkness, and enabled him to make some suffering corner of this earth less a Hades—more a Paradise.</p>
                  <p>And then a tender and sad memory will come, like the recollection of a dream of the Edith of his youth, and of his manhood. And he thanks HIM again that he has sent him on this road toward his haven of rest, where, perhaps, he will recognize and join in eternal thought, in eternal joy, in eternal progression, the being to whom he felt his soul of souls was united, with a love that time and suffering had purified from all it might at first have held of earth. And each year he leaves the tomb stronger to guide, and help, and bear, and feeling nearer to that Heaven where well he knows that, if he does<pb n="250-251" xml:id="VAC6162-00000126"/> not join his Edith in actual recognition, he will meet more than his ideal; he will meet the <emph>infinite</emph> of love and beauty, of which his earthly love was but an emblem: and alone, yet not lonely, toward Heaven he is "passing away! passing away!"</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>