<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6475">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >The Autobiography of a Latin Reader </title>
            <author >Francis, Samuel W. (1835-1886)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC6475</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >The autobiography of a Latin reader</title>
                  <author >Francis, Samuel W. (1835-1886)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >50 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >A.D.F. Randolph</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1859">1859</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-04-05">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text >
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The autobiography of a Latin reader</head>
            <p> 
               <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6475-00000001"/> THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY OF A LATIN READER. BY SAMUEL SYNTAX, ESQ  NEW YORK: ANSON VD F. RANDOLPH, PUBLISHER, 683 BROADWAY. 1859.      <pb n="0 (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC6475-00000002"/> Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1859, by ANSON D. F. RANDOLPH In the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United States for the Southern District of New York. BAPTIST &amp; TAYOR, PRINTERS, ' Sun Building," N. Y.   CONTENTS. Page. CHAPTER I.--M SECOND BIRTH  -    - 1 CHAPTER II.-MY EDUCATION,  -  -  -  7 CHAPTER III.-My TAILOR AND BOARDING HOUSE, 15 CHAPTER IV.-MY NEW HOME,-   -  -  - 19 CHAPTER V.-ARTHUR'S SCHOOL-PROSPECTS, - 27 CHAPTER VI.-MY SUFFERINGS,  -  -  -  35 CHAPTER VII.-VISITORS, -     -43 CHAPTER VI.-MY DEATH, -     -  -  47    <pb n="0" xml:id="VAC6475-00000003"/>  THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY  OF A- LATIN READER. THE first circumstance worthy of note in my life, of vicissitude and sor- row, took place on a rainy afternobon in the month of September, when while lying in the streets,; in a state of rags, I was picked up by a Dutchmafiin who was smoking the stump of ai cigar. Smoking, did- H say-? I was wrong.' He had more the appearaite: of trying to see how little smoking ,would keep' his cigar lit, and -thereby prplong    <pb n="2-3" xml:id="VAC6475-00000004"/> 2   THE AUTO BIOGRAPHY pleasure and his stump's existence. A puff-a grunt--a peculiar hitch of the shoulder-a shuffle of the foot, and, with a sudden twist of his hook, jerk- ing me into a basket which he acarried on his arm, he limped on, with the im- portance of one who had much to do and no time to lose. I was greatly angered by his rudeness, but feeling very like a wet rag, was obliged to submit in silence, strength having for- saken me. When he had filled his basket with shoes, bones, and pieces of calico, tak- ing a long bag from his shoulder, and opening its mouth, he seized me very roughly with my companions, and forced us into it. As it was very old, and presented the appearance of hav-   OFP A, LATIN READER.    3 ing been used for many years, my reader will not be surprised at hear- ing it was my good fortune to be pushed half out of a hole in the side; which, though it rendered my position very uncomfortable, gave me a fine opportunity of seeing everything that transpired. The old man having filled both basket and bag, proceeding on his way for some time, at length turned down a narrow alley, where some dirty children, half-naked, were playing in the gutter with some small pieces of wood, which they had made into little boats. Passing on a few steps, he entered a large brick house, where I heard a great noise, as if some machi- nery were in operation.  Here he deposited me with my companions on    <pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC6475-00000005"/> 4   T Hi E .A O UTi OBR O Ox 1  A:?H Y the foor, and, receiving his mDoney, left. On looking around me, I saw many other rags near by, and immediately began to question them with regard to the house; what it was, and why I was brought there. They told me we were to be thrown into the machine I heard thundering with so much noise, which would make paper of us, and then we were to be taken to a printing iestablishment. They said they knew no more, and that they had obtained this information from an old piece of newspaper that had been picked up in the streets with them. For when it -saw the machinery, immediately recog- nizing the place, it told them, with a shudder, and in a whisper, what   OF A LATIN READER .    5 their fate would be. As it was evening when I arrived there, nothing particu- lar occurred; but the next morning I was selected with my companions who were of the same color (white) and was brought before the fearful monster, who, in the course of a few minutes; cut us into very small pieces. We were then put into an elliptical tub, and water was poured on us, in order to wash off the particles-of dirt and render us of spotless purity. After this, a large hole being made in the tub, by removing a plug, we were very soon carried through it, by the water, into a reservoir, and from that drawn off into a vat. Then a large cylinder, covered with a fine wire cloth, stopped our progress, with        <pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC6475-00000006"/> 6   THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY its sharp claws, and turning round, the fibrous particles adhered to it; and as the water ran off, being pressed between two woolen cloths, we became Paper. We were then hung out on a line, until we should become dry. After remain- ing for some time in this situation, we were taken in reams and put in a cart, which carried us to a printing office, where we were left, more dead than alive.   OF A LATIN READER.     7 CHAPTER II. MY EDUCATION. I do not think that I ever suffered as much agony in my life, as when I was cut in pieces. I have been cut by my friends, and have suffered considerably from it, but to be chewed up by one's enemies, without being able to defend one's self, is almost too painful to be borne. On the day that I was to be printed, I was taken up, with a great many other papers, and placed on a stand near the printing press, which (as far as I was able to judge) con- sisted of some wood work around a cylinder which was covered with    <pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6475-00000007"/> 8   THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY types. I knew that in a few minutes my character would be formed, and my course of life truly marked out, but as to what I would be, I could form no idea. I had a great desire to be a book of deep research, that would be con- sulted by the great men of the times, fill the young mind with useful infor- mation, arouse the weary, influence the old, and do honor to my country. While on the stand near the printing press, I fell into a revery of a peculiar nature. I thought if I came out a novel, there would be a very large family of us, numbering about one thousand, the first generation. Of course we would be purchased by rich and poor, young and old.  Alas! how eagerly the poor, who often deny   OF A LATIN R EADER.    9 themselves the necessaries of life, to procure novels, having purchased one of us, go into a corner of their old shanty, and there, having sat down upon a broken stool, spell out the words, day after day, until they have read from cover to cover, two or three times. This is often done by poor persons, instead of laboring honestly for their food, and when affliction and destitution approach, with fearful strides, they rouse themselves as if from a trance, surprised that they are in such want. Again, I  thought of the rich, who can afford the money for novels, but not the time. Riding to a book store, in their carriages, they ask "if there are any new novels out;"     <pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6475-00000008"/> 10  THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY and having received an answer in the affirmative, purchase the book, and return to their homes, to waste hours in the perusal of a work that can do them no earthly good, but on the con- trary, "corrupt their hearts by infusing what may be justly termed moral poison." As I was thinking what good I might do if I were a history, the machinery seized hold of me, and in a moment I was turned round and round that huge cylinder. Reader, imagine my astonishment when, hav- ing received a stamp, my brain was instantly filled with Latin verbs, pre- positions, adverbs and conjunctions. My knowledge of Roman Antiquities was extensive; fables I knew by the hundred; and as to anecdotes, I could   oOF A LATIN READER.    " repeat them by the hour. I now felt happy that I was printed for a higher class of persons than novel-readers. I felt proud of my situation. Our family consisted of about five hundred, and we were destined for all parts of the United States. Having ascertained that my title was to be "Latin Reader," I began to look about me to see how the characters of my friends had been formed. One had become a Latin grammar; I therefore determined to cultivate his acquaintance. Another a novel by Dumas; I scorned such company, and tried to get out of the way, but could not, considering it far beneath me to associate with persons of such a low character. To describe the different changes that had taken I    <pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6475-00000009"/> 12  THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY place among my friends would be tire- some as well as superfluous; suffice it to say, some had become histories, others arithmetics, mythologies, etc. My young friend, you talk of trials in your bright and sunny days. 'You complain of the difficulty of learning to read. You call your kind teacher all sorts of names, because, forsooth, owing to your own negligence, you have not at the proper time prepared your lesson. But what can you say now? Think of my sufferings, while unable to move. Think of the agony I must have endured while in the jaws of that giant masticator. What say you to my feelings, when informa- tion, truly of great value, was literally crammed into my head, willing or not,   OF A LATIN READER.    13 by the mammoth press? Some day, when you have time, visit one of his dens. Listen to his roaring, breathing and unearthly hissing. See with what a sudden clutch he grasps his prey, and in one moment whirls him round and round, until, exhausted, he falls lifeless on the heap of other victims. When you return to your cheerful home, make up your mind to cease from imagining that your lot, as a schoolboy, is the hardest in the world. Conclude that there are others who have more to bear and less to be thankful for, and endeavor to cheer those around you, treating every com- panion with consideration, though it be only a Latin Reader. Having remained in this condition    <pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6475-00000010"/> "  THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY for several days, on a side shelf in one corner of the room, I was roused, one morning, from a drowsy feeling that had come over me, by seeing a little man with a very large head enter the room. Coming up to where I was with my companions, he shouldered us and went down stairs to a side door, out of which he emgrged and pro- ceeded on his way, through curious lanes and filthy streets, until arriving at the cellar of a large house, he entered and laid us on the table, full of anxiety, but in better spirits than when confined in the dreadful cage of the rag-eater! * .4   OAF A LA TIN HREAD DEIt.  5 CHiAPTER III. MY TAILOR AND BOARDING-HOUSE. I very soon ascertained that .this place was a book-binding establish- ment, and rejoiced inwardly that I would soon be dressed in a nice suit of clothes. It would take too much time, and would also be very tedi- ous, were I to enter' into all the details of binding; suffice it to say, that after undergoing a great deal of beating, sewing and pasting, I found myself bound in very neat cloth, and surrounded by other books, dressed    <pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6475-00000011"/> 16  T H R A U 'OT O t 0'i AP tH Y likewise in a very respectable style. We were then taken up-stairs, and given to the clerks of the establish- ment, who arranged us il different parts of the large and spacious room. I had the good fortune to be placed by the side of my old fiiend, the Latin grammar, and was also near some works on geography.  This pleased me 'greatly, for whenever I felt lonely, by conversing with my companions, I would thereby derive not only amuse- ment but information. Of all my fiiends I considered my neighbor, the Latin grammar, as the most inseparable and useful; for whenever I did not know how a verb was governed, or why a certain noun was in the dative case, upon asking my friend, I received   -THE A UTOBIOGRAPHY    1-7 the answer that was necessary to explain it. Day after day I remained in the store, never hearing my name men- tioned by any one, until finally I began to give up all ideas of ever leaving it. This was not because our owner had no customers-far from it; for, with his clerks, he was kept busy all day, packing: up and selling books. But it was because I was not the kind of book in demand. The taste of the public differed from mine. Many and many a time have I seen my scorned associate (Dumas' noveD put up in white paper and sold to all classes of society, until I almost envied his situation, and would have been willing to have given myinformation and superior education    <pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6475-00000012"/> 18  OF A -LA'TI N READER-. for this work "for a day." But, what was my delight-my rapture--when one afternoon, just as the gas had been lighted, and the streets were becoming deserted by the busy people, a little boy, with an open countenance and pretty features, on entering the store, asked the clerk if he had any Latin Readers. His reply was in the affir- mative; whereupon, taking me down from the shelf, he showed me to the little fellow, who requested him to put me up in paper, saying he would "take me." The clerk asked him if he, did not wish a Latin grammar also, as they generally went togethei'. He said no, that he had one at home; and picking me up, left the store.   THE AUTOB IOGRAP HY   19 CHAPTER IV. MY NEW HOME. While my little owner was proceed- ing on his way, I began'to think in what manner I could repay him for his kindness in rescuing me from that dull shelf, where I had lain so long. But, before I could arrive. at any conclusion, he ran up the' steps of a very hand- some house, and taking a key from his pocket, opened the door and went in. My little master appeared to be in fine spirits at the idea of studying Latin, for with a glistening eye and proud step, he entered the library, and sitting down by the fire, on a little ottoman, 23            i    <pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6475-00000013"/> 20  OF A LATIN READER. began to examine me; when, the bell ringing, (for tea, I presume,) he jumped up, and putting me on the table, left the room.  Now, having plenty o time for observation, I determined t look around me and see where I was and in what respect this room differe( from my former residence. The first object of interest that caugh my eye, was the old-fashioned fireplac with tiles; and the andirons of polishei brass seemed, from their aged and wor] appearance, to have supported man a pine knot during cold winter, and t have lighted up the countenances  laughing children on Christmas ev while hanging their stockings on tl fender, to be filled with goodies an toys. Then again, what a fine, lar ,   THE A U TOBIOGRAPHY    21 chimney for "Santa Claus" to come down. It appeared to be just the one he would choose, so nice and warm, and so spacious that he might descend without even soiling his clothes or breaking his toys; and as the fire cast glimmering shadows on the wall, it occurred to me that this was the room for ghost stories or spinning yarns. On looking up above the mantlepiece, I made out, by the uncertain light of the'fire, a picture of a wreck. There was the storm at sea, the raging bil- lows threatening to engulph, in an instant, the little boat with the surviv- ing crew. A  flock of sea gulls was hovering overhead with wondering eyes. Now darting down, with sudden sweep; now shooting by, as if in w    <pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6475-00000014"/> 22  THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY sport. A shark here and there, mov- ing with his cold and slimy body- waiting for his evening meal-a rare treat-good flesh and blood!  The clouds, themselves, seemed anxious to conceal the spectacle from mortal gaze. A little infant clung, as if by instinct, to a huge Newfoundland that was looking, with a tender zeal, for one he could not find his master. The dis- masted vessel, at a distance, was sink- ing, and all was gloomy. What a vast difference, thought I, is there between that scene and the one before me. There misery and a cold, cold, yawning grave; and here every com- fort and a warm fire. Books to in- struct and amuse. Ease and elegance for mind and body. A cheerful twink- t   OF A LATIN READER.    23 ling and suggestive fire-light. Ashes and cinders, that would assume any shape to please a thoughtful intellect, or assist a romantic contemplation. How thankful ought those persons to be, who enjoy such blessings. On turning round, to see in what manner the room was furnished, I be- held a long row of oak-colored book- cases filled with rare and choice works, bound in different styles; and as I looked, I thought that the possessor of such a study must be a man of learning and of taste; and I earnestly hoped it would be my good fortune to be placed in the company of such books. While thus cogitating, I was roused from my dreamy mood, by the r     <pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6475-00000015"/> 24  TH E AU TOBIOG APHY voice of my little owner, who came into the room with his father, and taking me up, showed me to him. The old gentleman, (for such he was, and one of the old school too,) having taken a seat, placed the candle nearer to him, and after looking at some of my anec- dotes, put me back again on the table, and said to his son: "Arthur, you know that your pa- rents have at length decided that it will be better for you to study in' the country, than to stay here and attend day school; for there are so many temptations; and besides, as your sister is going into company this winter, your attention would be drawn from your studies, and you would not make as much progress as   OF A LATIN READER.    25 at a boarding school. And moreover, my dear boy, going to boarding school makes a man of you, and you will learn to take care of yourself." "Very well, dear father," said the little boy, "I'm willing; but where do you intend sending  me?  Do send me, on Christmas, a nice sledge; and get Uncle John to have a pair of skates for me, on New Year's." "My dear boy, we have at length concluded to send you to Mr. Birch's school, where you will be taken care of, and wil receive a good education; and now, if you will tell me what things you desire, I will purchase them for you. You will start to-morrow afternoon, in the boat, and will arrive there at half-past seven o'clock in the    <pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6475-00000016"/> 26  THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY evening. Write me word as soon as you get there." Arthur enumerated all the things he wished. Having talked together for some time, his father finished by tell- ing him to study hard all the term, until the holidays, and then he might surprise the family by the extent of his knowledge. He also told him to try and resist all temptations he  should meet with. Arthur promised faithfully to fol- low, in every respect, his father's kind advice; andc bidding him a4 affection- ate "good night," left the library, to seek repose on his downy couch.   OF A LATIN READER.    27 CHAPTER V. ARTHUR'S SCHOOL.--PROSPECTS. Soon overcome by fatigue I fell into a pleasant sleep, in which condition I remained until I was awakened in the morning by the waiter, coming in to open the shutters and dust the room, Nothing particla happened during the morning; when, about 12 o'clock, my friend came running into the room, and taking me up, went up stairs to his bed room, where the servants were packing away; his mother giving many directions; the little canaries singing, as it were, a fond farewell, and Arthur busy doing nothing, but think-    <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6475-00000017"/> 28  THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY ing great things, full of the conse- quence of a young traveler. Having ascertained that there was nothing more to go in his trunk, he put me in, closed the lid and locked it, leaving me to get on as well as I could in the darkness. As it was very com- fortable where I was, and as I knew in a little while, I should be exercised frequently and handled very roughly, by my owner ; moreover, as I was con- fident it would require great strength of constitution to go through so much fatigue, I determined to take every opportunity of laying in a good store of health, and therefore went to sleep. I am unable to say how long I slept, but when I awoke I found myself in a small chilly room with a double bed   OF A LATIN READER.    29 and a cot, three chairs, a basin stand, (I should say the remains of one,) a pitcher without a handle, and a basin with a piece knocked out, which hole seemed to show high water mark. The window was small, consisting of six panes of glass, which were so dirty, and one, especially, was so patched with strips of brown paper, that it seemed to me that the window had been combating with AEolus, and one of its limbs being broken in the en- gagement, the poor schoolmaster- not having funds sufficient to justify him in sending for a chirurgeon to ampu- tate the shattered fragments, and 'sub- stitute another in its place, was there- fore obliged to plaster it himself, endeavoring to make it heal by the    <pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6475-00000018"/> 30  THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY "first intention." There was no carpet on the floor, but a small rug lay by the bedside. It was early in the morning when I awoke, and seeing no one, I concluded that the boys were at breakfast. It was not long, however, before my little friend came in. Putting me under his arm with a slate and geogra- phy, he went into the schoolroom. It was a large room, filled with rows of desks A peculiar murmur could be heard keeping time with the fluttering hearts of the little scholars. Every- thing looked like business; there was nothing that seemed at all calculated to distract your attention. One would almost study to relieve his mind from dreams. Many maps were hanging nc   OF A LATIN READER.    31 the walls, and a large black-board stood near the window, where the teacher, with many excited gesticula- tions, was trying in vain to explain a problem to a thin boy, who with a look of despair, agreed with him in every point, but when it came his turn to explain it, after making many use- less marks on the board with his chalk, was sent to his seat marked deficient. Leaning against the wall, behind a large mahogany desk, sat a little with- ered man with red hair, a pair of green spectacles on his hooked nose, a rod in his hand, hearing some little boys recite. Ihis was no less than Mr. Birch, "the Lord of the Creation," "Monarch of all he Surveyed.' Arthur, the moment he cast his eyes    <pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6475-00000019"/> 32   THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY on his highness, trembled, and going up to him, presented his father's letter. The clouds that had gathered on his brow disappeared; and in their place, a smile came, which contrasted with the man's visage, seemed to me no less than a contradiction of his real character. My little friend, would you like to know exactly how this learned tyrant looked? Well, I will tell you-did you ever see those little india rubber men, whose faces you can squeeze into any shape? Such was his. Full of flesh, no expression save dull anger. In other words, Mr. Birch thought it best to secure his prey first, and then he could do as he pleased. So having asked Arthur how he had slept during the night, and telling him to take a   OF A LATIN READER.    33 seat, he read the letter. Having fin- ished the perusal, he asked him if he understood Latin, and whether he could read Greek? Receiving an answer in the negative, he seemed surprised, at first, but instantly checking himself, said: "Never mind; if you apply your- self to your studies, you will soon un- derstand them." Having set Arthur a lesson in the Latin Grammar, he put me in the desk which my owner was to occupy. I remained there, I should think, for nearly three months, seeing daylight only, when the desk was opened by my owner, to get a history, an arithmetic, or a spelling-book. But I did not, however, waste this time in sleeping; I carried on many conversa- tions with the arithmetic, who having    <pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6475-00000020"/> 34  THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY been kind enough to introduce me to his friend the slate, by whose aid I was instructed in mathematics, I thereby gained a great deal of infor- mation on that subject.   OF A LATIN READER.    35 CHAPTER VI. MY SUFFERINGS. One day Arthur took me to his master, and a lesson being set, he began to study. It was not long, however, before he found out the difficulty of the construction of Latin. I date my misfortunes firom this day. Not being able to find out the derivation of a certain word, instead of quietly looking it out in my dictionary, if he could not find it out instantly, he would throw me on the desk, turn over my cover, write and draw all kinds of pictures on my fly leaves, and end by pitching me 7 o ,}    <pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6475-00000021"/> 36  THE AUTOBIOGR APHY headforemost into his desk, which I am sorry to say, was in great confusion. The treatment I received, ren- dered my appearance hideous in the extreme. My self-respect had vanished; my interest in surrounding objects no longer called forth investigation, and I longed for retirement, no matter where, could I but be fieed from such abuse. Once, while I was doing my best to assist Arthur in his classical pursuits, a tall, thin haired, pale boy came up to him and began to teaze. It was very hot, in fact, so excessive, that my stays had nearly given way. Arthur tried to send him away, but not succeeding in either removing this nuisance, or making out a sentence, seized me, and with a sudden hurl vanquished his   OF A LATIN READER.    37 enemy at my expense, sending me fly- ing to the end of the room. I now ceased to care even for my owner. My life did not pay. While on the floor, I saw a fly playing "tag" with its companions in the sunshine. Why! oh, why had I not been born a fly? Envy, sorrow,  desperation, over- came my  self-possession, and I remained senseless I know not how long. It would not do were I to relate all my trodbles and state the different abuses I received from my little owner. But I will assert, that when the summer vacation arrived, 1 had lost one cover, my back had been broken, and my pages were so dirty and dog-eared, that I was fain (com- 3    <pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC6475-00000022"/> 38   THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY paring myself with what I was) to exclaim with Eneas: "Hei rili, qualis erat! quanti'm mutatus ab illo Hectore - !" Alas! poor boys.  I was a boy once, and can feel for you. There is, indeed, no trial in a student's life equal to the first effort of making out that cart-before-the-horse-construction of Latin. It seems impossible, though you may understand every rule, to comprehend the idea that a writer, in his sound mind, can intentionally write, backwards, forwards, and some- times not at all! Arthur, previous to his leaving Mr, Birch's for the summer, having ascer- tained that he would no longer need   OF A LATIN READER.     39 me, but that, in the following fall, he should study Csesar, took me  one afternoon down a side street, in the town, and selling me, for a mere trifle, to a bookseller who kept a stall at the corner of a street, left me to my fate, without seeming to feel the loss of so valuable a friend as I had been to him. Such is gratitude. Poor me! My mode of living now changed. I n o longer felt a desire to mix with the world or vie with other works.  My spirits (if I had any left) were entirely crushed, and my appearance being anything but pre- possessing, I, felt that it was doubt- ful whether I should ever leave this stall; so, perched upon the top shelf, I determined to watch the coun-    <pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC6475-00000023"/> 40  THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY tenances of those who came to pur- chase, and form an idea of their char- acters and habits of life in my mind. The stall was attached to the side of a house in one of those crooked by- lanes, crossing a main street. By this means I had an opportunity of seeing everything-but a policeman.  The first set of features I made a study of, were those of my immediate owner; a red-faced Scotchman, whose heavy boots and cut-away coat seemed to have formed a conspiracy to abandon a lonely pair of rough, dirt-colored, corded pants, that in their turn made up their mind to shrink within them- selves and leave others to their fate. There was no waistcoat; but a shirt of any hue but white clung from ap-   OF A LATIN REA bE.    41 parent weakness to the soggy form of' this rough old fellow. I was much amused at his hat; a sleepless piece of pasteboard-for the nap had long  since left it-held together by a band of crape. This hat never left the head of the same red-faced man; at least I never saw him remove it, save to unfurl a huge, variegated, mutually red-faced hand- kerchief. It was a curious sight to see how the Scotchman would change the position of his books to catch the eye of some stray pedestrian. Strange the manner in which he would empty a shelf, as though the books had been sold. Absurd the way he pretended to read, with short-sighted spectacles, when a visitor approached, as though    <pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6475-00000024"/> 42   T It ni U T O I O ( I A "Y not at all concerned. After a while I liked the old man. lie exhibited talent. Hie seldom got angry, but he never took off his price for anybody. Punctual to the striking of the old church clock, he took down his shut- ters and "' aired his books," as I have heard him say. Moreover, the great- est care was taken of even the oldest work. You would have liked him. Per- haps you have seen him. If you know him, buy one book, for my sake: I mean for his; he has two sick children, his wife is dead, and he himself could find use for the little you might bestow.   OP A LATIN READER.    43 CHAPTER VII. VISITORS. One day I saw approaching with a feeble gait, pale and care-worn visage, sunken cheeks and a wearied eye, a country clergyman, with a book under his arm and umbrella in his hand. Addressing my owner, lie asked him if he had in his possession Cecil's Re- mains, and if so, whether he would be willing to exchange it for the book which he showed him, and a small amount of money. The manner of this gentleman and the longing look he gave to his old friend, caused me to suppose, he was not rich enough to    <pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6475-00000025"/> "  THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY keep both books, and having gleaned all the information he could from this work, was obliged to part with it in order to procure that which might aid him in writing his sermons. Having settled with my owner to his satisfaction, he passed on, and gave place to a customer quite the reverse in appearance and manner. With a firm, noble countenance, clear eye and elastic step, coming up to where Mr. Redface stood, I never knew his name, this gentleman a-ked in an independ- ent, though polite way, if. he had among his collection any voyages or travels? On hearing that he had plenty on hand, he asked to see them, and bought Acerbie, Lithgow, Carver, Anson, and Dambridge: and, telling   O i  L A T ATIN READE  45 my master to keep for him all the voyages and travels he might meet with, took out a handful of money, paid him and left. I could not help thinking, asI- saw this gentleman depart, how strong the contrast was between the poor parish clergyman and himself.  How  one devoted all his life, means and intel- lect to converting sinners, and in return received barely enough to live on, while this young man, free from cares and troubles, could purchase books of travels, return home, and sitting probably in front of his fire in his study, would read of mariners and of unfortunate beings, wrecked on desolate islands, without sufficient to support them for a day; hearing his    <pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC6475-00000026"/> "  T HE AUTOBIOGIRAPHY dinner bell ring, he would go down to a sumptuous repast, leaving the ship- wrecked to exist on half a biscuit, and a pint of water. How curious is the dispensation of Providence! How differently persons are placed in this life. Oh! how thankful ought we to be in hearing the same invitation for rich and poor, young and old. What a comfort, truly, to the poor man: "Unto whom much is given, from him much shall be required."  n P P   OF A LATIN READER.    47 CHAPTER VIII. MY D EATH:. Many months passed on, and I emained in the same condition, hav- g, however, learnt th it there were any others in this world more miser- )le than I, and that I had cause to : thankful for many blessings. One rening, I never shall forget it! after had been locked up and bound in r shutters and bars, I heard the fire "ring! ri rinring! and in a few oments windows were raised, and rsons, inquiring where the fire was, ssed by with hurried steps. Soon    <pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC6475-00000027"/> 48  THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY the engine was heard, and that dread- ful cry of fire was sounded in front of my stall. Presently the crevices of the shutters were lighted up, and the flames crept in and out like snakes, darting hither and thither with frantic twistings. In one corner of my berth I heard a deep groan emanating from a burning book in dying agonies. It crumbled and rolled down. I looked and beheld-the envied novel writh- ing in agony and contrition. I shut my eyes and shuddered.  Water at length deluged my little place of abode, and a crash followed, my stall being shivered to pieces by a falling wall. I lay on the pavement until the following evening, half burnt and soaked with water, my memory nearly   OF A LATIN' RIADE11. 49 gone. A little boy passing quietly by, picked me: up, and carrying me to his father's house, laid me on the table telling his brother he intended to make me into a tail for his kite. But the next morning before he was up, the waiter coming into the room, tore me in pieces, and rolling and twisting me with his hands, built the parlor fire with me. And it was during the fol- lowing night, that I wrote my life, with my ashes on the white hearth, desirous of showing the maltreatment that Latin Readers receive from school boys. Should you meet with one in your day, gentle reader, treat it as becomes a young man of feeling. Persevere in your studies. Break not its back    <pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC6475-00000028"/> 50     MY DEATH. because you are lazy. Act with for- bearance; and when you have derived all you can from it, place it on a secluded shelf, where it can enjoy the repose of a well-spent life, and review the passing events of the day. Fare- well! my ashes are exhaust--. THE END.     </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>