<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6048">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>George Welding, or, Crime and Its Consequences </title>
            <author>Choat, J. F.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC6048</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-0521</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                    participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>George Welding, or, Crime and its consequences</title>
                  <author>Choat, J. F.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>H.M. Rulison</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cincinnati </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1859">[1859]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2000-12-15">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="Pacific Data Conversion Corp." when="2001-12-21">Finished transcription and SGML encoding.</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-01-28">Finished TEI conversion and final editing</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-04-22">Converted document from SGML to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-04-22">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n="(TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6048-00000001"/>
         <titlePage>
            <docEdition>Price 15 Cents.</docEdition>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>GEORGE WELDING;</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">OR, CRIME AND ITS CONSEQUENCES.</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">A TRUTHFUL PICTURE, BUT A TERRIBLE RECORD.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>BY <docAuthor>REV. J. F. CHOAT.</docAuthor>
            </byline>
            <docEdition>
               <figure>
                  <head>Cautiously be stole down the stairs, his feet unshod, his weapons in his hands, and fierce passions that burned within him, crying out: <emph>"Blood! blood! blood!"</emph>
                  </head>
               </figure>
            </docEdition>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>CINCINNATI:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>H. M. RULISON, QUEEN CITY PUBLISHING HOUSE, <address>
                     <addrLine>141 MAIN STREET.</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </publisher>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
         <div type="advertisement">
            <pb n="2 (Advertisement) -3" xml:id="VAC6048-00000002"/>
            <head>LIST OF PUBLICATIONS, ETC.</head>
            <p>Agents wanted to sell by subscription some of the most useful and popular selling subscription books published in America, among which are found</p>
            <list>
               <item>Dr. Horton Howard's Domestic Medicine, being a revised edition of Horton Howard's Anatomy, Physiology, Midwifery, Diseases of Women and Children, Practice of Medicine and Materia Medica. Founded upon correct physiological principles, and especially adapted to Family use; containing all the important discoveries and improvements down to the present time,—forming a complete FAMILY MEDICAL GUIDE, and is presented to the public with the greatest confidence in its being a complete Family Companion and Guide, especially adapted to the demands and wants of the public. A book which is recommended by the most talented and popular professors in Europe and America. Retail price, $4 00</item>
               <item>The Land we Live in; or, Travels, Sketches and Adventures in North and South America, with descriptions of its towns, cities, states and territories, their inhabitants, manners, customs, amusements, public works, institutions, edifices, etc., together with a great variety of the most exciting adventures and highly interesting historical events of American History. By C. A. Goodrich. Retail price, $3 75</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Agents who sell my books, which are sold by subscription, will be required to take a township or county, and canvass it thoroughly, by visiting every house in the territory assigned. An applicant will be supplied with a sample copy by mail, by remitting the retail price, and naming the township or county he is willing to obligate himself to canvass thoroughly and immediately, also stating what experience he has had in the business, if any—and what amount of capital he could engage in the business. We wish none but the most energetic Agents, and those who wish to engage in the business, for the purpose of making money.</p>
            <p>We can supply many useful and rapidly selling books to those who wish to sell by direct sale—such as for instance:</p>
            <list>
               <item>Mrs. Bradley's Housekeeper's Guide, Family Receipt and Cook Book. Retail price, $0 50</item>
               <item>American Horse Tamer and Farrier, showing how to cure the wildest and most vicious horse in the world of kicking, balking, and other bad habits; also, directions to purchasers, hints on stable economy, and remedies for all diseases to which horses are liable; such as Spavin, Distemper, Ringbone, etc. By Jeremiah Bentwright, the celebrated American Horse Tamer. Retail price, 0 25</item>
               <item>Fair Rebel. By Emerson Bennett, 0 25</item>
               <item>Evaline Manderville. By Alvin Addison, 0 25</item>
               <item>New History of Texas, from the <choice>
                     <sic>Frst</sic>
                     <corr>First</corr>
                  </choice> European Settlement in 1692, down to the present time, including a description of the country, its soil, climate, resources and productions, towns, rivers, harbors, etc.; an account of the population of the different counties; the various traveling routes in the State, with the cost of traveling, etc.; with many other matters of interest to all classes, and especially to the traveler and emigrant. Paper cover. Retail price 0 25</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>George Welding, or, Crime and its consequences</head>
            <head>GEORGE WELDING.</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
               <p>ON a gloomy night during the winter of 1857-58, two young men were threading their way along the streets of the city of New York, engaged in earnest conversation. Their costume indicated that they moved in good society, if not in the highest walks of life; yet they seemed inclined rather to avoid than to seek the fashionable promenades and places of resort, and to choose the more unfrequented streets.</p>
               <p>But there is no part of the great metropolis of the New World, where life in almost all its various forms and aspects does not meet the eye. The lordly palace and the dismal cellar, where human beings huddle together in the damps of underground apartments, which they dignify by the name of <hi rend="i"/>home—the mansion where wealth delights to lavish its treasures, and luxurious tastes are gratified to satiety; and the lone garrets, where a little straw forms the pallet, and furniture is a myth; all these are there, and human woe and human pride are so near each other, that the same sunshine falls upon both, the same cloud casts its shadow upon them alike.</p>
               <p>As the young men passed a corner, a little girl stood there, and putting out a thin hand that trembled with cold, she pleaded with a voice that spoke plainly of sorrow, as her chattering teeth allowed the words to pass her lips:</p>
               <p>"Please, sir, will you give me a penny to buy some bread?"</p>
               <p>One of the young men was disposed to pass on without noticing the "little beggar," as he called her; but the other paused, touched by the intonation of distress that mingled with the voice of the child, and seeing her evident need of assistance, inquired:</p>
               <p>"Where do you live, my little girl?"</p>
               <p>"At No. —, — street," she replied.</p>
               <p>"Why do you ask for money to buy bread?"</p>
               <p>"Because my mother and little brother are starving." She spoke with difficulty, and at the close of the sentence burst into tears.</p>
               <p>"Let us go home with her," said the one who had addressed the child, to his companion, "and see what we can do for her mother."</p>
               <pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC6048-00000003"/>
               <p>"Perhaps she has only told you a story to get money for a bad purpose. One never knows when to trust these beggars."</p>
               <p>"No, she speaks the truth—there is no deception in the low wail of sorrow that followed her words. But if there was any room for doubt, by going with her we can ascertain the truth."</p>
               <p>"Well, you accompany her, and I will go on to the church. Mr. — is to preach to-night, and I have a great desire to hear him."</p>
               <p>"Very well; that is probably the best arrangement we can make. I will meet you in the church sometime during the evening."</p>
               <p>The young men then parted, one continuing on in the direction they were moving when the little girl presented herself; the other, taking the child by the hand walked with her toward the next street, where she said her mother lived.</p>
               <p>The young men here introduced to the reader's notice, we shall designate by the names of George Welding and Edward Williams. We do not give the real names, for the simple reason that many of the incidents we shall relate are still fresh in the memory of living friends, and we would not harrow up their feelings or tear open, to bleed afresh, the wounds we hope time and grace have partially healed. But we are sure that every reader will recognize the leading facts of the narrative we are now penning, as the names are not a disguise which obscures the fearful and terrible relation of facts which follow.</p>
               <p>George Welding was the son of religious parents, and had been brought up amid the prayers at the family hearth, where the altar of devotion had been erected, and the public and private means of grace connected with sanctuary privileges. But he had failed to improve his opportunities wisely; and now, at the opening of manhood, with the dim, distant future stretching away mistily before him, he had no determined course of action marked out. Upon his path the sunlight from eternity beamed not. He was traveling a dark road, where no illuminating rays of Divine radiance marked a place for his footsteps. Yet he was not a scoffer, not a despiser of religion, but professed a determination, <emph>at some period in the future</emph>, to become a practical Christian.</p>
               <p>Edward Williams, on the other hand, was endeavoring to "square his life by the gospel rule," and lived in the experimental enjoyment of the Christian's hope, and the "witness of the spirit that he was a child of God and a joint heir with Christ."</p>
               <p>These two young men had been friends for years. They attended the same schools, the same churches, the same social gatherings, and moved in the same circle of society. They were warmly attached to each other, and seldom had enjoyments possible to divide, that they did not share with each other.</p>
               <p>They had been conversing on religious subjects, and were on the way to church when we present them to the reader's notice.</p>
               <p>George proceeded, as we have seen, to hear the distinguished minister who was to preach that evening in the church to which he was bending his steps, while Edward turned aside to minister to the wants of the suffering and needy.</p>
               <p>The little girl led him directly to the number she had mentioned, and up three flights of stairs, old and creaky, to a small room in the upper story of the building, into which she bade him enter.</p>
               <p>An excuse for a bed was in one corner of the apartment, which was small, and a few coals in an old grate made scarcely an apology for a fire. A lady, whose appearance indicated that she was not over thirty years of age, sat beside the bed on a rickety chair, and when she arose to meet him, as her little daughter said she had brought a gentleman to see them, he perceived that the couch was occupied by a child younger than the one who had been his guide.</p>
               <p>The mother was pale and lean, with hollow cheeks and eyes that seemed larger than their wont from long fasting; but she was a lady in manners, and received her visitor with a grace he had not expected from one in such destitution, for he had learned that most of the destitute were illiterate and devoid of culture.</p>
               <p>"I came with your little daughter," he said, "to see if I could serve you in any way.</p>
               <p>"O, sir, I thank you for such kindness," and the tears filled her eyes, as she continued: "I did not care so long as I had bread for my children; I was content to go without food myself, while there was enough for them, and for three days I have supported myself on hope and simple cold water, that the little I had might last the longer for them. But yesterday the last morsel was consumed. I thought then I would fold my darlings to my bosom, and lie down with them to die; for I could not get the consent of my mind to ask for alms, and I saw no other way to get food—that is, no way that would leave my soul pure before God, and I preferred to die with heaven in view, if it pleased God thus to take me from the world, than to do aught upon which his blessing could not be asked. But when my dear Willie awoke with a slow fever this morning, and kept piteously pleading for bread, my heart was so deeply moved I overcame all scruples, and sent his sister out into the street this evening, to ask for something to get him the food he craved, and for lack of which I felt he was dying. If you can assist me in this hour of trial, I shall be ready to serve you with all my bodily strength. Give my children bread, and I will sew, or do any work to pay you for the kindness."</p>
               <p>"My dear Madam, if I had but one loaf in the world, and never expected to possess another, you should share it; but, Heaven be thanked, I am able to supply all your wants and not feel it. I will send you some fuel and provisions at once, and call again to-morrow and see what more you need."</p>
               <p>"God bless you!" fervently exclaimed the widow, and the tears which she had resolutely kept back, now flowed fast and faster down her pallid cheeks. Nor were Edward's eyes dry.</p>
               <p>At this juncture, the little girl came again to the gentleman's side, and taking his hand, said:</p>
               <p>"Come and see my sweet little brother," and she led him to the bed-side.</p>
               <p>"Be very quiet," said the mother; "he is sleeping now—the first good rest he has enjoyed all the day, and I would not have him awakened."</p>
               <p>As she spoke, she gently removed the scanty and well-worn clothing from about his face and neck, and Edward beheld one of the most beautiful of all the children he had ever met. The child's face was flushed with fever, so that the pale expression of the mother and the sister did<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC6048-00000004"/> not mar his loveliness. Every feature was perfect, and an expression of angelic purity rested upon the face, as the little one slept and dreamed in innocency. Edward gazed a moment in admiration, then a shadow fell upon his spirit, as the thought came; "He is too bright for the earth." He saw how the mother loved this, her treasure, and his heart felt sad as the presentiment came to his mind, that soon she would be called to look upon his beautiful face for the last time. But he kept these reflections to himself, and only spoke the one word, "Beautiful!" then turned away and bade the mother good evening, saying he would attend to their wants immediately.</p>
               <p>Half an hour after, the little room was growing comfortable with a warm fire, and soon after little Willie's hunger was appeased, and the juice of a sweet orange seemed to soothe the feverish heat in his mouth and throat. His mother showed him eleven more, as he finished the one she had given him, and with wondering eyes he inquired who had brought them.</p>
               <p>"A good man sent them to you, my darling; and he said he would come and see you in the morning."</p>
               <p>"Was he the Good Man's son, mother?" inquired the child in his innocent simplicity.</p>
               <p>"No, my child, not as you understand it; but I think our Father in heaven sent him to us."</p>
               <p>"I want to see him, I know I shall love him. Does he look like the angels, mother?"</p>
               <p>"Not yet, my son, but I hope he will; for I expect he will go where the angels are when he dies."</p>
               <p>"There is where I am going, and if he is there I shall see him."</p>
               <p>These strange words of the child sank deeply into the mother's heart; they were so much above his years, and she felt something akin to the thought that had impressed Edward, that Willie might not be long for this life. But it was so full of sadness she banished it at once.</p>
               <p>When supper was over, for they all had a plentiful meal, and provisions enough to last for many days to come, the mother read a chapter from the Bible, as was her custom night and morning, and then knelt at the bed-side, with little Elta at her left hand, and offered up fervent thanksgiving and prayer to God for his mercies, and invoked special and marked blessings upon him who had relieved their wants, and asked that the Father would restore to him four-fold in this world, and life everlasting in the world to come.</p>
               <p>"And oh, Father! bless the widows and orphans that are suffering this night in this great city, and in all the world, and send them deliverance. Oh, save the famishing and the hungry from the death of want, and bless all who shall minister to the forsaken ones of earth."</p>
               <p>Her prayer was eloquent, from the heart, and God heard it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
               <p>GEORGE WELDING, shortly after parting with Edward, entered the church. It was during the memorable Revival, which has become an era in the history of the progress of Christianity, and for some days he had been laboring under deep concern of mind, in reference to the subject of experimental religion and a turning from evil to good; but up to the present evening he had resisted all the influences brought to bear upon him, and still remained undecided.</p>
               <p>On this occasion his friend hoped much for him, and as soon as he had attended to the wants of the widow and fatherless, he hastened to the church, to be near George, and throw in the weight of his example and persuasions to induce him to come to a proper decision in this important matter.</p>
               <p>The sermon was one of great power and pathos. The minister seemed to be clothed with the Spirit, and the words fell from his lips, as from one "sent of God;" and the whole congregation were melted to tears.</p>
               <p>He spoke of the vows that his hearers had made to God to become religious,—vows made at the bedside of departing friends, now in heaven.</p>
               <p>"But have you redeemed them?" he asked, with a peculiar impressiveness. "They were solemnly made, voluntarily breathed into the ear of Deity, while listening angels paused to hear the pledge, and held their fluttering wings, that silence might lend its aid to bear the words which fell from mortal lips up to the eternal throne. And there the record stands to-night,—that record of vows made in the audience chamber of heaven, in the ear of the dying, and when the breath of the Destroyer was congealing to ice the life-tide in the veins of the dear one who was passing away.</p>
               <p>"O, man, where is that vow this night? Does it stand as a witness against you in that court, whence there is no escape, and from whose decision there is no appeal? Does a voice from the grave call upon you yet to redeem your honor? Has the last request of a mother, a sister, a wife been regarded? or, have you until the present hour deferred the fulfillment of the promise you made when their eyes for the last time looked in love upon you, and their voices grew tremulous with the feebleness of death that crept over them?</p>
               <p>"You remember the thin fingers that then held your own, the gentle pressure which told the gladness of that heart when you spoke the words which bound you to lead a new life; you remember the transparent hand that was reached forth in the silence of that hour which saw the last of earth, and placed upon your head, as the mother who bore you, and had held you upon her bosom, said so solemnly: "God bless you, my son!" and you can never forget the words of exhortation that fell from her lips, as she gave you her dying blessing, her last legacy, and bade you meet her beyond the scenes of time.</p>
               <p>"But oh, young man, that mother looks down from paradise to-night, and beholds you a stranger to grace, an alien from the household of faith, and an enemy to the Saviour. If there can be sorrow in heaven, how would she feel as thus she saw the son of her love turning away from the Redeemer, who says, "Come unto me," from her, who loved you as no other mortal ever will, and choosing the vanities and corruptions of sin, rather than the joys and purity of a righteous life. "There is joy in<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6048-00000005"/> heaven among the angels of God, over one sinner that repenteth;" and of the number of these angels is, doubtless, the glorified spirit of thy sainted mother. Oh, young man, will you thrill that angel-mother's breast with joy to-night? Will you cause a song of gladness to float from heavenly lyres and voices over your return to God?</p>
               <p>"I entreat you by the sacred name of mother, by the more sacred name of Jesus, to come to the mercy-seat. Let not the spirit of your mother leave this scene in disappointment to-night, because you have once more turned your back upon heaven; but come now, come quickly! Flee from the city of destruction and take shelter in the fold of Christ."</p>
               <p>For half an hour the preacher thus earnestly and feelingly addressed the people, and every heart was moved. Divine power accompanied his words; God was in the assembly of his people, and the whole congregation was deeply affected. As soon as the invitation was given, the altar was crowded with penitents, and the Master came down in converting power and spoke many souls into the kingdom.</p>
               <p>George Welding was greatly wrought upon, and when Edward approached him, he was trembling like Felix of old, and tears were in his eyes and on his face. He felt that the Spirit was there, and that God had spoken to him as with a voice from the sky.</p>
               <p>But he was not quite ready to yield; he would do so soon, but not then. He knew he ought to be religious, and he intended to be; but there was one or two worldly matters he wished to attend to first, and afterward he would become a Christian.</p>
               <p>In vain Edward urged the importance of immediate action, and pointed out the dangers of delay.</p>
               <p>"You know, George, that you ought to begin a good life this night," he said. "The Spirit of Truth has clearly revealed this to you, and you sin against light and a special dispensation from God, when you neglect or delay to heed the merciful visitation. To-morrow it may be too late."</p>
               <p>"I have heard that so often it has lost its influence."</p>
               <p>"I regret to hear you say so. There will come a morrow, if you do not turn to God, when it <emph>will</emph> be too late, and I feel a fearful presentiment that you are trifling with a last call. God knows whether this feeling arises from my deep anxiety for your salvation, or whether it is a premonition of coming events; be it from which source it may, I persuade you as though this were truly the last opportunity you will ever have of making your peace with God. It is a fearfully presumptuous sin to trifle with the calls of the Holy Spirit. It is the invitation of Him who died for us, to come and accept the salvation which cost the price of His suffering and death; and there is no ingratitude like closing our ears to that call."</p>
               <p>"I do not turn a deaf ear to the voice which has been pleading with me; I only ask a little delay to get prepared—to finish up my worldly affairs, so to speak, and relieve myself from all obligations to man before consecrating myself to God."</p>
               <p>"My dear friend, God has the first claim upon you, and if you have any earthly engagements that will conflict with your duty to Him, they are sinful in themselves, and need to be repented of before they are performed. How great, then, must be the sin of rejecting the present offer of salvation, hope and heaven, to complete that which is sinful. Oh, George, let me entreat you not to do it. It seems to me too great a stretch for even divine compassion to cover such a willful choice of evil before good, to say so plainly to the wooing spirit, 'Go thy way for this time,' I have some wicked obligations to perform, which I had rather consummate now than regard thy voice. How can you hope that God will invite you again, if you thus turn from him, on the plea, that you must finish a little sin before you can attend to the demands of the soul?"</p>
               <p>In this way Edward continued to urge God's claims, and argue with his friend until he was almost ready to yield, and he half gave his consent; but when his friend took his arm to accompany him to the altar, he drew back, and said:—"Not just yet."</p>
               <p>Three times he repeated these same words during the evening:</p>
               <p>"<emph>Not just yet.</emph>"</p>
               <p>It was a singular expression, though by no means an uncommon one; and as he spoke them the last time, the meeting for the evening came to a close, the benediction was pronounced, and he then remarked to his friend:</p>
               <p>"I think I shall be ready to-morrow night; for I intend to be religious."</p>
               <p>These words somewhat encouraged Edward; but we fear the angels, and the spirit of his sainted mother turned away with all the sorrow,—if sorrow it be,—which an inhabitant of heaven can feel when an immortal soul rejects the Saviour and goes aside into the ways of sin.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
               <p>WHEN George Welding left the house of God that night, he really thought he would return on the evening of the next day, <emph>or very soon</emph> seek a saving interest in the blood of Christ, and lead a new life; but he had not well measured his own strength to resist evil, or ability to stand firmly by a good resolution.</p>
               <p>As he passed along the street the following day, he was met by one of his associates, who was reckless in reference to religious matters, and a conversation, of which the following is the substance, took place between them:</p>
               <p>"I understand you are about to join the church and leave your old friends."</p>
               <p>"Yes;" replied George, "I think I shall do so."</p>
               <p>"I had no idea you would be so easily caught in that trap," rather sneeringly rejoined the pretended friend. "I presumed you had more sense than to become the dupe of priests."</p>
               <p>"We do not look at the matter from the same stand-point. I surrender no right, give the minister no power over me, by espousing the cause of Christ and becoming the servant of the Most High. We all owe God a debt, and it is the duty of every man to pay that debt."</p>
               <p>"Well, I will not argue with you; but if you intend to join the church, don't do it until you visit the club once more, pay up your dues, and bid us a kind farewell."</p>
               <p>"When do you meet!"</p>
               <p>"To-night."</p>
               <p>"I have partly promised to go to church this evening."</p>
               <p>"You can put off going there until another day, but, as the club only meets once a week, if you do not go to-night you will have no opportunity to leave it with honor; and I am sure you ought to square up your accounts outside before you join the church."</p>
               <pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6048-00000006"/>
               <p>"I am not sure of being under any obligation to the club."</p>
               <p>"Certainly you are. If you do not square up like a man you will be expelled and dishonored."</p>
               <p>George began to waver. The tempter saw it, and renewed the attack again, while good angels, doubtless, came near to strengthen his yielding purpose.</p>
               <p>"I am not willing to part from you without a promise that I shall see you at the club-room to-night."</p>
               <p>"And I do not think I shall give such a promise."</p>
               <p>"Shall I report you as a delinquent and have your name branded and expunged?" Again George was irresolute.</p>
               <p>"Come," said the tempter, "let me induce you to go <emph>this once;</emph> it is all I ask. Leave us honorably if leave you must. You can get through at the club in time to go to church, if you wish, and thus accomplish both purposes in one evening. You will feel better to part from us with a card of honorable discharge than to break away in debt and disgrace; I know you will."</p>
               <p>"Perhaps you are right." George was almost persuaded, and he was making a momentous decision.</p>
               <p>"I know I am," replied the other, "and I shall expect you with us to-night. When you can so easily compass both objects, it would be little less than an insult for you to refuse to meet your old friends for a few moments, to say a pleasant good-bye. I think you are not yet so near gone that you need be afraid to trust yourself thus far."</p>
               <p>"I will go; but remember, it is only for a few minutes."</p>
               <p>"That is all I ask. Only come, if it is but for half an hour, and then do as you please afterward."</p>
               <p>"I will be there."</p>
               <p>As George spoke these decisive words, a strange sensation came over him. He remembered how earnestly Edward had plead with him to become religious on the previous evening, and when almost ready to yield, and fully and clearly convinced that it was his duty to decide for God, he had said: <emph>Not just yet;</emph> and now, at the less tender, less reasonable, less disinterested appeals of a companion of sinners and a seeker of worldly pleasure, he had consented to be led into the way of temptation and sin. He would procrastinate with God, but not with man.</p>
               <p>His conscience smote him, and he felt like taking back his promise; but as soon as it was given without a proviso, naked and alone, his companion left him and went his way, and he was alone.</p>
               <p>He compromised the matter with himself by promising to leave the club early and go directly to the church; but we fear the spirit of that mother who had watched him from the unseen world through all the years of youth, followed him from that hour with a very faint hope of reclaiming him from the evil way to walk in the narrow path. And well she might fear the worst; for he who had acted as the messenger of Satan to tempt him from the right path, hastened to procure a snare in which to entangle his feet and lead him deeply into the mire of sin.</p>
               <p>How differently did Edward Williams spend the hours which were worse than lost to his friend.</p>
               <p>Early in the morning he made his way to the attic where the widow resided, to see how she and her little ones were doing. It was a matter of rejoicing, on his part, to find such a change for the better as greeted him at the first glance. Every thing wore a more cheerful aspect. The most scrupulous cleanliness marked the entire apartment and all that it contained. The mother had improved wonderfully in appearance, and the little girl's face no longer bore the traces of tears. Willie was almost well again, and the hearts of parent and children were full of gratitude and thanks.</p>
               <p>Edward was met with looks and words eloquent in the expression of feelings which sprang up spontaneously from overflowing bosoms; and as he saw and listened, he felt that truly "it is more blessed to give than to receive."</p>
               <p>"I must find you a better house than this to live in," said he, after the greeting and thanks were over.</p>
               <p>"It is not a very desirable place, but I shall be content if only I can find employment to keep want from our door.</p>
               <p>On further inquiry, Edward learned that the lady could embroider or do any kind of elegant needlework,—that she was capable of giving instruction in music or drawing, and had moved in the first circles of society, until the death of her husband and the misfortunes which followed that event stripped her of worldly possessions, when, like thousands of others, she had been deserted by friends, and left to contend with poverty and temptation, until starvation stared them in the face, as already related.</p>
               <p>"I will find you employment," said Edward, "and a more comfortable home."</p>
               <p>And with this encouraging promise he left them to carry out his good intentions.</p>
               <p>One week from that time the little family were snugly domiciled in a neat, small house on a quiet street, and the mother was engaged by three of the best families in that part of the city as music teacher to young ladies; and plenty of fine sewing and embroidery came in to occupy all the widow's spare hours, so that she was soon above want.</p>
               <p>Edward often visited them, and saw with pleasure and pride that the children were improving wonderfully under the judicious care of an excellent mother, and bid fair to become ornaments in society.</p>
               <p>Etta proved to be a girl of more than ordinary promise, and seemed destined to become distinguished for beauty, talent and accomplishments. But Willie always appeared to Edward to wear a look and to follow trains of thought which spoke of an early transplanting from this mortal to an immortal state of existence. But he would not pain the mother's heart by giving utterance to these convictions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
               <p>WHEN George Welding entered the club-room that evening, he found a full representation of the more jovial members already assembled, who greeted him with unwonted cordiality, and overwhelmed him with questions and congratulations on his reäppearance in their midst. They seemed determined not to give him an opportunity to do any thing but be merry, and for more than an hour he was kept in a constant state of mirth or turmoil.</p>
               <p>In the midst of this premeditated hilarity on their part,—for his friend<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6048-00000007"/> of the forenoon had seen them all and prepared them to act this part,—the voice of conscience whispered and then thundered in his mental ear:</p>
               <p>"<emph>Remember your promise to go to church this night</emph>."</p>
               <p>He was irresolute for a moment, and then concluded to heed the monitor within and go to the sanctuary. He accordingly made known his wish to pay up his dues, leave the club honorably, and retire.</p>
               <p>His companions were prepared for this, and at once began with such expressions as these, to sneer at him:</p>
               <p>"Yes; we understand you are going to join church and turn canting Methodist, or praying Presbyterian, or singing Baptist. Is the report true?"</p>
               <p>Thus spoke one, but before George had time to reply to the inquiry at the close of his remarks, another of the club took up the subject:</p>
               <p>"I don't believe such stuff. George Welding is not the man to turn aside from good companions and the pleasures of life, to put on a long face, and go with the priest-ridden crowd to make long prayers and sing whining psalms."</p>
               <p>"Nor I! Nor I! Nor I!" Exclaimed half-a-dozen of those around him, one after another.</p>
               <p>"I'm not so sure of that," said the one who had conversed with him in the early part of the day. "He talked very much like one of the hypocrites this morning, and I had hard work to persuade him to come and settle up and leave us honorably. I think he is about to become one of the faithful, and for any thing I know, turn parson."</p>
               <p>A general laugh was the chorus to this barren attempt at wit, and George began to feel his strength give way. The voice within urged him to leave the place quickly; to flee from the pestilential atmosphere of sin as from the jaws of death; but he lingered; he had not the courage to face a laughing crowd, or defend the right before a band of profligates and scoffers. He was in an unpleasant situation, but one bold act for the right could relieve him,—save him.</p>
               <p>"<emph>Beware, George, the hour of doom is at hand!</emph>"</p>
               <p>Some unseen presence seemed to breathe the words in his ear, and he started and looked around, but only his wicked associates were visible.</p>
               <p>All this passed in the briefest possible space of time, and the laugh had scarcely subsided, when one of the mocking tempters inquired:</p>
               <p>"Tell us, Welding, honestly, if there is any truth in these reports?"</p>
               <p>This was a home question, and George must either deny his Master and tell a falsehood, or acknowledge that the reports were correct, or equivocate and avoid a direct answer. He was not prepared for the first, he had not courage for the second, and so he must needs adopt the last alternative.</p>
               <p>"I do not know that I am under any obligations to answer impertinent questions, nor do I understand this club to be a branch of the Inquisition," he replied, with some asperity.</p>
               <p>"Good for George! He's game yet! I'll bet no such mettle is ever manufactured into priest, parson or layman," responded one of the group.</p>
               <p>"Don't be too sure of that, Jo," said the tempter of the morning. "I have heard of parsons and priests who were jolly fellows, and put on sacerdotal robes only to gain the praise of men and the ears of women. It is said to be a most capital calling for a lover of pleasure, and a priest's gown the surest passport to a lady's affections."</p>
               <p>This semi-blasphemous speech was greeted with a round of applause, in which, for the first time, George joined. The others were quick to perceive this, and encouraged to persevere in their efforts. A song was sung by the club, not by any means of the most chaste character, and then it was proposed that they have some refreshments. This proposition being seconded unanimously, a side door was thrown open, and Welding saw with surprise that a repast was awaiting them already prepared on the table. This was a new feature, which had been adopted since his regular attendance at the meetings of the club.</p>
               <p>He now proposed to retire and leave the members to enjoy their feast; but the one who had been instrumental in getting him there, declared that he had ordered the supper expressly as a mark of honor and a token of good will toward him, and to commemorate his parting visit to the club, and that it was out of the question for them to excuse him.</p>
               <p>Welding, whose firmness was already melting away, resisted no further, but suffered himself to be led to the table, where the post of honor was assigned him.</p>
               <p>Conscience thundered once more, and his spirit quailed within him, as he saw the revelry that was going on around him. He wished himself away, but saw no means of escape, except by a bold and manly avowal of principle, and a decided and emphatic withdrawal from the place. He debated whether he should do this: conscience said yes, but cowardice said get out some other way. There were but a few moments left in which to decide, and not having the courage to go boldly out, he remained.</p>
               <p>Presently the wine cup was produced and filled, and the beverage of hell began to pass the lips and fire the brains of those around the table. Welding at first positively refused to drink, but there was no use of his doing so unless with the refusal he left the scene of incipient debauchery. The one who had been his evil genius all the day knew his man, and when the proper time came, successfully pressed the wine upon him.</p>
               <p>One draught taken, the barriers were thrown down, and though he had been induced to swallow the first potation under the strong representation that just one small taste as a pledge of friendship would do no harm, yet it was an easy matter to induce him to take a second and third glass.</p>
               <p>The brain was now excited, the blood heated, and George Welding was one of the club.</p>
               <p>Songs unfit for ears polite were sung; then stories, not of a character to repeat were told; and each member had some adventure of his own to relate,—adventures that could only be narrated at a bacchanalian feast; and thus alternating with obscene songs, ribald jests and voluptuous stories, the revelry was kept up for an hour or more, until the baser passions were all excited into morbid activity.</p>
               <p>Welding listened and joined in the laugh, but said nothing. Seeming all at once to notice this fact, though it had formed a part of his programme for the evening, and was definitely premeditated, the tempter said:</p>
               <p>"How is this? All the members present are the heroes of some rare adventure but Welding, and he has nothing to say. Come, my boy," and he gave him a slap on the shoulder, "this will never do; you must give us the history of some of your pranks with the fair."</p>
               <p>"I have none to give," replied George, and it was difficult to tell, certainly, whether he was proud or ashamed of the fact he thus announced.</p>
               <p>"None to give!" cried the other with a look and emphasis of incredulity.<pb n="14 (Illustration) -15" xml:id="VAC6048-00000008"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>The next moment George Welding found himself alone with the most beautiful woman he had ever beheld.</head>
                  </figure> "Do you mean to say that you have never engaged in any intrigues with ladies?"</p>
               <p>"None of the character you have been describing."</p>
               <p>"A man of your age, and not yet initiated into the mysteries of love! That is a joke worth relating. If it was a declaration made by any one but the pious Mr. George Welding, prospective priest or parson, I should seriously doubt its truth; but the word of such an immaculate son of Eve must be taken for truth, without question; but, really, such an unsophisticated specimen of Adam's fallen race should be appropriated by Barnum, or some other prince of showmen, and exhibited as a curiosity. I think the ladies would look upon him as they would upon any other strange phenomenon and wonder at his verdancy. What think you, boys?"</p>
               <p>"Certainly they would, if you could persuade them that his story was true, which is very doubtful."</p>
               <p>And they all laughed; and George laughed too, though he could not see the point of the joke, nor perceive any wit or humor in the remark. He laughed because the others did so, and especially because the fumes of liquor had enveloped his brain and made him a fool.</p>
               <p>"Now, Welding," continued his evil genius, turning toward him, "I can not suffer you to remain the butt of ridicule for the club any longer. Come with me, and I will introduce you into a bower where Cupid and Venus play at hide and seek, and love rules the hour."</p>
               <p>Saying this he conducted Welding through a second door into another apartment. On entering the room the eyes of the young man, for a moment, were dazzled with the brightness of the light and the splendor of the decoration that met his bewildered gaze. Every luxury was there, and the room might have been the palace of fairies and less brilliant in its appointments. But a second glance, like the "sober second thought," revealed beneath the surface a half-hidden, half-revealed voluptuousness in all the decorations, paintings, and arrangements of the room.</p>
               <p>Welding had scarcely time to comprehend where he was and how he came there, before a beautiful female advanced from the opposite side of the room, where she had been concealed in the flowing drapery that hung in gorgeous profusion around and before the entrance to a boudoir, whose mazy interior could only dimly be seen, like a glimpse of enchantment, which allured while it eluded the sight. He was taken completely by surprise, as this apparition so unexpectedly stood before him, and for a moment quite embarrassed.</p>
               <p>She was a woman of extraordinary personal charms, and Welding was fascinated by her loveliness. He was at once introduced to her as Miss Kate, and immediately afterward, he who had acted as cicerone to the other gentleman, remarked:</p>
               <p>"As two is company and three is not, I will retire." Then to the lady:</p>
               <p>"Now, Kate, if you do not make a conquest to-night, it will not be my fault."</p>
               <p>A look of intelligence was exchanged between them, which escaped Welding's notice. As the young man left, he passed on the further side of the woman, and whispered in her ear:</p>
               <p>"Remember what is expected of you, and make sure work."</p>
               <p>She gave him a look which said: "Trust me for that!"</p>
               <p>The next moment George Welding found himself alone with the most beautiful woman he had ever beheld.</p>
               <pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6048-00000009"/>
               <p>And now came the hour of destiny! An immortal soul was in the balance, and a few fleeting shreds of time would weigh it for eternity, and the scale would rise to heaven or sink to the gates of death,—that death that never dies!</p>
               <p>The startling events of the few past minutes, which had been designed to bewilder the destined victim, had produced the contrary effect,—Welding was completely sobered, and what he should do would be done with all his faculties under command.</p>
               <p>At this moment there was doubtless a contest between the powers of darkness and the messengers of light, which should gain a soul. The Spirit of Truth was there, and a flash of divine illumination revealed to the young man his danger, while conscience cried out within him:</p>
               <p>"<emph>Flee from temptation!</emph>"</p>
               <p>His first thought was to heed the monitor, but he hesitated; the way of escape was difficult to one of irresolute will.</p>
               <p>Then appeared to him, as a vision sent from God, the scene of Calvary. His spiritual eyes, for a moment, seemed to have the veil taken from before them, and he beheld the expiring Redeemer on the cross, and had a most vivid conception of the dying agonies of that hour when the sun clothed himself in sack-cloth and the earth rested in darkness. A voice said:</p>
               <p>"<emph>He dies for you!</emph>"</p>
               <p>Then a narrow way seemed opened up before him; at first it appeared rough and uninviting, but beyond there was a light, full of the radiance of heavenly brightness beaming upon it, and far away in the distance it terminated in a shining world of glory, whose splendors the eye could not behold. Something told him, perhaps it was the spirit of his mother, as she thus sought to snatch him from the brink of destruction:</p>
               <p>"THIS IS THE WAY OF LIFE, WALK YE IN IT."</p>
               <p>An impulse caused him to turn his eyes downward, and there a broad road stretched away before him. At the beginning it was strewn with gaudy flowers, and overhung with deceptive bowers, which looked very tempting, and seemed to invite him to enter upon that way. It had the appearance of being very smooth and level at the first,—just such a way as travelers delight to journey upon. But beyond there were thorns instead of flowers, bleak wastes in place of bowers, and rocks and precipices instead of an unbroken and level highway; and far away lurid clouds and beating storms hung in the heavens and spread desolation beneath, while the end of the vision and the road was the blackness of darkness, hanging over a pit which the eye could not penetrate. And the same kind presence seemed to say:</p>
               <p>"THIS IS THE WAY OF DEATH, FLEE FROM IT!"</p>
               <p>All this appeared to him, or flashed upon his mind with the rapidity of thought and the swiftness of light, not occupying more than half a minute, in all probability. The suggestion came into his mind:</p>
               <p>"<emph>God is warning me for the last time</emph>." And conscience said:</p>
               <p>"<emph>Choose the way of life!</emph>"</p>
               <p>Reason said so too; but passion was arrayed against them both.</p>
               <p>Then the Saviour on the cross appeared to him again, and the Mediator at the right hand of the Father stretched out his hands, those hands that bore the prints of the nails, and said:</p>
               <p>"<emph>Come unto me!</emph>" And again the conviction fastened itself on his mind: "<emph>It is the last call!</emph>"</p>
               <p>Great drops of perspiration stood on his forehead, and his spirit trembled within him. He felt that his soul was in his hands, as it were, and that he was now to have it lifted toward heaven, or sink it by his own act toward the pit of darkness.</p>
               <p>Had he been at the church, where he had promised his friend he would go, and such a choice before him, without a moment's hesitation he would have entered the narrow path of life. But he had voluntarily placed himself in the way of temptation, and now the awful responsibility of deciding from the theater of his own selection was laid upon him.</p>
               <p>As the solemn duty presented itself, he said, "I will choose heaven;" but he forgot that the tempter was at his side.</p>
               <p>"Mr. Welding, you seem abstracted and absent-minded to-night.</p>
               <p>It was the woman that spoke. She had been watching the countenance of the young man, and was puzzled to understand its rapidly changing expressions, and really, somewhat awed by the strange phases the speaking face assumed. Had Welding at that moment manned up his courage and decided to retire from the place, she would have offered no resistance, interposed no barrier or hindrance; but again he paused undecided, and then the woman began to try upon him her fascinations.</p>
               <p>He apologized for his abstractions, by saying he had become subject to this peculiarity of late.</p>
               <p>The siren was an artful one. She studied her subject, and then attacked his weak points. By the most refined and insidious approaches, and by paths hidden from his sight, she advanced to storm the citadel and lead him captive.</p>
               <p>It is not the work of a moment to prostrate one who has knelt all his life-long at the family altar, and had prayers night and morning ascend in his behalf. And this had been Welding's history; and he had been told, too, that a dear mother, who had left her blessing upon him when she went from the earth, was in heaven, and that, doubtless, her spirit watched over him with deep solicitude.</p>
               <p>But the enchantress led him, step by step, to the brink of the downward career of sin, and yet so artfully, that the way seemed only a pleasant valley of flowers.</p>
               <p>We can not describe the wiles of the fallen woman to lure the young man to ruin, nor follow her as she weaves the web to entangle his feet. The place was prepared expressly to aid her, and when the first act in the scene was over, Welding was half intoxicated with passion, and half blinded with false philosophy.</p>
               <p>But when the moment came to bring the fierceness of temptation home upon him, the good spirit and good angels made one more effort to rescue a soul from perdition.</p>
               <p>Once more the vision of the two ways seemed to rise up before him, and the Saviour to open His arms to embrace him. Before, it was the hour; now, it is the moment of destiny.</p>
               <p>The enchantress whispered guilefully in his ear, and he turned to listen. The vision of offered mercy began to recede, and he cast a longing look that way. The Saviour paused, and the spirit said: "COME!"</p>
               <p>He made a start as if to obey; then the voice of the siren fell again upon his car.</p>
               <p>"<emph>It is the last offer!</emph>"</p>
               <p>He felt the truth as a burning fire; he knew it was heaven or hell;<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6048-00000010"/> the blessed offer was still extended; but while he lingered, loth to forsake all for Christ, the breath of the temptress was on his cheek, her lips pressed his, and that kiss of passion sealed his doom. He ceased to struggle, to resist; turned to the broad way, and quick as a flash the vision of mercy was shut from his view forever!</p>
               <p>God said, as to one of old:</p>
               <p>"He is joined to his idols, let him alone."</p>
               <p>Good angels turned away and veiled their faces, and if tears <emph>could</emph> be shed in paradise, the spirit-mother wept, as all heaven knew that another soul had plucked eternal doom upon it!</p>
               <p>"Lost! <emph>lost!</emph> LOST!"</p>
               <p>The words rang for a brief time in the ears of the young man, and a shudder ran through his soul and a shiver over his body. He <emph>felt</emph> the darkness that overshadowed his spirit, and for a second the blackness of despair enveloped him.</p>
               <p>Then he listened to the voice of the siren, and as he drank in her words, the spirits of darkness held a jubilee over another soul won from honor to shame, from God to Satan, from heaven to hell!</p>
               <p>That night George Welding fairly rejected the offer of salvation, turned directly from the Saviour and His offered mercy to "enjoy the pleasures of sin for a season," and as he made the choice of evil, the Holy Spirit took its everlasting flight, and he was left to himself.</p>
               <p>Impenetrable gloom and the night of the soul settled around him.</p>
               <p>Reader, mark the result, and learn wisdom from the fearful example which the subsequent career of George Welding furnishes.</p>
               <p>God is merciful, God is love; but his judgments are past finding out, yet full of righteousness and tempered with goodness.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
               <p>ON the evening which became such an era in the life and eternal destiny of young Welding, Edward Williams had sought in vain to find his friend, first to accompany him to the place of worship, and afterward in the church itself. He wondered what could have kept him away, and where he had gone so abruptly. All the evening he felt restless; a kind of foreboding of evil filled his mind; he dreaded lest his friend should lose his serious impressions and fall hopelessly into sin.</p>
               <p>Early in the morning he went to his home and inquired after him, but he had not been seen, and no one knew where to direct him. About ten o'clock the young men unexpectedly met on the street. Welding seemed inclined to avoid his friend, but Edward turned and walked with him.</p>
               <p>"Why were you not at church last night?" he inquired.</p>
               <p>"I was otherwise engaged," was the evasive reply.</p>
               <p>"And not very profitably, I should judge from your haggard appearance."</p>
               <p>"Do I look haggard?"</p>
               <p>"Quite so, indeed."</p>
               <p>"That is rather strange, for I enjoyed myself hugely, I assure you."</p>
               <p>"Where?"</p>
               <p>"At the club."</p>
               <p>He did not tell the rest.</p>
               <p>"Alas! George, how could you go the club, when you promised to be at church?"</p>
               <p>"I reconsidered my partial promise to you, for you will remember it was not a definite one, and visited the club for the purpose of paying up my dues and leaving it forever; but the events of the evening changed my purpose, and now I shall take a different course. The church is no place for me. I wish to enjoy the pleasures of the world."</p>
               <p>"<emph>George!</emph>"</p>
               <p>"I am speaking candidly, and wish no pious efforts on your part to change my purpose. Since our conversation in the church, the other evening, an entire change has been wrought in my views, and I no longer have any desire to unite myself with the church. Perhaps I may reveal more to you at some future time, but for the present this must suffice. I will seek enjoyment in the world, you in the church,—take your way, I will take mine,—and at the end of the year we will compare notes."</p>
               <p>"<emph>If we live to see the end</emph>," remarked Edward, seriously.</p>
               <p>"Yes, <emph>if we live to see it</emph>," repeated George, musingly.</p>
               <p>"I fear you are trifling with your soul's best interest, my dear friend, and that you will grieve the Spirit from you to return no more."</p>
               <p>George felt a shock come over him as he remembered the events of the past evening, and a pallor overspread his face, as he replied:</p>
               <p>"Let my fate be what it may, I must ask you speak no more to me on the subject of religion at present. As I said, go your way, I will follow out the path that lies before me, and your persuasions will effect no change in my purpose. Leave <emph>me</emph> in peace, and I will not seek to draw <emph>you</emph> after the pleasures of life."</p>
               <p>Welding did not wish to have his conscience troubled by mention of the past or advice for the future. Already had he felt the symptoms of approaching remorse, and he cared not to have the subject before his mind.</p>
               <p>His downward career was rapid. His only escape from reflection was in dissipation, and a wild, reckless pursuit of the phantom of pleasure, that allured but to disappoint him.</p>
               <p>Such a course could have but one result. He grew mad with passion, and desperate from remorse. The past, like an avenging spirit, rose up continually to upbraid him; the present mocked him with vain promises that never could be realized, and the future—oh the dark <emph>future!</emph>—reached out before him a long, endless, dark forevermore, without a ray of light penetrating the Erebean shadows that hung like a pall over it!</p>
               <p>Is it any wonder that he became desperate? any wonder that he forsook the family altar? that he threw off parental restraint, and sought to drown memory in the intoxicating bowl? that he sought to allay the gnawings of remorse by reveling in scenes of abandonment and debauchery, from which the mind turns in disgust, and every noble feeling of the human soul shrinks with loathing?</p>
               <p>But wherever he went, in every lucid moment, the terrible words of doom rang in his ears:</p>
               <p>"Lost! <emph>lost!</emph> LOST!"</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6048-00000011"/>
               <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
               <p>EDWARD WILLIAMS parted company with his early friend very reluctantly; but he soon perceived it was impossible for them to live on the old terms of intimacy, and so he only noted George's course with deep solicitude and much apprehension, and endeavored to direct his own steps circumspectly before God and the world.</p>
               <p>He still kept an eye on Mrs. Howard—we forget whether we have previously mentioned the widow's name or not—and her two interesting children, and when the warm spring came, sent Elta to school.</p>
               <p>Mrs. Howard did not forget those in poverty and distress, after she had met with the good fortune of which we have spoken, but divided her little means with the destitute and suffering.</p>
               <p>Through her influence, Mr. Williams became acquainted with many almost starving families, to whose pressing wants he ministered, and in thus "giving to the poor," he found that he was "lending to the Lord," and he found the great Giver of all good to be an excellent pay-master; the sums he spent in charity returned to him four-fold, besides the blessings and prayers of those who had been the recipients of his bounty.</p>
               <p>Nor did he stop with the bestowal of goods that perish, but in many a home and heart sowed the good seed of life, which produced fruit, "even an hundred fold" in some instances, to the benefit of man and the glory of God. And in this way, he "laid up treasures in heaven."</p>
               <p>During the month of May, Mrs. Howard was made glad by the visit of an uncle, who had for a long time been in the West Indies, where he had accumulated a fortune.</p>
               <p>He had an only daughter, whose mother had died three years before, and for whom he wished to obtain a suitable female companion, in whose company and under whose guidance he could safely trust his darling and almost idolized child. Mrs. Howard suited him exactly, and she was removed from the humble home she had occupied through the kindness of Mr. Williams, to the elegant mansion of her wealthy uncle.</p>
               <p>Edward was cordially invited to visit her in her new abode, and as the uncle, who was made acquainted with the benevolent part he had acted toward his niece, joined in the request, he accepted their united invitation. At the residence of her father, he was introduced to the daughter, a beautiful young lady of nineteen, in whom he soon became deeply interested.</p>
               <p>His first care was to learn whether she had a saving interest in Christ—the witness of the spirit that she was a child of God; and finding that her knowledge of the plan of salvation did not reach to experimental acquaintance with God as her Father, in that special sense which constitutes man a member of the household of faith, he set before her the necessity of dedication to Him, and faith in the atoning merits of the Lamb.</p>
               <p>She embraced the truth and received the spirit of adoption, whereby she was enabled to say Abba, Father; and thus was the heart of her new friend rejoiced, because another soul had been born into the kingdom.</p>
               <p>Thrown together often, with sympathies in common, and tastes much alike, it is little to be wondered at, that Mr. Williams and Miss Melville became deeply interested in, and ultimately much attached to each other.</p>
               <p>Alice Melville soon learned to be a missionary among the poor, and her presence was hailed by the inmates of many a wretched hovel, as a ministering angel of mercy. Edward found in her a most valuable assistant in this department of his labors, for it not unfrequently happened that cases of want and misery were difficult to meet by him, as the subjects were females, who could freely make known their condition only to one of their own sex; and these Alice took under her own care.</p>
               <p>In deeds of mercy these two abounded. Often they watched together by the bed-side of the dying, wiped the death-damps from the brow of those, who but for them would probably have died with no kind hand to close their eyes no words of comfort to cheer the last moments of life. Dark abodes of wretchedness and woe were made light by their presence, and hearts that had lost confidence in God and humanity, were restored to faith in the one, and humble trust in the other. Tears dried at their approach; hunger was appeased and despair turned to hope, in whatsoever place they entered.</p>
               <p>In one of her excursions, on a bright afternoon in August, Alice met George Welding. He was a stranger, but she supposed him to be engaged in the same merciful work as herself, and paid no attention to the fact that he seemed intent on watching her movements.</p>
               <p>The next day, and the next, he met her in the same quarter; and on the last occasion he made bold to approach her, in a style entirely too familiar for a gentleman. Alice repulsed his attempt to enter into conversation, with a chilling coldness, which would have sent any not lost to self-respect, quickly from her presence, to return no more. Not so Welding. He was now fully abandoned, and as reckless as it is possible for a man to become and live in the pale of respectable society. Constant association with the abandoned had fixed in his mind the common belief of profligates, that all persons of both sexes are immoral, or ready to become so, whenever the temptation or opportunity to sin presented itself.</p>
               <p>Acting on this presumption, or else impelled by sheer wickedness, Welding went again on the fourth day, expecting to meet Miss Melville, and if so, determined to make another attempt to become acquainted with her. He was not disappointed in his expectation of meeting her, but was surprised to find that Edward Williams bore her company.</p>
               <p>He avoided them, but Alice saw him, and pointing him out to her companion, the latter was much moved to behold, in the man who had attempted to insult the lady in whom he felt the strongest interest that can actuate a human heart, the companion and friend of other days, and bosom confidant of his youth!</p>
               <p>For more than a week after this, Welding endeavored to throw himself in Miss Melville's way, but she was on her guard, and when unaccompanied by Edward, took good care to avoid him.</p>
               <p>One evening he followed them cautiously, and satisfying himself that they were more than friends to each other, he became suddenly envious of the happiness enjoyed and in store for his former associate; and the devil entering into him, as he did into Judas Iscariot, he resolved to blight the hopes of his friend in the bud. How to do this was a matter over which he spent much time thinking and planning, and finally settled upon the most diabolical of all schemes that a human brain, aided by infernal agencies and powers, could devise.</p>
               <p>This was no less than to get Alice in his power, by inducing her, through false representations, to visit the room where he had sold himself, under bondage to sin and Satan, and when there to accomplish her ruin.</p>
               <pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6048-00000012"/>
               <p>This horrible design will give the reader some idea of the deep depths of infamy and pollution to which he had fallen!</p>
               <p>He lost no time in perfecting his arrangements. The enchantress who had enticed him into the broad way of death, was mistress of the place, and he had no difficulty in gaining her consent to engage in the plot. A girl in her employ was to go with a message to Miss Melville, imploring her to visit a sick lady, and conduct her to the house. Once within the door, they knew but too well how to consummate the villainy!</p>
               <p>The girl was to be taken into their confidence only so far as was necessary to enable her to act well her part, and the very next day was set apart for the commission of the crime.</p>
               <p>On that day the girl was carefully instructed how to proceed, and told that no excuse would be taken short of an utter impossibility, and that punishment of a sore character awaited her, if she failed of success through any other cause.</p>
               <p>She went, delivered her message, and started back in company with Alice, who suspected no evil, and whose heart always responded to such calls. On the way some good influence obtained access to the girl's conscience; for aught we know it was the guardian angel that had the young lady in keeping, who was about to be sacrificed; or, it may have been a messenger sent direct from God himself, who "suffers not a sparrow to fall without his notice," and has a watchful eye over all His children. But come the good thought from whence it may, the girl relented, and revealed to Alice the plot which had been devised for her destruction, the particulars of which she had overheard, and told her as she valued all that was dear to her in life, not to go.</p>
               <p>Of course Alice turned back, thanking God in her heart for the great deliverance He had wrought out for her from an unseen danger. After this she was on her guard, and no second attempt of the kind could succeed.</p>
               <p>When the girl returned without Miss Melville, she was strictly questioned why that lady did not come, and replied that she could not, as she had other engagements.</p>
               <p>She was sent out the next afternoon on the same errand, with a much more urgent message, praying the lady by the strongest appeals to visit the couch of the dying one without fail, and immediately.</p>
               <p>Of course she returned again alone. This time the suspicions of Welding and the woman were excited, and they cross-questioned the girl so sharply that she entangled herself, and Welding then openly accused her of turning traitor.</p>
               <p>A bitter altercation ensued. Both became angry, and in a fit of ungovernable passion, maddened by the taunting words of the girl, he drew a knife and plunged it in her side! With one wild cry of "<emph>Murder!</emph>" she fell to the floor, bathed in blood!</p>
               <p>"Oh God! Welding, what have you done?"</p>
               <p>"Killed the wench, I fear," he replied; and then as the fearful consequences of his crime stared him in the face, he turned ashy pale, while great beads of perspiration stood out on every pore of his brow!</p>
               <p>"We must conceal the deed!" said the woman. "It will never do to let it be known that a murder has been committed in the house, or it will break up our establishment. Here, take hold of the girl, and help me to carry her into the inner room. I will take care of the rest."</p>
               <p>They took up the body and bore it away into a secret or unfrequented room, to which no one had access but Kate herself, or such others as she chose to admit within its walls, and there laid it upon a bed.</p>
               <p>The woman removed all traces of blood and put every thing to rights; and then Welding left.</p>
               <p>But he was never again to know peace. Wherever he went, that one terrible word from the lips of the affrighted girl, as she fell at his feet, rang in his ears! In the midst of his revels he heard it. In his dreams it sounded like a death-knell in his ears, and sleeping or waking, it kept on sounding:</p>
               <p>"<emph>Murder! murder! murder!</emph>"</p>
               <p>He plunged deeper than ever into the mire of sin, and spent all his nights in debauchery, pausing for nothing, but rushing headlong into every species of vice, and into every den of wickedness. But still that voice pursued him:</p>
               <p>"<emph>Murder! murder! murder!</emph>"</p>
               <p>And often were his disturbed slumbers visited by visions of a gallows, a gaping crowd, and himself suspended or ready to be launched off the stage of action in this ignominious manner.</p>
               <p>Such a feverish state of existence could not last long without a change or a sad termination. Neither the mind nor the body could endure such exhausting debauchery, and such racking tortures.</p>
               <p>We may as well state here that the girl did not die. The wound was a desperate one, but not fatal. Kate, however, permitted Welding to remain under the impression that she was dead, as the fact that he supposed himself in her power, gave her almost unlimited control over him; and this influence she used for the accomplishment of her own purposes.</p>
               <p>The girl lingered a long time before she was able to go about; then she was kept out of Welding's sight, and his fears played upon by the artful Kate, whenever she found it necessary to do so to effect a purpose, or bend the dupe pliantly to her will.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
               <p>WE can not enter into the details of Welding's adventures, nor do we wish to cater to any depraved taste, by rehearsing the excesses into which he ran.</p>
               <p>Until the events recorded in the last few pages, he had managed to keep his father and most of his friends in ignorance of the vicious life he was leading in secret. But such dissipation as followed these occurrences could not long be concealed; besides which, the rioting was attended by expenses which caused him more frequently to call upon his father for money.</p>
               <p>In the course of a few weeks rumors reached the parent's ears, as to how and for what purposes the son squandered the money intrusted to his care, whereupon he gave George some excellent advice; but the good counsel was thrown away. Expostulations were alike unavailing; warnings of the terrible consequences that <emph>must</emph> follow such a life, fell upon heedless ears and a callous heart. Entreaties, prayers and tears were alike employed, and alike failed to accomplish any good. His heart<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6048-00000013"/> seemed as hard as the nether mill-stone, and as impervious to all appliances as adamant itself.</p>
               <p>A few weeks expenses and he was out of funds, and had incurred debts without the means to pay them. He went to his father again; but the old gentleman having learned more fully of his ways, and knowing that the money was to be used for bad purposes, refused to give him more, unless he would promise to reform, and expend it for some good purpose. At first he would not agree to the terms; but on the next day, having taken time to reflect on the matter, he deliberately resolved to deceive his father, and thus obtain the desired supply of cash.</p>
               <p>Accordingly, he feigned repentance; for once remained during family devotion, and made satisfactory promises of amendment, and received money enough to meet his most pressing obligations, and carry on in his wicked career for a few days.</p>
               <p>But he had chosen evil, and God "gave him up to his own lusts, that he might work out his damnation with greediness." The more he sinned, the wilder became his desire to seek deeper sinks of depravity, and wallow in all the mire of pollution.</p>
               <p>As the man who yields to the appetite for strong drink, descends from wine to brandy, gin and whiskey; so he went down, step by step, in the way of sin, until there was few degrees more for him to take, ere he should reach the lower depths of degradation.</p>
               <p>He was soon penniless again, and by representing that the former amount received, had been mostly used to pay debts already contracted, he having in the meantime kept up a show of reformation before the family, he succeeded in getting a second installment of the "needful," as he termed it, which kept him going for a short time.</p>
               <p>But he soon reached the bottom of his purse, and with passions grown voracious and ungovernable, he presently found himself once more without the means of gratifying them.</p>
               <p>He knew it would be useless to go to his father soon for a new supply, and so resolved to take it without his knowledge. Several times he succeeded in abstracting small sums from Mr. Welding's pocket-book without detection. Emboldened by this success, he went a step further, and took liberties with his parent's bank-book, which was sometimes intrusted to his care. As the first of these robberies (for we can call them by no other term) passed undiscovered, he imagined that all his pecuniary difficulties were ended, and that he had at length found the way to obtain the means for the gratification of all his desires.</p>
               <p>As might be supposed, he became more prodigal than ever, and soon the liberties he had taken with his father's bank deposits were made manifest, and he was called to account.</p>
               <p>At first he denied the allegation, but finding that the proof was ample and conclusive, he turned about and accused his father of stinting him in the money line, and that he had resorted to this method in order to get the necessary funds to keep up an honorable appearance in society, and be on an equality with the other young men of his set. This was only "adding insult to injury," and Mr. Welding rebuked his son quite sharply, and the latter left his presence in a sullen mood.</p>
               <p>Of course he was not trusted with the bank-book, or to transact any other business where he would have the temptation to steal before him, or the opportunity to wrong his father placed in his reach.</p>
               <p>He was now puzzled to get along. He could not stop. When he grieved the Holy Spirit from him, he was left to himself, and without the restraining grace of God no man can govern himself or tell where his own evil habits and inclinations will lead him.</p>
               <p>As the rock let loose from its moorings at the top of a mountain, starts on its downward course and gathers momentum and increases its velocity at every bound, so the man who starts on the declivity of vice, and throws off all restraints, soon gets beyond his own control, and madly rushes to destruction. And this was George Welding's case.</p>
               <p>He could not pause to think, because thought only brought remorse or fear. And ever, in his reflective hours, came the remembrance of his past evils deeds; of the choice he had made, when life and death were plainly set before him; of the hight from which he had fallen, never to rise again!</p>
               <p>And when alone, in the darkness, or in the glare of noon-day, there was the body of the murdered girl, the blood flowing from the wound in her side, the paleness overspreading her deathly countenance, and the terrible sound of that one word which came gushing out through her blanched lips!</p>
               <p>Had the deed been done in darkness, with no eye but his own and God's to witness the crime, he would have cared less; but Kate was there and saw all,—his life was in her hands, and, as a consequence, he was her slave; <emph>and she knew it</emph>.</p>
               <p>It is little to be regarded as a matter of surprise, that he should blindly plunge into the most exciting scenes of wickedness to drown his remorseful feelings, or create an excitement which, for the time, would be more absorbing than these haunting memories and phantoms.</p>
               <p>He tried the wine cup, but the liquid potions only added to his madness, and he had to abandon his cups, or drink only when some desperate deed was to be performed; but into the wildest scenes of sensual gratification he rushed with a headlong blindness of consequences, which would have been insanity itself, but for the fact that it was to escape the more fearful demons within his own breast.</p>
               <p>It was utterly impossible that such a state of mind, and such reckless waste of the physical powers could last long without producing results of a startling character. We would as naturally look for some tragical termination to such a career, as for harvest after seed time, or fruit after bloom. And it came.</p>
               <p>Young Welding was soon out of means, and managed to rob his father once more. He was detected in the crime, or found out shortly after its commission, and received a rather caustic lecture for his misdeeds; and after this more care was taken that no opportunity to repeat the crime should present itself. His father was a Christian, and desired most of all that his son should become virtuous and lead a new life, meekly following in the footsteps of the blessed Master.</p>
               <p>But he might as well have prayed for, and expostulated with, a rock, as with the wayward youth.</p>
               <p>One evening George came home and represented that he <emph>must</emph> have a sum of money to pay off certain obligations that had fallen due, and rather demanded than asked the amount he wished to receive from his father. The elder Mr. Welding had been deceived so often by his son, and had given him so much to pay his debts within the past three months, besides all which he had purloined from him, that he refused the ungraciously asked favor, and again expostulated with George on the evils of such a life as he was leading, for of late he had scarcely made an effort to hide his evil practices; and they were beginning to be the common talk of his acquaintances.</p>
               <p>The good advice of his father, coupled with the denial of the sum of money asked, instead of producing any good effect, only aggravated him, and he threatened his parent with bodily injury if he did not grant his request. His bad temper did not further his suit, and he left the presence of that father with murder in his heart!</p>
               <p>O, what a fearful thing it is for man to be left to himself!</p>
               <p>This was not the first time he had used violent and menacing language to his father, but it was the last. He retired to his room, divested himself of his clothing, and put on his sleeping gown.</p>
               <p>All this time his brain was on fire; the excitement of the recent interview had kindled the evil passions of his nature to a flame, and the thought of murder, which had been suggested days before by the tempter, now ripened to a purpose, and he mentally resolved to do a deed, which nine months before he would have shuddered at, even in the most distant conception, or if committed by the most savage of barbarians.</p>
               <p>He took from their hiding-place beneath his bed, where he had previously concealed them in anticipation of the present hour, one of Allen's three-barreled revolvers, which<pb n="26 (Illustration) -27" xml:id="VAC6048-00000014"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Cautiously he stole down the stairs, his feet unshod, his weapon in his hands, and fierce passions that burned within him, crying out: "<emph>Blood! blood! blood!</emph>"</head>
                  </figure> was already charged, a small hatchet, such as carpenters use, and an ordinary butcher's knife. He examined the weapons, saw that they were all in proper order, and then muttered to himself: "Now for an end to all this!"</p>
               <p>Then appeared before him the bleeding form of the girl he had stabbed, as though it came to warn him of the blackness of the crime he was about to perpetrate. But the specter only added to the fire in his bosom.</p>
               <p>"Too long have I been troubled with this gory sight; it shall trouble me no more! If there be a hell in the future, it can be no worse than the one I am enduring in the body, and I will go to it!"</p>
               <p>This dreadful sentence was scarcely uttered in thought, for he only spoke it mentally, as we may suppose, ere he started on his terrible errand.</p>
               <p>There was no outward excitement of manner; had he been met by a friend, no traces of the foul purpose that absorbed all his faculties would have revealed the state of his mind. The excitement was all within, and the more intense from its confined boundaries and the limits to which he had resolutely circumscribed it.</p>
               <p>Cautiously he stole down the stairs, his feet unshod, his weapons in his hands, and fierce passions that burned within him, crying out:</p>
               <p>"<emph>Blood! blood! blood!</emph>"</p>
               <p>Mr. Welding stood near the spot where he had left him, for all his preparations had been made in a few minutes. He walked deliberately up to him, and, as the father who had dandled him on his knee in infancy, and kissed the tears from his cheeks in youth, turned to see who approached, the son lifted the hatchet and struck him such a blow on the head as buried the weapon to the helve in his skull; then as he fell with a cry, struck him again on the temple, almost severing that half of the skull from the head! Then believing his parent to be dead, he rushed to the room where his step-mother slept, who had arisen in bed to see what was the matter, and notwithstanding her uniform kindness to him all his life, aimed deathly blows at her head, three of which she parried, but the fourth took effect, and prostrated her, after which he cut and mangled her in a most horrid manner, and left her for dead.</p>
               <p>Two brothers met him next; the one a tender youth of seven summers, the other fourteen. Surely there is no madness that could tempt him to kill these! But he pauses not. The bloody hatchet is raised:</p>
               <p>"Oh, brother George, do n't hurt Charlie!" pleads Nathan.</p>
               <p>And Charlie looks up innocently into the face of the murderer, and says:</p>
               <p>"Brother George, do n't hurt us!"</p>
               <p>Had there been any good left in his heart, his hand would have fell powerless to his side, and the boys would have escaped. But the fiend had possession of his bosom, and the boys were smitten down ruthlessly at his feet!</p>
               <p>By this time the servant girls from the third story, alarmed by the noise, came running down stairs. George met them and struck one of them down with a savage blow; the other seized the hatchet and wrested it from him, but with the strength of a madman, he wrenched it out of her hand, and despite her heroic resistance, soon left her covered with blood by the side of her companion.</p>
               <p>Two little girls, snugly asleep in bed, were all that now remained of the household. He had evidently determined on the destruction of every inmate of the house, for nothing short of such a horrible purpose, with a heart utterly and irredeemably lost to all hope and humanity, could have prompted him to seek these little innocents. He went to the door of their room, but fortunately it had been looked and he could not enter, and thus the little girls were saved.</p>
               <p>With the blood of parent and brothers upon him, he now proceeded to his own room, leaving the door of the children with an oath, and there placed the muzzle of the pistol to his right ear and blew out his own brains!</p>
               <p>What a scene of horrors that house presented!</p>
               <p>There were six human beings, from the one whose head was silvered with the frosts of age to the white-haired urchin of seven years, lying in their gore, covered with ghastly wounds! And a little way off was the mangled corpse of the wretch who had in one hour became in act, what he had already been in heart, a <emph>parricide, fratricide, murderer and suicide!</emph>
               </p>
               <p>We care not to dwell on this shocking picture. Very briefly have we hastened through the sickening and awful details, for the crime is too appalling to contemplate!</p>
               <p>The miserable wretch, however, did not <choice>
                     <sic>succed</sic>
                     <corr>succeed</corr>
                  </choice> in his intentions. But one of his victims, a servant girl, died of the wounds inflicted; the rest, after lingering for weeks, and<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6048-00000015"/> the father for two months, recovered, though they will bear the marks of that night's work to their graves.</p>
               <p>When did George Welding become a murderer? Was it when he plunged the knife into the side of the girl at Kate's house? Was it when he struck his father the first blow? No; it was nine months previous to that time, when he chose a life of sin, disregarded the invitations of the Saviour, cut off the hope of the soul, and insanely entered the road of death.</p>
               <p>And that young club-mate, who drew him aside from the path of duty, who urged him to go to the club once more to "pay up his dues and leave as a man, and not sneak out like a coward," and when he had gained a reluctant consent, went and prepared the snares, the feast and the fallen woman with her sensual beauty and beguiling words to lead him in the path of sin, is guilty of all the blood that was shed, of the suicide's mad career on earth, fearful death and eternal doom!</p>
               <p>We would not take that young man's place for the wealth of worlds! Woe! woe! woe! shall be upon his guilty head! The blood of his brother crieth out from the ground against him, and the cry has entered the ear of Jehovah!</p>
               <p>Oh, young man! beware how you tempt a companion to sin! Especially beware how you persuade one to shake off convictions of duty, or lay a snare, or place a temptation in his way, to lead him astray! BEWARE! You know not his strength of endurance. You know not the amount of light he will be sinning against, to accept of your offer, or join you in your revels! You know not what brood of devils you may let loose upon him or unchain in his breast! Therefore, by the priceless value of the soul, by your hopes of heaven, by all that is sacred, we charge you, BEWARE!</p>
               <p>And ye who are enlightened by the Holy Spirit, upon whose consciences the light from God's lamp shineth, and the monitor in whose breast points out the way of life, and warns to flee the presence of sin and destruction, trifle not with these things! We charge you not to shut the door of your hearts when the Saviour knocks there for admission. Oh, turn not your back upon Him, who suffered "even unto death" for you!</p>
               <p>Before you are the two ways, the broad and the narrow. You may not see them as plainly as George Welding saw them, because your present danger may not be as imminent as his; but they are <emph>now</emph> before you. Look upon them!</p>
               <p>There is the one with the straight gate at the entrance, requiring you to unload the incumbrance of sin you are carrying, in order to enter upon it. It does not seem inviting at the outset; but look yonder where the glory of the Shekinah rests upon it, and see the brightness that marks its near approach to the land, where all who travel upon this highway of holiness desire to enter! Yonder, at the end of the way nearest heaven, is a pilgrim preparing to leave it for a short passage through the <emph>dark valley</emph>. Behold the smile on his countenance, and the joy in his eye, as he exclaims: "<emph>I am almost home!</emph>" and exults in prospect of the glory that awaits him just across the narrow shadows of death! He fears not the monster, he dreads not the grave, but rapturously sings: <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"O death! where is thy sting!</l>
                        <l>O grave! where is thy victory!"</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q> And as the mortal tabernacle falls to its mother earth, the happy soul soars away in holy triumph!</p>
               <p>Now look down the other road. At first there are flowers, but every flower conceals a thorn. Tempting fruit hangs on green boughs, but it turns to ashes on your lips; and then down yonder a little further, there is nothing that looks inviting. The way grows rougher and darker at every step. There is the drunkard, the liar, the scoffer, the dram-seller, the murderer, and every other wicked person, including the hypocrite—all walking the same road. See the company, and behold the end! Clouds and darkness gather about the termination of this broad way. And look you upon him who is just leaving it forever, to enter upon the great beyond! What anguish is written on his features! what remorse gnaws at his heart! No joy in those eyes! no hope in that breast! No prospect after the short hour of life is over invites his spirit away, but a sad foreboding of evil to come. Groans instead of rejoicings, sighs in place of songs escape his lips! He leaves the world, enshrouded in gloom, and plunges into that awful abyss at the end of the road upon which he has traveled!</p>
               <p>Behold the ways, O reader! and choose ye <emph>now</emph> upon which one to journey.</p>
               <p>By the lesson which we have tried faintly to set before you in these pages, we conjure, we entreat you not to turn your back upon Christ. He now, this moment, holds out his hands to <emph>you</emph>, even <emph>you</emph>, oh, reader! and says: "COME UNTO ME."</p>
               <p>You hear the voice in your heart, shut not your spirit's ear to the sweet sound. It is mercy speaks, it is love invites, regard the heavenly call.</p>
               <p>We charge you by the fearful life and tragic death of GEORGE WELDING, <emph>not</emph> to trifle with Divine impressions, not to slight the offers of salvation. You may shudder at his fate—for it so recently sent a thrill of horror through all the nation, you can not have forgotten it—and shrink from it, and yet by procrastination do what he did by want of firmness. Be warned in time, and turn to God ere the Spirit takes its flight. It may do it: for, <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"There is a time, we know not when,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">A point, we know not where;</l>
                        <l>That marks the destiny of men,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">For glory or despair."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>From the scene of crime and blood which has been arrayed before us, we turn with feelings of relief, to one more in harmony with the nobler impulses and sentiments of the human soul. We leave the young man with his sins, in the hands of that Being, who is "too wise to err, and too good to be unkind," praying that the example of his life and fearful end may not be lost on the mind, heart and conscience of a single individual, into whose hands this little work shall fall. May the God of all grace bring good out of evil by sealing instruction upon the hearts of all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
               <p>THE world is full of what to a superficial observer might be considered strange contradictions. A murder here, a marriage there; a death in that house, a birth in this; happiness here, misery yonder; sin and righteousness, life and death, good and evil, sorrow and rejoicing—surely this is a strange world; but sin is the cause of all its disorders.</p>
               <p>At the hour when young Welding was committing a deed that would thrill a nation with horror, an occurrence as opposite to that as day is from night, or light from darkness, was transpiring in another dwelling of the great city.</p>
               <p>The home of the Melvilles had been visited by one of the messengers of Death, to herald the approach of the King of Terrors. Little Willie was smitten with disease. For several days he had suffered much pain, and the doctor had given small encouragement to the hopes of the fond mother, who had watched with unwearied constancy at his bad-side.</p>
               <p>If care and love could cure the maladies to which mortality is heir, little Willie would have been safe from all harm; but the Destroyer is stronger than human affections, and all that could be done availed not in this case. Neither the physician's skill, nor the resources of a mother's boundless love, could stay the steady approach of death; and now the son of the widow's hope lay upon his dying couch, and all present felt that further effort to save his life was useless.</p>
               <p>Oh! ye mothers who have looked upon the tender forms of loved ones passing away, well do ye know the feelings, which no pen can describe, that agitated the bosom of the mother of the little boy, who was soon to look for the last time with an answering smile, as she gazed in tenderness upon him.</p>
               <p>Slowly had the little bud of immortality faded before her eyes. She had done all that mortal or mother could do, and if watering the opening flower with tears could have saved it, there would have been no silence in the room that night, as the sorrowful group gathered about the bed.</p>
               <p>Willie had often talked strangely about angels. He never saw the picture of one that he did not have many questions to ask concerning it—questions so much above his years, that his mother was often startled at the premature intelligence of the child, and wondered in her heart whence came his wisdom. When he was taken sick, his sleep seemed to be blessed with strange visions of heavenly visitants, and his waking hours were much occupied in rehearsing what he had seen with his mental eyes, while those of his body were locked in slumber; but it did not strike the mother that these things were presages of what must surely follow, and she treasured them up in her heart without sorrow, to become precious memories in after years, when the full import of their meaning should be revealed to her consciousness.</p>
               <pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6048-00000016"/>
               <p>Each succeeding day told plainly that the child was "passing away," but the mother would not believe it. How could she think of her precious darling as a cold lump of clay? How could she reconcile her mind to the darkness that should reign in her spirit, when this light should be taken from her?</p>
               <p>But the hour came when even she dare not hope longer. She was awakened to this conviction by the child himself, who on opening his eyes after a short sleep, said:</p>
               <p>"Mother, Willie is going to join the angels. They have come to see me, oh, so often, and presently they will take me away with them."</p>
               <p>A strange thrill went quivering to the mother's heart, but stilling the emotions which filled her bosom, she inquired:</p>
               <p>"How does Willie know he will go away with the angels?"</p>
               <p>"One of them told me so. Oh, they are so beautiful! I shall delight to be with them! They are all dressed in such clean white robes, and their faces shine with brightness. Oh, how glad I shall be when I am an angel!"</p>
               <p>"Is Willie so anxious to go away and leave poor mother?"</p>
               <p>"Oh, I did not think of that!" and his sparkling eye filled with tears, while a shadow fell over the speaking face, which before had been so radiant. He put his little arms around her neck, drew her face down close to his, and pressed a kiss upon her cheek. He held her thus for a few moments, then his thoughts ran back to the theme he had been conversing about, and he murmured in her ear:</p>
               <p>"But oh, it is such a lovely place!"</p>
               <p>Closer the mother pressed her cheek to his, and the tears trickled silently down her face. When she lifted her head the traces of weeping were visible.</p>
               <p>"Why do you cry, mother?" asked the child, as though it were a matter of surprise, that a journey to heaven should be a cause of sorrow to his dearest earthly friend.</p>
               <p>"Because my only little boy is going to leave me, and never come back," she replied.</p>
               <p>"But I will come, mother. I have seen bright angels hovering over your head, and when I get to be an angel, I will come too; and oh, I 'll kiss you then, and the kiss will be so soft you will never know it or feel it. But I think it will make you happy, if you do n't know it; for when the good angels have been near you, there has always been a look of joy or peace on your face."</p>
               <p>In spite of herself, the tears flowed afresh from the mother's eyes; but there was comfort mingled with her sorrow. The child's words had been as balm to her heart.</p>
               <p>Much more passed between them on this and other occasions, and then the day dawned that was to be the last in which the dear child should ever behold the sun with his natural eyes.</p>
               <p>The severity of the disease was passed; he now suffered but little pain, but was gradually sinking away.</p>
               <p>"I can not stay with you much longer," he said to his mother in the afternoon. She wiped her eyes, but did not trust her voice to speak; for she knew that the fatal moment was rapidly approaching. After a pause of some considerable duration, during which he seemed to be thinking strange thoughts for a child so young in years, he resumed:</p>
               <p>"Bring me my toys, mother; I should like to look at them once more before I go."</p>
               <p>With a heavy heart, Mrs. Howard went to the nursery and returned with his toys. He requested to be propped up in bed and have them spread out before him. It was done.</p>
               <p>Then he took up each little plaything and examined it, telling some reminiscence connected with it in the past. When he had looked at one until satisfied, he handed it back to his mother, saying:</p>
               <p>"Put it away; I shall never want it again."</p>
               <p>Thus he went through with them all. Some that had been most highly prized he held long, and seemed to part from them with regret; and a few were pressed to his lips, ere he laid them aside forever!</p>
               <p>No heart could witness such a scene unmoved, and those around the bed only restrained their emotions by a powerful effort, for they did not wish to interrupt the child in this strange ceremony of leave-taking; but their tears flowed freely.</p>
               <p>"Now, mother, take them all out of my sight, and keep as many of them as you like, to remember Willie by."</p>
               <p>Mrs. Howard took them back to the nursery, and as she put them in their place, the long suppressed feelings asserted their mastery, and with a gush of tears, she leaned over the child's little treasures, exclaiming:</p>
               <p>"Oh! how can I bear this trial?" For a few minutes she remained there, until her heart was relieved of some of its woe by abundant weeping, and then returned to the bed-side.</p>
               <p>Presently Willie fell asleep. It was the last time his eyes should close in slumber, until they shut in that "sleep which knows no waking," until the spell of death is broken by the voice of God, through the archangel, at the funeral of time.</p>
               <p>The day was now far spent, and as the evening shadows began to gather over the earth, Mr. Williams was sent for, it having been his special request to see the child at the hour of dissolution. When Willie awoke, the light of day had departed, the room was illumined by artificial means, and the five friends whom he loved most, Mr. Melville, Alice, Edward, Elta, and his mother, were near him.</p>
               <p>"All here," he said; then turning to Mr. Williams, he continued:</p>
               <p>"But I should not be here now, if you had not come to us that night. O how delicious that orange was! But they have sweeter fruit up there where the angels are. Wont you kiss me, Mr. Williams, before I go away?"</p>
               <p>He bent down and kissed the boy a dozen times, and turned away with overflowing eyes.</p>
               <p>Willie next spoke to Alice:</p>
               <p>"You have been a sister to mother, and almost as good as a mother to me. I will ask the good angels to come and take care of you, as you have taken care of us; and I know they will be near you when you teach Elta to pray, and when you visit the sick. Ah, they are very near you then! Now you must kiss Willie too, and then let dear uncle take your place."</p>
               <p>Mr. Melville was not a Christian by profession, but his heart was deeply touched as he witnessed the scenes we have been describing. He now came to take leave of the child who had grown into his affections, as children only can find way into the bosom of age. He took Willie's hand in his, and his whole body trembled, so that he dare not trust his voice to speak.</p>
               <p>"Oh, how I love you, dear uncle." said the boy, "because you have been so good to mother and us. I would like to live with you always, and I want you to be sure and come where I am going. Will you, uncle?"</p>
               <p>"I will try," the strong man made out to say.</p>
               <p>"And if you try I know you will get there, for it is such an easy road to travel, and the bright angels will always help you, when you come to a hard place."</p>
               <p>"God bless the child!" fervently exclaimed the old gentleman, as the tears refused longer to be held back.</p>
               <p>"And God bless uncle, too!" rejoined Willie. "And I know He will, for you have blessed us so much."</p>
               <p>Then Elta came.</p>
               <p>"Oh Willie! are you going to leave Elta forever?" she cried out in a burst of passionate grief, as she buried her face in the pillow, and gave way to her emotions.</p>
               <p>"Yes, Elta dear; I will soon be gone, where you can see me no more in this world. You will have no little brother to play with then, and you will be all alone. I have thought of this, and felt like staying to be company for you, but I can not remain. It will be but a little while, and then you will join us up there—I mean those beautiful little ones and me. Elta must be a good girl, love our dear mother much, and pray every day. These beautiful ones are always near when you pray. I have seen them, and they looked so happy when you bowed down to say your prayers. I will come too; and when you kneel down, just think Willie is near, and then be glad that I am happy, and thank God. Be a good girl, Elta, and meet me up there, where we shall never part, and never weep."</p>
               <p>The sister had drawn closer and closer to her brother, and now her arm was around his neck, and her face pressed against his. Thus she remained for some length of time, unable to speak, and yet comforted by Willie's words.</p>
               <p>"There, Elta," he said at last, "my strength is almost gone, and I must talk a little with mother. Kiss me, dear."</p>
               <p>Mrs. Howard now came and laid her arm under Willie; and lifting him up, rested his head upon her bosom.</p>
               <p>"Ah, that is nice!" he said. "I love to get near your heart, mother, <emph>it always seemed as if I were at home there</emph>."</p>
               <p>This childish expression, so comprehensive in fullness of meaning, sent a strange thrill of joy to the mother's heart.</p>
               <p>"And this is the last time you will ever hold Willie in your arms, until we meet where death never comes to divide us. O, it will be so delightful to live where we never say<pb n="32-33 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC6048-00000017"/> good bye! I told you, mother, that I was coming to be near you. When you and sister are kneeling together in the morning, and the evening, I will be there. And when the stars begin to come out as it commences to get dark, if you will sit by my window, I will come and hover near you. I have seen those beautiful children in heaven come to the earth to bless those they loved, and I know I can come. Just think that Willie sees you, and—"</p>
               <p>His voice suddenly grew faint, and stopping short in the midst of his words, he began to sink heavily upon the breast that supported him.</p>
               <p>"What makes it grow so dark, mother?" he whispered presently. "I can scarcely see you. Do n't let them shut off the gas. I wish to see you to the end."</p>
               <p>"It is the end now, Willie. The room is light, but your eyes are growing dim."</p>
               <p>She spoke calmly, for she did not wish to disturb his quiet rest, but it cost her a powerful effort.</p>
               <p>"Draw the clothes around me, mother. I am so cold!"</p>
               <p>She did as requested, though she knew he would never be warm again. For a few minutes he lay quietly with his eyes closed, then he slowly opened them, and a bright smile overspread his pale face, as he looked upward and said:</p>
               <p>"<emph>They are coming!</emph>"</p>
               <p>And in a moment added:</p>
               <p>"Do you see them, mother? They are almost here! They beckon to me! I must go! Good bye, uncle, and Edward, and Alice, and Elta! Good bye, mother! They are here! O beautiful! Kiss me, mother! Once more! There—I—am—with—the—angels!"</p>
               <p>The voice died away to a soft murmur, and Willie was no longer of the earth.</p>
               <p>The delightful smile still lingered on his face, and his whole countenance seemed to be surrounded with a kind of halo, which gave it an expression almost heavenly.</p>
               <p>Gently the mother laid him down, and then fondly covered his brow and lips and cheeks with kisses!</p>
               <p>Tears flowed from every eye; but there was joy with their sorrow, for they felt that the place was very near the heavenly gates, and that Willie was at rest.</p>
               <p>"Blessed are the dead who die in the Lord," and such are all little children.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>CONCLUSION.</head>
               <p>WHEN the end of the year came, Edward Williams could not compare notes with George Welding; but the awful fate of his former friend superseded any such necessity. Sad thoughts filled his mind, as he remembered how the young man dashed the cup of mercy from his lips, and chose the pleasures of sin, in preference to the rewards of virtue.</p>
               <p>But he had found a new friend—a more than friend, and he blessed God that they walked together in the same path, and that their affection was sanctified by grace. He hopes to be united to Alice the present year.</p>
               <p>If we were merely writing a novel, we should have ended with a marriage, and the scenes we have tried faithfully to describe, would have been wrought up into pictures of horrors and startling panoramas. But we have a higher object in view, and if but one reader shall be warned from the error of his way, by the perusal of these pages, it will be reward enough for our toil. Gladly would we meet such a one amid that "innumerable company, who have washed their robes and made them white in the blood of the Lamb." Heaven grant that it may be so.</p>
               <closer>THE END.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="advertisement">
            <head>LIST OF PUBLICATIONS, ETC.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Greatness in Little Things. By Ruth Vernon. Cloth embossed, gilt back. 320 pages, 12 mo., $1 00</item>
               <item>Great Red Dragon; or, Master Key to Popery, 1 50</item>
               <item>Josephus' Works. The learned Jewish Historian and celebrated Warrior; with three dissertations concerning Jesus Christ, John the Baptist. James the Just, God's Command to Abraham, etc.; and explanatory notes and observations, translated by William Whiston, A. M., Professor of Mathematics in the University of Cambridge. Complete in one volume, with portrait and illustrations. 648 pages, octavo. Bound in leather, library style. Retail price, 1 60</item>
               <item>Do. black and red leather embossed, gilt back and marble edge. Retail price, 1 80</item>
               <item>Governor Gearey's Administration in Kansas, with a complete history of the Territory. Cloth, 1 00</item>
               <item>Paper edition, 0 50</item>
               <item>Arnold's Family Medical Companion, being a complete treatise on Anatomy, Physiology, Hygiene and Disease, its cause, preventive and cure, written in a familiar style, in form of a set of popular lectures, especially designed for the general reader, and adapted to the instruction of fathers and mothers. Fully illustrated in the most appropriate manner for a Family Medical Guide.—containing about 500 large 12 mo, pages. Bound in substantial embossed muslin, full gilt, spring back. Retail price, 1 50</item>
               <item>Private Correspondence of Henry Clay. By Calvin Colton. Muslin, 2 00</item>
               <item>Leather, library style, 2 50</item>
               <item>American Form Book and Legal Guide, adapted to every state in the Union, 1 00</item>
               <item>General Lane's Brigade in Mexico. "The operations of General Lane in the Mexican War were of the most brilliant character, so much so, indeed, that he won by them the appellation of 'The Marion of the War.'" This work is written in an easy and familiar style, embracing an account of many of the most important facts and events connected with the American Army in Mexico; together with numerous anecdotes, descriptions of the country, people, habits and customs, etc., etc. 12 mo., 336 pages. Cloth binding; gilt back. Retail price, 0 75</item>
               <item>Phelp's National Map of the United States, with all the principal Rail Roads laid down, properly colored in States; containing also a Statistical Table of the population of each State of the Union at the present time; also, the seals of each State in the Union, with a bird's-eye Map of South America; all colored appropriately, sheet form. Size of sheet, twenty-eight by thirty-nine inches. Retail price, 0 50</item>
               <item>Chart of Washington, containing a beautiful colored Picture of the Head of George Washington, 0 25</item>
               <item>Presidents of the United States, with a brief Biography of each. Colored in magnificent style. Retail price, 0 50</item>
               <pb n="34 (Advertisement) -35" xml:id="VAC6048-00000018"/>
               <item>Portrait of Wildey, the Founder of the Order of Odd Fellows in America, $1 50</item>
               <item>Portrait of Washington as a Free Mason, 1 50</item>
               <item>The Annunciation and the Lord's Prayer, 0 25</item>
               <item>George Welding; or, Crime and its Consequences, 0 15</item>
            </list>
            <p>This last named book is to be sold with circulars by Agents, who travel from town to town.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Map of Nicaragua, North and Central America, 0 25</item>
               <item>Union Harp and Revival Chorister, being a collection of Hymns and Tunes, designed more especially for the social means of grace, and for Sabbath-schools. It contains a greater variety of choice Sabbath-school and popular Hymns, old and new, adapted to social religious circles, than is published in any other one book. Selected and arranged by Professor C. Dunbar. Containing 532 pages. Marble board, leather back, 0 50</item>
               <item>Black leather, embossed, 0 75</item>
               <item>Turkey morocco, gilt, 1 25</item>
               <item>Antique, gilt, 1 25</item>
               <item>Union Sabbath-School Chorister, containing a great number of the most popular Sabbath-school Hymns of the day, both old and new, and adapted to all Evangelical Churches. Compiled and arranged by Professor C. Dunbar. Paper binding, 0 16</item>
               <item>Marble board sides, leather backs, 0 25</item>
               <item>Leather, embossed, 0 35</item>
               <item>Turkey, full gilt, 1 00</item>
               <item>Antique, gilt, 1 00</item>
               <item>Union Musical Tract, containing a number of popular revival Hymns and Tunes, for the choir and social circle; also the Chorister' Key giving the first part of Forty Standard Hymns and Tunes, for the benefit of the leading singer. By Professor C. Dunbar. Retail-price, 0 05</item>
               <item>The Lady's and Gentleman's Book of Etiquette, 0 25</item>
               <item>Hervey's Meditations. By Rev. James Hervey, A. M. Two volumes in one, 304 pages. Bound in muslin, gilt back. Retail price, 0 50</item>
               <item>Pilgrim's Progress from this World to that which is to come. By John Bunyan. 216 pages. Bound in muslin, gilt. Retail price, 0 50</item>
               <item>Danger in the Dark, 1 00</item>
            </list>
            <p>Sample Copies of either of the above Books will be mailed to any part of the Union, on the receipt of the Retail Price. For Sample Copies or terms to Agents, address</p>
            <trailer>H. M. RULISON, Queen City Publishing House, 141 Main St., Cincinnati, O.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>