<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6608">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Josephine Eloise </title>
            <author >Hammond, Adelaide F.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC6608</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >Josephine Eloise</title>
                  <author >Hammond, Adelaide F.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >93 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >Baltimore News Co.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Baltimore </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1872">1872</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-05-31">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2006-06-21">Finished TEI conversion</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <front> 
         <titlePage xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
            <pb  n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6608-00000001"/> 
            <docTitle> 
               <titlePart>JOSEPHINE ELOISE,</titlePart> 
               <titlePart type="sub">A NOVEL:</titlePart> 
            </docTitle> 
            <byline >BY <docAuthor xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Mrs. ADELAIDE F. HAMMOND.</docAuthor>
            </byline> 
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>BALTIMORE:</pubPlace> 
               <publisher >PUBLISHED BY THE BALTIMORE NEWS COMPANY,</publisher> 
               <publisher >JOHN W. WOODS, PRINTER, 12 SOUTH STREET.</publisher>
            </docImprint> 
            <docDate>1872.</docDate> 
            <pb  n="3" xml:id="VAC6608-00000002"/> 
            <docEdition>Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1872, by Mrs. ADELAIDE F. HAMMOND, in the Office of the Librarian of Congress at Washington.</docEdition> 
         </titlePage> 
      </front> 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Josephine Eloise</head> 
             
            <head>JOSEPHINE ELOISE.</head> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER I.</head> 
               <head type="sub">THE DISCOVERY OF THE BABE, JOSEPHINE ELOISE.</head> 
               <p>IN New England about a mile from the village of M-, stood a small cottage, far back from the road, and almost hidden from, view by large trees, and the thick undergrowth of bushes plainly denoted that for some years it had been neglected, and the house which, might once have been quite pretty was now in a dilapidated condition, and was inhabited only by two old people who had barely means enough to live upon in the most penurious way.</p> 
               <p>Old James and Martha Jackson were well known to every one in and about the village of M-as good, honest o'd people, but who were quite poor, and their neighbors often sent them delicacies which it was impossible for them to procure themselves.</p> 
               <p>These old people, according to their custom for years, were always up with the sun. So one bright morning in May, old Martha went to open the door of her dwelling, as usual, and her good husband stood by, when, what was their astonishment, to see a basket lying just outside the doorway, and neatly folded over the top of the basket a white damask cloth.</p> 
               <p>"Lord bless us, man, what have we here," cried Martha, in astonishment, holding up both hands.</p> 
               <p>"Our good neighbors must have brought us something after we were abed, and did not like to disturb us, so they left it here as a surprise for us in the morning," he replied.</p> 
               <p>"So, so, now let's look and see, Oh my, its heavy though," said the old woman, raising the basket; then the old couple proceeded to uncover it. After laying it on the table, first one piece of linen was taken off, then another, and upon raising the third piece, the old lady exclaimed, "Lord save us; man, its a baby, and ah such a sweet pretty one too, and here is a slip of paper, but I can't read it without my glasses, perhaps its a check for a thousand pounds, let me see, let me see, here they are; but, Oh gracious, no James, it is only written, 'her name is Josephine Eloise.'"</p> 
               <p>Now, while Martha had been so busy talking and supposing, the old man had looked on as if stupefied, but at last seeming to gain consciousness, he said:</p> 
               <p>"But, good gracious woman, what are we to do with a baby, we are hardly<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC6608-00000003"/> ly able to take care of ourselves, and not a cent of money sent along with the child to take care of it with; this will never do wife, it will never do."</p> 
               <p>"Lord bless the child, I must take it up; see, it's waking, it will never do to let it lie there any longer."</p> 
               <p>Just as Martha had uttered these words the child opened its great blue eyes, and stretched out its little hands and began to cry.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, James, James, it looks so like our baby Isabel, who died these forty years ago; how can I refuse to take the child? How cruel it would be to send so sweet a babe away to one of those asylums, where we should never know any more about her; why I love the child already, see how pretty and fair she is; she may turn out some great lady one of these days, and bring us riches and honors."</p> 
               <p>"Well, women are always in love with every baby they see, and always imagining something, and you are just like the rest of them; but I will tell you, great ladies don't travel in that way, they don't travel about in baskets and then left on strange door-steps; besides, without a cent of money to pay expenses into the bargain," said the old man, quite out of patience with his good wife's ardor.</p> 
               <p>"Well, James, my mind is to keep the child for the present at any rate. I know the Lord will provide for it in some way," she said, in a decided tone.</p> 
               <p>"Have your own way, then, have your own way, you always have had it, and, I suppose, always will; it's too late to change things now," he said, with a smile.</p> 
               <p>"Who would have the heart to leave such a pretty child as this for strangers to take care of; but there's strange people in this world; but the Lord has thrown the child in our way, and we, as good Christian people, must take the best care of it we can."</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER II.</head> 
               <head type="sub">JOSEPHINE FINDS A HOME AND FOSTER PARENTS.</head> 
               <p>IT had been two weeks since the old people had received the little stranger, and they had managed, though with great difficulty, to take care of the child, with the occasional assistance of some of their neighbors. As in all small villages and in the country, it was not long before every one knew that old Mr. and Mrs. Jackson had had a basket left on their door-step, which contained nothing less than a baby, and curiosity had led many of the country people to the cottage in the woods to see the little stranger, and to learn what the old couple intended to do with it.</p> 
               <p>It was about noonday, and Martha was seated on a low wooden chair, rocking the little Josephine to sleep? when a bright, robust village damsel entered the room, saying:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, Mrs. Jackson, 'it's an ill wind that blows nobody any good;' you are acquainted with Mrs. Templeton, well, her little baby, just three months old, died last week, and she is almost crazy about it; it was their only child: then they are so well to do in the world, and nobody to take care of but themselves. Now, I have thought of what I consider an excellent plan, and it is this: you give little Josephine to Mrs. Templeton, and let her bring her up as her own child; it's a pity such a pretty babe should grow up with the knowledge that she did not know who her real parents were; but, by adopting my plan, she need never know that Mr. and Mrs. Templeton are other than her own father and mother. Now, Mrs. Jackson, isn't that the best idea in the world, for you are unable to take the proper care of her, and she ought to be educated and brought up a lady." During this conversation, poor Martha had sat in a deep study, for she knew the truth of what Miss Hilton had said, and that they were not able to bring up the child; that, in all probability, they should not live a great many years longer, yet she had grown to love the child very dearly, so she answered in a rather sad tone:</p> 
               <p>"I know that all you say is very true; I love the child, and always have since I first saw her, for she reminds me of my little Isabel, who died about her age; but I know that what you say is for the child's good, and if Mrs. Templeton will take her as her daughter, and bring her up the same as she would her own child, I will give Josephine to her, although it breaks my heart to part with her, yet it is for her good."</p> 
               <p>"Now that is so good and sensible I of you. I will go immediately and see Mrs. Templeton about it; I am sure she will take the child, for it would, in a measure, fill the place of her lost one; she is very kind hearted, and when she sees Josephine, she cannot help loving her."</p> 
               <p>Then she left the house joyous that she had so far been successful.</p> 
               <p>In the evening Miss Hilton called at Mrs. Templeton's, whom she found in great grief at the loss of her child. She timidly broached the subject of the little Josephine, which was the object of her visit.</p> 
               <p>"If you should see her I am sure that you would love her, and I think she would, in some degree, fill the place of your dear lost one; those poor old people are not able to take care of the babe, and it would be such a Christian act for you to take her and bring her up as your own child; I cannot tell why I take so much interest in her but I have ever since I first saw her."</p> 
               <p>"I am glad you have told me about the child, and my husband and myself will go to-morrow to the cottage and see the old people and the child, then we will decide about it."</p> 
               <p>The next day found Martha and her husband called upon to part with their precious charge, and with many tears the old woman delivered the little Josephine to Mrs. Templeton to be brought up as her own daughter with the promise that she should never be told that she was other than their own child; and with the promise, that as long as they lived they should hear from and often see the little stray.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC6608-00000004"/> 
               <head>CHAPTER III.</head> 
               <head type="sub">MR. TEMPLETON A RUINED MAN.</head> 
               <p>SEVEN years had passed, and we find our little heroine grown to a lovely little girl, with curling golden hair and large blue eyes, a slight and graceful figure, with the sweetest of dispositions, the pet and pride of her foster father and mother, and they blessed the day that the darling child was so providentially given to them.</p> 
               <p>Josephine was universally loved by all who knew her. But at this time the dark clouds began to gather over that beautiful childish head, and may God strengthen her and angels watch over her for all she has to bear for years to come. Each succeeding year the clouds grow darker and darker, with only occasional glimpses of sunshine, until it seems as if the very abyss of the deepest sorrow is reached.</p> 
               <p>All had been happy and prosperous with the Templetons for many years; but in the seventh year of Josephine's life the storm clouds seemed to gather thick and fast. By one unsuccessful speculation after another, Mr. Templeton had lost nearly all the property he possessed; and Curtis Gary, a relative of his, was among the first to spread the report of his almost ruined state. One gloomy day in December the last stroke came, and Mr. Temple-ton was a ruined man. Gary then spread the report, which he knew to be false, that Mr. Templeton intended to abscond, hoping that it would lead to his arrest and imprisonment.</p> 
               <p>It was very late at night and Mr. Templeton had not returned home, and the anxious wife sat listening to every sound, not knowing but that her husband was in prison. Little Josephine knew, in her childish way, that all was not right; and coming close to her mother, she looked up and said:</p> 
               <p>"Mamma, where is papa? Mamma looks so sad; please tell me what it is so bad."</p> 
               <p>"My poor child, you cannot understand."</p> 
               <p>"Yes, mamma, I can; please tell me:" and the tears commenced falling down her cheeks.</p> 
               <p>Her mother kissed her, and, embracing her, told her that her dear father had lost all the property he had in the world, and that, perhaps even now, wicked men had put him in prison, she said, weeping with her child.</p> 
               <p>Josephine seemed to comprehend, as well as a child could, the misfortune that had befallen them. She knew that it was sorrow for a day, but little understood its depth and the privations it would subject them to. The Templetons had for years been the richest people in the village; and many thought Mrs. Templeton proud and aristocratic; her carriage arid horses were the best, and her apparel the finest that was seen there; therefore, her plainer neighbors envied her, and secretly rejoiced in the downfall of the family. But the most bitter and unnatural enmity of all, was that of Gary and his wife, and lie followed the almost ruined family for years with the most implacable hatred, and all this hidden under apparent great sympathy, when he was constantly working as a viper.</p> 
               <p>By the assistance of kind friends he was offered a good position in the city of B-- whence they were to go immediately. At least, thought Mrs. Templeton, there we shall have a good opportunity to educate our dear Josephine, and, even if we are poor, we can live happily and respectably.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER IV.</head> 
               <head type="sub">CARY'S PLOT DEVELOPING.</head> 
               <p>NINE years have passed since last we saw our heroine, and now she is grown to a beautiful young lady of sixteen, moving in the best society of the city of B--, sought after, praised, and loved by all. Mr. Templeton's business had prospered far beyond all expectation, and he was once more a wealthy man, besides being a man of influence in all the relations of life. Josephine's education had been conducted at one of the most fashionable as well as one of the best regulated schools of the city. She was a proficient in music, a graceful dancer, an agreeable conversationalist, and possessed every acquirement necessary for a young lady of high position, besides being an acknowledged beauty.</p> 
               <p>In the meantime the prosperity of the Templetons had excited the envy of the villainous Gary, who having, by dishonesty and neglect, lost his situation, which had formerly paid him a large salary, and being at his wit's end, and not knowing what to do, he bethought himself of going to B--, and try by his villainous arts to induce Mr. Templeton to help him in his extremity. He well knew Mr. Templeton was a good-natured, easy tempered man, and one who could be easily influenced, as he had often been induced to lay out large sums of money in perfectly worthless speculations, by the unfair representations of those he had supposed to be his friends.</p> 
               <p>"Ah! that's a lucky thought of mine. I've got it now. I will have all Templeton's worth in a year," chuckled Gary, rubbing his hands and walking up and down the room. "He is not averse to a class of wine; ha, ha! easy soul, I will fix his fortune for him, and will spoil, pretty thoroughly, the prospects of that fair daughter of his, for I must acknowledge she is pretty. I nearly ruined Templeton once, and I did'nt think he would ever get over it. Most men would have stayed just where I put him; but he, confound him, is so smart that he was rich again before I knew it. But I'll humble pretty thoroughly that proud wife of his before I get<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6608-00000005"/> through with them; and the aristocratic Mrs. Templeton will have to ask favors of me before many years are gone by. Then, my daughter Sarah is plain looking, and not very attractive, and she must have money to make her so. Now, that will do-that will do."</p> 
               <p>It was thus that the villain soliloquised the day previous to setting out on his journey of iniquity, not possessing brains enough to "be anything but a low, underhanded villain, whose whole thought was, how to accomplish the ruin of the now happy family, crush all their fair hopes, and have their hearts broken by overwhelming sorrow.</p> 
               <p>When they welcomed Mr. Gary to their house, little did they suspect that they were receiving one who would cause them years of untold suffering, and that he had already laid his plans for accomplishing their ruin. They had not forgotten the unnatural and wicked part that Gary had acted nine years before, when it seemed as if irreparable ruin was upon them; but they supposed that since that time, as they had seen little of him, and when they had seen him, he appeared to be very kind, they concluded that long ago he had repented of his wicked actions. But even now, Josephine could not but regard him with suspicion, and the terror of those wild December nights were so vividly impressed on her memory that they never could be forgotten during her life. The scene of her mother's tears and distress, and she a child clinging to her, waiting and watching to catch every sound, hoping that her dear father was coming soon, then disappointed, retiring to her bed in an agony of tears, not knowing but that her dear papa was in the cold dark prison. This terrible vision and the distress of those days she never could forget. On this evening, when she again saw Mr. Gary under her father's roof, she could not suppress a shudder of horror and fear passing over her as those memories rose vividly in her mind, and it seemed that the agony of those hours now returned upon her memory with double force. Before retiring for the night, she felt that she could not sleep until she had warned her father to beware of that bad man, especially as her parents had received him with great cordiality, and apparently without the slightest suspicion, for she had heard Mr. Gary propose that her father should lend him money sufficient to commence business, and that lie would soon be able to return it. Mr. Templeton had, in his usual easy good humored way, given his consent to the arrangement, which he pronounced was very satisfactory.</p> 
               <p>"But I feel that so wicked a man an he has been and one who has caused us so much trouble, must have a deceitful, cruel heart."</p> 
               <p>Thus reasoning, she went directly in search of her father:</p> 
               <p>"Dear father, I have felt so troubled since Mr. Gary came here, that I come to ask you not to have anything to do with that bad man, for he has made us so much trouble, and any one that would do as he has done must have a wicked heart. Now, please do not have anything to do with him, for if you should it would trouble me very much. Do not think me unreasonable, for I cannot help feeling as I do, when I think of what has passed."</p> 
               <p>"Why, my dear," replied her father, with a smile, "I am afraid that you are rather too suspicious of him. He is just now out of business, and has an expensive family to support. Some one must help him into business; it will not require a large amount of money to do that, which I can easily spare, and then he will be able to support himself and family. You are a good daughter, but I think that you are mistaken in regard to Mr. Gary. His intentions now? no doubt, are perfectly honorable, although he acted very wrongfully once."</p> 
               <p>"Now, my child, do not distress yourself any more on that subject, for your father will not consent to do any thing unreasonable for Mr. Gary. I do not think that he would wish to injure us, even if he could; besides, I do not see what he could say or do, if he wished to do so. Now, it is getting late; and yon had better retire, and not allow yourself to have such unhappy thoughts; so, good night, my dear," said Mrs. Templeton, kissing her daughter as she left the room.</p> 
               <p>Notwithstanding all these assurances, Josephine could not help feeling deeply troubled, and all her parents' kind words could not, in any manner, reassure her. As she slowly returned to her room she could not keep from thinking that "coming troubles cast their shadow before." "I most sincerely hope my dear parents are right in their opinions, yet I cannot remove this load of, as it seems, coming sorrow."</p> 
               <p>Gary had been in B-- one week, and during that time he had not ceased to follow Mr. Templeton everywhere he went, and induced him to stay out evenings far past his usual time for returning home; and Mr. Templeton had already lent him several thousand dollars for the proposed business, which, perfectly unsuspecting, he let him have; but this was only the first mesh in the net that the villain had laid for his victim to fall into.</p> 
               <p>Cary had now taken rooms at one of the fashionable hotels in the city, which always had the reputation of being extensively patronized by a class of men who are generally denominated as "fast." He had also called upon, to help him on with his scheme of iniquity, a man that had for years been his tool and dupe. This man, Elbert Vinton, was of a good family, who had supported him in idleness as long as they had means to do so. He was of a stubborn, indolent disposition; and there was hardly a low or mean action that he would not stoop to do for money. He was a distant relative of Mr. Templeton, and for several years he had given him his entire support. He I was constantly lounging about Mr. Templeton's office, and in that way I acquired a minute knowledge of his business. Although Mr. Templeton did not like the man, and knew that; he ought riot to support him in idleness, yet he was so easy, good natured, and afraid of offending any one, that he could not summon up courage enough to tell Elbert that he could no longer provide for him.</p> 
               <p>Now, Gary knew that Elbert Vinton was the very man he wanted, in order to successfully carry out his plans: so he offered him a large gum of money, and invited him to lodge with him at his hotel. With the basest ingratitude, he was only too happy to accept the offer, with the express understanding that he was to do all in his power to accomplish the ruin of his benefactor.</p> 
               <p>He was fully acquainted with the weak points in Mr. Templeton's character, and knew very well how easily he could be persuaded to do things which his better judgment told him lie should not. Thus, we find Gary and his boon companion in iniquity<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6608-00000006"/> closeted together in their handsome private parlor at their hotel.</p> 
               <p>"Ha, ha! Elbert, now I tell you we have a rich thing here; everything is working better than I could have expected. I induced him to take three glasses of wine with me to-day; then you came in and asked him to take a glass of brandy! Ha, ha, ha! he can't refuse any one; he'd be afraid that would hurt their feelings. Then we did'nt let him go home until nine o'clock in the evening, and by that time he was considerably under the influence of liquor. I will humble the pride of Mrs. Templeton considerably before I get through with her family, and that pretty daughter "in particular, as sure as my name is Curtis Cary."</p> 
               <p>"Ha, ha! You lay your plans well, and there is no doubt of their success. I will never have to trouble myself about money again, for Templeton has plenty of it, and when it changes from his hands into yours, my share of it will be enough to enable me to live at ease the rest of my life. I won't have to think where my next year's living is coming from. What a lucky dog I am! and you are the best fellow in the world, Cary. The share of the profits you promised me in this business, for a little help that I can give you, is very liberal. I always knew you were a good fellow;" saying this, he lay back in the luxurious easy chair, and commenced smoking a cigar, for it was too much exertion for him to talk any longer.</p> 
               <p>"Now, Vinton, if you will only exert yourself you shall have every dollar I promised you; but we hav'nt got much time to spend lounging round and doing nothing now. How is it about the report that a young nobleman has fallen in love with the pretty Josephine? Now you must find out how much truth there is in that report; and if it proves to be true, depend upon it, we have no time to lose. It would do very well to have it said that his Lordship married the pretty Miss Josephine, only child of the wealthy Mr. Templeton, of high social position, and she would have a dowry that some ladies of rank might envy. But 'Milord' will hesitate when it comes to this, that Miss Josephine is the daughter of a pauper and a drunkard! And it shall be so, too, before many months have passed," he said, with a fiendish laugh, and a twinkle in his snake-like eyes.</p> 
               <p>"W-e-ll," drawled out Vinton, "I think there is some truth in the story. I have seen him call there several times. She met him at the ball at Mrs. H--'s, and was introduced by Colonel James, who has been abroad for some time. It was love at first sight, I suppose, drawing my conclusions from what I have heard, and that is all I know about it. But you have put a stumbling block in the way, so there will be no danger of matrimony from that quarter-ha, ha!"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, yes I will take care of that," said Gary, getting up and walking back and forth across the room. "Yes, I'll have it so that the boys on the street will snap their fingers and laugh as old Templeton passes along-ha, ha! I think Milord's love would not be quite so great at the sight of such I a father-in-law as that."</p> 
               <p>"You are sharp, Gary. You know just how to manage these things," yawned out Vinton, by this time too sleepy to take much interest in what his companion was saying.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
                
               <head>CHAPTER V.</head> 
               <head type="sub">JOSEPHINE'S EXTREME DISTRESS-GARY'S VILLAINY RIPENING.</head> 
               <p>ONE month had passed since the arrival of the villain Gary into the happy home of the Templetons, and from the day he arrived, trouble had overshadowed that household. The first step he took was to induce Mr. Templeton, by all the powers of persuasion that he possessed, to drink freely and deeply of wine, to which he knew he was inclined; and often induced him in a friendly way to go to his hotel, where he would keep him drinking and talking until midnight. When in a state, by so freely indulging, he had almost lost his reason, and by threats he would induce him to sign checks for large Bums, and to sign away to him large amounts of property.</p> 
               <p>When Mr. Templeton would recover from this state, he then realized the dreadful injury he was doing his family, by neglecting his business, and that everything must go to ruin if be continued on such a course. Besides, the great grief he caused his dear wife and daughter; their remonstrances and pleadings with him not to do so again; how they reasoned with him to let what he had already lost by that wicked Gary go, and think no more of it; but never go with him, see him, or allow him to come to his house or office again. But all they could say was in vain; for a word, that Mr. Templeton could not say was <emph>no.</emph> He was so afraid of offending some one that he was his own worst enemy, and when he happened to fall into such villainous company, he was always an easy prey. If he could not be checked on the course he was now pursuing, utter ruin must inevitably follow.</p> 
               <p>Josephine had thrown herself upon the sofa, tired and full of grief. The large bronze clock on the mantel had just struck eleven. It was a dark, rainy night, and the wind whistled, through the streets in such a way as to make even those in the best of spirits feel a sense of loneliness. At last Josephine rose, and sobbing as if her heart would break, said:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, mother, why does not my dear father come home? How unhappy I have been ever since that wretched Cary has been here. It is he who keeps him away so late; and father has acted strangely when he comes home. What can be the cause of it? He says that he has lost large sums of money, and that wicked, wicked man is doing all this, I know, for lit; never acted so before he came."</p> 
               <p>"My dear child," said her mother, I trying to repress the grief and distress that she felt for the sake of her daughter, "do not feel so badly; things cannot continue in this way much longer. When your father sees how he is not only ruining himself but his family, I am sure he will have strength enough to forsake the downward course he is now pursuing. But you had better retire, and I will sit up until he comes, which must be very soon, for it is<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6608-00000007"/> nearly midnight. Now think no more of these sad things, my dear, for you certainly do not wish Lord Delmore to see you looking unhappy, and you surely will look so if you weep so much."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, mother, do not speak to me of Lord Delmore, for I know that I already care too much for him, I have often heard him express his abhorrence of drunkenness, and if he knew that my father was an inebriate, I am sure he would wish never to see me again, and that would break my heart. I should never care for anything in the world again; and even now I feel as if some terrible doom was hanging over us," she said; every feature of her beautiful face showing the great sorrow she felt.</p> 
               <p>"My dear daughter, you must compose yourself, and not make yourself so unhappy unnecessarily. Now, I will tell you what I did not intend to let you know for a few days, and should not now, if it were not that you judge Lord Delmore wrongfully, besides making yourself so very unhappy. It was only to-day that Lord Herbert Delmore asked me; and your father through me, for your hand in marriage."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, mother, is it really so? and what great joy it gives me to know that Herbert loves me;" her countenance suddenly changing from so much sorrow to joy, and forgetting all her troubles in the happiness of the moment.</p> 
               <p>"Now, my dear, you look much prettier than you did a few moments ago. We all have cause to feel both proud and happy that so noble a young man, not only in name but in character, has chosen our darling for his bride. And now it is time for you to retire."</p> 
               <p>"But I cannot go and leave you sitting up so late. Please let me stay until papa comes home," the shadow of the old sorrow returning.</p> 
               <p>"No, my child, I had rather be alone when he comes. So do not worry any more, for you can see how brilliant a prospect and how much happiness there is before yon," she said, in a cheerful tone.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, I hope so, and I cannot see why it should not be. Notwithstanding all my efforts there seems a dreadful cloud hanging over me, and oh, so dark and full of trouble." She burst into tears, then rose, kissed her mother and retired to her room.</p> 
               <p>"Poor child," mused Mrs. Templeton as her daughter left the room, "there has always been the air of mystery about you. One who is so singularly beautiful, so naturally refined, so delicate and lovely in appearance, must be the child of more than ordinary people. I am thankful that we have been able to give her so good an education, and that the mystery of her birth, has been so long kept from her. But when we give Lord Delmore our consent to her marriage, he must be told that she is only our adopted daughter. How often have I wished that she really was our own child."</p> 
               <p>At this moment Mrs. Templeton started quickly from, her seat, as she heard in the stillness of the night a carriage stop suddenly at the door, and a coarse voice, which she knew only too well, and as the following words reached her ears every vestige of color left her face, and she stood for a moment as if spell bound:</p> 
               <p>"Ha, ha, ha! this is the house. Ring the bell, driver. Here, help him I up the steps. Good night."</p> 
               <p>The speaker was no less than the villain Gary. The next instant the carriage rattled away at a tremendous pace, and in the darkness of the night was lost to sight before the servant had opened the door. In a moment Mrs. Templeton saw that her husband had drank more freely and was more overcome with liquor than at any time before. Almost overwhelmed with grief, she turned to the porter, and said:</p> 
               <p>"John, assist Mr. Templeton to his room. See everything is in order, and take every care for his comfort; he is not well."</p> 
               <p>"Yes, marm; I will, marm;" and the porter slowly conducted him up the broad stairway. When out of Mrs. Templeton's hearing, he mumbled, "I know he is sick, but I'm afraid that it's liquor that has made him so. I'm sorry for Missus and Miss Josephine; for no good ever comes of men acting like this."</p> 
               <p>Mrs. Templeton sat weeping, for sleep was impossible for her now, and her mind was filled with thoughts of the dreadful affliction that had fallen upon them, just at a time when all their prospects in life had seemed the brightest; but she thought more of the sorrow this caused her dear Josephine, and cared far more for her, than she did for herself.</p> 
               <p>Oh, that poor Josephine should suffer all this, and perhaps ruin her happiness for life; I almost wish that we had never taken the poor little stray as our daughter, then she would have been spared this affliction at least: may Heaven help us to bear our trouble with Christian fortitude; I know that my husband is every day becoming more and more involved in his business affairs, and I am sure that it is-that wicked Gary that is causing it, for even now did I not hear his voice, and laughing at our very door as if in mockery of our misery, as if it gave him pleasure to see the affliction he was causing us: well does Gary understand Mr. Templeton's weakness, and that it is only through the influence of wine, that he can manage to get his property away from him, when once under its power he will do anything that is asked of him. God alone can save us from the impending ruin.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER VI.</head> 
               <head type="sub">LORD DELMORE RECEIVES AN ANONYMOUS LETTER</head> 
               <p>IN a luxuriously furnished room, sitting before a table, on which there were writing materials, and also letters, sat a young man of about twenty-three years of age, his hair and moustache were of a dark brown color, his eyes hazel, and his features extremely handsome, and by his aristocratic bearing, any one would almost instinctively conclude that he was of high, and even noble birth; he was dressed in exquisite taste, yet without any thing that; indicated a fop: Such was the appearance of Lord Herbert Delmore, and it was not strange that he had already become the idol of Josephine's heart. He was intently reading a letter which he had just received from England, his home; he was an only son, his father had died when he was fifteen<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6608-00000008"/> years of age, and his widowed mother and her two beautiful daughters, lived at the splendid family residence, Delmore Hall. When he had finished reading the letter, which was from his mother, he took from the table an unopened one, of which he carelessly broke the seal, but as he read, an expression of anxiety came over his fine face: when he had finished reading it, he tore it in pieces and threw it on the table, and started up, hastily, exclaimed:</p> 
               <p>"No, my darling betrothed, Josephine, nothing shall separate me from you but death, or your own will; would I be base enough to desert you, because ruin and misfortune have overtaken your father? No, not if you were a beggar;" and he paced up and down the room, "but who had the insolence to write me this anonymous letter about the affairs of Josephine's father, doubtless some one who wishes to injure her family in my estimation: what if her father is a ruined man, I never wished or thought of money when I asked her hand in marriage, I only asked for her, and they gave her to me; Mrs. Templeton told me with many tears that their darling was a foundling, and their adopted daughter, but what care I for that, it would indeed be pleasant to know who her real parents were, but I feel sure that my dear Josephine is at least of a good family: that circumstance will be no hindrance to our marriage, and now comes this letter saying that Mr. Templeton is a bankrupt and a drunkard, which if I do not believe, by a little observation, my own eyes will show me, there is villainy in this, for no friend of Josephine's ever penned that letter: what if Mr. Templeton is poor, cannot I transfer a hundred thousand pounds to him from my own property, and hardly miss it; yes, and I will do it too, if his affairs are in the state this letter says they are. One thought gives me pain, and that is, that Mr. Templeton is an inebriate, I cannot believe it: however I will go immediately and see my dear Josephine, and' set all her fears at rest, for my darling I never loved until I saw you, and now nothing but death, or your own will, shall separate us," then he hurriedly left the room.</p> 
               <p>Soon the door of the apartment slowly opened and Lord Delmore's valet came yawning into the room, and drawled out:</p> 
               <p>"Well I do believe 'Milord' is about crazy, sure he never went on in this way before, but its either in love or crazy he is; oh, I wish I was back in Old England again, and I think we'll be going there soon so I'll take it easy while I'm here, and I'll get a little slape before 'Milord' gets back," then he laid down on one of the elegant couches for a doze.</p> 
               <p>Lord Delmore soon arrived at the handsome residence of the Templetons; he quickly mounted the broad stone steps, and was ushered into the elegant drawing-room, which was superbly frescoed, and the walls were set with elegant mirrors; there were superb cabinets, the rarest and finest bronzes, and a luxurious Turkey carpet, gave a charm and air of refinement to the place. Every portion of the large house was furnished with the most exquisite taste and beauty; and it was indeed a fitting home for the lovely Josephine. In a few moments she entered the room holding out her hand in token of welcome, saying:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, Herbert have you heard of our great trouble," and the tears commenced falling down her cheeks.</p> 
               <p>"Josephine, my darling, what is the cause of all these tears, all I know is, what I received in a letter this morning; I knew not whether it was true or not, and I came immediately here to see you, for I thought you must be in great trouble, if those reports were time, and by these tears I am sure that it is so; but you must not weep and distress yourself so much, for I can easily repair your father's ruined fortune."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, Herbert, you are too kind," and she tried to repress her tears, "and since these great misfortunes have overtaken us, I intended to offer to release you from your engagement to me, although it would break my heart to do so; yet I considered it my duty."</p> 
               <p>"My dearest, you must not speak so," he replied, kissing her affectionately, "for if you do, it will trouble me more than you can imagine, and to see you weep, and to know that you are so unhappy, gives me great pain; now, my darling Josephine, be assured that nothing that can happen to your family can in the least affect my love for you, and it gives me great unhappiness that you should have supposed for an instant that the worldly condition of your family could possibly make any difference with my love for you; no, dear Josephine, never shall I relinquish my claim to you, until you, of your own free will, take from your finger our bethrothal ring, and return it to me."</p> 
               <p>"Then, dear Herbert, that will never be," and her face plainly expressed the joy she felt, "but we shall soon have to leave this house, and live in a very humble way, for even now the officers with their attachments are in the house; and, dear Herbert, wherever I am you will come and see me often; for under the burden of all our afflictions, my heart would be utterly broken by sorrow, if it were not for that one bright hope, of your love for me, and with that hope to cheer me, it seems that I could be cheerful and endure any affliction that our Heavenly Father sees best to put upon me; for I know that He is merciful; and sometimes those things that we consider our greatest afflictions, at the time, ultimately turn out to be the greatest blessings."</p> 
               <p>"My dear, dear Josephine, your love and devotion to me makes me entirely happy, and your Christian fortitude, under afflictions, pleases me above all things, and proves your pure and noble character; our Heavenly Father is always kind and merciful to those that love him, and, obey His laws.</p> 
               <p>"Now, I will return to my hotel and make the necessary arrangements to settle on you for life the sum of one hundred thousand pounds, which will, in a measure, repay what your father has lost; and when you become my wife, you can then leave it all to your dear mother: do not distress yourself any more about having to leave your pleasant home, for you will not have to do so: you have my deepest sympathy in your affliction, and all will be far better than you think: when your father sees the trouble he has caused his dear family, I am sure that he will turn from all his evil ways."</p> 
               <p>Then he rose to take his departure, fondly stroking the golden hair of his beautiful betrothed.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, dear Herbert, how can I thank you for your great kindness, and I fear that it is asking far too much to accept such noble generosity, but you have the love and gratitude of my whole heart: and oh, my dear mother will be so grateful, for she is now almost heart broken; then when I tell her how good<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6608-00000009"/> and generous you have been, she will be so happy, and bless you too," she was quite overcome with the joy of the moment, for she had been so suddenly lifted from what she considered irreparable misfortune.</p> 
               <p>"Dearest, I do not deserve so much praise and so many thanks, for it gives me more pleasure to see you happy again, and to think that it is in my power to make you so, than it gives you to receive it. And now, my darling, there is no time to lose, for the officers of the law are like hungry wolves, and seem to delight in their wretched profession: and creditors seem to be driven by, and act more like, the arch fiend, than human beings, but thank God they will be baffled from breaking up a happy home, and sending innocent women out into the cold world this time," and his fine face showed as emphatically as his words expressed, the just indignation that he felt. It will not be long before I see you again, and until then, God bless and protect you, my dearest," he kissed her and hurriedly left the room.</p> 
               <p>When he had gone, Josephine wept for joy; fell on her knees and thanked God for his mercy: then rising, said:</p> 
               <p>"Was there ever woman so blest as I am, and was there ever woman delivered from the depth of woe, and restored, to so much happiness? I will go and impart this joyful news to my dear mother, and we will rejoice together.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER VII.</head> 
               <head type="sub">MORE PLOTTING.</head> 
               <p>WE will now return to the private parlor of the hotel which Gary and his companion occupied. Seated in a large easy chair, with his feet stretched across an elegant ottoman, and smoking a cigar as usual, sat Elbert Vinton the very impersonation of indolence; he was a man that above all things loved his ease, and his greatest abhorrence was of being disturbed: he would thus pass almost an entire day, alternately sleeping and smoking.</p> 
               <p>"Ah," at last he drawled out, "if I could only always live like this, I wish I could live a thousand years, nothing to do but smoke and sleep as much as I please, with this elegant suite of rooms; the best bill of fare in the city, and nothing to trouble my brain about, plenty of money and nothing to do; I'm one of the happiest men in the world."</p> 
               <p>Such was Elbert Vinton's idea of perfect happiness, and his appearance indicated, to an observing eye, that such grovelling ideas of happiness and ease, would be the highest aspirations that would ever fill his mind: he was of a large, coarse frame, inclined to be stout, with coarse straight black hair and dark eyes, a sallow complexion and full black beard; his features were regular and rather handsome, but the low narrow forehead plainly denoted an almost entire absence of intellect: he was of too indolent and sluggish a disposition to be naturally wicked, for that would require too much exertion, but was just lazy enough to be led by a villain anywhere he wished him to go, by the promise of money and the hope that he could then live at ease the rest of his life. Soon, however, his reveries were destined to be disturbed, for the door suddenly opened and Cary made his appearance, laughing and saying:</p> 
               <p>"Ha, ha, ha! Vinton, everything has worked to perfection, nothing ever went better in the world, just as I said it should be; old Templeton's notes came due to-day and lie could'nt pay them,-now that is rich; be don't know where his money has gone to; he probably has no very distinct recollection that he lost the five thousand that he had just drawn from the bank at the gambling saloon; he is not very lucky at cards, is he? and it was about the last cent of ready money that he had in the world. I suppose he thinks that he has been robbed, for he did'nt know what he was doing, or who took him home in the carriage the other night; as soon as I left him at the door, we drove away immediately, and did not give any one the opportunity of seeing me; I have been smart, too, for I have converted all those stocks he signed away to me, into cash, and have got it right here," he said, with a chuckle, slapping his pockets.</p> 
               <p>"Well, you are sharp, Gary, it takes you to do up things brown," drawled out Vinton in reply to his companion's harangue.</p> 
               <p>"They will have an attachment on that fine house and furniture, and the gallery of paintings into the bargain, then those fine horses and carriages will be gone, and they'll have no further use for those smart looking liveried servants; Oh no, haughty Mrs. Templeton and her pretty daughter will have to come down and live like common folks; ha, ha! and how does 'Milord' like this state of things; I guess about this time he is thinking of packing up and leaving the country, probably, he has suddenly received an urgent call home on business, which must be attended to; some one dreadfully sick or something of that sort; ha, ha! he'll say that so as to ease off Miss Josephine's feelings, so he can easily beat a hasty retreat for England, and when you see him again, pretty Miss Josephine, you'll know it; that is just what he'll do; everything is upset for those Templetons now, 'Milord' and all; ha, ha, ha! now that's pretty good; but we never could have done it if old Templeton had'nt have been so fond of liquor, and when he once begins to drink, there's no telling where he'll leave off," said Gary, with a laugh and sneer, his round shoulders and stooping figure, set off his wizen contracted visage to the greatest disadvantage, and with his snake-like eyes and coarse black hair, he looked every inch the villain he was.</p> 
               <p>"Now look here, Gary," said Vinton, at last a little aroused from his lethargy, "I know you will do what is fair, yes, I know! you will, but I hav'nt quite got my share of the profits yet, and I'm out of money just now, and as you have got so much, I,"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, I know what you mean, you would like some money, you're always short, but here take that, "and he threw down a hundred dollar bill, which Vinton eagerly took, complacently folded it and put it in his pocket.</p> 
               <p>"But I'll tell you," said Gary, angrily, for he hated to part with his ill gotten gains, as badly as a miser does his gold. "I don't know, but that there is more pork to be done yet; we have got all Templeton's money<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6608-00000010"/> and he is a ruined man; and before many days he will be sold out, house and home; so we are through with him, and have got every dollar he was worth, so we need never think of him again, but suppose that hair-brained young Lord should be so much in love with the pretty Miss Josephine, that he is determined to marry her at all events; what should we do then, we could not go to sleep over it after all we have done, and got as far as we have, why that would spoil half the game."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, pooh, you might as well say, suppose the sun should'nt rise to-morrow, and we should have to live by gas-light the rest of our lives; well, now, that is just as probable, as thinking that Lord Delmore will marry Miss Josephine now that she's a pauper; I have lived long enough in this world to know that this talk about love is all moonshine when the money is gone: don't trouble yourself about that, Gary, the next steamer will take 'Milord' to England, I'll risk my reputation on that."</p> 
               <p>"Your <emph>reputation,</emph> indeed, now that is good, ha, ha!" laughed Gary, feeling quite reassured by what Vinton had said, and being put in quite a good humor at the idea that Elbert Vinton thought he had a reputation. "No one can get ahead of me," continued Gary, "for I am sharp enough to look out for breakers, I don't suppose things to be just as I'd like to have them; no, indeed, I don't, I take into consideration almost impossibilities, so I have set a watch upon Miss Josephine."</p> 
               <p>"Well, now, I'll give up, I never should have thought of that, and how did you manage to do it," said Vinton, aroused to sitting up straight in his chair, and taking the cigar, he had just lighted, out of his mouth.</p> 
               <p>"Well, it was in this way: you know that Miss Josephine has a French maid that has waited on her for several years, and she trusts her with everything, and she has a way of listening and finding out all that is said inside that house; you know too that: it's perfectly natural for a French woman to like fine clothes, and I supposed that this one was no exception to the general rule. I knew very well when I first went to Templeton's house, that I might need the services of this woman, Camilla, before I got through; so I thought that the easiest way to make friends with her was to commence by making her presents, and in that "way I got her into my favor. I took times when I knew that none of the family would see me, and talked with her enough to satisfy myself that money and presents would hire her to do just what I wanted, and I can tell you she has helped me considerably in carrying out my plans, and keeping me posted, its a good deal to have a spy in the enemy's camp."</p> 
               <p>"Well, Cary, that is the best idea have had yet, but how in the world did you get her to do anything against Josephine, I thought she was all devotion to her."</p> 
               <p>"I am telling you as fast as I can, if you won't interrupt me," said Cary, angrily. "You see, she was greatly pleased with the presents and the money. It was very hard she said, to do anything against her dear little mistress, but the money and the visions of fine dresses was too great a temptation, so she consented to repeat to me everything that happened in the house, and particularly to be sure and place herself where she could overhear all the conversation that took place between Lord Delmore and Miss Josephine. So I am sure there will nothing be said there that I shall not hear of. She's worth the pay I give her, and if she's not a shrewd woman, I don't know who is. She was the one that gave me the description of Miss Josephine's magnificent solitaire diamond engagement ring. Ha, ha! she won't have much use for diamonds now; she'll want that same money for bread before many days, I'll assure you."</p> 
               <p>"I don't believe any one will ever get ahead of you, Cary." Then he continued, thinking: "Now, that is lucky for me, putting that girl on the watch. I thought that he let me have a wonderfully easy time. Why, if that woman was'nt watching them, I should have no peace of my life; he'd keep me continually running; but he's satisfied now, and so am I. He has'nt got the tenderest heart in the world for a fellow's feelings; but I'm lucky, he has got somebody else on the track; so I've nothing to do but sleep, and smoke, and live like a prince the rest of my life. All I've got to do is to let things work their own way, and when we come to settle, I know that he will be honest about the money, for he would be afraid to do any other way, for fear I'd expose him. How fortunate I am, I do declare; ha, ha, ha!" He was so absorbed in his reverie that at last forgetting himself, he laughed out aloud.</p> 
               <p>"Halloo there! what are you laughing at?" said Gary, for Vinton's loud laugh had interrupted the schemes of villainy he was planning in his own head, which was always fertile with all manner of wickedness.</p> 
               <p>"Ha, ha, laughed Vinton again, I was only thinking what a fine fix you had got those Templetons into, and the money we've made by the operation, that's all, and that's enough to make anybody laugh, is it not?" he replied, with his characteristic heartlessness, as an excuse for laughing.</p> 
               <p>"Well, well, that's so, but you disturbed me in what I was thinking about, that's all."</p> 
               <p>Everything was now perfectly quiet in the room; Cary went on with his villainous thoughts, and Vinton was thinking of composing himself to sleep, for he had already thought and talked about as much as it was possible for his at any one time. Suddenly there was a light knock on the door, and Cary started up as one aroused from a dream, he opened the door, and as he did so, exclaimed:</p> 
               <p>"What, Camilla, you here, and at this time of night, what does this mean?"</p> 
               <p>"Oh, wait, just a minute, sir, you see I am all out of breath; I have been in such a hurry to get here, I had to wait until after Miss Josephine had retired, before I could come away, without Mrs. Templeton, or Miss Josephine knowing it; then I stole out of the house, and came here as soon as I could."</p> 
               <p>"Here, take a seat," said Cary, "and now tell us what is the matter."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, enough is the matter; the young Lord called at the house this morning, and as soon as Miss Josephine had gone into the parlor, I hid myself behind the door, so I heard every word they said; well the young Lord said, that he was immediately going to settle on Miss Josephine, one hundred thousand pounds."</p> 
               <p>"What," said Cary, starting from his chair, "a hundred thousand pounds did you say?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, sir, that's just what I heard him say, and besides, he said that these family difficulties would not change any of his plans, that he should<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6608-00000011"/> marry her all the same as if nothing had happened, and that he should never relinquish his claim, except she wished it, and should return to him their betrothal ring, as a token that she wished the engagement to end: then he told her that the house would not have to be sold, and promising to see her very soon again, he went away: that is all he said, but I thought that you would like to know it right away."</p> 
               <p>"Why, woman, if I did'nt know this, everything would be spoiled. They already suspect me of leading Mr. Templeton to ruin, and if they were rich and had influential friends, nobody knows where I might end, for they'd never forgive me for the part I've played in this business; but if they are poor and Lord Delmore goes back to England, and the engagement is broken off, who then will listen to what they say, and what influence or how many friends will they have? But, now, what's to be done to break that engagement? There will some brain-work be required here; now that is just what I was afraid of, that perhaps he'd be so much in love with her that he'd marry her at all risks. I was afraid of that," said Gary, hurriedly pacing back and forth across the room.</p> 
               <p>Vinton by this time was thoroughly aroused. He looked anxious and frightened, for he was thinking what the consequences might be, both to himself and Gary, as matters stood now. Suddenly he looked up to his companion, saying, "Can't this woman manage to <emph>get that ring?</emph>"</p> 
               <p>"Ah! I have the idea now!" said Gary, his eyes fairly flashing with delight. "Camilla, can you manage to get that ring? If you can, I'll take care of the rest; besides, that will be the last service that I shall probably require of you; and you shall have five hundred dollars the minute you put the ring in my hand."</p> 
               <p>"Well, that's worth trying for, and I'll do my best to get it, but I can't promise you certain, for Miss Josephine never takes that engagement ring off her finger. Lord Delmore put it on, and she has never taken it off since. It will be the greatest undertaking of my life, but I'll try though."</p> 
               <p>"Can't you take it from her finger when she is asleep?" asked Gary, thoughtfully. "Now go back to Templeton's immediately, for there is no time to be lost. It will be easy enough to get the ring by a little management. By the time you return, she will be asleep, then you can easily slip the ring from her finger, and return here immediately with it, for there'll not be much sleep for any of us to-night. When she wakes up in the morning she will think that she has lost it somewhere, if she discovers so soon that it is gone. Now, my good woman, you had better go, and J shall expect you back before morning."</p> 
               <p>"Well, sir, I'll go and be back again as soon as possible; but you know it's a dangerous undertaking, for, suppose she should wake up when I was taking it, then I'd be ruined forever. But I'll do my best, for it's a large reward you've offered me. Good evening, sir." So saying the woman left the room.</p> 
               <p>"Now, Gary, you must give me the credit of that idea, for I don't believe you would have thought of it."</p> 
               <p>"Yes, I would have thought of it, too," replied Cary, snappishly, for he always wanted the credit of everything himself.</p> 
               <p>"Well, we'll let that go; we won't have any dispute about it. But after you have got the ring, what is the plan?" said Vinton, in a conciliating way, for he did not like to arouse his companion's anger.</p> 
               <p>"The plan is this, if you must know: Lord Delmore said that when she returned the ring, of course that would be the same as wishing their engagement broken. Now, you see, Camilla will bring me the ring; I will then have a forged letter written with Josephine's name signed, simply saying 'that for reasons which cannot now be explained, she wishes their engagement to end,' and this letter will be accompanied with the betrothal ring. Of course he will think that it is all ended, and it will not be agreeable for him to stay in this country any longer, so in all probability he will leave for England by the next steamer. And then, I say, who will give them a fortune and save their fine house for them? And, if Miss Josephine writes any notes to his Lordship, telling him that she has lost the ring, and complaining of his neglect, why, you know that it is Camilla who has the charge of posting all her letters, for Josephine never does as much as that herself, and the only post-man into whose hands they will fall will be mine. So I shall have the pleasure of reading all the pretty love letters she writes, instead of Lord Delmore."</p> 
               <p>"That is capital! and I don't think there will be any failure this time. You must have been born to be a general, for no sooner are your plans spoiled in one direction, before you have another better one," said Vinton, looking very grave, for at the prospect of their former plans failing, he had been thoroughly frightened.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head> 
               <head type="sub">STEALING OF THE BETROTHAL RING.</head> 
               <p>Camilla hurried along through the dark streets, which were now almost deserted. The darkness of the night, and the knowledge of the wicked part she had been acting, and also the wicked errand she was on, made her doubly fearful, As she passed the occasional street lamps, she started almost at her own shadow, which the lights cast. Occasionally she would turn and look round her in terror, for it seemed as if some invisible figure was following, her, or that perhaps some one knew of her wicked actions and was watching her. This was the first wrong action she had ever been engaged in; her heart misgave her, and she was filled with fear. At last she paused in her rapid walk before an apothecary store, stealthily looked round her, as if to assure herself that no one was watching, then hastily turned the knob of the door and entered. She purchased a small quantity of chloroform, and went out as quickly as she had entered. As soon as she had regained the street, she thought, at the same time hurrying on as fast as possible-</p> 
               <p>"Ah! I am so glad I have got this-this will insure safety; the poor young lady can't wake up after she<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6608-00000012"/> has breathed some of it. Then I'll take the ring, carry it to Mr. Gary, get the five hundred dollars, and be home again and in bed before it's time for the rest of the servants to get up. No one will ever suspect me. It's well for me that I'm the only servant that's allowed a night key; and if any one did see me come in, they'd only think I'd been out visiting some of my friends, for I've got plenty of them here. After I get my five hundred, it will not be long before I'll go back to France, although it's seventeen years I've been in this country."</p> 
               <p>A short walk farther and Camilla arrived at the basement door of the house, which she carefully and stealthily unlocked. When inside the door, she closed it, took a match from the small box which she carried in her pocket, lighted it, lit the gas just enough to cast a faint glimmer around the room, and then sat down and carefully took off her shoes; then with a handkerchief and the chloroform in one hand, she noiselessly ascended the stairs which brought her into the main hall, which was covered with a rich velvet carpet, as was also the stairs, which completely deadened every footstep.</p> 
               <p>"I bless my stars for the carpets," she thought, as she moved slowly along; then, up the broad staircase and through the second hall without a breath of noise, and she was at the door of her innocent victim's room. Here she paused for a moment, stooped down and put her ear close to the door so as to be sure that no one was stirring within. When she had convinced herself that everything was quiet, she slowly and cautiously turned the knob; the massive walnut door swung on its hinges without a sound, and she was inside the room. The gas was burning very dimly, just enough to make the different objects in the room visible.</p> 
               <p>Camilla's first action was to saturate the handkerchief she held in her hand with the chloroform, and cautiously approach the bed; then she looked eagerly at Josephine's beautiful face to be sure that she slept soundly; listened a moment to her gentle breathing, and carefully put the handkerchief close to her face. There she lay a vision of loveliness, one hand resting on the pure white counterpane, on which glistened the coveted diamond. No sooner did Camilla discover this than she could hardly repress a cry of delight:</p> 
               <p>"Ah, ah! the prize is mine now," she thought; "if I had arranged every thing myself, it could not have been better. But, poor child, it is a pity thus to ruin all your happiness; you are so sweet and pretty, and never did any one any harm; and you are so good to the poor-no one ever went from your door empty handed. Oh! I almost wish I had never undertaken to do this. All the days of my life nay conscience will never let me rest. I'm afraid I'll never be happy again, after doing this wicked, wicked action. But then the five hundred-time is flying. I must do it now or never. Then I'll return to France, and never see this country again, and I'll forget all about it."</p> 
               <p>She cautiously stooped down, with her hand directly over the coveted prize. Poor Josephine had by this time inhaled too much of the chloroform to be easily aroused, so Camilla had now an easy task. She slowly slipped the ring from her finger, put it on her own, so as to be sure of carrying it in safety to its destination, carefully removed the handkerchief, and as speedily as possible left the room, noiselessly closing the door after her. She did not stop to look round her until she had again reached the basement. She turned out the gas, passed out of the door, and into the street once more. When there she breathed freer, and muttered to herself:</p> 
               <p>"Thank goodness, that is over with! Oh! I feel as if I had done something dreadful, and I would'nt do such a thing again for a hundred times the money. I will never do such a thing again-no, never! How can I see Miss Josephine in the morning when she discovers her loss-she will feel so dreadfully. Oh! I pity the poor child. When she has so much affliction, to add this trouble also, seems too much. But it's too late now to repent, and I must go through with it if it kills me."</p> 
               <p>Thus reasoning she hurried on faster and faster through the dark streets, not pausing to look either to the right or left, for she now felt reckless, after the first fears had passed away. At last she arrived at the hotel nearly exhausted; the porter looked at her, suspiciously as she entered, wondering what could be her errand at that hour of the night and her great haste, yet he let her pass on without questioning her. She knocked quickly at the door of Gary's apartment, which was as quickly opened, for he was always on the watch when he had any scheme to carry out, especially so important a one as this.</p> 
               <p>"Have you got the ring?" was his eager inquiry.</p> 
               <p>"Yes; and here it is," she replied quickly, taking it from her finger; "and it feels as if it had burnt a circle there that never will come off," and she shuddered as she put it in his hand. "Oh! I shall never forget this night's work as long as I live;" fear and her better nature, for the time, quite overcoming her.</p> 
               <p>"None of that nonsense here, woman! I guess you won't have many scruples about taking this?" said Gary, holding out to her the five hundred dollars.</p> 
               <p>She eagerly seized it, and, without a word, darted out of the room, and out into the street again, when she went as if on the wings of the wind. She was soon again at the basement door, entered the same as before, slipped off her shoes, stole noiselessly up stairs to her room, and threw herself on the bed, utterly, exhausted with this night's work of iniquity.</p> 
               <p>It was now three o'clock, and in an hour longer all the servants in the house would be stirring.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6608-00000013"/> 
               <head>CHAPTER IX.</head> 
               <head type="sub">JOSEPHINE'S OVERWHELMING DISTRESS.</head> 
               <p>THE next morning Josephine awoke ranch later than her usual hour, feeling very languid and depressed in spirits.</p> 
               <p>"Why should I feel unhappy now," she thought. "Ought I not to he the happiest and most thankful of women? Are we not so providentially delivered from our misfortunes? and my dear father, when he saw the ruin he had brought on his family, has he not taken a solemn oath that liquor shall never again pass his lips? Am I not soon to be the happiest of wives? Then why will sad thoughts arise in my mind, and gloomy forebodings surround me? Cannot I feel reassured that all will be very bright and happy, when I look upon this-? Oh, mother! mother! my ring is gone-gone! Oh! Heaven help me!" cried Josephine, every lineament of her face expressing the wild grief and despair she felt; and she fell, half fainting, upon the bed, where she lay perfectly motionless.</p> 
               <p>Her mother heard her loud cries, and hastened to her room, exclaiming: "Oh, Josephine! my child t what is the matter! Oh, tell me, what is the matter!" She went quickly to the bed where Josephine was lying, and raised her in her arms:</p> 
               <p>"Now tell me, my dear child, what It was that made you cry out so? you frightened me dreadfully, my darling."</p> 
               <p>By this time Josephine had recovered from the first shock at her loss and began sobbing violently, for the trials and fears of the last few weeks had completely unstrung her nerves, and she now gave way to the feelings which at another time she would have borne more calmly.</p> 
               <p>"Try, my dear, and be more composed, for it is not right thus to make yourself so unhappy. Now tell me what it is all about," said her mother, soothingly.</p> 
               <p>"Oh! mother, mother, my betrothal ring is gone! Oh, could I have lost it, and if so, where could it have been? The first time I noticed that it was gone, was just now. It is some terrible omen to lose it, I know."</p> 
               <p>"My poor naughty child, to be so superstitious. Of course you are sorry to lose the ring, but do not imagine that losing it breaks your betrothal. Why Lord Del more will laugh when I tell him how my darling distressed herself because she had lost her ring. I Why that was no more valuable than any other of the same quality, excepting that it was given to you at your betrothal. Now, dry those tears, and let me see you look happy again, and we will search the room for it; for it might be that you lost it here, and we will also have the house searched. But I if it cannot be found, we can inform Lord Delmore of it, and no doubt he will replace it with one equally if not more valuable," said Mrs. Templeton, cheeringly.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, mother, you know that it is not the value of the ring I care for, but it is such a dreadful omen to lose it. When I woke up this morning, I felt so utterly unhappy and miserable, and why, I could not tell: while my mind was filled with these sad thoughts I was going to look at my ring for consolation, thinking of the bright hopes and promises it had sealed, and when I looked-oh, mother! it was gone;" and the tears fell fast on her lovely cheeks.</p> 
               <p>"Ah, my dear daughter, I do not wonder that it startled and frightened you at first, But now, my darling, cheer up, and all will be right yet. I will ring for Camilla, to aid us in the search. She will think it strange her little lady sleeps so late to-day," said Mrs. Templeton, ringing the bell, and commenced looking about the room, trying to discover the lost treasure. But it was impossible for Josephine to feel her mother's cheerfulness and courage.</p> 
               <p>Camilla had answered the summons and knocked lightly at the door. She could hardly keep from visibly trembling, for she knew very well that Josephine would soon discover her loss, and she well knew the consequences of that discovery. She had not long to wait, before she heard Mrs. Templeton's voice, telling her to come in. She entered the room, and as she did so the thought flashed through her mind-</p> 
               <p>"The last time I was in this room at the dead of night, adding the last drop of misery to her cup of sorrow. Oh, Heaven! keep that awful vision from my mind."</p> 
               <p>"I called you, Camilla, to have you assist us in trying to find Josephine's diamond betrothal ring. She has lost it somewhere, and did not discover her loss until this morning," said Mrs. Templeton, hurrying about the room and looking in every conceivable place. "Oh, I am so sorry, marm-indeed I'm so very sorry. I'll do nothing but search for it all day. Where could Miss Josephine have lost it? It was such a beautiful ring, too," she replied, pretending immediately to commence looking for it.</p> 
               <p>"Mother, I would, not look for it any more in this room, for I am sure I did not lose it here," said Josephine, utterly sick at heart.</p> 
               <p>As her words reached Camilla, she instinctively started and looked about her in a wild, frightened way, for feeling the dreadful guilt on her soul, she was every moment afraid of detection.</p> 
               <p>During the day every crevice in the large house was searched, but without success. Every servant in the house, with one exception, that of the wicked Camilla, seemed to feel almost as badly and search as diligently for the lost ring as Josephine herself, fur they all loved and reverenced their beautiful mistress. Not until nightfall was the search given up; when tired and heart-sick, Josephine and her mother retired to the library to write a note to Lord Del more acquainting him with her loss, their fruitless search, and blaming herself, "as she thought it might possibly have been through her carelessness that it had been lost and expressing her great sorrow that it had happened, and her earnest hope that she should soon see him again. Then she carefully sealed and directed the note, and rang the bell for her maid, who soon answered the summons. As she entered the room, Josephine said:</p> 
               <pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6608-00000014"/> 
               <p>"Camilla, I require a particular service of you this evening, and it is to deliver this note in person to Lord Delmore, for there is no one in the house that I would trust as I do you, for you have always been faithful, and I know always will be."</p> 
               <p>"Yes, marm, I always will be," she replied. But Josephine's kind words had stung her hard, avaricious heart deeply, and her hand trembled violently as she took the note; but this emotion Josephine only attributed to her natural sympathy. As Camilla closed the door, she remarked to her mother:</p> 
               <p>"Poor Camilla is so faithful, it would be very hard to part with her. May she find dear Herbert at home, then I shall soon have the pleasure of seeing him again. Oh, mother! was there ever man so good and kind as he is."</p> 
               <p>Camilla had hastily put on her hat and shawl. She was soon in the street walking rapidly along.</p> 
               <p>"In all my life I never suffered so much as I did last night and have today. It seemed sometimes as if my heart would break, and as if I must go and throw myself at her feet, confess all, and ask her forgiveness, when I saw the poor sweet child and her mother looking so earnestly all over the house, and sometimes the big tears gathering in her beautiful eyes. Oh, I've half a mind to carry this letter straight to the young Lord, and then all would be well Ah, but if I did, what would the consequences be to me? Did'nt Mr. Cary tell me though that if I ever exposed anything, and did not bring all her letters to him, that my life would be in danger. No; I can't go back now. I'll give him all the letters, and then I'll leave this country forever. But it would almost break a heart of steel to see all the misery I am causing; but now it's too late to repent."</p> 
               <p>A short walk farther brought her to Cary's hotel, where she delivered to <emph>him</emph> the letter.</p> 
               <p>It was towards the evening of the next day, and Josephine had neither seen or received any word from Lord Delmore. At last she remarked to her mother, who was always her confidant-</p> 
               <p>"Is it not very strange we have heard nothing from Herbert to-day? Camilla said she saw him, and delivered my note to him herself. Why does he thus neglect me, when he promised so soon to return? Oh, mother! if he treats me thus, I shall be utterly heart-broken. Oh, Herbert, Herbert! if I could only see your dear face again, if but for one moment, and have you speak a few kind words to cheer me, I could then take fresh courage; but when you are away, I feel as if all my strength had left me."</p> 
               <p>"My dear child, you must try and not worry so much, for no doubt you will soon hear from Lord Delmore. If you distress yourself so much, you will surely make yourself sick."</p> 
               <p>At this moment the conversation was interrupted by a loud knock at the door, which Josephine opened.</p> 
               <p>"A gentleman would like to see you, marm," said the porter; and near him was standing a man whom they had never seen before.</p> 
               <p>"Come in, sir," said Mrs. Templeton who had arisen from her seat and approached the door.</p> 
               <p>"Madam," Le began, "it is my gainful duty to inform you that next Tuesday is the day named for your house and furniture, also the horses, carriages, and everything pertaining to this establishment, to be sold. I inform, you of this, so you and your family will be prepared to vacate the premises on or before that day. Good evening, madam;" and with this information the officer, for such he was, withdrew from the room."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, my poor child!" cried Mrs. Templeton, sinking into a chair; "this is dreadful-it is too dreadful to believe. What will become of us, if we have to leave our dear home? Why, we have only one thousand dollars in the world, excepting our jewels. This news tells me, only too certainly, that your father has not been able to effect any compromise with his creditors. Oh, those wicked, wicked men! they have hearts of steel."</p> 
               <p>"It is now my turn to comfort you. Do you forget that Herbert promised us one hundred thousand pounds, and that he said our dear home would not have to be sold?" said Josephine, trying to hide her own fears, and to comfort her mother, for she loved her with the fondest devotion, and would rather suffer herself, than see her so distressed.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, I know that I do very wrong to give up to my feelings, and it is just what I was correcting you for a few moments ago. I have acted very foolishly, I acknowledge, but the words of that man struck to my heart in such a dreadful manner. We have no reason to doubt that Lord Delmore will do just as he has promised. Now, my child, it is getting late, and time, after all the excitement and fatigue of this day, for us both to retire. No doubt we shall see Lord Delmore to-morrow, and everything will be set right once more; so let us retire in peace, knowing that, under all circumstances, 'whatever is, is right,' and hoping for the best."</p> 
               <p>Thus cheerfully speaking, she kissed her daughter good-night, and each went to their respective rooms. But no words of comfort could dispel the gloom and sorrow which the unhappy mother and daughter felt, although they vainly tried to hide their sad feelings from each other.</p> 
               <p>As soon as Josephine reached her room, throwing herself on her couch, she sobbed out:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, my poor, dear mother!"</p> 
               <p>At the same time her mother was uttering the prayer: "May God have mercy on my poor Josephine."</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6608-00000015"/> 
               <head>CHAPTER X.</head> 
               <head type="sub">THE FORGED LETTER-LORD DELMORE SUDDENLY LEAVES FOR ENGLAND.</head> 
               <p>LORD Delmore was sitting in his apartment at his hotel. He was in deep thought, thinking of his beautiful betrothed, and completing his arrangements to transfer to her one hundred thousand pounds. He had already drawn drafts for a part of the amount on his banker, and in a few moments intended to order his carriage and go immediately to her house, for he was well aware that there was no time to lose now. In the midst of these kind thoughts he was interrupted, for just then his valet approached the door, holding in his hands a small silver salver, on which was a letter. The valet entered the room, and Lord Delmore carelessly took up the note, but looked with surprise when he saw that it was directed in a delicate lady's handwriting; he also noticed that the envelop contained something besides merely the note, and his curiosity was quite aroused. The valet had again retired from the room; Lord Delmore then hastily broke the seal, and as he did so his betrothal ring, for such it was, slipped from the envelop and fell to the floor. In an instant he recognized it; he gazed at the glistening bauble as if petrified; then, without moving to take it from the floor, he slowly opened the letter, as one in a dream, and, as he read the following lines, he turned as pale as death:</p> 
               <q>
                  <floatingText xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
                     <body > 
                        <div type="letter"> 
                           <opener>
                              <salute>"LORD DELMORE:</salute>
                           </opener> 
                           <p>"For reasons which cannot now be explained, I wish our engagement to end, and I return your betrothal ring in this note. It is far better that I never see you again; and, therefore, by the time you receive this, I shall have left the city forever. Farewell.</p> 
                           <closer>
                              <signed>"JOSEPHINE TEMPLETON."</signed>
                           </closer> 
                        </div> 
                     </body> 
                  </floatingText>
               </q> 
               <p>For a few minutes he sat as one stupefied with grief, then bowing his face in his hands, these words escaped him:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, Josephine, Josephine! my darling Josephine! oh, it cannot be true; this is only some terrible dream, some horrible imagination: dearest Josephine it cannot be true: oh, never could the arch fiend himself conceive of hiding so wicked and deceptive a heart, under so fair an exterior; must be a dream, or, Heaven help me, have I lost my reason?</p> 
               <p>He was so completely overcome by his feelings, and the great agony of the moment, that in spite of himself the tears gathered in his eyes; and for some time he remained motionless, without uttering a word; then he quickly started from his seat, and as if recovering from his emotion, hastily and impatiently brushed away the tears from his eyes as if ashamed of them, exclaiming:</p> 
                
               <p>"Away with these womanish tears; no, in this the greatest trial of my life, I will be a man; will I break my heart for that perfidious creature? She who always appeared so gentle, and so loving, the very impersonation of innocence and love, to have hidden beneath all that, a heart as black as Lucifer: to thus leave me with only these words, without allowing me even to see her again, and not giving me any opportunity to explain, or justify myself: arid to end that wretched letter by saying: she has left the city. Oh, was there ever such perfidy before."</p> 
               <p>He was pacing hurriedly back and forth across the room with his eyes cast upon the floor, and his hands tightly clasped, when almost beneath his feet, his eyes rested upon the glistening ring; as he perceived it, he uttered an exclamation of anger, and raised his foot as if to grind it in pieces beneath his feet. But his love for Josephine was far to deep for this anger to last long, and for him to indulge in such expressions, as had a few moments ago escaped him. Suddenly in the midst of all his anger, another, and entirely different train of thoughts, seemed to take possession of him; therefore instead of breaking the beautiful ring beneath his feet, he took it up, and pressed it to his lips, and with this great revulsion of feeling, he wept like a child:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, Josephine! poor darling Josephine! although you have thus cruelly and wickedly deceived me, yet I cannot but love you till the day of my death; you have broken my heart; still I love thee: oh, God forgive me for the wicked words I have spoken. Oh, darling, I will never curse your sweet name again, but pray God to bless and forgive you, as I also hope to be forgiven. Oh, Josephine! you are the only woman I ever loved; and I shall never love another: no doubt there are many women with hearts as true as steel, but yet, I shall never trust another: oh, Josephine! you have forever destroyed all my confidence in women. My poor darling, with your family in such ruined circumstance's, what will become of you? Oh, if I could only know where you are going, and if you would be comfortably situated in life, how much of the bitterness of this cup would be taken away, but even that poor consolation is denied me, and I am torn by these cruel words, forever from my idol, never to hear of her again. But it was her will that it should be so: why could she not have explained her reason for acting thus? However, may God give me strength to bear it and accept it, as it is."</p> 
               <p>"Now I shall immediately make arrangements to leave this country forever, and oh, would to Heaven that in leaving this place, I could forever blot from my memory, all that has transpired here: but that can never be, time may soften the sting of this blow, but the wound never can be healed. Worlds would not induce me to read that dreadful note again."</p> 
               <p>He took up the note, and together with the fatal ring, enclosed them both in the envelop, from which he had taken them.</p> 
               <p>"God and myself alone know the wound which it has inflicted on my heart; now, I will enclose these in a sealed packet, and keep them as long as I live, but my eyes shall never rest upon that cruel letter, or that fatal ring again:" he then folded them in a package of thick paper, and sealed it, with the family seal of the House of Delmore: as he did so, saying, his voice trembling with emotion:</p> 
               <pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6608-00000016"/> 
               <p>So sealed forever is my heart. I shall now soon be on my way to dear Old England again, where I return a broken hearted man."</p> 
               <p>He arose, and rang the bell for his servant, which was promptly answered.</p> 
               <p>"Thomas," said Lord Delmore, as he made his appearance "I wish to have everything in readiness, so that we can sail in to-morrow's steamer for England: you can commence immediately making The necessary preparations;" then he hastily left the room, for he felt that he could not much longer command his voice, to give directions: he was determined that no one should discover his grief, and that all his sufferings should be in secret.</p> 
               <p>"Ho, ho, ha, ha!" laughed the valet, fairly dancing around the room for joy, as soon as the door was closed:</p> 
               <p>"Then I'll see me dear Jennie again, and now I'm the happiest man in the universe, that I'm going back to Old England so soon, and it's the best country in the world too, for I've been all over the Continent and America with master, and I've never seen the country like it yet, and never shall." He paused suddenly, and looking very grave, said:</p> 
               <p>"Ah, but there is something wrong with master, that I know, for it's a very sudden thing his going home so soon; something remarkable must have happened to change his mind like this, and then when I come in he; looked so solemn and death-like, it scared me; I'm sorry, indeed, but perhaps it'll all go away after awhile: he can't help being happy when he gets back to Delmore Park again, and sees his mother and the handsome; young leddies, Miss Clara and Miss Helen, who are the best riders in the country, and take leaps at the chase that would scare many a fine young gentleman; ho, ho! but this'll never do, I was thinking so much about Old England, that I could almost see the young leddies going to the chase riding their fine horses, instead of packing his Lordship's wardrobe; and a pretty fix I'd be in if it's not done before this evening:" so saying, he hurried out of the room, and the rest of the day was wholly occupied, making preparations for their hasty departure.</p> 
               <p>The next day found Lord Delmore safely on board of the magnificent European steamer, which had been delayed a little past the usual time for starting to again cross the great deep. It had been a bright beautiful day, and it seemed as if the glorious and cheerful rays of the sun almost mocked his misery. Lord Delmore was on the deck walking slowly backwards and forwards, for the air of the saloon seemed to stifle him.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, how can everything look so bright and happy, when I am so miserable: Oh, Josephine, do you ever give one thought to me now; do you ever have for me one feeling of pity, knowing as you must, how much misery your cruel actions arid wicked deception has caused me: of all men in the world, I am now the most hopeless and wretched. Oh, would to God that when I leave these shores, I might forever forget that vision of loveliness and those brief days of happiness; but no, no, that cannot be, for so long as I live, that fair creature will forever haunt me."</p> 
               <p>Filled with such thoughts as these, he paid no attention to the busy scenes around. Dear friends and relatives; parting and wishing them "bon voyage." So occupied was Lord Delmore in his sad thoughts, that almost before he was aware of it, the great vessel was slowly moving out of the harbor, and the gay scene around only increased his sense of utter desolation and wretchedness, as he saw the waving of handkerchiefs and heard the cheers of the crowd:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, Josephine, my darling, my darling, fare thee well forever; I cannot but love thee still, although my body is borne away from thee forever, still my heart is ever with thee. Oh, America! would that I had never put my foot on your fatal shores: Oh, Josephine, Josephine! shall I now die, or must I live out this long life of agony? God alone knows, and may He support me now in this hour of trial, and in His mercy will he give the balm to sooth this aching heart."</p> 
               <p>His face was livid with the agony he suffered, and as he also realized that the noble ship was bearing him farther and farther from his loved one: added to his grief was the knowledge of the ruined state her family had been left in.</p> 
               <p>"May God protect and bless you my dear, sweet Josephine; and may your heart never be rent by such anguish as you have made me feel: Oh I darling Josephine, my dream of love is over, fare thee well, forever."</p> 
               <p>The great vessel was now far from land, and the darkness of night was fast approaching, and as the shadows of night covered the sea, so also were the shadows of sorrow closing darker and darker over his heart.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER XI.</head> 
               <head type="sub">THE CULMINATION OF JOSEPHINE'S WORST FEARS-THE TEMPLETONS LEAVE THEIR BEAUTIFUL HOME.</head> 
               <p>THE days had slowly dragged along, until it was the day before the time named for Mr. Templeton's whole household to be sold.</p> 
               <p>All these days had been filled with unutterable sorrow for poor Josephine, and each day had seemed an age, as she waited and watched for some word from Lord Delmore, but all in vain: she had written three pleading, loving notes to him, but all to no purpose; for the wicked Camilla gave them all immediately to Cary. Josephine would sit all day, almost like a statue, sick at heart, and too benumbed with sorrow to hardly speak or move, her whole thoughts fixed on the object of her love. Whenever she heard the porter answering the summons of the bell, she would start, trembling, from her seat, hoping that it might be, if only one word, from dear Herbert: but time after time she was destined to disappointment; then overcome with sorrow, she would sink back in her chair, crying:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, Herbert, Herbert! would you kill me with your cruel neglect, and at such a time as this: Oh, Herbert! I cannot believe that you have deserted me now: Oh, it cannot be, you are too noble and kind for that."</p> 
               <p>Yet, every night her sorrow was only increased, as another day had<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6608-00000017"/> closed and no word from Lord Delmore: so much had she suffered in the past few days, that on retiring for the night she almost dreaded the dawn of another day, they were so filled with sorrow and disappointment. So time had passed until it was the day before the sale was to take place, and the family would be obliged to leave their home forever. This last day, Josephine determined, as a last resort, to go to Lord Delmore's hotel and see him herself, then she should be satisfied when she had had one interview with him, then she would surely know the worst, for she could not believe that he had thus deceived her, until she heard it from his own lips."</p> 
               <p>"This dreadful suspense will kill me, I cannot endure it any longer, and although it may be considered as overstepping the bounds of a lady, yet in this case, I must go, even if I do have to endure a few of the world's sneers; it is far better to do that than suffer as I have for the last few days."</p> 
               <p>Josephine then went to acquaint her mother with the resolution she had taken, whom she found seated in the library, pale and anxious.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, dear mother," she exclaimed, as she entered the room, "it pains me above all things to see you looking so pale and careworn, I fear you will not be able to endure this great affliction: for my sake try to keep up your courage, for do I not have a double portion to bear; is not my heart breaking already; think for a moment the suffering Lord Delmore's conduct causes me; Oh, indeed, mother, the conduct of my father, then his failure and our ruin: the thought that to-day is the last one that we shall pass in our dear home, and that to-morrow we will have to leave forever everything that is near and dear to us from long association: that we go out into the world, now, to make our own livelihood: but in our Heavenly Father's protection, even in the midst of ruin, I trust, and if it were not for that hope, I should feel utterly lost, and die in the midst of all this Woe, but this trust in His mercy sustains me. Then, mother, in the midst of our afflictions, where are our host of friends? Is there one now to offer us a word of consolation or sympathy; of all those whom we have feasted and feted, and who in our days of prosperity crowded constantly about us, even to annoyance, where are they now; do they not constantly shun us since our misfortune has been made public? Oh, may I be forever delivered from such 'friends.' Ah, is it not enough to break one's heart to call to remembrance all these afflictions: then add to that the sorrow of having one whom you loved better than your life, and on whom every thought was centered, whom you thought the very soul of honor, and who had promised to stand by you, no matter what misfortune overtook you, and on whose love and faithfulness you relied: as a drowning man clings to the spar of the wrecked vessel, and knows that it is the only one within his reach, and that that is his only hope of life; then suddenly there comes an awful wave and wrenches it forever from his grasp, and he with a cry to God to have mercy on his soul, sinks to the bottomless abyss: Oh, mother, imagine that, and then you can form some idea of my sorrow now: my heart has forever sank to the darkest abyss of sorrow."</p> 
               <p>While she spake these words her face was as pale as death, and an expression of such anguish was written there, that one would doubt if such suffering could long continue, and have reason last: she shed no tears, her grief was far too deep for that: as she finished speaking, she threw herself on the sofa, her eyes fixed intently on the floor, as if forgetful of the presence of any one: her manner and the, expression of such deep grief, startled her mother, even to the forgetfulness of her own sorrow; she started quickly from her chair, and came and sat close by her daughter, taking her hand in hers and stroking, it gently, said:</p> 
               <p>"Dear Josephine, I well know what your feelings must be, and how great the sufferings are that you are called upon to bear, but you must not allow these feelings so to overcome you, for if you do, I fear you will lose your reason: seldom was a person called upon to bear so many sorrows as you are now surrounded with, but they cannot always last; some happiness dust surely be in store for us still, if we will only take our misfortunes with Christian fortitude."</p> 
               <p>"Do not speak of happiness for me, for that can never be again; this trial has been too great, it has broken my heart," she replied, raising her eyes, which were now filled with tears.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, my dear, dear daughter, I am glad to see those tears at last; for that cold terrible grief, was frightful to see; in such condition as that people lose their reason; it is too much for heart and brain to bear; take courage, and come with me to your boudoir, it is more cheerful there, than in this stately room," she said, rising, still holding Josephine's hand: "my dear child, if any man had ever so deserted me, no matter how much I loved him, I would never give him another thought, no, indeed, I would not; I would let no man think that he had succeeded in breaking my heart, and rendering the rest of my life unhappy; no, I would rob the wretch of that satisfaction at least."</p> 
               <p>"You surely do not even comprehend what you are saying; I, never think of Herbert again? Oh, mother, I would give worlds if I could not; but I could no more do that, than I could deny my God. Nothing but death can ever remove his image from my heart," saying this, she slowly rose, to accompany her mother to her boudoir: "to-day is the last that we shall have to see that dear room where we have spent so many happy days together: all these bright rooms and these beautiful things seem full of sympathy, they have been with us so long, and if they could only speak, it seems as if they would weep with us."</p> 
               <p>They had now reached this beautiful room, which was of rather small size, but its appointments were exquisite; the velvet carpet was of a pale blue ground, on which seemed scattered bouquets of the loveliest white rosebuds; rich lace and light blue damask curtains shaded the windows; the furniture was satin wood, with coverings of delicate blue satin; the ceiling was beautifully frescoed, representing birds and flowers; the wall frescoed in panels, in each of which was hung some glorious painting; there were elegant bronzes, marble statuettes, and rare vases placed in fine taste about the room, As Josephine entered the room, with which so many fond recollections were associated, she fell into a chair and began to weep afresh. Her mother took a seat near her, saying:</p> 
               <p>"My poor child, what can I say to comfort you? For my sake, if you love me, you will not weep so, and thus give up to your grief. I cannot endure to see you in so much sorrow."</p> 
               <p>"I will try to hide my sorrow for your dear sake. I know that I do very<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6608-00000018"/> wrong thus to give up to my grief, for I only add to your already overtaxed feelings. I will try not to do so any more. I will try; forgive me, but I could not help it, for I had almost rather see my dear, kind mother happy than to be happy myself," and she threw her arms around her mother's neck.</p> 
               <p>"Ah, my poor Josephine, you have the kindest heart in the world, and are always willing to sacrifice yourself for others' happiness. Surely no one ever had so good a daughter; and whatever afflictions assail us, when I look at you, so highly endowed by nature in every good gift, I always feel that at least I have <emph>you</emph> to be thankful for, for you are the greatest blessing ever given to any mother."</p> 
               <p>"I do not deserve so much praise, for have I not the best mother in the world, too," she said, for a moment forgetting her trouble. For a short time both were silent, then the old look of sorrow returning to her face, she continued:</p> 
               <p>"I came to the library to ask yon if there would be any great impropriety for me to go to Herbert's hotel, and see him myself; then I should have the satisfaction of hearing from his own lips the cause of his neglect."</p> 
               <p>"My dear child, I cannot listen to such a proposition; for, in the first place, it would be highly improper, and more than that, it would only add to your now already over-wrought feelings. But in order that you may be fully satisfied, I will take the carriage and go myself to his hotel and see him."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, you are so kind. That will be best, I know; how much I thank you. That will in a measure put an end to this dreadful suspense. Now, perhaps, there may possibly be some mistake, some misunderstanding that can easily be explained:" and for a moment she looked quite cheerful, as this faint ray of hope dawned upon her.</p> 
               <p>"My dear, I would not cause you any unhappiness; but do not be too sanguine concerning this visit, for if you are disappointed, it will throw you into another such a paroxysm of grief. My poor darling, my opinion is that my visit may only confirm your worst fears. Yet it is your wish that I should go, that you may then be assured of everything concerning Lord Delmore; but promise me that, whatever word I bring back, you will at least try to be calm, and to bear all things as a Christian should." She rose and rang the bell to order her carriage.</p> 
               <p>"I know what you say may prove only too true, and to please me you comply with my request. Dear mother, it is so kind of you, and I will promise that whatever word you bring me, I will be as calm as I can be," said Josephine, bursting into tears.</p> 
               <p>"Ah, my child, that is a very bad beginning, but I cannot blame you, your sorrows seem almost too much for any one to bear;" and Mrs. Templeton looked very anxious, for she really began to feel alarmed when she saw how great and how deep-seated Josephine's grief was. She slowly went to the door in answer to the light knock. It was Camilla who stood there, with her eyes cast down, for she felt that if she looked up, Mrs. Templeton could not help reading her guilt in her face. This downcast look Mrs. Templeton took to be one of sympathy for her afflicted family, and in a kind voice, said:</p> 
               <p>"Camilla, please order my carriage, immediately."</p> 
               <p>"Yes, ma'am," answered Camilla, and as she slowly walked away, muttered:</p> 
               <p>"It's the last time the poor lady will ever ride in her fine carriage."</p> 
               <p>"Now," said Mrs. Templeton, as soon as the door was closed, "I will go and prepare for my call; by that time the carriage will be waiting."</p> 
               <p>"Let me go and assist you, mamma." Then they both left the room.</p> 
               <p>In a short time they returned; the carriage was announced, and Mrs. Templeton set out on her unhappy errand.</p> 
               <p>As, soon as her mother had gone, Josephine sat down and fell into a deep reverie, murmuring:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, it cannot be that Herbert has deceived me. I cannot believe that he is faithless."</p> 
               <p>"My poor dear child," thought Mrs. Templeton, as she stepped into the elegant carriage. "I feel already that this visit of mine will only be attended with disappointment. If Lord Delmore wished to see you again, he would have done so before this, knowing as he did, our unhappy situation; and if he had wished to save our home, he would have done so, for it is now too late. Oh, dear Josephine, I could summon up courage enough to go through the affliction of parting with our house, and part with all the luxuries and comforts we have; but the knowledge that you are so brokenhearted, and your fair young life so soon blighted, quite overcomes me. Oh, cruel wretch that you are! to cause our darling all this grief." Such were her feelings of alternate sorrow and anger, until the carriage rolled slowly up to the grand entrance of the hotel.</p> 
               <p>The footman sprang from the box and opened the door. She then alighted, and was shown to the drawing-room of the splendid hotel by the obsequious porter, to whom she gave her card and requested him to inquire if Lord Delmore was in.</p> 
               <p>"Yes, ma'am; I will see immediately, ma'am," replied the man, making several bows.</p> 
               <p>Mrs. Templeton had not waited many minutes before he returned, and she perceived he still held her card in his hand; bowing as before, he said:</p> 
               <p>"I inquired at the office, ma'am; Lord Delmore sailed several days ago for Europe, ma'am." As she heard these words it seemed as if she should faint and as if the air was stifling her. She rose, commanded her voice sufficiently to say:</p> 
               <p>"Very well; thank you;" and hurriedly left the hotel and entered her carriage, which when she had reached, she fell back half fainting, saying:</p> 
               <p>"Drive home again. Oh, my poor, poor Josephine! I fear this shock will kill you. How will you be able to bear it? How can I tell her? I felt that this would be the result of my visit."</p> 
               <p>Thus she sat with such bitter thoughts coursing through her mind, until they had reached her own door again. She quickly alighted, hurried up the steps and through the hall; at the stairway she met Josephine, eager with expectation, explaining:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, mother, did you see Herbert? and if so, what was the cause of his neglect?" and she felt almost afraid to hear her mother's voice. "Then you have been gone so short a time; surely all must have been well."</p> 
               <p>"My dear, let us go to your room, and I will tell you all," replied her mother, taking Josephine's hand in her's; they entered the boudoir and closed the door. She drew her to a seat and said:</p> 
               <p>"Josephine, remember your promise.<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6608-00000019"/> Try and prepare your mind for disappointment."</p> 
               <p>"Yes, I will try; yet I already know, by your manner and your anxious look, that there is no more hope. Please tell me quickly."</p> 
               <p>"My dear child, Lord Delmore sailed for Europe several days ago." As she uttered these words not a sound escaped her daughter's lips. Her fair head fell on her mother's shoulder, and she was in a death-like swoon.</p> 
               <p>When Mrs. Templeton perceived this, she was overcome with fright and knew hardly what to do. She rang the bell violently, which brought the servants immediately to her assistance, among whom was Camilla.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, I fear she will never recover from this terrible swoon! Camilla, get some water immediately. Oh, my poor darling, it will kill me to see you in this dreadful state."</p> 
               <p>The servants had carefully borne Josephine to her room and laid her on the bed, while they hastily bathed her head and applied restoratives; her mother being so frightened as to be perfectly unable to render any assistance, occasionally murmuring:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, why did I tell her? The shock was too great."</p> 
               <p>In a short time she began to recover from her swoon; slowly opened her eyes, and a low moan escaped her.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, my darling, speak to me."</p> 
               <p>"What is it? What has happened?" then covering her face with her hands, she cried: "Oh, mother, mother! that dreadful truth. Oh, can it be true? Yes, it is-it is. I know all now."</p> 
               <p>Mrs. Templeton then motioned the servants from the room, thanking them. She came and sat down by her daughter's bedside, saying:</p> 
               <p>"My dear, this is the greatest trial of your life, and if you should sink under it, I should have nothing to live for-I should wish to die too. Try, my poor darling, for my sake and for your own good, to be brave under this, and you surely will be rewarded for it."</p> 
               <p>"Yes, dearest mother, I know that I <emph>must,</emph> and <emph>I will try</emph> to do <emph>my duty.</emph> I shall never give up to such wild grief again. All those feelings have passed forever, and now I feel and know that <emph>my heart is dead.</emph> Yes, dead forever; my body lives, but my heart is dead, and the sepulchral stone that seals its tomb, is the image of Herbert Delmore."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, my darling, it pains me greatly to hear you speak so; do not give way to such feelings. Oh, what can I do for you. This will never do;" and the tears began to fall down her cheeks.</p> 
               <p>"That grieves me above all things-to see you weep, and to think that I am the cause of it. Henceforth I shall contribute all in my power to your happiness, although joy or love will never be known to me again. I am willing to live out this bodily life as long as the Lord sees fit; but my heart will never rise from its tomb until that 'last great day' when body and soul rise together. I will never more make you unhappy by my grief and vain repinings."</p> 
               <p>"I trust that you may soon find some consolation that, in some degree, will compensate you for your great afflictions;" and with a sigh she rose to leave the room. "Now, I will leave you to take a little rest, while I go and direct the arrangements for our departure. Rest, my darling, is what you most need. I will soon return. In the meantime try to compose yourself to sleep;" and Mrs. Templeton left the room.</p> 
               <p>"I sleep now? Oh, mother, mother, how little you comprehend my feelings. I cannot sleep, I cannot rest, and I must not allow myself to <emph>think.</emph> I will now go and assist in the arrangements for our departure. Oh, how mechanically I can do that now, which a few short hours ago would have given me the greatest pain."</p> 
               <p>With these thoughts she arose and prepared to put together all her wardrobe. She ordered her trunks to be brought to her room, which was immediately done. At this moment her mother again entered, exclaiming:</p> 
               <p>"Why, Josephine, what are you doing? You are not strong enough to do this; you must have Camilla assist you."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, no. Please let me arrange these things myself. I feel quite strong now, and had much rather do it myself."</p> 
               <p>"Well, my child, you shall do as you wish; but I will remain here and try and assist you all I can."</p> 
               <p>Thus every one in the house was busily engaged until late that night; when, at last, everything was in order for their departure early the next morning.</p> 
               <p>Just before the family were to retire for the night, there came a loud ring at the door; and it proved to be no other than the officer whom we have seen here before. He wished to see Mr. Templeton, and was shown to the library, where he was then sitting. He made a low bow as he entered, saying:</p> 
               <p>"Mr. Templeton, I am ordered to remain in your house until after the sale to-morrow, to see that nothing is removed but the wearing apparel of the family."</p> 
               <p>Mr. Templeton sprang from his seat, livid with rage, exclaiming: "Would you add another insult to my already afflicted family, by thus insulting them at the last hour? Would you now accuse us of dishonesty?"</p> 
               <p>"It is not I who do this, sir, of my own will. I am only acting under orders which I cannot disobey," replied the officer, bowing politely.</p> 
               <p>"Well, I suppose so; but this insult is almost too much to bear. But this teaches me a lesson that I shall never forget, and that is never to owe another man a dollar; no, not if I starve or have to beg, for a beggar is treated with far more respect than a gentleman who is a debtor; and creditors are like very fiends. You will stay here then, on guard, I suppose," said Mr. Templeton, leaving the room acid closing the door violently after him.</p> 
               <p>He was a man of spare light frame, a little over the medium height, with black hair and eyes, and wore no beard; his face had a haggard, careworn appearance, which was partly caused by his late dissipation, and partly by the difficulties with which he was surrounded. He knew that liquor had this time caused his ruin, and that Gary was instrumental in bringing it about; yet to others he was ashamed to acknowledge it. He loved and pitied his family, and was heartily sorry for what he had done; but the poor man was of too weak a character to resist temptation when in its way. But now he had been taught a lifetime lesson, and had determined to overcome his fatal weakness, or die in the attempt; and this resolution held good for the rest of his life, to I the great comfort and joy of his family.</p> 
               <p>Early the next morning everything was ready for departure; and with many tears, the last farewell looks were taken of all the beloved objects, As Josephine descended the stairs, she said:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, mother, I must go and bid<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC6608-00000020"/> dear Sappho good bye, who has so faithfully carried me so many miles on her back. I cannot go without seeing the dear creature again. Thomas, bring her to the stable door, and I will go out to see her once more."</p> 
               <p>Sappho was a jet black saddle horse, of rare beauty, of fine light symmetrical form, and had been Josephine's pet for years. She had become as attached to her as one could be to a dumb animal. As Sappho was brought to the stable door, when she saw Josephine approaching, she "began to whinney, as if in recognition. Josephine came close to her, and put her arms about her neck, saying:</p> 
               <p>"You do not know that this is the last time I shall ever see you," and she began to stroke her glossy black mane; "but I cannot stay any longer now, dear faithful creature, and I only hope you may fall into kind hands;" in saying this, tears filled her eyes. "Now, good bye, dear Sappho," and in her warmth of feeling, she kissed the poor creature's face, and hurried away. As she turned to go, the noble animal began to whinney loudly. Josephine heard her, but did not stop to look back. She hurriedly entered the house and closed the door.</p> 
               <p>The hired carriage was waiting to convey them away to the railway station. The servants stood on each side of the hall, with tears in their eyes, for they fully sympathized with the afflicted family, who had always been so kind to them. At last the time had arrived for their departure, and Mr. Templeton, his wife, and daughter stepped into the carriage, and were driven rapidly away, having bidden farewell forever to their beautiful and once happy home.</p> 
               <p>Josephine was almost of a deathlike calmness; but Mr. and Mrs. Templeton showed more emotion. A rapid drive of half an hour brought them to the depot, where they entered the railway cars, and were soon borne rapidly away to their new but humble home.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER XII.</head> 
               <head type="sub">CARY AND VINTON EXULT OVER, THE SUCCESS OF THEIR VILLAINY.</head> 
               <p>WE now return to Cary's apartments at his hotel, and find Elbert Vinton sitting in his favorite chair, smoking a cigar, thinking what a fortunate man he was, to have so much money and the promise of a great deal more, without having to exert himself to obtain it. His conscience never troubled him concerning the wickedness of his actions. At this moment Gary entered the room.</p> 
               <p>"Ha. ha, Vinton!" he exclaimed, "there never were plans that worked I as well as ours have before. Everything has gone just as I wished it. 'Milord' sailed for England three or four days ago. Old Templeton and his family left the city this morning, and their whole household was sold out to-day. I was at the sale, and bought some of the best furniture, besides sides the finest pair of horses arid a coupe, with his own money-ha, ha, ha!"</p> 
               <p>"Well, that is smart in you. The old saying is, that 'it's as well to be born lucky as rich,' and I believe it. I suppose you will take a house in town, and you'll make a great swell. Now, that's the easiest way of getting a fortune I ever heard of. I would like about a thousand dollars, to pay up some old bills, if it's convenient. You know you promised me half the profits for my share in the business," said Vinton, for he had already began to suspect that Cary might not pay him as promptly as he wished.</p> 
               <p>"I've just paid out nearly all the funds I had about me; for I don't carry my fortune in my pocket, I would have you understand. I'm not in the house five minutes before you ask me for money. But here is three hundred dollars; now I hope that will satisfy you for a week at least. I've already paid you a large amount; but we'll settle our accounts when I get time," replied Cary; and then continued thinking:</p> 
               <p>"It will never do to get him angry, for he might injure me considerably; so I'll give him a hundred or two now and then. But if he thinks that he is going to share with me in the profits, why then he is mistaken, that's all."</p> 
               <p>Vinton took the three hundred dollars, with a sullen expression coming over his face, but he did not dare remonstrate with his companion.</p> 
               <p>"Well, I suppose it will do for a few days, but I'd like to settle."</p> 
               <p>Just then the conversation was interrupted by a loud knock. Cary started suddenly, for every noise frightened him, his guilty conscience allowing him to have no rest. He went to the door, and, on opening it, exclaimed:</p> 
               <p>"What! you here again? What do you want now? I thought our business was finished long ago."</p> 
               <p>"Well, it is, sir," replied Camilla, entering the room, "and I'm glad it is, for I could riot have stayed there and seen my poor little mistress suffer so much longer. Why she looked like a ghost when she went away this morning; and after all I've done, I could not keep from crying when I saw them leave the house. I could'nt do what I have done again for all the money in the world. I know I'll never have another minute's peace in my life. I came to tell you to destroy the three notes that Miss Josephine wrote to the young Lord, for if they should fall into any body's hands, then I'd be undone."</p> 
               <p>"You need not have told me that, for the minute I read them, I burnt them, so there would not be a scrap left."</p> 
               <p>"Well, then, that is all I've got to say. I am going to sail in a French vessel to-morrow, for France; and it would be strange if I am ever allowed to cross the ocean in safety, after all the wickedness I've done. You've ruined my peace of mind for life. I left France an innocent little girl; now I return a woman, but the wickedest of my kind. Oh, I wish I'd never seen this country. Good-bye, sir; I shall never see you again." She then hastily left the room, and hurried down stairs into the street.</p> 
               <p>"There," said Gary, throwing himself into a chair, "I'm glad she's out of the way, for she might have made us trouble. Now the coast is clear, and there is no one in the secret but you and I. That French woman was so tender-hearted and had so much<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC6608-00000021"/> conscience about this affair, that I constantly trembled in my shoes for fear she would expose something."</p> 
               <p>"Yes, that was what I was afraid of, too," replied Vinton; "but now all our troubles are out of the way, and all we have to do is to live in ease and luxury the rest of our lives. Things have worked well, I declare. Ha, ha, ha! I'm a happy man now."</p> 
               <p>"And so am I! Ha, ha! Well, I guess we are about the jolliest fellows going just now," said Cary, with an air of satisfaction, settling himself comfortably in his chair, and continued:</p> 
               <p>"Now I shall bring my family to the city, and, by the style I'll live in, people will think that I am a millionaire. I shall tell every one that I am a retired gentleman, living on the interest of my money, and so are you, too, Vinton. Ha, ha! of course we are, and nobody will ever be the wiser. When I find out where old Templeton and his family have gone to, Mrs. Cary and I will go and visit them. Then see if the haughty Mrs. Templeton and her pretty doll-faced daughter are quite so proud as they were a short time ago. Ah! I guess they'll consider our call quite a compliment under the circumstances. I always said the day would come when she should ask favors of me, and it's pretty nearly here now." His small snake-like eyes twinkled, and a smile that fairly made his face hideous, played about his mouth, in anticipation of this last expected triumph, for he never was happy unless he was tormenting or ruining some one.</p> 
               <p>Three weeks had now elapsed, and we will follow Cary to the large elegant house which he had purchased. It was situated on one of the most fashionable squares in the city. He had selected the furniture with the one pre-eminent idea of what would make the greatest display; therefore, everything was purchased of the most glaring and striking patterns, without the least regard to taste. The velvet carpets were those which had enormous bouquets of the brightest possible colors scattered over them. The silk damask drapery was of one color, and the rich upholstery of the rosewood furniture of another. Paintings he considered a necessary adjunct, for he saw everybody else have them, so, of course, he must not be outdone by any one. Of paintings he was no judge, and never had had any experience in purchasing them before; as his taste was regulated on other subjects, so it-was in this: he selected those of the most glaring colors; and mere daubs were sold to him at extravagant prices.</p> 
               <p>In this way he at last completed the furnishing of his house, as he thought, elegantly. With two fine carriages and splendid horses, he was now prepared to bring his family to the city and have his wife and daughter make their debut in society. All these things were purchased with the money that he had robbed Mr. Templeton of, yet that had no effect on his callous heart, and he surveyed his stolen possessions with as much satisfaction as if he had honestly earned every dollar himself.</p> 
               <p>In the meantime his family had arrived, and they pompously entered their new home. They knew that in some way their father had managed to cheat Mr. Templeton out of all his money; but how it was done they did not know, but were as happy as he was to take the fruits of his dishonesty; and Mrs. Cary rather gloried in it, rejoicing that her rivals were now poor and barely had the commonest necessities of life. This seemed to give her the most intense satisfaction. All her hatred of the Templetons was prompted by the one feeling of envy.</p> 
               <p>"Ah, Miss Josephine," she thought, "you have enjoyed all these luxuries long enough. Now we will have them for awhile; and Sarah shall be as much sought after and flattered as you have been. No one shall exceed her in fine dresses and jewels; then, although perhaps her face is not quite as doll-like as yours, yet when dressed as fine as I intend she shall be, her rather plain features will not be so much noticed. No doubt that she will make a brilliant match; her affianced husband will not be liable to run away to England as yours has done." Such was the tenor of her thoughts, as she surveyed with pride the luxurious appointments of the different apartments. They employed a large number of servants, and everything was conducted in the most extravagant manner.</p> 
               <p>The next morning Cary hurriedly entered the room where his wife arid daughter were sitting, exclaiming:</p> 
               <p>"I have just found out where the Templetons are living."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, do tell us, quickly, papa, for I am very anxious to know how they will act in their present circumstances," said Sarah, looking up with a slight expression of animation on her dull, heavy features.</p> 
               <p>"Well, they have gone to the village of S--, about twenty miles from here, where Mr. Templeton was offered the salary of one thousand dollars a year for his services. Now, if that does'nt humble those fine ladies some, then I'm mistaken. Besides, I heard that they have taken a little old brown cottage there, which looks more like a dilapidated porter's lodge than any thing else;" and he began walking up and down the room, rubbing his hands in high glee, as he contemplated the success with which his nefarious operations had been attended.</p> 
               <p>"Nothing ever gave me so much pleasure as to see those Templetons poor, when we are rich; they always seemed to feel so much above us-now we are far above them. How I should like to go and see them now, living as they are, just to mortify them, and I believe that Sarah and I will go; we will dress in the finest we have, so as to annoy them. It is so pleasant to think that we are living in such elegance, with servants, horses, and carriages at our command, and the Templetons living in a miserable house, with hardly the comforts of life, with no other prospect before them than that of having to support themselves, with all their fine ideas into the bargain, on a thousand a year. Well, I really feel quite happy now," said Mrs. Cary, with an expression on her coarse face which was something between a sneer and a smile.</p> 
               <p>"Yes," replied her husband, "that was just what I intended you should do;" and he looked perfectly Lappy, thinking how he could still continue to annoy his victims.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6608-00000022"/> 
               <head>CHAPTER XIII.</head> 
               <head type="sub">THE HUMBLE HOME OF THE TEMPLETONS-THE MALICIOUS MRS. CARY AND DAUGHTER VISIT THEM.</head> 
               <p>WE will now enter the small village of S--. It was what would be called a manufacturing town. In the most thickly settled portion, houses and factories looked as if scattered about in a promiscuous fashion-here a factory, then close by was a house, and so on, throughout the village; and it appeared as if taste or comfort had never once been thought of in its construction and plan, although it is to be doubted if there ever was any: it was evident that each villager built a house or factory at his own discretion.</p> 
               <p>We will take a winding road that leads across a long bridge. We follow this road for about a quarter of a mile, and we see a small brown cottage, which has the appearance of having been for some time quite neglected. It is early in March, and vegetation has not yet begun to spring forth; the winds are cold and bleak; everything presents the appearance of desolation and sadness. Any one, even in the best frame of mind possible, to look at this place, walk up the neglected pathway leading to the cottage, could not help feeling a sense of sadness and gloom. How much, then, would this feeling be increased in one who felt that the burdens of life were already too great to bear; and one who had left a luxurious home which possessed every comfort that money could purchase, and who had been deserted by the one on whom her happiness depended? Such were the feelings with which Josephine entered this gloomy abode.</p> 
               <p>Mr. Templeton had very limited means with which to furnish even so small and plain a cottage as this. One thousand dollars was all the money he possessed in the world, and when that was gone he had no way of replacing it. He knew that his small salary would be barely enough to supply his family with the commonest necessities of life. As he thought of these things it made him unutterably sad, and it seemed as if he could not bear up under it.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, how can my dear wife and poor Josephine ever live in this way, and submit to such privations? I have brought it all upon them by my misconduct. What can I do to atone for what I have made them suffer? It is enough to drive one mad, to contemplate the ruin I have wrought. If I had have had more firmness of character, Josephine might now have been the happy wife of Lord Delmore, and we, at our beautiful home, in prosperous circumstances. Instead of that, this scene! oh, it is too dreadful!" he exclaimed, surveying the interior of the house.</p> 
               <p>The ceilings were very low, and bare whitewashed walls. The carpets that covered the uneven floors were of the coarsest, cheapest kind. There was what was called a parlor, but which supplied the place of sitting room also; a dining room and kitchen on the first floor; above this the same number of rooms, which was all the house contained. The sitting room was furnished with several pine cane-seated chairs and a small wooden table in the centre of the room; that was all-not a mirror, or picture, or a single ornament of any kind. The dining room possessed only a large pine table and chairs. Mrs. Templeton's and Josephine's rooms were furnished with the cheapest and plainest furniture. There were nothing but the bare necessaries of life to be seen in the house. It can only be imagined what so great a change must have been for them. What their feelings were, and how muck they suffered can hardly be described. They employed only one old woman, who acted as general servant.</p> 
               <p>Josephine and her mother entered their humble and cheerless abode, neither of them speaking a word. Josephine was calm and pale. She hastily laid aside her hat and cloak, murmuring,</p> 
               <p>"Oh, fate! thou canst do no more. I care not what comes now, for I have drank the bitterest dregs of my cup of sorrow. I can bear all things calmly. I can never suffer again as I did in that <emph>one</emph> terrible agony, for since then, and forever more, my heart is dead. What is the mere comfort of worldly surroundings, compared to what I have suffered? Now I will forever dismiss all thought of <emph>self,</emph> and try to live to cheer and comfort my dear parents. It will only add to their unhappiness, if I am sorrowful. My duty now is to try and cheer them, for they are overwhelmed with sorrow."</p> 
               <p>With this resolution she hastened to the room where her father and mother were sitting. Her mother was weeping when she entered; on perceiving her, she looked up, saying:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, my poor Josephine, above all things, I am so sorry for you. How can you endure all this; having the affliction of this dreadful poverty added to your other troubles? It seems as if the fates combined to put upon us every affliction which could be imagined, and to bring us to endure all that mortals can, and live. This is torture. How can a merciful God allow sorrow upon sorrow thus to overwhelm us?"</p> 
               <p>"Do not speak so, mother; do not think of me, for I will be very cheerful, and do all I can to make you happy. We at least are all blessed with health, and soon the bright beautiful spring days will he here: we will have roses and flowers, then all will not look so desolate, as it does now; for I love flowers and the country; here I can take care of them myself, and see them grow: then we can take long walks together on the pleasant country roads; we shall be in better health than constantly riding in carriages: why, mother, we can soon be quite contented, if we will only try: besides, papa can get us some good books, and in the long summer days we can sit under the shade of these large beautiful trees, and I will read to you. We have nothing to do, now, but amuse ourselves; we will not be troubled with society, to claim nearly all of our time. So, by looking on the bright side, we can be quite comfortable, even in our circumstances," said Josephine, drawing a chair close to her mother, and seating herself beside her.</p> 
               <p>"My precious child," exclaimed Mr. Templeton, "your beautiful presence and cheerful words would make sunshine<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6608-00000023"/> shine any where. I had no idea that you were such a little philosopher, and such a heroine as you have proved yourself to be: for great and noble natures shine the most brilliantly in the midst of adversities; it is then that they show to full advantage, their best qualities; it is only weak, cowardly natures that give up and sink under trials; those who are brave, only grow the braver, and they are the ones, who, at last, with the help of Heaven, overcome all obstacles."</p> 
               <p>"I do not deserve so much praise, papa, yet I try to be cheerful, and make the most of the few pleasures we have," and a slight smile passed over her lips for the first time, since she had heard of Herbert Delmore's treachery.</p> 
               <p>"My dear child, said Mrs. Templeton, wiping away her tears, "you really make me feel ashamed to have given up to my grief, as I have, when you have double the sorrow to contend with that we have; to see you so brave and cheerful, although I know that your poor heart aches, yet for our sakes you do it. After all it is not the greatest affliction in the world to lose a beautiful home, and all our property, if we only have such a good and noble daughter to cheer us, and take away the thorns from our rough pathway."</p> 
               <p>"Thank you, mamma, I am so glad to see that sad expression leaving your dear face," then she thought, "how little can any one ever know how much this forced cheerfulness costs me; yet, see how much pleasure a few kind words have given my dear parents, and to see them happy, more than repays me: to them and to charitable deeds, I henceforth dedicate my life."</p> 
               <p>As in all country towns, the arrival of strangers is quickly heralded; and they are freely discussed, and commented upon. Any one who seems to possess the least knowledge of them is eagerly listened to; the villagers of S-- were no exception to this rule. Had anybody seen them? And did any one know who they were? Were the first eager inquiries. At last, to their great satisfaction, their curiosity was gratified, and it was commonly reported that the Templetons had been recently very wealthy people, but were now in reduced circumstances; and the young Miss Templeton, was said to be very beautiful.</p> 
               <p>Mr. Templeton being out of business, had accepted the position of clerk, at a small salary in one of the manufactories.</p> 
               <p>"Well, for my part," spoke up one of the village damsels, "I don't see how such great people as they have been, could come here and live as they do. I suppose they feel above speaking to any of us, even if they are poor; but I shall call and see them out of curiosity."</p> 
               <p>"They are not that kind of people, I know," replied Lucy Saunders, "for they have hired old Hannah to live with them, and she told me, that they were the nicest people, she ever saw; that Miss Templeton is a perfect beauty, and as fair as a lily. So we will go together and call and see them, for they must be lonesome there all alone."</p> 
               <p>"I would like to see them, and perhaps you are right, time will determine," replied her companion, and saying good-bye, they parted, each to return to their respective homes.</p> 
               <p>It was an impossibility that Josephine could make companions of these uneducated country girls, even if she had wished for society; but of all things she wished to avoid was that; she had seen too much of the shallow ness of what were called "friends" in society.</p> 
               <p>It was a beautiful day, towards the latter part of March; Josephine was sitting near the open window, busily engaged on some fine needle work, for her mother. She always dressed with exquisite taste, and although she was now deprived of her beautiful home, and was living in the poorest and most humble way, yet that innate sense of refinement, and love of the beautiful, never left her. Her dress at this time presented a strange contrast to the scene around her; she wore a delicate blue cashmere, beautifully embroidered, and a collar of fine lace: around her neck a heavy gold chain, from which was suspended a turquoise and diamond locket, which contained the portrait of Lord Delmore: and earrings of the same precious stones. This was Lord Delmore's last gift to Josephine.</p> 
               <p>She was so busily engaged that she did not notice the approach of two gaudily dressed ladies. Old Hannah answered the summons at the door, and gave Josephine their cards; she glanced at them, as she did so, a flush of indignation passed over her face, and she said, half audibly:</p> 
               <p>"How dare they, when I well know that it is Mr. Cary who has brought all this ruin upon us: yet I must control my feelings enough, to treat them politely."</p> 
               <p>Mrs. Cary and her daughter, swept into the room, with an air of great condescension and disdain; but in an instant, her presumption deserted her, for immediately she felt, that even now, Josephine was so far superior to her, and that nothing she could do, would ever bring her to her level: that superb and natural grace, that glorious and noble nature, were something, that neither her daughter or herself could ever attain. She had expected to find Josephine totally humble and dejected: that in her miserable country home, and their poverty, she would become so wholly despondent, that she would no longer think or care for appearances: yet, how great was her surprise, to find everything so different. She found her dressed with as much taste and care, her luxurious and beautiful golden hair dressed as handsomely, as if she were receiving her friends, in her splendid drawing-room at B--. Everything in the house, although very plain and poor, was scrupulously neat, and arranged in the most perfect order, and wore almost an air of cheerfulness. She felt how far, even now, they had failed in rendering this family utterly miserable; and she was both, angry and mortified, at the result of her visit.</p> 
               <p>"My mother is ill, and will not be able to see you," replied Josephine, in answer to Mrs. Cary's inquiries.</p> 
               <p>"I do not wonder," said Mrs. Cary, "the change must be very great, and you must be very lonely here, I should die in such a place."</p> 
               <p>"It is not so unpleasant as one would imagine," replied Josephine, trying to conceal her emotion.</p> 
               <p>"I think you had better take off some of your jewelry, Miss Templeton, it would compare better with your surroundings: and when you get ready to sell, your wardrobe, let us know, for it is not probable, from present appearances, that you can long afford to dress as you do now," as Mrs. Cary said this, she rose, saying: "it is now time for us to go; good morning; Miss Templeton."</p> 
               <pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC6608-00000024"/> 
               <p>"Good morning," she replied, and Mrs. Cary and her daughter swept out of the room.</p> 
               <p>Josephine stood for a moment as if bewildered at their insulting words, then sank into a seat, crying:</p> 
               <p>"Oh those dreadful women, have they gone at last. May I never see their cruel faces again: is not all we have suffered enough to satisfy their inhuman hearts, without coming here to add this last insult. I am so thankful poor mother was not here. Surely those wicked people will some day be punished as they deserve."</p> 
               <p>This last malignant action, brought back every sorrowful memory again, for Josephine had striven bravely against allowing her thoughts to dwell on what was past.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER XIV.</head> 
               <head type="sub">THE SANFORDS VISIT THE TEMPLETONS.</head> 
               <p>ABOUT a mile from the Templeton's cottage, there stood on an eminence of ground, surrounded by magnificent trees, the splendid summer residence of Isaac Sanford: this house was the admiration of every one for miles around, and was considered one of the most beautiful country residences in the state. Mr. Sanford was a native of New England, but when quite young had gone to the south to reside, where he had amassed an immense fortune. Then he returned to his native state and built the splendid residence, widely known as Sanford House. He had selected this spot for its rare beauty, the eminence on which the house stood, commanding an unsurpassed view of the surrounding country. His wife was a southern lady, of high family; and they always passed their winters at the south.</p> 
               <p>Mr. Sanford's eldest son, Horace, was a handsome though rather conceited young man, of twenty-one years of age. Ella, a young lady of eighteen, and three younger children composed his family. They arrived in the month of April, and had now taken possession of their house, which they were not to leave again for several months. It was about a week after their arrival, when Horace came hurriedly into the room where his mother was sitting, saying:</p> 
               <p>"I wish you would go out with me this afternoon to make a call."</p> 
               <p>"Why, that is something new for you to wish to make calls on the villagers: I think I have heard you say that their company was rather stupid."</p> 
               <p>"So I have, but this is of a very different character; for I wish to make the acquaintance of a young lady I have seen to-day; her name is Templeton, we met her when I was out riding with Henry Winters, and he told me who she was, and all about the family: they have been here only a short time, but were recently very wealthy, and lived in B--, they are now poor, and her father has taken a situation here. I think she is the most beautiful person I ever saw. I am determined to make her acquaintance."</p> 
               <p>"Now, I hope this is not a case of love at first sight," replied Mrs. Sanford, laughing.</p> 
               <p>"I did not say anything about love, but I would like to have the pleasure of her acquaintance."</p> 
               <p>"Well, my son, I am very particular who I call on; but in a country place like this, one need not be so particular; so I will go, in order to please you. No doubt the ride Trill do me good; and since you have said so much, I already begin to feel a little curious to see such a prodigy," she replied, smiling.</p> 
               <p>At three o'clock the elegant phton, with a splendid pair of "bays," stood before the large portico of the entrance hall. Mrs. Sanford and Horace came and took seats. He then gave directions to their sable coachman (whom I they always brought with them) where to go.</p> 
               <p>"Yes, massa," he replied. Then drawing the reins, the noble animals quickly started, as if impatient of waiting so long. They passed rapidly over the pleasant country roads, and in a short time stopped before Josephine's humble home. They were informed, in answer to the coachman's inquiries, that both Mrs. and Miss Templeton were at home. They received their visitors with that cordial grace which at once distinguishes the refined lady of society, and makes every one feel perfectly at ease. The conversation was on general topics; Horace addressing himself more particularly to Miss Templeton, with whom, he became more and more charmed. They made quite a long and very pleasant call. As they drove away, Mrs. Sanford exclaimed:</p> 
               <p>"What delightful people." She was very fastidious, and when she praised any one it was indeed a compliment.</p> 
               <p>"I agree with you, and am very glad that you are so much pleased with them."</p> 
               <p>"She will be such a pleasant companion for Ella. She is so highly educated, speaking both French, and Italian; understands German, and performs both on the harp and piano."</p> 
               <p>"I am sure she must be a fine singer, for her voice is so melodious, even when she speaks," replied Horace, with animation.</p> 
               <p>"Is it not very strange how they became so reduced, for it appears now that they must be very poor? Yet any one can easily see that they are very refined and elegant people. How strange are these freaks of fortune? Yet they are liable to befall any of us, and we should always think of that;" for the visit she had just paid had made a great impression on her.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC6608-00000025"/> 
               <head>CHAPTER XV.</head> 
               <head type="sub">JOSEPHINE ON AN ERRAND OF MERCY.</head> 
               <p>THREE months had passed slowly away since the Templetons had come to their humble cottage. Josephine's fortitude seemed never to have deserted her since the first day of their arrival, for she had now given up her life entirely to try and make others happy. She felt that happiness for her had gone forever.</p> 
               <p>The country now began to look very beautiful. The green grass had again covered the fields, which had before looked brown and desolate. The trees were in leaf again in all their spring freshness, and the flowers began to appear in all their beauty. The farmers were busily engaged cultivating their fields; planting and sowing, and everything presented a scene of life and activity. The days were bright and beautiful. It seemed as if such scenes would cheer one, even if the most desponding; but it was not so with Josephine, for the contemplation of so much beauty and brightness seemed only to increase her utter wretchedness and hopelessness, when everything was so full of hope and life; but there was no hope to which she could look forward. She had hoped that when the spring had come she should then feel more cheerful, but it had only the contrary effect, and increased, if possible, her sense of misery. Josephine sat gazing out of the open window, her mind filled with sad thoughts.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, everything has hope, but I have none. What have I done that so many sorrows should come upon me V Oh, it seems as if the very stones must pity my wretchedness; yet there are others that suffer as much as I do, and what little comfort or aid that is in my power to bestow, I will give willingly. I have promised to go and see Jane Elstone, and I will go now, for I shall not be less happy trying to cheer others, who as well as I, are almost ready to sink under the heavy burdens of life."</p> 
               <p>With these thoughts she arose and informed her mother that she was going to visit the poor sick woman in the village, that Miss Saunders had told her was very destitute, and seemed all alone in the world, and that she was always so thankful to those who took pity on her forlorn situation, and through charity visited her.</p> 
               <p>"My dear child, you are never tired of doing good to others, and you surely will be rewarded," said Mrs. Templeton.</p> 
               <p>Josephine then went and prepared for her visit. A walk of some distance brought her to the most thickly settled portion of the village. She walked quickly through a narrow street which was inhabited only by laborers, and the air was filled with the smoke of the adjoining factories. She stopped before a long, low two-storied wooden building; took a slip of paper from her pocket, and saw that it answered the directions. Then she inquired of a group of dirty looking children if Mrs. Jane Elstone lived there.</p> 
               <p>"Yes; do you want to see her?" replied a bright looking, chubby little boy, the others being afraid to speak. "I will show you the way; it's up stairs;" so saying he hastily led the way, leaving the rest of the children staring in bewilderment after them, for it was seldom that they ever saw so fine a lady in that part of the town. They entered by a low door, and ascended a narrow stairway, at the head of which her little chaperon stopped and said:</p> 
               <p>"This is her room."</p> 
               <p>Josephine thanked him, and gave him a piece of money.</p> 
               <p>"I am much obliged to you," he replied, scampering down the stairs as fast as he could go. He returned to his little companions in the street, and proudly displayed the money that the good lady had given him.</p> 
               <p>Josephine knocked lightly at the door and heard a low voice from with-in, saying: "Come in."</p> 
               <p>She opened the door and entered the miserable room. The floor was bare. In one corner of the room was an old chair; in another, a small bedstead, near which wan a coarse pine table; on it was a bottle which served as a candlestick, in which stood a half burnt candle; and that was all.</p> 
               <p>The woman that lay on the bed was indeed pitiable; every feature looked pinched and worn by suffering. She lay on an old mattress, and had only an old blanket to cover her. As Josephine entered, she partially raised herself, saying:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, dear lady, you are so good to come and see me. It's few that I ever see now, and I've been so very sick."</p> 
               <p>"My good woman I came to see if I could do anything for you, having heard that you were sick."</p> 
               <p>"The Lord bless you, Miss, it's not everybody that's like you, it's seldom that the rich who have more than they know what to do with, ever think of the poor; they go to church, riding in their fine carriages and wearing rich dresses, but they don't practice what they hear there; they don't do what the bible tells them to do," as she said this, her head fell back upon the pillow, and her eyes filled with tears."</p> 
               <p>"I fear that what you say is in a great measure true, but how long have you been sick, and do you take any medicine?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes Miss, the doctor came here twice, and gave me some, and when that was gone I had no money to buy more; but take a seat, Miss, and I will tell you something of my history, for I hav'nt always been like this, and I would'nt have you think so."</p> 
               <p>Josephine took a seat and the old woman proceeded with her story:</p> 
               <p>"Well, I will commence at the beginning: I'm a native of this country, my father and mother were well enough off, but I had to work for a living. When I was fifteen years old, I went to live with Mr. and Mrs. William Ghent, who lived in the village of M--."</p> 
               <p>"Excuse 'me, for interrupting you, but the name of Ghent is familiar to me; for I have often heard of them, I myself was born in M--, and lived there seven years."</p> 
               <p>"While Josephine was speaking, the woman raised herself to a sitting posture, and was gazing eagerly into her face."</p> 
               <p>"You lived there? Oh, tell me your name?"</p> 
               <pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC6608-00000026"/> 
               <p>"My name is Josephine Templeton." As she spoke these words the old woman's face turned an pale as death, and she exclaimed:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, no, no, it cannot be so," and covering her face with her hands, fell back on the pillow, sobbing:</p> 
               <p>"My good woman what is the matter? Are you ill?"</p> 
               <p>"Oh, no, no, child, it's nothing, nothing at all, I knew of the Templetons when I lived in M--, and it brought back old memories of the time when I was happy."</p> 
               <p>"Then you are the same sweet child I used to see with golden curls, now grown to be a beautiful young lady," he said, gazing through her tears at Josephine's lovely face; and you've come here, now, to comfort me when I am old and almost dying, may God bless you, child; what strange things do happen in this world that we should have met here again by accident, as it were; Ah, child, since I left M--, I've been from one place to another, and have never heard of you since, though I've often thought of you."</p> 
               <p>"Thank you, you must have taken a great deal of interest in me."</p> 
               <p>"Yes, that I have, and always shall till the day I die, which I don't think is very far off."</p> 
               <p>"Do not feel so badly, but take courage, for you may yet be quite well again," said Josephine, cheeringly.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, no, child, that can never be, I'm only forty-five years old, yet see these gray hairs," she said, smoothing back her hair, which was almost white, "why it looks as if I was sixty, and my face is as wrinkled as a person's twice my age; but it's all trouble that caused it, and I hav'nt the strength of a child. Oh, how good you are to come and see me now, and in this poor, miserable place, too."</p> 
               <p>"Do not speak of that, for it is a great pleasure for me to do anything I can for you, and if my visits are any comfort to you, I am very glad."</p> 
               <p>"You can't tell how much good it does me, to see your sweet face; its seldom any one thinks of me, but the woman that lives in the house is very good to me, and brings me something to eat every day. I paid the rent of the room the other day, and I've hardly a cent left."</p> 
               <p>Josephine took five dollars from her pocket book, and handed it to the woman, although she knew that she would have to deny herself many things in, consequence of giving so freely; for five dollars was more to her than so many hundreds had been in former days; but she could not see any one suffer, and not do all in her power for their relief."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, thank you, child, but this is a great deal too much; I did not mean to beg."</p> 
               <p>"Keep it, for you need it more than I do. I interrupted you in your history of yourself when you spoke of living in M--, I should like to hear more of it, if you feel able."</p> 
               <p>"Yes, I remember, I was so startled when you told me who you were, that I had forgotten what I was telling you: I feel that I am not worthy to take this money, but you are so kind, I will, and the Lord will surely repay you some day. Before I die, I may be of some service to you. Let me see, I had just told you that I was living with the Ghents in M--:" at this moment, she shuddered and covered her face with her hands; she was silent a moment, then seemed to gain courage and continued:</p> 
               <p>"I lived in that family fifteen years; they were well off, but they were very hard hearted, avaricious people, and where money was concerned, there was hardly anything they would hesitate to do; but their appearance to the public was everything that was honorable. They never did a mean action openly, or where they thought there was any chance of their being discovered; for they had the greatest respect for public opinion. I lived with them long enough to know some of the wicked ways in which they managed to get money that did not belong to them. I've overheard more than one conversation, that was'nt intended for anybody's ears but their own, but I would'nt dare expose anything I ever heard them say, for my life would'nt be safe a minute. William Ghent is a wicked man, and has a bad heart, and he'd hunt me to the ends of the earth, and murder me: for they know that I'm the only person who knows about their wickedness."</p> 
               <p>Can this woman be insane, thought Josephine: her wild look and strange words frightening her.</p> 
               <p>"Well, when I was thirty years old, I married Carl Elstone, and a sad day it was to me when I became his wife, for since then it's been nothing but trouble after trouble, until I'm reduced to this, as you see me now. Everybody told me not to marry him for he was a worthless man, and I'd never be happy if I did; but I did not heed anybody then. I would have my own way and only found 'out my mistake too late. The Ghents gave me some handsome presents, and one hundred dollars in money; but they did that for an object, and that was to keep silent about whatever I may have heard or seen there; and I've served them well so far. As goon as we were married, we left M--; I gave Carl all the money I had, which I had been saving for years, If I had kept it myself, I should, probably, have never been where I am now, but it's no use to think of that. It was not long before he had spent all the money he had. He worked at a trade and was a good hand, but was so negligent that no one would employ him long, and so we went wandering about from; one place to another. I tried to persuade him to do better, but it was of no use, the more I said the worse he seemed to grow. He went in bad company and took to drink; then he was taken sick with a dreadful fever, and died six weeks afterwards.</p> 
               <p>"Some of the neighbors helped me, and I got together money enough to have him decently buried, when that was done I had hardly a penny left, most of my clothes were gone for I had already parted with the best of them at a pawn brokers. I had lived with him two years wanting one month when he died. I was ashamed to go back to M--, for they had predicted the bad end I would come to, if I married him: so I was determined I would starve, rather than let my friends know that what they had said, had only proved too true. I went out doing sewing by the day, but my health, had become poor, and I could'nt work all the time, and do the best I could it was very little I was able to save, My strength failed, more and more, and I had to give up work. Then I got better again, and was fortunate enough to now and then get a little sewing, which I could take home with me. I could earn but barely enough to live upon, and in that way I lived for years. I thought that this place would be better for me, as I could get higher prices for my work, so I came here two months ago; but the change only made me worse, and I have not<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC6608-00000027"/> been able to sit up a day since, and when you came, I had paid out my last dollar. I feel that I shall not live much longer, I am broken down with sorrow and disappointment," said the woman, closing her eyes and sighing, for the long recital seemed to have tired her greatly.</p> 
               <p>"Yours is, indeed, a very sad history, but do not feel too desponding, for brighter days may come yet: you may be quite well again, soon, and I am sure that we shall be able to find plenty of light work for you to do. "While you are sick I will come and, see you often, and do everything I can to make you comfortable, "said Josephine, rising.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, the Lord bless you, child, I never met a person with so kind a heart as you have before; I only wish that there were more people like you, but you are not going now, are you?" she said, noticing that Josephine had risen from her seat.</p> 
               <p>"Yes, for I think that I have made you a very long visit, and fear that I have tired you talking so much."</p> 
               <p>"No, no, you hav'nt, I wish you could stay longer, but come again very soon, for I have some tiling important to say to you before I die. I know that I am not much longer for this world. I thank you a thousand times for your kindness to me; you seem almost like a saint, you are so good and beautiful. I feel so much happier now than I did before you came."</p> 
               <p>"I am very glad that I have been any comfort to you. I will come again soon to see you, and I hope you will get well again, now I must bid you good-bye."</p> 
               <p>"Good-bye. God bless you," said Jane Elstone, as Josephine left the room.</p> 
               <p>Josephine walked quickly through the narrow street, and hastened home, for she had been gone quite a long time, and she feared her mother might feel alarmed about her. The woman's history, the destitute condition she was in, the strange interest she seemed to take in her, and the startled, frightened expression of the woman's face, when she told her her name, made a great impression on her.</p> 
               <p>She thought the woman's actions were extraordinary, besides her words were strange and seemed to Lave some hidden meaning. Josephine pondered over all these things, and was almost inclined to believe that the woman's sufferings and trials had unsettled her mind. Josephine had now reached home, and her mother met her at the door, saying:</p> 
               <p>"Why, my dear, you have been gone so long that I began to fool alarmed. I am always afraid to have you go to see these poor people alone; you have to go through such dreadful streets." "I am sorry you felt worried about me, I did stay longer than I expected to, but I could not very well come away before. When I am doing a good action, I never feel afraid, no matter where I am, for I think the angels protect us when we are doing charitable deeds and trying to assist others."</p> 
               <p>"Ah, my dear, you always have some such beautiful reply to make, which at once dispels all my fears, and I can say no more."</p> 
               <p>"Thank you, mamma, if you praise me so much you will make me vain," replied Josephine, smiling: now let us take a seat, for I feel quite tired, I have walked so fast, and I will tell you all about the poor woman I have seen to-day,</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
                
               <head>CHAPTER XVI.</head> 
               <head type="sub">RECEPTION AT THE SANFORD MANSION-HORACE SANFORD MAKES PROPOSALS TO JOSEPHINE.</head> 
               <p>IT was a beautiful evening in May, the San ford mansion was brilliantly illuminated, and as you approached the house the sounds of music were distinctly heard. Several of their friends from the South were stopping with them for a short time before going to the fashionable Northern watering places. They had also invited a number of their city acquaintances, and with the addition of some of their neighbors, it made quite a large assemblage. The interior of the house was most beautifully and tastefully decorated with a profusion of rare plants and flowers. The rich carpets were covered with white cloth, and the white lace drapery contrasted handsomely with the bright colors of the velvet and satin furniture. A very large and splendid conservatory, led from the library between which were large folding doors, set with immense panes of glass; but on this occasion they were thrown open. The conservatory was lit up by a number of Chinese lanterns. Several mocking and canary birds, and a large white parot, in gilded cages, were hung among the tropical plants and flowers, and made a most charming scene. On the opposite side of the large hall were two spacious drawing rooms, where there was dancing: the musicians being stationed in an alcove of the hall, into which a door from, the drawing room opened.</p> 
               <p>Mr. and Mrs. Sanford, assisted by their eldest daughter, Ella, stood in the reception room gracefully and cordially receiving their guests. Ella was by no means handsome, but on this occasion looked remarkably well. She wore a dress of white tulle, almost entirely covered with puffings of the same material, with necklace, ear-rings and bracelets of pearls, and a rope of pearls wound gracefully among the heavy black braids of her hair. Horace, with a young lady leaning on his arm, with whom he had just been dancing, took seats on a sofa in the library, which commanded a full view of the reception room, and he looked eagerly at each one as they shook hands with the host and hostess. The young lady who sat beside him was a perfect type of Southern beauty; her hair was black, and she had large, sparkling black eyes; her complexion was a clear olive, and features very regular and handsome. Her rich dress set off her style of beauty to perfection. It was of heavy crimson silk, with overdress of Honiton lace; necklace and earrings of rubies and diamonds, and a single japonica confined a, heavy curl of her hair, which reached to her waist. Such was the appearance and dress of Castina Emarton, whom both the Sanfords<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC6608-00000028"/> fords and Emartons hoped Horace would sometime marry. She had noticed how much occupied Horace was noticing the arrival of the guests, and for some moments he had been silent. At last she said:</p> 
               <p>"Your thoughts seem to be entirely engrossed noticing the arrival of your friends. I suppose that you are expecting to see the charming Miss Templeton, of whom you have given me such glowing description. Haying heard so much about her, I really feel quite anxious to make her acquaintance."</p> 
               <p>"I beg your pardon, Castina. I confess that I was thinking of the Templetons, for it is now getting late, and I had expected them to arrive early."</p> 
               <p>"It pleases me to see you so candid," she replied, smiling; "but ah, who is that? She certainly answers your description, perfectly, of Miss Templeton."</p> 
               <p>"Yes, it is Josephine," he replied, rising quickly. "Pardon me for a moment; I will go and speak to her, and then introduce you."</p> 
               <p>He reached the reception room in time to receive her. After passing the usual salutations with Mr. and Mrs. San ford and their daughter, Horace offered his hand, saying:</p> 
               <p>"Good evening, Miss Templeton; we are very happy to see you, for at the moment of your arrival, I was regretting that we had not had the pleasure of your company earlier in the evening."</p> 
               <p>"Thank you; we were a little delayed. The scene here is charming."</p> 
               <p>"I am glad you are pleased with it, and, as you are so fond of flowers, I would like to have you go with me to the library, where you can have a fine view of the conservatory; and I wish to introduce you to my friend. Miss Emarton, whom I left when I saw you arrive," said Horace, offering his arm.</p> 
               <p>"Thank you; I should be pleased to do so," replied Josephine, taking his arm, and looking round saw her father and mother conversing with some elderly people to whom their hostess had introduced them. Josephine's dress was quite simple, but exceedingly becoming, being of white muslin, handsomely embroidered, with trimmings of valenciennes lace; her only jewels being a diamond cross, suspended from a black velvet ribbon which encircled her pure white neck, and solitaire diamond ear-rings. Her beautiful golden hair was dressed in curls, among which were several drooping sprays of clematis. Horace introduced Josephine to his friend, and they then took seats, Josephine admiring the fairy-like effect produced by the flowers, the lights, and the singing of the birds in the conservatory.</p> 
               <p>"How beautiful," exclaimed Josephine: "these birds must think they are again in their tropical home."</p> 
               <p>Ah, if you are such an admirer of nature, you should go to the South to live, for there the air seems filled with their songs, and the flowers that here are cultivated in conservatories, with us grow luxuriantly in the open air. I enjoy coming North in the summer, but nothing could induce me to make it my permanent home," said Castina.</p> 
               <p>"I do not doubt that I should be greatly pleased with the South, from the descriptions that I have both heard and read about it," replied Josephine:</p> 
               <p>At this moment, a tall fine looking young man approached from the adjoining room, and after being introduced to Miss Templeton, remarked:</p> 
               <p>"I have been looking for you sometime, Miss Emarton, shall I have the pleasure of dancing the next quadrille with you?"</p> 
               <p>"Certainly, with pleasure," she replied, rising, and taking his arm, saying: "excuse me Miss Templeton, I will see you again," and they left the room.</p> 
               <p>Horace then took a seat on the sofa, beside Josephine, saying:</p> 
               <p>"I would ask you to dance, but perhaps you had rather sit here, a while, first, as you have just arrived. Since our acquaintance of nearly three months, I believe this is the first opportunity that I have had to speak to you alone."</p> 
               <p>"My mother and I, appreciate the kindness that you have shown us since we have been here, and the frequent and pleasant rides you have given us in the fresh country air have, I think, materially improved my mother's health; for which I am very grateful; and I thank you for the beautiful collection of plants, you sent me. I had them planted in the grounds about the cottage, and they are a great improvement," said Josephine, trying to turn the subject of conversation.</p> 
               <p>"I am glad you liked them. You heard what my friend said only a few moments ago, that you ought to live in the South, and I think so too, and when there, you shall not have a wish ungratified, that money will procure. Josephine will you accept such a home from me?"</p> 
               <p>"Oh, Mr. Sanford, if you would not make me unhappy, do hot speak to me on that subject, you would not if you knew all; you have been very kind to us when we were poor and almost friendless, for which I feel very grateful."</p> 
               <p>"Josephine I would not cause you a moment's unhappiness for the world; perhaps you may change your mind. I shall never cease to hope," replied Horace, an expression of great disappointment coming over his fine face.</p> 
               <p>At this moment, to Josephine's great relief, the guests began returning to the library, and promenaded through the different rooms, the dancing of the quadrille being over. She felt heartily sorry that Horace had formed so unhappy an attachment, for he was a kind and pleasant friend, but more than that he could never be, she had loved once, but should never love again.</p> 
               <p>"Will you at least grant me the pleasure of being my partner in the next dance?" Said Horace, rising, as he saw Miss Emarton, and her companion returning.</p> 
               <p>"With pleasure," she replied. Castina took her seat again beside Josephine, saying:</p> 
               <p>"Are you not fond of dancing, Miss Templeton?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, I think it very pleasant, and intend joining in the next dance," replied Josephine: but she felt little like taking part in any amusement now, yet she was obliged to do so, to please her father and mother, but it was almost torture to her. She struggled to compose herself, appear calm, and take an apparently cheerful part in conversation, which she succeeded admirably in doing, and was admired and noticed by every one. A magnificent supper was served in the large elegant dining hall, and at a late hour the company separated; all being delighted with the evening's entertainment.</p> 
               <p>After all the guests had departed, Horace walked slowly through the deserted rooms, feeling very sad, yet not without hope. "Even if she does not love me now, well enough to be my wife, she certainly will learn, to love me. A person with so muck refinement, with such exquisite taste,<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC6608-00000029"/> and having been brought up, as she has been, should not now be living as she does. I can restore to her and her family, every luxury they ever enjoyed. I will have an interview with Mr. Templeton, and ask his consent to our union, no doubt he will look upon it favorable, for I cannot see why he should object. Josephine answered me hastily this evening; but when she comes to consider the subject, her answer in all probability, will be very different."</p> 
               <p>Thus arguing with himself and coming to these satisfactory conclusions, he retired to his room.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER XVII.</head> 
               <head type="sub">JOSEPHINE GOES IX A THUNDER STORM AT NIGHT TO THE DEATH-BED OF JANE ELSTONE.</head> 
               <p>IT was a dark stormy night, the rain fell in torrents, and there were occasionally vivid flashes of lightning-accompanied by terrific peals of thunder. Josephine and her mother sat in their humble parlor, busily engaged with some needlework, and Mr. Temple ton was reading the daily newspaper. All was perfectly quiet, at length Josephine looked up and said:</p> 
               <p>"What a dreadful night: how I pity any one out in such a storm."</p> 
               <p>"It is, indeed, and at such times as these, I realize how thankful we ought to be, for comfortable shelter, however humble it may be," replied Mrs. Templeton.</p> 
               <p>"Yes, that is very true, for when we look out into the world, we see more worse off, than better than we. Once, if we had seen ourselves reduced to our present position, we should have thought it impossible to pass one pleasant moment, but now we find by actual experience, that by doing our duty, trying to be cheerful, and making the most of the few pleasures we have, that we are not altogether miserable."</p> 
               <p>"My dear child,'' said Mr. Templeton, laying aside his paper, "if it had not been for your kind, and encouraging words, when our misfortunes first came upon us, I fear that I should have sunk under the burden. If you had been desponding, and unhappy, I never could have borne it, but your bright, cheerful and hopeful words, and conduct, have given your mother and myself renewed courage, and some of your brave spirit, seems now to have been imparted to us. I cannot now mourn over our losses, for if they had not have happened, we never should have known half your real worth. The fortitude with which you have borne your afflictions, is a more glorious crown, than any earthly honor could possibily have been."</p> 
               <p>"Yes, my dear child," added Mrs. Templeton, "many a dreary hour, that I should have passed in tears, you by your cheerfulness, have turned to smiles."</p> 
                
               <p>"I am very thankful," replied Josephine, "if I have been able to add anything to your happiness."</p> 
               <p>"I am sure," said Mr. Templeton, "that the time will come when you will be rewarded for your noble conduct."</p> 
               <p>At this moment, rapid steps were heard on the graveled walk, approaching the house, then a loud knock at the door.</p> 
               <p>"Who can it be, coming here at this hour, and on such a fearful night," exclaimed Josephine, dropping her work upon 'the table, and glancing at the plain wooden clock on the mantle, which told that it was half past ten o'clock. Before there was time for a reply to be made, old Hannah appeared at the door, saying:</p> 
               <p>"There is man here, who says he wants to see Miss Templeton, immediately."</p> 
               <p>"Ask him into this room," replied Mrs. Templeton, excitedly.</p> 
               <p>In another moment the man entered; he was dripping with rain, and held his cap in his hand, he was evidently a laborer, from appearance; he wore coarse clothes, and thick heavy boots, and seemed very much embarrassed at finding himself in the presence of such people.</p> 
               <p>"What is it that you wish" inquired Mr. Templeton, kindly, The man then regained his self-possession, sufficiently to say:</p> 
               <p>"Jane Elstone is dying, sir," as he said this, Josephine started from her seat, with an anxious startled look, listening intently to hear every word the man said, "and she told me, that she must see Miss Templeton before she died, for she had a great secret to tell her, which she would impart to no one else in the world."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, I must go immediately to see her," cried Josephine, "there is no time to be lost, for she may die before I get there, and then her secret would die with her. Father will you go with me?"</p> 
               <p>"Why, my child, you must be wild, to think of venturing out on such a night; I cannot consent to it; by such imprudence you would in all probability, be running the risk of your own life, you must not go," said Mrs. Templeton, in great excitement, taking her daughter's hand in her's.</p> 
               <p>"I told Mrs. Elstone, that no lady could go out in such a storm, and that I would not ask any one to, but she Hold me if I did not go, and toll you what she said, the curse of a dying woman would be upon me, and when' she said that, I could say no more: so I came, but it's one of the most dreadful storms I was ever out in, sir," said the man, looking down at his wet clothes.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, mother, how can I refuse the request of a dying woman? It surely must be important, or she would not be so anxious to see me; do not forbid me going, for I do not fear the storm, I can put on such heavy clothing that I shall not get wet, or take cold," said Josephine, earnestly looking first at her mother, and then at her father, as if to read their consent in their faces. During this time Mr. Templeton had remained thoughtful and silent, for he did not like to refuse Josephine any thing that she wished to do, for she never asked what was unreasonable, Pie could not imagine what the woman could possibly have to say, of such importance to Josephine, yet it might be something of benefit to her, and he finally concluded, that as Josephine seemed so anxious to go, that he would accompany her; and by protecting themselves well against the<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC6608-00000030"/> storm there would be no very great danger.</p> 
               <p>"My child," at last said Mr. Templeton, "all things considered, I think you had better go, and I will go with you."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, thank you, papa; and you are willing, too," she said, turning to her mother.</p> 
               <p>"Yes, if your father thinks best; but you must dress warmly," replied Mrs. Templeton, the expression of whose face indicated plainly that she did not entirely approve of it.</p> 
               <p>In a moment Josephine left the room, and Mr. Templeton also went to make the necessary preparations. In a short time they both returned to the room, looking well prepared to meet the storm.</p> 
               <p>"Now," said Mr. Templeton, turning to the man, "we are ready."</p> 
               <p>The three then left the house, Mrs. Templeton following them to the door, anxiously giving Josephine the last precautions.</p> 
               <p>We will now precede their arrival, and enter the room of the dying woman. There were several women standing about the room, who had come there when they heard that Jane Elstone was dying. Everything was hushed and still; nothing could be heard save the heavy breathing of the woman who lay on the bed. Occasionally she would moan in a low voice:</p> 
               <p>"Has she come? Oh, it will soon be too late. Cannot some one go and tell her that if she does not come quickly I shall be gone?"</p> 
               <p>"She will be here soon," said one of the women, coming to the bedside and trying to soothe her.</p> 
               <p>"Is there anything I can do for you?"</p> 
               <p>"No, no; but I must see <emph>her</emph> before I die."</p> 
               <p>Time passed slowly to the anxious watchers, for they expected that every moment would be her last. She seemed to be rapidly sinking, and her breathing became fainter and fainter. At last they heard light footsteps on the stairs. One of the women went and noiselessly opened the door, and Josephine and her father entered the room.</p> 
               <p>"She is almost gone," the woman whispered. "She has something to tell you. Perhaps she will rouse a little when she sees you."</p> 
               <p>Josephine had laid aside her wet outer wrapping and approached the bed; as she did so the woman slowly opened her eyes, and when she saw that it was Josephine, she said in a hoarse gasping whisper:</p> 
               <p>"Thank God, you have come!" Then there was a pause, as if trying to regain some little strength, and a convulsive struggle. At length she said:</p> 
               <p>"There is a large amount of money"-again she paused, gasping for breath-then again continued, "that belongs to you."</p> 
               <p>Her voice was now so faint that, as Josephine leaned her head close to the dying woman, she could barely catch the words. Another struggle, and Josephine heard the faintly whispered words:</p> 
               <p>"Too late! too late!"</p> 
               <p>In another moment Jane Elstone was dead; her earthly sorrows were ended, and her secret had died with her, not having been able to tell enough to make it intelligible.</p> 
               <p>Josephine slowly raised her head, her eyes filled with tears, and going to her father, sobbed:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, father, she is dead."</p> 
               <p>"My dear child, do not weep," he said, putting his arm about her, and drawing her close to him.</p> 
                
               <p>"The poor woman is delivered from her afflictions, and gone, I hope, to a brighter, happier home, where sorrow and tears are never known. Now, it will not answer for you to remain here longer. I suppose that you," he said, turning to the women, "will make all the necessary preparations for the funeral. Here is some money to help defray the expenses;" and he gave one of the women the money.</p> 
               <p>"Thank you, sir," said the woman, in a trembling voice, making a low curtsey.</p> 
               <p>Josephine, with the assistance of one of the woman, had again put on her thick cloak.</p> 
               <p>"Now, Josephine, we must go." They both went to the bedside arid took one last look at the poor woman's face, and then bidding the people good-night, they left the room. As soon as they reached the street, Josephine said:</p> 
               <p>"What could her secret have been?"</p> 
               <p>"What did she say when you first entered the room?" eagerly inquired Mr. Templeton. "Her voice was so weak and indistinct that I could not understand a word."</p> 
               <p>"All she said was, that there was a large amount of money that belonged to me: then said, too late, too late, for she must have felt her strength failing her. "What could she have meant?"</p> 
               <p>"It is certainly very singular what that poor old woman could have known about you. It must be that she has heard that Gary and his dupe, Elbert Vinton, had literally robbed us of our property."</p> 
               <p>"It must be so. I know of nothing else she could mean. But I wish we had arrived a little sooner, as then she might have been able to explain. I am very thankful that I was allowed to make the last days of her unhappy life as comfortable as it was in my power," replied Josephine, with a sigh.</p> 
               <p>Nothing more was said during their walk home, each one's thoughts being occupied with the strange events of the evening. The storm had now abated in its fury, and they reached home safely, where they related what had occurred to Mrs. Templeton, who had been anxiously waiting for them.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC6608-00000031"/> 
               <head>CHAPTER XVIII.</head> 
               <head type="sub">JOSEPHINE RESISTS ANOTHER PROPOSAL OF MARRIAGE.</head> 
               <p>IT was a beautiful day in early summer; the sun was just setting, and its golden rays lit up the scene, and even the commonest objects looked beautifully in its gilded light. Josephine and her father and mother had for some time sat contemplating the beautiful scene before them, when Mr. Templeton spoke, saying:</p> 
               <p>"Josephine, I have delayed speaking to you on a subject of great importance, until this evening."</p> 
               <p>"Indeed, I should like to know what it is about," said Josephine, looking at her father.</p> 
               <p>"You must have been aware, my child, that for some time past Horace San ford has loved you."</p> 
               <p>As he said this, Josephine started quickly, a troubled expression coming over her face, and without waiting for her to reply, her father continued:</p> 
               <p>"Several days ago he asked me for your hand in marriage. Your mother and myself have well considered the matter, and have concluded that he is entirely worthy of you."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, father!" exclaimed Josephine, her face turning very pale, "You cannot mean what you say, I marry, now? No, never; I would die first."</p> 
               <p>"Do not speak so rashly, my dear," said Mrs. Templeton, in a coaxing tone. "You do not consider the great advantages it would give both yourself and us, for you would again be restored to wealth, Do not let any sentimental, romantic ideas keep you from doing what we know to be for your good. Lord Delmore basely deceived you, and I would not allow the thoughts of that bad man to ruin my life. Then, consider how happy it would make your father and myself to see you happily situated in life; and surely Horace is a most exemplary young man. You have been so self-sacrificing and done so much for our happiness, why will you now refuse to do that which would insure our happiness and comfort for life. I can see no reason why you should not love Horace. There are few young men that have his wealth and position; besides he is considered very handsome, and is a perfect gentleman. What more can you ask? Josephine, I shall insist that you do not refuse so advantageous an offer. In our position it would be worse than folly to do so."</p> 
               <p>During this recital, Josephine had sat with her hands tightly clasped, listening patiently to every word. As her mother finished speaking, she said: "Oh, you cannot add this last sorrow to my already unhappy life. You surely would not force me to commit; that worst of all perjury-of going before the Holy Altar and saying that I loved, when I did not? No, mother, I would be a wanderer and a beggar rather than commit such a crime, and; have such a sin-stained soul. You saw but a few moments ago the glorious ous rays of the sun, gilding the earth with its beauty, and so there also rests over my wrecked life the faint glimmer of past happiness. But if this unholy union was urged upon me, then even that faint radiance would pass away, and my poor life would be left as utterly dark and dreary as the setting of the sun has left the earth. Why does Mr. Sanford urge this matter? He has spoken to me on the subject, and I told him that if he cared for me he would never mention it again, and I supposed that he never would."</p> 
               <p>"My dear child," replied Mr. Templeton, "I shall never force or urge you to do an action to which you are so bitterly opposed. But perhaps you may live to see the day when you will wish that you had taken a father's advice, for I can see nothing before you now but a life of poverty and privation, There is no prospect that I can ever attain another fortune; and we have only advised you for what we sincerely think is for your own good and happiness."</p> 
               <p>"I know you and mamma have always been so kind and indulgent that you would not wish me to do anything that you did not think would contribute to my happiness; and on this subject of marriage you cannot think or feel as I do. Even if I am destined to be poor the rest of my life, I shall at least have a clear conscience, and that is better than to possess the whole world with a guilty one. I would willingly spend my whole life in toiling for you; but to gain riches by committing a deadly sin, that I can never do, and if you love me you will never ask me to do so," she said, tears filling her eyes.</p> 
               <p>"My dear child," said her mother, taking a seat near her and putting her arms around her, "I am very sorry that we have said so much as we have. I did not think that you had so firmly kept your resolution-never to love again; but I promise you, my dear daughter, that we will never trouble you by mentioning the subject, for you are, and have always been, the best and kindest child ever given to any parents, and your pure mind abhors anything where there is even a shadow of deceit."</p> 
               <p>"My dear," said Mr. Templeton, coming near his daughter and kissing her, "I fully endorse all that your mother has said; and I will give Horace his answer in accordance with the wish you have expressed, but it will be a great blow to him, for I know that he loves you devotedly. Now let what has passed this evening be forgotten, and in the future we will live for each other's happiness, as we have done in the past; and we shall have the comfort of knowing, that our dear daughter will always be with us to cheer our old age, as she has always been the brightest object in the midst of our greatest prosperity or darkest adversity."</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC6608-00000032"/> 
               <head>CHAPTER XIX.</head> 
               <head type="sub">HORACE SANFORD'S DISAPPOINTMENT-HE LEAVES FOR EUROPE.</head> 
               <p>THE Sanford mansion was filled with guests, and every amusement one can have in the country was enjoyed to fullest advantage. A gay party of six, on horseback, came dashing up the broad avenue at full speed. They stopped before the broad piazza and dismounted. The grooms led away the horses; the rest of the party had now entered the house; but Castina lingered on the piazza, and, turning to Horace, who was beside her, said:</p> 
               <p>"Horace, what is the matter? I fear you are not well. I surely never saw you looking so dejected. You are; usually the gayest of all, but this morning you have spoken hardly a word. I fear this Northern climate does not agree with you, but it does with me; for my part I never felt better in my life."</p> 
               <p>She looked a perfect picture of health and happiness; her dark riding dress and hat being extremely becoming, and setting off her fine figure and handsome face to full advantage.</p> 
               <p>"I am not ill," he replied; "and if I appear sad, it is indeed very reasonable that I should feel so when I contemplate that this is my last week at home I intend to sail for Europe next Wednesday, and I shall probably not return to this country for several years. You know that my father has promised me that I might go abroad, and I have chosen this time to go."</p> 
               <p>"Why, how you surprise me! Yon must have changed your mind very suddenly, for it was only last week that I heard you planning a grand hunting party that you were to have in the autumn," said Castina, looking at him in astonishment, and there was a slight expression of disappointment in her dark eyes.</p> 
               <p>"I acknowledge that I have changed my mind since then. I dislike to leave my friends here; yet I hope that my absence will not interfere with their enjoyment."</p> 
               <p>"We shall miss you very much, for we shall then have no one to get up those delightful excursions that we have all enjoyed so well; and why do you intend remaining so long in Europe? Do you go to travel or study?"</p> 
               <p>"Partly for both, for I should like to complete my university education there. I wish to do that which will the most completely occupy my thoughts and time."</p> 
               <p>I should imagine that it would be exceedingly stupid being in a foreign country alone. I am sure that I should prefer the company of some friends if I were going.</p> 
               <p>"You forget that my mother has a cousin living at Berlin, who has often urged us to come there, promising that they will make our visit as delightful as possible."</p> 
               <p>"Yes, I had forgotten that, but I remember now hearing Ella speak of her, I see that you are well provided for, and I hope that your proposed residence abroad will be a source of great profit and enjoyment to you," she replied, with a smile, and then hastily entered the house and passed lightly up the broad staircase to her room. When there, her expression changed to one of anger and indignation.</p> 
               <p>"Why has Horace Sanford thus trifled with me? and now leaves for Europe without, saying a word. I love Horace, but he shall never have the satisfaction of knowing that I do. No, indeed; I will appear gayer and happier than ever. I am not one of those tender hearted young ladies, that can never love but once and pine away or die, if they happen to be disappointed. There are many young gentlemen that would make equally as brilliant a match as to marry Horace Sanford. I am very thankful that there is not an over stock of sentimentality in my composition. I would not marry a poor man if he were an Apollo Belvidere."</p> 
               <p>Such were her thoughts, as she selected one of her richest and most becoming dresses, in which to make her appearance that evening.</p> 
               <p>After dinner the whole company were assembled in the large drawing rooms, when Horace's intended departure was announced to the guests. All were greatly surprised, and regretted it very much.</p> 
               <p>"Do you intend going alone?" inquired an elderly lady of Horace, at lie same time casting an inquiring glance at Castina, who was apparently in the best of spirits.</p> 
               <p>"Certainly," he replied, "but I have a relative there whom I intend to pay a short visit."</p> 
               <p>Did I understand that you were to remain abroad several years?" said the old lady, with another glance at Castina.</p> 
               <p>"Yes, madam, that is my intention," he replied.</p> 
               <p>Then the conversation ended, and the old lady fell into a deep study. The day of departure had at last arrived, and Horace was taking his last farewells of the friends who had assembled on the piazza to bid him adieu, and wishing for him a prosperous voyage. His mother and sisters were in tears, and Mr. Sanford tried to conceal his emotion as best he could.</p> 
               <p>No one knew the real cause of their son's sudden departure but Mr. and Mrs. Sanford, to whom he had imparted the secret of Josephine's refusal. He told them frankly that for that cause he did not like to remain there; but if he went away and had a change of scene and other things to occupy his thoughts, he would try and forget her.</p> 
               <p>"But, mother, my last request is, that you will all do what you can to make it pleasant for the Templetons during your residence here. Josephine no doubt has good reasons for this refusal; and let your conduct towards her and her family be the same as if this never had happened. Josephine is a beautiful and noble girl, and could never be induced to do anything that she did not conscientiously think was right."</p> 
               <p>But the knowledge of their son's disappointment only increased their grief, yet they hoped that travel and change of scene would have the desired effect.</p> 
               <p>Horace shook hands cordially with all, but last of all with Castina, on whose handsome face there rested a shade of sadness, notwithstanding all<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC6608-00000033"/> her attempts to appear otherwise. Then he affectionately kissed his father, mother, and sisters, and stepped quickly into the carriage, and was borne rapidly away. For a few days after his departure there seemed an undefined feeling of sadness and gloom resting over the house, and one by one the guests began taking their departure for the gay and fashionable watering places; but among the first to go was Castina and her father, and many whispered privately the reason why they had done so.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER XX.</head> 
               <head type="sub">DESCRIPTION OF ELVA CASTLE-EARL ELVA INSISTS UPON HIS SON, LORD ALFRED, MARRYING-SUDDEN DEATH OF THE EARL.</head> 
               <p>IN one of the most beautiful counties in England stands the magnificent Elva Castle, which had been for centuries the residence of the Earls of Elva. The architecture of the castle showed plainly that it dated back to the sixteenth century; but there had, with the succeeding years, been new and large additions made to it, and its appearance was now grand and stately in the extreme. The park which surrounded the castle was correspondingly grand and covered an immense amount of ground; some of which had been left in its natural state, the rest being in a high state of cultivation. One could drive for miles on the broad avenues, which were completely shaded on either side by magnificent old trees, occasionally startling a timid deer, which on perceiving you, would dart away into the thicket. As you neared the castle there were several magnificent fountains, composed of exquisitely carved marble figures, huge serpents, and immense vases carved in fanciful designs.</p> 
               <p>Throughout the extensive grounds were interspersed the most beautiful rare flowers and shrubs; and trees taken from every part of the continent, that would grow in that climate, had been planted there.</p> 
               <p>The interior of the castle corresponded entirely with the beauty and grandeur of its surroundings. You enter the stately hall by massive oaken doors, which are elaborately carved; the floor of the hall is tiled in mosaic work of different colored marbles; the ceiling being very high and of carved oak, and on the walls were hung on either side the portraits of their ancestors. The broad stairway led from the centre of the hall, being entirely composed of the most beautiful variegated Italian marble. At the base of the stairway were two beautiful statues of the same material, each bearing, in an uplifted hand, a bracket filled with wax tapers. On the main floor were three spacious drawing rooms, each opening into the other: the first room was furnished in blue and gold, the second in delicate buff, and the third in crimson. The floors were covered with Turkey carpets; all the windows and doors being hung with heavy silk drapery, corresponding with the colors of each room, and the walls were set with immense mirrors, which reflected their beauty and richness. Then the grand library, the walls of which were almost entirely covered with books which had been collected for ages and were almost priceless. There were also busts on porphyry pedestals, of some of England's kings and queens, and some of her greatest statesmen and poets; and the richly carved heavy oaken furniture corresponded well with the stately room. The music room, the large dining hall, and the breakfast room were all fitted up with an equal degree of elegance. The gallery of paintings was justly considered one of the finest in the United Kingdom, and the statuary was by the greatest artists, not only of our own day, but of the generations past. The upper portion of the castle was divided into suites of three rooms each, consisting of a parlor, sleeping apartment, arid dressing room; and were furnished and adorned in a most luxurious and beautiful manner. Nothing was wanting that wealth could procure. The stables belonging to the castle were very large, and no expense had been spared to make them as near perfection as possible, and they contained a stud of thoroughbred horses. The young Lord was fond of the chase, and prided himself on having the finest pack of both deer and fox hounds in the country.</p> 
               <p>The Earl of Elva was a stern, haughty man, of sixty-five; he was as <emph>straight</emph> as an arrow, even at his age; his hair and side whiskers were almost white; he had cold gray eyes and florid complexion; was rather inclined to embonpoint, and was in every respect a fine representative of a well preserved English gentleman, At this time he was in the library, and had taken a seat before the large oaken table, on which were lying some parchments which he began examining. While he was thus engaged, Alfred, his heir and only child, entered the room. He was a man a little over the medium height, Very straight like his father, and eminently handsome; his hair, moustache, and side whiskers were light; his eyes blue, and complexion very fair, inclined to be pale. He was a man about forty years of age. As he entered the room, the Earl looked up from his parchments, saying:</p> 
               <p>"Are you going out this evening, Alfred?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, I had intended to, do you not remember that I accepted an invitation to attend a dinner party given by my young friend, Lord Delmore?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes," said the Earl, "I recollect now," and he began again examining the documents which were deeds of property.</p> 
               <p>"Then," he continued, "Alfred I am growing old, and I cannot die happy, without seeing you married, as becomes your station: when I look at these deeds and consider the immense amount of property I own, besides this castle, and the park, which has been the pride of our ancestors, and that you are the last representative of the proud family name of Elverton, it makes me miserable. Think of this domain passing to distant relatives, who do not even bear our name, for I have the misfortune of being an only child, as you are, and my nearest relative is my cousin, the Lady Eleanor, to whom my property will descend at your death, in case you do not marry.<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC6608-00000034"/> There is hardly a lady in the realm who would not consider the offer of your hand an honor. Are there not beautiful and accomplished ladies enough among the nobility of England, for you to choose from? You would be far happier married, than you are now. Indeed, if I am obliged thus to urge you, and if you do not understand the importance of what I say, I will contract an alliance for you, and then you must obey me."</p> 
               <p>"There is no power on earth to compel me to marry," he replied, in a manly tone, at the same time rising. "I beg of you not to allow yourself to become so excited on this subject, I have obeyed you in everything during my life, but this request I must now, and shall ever, refuse to comply with, Why do you refer to that often argued subject, for it always ends in discomfort to us both, for my resolution is irrevocable. It is now time for me to go to Lord Delmore's, and I hope you will dismiss this subject from your mind," saying this, he left the room.</p> 
               <p>As the door closed, the Earl stopped, in his walk, and with his hands tightly clenched, said in a voice of anger:</p> 
               <p>"I could almost disinherit such a disobedient and willful son."</p> 
               <p>The next morning the valet knocked at the door of the Earl's sleeping room, but received no answer.</p> 
               <p>"His Lordship sleeps very late this morning," said he, and yawning, walked away. About half an hour afterwards, Lord Alfred met his father's valet in the corridor, and inquired of him, if the Earl had risen yet. The man replied:</p> 
               <p>"No, my Lord, I have knocked at the door several times, but received no answer."</p> 
               <p>"That is very strange," he said, looking at his watch, "it is now eleven o'clock. I will go to his room myself."</p> 
               <p>When at the door of his father's room, he knocked loudly, but received no answer, then he slowly and carefully opened the door, and entered; at first he thought that he must be sleeping very soundly; or, perhaps, was ill, as he lay so motionless, but as he approached the bed and bent over the inanimate form of his father, a cry of horror escaped him; he covered his face with his hands, and fell heavily back, he would have fallen to the floor had not the valet, who was standing near him, sprang forward, and caught him in his arms and assisted him to a chair.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, my father is dead, my dear father is dead!"</p> 
               <p>Tears came to his eyes, and for the time was so completely overcome, that he could hardly speak or move. In the meantime the valet rang the bell, which brought the servants to the room in a few minutes. The news had spread throughout the castle, that the Earl was dead: everyone was in the greatest excitement and grief, The doctors were quickly summoned to see if they could tell the nature of the disease of which the Earl had died. Lady Eleanor who had resided at the castle since the death of the Countess of Elva, was summoned from her boudoir. She came, quickly, trembling from head to foot, scarcely believing the dreadful news she had heard; and to satisfy herself went quickly to the bed-side; but when she beheld the cold deathly face, she uttered a loud cry, and soon left the room.</p> 
               <p>As the excitement, consequent upon the sudden announcement of the Earl's death died away, a dreadful gloom came over all. The servants stepped noiselessly about the house, and spoke only in whispers. At last, when the first sharp agony of feeling was somewhat over, Lord Alfred rose, and approached his father's bedside, saying:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, father, can it be that you have gone. You who were the noblest and best of men, to be thus suddenly taken from us; you never did that which you did not sincerely think for my good. I never did but one action without your consent, and never refused to comply with but one request, and that was what it was impossible for me to do. Oh, my beloved, long lost darling Clara, your dear spirit is the witness of the truth of these words, and through the mercy of Heaven, may our darling child, for whom my heart has yearned all these dreary years, be restored in safety to her father's arms."</p> 
               <p>It was not long before the physicians, who had been summoned arrived, and they pronounced that the Earl had died of apoplexy.</p> 
               <p>The news quickly spread throughout the estate, that the Earl of Elva was dead, and there was much mourning among the tenantry: for, although a very stern man, he had always been kind to the poor, and not one could remember a cruel act that he had ever done; and every one loved and reverenced him.</p> 
               <p>Preparations were being made for the funeral. The castle was draped in mourning, and the servants in mourning habiliments, moved noiselessly about.</p> 
               <p>The day of the funeral arrived. The body of the late Earl lay in a magnificent casket covered with the rarest flowers. There was a large assemblage of the greatest peers, nobles and gentry of the realm. The hearse drawn by four black horses, fully caparisoned in black, and a long line of carriages stood before the entrance of the castle. The tenantry had gathered on either side of the broad avenue: they had thus remained stationed for a long time, when at last the funeral cortege began to move; and as the hearse which bore the remains of their late master, slowly passed, many a cry and moan broke forth on the still air, and they turned tearfully away.</p> 
               <p>Three months after his father's death, the young Earl of Elva began making preparations for his departure for America. Lady Eleanor had been left in charge of the castle, and on a beautiful day in midsummer, he left England for America: and, Providence permitting, would soon again set foot on the shores of the United States. He felt full of hope, rejoicing that he was so soon to take to his heart, never to be separated again, his child on whom all his love was centered.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC6608-00000035"/> 
               <head>CHAPTER XXI.</head> 
               <head type="sub">THE EARL OF ELVA'S ARRIVAL IN AMERICA-DISCOVERS THE WHEREABOUTS OF HIS DAUGHTER JOSEPHINE.</head> 
               <p>WILLIAM and Ellen Ghent were seated in their rather pretentious parlor, at M--. The house was quite large and handsome: and the furniture rich and elegant. Mrs. Ghent was a fine looking woman, and appeared to be a lady, yet there was a sinister expression about her face, that was very disagreeable to an observing eye. William Ghent had large and rather coarse features: black hair and eyes, and wore a full beard, Among business men it was well known that he was not over scrupulous, in regard to many transactions. Ellen Ghent had sat for a long time as if in deep thought. Then she looked up to her husband saying:</p> 
               <p>"I have heard to-day, accidentally, that Jane Elstone, our old servant, died nearly a year and a half ago at S--, in great poverty, is it not strange that I should not have heard; of it before. She was the only one who knew anything about the babe and the money, excepting ourselves; and I feel quite relieved to think that we are the only ones who possess any knowledge of that transaction."</p> 
               <p>"Is it really so," said Mr. Ghent, well I must soy that I do not feel extremely sorry: for I think as you do on the subject."</p> 
               <p>"Then the conversation ended; for it was not a very pleasant topic to them, and each were entirely occupied with their own reflections. There was a knock at the door, and the servant-announced that there was a gentleman in the reception room, who wished to see both Mr. and Mrs. Ghent. They both rose quickly and went directly to the room. The gentleman rose as they entered, saying:</p> 
               <p>"Perhaps yon do not recognize me now, after the lapse of so many years, yet I owe you a debt of gratitude which I can never repay. I am the same young English gentleman, Alfred Elverton, who, eighteen years ago, left in your charge my infant daughter, Josephine Eloise."</p> 
               <p>As he spoke these words, Ellen Ghent caught her husband convulsively by the arm, as if for strength and support: both their faces turned as pale as death; their eyes seemed fixed and glazed, as they stared at him with a meaningless expression: neither of them speaking a word, both seemed completely stupefied, through astonishment and fear.</p> 
               <p>"What does this mean," cried the Earl, in a tone of great excitement, "where is my daughter? tell me instantly. Why do you stare at me in this blank amazement without making any explanation."</p> 
               <p>He approached nearer the awe-stricken couple, his face turning deathly ly pale, as the dreadful fear came over him that perhaps by their silence and strange look, something might have happened to his darling.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, sir, have mercy upon us," at last cried the terrified woman, "have pity upon us; we never supposed that we should see you again."</p> 
               <p>"Wretch," cried the Earl, unable to control his exasperated feelings longer, "where is my daughter? what have you done with her? Oh, my God can it be that she is dead!"</p> 
               <p>"Tears came to his eyes, and he wept like a child, for his hopes had hitherto been so bright, and the prospect that he was so soon to meet his dear daughter: the glorious happiness of holding her in his arms, and telling her that he was her own dear father, and that she was the future Countess of Elva, instead of being a simple village maiden. All this he had pictured in his mind; but now this dreadful disappointment; this sudden revulsion of feeling, was more than he could bear, and he seemed completely unnerved by so much grief.</p> 
               <p>William Ghent had sufficiently recovered his senses, to say, in a trembling voice,</p> 
               <p>"She is not dead! sir, she is not dead!"</p> 
               <p>"Oh, thank God, thank God! you say my daughter lives?" he cried, "I can ask no more, but tell me where she is. Oh this suspense is torture." The wild words and actions of the Earl, and the agony of suspense which he suffered, at last seemed to rouse the woman from her lethargic state of fright and bewilderment, and the gasped out in broken words:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, sir, sit down. We were not so much to blame."</p> 
               <p>"No more excuses, woman, proceed with what you have to say; tell me of my daughter," he said in a commanding tone, which once heard, no' one would dare to disobey.</p> 
               <p>"Be patient, sir, and I will, I will. You left the babe here after its mother died," as she said this, a shadow of great sorrow passed over his face, and he struggled to remain calm. "Well, you know, that we then had three small children, and the thousand pounds you left for the babe's support, was just what we wanted to pay a debt; we had no means to raise that amount of money, without sacrificing our property, and if we had done that, my husband's credit would have been ruined. So when you had gone away, we thought that you were only some reckless young Englishman; and that after you had left the country, you would never think of the child again." "Wretch," cried the Earl, here interrupting her, "by what right did you thus interpret my character."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, we had none," replied the woman, "but do not speak so, you frighten me so, I cannot say a word. The child would have been a great expense "to us, and I had all I could do to take care of my own. We did not think that you would ever send the four-hundred pounds a year which you promised to do, and which you have done ever since. Well," continued the woman, "our servant, Jane Elstone, was the only person in the world that knew that you left the child here; so she had to be in the secret, for you said that you did not wish the child to know that we were not her real parents, until the time that you came and claimed her, which we supposed would never be. We knew of good honest old people, James and Martha Jackson, who lived a mile from the village; so, the next night, we dressed the babe, put her carefully in a large<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC6608-00000036"/> basket, warmly covered, and at midnight we went to their cottage and laid the basket on their doorstep; so that they might find it early in the morning. We knew no harm would happen to her, and that they would take care of her."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, hard-hearted fiends that you are, to devise and execute such villainy, who would have supposed people capable of such wickedness. Is this my just punishment for leaving you my darling, to the care of strangers- and not taking you with me, even if my father had disinherited me and turned me from his house as he had threatened to do, if I married without his knowledge and consent; but I thought the money I paid you, ample to insure her protection, support and education. Tell me, quickly, where are these people now, and did they discover the child?" said the Earl, in great agitation, and it seemed, sometimes, as if he could hardly endure to listen to the woman's recital.</p> 
               <p>"Yes," she continued, trembling with fear: "the next morning they found the basket and the babe, and took good care of the child. A young lady in the village, Miss Hilton, saw the child, and thought her so pretty, that she induced a lady, Mrs. Templeton, whose babe had just died, to take this one, and adopt it as her own.</p> 
               <p>The Templetons were quite wealthy people, and Josephine was the only child they had. When she was seven years of age, Mr. Templeton lost his property, and the family removed to B--, where he soon regained his fortune, and became far more wealthy than he was before. They gave Josephine every advantage of education. After living there nine years, misfortune again overtook them, and since that time, they have been living in obscurity at the village of S--."</p> 
               <p>As she finished speaking, the Earl inquired:</p> 
               <p>"How were you informed of all that happened to this family?"</p> 
               <p>"Why," she replied, "Miss Hilton, who lives in the village, has always corresponded with them, for they feel very grateful to her, for conferring so great a benefit on them."</p> 
               <p>"Where are the people now, on whose door-step you left the babe?"</p> 
               <p>"Oh, sir, they both died some years ago."</p> 
               <p>"I am very sorry for that, for I wish that I could have rewarded them for their humanity and kindness to my child. It was by the description of others, then, that you were enabled to reply to my inquiries concerning Josephine, and give me such accounts of her great beauty, brilliant accomplishments and loveliness of character. Where is this Miss Hilton? I wish to see her immediately."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, sir, she lives on the next street to this. Mr. Ghent, would be happy to show you the way; but please! do not expose us, sir: it would ruin us if you did."</p> 
               <p>"Ask no favors of me, madam. I can conceive no just punishment, for the great crime you have committed; but I thank God, that through His protection, all has been so well with my child, for she might have died; there is no telling what misfortunes might have overtaken her, if she had not providentially fallen into such good hands as she did. Suppose she had been left with those old people, and they had died, my darling, would have been left a wanderer, in the? world. Oh, it is too horrible to think of. A just God will punish you, for your wickedness, as you deserve."</p> 
                
               <p>"We will pay you back the money, sir, if it takes the last cent," exclaimed Mr. Ghent.</p> 
               <p>"No," cried the Earl, "I would not take such sin-stained money. Show me immediately to Miss Hilton's house."</p> 
               <p>"Yes, sir, I will, I will:" and without another word being spoken, they left the house, and entered the carriage standing at the door, and were driven rapidly to her house, where the Earl, and William Ghent, parted company forever.</p> 
               <p>When the Earl, had entered the house, he made know to Miss Hilton, who he was, and his errand;' and when he had done so, she burst into tears, and then would laugh outright. He could hardly understand her actions.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, I am so happy, now; I never was so happy in my life before. I have always loved Josephine so much, and the poor darling has had such a troubled life. She has been almost heart-broken, and all the hope of her poor life has been almost crushed out the, has had sorrow: upon sorrow, yet she has" borne up so bravely under all, she has proved herself almost a saint."</p> 
               <p>"Explain to me, madam: I have heard nothing of this before," cried the Earl, in excitement. "Oh, where is all this trouble to end?"</p> 
               <p>"Oh, sir, do you not know that her father, was the same as robbed, by wicked men, and they were reduced to the greatest poverty, and in the midst of all that, her heart was broken, by the deception of a young English nobleman, to whom she was engaged, and whom she loved with her whole heart. When he knew of her father's misfortunes, he cruelly deserted her, without a word of explanation. There is no harm, in telling you this, for you are her father, and should know all.</p> 
               <p>"What was that man's name? Do you know?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, his name was Lord Del more; Herbert was the first name"</p> 
               <p>"Madam, it cannot be possible, he could not be capable of such villainy. Oh, shall I lose my reason, with the revelations and disappointments of this day?</p> 
               <p>"Then you are acquainted with him, sir?"</p> 
               <p>"Certainly, and I have always considered him one of my best friends, and that he possessed the noblest character: there must be some mistake; but if it be true, that he has thus trifled with my daughter, and added to her afflictions, he shall sadly repent it, Tell me inhere of my daughter."</p> 
               <p>"Well they had to leave their beautiful home, and went to the small village of S--, to live, where they have merely the necessities of life. They are very poor. Mr. Templeton receiving only a thousand dollars a year for his services. I offered to let them have what little money I had, but they would not accept of it: Now, her dear father has come to claim her, she will never want again: I always thought that so beautiful a person as Josephine, must be of noble parentage, and now it has proved true. And I am so happy."</p> 
               <p>"You shall be rewarded for the great kindness you have shown my daughter. I feel utterly confounded with what I have heard this day." Then he made known to her the part that the Ghents had taken, and the money that he had regularly gent, for his daughter's support."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, the dreadful creatures, I never<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC6608-00000037"/> did like them. I always thought that they were bad people."</p> 
               <p>"My heart is sick with disappointment, everything being so different from what I had expected. I must now hasten to my darling, and relieve her of her suffering," said the Earl, rising. "May God speed you on your journey, and tell Josephine that my heart rejoices with her, in her new found happiness." The Earl then proceeded directly to S--.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>CHAPTER XXII.</head> 
               <head type="sub">THE FIRST MEETING OF THE FATHER OF JOSEPHINE WITH HIS DAUGHTER.</head> 
               <p>IT has been nearly two years, since we last saw Josephine; and the shades of sorrow, are drawn deeper over her beautiful face, it has a look of hopeless resignation. Yet, she never made others unhappy, by vain repinings, on the contrary, she always appeared cheerful, and whatever she suffered, was in secret, A rustic seat had been constructed, under one of the magnificent elms, on which she and her mother were seated; and Josephine was reading aloud. She was dressed in pure white, and looked very lovely. Their attention was attracted by seeing a rapidly driven carriage approach and stop before the cottage, from which a fine looking gentleman alighted, and hastily approached the house.</p> 
               <p>"My dear, we had better go to the house now, for that must be some one, that "has called to see us: although I have no recollection of ever seeing him before; and he is evidently in great haste."</p> 
               <p>"Yes," replied Josephine, and they rose and walked slowly towards the cottage. As they entered the house, old Hannah met them at the door, saying, that a gentleman wished to see Mrs. Templeton. She entered the parlor alone, and the Earl of Elva rose to meet her.</p> 
               <p>"Madam," he said, "I have come here to cause you both joy, and sorrow, I owe to you that which I value far more than my own life, and that is the life of my daughter."</p> 
               <p>As he said these words, Mrs. Templeton's face became livid, for the thought, in an instant, flashed across her mind, that this must then be Josephine's real father; and that he had come to take her from them, and she sank half fainting into a chair.</p> 
               <p>"Are you our darling Josephine's father?" She cried, in amazement and fear.</p> 
               <p>"Yes," he replied, "I am Alfred Elverton, Earl of Elva, and after the lapse of all these years have at last come to claim my daughter, and can I see her now? And then I will explain all. It seems as if I could endure no longer, this dreadful suspense of being separated from her. Oh, I must take her to my arms, and tell her that I am her long lost father. There is no reward, which it is in my power to give, that you shall not have for the service you have rendered me, in caring so fondly for my poor child."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, do not speak of reward, she has been a greater blessing to us, than we have been to her," she replied, weeping violently.</p> 
               <p>"I will go and tell her immediately, although it breaks my heart to do so, Yet, I must."</p> 
               <p>As she said this, she left the room. When she found Josephine, she said:</p> 
               <p>"My dear, come with me; there is a gentleman who wishes to see you; he is a near relative, and the dearest friend you have in the world, excepting those whose name you bear."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, mother, what is the matter-has anything happened? Why do you weep so?" cried Josephine, greatly alarmed and pained to gee her mother thus agitated, and not knowing the cause.</p> 
               <p>"Come with me, my dear, and all will be explained," she replied, taking Josephine by the hand and they entered the room.</p> 
               <p>For an instant the Earl gazed upon her, then he caught her to his heart, crying:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, my child, my child!" He wept, and spoke not a word for several moments, being completely overcome by emotion.</p> 
               <p>Then he drew her to a seat, and putting his arms about her, kissed her repeatedly. All this time Josephine had been utterly bewildered, not understanding and hardly knowing what to think or how to act. Then the Earl exclaimed:</p> 
               <p>"As you look to-day, my daughter, so did your dear sainted mother look nineteen years ago, and it was her great beauty that won my heart, and I married her at all hazards. My darling, I am your father."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, is this possible? how can it be? I do not understand-do I dream?" said Josephine, looking pale and terrified.</p> 
               <p>"My dear, it is true. You were only our adopted daughter; we took you when you were an infant, and I never knew till now who your real parents were, "replied Mrs. Templeton, through her tears.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, father, father!" cried Josephine, throwing her arms around his neck and kissing him, burst into tears. He drew her closer to him, laid her fair head close to his heart, and gently stroking her beautiful golden hair, said:</p> 
               <p>"My darling child, to be thus restored to you again in safety, is the happiest hour of my life. Through all these long years I have waited and prayed for this hour. Oh, my darling, can you forgive me for thus neglecting you so long? You will learn to love me, and we will thank God together for his marvellous goodness. Now, my child, I will explain the mystery of your life. My mother, died two years previous to my coming to America. I had a great desire to travel, arid my father indulged my inclinations to the fullest extent. "I had traveled extensively on the Continent, and on my return to England, I requested him to allow me to visit America, proposing to be absent for at least several months, and perhaps a year. He reluctantly consented, and I sailed for the United States, accompanied only by my valet. I was naturally fond of adventure, and liked constantly changing scenes. I was consequently in high spirits when we landed in this country, of which I had heard so much. I was fond of nature and fine scenery,<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC6608-00000038"/> and was informed that the surrounding country about the village of H-- was remarkably beautiful, wild and romantic in its appearance, and that it offered splendid scenery for an artist-for I never traveled without my sketch-book, and I prided myself on being no inconsiderable artist. The scenes which I had sketched while on the Continent had been greatly praised, and I intended to pursue this delightful study in America. I accordingly leisurely journeyed until we arrived at H--, which fully answered the descriptions that I had heard of it and my expectations. To the North and East were an immense chain of bills', as the villagers called them, but I should think that they could, more properly be called mountains, and as far as the eye could reach they rose, peak on peak, until nothing could, be seen but what appeared to be a dark blue mist. I was delighted with the place, and at once decided to spend some time there.</p> 
               <p>"It was there I first saw your dear mother. I thought her the most beautiful woman that I had ever seen. I soon made her acquaintance, which only increased my love, for I found that both her refined mind and sweet disposition were as beautiful as the loveliness of her face. She was an orphan, and then living with distant relatives. I resolved to marry her, and obtained her consent. I knew that it would be imprudent to marry my darling Clara publicly, for if my father had heard that I had married without his knowledge, and any one who was not of noble family, he "would have disinherited me, as he had many, times threatened to do. He had vehemently urged me to marry the Lady Elizabeth, which request I had peremptorily refused to comply with. I explained all this to Clara, and she at once saw the ruin it would bring on us both to have a public marriage; therefore, a private one was agreed to. We went to a neighboring village, where the pastor of the little parish church performed the marriage ceremony at the rectory, and Mrs. Vereman, his wife, was the only witness. When that beautiful girl became my wife I felt that I was the happiest man in the world, and I became so fond of her I could have endured poverty or any hardship, rather than be separated from her. We journeyed from place to place, both being perfectly happy. Everything looked brighter than it ever had before, now that I had her fine mind and delightful company to enjoy and appreciate with me.</p> 
               <p>"These, my darling, were the happiest days of my life but now that I am restored to you, who are so much I like her, it will recall those happy days again. I had now been absent from England a year, and my father; had begun to write me urgent letters to return. I made many excuses for delay, and he at length demanded my immediate return. To leave my darling Clara was impossible. You, my dear, were born on the second of March, and it was in the latter part of that month that I received the letter. I therefore resolved to go to England, taking my wife and child with me; but to keep you there privately until such time as I could act for myself. Your mother had been an invalid since your birth; yet, we concluded that by May, when the weather would be more favorable, that she would be able to travel, and such was the doctor's opinion therefore, I replied to ray father's letter that I would return to England in that month; but, even under the best medical skill and the tenderest care, her health rapidly failed from day to day, and on the thirtieth of April your mother died."</p> 
               <p>As he said this his voice trembled with emotion, and he hastily brushed the tears from his eyes.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, father," said Josephine through her tears, "then my dear mother is dead. She surely is an angel in heaven, and has watched over me all these years, and now sees our happiness in thus being restored in safety to each other, and her holy spirit rejoices with us."</p> 
               <p>"My darling, it must be so; she was an angel upon the earth, she surely must be one in Leaven," replied the Earl.</p> 
               <p>There was silence for a few moments, and slightly overcoming his emotion, he continued:</p> 
               <p>"You were left an infant in nay arms, only two months old. I was completely overwhelmed with grief at your mother's death; I did not care to live, now she was gone. I wished that I had been taken instead of her; it seemed as if I could not live and endure such sorrow, for no man ever loved a woman more than I did her. Then I looked upon you, and thought, I surely have my darling child to care for, and I must live for her; she shall be my only care now. After a great deal of thought, I concluded that the best plan I could adopt, both, for my child's good and my own, was to leave you in America with some good family, and pay them liberally for taking care of you, and to bring you up as their own child, until such a time as I should come and claim you, for I did not want your childish mind tormented with the thought of not knowing who your parents were. It was impossible for me to explain the reason for leaving you here; therefore as little was said on the subject as possible, excepting that I gave the directions that I wished followed put with regard to your education. Such a family as I was in search of with whom to leave you, I at last found. After making many inquiries and many anxious researches, I was at last satisfied; and to the family with whom I left you, I gave one thousand pounds, besides agreeing to send regularly, every year, four hundred pounds for your support, and would have doubled the amount had it been necessary. All was arranged satisfactorily; and I felt quite relieved on being so fortunate as to find so good a temporary home, as I thought, for my child. It caused me the greatest sorrow to part with you, yet I knew that it must be done, and one bright morning in May I gave my precious darling into the charge of Mr. and Mrs. William Ghent, kissing you again and again."</p> 
               <p>"What!" cried Josephine, starting in surprise. "Oh, mother-for I must call you mother, even now, for you have indeed been the kindest of all people in the world td me-that explains the words of the dying woman, Jane Elstone; she was trying to explain this mystery to me, and if she tad lived would have done so."</p> 
               <p>"Have you then seen Jane Elstone? She was a servant in their house when I left you there a babe. What I intended for your greatest good, might, but for a providential deliverance, have proved your ruin; for it was they who the next night after my departure laid you in a basket on the doorstep of an old couple named Jackson who are now both dead; and it was Mrs. Templeton who through the persuasion of Miss Hilton, took you from their cottage and adopted you as their own child. But instead of being Josephine<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC6608-00000039"/> sephine Eloise Templeton, your real name is Josephine Eloise Elverton, the future Countess of Elva," concluded the Earl, fondly kissing again and again the beautiful face of his beloved daughter.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, father, can this be true; and how can I be sufficiently thankful for being blest with so much happiness? But where is my dear mother buried?"</p> 
               <p>"She is buried near her native village, and we will go to her grave and weep together for the dear departed one."</p> 
               <p>All this time Mrs. Templeton had sat almost convulsed with grief at the thought of their separation, yet rejoicing that Josephine was delivered from so much sorrow, and restored to so noble a father. Josephine had grown to be almost a part of her existence, and it seemed that she could not part with her now. Josephine had observed her deep grief, and came and put her arms about her and. kissed her, saying:</p> 
               <p>"Dearest mother, do not weep, and do not think that my new-found joy has caused my forgetfulness of you or my dear foster father, for it has not; do you think that the love of my whole life can change in an instant? I shall always love you both, the dearest of any one on earth, excepting my own dear father."</p> 
               <p>"Mrs. Templeton," said the Earl, "do not weep, thinking that you will now be obliged to be separated from Josephine, for it will not be so. The kindness and love that you have shown the poor little foundling, as you thought her, shall not go unrewarded. Both you and your husband shall go to England with us, and henceforth reside at the castle."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, thank you-thank you; you are the best and noblest of fathers!" cried Josephine, unable to restrain the joy she felt as she heard his kind words.</p> 
               <p>"And, mother, then you will be so happy, too, for you have had such heavy burdens to bear; your life has been so full of sorrow and bitter disappointment; but now, through the mercy of God, we will all be so happy again."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, this is too much happiness-never to be separated from you. Oh, my child, my child! may I always call you so?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, mother, always."</p> 
               <p>"I know how much you love Josephine," said Mrs. Templeton; "yet it is impossible for you now to comprehend how much, you have to be proud of, and love in her; for even when she herself was completely heartbroken with sorrow, she always had a hopeful word to cheer those who were likewise afflicted. When we were reduced to poverty, and had to leave our beautiful home and come to this place, at the same time having had added to these afflictions the sorrow and disappointment of having been basely deceived by a wicked man, she bore all with the spirit of a martyr. After the first sharp pang was over, I never heard her utter another sigh, or another word escape her, complaining of her unhappy lot. One could not be dispirited and mournful, when she was present to cheer. If it had not have been for her, my days would have been utterly hopeless and sad; but her brave, hopeful spirit has, in a measure, been imparted to us, and we have passed the days of our adversity in comparative happiness and contentment. She has been tried in the furnace of affliction, and has come forth as pure and spotless as an angel. Although poor herself in wordly goods, she has never ceased to find out, comfort, and lend a helping hand to those worse off than she; and however little she has had to give, she has given of that freely. Now that she is restored to so noble and loving a father, and has, besides, wealth and a high position, I assure you she richly deserves it all."</p> 
               <p>"Thank you, mother, but you surely praise me too highly. I feel that I have a great many imperfections."</p> 
               <p>"Others cannot see them if you have, my darling; and to hear these words from your foster mother's lips, gives me more pleasure than anything else in the world possibly could. You are indeed the prototype of your dear mother, for she possessed every virtue that is beautiful in woman; and you deserve great prosperity and happiness as a reward for your many afflictions and the Christian resignation and fortitude with which you have borne them. Now we must immediately commence making arrangements for our departure for England, your future home. My father died three months ago; he was a good man, but was very stern, and had an iron will which no argument could" change. I could not, therefore, claim my child, and bring her to England until after his death. We will not think of him harshly, for I loved him most devotedly. He always did and counselled what he thought was for my well being; although his conduct was apparently cruel in regard to trying to force me, to marry some one that I could not love; but it is all passed now, and we will think of it no more, although it has caused us both long years of suffering and unhappiness. My child, I nave heard from Miss Hilton that it was Lord Herbert Delmore who basely deceived you, to whom you were engaged, and when misfortune overtook you deserted you."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, father, I forgive him," said Josephine, seating herself close beside him.</p> 
               <p>"Then yon are acquainted with him," said Mrs. Templeton. "Josephine, it is but right that your father should know the wicked deceitful part he acted."</p> 
               <p>"Most certainly I should, for heretofore he has been one of my most heartily welcomed and honored friends at the castle. I always thought him the very soul of honor, and it seems hardly possible that he could have done as you say; but seeing that it is so, he shall never come under my roof again, and it is in my power to punish him as he deserves."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, father," said Josephine, the tears coming to her eyes, "you will grant me, this one request-the first boon that I ever asked of you-you surely will not refuse it: promise me that you will forgive him as I do. How can we hope for forgiveness if we do not forgive others; you surely will promise me this: that you will never mention the subject to him."</p> 
               <p>"Much as I love you, my darling, I cannot grant so unreasonable a request. It would be wrong to let such a sin as he has committed go, unpunished. Where is the man that can artfully gain your love, and then, with impunity, desert you without offering a word of excuse for such dastardly conduct. No, I shall not consent to that-no, never, never," replied the Earl, his face flushing with rage.</p> 
               <p>"Father, would you darken this hour of our great joy by one shade of sorrow? You know what I have suffered. Would you not now contribute all in your power to add to my happiness? For my sake say that you will forgive<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC6608-00000040"/> him," she said, looking pleadingly into his face.</p> 
               <p>For a few moments all was silent. The Earl seemed struggling between two emotions: one, love for his daughter and a desire to please her; the other, hatred of Lord Delmore and a wish for revenge. At last love triumphed, and taking her close to his heart and kissing Her fair face he said:</p> 
               <p>"My darling, for your sake, I forgive him.</p> 
               <p>"It is now known in England that many years ago I was privately married in America, and that when I return I shall bring my daughter with me. It is my wish that we now leave this place and go to the city of B--, until we have made the necessary preparations for our departure for England."</p> 
               <p>Mr. Templeton had arrived at the cottage, and the joyful news of Josephine's new-found happiness was quickly imparted to him, also that they were to accompany her to England, and in future reside there. He was overjoyed with the thought that so much good fortune had at last rewarded his dear Josephine, and that they were not to be separated from, her even now Turning to the Earl, he said:</p> 
               <p>"You can justly be proud of such a daughter as Josephine, for she is the best and noblest of women. She is one that cannot be appreciated in a day; you can see the beauty of her face and form, but that far more precious beauty-the loveliness of her character-can only be seen in the changing scenes of life. She has been tried both prosperity and adversity, and in each has worn the crown; neither being haughty and elated by prosperity, or desponding and sorrowful in adversity."</p> 
               <p>"My heart overflows with joy to hear such praises of you, my daughter, and I feel that I am supremely happy."</p> 
               <p>The subject of their intended departure was then discussed, and it was finally decided that they should on the next day bid farewell to the cottage forever; and until the necessary arrangements could be made, they would reside at one of the fashionable hotels at B--. Josephine and her father were to sail for England the following week, Mr. and Mrs. Templeton delaying their departure until the next month. The dark clouds of misfortune and sorrow had at last broken away, and joy and happiness had dawned brightly upon them.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
                
               <head>CHAPTER XXIII.</head> 
               <head type="sub">CARY ARRESTED AND IMPRISONED FOE ARSON.</head> 
               <p>DURING the last two years Gary had been living in the most reckless extravagance, and wasted and squandered his money in every conceivable way, Mrs. Gary and her daughter appeared in society attired in the most costly silks, velvets and laces, and glistening with diamonds. Yet, with every art which fashion could devise, their coarse manners and want of refinement could not be hidden. They were always spoken of as wealthy, but ill-bred women.</p> 
               <p>"If any one marries Miss Gary, it will be solely for her money," was the general remark; and no doubt that some worthless, dissipated fop would have done so, if Gary's villainy had not so soon been discovered. Every day he became poorer, for he made heavy drafts upon his money, but had never added one cent to the original amount that he had stolen. He had disposed of much valuable property at a sacrifice, in order to get the money to meet his immediate demands. At last he had only one piece of property left, which was of much value, and that was a large storehouse, situated a short distance from the most thickly settled portion of the city. He had tried in vain to sell if, but could not get a price that was anywhere near its real value.</p> 
               <p>"I must dispose of that property," said Gary, walking back and forth across the room, his hands tightly clenched, and his wizen face had grown more contracted and his snake-like eyes gleamed fiercer than, when we saw him last.</p> 
               <p>"I must dispose of it immediately, and at a high figure too, for I have hardly a dollar left; and if I should sacrifice that building at a small price, why when that is gone, I have nothing left worth naming. What am I to do, then, without money, and an expensive family to support, who must live in style; at any rate they've got to do it, no matter where the money comes from.</p> 
               <p>"I have the right thought now; why did'nt I think of that before: Everybody knows that that property is valuable, and I can get a heavy insurance on it; that's what I'll do," he thought, rubbing his hands together, quite in extacies over so brilliant an idea, as he thought.</p> 
               <p>"I'll not trust even Elbert Vinton with this delicate piece of business. I'll do it alone, and will not be troubled with constantly bribing some one to keep quiet on the subject. I know better now than to have a partner in any such undertaking. I know that from experience with the Templetons, I've had trouble enough with Elbert Vinton, and always had to be giving him money, for fear he might expose me; but I've never given him a great deal though, only enough to keep him out of the street; for he's afraid of me,<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC6608-00000041"/> and he knows that it would'nt do to get my ill will, for he has some idea, by others' experience, what it amounts to when it is once aroused.</p> 
               <p>"Now I'll execute this little plan alone; after I have got the largest insurance I can, I'll burn the building and pocket, the cash, which will be at least thirty thousand dollars, and no one will he the wiser. Then I will make a terrible ado over my loss, I will say that if it was not for other property that I should be a ruined man, by suffering such a loss; why I really believe that I will shed tears, for I always had the effective little art of shedding <emph>crocodile ones,</emph> when the occasion required, and many a nice little bargain I've gained, in that way, by working on the feelings of others, always being sure to have the tears come in just at the right time; can't many stand out against me, when it comes to that, so I always gain my point, in the easiest manner possible; so much for having a little tact in this world. Now old Simpson stored a lot of pressed hay in the building, a few days ago, and I could not ask anything better than that to help me along, in my purpose. I'm fortunate, I do declare, in all the plans I make, everything seems to come right along to help me, just exactly as I would have it if I arranged things myself: there's no doubt that I am a lucky man, as Elbert Vinton always says. I'll go and get it insured, as soon as possible, then my way will be clear; I can almost see the money now."</p> 
               <p>With this nefarious scheme in his head, and chuckling to himself, he took his hat and hastily left the house. Gary had exerted every means, to appear honest and upright among men; yet, notwithstanding all that, he was invariably regarded with suspicion: he was generally disliked, and there was hardly any one that he could call his friend. Although his wife and daughter entertained, and tried in every way to win popularity, and the good opinion of others, they signally failed; the hauteur of their manner, and the airs they assumed, making them not only disliked, but ridiculed, also, These ill gotten gains had, in many respects, been a source of irritation and mortification to them.</p> 
               <p>It was a dark night and there was a high wind prevailing; it was mid-night, and one might see the figure of a man, walking stealthily and cautiously through the now deserted streets, occasionally he would glance around him, to assure himself that no one observed him. Thus he walked on for sometime, until he came to the more thinly settled portion of the city, where his storehouse was situated, and as he approached it, he thought:</p> 
               <p>"Everything is favoring me again; nothing could have been more favorable than this high wind; I must make a sure thing of this undertaking, for it will not answer to make a failure of it: for, if I should fail in destroying it, I would be ruined: it would never do, to set the fire a second time; some one would, then be suspected immediately; besides, to only damage the building by fire, would make it unsalable, and I should be obliged to have it repaired before I could sell it for the price it would bring now, and I have no money to expend in that business. I'll enter the building, and set fire to the hay, and when twenty tons of hay have got well to burning, I'd like to know who is going to save it then? I'd def all the engines and firemen in the city to do it; and it would take some little time to get here, too; then the alarm would probably ably not be given until the building is well under way; for, at this hour, and in this part of the city, who will discover it until it is too late?"</p> 
               <p>With these arguments and resolutions he quickly darted into a narrow alley, which led along the side of the storehouse, then he cautiously and slowly went to the back door of the building, where he drew a key from his pocket, and noiselessly unlocked the door, and entered.</p> 
               <p>"Now, the worst is over," he thought, "I have reached here without being seen; all is clear, and there will be no further trouble."</p> 
               <p>But he had not discovered the figure of a policeman that had followed him, for some distance, with a cat-like tread.</p> 
               <p>"What is that man doing here, at this hour of the night?" He thought, "his actions are suspicious, see how he stops and looks around, and then stealthily moves along again. I'll venture that it will pay to watch that man: so I'll follow him for awhile; no doubt he is a burglar, and intends, if he gets a good opportunity, to rob some of these counting houses."</p> 
               <p>So he followed Gary a little distance, and the more he saw of his actions, the more confirmed he became in his opinion that this was a bad man, and intended some mischief. He saw him-dart into the alley, and cautiously and quickly followed him, but remained some little distance behind: he was greatly surprised at seeing Gary take a key from his pocket and unlock the door.</p> 
               <p>"He certainly cannot be a burglar," he thought, "for what is there to steal in this storehouse that he could carry off enough to pay him for his pains; perhaps I may be mistaken, but his actions are strange, to say the least, I'll watch that door for awhile, and see how long he stays here, and when he comes out, for he will probably leave the building by the same door he entered, as he has the key and will wish to lock it after him."</p> 
               <p>With this resolution he crouched down by the side of the building so as not to be observed; with his eyes fixed intently on the door. Gary had cautiously closed the door after him:</p> 
               <p>"Now, I must make quick work of this," he thought, drawing a small dark lantern from his pocket, which, when lighted, gave barely sufficient light for him to see his way. He proceeded immediately to where the hay was stored: he held a bottle of petroleum in his hand, then took a bundle of paper, over which he poured some, of the contents of the bottle, the rest of which he poured over the floor. "Now, all is ready, and there is no time to lose."</p> 
               <p>He looked around him an instant, then quickly surveyed the arrangements he had made with an air of satisfaction.</p> 
               <p>"It's all right now, I must get away from this place quicker than I ever disappeared from any scene before. Now is the time," and with this thought, he lit a long strip of paper, and in an instant applied it to the hay. It blazed up brilliantly, and instantly he darted out of the door: he was just starting to leave the alley, running at full speed, when a strong hand caught him in an iron grasp: In an instant, Gary drew a revolver from his pocket, which before he had time to discharge, the officer wrenched from his grasp. Gary struggled like a mad man to free himself, but he was a weak man, and was overpowered; yet, not without some difficulty, for in his frenzy and fright at<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC6608-00000042"/> being detected, it seemed to redouble his strength: at last, after repeated struggles, the officer succeeded in subduing him, and applied the handcuffs.</p> 
               <p>"You are my prisoner. You have set fire to this building, and I must immediately give the alarm," said the officer, half dragging Gary along after him, who raved and writhed in an agony of fear. But all to no purpose. At last Gary took a different tack, saying:</p> 
               <p>"I am rich, and you shall have every dollar I'm worth, if you will let me go."</p> 
               <p>"You need not try that, you can't bribe me: I'm paid for doing my duty, and seeing justice done; and I shall do it, so come along."</p> 
               <p>"When Cary saw that it was impossible now to make his escape, and that threatening and money were' of no power to release him, (as all cowardly natures do, for whoever saw a mean or wicked man that was not a coward,) he began to cry, plead and beg, that he would let him go; appealed to him that he had a family wholly dependent on him, and for their sake to release him."</p> 
               <p>"So have other people got families; and you might have ruined thousands in the crime that you have committed. You need not speak another word, for you will get no sympathy from me; and I'll soon have you locked up, where you will do no more harm for one while."</p> 
               <p>In the meantime, the officer had repeatedly sounded his policeman's call, and several quickly answered and were now on the spot. The fire alarm had been given: the policemen had broken open the doors of the building, which was now burning rapidly, the flames issuing from every portion of it. All was a scene of the wildest confusion and terror. The engines had began to arrive, and came dashing over the pavement at a tremendous speed. Groups of half clad people had gathered about the burning building; who had sprung from their beds, on being awakened by the alarm of fire, and seeing the bright light had hastened to the scene, where they looked on in awe and fright, fearing that if the flames were not subdued, they would spread to their own dwellings; for in this vicinity there were a great number of poor tenements, inhabited mostly by laborers, and what their poor houses contained, usually comprised all that they possessed in the world; and if they lost that, they lost their all. But the heartless Gary never thought or cared, that he was endangering the lives and property of others: he only thought of self; and did anything which would aggrandize himself and his family, regardless of the laws of God or man.</p> 
               <p>Two officers had now led him off to the station house, where he was securely locked up for the remainder of the night, before "being committed to jail. His course of deceit and wickedness had at last ended, and he was punished, as all those who commit sin inevitably are, sooner or later.</p> 
               <p>By the greatest exertions, both of the firemen and the people, the flames were at last partially subdued, only after hours of the hardest labor, and were prevented from spreading any farther; the combustible material that the building was stored with and the high wind, making it an unusually dangerous and difficult task. It was not until the gray daylight dawned, that the firemen left the scene where they had worked so bravely and nobly. The building was left a smouldering heap of ruins-a monument of Gary's last act of sin. The poor people returned to their houses when they saw that the danger was over, thankful that their homes had been spared.</p> 
               <p>Mrs. Cary was not at all alarmed because her husband had not returned home, for it was no unusual thing for him to be from home all night. He always told her that it was important business that kept him away, and she knew that what he said was true. It was not until late in the morning that she received, a hastily written note, written in pencil, on a scrap of paper, in her husband's handwriting, informing her that he was in prison and wished to see her. On reading this she was thoroughly alarmed, and turned pale, doubtless for the first time in her life. She was now feeling a little of the agony which she had goaded her husband on to cause others. She had been merciless and pitiless to the sufferings of others, and did all in her power to add to the sorrows of those whom her husband had ruined.</p> 
               <p>Now that misfortune had fallen upon her, she felt utterly lost and overwhelmed. She had never in her life expressed one word of sympathy for the sufferings of any human creature, or offered in any way to relieve them. What now could she expect, or who could she look to for help or comfort, now that her hour of trial had come, and they were at last overtaken in their wickedness. She knew that her husband had squandered nearly all his property, and that if he should be sent to prison, all they had to depend upon was what they could earn by the labor of their own hands; and this thought seemed to trouble her more than that her husband was in jail. She raved about the house like one in a frenzy, saying:</p> 
               <p>"I suppose he has done some stupid thing without asking my advice. What can it be! what, can it be! But I must go and see him, and find out, and know what we are to do now. Then, suppose any one should see me going to the jail, how dreadfully "mortified I should be to have any one think that I had a friend there, much less a husband. Then, suppose that it should appear in the papers, that Curtis Gary had been committed to prison; I never could endure such mortification-it is dreadful. He must have done some such stupid thing, that I can hardly feel any sympathy for him," she said, hastily putting on her hat and shawl, and throwing a thick veil over her face so as not to be recognized.</p> 
               <p>"Sarah, besides the disgrace, we may be reduced to poverty," she said, turning to her Daughter, who stood near her, and who had hitherto been too much 'surprised and frightened to speak.</p> 
               <p>"If that be so, mamma, (it would ruin my prospects in life," she demurely replied, for it seemed that nothing could startle her dull mind and nature to anything like emotion.</p> 
               <p>"Yes, but you should have been married long before this. For the last two or three years you have had every advantage that money could give you, yet you do not seem to have profited by it."</p> 
               <p>"I can't help it, mamma;" and, as she made this reply, Mrs. Cary hastily left the house, walked a square or took a carriage, and ordered the driver to drive to the city jail-she not wishing her own equipage seen standing before the prison, or to order a public carriage to come to her own door, for fear of exciting suspicion.</p> 
               <p>The proof of Gary's guilt was so strong, and the case so clear, that the<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC6608-00000043"/> trial was only a mere form, and the verdict of guilty was quickly given; and Curtis Cary was sentenced to the extent of the law to the State prison, with hard labor, for arson.</p> 
               <p>Thus, after a life of sin, at last meeting with a just punishment for his deeds.</p> 
               <p>When it was told Mrs. Cary what the verdict had been, she cried out:</p> 
               <p>"Now we are ruined! we are ruined! What shall we do? I never expected this. Already it is known that my husband is in prison; and bill after bill has been presented to me for immediate payment, and I have not a hundred dollars in the world, We shall lose our house; we shall lose our reputation, and everything else. We shall be obliged to earn our own living in some way. I never thought that any thing could happen to us. This is laying everything in hopeless ruin at once. Oh, it is too dreadful;" and Mrs. Cary suffered as much as her coarse mind was capable of, she being wholly destitute of those fine susceptibilities and delicate feelings which belong to a noble mind and refined nature. Sarah seemed like one wholly bewildered, and hardly said a word in reply to her mother's remarks.</p> 
               <p>Cary had contracted large debts, and they began sending in their claims, clamoring for their money, which Mrs. Cary was unable to pay. Attachments were put upon the house and furniture. Their servants, to whom they had always been austere and cruel, now deserted them, and they were left alone to provide for themselves as beet they might. Mrs. Cary made known to her mother (who was an old lady of very limited means, who lived in a small country town in great obscurity,) their miserable condition; and she could not refuse to share with her daughter what little she had, now that she was in such a pitiable condition. She had often heard of the course her daughter and son-in-law were pursuing, with great displeasure; she was afraid that their extravagance and suddenly acquired wealth might, some day, be a source of grief to them, and now it had only proved too true.</p> 
               <p>One month from the day of Gary's sentence, Mrs. Cary and her children were leaving forever the house and luxury that her husband had so dishonestly and wickedly gained. The house and everything it contained ha d been taken for debt, for Cary had never failed to contract a debt wherever any one would trust him. Mrs. Cary and her children were now leaving their home, without money and without friends. She was suffering the very same thing, that a few years before she had rejoiced to see others suffer; having besides the additional mortification of her husband's disgrace and crime. Both she and her husband were, therefore, justly punished for the crimes they had committed and the sorrows that they had caused others.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
                
               <head>CHAPTER XXIV.</head> 
               <head type="sub">JOSEPHINE AND HER FATHER'S ARRIVAL IN ENGLAND-MEETING OF JOSEPHINE AND LORD DELMORE.</head> 
               <p>JOSEPHINE and her father had arrived in England, and were to proceed directly to the Castle. At the railway station, the Earl's carriage stood in waiting. It was an open carriage drawn by four beautiful horses; the coachman and two footmen wearing the Elva liveries. The tenantry had not been idle in preparing to welcome the young heiress. From the grand entrance gate to the Castle, they had erected numerous arches, decorated with flowers, with which were blended the British and American flags. They had put on their holiday attire, and were anxiously awaiting the arrival of the Earl and the Lady Josephine. At last the carriage was seen approaching, and there was a shout of joy; and as it proceeded slowly up the broad avenue, and they saw for the first time the fair daughter of the Earl, their admiration and <emph>enthusiasm</emph> knew no bounds.</p> 
               <p>"She's the fairest lady in the kingdom," was whispered from one to the other. Josephine smiled and bowed to either side, as she passed; they standing with uncovered heads, cheering and waving both hats and handkerchiefs. She felt greatly pleased to be so cordially welcomed by these people to her new home. She was soon to have a public reception, when there were to be presented to her the Earl's friends, besides the nobility and gentry of the surrounding country. The news that the Earl's daughter, whose existence had so long been kept a secret, was soon to arrive in England, had caused great excitement among all, and every one felt both anxious and curious to see her. Josephine was as much at ease and as perfectly self-possessed in the castle, as she was in the cottage; in fact, more so, for she was now in the position for which she was fitted by nature as well as birthright to fill.</p> 
               <p>It was the day of the reception, and Josephine was in the main drawing room; her. father and the Lady Eleanor beside her, receiving her new friends. She was attired in a dress of black velvet, trimmed with crape and jet, and wore a <foreign xml:lang="FRA">parure</foreign> of diamonds set in black enamel. She had the same sweet smile and gentle grace, that ever distinguished her, and won all hearts. Every one expressed their admiration in unmeasured terms. The drawing rooms 'were now well filled with beautiful ladies and elegant gentlemen. Lord Delmore was in the ante-room, leisurely making his preparations before entering the drawing room and being presented.</p> 
               <p>"If it were not for my love and respect for "the Earl, I would not be here to-day. The very name of Josephine<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC6608-00000044"/> sephine fills me with pain and unhappiness."</p> 
               <p>With this thought, be proceeded to the drawing room.</p> 
               <p>"Is not this an hour of triumph for me," thought Josephine. "If Lord Delmore comes here to-day, will he not he both greatly surprised and mortified? What will he his feelings when he sees my position; when he reflects that he deserted me because I was poor and unfortunate? Will he not then consider how great are the changes of fortune, and how impossible it is for man to know who will secure the prize? I surely can, and must, meet him calmly."</p> 
               <p>As these thoughts passed quickly through her mind, Lord Delmore had entered the room, although unperceived by her; the next instant he was presented. At this crisis, all her resolution failed. To be thus again face to face with the man whom she had loved better than her life; who had so wickedly deceived her, and had caused her such untold suffering. The great trouble that her supposed parents were in, and the scene of utter desolation and ruin-all flashed across her mind in an instant, and seemed to pass before her as vividly as at the time when it all really happened. She turned as pale as death, and neither spoke or moved, Ail thought of the present, for an instant, seemed entirely to desert her; her mind was far away in America, among scenes of desolation and sadness.</p> 
               <p>In an instant Lord Delmore recognized his long lost love. For this he was wholly unprepared. Such a thought as that the daughter of the Earl of Elva and Josephine Templeton were one and the same person, could never have come to him in his wildest dreams. He trembled from head to foot, and gazed upon her in perfect bewilderment. He did not speak, and' hastily left the room, hardly realizing what he was doing, or whether this was some strange dream or reality. On reaching the library he sank into a chair, completely exhausted and overcome, for in these few minutes he had suffered a world of agony. The Earl had watched Josephine's face, and as he perceived the deathly pallor that had settled" over it, and her apparent oblivion to what was passing around her, he felt greatly alarmed, and said to her:</p> 
               <p>"My dear, you are not well. You were not strong enough to bear so much excitement and fatigue as you have been called upon to endure for the last few days, after the weariness of a sea voyage. You had better retire to your boudoir for a short time, in order to gain rest and quiet."</p> 
               <p>"I will, for a few moments," she replied; and leaning heavily on her father's arm, with faltering steps, she left the room.</p> 
               <p>When she had reached her boudoir, she sank on a couch; her maid bathed her head with cologne water, and hastily fanned her. Josephine assured her father that after a few moments' composure she would quite recover. Just then there was a light knock at the door, and the servant passed to the Earl a hastily written note, the handwriting of which he immediately recognized. He ordered the servants from the room, and, turning to Josephine, said:</p> 
               <p>"Lord Delmore craves an interview, if but for one moment, with my daughter; but he shall never see you again; he has caused you trouble enough. He would now probably try to excuse his conduct, but his apologies will not be accepted."</p> 
                
               <p>"Oh, father, let me have one interview with him, for I have always wished to hear from his own lips, the reason of his cruel desertion. You surely will not refuse our joint requests."</p> 
               <p>"He will probably only come with some paltry excuse. Although your request is unreasonable, yet to gratify you, I will allow him to be admitted for a few minutes, and then after he has made his apologies, he shall on no consideration enter this house again. I am more lenient to you, my darling, in affairs of the heart, than I should probably otherwise have been, had it not been for my own unhappy experience, and years of wretchedness to us both, caused by having a tyrannical, yet well meaning, father: and I shall endeavor not to fall into the same error, in regard to you;" saying this, he rang the bell and gave directions that Lord Delmore be shown to the room. He soon entered, looking pale and careworn. He saw plainly the pallor and sorrow written on Josephine's face.</p> 
               <p>"Josephine," he said, his voice trembling with emotion, "for I can never call you by any other name, I have sought this interview with you, perhaps too hastily, yet it seemed that I could not live another hour when you are so near, not to have the mystery of our broken engagement explained. You can judge of my feelings when I recognized you here to-day as the daughter of one of my most honored friends. Josephine, if you still cherish any regard for me, you will tell me frankly the reason why you returned to me our betrothal ring, and wrote that note, from the sting of which my heart never has and never will recover."</p> 
               <p>Josephine had listened to his words, sitting perfectly motionless, until he spoke of the ring; then she suddenly started, clasping her hands upon her forehead and gazed at him intently, as if to realize that this was all reality, and not some strange fancy. As he ceased speaking, with his eyes fixed steadfastly upon her, she cried:</p> 
               <p>"Oh Herbert, Herbert, I lost the ring: I never returned it to your; and never wrote a note to you expressing anything but tenderness and love."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, my darling, my darling Josephine," he cried, embracing her: "What can this mystery be; you did not return the ring, "but lost it: Oh, my dearest, there is deep treachery here: some one has deceived us both, and caused us these years of suffering; Oh, what miracle of Divine Providence has thus restored us to each other and caused this explanation?"</p> 
               <p>With this great joy coming so suddenly upon her, the strain of the so long forced calmness had been more than she could bear, and she wept for joy. Lord Delmore took a seat beside her, and drew her to him, pillowing her fair head on his manly breast, saying:</p> 
               <p>"My darling, do not weep, for I too have suffered more than can be told since I last saw your dear face: but now that I am again restored to you, those years of sorrow shall appear only as some sad dream: my dearest, I feel that you love me, and always have; our engagement, then, never has been broken; and with your consent, may it still continue."</p> 
               <p>"Dearest Herbert, I never have, and never shall love any one but you," that reply was sufficient, and kissing her, he said:</p> 
               <p>"My darling, the angels in Heaven witness our happiness: we that have suffered so much."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, dear Herbert, will I lose my<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC6608-00000045"/> reason, being overwhelmed with so many blessings. Once I thought myself the most wretched and forsaken of all beings upon the earth; it almost seemed as if our Father in Heaven had withdrawn all his mercy from me; but oh, no, no, it was not so, for He works in a mysterious way, and now I feel that I am crowned with blessing upon blessing, until there is not another earthly joy that I could ask, surely my cup runneth over' with happiness, and I am rewarded for all my sufferings, but what I have suffered, no one can ever know. God and my own heart alone know the agony that I have endured."</p> 
               <p>"My dearest, I can plainly see in your beautiful face, the evidences of suffering, but if in my power to make you happy, you shall never see another day of sorrow. We are now both supremely blest, we can neither of us ask for greater happiness. Dearest Josephine, if you only knew of the days, months and years that I have spent mourning and weeping for you, you could then form some idea of the devoted love I bear you. But the wretch that has caused us both such woe, deserves greater punishment than any earthly power can inflict and what could have been the object of such wickedness; tell me, my darling, if there is anything more that you know of concerning this mystery?"</p> 
               <p>"All I know, is, that not having heard from you, (when you left that day, promising to return so soon,) that I wrote you three notes, asking the cause of your silence, and why I did not see you: and in each, renewing my expressions of love; but to them I received no reply. I sent them all by my maid Camilla, so as to insure their safe delivery."</p> 
               <p>"My darling, I did not receive any, excepting the one that I mentioned."</p> 
               <p>"How can it be possible, it was she, then, who kept them. One morning I woke and found that my ring was gone; I thought that I had lost it: every place was searched, but to no purpose; I felt even, then, that some dreadful omen was attached to its loss. I then wrote to you informing you of it, expressing my great sorrow, but no answer from you: Oh, what I suffered then, I could never endure again; it makes me shudder to think of it. I must have been indued with superhuman strength, not to have died under such a weight of woe; and from that day until now, my heart has been wholly dead: I have lived only inwardly a life of agony, forcing myself to appear cheerful for the sake of my dear foster parents, who, with the loss of property, and being obliged to live in poverty, were well nigh crushed in hopes and spirits. Thus we lived, struggling to do our duty, and bear up under every burden; until my dear father come and claimed me; not until then knowing that my kind foster parents were not my real ones."</p> 
               <p>"I can imagine it all, my darling, but thank God it is all passed now, and you are restored to a noble father, and to one who loves you more than life. Concerning our betrothal ring and your letters, there must have been some deep plot in which your maid was concerned, which I cannot fathom; she must have been bribed to play the part she did, for she could not possibly have had any motive for causing our separation: this is a mystery which may perhaps always remain unraveled."</p> 
               <p>"I can think of only one person base enough, and who could have had any object for doing such a thing, and that man's name is Gary; my mother and myself feel confident that it; was he that led my foster father to ruin: he might have done that in order to destroy every hope, and cause, as far as possible, our entire ruin."</p> 
               <p>"That is very probable; if Mr. Templeton had an enemy that would rain him, he would not scruple to ruin his daughter also: if we could prove our opinions to be correct, he should be, in a measure, for it would be impossible that he could be fully punished for the crime he has committed."</p> 
               <p>"No, dear Herbert, we do not need to do it, for the Judge of All will surely some day cause him to be punished as he deserves."</p> 
               <p>"To-morrow, dear Josephine, I will show you both that fatal ring, and also the note, which are enclosed in the sealed packet, in which I put them, the dreadful day that they were received, and I have never looked upon them since; but now I can break the seal with as much joy, as I placed it there in sorrow, expecting never to behold them again."</p> 
               <p>"Now, dearest Herbert, let us acquaint our father, with our great happiness. How can I express my thankfulness for so many blessings, and so much joy: being thus at once restored to my dear father, after long years of separation; and restored to you, on whom the happiness of my life depends. We will repair to the chapel, and there, together, offer up our praises and thanksgivings, to the Giver of All Good."</p> 
               <p>They rose to leave the room, Josephine leaning upon the arm of Lord. Delmore; and as they did so, they met the Earl, who had come in search of his daughter.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, father," exclaimed Josephine, her face beaming with happiness: It was all a mistake; there has been a conspiracy against us; and we both were deceived but we are so very happy now, and ask your blessing."</p> 
               <p>"My darling, I am thankful that it is so; I never saw you looking so happy, and I could not bestow you, on one more worthy of you. My children, I give you my blessing."</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC6608-00000046"/> 
               <head>CHAPTER XXV.</head> 
               <head type="sub">CONFESSION OF ELBERT VINTON.</head> 
               <p>MR. and Mrs. Templeton, were sitting in the elegant apartments of their hotel in B--: they had been there for three weeks, and the following week were to sail for England, to rejoin their darling, Josephine.</p> 
               <p>"The events of the last few weeks, seem more like a dream than reality, do they not? Josephine is now the heiress of an Earldom, and possessed of immense wealth and restored to a loving father. We, through her, have every blessing that we could desire; and the prospects of having an old age of happiness, after all the various conflicts, misfortunes and sorrows that we have endured, during our stormy life. Cary, whose wickedness had for so long seemed to prosper, has at last, met his just reward," said Mrs. Templeton.</p> 
               <p>"Yes," replied her husband, "and this should be a warning to all, that virtue and goodness are as sure to triumph, and be bountifully rewarded, as sin is to fail, and meet it's just disgrace and punishment."</p> 
               <p>"There is a gentleman, sir, that wishes to see you," said the servant, who had just entered the room.</p> 
               <p>"He says it's very important."</p> 
               <p>"Certainly, I will see him immediately," said Mr. Templeton, rising, and they both quickly left the room.</p> 
               <p>Mr. Templeton soon returned, saying in an excited manner:</p> 
               <p>"It was a man from the hospital, who says that there is a man there, very sick, and wishes to see us, as soon as it is possible for us to come; and that man, is Elbert Vinton."</p> 
               <p>"Is it possible, Elbert Vinton in a hospital, and Cary in prison; surely, their day of retribution has come, and they at last suffer the just punishment of their deeds. But, if he has sent for us, suffering and penitent, we must not refuse to go and see him: we who are now surrounded with every blessing, can well afford to be charitable, and show mercy even to those who have been our worst enemies, and caused us years of suffering and sorrow."</p> 
               <p>"We will go, then, immediately, and see him, and while you are making your preparations, I will go and order the carriage," saying this, Mr. Templeton left the room.</p> 
               <p>In one of the wards of the hospital, we see lying on a small narrow bed, the emaciated form of Elbert Vinton, the expression of his face has greatly changed; it has no longer the indolent, good natured care-for-nothing expression, which once characterized it; and his eyes, which were always dull, are now very heavy and sunken. He was breathing heavily, and a deep sigh occasionally escaped him.</p> 
               <p>Mr. and Mrs. Templeton had entered the ward, and followed the man, (who was the same one who had called at the hotel for them) and was showing them which bed was occupied by Elbert Vinton. As they saw him, instinctively they shuddered, and for a moment Mrs. Templeton turned away.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, what a wreck of a man, is this," she thought, "who, had it not have been for his intolerable indolence, and having had rather commit sin, than to exert himself to gain a livelihood honestly, might now have been prosperous and respected: but he had both paths before him, and he chose the evil one, and this is the result; lying here in a hospital, consumed with disease, not having lived out half his days; without money and without friends, an object of charity, and being burdened with a guilty conscience; if, indeed, the life he has led, indicates, if he was ever possessed of any: and he now summons those to his bedside, whom he has so cruelly wronged, and whom he, and his accomplice, tried in every way to ruin: and we now come to comfort him, in his day of misfortune."</p> 
               <p>As he perceived them standing by his bed-side, he feebly stretched out his hand to Mr. Templeton:</p> 
               <p>"I am thankful that you have come, but I could hardly have expected it, after all the trouble I have caused you; but you see that I am punished, and so is Cary, for I should never have done what I did, if it had not been for him. I should have told you, the secret that I am now going to reveal, long ago, had it not been for Cary, but I was afraid of him, and dare not do it: now he is safely locked up, and out of the way, I have nothing to fear. He promised to give me a great deal of money, for the crime which I assisted him to commit, but I never got it; he gave me barely enough to keep me alive: now don't blame me too much; I acknowledge that I have committed a great sin. I have many, many times regretted it, and feel deeply penitent: and I beg of you both, and Josephine, also, to forgive me, and have pity on me. I have heard of your great good fortune and that Josephine is the daughter of an Earl. Before I was brought to the hospital, I heard that you were stopping at the St. C-- hotel."</p> 
               <p>He stopped a moment, as if to gain courage, then resumed: "Lord Delmore did not desert Josephine, as you supposed: we heard, through the French maid, Camilla, whom we bribed to serve us, that Lord Delmore was going to marry Josephine; then we hired the maid to steal the betrothal ring from her finger, while asleep. We enclosed it in a note, purporting to be from Josephine, breaking the engagement, and sent it to Lord Delmore: he then left the country. All the notes Josephine wrote to him, were delivered to Cary, by the maid, and he destroyed them. It was Cary and I who induced you to drink, and" then persuaded you to sign papers, conveying to Cary your property, which at last ruined you: and it is on your property Cary has lived ever since. I have confessed everything now, and my mind is relieved: we have committed great sins, and indeed have -received great punishment. When you see my wretched condition, can you refuse to forgive me?"</p> 
               <p>During this confession, Mrs. Templeton leaned heavily upon her husband's arm; tears came to her eyes, as she thought, that now at last, the dark shadow that rested over her darling Josephine's heart had passed away, and that which caused her such a life of sorrow, had been explained.</p> 
               <p>"Now, there is no obstacle in the<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC6608-00000047"/> way of her perfect happiness; how delighted she will be when she hears the joyful news I have to communicate to her; and when she knows that Herbert was always true to her."</p> 
               <p>She was so much occupied with the thought of the great joy this revelation would give Josephine, that for the moment she did not realize the guilt of the miserable penitent who had caused them so much suffering, and who lay before them begging their forgiveness and asking their pity.</p> 
               <p>"This is, indeed, a chapter of crime; and could a man be human, who would thus artfully plan and execute such a diabolical crime, and thus cause the ruin of his innocent victims. But we are commanded to forgive and relieve even our enemies, and we both do so. I can assure you of Josephine's pardon, for she is symbolical of mercy and pity. Mrs. Templeton and myself sail for England next week, but I will leave sufficient means here for you to insure your comfort and support while sick."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, thank you, thank you; and may God bless you for your kindness to me; I know that I do not deserve it, but by doing so it causes me far greater sorrow and anguish for the sin that I have committed, than any harsh words or act of cruelty could cause me. I shall not long be burdensome to you, I feel that I shall never recover from this fever. My mind is relieved of its load of guilt now, and I can die in peace: and to nay dying day I shall never cease to bless your name."</p> 
               <p>Mr. Templeton then left a sufficient amount of money to secure every comfort for him, and bidding him farewell, they left the hospital: their minds filled with the strange confession they had heard: how at last a just retribution had overtaken the followers of sin, and that now there appeared no obstacle to prevent Josephine's perfect happiness.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
                
               <head>CHAPTER XXVI.</head> 
               <head type="sub">JOSEPHINE'S MARRIAGE TO LOUD DELMORE.</head> 
               <p>JOSEPHINE'S marriage was to take place one year from the time of her arrival in England, being thus delayed on account of the recent death of the late Earl. The wedding day had now arrived; The marriage ceremony was to be performed in the Chapel of the Castle, which was superbly decorated with flowers, as was also the entire Castle. Everything presented a scene of the greatest gayety and festivity. The tenantry were to be treated to a bountiful and splendid banquet. Josephine was devotedly loved by all, and the poor almost worshiped her, so liberal and extensive had her charities been. If any one was in distress, they always sent immediately to the good lady at the Castle for relief, which was never refused them. Splendid equipages thronged the broad avenue, and elegantly dressed ladies and gentlemen alighted, stepping on to a velvet carpet, over which was a beautiful canopy of white, festooned with flowers. The Chapel was now filled and well represented the proudest families, and greatest people of which the kingdom could boast, dazzling in their superb jewels and rich attire. But the fairest and most lovely of all, was the beautiful Lady Josephine as she entered the Chapel followed by eight bridesmaids.</p> 
               <p>Her dress was of white velvet; a veil of the finest point lace, completely enveloped her person, and was confined to her head by a coronet of superb diamonds. She never looked more beautiful than on this occasion, and as she entered, a murmur of admiration was distinctly heard. Lord Delmore stood before the altar, awaiting his bride, and looking extremely handsome. The service was performed by the Bishop, assisted by the resident clergyman. As soon as the ceremony was performed, she was most heartily congratulated by all: but few knew the years of suffering that had intervened, before this happy consummation of her earthly bliss. In the evening, the park surrounding the Castle, was brilliantly illuminated with countless bright hued lanterns, which were suspended from the trees. The tenantry lit large bonfires throughout the neighborhood, and many carried torches about in their hands. A band of music was stationed on the lawn, to the music of which great numbers of the tenantry were merrily dancing. There was also music and dancing at the Castle. Lord and Lady Delmore, the Earl, and Mr. and Mrs. Templeton stood a little apart from the company.</p> 
               <p>"Father," said Josephine, "I feel now that I am crowned with all earthly happiness."</p> 
               <p>"Yes, my darling, you surely are, and it is only your just reward; your sufferings have been far greater than fall to the common lot of mankind; you have borne them nobly, and surely deserve an equally great reward."</p> 
            </div> 
         </div>
      </body> 
      <back> 
         <div type="advertisement"> 
            <pb n="94-95 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC6608-00000048"/> 
             
            <head>JOSEPHINE ELOISE.</head> 
            <head type="sub">A NOVEL.</head> 
            <head type="sub">By Mrs. ADELAIDE F. HAMMOND.</head> 
            <p>PRICE 50 CENTS.</p> 
            <p>BALTIMORE: PUBLISHED BY THE BALTIMORE NEWS CO.</p> 
            <p>PRINTED BY J. W. WOODS, 12 SOUTH ST.</p> 
            <p>1872.</p> 
         </div> 
      </back> 
   </text>
</TEI>