<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6905">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Sophie de Brentz, or, The Sword of Truth </title>
            <author >Johnstone, O. A., Miss</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC6905</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >Sophie de Brentz, or, The sword of truth</title>
                  <author >Johnstone, O. A., Miss</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >190 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >H. Hoyt</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1859">1859</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-08-25">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text >
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Sophie de Brentz, or, The sword of truth</head>
            <p> 
               <pb n="Illustration" xml:id="VAC6905-00000001"/> "The princely mansion of Baron De Brentz." Page 0.I   SOPHE T Bln T- , ;. ^. T    <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6905-00000002"/>   SOPHE DE BRENTZ;  OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.  BY THE AUTHOR OF "HOME SCENES IN THE NORWOOD FAMLY," ( EVELYN WILLIS AT SCHOOL," "HLLSIDE FARM," ETC., ETC.   BOSTON: HENRY HOYT, 9 CORNHLL, CHCAGO: W M. TOMLINSON. CINCINNATI: GEO. CROSBY. 1859.   <pb n="0 (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC6905-00000003"/> Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1858, by HENRY HOYT, In the Clerk's Office of the District Court of Massachusetts.  BAZIN &amp; CHANDLEB Electrotypers and Printers, 37 Cornhill. Boston.   CONTENTS. CHAPTER   I. "FE AND DEATH. The Tyrol-Sketch of Baron De Brentz-Descrip- tion of Nasseriet -The Baron's Decision- Death of Conrad and Frederick- Sorrow of the Parents-- Birth of Sophie- Illness of the Baroness- Death and burial of the Baroness--The infant Sophie-A A Mother's Love. CHAPT1 R II. THE NEW   HOME I The child Sophie- Illustrations of Character-Her Father's Marriage - Description of the Italian Home  - Sketch of Florence - Manners and Morals of It-  aly -Cathedral at Florence -Sophie's Step-mother - Unanswered Questionings.    <pb n="vi (Table of Contents) -vii (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC6905-00000004"/> Vi   CONTENTS.   CHAPTER III. TRIUMPH or TRUTH. Sophie's Confirmation-Requisitions of the Romish Church- Sophie attends the worship of the Cathedral -Idolatry-The Confessional-Senora Isola-So- phie's love for Music - The Convent of Santa Maria - Sister Agnes - Description of the Convent - Em- ployment of the Nuns - Sophie's acquaintance with Lord Ardley - The discovery of a Bible, and the re- sult. CHAPTER IV. PERSECUTION. Questionings and Replies - Their results - Conference between Countess De Brentz and Father Ambrose - So- phie confined to her room - Her feelings and determine ations-Refusal to confess, and hatred of Father Ambrose - The Romish Church the same in all ages. CHAPTER V. CONVENT LIFE. Sophie summoned before her mother and the priest - Her firmness - She is conveyed to the Convent - Life in the cloister - The Testament - Helena Peruzi takes the veil - Intimacy between the two friends renewed - Wretchedness of Sister Cecilia - Religion consists not in shunning the society of mankind. CHAPTER VI. THE RETURN. Sophie wearies of the Convent - Father Ignatius- So- phie's confessions - The priest's advice - Sophie leaves the Convent - The meeting between mother and daughter - Return of Count De Brentz - He decides to take Sophie to Rome.   CHAPTER VII. R O M E. The journey- Sight of Rome-Emotions caused by past memories and present associations -The visit to St. Peter's-Meeting with Father Ambrose-View from the Dome of St. Peter's. CHAPTER VIII. BEAUTIES AND DEFORMTIES OF THE ETERNAL CITY. The Vatican, and the Pope-Palm Sunday - Mumme- ries of the Romish Church - The "Three Hours of Agony "- Ancient Rome - Lord Ardley - Suprema- cy of the Papal Power. CHAPTER IX. CHANGES AND REVERSES. The return to Florence - Sophie's Employments-Ro- manism gains a temporary sway -The Count's Re- turn- Baron Von Amsdorff- Sophie's Marriage - The insurrection, and flight of its leader - One" gone before " -The mother's grief- Switzerland. CHAPTER X. M EYRINGEN. The village of Meyringen, and its pastor - The mutual recognition - The pastor's prayer - Its effect on the Baron and Baroness - Conversation of the latter with the pastor - Her despair. CHAPTER    XI. A SABBATH AMONG THE MOUNTAINS. The Sabbath in Meyringen - The Sermon -Its effect on The Baroness -Light and Happiness.     '    <pb n="viii (Table of Contents) -9" xml:id="VAC6905-00000005"/> I         uJMAlIn'ii.            , CHAPTER XII. THE Swiss H o    E. ws from Italy- The Baron an exile, and deprived of his estates-- Effect of the tidings- The home in Mey- ringen - Visit to the buried village- Fearful nature of the Alpine Avalanche. CHAPTER XIII. CHE EAGLE'S FLIGHT, AND THE MOTHER'S VICTORY. etch of little Albert-The eagle's flight, and the mother's pursuit- Her success-- Little Albert's sick- ness and death - Resignation of the mother - M. Or- ol1i - Trial sanctified. CHAPTER XIV. CONCLUSION. i eventful Sabbath-Arrival of Count DeBrentz- Death of the Countess - The fugitive Nun - Manner Df her escape- The Count decides to remain in Swit- zerland - Marriage of the pastor - Terrible death of Father Ambrose - Conclusion.   SOPHE DE BRENTZ: OR,  THE SWORD OF TRUTH.  CHAPTER 1. Life is real: Life is earnest; And the grave is not its goal; Dust thou art, to dust returAest, Was not written of the soul. "ONGFELLOW.  SITUATED in the southern part of Aus, tria is the little district of Tyrol, which, though small in compass, is one of the most interesting countries in continental Europe. The Alps, with their summits of perpetual snow, surround it, yet the  <pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6905-00000006"/> 10   SOPHE DEBRENTZ;   valleys below are green and beautiful. Here dwell a race of beings unlike all others, unless we except the Swiss. With more cultivation and refinement, they are, like the latter, brave, hardy, and in- dependent; while in scenes of danger their courage never fails them, or their fortitude in time of trial. The distin- guishing national trait is love for home and country; which absence cannot re- press, or time subdue; and many are the tales rife among the Tyrolese peasantry to illustrate this feature of their race. In Nasseriet, a little village in the southern part of Tyrol, rose the princely mansion of Baron De Brentz. The Baron had for years mingled in the noise and strife of camps; but at length, tired of the tumult of war, and the pomp and pa- geantry of courts, he determined to seek a quiet home, where he might spend the   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.  " remainder of his days in the enjoyment of domestic life, with his wife and sons for companions. Early education in the arts of war, more than any natural predilection, had made Albert De Brentz a soldier; and when his dreams of glory faded away, revealing the dark side of the picture, - the dead and dying, wives made widows and children orphans, his naturally noble heart revolted at the sight; and young though he was, bue determined to leave the army. One day in the early summer, while journeying through Tyrol, he came to Nageriet, and was charmed with its quiet beauty. An air of neatness per- vaded the homes of the industrious vil- lagers, and the sunlight, brightening the snow-capped heights and sparkling on the streamlets as they  ran merrily   i    <pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6905-00000007"/> 12   SOPHE DEBRENTZ;   down the mountain sides, glanced into the open cottage doors, and rested on the thresholds. The notes of birds were heard among the delicate foliage of the tall larches, groves of which were scat- tered along the slopes. Sitting, or stand- ing in the shade, or farther up on the mountains could be seen the hardy shep- herds, with their flocks of sheep and goats feeding around them.  Flowers bloomed in profusion along the travel- ler's path-way, among which the blue- eyed gentian reigned supreme.  Here and there auriculas lifted their bright heads above the moss, while tufts of ranunculas were often crushed beneath the horse's feet, and bushes of the glossy- leaved phillyrea now and then obstructed the pathway. As the little village, in its quiet beauty, lay, like a picture before the traveller, his mind reverted painfully.   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.  13 to the past, and at once he resolved to make this his future home. The quiet and gentle Baroness was glad to second his decision, for she too longed to retire from the giddy world, whose pleasures she had found hollow and unsatisfying. The Baron possessed large revenues'ad both parents viewed with a fond pride the boys, Conrad and Frederick. They looked forward to long years of happiness in the society of their sons; who, like the boys that they were, busied themselves in becoming fully ac- quainted with their new home, and the village in which it stood. Then excur- sions to the mountains were planned and executed; and the boys almost envied the chamoisS as he leapt from rock to rock, so fully did they enter into the spirit of these expeditions. With them the time was passed in alternate study and recrea.     <pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6905-00000008"/> OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.   tion; and both  parents and children thought that they were never so happy it   before. But there is no spot so sacred that death may not invade it, no earthly hap- piness so complete that death may not disturb it. Only a few months had passed over the new home, when the two boys   were stricken down within a few days of each other with a malignant fever. The parents watched over them with unspeak- able solicitude, but after a brief period of suffering, death claimed them, and they were laid one after the other in the tomb. Then were the parents' hearts indeed desolate. Reared as they had been from infancy amid the soul-deadening influen- ces of the Roman Catholic religion, they knew nothing of the comforts which true piety brings its possessors. As they had   hitherto lived unmindful that all their blessings came from God,--as they had never made Christ their portion,-so now their proud spirits rebelled because God had taken his own. They shrunk from contact with the world around them, and almost envied the mountain shep- herd, his wild, sturdy boys. Reader, are you longing for wealth, thinking it will bring you happiness? Believe it not. The elements of true happiness are in every human heart, and over these external circumstances has but little controlling power. If the heart be filled with love to God and gratitude for His mercies, if we rest contented in the sphere where He places us, be it one of wealth or poverty; if we strive earnestly to labor in the cause of right, if we trust God implicitly in the hour of trial, if we seek and find grace to over-     <pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6905-00000009"/> OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.  17   come temptation, - in a word, if we are wholly consecrated to God, happiness will be ours whatever be our condition in life. As the long months passed away, a lit- tle girl came to cheer the hearts of the bereaved parents, and the withered ten- drils of their affections once more took root, and twined round this new ob- ject. Most tenderly was the little So- phie cared for, but when one year of her brief life was measured, another sor- row came. The gentle Lady Anne had become an invalid, and every day found her weaker than the last. The Baron had. been absent on pressing business for two weeks, when tidings came that the Baroness was dangerously ill, and he hastened to Nasseriet. Having reached his home, he waited a moment for the news of his arrival to precede   him, then hastened, with a heart full of misgivings to the sick chamber. The Baroness lay panting for breath, but a sweet smile lighted up her features as the Baron entered, and for the last time they exchanged  greetings. The physician stood by the bedside, and the husband tried to read hope in his features; but the expression continued unchanged. When he went out the Baron followed. "Tell me; is she dangerously sick?" he asked, as together they entered the library. The physician hesitated before replying, dreading to reveal that which must soon take place. "There is but little hope. I fear her life will last only a few hours longer." An expression of anguish passed over the Baron's features but he did not speak, and the physician left him. After a time he came from the library, and having de.      <pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6905-00000010"/> 8     SOPHE DEBRENTZ; spatched a messenger for the village priest, returned to the bedside of the Ba roness. A change had come during hiss. absence, and death had set its seal in unmistakable lines upon her sweet coun- tenance. Looking up as the Baron entered, she exclaimed with the foreboding which often precedes dissolution, "Tell me; is this death?" That expression of agony again re- turned, but his lips could form no an- swer. "It is enough;" said the dying woman. "Let my child be brought to me." The little one .came, and the mother clasped her passionately to her heart. The child, all unconscious of her coming bereavement, looked up into the soft, dark eyes of her mother and smiled. The door now opened to admit the priest,   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.  19 and the countenance of the Baroness brightened. Going up to the bedside, he dipped his finger in the holy water and made the sign of the cross upon her fore- head; then held up the crucifix which she devoutly kissed. After giving her the pretended absolution for sin he asked, "Does the way look dark to you, my daughter?" The countenance of Lady Anne wore a troubled expression as she replied, "The river of death is deep; I shrink from entering its waters." "May our holy mother, her Blessed Son, the angels, and all the saints sus- tain you!" was the response of the priest. A moment of silence was fol- lowed by the death struggle, which only ceased when the breath left the body forever. Deep gloom now hung on the Baron's     <pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6905-00000011"/> '0    SOPHE DE BRENTZ;        / Lome. In a spacious room, draped in  black, and lighted by dim tapers, lay the  precious dust; and the humble villagers   to whose wants she ministered in life,  came to look upon the revered one there,  re she should be interred with all the  pomp and show attending a Roman Cath- lic funeral.   The death of the Lady Anne was a  sore bereavement to the Baron, and his   heart rebelled still more against his Heav-  enly Father, now  that he had taken  another of his treasures. He murmured at what he called the injustice of God, had but for the little Sophie, life would  have lost all charms for him.  Mis-  guided man! He had yet to learn that  whom the Lord loveth, He chasteneth." The little motherless one, in the arms  of her nurse, laughed in infant glee, all unconscious of her bereavement. What   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.  21  can compensate for the loss of a mother? Who fills the aching void made by her removal? Others may be kind to us, but it is not a mother's earnest, self sacri- ficing tenderness;-- others may be inter- ested in our welfare, but it is not the deep, all-pervading solicitude of a moth- er;-others may be friendly, but they will not cling to us in weal or wo, in health or sickness like a mother. Yea, though poverty, and disgrace overtake him, and the whole world forsake, still she will cling to her offspring. Though vice has left its impress on his brow, and his hands are blackened by crime, still will she remain true. She will follow him to the noisome dungeon, to torture, and to death itself. A mother's love  It is deep as the ocean, and limitless as the universe.   <pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6905-00000012"/> ()        .1 CHAPTER II. "And colored lamps sent forth their odorous light Over gold carvings, and the purple Of tapestry; and round each stately hall' Were statues, pale, and delicate and fair, And all of beauty, save her blush was there. And, like light clouds, floating around each room, The censers sent their breathings of perfume; And scented waters mingled with the breath Of flowers, that died as they rejoiced in death. *  *  *   *. *  *  * At first the pillared,halls were still and lone As 't were some fairy palace, all unknown To mortal eye or step. This was not long; Soon woke the lute, and rose the voice of song; And the wide mirrors glittered with the crowd Of changing shapes." *    *  *  * Two  years  had  passed  away, during which  time the little Sophie was left al- most entirely   to the  care of  servants. So many sad associations clung around the Baron's home, that notwithstanding his attachment to Tyrol, he was glad to be  away;  and  only  returned  now  and 22   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.   23 then to visit his little girl. Sophie, in the meantime, was indulged in all her childish caprices; and her self-will, and proud, imperious temper were already beginning to show themselves. The fol- lowing will serve as an illustration. One morning in the temporary absence of her nurse, the little one strayed into the libra- ry, and soon busied herself with a valua- ble book, of .engravings which had been carelessly left on the chair. Her excla- mations soon. attracted the servants, who were seeking her, to the room; but no persuasions could make, her relinquish the beautiful book. At length the nurse forcibly took it away; when the child stood with flashing eyes, and stamping her little foot, demanded its return. No atten- tion was paid to this, when she passion- ately threw herself on the floor amid loud sobs and cries. The nurse, thus    <pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6905-00000013"/> 24     SOPHE DE BRE'TZ; frightened into obedience, raised the sob- bing child, soothed and quieted her, then gave her the book and led her to the nursery. When the little girl was four years old her father married an Italian lady, and having sold his Tyrolese home, took Sophie to live with him in Florence, Italy. Shall I describe to you the new residence? Imagine a stately edifice of white marble, of Grecian architecture, overlooking several terraces covered with orange trees, and rich exotics. The front entrance was reached by a wide stair- way, with broad steps of marble. Pillars of porphyry surrounded the building, and in the court two 'fountains were constant- ly playing, while other fountains rose along the terraces, glittering in the sun- shine, and then falling in a shower below. The spacious saloons were furnished with   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.   25   crimson velvet and gold, and the private drawing-room with white satin, embroi- dered with various colors. The rooms were profusely decorated with valuable pictures and beautiful statues, beside the smaller ornaments of jasper and lapis la- zuli. In a retired part of the building was the large and valuable library, con- taining the standard works in Italian and German, beside many in Latin and Eng- lish literature. Florence, the adopted home of the Tyrolese nobleman, is one of the most beautiful cities in Italy. It is situated on the classic Arno, at the base of the lofty Appenines, which, sweeping round to the north, screen it from the storms of win- ter. With their peaks glittering with snow, and their sides covered with chest- nut groves, they form, in their solitude, a striking contrast to the busy streets 3     <pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6905-00000014"/> 26     SOPHE DE BRENTZ;  of the populous city. Nearer, and im- mediately ovrlooking the town is the vine-covere height of Fiesole, on whose summit stands a convent half hid in the cypress grove. The city itself presents many attrac- tions; commodious houses, good shops and markets, extensive and accessible libraries, well-filled galleries of paintings and statuary, and public parks for riding or walking; yet, like the rest of Italy, it shows the baneful effects of a govern- ment without the Bible. Beggars crowd the streets, vehemently soliciting charity of the passer-by, and in every depart- ment of trade falsehood and cheating are i   constantly practised. Nor are the mor- als of the higher classes more unim- peachable. Wanting in the right princi- ples themselves, they look upon others. with coldness and distrust; thus com,:   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.  27 pletely banishing that confidence which is the great bond of human society. Says an English traveller, "There is a lamentable want of true dignity and le- gitimate pride among the Italian nobles. They consider the practice of useful employments beneath them; yet often stoop to base, dishonorable actions, and are for the most part uneducated and illiterate. No ennobling pursuit, no hon- orable end of existence gives a useful stimulus to their lives, or energy, dignity, and consistency to their characters * *  *  * "Among the lower classes, truth, honesty, and industry are but little prized. They will cheat whenever they can, and sometimes take more pains to accomplish this than would enable them to gain far more by fair dealing. When detected in falsehood they exhibit a won- derful degree of coolness and careless-   <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6905-00000015"/> 28     SOPHE DEBRENTZ; ness. I have met with honest and excel- lent Italians in all ranks; but must admit that knavery, meanness and profligacy are far more common. "But their indolence is to an English- man the most extraordinary feature of their character. When asking for goods at a shop in Rome, I have frequently been answered with a drawling 'We have none,' when I saw the articles before my eyes; and was once actually told that they were too high to reach I At one time a shoemaker, after having taken my measure, resigned my future custom, rather than send the shoes home at the distance of two streets." Such is Roman Catholic Italy; and in her cities these elements of society are most clearly exhibited. The Bible is withheld, and such results must of neces- sity follow. Yet in spite of such disad- vantages, Florence has given birth and   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.  29 residence to some eminent men. Michael Angelo, the prince of Italian sculptors, the painter Raphael, the poet Dante, and the great astronomer Galileo all had here their home.  The pride of Florence is its cathedral, standing in a fine open situation, with its proud octagonal dome towering above every other church, and distinctly seen from every part of the city. It is built of black and white marble in alternate stripes, and profusely ornamented. The style of architecture of both exterior and interior is a mixture of Gothic and Gre- cian. The interior is inlaid and paved with marble, hung with paintings and adorned with statues. The ERomanists spare no expense in building and adorn- ing their churches, as though outward pomp and splendor could fill the place of pure religion in the human heart. 3*    <pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6905-00000016"/> 30     SOPHE DE BRENTZ; The following extract is taken from the letter of an English resident in Italy, written after having visited the cathedral at Florence. "Above the altar, the statue of God himself was pointed out to me, sitting behind some candle:sticks! Inexpressi- bly shocked, I asked the lacquery if it was really meant for the Supreme being? 'Sicuro!' replied he, no less aston- ished on his side at the abhorrence I (  expressed. Sometime passed before I recovered from my amazement and hor- ror. The image of God, fashioned by the hands of man was to me the excess of profanation; and shocked me like blas- phemy. But the Italians seem to think representations of the Deity in painting and sculpture neither impious or repre- hensible and not more profane than those of the Virgin Mary. The image of the   ' Eternal Father' is less common than any other in Italian churches, only I appre- hend because he is less the object of worship. The Virgin is beyond all com- parison the most adored.  Particular saints in particular places may divide with her the general homage, but they enjoy at best only a local and transient popularity. A saint which is greatly venerated in one town is thought noth- ing of at another, while the worship of the Virgin is universal in all places where Romanism holds its sway. "After the Virgin, some of the princi- pal saints appear to me most worshipped, while ' the high and lofty One who inhab- iteth eternity' occupies the last, and smallest place in the hearts of Roman- ists. This pmay appear shocking, but it is too true. I do not exaggerate in affirming that throughout Italy, Spain    <pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6905-00000017"/> 32    SOPHE DE BRENTZ; and Portugal, for one knee bent to God, thousands bow before the shrines of the Virgin and the saints. "I know I shall be told by the advo- cates of Romanism that the latter are addressed only as mediators at the throne of the Most High. This may be the doctrine of the clergy when on their guard, and especially in their represen- tations to Protestants, but it is the belief of the compmon people whom they teach, that the virtue and holiness resides in the image itself. If this were not true,-- if the image of a saint or Madonna, (the Virgin,) were considered as nothing more than their visible representation, why should one be better than another? Why should distant pilgrimages be performed, and crowds flock to worship one particu- lar image if it possessed no specific pow-   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.   33   er or virtues? And why should there be any miracle-working images at all?" Such were the scenes and influences now encircling, Sophie DeBrentz. Her step-mother was a rigid Romanist. Un- like the gentle Lady Anne, she was proud, stately and reserved, delighting in pomp and parade. Much of her time was passed in scenes of pleasure, leaving Sophie to the care of her ignorant nurse, who was always ready to indulge all the whims of the self-willed child. Sophie was far from being stupid. On the con- trary she thought much, and was disposed to ask questions about what she did nQt' understand. She saw but little of her mother, and then the cold reserve of the latter prevented inquiries on the part of the child. The Baron, now Count De Brentz, held an office under the Italian *Rome in the Nineteenth Century. *   <pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6905-00000018"/> 34    SOPHE DE BRENTZ; government, and spent the most of his time in Rome. She could only ask the nurse about the things she did not un- derstand, who generally answered her questionings with an indolent "I don't know." "Why is it," asked the little girl, going up to her nurse one day, "why is it that the Virgin is called the Holy Mother?" The other, without lifting her eyes, gave her usual reply; "I don't know." "But I will know," persisted the child. "Tell me quick, or I will break this; " she exclaimed, raising a beautiful vase of lapis lazuli. "Why, what did you say?" asked the nurse cousing from her stupor. "Why is the Virgin called the Holy Mother? Tell me quick." "Because,-because she was the moth- er of Jesus."   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.  35 "Sut who was Jesus?" asked Sophie. And why did being the mother of Jesus make her holy?  "That is all I know about it;" replied the nurse. "You are a great trouble to me." And she turned her back to the child, who threw the vase on the table and left the room, slamming the door after her. Thus she lived and grew; no labor or expense was spared to adorn the exterior while the immortal soul was left uncared for and neglected.    <pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6905-00000019"/> mi of CHAPTER III. Onward for the truths of God!  Onward for the right!  Firmly let the field be trod In life's coming light! Heaven's own hand will lead thee on;  Guard thee till thy task is done!" WHEN ' Sophie  DeBrentz  was very young she was confirmed, or admitted to  the communion  of the church.  The  Romish creed does not require the heart  to be changed before one is admitted as a  communicant, but one has only to be- lieve that the Roman Catholic is the true  religion. The children are baptised in infancy, and when still very young par- take of the sacrament, which the Roman-  its consider a saving ordinance. After her confirmation Sophie was in the habit of attending the services at the  cathedral. She by degrees became fa- 36   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.  37 miliar with the forms and ceremonies of the church, and with a natural re for the beautiful, gazed with ad- miration on the pictures and statues of the cathedral, and became a devout wor- shipper of the Virgin Mary and the saints. Ask you how the Romanists can with impunity break the command, "Thou shalt not make unto thee any graven image, or any likeness of anything that is in heaven above, or in the earth be- neath, or that is in the water under the earth; thou shalt not bow  down to them, nor serve them?" Their version of the Bible differs from the Protestant, and is changed to suit their religion. The commandment just quoted is stricken out from their Bibles, and another divided in order to make the    <pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC6905-00000020"/> 83  SOPHE DEBRENTZ; At stated periods Sophie went to a priest, her mother's confessor, to ac- knowledge all her childish errors, firmly believing that he had the power pos- sessed by God alone; that of forgiving sins. This priest, Father Ambrose, was of mediuml height, and his coal black hair :nd eyes betokened his Italian origin. His features were regular and might have been pleasing had not the wily character of the man been impressed upon them. Yet he was a good speci- men of the priests of Rome. Outwardly sanctimonious in demeanor, and wholly devoted to the intersts of the church, he believed, and acted upon the doctrine, "that the end . sanctifies the means." Possessing no small share of cunning, and a deep reserve which concealed his designs, he cared not how proselytes to Romanism  were made, if they were   wealthy, and their wealth would be like- ly to revert to the Church. The priests of the Romish church as- sume an almost unlimited sway over the minds of thq people. It is policy with them to keep the mind in ignorance, and the reading of the Bible is prohibited under the pretence that it cannot be understood by the illiterate. The ser- vices of the churches are usually in Lat- in, and few can comprehend, and still fewer profit by them. When Sophie DeBrentz was six years old a governess was provided for her, and she daily spent several hours in the school-room. This governess, Senora Isola, was a beautiful, but indolent and unprincipled Italian girl, belonging to a noble family. No pains or expense had been spared in her education, but she learned much in the nunnery, where she     <pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC6905-00000021"/> went for instruction, that was calculated to corrupt and debase, rather than ele. vate and refine her nature. Ere the death of her parents, and their previous loss of fortune she had become an adept in artfulness and deception, and though urged to take the veil, refused; for she loved the world too well; and rather than quit it forever, preferred to take a humbler position in life. Such was Senora Isola; one little fitted to have the control of an immortal mind. Yet Sophie's intellect, under circu(stan- ces so unfavorable, developed rapidly; and her love for reading and study shield- ed her in a great degree from the influ- ence of the governess; who soon indo- lently yielded to the child's imperious will, and allowed her to follow her own inclinations. It seemed the great misfor?;- tune of Sophie's childhood, that the man4 B           * ^r.   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.  41   inquiries that suggested themselves to her mind should remain all unanswered. She learned little from Senora Isola save what was in her text-books, for the gov- erness was too indolent to search out what was deep, or grasp what was com- prehensive. But difficulties, instead of discouraging the child only incited her to greater effort - rousing her dormant ener- gies, and calling forth the slumbering powers of mind. There was one branch of study how- ever, of which teacher and pupil were alike fond; the science of music. Senora Isola took pleasure in cultivating the sweet, expansive voice of her pupil, and introduced her into the class of young girls, which the Abbess was training to sing in the cathedral. They met in the chapel of the convent, where the Abbess ,*so assembled them once a week to in- 4*     <pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6905-00000022"/> struct them in the doctrines of the Romish Church. The Abbess, or Sister Agnes, as she was called by the nuns, was a noble look- ing woman of fifty. At the early age of seventeen she entered the convent of Santa Maria, of the Franciscan order, where she still remained. The Francis. can is one of the mildest forms of con- vent life, yet the face of Sister Agnes wore an unhappy expression, and the fire that flashed at times from her dark eyes, showed that the passions of earth had not wholly died out in her heart. The convent was a large building, three stories high, in the quadrangle form. Within this quadrangle was a small gar- den where the nuns were allowed to walk, but could go no farther from the convent walls. While the nuns belonging to some orders are never allowed to see   their friends, those of the convent of Santa Maria could converse with them through the iron grate, and at times were permitted to meet their female friends in the parlor of the convent. They were all from the families of the nobility, and by virtue of the order, exempted from the daily fasts, nightly vigils, and mortifi- cations of the body, which devout Ro- manists consider the path to Heaven; believing that bodily austerities, instead of a heart renewed by grace, will pre- pare them for the abodes of bliss. We now pass over some half a dozen years in the life of Sophie when her hours of study were in some measure diminished. Thus released from the school-room, she saw more of her moth- er, and the numerous visitors, who fre- quented the place. Many of these were foreign noblemen, and Sophie listened   <pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6905-00000023"/> with interest to the description of coun- tries and people different from her own. She was particularly interested in the conversations of Lord Ardley, an Eng- lishman, past the prime of life, with whom her father had contracted a friendship abroad. He was a true nobleman, and a sincere Christian. Observing the interest which Sophie took in his recitals, he sometimes invited her to walk with him on the broad terrace, in the shade of the orange trees, and told her of his home in England. He spoke of England's schools and churches, and described the institu- tions where the English youth meet to study God's word, and their hearts, as well as their intellects, are educated. These interviews made Sophie very thoughtful. She could not understand why she should be forbidden to have and read the Bible any more than the English   a / l I II- ,'-' ,   girls. She dared not speak her thoughts to those around her, for she well remem- bered how shocked Sister Agnes once looked, when Helena Peruzi, one of the music class, asked her if she had a Bible. Her longings to see the forbidden book grew stronger every day; and one morn- ing, after she had been reading of a Sabbath School celebration, in an English paper loaned her by Lord Ardley, she went out and joined that nobleman in his walk along the terrace. "Why are not Bibles as common here as in England?" asked she, abruptly. The other hesitated, and then replied, "Because the government and religion are different." "But is it not a good book? and if so, why is it not read? Why should any be unwilling to possess it?" "Yes, it is the' best of books; but    <pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC6905-00000024"/> "    SOPHE DE BRENTZ;  there are many who do not wish to read it, and some think it a sin to possess it." "You have them, have you not?" "Only one copy for my own use." "Can they not be purchased at the book-stores?" "Not in Florence, or Rome; but in England they are to be had in every town." "Then I wish that I lived in England; for I know it must be a better country than this." Lord Ardley sighed as he answered, "Perhaps your father will take you there some day." The ringing of the study bell ended their conversation, and as Sophie slowly passed up the walk she determined in the face of all prohibitions and difficulties to see and read the Bible. This was not a strange determination for one whose   -OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.   47   wishes were seldom opposed, and who was unaccustomed to consult any will except her own. One afternoon not long after, becoming weary of the insipid gossip of Senora Isola, and of her mother's stately reserve, she wandered into the garden and turned into a rose-covered arbor, beside which a cool fountain was playing. A book was lying on the cushioned seat, and sitting down she carelessly took it up and open- ed it. The book was an English Bible, bearing on the fly-leaf the name of Lord Ardley. Uttering a joyful exclamation, the young girl eagerly commenced read- ing the forbidden book notwithstanding the conscientious scruples that would now and then trouble her. She had opened at the twenty-second chapter of Luki, and with deep interest she read the account of the Last Supper,     <pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC6905-00000025"/> of our Saviour's arrest, trial, crucifixion, and death. She had already learned that Christ died to save sinners, but now the sacrifice stood forth in its unparalleled magnitude nhldshe saw and felt that Christ died for her as truly as if there were no other being to be saved. But the plain, simple sketch of the Last Sup- per troubled her. Like all Romanists, she had been taught to believe that the bread and wine used at the sacrament are, by a miracle, changed into the real body and blood of Christ. But she read, "Do this in remembrance of me," and gradually the scales of error fell from her eyes. She perceived that the sacrament of the Lord's Supper included no miracle, but it was instituted simply in memory of His death; merely to keep in view the one great sacrifice for sin. Sophie was not conscious that in even   conceiving' this view of things she was, in the opinion of Romanists, guilty of the grossest blasphemy; for the Host, that is, the bread pretended to be changed into the body of Christ, is, on being elevated by the priest, actually worshipped by the people. Still, till the twilight hour came on, she sat reading truths never forgotten; for long afterward they became to her the " savor of life unto life." The Sword of Truth had pierced her heart, and the wound never wholly closed till healed by the all-availing blood of Christ. As the young girl closed the volume, and was rising to leave the arbor, she was startled by approaching footsteps. It was Lord Ardley searching for the lost book. A troubled expression passed over his features when he saw it in Sophie's hand. Possessing a high sense of honor, he deemed it ingratitude to his kind and    <pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC6905-00000026"/> O    SOPHE DE BRENTZ; hospitable friend, the Count, should he seek to make a convert to Protestantism of his daughter. Yet he feared that thus leaving his Bible in her way night be construed into such an attempt, for he well knew its power to reveal the errors of Romanism. Sophie noticed his anxious expression as she gave the Bible into his hand. "You have passed the afternoon pleas. antly?" remarked the nobleman, forcing a smile. "Yes, and profitably too, I trust, was the reply. "Are you willing that your friends should remain ignorant of the manner in which this afternoon has been spent?" Another glance into his face, and So- phie replied, "Do not fear that I shall ever betray my father's friend. If there is any blame I am the guilty one; and    yet I am glad I have seen that long covet- ed Bible. I spend many afternoons alone, and no inquiry is ever made as to the na- ture of'my employments; so there is nothing to fear." The nobleman turned away without re- plying, but tears were in his eyes, and he mentally prayed that the straying one might be led into the fold of Christ. Not long after this interview, Lord Ard- ley left Florence; and a long time passed before he and Sophie again met; an eventful season to the young Florentine.     <pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC6905-00000027"/> CHAPTER IV. "Blessed are ye when men shall revile you, and per- secute you, and say all manner of evil against you falsely for my sake. Rejoice, and be exceeding glad; for great is your reward in Heaven; for so persecuted they the prophets that were before you." THE morning had dawned bright and beautiful over "Florence the Fair," and the dew-drops still lingered on the flowers as Sophie, accompanied by Senora Isola, descended the marble steps of her palace home, and took the carriage for the con- vent. It was Sister Agnes' hour for catechising her young class, and as the convent bell sounded on the still air, the young Italian girls entered the chapel, and took their several places. Sister Ag. nes went on undisturbed in the exercise till she came to Sophie with the question,   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.  53 "What is the bread used at our holy com- munion?" Instead of giving the expected reply- "The body of Christ," the maiden quietly replied "Bread." Sister Agnes looked a little surprised, but supposing that she was misunderstood repeated the question. "Bread;" again replied the young girl; "Bread made of flour and water." Fire flashed from the eyes of Sister Agnes, and raising the little rattan which she held in her hand gave Sophie a se- vere blow upon her neck; then openifg the door of a little ante-room that led out from the chapel, bade her enter. She dared not disobey, but went proudly in; and when the door was closed, yielded to all the violence of unrestrained pas- sion.  Poor Sophie! It was a hard lesson for the self-willed girl, but she .had only yet 5*     <pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC6905-00000028"/> SOPHE DEBRENTZ;  began to know the strength of the Arm of Rome. After the exercises of the morning were over, Sister Agnes went to the angry girl, and endeavored to ascertain what motive prompted the heretical an- swer, but was received in proud silence. Finding that she could learn nothing from Sophie, she charged Senora Isol; to ac- quaint her parents with the circulmstan- ces, and the two departed. Count DeBrentz and his lady were both away; he at Rome, and she at a fete given in honor of one of Rome's cardi- nals in another'part of the city. When she returned Senora Isola told her of Sophie's strange conduct, making some additions and comments of her own; for little love existed between teacher and. pupil. Sophie was too truthful for the scheming Isola, and the latter well knew   that the stronger terms she used, and the more indignation she expressed, the bet- ter should she recommend herself to the bigoted Countess. Astonishment and anger governed the latter by turns, while she was perplexed, and. undecided what course to pursue; for Father Ambrose, as well as the Count, was absent from the city. Without seeing Sophie, or asking any explanations, the Countess ordered her to be confined to her room. This act of injustice roused the temper of the young girl to the highest pitch; and very bitter were her feelings towards her mother and Sister Agnes, while from the depths of her heart she execrated Romanism. At the end of two days Father Am- brose returned and Sophie was summoned to the confessional. She went with a. firm determination not to reveal the se- cret of her changed sentiments, and thus    <pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC6905-00000029"/> 6    SOPHE DE BRENTZ; implicate Lord Ardley, though it should subject her to life-long imprisonment. Father Ambrose greeted her kindly and bade her to be seated; then in a moment or two, repeated the question asked by Sister Agnes; and Sophie with flashing eyes gave the same reply.. Without mak. ing any comments on this, the priest pro- ceeded to question her concerning the other articles of the Romish faith, and re- ceived satisfactory answers. Then he tried to ascertain from what source she had imbibed the heresy, but in vain. "Leave me, heretic!" at length ex- claimed the priest angrily; "Leave me, till you are willing .to confess the power, and submit to the' doctrines of the True Church - our Holy Mother." Sophie turned away disappointed, as- tonished, and indignant. "I do not deserve such treatment," she exclaimed,   when he had left the room. "I have con- fessed to him all these years; and now for him to regard me as base and reckless is more than I will tamely submit to. I will never, never confess to him again, though my life be the forfeit." Of her mother the proud girl expected neither sympathy, or charity; for the Countess had never sought, or received her confidence. So she was not greatly surprised when, after her interview with Father Ambrose, she knelt as was her custom on returning from the confessional to receive her mother's blessing, that the flatter turned coldly away telling her to return to her room. Reader, do you wonder at the intoler- ance shown to Sophie DeBrentz? The Roman Catholip is an intolerant religion. Its adherents, believing or professing to believe that all without the pale of the   <pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC6905-00000030"/> Romish Church are lost forever, and that the extermination of heretics meets the approval of HlAven, have always been noted for their persecutions. It was this spirit of persecution that kindled the fires of Smithfield, and presided over the slaughter of St. Bartholomew's Eve; which hunted to death the Scottish Cove. nanters, and the pure-minded Waldenses; and which has made martyrs in every age and country where the Roman Catholic is the prevailing religion. Alas I How unlike the precepts and example of the meek and lowly Jesus, whom the Roman- ists profess to follow I    CHAPTER V. "There are three preachers ever preaching, Each with eloquence and power; One is old, with locks of white, Skinny as an anchorite; And he preaches every hour With a shrill, fanatic voice, And a bigot's fiery scorn, ' Backward; ye presumptuous nations! Man to misery is born; Born to drudge, and sweat, and suffer; Born to labor, and to pray; Priests and kings are God's vicegerents, Man must worship and obey! Backward; ye presumptuous nations! Back! Be humble and obey!'" FOR several days after the return of Father  Ambrose,   Sophie  DeBrentz  re. mained  confined to  her  room.  In  the meantime the Countess and the priest held several conferences, the result of which was a decision to send the refraco tory girl to the convent of Santa Maria;    <pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC6905-00000031"/> SOPHE DE BRENTZ. ere to remain till she confessed her  errors and renounced them forever. The last two weeks had been a severe trial season for the hitherto spoiled and pet ted child of fortune. Yet her proud spirit was far from being broken, and instead of the fretfulness of a child, she assumed the dignity of the woman, scorn- ing to complain. One morning her door was thrown open, and she summoned to the library, where sat her mother and the priest. They greeted her kindly, while she still maintained her haughty bearing, and Father Ambrose addressed her in his blandest tones. "We have sent for you, my daughter," said he, " to consult with you. Our course may have seemed to you severe, but you have been guilty of the grievous sin of blasphemy; and the punishment    OR) THE SWORD OF TRUTH.   61 has been light when compared with the fearful nature of the offence. Two courses are now open before you. Either confess from what source you imbibed those heretical principles, which you have so unblushingly avowed, and, repenting, perform such penance for your sin as I shall deem proper to inflict, or else go to the convent of Santa Maria, there to re- main and perform all the duties of a nun, till you confess your sin, and receive absolution. Three hours will be given you, and then we shall await your de- cision." "I do not wish for a moment;" replied Sophie, her eyes meeting the priest's with a look as firm as his own; "I shall iot confess." "Prepare then to leave the home4hich you have forfeited;" exclaimed Father Ambrose harshy, while the Countess sat     <pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC6905-00000032"/> SOPHE DE BRENTZ; ? -mor in stern silence. Without another word Sophie rose and left the room. An hour had not passed when Sophie entered the carriage that stood before the door. She went forth alone; for her mother and Senora Isola purposely avoid- ed an interview. As she sank upon the cushioned seat, a sense of her helplessness and desolation rushed over her, and, giv- ing one yearning look toward the home she was leaving, her proud heart at last gave way, and throwing herself back into the carriage she wept bitterly. Yet no thought of accepting the conditions pro- posed by Father Ambrose entered her mind. Had a different course been pur- sued, had she been treated less sternly and harshy she would probably have yielded to the wishes of her friends. Her offence was not an intentional one, and every new unkindness only roused within,   more of the spirit of resistance and more hatred toward Father Ambrose and Ro. manism. Had not Count DeBrentz been deeply attached to his only child, and regarded her as the  perpetuator of the noble house of DeBrentz, she would have been forced to take the veil and become a nun in reality; for the stern priest, deeming the measures he had taken most pacific, now thought to have recourse to harsh- ness. Sophie was the sole heir to an immense fortune, which he was deter- mined should at some future time revert to the church. This was the secret of his zeal. Sister Agnes had been apprised of So- phie's coming, and instructed how to pro- ceed. She met the young girl at the convent gate,' and coldly greeting her, conducted her to the room which was to    <pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC6905-00000033"/> SOPHE DE BRENTZ;       3 be hers while she remained in the place. Here Sophie was obliged to attire herself at once as a nun in a long, ill-fitting gown of black serge. The love of the beauti- ful was a strong element in the young girl's nature, and when she glanced around the room with its bare floor and walls her heart sank within her. The only furniture was a narrow bed, with its coarse covering, a little bare wooden ta- ble, on which lay a prayer-book and cru- cifix, and one chair. Sister Agnes had left Sophie to the companionship of her own thoughts, and the poor girl was in no enviable frame of mind. She knew not how long she had sat brooding over her wretchedness, when she was roused by the ringing of a bell, and one of the nuns came to conduct her to the dining hall. This was large, cold, and cheerless, and the soup, of which the   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.   65   nuns eagerly partook, was nauseating to Sophie, accustomed as she had been from infancy to the luxuries of life. She was allowed to spend her time pretty much as she pleased with one exception; the reli- gious duties imposed upon the nuns she was required strictly to perform. The nun's apartments in every story opened upon a walk which extended round the quadrangle of the buildings, and surmounting the convent was a cupola. In a few days Sophie had become familiar with the localities of the convent,-the little square garden surrounded on every side by the walls of the building, the walks running around its sides, and the cupola, from which she could see the smoke, and sometimes hear the distant din of the city. Ono or two of the nuns were friendly to the young outcast, and taught her how 6*      <pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC6905-00000034"/> SOPHE DE BRENTZ;  to embroider, and do the various kinds of needle-work which took no inconsiderable share of their time. But as a general thing however, she was avoided by the sisterhood, for her story was well known among them, and she sought not their friendship. She had not been long at the convent when she sought the library; but the books there were not calculated to feed a mind like hers; as its principal works were the lives of eminent Roman Catholic saints, and foolish legends of their pre- tended miracles. All the books bore the marks of neglect, being mouldy and cov- ered with dust. They had not been disturbed for months before Sophie's coming. One day as she was rummaging among the old books, she removed one from its place, revealing a smaller one which had been hidden behind it. She took up the   latter, and her surprise and delight may be better imagined than described when she discovered that it was a copy of the New Testament in Italian. How it came there was a strange mystery, but Sophie did not stop to speculate. Concealing the book in the ample folds of her dress, she conveyed it in triumph to her apart- ment. Once a week Father Ambrose came to the convent to give Sophie an opportuni- ty to confess if she would, and she as often firmly refused to see him. Left much to herself by Sister Agnes and the nuns, she spent her time in studying the little Testament; and the more she stud- ied, the stronger was her opposition to Romanism. After the young girl had been with the nuns for a few Bnonths, she learned that a young. lady of noble family, one of the    <pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC6905-00000035"/> 3s   SOPHE DE BRENTZ; Abbess' music class, with whom she was intimately acquainted, was about to take the veil in the convent of Santa Maria. This was a happy event in the monoto- nous life of the nuns, not only because it added another to their numbers, but be- cause it relieved the tediousness of their weary existence, and gave them some- thing to think and talk about. Helena Peruzi, as we have before inti- mated, belonged to one of the noblest families of Florence. Influenced by the pomp and show attending the ceremony of taking the veil, as well as the superficial beauty and sanctity of the scene, she had * expressed a half-formed determination some months before to become a nun. In this she was warmly seconded by the priest, her confessor, and there was policy in his encouragement; for by her becoam- ing a nun her large property would revert   us, T'LE SWORD OP TRUTH.  69 to the church. Her parents also second. ed the resolution, feeling that they were performing a most meritorious act in thus giving up their daughter to the undis- turbed observance of a religious life. The day came at last, when the beauti- ful Helena was to leave the gay world forever, and immure herself within the gloomy walls of a convent. At an ear- ly hour Sister Agnes with her train of nuns, among whom was Sophie, took their places behind the gilded grate, through which, though unseen themselves, they could behold every part of the church; and Sophie's heart thrilled with emotion as she saw her mother enter with the crowd of people with whom the building was soon densely filled. The crowd enjoy this pageant of artifi. cial sanctity, and it has upon them the intended effect; to make them believe    <pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC6905-00000036"/> 70     SOPHE DEBRENTZ; the cloister a welcome retreat from the sins and sorrows of earth. Alas How often do those within its walls bitterly execrate their fate I The pathway to the church, the aisle, as well as the steps of the altar were strewed with flowers, and soon the fair Italian, richly dressed, and supported by her mother, entered and advanced to the altar. A discourse was then pronounced by a Dominician monk. He addressed her as the affianced spouse of Christ, a saint on earth, and one who had renounced the vanities of earth for a foretaste of the joys of heaven. There was much praise, much that was calculated to inflame the imagination in this discourse, and little of admonition, sober reason, or religion. When it closed, Helena knelt before the altar at the feet of a cardinal, and solemnly abjured the world, whose pleasures and   ,114 I. ,I ";-I -q   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.  71 affections she seemed so well calculated to enjoy, then pronounced those vows which severed her from them forever. As her voice in soft recitations chanted the fatal words, many eyes were moisten- ed with tears, and Sophie who well knew how bitterly her friend was being de- ceived, sadly wept. The diamonds sparkling in Helena's dark hair were removed, and the long, luxuriant tresses fell upon her shoulders; one lock being cut off by the cardinal. The grate about to entomb her now opened, admitting Sister Agnes, and the nuns, who chanted a strain of welcome. She then renounced her name and title, assured the new appellation of Sister Cecilia, received the solemn benediction of the cardinal, was folded for the last time in the embrace of her weeping friends, and passed through the grate,    <pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC6905-00000037"/> ghUpnlrrn         A  d wh( which was to separate her forever from all she had known and loved. In a few moments she again appeared before the grate. Here she was divested of all her ornaments, and her beautiful hair cut off close to her head. She was then attired in the sober dress of the. nuns, the white coif, and noviciate veil. This last is a piece of white linen fixed on the top, or back part of the head, and falling down behind, or on each side, pre- cisely in the manner of a veiled statue. Throughout the whole ceremony Helena, or Sister Cecilia as we must now call her, manifested great calmness and decision; but after the ceremony was all over her tears could n6t be restrained. She afterward appeared at the little postern gate of the convent to receive the sympa. thy, praise and congratulation of friends, acquaintances, and even strangers; all of acquaiutauces, ude   I I I Pld -i -4    whom were expected to pay their compli- ments to the young novice. A nun, after taking the white veil, may leave the convent if she chooses; and such instances have occurred, though they are very rare. Extreme ill-health, an incurable disease, or the death of brothers and sisters making it necessary for the victim to be recalled to support the name and fortunes of the family, are almost without exception the only rea- sons of such an event. Repentance of the choice, either concealed or avowed, is wholly vain. A novice who should persist in returning to the world would be received with its severest reprehen. sion, as well as its dread laugh. Her family would consider themselves dis- honored, and would in all probability disown her. During her whole life she would stand, an object toward Which the     <pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC6905-00000038"/>  finger of scorn would point continually. Such are the chains in which Rome binds her victims; such the influences that envelop in eternal secrecy the weariness and discontent of the cloister. The first few days of Sister Cecilia's convent life was spent almost wholly in religious exercises; and it was nearly a week before Sophie obtained an interview with her. She seemed at first desirous of avoiding her former friend, but a few con. versations quieted her scruples, and the two mingled together almost as familiar- ly as of yore. Two months had not passed ere Sister Cecilia became rest- less and unhappy. She found the reali- ties of convent life widely different from what her imagination had pictured them. There was not that calm, heavenly peace in her soul that she had been prepared to expect, and though shut out from the   OR, THE SWORD OF TRVTH.   world, her heart longed again ito share its pleasures. Now, the memory of past scenes, when she could wholly forget the present was her only enjoyment. As the time drew near for her to take the black veil and the irrevocable vows of the nun, shebecame still more wretch. ed, and one afternoon relieved her over- burdened spirit by disclosing her feelings to Sophie, as they sat together in the cu- pola. "But why do you take the black veil at all?" asked Sophie. "Why do you not return hqme when your noviciate term has expired?  Tell them that the , life of a nun is not what you imagined it to be, and as you are under no obligation to stay, you shall leave them. I know not hQw much longer I shall have to re- main in this stupid place, but I will die before I will confess to Father Ambrose,    <pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC6905-00000039"/> 36    SOPHE DE BRENTZ;  or become a nun. They would not dare to try to make a nun of me;" and the maiden lifted her head as proudly as of yore. "Oh Sophie, do you not think I would go home if I could? Why do you talk to me thus?"? replied the unhappy novice. "You do not know my father. He would rather see me dead at his feet, than to have me leave the convent; and my mother, who, as she supposed, gave me up to the undisturbed enjoyment of re- ligion, would spurn me from her presence. They would disown me, former friends would refuse to notice me, and I should be an outcast, subjected to scorn, de. rision, and insults. No, the life of a nun, weary, monbtnous, and dreadful as it is, is preferable that." Sister Agnes now appeared, and her quick ear catching the earnest tones of Sis-   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.     ter Cecilia, she sent Sophie away on some trifling errand, and forbade the other to hold any further communication with her. Thus deprived of every enjoyment, the wretched girl became silent and apathetic, scarcely caring whether she lived or died; and in this state of mind passed through the ceremony of taking the black veil. It is not in accordance with the will of God for human beings thus to shut them- selves out from their fellows. One beau- tiful passage in Christ's prayer for His disciples is, "I pray not that thou shouldst take them out of the world, but that, thou shouldst keep them from the' evil." We are placed in this world, not ; for our own good alone, but to minister to the wants of those around us; to miti- gate their sorrows, and sympathize with their joys; and by our own influence and 7*     <pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC6905-00000040"/> SOPHE DEBRENTZ; labors, to make the world wiser and purer. God refuses not to bless individ- ual effort, if made with a humble reliance on his power to give it effect; and it is the one who labors most for others who possesses the most happiness himself. "He that watereth others, shall be water- ed also," is a truth having its foundation in the nature of man; and while that is a living principle of the soul, so long will monasteries and convents remain the abodes of discontent and sorrow.   CHAPTER VI.   "Mild and mighty is forgiveness, Meekly worn if meekly won; Let the heart go forth to meet it, Ere the setting of the sun. Angels wait and long to hear us Ask it ere the time be flown; Let us ask it, and receive it Ere the midnight cometh down."   NEARLY a year had passed since Sophie DeBrentz entered the convent; a season of weariness to herself and perplexity to her friends. They expected that long be- fore this time she would yield; and hav- ing made confession, return home. They knew not the firmness of the young girl's nature, nor were they aware of her deep hatred toward Father Ambrose. Her litk tie Testament was still faithfully, though secretly studied, and while its truths were 79   <pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC6905-00000041"/> 30    SOPHE DE BRENTZ; received and embraced by her intellect, her heart remained untouched. She had become very weary and un- happy, and sometimes half repented the rash vow that was keeping her thus a prisoner. In the meantime Father Am- brose had gone to Rome on business relating to the Church, and another took his place. Father Ignatius was young in years, but possessed of a large experience and ex- tensive knowledge. The younger son of a noble Roman family, he was early des- tined for the church; and instructed from childhood in the principles of the Roman Catholic religion. There was something in the nature of the young priest that yearned for a purer life; and, unlike most of his order, he became a diligent student of the Bible. Slowly, but surely his belief in the infallibility of the Church of Rome   was undermining and giving way; but so firmly were papal principles wrought into his very being, that a long time was required wholly to eradicate them. Though no longer a Romanist, he was not ready to declare himself a Protestant when called to fill the place made vacant by Father Ambrose's removal. He had been informed of the heretical principles of Sophie, and one day started on the errand from which Father Ambrose had returned so many times without suc- cess. Sophie was standjng in the cupola, her favorite resort, g1 4g- . ipon the smoke that hid the ci  eiw u nun came to tell her that Father Ignati;s the Confessor, had come, and wished4see her. It was pleasant to hear the sound of a new name, and she immediately' d-? cided to meet the new Confessor. There was a momentary shrinking, but another    <pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC6905-00000042"/> 82    SOPHE DE BRENTZ; glance from the cupola made her firm, and she felt almost willing to risk life itself in order to be released from those hateful walls. The nun left without another word, and as soon as her decision was made Sophie followed her, and with some slight misgiv- ings entered the presence of Father Ignatius. One look, however, into his face beaming with kindness, and one sound of his gentle voice quieted all her apprehen- sions. The priest was not more than thirty. He had the coal-black hair and eyes Icaharacteristic of the Italians, but his countenance wore an habitual expres- sion of meekness and charity, and was as frank as Father Ambrose was sinister and reserved; and Sophie, feeling, as by in- stinct, that he could be trusted at once revealed to him her secret. She told how unconscious of wrong    OR, THE SWORD OP TRUTH.   she had been when giving the reply to Sister Agnes, of the manner in which she had been treated by Sister Agnes and the priest, of her mother's coldness and re- serve, and lastly of her convent life, of finding the little Testament, and of the use to which she had applied it. She dwelt with peculiar emphasis on her treatment by Father Ambrose, of her entire confi- dence in his integrity so completely de- stroyed by the harsh measures to which he had resorted; then forgetful where she was, the indignant girl broke out into bitter invectives against the absent priest. "Nay, my daughter;" exclaimed the kind Father Ignatius; interrupting her, "I cannot hear you talk thus. Remember the prayer offered by Christ for his ene- mies; 'Father, forgive them, for they know not what they do.' If He, the sin-   <pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC6905-00000043"/> less One, prayed thus, how much more should we, who have so much to be for- given! But why are you here?" he continued. "Because, in consequence of a firm resolution formed before coming here, I refused to confess to Father Ambrose, what I have just told you. I was to be confined in this place till I made con- fession; when that was done I was to be set at liberty and return home." The mild eyes :of the priest filled with tears as Sophie ceased speaking, and he rose and walked to the window; So- phie in the meantime awaiting his reply with feverish impatience. "Go," said he at length, turning toward her, "go; and when you wish to confess again, confess to God. Seek him in faith, tell him what temptations beset you, or what trials assail; ask Him to forgive all   I   I   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.   your sins for the sake of the Saviour, who died to redeem you, and implore His aid to help you in overcoming your proud, unforgiving temper." "Is this all?" asked the astonished So- phie. "Is there no atonement to make, no penance to undergo?" "No, none of these. Christ has died to redeem you. Go then to Him, and seek to become like Him. This is all I require of you. And now you are at liberty to leave the convent, and 'iiay again be received into the communion of the church. When you are ready to de- part meet me here." Joyfully the young girl left the room, but before leaving the convent she sought a stolen interview with Sister Ce. cilia, to whom she gave as a partinggift, the little Testament; feeling that she had no right to take it away, and hoping that 8    <pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC6905-00000044"/> SOPHE DE BRENTZ; it might serve in some degree to relieve the tediousness of Sister Cecilia's life. Her nun's attire was soon changed for the dress worn to the convent, and then, joining Father Ignatius, the two passed on to the cathedral. As they entered, Sophie descried her mother standing near an image of the Virgin. For a moment their eyes met, and the surprise of the Countess was visible on her countenance. Coming near them, she turned with averted eyes from Sophie, who stood, proudly wait- ing her mother's greeting, and hastily motioned Father Ignatius aside; for the services were not yet commenced. "Do you know," she asked in excited tones, " that that young girl who enter- ed with you is very sinful, unworthy to be present here?" "I wish I were as pure as that young   girl;" said the good priest, in gentle tones. "Are you aware," continued the Coun. tess, "that for nearly a year, she has con- stantly and firmly refused to enter the confessional." "She has just confessed to me. I have no fault to find with her;" was the quiet reply. "Can it be possible!  She is my daughter." "Then take her to your heart as well as your home, and watch over her tender- ly. Be gentle with her; you cannot in. fluence her by threats or harshness;" answered the priest. Just then the choir commenced a chant, and the notes of the deep-toned organ filled the house. At the close of the ser- vices the Countess met Sophie with a warm welcome, and she again became an   i   <pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC6905-00000045"/> 5    SOPHE DE BRENTZ; inmate of her beautiful home. She had been there but a few days when her fath. er returned to spend a few weeks in Flor- ence; and he was surprised and delighted to find Sopkie once more at home. Noth- ing except the strong remonstrances of Father Ambrose kept him from seeking an interview whith his daughter while immured in the convent; and it was in compliance with the advice of this priest, that the Count decided to take Sophie to Rome. The Holy Week was fast ap- proaching, and the father, seconded by the priest, deemed that a view of its im- posing ceremonies would banish all heret- ical fancies from the mind of the young girl, if any yet lingered there.: Hea little thought thus to reveal to her moreColear- ly, the hollowness, and enormie the papal religion, for in Rome, more than any other place are revealed its worldli- ness and impiety.   I   CHAPTER VII. "Thou art in Rome! The city that so long Reigned absolute, the mistress of the world; - Thou art in Rome! The city where the Gauls, Entering at sunrise through her open gates, And, through her streets, silent and desolate, Marching to slay, thought they saw gods, not men; The city that by temperance, fortitude, And love of glory, towered above the clouds, Then fell;-but, falling, kept the highest seat, And in her loneliness, her pomp of woe, Where now she dwells, withdrawn into the wild, Still o'er the mind maintains, from age to age, Her empire undiminished. *  *  *  * IT was one of balmy Italy's loveliest mornings, when the  carriage  of Count DeBrentz, with himself, the Countess, and Sophie for inmates, left Florence for Rome. Perhaps  ther, is  no  country  in the world with more natural beauties than Italy, or one possessing greater natural   <pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC6905-00000046"/> SOPHE DE BRENTZ; facilities for improvement; but the papal power broods over it like a malediction, crushing out the spirit of enterprise, and enveloping the souls of the people in mor- al darkness. The hedges on either side of the road, over which the carriage containing our travellers passed, were covered with the brilliant, blooming Lauristinus, the creep- ing Clematis, and the sweet-scented Bay. The pale, saddened hue of the Olive, now in full leaf, contrasted finely with the deep, rich green of the majestic Oaks, to which th, ivy clung in its bright beauty, seeming to say that strength should ever be the support of weakness.  Cottag- es were scattered here and there along the road, and the fields of the peasants were enclosed by rows of poplars, con- nected by intermingling lands of vines, twined from tree to tree, and hang-   ing from the branches in gay festoons, making the country look as though deck- ed for a gala day. Sometimes the road wound round the sides of hills, looking down into fertile, peaceful valleys, and for a long time ran through a beautiful vale, by the side of a clear, rippling stream, half hid in the for- est. Now and then they passed the gray walls of monasteries half concealed by the deep shade of the Columbar cypress, and spreading pine; the abodes of men who think that a life of seclusion is acceptable to God. The distance from Florence toaRome is one hundred and fifty miles; and our travellers, in the slow-moving family car- riage, were nearly a week in mipg the journey. At night they were oled to stop at the little osterias, or inns a-S the road, most of which were destitute    <pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC6905-00000047"/> 92    SOPHE DE BRENTZ. of the luxuries, and even the convenien- ces of life. It was on the afternoon of the fifth day, as the sun was resting on the western horizon, and bathing woods promontories, waters and mountains in one flood of yellow brightness, that the travellers beheld, gleaming in the depart- ing light, the beautiful dome of St. Peter's Church. Darkness, however, had gath- ered over earth before they reached the gates of the city. Rome! The Queen of Nations, the land of patriots, heroes and poets,-she is venerated alike by the Protestant and the Romanist; by the former, because she is the home of the arts; because around her cluster a thousand classic and historic memories and associations,-by the lat- ter, because she is the residence of the Pope, and the seat of the papal power. "Other cities, hdwever great or dis.   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.   93  tinguished are only the capital of a country; but Rome is the metropolis of the world. Recollections dear to every human heart, in which every nation and people can sympathise, seem to make it the common mother of all. The awful fuins of its former greatness, the proud ornaments of its early years of glory, the accumulated memorials of long years of vicissitudes, and the noblest works of genius and art in every age, unite in giv- ing it an interest and a dignity which no other spot on earth can boast. And, as we gaze upon it, all the long story of its fame, the deeds of its heroes, the shades. of its philosophers, and the strains of itf:- poets, burst upon the memory, and fill the heart with irrepressible emotion." For centuries it has been the seat of the papal hierarchy, and to the unen. "tened Romanist, is the dwelling-place    <pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC6905-00000048"/> SOPHE DE BRENTZ; of sanctity. Not half so precious to him are its ruins of the past, as are its church- es and convents, its pope, and its car- dinals. But we will return to the weary travel- lers, whom we left at the gates of the city. They reached their hotel without accident, and the next morning found them considerably rested from the fa- tigues of the journey, and prepared to meet their numerous acquaintances resid- ing in the city. Sophie was as eager to see the wonders of Rome, of which she had heard and read so much, as her father was to show them; and not long after their arrival, they rode out to see St. Peter's Church. This is usually the first place visited by strangers. Their course lay through the narrow streets of the Campus Martius. for nearly a mile; then crossing the yellow    OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.   95 Tiber, they took one of two parallel streets, the termination of which is St. Peter's, the largest church in the world. No description can do justice to its beauty and magnificence. Enriched by the spoils of ages, it is the grand empo. rium for the exhibition of useless wealth, while men in temporal' and spiritual beg- gary tread its lengthened nave, and kneel before its altars. From the wide-extend- ed front of the church, a grand semi-cir- cular colonade, sweeping round, incloses the immense area. In the centre of this area, between two beautiful fountains, stands an Egyptian obelisk of red oriental granite. The church itself is built of Tiburtine stone, brought from Tivoli. It is in the form of a cross, Aix hundred and seven feet long, and four hundred and forty-eight high. Crossing the wide piazza, the Count   <pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC6905-00000049"/> SOPHE DE BRENTZ; and his party entered a beautifully cov- ered portico, extending along the whole breadth of the building. This is support- ed by gigantic marble columns, and ter- minated at the ends by equestrian marble statues of Constantine the Great, and Charlemagne. Five doors, corresponding to those of the portico, and covered with ponderous curtains, are the entrance to the body of tfe church. Through one of these doors the party entered, and beheld the interior. of the edifice resplendent in grandeur and magnificence. As Sophie slowly and. silently walked up the long nave, empanelled with the richest and rarest marbles, discerning through the lofty arches opening views of chapels,A tombs, and altars, vieing with each other in splendor, she found that her wildest imaginings of the place had fallen far short of the reality.   The stained glass windows threw a dim light, like that of the early twilight over he church; and on every side were cross- es, decked in all the splendor that the la- bor of ages, the wealth of kingdoms, the spoils of ancient times, and the proudest inventions of modern magnificence have combined to furnish. The party now de- scended into the subterranean chapel, con- taining the tomb of St. Peter. The latter is illuminated by a hundred undying lamps, and profusely ornamented. As before remarked, Sophie DeBrentz pos. sessed a strong natural love for the beau-  tiful, and the magnificence of St. Peter's  atonished and delighted her, notwith- standing her aversion to Romanism. Now, as they stood in the gloomy abode of the dead, a silent awe crept over her - and the superstitions once resolutely cast away, gathered thickly about her; 9     <pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC6905-00000050"/> urVLU YVD DXDj iN LAL , while ever and anon the inquiry would suggest itself, "What if this religion should be true, after all?" But, firmly resisting the influence, she turned from this abode of the dead, and found her way out of the chapel. When the rest of the party joined So- phie, she stood in admiration before the great altar in the centre of the church. This is elegantly adorned with a mosaic painting, so perfect that one finds difficul- ty in believing that it is not the work of the pencil; and indeed all the altars are decorated in the same manner, though perhaps less elaborately. "Come my daughter," said the Count, when they all had sufficiently admired the painting, and taking her hand, he led her up to the statue of St. Peter, sitting in state, and holding in his right hand two keys. As is the universal custom, the   Count prostrated himself and kissed the toe of the statue. Rising he turned to- ward the maiden, who, though much she wished it, dared not to neglect this act of devotion; for was-she not in Rome? and fearless as she was, she trembled before the manifestations of papal supremacy. The chapel of the Madonna, containing an old fresco painting of the Virgin next drew their attention. Several were per- forming their devotions before the pic. ture when they entered, and among the rest, a priest. While the Count was relat. ing to his party the wonderful miracles performed by this image, the priest arose, and Sophie at once recognized her old acquaintance, Father Ambrose. A gleam of hatred shot across his features, as his eyes fell on Sophie, who, since they part- ed, had grown up tall, fair, and graceful. In an instant he resumed his old look of     <pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC6905-00000051"/> iJV&amp; r. J J J1 .lWJ, AL.  downcast reserve, but not before the young girl had had time to scan his fea- tures, and gather the meaning of what she there read. Coming forward, he cordially greeted the whole party, and warmly congratulated Sophie upon hav- ing renewed her allegiance to the church. It would have been wiser in the priest not to have disturbed the past, for this, together with that first dark look, stirred Sophie's old feelings of hatred; and re- turning his greetings coldly, she turned haughtily away. Nor did the sight of the confessionals scattered at intervals around the church tend to allay her excit- ed feelings. She well knew that by confessing to Father Ignatius when she did, she had been saved the disgrace of a public ex- posure, and that if she had still persisted in her self-willed course, excommunica-   OR, THE SWORD OP TRUTH.   101 101   tion from the church, and banishment from her father's house would have been her portion. Yet all this would have had no influence in causing her to confess to Father Ambrose, so great was her hatred toward him. After the eventful morning of her release from the convent she had regularly sought the confessional, but it was to gain that religious instruction which Father Ignatius delighted to impart. But we have kept the reader too long in the chapel of the Madonna, and will follow the, party up the broad, winding course leading to the top of the church. After a tedious and circuitous route through passages, and up winding stair. cases, they stood at length in the top of the dome; and if Sophie had been sur- prised and delighted before, she was now overwhelmed with astonishment and rap- ture at the prospect before her. 9*      <pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC6905-00000052"/> The beautiful ampitheatre of hills enclos- ing the Campagna, the loftier summits of the Appenines behind, the Tiber in its long windings through the waste, and Rome itself, with her churches, palaces, and dark, distant ruins, could not but fail to awaken deep and varied emotions in every heart. Warned at length by the lateness of the hour the party slowly and thoughtfully descended from the vast height, and again entered the church. Here Father Ambrose, who had remained waiting for them, drew the count aside to make some inquiries respecting the man- ner in which Sophie had been brought back to her allegiance; giving the latter an opportunity to observe how easily "Plenary indulgence and remission of sins," could be purchased with money. The following is one form of absolu- tion: "May our Lord Jesus Christ ab-   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.  103 solve thee through the merits of his most holy passion. And I, by His authority and that of his blessed apostles, Peter and Paul, and our holy master, the pope, do absolve thee; first, from all ecclesiasti- cal censures, howsoever incurred; next from all sins, faults, and excesses hitherto committed by thee, howsoever enormous, even those reserved to the Apostolic See, as far as the keys of the holy mother church extend; remitting by plenary in- dulgence, all punishment due to thee for the aforesaid in purgatory. And I restore thee to the holy sacraments of the church, and to -the unity of the faithful, and to the innocence and purity conferred on thee by baptism, so that the gates of punishment may be closed against thee at thy departure, and those of the joys of paradise be opened. Or, shouldst thou not presently die, let this grace remain in    <pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC6905-00000053"/> ?SbUMJE DlJE IU liN'1'TC full force, and await thee at the point of death. In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost." * A certain sum of money is thus paid for the forgiveness of sins; while the Gospel offers pardon only as the reward of sincere repentance, and amendment. Sophie turned away from these mumme- ries with feelings of strong repugnance, remembering the words of Peter; "Thy money perish with thee." The Count having returned, they entered the car- riage, and were soon at home; thus bring- ing us to the end of the chapter *Tetzel, 1517.   CHAPTER VIII. "All that we have thought, read, admired, and ven- erated from our earliest years,- all that awakens our youthful enthusiasm, -all that exalts the mind, fires the imagination, or touches the heart, is concentrated on the soil of Italy, and amidst the ruins of Rome." WEEKS passed on, and found Sophie still in Rome, still enjoying the betty and magnificence of the capital. Next to visiting St. Peter's church, she had spent a day in the Vatican. This vast edi- fice, with its gates of bronze, its polished columns of ancient porphyry, its frescoed ceilings, its ancient' Mosaic pavements, its endless accumulations of Grecian marbles, Egyptian granites, and oriental alabasters, and its amazing treasures of painting and sculpture were to her full of interest.- Hours had been spent in the extensive 105    <pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC6905-00000054"/> l. VVJ  . library, inspecting not only its books and manuscripts, but its curiosities, so innu- merable and interesting. In places like these Sophie was at home, and familiarity with such objects enlarged her mind and strengthened her character. The Holy Week was now drawing near, when pilgrims from all parts of Italy flock to Rome. A few days previous to its commnencement, the Countess and Sophie had an interview with the Pope in the summer-house of the Vatican gardens. The maiden had always been taught to consider the asssumed successor of St. Peter perfectly holy; and though now doubting everything connected with Ro- manism, it was not without a sensation of awe that she seated herself by her mother in the carpeted drawing-room of the sum- mer-house to await his arrival. He soon entered, accompanied by a cardinal, who   presented the travellers. His Highness greeted the young girl kindly, and then, entering into conversation with the Count- ess, Sophie had an opportunity to observe him closely. When at the close of an interview somewhat prolonged, they de- parted, Sophie could not help thinking that His Holiness, the Pope, seemed very much like other Italian gentleman. The palace of the Pope is within the walls of the. Vatican; but no lady may enter it.  They are invariably received in the sum- mer-house, where levees are held for them at stated seasons. Palm Sunday'had n6w come,/and at an early hour the Count and his family took seats in the Sisline chapel; and after .-; some time spent in waiting, the poped' made his appearance, attired in a robe of scarlet and gold. With a grave counter  nance and dignified bearing, he entered and- '       '       Its    <pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC6905-00000055"/> SOPHE DE BRENTZ; took his throne. The cardinals followed, arrayed in splendid vestments, and suc- cessively approaching, kissed the Pope's hand, then having retired one step, made three bows; one to the Pope in front, one on the right hand, and another on the left; the first intended for His Holiness as the personification of the Father, the others for the Son and Holy Spirit, on either side of him!  Thus does impiety and blasphemy mingle with all the sacred rites of the Roman Catholic religion! The cardinals having retired, the infe- rior priests came forward, one by one, and kissed the pope's toe. This was fol- lowed by voices chanting around the altar, after which, two palm-branches, of seven or eight' feet in length, were brought to the Pope, who, after raising aver them a cloud of incense, pronounced -upon them a benediction. A g'^ tnum-   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.   109   ber of smaller palms were then brought, and a cardinal, the Pope's assistant on this occasion, presented one of these to each cardinal, as he ascended the steps of the throne.  The latter received the palm, again kissed the Pope's hand, then retired. Then came the archbishops, who kissed both the Pope's hand; and toe, fol- lowed by the inferior orders of the cler- gy, who only kissed the toe as they carried off their palms. After the higher dignitaries were all provided with palms, the deacons, canons, choristers and cardi- nals' train-bearers were each furnished with branches -of olive, a small cross, being suspended to each, as well as to the palms. This ceremony completed, a procession. was formed, beginning with the lowest in clerical rank, who moved off, two by two, rising gradually in dignity, till they came  <pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC6905-00000056"/> to prelates, bishops, archbishops, cardi- nals, and ended with the Pope himself. borne in his chair of state on the shoul- ders of men, a crimson canopy being raised over his head. This procession of palm-bearers marched round the chapel, and after a few moments' chanted parley at the closed gates, they were opened, and the dignitaries resumed their seats. A chant was then commenced, which was i succeeded by a long and tedious service, then a series of ceremonies too insignifi- cant and wearisome to enumerate. The whole was concluded by the cardinals embracing and kissing each other, which is called the kiss of peace. This is only one of the many absurd customs observed by the papal hierarchy, seen by Sophie DeBrentz at Rome; and we have described it in detail in order'-to show how completely form and ceremony    has taken the place of true religion in the Romish Church. That there have been good men, sincere followers of the meek and lowly Jesus in this church, we do not deny; but only a glance is needed to show that the system itself is impious and unholy. We will weary the reader with but one more of the ceremonies of Holy Week, one more absurd and impious if possible, than that just described. It was on Friday, that the Countess and Sophie rode to the church of St. Andrea delle Fratte, to attend the service of "the Three Hours of Agony " of Christ upon the cross, which lasts from twelve to three. The church was crowded almost to suffocation. In the upper part were painted trees, and pasteboard rocks, and thickets, resembling Mt. Calvary. High up on the mountain were 'three crucifixes    <pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC6905-00000057"/> After with figures of Christ and the two thieves nailed upon them. A little farther down the eminence, were two Roman centu- rions, large as life, and dressed in mil- itary uniform, mounted on pasteboard horses, and carrying pasteboard swords. Romanists say that Christ spoke seven times upon the cross, and that each time a dagger entered the heart of the Virgin. She is therefore painted with seven dag- gers sticking into her breast, and is adored as "Nostra  Signora de sette dolois," "Our Lady of seven sorrows." The service is in consequence divided into seven acts, and between each is a hymn. A Dominican priest occupied the pulpit, and opened his sermon by a pre- paratory exhortation, inviting his hearers to listen to the last accents of Christ, and behold His dying agonies; saying they were caused by the ingratitude of sinners. ,   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.   After a string of apostrophes to Christ on the cross, he reviled 'the people, and re- proached them bitterly, because they did not die with grief when beholding the suf- ferings of their Redeemerl He not only abused men, but angels, and also high heaven; reproaching the latter as un- worthy of a Saviour, and adjuring it to prize Him as it ought!  At last the discourse was drawn out to the right instant of time, and the three hours were about expiring. "Ecco il memento!" "The moment has come I " cried the priest, and all sunk prostrate upon the earth, in tears; sobs, groans, and cries mingled in one loud burst of agony, filling the crowded church; as he continued, "The moment has come! t Now Jesus Christ expires!  Now our Redeemer dies! Now our Father ceases to live!    <pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC6905-00000058"/> I have said that all in that vast audience were overwhelmed with emotion; but there was one whose only change of feel- ing was contempt. That one was Sophie DeBrentz. "I enjoy going to the theatre as well as any one;" thought she, " but theatrical representations in a church dedicated to God, arfe neither right nor consistent, how- ever sacred the characters or scenes." The great object of the priest appeared to be to move the passions and emotions of his hearers; and here he was eminent- ly successful At length he loudly ex- claimed, "Here they come,- the' holy men to bear the body of our Redeemer to the sepulchre!" and a band of friars, clothed in black issued forth, and gradual- ly climbing Mount Calvary by a winding path among the rocks and bushes, reach- ed the foot of the cross unharmed by the   paper centurions. When they commenc- ed drawing out the nails from the body, the house resounded with the shrieks, cries and groans of the people. Five prayers separately addressed to the five wounds of Christ, were next re- peated. They were nearly alike, and all commenced with "Via adoro, piaqa santis- sima!" "I adore thee, most holy wound!" The pretended body of Christ, made of pasteboard, and skilfully painted, was now laid on a bier, decked with flowers, and covered with a transparent veil. It was thus brought down the artificial mountain by the friars, and laid on the front of the stage; while people of all ranks, from the prince to the, beggar thronged around to kiss the toe, and weep over it. Alas Alas! What a tribute was this to " the high and lofty One, who inhabiteth eternity!" A dramatic exhi-     <pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC6905-00000059"/> "O    ;UP!lki DE ISREJNTZ' bition, introduced under the name of a religious festival! We pass by the washing of feet, the baptism of the converted Jews, the bless- ing of horses, beside a hundred other senseless mummeries witnessed by Sophie DeBrentz, during her stay in Rome. These, though bearing no immediate fruit, except contempt for the Roman Catholic religion, and most of its adher- ents, aided her in after years to break from the fetters of guilt, and become a child of God. Ancient ruins of Rome  possessed a strong charm for the Florentine maiden, but not one of these had she yet seen. The Count and Countess were too devout Romanists to care for the ruins of the ancient city when surrounded by the splendor of the modern, and she could not go alone. One day when alight-   ut jUtn Hwuis D OF TRUTH. 117 ing from the carriage on her return from High Mass, what was her delight to see, standing on one of the broad marble  steps leading to their hotel, Lord Ardleyl He had come to spend some months at the capital, and with him for a companion, Sophie became familiar with ancient Rome. Together they visited the Forum, immortalized by the eloquence of a Cice- ro, and ascended the Capitoline hill, to look down on the ruins of centuries gath. ered at its base. They wandered through the Colosseum, so majestically beautiful in its decay, and looked upon the Tarpeian Rock, unchanged since the day the hap. less victims of Roman tyranny were hurl- ed from its top to the depths below. The information derived, and the enjoy- ment received from the places visited by travellers, depends very much upon their companions. Lord Ardley, with his strong    <pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC6905-00000060"/> ;U rtlJ i VJ tiBiLJN'1 ;t, imagination, well-stored mind, and noble, unselfish heart, was eminently fitted to interest another, in what at first sight had so fascinated and absorbed himself; and some of the views in ancient Rome almost overwhelmed with emotion the heart of Sophie DeBrentz.  Many a record of history did Lord Ardley bring forth from the ruins; many a classic mem- ory shone up from the yellow Tiber, as it wound its way onward to the sea; many a story of former years, and buried great- ness came forth from the Palatine Hill, Mount Aventine, and the now buried path of the Via Sacra. The visit to the Colosseum was made on a still summer evening, in the calm, sub- dued moonlight. All around seemed to feel nature's influence, and the hum and bustle of the great nmetropolis rolled on with a more quiet flow.   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH. 119 "Why is it," asked Sophie of her com- panion, "Why is it so much the practice to visit these ruins by moonlight?" "For several reasons;" replied Lord Ardley. "In the first place, there is a subduing influence felt when standing be- neath the pale, silent orb of night, never known at any other time, and leading the mind to thought and reflection. The glad sunshine, the quiet, holy twilight, and the thick darkness, all have their mis- sion; but each differs from the other. Did you ever think of this?" "No;- yes ;-" replied the other, is- itatingly; and then added, "I think I have known it, without thinking of it." "Then again," continued the nobleman, "moonlight shrouds the Colosseum in mys- tery; opening deep vaults of gloom, like those you see yonder; where the eye be- holds only an ebon wall, but the fancy    <pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC6905-00000061"/> brings shadowy forms of emperor and lic- tor, vestal virgin, gladiator and martyr, out from the darkness, and they seem to pass before us in a long and silent proces- sion. I can imagine I see them now pass- ing yonder broken column, and disappear- ing in the darkness below it. There is far more play for the imagination now than in the broad light of day." "How still it is here!" again exclaimed Sophie, after a long interval of silence. "We can just hear the barking of the watch dogs on the Tiber's bank, and, hark I what is that strange sound, coming from the palace of the Cmesars?" "Have you never heard it before,- the owl's long cry?" asked Lord Ardley, with a smile. "How should I, when I have never visi- ted ruins before at night? See how the stars shine upon those broken battle-   ments. We should have lost that sight, had the moon been a few nights older. Are there other ruins in Rome so exten- sive as these?" "None;" replied Lord Ardley, thought- fully. "In the broad light of day, or by the light of the moon and stars, the Colos- seum stands alone and unapproachable; a monarch ruined, and deserted. It is a colossal type of the struggles of human- ity against the destroying hand of time. 'Built of indestructible materials, and seemingly for eternity, being of a size, material, and form to defy the 'strong hours' which conquer all, it has bowed its head at their touch, and passed into the inevitable cycle of decay.'" Slowly and thoughtfully the travellers departed from the ruins, ever and anon turning to give them another look, and in after years the mind of the maiden often "   <pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC6905-00000062"/> SOPHE DE BRENTZ; recurred to that view of the Colosseum by moonlight. It may be asked why Lord Ardley, during such interviews as the one above described, did not rather seek to store the mind of his young friend with divine truths. He feared the papal power. He well knew that here, in catholic Rome, all other topics might be discussed, and in- struction given on all other points; but on subjects relating to the higher life, the tongue must be silent; for there the very walls have ears, and words of heretical import, though whispered ever so softly, reach the ears of the Romish dignitaries. Oh Rome I Rome I What iniquity will be charged to thy account in the day of thy final overthrow.   CHAPTER IX. 'Thou art mo e blest I deem Than in thy gayer hours, though grief hath laid His surgeon hand upon thy hea* and left Some aching wounds." THE time had now come for the Coun- tess DeBrentz and Sophie to leave Rome. A firmer opposer of Romanism than be- fore, and with her heart gladdened by a thousand pleasant memories, the maiden bade an affectionate adieu to her father and Lord Ardley, who seemed to her al- most like another father, and then the carriage turned away from the Eternal City. Of Father Ambrose, Sophie had seen but little during her stay in Rome. He 123    <pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC6905-00000063"/> Lo rall C U"JM DJlt;LYs- 'Ci had marked her coldness and wisely stood aloof; though in his heart burned a deep hatred toward the young girl, and he de- termined to lose no opportunity of making her feel his vengeance. The time, how- ever had not yet come. Fear not, Sophie, there is an Arm stronger than that of the Romish priest. The maiden returned to Florence with the influence of ancient Rome still upon her; and urged on by her love of the beautiful, she sought out the works of art with which the city of her residence abounds. The bronze and marble statues adorning the streets and public fountains, before hardly noticed, were now objects of deep interest. Accompanied only by an attendent, she spent hours, and some- time days, in the galleries of painting and sculpture, than which Italy cannot boast of a finer collection. The names of Gali-   leo, Michael Angelo, and Raphael became as familiar to her as household words; and with their history. and labors she made herself fully acquainted. When weary of these, she turned to the soul- inspiring strains of Dante and Tasso; and her imagination revelled in the efforts of 'their master pens. Nor was her music forgotten. Senora Isola, still the compan- ion and confidante of the Countess, often joined her voice with Sophie's in singing, as the latter played on the harp or guitar. Music alone brought the two together; for in everything else their tastes were unlike, and the objects of their pursuit different. Thus passed the days of the fair young Florentine. In the meantime Father Ig- natius had left the country; and Sophie, deprived of her former, religious instruc- tion, with her mind intent on other ob- "*   <pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC6905-00000064"/> jects, forgot her previous scruples, and gradually yielded to such forms of the Romish church as are binding upon its members. Father-Ambrose's absence also served to make her forgetful of the past, and her friends regarded her as having entirely given up her heretical opinions. Since her return from the convent she had been wholly without the Bible. When she first went home she sometimes thought that she would ask Father Igna- tius for one, but neglected it, and divine Truth gradually lost its power over her heart. Then he went away; and had she desired it, there was no way for her to obtain the Word of God. The Countess and Sophie still sustained the same relations toward each other. There was no familiarity existing between them, no confidence, little congeniality, and but little love. Still they daily spent   OB, THE SWORD OF TIRUTtI. 127 more or less time together, and though reserved in their intercourse, the stran- ger would not be likely to detect cold- ness of manner in the proud, high-born Countess DeBrentz, or the prouder So- phie. Nearly a year had passed away, when * the Count again returned from Rome to spend a season with his family. He was accompanied by a young Tyrolese officer, who had rendered him some sig- nal service at the capital, the result being a long and lasting friendship be- tween the  vo. Baron Frederick Von Amsdorff, th Count's young friend,was an officer in the Austrian army. Young, patriotic, and courageous, he was regard- ed with favor by his sovereign, and already a knight, seemed on the high road to honor and preferment. . He was a Romanist, and highly educated, but     <pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC6905-00000065"/> SOPHE DE BRENTZ; without any taste for the priestly garb and employments, or for the profession of law, which in that country offers few inducements to the ambitious mind, he early sought the army; expecting there to find the path to fame and glory. High-minded and chivalrous, the Baron was never known to stoop to the com- mission of a base action, being regard- ed by his fellow officers, and all who knew him as generous as te was brave. A mutual interest sprang up between the Baron and Sophie DeBrentz as their acquaintance progressed, which resulted in their betrothal and subsequent mar- riage. We now pass over a lapse of two years, in which the young Baron and Baroness had visited their native Tyrol, and then they returned, thinking to spend the remainder of their lives in      Italy. But dark clouds were gathering in the political sky, and a storm that no earthly power could avert was close at hand. The Italians, stung to madness by the oppressions of the government, were on the eve of an. insurrection. Secret meetings were held, and oaths of eternal hatred sworn against the rulers. Baron Von Amsdorff was in the service of the Grand Duke; but he saw that the cause of the people was supported by justice, and joined them. The patriotic young nobleman was warmly welcomed to their ranks, and unanimously chosen as their commander. The insurrectionists were now busily collecting arms and ammunition, prepara. tory toattacking one of the strongholds of the country, while their leader had returned home to make a hasty visit. It was the evening before his intended de-   <pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC6905-00000066"/> parture, clear, bright and beautiful. He sat with the Baroness watching the stars, as they came twinkling one by one in the blue sky, when one of his officers rushed into the room, pale and breathless. "You are in imminent danger; " he ex- claimed, turning to the Baron, " and must fly immediately. The myrmidons of ty- ranny are already on your track. It is you alone they seek, - from some strange cause none but you are implicated." Then he told how one of the soldiers, forsaking the cause in which he was en- gaged, had gone to Father Ambrose, his confessor, and revealed the whole plot. Also, that the priest had immediately informed the officers'of government, but, for some unexplained reason, the Baron alone was denounced; and that he, the narrator, had accidentally heard the whole from two state officers, sent by the Grand Duke to apprehend the Baron.   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.  131 "They thought you had left the city;" continued the man; " and you are safe when once beyond the frontiers of Italy." The Baron hesitated; for with him, flight was coupled with dishonor, and death seemed preferable to a dishonored name. But when he looked on his young wife, and thought of his child, the baby Anna, all other emotions were swallow- ed up in fears for their safety, and he immediately decided to pass over the Alps into Switzerland. The face of the Baroness was very pale, as she listened to this, but she betrayed no emotion of fear, either by word -or manner. Calmly she commenced making the hasty prepara- tions for th Kourney. But down deep in the heart of the young wife, hatred against Father Ambrose burned with a fiercer flame for this new offence, and her thoughts were full of bitterness; the    <pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC6905-00000067"/> OurnlnJ. IJ J D.YI I ,Z Baron, busy as herself, took no note of her unwonted silence, or, if he observed it at all, attributed it to the great change that night had made in their circumstan- ces. They would gladly have seen the Count DeBrentz once more before leaving Italy, but the distance was too great, the time too short, and the danger too immi- nent to make it practicable. At ten that night the exiled ones start- ed, accompanied by the faithful friend who had warned them of their danger; and it was well that he could be with them; for in this hour of peril they knew not whom to trust. As they journeyed onward, the soft airs of Italy began to change into the keen mountain blast; and with watchful care the Baroness sought to shield her infant from the piercing cold. The little Anna lay very still in her arms, and the mother thought her asleep.   All night they travelled; and when the grey light of morning came from the eastern sky they were in sight of the welcome hospice of St. Bernard. Urging their tired horses onward, they reached the hospice gates just as the sun, rising, revealed the wild solitude by which they were surrounded. Here the chilled and wearied travellers alighted; and the Bar- oness passed into the room allotted to ladies, and gently laid her infant on the sofa, murmuring "Darling! how long she has slept " The attendant immediately commenced removing the thick coverings from the child, and in a moment a slight exclama- tion escaped her, causing the mother to look round, when she saw that her Anna indeed slept, but it was the unbroken sleep of death! At first the Baroness could not believe that death had set 12   <pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC6905-00000068"/> rmI VuurtJhLi  IMM jCtU^ its seal on the beautiful features of her child, and warmth, and restoratives were quickly applied; but all in vain. With her life-blood chilled by the intense cold, the little Anna had died in her mother's arms, while they were crossing the moun- tains. The suddenness of the shock deprived the wretched mother of all energy; and, for a long time, scarcely caring whether she lived or died, her countenance wore the settled apathy of despair. In vain the Baron strove in various ways to rouse her; in vain the kind old monks at the hospice, exerted themselves to lighten her bereavement; but many times a day the stricken mother would go slowly and stand within the Mosque, where lay her child, beautiful as when in perfect health she had impressed kisses on its soft cheek. But, fearful of being pursued and over-   I   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTI:   135   taken, the travellers hastened their de- parture. The trusty Italian who had ac- companied them to St. Bernard returned as soon as practicable after their arrival at the hospice, that suspicion might not fasten itself upon him; and the travellers were attended by a guide from the moun- tains. The Baroness still continued incon- solable. The grand and sublime mountain  scenery through which they were now passing was wholly unheeded; for the sadness of her feelings made the face of Nature seem gloomy and barren. "Why should we be thus afflicted?" she one day asked the Baron, after they had been riding for a long time in silence. { Do you believe that it was right for our only one to be taken when others have so many bright faces to cheer their hearts and homes? I do not; I cannot believe that it is just." "I know not what to be-     <pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC6905-00000069"/> lieve," replied the Baron. "I grieve for our Anna; and her loss has made a deep void in my heart. But I am filled with misgivings for the future. I know not which way to turn or where to look. I fear the worst. With my honor gone, it matters little where I end my days. Would to God that we had all died on the 'moun- tains!" he added bitterly. Thus was the heart of the Baroness filled with proud rebellion towards the wise Being who had taken the young child in her purity to dwell with Him above. She forgot all the unmerited blessings that had crowned her past life, her dependence on God for every mercy, the years that had been spent in forgetfulness of Him-all save her own despairing grief. The Baron knew not how to comfort her, but till this afternoon, had not spoken of the trials that appeared to envelope their future.   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.  137 He did this, feeling that Sophie could not be more hopeless or miserable than now; and he hoped, by turning her thoughts into new channels, to break the lethargic stupor which seemed fast settling over her. He did it for the same reason that God took their child-with the design to do her good. 12*    <pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC6905-00000070"/> CHAPTER X. "For the strength of the hills we bless Thee, Our God, our fathers' God! Thou hast made thy children mighty Bty the touch of the mountain sod. Thou hast fixed our ark of refuge Where the spoiler's foot ne'er trod; For the strength of the hills we bless Thee, Our God, our fathers' God! We are watchers ox a beacon Whose light must never die; We are guardians of an altar, Midst the silence of the sky. The rocks yield founts of courage Struck forth as by thy rod; For the strength of the hills we bless Thee, Our God, our fathers' God!" IT was late in the afternoon of a bright, sunny day, that our travellers reached the little village of Meyringen, on the Aar. This village is situated in the extensive valley of Hasli, one of the most beautiful in Switzerland.  The lofty Alps rise on either side;  and, running   through  the   138   1   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.   valley, are the rivers Aar and Rechenbach, each dashing over cataracts, and then rushing onward, wild, free, and impetuous,. towards the illimitable sea. The lofty spire of Meyringen was a welcome beacon to the weary travellers, and the Baroness even roused from her wonted apathy as they approached the village. The fields and meadows bore marks of luxuriant cultivation; the people they saw were well dressed and intelligent looking, and their dwellings bore the ex- ternal marks of neatness and comfort, while the peace that seemed brooding over the village threw a softening influence round the hearts of the strangers. Driving up to the little auburge, the travellers hoped there to find rest and refreshment, but the travelling season had commenced, and it was already filled to overflowing. "I can do nothing for you," added the    <pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC6905-00000071"/> SOPHE DE BRENTZ; kind-hearted landlord, after telling them this, "except to advise you to stop yon- der, at the house of our pastor;" and he pointed to a little brown cottage near the church. "A better man never lived; and you will find good accommodations at his house, better than I could give you now, had I a room, to place at your disposal." So they thanked the talkative landlord, and turned the horses' heads in another direction. In a few moments the carriage stopped before the pastor's gate; and the pastor himself came forth to meet and welcome them to his dwelling. Relapsing into her former apathy the Baroness did not heed the halting, till the tones of the pastor's voice broke upon her ear. It sounded strangely familiar; and upon rais- ing her eyes what was her surprise to behold the well-remembered features of her old friend, Father Ignatius I The as-   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.   "1   tonishment was mutual; and after partak- ing of the refreshments soon spread before them, the pastor and his guests sat and conversed till late at night; for all had much to hear, and nmuch to tell. Father Ignatius, more and more dis- gusted with the empty forms of the Rom- ish church, as he continued to study the Bible, determined to leave them, and his native country. After spending some months with some Protestant friends in Berne, he received, through their instru- mentality, the appointment of Cure of Meyringen. "Let us unite in praising God," at length exclaimed Father Ignatius, or M. Orsoli, as we must now call him, he having resumed his own, name when he left the Romish church. After reading the one hundred and third Psalm, he knelt and offered a prayer, earnest and forcible, yet    <pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC6905-00000072"/> SOPHE DE'BRENTZ; beautiful in its simplicity. He thanked God that they had been kept during the years that had passed since their sepa- ration, and prayed that their coming thus together might result in the mutual good of all. Re asked that comfort might come to the hearts of the stricken parents ; that their loving heavenly Father who had chastised in love would sanctify to them the death of their little one. He implored for the bereaved mother that she might seek constantly to prepare for Heaven, now that her child was there, and that the truths to which in early years she had so firmly adhered, might still continue to be her shield from sin and error. To this prayer the Baroness listened, while her heart swelled with new and un- wonted emotions. The past that had lain slumbering so long, now rose like a vision before her, and she saw the good hand of   her heavenly Father in the events of her life. She felt her ingratitude in murmur- ing and repining because God, in his infi- nite wisdom had withholden a few of these blessings, and her heart was sadder than ever to think of the means of grace which she had enjoyed and misimproved. This constituted the past; and when she turn- ed to the future there was only deep, dark despair. Poor Sophie! The Baron had also been much impress- ed by the prayer of the village pastor. He was never a rigid Romanist, and there were times when he would ask himself if all the parade and show that he daily witnessed were acceptable to God, and he could not but feel that this prayer, power- ful in its simplicity received more favor from God than all the empty forms of the Roman Catholic religion. Sleep long held the weary travellers in    <pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC6905-00000073"/> SOPHE DE BRENT ; its embrace, and before they woke the next morning, the sunbeams were dancing around the room. When they appeared in ,  the little sitting-room, their host greeted them with his wonted pleasant smile, and cheerful words. After the breakfast was over, the Baron withdrew to write to. Count De Brentz, leaving the Baroness to be entertained by M. Orsoli. Fi% One of the first inquiries of her old friend was with regard to her spiritual well-being; and Sophie poured out to him the emotions that filled her sad heart. She told him of folly, sin and rebellion; of unimproved privileges and deep ingrati- tude. This constituted her past; and over the present hung that dark impene- trable cloud of despair. In vain the pas- tor repeated to her the gracious invita- tions of the gospel. iji,   "Have you then so completely forgot-   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.   "5   ten the words of that little Testament you found in the nunnery?" asked he. "Do you not remember the gracious promise, 'Him that cometh unto me, I will in no wise cast out? '  "Yes, I remember them all; " was the reply, "but they are not for me. How can God forgive me, when I have sinned against him so long and so deeply; when I have been so rebellious and unsubmis- sive?"   "Have you quite forgotten that you have a Saviour?" asked the other in gen- tle, yet slightly reproachful tones. "Did not He die for the chief of sinners? and has He not said that all may come and be saved? Oh, believe me, my friend, God loves to save sinners, and the greater the  sinner born into God's Kingdom, the more is He glorified; the more is His power and goodness revealed to angels and men.    <pb n="146-147" xml:id="VAC6905-00000074"/> 10    bUnfll- UJiti U!N'L;Ci  I know that you will say that God is just as well as merciful, but do you not see that the Saviour in infinite love, has satis- fied the claims of justice, while our Fath- er in infinite love stands ready to pardon the sinner for His sake?" "It is,-it must be so," replied the Bar- oness, hesitatingly, and then added, "Oh, how I wish I could feel all this!" "Pray  earnestly to God," said her friend. "No one ever perished at the throne of grace,- no one ever offered up earnest, heartfelt prayer, without some good results. Strive to believe that Christ is ready and willing to save you, and then give yourself up into His hands. This is your duty, and if you do this, rest assure ed that Christ will accomplish your salva- tion." ' I will try to do this," said the Baron- ess, as she rose to leave the room, "and may God help me."   v  r Kx ini WURoD OF TRUTH. 147 "Amen!" responded M. Orsoli; "and now will you take this?" continued he, giving her a Bible," and may God sancti- fy its precious truths to your heart." With emotions too strong for utterance, the other received the sacred book and withdrew to reflect upon the truths she had just heard. Thus was her heart again pierced by the Sword of Truth; but in the darkness now surrounding her she saw not its dazzling brightness; she felt not its power to heal as well as wound; and in the place of deep, unmiti- gated sorrow, to give that "Peace that passeth understanding." fI    <pb n="148-149" xml:id="VAC6905-00000075"/> CHAPTER XI. "Great God, this hallowed Day of Thine Demands our soul's collected powers; May we employ in works divine Its solemn, consecrated hours." THE day following the one on which the preceding conversation was held was the Sabbath. White and lofty towered the Alps upward, resting their snow-clad heights against the clear blue sky, and sending down cool, refreshing breezes in- to the valley below. The solemn stillness was disturbed only by the shepherd's bell, coming faintly from the green moun- tain slopes, and the loud; interminable roar of the foamy cataract. By and by, came the toll of the church-bell, clear "8   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.  149   and solemn, rising up from the valley to the distant dwellers on the mountain sides. Then they might be seen winding their way down the descents over " rock and bank and brae," to the services be- low.   High up among the mountains was many a scattered cottage, where there were no trees,-nothing but the "shadow of a rock," from whence could be seen coming forth the little family party; and even from the lone chalet beside the region of eternal snows, the shepherd had left his flocks, and descended many leagues to the church in the valley. These lonely men, coming from their deep solitudes with a busy step and rapid mien, contrast- ed strangly with the peaceful air, and measured tread of the villagers. The scene was an animated one, though peace- ful and quiet, as befitted the holy hours. 13*     <pb n="150-151" xml:id="VAC6905-00000076"/> SOPHE DE BRENTZ; The mountain paths were steep and rug- ged, and the groups were sometimes broken, then for awhile lost to view be- hind a projecting rock, or in the shadow of a wood; while others passed with sure foot along the verge of the precipices. Old men were there with silver locks, clear eye, and robust figure; the patri- archs of the scene. They were a fine and hardy peasantry of which a land might justly be proud; and their subdued de- portment, and quiet manner, proved that they were aware of the claims of that religion in which they were about to engage. Accompanied by his guests, the pastor mingled in the throng who bent their steps toward the sanctuary. During the singing and prayers, the Baroness had re- mained absorbed in her own wretched- ness; but the words of the text now   F   repeated by the pastor, aroused her: "'Oh, that thou hadst hearkened to my com- mandments  Then had thy peace been as a river." Isaiah xliii. 18. Never was text more aptly chosen. In full view from the church windows rolled the Aar, full, proud, and placid, on its winding course. After some remarks on the disobedience of the Israelites, the preacher delineated the life of the sinner, his love for the world, his supreme sel- fishness, his forgetfulness of God, and his indifference toward the true aims of life.   The scene changes. The sinner is awakened to a sense of his danger, his sins are spread in appalling array before him, and he is too proud to seek forgive- ness, or else he despairs of mercy. Then another picture, painted with a master hand; the subject, the sufferings and    <pb n="152-153" xml:id="VAC6905-00000077"/> SOPHE DE is,N-1 j death of Christ. He is pointed out as the Saviour of all who) cast aside their own righteousness, and trust to His merits alone; but they must bow their wills to His, and consecrate their lives to His ser- vice. Faith now stands forth in the preacher's discourse, powerful in her sim- plicity, beautiful in her implicit trust; and then the sinner comes again; but oh  how changed  Clinging to his Saviour, his heart no longer tossed by conflicting emotions, he is joyful in the hope of im- mortal glory, determined to go on from strength to strength in the way to eternal life. The speaker then showed the deep, calm joy pervading the heart of the true Christian, unconsumed by the fires of adversity, undaunted by the sword of persecution. This was followed by a stirring, affectionate appeal to the impeni-   I   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.   153   tent to become partakers of that "peace that passethinot away." The sermon was finished; and a deep stillness reigned throughout the house, broken only by stifled sobs, telling that the preacher's words had not been want- ing in power. The services of the day were con- cluded and the shades of evening rested on the quiet valley, while the moon rode high in the heavens, clothing the earth in light and beauty. The Baroness sat by the window, with a heart attuned to the lovely scene; for the morning's sermon had been to her "the savor of life unto life," and after a severe struggle she had yield- ed her heart to God. Love to Him and His creatures, peace, and joy unspeakable pow filled her soul, and she would have willingly given her life a sacrifice to the cause she had espoused.   <pb n="154-155" xml:id="VAC6905-00000078"/> With feelings of. deep gratitude toward Him, who had led the straying one into His own fold, the pastor learned the mighty change wrought in the heart of Sophie Von Amsdorff; while to the Baron this sudden transition from deep gloomto joy so rapturous, was strange and inexpli- cable. He was rejoiced, however, to see the light of happiness again basking in the dark eyes of the Baroness, regardless of the source from whence it came; and thus the Sabbath evening in the pastor's dwelling was fraught with deep, quiet happiness.   I   CHAPTER XII.   "They came and went like shadows, The gorgeous dreams of youth, And left behind no impress, Or record of their truth."   TBH affairs of the Baron were involved in so much uncertainty, that M. Orsoli gave him and his wife a cordial invitation to consider his house their home, till news came from Italy, and they should be enabled to form some plans for the future. After a season of waiting, came letters; and among them  one from Count De Brentz. He deeply regretted the necessi- ty which had driven his children away, and in such haste that he could not even bid 156      <pb n="156-157" xml:id="VAC6905-00000079"/> JU    BUIr'l Li JSDtiN ID 2 them farewell. He also informed them that by the order of the Grand Duke they were condemned to perpetual exile, and the Baron's estates confiscated to the church. He assured them both of his unchanging affection, and besought them  ever to consider him as their truest friend, ready to assist them by any means in his power. i    Both the exiles were much affected by this letter, but in far different ways. jThe Baron, proud and ambitious, had lopked forward to a life of glory; now to be de- prived of his estates, and condemned to perpetual exile, with no opportunity of retrieving his lost honor, was a terrible trial to the young soldier. But, persuad- ed by the pastor, and seconded by the Baroness, he decided to purchase a pleas- ant residence standing near the pastor's cottage; and having thus created a new   home, to turn his attention to scientific pursuits, for which he had a decided pre- dilection. His means were small when compared with the large revenues that belonged to him by right, yet wholly suffcient to support his family in compe tence through life. The Baroness was rejoiced to hear from her father, whom she ardently loved; and but for him she had little desire to return to Italy. It had been to her the land of trials; and she turned shrinkingly away from the thought of again placing herself un- der Roman Catholic influences. Besides, there was something in wild, free Switzer. land, with her bracing mountain winds, aiore suited to her energetic nature than the enervating airs of Italy. Thei once imperious and queen-like Sophie:-ad learned in humility the prayer of Agur; and though foreseeing that the Baron's "    <pb n="158 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6905-00000080"/> 58     SOPHE DE BRENTZ; loss of wealth would make her life one of toil, she shrunk not back, but entered up- on it cheerfully and courageously. The new home was a pleasant one, with a large garden in front, and farther on an orchard of fruit trees, and a small vine- yard. Two servants were employed, a man to cultivate the little estate, and a girl for the household labors. But the Baroness, inexperienced as she was, found much devolving upon her; and those hands, all unused to labor, became after a time expert in all the various toils that go to make up the happiness of a household. Beside her more active labors, she found ample time to devote to intellectual pur- suits, and the Baron often found her an efficient assistant. He, in the meantime, was progressing gradually and steadily in his scientific labors, and his home had be- come the resort of literary men and   <pb n="-159" xml:id="VAC6905-00000081"/> women. He and M. Orsoli were firm friends, and he often accompanied the pastor on excursions over the mountains, or through distant parts of the exten- sive valley of Hasli. Early one morning, the appalling intelli- gence reached Meyringen, that a small hamlet, containing a population of from ninety to one hundred souls, had been buried beneath an avalanche. The village stood apart from any other, being encom- passed by mountains; and its inhabitants were frugal and industrious, cultivating their little territory, and living almost wholly on its produce. The oldest of them had never known an avalanche to fall near the village, or heard their fathers speak of such an event; so they lived on in fancied security. The fall of snow had been unusually heavy the previous sea- son, and one morning when most of the   <pb n="160-161" xml:id="VAC6905-00000082"/> 50    SOPHE DE BRENTZ; men were at work in the fields, few beside the women, the aged, and the sick remain- ing in the houses, the laborers suddenly heard a rushing sound, and looking back, saw an immense body of snow issue from the mouth of a descending ravine, through which it had travelled three miles from the precipice where it first fell! The village lay directly beneath, and the avalanche buried it; cottages, gardens, and trees all disappeared. The snow lay upon the roofs to the depth of several hundred feet; and to those whose loved ones were beneath it, the time passed in its re- moval was one of terrible suspense. The father knew not if he were childless, or the husband if he should find his wife liv- ing or dead. They called aloud and shout- ed during their labors, but could hear nothing save some faint cries and groans. It was a scene for the pencil of a t   Titian. The agitated groups of peasantry, with every shade of hope and fear depict- ed on their countenances, digging deeper and deeper into the fatal avalanche, each drawing nearer and nearer to his own home, which he earnestly longed yet dreaded to behold. It was some days before the canopy of snow was removed; and then it seemed that the dead were better off than the living. The latter were fearfully maimed and crushed, having remained thus be- neath the snow without food, light, or motion; for the long-continued darkness was terrible to bear. Many lay dead; some in the chambers that were shattered above them, some out of doors in their little gardens, or wherever the destruc- tion found them. Twenty of the wounded were carried to the nearest hospital, and poverty and "*    <pb n="162-163" xml:id="VAC6905-00000083"/> 62     SOPHE DEBRENTZ; sorrow  came upon every family; while clinging to each was the peasant's great- est curse - loneliness.  The cottage that was destroyed, and the little garden, now desolate, might again be restored; but who could bring back the lost wife and children? Who gather again the happy fireside circle?  Who  replace the fond ties of affection, now so rudely sundered? Poor Swiss!   His " golden bowl" was rudely broken, and his cup of happiness dashed to the earth. It is often impossi- ble for mortals to see why God sends afflictions, but it is enough that He "doeth all things well." "One part, one little part we dimly scan, Traced through the medium of life's feverish dream; Yet, dare arraign the whole stupendous plan, If but that little part incongruous seem. Nor is that part perhaps what mortals deem; Oft from apparent ills our blessings rise, Oh! then renounce that impious self-esteem That aims to trace the secrets of the skies; For thou art but of dust: be humble and be wise."   Only one was left unharmed in the little village; a young boy of five, who was found clinging to the neck of a faith- ful dog. When the mass of snow fell in which perished his grandfather, mother, brothers and sisters, he had clung in ter- ror to the large dog,i who happened to be lyig by his side. The sagacious animal never moved, and by the warmth of his body, and his brute companionship, sus- tained and cheered the poor boy during the long darkness. "How did you feel when you found you were alone in the darl, Jean?" asked the boy's father, as he held him in his arms.        * "I was, frightened at first," replied the child, raising his blue eyes to his father's, "'and tried to find mother; but it was so dark, and I could not move. Then I cried, and Bruno put his paw over me, so    <pb n="164-165" xml:id="VAC6905-00000084"/> 1Ut     Ur kUtI'll/i VJ bKti;'N1 I laid my head on his back and went to sleep. Oh, I was so hungry! and I was cold, too; but Bruno tried to keep me warm. I tried to sleep all the time I could, but I would hear people screaming, and that would wake me, and frighten me." Tears stood in the eyes of the listeners at Jean's artless tale, while the latter was taken to the nearest hut, where he might once more enjoy warmth, light, and food. It was a btsy, yet mournful season with M. Orsoli. To bury the dead, to comfort the bereaved survivors, and to visit the wounded and dying, were now the tasks of the Swiss pastor; and most faithfully were they performed. Nor were the Baron and Baroness idle. They had taken upon themselves to provide relief for the surviving sufferers, and their appeals met    with a ready response throughout the cantons. Reader, is your heart ever raised in gratitude to God that you are exempted from dangers like these? Or are you liv- ing on, unmindful of Him in whom you "Iive, and move, and have your being?" If so, you stand on the brink of a preci. pice, more frightful than any on Alpine heights, and an avalanche, more terrible than the one here described, is threaten- ing to engulf you.    <pb n="166-167" xml:id="VAC6905-00000085"/> CHAPTER XIII. Young children are the gems of earth, The brightest jewels mothers have; They sparkle on the throbbing breast Brightest shine beyond the grave. AboN. Spirit! Thy labor is o'er; Thy term of probation is run; Thy steps are how bound for the untrodden shore, And the race of immortals begun. MOZART'S REQUIEM. THREE years had passed since the exiles found a home in Meyringen, in which peace and plenty had smiled upon them, and their trials had been comparatively few.  A little boy, now  nearly two years old had been sent in the place of the lost one. He was a beautiful and interesting child; and his father loved him to idola- 166   I   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH. 167   try. The mother, deep as was her affec- tion, had not forgotten her former loss, and held the little Albert as a loan from her heavenly Father, to be recalled when- ever he willed. Infant as he was, his rare beauty, and sweet, infantile ways, made him a favorite with the peasants, who watched him from the garden, door- way or open window; and he was also very dear to M. Orsoli, who, as he looked upon him, would send forth thoughts into the future, and implore heaven to make his career one of usefulness. One bright June morning, the Baroness was left alone with the little Albert; the husband and father having set out at an early hour for Berne. The domestics were both in the garden; and the little boy, after standing by his mother's side for a few moments, as she sat sewing, ran out after them. Suddenly a scream rose    <pb n="168" xml:id="VAC6905-00000086"/> 168    SOPHE DE BRENTZ; on the still air. The mother turned to the window, and horrified, beheld an enor- mous eagle with her child in his talons, soaring slowly upward! The servants were motionless with terror. There was no time for thought, and without uttering a word, the intrepid mother swiftly passed the people who were beginning to gather, and bent her course toward the mountain whither the eagle was flying. Voices were raised to call her back, but she heeded them not. On, on she flew over the green pastures, and the shepherds gazed after her in as- tonishment as she flitted by, with her long, dark hair streaming in the wind, and her black eyes half starting from their sockets. She regarded them not; but with the eagle and her child before her pressed onward. The pine groves were passed, and then precipices and crags,   f j 4 I a c I I    <pb n="Illustration-169" xml:id="VAC6905-00000087"/> chaJ eag] ciol flow lu-ge 39.fled trod stat verl ? i7      pra3 men pass ing one mother snatching th (efie child, pressedhim to her hleart."      'tain Page 169.             tere   UTI 'AtLPJ iJWUVtK U tUll. JU lerto untrod save by the sure-footed mois-hunter, till she stood by the le's nest. He had dropped his pre- is burden by the side of the nest, and In. The mother, snatching the terri- child, pressed him to her heart, and imenced her downward course. With re foot the dangerous path was again [den. The shepherd and his family,    j ding by their lone chalet, on the  re of eternal snows, blessed her, and ' red her to stay for rest and refresh-     ;? t; but she lingered not. As she ;ed downward, the dwellers on the ntains and in the valleys stood, watch-  eagerly each step, and when her feet 3 more pressed the soil of the valley, . long, loud, universal shout rent the and echoed back again from the moun- s. The steps of the mother now fal- d; M. Orsoli took the young boy from ,15 HE    <pb n="170-171" xml:id="VAC6905-00000088"/> U -  SOPHE DE BRENTZ; her arms, and she fell senseless upon the grass. Days passed before the Baroness recov- ered from her fatigue, terror, and that long, death-like swoon. When she recovered i   the little Albert was guarded with a ten- derer care than ever; and it was the moth- er's quick eye which first saw that disease was preying upon him. A physician was called, who pronounced his disease the brain fever. He remarked that it was caused by a blow on the head, probably received when he fell from the eagle's talons. Both parents shuddered at the sound of this fatal disease; and the father, fearing the worst, -lclaimed, "He must not die. Save hip, and all I have 'in the world shall be yours." it  -The physician promised to do all in his power, and after prescribing some simple   j, I SWORD OF TRUTH.   171 medicines, took his leave. The Baroness had not spoken; and now flung herself beside the sofa where the little one lay, and poured out her soul in silent prayer. She asked that if it were consitent with the will of God the child might be spared to them, but if not, that they might re- ceive strength to say from their heart of hearts, "Thy will, O God, be done!" and prayed that this trial might be sancti- fied to the heart of the father, and be the X means of leading him to the Saviour. The Baroness rose from her knees re- freshed and strengthened; and with com- posure ministered to the wants of the languishing boy. Day followed day, and each time the physician came his counte. nance would wear a deeper gravity, and he go away more sorrowful. When a long, weary week of suspense had passed, he said he could do no more; the child     <pb n="172-173" xml:id="VAC6905-00000089"/> [2    SOPHE DE BRENTZ; must die. At first the father could not believe that his idol was to be taken away, but when he saw the cords relax, the breath cease, and the death film steal over those beautiful eyes, now calmly closed by the mother, he felt that he was indeed be- reft, and groaned in bitterness of spirit. "The Lord gave and the Lord taketh away; blessed be the name of the Lord;" said the mother in tremulous tones, as she stooped over and kissed the pallid fea- tures of her boy. "Amen; " responded a deep; rich voice, and their friend, M. Orsoli stood by their side. He mingled his tears with theirs; first letting their grief have way, then seeking to adminis- ter consolation. He gently reminded them that their children were now remov- ed forever from the sins, temptations, and trials of earth, and had only preceded them to the world of bliss. He besought   them henceforth to seek for a closer walk with God, that they might be enabled to meet their dear ones in heaven. Then he knelt in prayer with the be- reaved ones, and asked that this trial might be sanctified to their hearts, and they be enabled ever to trust in that God who chastises only in love. "The effec. tual, fervent prayer of the righteous man availeth much; and it brought peace to the hearts of the bereaved parents. Nev- er before had the Baron seen the power of religion so fully exemplified; and standing by the side of his dead boy, he determined to seek for it, as for hid trea- sures. But the sad day came when the sacred dust must be committed to its .kindred dust, and almost the whole parish were gathered at the funeral, so deep was the feeling of sympathy for the bereaved par. 15'    <pb n="174-175" xml:id="VAC6905-00000090"/> l af'i  SOPHE I)DERKEINTZ; ents. Very lonely seemed the late happy home when they returned thither, and for a long time the little Albert was constant- ly missed all through the house. But time, the great healer of sorrow, took away the sting from theirs; though they never forgot the loved ones who had gone before them in the-hiing way to heaven. Now, with hearts united, they followed in the same peaceful path.   CHAPTER XIV. "Full many a light thought man may cherish, Full many an idle deed may do; Yet, not a deed or thought shall perish; Not one but he shall bless or rue. When by the wind the tree is shaken, There's not a bough or leaf can fall; But of its falling heed is taken By One who sees and governs all." ANOTHER beautiful Sabbath had dawned over the village of Meyringen, bringing the day of our'Saviour's death and suffer- ings.   It was a glad, though solemn sea- son to the Baron and Baroness, for that day they were to unite with the little church  of Meyrinigen.   The simple and impressive rites, so unlike tie tedious, un- meaning   ceremonies  of  the  Romish 175      <pb n="176-177" xml:id="VAC6905-00000091"/> SOPHE DE BRENTZ; church, were soon over; and with new resolutions, and stronger desires to live near to God, the little church thus strengthened, quietly and thoughtfully wended their ways homewards. A few months afterward the Baroness was surprised and delighted by the arri- val of her father, the Count De Brentz. It was just at the close of a misty, rainy evening, that the Count unexpectedly presented himself; and so overjoyed was the Baroness at the sight of her father, that several minutes elapsed before she noticed that he was accompanied by a lady, closely veiled. As she turned to accost the stranger,. the veil was raised revealing features wan and pale, and with traces of strong suffering enstamped upon them. For an instant the Baroness stood irresolute; then with the words, "It is, --it must be Helena," clasped her in a   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.   1"   warm embrace. Yes, it was Helena Pe- ruzi, but only the mere relic of her former self. Her marvellous beauty had faded; sorrow had paled her cheek, and dimmed the lustre of her eye. As the shades of evening came on, the re-united friends gathered round the bright wood fire burning on the hearth, and related what had befallen them since the parting so long ago. The Countess De Brentz had pursued pleasure as un- weariedly as ever, till sickness the result of her dissipation, brought her low, and in a few weeks the grave closed over her; another victim 'offered -at the shrine of fashion. Senora Isola, thus deprived of her protectress, and unwilling to engage in any lucrative employment, on account of long-indulged habits of indolence, had entered a convent, there to wear out the remainder of her days in listlessness and inaction.   <pb n="178-179" xml:id="VAC6905-00000092"/> SOPHE DE BRENTZ; The Pope had but illy requited the old Count for his long and faithful services, and forsaken by those who should have befriended him in the evening of his life, and feeling lonely, and almost forsaken, his heart had turned with fond longings toward his long-absent daughter. The sentence of excommunication from the church, so terrible to the Romanist, issued against the Baroness, had made him more observant and thoughtful, and he began gradually to see the errors of the system. Helena Peruzi had seen Sophie leave the convent with deep regret, and when she could elude observation, had applied herself to the study of the little Testa- ment, in order to while away the weary hours. Here she learned the deep sinful- nesg of her own heart, and her need of a Saviour; and her proud, unsubdued spirit now bowed to Him in humble ado-   ration. Thus months passed into years; and the still discontented nun was reaping the fruits of her rash resolutions. In the meantime Sister Agnes had paid the debt of nature, and another nun assumed the office of Abbess. If the sit- uation of Helena was unpleasant before, now it was hardly tolerable; for the new Abbess, ill-natured and exacting toward all, held a grudge against Helena for some trifling offence committed months before; and the persecuted nun turned her thoughts toward planning some method for escape. She found means to convey a few lines secretly to a trusty Tuscan, who was once a servant of her father's. This was done through the instrumental- ity of a friend whom she met at the gate, and a novel method was contrived for her egress from the convent. Connected with the building was a large sewer; and this    <pb n="180-181" xml:id="VAC6905-00000093"/> was to be the door of deliverance to the weary Helena. One night, when all the inmates of the convent were sleeping, she left her room, and glided swiftly and silently down the dark stair-cases to the entrance of the sewer, where she was to meet her trusty friend. He was standing, hidden by the shadows of the building, and, upon see- ing Helena, came forth, bearing a suit ot clothing, and a coarse outer garment to be worn through the sewer; besides some paints and colorings with which she was to disguise herself. The next night was the one fixed on for the escape; and when all these prelimina- ries were settled, Helena very naturally asked herself the question, "To whom shall I go for refuge?"Fearing that her parents would betray her, rigid Romanists as they were, she determined to seek the ---n. rr       I   protection of the kind-hearted Count De Brentz, and conjure him by her love for his daughter to receive and shelter her. The following night was dark; and the wind moaned fitfully through the tree- tops, and shook the windows of the con- vent. The clock struck the hour of eleven. The convent was still, and all save one were sleeping. The excited.  Ielena hastily changed her attire, and then glided down to meet her faithful friend. Once she thought she heard approaching footsteps, and drew back into a recess that she was passing; but it was only the wind rattling the casement, so she gathered courage, and passed on. She met her faithful attendant at the entrance of the sewer, and they emerged to the opposite end in safety. Discarding the coarse garment worn throgh the pas- sage, and closely veiled, Helena Peruzi 16    <pb n="182-183" xml:id="VAC6905-00000094"/> SOPHE DEBRENTZ; was to be the door of deliverance to the weary Helena. One night, when all the inmates of the convent were sleeping, she left her room, and glided swiftly and silently down the dark stair-cases to the entrance of the sewer, where she was to meet her trusty friend. He was standing, hidden by the shadows of the building, and, upon see- ing Helena, came forth, bearing a suit ot clothing, and a coarse outer garment to be worn through the sewer; besides some paints and colorings with which she was to disguise herself. The next night was the one fixed on for the escape; and when all these prelimina- ries were settled, Helena very naturally asked herself the question, "To whom shall I go for refuge?"Fearing that her parents would betray her, rigid Romanists as they were, she determined to seek the ---n. rr       I   protection of the kind-hearted Count De Brentz, and conjure him by her love for his daughter to receive and shelter her. The following night was dark; and the wind moaned fitfully through the tree- tops, and shook the windows of the con- vent. The clock struck the hour of eleven. The convent was still, and all save one were sleeping. The excited.  Ielena hastily changed her attire, and then glided down to meet her faithful friend. Once she thought she heard approaching footsteps, and drew back into a recess that she was passing; but it was only the wind rattling the casement, so she gathered courage, and passed on. She met her faithful attendant at the entrance of the sewer, and they emerged to the opposite end in safety. Discarding the coarse garment worn throgh the pas- sage, and closely veiled, Helena Peruzi 16    <pb n="184-185" xml:id="VAC6905-00000095"/> SOPHE DE BRENTZ; way to the room of the missing nun; and. great was her astonishment to find it ten- antless. "She must, have escaped; " muttered the Abbess between her teeth; "but how?"  She saw from the clothing Hele- na had left, that she had a friend without the walls; and she immediately sent for a priest, apprised him of what had passed, and directed him to neglect no efforts to discover the fugitive, saying that, if found, she must be sent to a distant con- vent. She then assembled the nuns in the chapel, and told them of Sister Ceci- lia's disappearance, and that on account of her fervent piety, their patron saint had clothed her in-white, and translated her to heaven! This, the Abbess affirmed, was revealed to her in a dream-the previous night. She then distributed pieces of Sister Cecilia's clothing among the nuns,   f'; ,n"- t' ^"ib   5t   enjoining upon each to preserve them as precious relics of the departed. This farce through, and each went about her avocations, with her thoughts full of pious Sister Cecilia. In the meantime the travellers sped on- ward, almost without halting; till they reached the friendly hospice of St. Ber- nard. Here they remained two days for rest and refreshment, then continued their journey. Nothing of material im- portance afterward occurred till they'):^ reached Meyringen, and the residence of Baron Von Amsdorff. Away from Romish principles and cere- monies, and surrounded by those whose lives bore witness to the purity of their creed, the Count's faith in the infallibility of the Romish C nch continued gradual- ly but surely to blessened. With his heart weaned fron his adopted country, 16 /.   <pb n="186-187" xml:id="VAC6905-00000096"/> 186    SOPHE DEBRENTZ; and in compliance with the earnest wish es of his children, he decided to pass the remainder of his days in Switzerland; and only returned to Rome and Florence to settle up his business; then bade Italy adieu forever. Thus the seasons came and went with the exiles, and peace, like a dove, brooded over their hearts and home. Again the prattle of infancy was heard in their dwelling; for two children, Helena and Frederick, were given them, and the par- ents endeavored to train them in such a manner that their lives should be subser- vient to life's great ends. When a year had passed, Helena Peruzi was no longer'an inmate of their home.* The invigorating mountain airs had again brought the rosy hue of health to her cheek, and the pastor of Meyringen, re- garding the vows of celibacy, binding   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH. 187 upon Rome's ministers, as contrary to the word of God, had married her, and taken her to his home to assist and cheer him in his labors. One cold, stormy evening, as the pastor and his wife sat before a bright wood fire, quietly conversing, a breathless messen- ger from the little auburge, announced briefly that an old man had arrived at the inn a few hours before, extremely ill, and they now feared he was dying. The landlord, shrinking from the scene, had sent in haste for his revered pastor, whose ministrations to the dying he had often witnessed. In a few moments the pastor was ready to follow the messenger, and a rapid walk soon brought them to the door of the inn. M. Orsoli was conducted into a dimly lighted room, and on the bed in one cor-  ner beheld an old man with matted hair, I              (    <pb n="188-189" xml:id="VAC6905-00000097"/> and dark eyes wildly gleaming. Already the damps of death were gathering on his brow, and when the pastor approached nearer he recognized the man; it was Father Ambrose! But the latter was too much engrossed with bitter memories of the past, and thoughts of the terrible fu- ture, to remember his old acquaintance. Remorse, deep and agonizing, had made him its victim; and it seemed as though all the deeds of his past life of wrong were gathered and crowded into one short hour. All night the pastor stood by his bedside, listening to his despairing excla- mations, while he ministered to his tem- poral and spiritual wants. He endeavored to bring consqlation to the dying man; and prayer, deep and fer- vent, ascended from the sick room; but the priest could only see a long life spent in sin with no hope of pardon. The   OR, THE SWORD OF TRUTH.   mists of death gathered about him, and just'as the morning light was breaking in the east, a convulsive struggle passed over him, and the spirit took its flight. "Be not deceived; God is not mocked; whatsoever a man soweth, that shall he also reap," Reader, are you one of those who would put off repentance till prostrated by deadly sickness? Would you spend ydCir brightest and best days in the ser- vice of Satan, and when you see the hour of death approaching, devote the poor, pitiful remnant to God? Beware, lest it then be too late. ', Now is the accepted time, now is the day of salvation." The following day the Baron and Bar- oness went to look on the face of their old enemy, now cold in death, and to pre- pare for the funeral, the expense of which they intended to defray. The Baroness    <pb n="190-191" xml:id="VAC6905-00000098"/> 190    SOPHE DE BRENTZ; wept as she looked on the pallid features of the priest, and thought of his sad end. None of her old hatred toward him now remained; she had long since ceased to think of him except with pity and forgive- ness. In conclusion we would say to all who have perused this unpretending narrative, make the Bible "the Man of your Coun- cil;" believe its doctrines and follow its precepts; and it will be "a Light unto your feet, and a Lamp unto your path."      </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>