<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6547">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >The Partisan's Oath, or, The Trooper's Revenge </title>
            <author >Greeley, Robert F.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC6547</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >The partisan's oath, or, The trooper's revenge</title>
                  <author >Greeley, Robert F.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >96 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >Bunce</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date  from="1800" to="1899">[18--?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-05-07">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text >
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The partisan's oath, or, The trooper's revenge</head>
            <p> 
               <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6547-00000001"/>  THE A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION BY ROBERT F GREELEY, ES Q. *AUTHOR OF OLD ERNEST"ETC. NEW YORK:  BUNCE &amp; BROTHER, PUBLISHERS 184 NASSAU STEEET.    <pb n="0" xml:id="VAC6547-00000002"/>   THE PARTISAN'S OATH: A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION. CHAPTER      I, IT was on a calm, bright morning at the close of July, 1776, that a peaceful hamlet on the banks of the romantic Bronx-- that miniature rivh-, which irrigates one of the loveliest sections of the county of Westchester--became the scene of an excitement unusual to the locality in which it occurred, and quite foreign to the homely and unwarlike dispositions of the dwellers in that secluded and hitherto undisturbed region. The time had been, when the lowing of cattle, the clacking of mill-wheels, or the scjunds of the busy flail, threshing the grain, were the only noises which occurred to break the calm repose which brooded o'er it. Old men were there, who had seen, for half a century and more, their pro- geny grow -up and multiply around them, without experi- encing a desire to change the scenes of their mortal joys or sorrowings; for even this beautiful little hamlet upon the Bronx, hadcmore than once resounded to the wail of sorrow, and a moss-grown graveyard, studded here and there with wooden slabs-the only monuments within its precincts- pointed out the resting places of those who had terminated here their earthly pilgrimages. Scarcely a stone's throw. from the water, stood the village church, with modest spire" pointing heavenward, and in front of, this, a grassy lawn, on which a considerable crowd had collected. Upon the steps of the church the pastor, withl silvery hair, and- form bowed down by age, read from a newspaper the memorable act that had, only a few days previously, at Phil-    <pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC6547-00000003"/> 6      r TE PBRTHE PAITISAN'8 OAT : to follow the example so nobly set them by young: Gayler. In the mean time the women were seen hurrying towards. the spot with arms and accoutrements, .with which they hastened to endow the little band of heroes, "Now, boys," exclaimed Gayler, ' to the church : A prayer for those we love, and a blessing upon the sacred cause to which we have pledged ourselves, and then to meet the red-coats!"  'The little bell had ceased its peals; all Was silent as the grave. The group moved as by a common impulse, towards the church, at the portal of which they were met by the aged pastor, whose outstretched hand and reverent attitude ar- rested them.  "Beneath this glorious canopy," he said,--" nature's self- chosen temple-most fitting scene for so solemn an occasion-- let us beg that blessing without which no cause is certain of success." ' We'draw a scene over the picture; there are feelings which may be better imagined than described, and of this nature were those which actuated the little band whose move- ments we have just described. ,  Before the sun had thrown his parting rays over the little liamlet by the Bronx, Reuben Gayler and his party were/on their way to join their brother patriots at New York. ' One afternoon, not long after the occurrence, of the forego-, ing incidents, a party of mounted troopers, wearing the British uniform, came in sight of the Bronx, not far distant from the spot on which Reuben and his comrades iiad taken a last adieu of their friends. Strangely: enough, the indi- vldual who rode at their head, although attired in garments faridifferent from those in which we last saw him clad, wore the ill-favored lineaments of' Ralpih Osborne. For this glit- tering distinction, and not from ahy feeling of attachment towards the-mother country, he had bartered his honor; and, it may readily be' imagined, that one who was. capable of such:; black hearted treachery would' not hesitate at the per- formance' of any action, however'vile and degrading, that might gratify his 1sts, or pamper his fiendish passions. It seems almost"hpossible that such villainy could: spring spontaneous in the breast of one so young; ,for Osborne wass not, certainly, olde;r than twenty, and, though he :had'earned' an evil reputation throughout the country, fei looked upon him, up to the time of these proceedings, as .being anything more than a drunkard and an idler. The mtime: had.'come,; however, for him to throw off the mask, and before that day had passed, the name of Ralph Osborne, coupled with epi-   A TALE Of THE REVOLUTION.       7 thets denoting everything that's. vile and infamous, had spread with lightning-like rapidity. So, this is your viper's nest," said one of the troopers who rode at Osborne's side. "A pretty spot for a painter, it must be confessed. What a pity that your countrymen are such a stubborn pack of rebels! There are some good' fellows among 'em, too, I dare say; but we are commanded to regard. them all as so much carrion, and if they persist in their per- verseness" "They must suffer for it," added Osborne. "I owe many a grudge in this same village, and sincechance has put it in my power to be revenged, I assure you I shall not neglect the opportunity." "It must come rather hard, though, to betray one's friends," said the other, with a quiet sneer. "' Yes-provided one has any friends to betray," replied' Osborne, sulkily. "As for me, I have no friends, and shall therefore have the fewer sins to charge my conscience with. I have not forgotten how farmer Leslie slighted me, nor how the old tub of butter that keeps yonder tavern cast me from his door one winter's night, because: I was drunk, and wouldn't ' 'pay my score. I have not forgotten these, and many other slights; and, d-n them! they shall pay for it, as sure as my name's Ralph Osborne!" Even the sergeant of the company of troopers-with whom Osborne was riding could not utterly conceal the disgust and contempt inspired in him by the words of the latter; but he prudently forbore to comment upon what he had heard, and after a pause of some minutes the party drew up before the door of a small tavern, which stood at the road-side, about a mile from the village. The moment the troopers made their appearance, there was a general scampering about the premises. The red-headed ostler hid himself in the hen-roost; the fat chambermaid ran to the garret for protection; while the landlord and his wife, after barricading the doors, beat a hasty retreat to the garret, where was deposited their only weapon of defence-a huge, old-fashioned blunderbuss, which had evidently been an heir- loom in the family.  Do these good people take us for cannibals, that they scatter thus at our appearance?" said the sergeant; "'go, some of you, and sound a summons,?' he added, addressing the men.                      ... . "You stand too much upon ceremony, sergeant," said Ralph, sulkily. "Were mine the right of command, I'd have the old sinner's house about his ears in short order." ^-    <pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6547-00000004"/> 8^        TOhE PARTISAN'S OAT:  "Doubtless," replied the sergeant drily; "and return to, Kingsbridge supperless, with a pack of howling Continentals at our heels. Iprefer a less troublesome method of accom- plishing our object." The loud and continued knocking at the doors and shutters, coupled with a few threats from the indignant and fatigued troopers, had soon the effect of bringing Boniface to his senses, and, ere long, himself and his trusty blunderbuss were seen to emerge from one of the topmost windows. "Have patience, gentlemen, and you shall be satisfied," he cried, in great trepidation. "Only spare our lives, and everything we have is at your disposal.". "Tut, tut, man," said the sergeant; " all we desire is good fare, and straightforward answers. So that these be accorded, no harm shall happen you."  The rapidity with which Master Dawson, the proprietor of the"Jolly Farmer's Inn "descended from his elevated station, was somewhat surprising to men who expected to meet with nothing but opposition wherever they might turn their steps. A table and benches wer6 provided in front of the hostel- a spot wisely selected by the sergeant, on account of the view which it afforded, both of the road and of the adjacent coun- try; a circumstance which would enable the little party to guard against any surprise; for the sergeant's confidence in Ralph Osborne's honesty was not of the strongest nature, and he always preferred being on the safe side of the question. They did not know that Reuben Gayler had departed for the city only a few days before, taking with him all the available force in that section of the country, or they might have taken less pains to ensure their safety. Osborne knew this fact well, though it did not exactly suit his purposes to confide it to the sergeant; for he had an especial motive in offering himself as a guide to this small party of British troopers, secretly despatched bj General Howe, for the purpose of exploring that fertile region of country lying between Byram s River and Kingsbri'dge. A rather hazardous undertaking, had the circumstance come to the ears of Washington at the proper time. But the expedi- tion had been, thus far, conducted so secretly, and Ralph Osborne, its director, was so intimately acquainted with the ground they were traversing, that there was little or no danger of a surprise. To return to the sergeant and his companions. Dawson had ransacked his larder, according to promise; and soon the savory fumes of pig and bacon, sent up their odors on the evening air. The exertions of the landlord had been the   A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION.  more earnest, inasmuch as Ralph Osborne had communicated to him, in a whisper, the gratifying intelligence, that any lack of civility or liberality on his part, would lead to the inevitaW ble destruction of his family, while of his hostel, not one stone should rest upon another. Under such circumstances, Master Dawson was only too willing to oblige. "Come hither, mine host!" exclaimed the sergeant, when. he felt himself waxing content upon the old man's good cheer. "From seeing so many red coats in your vicinity, you, of course, must naturally imagine that our errand is of anything but a friendly nature." "You are good enough to say so," responded Boniface, bowing and scraping, as though the sergeant had conferred a great favor on him, by the announcement. "While we confess that our object in visiting these parts, is to hold in proper subjection the enemies of the King," pur- sued the sergeant, we are not unaware that an honest soul may be occasionally found-like yourself, for instance,-who ails joins with his Majesty's loyal subjects in condemning the shameful rebellion, which some discontented colonists are endeavoring to hatch against the laws." "You're right in calling it shameful, stammered Dawson; "it's a most wicked, shameful,undutiful piece of business, and I, for one, wash my hands of it! Allow me to replenish your tankards, gentlemen,-pray do!" "Thank ye! Well, as I was saying, when his Majesty's officers find so staunch a friend as yourself, they never ail to make known his name and services; and the King, mine host, is liberal towards the loyally inclined. Behold ' he exclaim- dd, drawing from his bosom a well-filled purse, and holding it, up before the astonished inn-keeper; "that is one of the results of a close attention to duty!" "And does his Majesty thus reward all who serve him?" asked Dawson, who could not keep his eyes from the sergeant's. purse. "All, without exception. But, perhaps you doubt what I say! Here! help yourself, man. Nay, don t be shy. There's more where this came from 1" and he proffered the purse to Dawson-who, tremblingly withdrew a single piece, and then looked like a thief, caught in the act. "Take back your gold, Mr. Sergeant fl he exclaimed, a moment afterwards, "I love the dross, but I won't betray m' country. Take all I have, and welcome,-all but my honor. "There's language for a tavern-keeper," said the sergeant, overflowing with ale. "It's too late, my man; you've accept- ed the dross, as you call it, apd are now in the King's service e t        ds    <pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6547-00000005"/> 10     \  THE PARTISAN'S OATH: as long as he ees fit to hold you. Here, Seymour-Larkins, give him a cockade, and bring him along with you. The sun is getting low, and we must be moving.". If the appearance of the troopers had created a commotion, when their vicinity was first made known to the'inmates of the Jolly Farmer, far greater was that occasioned by the sudden command of the sergeant. In an instant, the women- folk were clinging to the knees and arms of the furious ser- geant, who wag rapidly beginning to feel the effects of his potations, while Mistress Dawson, with her arms a-kimbo, stood in the doorway, and launched at him a volley of invec- tive and reproach. "Death and damnation!" cried the sergeant; "will no one release me from these she-fiends? And you-you d-d Yankee turn-coat;" addressing Osborne-"I'll make you sweat nicely for betraying me into such a den!" "Revenge is in your power l" said Osborne, quietly; "shall we burn the old rookery? I await only your word." "Do what you please; burn, tear, destroy. Do anything torid me of my troubles!" was the angry reply of the half- drunken trooper. It did not require many minutes for Osborne-still rankling under the recollection of the slight put upon him by Dawson- to execute this- order; and as the moon arose, her early beams were mingled with thio lurid glare of the flames kindled by the traitor's hand. Heedless of the shrieks of the women, the marauders-hav- ing sated themselves with booty-placed the unlucky landlord upon a horse, and having securely bound his arms, to guard against an escape, the entire party took their way in the direction of the village, whose inhabitants awakened from their fancied security, only to fall by the bullets of an unspar- ing foe. A few resolute men, who had been left behind, to protect the property of the village, assembled, in haste, at the church, and for some time managed to keep their assailants at bay; but the torch of the incendiary, by filling the sacred edifice with smoke, soon convinced the little band of heroes that resistance was worse than useless. At the extreme limits of the village, lived the Leslies-the family of a sturdy farmer, whose entire happiness was .cen- tred in those by whom his hearth was surrounded. The ab- rupt entrance of Ralph Osborne, with a file of men at his heels, was ,the first intimation they received vOf the neighbor- hood of an enemy. "So-ho! farmer Leslie," he exclaimed, in a taunting tone; "does your cheek grow pale at the sight of one whom only a   A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION.      " week ago you- spurned from your door with contempt and loathing? The renegadeas you called him,has not forgotten the debt he owes you, and has come to pay it back with inte- rest." "Mad boy! what freak is this?" asked Mr. Leslie, with an eye flashing fire and disdain; and, while he spoke, he reached down from its resting-place above the mantel, a rusted gun. "You will find it a feak that:will costyoudearly,-farmer! was Osbornes reply. "Give them a volley, lads, if they resist. As for the maiden, I will look to her." A fragile figure, with a profusion of auburn ringlets falling down about her w 11-rounded shoulders, sprang from the cor- ner into which hb had shrank, upon the 6ntrance of Osborne, and threw herself with a cry upon her father's breast. "They shall slay us both," she exclaimed; "they shall not part us" My poor Grace!" replied the farmer, despondingly; they have us in their toils, and it is impossible for us to escape; yet let me strike one blow for thee! Though my arm is weak and feeble, it owns yet sufficient strength to shield from harm a daughter's-chastity.. Back or you rush upon sure destruc- tion!" he added, as Osborne made a motion to approach. "Tempt them nof-oh! tempt them not! cried Grace. "The loss of a single life may transform thennto fiends, and we shall all be sacrificed to their fury." "The shedding of blood may be easily avoided," said Os- borne; " let the maiden become an hostage for her father. I  ask no more." "Villain!" exclaimed Leslie. "Nay, father--let them have their way. They will not harm me. I will willingly become an hodtage-I am sure they will not long detain me. Their General will grant an inter- view, and I will return ere half the week expires." "You do not know them, child. Above all, you know not him. I would sooner die than witness thy dishonor." "We waste time," said Osborne; "take them in charge, I say!" "The consequences be on your own heads!" exclaimed the excited farmer. They were his last words. Several of the troopers advanced to seize him, when a ball from the farmer's gun laid low the foremost. Forbearance is no longer a virtue," exclaimed Osborne, who felt himself slightly wounded in the wrist. "Fire, and spare notY? Simultaneously with the command, Grace'Leslie found her-    <pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6547-00000006"/> 12        STHE PARTISAu'S OATH: self torn forcibly from the embrace of her father, who almost instantaneously fell beneath the murderous discharge. She was conscious of being raised in some one's arms-of being carried through smoke and fire into the open air; and then her senses utterly forsook her. Osborne, mad with pain, and almost delirious at the thought of possessing one whom he had so long viewed with a covetous eye, raised her quickly to his saddle, and the party, satisfied with the mischief they had effected, beat a hasty retreat, guided on their way by the light of the unholy fires which they had so wantonly kindled. ,     w     X                       9 CHAPTER     II. a i TowARD evening of a certain day in July, about the time of the foregoing occurrences, a large concourse of people, of all ages and conditions, were assembled in Broadway to wit- ness the entrance into the city of a regiment of troops, which General Lee had withdrawn from Connecticut, for the pur- pose of protecting the rights of the inhabitants, who had for so many years had cause to complain of the unjust and op- pressive measures pbued toward them by the mo[her coun- try. The' occasion was interesting on more than one account; for various events which had recently transpired, rendered it evident that, unless some act of concession was speedily adopted in behalf of the colonists, a long and sanguinary strug- gle was impending. Before proceeding farther with our narrative, it may be as well to dwell, for a few moments, upon the position of affairs at this crisis. New York was then in a condition which ren- dered the result of a contest, in the event of the war being transferred to that vicinity, very uncertain. Not only was the arsenal of the State deficient in supplies, but the citizens were so divided into cliques and factions, that there was no knowing upon 4vhom to place reliance. New York had al- ways been a stronghold of Toryism, and many of the most influential families were devoted loyalists. A number of British troops had also been quartered,' from the days of the old dominion, in the town, and even at the period of which I write, the "Asia," British man-of-war, lay for some time oppo- site the city, ready to unmask her guns in case of an emer- gency. Notwithstanding these discouraging facts, the Sons of Lib- erty" succeeded in getting the upper-hand of their political opponents, and it was while matters were in this condition. that Lee entered the town with his continental troops. 'The    <pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6547-00000007"/> "        THE PARTISAN'S OATH commander of the "Asia" hearing of his advance, sent word to Lee that it he entered the city, he would set it on fire. Lee's answer was in perfect keeping with his character. "Go back," said he to the messengers, " and tell your com- mander that if he sets fire to a single house, in consequence of my coming, a hundred Tories shall hang in chains for it!" It is almost unnecessary to say that the British leader thought better of his threat and did not fire the city! The arrival of Lord Howe, and Washington's appearance upon Long Island, soon put an end to this suspense. The little party which had placed itself under the command of Reuben Gayler, arrived just in time to participate in the glo rious but disastrous action which ensued. The events which accompanied the memorable battle ot Long Island are so well known, that to recount them here, would be superfluous. The Americans fought courageously, but without skill, and the prospect of being cut off by the British, induced a panic, which ended in the total overthrow of the American army. With the concurrence of his brother officers- Washington .ordered a retreat, and the American forces eventually took up their quarters at KEingsbridge, leav- ing the city in the hands of the enemy^a A party of ladies, whose attire andreneral bearing pro- claimed their standing, were gathered upon the balcony of the Governor's mansion-then occupied as a temporary residence by General Clinton. The day had been exceedingly mild and pleasant, and the natural vivacity of the party was much en- hanced by the presence of a party of officers, dressed in the British uniform, who were in the %best possible spirits, owing to their recent successes. One only among this merry group appeared sad. This was a young lady whose extreme loveli- ness of face and figure rendered her a formidable rival to the more matured beauties by whom she was surrounded. Her hair was of auburn hue, and fell in a cloud of glossy ringlets about her symmetrical form, in which were united the graces of a Hebe and a Venus. The unremitting attention paid her by the officers showed that she had nothing, to regret, as far as that particular was concerned; but there was a settled mel- ancholy in her dark blue eyes, and a sadness upon her lip, that not all the endeavors of the thoughtless crowd gathered about her could relax. "Hfear that we shall fail of making a convert of our fair little American, here," said the eldest of the ladies, interrupt- ing a short pause which had taken place in the conversation. "Albert tells me that he has given up his self-imposed task in despair," she added, turning to Grace.   A TALE, OF TBE REVOLUTION.     15 "Lady Arlington cannot blame me for being stubborn on this point replied Grace, raising her eyes, which had been fixed in revery upon the ground, to those of the speaker. I was- born and bred upon American soil, and much as I depre- cate the unhappy quarrel which has alienated us from our kin, I carnnot but believe that my country's cause is a just one. "A year's experience will soon undeceive you, vita Zble, - returned: Lady Arlington, lightly; "why, or my part, the mere contrast between our dashing officers and the clumsy boors who pretend to lead your armies, would be sufficient to make me turn traitor."  Grac colored to the temples at this ungenerous allusion to mortification wlhich was so plainly depicted upon the features of Grace Leslie, hastened to relieve her embarrassment. "Nay, mother, you are nkind," he said; " with us soldiers, generosity toward a fallen foe is considered a duty. I under- take, henceforward, to become Miss Leslie's champion against your attacks." trust that Miss Leslies arguments may not make con- verts of us, by way of turning the tables," said Lady Arling- ton; "but see-her, is an instance of that soldierly generos- ity to which you alluded just now."  And as she spoke, she pointed to a crowd who were at that moment passing the house, driving before them, with the assistance of a fle of soldiers, a group ofAmerican prison- ers, who had, apparently, justheen taken. 1w eyes centered upon this picture, at the words of Lady Arlington; but fear- ful as the change which came over Grace. She cast but one glance upon the group, and uttering a slight cry, fell back,  without sense or motion, into the arms of Captain Ar lington. To those who were witnesses to this thrilling scene, the emotion manifested by Grace was a profound nystery; but there was one, and one alone, among the group, who, by a species of instinct vouchsafed only to lovers, comprehended b at one- the cause of her agitation.  Captain Arlington b- serveA the glances which passed between Reuben- and Grace, and then, for the first time since his introduction to oMiss Leslie the gallant officer became aware that he had a rival. tapily for. euben in the hasty and disinterested glance whiech e had cast at the window occupied by Lady Arlington, he had not recognized Grace, or he might have gone to his place of confinement with feelinls far dliferent from his pres ent sensations.                          ;    <pb n="16-19" xml:id="VAC6547-00000008"/> 16    BTHE PARTISAN'S OA TB. At an angle of the open and irregular common now known as the Park, stood, in those days, a tall,n unfinished edifice of dark stone, to which common custom bead imparted the name of Bridewel, but which, Under the government of the infa- mous Cunningham, had earned the title of Psovos. t ere in cells scarcely larger than the dens intpi ch they confine the, wild beasts of the rienagerie, were huddled together hundreds of human beings, whose pnly crime was in having fought for the libertie's of their common country2 Fed upon of the coarsest description, and denied the smallest lnx- ury, they were treated more as cattle than as prisoners of war and many perished from the manifold sufferings which Cun- ngnhams s infernal malice compelled them to undergo. During the day, the pale, wan features of the more favored prisoners might be detected at the grated apertures which gave a dimn and uncertain light to the interior of this Ateri- can Bastile; and at night the air resounded with the groans and imprecations oPfits dying victims-sound- which were as music to the ears of Cunningham. Into this loathsome place Reuben and his companions were huddled, like so many sheep, by their magnanimous captors after being paraded througll the town, in all their rags a spectacle t  the populace, and subjected to every idi nity mtat human malice can devise. Somne of these poor f'ellows looked upon death as being certain, and had given up all prospect of deliverance; but there were others whose sanguine temperaments were not as susceptible of discouragement, and wlho looked forward to the future, in the midst of their trials, with renewed hope and confidence. Of this number was Reuben Gayler. Re was yet extreeaely young, and to minds determined upon overcoming every impediment which they may be called upon to encounter, life, he knew, offered no obstacle that might not be surmounted.' When therefore the gates of his gloomy dungeon had closed hir in, he did not give himself up to despondency, but endeavored, with all the eloquence of which he was master, to reanimate the drooping spirits of his companions in misfortune, and in his dreams that night, the gentle figuire of Grace Leslie hovered about his stony couch, and bade him still hope on!   A TALE OF THE REVOLION.   19   Ralph Osborne, made valorous by wine, and burning to accomplish his anticipated victory over Grace, approached Mother Kelly's domicil. The moment the hag laid eyes upon Osborne, her figure was agitated by an unaccountable tremor. "Sure, here's a pretty to do!" she whimpered, piteously; "Mr. Captain, dear, come down, do, and save the bones of a lone widow woman, that has nobody but yerself to protect. her from harm."  But Captain Arlington had already introduced himself to the notice of Miss Leslie, and his ears, preoccupied with the damsel's tale of distress, heard nothing of the cries and remonstrances of the terrified widow. It was not until a scream in the shrill accents of Mother Kelly's piping voice reached him from below, followed by the fall of a heavy body, and the noise of a scuffle, that the young officer assured him- self of the fact that others had entered the domicil. Before he could call upon the beldam to explain the meaning of the interruption, a number of British soldiers filled up the entrance to the apartment in which Grace had been confined, prominent among whom arose the ill-boding countenance of Osborne. "H--l and furies I am I to be thus thwarted in all my un; dertakings .' shouted Osborne, mad with vexation. "Arrest that officer for neglect of duty!" he exclaimed to those who were nearest him. "I will be responsible for the charge-" "Heed him not, madaam, said Arlington, in reply to a cry of terror from the affrighted Grace; " he dares not offer vio- lence to me. Stand aside, or you shall repent this inso lence," he added, drawing his sword, and turning to Osborne. "I simply perform my duty,' answered Osborne, in the same strain as before. 'It is known that you are in charge of dispatches from the Commander-in-chief at Boston) and it can hardly redound to the credit of a British officer to be dis- covered in such close vicinity to a pretty woman, when he should be, ere this, in the presence of his superiors." Astounded at the insolence of the charge, Arlington knew not, in the surprise of the moment, what answer to make, and Grace was struggling wildly in the arms of Osborne and his own arms were pinioned behind him, ere he could exclaim against the villainous treatment to which he had been subjected. He caught but onq glimpse of Grace as he was hurried from the room; resentment and mortification rendered him speechless, and even the sight of the bleeding and inanimate form of the old beldam, who lay at the foot of the stairs, where she had been hurled by Osborne, drew from him not the slightest manifestation of surprise.    <pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6547-00000009"/> CHAPTER IV. THUS far, Osborne had triumphed but even the most ac- complished of villains are prone to overreach themselves in the end, and Osborne was not an exception to the general rule. Captain Arlington, finding resistance to be useless, had suffered himself to be conducted under the escort of half-a- dozen tipsy troopers, to the city, where, having related in a clear and concise manner, the history of his previous day's adventure, he was honorably released, while, at his sug- gestion, Osborne was placed in a separate room of the old Provost, and held to answer. The upshot of the entire npat- ter was the release of Grace Leslie, who immediately found shelter undei the protecting roof of Lady Arlington-a near connection of Lord Howe, and 'mother to the young officer, whose name we have so frequently made use of in connection with that of Grace-and the signal punishment of Serjeant Osborne, who, after being publicly flogged for his misconduct, was drummed from the regiment to which he had attached himself-the jest and bye-word of his former companions. Such were the circumstances which had made Grace an in- mate, against her own desire, of Lady Arlington's dwelling. Taking into consideration her inartificial loveliness and nu- merous charms of person, it was not to be wondered that Cap- tain Arlington had become so deeply interested in her welfare. But a "change had come o'er the spirit of his dream," and the time had at last arrived, when he saw that the fair fabric upon which he had based so many visions of happiness, was about to fall. Attached to the Governor's mansion was a luxuriant garden, beneath whose shadowy retreats Grace had often delighted to wander, for the purpose of indulging in those thoughts of the by-gone time, which had once rendered her life a summer's day without a cloud, and upon which the presence of Lady Arlington and the frivolous circle by whom she was continu-   A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION.      21 ally surrounded, operated as a restraint. The day following the occurrence which had produced so great a change of feel- ings both of Grace and of Captain Arlington, was one of un- usual magnificence, and Grace had strolled forth upon the lawn, to catch a parting glimpse of the sun as it sank' in fiery lustre beneath the horizon, and to inhale the cool breeze of the evening, sweeping townward from the sea. Bathed in a perfect flood of golden light, the different islands of the bay stood out in bold relief amid the sparkling waters; suggesting in the mind of the gazer an idea of those blest retreats whic Oriental fable designates as the future home of lovilng spirits, separated by adverse circumstances, and permitted to mnct no more on earth. It may be conceived that the thoughts of Grace Leslie wru not of a very lively or agreeable nature; the loss of a fiond, doating father, and the destruction of a home, of whiclh sli had been at once the ornament and the idol, were circumstan- ces by no means calculated to excite agreeable emotions in the breast of one so young, and when alone she could give free vent to her feelings, without the fear of incurring the ridicule or the pity of a circle of newly formed acquaintances, whom  she could not avoid looking upon as having been' instrumental in promoting her misfortunes. While absorbed in one of these customary reveries, Grace had strolled unconsciously some distance toward the beach, and it was not until she had advanced to within a few yards of him, that she became aware of the presence of Captain Arlington, who had been drawn to the spot, apparently, by the same impulse which had actuated herself. Both felt v somewhat embarrassed at this unexpected rencontre, for Ar- lington, with that delicacy which is an innate characteristic of the true gentleman, had refrained from intruding upon her privacy, when he understood that it was her desire to be alone. An opportunity had presented itself, however, for the solution of the mystery which had so long troubled him, and he resolved that, come what might, he would forever set at rest these doubts. If the result proved favorable, he would make an honorable offer of his heart and hand. If unfavorable, he would immediatelythrow up his furlough, and rejoin his regi- ment, then on the point of entering into active service against the united force of Washington. "I beg, Miss Leslie, that you will not withdraw, until I htave had an opportunity of parting with a secret which is now the great annoyance of my life," he hurriedly exclaimed, as he took her hand. Grace knew too well what was coming, and her frame was    <pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6547-00000010"/> "22$    THE PABTIBAqL S PATH: agitated by an unaccountable tremor, at the words of her companion. Arlington observed the change, and drew from it, at once, in augury favorable to his hopes. Poor fellow, he was doomed to inevitable disappointment. "I see that I am already half anticipated," he continued; "bluntness, Miss Leslie, is a soldier's characteristic, and, in short, I must be pardoned if I have not on this occasion se- lected the most happy method of telling you that you are- that you long have been the object of my unalterable affec- 'ion i" He fell on one knee, as he spoke, and pressed to his lips the small, fragile hand that thrilled with agitation in his own. But Grace could only turn aside her head and weep. "I see," said Arlington, rising immediately to his feet, and relinquishing her hand, to retain which he now felt would be presumption-- my worst apprehensions are fully realized. frace Leslie can have no other feelings than hate toward one who has fought against her country. I was mad, indeed, to believe that it could be otherwise!" Stay, Captain Arlington," cried Grace, seeing him about to depart, and unwilling that he should leave her thus ab- ruptly; "that I have already bestowed my affections on an- other, I am free to confess; but, although I cannot return ybur passion, I can still esteem you as a friend." "And do you, indeed, esteem me, then?" "I do-from the bottom of my heart; and I regret most deeply that circumstances should have placed you in a situa- tion which brings you in fatal contact with those most dear to me." "Alas! dearest Grace! for thy sake I would at once resign the most brilliant prospect that ever opened before the path of a young adventurer." "And why not so, as it is? Why not act the generous part, confess your error, and cease to take up arms against a land which you know is already groaning beneath the oppressions of a tyrannical and exacting administration? Oh I that my woman's voice could be heard in your halls of legislation; I think that I could almost persuade myself to forego my sex, if ILthought that, by so doing, I could bring success to our glorious cause!" Arlington stood gazing upon Grace in speechless admira- tion, while, with form erect and flushed cheeks, she continued the glowing eulogy; in the excitement of the moment she appeared as if inspired with the spirit of prophecy. But when that excitement had'passed away, her cheeks resunAed their wonted pallor, and her eyes once more modestly sought the   A TALE O THE REVOLUTION.       23 ground. Her arguments were so convincing, that .Arlington dreaded to hear her speak again upon the subject; for, to say truth, they only echoed an opinion which had for some time been slumbering in his bosom. "I should become unworthy of the name I bear, if I longer #   listened to such discourse!" he exclaimed, hastily; and was about turning from the spot, with a confused apology for hav- ing intruded upon her leisure to so little purpose, when a wild and hideous figure leaped the little picket which separated the garden from a narrow lane that ran beside it, and placed himself directly in the path which it was necessary for both to take to return to the dwelling. Both Captain Arlington and Grace started back in un- feigned amazement, and well might they be held excusable; for the wretched object which met their gaze had nothing earthly in his wild appearance. Great masses of tangled, knotty hair overhung his brow, and every bit of covering was a rag. His jaws were hollow, his eyes deeply sunken in their sockets, and his cheeks pinched from famine, while the livid hue which overspread his features, suggested the idea of a corpse newly arisen from the tomb. In the surprise of the instant, Arlington mechanically drew his sword, but the first words of the miserable creature immediately disarmed him. "Food-for the sake of Jesus-food!" he howled, rather than said; and, stretching out two gaunt and wasted arms, he made an effort to approach still nearer, but fell, exhausted, almost at their feet. Grace Leslie's humanity was at once aroused, and with the  sped of light she bounded towards the house, whence she was quickly seen returning, bearing in her hands the wherewithal to relieve the wants of the sufferer. Hearing her footsteps, the poor fellow raised -himself slightly, with Arlington's assistance; but, on seeing who it was that brought hinv the food, he cast her from him with all the strength that he could muster, and bounded to his feet. "Is it you, Grace Leslie!-you, from whom I trace every misfortune that has beset my wretched life! You to whom I am. indebted for a lacerated back, and sufferings worse than those which the damned are said to suffer in the world to come! Oh! you are Fortune's chosen favorite now, but for you, and for all who surround you, a day shall come, when a word in mercy from the despised RALPH OSBORNE would be a boon inestimable. Aye, tremble and turn pale! From this time forth I dedicate my life to sweet revenge. Wherever you bend your steps, my hatred shall pursue-wherever scenes of gaiety invite you, a thought of me shall check your mirth,    <pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6547-00000011"/> 24        THEr PARTISAN'S OATH: and thrill your trame with apprehension! A blight shall come on every thing you touch! You shall be shunned and dreaded as a leper! My curse!-my curse- Grace couldiear no more; terror had done its work with her; a death-likswpon suspended all her faculties, and when Arlington arrived tciemnove her to the mansion, he could hardly persuade himself ^th did not carry i4 his arms a corpse. ,       .    . -CHAPTER V. WEEKS fled rapidly' away, and still each succeeding day found Reuben Gayler a prisoner im the old Provost. It is al- most impossible to conceive the sufferings which Reuben and his companions, the little- band of patriots, from the Bronx, had *P            ,   '          .X been compelled to undergo. Animated by his example, they had sustained an active part in the disastrous battle on Brook- !1 tlyn HWights, and although many, becoming entangled with the retreating columns of the Maryland forces, in their disordered flight across the marshes of Gowanus, had perished under the guns of the foe, a small portion of their number managed to escape, only, however, to fall again into the power of the adversary. Deprived of wholesome air, and living in continual darkness, the feelings of these wretched beings may be faintly imagined, Every day witnessed the death of one or more of their number, until, at last, only a dozen remained to animate each other by their presence. One morning, toward the end of December, as Reuben was lying in his straw, borne down by weakness, and racked by bodily pains, the door of "the miserable cell in which he and his few remaining companions were confined, swung upon its hinges, and an English officer stepped into the loathsome place, followed by a man bearing a light, while the scarlet uniforms of a file of soldiers could be dimly detected in the passage be- yond. For an instant he paused upon the threshold, as if over- come by the sight which met his gaze, but conquering his re- pugnance, he advanced into the centre of the cell. "Which of you," he asked, "goes by the name of Reuben Gayler 1") Reuben, who had heretofore scarcely noticed the intrusion, supposing that he, was about to be honored by one of Cunning- ham's customary visits, on hearing his name pronounced for    <pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6547-00000012"/> 26        THE PATISANiS% OATH: the first time in that dreary place, raised his head, which had been bowed dejectedly upon his breast, and replied: "That name was once my own, but misery has made such havoc here, that my best friends would hardly recognise me." "My name is Arlington ;" continued his visitor, " captain in his Majesty's fourth regiment of foot." "I guessed as much," returned Reuben, contemptuously. "You British officers are always known by your trappings." "You mistake my motive, sir," said Arlington. "T'he busi- ness which brings me here, is of the first importance, not merely to yourself, but to another, who takes a lively interest in your welfare. I am here at the instance of Miss Grace Leslie." He did not dare, as yet, to expose the whole truth to Reuben, for he saw with pity the exhausted condition of his rival, and should he proceed too incautiously in his revelations, the worst of consequences might be dreaded. At the pronunciation of that name, so hallowed in the young patriot's recollection, Reuben raised himself to a sitting posture, and eagerly scanned his visitor's face. She is true, then, notwithstanding all I have heard to the contrary!" he exclaimed, in an agitated voice. "But hold, forgive me, sir, if I suspect your motives wrongly, but in my dealings with my fellow men, I have always judged it best to be fair and above board with them, and I may be excused for asking of you a similar favor. Is Miss Leslie a prisoner." "iShe is not, save of her own free will." "Then why do I find her in contact with one wearing a muiform she has always been taught to despise? Can it be that she whom I imagined so pure, has changed?" ,(ICease, my triend,.to distract yourself with idle fears. Miss Leslie is not a prisoner, neither is she a traitoress to her coun- try. Above all-"Arlingtan's voice trembled slightly as he dwelt upon the words-" above all, she has not forgotten the love which once existed between herself and a certain Reuben Gayler, whom she knew in days of yore." 'God bless you, Captainl" exclaimed Reuben, seizing Ar- lington by the hand, and pressing it to his lips, "your words carry consolation'with them. I can not doubt your motives any longer. But you bear a message-is it not so?" "There is no time for the exchange of idle words," answered Arlington; "I am here for the purpose of conducting you to freedom, to the presence of her whom you so ardently love. Do you still doubt me? Behold the instrument that sets you free! After weeks of constant exertion, I have obtained from Lord Howe the order for your release." Reuben gazed upon the faces about him with a bewildered   A TAL OF TBE BI OLUTION.     r air, and it was some time before he could suflcieltly accustom 'himself to the light, to be able to peruse the document hande him byr Captain Arlington. bim b Captain Axeingtn.' ed at. the prospect; a thou- At first he appeared as if overjoyed at the prospect; a tho- sand recollections of the past came thronging to h  bain - figure of his early love seemed beckonu i ng h m te di- tance. Then he gazed upon the sallow and emaated coun- a + g ile vanished from tenances of his fellow-ufferers, and the smile vanished fro his face, even as the sunbeam is obscuredby the cloud. arm's length for Arlington to recei t fr g    m  "I should be gilty oanu    hac, if   s I ter edmy scious of the sacrifices which you must have made i behalf; but that document mentions only a single name, and famine and disease in a loathsome dungeon, for the sake of en- suring hi own safety. Enough has been said upon this sub- ject; either my fellow-prisoners must also be released, or I remain to share their fate, be it for good or evil." I should be guilty of an unworthy act, if I withhelde m admiration from the sentiments which you have just ut red," said Arlington; "but the happiness of another is involved in your fate, and if my arguments are of no'aval, I must intro- duce one who will, perhaps, succeed in altering your rash determination." deAt a signal from Arlington, the ranks beyond the door were seen to part-a fairylike figure darted into the apartment, and Reuben Gayler clasped in his arms the yielding form of Grace Leslie. "Oh I Grace, Grace!" he said, gazing upon her with a look of ardent affection. "Oan you, too, seek to tempt me into a measure which canr only replete dishonor on us both, and which will embitter my happiness to the last day of my existence.' "What are a thousand lives to you?") pleaded Grace through her tears. "Oh I Reuben-'after many days of anxious seek- ing, I have at last obtained for you the inestimable boon of liberty. I am alone in the world, and am indebted to the charity of strangers-those strangers, too, our country's ene- mies-for a livelihood. Can you refuse at a moment like this, to become my protector?" It was a trying moment for the young patriot, and it was evident that he felt his position keenly. Folding in his arms the form of one who was dearer to him than life itself, he gazed around once rmore upon the faces of his fellow-sufferers, and read, in the lines and cares, which there so thickly abounded, many a tale of sorrow and privation; and, turning back to    <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6547-00000013"/> 28 28 i PARTISANS OATH  Grace, almost angelic in her pallid loveliness, he emitted a heav- groan, and allowed his head to fall upon his bosom. In tha; e . ^     r .               's at djected and despairing attitude, Grace read that all be withdrawn from his relutant arms; and so they parted. '.In vain did the poor irl im             inhisdet              'erin him  ,r   CHAPTER VI. DURING his interview with Grace, Reuben had, by a vigor- ous effort, managed in a great degree to control his feelings, but when the door of his dungeon had closed upon her retreat- ing footsteps, and the place had resumed its accustomed air of death-like solitude, a feeling of utter desolation came over him, and for the first time since iis incarceration in the Pro- vest, he yielded himself upl, unrestrainedly, to the feelings of the moment. He thought of the peaceful little hamlet by the Bronx-of the gray-haired pastor-of Grace, and of the many happy hours he had passed at her father's hearth, and his soul sank at the magnitude of the contrast. Not long were his thoughts of this unpromising tenor. Most of his comrades having relapsed into their former apathy, the cell was silent as the grave-and Reuben thought he could detect, amid this sepulchral stillness, the sound of human voices. He listened, and the sound was repeated, with such distinct- ness, that, by applying his ear to one side of the wall-that nearest to the portion of the prison occupied by Cunningham -he could distinctly hear the language of the speakers, Heaven at this moment suggested to him an idea which, he lost no time in making use of. Going round among his com- panions, he endeavored to arouse their attention by telling them of whjt he had heard and seen. "By every indication," he argued, "we must be in close vicinity to the rooms of the keeper, from which our cell is divided only by a temporary partition. It would be no hard matter, I think, to remove, this obstacle, and as the Provost is poorly guarded just now, and as the keeper's room communi- cates by a broad passage with the common, we can easily make our way thither, if we have but the courage to sustain us. What do you say? Shall it be tried " "You forget," replied one, "that during the time which it IcV V j,    <pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6547-00000014"/> s8        THE PARTISAN'S OATH would be necessary to employ in removing this partition, the attention of the guard would be aroused, and, once detected in such an attempt, our death is certain." "You say truly," said Reuben, relapsing into his former dejection; "yet, stay, all hope is not yet lost. There is a certain period in the evening, as I judge, when this room- which appears, from the conversation to which I have been listening, to be a kind of lodge, or ante-room for Cunning- ham's subordinates-is untenanted. That hour cannot be far distant. Let us listen .If our suspicions prove correct, a few minutes energetic labor may liberate us from our thral- dom, without the necessity of others' interference." The hope diffused aniong the wretched inmates of the cell by the words of Reuben, had an astonishing effect upon their wasted frames; they seemed animated by a new vigor, and to Reuben the dungeon was no longer gloomy, as before. fot a word more was said; but, applying their ears to the partition, they listened intently to catch the sound of retreat- ing footsteps, which would be to them the signal for the com- ,mencement of operations.  Al night they listened, but no opportunity offered. 9 Days passed away; the hopes inspired by Reuben's convention were once more growing dim; when, at length, just ashey were abandoning the project as impracticable, ieubei -had unmistakable indications afforded him that the coast was clear for his proposed operations. The iron-bound benches of the cell were quickly torn from their fastenings, and men who had seemed, but a few moments before, devoid of every appliance, found of a sudden, instruments sufficiently sharp and heavy to carry out their long-anticipated design. To re- move the plastering-to tear away the decayed laths, was the work of a few minutes, and Reuben and his companions, astonished, as they well might be, at their success, found themselves the sole occupants of a comfortable apartment, heretofore devoted to the officers of the Provost. At the rear of the room was a window, and on the walls were hanging as variety of cloaks and other garments, which the prisoners, under the circumstances, felt fully justified in appropriating, to themselves .     * Immediately beneath the corridor already mentioned, lay the yard, or area of the jail, separated from the common by a high board fence. It was night, and, fortunately for the fugi- ties, a storm appeared to be impending, for the sky was veiled by clouds, and the moon only peered at intervals through the flying-mists. Everything seemed to favor the plot. To unbar the casement, to let themselves drop into the !    A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION.      31 yard, to scale the fence, was a work quickly accomplished. The place was deemed so secure, that Cunningham had, at this time, placed no sentries outside the walls, and thus every obstacle which had presented itself was removed. While Cuinningham and his minions were hobnobbing it over their wine, Reuben Gayler and his comrades were rapidly putting a barrier between themselves and their late masters. Disguised in a common cloak and slouching hat, which he had found among the contents of the room he had lately left, Reuben immediately took his way towards the Battery. As he approached it, his ears were attracted by the sounds of revelry, and looking up at the Governor's house, he observed that the windows were brilliantly illuminated, while the jar- ring sound which always accompanies such an occasion, left no room for doubt in his mind that a ball was going forward. He would have given worlds, at this moment, to have attract- ed th6 attention of Grace; but, even while he- was contem- plating the means of obtaining an interview without perilling his person, a hand was laid upon his shoulder, and a rough voice saluted him. :"Fine doings, neighbor, for you and I to witness, yet not partake of," said the new comer, in a tone which seemed as if thji speaker at once solicited and imparted information.  Reuben turned suddenly around, and an exclamation burst from both their lips, as they confronted each other. "Ralph Osborne!" cr ed Reuben, shrinking back as he made the discovery. "Of all whom I thought to meet, you are the last," said Osborne, trying to conquei his surprise, and as Reuben's eye, aided by the reflection of the light from the windows of the mansion, rapidly scanned the other's person, he saw at a glance the result of Osborne's apostacy to his country. "You have not fared over well, friend Osborne, since we last met," exclaimed Reuben, with a slight touch of irony in his voice aud manner. Have the King's servants proved un- grateful, and refused to acknowledge your distinguished merits, that I see you in this sorry plight!" "Come, come, master Reuben," replied Osborne, sulkily, his choler rising as he recalled the ignominious treatment which he had lately undergone. "I have erred, and bitter experience has taught me the virtue of repentance. I am no longer a King's trooper; for a time, it is true, I was dazzled by the glitter of a handful of British gold, but the hallucina- tion is passed, and I am now anxious-nay, eager to serve my country." Reuben looked at him sharply, to see if he was jesting; ,    <pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6547-00000015"/> 82      - THE PARTISANS OATH: but Osborne's appearance was so dilapidated and woe-begone, and his face wore such a repentant aspect, that Reuben could no longer doubt him, and when he again spoke to Osborne it was with less asperity than before. "And you are sincere in this?" he asked. " May I perish on the spot," began Osborne. "The oath," replied Reuben, "is unnecessary. Although, at first, I could not avoid harboring a doubt, your present ap- pearance goes far towards-convincing me." The two, hereupon, entered into along conversation, in the course of which Osborne so represented Grace in the eyes of her lover, that Reuben almost came to the determination of surrendering himself to the Provost-Marshal once more; but that there was still a doubt. "Can it be possible?" said Reuben dejectedly; "can Grace Leslie, whom I thought pure and unsullied as an angel, parti- cipate in the gayeties of a ball-room for the sake of pleasing Arlington, while I am supposed to be breathing my last in a - crowded and noisome dungeon?" He little knew that Grace had more than once deprived herself of rest, that she might pass a night under the frown- ing walls of his place of confinement, glad to be near him even though he knew it not. In the midst of his reflections, the voice of Osborne again interrupted him. "Let us make our way into the garden," he whispered; "if we were to be discovered here, the result might not be a pleasant one to either of us." Reuben concurred in the suggestion, hoping that it might lead to a rencontre between himself and Grace, and together the two bent their steps towards the seaside; Reuben framing a course of conduct to pursue in case of a meeting, and Os- borne quietly gloating over his anticipated revenge. More than once he felt tempted to stab his'companion to the heart, as he unsuspiciously walked before him, but there were too many risks to be encountered, and he therefore put up the weapon which he had half-drawn, determining to postpone that preasure to a more fitting time. "Here we are," said Osborne; " and as it will not answer for me to be seen lurking about the premises, I will remain here and keep watch for you." "Very well," replied Reuben; "I shall not detain you long; and as he leaped the paling which divided the garden from the adjoining space, Osborne turned rapidly upon his heel, and walked away in the direction of the barracks. When he arrived there, all was, of course, commotion, on ac- count of the recent escape, and when Osborne made his ap    .;*      A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION.      33 pearance, they came very near hanging him, as some atone- ment for their loss., "Is this the thanks one gets for doing you a service?" said Osborne, angrily. I came for the purpose of assisting you to recover the ringleader in this proceeding; but, if you will not vouchsafe me fair treatment, I will e'en go back to whence I came, and keep my knowledge for those that deserve it better." Well, and how much must we pay you for your informa- tion?-for, of course you do not gwe us the benefit of your knowledge!" the officer in command asked of Osborne, in a sneering tone, which evinced the utter contempt with which he regarded him. "You are right, lieutenant; one makes nothing in this world by giving; I shall therefore charge you a crown for the trouble I am about to take in your behalf!" "A modest demand, that!" said the other, turning to his brother officers, with a laugh. "But I suppose there is no help for us; so here, fellow, is your gold, and now we are at your disposal." "Let us away, then, or the bird may escape;" and, with these words, Osborne passed from the barracks, followed by an officer, and a file of men selected for the purpose, and took his way, as rapidly as he might, towards the spot where he had parted with the unsuspecting object of his hatred. i-  In the meantime, Reuben, finding, by observation, that the attention of the inmates of the Governor's mansion was -con- centrated in that portion of the domicil in which the festivi- ties were going forward, stole unperceived toward the open door of the hall, and was on the point of entering at all hazards, when a female figure, clad in black, swept past him She paused, and was on the point of making an outcry, when a single word from the intruder caused her to forego the in tention, and throw herself upon his breast. For an instant Reuben allowed his long pent-up emotions full sway, forgetful of the dark insinuations of Osborne. But, suddenly a thought flashed upon him, and he relinquished the. fragile waist of the lovely being before him, to gaze upon her with looks of distrust and suspicion. Utterly unable to com- prehend the meaning of this rapid change, Grace returned his glance with one of silent wonder. "Forgive me, Grace," said Reuben, " if I wrong you; but this scene of revelry and mirth accords not with our mutual circumstances, and I fear that even your heart, has not been able to resist the fascinations of a scarlet coat and glittering epaulettes."    <pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6547-00000016"/> -Sa4 .       ATHE PARTISAN'S OATH: "I do not understand," replied Grace, with an air of bewil- derment. "You are jesting, surely." "A sorry subject- for a jest," he rejoined, seriously. "'Hearts now-a-days are merely toys, it seems, and I was fool- ish to imagine that I had found an exception to the rule." "Great Heavenl what horrible words are these?" cried Grace, upon whom the meaning of her lover was just begin- ning -to dawn. c"R6uben-was it for this I labored to restore you to the light?-for this!" "Grace Leslie, hear me I How true the tale may be I know not, but it is said that a certain Captain Arlington has been far more intimate with yourself than comports either with your own honor, or my happiness. This dreadful doubt, which seems to have some foundation in truth, must be cleared up, so that not a taint of suspicion may rest upon you, or henceforth and forever we are strangers!" "I see it all," cried Grace; "but it is not too late, thank Heaven, to vindicate myself. Captain Arlington is a man of honor, whatever may be the circumstances under which he is placed. He will at once clear up the mystery." "It is highlyimprobable that one holding a position so envi- able as that of Captain Arlington would render an account of his actions at the demand of a despised Continental!" said Reuben, with a sarcastic smile. "He will not be convinced," cried Grace, wringing her hands, in despair of overcoming her lover's suspicions. "Heaven be my witness, foundation for this rumor there is none. And yet with nothing upon which to base your dis- trust more reliable than the unsupported assertions of an utter stranger, you, whom I have loved so fondly and so well, deny me a privilege that is not refused the culprit at the bar- the right of self-defence." "I cannot doubt you, Grace-ahd yet, your presence here, and Arlington's evident familiarity! What would I not sac- rifice to have these fears forever set at rest.' "At least," she said, "you cannot choose but hear me." And in as brief and concise a manner as she could, Grace nar- rated to her lover all that had befallen her since her seizure by the villain, Osborne, and the destruction of her family and home. The most prejudiced skeptic could not withhold his belief from Grace, whose artless but earnest manner was an evidence of her truth. Long ere she concluded, Reuben had pressed her once more earnestly to his heart, and owned that-he had wronged her. At this crisis of affairs, a drum was suddenly heard to roll without, and Grace emitted a   A TALE OF THE BEVOLUTION.        E piercing cry, as she found her lover surrounded by a band of soldiery, whose object was evidently to take him into custody. No ray of hope appeared, until Arlington, advancing into the garden, bade the officer to release his prisoner, and tendered him the order for his discharge!   \     <pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6547-00000017"/> CHAPTER VII. / . THE scene of our narrative has changed to the banks of the Brandywine It is midsummer, and the sun hangs in the cloudless sky above, like an enormous globe of burnished gold. The foliage of the trees is dark ana luxuriant, and bends the boughs so close to the water's edge, that the leaves in many places touch the cooling stream, creating a shadow that strongly invites the observer to a bath. And from un- derneath the sea of leaves and vines in which it is embedded, the white walls of a low, iood-bined cottage are lainly per- ceptible. Surrounding the cottage are fields over'owing with agricultural wealth, but not a solitary soul is visible am6ug them. All is silent and deserted; even the chimneys of the husbandmen, whose dwellings may be seen on every side, fail to send forth their accustomed smoke, telling of the good cheer that might be had within; About ten o'clock on a morning in July, such as we have jst described, this little hamlet on the banks of the Brandy- wine became suddenly converted from a deserted village, into a scene of the greatest animatiou--exhibiting all the evidences of a hasty and disordered flight. First came a body of horse- men, covered with dust and b egrimed with powder; then fol- lowed several cannon, bearing every indication of havin been used in some recent engagement between two powerful opposing forces. A group of general officers, surrounded by their staff; next made their appearance followed b a num- ber of wagons, bearing the wounded. These were the scat- tered remnants of the American forces, which had just re- ceived, under Washington, so signal a defeat upon the banks of the Brandywine. As this disordered bod rode into the little hamlet, a lovely girl just emerged from the door of the picturesque cottage alluded to, and gazed with anxiety at the    A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION.     37 group of officers who were approaching. As she made her appearance, a young lieutenant who rode among the staff, wheeled his horse out of the road, and turned towards the cot- tage, where, when he had arrived, he dismounted, and fol- lowed her within. "Heaven be praised, that has carried you, dearest Reu- ben, thus far in safety through a dangerous campaign!" was her salutation, as she submitted to the embrace which Reuben Gayler-advanced to the rank of an aid to the commander- in-chief, had cast around her. "When I heard the roaring of your cannon, my heart sank within me with apprehension. All is lost then?" "Not while there lives a Wash'ington to direct our cause," replied Reuben, warmly. "We have sustained a defeat, it is true, but all have not perished, and thousands will ere long throng to take the places of those who have fallen. Has not France sent us a Lafayette, to stimulate our soldiers to exer- tion by his chivalrous deeds? And with such incentives to perseverance, is it probable that Americans will despair? their conduct, hitherto, forbids thq thought." "' But you will surely remain a little while with us?" asked Grace. Long enough to recruit our weakened forces," he replied; ( for now we have hardly what niay be called an army. But I have a favor to ask, which I hope my Grace will not refuse me." "Can I refuse you anything in reason 2" she returned reproachfully. "Briefly then, the fortune of war has placed in my keeping as a captive one whom I fain would serve, were it only in atonement for the benefits which I have received at his hands, and for the unjust suspicions which I once persisted in fasten- ing upon him."      . Do you speak of Captain Arlington?" "The same. Wounded in the thickest of the fight, he fell almost at my feet, and common humanity should alone have prompted me to the course which I have taken. I gave him in charge of a competent surgeon, who has dressed his wounds, and only requires for him a refuge where he may receive bet- ter attention than can be found in a crowded hospital. With your consent, therefore, I will make you his nurse, and will visit him as often as I can find relief from my duties." "Your will is always my law," answered Grace, gently, "and in this instance I have a double motive for doing as you dictate. Captain Arlington will find in me a sister." "No more was said upon this subject, but, as soon as prac-    <pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC6547-00000018"/> 38        THE PARTISAN'S OATH: ticable, the wounded man, unconscious of his benefactor, was removed from the crowded vehicle which had brought him hither, and placed in comfortable quarters within the cottage. As soon as Reuben became convinced of this fact, he left him in the care of the willing Grace, and departed to look after his manifold duties. It was 'nightfall, as Gayler turned from the gateway of the little cottage, whither Grace had followed him, in the fullness of her affection, reluctant to have him go; but the moon was shining brightly, except when obscured at intervals by a pass- ing cloud, and although the road the young officer had to follow was a lonely one, he had no thought of danger, and did not take any unusual precautions to avoid it. He had just entered a patch of woods, not more than a quarter of a mile distant from the scene of his- parting interview with Grace, when he became conscious that he was followed, and ere he could find time to questibn the intruder, some one sprang with the rapidity of a panther, from the thicket which lined the path on either side, and Reuben caught the glitter of a blade, which the next instant pierced his shoulder, deluging his uniform with blood. With equal alacrity he grasped the assailant by the throat, and succeeded, after a fierce struggle, in depriving him of the instrument. Finding himself worsted, the ruffian, by a dexterous movement, freed himself from Reu- ben's grasp, and took to the thicket again, exclaiming ere he vanished from Reuben's sight: "This is your hour of triumph! the next is mine!" ,    CHAPTER VIII, A SPOT more lovely than that which Grace had selected'for her abode, could hardly be imagined. It was replete with every charm that can be -crowded together in so small a space. Thick clusters of the honeysuckle and eglantine over- ran the small, but comfortable cottages the windows of which looked out on a garden profuse in floral ornament, and upon the placid waters of the romantic Brandywine, stretching as far as the, eye could reach, beyond. But a new charm, and a brighter one by far, was now added to those with which Nature iin one of her most pleasant moods had invested the spot. Through the influence of Lady Arlington, which was almost unbounded, Grace had obtained full restitution for the losses which she had suffered, and the privations she had undergone, and she had concluded to cast her future lot among some relatives bf her mother, whose family had for several generations been the sole proprietors of-the spot. The war, she trusted, would soon be at an end, for measures of conciliation were already talked of; and Reuben had promised, should his life be spared, to settle permanently among her kin, and devote the remainder of his existence to her service. The intense anxiety with 'which she perused each succeeding Gazette, announcing battles lost and victories won, may be easily conceived by such as have experienced similar sensa- tions. The triumphs of Washington animated her with con- fidence and hope, while those of the enemy made her tremble for the ultimate fate of her country. She often saw her lover's name mentioned with honor, and this only served to increase and strengthen her affection. As for Arlington, she thought of him less, it is true, but as one who had performed so many acts of kindness in her behalf, she could not but regard him v with gratitude and esteem. Only a few months had rolled by since Grace had bidden    <pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC6547-00000019"/> 40        THE PARTISAN'S OATH: adieu to Reuben at New York; he to volunteer his services once more in the ranks of his countrymen, and she to repair to the spot which had been decided" upon as her future abiding place. During thatj time many changes of high im- portance to the nation had tken place; the battles of Trenton and Princeton had been fought, and the name of George Washington rang in every mouth, and was even mentioned with respect by the most determined of'his enemies. Such was the aspect of affairs when the famous battle of Brandy- wine, at which the young and generous Marquis de Lafayette won his first laurels as a warrior, gave a temporary check to the American arms, and caused a cloud to lower over the country's prospects. But her lover had escaped from the conflict free from scathe, and his ardent and glowing language gave Grace renewed hope for the future. Blest by his society, she was content to find happiness in the present, and all else was, for the time being, forgotten. For many days subsequent to his removal to Grace's dwell- ing-occupied only by herself, and a plain, pains-taking farmer, with only his wife beside for a companion-Captain Arlington lingered upon the confines of the grave. His wound had been of so serious a nature, that the surgeon who had attended him had given over all hopes of his recovery; but a comfortable apartment and unremitting attention on the part of Grace and her relatives, soon brought about a favorable change in his condition. In the meanwhile, Grace had spent all that portion of her time not devoted to'her patient, in the society of Reuben, whose visits enhanced the delights of a home that was already an earthly paradise to her. -It was one pleasant summer's morning, when Arlington first awoke to a consciousness of his situation, and a know- ledge of the source from which he had received assistance and protection. ..The sunlight was streaming through the half- opened window into the apartment in which he lay, disclosing beyond faint glimpses of a landscape, such as artists delight to picture, and poets are wont to image in their dreams. But by far the loveliest object which met his gaze was the fragile figure of a girl of seventeen, who sat close by the latticed casement, bending over her needlework, while the sun, pour- ing full upon her exquisitely rounded form, lit up with tints of gold her chestnut hair, and enveloped her in a kind of glory, so that she more resembled one of those creations which we see depicted in the works of ancient masters, than a being of mortal birth. It-took all of Arlington's strength to raise himself on his elbow, and for nearly an -hour he continued to gaze upon her, drinking in rich draughts of beauty, such as   A TrALE OF THE REVOLUTION.     41 he thought he ne'er had gazed upon, and yielding to visions of earthly happiness, which were almost too transcendent to be realized. A deep sigh from"the convalescent aroused the attention of the fair object of his thoughts, and Grace, turning toward her patient, uttered an exclamation of surprise and alarm, while the Captain, on his part, was not less aston- ished to find himself under the charge of Grace, whom he had supposed to be miles away. "There is no occasion for this alarm, my dear Miss Grace,"' said Arlington, observing her alarm, and thinking only of the elysium in which he had been basking. "I am doing well enough, I assure you, and beg that you will not pause in your employment on my account. I shall be perfectly content if you will suffer me to remain as I am,. And relapse again into your former state, as you assuredly will, if you persist in thus overtasking your powers," returned i Grace, resolutely, and going to his side. "Believe me; I am getting strong again-indeed, my -pain has entirely left-me,' added Arlington, but almost as the words escaped his lips, he was struck with a convincing proof of his inefficiency. The excitement which had produced so rapid a revulsion in his feelings had subsided, and with it the momentary power which it had produced. He strove to rally against the weakness, but in vain; a sudden pain oppressed him, and he sank backward, with a groan, upon his pillow. Grace instantly tendered some restoratives, and after some minutes he again sufficiently recovered himself to be able to converse-contrary to the express injWpctions of his lovely nurse. "I must have been very ill," he said, as soon as he regained his voice; "I can remember being severely wounded in the chest, but how, or where, is a profound mystery to me."' "You received your wound,'" she replied, " at the battle of Brandywine, where you behaved, as I have been told, bravely and well. Had it not been for Reuben Gayler, who took you prisoner, I might not now have the pleasure of officiating as your nurse." "It is a pleasure, then " asked the Captain with a latent hope. Grace colored and looked down, not knowing what to say, when Arlington saved, her the trouble of speaking, and relieved the embarrassment under which she was evidently laboring. "Forgive me, Miss Grace," he said; "I did not think when I spoke; it is an interdicted subject, and I will take care that it is not again touched upon by me. Would that I had been    <pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6547-00000020"/> 4-9    THE PARTISAN'S OATH: left to perish upon the field where so many of my brave comrades left their dust before me. I had then spared you this mortification, and nmself an additional pang." "You are wrong to speak thus, Captain Arlington; indeed, you are, she replied, with tears in her eyes; "you are now exhausted from the effects of your illness, and hardly know what you say. You will soon recover from your present prostration, and will learn to conquer feelings which you are aware cannot longer be encouraged with safety to yourself. Besides, they might lead to a difference between yourself and -and another, and, as a friend to both, I could Wvish so sad a mishap avoided. Take what repose you may; for you are getting momentarily more weak, and before the day expires I will revisit you." He would have interposed to stay her-he would have promised not to utter another syllable for the remainder of the day, for the sake of knowing that he was still in her company, still gently watched by her; but ere he could articulate a word, she had vanished, and the high-heeled shoes of her aunt, which were shortly afterward heard upon the stairs, took from him all disposition for conversation. He soon. fell into a refreshing slumber, from which he did riot awake until early on the following morning; but Grace was not sitting, as usual, by his bedside, and the chamber seemed dull and dreary without her presence. ,    CHAPTER IX. I was a goodly sit for the eye to rest upon, in those of republican simla gocitoy and contention, the camp of the ofAmeican r armybupn the Brandywine. Although less bril- liAnt perhaps than th at which the British army would have offered under similar circu tances, h   placed itself less imposing e.  e principal division ad paced itelf in a large field situated upon th  - ile that to whrh mile distant from Grace's dwelling, hile Occupd a field Lafayette was, for the time being, attached, oupidn oeld of lesser dimensions, adjoining it. In various positions on either side were the other portio  of the little army, whose numbeither side were thouh comaratively insignificant, were sufficient to affonumbers thouh ritis generals, who had hitherto anticipated toan easy fford three of anxiety.. The forces of an  tterasy commanded by Howes, were pressing on towards Philadelphia, which was already fairly in their poer; but,re it was not the intention of Washem to rewas tain possession of that city without a struggle, and he was merely recruiting his forces, in order to prewere them for the task which lay before them, and upon which all were willing and eager to enter. The adventure of Reuben Gayler had naturally created much excitement among his comrades, and the country was scoured in al directions, as far as comported with their safetyoured by parties of armed horsemen, with a view of dtect-g ing the assassin. Their exertions, houwever, were unavaieng, not having been able to discern the ruffian's countenance owin g to the darkness of the night, and the rapidity of the owing to the darkness ..    .escription o, transaction, Reuben could not give a description of him, and. transaction,leue. ,....-ots  had been made, the per- of course, although several arrests had been mde, te per- sons spect re discharged for want of sonsate sthusm. eted we uben disclosed the whole matter to Grace, she might have given him a clue which would have    <pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6547-00000021"/> THE -PARTISAN'S OATH: 'led toothe desired result; but, fearing to alarm her by unne- cessary fears, and firmly believing that he had been mistaken for another, he hesitated to reve hat had befallen himtaen thus the subject passed over, and was suffered gradually to drop. At the time of these proceedings, the whole country was infested by bands of desperate and unprincipled wretches, who, having no particular bias in favor of either side, ravaged the rural districts, plundering and pillaging herde'r they turned their steps--sonetimes burning the houses of those to whom they chanced to take a dislike, an performing other outrages, with the recital of which we h sitate to sully our the midst of a lonely and desolate moor not far from  the scene, of the foregoing occurrences, was situated a hut which, probably from its solitary situation and the fact tha a murder had once been erpetrated within it, had long ha the reputation of being aunted. Strange cries, and fiendish  noises were asserted, by the peasantry who resided in he vicinity, to issue from it throughout the livelong night, and unnatural lights glimmered through ever1y nook and cranny  of the old rookery, giving it the appearance of a living fur- nace. One or two, more reckless, or more foolhardy than the rest, had sought to penetrate its mysteries; but they had never been seen again; and thus the place had grown to be sphunned and avoided, until, at lastj it was declared a haunted On a wild and tempestuous evening in October, when the sky is overcast by thre-atening and airy ouds, and the   I forest paths are strewn with faded leaves a poor wretch, with iardly sufficient clothing to disguise his nakedness,' hiverint r'omi cold, and pinched with famnine, turned his steps in the lrection of this same hovel we have been describing. H  ad been to a neighboring hamlet, craving alms; but the war ad hardened the hearts of men, even as it had changed the spect of their fields, and wheresoever he bent his steps, he xet with a chilling rebuff. Refused the means of prolonging fe, the wretch was about turning his steps towards the fields  ith the view of giving himself up to death, when a careless ublican .jokinly advised him to pply atth when a carnel house on ie moor, whee, he was told, he was certain of finding ac- )mmodation. Reckless of consequences, the beggar took his way towards e aunted spot. As he approached it, lie found it bril ntly lighted up, while from within there issued a series of unds that might well have given it a supernatural reputas   A '1'ABli UA t 'JLO'll TEVUIYUTIO'I'. TV tion. The noises which issued from it, however, had to a practised ear the sound of Bacchanalian rejoicings, rather than anything else, and did not deter the wanderer from ap-. proaching. He had not gone far, when an athletic form sprang, as it were, out of the ground directly, before him, and in a rude voice, demanded his object. "Doo you know," he asked, "the nature of the place you are about to visit?" "I know not," replied the outcast; "neither do I care; I am alone in the world, penniless, without a friend; famishing, almost, for. want of a crust." '"Jf this be so, why*did you not ask for succor at the vil- lage?" inquired the other, eyeing him suspiciously through a mask, which he wore for the purpose of avoiding recogni- tion. "Would you mock me?" returned the outcast. "Have you not lived long enough in the world to kifow that it has no pity for the unfortunate?" "You have tried the experiment then?" "If begging one's bread from door to door be a degrada- tion, then am I one of the lowest of human beings." "You would work, then, if a chance were afforded you?" "Work! aye, till I could work no longer 1" ' "Hark ye! my lad, art particular as to the nature of the employment a?" I am indifferent to everything. I ask only food, and a place whereon to repose my head. For this I will do any- thing-for conscience and I have long since parted com- pany." "Come then, with me," said the unknown, taking him by the hand as he spoke. "You may, or may not be sincere. If you are, you shall be regaled upon the best that the land affords; but, if evil your intent, remember that a power greater'than that of the law itself surrounds you, to escape from which were impossible; 'and remember, also, that more than one adventurous wretch, whose sole offence was the desire to make himself acquainted with our secrets, has fallen a victim to his rashness. Come-for now there is no re- treating."  "Retreat is out of my thought," replied the outcast, with a contemptuous laugh; "I have already steeped myself in guilt, and reck not what may be the nature of your calling.  Henceforward, I am with you, heart and hand!"  The other grasped his hand with a firmer pressure, and both hastened on until they had approached to within. afew. f' - ,          t    <pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC6547-00000022"/> 4* 0TUJ PARTISAl    ' OATH: ards of the hovel, when they were again challenged, as be- fore. Upon a certain reply being made by the man in the mask ti e questioner instantf disapeard, and th they found themsees at the door of the hovel, which opened to them mmediately upon agiven signal. The stranger found him- self, by this means, in the centre of a scene of Bacchanaliaji confusion. A huge ire was crackling and blazin in the i-' mense. chimney p aces before which were seated at leas twenty ruinly looking fellows, at a long wooden table, laden with articles of food of various descriptions. A younporke was steaming upon a huge platter in the centre, flanked by meats and vegetables of various kinds, and this, with. the addition of a keg of brand which strod beside, formed the chief feature of 'this Epicurean repast. rious a nature, that it would have puzzled many an old clothes dealer of the present generation Some were clad in farmers' hexce  tiasof utse,'th tad lohe ho xception of their faces, which were masked, and therefore undiscernible. Others affected a ppnichant for military attire, and, to show their neutrality, wore a dress compounded equally of the Continental and British uniforms. He who sat at the head of the table, on a seat elevated some feet above the rest, was a gaunt, burly ruffian dressed in the combined costumes of an English and an American officer, while, for want of something more appropriate, his head was surmounted by a cocked ha't, from which protruded  a long, straight, black feather, or pomon, which had the effect of addng several inches to his height. This worth held in his rigt hand an enormous sword, while his let brandished a pipe, which he stretched over the assemblage like a -wand, whenever he spoke. Some were seated upon the heads' of upturned barrels; others had boxes for seats while one or two were compelled to sit upon the table Innumerable cobwebs depended from the ceiling, and the wind, roaring and whistling through every cranny in the old rookery, made a harsh, discordant sound, which added mate- rially to the uproar which prevailed. "What makes Black Jack so late, to-night?" quoth he who appeared to act as chief over this violent assemblage. "Don't you seeIbrin with me a friend -" .  replied the new comer; " one who will do us good service, unless I am much mistaken in my man. Look at him lads   Sawye ever such a scarecrow 2' And with one powerful effort of his hand he whirled the   outcast around, so that his person became fully visible to all-- at which a roar of laughte;arose, that made the place fairly ring again. "Scarecrow, or not," rejoined the outcast, angrily; I have seen the day when I could turn the stoutest of you around my finger, with scarcely an effort. You laugh, but it is true, as lit- tle as I seem capable now of such a feat. But I came not here to boast, nor to be your jest. I am in want, as you may see, and I ask no greater boon than to be admitted among your number." "How do we know that you will serve us truly?" asked the chief of the outlaws, scanning him with a suspicious eye.  c I have no present means of proving my sincerity," was the reply; " but these are times of trouble and excitement, and I may not long be without an opportunity. Society has driven me forth to die; must I meet with a like fate from you?" "You speak us fairly," returned the chief, " and I see no reason to doubt your word. Black Jack will show you the fate of those who have sought to betray our secrets; if, after that,  you are willing to join our band, we are equally willing to re-  ceive you as a brother; but should you betray any signs of  fear or trepidation, be sure that the same doom is in store for yourself. Ho! Jack-idle vagabond that you are! show the stranger our treasury forthwith!" The alacrity with which Jack set about obeying the com- mands of his leader, showed the awe which' he entertained      { towards that redoubtable personage. Say not a word," he whispered to the outcast, as they left the apartment, " and you are safe; but do anything to show  that you are afraid, and you are lost beyond redemption t Trust in me, for I am your friend." After descending through a winding passage some twenty steps, they entered a vault, the atmosphere of which was so damp that it struck a chill to the bones of the outcast; but not a single shiver passed over him. Their way was lighted by a torch, which Black Jack had brought along, and when they had reached the midst of the vault they stopped. Two holes attracted their attention. Black Jack paused at the first one, and bade his companion look within. He did so, and his breath came thick and fast, as he saw that it was filled with massive plate, and with gold and silver articles of various kinds. "Let us now examine the next," said Black Jack, conduct- ing him a few steps farther. The outcast gazed into the second pit, and a thrill of horror came over him, as he caught the sight of a mass of mangled '      ,                    ^ *    S1    <pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC6547-00000023"/> PARTISE PA 'S OATH: bodies, from which the blood was still flowing. Overcome by the odors of the place he started involuntarily back, and as he did so, he saw the hand of the outlaw uplifted above iim, bear- ing a spade, which in an instant more would have descended but, with the strength of desperation he tured and grasped the other by the throat, and held hi' . . .. urned and grasped which had so nearly become his own grave. RaULPH OSBOP-r. had again escaped death by a single hair. ^"-x  *   .     .          c   .          -   CHAPTER XI THE recovery of Captain Arlington, from the hour of his last interview with Grace, was so rapid as to be surprising. He suffered no relapses, and in a few weeks had gained so much strength, as to be able to walk about; his room with the assistance of a crutch. In a week more, he was sufficiently advanced to take a stroll in the garden, with Grace for a companion-- a happiness which he had longed for, but hardly expected to enjoy. Day by day, as he gazed upon her unfolding beauties, he felt the promptings of love becoming stronger within him, until, at last, he made no efforts to conquer the passion which swayed him, but surrendered himself entirely to its power. In the meantime, the subject of Reuben's singular adventure was gradually forgotten; divided between his attentions to Grace and the arduous duties of the camp, he totally overlook- ed the circumstance, and matters were thus situated, when pre- parations were set on foot for the removal of the army. Reuben was busied one morning in completing his' own arrangements for the departure, when a messenger entered his tent, brining + a note, which had been found by one of the sentinels on the ground, close to the outskirts of the camp. It was written in an unknown hand, and ran in these words :-  "You deem yourself secure, but you are not so. The viper, warmed into a new existence, is about to sting the breast- that gave it shelter. Beware of Arlington! beware of Grace! Have a wary eye upon both, and do not be too easily per- suaded!1" 71Uis mysterious nissive was signed-"' A FRIEND;} but Reuben had! had enough of jealousy, and he immediately has- tened to Grace, for the purpose of laying it before her. She as walking in the garden with Arlington, when he approached    <pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC6547-00000024"/> 50        THE PARTISANS OATH: her, and for an instant a jealous pang shot across his breast, but he quickly repelled the fear, and as he came up with them, said in a jesting tone, while he handed the letter to Grace for perusal:  "Here is a billet douz with which I have been favored; is it not sufficient to make one jealous?" Grace handed it in turn to Captain Arlington, and answered with a laugh: "And do you not feel jealous, master Reuben?-do you for- get a certain scene which took place in New York not lang syne, when a certain lady, who shall be nameless, was the heroine, and a certain gallant officer the hero?" "Thanks to your own candid nature, which sets all suspicion at defiance, I have long since, conquered that ridiculous pro- pensity," he answered lightly. "But what thinks Captain Ar- lington of so important a document?"  "It is plain, friend Reuben, that you have an enemy some- where," returned Arlington. Can you not call to mind some circumstance, that may afford a clue to this little mystery?" "It is impossible," replied Reuben; "I am not aware of having given offense to any one. Yet, stay! 'but no-he dared not do as much!"      o Arlington asked, 1 Who dares not?" but Grace said nothing, she knew too well who was the object of her lover's thoughts. "Oh! 'tis nothing-a passing thought," returned Reuben, lightly. And yet, the singular affair which so closely in- volved my, life on a recent occasion-" "Your lif,'" cried Grace, with a look of alarm. "Was there a secret with which you feared to entrust me?"  "Forgive me, dearest Grace, but my motive was a good one, although now it appears that I erred." And he proceeded to tell the story of the attack on his life, and his escape. "It is Osborne," said Grace, with a look of terror; " it can be no other. His oath-that fatal oath!-ah! I recall it now; it was too deeply meant!" "Calm yourself, dearest Grace; belive me, these fears are idle. To-morrow I will take measures to ensure the apprehen- sion of the villain, whoever he may be. And now, good- nght! I have much to do ere daylight comes again, and ashington is particular. Captain Arlington, I give you my hand; I believe you to be a man of honor, and as such I am proud- of your friendship, even though our destinies have been cast so widely asunder." "Sir," rejoined Arlington, "you are a gentleman and a sol- dier, and I can not but regret that you have devoted yoir talents to so mistaken a cause. Farewell!" 9 .   A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION.      1 And speaking thus, they parted. We must now return to Ralph Osborne and his new-found associates. Osborne's-career had been that of many who had pursued a similar course. Going from one vice to another, he had plunged deeper and deeper into iniquity, until, at last, honest men shunned him as a pestilence, and society refused any longer to receive him as it own. Then came that desperate resolve which we have so recently seen him attempt to execute. But a higher power than man's interposed to thwart his inten- tions. On the night on which Reuben had been attacked, Osborne had gone forth with the desperate purpose of robbing the first person whom he mightchance to meet. Accideht threw in his way Reuben Gayler, and it was not until they had clenched, and he had recognized the voice of the latter, that he knew his old enemy and rival. Lucky for Reuben was it, that he pos- sessed the greater strength, or a far more different result might have attended the meeting. After the scene which had occurred between himself and the outlaw, Black Jack, in the vaults of the old house on the moor, Osborne expected to encounter the signal vengeance of the dis- orderly crew among whom he had so unexpectedly been cast; but, to his astonishment, they applaudel him for his courage,. laughed at Black Jack for his clumsiness, and gave the hero of the adventure a prominent seat at the well-filled board. How rapidly the food disappeared beneath the ravenous jaws of Osborne, it matters not to relate. Suffice it, that, after gorg- ing himself with food, until his eyes were nearly protruding from their sockets, he took to the brandy, joined in the wild revelry of the Bacchanals, who, by the way, had removed their masks, and finally rolled on the floor in a fit of beastly intoxi- cation; a denouement which gave the'ruffians a still higher idea of his capacities, and he became thenceforth established as one of the foremost ringleaders of the gang. On the next day, Osbdrne, after having recovered from the effects of the previous night's orgies, began to revolve in his mind some plan for the consummation of his villainous inten- tions with regard to Grace Leslie. Then, by degrees, as- he reflected, the recollection of the riches which had been .h5wn to him, crept into his mind, and he thought what a finedg it would be, if he could, by some adventure, possess himselRot all this wealth, and, taking forcible possession of Grace, con- vey her away to some far distant clime, where ,she would be taught to forget the troubles through which she had passed, and the breath of suspicion be for ever silenced. Such was the nature of Osborne's meditations, when he received a most unexpected disciple in the person of his cap-    <pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC6547-00000025"/> 52        THE PARTISANIS OATH: tain. Having wandered one morning to a solitary spot at some distance from the stronghold, the latter began the sub- ject by sounding him as to his idea of the kind of life which they led, and his aspirations with regard to the future. "A free life and a merry one," replied Osborne, " that is my great desire. Give me plenty of money, plenty of fine companions, and a long life to enjoy them, and I am con- tent." "You are easily pleased, dt any rate. But did no thought of wealth and splendor ever cross your mind; have you never had an ambition to become a powerful member of that society that has oppressed and degraded you; to wring men's hearts, as they have wrung yours before now?."' "Aye! that would, indeed, be worth living for," answered Osborne, eyeing the other warily. "To-be-sure; and who is better fitted to enjoy such an ex- istence, than you?" "Is this some scheme of yours, to entrap me?" asked Os, borne, glowingly. "Hark you, comrade," rejoined the outlaw-" this is pa- lavering to no purpose. H may as well be frank with you, because to tell the truth, you are in my power, and it matters not tome in what light you may receive my disclosures. Last night in your dreams, you made use of certain expressions, which testified, but too plainly, that you had already become wearied with the sort of life we lead. Nay-don't frown, and fumble for your knife! I approve of your sentiments, rather than discountenance them, and having brought my mind to a similar conclusion, I have sought this opportunity of ccmsult- ing with you on the subject." "You have said that I am in your power; suppose that I were to betray this conversation to our comrades?" "They'd laugh at you, for your pains." "That's probable, I admit. But, proceed; you have not yet said all." "I propose, then," said the other, in a low tone, that on some night when a favorable opportunity seems to offer, we leave our brother drones to take charge of the old hive, and appropriate to ourselves those certain baubles of gold and sil- ver which our friend, Black Jack, was so kind as to show you on the night of your initiation into our mysteries. Once in possession of them, we can easily make our way to sonde dis- tant port; our comrades, fearful of the law, and penniless, withal, will not dare to follow us; with stylish clothes and  clean faces we can mingle with the world withoutea fear of i   A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION.      58 being detected, and thus at once enjoy its pleasures, and per- fect our little scheme of retaliation. What say o  Well conceived," replied Osborne, thoughtfully. You have only given words to an idea that has long been slumber- ing in my own breast, but which it would have been impossi- ble for me to accomplish without your assistance. But there must be still another participant in our contemplated flight. How ; anoth er " Yen h a woman           s    o "Ah r! I  the casee-,sly dt you dispatch him "I do not mean one of your common kind," pursued Os- borne, " forl the person of whom I speak, is as far removed above my degraded sphere as the sun is from the earth it illu- minates." "Is see; you would make her take a little journey for the sake of her health." Precisely. Besides, 'twere an act of charity to throw the arm of a protector about her; for she is an orphan, and my rival is so much of a soldier, that he can not pay her that atten- tion lhich a prudent woman always exacts from her lover. "A rival in the case, bah? Why don't you dispatch him at once?" "m e is hot so easily dispatched. And, besides, I would have him live, that he may suffer such pangs as he has inflicted upon nem -only in tenfold proportion. The girl must be mine and er e trecan move a step in the other matter I must have the assistance of our comrades, to ilake sure of ay primary object." It shall be done," replied the other; and, after shaking hands they parted-each taking a different way, that they might not arouse the suspicions of the rest. Ait the expiration of a week, during which time the captain of the outlaws and Ralp Osborne had had several interviews upon the subject of their recent conversation, the former took the latter aside-the whole band having absented themselves from the hovel on some marauding expedition, purposely plan- ned by the two worthies, that they might have the field all to themselves-Ad together they descended to the vaults, where lay the treas which were to enrich them both for life. "How beautiful they look 1" exclaimed the outlaw chief, waving his torch above his head, and bendingover the treasures, that he might obtain a better view. A fiendish thought crept into Osborne's brain. "Gold and silver, and precious stones," continued the out- law, " enough to enrich a dozen such as we. How we shall enjoy them, friend Ralph, when thev are ours!' /    <pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC6547-00000026"/> h     r   aearS4 h ing suTHEd, PARTISANS OATH: There came a rushing sound, as of the passage of some heavy body through the air; a dark and massive instrument glistened for an instant in the red light of the torch, a heavy groan re- sounded throughout the vault, and the next moment Osborne stood alone above the coveted treasures, leaning upon a gory spade. The first transports of delight having passed over, the next thought of Osborne was the concealment of the body. It was now late in the afternoon, and in a few hours his comrades might be expected to return. Should he be detected, his death he knew was inevitable. After a little reflection, he remem- bered a quagmire, which stood in a solitary part of the moor, and in whose slimy depths a number of the band had been re- ported to have lost their lives, at different times. Wrapping the body of his victim in some old canvass, the assassin slowly ascended with his burthen, and, in a few mo- ments more, as daylight began to blend with the shadows of evening, a man might have been seen stooping over some dark and indistinguishable object in the centre of the marsh. ' The removal of the treasures was a task not half so easy of accomplishment; but it was more pleasant than the other; and it was not long before Ralph Osborne had removed to a place of temporary safety the valuable deposits, to secure which he had imbrued his hands in the blood of a fellow being. It was a lovely night, and the moon had risen ere' Osborne had completed his voluntary labors. The family of the little cottage in which Grace Leshe had found a refuge, were long retired to rest, and not a sound disturbed the solemn stillness of the night. The hours passed on; Arlington, alone, found it impossible to close his eyes in sleep; there was a vague sense of impending calamity about him, which rebuked all thoughts of repose. He arose about eleven o'clock, dressed himself, and went forth into the moonlit garden, over which a gentle breeze was straying. At this moment there gradually emerged from the leafy covert a single dark figure, followed with like precaution by several others, and in a trice, before Arlington could make an effort at self-defense, or utter a cry for assistance, he found himself, bound and gagged, a prisoner in the hands of un- known adversaries, who were rapidly hurrying him away from the spot. As for poor, frightened Grace, she awoke from a quiet sleep, onlyj to encounter the vindictive glances of the miscreant Ralph Osborne. "It is in vain to cry for mercy," he replied, in. answer to her ! e   A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION.      55 supplications. "Remember my oath, and cease to disturb the air with unavailing lamentations." The trampling of hoofs below, and the confused sound of voices, announced that all was ready; and thus, for a second time, Grace Leslie found herself in the power of the only being whom she had ever hated. b,     <pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC6547-00000027"/> CHAPTER XI. THE whole transaction narrated in the preceding chapter was the work of a minute. So secretly and suddenly was it accomplished, that not a single dwellerin the vicinity was aware of what was going forward. It was only when day had fairly set in, and the lifeless bodies of the old couple -with whom Grace Leshe had found an asylum, were found welter- ing in their blood upon the floor of their apartment, thadt the circumstance became fairly known. The whole country, for miles around, was up in arms, and ready to revenge so bar- barous a proceeding. The first intimation of the occurrence which Reuben re- ceived was from an anonymous note, written in the same hand as that which had been sent to him a few days pre- viously, and reminding him of the warning which he had treated so lightly. "Arlington and your faithful Grace," it ran on, "have blinded your eyes until they can be blinded no longer, and, aware of this fact, have taken steps which will, at least for the present, place them beyond your power." Reuben was singularly agitated at the perusal of these mysterious words. Could it be possible that she to whom he had sp frankly trusted, and whose manner always appeared so devoid of guile, could have been playing, all this while, a deceptive part, for the purpose of accomplishing so sinister an object Nothing but the jealous doubts which had for so long a time, tortured him with regard to Arlington, could induce him to believe it.  Having asked and obtained permission to inquire into the affair, and, if necessary, to punish the perpetrators, Reuben selected a small party of horsemen, most of them well ac- quainted with the country, and immediately departed for the scene of the outrage, in a state of mind which little fitted him for a duty requiring so much caution and dispatch. The   5T A TALE OF THE RBVOLUTION. appearance of everything about the little dwelling too soon convinced him of the truth of all tlhat he'had heard. As for Arlington, the fact of his having disappeared with Grace was, to Reuben, sufficient evidence of her guilt. Having made numerous inquiries among the neighbors, but all to no purpose, he set on foot a search which led to the discovery of the old hut on the moor, and of the mangled bodies, the sight of which had occasioned so much horror in Osborne's mind on a recent interesting occasion. But beyond this, there was no clue left to tell in what direction the out- laws had departed, Convinced within his own mind that Arlington had planned and executed the whole affair, with the assistance of some of those lawless wretches whose deeds were already the terror of the entire country, Reuben felt that pursuit would be useless, and having come to this conclusion, he reluctantly gave the order to return. Once more am  ong his comrades, Reuben endeavored to free himself from the thoughts which harrassed him by a still closer attention to the duties of the camp; but all he could do would not for a moment divert his attention from the sub- ject which engrossed his mind. Half maddened by his suspicions, and determined that, he could not support life wucJ longer under such a variety of conflicting emotions, he reed to seek out Arlington, even in the face of the British camp, and demand from himn an account of his treacherous conduct. In a word, forgetful of the dangers to which such conscious of the danger in which he had placed himself Osborne, with a sagacity for which no one would have given him credit, divided his party, and sent them off in different directions, thus creating a variety of conflicting reports, which had the effect of throwing Reuben off his guard, as we have already seen. One division was ordered'to conduct Arling- ton to within a short distance of the nearest British encamp- ment, while Osborne, who had succeeded to the command by making it appear that his predecessor had fallen into the hands of an American scouting party, from whom he himself had narrowly escaped, conveyed Grace towards the wildest and least inhabited district, where he knew that, at least for the present, he would be safe. The party to whose keeping Captain Arlington had been entrusted, fulfilled their duty to, the letter. They conducted him to the neighborhood of the British camp, and there deserted him.    <pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC6547-00000028"/> 58        TSTHE PARTISAN'S OATH: Weakened by his recent sufferings, from the results of iwhich he had, as yet, scarcely recovered, Arlington wan- dered at random about the country, sleeping at times beneath the roofs of deserted farm-houses-at others exposed to the inclemency of the elements, until it seemed as if nature must sink under so many privations. He was, in fact, reduced to so lamentable a condition as to be scarcely able to walk, when he fortunately fell in with a party of British troopers, on a foraging expedition, and by them was recognized, and conducted to the camp, where he had been given up as lost, and his name so reported upon the books of the regiment to which he belonged. In a few days he was entirely recovered, and once more ready for active duty. Villains, it would appear, generally manage to overreach themselves at the moment when they feel surest of success, and thus it proved with Ralph Osborne.  Terrified at her situation, and deprived of all energy by the fresh misfortune which had fallen upon her, Grace felt that her mind was losing its wonted elasticity. Willing to give her a brief respite, after the troubles which she had been compelled to undergo, Osborne for some days wisely refrained from annoying her with his presence. But, while he was passing the time in listless apathy, a plan was concocting in the fertile brain of one who, with a fair start, might prove a formidable enemy to Osborne. We have already introduced upon the scene of action a character under the soubriquet of Black Jack-so called from the jetty color of an enormous beard, which almost concealed his face from view. This remarkable individual had never forgiven Osborne for getting the letter of him on two succes- sive occasions, and he was contriving how he should rid the' band of Osborne, and return to take possession of the riches left behind them at the hovel-in case they should be still there -when an incident took place which assisted him in the ac- complishment of his design. Osborne, one afternoon, had disguised himself as a farmer's boy, and left the band, under pretence of visiting a neighboring town, and ascertaining the movements of their enemies; but, in reality, for the purpose of removing from their place of deposit th9 valuables which he had secreted, unbeknown to his companions; who had been so constantly in motiob, that they had no leisure to look after, their treasures. Black Jack, who was left in command until Osborne's return; judged this a fitting opportunity for the accomplishment of his project. He, therefore, cautiously broached it to his comrades; and, finding that they were by no means unwilling to second him, proposed that they should i            *     A TALE OF THE LEVOLnTION.      9 abandon Grace Leslie to her fate, return without dela to the hovel, Gd, securing what remained of their wealth, to remove with it to some remote spot, where they would be less liable to detection. to dsooner sid tan done  Grace was informed by Black Jack of their intention, and advised to make her way to the j a5kc of their intentions) au atting that he could not longer nearest inhabited spot; regreti t at e  cul nt longer favor her with the protection of tihe band. But oor Grace listened without emotion to this offer of release. It hadcome t   oo late to be of an use to her; and she had not long been tab late to be of ay uself, when sense deserted her, and she be- caine a maniac!               h  Great was the consternation of Oaborne,when  he found how he had been served by his late adherents and his accom- plices. Great also was the astonishment of Black Jack and his assoiates, lhen they found that some one had secured the prize which they were bent uonpo ssessing. Not having the means upon which to subsist, these wretches were forced to attempt a fresh series of depredations  tried and exe- in one of their marauding expeditions, were trie and ex- cuted for their crimes. frf    <pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC6547-00000029"/> 4   /^     t CHJAPTER XII, fT was on one of the most melancholy days of October, and everything bore indications of winter s rapid advent, hen two men approached one another in th mdst of a  en two through *hich was a -a    e midst of a dense wood throag Wch wa s a pah, now known as the Germantown oad to -Philadelphia. One was dressed in. a common ernock frock and buff hat, and carried in his hand a heavy handled riding-whip, whistling to himself, by way of accompaniment, as he journeyed. There was nothing very inviting in the appear- ance of this worthy, whose hair was as red as that article Was ever known to be, while his eye brows were thick and bushy, and black as the night itself. Th ther as a pale, se looking a black of twenty-four, or thereabouts, 'and .w. s h abited in a blac velvet coat, knee breeches of the same mhaterial with silver buckles, cocked hat, peruke, and continuationsthe cos- tlime usually adopted by travelling schoolmasters of that pe- riod. He had a stout ash cudgel over his shoulder, from which Was suspended a small bundle, containing to all appealances the poor fellow's wardrobe. The Germantown road, at this point, continues in a straight, unbroken line, until, encounter. ing that pretty and romantic little stream the Wissahickon it turns off at an abrupt angle, and proceeds in the direction of Philadelphia. The scene was dreary  in  I coci  of and the foliage being, at this point, vey dense the two tra- vellers did not observe each other, unti they had lessened the,., distance between them t a yard or so, when they ptl paused, and each produced his instrument of d  .fene, not knowing but the other might be an eney,. "Stand fast, th ere and answer an honest straiobtforward question " exclaimed he of the smock trock, whirling his whip about his head in, a manner which p roved that, in his hands it would have proven no unformidable weapon. "Do we xnmeet as friends or foes --for both go the same way, it seems, and two enemies can never take the same track together."   A TkLE OF THE REVOLUTION.      61 "' The same reason for distrust exists on my part also," re- plied the young schoolmaster. "Nevertheless, although the question was somewhat rudely put, I will be frank with you, and if the answer displeases, I can only say, that I am ready to take my own part, and ask no odds of any that handles a cudgel. I am a poor schoolmaster, journeying on foot towards Philadelphia, for the simple reason that I can not afford to ride. My name is of no consequence to any one; my capital you see in this small bundle, which contains all that I possess in the world, but which I would not relinquish without a strug- gle. And, now, who may you be?" "Oh! I am jack of all,trades, sir," was the answer; " some- times one thing-sometimes another, and not overburthFned with learning, I can assure you. In times of peace, I owed a mill, and made meal for my neighbors, to gain me living. In these warring times, I am everything by turns; y sterday I was a spy for General Washington-a few days be re I as- sisted him to thrash his foes on the Brandywine, and t present I am on the look-out for a deserter, named Reube Gayler. (who) but hold-I may be talking to the very man desibed in these papers." And, withdrawing to a prudent distance, to be beyond the I '  reach of the other's cudgel, he perused the document whic he had drawn from his pocket, and compared the person of e latter with the written description. In the meanwhile, te schoolmaster's countenance underwent a transitory change, and became, almost immediately, as stoical as before. "I am satisfied," said the miller, after his examination, which had occupied scarcely a mirfute, and returning the docu- ment to his pocket. "You don't at all resemble the fellow described in these documents, and you'll forgive me that I suspected you.-Here's my hand; if you'll take it, we will journey together, and I will share my little allowance with you, as though we had been friends forever. If you regret it, we will draw cudgels, and decide upon the spot who is the stronger of the two. What do you say to my proposal? Is it a fair one 2" "I accept it with all my heart," replied the schoolmaster; "and the more gladly, as I feel lonesomely inclined, and have need of company. We will journey together, since you say so, and, as I have friends in Philadelphia, you may command my services when there, and whatever assistance I can render shall be freely given." "Thanks, friend schoolmaster, for your offer, which .I may, or may not accept-according to circumstances. But it is nearly time for us to be thinking of refreshment; if I am not    <pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC6547-00000030"/> B         iE'THfE PARTISAN'S OATH: greatly mistaken, there should be a tavern somewhere in this -neighborhood, or at least Isome place of shelter, where we may frepose our limbs, and partake of a slight repast together.' "'I see yonder the walls of an old mill," said the schoolmas -ter, asbthe object alluded to came in view. "That, as far as 1 can relmember, is the only house within convenient distance." t4 Be it so--if the inmates are not unwilling, we will sup at the mill. By my faith, I like these adventures; one might almost persuade himself that he lived in the days of romance -so many strange occurrences are taking place around us." By this time the two had reached the mill. It was an old, dilapidated edifice, even then, to which access was gained by a little bridge, spanning the miniature stream that supplied it with water. It was built of Dutch brick, but all signs of pros- perity had departed from it; the wheel was silent, and several of the paddles had fallen from it. The shutters, also,' were dangling from their hinges, and everything about the place seemed hastening to decay. "Rather a cheerless prospect this," said the miller, as they threw open the door, and walked within. "One of the effects of the war, I suppose. The passage of the red coats has scared the inmates away like frightened sheep, and they have left the place at our disposal." "What matters it?" rejoined the schoolmaster; " we can enjoy our supper all the better for that we are alone. I rather like the idea. We will pass the night in this place, and I, drawing privilege from my costume, will pass for the Bldck Knight, of whom we read in the story, while you shall be Robin Hood, and this old mill your ruined castle."' "The thought is not a bad one,' responded the miller; " he it so then. But what shall we do for our friar .?" "I thought not of thatt; but we are a host in ourselves, and shall not need him." These words had scarce escaped the schoolmaster, when footsteps were heard upon the bridge, and the new comer, evidently alarmed at the light of the fire just kindled by the miller, turned and fled away, as rapidly as his feet would allow. "That must not be; he will spoil all our pleasure," exclaimed Robin Hood in a breath, and in a moment he was in close pur- suit of the intruder. In a few minutes, however, he returned, flushed by his recent exercise, and breathing like a porpoise, from his exertions. "The little rascal was-too nimble for me," he said with a good humored laugh. "It was but a farmer's boy, however, and his fright will not allow him to return." They now: set about the preparation of their evening meal;   it was already dark, but the fire kindled by the miller fPad the effect of setting the brick-paved kitchen in a glow. Before long the savory steam of a piece of dried meat, taken from the fmiller's pouch, perfumed the place. These preparations being finally completed, both set to with a right good will, to dis- patch what lay before them, when the distant tramp of horses caught the ear of the miller, who seemed, all the while, to be anxiously waiting for something, and whose countenance un- derwent an immediate alteration. "It must be pretty evident to us both," he said, " that each has been playing a part for the last hour or so. In despite of your carefully concealed peruke, your tri-colored hat, and sable vestments, I recognise in you no other person than Reuben Gayler, the Deserter! "Discovered!" cried Reuben, with a look of terror; " but no-you villain, whoever you may be, you shall not have the satisfaction of reaping the reward of treachery. Let this for- ever silence your lips!" and before the other could anticipate him, he had drawn from his waistcoat a pistol, and discharged it in the direction of his betrayer. The latter coolly drew another, and replied with a sarcastic smile: "That was well meant, and had it come a little nearer, might have done me injury.-As it is, it has merely made a hole in my hat, and the money that I shall receive for deliver- ing you into the hands of justice will enable me to purchase a new one. As for taking your life, that would deprive my re- venge of half its keenness; for know, Reuben Gayler, that you stand in the pre'sence of your mortal enemy, RALPH OSBORNE!" Reuben started back, overcome by his sensations, but not intimidated. At this moment the trampling of hoofs was heard upon the bridge; but Reuben was resolved to make a single effort to avoid the fate which seemed in reserve for him. He rushed fiercely at Osborne, caught hin by the throat, and dashing him aside, sprang through the window at a bound, and made for the little bridge, across which the troopers had just passed, Osborne immediately recovered himself, and darted to the doorway, where the soldiers were assembled, crying, "Pursue! pursue!!" and foaming at the mouth with rage. At this instant, and while a dozen rifles were levelled at the fugitive, a wild-looking female, of almost unearthly loveliness, with garments disarrayed, and her untrameled hair streaming upon the wind, flitted like a shadow past Osborne as he stood in the doorway, bearningil her hand a lighted brand, plucked fromn the fire, and flew toward a pile of stubble, that stood    <pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC6547-00000031"/> "        THE PARTISAN'S OATH: upon the entrance to the bridge. In an instant all was in flames; the rotten material of the bridge took fire almost in- stantaneously, aided by the violence of the wind, and the astonished soldiers were glad to retire before the advancing heat. In a few moments more, the woodwork was eaten through, and fell, with many a hiss, into the stream; but, al- though a pursuit was ordered,.Reuben succeeded that night in eluding his adversaries. f Is   CHAPTER XIII. IT was one of the luckiest circumstances that could have happened to Reuben that he did not look behind him as he fled. Had he seen Grace Leslie in her present condition, he would have turned back at all hazards, and thus have placed himself within the power of his enemies. As it was, how- ever, he: was conscious only of the immediate danger which threatened him, and nothing, save the thought that Grace was present, and had exercised a principal agency in his escape, could have induced him to retrace his steps. He made rapidly for the Wisahickon, into which, without hesita- tion, he plunged, and gaining the woody swamp which lay on the opposite side, hid himself in its tangled labyrinths, until such time as the pursuit should have died away. There he had ample leisure to reflect over the consequences of the step which he had rashly taken. Wandering for days about the dreary wilderness, with only a few berries to sustain him- self, he soon became so emaciated that he had lost all traces of his former self. Had it not been for the uncertainty which he felt in regard to the fate of Grace, he would have delivered himself to his comrades, reckless as to what might be his des- tiny. 'But, under present circumstances, he had braced his mind to the endurance of every privation, for the sake of accomplishing the one principal object that lay nearest his heart. We must pass over the events of a few weeks, during which time many important operations were performed, which re- flected great credit upon the American arms, and once more transfer our readers to New-York. Poor Grace! after all her sufferings and privations, she had once more found a home beneath the root of the kind, but eccentric Lady Arlington. Chance had thrown her in the    <pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC6547-00000032"/> THE PARTZISAN'S OATH: way of the British army, after the occurrence mentioned in the preceding chapter, and she had been recognized by Cap- tain Arlington, who, struck with commiseration for the calam- ity which had befallen her immediately obtained a furlough -the campaign having just drawn to a close-and hastened with his charge to New York, where he besought his mother t leave no stone unturned that might restore the unfortunate girl to reason. ' About the period of these occurrences there arrived from some southern port, a gentleman of prepossessing exterior who was reported to have come into the possession of enor- mous wealth, by the decease of a near relative in Enoland. le immediately rented one of the finest houses in the city, and -had it furnished in a manner that put to the blush even Lady Arlington's elegant mansion, which had, until then borne the reputation of being the most stylish in town. IIis equipage was of the finest description, and several negroes attended him wherever he went. Such was the urbanity of his manners, the dignity of his address, the liberality with which he showered his favors on all alike, that he was soon an- established guest at the houses of the most aristocratic citizens, and, for a while, public attention was divided almost equally between him and the war. Captain Arlington, however, was not among the number of Sir ichard Gresham's admirers, fo such was the title by which this individual was best known, although the latter was a frequent visitor at his mothers. He had witnessed with surprise and dislike the introduction of Sir Richard to the family circle of which he was a member, and he took no pains to conceal the aversion that every act of the stranger inspired in him, It so chanced that, a very short time after his introduction to the elite of New York, Sir Richard gave a sumptuous en- tertainment, which was attended by the beauty and fashion of the cit3y. Lady Arlington, in spite of her son's remonstran- ces, would be present, and, as a matter of course, not wishing to cast discredit upon her to whom he owed his being, the gal- lant captain, whose heartwas in a far different quarter, was compelled to accompany her. The entertainment was all that could have been desired. All that could please the eye, the sense, was pressed into ser- vice on the occasion, and the guests vied with one another in the magnificence of their dresses, and the brilliancy of their jewels, while the host was even more affable and kind than was his wont. In the early part of the evening, Sir Richard approached   67 A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION. Captain Arlington, who would fain have avoided him, but that it was not practicable, just at that moment, and requested a few words in confidence. Captain Arlington," he said, extending his hand, which the latter reluctantly to6k; "I see that there is a prejudice existing against me in your mind, and I will do you the credit to say, that you have not endeavored to conceal it; but, it cannot be matter of surprise to you that I should feel hurt by such treatment. I am unconscious of having done anything to merit it, and as your evident coolness may operate against me in the minds of others, less fastidious than yourself, but whose good opinion is, nevertheless, still dear to me, I must beg that you will do me the justice to state your rea- sons.  4 "SE Richard," replied Arlington, in some confusion; " you have taken me unawares, and I must confess that I am unable to answer your-question satisfactorily. Prejudices will some- times arise almost without our own knowledge, and I can only ask you to overlook the past, and consider that we are, here- after friends.'" Sir Richard took the captain's proffered hand, which he shook heartily, and a singular smile--it might more appropri- ately have been called a sneer-passed over his countenance, which might have aroused a fresh suspicion in Arlington's mind, had he observed it. It passed unnoticed, however, for at this instant the latter was approached by a messenger, who handed him a note, which ran in these words: 4 "At ten to-night, one will be waiting for you in the rear ward-room of the George's Inn, in New street, having matter of import to communicate. As this is a public resort, you may safely come unattended; and, indeed, it is necessary that the interview should be strictly private, as the lives of more than one person depend upon the issue.-A FRIEND OR FOE, AS CIR- CUMSTANCES MA]Y PROVE HM?."t Struck by the singularity of such an incident, Arlington excused himself from longer attendance, and at the appointed hour hastened to the place designated, in the anonymous note, as the George's Inn. Although Arlington was 10o coW- ard, he could not but feel slightly agitated on entering the apartment appointed for the interview, for an inward some- thing told him that the business which could "involve the life of more than one person" must be of some importance, and his heart half whispered him that it was, somehow or other, connected with Grace. A tall personage, enveloped in a cloak, was pacing the floor, as Arlington made his appearance. On hearing the latter,    <pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC6547-00000033"/> he made an abrupt turn, and disclosed the pale and altered lineaments of Reuben Gayler. Arlington tarted back, in a firiends treachery have  wrouih^t i  'e   ' I an no longer Reu- 'I call only stppose from your manner, that youthaye alluded nd of h  orroresl   a myselft Yet, yo cannot be ignorant.of tie "Goodid not can thslie fly her home at your instigaertion with is par   witnesse were torn thence  y ruf- since a maniac from the circumstn8ce." She then proeeded to inform Reuben of all that had trans- pired since umweal tae th ast eetintion But all is not yet past hope," continued Arlington. ( I will see ifwI cannot ba cng yourself and Grace together; a nd to restore aher wea vened iwtellect i "  would gdly see her said euben; -  nd yet, I am so far beneath  now, that shne woald nonly spurn me. donCaptein Arlington, I fear tat your friendship for e, hereto foAnd Reuben seated himselfl proveandr willeasllowed his headrn that I am ane Arlington was soveromewhat astonished the information. Yobut he knew that there all a myst be some circumstance which c;I must f. ..st hear ;our story, said  Aringto n for I know that ou must ha e rhad some urgent motive for the s  ep.' o Mss know not how I shall reuite such kindness. y-n a mo-uded tent of passionr almosaYobt c dthe  10s of one in hom  my every wish was en istered, I confess that I was mad enough to defians, aert mythe dead of night afriend iss Leslie has been ever iain the toanents I have since then sucred.  Not a day-not any houred thiat has not been fugt with suffering.  n  my ght with KIMenng. Even in my   dreams, I imagined that I saw the finger of scorn and hatred pointed at me." "You overdraw the picture; trust me, all is not so bad as you would believe. Your general is said to have a humane heart, and when all the facts in regard to your desertion shall have reached his ears, he will make excuse for your error, and restore you to your former honorable standing. But come, there is no time to spare, and the quicker you see Miss Leslie, the better for both." Upon this, Reuben pulled his cloak about his ears, and fol- lowed the captain from the tavern. The Governor's mansion was but a few rods distant, and they were only a minute, or so, in gaining it. While Arlington went up stairs to find Grace, whp had been left under the charge of a governess in the absence of the family, Reuben was cautioned to await his coming in the garden; and in a frame of mind far from being enviable, he continued pacing the graveled walks, until the footsteps of Arlington met his ears, and the latter, almost immediately afterward appeared, leading Grace, as lovely as ever, by the hand. A settled melancholy was on her face, and in the glistening moonbeams, which shone full upon the  spot where they stood, she more resembled a statue, than a being of human mould. For some moments she remained gazing earnestly upon Reuben, although not a word had thus far been uttered by either. But gradually a chord was touched-memory, that had so long lain dormant, returned to lighten up the clouded brain; she burst into a flood of tears, at last, and threw her- self, weeping, upon Reuben's breast. Reason had resumed its seat, and for the moment both were happy; all but Arling- ton-who turned away to hide an emotion that he could not but feel. Long and earnest was the interview between the lovers. In the happiness of the moment, Reuben forgot his troubles; and he was only reminded of them when the sound of a clock came upon the drowsy air, chiming the hour of twelve. As the last stroke vibrated upon the ear, a small boat, containing several figures, grated against the beach at the bottom of the garden. Bidding a hasty adieu for the present, Reuben parted from Grace with a heavy heart, and, waiting until he had seen them both enter the house, he turned for the purpose of departing, when he was astonished to find himself sur- rounded by several rough-looking men, who, without stopping for parley, laid violent hands upon him, and hurried him towards the shore. Resistance, he saw, would be useless,    <pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC6547-00000034"/> 70        THE PARTISAN S OATH. and he 1therefore submitted with a good grace to what he could not avoid. As the boat receded rapidly from the beach, a solitary figure, which strongly resembled that of Sir Richard Gresham, was seen peering out from the shadow of the trees which lined the shore! Our narrative is now drawing to a close. Early on the following morning, Reuben Gayler found himself a prisoner in the American camp, charged with being a deserter, at a time when his country was most in need of his services. The offence was a flagrant one, and it seemed as though it must go hard with him. The circumstances, however, were laid efore Washington by Grace, herself, who had contrived, with a woman's ingenuity, to obtain an interview, and, her tears and, supplications prevailing, after a delay of several days, Reuben, upon promise of future good behavior, was dis- charged from custody, and restored to his commission. The battle of Yorktown occurred shortly afterwards, and by his bravery on that occasion, Reuben fully recovered the good opinion which he had temporarily lost. Peace being declared, the young soldier hastened to New York, where he was short- ly afterwards united to the object of his choice. Our story has now one person, only, to deal with. For some months, Sir Richard Gresham pursued his splendid career, without interruption, but an accidental encounter with Reuben Gayler, who immediately recognized in him his old enemy, Ralph Osborne. And after removing the veil which had enshrouded his history, the facts of Miss Leslie's case having been made known, a warrant was forthwith issued for his arrest. When the officers deputed to perform this duty went to Sir Richard's house with that intent, they found him lying upon a sofa, with an awful gash in his throat, and a razor by his side. Foiled in his contemplated revenge, and deprived of the means of indulging his inordinate desires, Ralpli Osborne had committed suicide    EDGAR EDGERTON; A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION. CHAPTER I. So soft and so lovely seemed the night; the moon was up, and in -her star-lit course moved in silent grandeur. The darkening shades of the tall forests, and the gentle rippling of the stream, casting benign soul-revering beauty o'er the scene, and wrapping every attribute in silent wonder. Oh i 'twas a night for the poet to love, and a night to make all mankind poets'! None was there that loved that same night with aught of the deep devotion that two, did, who had wandered forth to gaze on its matchless beauty. They were sauntering towards the river's side, to catch a breath of the soft and wooing air which was wafted from among the highlands above, and as they moved on they seemed to have been completely lost in ad- miration of the surrounding scene. One was a young girl, whose mind had received a genial warmth and coloiring of seventeen summers: not tall, nor yet small, but light and straight as a reed; the limbs well and full rmnded, but with such an exquisite delicacy that they could not attract the eye of the mere voluptuary. We cannot describe her face, for if we had gazed into her clear, large blue eye, and looked upon the exquisite delicacy of her features, we would have mar- velled she was o fair, and could not criticise or analyze. Her arms encircled the waist of her companion of the opposite sex, and her head rested upon his bosom, while her golden locks flowed idly in the wind. Of a tall and finely moulded figure, his face was rather of the femhinine beauty, than the coarse masculine; yet his features were boldly and distinctly marked, impressing the observer with the strength of his character. His feminine qualities existed more in the fairness and whiteness of his complexion, his light and irregular curls which lay in masses o'er his forehead, rather than in any part whichl might lack of the true dignity of manhood.    <pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC6547-00000035"/> 72       A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION. They had reached the river's side, and wandering some -distance along its shore, where, at times, the very waters washed their footprints, they reached a spot where the bank being somewhat irregular, they ascended a slight steep, and stood upon a huge rock whichjutted out some distance from the main bank into the stream, was then reposing in the deep shade of a tall oak which leaned forward as if to clasp with its long and moss-grown limbs the tiny waves beneath in its venerable embrace. Seating themselves upon an irregularity of the rock which formed an admirable rustic seat, overgrown with moss, they gazed in deep silence on the waters beneath. Suddenly a schooner came ploughing its way down towards them, her broad sails in bold relief against the horizon. The rushing of the water against her prow, the shrinking cordage and straining masts, as she came sweeping majestically on, impressed our observers with feelings of admiration. On she came, as though the frowning shore was to be no impediment, *and- yon dark buried forest was her harbor. Now so close upon them that they instinctively drew back, when suddenly she veered, her sails shook idly in the wind, and the next moment she was creeping away on another tack.   f "Thus, my Julia," spoke our hero, " moves man on to his mighty desires, and in that little incident may we read the fate of thousands. Thus intellect grasps at its high hopes, and even like yon now snail-paced vessel, seems to have its prospects within reach, when lo! in one little moment they are dashed to the ground, and with wearied limbs and dejected havior slowly retrace their weary way." "Nay, my dear Edgar," replied his younger companion, as she wound her arms more closely around him, and looking up into his face with a deep, fond look of affection," why do you ever thus seek after sad similes? Wilt ever allow thlat dark shadow of despair to settle over your mien, with its brooding reflections, and dull moody thoughts?" "I did not seek after it, my dear Julia; it stood before me unbidden; even as I expressed it." "Edgar,' replied the fair girl, "Edgar, I have watched you long, and know the deep secret of your bosom. You would stand among men as one worthy to be placed on an equality with the highest; but think you you can obtain that position without an effort? Honor will not seek you as one worthy of its especial favor; but you must task your soul to its utmost power toreach it. Study, arduous and assiduous study, can only place you there; and so sure as you thus strive, so sure as you labor, will you reap the amount you have sown. My noble Edgar" said she, drawing still nearer to him, "there are none who will more rejoice with you at wh!at'honors you   A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION.      3 may win, than she you have professed to love: but' think not it is the laurels that wreathe your brow I should love; no it is he who has won them. It is one who, having a great and mighty object in view,nobly strives to win, and nobly striving, smiles at all obstacles." i TThe young man had turned his face aside from the gaze of his companion, who, with the enthusiasm of her motives, as she proceeded, had leaned forward as if she would read the heart on the expressive page of his features. His fist was firmly clenched, and a dark frown was settled on his brow; for a few moments silence ensued, when turning quickly, he seized her hand; his voice way husky, and there seemed in his bosom a world of wild thoughts and emotions striving for utterance. "Julia!" said he, "Julia, listen to me. You know, dear Julia, that I love you. Ay I the fondest hopes that ever a wild and ardent imagination conjured up, have had thee for their object. Even that ambition which, before I knew thee, 1A was essentially a selfish one, now takes its color from you, lives but in thy smile, aspires but for thy favor; and should those wild dreams of my youth but prove real, imy greatest happiness would be for you to share my honors, since they would only set gracefully on me as they were reflected back from thee, and I could read their worth in the mirror of thy soul. "Long have I watched the dark cloud which is settling between our mother and our native country. The bursting of that cloud will resound far and wide, as indeed the faint distant rmnblings are already heard. The progress of thosq events will eventually result in the existence of the colonies as independent States; but when, hope can only surmise, The most sagacious foresight cannot count the years of war and peril that may ensue ere that event can be consummated; the present generation may cease to exist, and their posterity, with the sword and musket, with perhaps, a little of that indomitable hate against their enemies that will surely exist in such a revolution, as their only legacies, may still continue to fight and struggle on. Yon know, Julia---- "Edgar," interrupted Julia, " it was on this very subject I would lave spoken. You know my feelings; I have expressed them many times, and I now tell you frankly, Edgar, that un- less you take an active part in the defence of not only our country, but our honor, and our liberties; unless, I say, you  can produce a claim to my hand based upon higher motives than self-interest and self-aggrandisement, that hand must re- main a maiden one!"She spoke calmly, thougl; her voice was slightly tremulous. i     <pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC6547-00000036"/> A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION. Oh, my God!" groaned our hero. "Edgar," said Julia, laying her hand uponhis arm, and looking into his face reproachfumlly. "Julia, if you hold toward me aught of that affection you have so often told me was mine, listen, ere you should proceed farthr; ay, as you value you soul." His face as fushed his lip quivered, and a choking feeling at his throat almost denied him further utterance. Julia looked upon him with astonishment, and the startling thought presented itseLf to her mind, could it be that he actually was --his strange demeanor, what could that mean? Yet he could not be so fallen; no, no! for if false to his honor and to his country, might he not also'be false to her? But the convulsive work- ings of his fingers, the large drops of sweat that stood on his brow, were almost damning proofs of the truth of her fears. A silence ensued for a few moments, when Edgar spoke: "I know not, Julia, what I have said or done to lead you thus to suspect me of desiring to take part against our coun- try-bowever, circumstances may prevent m-e join'ig with her-nay, Julia! I beg of you a patient hearing. My father is English born, and with a sagacity that does more credit to and the colonies. Surmising that being daily thrown among those ho would, to a man, take the side of the-as he calls them-rebels, he early strove to impress on my mind the mag- nitude of certain duties to the king; and of a lively imagination I soon became so far wrapped up in admiration with the rh u hel aumlrnon  with  the royal Prince, that I considered the holiest and most sacred duty a man was called to perform, was to lay down his life in defence of his rightful king. With these views, my father readily obtained irom me a promise not to take part against my sovereign in any civil commotion that mLight arise. Wil- lingly did I promise, more because I had no fears of such an evil, as was not experienced in the signs that mark the gathering storms in the political horizon. A promise that I regretted almost as soon as made, and now it is likely to bring upon me a train of evils, far more fearful than even those which lie held before my eyes as surely to 'ensue from disloy- alty." "Edgar," said Julia, '"I was aware of your father's predilec- tions for the English king--piedilections we should not won- der at, since his education has made that a virtue in him   A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION.       75 I   which becomes a vice in us; but I had not thought you had sworn away your duty to your true country, nor can I con- ceive that that country would receive such a reason as sufficient for her to withhold the ordeal of her opinion of your actions." t      ( "I feel, I know it!" gasped Edgar, "but may I not hope, dear Julia, that at least you will not look upon me in so cruel a light 2" Julia did not answer. Edgar-they had arose, and were now sauntering towards the house-stopped short, and clasping her hand in his, gazed long and ardently in her face. "Julia," said he, with forced calmness, do you not love me? or have you, in your deep devotion to a country which requires not your service, forgot the kindness which an earlier love had promis- ed, until you became, a politician, and made the acceptance of your hand depend on the success of dynasties, and the fate of states." lHe spoke with bitterness, and ere he was done, releas- ed her hand. 4     "Edgar," said she, as she fixed her eyes upon him, which were moistened with tears, "Edgar!" "Forgive me, Julia-oh! forgive me!" said he, clasping her to his breast. "Bless, bless you, Julia," said he, with emotion, as weeping, she dropped her head on his bosom; "but let us return to the house now; it is late, and I perceive the light from my father's library has been extinguished; we will walk again to-morrow evening. I have much to say to you. They had reached the house, and with a fervent kiss for good night, they seek their respective rooms-the one for a sweet sleep and pleasing dreams; the other to pass a restless night, brood- ing over the past, and prophecying for the future. And what are thy dreams, fair one? Methinks that one so pure and lovely as thou, should, when thou movest in the space of dreamland, hold converse with fairy elfins. Music should accompany thy entranced spirit, and the soft zephyrs of Arabia float above thee. But say, what are thy dreams! Hush t the delicate, white moulded arm lies heedlessly on the pillow I Trhy trpsses all unconfined float o'er thy bosom, and thy lips are gently parted, and ever and anon a sigh escapes therefrom. Can that sigh and that murmur be for aught of dreamland? Can Edgar's soft whispered name be but the appellation of some winged elfin? oe are thy dreams but mortal, and Peri like, when thou dost wander forth in the person of thy dreaming spirit, find'st the boon that is to move the golden bar of the paradise of thy bliss, not in the glittering form of pleasure, but in the tear caught in the up-turned cup of confidence as drop- ped by true and fervent love.    <pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC6547-00000037"/> 76 '     A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION. CHAPTER IL. THE gray herald of morning was lighting the eastern sky, and yet our hero still paced his room, until at last, wearied out, he flunrig himself upon his couch with the hope of a few hours sleep, and presently dropped into an uneasy slumber. Charles Edgerton was the third son of an English gentleman in the possession of some wealth and a broad domain, with a baronetcy to support its dignity. The Baron Edgerton died when Charles was at the age of twenty, and then coming into the possession of a yonlger bro- ther's share, and also being actuated by a spirit of adventure he embarked for the English colonies. Having letters of in- troduction to distingu;ished families in the States, he soon became so enalnoured of the new world that he from month to month deferred his return to England. An acquaintanceship having sprung up between himself and the family of a Major Cart wright, he became enamoured of a lovely daughter of the Major's. Two years after his arrival at the western country, he was accepted and was duly married to the object of his love, and immediately purchased a lovely residence on the banks of the Hudson River, aboutt forty miles from iNew York: lie be- carne the father of two sons, shortly after which he lost his wife of a fever. The elder son was sent to England for his education; but the younger, Mr. Edgerton preferred to keep with him, and to act in the capacity of tutor as far as practica- ble; and early teaching his son to look upon him as one in everV way worthy of his respect and confidence, there existed between father and son a friendship of a breadth and depth not usually found in such relations. Edgar almost worshipped his father; he-conceived him a superior being; and the early influence which Mr. Edgerton had obtained over Edgar was such that our hero readily consented not to take part in any way against his king in case of any civil disturbances. It was not until some time after this promise was made, that Edgar became aware of the full particulars of his situation. As one-of the highest circle in the country, his course in the then fast approaching struggle between England and the colonies was looked forward to with interest. His silence on the subject at last began to be mistrusted, while dark hints and inuen- loes were exchanged between the more suspicious neighbors. Some already looked upon him as a rank tory, while the dis- lain and contempt so industriously bestowed upon that party of he Revolution was now heaped upon him. Of an exceedingly sensitive nature, his proud spirit could not brook such suspi- ,ions; and to avoid the insults he might be subjected to on going   A TALE' OF THE REVOLUTION.      7 abroad, he remained as much as possible at Eddsville--the ap- pellation of his father's homestead; but this very confinement was seized upon by his enemies, and heralded forth as a fear; this happily Edgar was not aware of, but imagined that in his retirement he was free from suspicion or insult. From boyhood 'twas Edgar's favorite pleasure to wander forth alone amid the wild woods or along the banks of the river, and indulge in those wild thoughts and fancies which had stamped him as a vision-. ary. A mind richly stored with poetic lore, his greatest hap- piness was to draw in his mind's eye the beauteous conceptions of the poet, or even perhaps the uncertain and indefinite embodi- ments of his own flickering genius. Thus, with the universal world of thought before him, and the universal book of nature to suggest thought upon thought, until his mind, with nothing to check it, sought far and near for new objects to exhaust it- self upon. Ambition, the master passion of the soul, had early abided in his breast, and indeed these lonely musings were not calcu- lated to dispel the illusions which an ardent and unbridled im- agination drew from its deep resources. Like the increase of appetite, which grew upon what it fed on, it colored all his thoughts, his day dreams and night dreams-meditations-all had for their being the aspiring impulses of fame and glory; but alas! lis ambition was essentially a selfish one. Nurtured 'mid those scenes, he made himself his god, and Intellect the altar at which lie worshipped. Self! mighty self was the sun which his thoughts and dreams revolved around, and so far was he wrapped within that circle that he might perchance even have smiled had the descending sun of his country's glory but lit up the star of his own arising fame. Not that he would have ac- knowledged or even believed it; for in all the boasted know- ledge and resources of man, he is ignorant of some of the very first springs that urge him on to good or bad actions. Patriot- ism is a noble virtue; but where there is one who will sacri- fice his interests for his country's real good, there are hundreds who make it but the stepping stone to their own individual ag- grandizements. With these aspirations after distinction, we would look for himn, to bend his energies to the consummation of his dearest hopes; but alas! the weakness of man! those energies were daily wasted in enervating day-dreams and air-built castles. 'Twas thus our hero let day after day slip byuntil he had reached his twentieth year, when Julia Melville, an orphan ward of Mr. Edgerton, came to reside with her guardian. She was the daughter of Colonel Melville, an old friend of Mr. Ed- gerton, but who, at that time, had been deceased three years. It has been said that ambition, love and avarice, are the great    <pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC6547-00000038"/> 78      A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION. master passions of the soul; but the two first are nearly al- lied, or, if they are not, the one is but a selfish desire and the other but lust. Suffice it for us to say that Julia and Edgar met-met and loved; together they wandered hand in hand through the grounds of Eddsville. Thrs their tastes, feelings, desires, flowing into one channel, moved that ambition which solitude and day-dreaming had nurtured into a higher and a nobler course. She, with the instinctive nature of her sex, early dived into his thoughts, and led him, unaware to himself, in the path which her own ardent imagination pointed out; an imagi- nation which had been guided and directed by the observing care of her father. Often, when our hero would listen to her bursts of patriotism, he would collect the spirit of her own noble language, and for a moment indulge in the thought and prospect of joining the American forces; but then would come the thought of his promise, dashing his new-born hopes to the ground. The startling news from Lexington and Boston had awakened the country around to a high pitch of enthusiasm al- most unparalleled; and then Julia would ask and wonder why Edgar did not even express a desire, in common with other men of the country, to enlist under Washington. The deep and early impressed respect for his father-a respect that amounted almost to adoration-forbade him to mention his promise to Julia, until she, suspecting and fearing that he would adhere to the royal cause, introduced the subject, as we have perceived, and with a thrill of joy learned, that though inactive, his heart was. with his country. Edgar did not awake until the sun was high in the heavens. Springing from his couch, he hastily adjusted his disarranged toilet, and left the house without even waiting to see if the fa- mily had breakfasted or not. It was indeed a lovely morning. The river was sleeping in the sunbeams; and, as it reflected them back, it resembled a mass of molten silver. The man- sion lay in the shade of a tall bluff, which reared its forest- crowned top beyond it, while the venerable trees, scattered about the lawn, cast their long shadows o'er the dew-crystalled grass. The house in itself was one which, in those days, had many claims to architectural beauty. But, under the supervi- sion of Mr. Edgerton, he had combined a variety of stylesr- the steep, peaked roof and irregular form 'of the Elizabethan age, with many pretensions to the Gothic, and also additions, which taste or comfort had suggested, gave it a nondescript ap- pearance. In front of the mansion were sone fifteen or twen- ty noble and steady oaks, which almost entirely concealed the building from the river, although the view from its Gothic win- dows of the stream was tolerably fair. Below the spot for some mile or two, the ground was open, interspersed with patches of   A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION.      79 wild woodland, rugged rocks, and, here and there, softer scenes of most exquisite beauty. It was among these wilds Edgar had unconsciously wandered, his mind completely last in hopes and fears; he did not mark how far he had proceeded, until he sud- denly found himself close upon the village of B--, a beau- teous hamlet, seated mid two high bluffs on the river side, and about four miles from Eddsville. An irresistable desire impelled him on, and he had proceeded but a little distance into the village, when he perceived an old and much valued friend approaching, one whom he had been very intimate with ere he had confined himself so closely to the homestead. Ed- gar hastened forward impatient to greet him." "My dear WilliamL-" "Good morning, Mr. Edcerton," replied his friend, and passed on with a cold bow. Edgar felt the hot blood rush in a torrent to his face : for a moment he stood and gazed after him, and then started on, heaping vindictive curses on the head of his-as he thought-false friend. With a clouded brow and clenched fist he moved on. All seemed to avoid him as if he were a leper. As he approached the more busy part of the village, he noticed a crowd of men in earnest discourse, among whom were many an old companion. With an effort he smoothed his brow, and calming his ruffled temper, walked into the centre of the group. "Any news, gentlemen, from below, said he. "None that an Englishman would be glad to hear, much less one who, forgetting all gratitude for a country which pro- tects him, basely panders with her tyrants," replied one. Ed-' gar, nigh choked with the tumult of passion that raged within him at this cutting rejoinder, but determined to master his passion before his new found enemies, and aware that anger would be received as convincing proof of his guilt, spoke with forced calmness, ay, even with levity. "What! have the. royalists found the buff and blues too much for them'?" "Ay, and they will also teach both royalists and tories that they are not to be trifled with, even if their enemies do seek for society within their own grounds."  If I may be allowed to judge by your manner of speaking, I should infer that you had a particular object in view," re- plied Edgar.  "You are privileged to draw your own inferences. "A privilege, believe me, sir, I fully value," said our hero. "Ay! as you may value 'your safety, until the skinners. determine to punish one so early'a traitor to his country." "Charles Wood," furiously exclaimed Edgar, " do you call me a traitor " 4     <pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC6547-00000039"/> A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION. "The charge fits well,"' replied the other, cooly. "Take that, then, for thy base insinuations," said lie, dsh- ing his clenched fist full inthe face of his antagonist, who reeling back fell heavily upon the ground, the blood gushing from his mouthl and nostrils. "Secure him! secure him!" cried a dozen voies. 'Stand aside! I'm dangerous-give me free passage, or by G--od!" said he, drawing a pistol fom his pocket! Upon him! seize him!" exclaimed one, while a simulta- neous rush was made by the whole crowd upon our hero. In the melee his pistol was dischargd, and a wild scream gave note to what effect. With a bound he cleared himself from their grasp, and dashed rapidly from the village by the same road by which he had entered. His pursuers, however, were close upon him, On, on he fled, the shouts and cries of the mob iving new speed to his already deer-like motions. Strong of lmb, young and buoyant, he soon distanced his most ener- getic pulsuers. Reaching the country immediately in the neighborhood of Eddsville, lie relaxed his speed,and then the flood of his passion resumed its sway. "And it is for this I have hoped and struggled! H who plumed my hopes so high, to be branded as a traitor! My God!!my God! wy did I make that accursed promiseo I must be released else I'llgo mad! Julia! what will she say  How can I look upon her with the indelible name of 'traitor' stamped on my brow?"Now lamenting his ill made promise, and now pouring out curses on the heads of thse who had so insulted and disgraced him, he reached his home. He walked througIh the all and from room to room. Julia was not to be found. Hlie Sauntered through the grounds, and down to the spot where last evening he had conversed with her. He was not there, and returni'ng to the house he found her just leaving his father's library, She was in tears. "Julia,; why do I find you thus?" "I have seen your father, dear Edgar, and he will not re- lease you from your promise--indeed he spoke harshly to me." "And kindly consents to myeternal shame and disgrace" bitterly replied the young man. "'Oh, Edgar, speak not harshly of your father," interposed Julia,  "Why should I not? The world condemns me and not him, while I am acting under his orders." "But, Edgar, you owe that father much; ayeverythin " said Julia reproachfully.         e  h "Ay! and as if to wipe out my gratitude, or perchance as a t recompense for my great debt, he would bid me become a thing I loathe to think of. What wonder then if I curse not   A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION.      81 only the promise he drew from me, but that very care and education which now makes me feel my disgrace so keenly? And you too, Julia, do you side with him-with all the world against me? Well, be it so!" "Edgar!" said Julia, as her eyes suffused with tears. Forgive me! Oh! forgive me! Julia, I know not what I say. I have been to the village," said he suddenly and with fierceness, "and--" "Edgar, dear Edgar, be calm! how fearful you look! do not stare so wildly! What can it all mean 2' "Listen to me, Julia," said he with ungovernable passion. "Listen to me! I have been to the village, and was hooted  at as a traitor! Do you hear me, Julia? hooted at as a traitor! Oh heavens! that I should have lived to hear it!" Edgar,. dear Edgar," said she, winding her arms arouid him.  Forget it, Edgar; do, for my sake, and of your much loved father. 'They were but the boors of the village, not worth your minding." "By the gods, but they shall repent it. Me! me! a traitor. Hell and damnation!"-- "Edgar, unless you fear my displeasure," interrupted Julia. "Displeasure! what is that to me when men say there goes the traitor, and the finger of scorn is pointed, as one base enough to sell his honor and country. Oh! I see it all, all! A traitor, a traitor indeed." "Edgar,' said Julia, while a slight paleness overspread her features-" passion has got the better of your reason, and un- til you are in a better condition to master it, I must leave you." She spoke firmly, and with a calm unaltered mein passed him and entered her room. Edgar gazed with silence upon her, retiring form. With a vacant stare he looked around, and the anext moment dashed madly from the house. For an hour he wandered about without a notice of surrounding objects, giving vent to his overcharged feelings. At last he flung himself upon a grassy bank from sheer exhaustion. Scarcely had he been seated when he heard the murmur of voices. Delicacy would have urged him to retire or show himself to the parties; but in the time of war delicacy and good breed- ing are often lost sight of in the greater considerations of life and liberty. Iad our hero any doubts upon the propriety of his course they were instantly put to rest by the name of Washington in a much louder key than the tone of their usual converse, and also coupled with terms which clearly proved an enemy near, and their object not very praiseworthy. Draw- ing cautiously near to where the sounds proceeded fromn inter. vening between which was a curtain of brush and stunted wood, that completely hid the party from his viewl . With 6    <pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC6547-00000040"/> -82      A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION. difficulty he managed to draw near enough to hear their dis- course. At first it was irregular and disconnected, so that it was no easy matter to make out their object. Gradually how- ever, he began to connect the links of their plan, and soon became possessed with valuable information. It seemed they were discussing a plan-for by their language they were evi- dently officers of some renown in the English army-whereby Washington, then retreating throughl the island of Manhattan, might be surprised and captured. It was some time before Edgar could learn all the minute particulars of their plot, but as soon as he was possessed of the details, he instantly left the spot and hastening towards his residence, he immediately ordered one of the fastest horses of his father's stables to be saddled. In half an hour he was mounted and galloped rapidly off without even seeing his father, and he scarce dare turn his eyes towards the house, lest he should meet the frown- ing face of Julia. In order to avoid the village of B --, he took the road which wound around the foot of the high bluff we have spoken of directly at the water's edge, after which it ascends the high ground, and wandered for some distance into the interior, until by a cross road he took the southern route, and after passing the point of the village he neared the river where the road at times mounted some rising knoll which overlooked the Hudson for miles as it wound its intricate course among the highlands, while smiling villages, beauteous meadows, and forest capped hills met his gaze. He did not, however, then stop to contemplate that which at another time would have delighted him with its loveliness. His heart was now light and buoyant; there was a chance for him to redeem his spotted name, and would not America thank him for thus preserving the life and liberties of its great chief? 'Twas late in the day before he drew near the vicinity of the Continental army. He had ridden hakd and was nigh exhausted with fatigue, but determined to see the Commander and lay his information before him as soon as he could obtain an audience. It was with some difficulty that he obtained the desired interview, but at last, after repeated requests he was summoned to his presence. With feelings of reverence amounting almost to adulation, Edgar stood before the master spirit of the age; he bowed low, his eyes bent on the floor. '  "Whom, sir, have I the honor of addressing?" Edgar looked up at these words of Washington. He was seated in a large oaken chair by a table covered with maps, charts and documents. Washington waved him to a chair and desired to know his business. Briefly as possible Edgar related to dim what he had overheard, with all the details, as he had heard it, of the plot.   A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION.      83 "Andnymous information," said Washington, "is often questionable, sir. May I owe a still greater debt of gratitude by enlisting your name among the benefactors of our common country 2" "Edgar Edgerton, sir." "What, the son of Mr. Edgerton, of Eddsville," sternly de- manded Washington. "The same, sir." "I know not," resumed the commander-in-chief, " whether this s meant to amuse yourself or us, sir; but beware, young man, how you trifle with a power it is your habit to deride- I may say a power that, were not lenity one of its greatest at- tributes, might well question the lawfulness of your relation to it." Sir," said Edgar, with difficulty repressing his rising emo- tions, "believe me! upon my honor what I tell you is true; and I pray you, sir, do not let any question of my honesty interfere with measures for your safety." "Your suggestions may be right, sir; but we are not in the habit of suiting our actions to the advice of a tory, if we cannot term him by any harder name!" Edgar could hear no more, but abruptly rushed from his presence, with his last words ringing in his ear. An hour afterwards he was dashing furiously towards Eddsville, madly urging his horse to its utmost speed. CHAPTER   III. THE setting sun, streaming through the richly curtained windows of an elegantly furnished library, lit up with a golden light the long shelves of gilt-bound volumes. The furniture was rich in the extreme: cushioned antique chairs, curiously  carved, were scattered about,-the carpet soft as down and of the most pleasing combination of colors,-tables curiously in- laid with many colored woods. The shelving was low, about seven feet high, and mounted with a rich heavy cornice work of mahogany, over which there ranged busts by Canova, land- scape paintings, and a Madonna; these, at the time of which we are writing, basked in the mellow light of the setting sun, and were exquisitely beautiful. On one side hung an antique sword, which in the hands of an Edgerton had seen service in the old French wars under a Talbot. By a table in the cen- tre, in a luxurious arm chair, sat an elderly gentleman, of: about fifty years of age, of a noble and prepossessing appear- ance. His features were boldly marked, his nose slightly equaline, and a mouth, delicately and firmly curved, expressed.    <pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC6547-00000041"/> 84 -A TALE OF THE REYOLUTION. the firmness of his character and his intellectual refinement. Eyes of so deep a grey that they bordered on the hazel, shaded as they were by his heavy eye brows and the massy hair that hung over them. He was dressed in the style of the old English gentleman-knee buckles and silk hose, the white cravat and cue; his feet were encased in velvet slippers of curious workmanship, resting on a stool covered-with rich embroidery worked by the hands of the fair Julia. An open volume of Tasso lay before him, on .the table, which was covered with periodicals, late publications, papers, and some of the violent party tracts which were at that tiipe daily issued. The window curtains were partially drawn aside revealing a most exquisite scene beyond, which the gentleman seemed enraptured with; so much so, indeed, that he did not mark the clattering of a lhofse's feet below, nor the approach of footsteps. Suddenly the library door was thrown rudely open, and a person covered with dust and dirt rushed into the room. His clothes were torn, and his whole person denoted extra- ordinaiy excitement. Staggering forward he sank into a chair. "Good heavens, Edgar!" exclaimed Mr. Charles Edgerton, starting up from his arm chair, "' what can all this mean?" "Father," gasped Edgar, "give me back my-promise!" "Promise! why how now a" "Look you, my father, heaven forfend I should say aught to lessen myself in my own eyes, or what it may become you to listen to: but you jemember my promise, though freely granted-yet was it drawn from me, inasmuch as I was una- ware of the extent of the sacrifice you were calling upon me to make." ' My son!" "Father! father! you hpve blasted all those hopes which the fond desires of an aspiring mind strove to realize. Oh! how I longed for some honorable distinction. It was my dreams, my hope, my all. I doted on it, and as I gazed forth upon the world how bright and glorious did it seem, and I longed to enter into the glorious arena to strive for the ever- sought prize, and when love urged me on up the paths of fame, did I not thank heaven and you for boon so gracious 1"' "But, Edgar-" Hear me out, father. One by one of those early aspira- tions which fancy and hope had wove-have you plucked asunder-blasted the laurel ere it encircled its owner's brow, and now what am I! A traitor! do you hear it, father? your son a traitor-I-Edgar Edgerton branded as a tory-my name the by-word and scorn of all men, and driven with con- tempt from the presence of the great head of a country I so longed to serve. Oh! would, would that I were dead Must   A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION.     85 I submit to it?"In a perfect paroxysm of contending pas- sion he strode up and down the library, foaming at the mouth, his face pale, and at times his eyes seemed to be flashiig fire. Suddenly perceiving the sword which we have mentioned, he snatched it from its resting place, exclaiming, "Slall this insignia of the honor and renown of our ancestors stay here to taunt us with our present disgrace! No, no, no!" said he furiously, as he shivered it in a dozen pieces over his knee. "  Edgar Edgerton!" "Ay I frown father! it is well that you should set your brow to the mood of the world; but I now must be free from that iron promise ; a promise so made cannot be binding, for there is a higher than even filial duty-a duty due to our country, and that country's calls; and so tregsonable a promise--- -"Edgar, by a father's rights," interposed Mr. Edgerton, "I charge you now to hear me. You know my settled allegi- ance to a king which these mad brained rebels cannot move, and yet you strive to alter them by this vain bombast. I am doubly bound to the court of England ; first, as a descendant from one of her highest and noble families, and, secondly, lands and titles which now I have a fair prospect for, would be confiscated to the crown in case of any suspicions of an attachment to these rebels. Not only those lands, but even these we possess here will certainly be lost, for as sure as the sun rises to-morrow, so sure will our king punish these auda- cious traitors." Can gold," impatiently exclaimed Edgar, " can gold pur- chase a fame more lasting than itself? Must I against my conscience and right sell the bright halo of an honorable namefor the miserable pittance of a few feet of land? No, father! I may be a rebel but I must not be a traitor." ,n   "Ti'aitor, boy! are you not a traitor to your king and coun- try in thus joining with his enemies?" said Mr. Edgerton. "A traitor," interposed Edgar, "to a king, I may be, as viewed by royal eyes, but not to my country. The first duty I owe is. to her and to defend her rights, whether threatened by foreign invasion or the tyranny of her self-constituted rulers. Kings may be powerful, but nations are far more so. Father, I must be free to join my fellow men, and henceforth I shall consider that accursed promise annulled." "Is it for this that I have so studiously strove to engraft in your mind the--  "Father I no, never, I must not hear it. I am before you as a rebel. Am I to understand that I am also your enemy." "Edgar! this, this from my son!" "Father! the chain that binds us may be now cemented, or else the first blast of war that rings in your ears may snap 'AS    <pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC6547-00000042"/> 88       A TALE OF, THE ]VOLUTION. its links.- The mighty events which are to shake dynasties cannot but ruffle the eddies of our social relations; but he who adopts his country and her dictates as his rule of con- duct must in the grandeur of the chains of that country forego private predilections and family sympathies. His country becomes the embodiment of every wish and feeling; and how great soever the sacrifices he may be called upon to make, the will and the purpose must not loosen a hair's breadth from their stern duties and the imperative decrees of honor. Father! when I am a patriot, the enemies of the Continental Congress are my enemies also!" "Edgar!" exclaimed Mr. Edgerton, but he was gone. Hastening down the broad stairway with its massive oak bannisters curiously carved in the antique style, Edgar passed from the building and strolled unconsciously towards the river side. lie stood upon the spot where a few evenings since he had conversed with Julia Melville. It was now twilight. The ruddy brightness of the western horizon had mellowed into mosti delicate tint, while the stealthy steps of dark-eyed night had fast settled its gloom o'er the distant hills; but as yet the stars were scarcely to be seen save bright Venus, which stood in the golden edge of a purple cloud, alone in its transcendant beauty. Bitter were the thoughts that stirred in the young man's bosom, and thus he marked not the beauty so displayed before him. Living under the eye of a father he loved, with a re- verence devout as it was unlimited, he felt the more keenly the position he was forced to choose, and thus the fierce language which had probed his father's heart to the core, had also ran. kled deep in his own bosom. He felt that the uncertainty of his former principles was a greater reason why his new posi- tion should be made secure by a determined course of action  and however much his filial love would induce him to forego the stern purposes of a patriot, the greater claim of his coun- try pointed unwaveringly to the course to be pursued. Thus early in his new career did he learn the mighty efforts that were needed to place him on an equality with the spirits of the age; and the first-stern sacrifice, the estrangement from a father's heart and love, told his young heart that it was no "primrose path of dalliance" he had proposed to travel, but the stern and inflexible road to freedom and honor. Pride, the hydra-headed passion of the soul, which so often warps the best affections of our nature, assumed in our hero an unwonted sway. We have seen that, though always par- tial to the American cause, his partiality had mostly arisen from his selfish aspiration after admiration and fame, and it was not until his daily communication with Julia Melville that he had imbibed those stronger and deeper principles of   A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION.      8T disinterested patriotism. Albeit, there still remained in him something of the early self-considerations, which even now were the promptings of the pride of his nature. He could not but own that he was first prompted to his adopted course by her own soft and gentle persuasions, rather than to any primitive stern principles of right, howheit those principles had been nurtured into being by her inspiring language and noble sentiments. A self-worshipper, he could not bring him- self to acknowledge his own lack of moral courage and her superior knowledge of right; and -thus actuated, he almost blamed her that she had. placed him in so humiliating a light. Thus tossed between his consciousness of wrong, at times bitterly blaming himself and her, and at others going as he thought to the very foundation of all his grievances, le fiercely cursed his weakness in making so unfortunate a promise. He stood upon the rock and noted not the approach of a footstep; a hand was gently placed upon his arm, yet he stirred not. "Edgar," said the soft low voice of Julia. Edgar started back, but recovering himself, he bowed low. "Good evening, Miss Melville! you seem to have a fond- ness for the night air," said he, and was about passing on, when Julia in her low and mournful voice, exclaimed, "Stay Edgar-I mean Mr. Edoerton" "Oh! I beg pardon, I was afraid lest you could not see me in this dishabille." "Oh! Edgar, what can this mean?" l Simply this, Julia! I know the obligations I am under to you who first taught me the baseness of my own nature, and then as if to correct any misapprehension I might be subject. to, plainly told me that you would not wed me with the s  damning stain of a traitor on my name. Madam, I will not insult you by any supposition that would forego your deter- mination; but trust you will view me in the light the bene- volent world does, and that you will not insult me by any uncalled for t6kens of pity or commiseration." "Can this really be you, Edgar?" faintly exclaimed Julia. "O ! no, good Madam, a traitor, at your service. Your idol, Washington, has pronounced me so, and his unerring judgment must be right. And though I have forfeited all claims upon your hand, may I not hope that when you see me in scarlet and epaulettes, I may win my way to your fancy, if not to your heart, under other auspices." Like one rooted to the ground, stood Julia-her face white as alabaster,while her eyes were fixed upon him in a vacant stare. She seemed scarely to breathe, but motionless as a sta- tue she stood with not the movement of a muscle to denote that she was conscious of aught around her.    <pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC6547-00000043"/> A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION.      89 the collar, for an instant he was suspended in the air and the next moment he was safely landed on a low fishing boat that was ascending the river., The suddenness of this movement 3s completely surprised our hero that it was for a moment or two before he could freely comprehend where he was and how he came there; but as he looked around he caught a glimpse of a remnant of his skiff disappearing behind them, which told him the danger he had escaped. It seemed that lost in his reverie and surrounded by the thick darkness, he had not noticed the approach of the vessel, while the lookout of the fishing smack perceiving a small boat directly in their course had shouted for the occupant to clear their path-not being heeded he again shouted, but by this time they were close upon the skiff and the next instant the bows of the smack struck Edgar's boat, which from its light- ness-though crushed in-swept around and rushed by the side of the larger vessel; but with great promptness the look- out seized Edgar as the vessel swept by and dragged him on board. ,Edgar found himself surrounded by some twenty-five or thirty whigs, who were eyeing him suspiciously, notwithstand- ing the fact of his being clothed in the continental uniform; but in those wary times this was far from being received as conclusive evidence of his Whig attachments, besides the sus- picious place he had been found in gave them reason to sup-  pose that he was sailing under false colors. The open frankness of his manners, however, soon grew into favor with them; and when he stated that he was about seeking the American encampment when they had thus so unexpectedly met, they crowded around him with congratu- lations and cheers, and in return he was partially given to understand their present object and course. Although their information was uncertain and somewhat mysterious, he learned sufficient to comprehend that they were proceeding on a secret mission to take prisoner a well-known suspicious character. Emboldened by their frank manner he at last ventured so far as to enquire who they were after. "One the General suspects strongly of treachery," said the captain of the band; "he s the son of an old Englishman living above here somewheres, and it is said that he was endeavor- ing to induce Washington to be on his guard against treason, but which it is generally suspected was only a snare of some tories to get the General into their power." "His name?" faintly exclaimed Edgar. "Edgar Edgeiton!" returned the captain. Our hero felt the hot blood rush in a torrent to his temples at this information. Was indeed his reputation at so low an      <pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC6547-00000044"/> A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION.      91 such a mind as Edgar's, albeit however noble in itself, the mooted question was too often, not its intrinsic right, but its coloring to the world-might they not place it to parricide, and then what future honors could wipe out the indelible stain. But yet he thought it was not his father, but himself they sought; and how strange soever it might appear, he was but one of a party of rebels to seek out a fancied traitor-and that traitor himself-and when the truth was known, would it not be convincing proof of the honesty of his professions. Had lie not led them to his father's door, and drowned all feelings of filial,love in the sterner duties to his country. What more could be required  though he felt the consciousness of right; yet, to his mind, it was not enough; he had too long taught himself to aspire to the good opinion of mankind, to be con- tent with such a reward. Fortunately, Edgar was left among those who watched without, or perhaps he would have been discovered by his father or Julia, had he been one of those who proceeded to search the building. While this search was proceeding, he endeavored to devise some plan, whereby he might induce the whigs to intercept the tories, who he knew would be moving near them on their way below, for the purpose of carrying out their designs. Half suspected as he was, any urgent requests to that effect would be received with distrust, while a mere suggestion would be unheeded; and, inasmuch as his sto'y had been disbelieved by Washington, how could he hope that these would listen to his account of the conspiracy ? In the possession of facts, the untold knowledge of which was treach- ery; yet, his very communication of them was so received that he could not speak all he knew, but determined, blindly, to trust to fortune and chance. The searching party returned with the information, that the object of their search could not be found; and the captain giving instructions that none of the property should be touch- ed on pain of 'the severest punishment,-ordered a close ex- :amination of the grounds in the vicinity. Scattering in every direction, Edgar soon found himself alone in the search of his traitorous self. A thought struck him; might he not desert, and lead the militia to the back country in pursuit of him; but, would they take that danger and risk for so uncertain a result? If he could but alarm the neighboring country, and the countrymen gathering together, would they not intercept the tories, if they had not already passed ? A sudden thought flashed across his mind, which, for a moment, almost stag- gered him; for a little while, he seemed lost in a complete reverie, while the workings of his countenance denoted a strange struggle within. " Alone !" at last said he, " alone       <pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC6547-00000045"/> 92       A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION. and why should I not, 'tis a great sacrifice; but is not the object worthy of it? It shall be done!" exclaimed he, firmly, and imme- diately moved towards the house, where he readily obtained entrance unperceived through the door in the rear of the house, and reached his own room without any disturbance. The windows of his room opened on the front and side of the building ; therefore tightly closing them all, he struck a light by means of the flint of his gun, and immediately set fire to every combustible material in the room, placing them in situations where the blaze would easily reach the woodwork of the building ; he left the room, and ascending into the loft, applied the flame to heaps of rubbish, worn out furniture, &amp;c., which had lain there 4i undisturbed repose for years. Edgar felt his heart bound within him in a new and undefined delight as he descend- ed the stairs. Had he not fired his own homestead--that the burning pile, casting its lurid glare for miles around, might show the Whigs their danger and lure the Tories on to certain destruction. Would not that flame, as it ascended high towards the heavens, write his name in burning letters, which time could only pale. So effectualty had EdTgar carried his plan into execution, that by the time he had joined his companions-who had not noticed his absence-smoke was perceived slowly issuing from the crevices of the shutters * instantly a dozen voices shouted " fire fire!" while many, forgetting all dis- cipline, rushed in the utmost confusion to the house; but, above all this hubbub, the clear free voice of their captain was shouting out his orders. Many, however, either did not hear them, or did not wish to; but rushing to the room from whence the smoke had been seen issuing, they burst open the shutters. The draught rushing in, fanned the then smoking embers into a wild and raging blaze, which drove the busy meddlers-who had thus hastened the destruction of the mansion-from the room.  The imperative 'commands of Captain Stanton soon, however, assembled them all on the green before the now raging furnace; his quick eye had soon perceived that any attempt to save the building would be useless, as the flames had gained too much ere they were discovered ; and also fearing that his proximity might be known to prowling parties of tories, who would intercept in a measure his return to camp, he determined to ehibark with all speed, taking with him Mr. Edgerton, Julia, and the servants of the family. Indeed, so anxious was he to get off ere he was dis- covered, that he forbade any attempts to save the valuable furniture and library of Mr. Edgerton. It was now a scene of wild grandeur and startling beauty ; the waving columns of fire sweeping on in their all-consuming course; while here and there tall spiral pillars of flame shot up their forked ends to the heavens, casting their lurid glare on the urgent and impetuous crowd below, lighting up their faces in brilliant and unwonted glow, and chasing the dark shadows far o'er the river's side, and deep into the thick forest. The light vessel was turned towards her return course, and just began to feel the breeze, when the tramping of horses' feet was heard, and a large party of horsemen rode on to the green in full view of thece on board the vessel, and to whom it soon became apparent that they were the much   A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION.         93 'hated Hessians. Captain Stanton cast an uneasy glance at the shore, and at the slowly filling sail; when, suddenly, as the vessel came from the shadow of the high bluff we have spoken of, the sails filled, and bending low to the water, she flew along her course; but by this time the Hessians had rushed down to the water's edge, and dis- charged their pistols at the retreating vessel, but without effect. Suddenly, however, the sharp crack of a rifle broke on the air fol- lowed by an irregular discharge of musketry, told our little party that a dreadful struggle was about to ensue. Had Captain Stanton followed the impulses of his ardent and courageous nature, he imme- diately would have put back to the assistance of the whigs ; but his orders were imperative, and he must perforce proceed. Those reports, which came to the ears of most those on board, as the death doom of some hopeless mortal, were to our hero the tones of a preserved country; and shall we add, the resounding of his own fulture fame. We would we could, for the sake of our romantic readers, expatiate on the disinterested patriotism of his act. Patri- otic it most assuredly was, but he had allowed sel( interest to go hand in hand with it. We have seen, though patriotism had forbade him taking part with the English parliament, it bad not induced him to take up arms in defence of his country until his own sufferings had prompted him ; but the consciousness of right thrilled the bosom of Edgar with intense delight; and as he sat back in the shadow lest he might be recog- nized by Julia or his father, he revelled in the thoughts of the praise his Julia would bestow upon him, when she heard of his act, and mused upon what light his father would receive him. Would he altogether disown, or would he forget party prejudices in the noble- ness of his son? After the first flush of excitement was over, the stern eye of Cap- tain Stanton surveyed his subordinates around, as if he would read their very souls, and ferret out the one who had applied the incendiary torch. "If I knew," said he, fiercely, " the one who fired that building, by Jove I'd hang him to the first tree we meet on landing." Edgar started at this blunt threat. "Would he dare do it?" thought the young man; "have I not been too rash, and should I be discovered ;" his frame quivered at the prospect before him. .Must all his hopes, his ambitions, and his love thus ignominiously end? And must his sacrifice be laid in his grave with him? The sweat stood in huge drops on his forehead, as he thought of so fearful a fate. Looking up he perceived the eyes of Captain Stanton and his soldiers fixed upon him. Seeing that he was the suspected person, he, with an effort, mastered all emotion; and rising from his seat turned to the captain. "It was I that did it, sir," said he, firmly and calmly. A dark frown lowered on Stanton's brow, and his fingers involuntarily clutched his sword handle as he furiously said: By G- I sir, I have a mind to make you feed for the fishes. Who are you, and what are you, sir? that you thus dare to insinuate    <pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC6547-00000046"/> "A     .   A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION. yourself into our company, and then bring eternal disgrace on our name I By heavens I did I not know you were a villain -" "A villain!" thundered Edgar.  "Captain Stanton, recall those words, or---'"  The blood rushed in a torrent to his face, while his eye flashed, and his whole frame was convulsed with passion as he flung his muskl th  above his head, as if to crush Stanton to the ground. Seize him!" cried a dozen voices. "Back, my men!" shouted the captain, "let me deal with him," said he, drawing his sword, and waving it above his head, was about to spring upon him, when a loud scream  broke upon their ears as Julia rushed forward, springing between, exclaiming, "Spare him, Captain-he is-Edgar, oh!" and sank fainting on the deck between them, while Mr. Edgerton sprang forward with his hands clasped, exclaiming, "My sen! Edgar I oh my God lI and covering his face with his hands, sank upon his seat. "His son 1-Edgar-spare him-what can all this mean? ' said the bewildered captain; but, perceiving the fainting form of Julia, he raised her up, shouting for water. In a few minutes she revived mut- tering incoherently. Edgar had dropped back into the shadows of the sail, with his musket leaning listlessly by his side; but with his bold, undaunted front and high demeanor, his proud eye glancing from the group of wondering soldiers before him to the strange scene beyond. "May I ask, sir; for an explanation of this?" said Stanton, turning towards Mr. Edgerton; but a groan was his only answer. Let that father who has spent his life in the careful training of a much loved son-and when he has moulded his mind to all that is noble and good he turns his admiring eyes, and exclaims " behold I "-but as he gazes, the wreckers of vice engulph the fond hopes of years I Let him, we say-for he only can feel the agony of that father's heart.  The thought that his son-that son whom he had taught to revere and respect him-should not only mock at his teachings, but fire the very roof over his head-could there be so much depravity in one he had ever thought good and noble? The agony of the doating parent, whose tears wash the grave of its idol; is happiness to one like this, who buries not his son's body, but his virtues. Unable to obtain any information from Mr. Edgerton or Julia, Captain Stanton turned to Edgar, saying: "Your relationship to Mr. Edgerton, sir, and your singular situation is such, that I must defer all action until I have laid the case before the cdmmander-in-chief; in the mean time, I think, sir, you will pardon me if I impress upon you the neces- sity of your being considered as a prisoner." Our hero stepped forward; and, re- signing his musket, dropped back with a low bow to his former position. The ves- sel was now rapidly nearing the York side; and, in a few minutes, it was moored by a rough pier of loose stones which extended some fifty feet out into the river. Mr. Edgerton and Julia were then left with an honest farmer livihg close to the spot, until they could be conveniently removed; while Captain Stanton and his men mounted their steeds, which had been left in charge f the farmer; and with their prisoner, rode rapidly towards Washington's army-then approaching White Plains. Julia, mid all the varied scenes of excitement of the last tew hours, had borne up with a praiseworthy endurance; but now exhausted, she immediately sought such accommodation as her humble hostess-the good farmer's dame-could furnish, and   A TALE OF THE   REVOLUTTION.  retired to her bed-if not to sleep, to think over the strange events which she had taken a part in. Nor for one moment s had Julia accused Edgar--in her own mind --of the deprave4t act he was adjudged guilty of. She knew that when he had ap- plied the torch, his object was worthy of the effort; -and, thus confident of her lover's innocence, she felt none of that pang which Edgerton was writhing under- still she trembled lest he should be a victim to circumstances i and the thought of an ignominious death to one so endeared by every tie, racked her soul with a thou- sand fears. Now she thought of seeking Washington and flinging herself at his feet, to implore his pardon; and now she felt that he would be adjudged innocent, and that they dare not harm one so pure and so noble and so dear to her withal. Midst a thousand plans, hopes, and fears, she at last fell into a deep sleep-thouh, perchance, not without its dreams.           I Two hours riding brought our party to the encmpment. The first tint of morn was just breaking in the east, as they entered into their quarters. The encamp- ment was a few miles from the Plains, among a small cluster of buildings raised to the dignity of a village, where they had taken quarters for the previous niht, preparatory to their movement to White Plains. Our hero was escorted to a large barn, where a number of whigs were ensconced, and left in the charge of t sentinel. Anxious to be alone, he drew his cap over his eyes and seated himself in one corner; but the morning soon summoned them to their respective duties, and he was left alone with the sentinel; who, respectfully withdrawing to a distant part of the house, left him to his reflections. Notwithstanding Edgar's contentment in the knowledge of his right, he could feel anything but easy at heart. Uncertain whether his story would be believed, its doubt would fling new disgrace on his name; while even, perhaps. a partial belief in it, would relieve him from his im- prisonrment-would give him what he valued .more than liberty-an honorable reputation. "Oh! have I not borne enough!" exclaimed he almost aloud. 'Can I Hnever win that place I have so much aspired for? and must I ever be inisunder- stood an-d my motives misinterpreted t" In a few hours he was summoned, and informed that Washington had preceded the army to the Plains that very morning, and that he now must take up his march. Not seeing Captain Stanton, he pre- sumed he had hurried on to Washington, and that his case was already laid be- fore him. Arriving at the Plains he was placed under charge of sentinels in a small low wooden buildin, situated in the oegnfines of the town. from the window of which he perceived the rapid advancement of a breastwork or mound which the Americans were throwing up on the brow of the hill, on which this town is situated. These tokens of an approaching conflict were anything but satisfactory to Edgar, shut up as he was. and debarred from an active part. How he longed to be one of them; that, by his individual efforts, he might win a little share of the glory which his ardent imagination had already secured for the American arms. The day was rapidly waning, when his room door was thrown open, and an or- derly entered, commanding his company. With an anxious heart our hero obeyed the summons, uncertain as he was to his fate, and in what light his incendiarism was viewed by the commander. Following the conductor to another portion of the town, they entered a large irregular wooden builllng. Passing along the wide hall which ran through the centre of the house, a doon at the side was opened and the orderly fell back, motioning Edgar to enter. Calming his anxious heart, he stepped into the room, and found himself in the pre- sence of Washington. He was seated at a table at the extreme end of the room and by a window which overlooked the movements of his armny. Captain Stanton stood at the opposite side of the table, the only officer present. Edgar gazed calmly in the face of the commander, awaiting him to break the silence, "Edgar Edgerton, " said he,': Captain Stanton has informed me the particulars of your insubordination. The act seems to-have been one too heinous without an effi- cient cause, and since I once too hastily dismissed you from my presence, when you claimed to have valuable information to give, perhaps, sir, you can justify your conduct." "To what purpose? to be misbelieved!" said Edgar bitterly. Am I right, sir, in supposing that you was induced to do this, as an only alterna- tive to preserve the liberty of one you had chanced to overhear was threatened." A bright glow suffused the face of Edgar at the words of the General. Briefly    <pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC6547-00000047"/> 96      A TALE OF THE REVOLUTION. and simply he explained to him his motives, which Edgar readily saw by the brightening countenance of Washington, was believed. t" 'Tis, said the General, "OTis as I thought, for I no sooner heard of the destruc- tion of your father's mansion, and the hand who had committed the deed, than the remembrance of your bearing on a former interview was recalled to my mind, and I felt confident that the act was one noble and praiseworthy. Could I, sir, place you in rank for services done myself, I would readily do so, but sir, that cannot be. and therefore, IFfear your disinterested act must go unrewarded: but, sir, the ranks are before you, and rest assured that acts of zeal and valor, will in time biing you a cotmission.-   - . ' The countenance of yourself, and my own knowledge of right is my reward sir, added to the good opinion of my fellow men," said Edgar. 'tThe good opinion of the world is to be desired, sir, but not sought after as para- ouni t to other considerations; but there are others who now desire a reconciliation. ;Captain-Stanton, I must beg your leave awhile. With a low bow to the General, and'also to Edgar, the captain approached him and, said, "Sir, I cannot leave you :without apologizing for the terms I bestowed upon you yesterday, and I also trust, sir, you will allow me to congratulate you on the position in which your noble deeds will surely place you in the eyes of every true American." Edgar could hardly speak, but grasped the Captain's hand with emotion. Captain Stanton then with- drewt when Washington opened the door which communicated with the ante-room, exclaiming?"It is as I supposed, Mr. Edgerton! you should be proud to own such a son.  "My father!" said Edgar-" oh, sir, your pardon, your pardon I. Nay - nay;! Edgar, tis I should ask for that," said Mr. Edgerton, clasping his son close to him while his voice was feeble and tremulous, with emotion. "Oh! I thought youlbase and mean, and I have found you more than noble I for- give me, my 'son; so unjust a suspicion! but where is Washington? ) He was gone, desiring that their meeting should be private and sacred. "Yes, my boy," resumed his father, ' you shall now join the American forces-such nobility and stich a /sacrifice must be for a cause worthy of it, and though I cannot join with you, you at least have my prayers and my wishes."7   . "Thanks, father Hbut where's Julia "-he stopped short. She is here, and you shall;see:her: stay I will fetch her."  ' Let us drop a veil overlthat meeting. It was, the joining of hearts whose only happiness consisted in their beating in-unison.- Edgar fought on the morrow in the renowned battle of White Plains, and won especial favor at the hands of Washing- ton.;- 'He afterwards rose rapidly, and was at one time on the staffof the com- mander Two'years afterwards they were married, and after the war resided on the same spot where our tale opened. The name of Edgerton was borne by many a lovely girl and a noble' boy, who held in trust the natures of Julia and 'Edgar Ed- gerton. THE  BND.    </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>