<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6457">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Madelaine Darth </title>
            <author>Ford, E. L.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC6457</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-0927</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Madelaine Darth</title>
                  <author>Ford, E. L.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>71 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Western News Co.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Chicago </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1867">1867</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-03-30">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Madelaine Darth</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6457-00000001"/>  E s hti. E vt BY E. L. FORD.   CHCAGO': WESTERN NEWS COMPANY. 1867. Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year, 1867, by the Western News Company, in the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United. States, for the Northern District of Illinois.    <pb n="0" xml:id="VAC6457-00000002"/> II   MADELAINE DARTH. PART I. NARRATIVE OF ROGER TIERNAY. PERHAPS if I had been more of a sentimentalist and less of a lawyer the events I am about to relate would never have occurred. It is cer- tainly true that had I not possessed the lawyer-like attributes of method and exactness this story could never have been written. The dreamer neither records dates, nor remembers causes. He lives for that which is to be, and plays his part, unconscious that a tragedy is in progress, until the last scene is enacted. This is no sensational tale. I shall give you the clue, even as quietly as Fate placed it in my unsuspecting palm, and you shall follow it as blindly and laboriously as I followed it to the end of the tangled skein. So much for the prologue. The play opened thus: Mr. Matteson, hotel proprietor, Jim Rainey, a rusticating college youth, and myself, stood on the steps of the Matteson House, in Quarrytown, Wis., waiting for the carriage to be brought-around. "I say, Matteson," cried Jim, switching his polished boots with a dandified cane, "that new boarder of yours is a rather fine thing-in    <pb n="2-3" xml:id="VAC6457-00000003"/> 2       MADELAINE DARTH. a statuesque point of view-for she neither looks nor acts like flesh and blood." To which remark Matteson made no reply. "Come, Matteson, do n't assume the I O-no-we-never-mention-her' style," pursued the reckless Jim. " What's her name?" "Darth." "From where ? whither bound ?" " I do n't know." Matteson went around to the other side of the horse and began to inspect the harness, and talk tothe servant. Jim assumed the air of a juvenile translator of Esop's Fables: " ' A certain philosopher being asked how many stars there were in the heavens, answered, "I do not know; I attend to that which is near me."  ," How many hairs, then, are upon the back of your cat ? " 'I do not care," was the/ answer. 'c MoRAL.-From this we learn never to question a philosopher, since the answer direct denotes lack of wisdom.'" Having finished his caricature, Jim vaulted into the carriage. Mat- tepon, either deaf or callous to his raillery, silently followed, and we drove away.  'Matteson was so unmarked a man, his appearance so commonplace, his individuality so unimpressive, that one felt grateful to redeeming Time, which allowed him to be described as a middle-aged man, some- what gray.  His clothes, neither neat nor slovenly, were of such common cut and color that they defied scrutiny. He was the easiest man to lose in a crowd, the hardest to describe in a handbill. Men neither spoke well nor ill of him. He plodded quietly along the even tenor of his way, his good sense and good nature preserving him from jostling or being jostled on the road of life. It was late that night when Matteson and I drove back. Rainey returned in the cars. We rode quietly along for some time until, at length, Matteson abruptly broke the silence.   MADELAINE DARTH.            3 "That rattle-tongued Rainey asked after that new boarder this morn- ing, and I held my tongue. I do n't pour water into sieves. But I 've been rather watching and waiting to have a talk with you. Mebbe you remember when I went up to Wild Cat Falls, a spell ago? Coming home on the cars, that woman sat in front of me; I see she was sick as soon as ever I looked at her. She kept getting worse, and, when we stopped at Quarrytown, I thought it was only common hu- manity to get her off the cars, and take her up home to the hotel with me. - She was pretty sick for nigh three weeks; but Doctor Felton he's been a doctoring of her, and she's a'most well now. She's got- so as she can move 'round the house and come to the table." Matteson came to a conversational halt. I reflected that, having a good income, keeping a hotel, and being of liberal 'heart and unsus- pecting nature, he would readily become the victim of an adventuress. s And, she being well, you wish to be rid of her," I suggested. Wall, no, not exactly that, either. In fact, my wife's taken a great fancy to her, and wants. to give her a home with us; but-wall, there's something rather curious in the matter. Her sickness has affected her memory, and she's forgotten all about her past life." "Perhaps that 's the best thing she could do." "I should be sorry to think that," said Matteson, gravely,.after a moment's thought. "The woman, she's young-not more 'n twenty, I should judge-looks very modest and nice. She took Mrs. Matteson all through her traps, and the only thing she had that looked as if it might lead to her identification, was a packet of letters. My wife gave 'em to me. Her name, though, was on her clothes." Lawyers are never very confiding in human nature, as usually devel- oped. I thought much, but said nothing* "1 take it, to-day has nearly finished the law business that brought you here," said Matteson. "I thought, mebbe, you could find time to read the letters and see what you could do at finding out the woman's friends. I 'll make it worth your while." ,I '1 read the letters, at any rate. You can give them to me to-morrow."    <pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC6457-00000004"/> 4            MADELAINE DARTH. The letters proved to be about thirty in number. They had been freed from  their envelopes and filed according to date.   They pur- ported to be the epistles written by Madelaine Darth to one Karl- surname not given. Whether written for fraudulent purposes or in genuine correspondence, they were unmistakably the work of a gifted and cultivated mind.  They contained some good art criticisms, some brief literary reviews, interspersed here and there with short poems. The humor was fine and keen, the sentiment beautifully expressed. I felt grateful 'to the writer for the literary treat I had enjoyed.  I inferred from some passages that the correspondence had its rise ir some one of the numerous advertisements requesting anonymous epistles. All these letters were written in chirography almost as clear anm elegant as engraving, and were dated from Owanee, a small place dis tant some forty miles from  Quarrytown.  The last letter of the pil was indited in a bold, clerkly hand, dated at Memphis, and signe "' Karl." It being the hinge upon which turned the door of discovery I decided to retain a copy: MEMPHS, June ad, 18-. DEAR MADELAIN :-I arrived here to-day, and found awaiting me a large amour of work. Therefore, I have only a few minutes in which to write. I find myse continually wondering if the few words spoken over us by that venerable pastor ha' really made such a difference in our lives. We shall see. I nearly forgot to mention that at St. Louis I took out a life insurance for $xo,oo Of course, woman-like, you will not understand my prudence, but will superstitious believe that I have hastened my death. Well, so be it. That policy and our marriage certificate, which- ninny that I was- I carried aw in my pocket-book, I will send you assoon as I know of some reliable person goi North. I do not care to trust the chances of the mail. Everything is so insect and unsettled here that I am glad to be relieved of any trust. I rejoice that you h. your letters in your own hands. I shall write again soon. Keep up your spirits, and God bless you. KARL. Out of this letter there dropped the photograph of a young mE "For value received," was written under it, with the signature "Kar attached.  The writing was the same as that of the letter.   V '      -  MADELAINE DARTH.              S This, then, was my summing up of the whole matter: Thrown upon the charities of Mr. Matteson was a young woman, who, upon the subject of her past life, maintained a complete silence, either voluntary or otherwise. In the letters purporting to have been written by herself, there was but one clue to the mystery, of this woman's antecedents-that was the name of the town whence the let- ters were posted. Supposing the correspondence to be a fraud, that apparent clue would, of course, prove a false lead. The letter signed ' Karl" was exactly the letter that the designer of the imposition- always supposing there was one-would have thought it necessary to write, in order to complete the fraud. ,The loss of the envelopes oblit- erated all hope of obtaining the surname of the mythical Karl. As for the picture it might have been bought or stolen at any photograph gal- lery. There was an allusion to a certificate recording the marriage of the woman Darth to some one unknown. No clue was given as to the time, place or witnesses of the ceremony. In regard to the life insur- ;]   ance I pondered over the matter but failed to see the motive of the writer, in asserting the existence of a life policy but concealing, at the same time, all traces of the policy holder. I finally concluded it was introduced merely to strengthen the idea of a previous marriage and demonstrate the forethought of the husband. My duty-should I choose to comply with 'Matteson's request and endeavor to ferret out the mystery-was simple enough. First, to obtain from Dr. Felton a medical opinion in regard to his patient's loss of memory. Second, to proceed to Owanee and there make inquiries in regard to a woman calling herself Darth. Here I expected to meet with a check in the ignorance of the inhabitants of Owanee in regard to the subject of my search. I could then rest on my oars till I decided'upon a new line of action. Dr. Felton was a genial, jovial M. D., converted from- Allopathy to Homeopathy. Such a sympathizing nature could not long, continue to inflict nauseous potions on helpless victims. He invited me into his library, and refreshed me with fruit cake, and currant wine of his own manufacture. We exchanged short biographical sketches, and finally, a -    <pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC6457-00000005"/> 6          MADELAINE DARTH. by easy gradations, we arrived at the subject nearest my thoughts--the illness of the woman, Darth. She was subject to a sickness to which I find parallels in medical records, though I have met with none in my experience. It was cata- lepsy of an uncommon nature, and was necessarily attended with peculiar effects upon the mental as well as physical health of the patient. I have found in an old medical gazette a description of a somewhat simi- lar case. The subject of the article, a Scotch servant girl, was afflicted with periodical cataleptic fits, which in course of time increased in length, while her slumber was more profound with each recurring at- tack. They weakened her memory to such an extent that events occur- ring in the time between the attacks would be partially or totally for- gotten. Her mind became unsettled, and her horror of these fits was so great that it finally induced the commission of suicide." "You then believe the loss of memory in the case of your patient named Darth to be real?" "I do." I held my glass between me and the light, and enjoyed the clear amethyst tint of the wine in silence. "Have you seen Miss Darth yet?" asked the Doctor. "No." "You have something, then, to live for. When she commits suicide, I hope she will open a vein. It is too pretty a face to be discolored with poison, or mangled with knife or bullet." "A dismal prospect under any circumstances," I said, rising. "What woman has done, woman may do," answered the Doctor, getting briskly on his feet. "I beg your pardon for being so prolix or a professional subject. I do not know how it happened. I don' usually talk of my patients. If you had ever seen Miss Darth, I shoulc think you led me on to talk of her. I wonder if I am driving yoi away. Come again, Tiernay; come again."   MADELAINE DARTH.             7 EXTRACT FROM THE JOURNAL OF MADELAINE DARTH. Mrs. Matteson was playing a piano accompaniment to the solo I was singing, when we heard footsteps in the hall, and Mr. Matteson's voice. The door opened, and there entered, first a young man, with a frank, handsome face and bright black eyes, whom Mrs. Matteson greeted, and introduced to me as Mr. Rainey. The second comer was a Mr. Tiernay, and lastly entered Mr. Matteson. "Have we silenced the music?" queried Mr. Rainey, glancing at me.  My thoughts come so slowly, expression is so tardy with me, that I dread replying to strangers. Mrs. Matteson, knowing this, came to AI   my rescue. At her suggestion, she and Mr. Rainey began practicing duetts. Mr. Matteson strolled out upon the piazza. Mr. Tiernay seated himself at a little distance from me, in the shadow of the win- dow draperies. He seemed to be intent upon the music. He neither looked at nor spoke to me. His eyes were fixed upon the starlit night outside. Presently, some one proposed cards. Mr. Tiernay drew the table in front of me, and seated himself opposite. I fancied Mr. Rainey would have liked a choice of partners, but politeness silenced him. I played well; for during my convalescence my chief amuse- ments had been cards and books. Mr. Tiernay is an ambitious man.  His gray eyes deepened in color and grew luminous at each fresh suc- cess. Mr. Rainey laughed and jested, but his opponent played as if for life. "We could not bear to break your heart by beating you, Tiernay," laughed Rainey, at parting. -' One gains self-confidence with each small success," retorted Tier- nay. "He who allows himself to be beaten in small things, will never have confidence to attempt great ones." When they were gone, Mrs. Matteson stood some time with her face turned from me, arranging her music. i   arnigh    <pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6457-00000006"/> 8          MADELAINE DARTH. "We are going to the County Fair to-morrow, Madelaine," she said, "will you go? It will do you good." I assented. She came close to me, and taking my chin in the hollow of her hand looked in my eyes. I fancied her expression was that of compassion. 'Poor little chick!" she said. "She is pale and sleepy; go tc bed." When I was crossing the hall, she called after me: "Sleep on the square inch, Madelaine, and look your best in th( morning. Mr. Matteson has asked those two gentlemen to accompanJ us." NARRATIVE OF ROGER TIERNAY--(CONTINUED.) Having once seen Miss Darth, (for as such she was introduced tc me), I was so much impressed by the guilelessness of her manner thai I resolved that whatever measures I adopted should be taken, as far a practicable, without her knowledge. When it became necessary t( have her identified in Owanee, we took advantage of a Fair whici was being held there, and calling the place by another name, les she should recognize it as the address of her letters, we all wen there as if on a pleasure trip. We rode thither on the cars. Raine) turned two seats together, and thought he had achieved a master-stroke of diplomacy when he had secured a seat beside Miss Darth. As fo: me, I was satisfied. Sitting opposite, I could view her full face with out staring. When she turned and looked out of the window, I coulc see her profile, which was exceedingly regular, while her complexion was so delicate it gave her features the appearance of being outlined ir shadow tint, as in paintings. Arriving at our destination, I watched her face narrowly, a iRaine) helped her from the cars and escorted her to the hotel. She looker about her with a puzzled, memory-searching expression, that finallj   MADELAINE DARTH.            9 settled into the amused curiosity of a stranger in a country place. If she were really playing a part, and pretending " ignorance where it was folly to be wise," her acting was perfection. If she were really in Owanee for the first time, then the letters dated from there were a fraud.  Rainey accompanied the ladies to the Fair, while I, under pretext of business, took my solitary way to the post-office. In a village, one needs but few directions to find that building. On my request to see the Post Master, the clerk, an insignificant youth of eighteen, with a nose that seemed put on as an afterthought of his crea- tion, showed me into a back room, where, with their coarse cowhide boots elevated to the very top of the rusty, fireless stove, sat that im- portant official and two of his village cronies. Not one of them changed his posture. With their battered, dusty hats upon their heads, with their clay pipes in their mouths, they fixed their unflinching eyes upon the stranger, and stared in undisguised curiosity. Upon my repeating my inquiry for the Post Master, one of them deliberately took his pipe from his mouth, intensified his stare, and laconically answering, "That's me," put his pipe back in his mouth, and evidently awaited developments. His clumsy astonish- ment was still further excited when [ requested a few private words with him. On my beginning to speak to him in a low voice, the two other men rose to .their feet. "We may as well 'be going, Jake," said the elder, knocking the ashes out of his pipe. "Come along, then," said Jake, making some slight alterations in his toilet, such as pullings off his worn felt hat, producing therefrom a red silk handkerchief, wherewith he wiped his face, flung it back into the hat, which he clapped on his head, and the pair strode heavily from the room. "I am a lawyer from Chicago, up here on business," I said to the Post Master.  "I would like to see your box-list, if you've no objection." "Well, I don't know as I have."    <pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6457-00000007"/> IO         MADELAINE DARTH. He lumbered across the room, and came back with the list. Begin- ning with the "A"s, I took my pencil steadily through the alphabet. Back and forth, from the paper to my face, went the eyes of my coun- try-bred companion. The last name in the "D"s was Darth. I carefully avoided any pause at that discovery, but ran my pencil through the whole alphabet. Then, commencing at the beginning, I made inquiries of some names under each letter, making a hap-hazard selection. ( Adams? O, he lives up by the mill. T' aint likely he 'll be in town for two or three days. He comes mostly on Saturdays. Mrs. Clay? She 's a widow; lives in the little red house just aiound the corner. Darth? Well, she 's gone now. She did live at Hackman's, but she went away a couple of months ago." Two or more queries, and the "H "s were reached. "Hackman  He lives in the next street above here, in the big white house," pointing, with his thumb. "He keeps a school. He used to preach-does yet sometimes-when he gets a call." And so through the paper, to the "c W "s. "Going to be here long?" began the inquisitive office-holder. "I leave to-night. Much obliged to you for your trouble." "'T ain't any trouble. No occasion for feeling obliged." Under the genial influence of ungratified curiosity, my companion began to gain animation. I did not await a thorough revivification. I seized my hat. Secure of having left no clue to distinguish the name of Darth from the rest of the list, I departed in the most hopeful spirits. I went back to the hotel. It was no difficult task to have a private consultation with Mrs. Matteson. Rainey was only too eager for a tete-a-tete with Miss Darth. The next thing to be done was to see the Hackmans, Knowing, from experience, the curiosity and gossip- ing propensities of villagers, I resolved to find the house by the aid simply of the Post Master's description. A gaunt, ungainly man opened the door, gave an ungracious assent to my inquiry if his name was Hackman, and ushered me into a   MADELAINE DARTH.            II scantily furnished apartment, where sat two women engaged in sewing. I seated myself at a window, which commanded a view of the main street. -Mr. Hackman was arrayed in a panoply of distrust. Not a remark would he make to break the icy silence. Grim and implacable, he sat motionless in his chair, awaiting the explanation of my call. "Mr. Hackman," said I, "I have come to ask you some questions in regard to a Miss Darth, who was with you about three months ago." When I began speaking, the two women dropped their work and were all eager attention. Mr. Hackman, however, was determined to answer none but direct questions. He sat in defiant, silent expectation. How long did Miss Darth remain with you?" "Three months.", "What did she do?" "Nothing." A thinly disguised strain of vindictiveness in the answer. The elder woman laughed a sneering little laugh, and said, in an audible aside: O, yes, she did something-she made trouble." "What did she pretend to do?" "Everything she did was only a pretence." I had provided myself with a slip of paper and a pencil, and wrote down the answers as they were given. I conceived that I should learn quite as much from Miss Darth's enemies as from her friends; so, indifferent to Mr. Hackman's forbidding manner, I pursued my queries: "When did she leave?" "May 7th."  "Where did she go?" "I don 't know." "Where did she say she was going?" "She did not say." It was evident that Mr. Hackman's innate meanpess induced him to be as baffling and malicious as possible, but his christianity would not allow him to utter an untruth. I had very little time for word-fencing. I deliberated for one moment, wherein I caught a gleam of triumph    <pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6457-00000008"/> 12         MADELAINE DARTH. from Hackman's gray eyes, and an ill-concealed smile of vindictive satisfaction on the face of the woman who had spoken. You keep a school. Did you engage Miss Darth as an assistant teacher?" ,. Yes." How did you hear of her?" "I advertised, and she answered." "From what place " "Whitewater." I had kept a close though stealthy watch of the street. At this point in the dialogue I perceived Mrs. Matteson and Miss Darth com- ing down the opposite walk, as previously arranged between the former lady and myself. Mr. Hackman," I said, "s have the. goodness to assert whether the lady nearest to us, on the opposite side of the way, is not the Miss Darth who taught in your school." If my suspicion of Hackman's animosity to Miss Darth had needed any confirmation, I should have found it in the reluctance with which he glanced into the street, and the ill-concealed dislike which instantly showed itself on his thin, misshapen lips, and in his cunning gray eyes. The woman who had spoken left her seat, and, under pretext of arranging some books upon the stand at Hackman's elbow, looked over his shoulder at the two ladies. With all the belittling envy and spite begotten of a narrow mind aid circumscribed life, for that which is greater and higher, plainly visible in her face, she watched the reced- ing figures out of sight. Then she resumed her seat, and took up the half-sewn garment of unbleached cloth with an impatient jerk. "Fine feathers make fine birds," she sald to her companion in a half-audible voice. The man and the woman had both recognized their enemy, but each had done it in a way peculiar to the sex. Hackman having assured himself of the identity of the hated individual, hastily averted his eyes; but the woman (whom I believed to be Mrs. Hackman) not only assured herself of the identity of Miss Darth, but noted also   !r             MADELAINE DARTH.        13 every detail of the tasteful dress, and all the evidences of grace and refinement, and these things being the attributes of one whom she hated, tended not to ameliorate, but to embitter her feelings. "Mr. Hackman," said I; {" it is plain that you have given your answers more from courtesy than from any desire to converse on the subject. I should not have trespassed so long upon your time and your politeness had I not hoped the information you were so kindly giving might enable me to dispense with future legal measures." From an indescribable look that glimmered for one second upon Mr. Hackman's impassive face, I conjectured that the hint had been taken. Still busy with my pencil and notes, I again asked from what place Miss Darth answered his advertisement, "From Whitewater." ' Had she any friends there, and what were their names?" "Yes, she had a sister. 'Lis'beth, what was the name of Miss Darth's sister?" I am inclined to believe that the reverend gentleman bestowed an optical " aside" upon "'Lis'beth," for she briefly and sulkily responded "Bateman," jerking out the monosyllable "Mrs." after it, as if she were reading a post-office list. So far, so good. When there should arise any subsequent need of the Hackmans, I should know where to find them. I left the room, followed by the. stealthy, sidelong glances of the two women. Every thing about the house, and its inhabitants, gave proof of the hourly struggle they had with Poverty. Years before, I had wrestled with and overcome that adversary. I pressed a good sized greenback into Hackman's hard hand. He made but slight remonstrance. Like win- try sunshine falling upon a weather-beaten rock, a ggrim, feline smile embellished, without in the least softening, the impassiveness of his face. <pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6457-00000009"/> "         MADELAINE DARTH. PART II. NARRATIVE OF ROGER TIERNAY--(CONTINUED.) I went back to the hotel. Mrs. Matteson was a woman of tact- a domestic diplomatist. There was no doubt of my Einding her read2 for a private consultation. She heard the narrative of my interviev with Hackman in silence. At its close, she made a few pertinen queries, but offered no comment. I imagined she wished, while stil she dreaded, to hear my opinion. "Mrs. Matteson," I said, c it is neither my province, nor m: inclination, to offer an opinion in this matter; and it is for you to sa] whether or no I shall follow this clue to the final revelation, whateve that may be. The next step must be a trip to Whitewater. Shal Igo?" If Mrs. Matteson, like all other women, laid claims to persona beauty, such claims were illegitimate. She' had, however, an innate sympathy with the joys and sorrows of all humanity; and, at certair moments, the expression of that sympathy beautified her whole face She turned to me, with her eyes eloquent with entreaty, and a wistful smile upon her lips. "Mr. Tiernay," she said, i" you do n't care for Madelaine, and I do. I mean that she shall have a home with me so long as she wills to stay. I do n't see that we are obliged to pay any attention to the insinuations of the Hackmans. I do n't know them, and I do know Madelaine, and I believe in her." "She could not have a better friend, or a better home, Mrs. Matte. son," I said, sincerely. Too well I knew that to Madelaine Darth would come but few such benefactors or benefits. There was a few moments of silence, and I heard Rainey's voice, shouting a hunting chorus, as he came bounding up the stairs, two at a time. I hastened to finish our converse.   AIx MADELAINE DARTH.                   I1 "If you decide upon my going to Whitewater, it will be-as well previously to have a good picture taken of Miss Darth, as a means oi identification at that place." "We must go to Milwaukee for thepicture. There is no gallery here. Can you go to Milwaukee with us?" Rainey entered just in time to hear the question, and my answer in the affirmative. He turned over the music on the piano, struck a few chords, and sauntered away. Later in the evening he came to my room, and sat in brooding silence, with his feet on the window sill, and an unlit cigar between his lips. - The mystery srurounding Miss Darth, and the efforts which were being-made to dispel it, were subjects upon which he had never been informed. When he rose to leave, he paused a moment with his hand upon the door. When he spoke, it was with a strong effort at indifference. "Mrs. Matteson said to me'that she was obliged to go on to Mil- waukee in the morning. Are you going back to Quarrytown?" "No; I am going with her." "Good night, then," he said, passing quickly out into the hall. "Rainey," I thought, in solitary communing, "'is twenty-two. At that age, if Miss Darth had merely captivated his imagination and awakened his admiration, he would have anathematized the Fate that so early in their acquaintance deprived him of her society. He would have declared to me his opinion that the whole thing was a deuced bore.' His silence and assumed indifference do but prove his earnest- ness. Earnestness is objectionable-unless it terminates in success."  Here I paced the room back and forth, and paused in front of the mirror.  Unless," I said, contemplating the reflection therein, " it terminates in success"-and turned away, sick at heart. Mrs. Matteson represented to Miss Darth that the portrait was to be taken to assist in the search for her friends, but of the steps already taken in that search, she held Miss Darth in ignorance. The day followin e iin the ittig for the picture, the ladies returned to Quarrytown, while I remained in Milwaukee, to await the completion 7 2    <pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6457-00000010"/> 16         MADELAINE DARTH. of the portrait, which was taken on porcelain, and was to be colored in oil. It proved to be a success, and elated both with its possession and with my hopes in the revelations it would produce, I proceeded to Whitewater. A carelessly put query to the landlord of the hotel gave me the information that "C the widow Bateman had lived in that first brown house on the street next below-Rush street was the name. Did n't know whether she lived there now, or not." Thereupon I wrote-a brief note to Mrs. Matteson, ate my dinner, and smoked my after-dinner cigar, all with the serenity of one confident of success. It was during the reverie over my cigar that I refreshed my memory with another look at the miniature I carried. It quickened my resolves and my energies. I hastened to seek Rush street. The house was a small brown one, with green blinds. Locust trees bordered the fence, and a green vine struggled for existence at the corner of the piazza. Alto- gether a conventional house, such as we see advertised and rented year after year. I rang the bell. A piano, which was rewarding a tyro's touch by dismal discords, ceased its wailings. A door was opened and shut. I fancied I heard subdued voices, evidently dictating terms for the party outside, and then in the doorway appeared a little girl of some nine or ten years of age. I inquired for Mrs. Bateman. "Nobody lives here by that name." "' Who does live in this house?" - Mr. Clay." "Do you know who lived here before him?" "No, sir." She continued to stare at me with innocent wonder, then added, confidentially "' We only came here from Detroit six weeks ago. We don't know anybody 'round here." Mechanically, I turned away. The child watched me curiously, till I closed the gate. Walking slowly down the street, I passed the meat market; then, struck with a sudden thought, I turned back, retraced my steps, and entered it.   MADELAINE DARTH.            I7 The traditional butcher is of rubicund'face and portly figure. This dispenser of animal flesh was tall and sinewy. He favored me with any quantity of bows, and with his soiled cloth cap in his hand, stood before me in a reverential attitude. "Would the gentleman like a nice, juicy beefsteak? He could recommend those upon the block; or, perhaps the gentleman was looking for poultry? Those chickens came from the Gresham farm, Observe their yellow legs, their tender breast bones! Such chickens were not to be found elsewhere." "I am a stranger in Whitewater. I am in search of a Mrs. Bate- man, who, I was informed, resided on Rush street. I thought per- haps, if she were a customer of yours, you might know of her whereabouts." The complacent suavity, inspired by the presence of a probable customer, faded from his face and manner. SHe eyed me with curiosity, thinly dissembled by a quickly assumed air of condoling sympathy. Your information, sir, is quite correct. She didlive there--but -may I ask if the lady was a relative?" "Certainly. She was a stranger to me."  "Ah!" His manner grew a little colder. The less I was to be afflicted, the less his curiosity. "That relieves me," he ejaculated. " I do assure you it is a great re- lef. I have a great distaste to imparting evil news, but it is necessary to tell the truth. Mrs. Bateman died in June last." Tracing out this mystery was like retracing your way through the darkness of- the Catacombs by means of a thread. You live in mo- mentary danger and dread, lest the slight clue slip from your hand. I reflected. It was imperative that I should make more inquiries. Whoever was with Mrs. Bateman in her last sickness, must at least have seen Miss Darth. I knew that to whatever motive the butcher might attribute my interest in the dead woman, it would certainly be a wrong supposition. "Her sister was with her to the last?" 2    <pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6457-00000011"/> 18          MADELAINE DARTH. "O, yes. She manifested great sisterly affection. Mrs. Bateman was not alone. She was respected and loved. Mrs. Wilson-she lived just across the road from Mrs. Bateman-she used to take turns with Miss Darth in watching the sick lady. I used to see her crossing the street. Not," and here my companion grew dignified and earnest, "that I am idle, or given to gossiping. No man pries into his neigh- bors' affairs less than I. But the gentleman can see for himself that my shop is so placed that it affords excellent facilities for observation. I have never, however, I beg to assure the gentleman, abused those facilities." His accent and his phraseology were foreign. At any other time he would have served,me for another lesson in my study of human nature; but I was too eager in my solving of the mystery I studied to dally with inferior subjects. I assured my newly made acquaintance of my belief in his exemp- tion from the otherwise universal sin of curiosity, and forthwith wended my way to the home of Mrs. Wilson. Closing the gate after me, I glanced down the street, and had ocular proof that if the butcher did not abuse his facilities for observation, neither did he neglect them. Mrs. Wilson herself opened the door. Fair, plump and rosy, she reminded me, in some inexplicable way, of apple blossoms. She was one of those women who never seem old, who marry young, and whose daughters appear to her more like sisters than children. I had arranged no plan of introduction. I had waited to see the person with whom I had to deal, trusting that when the occasion ar- rived, my powers of invention would be equal to a plausible story. But when-I stood face to face with Mrs. Wilson, I vacillated. I had no knowledge of the former relations existing between her and Miss Darth. How was it possible for me to possess myself of Mrs. Wil- son's knowledge of Miss Darth, without exposing my own ignorance. What message could I frame, wherein the counterfeit would not be palpable. Diplomacy suggested averting suspicion, and gaining time by feigning an awkward, embarrassed manner. i,   MADELAINE DARTH.            19 "I come with a message from a sister of the late Mrs. Bateman," I began, exaggerating rather than concealing my hesitation. "From Miss Darth!" cried my companion, banishing all ceremony, and beaming with smiles. "Then you are welcome, indeed." c Miss Darth has been very ill." "I knew it," eagerly exclaimed my impressible companion. "I just knew how it would be. I told husband she'd no business to try to teach, but he said he could n't interfere in what was none of his business. O, dear!" The little woman was very impressible. The tears gathered in her bright, brown eyes, and her dimpled chin began to quiver. She put. up one of her white, plump hands, and brushed the tearful tendencies from her face. Then, with a little laugh, which was half kin to a sob, she fell to smoothing her satin apron, which crackled under the touch of her shapely hands. "But," said I, anxious to divert her mind from dwelling upon the object of my mission, "Miss Darth has been among friends, and has had the best of care." "Among friends! Of course she was. She makes friends wherever she is. She deserves kindness, if only in paymentl for the devotion she manifested for her dying sister. She hardly rested day or/night while waiting on her, and yet, when it was all over, nothing could restrain her from going back to teach in the Hackman Seminary. I do n't believe she would have gone back if her sister had not died. Her husband did not wishther to teach after her marriage." I tried to smile, though I felt sure the color was receding from my face in my anxiety and suspense. " thought, from your calling your friend Miss Darth, that you were ignorant of her marriage," "I 'ignorant! Why, I was almost the only witness to her wedding. Madelaine wanted it postponed on account of her sister's illness, but Mrs. Bateman would not hear to any such thing. She said that whether she lived. or died, she wished to know that Madelaine was well settled for life. She brought Madelaine up from a baby, and being a childless    <pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6457-00000012"/> 20          MADELAINE DARTH. widow, she naturally had her sister's interests very near her heart. I -  did n't suppose she 'd ever be brought to think any man good enough  for Madelaine, but I believe she was perfectly satisfied with the man she married--I forget his name. Dear, dear! I can't believe she's married, though I was at the wedding. What a handsome couple they were!" "They were a handsome couple," I echoed, assentingly. I opened the miniature I carried, and placing beside it the photograph of the mysterious Karl, I asked, quietly: "Do you think those good portraits of Madelaine Darth and the man she married?" Much has been said of the innate jealousy of women for their own sex. Mrs. Wilson had none of that feeling. As her eyes rested upon the portrait of Madelaine, she uttered an exclamation of unmixed de- light, of unalloyed admiration. I, standing beside her, looked also at that well remembered face. Still and serene it looked back at us. The eyes, limpid and brown, like the bed of a sunlit brook, the golden hair deepening into bronze-hued shadows, and the waxen complexion flushing into a delicate bloom upon cheeks and lips- "Sweet lips, whereon perpetually did reign The summer calm of golden charity." For the first time, the sight of that face gave me a pang of pain. In the countenance placed in contrast with it, I recognized the blight of all those hopes that had rooted themselves so deeply and bloomed so quickly in my heart. That face, oval shaped, with haughty eyes and gentle lips, and stamped with self-control, was such a face as women most admire; indicative of passion, pride and power; and it was the face of Madelaine Darth's husband. "He was married in a citizen's dress," said Mrs. Wilson, reflectively, ," but he has on an army blouse in this picture. Seems to me he did wear one to travel in. I do n't quite remember. He was only here a day and a half. But this is an excellent portrait, as I remember him. Madelaine told me, one night when we were watching together, all about her acquaintance with this Mr.-Mr.-well, now, I can't re- member his name. Strange, too! But then she almost always called him Karl. It began with an H. Hazel? No, that can't be it, though   MADELAINE DARTH.            21 it sounds like it. Now," with an air of profound conviction, "some day, that man's name will come to me when I am not thinking of it." I regret to say this solemnly enunciated fact of a discovery indefi- nitely postponed, did not afford me as much satisfaction as it appeared to give Mrs. Wilson. I proceeded, however, to encourage further revelations from my companion. "It began in an anonymous correspondence," I quietly asserted. ," Yes; and then he came home on a furlough and saw her. After he went back to his regiment they were engaged, and when he came home this time-he came up from   Chicago-they were married. Only Mrs. Bateman and I were witnesses. Old Mr. Carton married them, but he has had a call, and moved to Rockford, Ill., since then." Never before had I realized the benefits of that feminine garrulity which brings into conversation all details relevant or irrelevant to the subject matter. Mr. Carton's full name' I could easily discover. I mentally decided that one more direct question, fully answered, would complete Mrs. Wilson's testimony. That question I asked standing, and with my hat in my hand: "When did Miss Darth leave Whitewater for Owanee?" "She went-let me see - it was somewhere near the first of July. Her sister died June loth. I know she had a music class to teach through vacation. I can tell the exact date, though, for a letter came to her from Owanee, post-marked the very day she'left. She left the room, and returned quickly with a letter in her hand. Yes," she said, "  Madelaine left here on the 3d of July." At last I had discovered an excuse for my call. "With your permission," I said, " I will take charge of that letter, and deliver it to Miss Darth. I was commissioned to see if I could find any letters or papers belonging to her." Mrs. Wilson followed me to the door, reiterating her hospitable invitation to Miss Darth. I left her standing in the doorway, me- chanically smoothing her jaunty satin apron with her plump, white hands. This letter from Owanee proved afterward to have been a few lines from the Hackmans containing an abrupt dismissal-assigning no cause therefor.    <pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6457-00000013"/> 2-2           MADELAINE DARTH. PART III. NARRATIVE OF ROGER TIERNAY--(CONTINUED.) "ETTER FROM REV. EDWARD E. CARTON TO ROGER TIERNAY, ESQ. BELOIT, WIs., August Ioth, I86- ROGER TIERNAY, Esq: Dear Sir  I this morning just rec'd your letter of the Sixth inst., owing, no doubt, to the heaviness of the late rains. Not that I desire to speak ungratefully of the rain which falleth from heaven and maketh glad the waste places, but that there- in lieth the apology for my delay in answering. I have well considered the queries you made to me in regard to the marriage of Madelaine Darth. I have a vivid recollection of the young woman, not so much for her graces of person and comeliness of feature, though she was remarkably so en- dowed, but more for her self-sacrificing and lovely spirit. Also, I remember her hus- band-he whose portrait was enclosed in your letter. A well favored youth, and one of culture. His name escapes my mind. Neither of that, nor of the date of the marriage, have I any record, the keeping of such records not being habitual to me. I never possessed a lively sense of order, that being, it hath ever appeared to me, rather a gift from Heaven than a result of education. Now that I am an old man, these requirements of order appear daily more onerous. Never do I so regret my in- ability to meet them as when my neglect brings embarrassment to others, as I fear it will do to you.          I remain your ob't servant, EDWARD E. CARTON. A search through a file of the Whitewater newspaper for the mar- riage notice proved both laborious and unavailing. I returned from the printing office to my room in the hotel, dejected and weary. As regarded the matter which had brought me to Whitewater, I found myself completely at a stand-still.   I took the miniature and photograph from my pocket, where they were habitually .carried, and studied them  long and attentively.  I asked myself the object of this mystery.  Why did not this mysterious Karl communicate, by word or letter, with the wife to whom he had been married not three months?  His first letter after the marriage, sent from Memphis, and dated June ad, had been received. Any succeeding epistles to that ame address would, in the absence of Madelaine, have found -their   MADELAINE DARTH.            23 way into Mrs. Wilson's hands. What motive could this young hus- band have for this concealment of himself? Turning the photograph over and over in my hand, I brooded upon the subject. The revenue stamp upon the back of the card was canceled with the date May Io, and the initials (,F. H. G." I recollected, with a slight tinge of bitterness, that it was taken but a little while before the probable date of the marriage. As a specimen of photographic art, the picture was very fine. I remembered Mrs. Wilson's remark about the bridegroom having come from .Chicago, and determined to proceed on the conjec- ture that the negative of this picture could be found in some gallery of that city. It was rather an unpleasant matter to write to Mrs. Matte- son and- inform her that we had come to a stand-still--that the trail was utterly lost. But the more unpleasant the duty, the greater need of haste, lest the unpleasantness become unbearable. I wrote and destroyed letter after letter, but late in the night I made a decision. I would go to Owanee, and relate, in person, the discoveries that had been made. After that I would move no more in the matter. What object had I in recalling to Miss Darth's memory the husband she had forgotten? What did it matter to me if he shrouded himself in silence and secresy? In establishing beyond doubt the fact of the marriage, I had learned all I cared to know. Here a thought of Rainey crossed my mind. At any rate she could not marry that boy. I found a sort of consolation in the fact that at his age it was safe to predict his for- getfulness of her in three months' time. Each one -likes to imagine that he alone is capable of constancy. In the morning, however, I received a letter from my business part- ner, which recalled me to Chicago. I was obliged, therefore, to re- count the results of my trip to Whitewater in a brief and concise letter which I dispatched to Mrs. Matteson. Then for a month I buried myself in business, and worked early and late, persistently refusing to allow myself one moment for solitude or reflection. But it is useless to strive against Fate; that which is ordained to be done, will be accomplished. In the moment when I was most deeply    <pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6457-00000014"/> 24         MADELAINE DARTH. engrossed with other matters, when I was most oblivious of the mys- tery I so persistently avoided, it was again presented to me, and the clue once more thrust into my unwilling hand. In the afternoon of an unusually busy^day, my partner and I were discussing a law case. In order to find the address of a certain witness residing in the city, he opened the Directory and glanced through the "G s."  "Grattan, Grayle, Graff-Franz H., Photographer, No. 32 Vale street." The Graff we want is a shoemaker, and his name is Henry. O, yes, here he is-No. 58 Hyde street." All unconscious of the work he had wrought, my companion re- sumed his letter-writing. As for me, I resolved, then and there, to succumb to the irresistible current which seemed bearing me onward to the Land of Discovery. Long had I battled against the strong temptation to examine the Directory for the photographer signing him- self"F. H. G." Yet the knowledge which I had persistently refused to acquire for myself, had been forced upon me by another. From that moment I ceased to struggle against Destiny. I went steadily and surely forward in the appointed path, until the mystery of which I write was dispelled, and all things were made clear to me. The next morning, while I sat smoking and ruminating, the door opened, and Monsieur d'Arteau appeared. Quiet in his manner, and faultless in his dress, he appeared as nonchalant as if we had been parted for moments instead of months. This M. d'Arteau was the chief detec- tive in the great Ambra Browning mystery. For the trquble and per- plexity which weighed so heavily upon my mind, what better confidant could I have than this man? "I am inclined to place more importance than you have done upon the life insurance," he remarked, when 1 concluded my recital of the case. "It looks to me something like the opening scene of a huge swindle on some Insurance Company."  He sat silent a short space, lost in thought. "Come, my friend," he said, "let us arm ourselves with the requisite authority, and search the photograph gallery for a portrait of this mythical Karl."   MADELAINE DARTH.            25 We found Mr. Franz H. Graff, the proprietor of the gallery, to be a young man scarcely twenty years of age. To judge from the languor of his graceful movements, and his slow speech, one would have lo- cated his birth-place in a warmer clime. He showed a slight surprise at the object of our visit, and glanced carelessly at the photograph we presented. Yes," he said, "those are my initials, and it certainly appears like my writing. I dare say it is." He gave the picture back, but seeing the fixed, intent look upon M. d'Arteau's face, he added, with a slight smile, "Surely, I cannot be expected to remember the original of this portrait among all my sitters." "Certainly not," assented M. d'Arteau; and aided by the employ- ees of the gallery, he began the examination of the negatives. Mr. Graff and I stood a little apart from the rest, and he, taking up an Argentotype, began talking of the details of his business in an off-hand style. He spoke slowly, like one abstracted by deeper thoughts. His voice had a lingering cadence in it that inspired in its hearers a pleas- ing melancholy. M. d'Arteau considered' him affected. He con- temned the pensiveness of his manner--the gentle gravity of his face. "He is constitutionally afflicted with a vague regret," sneered M. d'Arteau, in after days. It seemed very improbable that any guilt would be attached to the photographer of the picture of Karl, yet so great an interest had this Mr. Graff inspired in me, that I felt relieved when M. d'Arteau ap- proached to say that the negativei had all been passed in review, but with no favorable result. Mr. Graff expressed his regrets at our fail- ure in his peculiar, gentle voice, and bowed us out. M. d'Arteau, unconvinced and skeptical, made his exit with habitual and politic courtesy. "The fact of that negative not being in the gallery now does not prove that it has never been there," he said, as we stood upon the pavement. As he spoke the last words the solemn tolling of a bell smote heavily upon the-air.    <pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6457-00000015"/> 26          MADELAINE DARTH. "Ah," said M. d'Arteau consulting his watch, "that is tolling for the meeting in honor of the deceased members of the Commercial Battery. I promised to be there." There was quite a stream of people setting in the direction of the Court House, and we joined the current. M. d'Arteau had been pay- master to this battery, and most of the officers and men were his ac- quaintances or friends. My motive in going was merely curiosity and a desire for his companionship. Although the crowd was great we were fortunate enoagh to secure good seats. Slow solemn music surged through the room. Black draperies festooned the walls, and from their crape wreathed portraits above us there looked steadily down upon the swaying crowd those members of the battery who rested "Beneath the low green tent, Whose curtain never outward swings." M. d'Arteau had the rare gift of noticing all accessories without appearing to see aught but the central figure. In the midst of the discourse he slightly changed hisposition, and whispered in my ear. "Look through your eye glass at that second portrait on your left." I was a little chary about owning to my shortsightedness, neverthe- less I put up my glasses and looked. The picture was the enlarged duplicate of the photograph of "Karl" in my vest pocket. For one moment the discovery overwhelmed me and the room seemed to whirl and darken. The next instant I felt as if I had always had a pres- cience of the revelation being made then and there and waited in patient expectation.' The meeting ended and the audience began to disperse. M. d'Arteau recognized and introduced to me the Captain of the Bat- tery. After the usual commonplaces M. d'Arteau asked, carelessly, the names of the originals of some of the portraits around the room, all of whom the Captain knew. "And that second portrait on the left?" asked M. d'Arteau. "That young fellow? His name was Hartzell. He didn't serve long. When we reached Memphis he was detailed for special duty at Headquarters." "And is that the extent of your knowledge?"   MADELAINE DARTH.            27 ' Yes, I did hear something about his death, but really I have for- gotten it. It occurred after the battery left Memphis." "It is rather important to me to know something more about that Hartzell," said M. d'Arteau, musingly. The Captain evinced neither surprise nor curiosity. He glanced over the crowd till his eyes rested on a young man coming toward us, dressed in the uniform of the battery. "Here comes Sleighter, a young fellow who was with Hartzell at Headquarters. I think he can tell you all you want to know." Sleighter was fresh and hearty. A little vain of his well favored person, as was evinced by the jaunty buttoning of his well fitting coat. Very susceptible, as was shown in his notice of the ladies who glided past us. "O yes! I knew Karl Hartzell well. He was one of the best fel- lows that ever lived. I knew him before he entered the service. In fact, he was the cause of my enlisting in this battery. Were you acquainted with him, sir?" "Not at all," answered M. d'Arteau, and smiling faintly either at the abruptness of the question or at the ease and rapidityowith which Sleighter had shifted the conversation from Karl Hartzell to himself and his own history. "I knew something of his antecedents, and was surprised to learn from the crape around his picture that he was dead." "Yes, he died at Memphis. We were clerking together at Head- quarters. One June afternoon a party of some half a dozen of us young fellows were riding out in the country. We had fire arms, and one of the boys, fooling with his piece, accidentally shot Hartzell, who was riding in front. It was a bad business, very bad,"-with a shrug of the shoulders and a saddened face. "We got him back to Headquarters, but he only lived about thirty-six hours." "Were his remains taken home?" "Yes, his brother, or rather his step-brother, came down from Chicago and took charge of the body and the personal effects."    <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6457-00000016"/> 28          MADELAINE DARTH. "Was Hartzell --excuse my questioning; it is not, I assure you, idle curiosity-was he ever married?" "No." "I have reason to believe otherwise." Sleighter looked M. d'Arteau steadily in the face, and for the first time appeared to feel a personal interest-in him. "Indeed," he said slowly and thoughtfully. "I knew him for years before he went to the war. I was with him through his term of ser- vice, till his death. In all that time I never heard him speak of his wife, and never had any reason to suspect that he possessed one. I am pretty certain the step-brother inherited the insurance money." "In what company was Hartzell insured?" 'The Randolph Life. I remember that, because all the witnesses to the shooting of Hartzell were obliged to swear to a written state- ment of the affair, in order to convince the Insurance Company that there was no fraud attempted." "Did you know this step-brother of Hartzell?" "No; he reached Memphis one night, and I was ordered to start o r my regiment next morning." The Captain had sauntered away during this conversation. ' A silent and apparently an uninterested listener, I had heard enough to show me my next step. I bowed to my companions, glanced at my watch and hurried to my office. "ETTER FROM ROGER TIERNAY, ESBQ OF CHCAGO, TO HARVEY &amp; WOOD, AGENTS RANDOLPH LIFE INSURANCE CO., ST. LOUIS, MO. CHCAGO, Oct. 4th, 18-. MESSRS. HARVEY &amp; WOOD, Agts. Randolph Life Insurance Company, St. Louis, Mo. [ eGnts:-I address you in the hope of obtaining some information relative to one Karl Hartzell, who died last June and was reported to have been insured in your company and at your agency for $x1o,oo.   MADELAINE DARTH.               29 In case you had such a policy holder, will you oblige me with all the important items in regard to his insurance, and also the facts concerning the payment or non payment of the principal sum, at the death of the insured. I remain, yours truly, ROGER TIERNAY. Of this as of every fresh complication or revelation in this mystery, I kept Mrs. Matteson promptly informed. She always answered me in faint, illegible little characters, and always spoke of Madelaine. Once or twice she mentioned Rainey, who had opened a drug store and established himself in Quarrytown. That did not trouble me. If I thought anything about it, I thought Rainey, senior, should compel his son to finish his collegiate course. To Madelaine herself I never wrote, simply sending my regards in my letters to Mrs. Matteson.   The first night after I heard of her widowhood I spent the whole night in composing a letter to her which I destroyed at the first daylight reading. Common sense showed how just to both was the enforcement of my silence so long as a vestige of mystery shrouded her life. PART IV. "ETTER FROM HARVEY &amp; WOOD, AGENTS RANDOLPH LIFE INSURANCE CO., ST. LOUIS, MO., TO ROGER TIERNAY, ESQ., CHCAGO. ST. Louis, Mo., Dec. IIth, I8-. ROGER TIERNAY, Es%. Dear Sir: Yours of the zd inst. came duly to hand. Our delay in answering arose from the fact that it required some time to consult our papers relative to the Hartzell loss. We send you a brief summary of the facts and evidence in the case: Karl Hartzell, of Chicago, Ill., clerk, aged twenty-four, was insured in this com- pany on the a9th of May of this year, in the sum of $1o,ooo, for the benefit of his heirs. He was killed, June I2th, by the accidental discharge of a 'pistol in the hands of a companion. The claim for the amount insured was then brought forward by his step-brother, H. F. Graff, of Chicago. The law of Ill. allows no distinction to be made between own brothers and step-brothers in the matter of inheritance. Mr.    <pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6457-00000017"/> '30          MADELAINE DARTH. Graff proved his identity. Hartzell, it was affirmed by reliable witnesses, was an or- phan, was unmarried, and had no fraternal relatives besides this Graff. The Com- pany was satisfied of the justness of the claim, and in four weeks from the date of the presentation of the claim, it was paid. Hoping that our information will prove satisfactory and comprehensive, we remain Truly yours, HARVEY &amp; WOOD. While I was reading and pondering over the epistle from the St. Louis insurance men, d'Arteau came sauntering in. He never seemed to have any pressing business. He was an expert detective; the results of his efforts were perfectly satisfactory, but the efforts themselves were invisible. "Listen, d'Arteau," I said. "Here are the last items in the Hartzell case ;" and I read aloud the letter. "So it was young Graff that grabbed the money," he said, in an acquiescent manner.  "Wcell, daily observation teaches us that the science of swindling is but yet in its infancy." He calmly unfolded the still damp morning paper, and brought to view a fresh column. "D'Arteau," said I, "he must have suspected the object of our visit, and destroyed the negative of Hartzell's picture." "Doubtless," acquiesced d'Arteau, and went on with his paper. When he rose to leave, he adverted to the subject voluntarily: "Come to the Tremont, Tiernay," he said, " and dine with me. Afterwards we will call upon young Graff-the sentimental swindler -the object of your admiration." Having indulged himself in a sarcasm, he retreated in good spirits. Left alone in my office, I recalled the image of young Graff. His delicate beauty, the winning pensiveness of his manner, his quiet, gen- tle voice came vividly to mind. I remembered his manner as we wait- ed for the end of the search among the negatives. Was he veiling the fear of discovery with that graceful courtesy, that languid interest? How calmly he had gazed upon the portrait of the brother by whose death he had profited.   MADELAINE DARTH.            31 We found Mr. Graff as languid and graceful as ever. He invited us to resume our seats, while he himself sank indolently into an easy chair, much as if he were preparing for a sentimental tete-a-tete. His youth and his beauty were more winsome than ever in my eyes. I was determined to believe him innocent, despite all proofs to the contrary. Yet, should he be found guilty, I was disposed to be lenient. "Mr. Graff," I said, my business is very unpleasant to me now, and will ultimately prove so to you." Here M. d'Arteau, who was prospectively enjoying the discomfiture of the exposed swindler, made a slight aside gesture of assent. However indifferent and even abstracted Mr. Graff appeared, he was evidently alive to the most trifling details of the interview, for he saw the action, slight and quick as it was, and moved a little in his chair, so as to command a better view of M. d'Arteau, and waited for me to resume speaking., "I believe," I commence/, "that you had a step-brother named Karl Hartzell, who died at Memphis in June last." He bent his head. The only sign of increased interest was the lifting of the heavily lashed lids from the sleepy brown eyes. "This step-brother's life being insured, upon his decease you re- ceived the principal sum due?" For the second time he inclined his head. "Were you aware, Mr. Graff, that your step-brother was married, and that the insurance was rightfully due his wife?" 'His eyes were fixed full upon mine. His gaze never altered and his face never changed. "I am not prepared," he answered in his peculiarly gentle voice and with his habitual slow, clear enunciation, " to acknowledge what has never been proved." "Mr. Graff, I have seen Mrs. Karl Hartzell. This is her portrait. I have conversed with a Witness to the marriage, and I have received a letter from the clergyman who performed the ceremony." "I hope you found the conversation of the witness entertaining and the correspondence with the clergyman interesting and instructive."    <pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6457-00000018"/> 32          MADELAINE DARTH. His manner expressed nothing but graceful courtesy, but both M. d'Arteau and I felt the concealed satire in the speech. I might have been angered had I not bethought myself that the speaker was but half my age, and smarting under a sense of wrong-doing, and so passed over the words as the petulant utterances of an erring boy. Not so d'Arteau. A slight flush tinged his usually sallow cheeks, and a glitter came into his black eyes. He changed his seat for one directly facing Mr. Graff, and, leaning his arm on the table between them, fixed a steady gaze upon him. "Setting courtesy aside, Mr. Graff," he said, " flippancy at such a time is an insult; and insults, I warn you, are dangerous." There was an instant's silence; then Mr. Graff responded with his usual gentle gravity of speech: "Your words are ambiguous. Insults may be dangerous--not to me, for I never receive them. If the danger comes from the receiver, I never should have suspected it. Thanks for the useless warning." He opened wide his languid brown eyes, and looked at d'Arteau with an indolent scorn, changing to the amused curiosity with which one regards a beast, dangerous but caged. Surprise and anger for the moment sealed d'Arteau's lips. Before/ he 'could rally, I hastened to interpose. s D'Arteau," I said, in an undertone, "I regret that I dragged you into this. Don't stop here to bandy words with an insolent boy. There is nothing to be gained by it." He sat irresolute, raging with speechless indignation. ' Go; I 'It manage this affair, and come to your rooms when it's settled." "D'Arteau's personal dignity was dear to his heart. To the cool impudence of a mere boy what weapon had a man like him to oppose? Making some half audible exclamation in regard to an " insolent young swindler," d'Arteau departed. I seated myself in the chair he had vacated. Mr. Graff showed no emotion. His dreamy eyes met mine in passionless expectation of what was to follow.   MADELAINE DARTH.            33 "Now, Mr. Graff," I began, with the sense of his youth and beauty strong upon me, " we are left alone to talk over this matter calmly and dispassionately. A moment's reflection upon the facts will show you how impossible it will be for you to maintain your present impassive attitude. Here is a statement of the case. Karl Hartzell died sud- denly; you, as his nearest relative, took charge of his papers 'and ef- fects, and came into possession of that sum of money for which his life was insured. The legal title to that money was and is vested in his wife, Madelaine Hartzell. I have a letter from Hartzell, addressed to his wife, dated June zd, in which he speaks of his intention to send her his life policy and the marriage certificate as soon as practicable. It is pretty evident, therefore, that the certificate was among his papers, and after his decease it fell into your hands.- There is, however, other evidence in regard to the marriage-that of the clergyman who per- formed the ceremony, and the witnesses present. Hartzell's photograph has already been identified by those parties." Mr. Graff had been gazing dreamily out of the window into the busy street below. At those last words he turned and looked at the photographs I had laid upon the table. "Great pity Karl died, and got me into such a muddle with that money," he said, musingly.  What is it the beautiful widow requires of me?" "Ten thoasand dollars." "Less three months jinterest at seven per cent.," he said, as quietly as if we were discussing a new poem; "that was the original payment." "Well, yes; I suppose Mrs. Hartzell will be easily satisfied." He retained Madelaine's picture in his hand, looking down intently on the lovely face. "  He told me she was beautiful, but I never imagined such perfect loveliness." ' He!'-who?" "The spy I sent to Owanee and Quarrytown."  Then seeing a look of surprise on my face he added, with indolent wonder, "Do you 3    <pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6457-00000019"/> 34         MADELAINE DARTH. think a man would venture on such a step as mine without knowing facts?" "Then, having knowingly defrauded Mrs. Hartzell of her due for this length of time, what do you propose doing?" He sat silent, with his arm leaning on the table, and resting his chin in the hollow of his hand. His eyes,were downcast, and his face, feminine in its delicacy of feature, was overspread with a tender pen- siveness. His troubles did not seem to distract and perplex him, but only produced a gentle gravity, such as one would feel in contemplating the misfortunes of another. "I have just sold my gallery, and the price of that, together with what ready money I have on hand, will, I think, pay Mrs. Hartzell's claim." "And you,-where will you go? How will you live?" I had made my plans to go to Europe, and study for an artist." "Can you paint?"I asked, in surprise. ' Come and see," he answered. He rose and led the way, with his slow, graceful step, to a studio attached to the reception room. Upon the easel was an unfinished picture. It represented a scene in "cThe Two Gentlemen of Verona"-Launce soliloquizing over his dog, "I think Crab, my dog, be the sourest-natured dog that lives." There were great and obtrusive faults in the work, but the exquisite humor of the scene had been transfixed upon the canvass. The maud- lin earnestness of Launce, and the abashed, humble deprecation of the dog were capitally rendered. It seemed, in its grotesque humor, such a strange subject for the dreamy, poetic artist that I immediately bought the painting as a souvenir of the time and circumstances, paying a price which would, at least, defray the expenses of the artist's trip to Europe. Then we returned to the reception-room, where Mr. Graff paid part of the insurance money, and wrote a check for the remainder. I watched him as he sorted the bills, and leaned over his writing. I tried to account to myself for the sudden and strong liking I had con- ceived for this youth. His beauty won my interest, and his personal   MADELAINE DARTH.  magnetism retained it. He raised his eyes and, meeting my intent gaze, a faint flush tinged the clear dark of his complexion. "Mr. Graff," I said, "this act of fraud seems so antagonistic to your nature, that I have been wondering how you conceived the plan." He dropped his darkly fringed eyelids and trifled with his pen. "It scarcely seemed a fraud to me," he said, thoughtfully. "I found the policy among Karl's papers long before I found the marriage certificate. I had grown to believe the insurance money mine before I had any suspicion of another claimant. Karl having died before I reached Memphis, I had nothing to-guide me in the disposition of his estate. When I became aware that there-was a Mrs. Hartzell, I un- derstood immediately how zealously a man like Karl would guard the secret of his becoming acquainted with her through an anonymous cor- respondence. The insurance claim was even then in the hands or Harvey &amp; Wood. I sent a man to Whitewater, who traced Mrs. Hartzell to Quarrytown and learned her loss of memory. The chances were so many against her ever presenting a claim, that I determined to run the risk." He selected the marriage record from the papers in his pocket-book, and laid it with the check and money; then he again took up Made- laine's picture. "If I were not an unsuccessful swindler bound for Europe, I might have a chance to present this beautiful woman with still another mar- riage certificate. Love is, I suppose, incidental to her acquaintance. No need for me, poor vagrant, to look upon her picture and inoculate myself. " I received back the portrait and rose to go. Without the slightest shadow of doubt or embarrassment in his manner, he extended his slender brown hand. As I held it in mine I ventured a word of advice and encouragement. "Mr. Graff," said I, "you have made and retraced one false step; begin again."    <pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6457-00000020"/> 36          MADELAINE DARTH. He looked in my face with his gentle eyes, and a thoughtful smile came slowly to his lips. He laid his left hand, with a touch light as a woman's, upon my coat sleeve. ", Tiernay," he said, "there are not many men as charitable as you. Had I known you before, I dare say I should never have taken that  step. Good-bye." The setting sun shone -through the western window, defining the oval outlines of his face and the graceful contour of his figure. For one moment I saw him so, and the next I was in the noisy street, and his beautiful face was buried in the Past as in an ocean. I transferred all the papers and funds concerned in this case to Mrs. Hartell, enclosed in a quiet business-like letter, and then set about arranging my affairs so that it would be possible for me to spend a few days in Quarrytown. As the day set for my departure drew near, I found that my courage had lain in procrastination, and, great as was my anxiety to leave, I felt a strange relief at every trifle that tended to slightly postpone my departure. Even while on my way I felt no hurry. I pictured Madelaine in every attitude in which I had seen her. I imagined a hundred different greetings from her. Would she be in the room when I entered, and what would be her occupation  Or would I wait to hear her step in the hall, and the rustle of her dress against the wall? Would she appear pleased or indifferent? Her face, pale, with golden hair straight and silky, and amber eyes, was ever before me. Her quiet, contralto voice, with its lingering cadences, was ever in my ears. There had been a fine snow falling when we left Chicago. Faster and faster fell the tiny flakes upon errth already Covered with like mementoes of the last storm. A fierce wind came sweeping over the open fields, driving the snow before it, and whistling keenly around the rushing train. The wildness of the surroundings seemed to favor the growth of familiar converse among the other travelers. I, however, sat abstracted and alone, thinking of Madelaine-always thinking of her.  *   MADELAINE DARTH.            37 Two men, apparently strangers to each other, sat in the seat in front of me. Suddenly, in the open prairie-a desert of snow-the train came to a stop. One of the men who had been outside came in and, seating himself, turned towards me. I hope every body's business can wait as well as mine," he said. "We can go no farther to-night. We are in a huge drift of snow." He was a man about thirty-eight, dressed in rough business apparel. He had an open-hearted expression oddly contrasting with the air of shrewdness acquired by worldly experience. I set him down in my mind as a well-to-do commission merchant, rather given to Mission Sunday Schools, Homes for the Indigent, and such charitable enter- prises. One casual remark led to another, and finally we turned our seats vis-a-vis, and, to while away the long sleepless hours till day, told stories. It began by my brief version of the Ambra Browning case, in which M. d'Arteau had recently played so conspicuous a part. Then the conversation was resumed by the man who had first addressed me. I * remember some of his very expressions. The next 'day I wrote out the story as well as I could recall it. "I am," he said, "a grain merchant. My friends call me an odd man, because I have a liking for the company and conversation of ragged and uncouth men, the poor wretches whom I encounter on the streets, and whom, by the promise of a warm meal or good liquor, I seduce into the comforts of a restaurant or the charities of my own room. Once comfortably ensconced with these ragamuffins, I manage to draw from them the frightful and sometimes wondrous stories of their lives, which I write down in my book of "Poor Men," and read at times when my soul is heavy with misery. There is a world of wisdom to be derived from these narratives, and thus far I have found in their perusal a panacea for my own woes, so much are they belittled by the comparison. I seek out only poor men's histories; the rich can take care of themselves. I find pleasure as well as pain in thus transcribing these sorrowful stories, revealing, as they often do, more startling inci- dents than are usually conceived by the fertile brains of imaginative    <pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC6457-00000021"/> 38         MADELAINE DARTH. novelists. Because I do these things I am called an odd man, some- times a monomaniac--all of which' I acknowledge. By this little explanation you will understand why I came to know the story of Bob Campbell. "One night, coming out of the theater, I saw a man vigilantly watching the' gutter-rats,' 'roughs' and workmen pushing and crowd- ing out of the gallery exit. He was a thin, haggard, whiskered fellow, with a wild glare in his eyes, hair uncombed, and a liberal sprinkling of shavings over his wrinkled clothes. Leaning against a lamp-post, the crowd, as it surged heavily along, jostled him from his position, and I saw, by his empty coat-sleeve, that his left arm was gone. There -was something peculiar about the man, perhaps the painful eagerness of look and manner he exhibited, that caused me to lounge against the building and wait for resnlts. The crowd dispersed, and the man and I were left together. "Were you looking for some one? I inquired, stepping into the light. His wild eyes scanned my person from hat to boots. ' s Yes,' he answered. ' A friend? "s An old acquaintance,' and he turned away from me. "Stop a minute, I said, seeing his annoyance. I am called a queer fellow, and you must excuse me if I ask you if you would like a good warm supper? "' I am hungry,' he answered, energetically, and moistening his lips with his tongue. "And thirsty?  "'Very t' "You shall have something to eat and drink, upon one condition. Well!' "That you tell me how you lost your arm. "'Are you a detective, mister?' he suspiciously demanded. "No. "'Then I'll go with you, thank you,' and he began to brush the shavings from his clothes, and to clumsily smooth the unkempt hair.   MADELAINE DARTH.,            39 "There was a restaurant close by, where I ordered a substantial meal for my guest. That finished, and with a pitcher of something warm within his reach, he told me the following story, beginning in a moralizing strain, and stopping at times to fill his glass from the pitch er, or to walk the little compartment with a nervous step that seemed to ease his heart a little. I did not interrupt him to question or com- ment on his story, told in a deep bass voice, with a broad accent that made the interview strangely musical. His narrative, pruned of many inaccuracies of expression, began as follows: "If, as I have somewhere read, (and I have read a little,) man's life is made up of accidents, then the history of my life would prove the truth of that assertion,-for I am scarcely out of one trouble, great or small, before another treads on its heels and trips me up. I am a poor man, always have been one; if poverty has any blessings, any salve for the ragged wounds it gives to ragged men and women, I know little or nothing of them. "I have seen women string beads; black and white and red and blue beads, held on a needle for a second, then pushed downwards to make room for more. That is the way the thread of my life has been strung with troubles, and there 's been very little of the pure white among that kind of beads. It's been tawny white and grey white, and jet black, and bruised green, and blue, but little that was pure and unsoiled; no beads of amber, pearl or gold. "  I 'm not complaining; for years of trouble have ruined that mis- erable way of relief. After thirty years ofrconflict with the world, I am like a blind man in a fight; everybody hits me when I do n't see 'em; accidents and incidents bruise body and soul, and I can 't see whence they come or whither they go. What's the use of such a fellow as I am? He 's of no use to any one-not even himself. "You wanted to know   how I lost my arm. Should n't you think that was a pretty bad misfortune.? I count that as one of the dingy white beads of my life; for, though I lost my arm, I saved my life, and I cling to life as if it were full of happiness. This may seem unreasonable, yet it 's natural.  -2\    <pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC6457-00000022"/> 40         MADELAINE DARTH. "If it had n't been for England and Chicago, I do n't think myleft sleeve would be empty. There 's a riddle you can 't guess. No one can guess it who does n't know my whole life; and I 'm the only one who knows its alphabet from A to-well! almost to Z, for I do n't think I 've many more years to live. "Perhaps you 'll not think much of my riddle when the story 's told; but you must n't forget that it cost, me my arm, and you 'd place a big price upon your arm-yes! upon a little bit of your little finger! Mine was a dear adventure, therefore; but, through it I got something I can 't sell; nor can I buy that which went for nothing. I 've said that if it had n't been for England and Chicago I should have what I have not, and should not have what I have-a dangling sleeve. To make this plain I must go back ten years or so, to show how the whole thing happened. "My parents, a buxom, hale and cheerful couple, with a heartiness of life and living that sweetened their food with wholesome flavor, were small farmers in England. They were poor and had six children. Children are the teeth of poverty and bite hard. But my good parents kept cheerful and worked hard, and the teeth stopped biting after a while. My mother used to say that her children kept her alive,; be- cause as long as they were dependent upon her she couldn't give up; and when they became independent she could not get out of the old habits. Anyhow, they had the children, of whom I was the eldest. When I was about twenty-two years old I came to the conclusion that I had milked the cows and held the plow and trampled in its furrows about long enough to prove, that I could n't succeed in life in such a way. It-'s the hardest kind of an existence, this farm-work, and I've always wondered how young men of spirit could endure its dullness when they were working for somebody besides themselves. Shine and storm bring no relief; and finally the boy grows up to be a man, with mighty little spirit, and whose thoughts are all for plowing and sowing the ground, and getting out of it food enough to fill the stomachs of those belonging to him. I thought it would be with me as with my father and his father, and for generations of fathers and sons.   MADELAINE DARTH.            41 "Even now I tan not decide whether I was right or wrong in going to another country. At that time we had lots of stories of how poor people thrived in America; how they had a little ease and comfort in that country before they died. Here and there I had managed to save a little money, and I resolved to leave the home folk and go to Amer- ica, believing that I should not fail of success. The old people had children to comfort and care for them while I was gone. Ah! those were grand hopes of mine! And you see me, now! "It was all arranged among ourselves; and father, out of his little savings, gave me money which I was to return to him if I got along finely in my new home. But I did not intend to set out on this long and lonesome journey without taking with me, as my wife, a little fair- haired lass; as modest and industrious a girl as could be found in the country. This lass was Bessie Tillott. One day I spoke out my love. ' Bessie, dear, will you go to America with me? Do you love me enough 'for that?' "She put her arms about my neck and looked up into my face with her great hazel eyes. "'Robert,' she said, I will go with thee anywhere, and be glad all the time.' Then she kissed me. "' But, Bessie, girl, I 'm poor, you know. And there 's the great ocean to be crossed. When that's betwixt us and the old folks, we 'll be among strangers, and have much to suffer. There 's hard work to be done, and worst of all, there's tearful loneliness and home-sickness. Eh! Bess, can you bear hunger in many a way?' "' Try me! I 'll go with thee, Rob, and help thee all I can, and be a good wife.' I knew she was as true as steel. "One night, going home from a visit to Bess, I met Tom Brinton. He was waiting for me at the big elm just by the turn in the road. An idle fellow, given to beer-drinking and low companions, he had more money than any one in his station of life. Where he got his money was uncertain. Learned in horses and jockeying, he had a knack of tickling the pride of owners of nice nags in the neighbor- hood. He -was not a handsome fellow by any means; but his smart I'    <pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6457-00000023"/> 42-         MADELAINE DARTH. ways and speeches made him a favorite with many of both sexes. The way I came to know him was because we lived within a mile of each other and met on the highway and at country fairs and frolics. I had seen him, too, a half dozen times at Tillott's house during pre- vious years. I had never liked, only endured him, knowing him as a very muscular fellow, a good wrestler and no mean player with his fists; in fact, a bully, as you call that kind of a man in this country. He was sitting on a log by the road-side. "' Good-evening, Bob,' he said, as I came opposite him. 'Going away soon, I hear.' "'A fortnight hence,' I replied, not stopping in my walk. Seeing this, he jumped up from the log and came after me. "'Stop, Bob,' he commanded. 'Stop! I 've something to say to you; and I wart to say it to-night, now, because I 'm going away in the morning.' "' Well, what is it?' I said, stopping. ' i'm in a hurry.' "' Yes, yes! And you are truly going to Anerica?' he asked once more in a musing sort of a way, and looking at me from toe to head. 'And-and-confound you! is Bess going with you?'-angrily. {"Yes.' ' Do you know, Bob Campbell, that I loved that girl, that I love her now? and she said '- "'There, there, do n't tell me your secrets!' I cried, with a wish to get peaceably away from the fellow, who, it was plain to me, had  been drinking. "'But I will tell thee. Why not listen quietly until I 've done. I loved her and told her so. And she refused me; but she did not tell me she loved you. That I found out yesterday. She threw me off for that baby face and the few pounds you've begged or-' "' Stop!' I commanded, pushing him away from me. II 'll hear no more such vile stuff,' and I walked off. But I had not gone three steps when I felt his arms clasped: around my waist, holding my arms close to my side.   MADELAINE DARTH.             43 "'You shall hear me, curse you!' he shouted, close to my ear. 'I 've waited for you, to tell you that I hate you-hate you because you 're going to take away from me the only woman on earth I can love. You needn't try to get away. Be still, or .',11 kill you. So long as I live you will have an enemy. You 'd better remember that.' "Just then I heard the rumbling of a wagon coming towards us. He heard it, too, and for a moment stood and listened. Then with an oath, he suddenly whirled me around and struck me three heavy blows full in the face with his huge fist, knocking me senseless to the ground. When I opened my eyes again a farmer, a neighbor of ours, had my head on his knee, and was wiping the blood from my face; the rascal had given me one blow that had cut open my cheek, and left a mark until this' day. Tom Brinton had run like a deer across the fields, the farmer said. Anyhow, that was the last seen of him in the neighborhood as long as I remained. Bess and I were married and came to America as happy and loving a couple as ever crossed the waters. When I landed in New York my pocket was picked of all my money-the few pounds I had saved to buy me a little land-and I was friendless. It was an awful time that followed, sir." The poor fellow seemed overcome by the memory. The-perspira- tion beaded his forehead, his eyes filled with tears, and he nervously fingered the glass that still contained a few drops of liquor. Then, with a determined effort showing itself in his compressed lips, with a gulping noise in his throat and a dash of his arm across his face, he struggled with his feelings to continue the story. "After this misfortune, I tried to obtain work. Now and then I got a job that gave me enough to buy us a little food. But what could I, a farmer and a farmer's son, do in a great city that needed artisans, not farmers? It was a hard and bitter struggle for life. I had just got a place as porter, at good wages,' when-when-my dear, darling Bessie-when she-she died." His groans and tears and sighs mastered his firmness, and he bowed his head upon the table. I could understand the loneliness of his life,  and that the dead wife was a being worshipped above all else in the    <pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6457-00000024"/> 44  .MADELAINE DARTH. " world. It seemed so cruel of me to obtain from my guest so sorrow- ful a story, to recall memories so pregrant with keen, undying grief, that I placed my hand on the head of the weeper, and tried, by words of sympathy and of cheer, to lead him away from the sad,-story of his life and leave it untold. But after a little while he raised his head, the face white and the eyes tearful. "You must excuse me this weakness," he said. "It is nothing new. I suffer every day, as now. I can not forget my darling. Only when I 'm dead will the trouble end, and the heart-ache stop, and the tears be unshed. It does n't seem right,- perhaps, for a poor man to nurse his sorrow for sou many years. Yet, many a man does it, and no one knows it but himself. One can not forget the happiness and mis- ery of the past; the memory of them grows upon him like a cloud. I ask God that it may soqn end." For a little while he was silent, his eyes closed and his lips moving as if in prayer. "After Bessie's death," he continued, with a shudder, "I took to liquor just to stop thinking, to have an easy spell. But I only made matters worse, and finally, after a touch of the tremens, I went on board ship and sailed to Cape Town in Africa. It was five years be- fore I got back to America. I was tired of sailing and of life; but not having the cowardice to commit suicide, though I was always wishing myself dead, I struggled along as of old, to get my daily bread. Drifting hither and thither, working a week in one place, a month in another, I finally brought up as a laborer in an elevator in Chicago. It is not nice work, I must say; but one grows to be proud of the great things that dot the wharves along the nasty creek. To me an eleva- tor always seemed a monster, restless with a hungry life; and we poor fellows did nothing but tend to its wants, running up stairs and down stairs, through clouds of choking dust, and deafened with the din of rattling machinery-no little job, sir, I can assure you, seeing, that an elevator is seven, eight, ten stories high, and big enough,to hold the houses of a small village. Ah, they are wonderful things, those eleva- tors And now that I am away from them I feel the strength of their   MADELAINE DARTH.            45 size, and what a little thing I was in such a place. Then, the rattle of the cups going up or down with their fill of grain made music to my ears, and started miany a queer thought in my mind as I went through my hours of day or night work. It was strange to see how quick their armies of banded cups would drink to emptiness a car or vessel loaded with grain, and carry it up to giddy hights to be tumbled into huge bins. These bins, sir, are forty to sixty feet deep, and funnel-shaped at the bottom, where there is a sort of valve or, gate which, when opened, lets the grain into a spout. If the gate is opened when a bin has six or seven thousand bushels in it, you can judge, sir, that there would be a whirlpool that would suck down the strongest man to a horrible death. Wonderful, terrible monsters are these elevators, with their humps of houses on their roofs, their awkward spouts, their dizzy hights, and dismal, dusty chasms of empty bins. It makes me sick to think of them now."  The man really did look a little whiter in the face, and nervously fingered the empty sleeve of his jacket; but he was over with the feeling in a minute, and went on with his story: "I had been at work about a week in one of the largest of these elevators, when, one afternoon, I was sent, in company with another laborer-a big, whiskered, swearing, ruffian fellow-to tend to a bin that 'was about to be emptied. We were sitting on the edge of the bin, waiting for the grain to run, when my companion, who seemed to be under the influence of liquor, called out: ' I say, Mike!' As I have said, the fellow was a ruffian'in appearance. He seemed to have quite a liking for me, as he tried to be with me in my work as much as possible; but I could n't bear him, and did everything to be rid of him. He knew my name well enough,.and it angered me to have him call me in this way ; so I said, sharply, "My name is not Mike!' "' How should I know?' he asked, looking angrily into my face, as if he wished to make me quarrel with him.    <pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC6457-00000025"/> "         MADELAINE DARTH. "' You have heard it more than once,' I said. ' You know very well what it is, Joe, and there 'a no sense in giving a man a name as does n't belong to him.' "'Then do n't call me Joe! That ain't my name. It's a coun- terfeit. I 'm Tom, which is a better name.' ' "He had a piece of chalk in his hand, and began to print with it on the big beam where we were sitting. T-o-m, T-o-m, T-o-m, he scratched in large, scraggy letters, all the while looking at me from under his heavy eyebrows. Then he made a B, and rubbed his hand across it as soon as it was made. "Bob, it's a long way down there,' pointing into the half-filled bin. "Twenty feet, perhaps.' "s' T would n't kill a man, the fall, eh?'-moving closer to me. , c No.' " s But it's as good as water to drown him if' the grain be moving and the dust and chaff flying?' "' He would n't live long, that is sure!' ,c c Then go down there!' he yelled, giving me a blow and a push that hurled me headlong from my seat. 'Go down there! stay there! die there! rot there! Bob Campbell; and do n't forget, when you're a-dying, that Tom Brinton sent you.' "The fall did n't hurt me a bit, and I began to crawl toward the rope-ladder hanging against the side of the bin, thanking God that the grain had n't begun to move, else I 'd be a dead man in no time. But as soon as the ruffian saw what I wasafter, he went round and pulled up the ladder. "C Let that alone!' 1 shouted, feeling how little hope of escape I had with the ladder out of my reach. He laughed and flung the ropes over a beam. "'D Do you mean to murder me?' I cried. "' c No! I'm going to leave you there, Bob. You've fallen in, you see. That 'll be the verdict when they find your body. You'l1 want   MADELAINE DARTH.           47 your shovel, man, to make the thing look natural. I 'll throw it to you'in a minute.' "I felt quite sure that it was so dark in the bin that he could n't see me very plainly, if at all; and that he would try to hit me with the shovel. I crawled close to the side with one cheek against the wood; looking up I could see him directly above me, peerirn down into the gloom, and with the shovel in his outstretched arm ready to spear at me as if I were a fish. There:followed a stillness that continued for five minutes, during Which he stood on his guard. Suddenly I heard the muffled rattle of machinery and felt a strange power pulling at my feet, while my whole body seemed to be sliding gently down a bottomless pit. In an instant I knew what was happening. "The grain was running. "I madly flung out my arms, and my fingers clutched one of the upright beams. As I drew myself up against the receding torrent I heard a laugh above me and the words, "' Remember Bessie Tillott, Bob Campbell, and that I loved her, and the words I spoke to you by. the big elm! Good-bye!' "When I looked up the man was gone from my sight. I do n't know exactly how 1 managed to climb that huge beam. I think there were nails Mere and there that helped my feet and hands; for after I was rescued my body vas found to be covered from head to foot with great gashes or scratches. Anyhow, slowly and painfully I managed to reach the top, and threw my left arm over the edge of the ban, and gasped for breath. Then, when 1 was so near to safety, to hope, to life, I felt a horrible, sickening blow upon my arm-a blow from something neither dull nor sharp. I seemed to feel the catting of the flesh and to hear the breaking of the bone. The arm, battered and broken, lost its grasp and 1 fell back into the darkness and horror of the bin. Hardly had I touched the yielding wheat when my shovel was thrown from above and struck within a few inches of my head. Though my arm hurt me terribly I didn't faint. I was helpless. The dust was stifling. The grain was whirling and tumbling and hiss- ing as it slid toward the vortex a few feet distant. I heard the murmur    <pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC6457-00000026"/> 48          MADELAINE DARTH. of machinery in motion and the rushing sound of the wheat as it poured into the spout. Where I lay the grain had not yet begun to move into the little whirlpool; but I knew it would only be a minute or two before I should be tossing and struggling in that treacherous quicksand, and then, stifled, mutilated and dead, at the spout. The dust seemed to circle above me and leave me a little air to gasp. "Lying thus, hopeless and helpless, a carelessness of death came upon me. My life came to me again in all its details, its joys and sor- rows.' I had visions of green fields, and heard the soft gurgle of brooks and the songs of birds and the rustling of leaves. Then Bes- sie's sweet face, as it was when we were married, smiling and pretty with dimples, seemed to be above and close to mine, as if waiting for a kiss as in the olden time before she was taken from me. I forgot all else but her face. I had only a consciousness that I was going to her, that she was waiting for my release that she might go with me on the last great journey. It seemed as if the great Relief would never come and give me to my darling. "I must have been growing unconscious, I think, for a sudden throb of pain in my arm robbed me of my wife's face and brought back the old feeling of resistance against death. I felt that I was going down- ward, gently, but irresistibly; that every grain beneath me was moving and shifting and slowly descending. The circle of the whirlpool had reached me, and was dragging me down to torture and to death. I could not, IPvould not submit to such a death. I must live. It was horri- ble agony of soul and body, sir. I screamed for help; but the dust entering my mouth, nose and eyes, strangled and blinded me. I looked for the shovel. -It had disappeared. I was going, too. Maimed, and gasping for breath, I fought against the power that was slowly, but surely, dragging me down. I plunged my arm deep into the wheat and tried to pull myself up. In the dismal, murky light of this hid- eous den I struggled as but few men have ever struggled. I was a giant in my battle for life. I thought no more of my broken arm. I was burning with heat, parched with thirst, blinded and choked with the fine dust, but I fought and shrieked, for help all the time. In my   MADELAINE DARTH. " fierceness I tore my clothes fProm my body and flung them away, and the grains of wheat scraped my wounds and piercd  my naked flesh as I tried to spring forward; but nothing hurt me, not even my arm "Hard as I struggled I could not get clean away from the whirl- pool. if I leaped forward, or crawled a little way over the treacher p ."y over the treacher- ous surface, I found when I stopped that I was swiftly sliding back again to the old place. It seemed as if I struggled in this way for hours; yet, I accomplished nothing. Tired and breathless, 1 looked around and felt sure that in less than three minutes I should be in the Spout and a' dead man. My efforts were in vain. There was a cer- tain circle beyond which I could not go. Once the thought came into my mind that, to save myself from the horrors of the death before me, I had better open a vein and bleed to death; but I could not find my knife, and had I found it I might not have been able to use it. Well! I saw everything plainly. There was no hope for me. I must die; and must look and wait for death. When hope deserted me, a kind of resignation to my fate succeeded, and I closed my eyes wearily, never thinking to open them again. "Gradually my body slid downward.  The noise of the grain rushing through the valve or gate became louder and louder; the sti- fling dust was thicker and heavier. A thousand unseen, irresistible forces were drawing me to destruction. Suddenly, my body fell sev- eral feet. I felt the tremendous suction of the whirlpool. The grain crept up my legs; it reached and pressed heavily upon my breast and back as if to squeeze the life out of me; it ascended higher and clasped my throat. Then I closed my eyes and waited for death. I no longer feared its terrors. "At this moment I felt that there was a strange silence; even in my half-conscious condition I realized a change in my surroundings. The dust began to settle. I realized what had happened. "The valoe was closed. "sAt te very gate of death opened to receive me, there was an ob- stacle, and I fainted away with joy. When I became conscious again I heard a voice crying out. 4    <pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC6457-00000027"/> MADELAINE DARTH. "Is anybody down there?' said this voice. That question was twice repeated' before I could answer, and then so faintly, that it was but a husky whisper We " It's all a humbug, a false alarm, Jim,' said another voice  are fooling away time by traveling up and down these twenty stories We can 't stop work for such nonsense.' ' It 's not a humbug,' said the one who had first spoken. sYou saw, as well as I, the shovel, and hat, and shirt come through the spoutl There's a man to follow, this way or that. Hillo, there! e It seemed to me as if I had the nightmare, so hard did I try to speak out, but I didn't make a noise. Yet, when I heard them going away, leaving me to my horrible death, the noise in me got the better of my throat, and I yelled so that myself was frightened The men came back. "'I knew he was there,' said Jim. 'Are you hurt, man? Of 'I knew he was the      o.  Whrethe sed, is the leadder course he is, or he would n't be there. Where the devil is the ladder? That looks strange--it 's hanging over the beam. Give me the rope and lantern!' "I saw the light, a blessed star of relief, come slowly down against the wall of the bin. A little later I was raised, as tenderly as possible, to the top of the bin and thence carried to earth. A surgeon was soon obtained. He looked at my arm that was making me cry with pain. Mortification.  Amputation,' was the judgment, and the arm was cut off'. That is all,' said my guest, drinking his liquor and rising from his scat. e, 'And what has become of Tom Brinton?' I asked, as he reached the door. ,' I am looking for him,' he answered, with the old ugly look about the eyes and mouth, and he stalked out of the door into the night.' There was a little silence between us after the grain merchant ceased speaking. His seat-mate was a little old gentleman with gray hair and a very amiable face, reminding me of. the last pippin ripening alone in the autumn sunshine.   MADELAINE- DARTH.            5  "Did you believe the man's story?" he inquired, with an effort to appear easy. "O yes," said the grain merchant. "Stranger things than that have happened." "To be sure.  Certainly. To be sure," assented the little old man, and he' began to rub his hands with such a cordial, unselfish air that I immediately felt as if his rubbing them was a personal kindness to myself. Speaking of strange things, I had a manuscript donated yesterday to our library, which was very curious. I am State Librarian. Bless me," he ejaculated, tugging at his coat skirts, "mypockets are loaded. Perhaps, sir," he added, "'you and this gentleman would be gratified to hear it. You," he added, to me, "are a lawyer; perhaps you would  read it aloud. Public reading is more in your way, although this is not a brief, being some sixty pages." I am quite sure he meant this as a joke. There was not much wit in it, but he looked at us with such genial expectation, such unalloyed admiration of his own facetiousness, that the grain merchant and I both smiled, exchanged glances, and I began to read. I was often obliged to pause and examine words, for the manuscript was old and the writing was quaint and hieroglyphic, like that of one accustomed to translating Arabic characters or Egyptian inscriptions. THE MUMMY'S SOUL. It was high noon, and fresh, luxuriant life without, and the darkness of mid-night, and the dead, within this Egyptian tomb- hollowed out of the Libyan chain of mountains. Two hundred feet above me,- massive ruins, half-buried beneath the yellow, glittering sands of the desert, were revealed as the skeleton of a city of gigantic wonders. Now, Thebes was not so desolate. The sculptured faces of collossi gazed with stern, tearless eyes over the dreary waste, as if in mockery of the frailty of cotemporary creations. Around me were mummies, sculptures, and rough paintings on the walls. .Life and death here    <pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC6457-00000028"/> MADELAINE DARTH. touched each other, and were identified by the reality of mutual exist- ence. A humanity of forgotten ages, by its ashes, preached sermons of profoundest truths in stopendo'us charnel-houses. Yet I asked myself, in a spirit of unbelief of such truths, if the oracles of Egyptian my- thology spoke falsely when they asserted that the soul, after three thousand years of pilgrimage to other shrines, would re-invest the bodies of the dead with new life? A startled bat flew in and out of an empty tomb, and an angry scorpion clickid his armor-plates as he crept along the ledge of one of the crypts above me.' A faint puff of air from the passage filled my nostrils with the sickening effluvia of mummies, and scattered the, dust from the carvings of the pillar. I was in a casket of Death, and the jewels were mummies. Dead for centuries, yet alive in everything but life; lacking only a breath of that life to cast off the swathing-cloths and confront me  The thought of seeing them step from the tom in the hideousness of such a resurrection, made me shudder. Yet, if their doctrine of a renewal of life after thirty centuries were to proe true, there might at any moment be a resurrection, and a con- sequent paroxysm of terror on my part. What if I should be attacked, as I threaded intricate passages in this birth-place of antique horrors, by mobs of these resurrected Egyptians, infuriated by the sacrilege of my presence? The mere idea of encountering their shriveled forms in deadly struggle, and wrestling for victory with entwined limbs, while their crisp hair; odorous of the crypt, brushed my face a these oish romptings of an imagination excited by my strange surroundings, together with a shuffling noise in a distant passage, caused me to drop my torch and rush to the entrance of the tomb, where I stood quiver- ing with fright, not knowing which way to turn. my guide, was the comer; else, in the darkness and sickening solitude, I should have become mad. The tomb in which I stood had been discovered the previous day. It consisted of one large chamber with heavy arches, a massive pillar in the centre, and with three tiers of niches on each side, the fronts   MADELAINE DARTH.            53 being ornamented with outline paintings of a brilliant red color. The ponderous carvings of the pillar were merely heavy lines of sculpture, with no delicacy of outline, no airy gracefulness to mar the effective- ness of their stupendous symmetry. Every curve and straight line on' pillar and tablet was harsh, rigid, and even cruel in its expression of power.' The rough granite had been carved, in many cases, into crude and intricate delineations of human pageantry, by the ready skill of the patient artist. Yet the hands that had cut and painted, day after day, in the service of cunning priest or mourning relative, had dropped the chisel-and the brush thousands of years before, leaving outlines of works to be memorials of undeveloped grandeur. Many of the niches in the tiers had been despoiled of their con- tents. One only remained untouched ; upon its tablet was painted, in rich colors, a lotus-flower broken at the blossom. There was no in- scription upon the tomb to designate its occupant; no legendary engrav- ing of his or her life's events. The cement around the edges of the tablet was as hard as the rock in which the tomb was cut. A half- hour's labor with a crow-bar had but meagre result; so I placed a quantity of powder under the lower edge of the stone, where a small cavity had been made with the bar. There was a hissing noise as the fire ran up the'fuse, followed by a dull sound of explosion that was immediately hushed and smothered by the dead silence of the passages without. The slab with its painting fell to the ground and was shattered. Within the niche thus opened was a mummy-case, containing a mummy bandaged from head to foot in fine linen, and lying upon a bed of crumbling flowers.  I reproached myself, in a sorrowful, musing mood, for such a sacrilege, when I found it was the body of a woman. But a sickening, musty odor from the corpse spread its subtle essences throughout the chamber, and stealing to the brain intoxicated it. I seemed to see, in this momentary inebriation of the senses, the body of this mummy snap its cerements, and slowly recede through the rocky walls, which closed not after it; while it floated, in plain sight, down a passage in the mountain, bordered by rows of tombs, l    <pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC6457-00000029"/> MADELAINE DARTH. one above another.. And out of these 'graves of stone stretched ban- daged arms of tawny-skinned mummies, whose fingers vainly clutched at the phantom, as, motionless in features and limbs, it glided down the terrible aisle, and was lost in the gloom. The agony of the vision was over. My forehead was covered with a cold perspiration, and my eyes ached with the fierce heat that had created the appalling vision; while white flames of light seemed, now and then, to mingle with the darkness of the corridor. I looked behind me. Ferraj sat cowering upon the ground, with his hands covering his face. Ferraj!" , Howadji! Brave Sidi!,did you not see the body move and motion with its hands  Did it move away into the darkness?" he cried, seizing my hand. "O; course not, you foolish fellow. Is it not there in the case  It is impossible for the dead to come to life." I laughed feebly to put him in good spirits; but he was not at all re-assured, and I noticed that, while we remained in the tomb, he stood at a distance from the mummy, holding his torch like a sword, as if to parry a blow from unseen hands. In profound awe, and with a delicate touch, I unwrapped the face of the body. A woman's features, black and shriveled, were revealed. I was startled-even sickened-at the hideous revelation. For an instant I had forgotten my situation and its surroundings, and remem- bered only an occasion when I turned back the coffin-lid, and gazed for the last time upon the face of my dead sister. I thought, in my reverie over this mummy, of a lovely face and fair features like mar- ble. Imagination had never conjured up so shocking a vision. But my zeal as an antiquary suppressed delicate dreams and disagreeable realities. This woman might have been handsome in the era in which she existed; she was, perhaps, considered as the possessor of great beauty. She was very short, slight, with a low forehead; thee cheek- bones were high, but not prominent, and the nose delicate and small; the eyes, the windows to a woman's soul, were closed in a sleep of   MADELAINE DARTH.            55 centuries. Her hair was black, curled and somewhat faded. Her mouth was small, exquisitely formed, and the lips were devoid of any heaviness of curve to mark the tincture of Ethiopian blood. But the dark, parchment-like skin, wrinkled and rough, made me loathe the corpse, and to wonder at the love that thus burned out beauty by slow consuming fires of subtle chemistry, and laid away the shell of the soul that it might once more be re-invigorated with a life that in its wanderings had animated beast, bird, or insect, and acquired strength at each succeeding transmigration. As I unwrapped the long bandage from the breast, a strong gust of wind rushed from the desert into the dim crypts of the mountains. It flared the expiring torches, scattered dust from pillar and niche, and caused the mummy to crumble into a nauseous powder that half choked me with its subtle essence of hu- manity. From a mass of beads and shreds of cloth I picked out a stone searalbaes, on whose back was engraven many minute hiero- glyphics. I succeeded in translating the following: "Three thousand years hence, a new life." So the prophecy had been refuted, and dust returned to dust, I said to myself. But the doubt whether the resur- rection predicted would not reform this dust into a re-created body, intruded itself, and strengthened the imagination, which hoped it would 'be so. In the crypt, at the head of the body, I found a tiny vase of green, translucent stone, of antique form, embellished with exquisitely carved devices. From either side sprang a serpent, which extended up with light, graceful curves, until with its hideous fangs it indented the deli- cate rim of the vase. It was so fragile that it seemed as if a touch from the most careful fingers would crush it to atoms. I accidentally inverted it, and there fell upton the floor a quantity of light, fine ashes, and an insect of enormous size. It lay upon the ground, at my feet, with outstretched wings. Ferraj stooped down and, taking it in his hand, gazed upon it a minute, his lips quivering, and his hand trem- bling so much that his torch almost fell to the ground. "Efrit! Efrit! a foul devil!" he shouted, and cast the thing from him into the remains of the mummy. Picking it up, I examined it *     <pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC6457-00000030"/> 56     .    MADELAINE DARTH. carefully, but with an indescribable loathing that seized me whenever I saw the vile thing. It was a fly, six inches long, with a head the size and shape of a pea, and appeared like a globule of liquid silver. Its small white eyes sparkled with the brilliancy of a diamond, and projected slightly from the head. The body was elastic, and of a bright golden color, encircled at regular distances with bands of green. Its long, delicate, --many-jointed legs were adorned with a fine yellow hair. Its wings were broad sheets of beauty-traceries of golden lines, shadows of deep blackness -gorgeously embellished, where veins of silver hue tinged the edges, with a net-work of marvellous loveliness. These labyrinths of delicate colors so merged into one another that the eye wearied in striving to find where one hue ended and another com- menced. The-brilliancy of color had not been dimmed by the death of the insect, but was revealed in all its glory. From the sharp-point- ed tips of these wonderful wings hung tiny tassels of finest hair, filled with the dust in which it had been buried. Notwithstanding its diver- sity of colors, and wondrous construction, it was hideously deformed; for springing out of the very centre of the front of-its head, lay coiled a fine elastic antenna of blood-red color. Upon seeing it, my admira- tion changed to disgust. A shudder of terror ran over me when, with a sharp click, the extended antenna slipped from my fingers and struck the head. Ferraj had stood apart from me during this examination; but when he saw my movement, and heard the sharp sound as the coil flew back, he uttered a low moan. The remarkable elasticity of the insect convinced me that it had been embalmed in the vase in a fluid. The ashes might or might not have formed a part of an embalming mixture. Every thing about, the insect was flexible and moist, as if life had just gone out. I could not conjecture its use when alive, or what it symbolized when dead. The insect fascinated me, not simply=by any hitherto unknown pecu- liarity of structure, nor by the brilliant appearance of its eyes,- but as a whole; even the loathsome helmet upon its head was an essential in the fascination. I hated myself for yielding to the feeling that in after   MADELAINE DARTH.            57 days grew into an intense passion, and a pride in'the possession of so wonderful a creation. I gathered one or two handfuls of the mummy's dust, and put them with the fly, i..to the vase, and left the tomb, dispirited overcome by the sensations experienced and the discoveries I had made. I had not the heart to farther prosecute my investigation among the tombs, and almost- immediately departed for America. I often exhibited my mementoes to friends; the ladies, aclnowl- edging the wondrous magnificence of the insect, almost invariably de- clared it to be the most treacherous thing they had ever seen and inveighed most bitterly against a judgment that selected such abortions as mementoes of my sojourn in Egypt. But mywife--my young and beautiful good angel-became terribly fascinated with this insect. I did not discover this slavery of her mind until after many months; even then, by becoming suddenly cog- nizant of having found it in her hands upon many occasions, it occurred to me that she might be enthralled by this creature. When I accused her of it, she burst into tears, and acknowledged the truth of my accu- sation; saying, in a piteous, apologetical strain, "that the fascination of the pretty thing was- so irresistible, and at the- same time reminded her so strongly of my long absence in foreign countries, that she could not avoid dwelling in thought upon the strange scenery and discoveries that had kept me from her, and of contemplating the only memento of such an absence." Then, for the first time, I told her of the occur- rences in the tomb. When I had concluded, she clasped her pretty little hands, and said: "Fred, this insect attracts me as it attracts you; Only that with my submission to its thraldom is allied a premo- nition that it will work me a fearful injury. I have repelled the idea again and again, but it always returns. I strive to be philosophical and treat it as a frenzy, but there is no relief." Thereafter, in company, we used to pass hours in contemplating the antipathetic features of this fly, and in conjecturing what part it acted in the economy of nature, when it winged the air among people whose existence was almost forgotten. These examinations intoxicated our    <pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC6457-00000031"/> 58          MADELAINE DARTH. imaginations, by the antiquity and mystery surrounding the object of our investigation. We clung more to each other by reason of our ser- vility to this incomprehensible influence of the fly. We were not un- happy, but simply uneasy; never striving, after a couple of months, to throw off the bondage. If this were the termination of the history, I would weep for joy. But it is at this particular point of time that the insect, hitherto quiet, plays its active part in a tragedy to which there is no parallel. One evening, in making an experiment, I had occasion to use a mix- ture of ammonia and ether, and had prepared it in a saucer, when I was suddenly called from the house, leaving the compound upon the table, in the dish. When I returned, late in the evening, I ascertained that a servant had emptied the contents of the saucer into a vase. It never occurred to me to ask what vase she meant; as there were sev- eral in the room, it surely was one of them, and I gave no thought to the matter. The bed-room opened into the study; the two rooms were separated by a partition of lath and plaster, and the door at night always stood open. About half-past twelve o'clock my sleep was broken in a quiet, unaccountable way that is often the precursor of danger. Every fac- ulty was fresh and keen, and unusually active. Listening, my ear sud- denly caught a faint sound of music, whose delicate strains floated softly toward me from a corner of the bed-room; then, with the rapidity oj lightning, there burst upon me a delicious, maddening flow of measure after measure of passionate symphonies. They flowed in from the study, and 'beat the stagnant air to-and-fro until every particle became a bell that tinkled sweetest melody. This music was so sweet, yet so fierce; so gentle in its cadences, yet so vigorous in its utterances; so peaceful, yet so thrilling, that the room trembled with the reverbera- tions. A delicious languor possessed me. There was a profound silence for a minute. 'Then, just above my face, there was another outhreak of this wild melody, these chiming echoes. My wife moaned, and in her restlessness her hand fell upon my face.   MADELAINE DARTH.            59 My thoughts had been so absolutely controlled by the weird, soul- less music, that the touch frightened me; it was as if a hand had been put forth from the thick darkness and laid upon my forehead. But the alarm, soon repulsed by calm reason, was succeeded by another shock, less sharp and sudden, but more lasting, and full of subtle terrors and keen agony. The hand of my wife was dry, feverish and shrunken, as if a quick, consuming fever had burned out its freshness and left beneath the parchment-like skin the hot ashes of its previous beauty. She moaned feebly when I passionately called her name. I pressed my lips to her face; it was as terrible as her hand. Alarmed at her incomprehensible silence, and at the swift, silent change manifest to my touch, I lighted the candle. She was lying upon her side, looking at me with eyes so senseless in expression,. so devoid of life or brilliancy in their idiotic fixedness, that the unexpected, terrible transformation, more grievous because of its hopelessness, touched my heart like the keen edge of a knife. I wept. As I moaned and cried in my hopeless agony, her rough, hot hand once more rested upon my face, as if to express, feebly though it were, her sympathy for my affliction; though she could not appre- ciate the bitterness of my agony, she comprehended, dreamily without doubt, that a sorrow had fallen upon me. With a cry of joy at this manifestation of her intense love, I clasped her in my arms; but the hope that had suddenly sprung up in my heart was cruelly crushed to death, for she lay in my arms a passive, undemonstrative being, with swift pulsations of the hot blood that scorched the delicate skin until it was like fine parchment.. But while I was suffering most intensely, while my brain grew delir- ious under this desolation of my love-this mysterious, maddening affliction-I heard, with inexpressible fear, the wild, varying music. My wife trembled violently at the u-ound of the clear, ringing notes. Every second was affecting her appearance, developing a woman whose features were shriveled and brown; the eyes, once animated by holiest ove, were cold, passionless, and fixed in a soulless gaze. She lost all    <pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC6457-00000032"/> 60          MADELAINE DARTH. volition, and sunk into a dreadful apathy. In every thing but form and face, she resembled the mummy in the tomb. Hitherto my mind had been paralyzed by terror and grief. Now, it was recovering from its shock. I implored my wife to tell me the cause of her illness, to speak to me/; and I put my ear close to her lips, to catch the faintest whisper. But the musical hum in the study was the only sound I heard. Frantic with the thought that my delay might hasten her death, I summoned a physician, who, after much delay, dared not pre- scribe. Another one was sent for; he had never heard or read of so strange a case. He prescribed brandy to stimulate the blood, which was fast becoming sluggish, and said that he could do no more. It was after he had gone that, in bending over my wife, I saw sev- eral small spots of blood upon the pillow. Back of her left ear was found a spot where the skin was a little broken, as if by the prick of a pin, and from which blood slowly oozed. I was still stooping over her, and the servants were chafing her hands and feet and giving the stimulant, when suddenly the mysterious music thrilled the air. My wife shuddered at the sound, and the women rested from their labor to gaze upon each other in wonderment and alarm. Taking a light from the stand, I passed into the study, closing the door after me. I had not removed my hand from the knob when, with a whizzing noise, a large object, hot'as a coal of fire, struck my face; and being beaten off, rose and fluttered hither and thither against the high ceiling. In amazement I recognized this assailant, this musi- cian, this exuder of sweet sounds. It was the Insect. Its body, like glistening gold and flashing emerald, was distended to its full propor- tions; its great tasseled wings beat the air, until it frothed into un- earthly music; its eyes, sparkling like diamonds, seemed the prisons of a thousand tiny fires burning with a steady flame; its antenna was out- stretched and felt nervously along the white ceiling, leaving small red dots as indices of its touch. The loathsome thing flew from point to point as I pursued. It easily eluded the missiles I cast at it, and suddenly disappeared through the ventilator. X   MADELAINE DARTH.            6i I picked up from the table the little green vase in which the resur- rected insect had been kept, and found it was nearly full of the mix- ture I had left in the saucer. By the agency of these liquids vigorous life had been created in the body of the embalmed insect. That I did not comprehend the principle of this resurrection, through the instru- mentality of such subtle materials, was not my fault. The insect was alive, and its place in the vase filled by fluids in which it must have been immersed. I accepted the facts as they were presented. And the. insect lived on human blood! As my eye glanced along the ceiling, the red dots thereon were a revelation of the cause of my wife's suffering, and were proofs of -the injection into her veins of a subtle poison to dry up her blood and parch the fair skin. The full extent of my sorrow, past and future, passed before my straining eyes like a terrible vision; it shook me as the wind beats a blade of dried grass. I returned to the bed-side of my wife, as a man blasted by the bitterest sorrow and sharpest agony of the soul. Eternal misery chained me, like a felon, to ghastly horrors; while Imagination decked my future with gloomy robes and bid me hope only for death, as life would be full of vivid phantasms to blight the most joyous moments. To love a woman as passionately as I loved my wife, and hold her in one's arms as the last great change of life gradually develops; to feel the beatings of the heart diminish, to see the gasps for breath, to look into the eyes soon to close forever, and read in them the love they look back into yours, are the saddest. of duties to the dying. But how ter- rible the anguish when the eyes are fixed in an idiotic stare, their light forever extinguished, and the loved one, unconscious of your madden- ing grief, your piteous, unavailing love, is released by Death from her unhappy life! My wife changed but little in appearance after that memorable night.  Her body became emaciated; the skin became black, and hot to the touch; the eyes were half-closed and their light hidden. She would lie in my arms, at the window, for hours, and, with her cheek pressed closely to my breast, just over my aching heart, would imitate the sweet sounds that had been made by the insect's wings. She never spoke; nor did she evince the slightest consciousness    <pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC6457-00000033"/> 62         MADELAINE DARTH. of my presence.  Oftentimes she fiercely pressed her hands upon her head, as if it suffered intolerable pain. In my lamentable help- lessness I could do nothing but support her in my arms and calmly endure the awful agony of the sight. Since the night of its disappearance I had not heard the insect. I cared not whither it had flown, so that it had left me in peace.. But one afternoon, when the rain was falling in broad sheets, while sitting as usual at the window, my wife lying in my arms, the hated music sounded, faint and low, in the partition separating the study from the bed-room. The strains aroused my wife from her apathy. She raised herself up, repeated them in all their variations, and as she ended, she quickly turned her face toward me, and threw her arms around my neck. There followed a sudden, convulsive gasping for breath, and a short, feeble moan. The arms unclasped, and my wife was dead. After this horror had had its culmination, my only thought, the only thing for which I cared to live, was in what manner I might seize and destroy the insect-the cause of all my sorrow. I tore down a large part of the partition'in which it was last heard, but was unsuccessful in my search. I was in despair. I sat for hours at the breach I had made in the wall, listening intently for the slightest sound; but none was heard, and I had come to believe that the insect had crept through some crevice into the chimney and flown away. The wall had not been repaired when, one night, in a pleasant stu- por, I heard sweet music close tonmy ear, and felt cool air, and then a sharp, stinging pain, lasting only for a second. The low, plaintive music soothed my brain. A delicious languor possessed me. For an instant the sublime solitude of the grave, with musical silence awed my soul. Then, with a noise like the distant cries of a vast army, there rushed upon me a scorching wind and monstrous phantasms. I lay upon the sand before the front of the grand temple of Abou Simbal, with its three colossal statues hewn out of he mountain, sitting in a majestic agony of silence, watching the Nile with their staring eyes of stone as they have watched it for three thousand years. The   MADELAINE DARTH.             63 desert laves them with its billows of sand, half-submerging their huge limbs in its yellow flow, half-revealing their stupendousness, while it contrasts the solemn grey of the rocks and statues with the gleaming of the swift river. I hear voices sounding in the inner temple, where sit the gods in gloomy darkness, where sacrifices were made and agonies endured. As I listen, the magnificent temple dissolves in the soft twilight, and the sublime idea of Sesostris shadows my soul like a cloud. Palm-trees and shattered columns!  Phile and Isis and Osiris! Mecca of a people of stupendous wonders! Island of beautiful ruins and lovely desolation! The great black rocks inclosing it smoothed their jagged edges, and the moonlight trembled in its avenues and lin- gered in the courts of its temples as the darkness in which I wandered over a great desert plain was parted by the heavenly vision. One glimpse of its magnificent beauty, and the gloomy blackness gathered and swung to-and-fro-the proscenium to a revelation of exquisite loveliness. Once again,as in by-gone days, I wandered among the majestic ruins of Karnac. Masses of rock carved into graceful shapes stopped my way. Architraves of noble temples, fragments of fallen columns, made me sigh at their downfall. I walked down the avenue of sphinxes, amid mutilated colossi and rudely sculptured columns half-buried in the glittering sands of the desert. I lingered in the great halls of temples of stupendous! size, where light and darkness struggled for superiority; and the imagination shrunk to nothingness as it essayed to compass the magnificence of dead Thebes, whose gigantic skeleton lay unburied upon the desert. I was lost in the forest of columns of the grand hall at Karnac and shivered with supernatural terror beside the granite statues at the entrance to the temple at El Uksorein. I hungered and thirsted in my journeys among these shreds of ancient grandeur, and my soul asked for relief; for terror itself had become colossal. And amid this rubbish of dead cities, oppressed by the very magnitude of desolation, my soul cried for relief. But the hot sun /       *                f    <pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC6457-00000034"/> "         MADELAINE DARTH. poured down its hottest rays, the monstrous obelisks hid me from the cool, refreshing wind, and vast walls threatened to crush me under their. broad surfaces of hieroglyphics. In my agony, I dug a shallow grave in the sand, and hid myself therein, and. let the sun pierce it with its rays, and sloughing stone to descend upon it-but I slept. Suddenly, in my fitful slumber, surrounded by these well-remem- bered scenes, there shivered the air, shrilly and clearly, a sound that thrilled every nerve in my body, and echoed in my brain, until the air seemed a tumult of piercing chords that racked the sensitive nerves, and pealed upon the fastidious ear until it was deafened. Vibration 'after vibration of sound overwhelmed me with its powerful utterances. I rise from my grave and listen for their source. The faint glow of the rising sun steals down the rough sides of the Libyan mountains, and the lordly river sweeps past on its unending journey. Once, twice, thrice, sounds the shrill note; then the fabled Memnon, as gigantic as if it still sat upon its carved throne upon the western plain of, ruined Thebes, strides toward me, falls upon and mangles me. I am stung by thousands of quick, sharp pains; my body burns with their fires. The music grows fainter and is still. Thick darkness overwhelms me and I unavailingly buffet its noiseless waves. The memory of the disease that tortured my mind and body during the month succeeding my visions, is rendered prominent by an illusion as painful as it was enduring. I believed that my wife, swathed in linen, aromatic of rich gums and spices that poisoned the air with their heavy fragrance, sat at my bed-side in all the hideous blackness of her transformation; that she clasped my hand in hers and gazed into my aching eyes with the blank idiotic stare which had characterized the final stage of her disease. I did not doubt the reality of the vision; nor would my mind be disabused of its belief by cunning stratagems of kindly-disposed physi- cians. The close communion of souls existing between living beings, was thus continued when one of them was dead. The agony of this companionship was, at first, exceedingly acute. My delirium added   MADELAINE DARTH.            65 nothing to the happiness of this intercourse, and detracted nothing from its terrors. I was continually reminded of the mummy and the insect and all the incidents connected with their discovery. Day and night saw no change in the position of my wife sitting silently at my bed-side. My head weighed me down as if it were a mountain-a quiet Vesuvius of dormant horrors. My slumbers were infrequent, short and unquiet, full of visions of monstrosities in repose. A month passed replete with these torments, and I fell into a deep sleep that continued for fifty hours. When I awoke, my consciousness of external things, much enfeebled to be sure, had returned. But the vigor of the mind was forever gone. I could think but slowly, and my conclusions were very imperfect. A lagging, slow-consuming fever flowed in my veins, and my limbs had been shorn of their strength, and their quickness of movement was lost. The condition in which I had been found by the servant, and the fatal drops of blood from the wound behind the ear, surely indicated the cause of my suffering as identical with the cause that killed my wife. If my many hopes had been blighted, my ambitions crushed, my heavy sorrows made still more heavy, and the swift-running current of my life turned backward by the mysterious agency of this terrible insect, there yet flourished and thrived by their extinction a bitter hatred fo the cause. Although my brain was dulled in its acuteness of perception, and my body was parched with a fierce, unnatural heat that burned the skin into large wrinkles, and scorched the fair com- plexion to a tawny hue, yet I hoped and planned and lived only to destroy the insect, whose music I could now and then hear in the wall, and from which place of concealment the fiendish thing seldom ventured. One day, in an unusually dejected mood, I entered my study, closed the door and sat down. In an instant, 1 heard the music of the insect above my head and, looking up, saw it clinging to the chandelier, near the ceiling. A sense of ineffable happiness possessed me for several minutes. I thought of all I had suffered since I found the fly in the Egyptian tomb. The minute details of this life of strange catastro- phes, culminating in my own sickness, were quickly reviewed. I 5 )    <pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC6457-00000035"/> "         MADELAINE DARTH. watched the insect as it clung to the iron pipe of the chandelier, and fluttered its great wings; they fanned the air into delirious music, but- I was not charmed; its eyes glistened in all their brilliancy, but I was not fascinated. Suddenly the long legs of the creature loosened their clasp and it dropped like lead almost upon my upturned face; but before I could strike it, it had risen to the ceiling. It was not an unequal contest that followed this attack. The insect, eluding with ease my furious blows, smote me many times in the face with its antenna, but without penetrating the skin. I struck at it with books, with sticks, and with my fist, as it circled around or above me and fanned my face with its musical wings. Its eyes, with the cold brilliancy of a diamond, were ever on the watch; and at the slightest motion I made the insect would rise or fall in its circlings. When at last, panting, disheartened at my failure to wound or kill it, I was about to yield in despair, the insect, likewise fatigued, settled down upon the top of my bookcase. The sight revived me, and I seized the nearest missile; it was the vase in which I had found the insect. My enemy was rising when I threw the vase. There was a sound like the shattering of glass; the wall was splashed with blood and there fell upon the floor with the pieces, the stone scarabavus, and the insect. With an exclamation of joy I picked up these and went into the bed-room where a fire was burning in the grate, So strongly did I loathe the insect which, bruised and bleeding my blood, wound his trembling antenna around my fingers and thrust against them with its strong legs, that without a moment's hesitation, I cast it into the flames. I heard a wail,-like the cry of a woman in agony, and the study- door closed with a loud noise, as the insect was speedily consumed by the fire. With its death expired the flames. A sudden fear of some- thing terrible about to be seen, or to happen, made me shudder. I looked at the graven stone in my hand, and at nothing else. I read, as of yore, ' Three thousand years hence, a new life.' A year or more had passed since I had thought of the prophecy that now flashed upon me at a time of all others to be avoided; for the reminiscences   MADELAINE DARTH.            67 of the Egyptian tomb ought to have perished with the insect in the purifying fire. The unnatural strength that had sustained me through my conflict with the enemy, had gone, and left me weakened by exertion and excitement. My limbs shook, my head throbbed with acute pain, and my tongue wasrparched. I arose to leave a room whose atmosphere was pregnant with terrors that I breathed, and whose every nook and corner, the breached partition, and thewdead ashes in the grate, too strongly reminded me of scenes and incidents I wished to have forgotten. O my GOD! In the chair behind me sat the mummy of the tomb, alive, watching me with its small, cunning eyes, as it tried to free one of its hands from the decaying cerements. It was the mummy I had found, not the one that crumbled into dust before the breath of a pure desert wind. It motioned me with its 'disengaged hand back to. my seat, and strove to stand and oppose my passage, as, with a cry of horror, I rushed from the room. The cool air and the passing crowds in the street soon restored me to a calmer mind and, ashamed of my terror, I returned to my bed-room that I might prove the falsity of my illusion. I opened the door and looked in. The mummy had drawn its chair close to the grate, and was gathering from it white ashes- the remains of the burned insect. The old terror, that ever bided in my soul, crept into my reasonings and confounded my judgment. With a despairing cry, I frantically locked the door and fled from the house to wander"up and down the streets until long after midnight. - She is still in my bl-room, and i am trying to sa'rve her to death. I cannot sell the house. One or two particular friends, who wished to purchase, when I told them of the occupant of the study, and, to prove the truth of my assertions, bade them look through the key-hole, looked upon me with white, terror-stricken faces, and fled forno the house. The consequence of such a revelation to a stranger would be worse and cause rumors to be circulated prejudicial to my reputation. So I have concluded that the only manner to rid-myself of this living incubus is to kill her by starvation. [ have no pity, no heart. T'he    <pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC6457-00000036"/> 68         MADELAINE DARTH. possession of so terrible a creature is worse than Murder deliberately committed. I have boarded up all the windows and discharged the servants, living alone with my burden. Having partly overcome my fear I occupy an apartment next the 'study; and in the quiet of the night I can hear the woman moving about the room with a slow movement; now and then she sings such strange, unnatural tunes that, in my fear, I am compelled to leave the house for hours. It seems as if she would never die, for it is nine days since she made her appearance. The other day, when in the parlor listening to an unusual grating sound in the study, such as I had not before heard there, some plastering fell from the wall separating the rooms, upon the floor. The Form, the Death in Life, was endeavoring to break throughl! 1 promptly collected building materials and made the wall three feet thick. I worked night and day. I secured it.  I Those are her dying groans. But whither-oh! whither! out into what new life goes that undying. Egyptian soul? And I? -Shall I be linked through eternity by a terrible destiny of unknown mystery, whirling through what Hermes Trismegistus of Thebes calls 'the downward-borne elements of GOD?'* I, too, am dying. But a few hours hence, she and I will again know in clearness and in truth, the meaning of the words which Sothus wrote on the painted stone in the valley of Memphis, 'wherein appeared, in but few letters, all the lore of life, and of the soul, and of after-days, and of the eternal flood.' Free! My will still moves the dead hand which pens these lines, but I hover afar over it like a star. Out'into eternity! * Hermes, poemander, lib. I.   MADELAINE DARTH.            69 EXTRACT FROM THE JOURNAL OF MADELAINE DARTH. Mr. Rainey and I were watching the early wiiter twilight settle down on stupid little Quarrytown. I was seated at the piano, idly recalling some Reverie whose musical rhythm was like the lapsing sound of ebbing waves. Mr. Rainey occupied the ottoman not far from me. Suddenly the twilight hush was broken by Mrs. Matteson's voice, speaking in joyous, welcoming accents. Then the door opened, and Mr. Tiernay stood upon the threshold. Evidently my mourning dress was a surprise to him, forI fancied he gave a slight start as his eye fell upon it. Neither of us spoke more than the other's name, but Mrs. Matteson's high spirits and gay raillery smoothed away all awkwardness, covered all deficiencies. I was silent from emotion at standing face to face with the man whose patience and acuteness had solved the mystery of my life and restored to me my name and my fortune. I remembered that there must have been a time when he entertained suspicions of me as an imposter and an adventuress. Now he knew as much, if not more, of my past life than I myself. The lights were brought. Other callers--boarders in the house- came in, and the conversation became general. Mr. Tiernay came and sat beside me on the lounge, in order to exhibit some fine engravings he had' brought from Chicago. There was in his manner a marked deference to me, a preference given to my tastes and wishes which was iew and pleasant. Mrs. Matteson enjoyed it even more than I. Having adopted me as her companion and friend she will not allow, even to herself, that I am not in every respect perfect and admirable. In her unselfishness she ranks me even higher than herself. In our former intercourse it would have been impossible for me to have described Mr. Tiernay, for he never impressed me. For the first time, I consciously observed him. His, profile was sharply cut, but the features were regular. His dark brown hair and beard were    <pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC6457-00000037"/> 70         MADELAINE DARTH, -like his nature--rigidly pruned and trimmed. In his keen blue eyes there was a look of hard, unsympathetic isolation, and, in some indescribable way, this expression characterized the whole face; so that, if the eyes had been bandaged, it would have shown in the- mouth, and if that were hidden, the long, set jaws and prominent chin would have revealed the trait. When he was listening, the half-shut eyes were turned from the speaker and seemed as if searching some dark recess. His dress, though manufactured from expensive materials, was fastidiously neat and plain. His voice was unpleasant to the ear, being thin and sharp and with an Eastern accent, which is that of one who speaks through his nose lest the salt sea wind enter his lungs. He was a man devoted to details. In examining and criticising the pictures, he spoke only of the lights and shadows, and the arrange- ment of draperies, wholly ignoring the choice of the subject, or the style in which it was rendered. I thought, in looking at him, that were his the power of creation, there would have been no mastodons -he would never have progressed beyond the ants. Had he been a machinist, he would have devoted his energies -to perfecting a wheel to break flies, or a rack to kill butterflies. In his nature there was no luxuriance-only cultivated sterility, like that of his native State. His passions were but licenses given to Reason to trade somewhat in sentiment. The evening seemed to pass quickly. Mr. Tiernay asked me to sing, selecting a simple Scotch air, which, he said, I was singing when he first saw me. I was surprised at his memory in trifles. After the music, the rest went away and left Mrs. Matteson, Mr. Tiernay, Mr. Rainey and myself sitting round the grate. In parting, Mr. Rainey, with a gay, deprecating look at me, extended his hand. Mr. Tiernay seemed glad of the precedent, and so we gaily separated. Mrs. Matteson came to my room for a little good-night chat-a habit she never varies. "Madelaine," she said, unbinding my hair, " dofyou know I begin to think Mr. Tiernay takes to you?"   MADELAINE LDAR;tH.          71 I laughed at the queer expression and, glancing in the glass, saw in the face reflected there a look of conscious triumph. "However, that is useless, of course," she continued, rapidly unplait- ing a braid. "You are engaged to Mr. Rainey-signed, sealed, and ready for delivery, all but your wedding dress. The two gentlemen have gone up stairs for a quiet smoke, and I presume the gushing Rainey will reveal his glowing prospects to his friend." (, Well," she continued, after a pause, "Rainey has a comfortable income, is gay, sociable and amiable, and fond of you. I think you will be happy. Mr. Tiernay is a fine man and has a good position, but then he is too solemn. Living together, you would degenerate into a couple of old owls. He looks," and here she assumed Tiernay's veritable expression, '" as if he were constantly in the act of saying, 'Do not ask me to laugh. I cannot-I will not imperil my hopes of salvation by one unnecessary smile.'" Mr. Tiernay's habitual expression seemed to me a sad, rather 'than an austere one. I thought Mrs. Matteson exaggerated for the sake of a joke. She kissed me good night, and then, looking at me with wistful tenderness, and as if trying to strengthen her own belief, she reiterated that she was sure I had chosen a good husband, and went away, leaving me alone. The next morning, Mr. Tiernay received a letter which recalled him to Chicago. Mrs. Matteson and I watched his departure. He looked up from the hack to the window where we stood, and touched his hat and waved his hand. His habitually pale face seemed paler and more rigid than ever as he rode away in the cold winter 'morning. -Mr. Rainey entered the room, and came to us. He held in his hand the picture of me taken in Milwaukee. "See," he said, what Tiernay gave me. I told him I possessed the original, and he handed me this, declining to infringe on my copy- right. It is more convenient to carry than the original, since it fits my vest pocket "-and I, thrilled half with pleasure, half with pain, 'knew well why he had kept the portrait so long, and why he had not kept it longer.     </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
