<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6467">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The "Fourth" </title>
            <author>Anonymous</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC6467</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-0938</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The "Fourth," 1854</title>
                  <author>Anonymous</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>W.H. Tinson</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1854">1854</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-04-04">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The "Fourth," 1854</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6467-00000001"/> THE "FOURTH," 1854: LOG OF THE SMOOTHING IRON.   NEW YORK: W. H. TINSON, PRINTER AND STEREOTPER, NO. 24' BEEKMAN STREET.      <pb n="0" xml:id="VAC6467-00000002"/>  'FOURTH,"      1854: "OG OF THE SMOOTHING IRON. ON July 4th, 1854, at 9h. 30m. sailed from Washington Baths7 Hoboken, with sealed bottles, for exploring the unknown regions of our north- ern waters, the fast sailing American sloop, "SMOOTHING IRON," with the following officers and crew: ROSETTE D. MORTON, Commander; CHARLES E. BAILLIERE, 1st Lieut; EDMUND L. MORTON, Master; EDWARD R. MORTON, Mas- ter's Mate; F. COOPER, Clerk; R. SMEDBURG, Assistant Clerk and Chronometer; F. COOPEIR Surgeon; W. D. MORTON, Gunner; G. . MEm- O .    <pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC6467-00000003"/> 4 RITT and W. COOPER, Seamen; MKE, Cabin-boy; F. COOPER, Cook. GEN'L. MONTGOMERY, (J. H. Suckley,) Acting Steward and Commander of Marines; M. COOPER, J W. COOPER, FRED. SCHWIETERING, Marines and Musicians. 9h. 40m.-Unshipped main boom, put'to rights promptly; whole ship's company gave evidence of great strength of mind on this trying occasion. Sailing at the rate of 2 in. per hour against a- strong ebb tide. Wind SS. W., light and un- steady. The casualties from the accident were three dead men overboard. 9h. 50m.-Mainsail jibed-struck Capt. on skull, which, fortunately, was thick, though the sound was hollow. Took an observation, but found ourselves in no particular latitude or lon- gitude. Wind SS. W., going at the rate above mentioned. Claret bottle over board, rescued by Gen'l. Montgomery, whose talents begin to shine forth. Salute from shore. Last farewell of friends. All hands in good health and spirits. Gen'l. Montgomery makes 2 pts. of Claret Punch.   5 9h. 56m.-Gen'l. Montgomery takes 1st. glass. 9h. 58m.-Changed our course to southward, -made Washington Bath. Wind as before, sky cloudless, crew well, and doing their duty, by making themselves happy. Master asked man at the helm, why he didn't go about. Helms- man said he couldn't. 10h. 5m.-One man at the pumps, trying to pump us up the river, while the tide carries us down. Course E. N. E. Gen'l M., saluted clip- per sloop Fanny," Capt. Thomas, of and from Barker's Bay, destination not known. lOh. 10m.-Latitude 41; Passed the Fanny. Man sent forward to boom out mainsail. Marines and seamen sitting at the bows (holding sweet converse), in shade of jib. Captain and 1st Lieu- tenant sitting with Gen'l M. on starboard deck, listening to adventures of Gen'l M. Master at helm. Clerk and chronometer down below, ma- king notes under shade of umbrella, assisted by Surgeon and Cook. Spoke rowhoat, "Loafer," of and from Spring street, for Elysian Fields, with cargo of live stock. ,  -    <pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC6467-00000004"/> 6 10h. 15.--Lost streamers from maintop, and bloomer hat; sun very powerful.   Captain sits under shade of umbrella, held by first officer. 10h. 20m.-Great mortality among the crew, another dead man overboard. Symptoms of mutiny-deckhand declares he "wont go home till morning." Courage on the part of Captain; Gen'l M. and corps of marines stand ready for action. The Gen'l cheers on his men, speaking of exploits at Quebec. At this time all hands were warm and thirsty. The thermometer, (if we had had one) would have been at least 90 in the coolest place. There was not a cloud visible, and the wind very light, "and hot as the draught from an oven," says the Cook. None but hearts, resolved as ours were, to en- joy anything in their country's cause, would have held on their course unflinchingly. Nothing but the purest patriotism could so have brightened all faces, excited such facetious remarks, and raised the shouts of laughter that echoed from our decks, as we sat there heedless of the scorching sun-   rays, with the shades of the Elysian Fields in full view, and easy to get at. 10h. 25.-Gained on the "Fanny," with which we had been sailing in company for some time, and whose crew looked serious, in spite of an awning, and a quiantity of palm leaf fans. 10h. 26m.--"Fanny" gained on us ;we tacked, and stood W. N. W. Passed Washington Baths. 10h. 26m. 80s.--Gained on "Fanny ;" passed a dangerous reef called "Shadpole;" took an ob- servation, observed considerable "confidence" among our crew. Saw sloops loaded with live- stock far to leeward; Gen'l M. injured by pre- mature explosion of lemon soda.   Spoke by rowhoat from  New York, name and destination unknown; supposed that crew, at any-rate, were going  to the port known as "Old Nick's." The band performed airs from some unknown oratorio.- 10h. 35m.- Towhoat "Norwich" ahead; alarm of fire melodiously given by crew, in the words of the well-known song, "Says jolly Captain, to jolly crew," &amp;c. &amp;c.    <pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6467-00000005"/> 8 10h. 40m.--Mutiny among marines, subdued by prompt energy of Gen'l M. 10h. 41m.-Gen '1 M. makes punch, which is received by the whole ship's company as a delis cate attention from the hero. Captain expresses approbation by a look; crew, by smacking of their own lips. Much hilarity, in spite of the weather. 10h. 43m.-Extreme heat, 1st officer, who holdsumbrella over Captain, gradually roasting. Captain inexorable in matters of discipline, does not release him from his duty. Another M. T. overboard ; Pun from Assistant Clerk too start. ling to be recorded. 10h. 25m.-Passed surveying cutter lying at anchor. Almost ran into the "Fanny ;" marines showed themselves good seamen, then modestly returned to their original occupation of sitting in shade of jib, talking a little, singing a little, and gazing at the scenery. llh. 5m.-Passed, at the distance of a mile and a quarter, the shady foot of Weehawken Hills. Fire on maindeck, &amp;c., in the shape of cigars.   9 llh. lOm.-Master's Mate, actuated by heat of weather and mental derangement, dives from the deck into the inviting waves; within five seconds Gen'l M., and then the Chronometer, Gunner, and one Marine, forgetting that they had watches and pocket-books about them, go where their. illus- trious predecessors are imitating porpoises to the best of their abilities. Great astonishment ex- pressed on various craft in the vicinity. A faint Irish war-cry is heard; all eyes are turned towards our stern, and see the cabin boy carried overboard by the ruling passion. The Master, who is at tie helm, declares his intention to -stand by the ship, and so inspires confidence in the hearts of the few who remain on board. The wind is light W. S. W., our brave bark scarcely moves, and the "Fanny/' -now astern, looks even more than we like a "Painted ship upon a painted ocean." llh. 15m.-All hands aboard spreading out contents of pocket-books in the sun to dry. Bank notes pinned to mainsail make us look as if we had found a substitute for the Golden Fleece.    <pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6467-00000006"/> llh. 19m.-All hands overboard. l1h. 25m.-Breeze freshens, our sails fill, and we begin to leave a white streak astern. All hands hurry aboard. Gen'l M. performs Gym- nastics; collar of Gen'l M. exhausted. Pass astern of sloop, "Trouble," ofi Island City. "h. 30m.-All right; Gen'l M. making punch. M. T. overboard. lh. 35m.---Salute from S. B. Alida- answer salute. Marines suffering from thirst. Passed Highwood. Likewise passed the--- llh. 47m. 30s.-Breeze fails; Captain orders Gen'l M. to stay aboard; insubordination on the part of Gen'l M., who goes over, followed by As- sistant Clerk. The breeze freshens, and they are obliged to cut short their aquatic  diver- sions. All hands sit about deck from sundry motives. Captain reprimands Gen'l M., who acknowledges his error, and speaks of former exploits. -Master's Clerk, Cook, Surgeon, and Marine, J. W. COOPER, all at helm; 1st officers. booming out. ilh. 53m.--lst officer exhausted; revived by   " timely   assistance of extraordinary seaman, G. Merritt; is obliged however to go below. 12h.-- Fired mid-day gun; lunch ordered; Gunner reports us out of powder, except what is contained in firecrackers. Order for lunch coun- termanded; Gen'l M. suffers from hunger, and reports himself never so dry in his life. Made Dead Point; 1st officer on the sick list; his case is decided to be a sun stroke. 12h. 15m.--Genl M. and ..  12h, 29m.-What was about to be written, will ever remain unknown. We were sailing along gaily, without a thdught of danger ahead. The Captain, assisted by Gen'l M. was cheering the crew, by agreeable conversation on the forecastle. We drew near the port of Cedar Park, where we were to make our first landing, and take up two passengers. At the end of the dock lay two schooners belonging to the Russ Pavement fleet, and as we ran in along side the pier, the boom projecting over the stern of one .f these schoon. ers, did not catch the eye-of the Man at the helm, eofBequently did  catch our fainsail, tearing    <pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6467-00000007"/> 12 through it with a rip that startled from their care - less security every eye and ear on board. The helmsman tried in vain to arrest the mischief, he only succeeded in losing overboard the Cap- tain's pet umbrella, a treasure connected with many touching episodes of our gallant command- er's life. This loss excited much sympathy on all sides. "Who hath not lost an umbrella?" All was consternation on board. "What shall we do?" were words that echoed from stem to stern. "Mend it," answered some bright and ever-ready genius. But how? All the dam(n)-  ing in the world would not. fill such a break; besides, such means might not be considered quite proper, and etiquette was the first rule in the discipline of the "Smoothing Iron." "Darn it," mildly remarks some elderly maiden, whose basket is filled with well-mended stockings. My dear madam, there was not one on board who did not darn it as well as they were able and their sense of what as right would permit,- but it did nogood.  ohat did do good, was, as it were, the "hair of the dogthat biti:s," in the form of sail   13 needles and thread, in the skilful hands of two "brave tars," belonging to the schooner, whose boom had become tenant of our sail, and sent in rents. While the mending was going on, the captain, Genl. M., and part of the crew went ashore for the passengers. During the General's absence, sundry marines were dancing on the pier, with much levity and disregard of appearances, and divers of the crew were plunging about in the water like a flock of wild geese, which they might easily be taken for. Lemon Soda was served to all hands. The first officer still suf- fered'very much from his " coup de soleil," but the wonderfully scientific and skilful treatment of the surgeon, with the advice of the cook, appeared to have a beneficial effect. Ih. 2nm.-Sail mended, menders departed. Capt. returned with crew and passengers, after exploring a vast extent of country, and making many important discoveries. We set sail, but where was Gen'l. Montgomery? Gen'l. M. had found a mother, a mother lonig unseen, and ,i?,    <pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6467-00000008"/> " was staying on the hill tops to indulge for a few moments in the outpourings of his filial affection. This delightful trait in the character of our hero, touched every heart,. Ih. 40m.--Made port of Cedar Park again, this time safely, and took aboard Gen'l. M., now arrayed in a suit of spotless white. (What a thing it is to find a mother!) This change for the better occasioned envious murmurs from those for whom the river, wind, and sun had done the laundress's duty. Ih. 45m.-Thermometer supposed to be 109. Gen'l. M. washes his original trowsers. Ih. 63m.-Passed Gregory's,   saluted by natives. 2h. 10m.-Landed at Powder House dock t found it too hot to. dine, so re-embarked with all our provisions, and sailed off till 3h, during which time we dined. :Salt' hard pork and-beef, and stony biscuit, washed down by a scanty supply of water not thp coolest or freshest, might not. have seemed delicacies to those who have every luxury within r:ach, but the famishing crew of        s             . *      s   'the Smoothing Iron did not complain of thei provisions, or sigh for a market and French cook. No, their thankfulness gushed forth; when all having dined, Gen'l. M. made an oblation to Neptune, by sacrificing a yellow pudding dish having a large hole in the bottom. Raced with the schooner yacht "Mystery" off Fort Lee, and beat her. Wind SS. W. steady and fresh, sails ing at the rate of 600 knots per hour. 3h. 45m.-Sailing down the river at the rate of 700 knots an hour, now on our return voyage heading for Manhattanville dock. Master's mate at helm. Breeze steady. Since three o'clock, the cook, clerk, and surgeon have all been taking a nap on the cushions below, but are now wide- awake. Gen'l. M. is asleep ,on deck. Captain and 1st Lt., who has almost recovered through the delicate attentions of his commander and a squad of marines, are holding a consultation, which seems to be interesting. Cabin boy asleep to leeward; marines reclining about the bows; great placidity everywhere on board. *8h. 52m.--S. B; "Alida "-again, in sight.    <pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6467-00000009"/> 16 3h. 55m.-Salutes from "Alida " and "Ameri- ca." Gen'l.- M., while asleep, made fast to main- boom by cabin boy. Cabin boy reprimanded by Captain, while the hero's innocent slumbers are unbroken. Crew singing. 4h.-Gen'l. M. sings first line of Picayune Butler. Gen'l. M's. extra pants float on the breeze, from where they are fastened to the mainsail. 4h. 3m.-Made dock at TillieTudlem. Master's mate, gunner, and one sailor went ashore for water. Spoke by the Governor of Tillie Tudlem. 4h. 10m.-Left Tillie Tudlem with a salute for the Governor. Gen'l M. reported shot in the neck, not seriously as at Quebec however. 4h. 15m.--Crew generally disposed to be comfortable and quiet. Chronometer who has tried for the last hour to get on his last boot, has faint hopes of success. 4h. 20m.--Chronometer's boot on, likewise gunner's slippers. Passed Manhattanville. 4h. 30m.-Gen'l. M. loses Captain's hat over- board for the second time. We go about beau- tifully and pick it up. Master at the helm.   17 Gen'l. M. seems happy at the rescue; his hair is somewhat subdued. 4h. 35m.-Gen'l. M. assiduous in attentions to all hands. Seaman G. ,R. Merrit warbling on forecastle gives dim hints that he is not what he  seems, but a hero great as Gen'l. M. 4h. 40m.-Sailing in a SS. E. direction all serene. Capt. discoversa supply ofpins. Tack. 4h. 45-Made Vreeland's Point. Tack again. 5h. 10m.-All Melodious. Gen'l. M. rouses himself and encourages the crew by farther ac- counts of exploits at Quebec. Another M. T. overboard. The shores under which we are sailing are beautiful beyond description. The. air is somewhat cooler. Music upon various instruments. 5h. 22m. 30s.-Gen'l. M. loses the use of one eye. 5h. 25m.-Gen'l. M. falls into the hold but appears to receive no injury; his eye recovers. Ground and lofty tumbling by the Gen'l. 5h. 32m.-Gunner at helm, meets the vessel. Gen'l. M. says or sings "Meet her by moonlight alone."    <pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6467-00000010"/> 18 5h. 47m. 30s.-Reach Bull's Ferry, a celebra- ted port. Conclude to stop for water, all well and happy. Weather clear and warm; wind SS. W. Steamboat "Flora" coming down, we are obliged to leave port on her account. 6h.10m.-Sailed from Bull's Ferry, with plenty of fresh water. Gen'l. M. and Captain are hold- ing a comfortable conversation, and give pleasure to the crew by appearing to be on friendly terms. Wind as before. 6h. 27m-Touching condescension on part of Gen'l. M. We meet steamers "Hendrick Hud- son " and "Troy." Salutes. 6h. 47m.-Stopped at port of Cedar Park. Left the two passengers. Gunner and ordinary seaman, William Cooper, desert the ship. Much singing of birds heard on shore. Gen'l. M. ex- presses his love for discipline and activity, and tells his experiences aforementioned. 7h. 13m. 30s.-Raced with a North River schooner, and beat her. Sailing now delightful. 7h. 20m.-The shores of our home loom up. Washington Baths in sight once more. Signs of   19  emotion and deep feeling on all sides. Pass a sloop. Gen'l. M. and corps of marines stand by to salute. 7h. 30m.-Splendid sunset; fine breeze. Capt. orders all hands to become respectable, a few murmurs are heard at this order. 7h. 40m.-All hands respectable. Last M. T' overboard. We near our homes; welcoming crowds, joyfil salutes. Flags hoisted on Wash- ington Baths, which we go by for a sail down the bay. Gen'l. M. with assistance from all hands gets his last boot half on. 7h. 50m.-Off Barker's a singular discovery, the supposed Gilbert B. Merritt appears in his true character, the celebrated Gen'l. Quebec, whose life has been a romance, and whose glory approach- es that of Gen'l. Montgomery. He now shines in all his splendor, and calls out the moon, stars, and myriads of flashing rockets, by- his exquisite performance of songs of all nations. The sailing is-now perfect, we dash along like a telegraphic despatch. The view of the villages of New York and Jersey City, illumainated as they now- ark    <pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6467-00000011"/> 20 by a mixture of moonlight, and fire works, is very fine. The metropolis, Hoboken, needs not our praise. The only drawhack to the general hap- piness is that the man at the helm has no tobacco. 8h.-Sailed round the steamer "Falcon," at an- chor in the bay. "Lilly Dale," "Blue-tailed Fly," "New Sack Coat," "Viva la Companie," and other songs from Gen'l. Quebec, with all hands at the chorusses. Homeward bound. 8h. 25m.-Reached   our port, Washington Baths. The cruise over; Deep sorrow of all on leaving the ship. 8h. 30m.--eported ourselves at 17 Franklin Terrace. 8h. 40m.--Reported ourselves at head- quarters The sun had set as brightly as it rose, and Gen'l Montgomery, altho' one boot was but half on, as well as the Captain and whole crew, felt happy in knowing that few ever did and suffered in the cause of their country, what had been done and suffered during this cruise of the "SMOOTHING IRON." July 4, 1854.      </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
