<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6843">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >An Adventure on a Frozen Lake </title>
            <author >Hunt, J.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC6843</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >An adventure on a frozen lake</title>
                  <author >Hunt, J.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >46 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >Ben Franklin Book and Job Office</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cincinnati </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1853">1853</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-08-13">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text >
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>An adventure on a frozen lake</head>
            <p> 
               <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6843-00000001"/>    
               <pb n="0" xml:id="VAC6843-00000002"/> i A4 Entered according to an act of Congress in the year 1853, BY JESSE HEALY,           In the Clerk': Oflge of the District -ourt, for the'Di',.to hio.  CLARE &amp; CO., PRINTERs, Ben Franklin Printing Houwe^O ilOAnat, Ohio     <pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC6843-00000003"/> *4    MY ADVENTURE ON A FROZEN LAKE. Gen. Lucius V. BIERCE, a prominent individual of northern Ohio, having received by the Patriot Congress/ thh appointmnt- of Com- mander in Chief of the forces to be employed for the invasion of the Upper Province-I placed my pecuniary matters in such a shape as to warrant an absence, and toward the close of 1838, pre- sented myself before that gentleman, as a volunteer in the expedi- tion; and was informed that- i twould bhe fiesesary for me to repair to a place called Swan Creek, situated about eighteen miles to the south of Detroit, in the State of Michigan; that being, the place of rendezvous, and there make' a regular enlistijnt. 'I accordingly set out, joined the Patriot service, passed through the thousand and one diffiulties previous to the battle of Windsor, which encoun- ter took place on the morning of the 4tl of December, of itat year. the whole force wlich crossed over, did not exceed in number, one hundred and forty, and, as a general thing, they were greatly deficient of proper arms. The landlng wys effected about four miles up the river, and a4ove the town of Windsor ,w ich is immediately opposite Detroit. It was after midnight 'before allf' things wpre ar- ranged, preparatory to marching down,. The ad4rance guard arrived at the enemy'. barracks just as the day pegan to dawn, and, thteir sentinel, stationed on the; "oute wall," it eems, by infornaion gleaned afterward, was asleep at his' post Hearing our trau p, however, he roused' suddenly up, and demanded in a. stern voice, "who is there? come forward and give, the countersign." He soon found out who was there, 'for a. fellow by the name of Thompson, one of the greatest dare-devils ,the world'ever knew, and a common soldier, by the way, brought his gun to his face; without any order from a superior, fired at the sentinel, and dropped him dead in his tracks. This broke the silence of the scene, al'tie battle commenced in good earnest en. en Bierce camea imi' t'diately forward, and ordered the whole force to surround the barracks, which order was instantly obeyed, sor that al who 'a it ted to make an escape, were shot the moment hey came, in sight. 'Some fifteen in number were thus shot dead, while attempting to escape by the front door. I was in the foremost ranks, and iap;lain sight f all the proceed- ings, but the old musket which I had,' iavng been exposed for a long time, before crossing over, tothe dampnesp of concealed places, rendered it wholly unfit fr use. I tried ahalTf-a-dozen-times to dis- charge it, but all to no purpose. 'A41 this time the balls were flying around me like a shqwer of hail-stones. i' stepied out of the ranks to one side of the barracIss, for thee purpose ;'f picking my 4int," and while standing there, a fellow, whom it appeared a had'watched my movement, and who, too, had managed, to make his escape rom the barracks, by one of the windows cpame suiddenly upon m' and puTled trigger. As fortune would iayd It, however, his 4un mlsed fre.  ol. "Harvell came up at the same moment, discovered, the movement, and having a rifle in his hand, brought thie man to the   XY AIvENTXRE B ON s. A' RO fLAr . L earth. - I ran immediatly iup; to ,th fellow* determined .,to 'bay onet him; but founa'the fire otC:ol. Hartvell hadd!ote ts fatatwoqrk., I did nothing urtiher thati tpirh im over bon his backO. For a ,onent a sudden athl noftr horror ,tased over- me, as Ii watched the fellow gasping f6rbreathi in:the last agonies of death. . .; . .; j eAs ftwas abotle4viihg the place, ,I- .wsom wihat' startled by at- !other fellow fallingatfithlength besideme,.,from ofe of. he windoWs !of the, upper store:o. the ,barraCk, e He struck th arti with- t trd- mendous force, and after givhg one of thos'e;nearthl groansjprefi- 6us to the: last ebb of life, he stretqhed himself out, ahidrw a dead. iHe was shot by one whilendeavoring o makeg o dhiSAca tpe, by the window. Along with him fell his musket, and ;peeivng it to be ,a good one, I concluded ,that onl such an oecasion,'at lea ti an' ex- change was no robbery. I placed: mine by his side, and converted 'his to- my use. On examination, I discovered that the musket was primed and loaded.   '     ' '  - By this time, the cofusion and. nise eeeede d ay thi-ng of the kind .whichb it had ever. been: my, fortune to. witness. -That order which is nessary, e evnn -in the beat,of o battle, was,. in ,. great 'smeasure, dispensed with, despite $th!,vigilance of Oen. Biercefand th: other officers. I stepped ,outrom n the'barrafks,about. fifteen paces, and wishing to try my gun, I let th, contents- hrough one of the window$; ,but whethertit 41d 'any'-execution,; I iknew not, and *cared s. little.   -   -          !" ' When I came to teload, I found that the, catridges which I .hal would not fit his: gwun they being too small : X retuTred: to nly d ead 'tadesman, unbuckled .bhi cartouch box from him, :and ,cas ting mine aside, reloaded and returned to my post,;. Gen,..ierae, ;seeing o prospect of a, surrender being effected, came ;up,;.and oridered ien. Putnam to communicate. fire ;to the barracks.:: The'orderwasearried into. execution, and in twenty mirutes the buildings, three innuibber, -were envelsped in. a^sheet of flame, presenting' alone and dt the same time, a scene of horror and sublimity;. .: .'  Those in the barracks finding a retreat impoasible, called aloud for quarters, which ,vas immediately granted, and all who had'escaped the ball and the bayonet, some fifty in number, surendered them- selves. to our generosityv. This at once placed the whole: town of Wmdor, w:ith -11 its yaluables, in the; hands of -Gen. Bierce . Elated by, thetiviotory thus achievdd, the whole 'Patriot forces maarhe; 'ut. to the. front of fthe town, and in full sight of the in- habitants of Detroit, :many of whom were on the lhousetops, watch- ingwith intense anxiety our movements, and therews,en asse raised the shout. to the full of our voiees, '"Reneiber t;he .! atolinm," o- gether with other expressions1 of joy. Many, of; he inhabitant .of the place, in the early part of the encounter, had fled to the:iooods, or to the town of SandwFich, situated three niles belot, while, those ' who remained begged in the nost. suppliant manner for their lives. Orders, however, had previously been icsued by Gen, Bierce, not to    <pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC6843-00000004"/> '6      I. ADV STUlR- ON A .F OZEN LA " fA. molest. any of th:pllate fiabitknt ; zalso, that, in ,o Ceaseimust pri- vat6 poperty be diried,'4tnd 'is'oiter w ,rligiously'observed. Peace however, was of short duration'; for d so iehkh Genlenal 'Bierce 'had taken thepreoautiow th, send dowri thwJdithe tdwn of Sandwich, returned -with the uwwehome tidings h,fat ,lrge reii- -forcement of British RegularS, were close: by, andiiarehing up in battle array.', The news fell upon my er'likM, d ath knell, as I knew too '-ell that we had no buniness wiithBritish Regulars., 'Had they been;'only the militia and volunteers," we'!otold have played, ,to their hand' in good earnest. A sort of: panic'rari, through the Whole Patriot force; ubt there was no alternative left us but to meet the emergencr'aa beetVwe could.: '  :. .   ,  .. 'Gen. Putnam, a regular descendant of :our'Revolutionary Putnam, under whose division I was seriing, gave orders'that we repairtoan orchard,- which was near by, and form in line of battle. The order was obeyed, so far as it was possible under the then existing cir- cumstances. By this i   movement' the two' divisions, the one under :Gen. Bierce and the one under Ge:itPutnam, 'became separated,;aid, as 'a matter of consequence, seived to -iveaken our abilihty for pr"se- 'outing a regular battle ;' and'what was mniore, it'disheartened manyof 'our men, who, instead of making preparations fo1r the encdunter, thought Only of escape.,  We had scarcely got in line before'a volley 'from the Regulars was poured in upon us, from a quarter we least expected it'; and imme- 'diately in our rear. We wheeled andi iethmtfnd the compliment '.but in such a fednfused, and hurried manier, that I do not suppose thre balls did the slightesta execution on either sile The moist of us fired too high'; and'tiisw'.ws the case on the part of the enemy.. We 're- loaded and poured, another volley into their maidst, and by this! time the-firing on both sides became general. One or two attempts' *ere made,' on 'the part' o fihe Regulars, to charge upon us, but a' volley from our division would check them. During this timeqp'iteoa num- ber on both sides fell dead, or badly wounded. ; While thus engaged, another detachment of the'eneminy Camte up, and endeavored to get between us and the woods inorder to cutoff our retreat, and' to divert our attention. A yolletWa':fied into them; killing two. We instantly made the attetpt 'tth char2: on them, but they fled in an opposite direction; and in fioking' ,iund, we found the detachment oose upon us, and in fll charge. .. The regularity of their movementS, the uiifr'dity of th6':Arpss, and brightness of their musket5--this itnhigled with the oarxiing groans of the wominded- struck a panic on the majority of ouir men, and escape e'mied their only thoughiit. About thirty actually threw down their guns;, hnd rati' for the woods, which are gitiiated about one mile in the rear6 of the to* of Windsor. . '  The infection soon spread among our men, and-presently the whole number, with some few 'notable exceptions, and: against very persua- sion and entreaty of General Putnam and Col. Harvell, joined' in the   MY ADVENTURE ON A FROZEN LAK.     7 retreat. Perceiving that to remain was certain death, I took up my line of march with the flying fugitives, turning now and then, as many did too, and diqcharg' my iun, at our pursuers. The air seemed alive with screiehing bail; and the nost I dreaded was being wounded while flying. A-bad-scar to exhibit to posterity. I made several atteupts ttp I lwlfng%    o  ,Qine   <pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6843-00000005"/>    
               <pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6843-00000006"/> line with the river, two horsemen swept by us at full gallop. When they had passed by us a short distance, one of them halted, and partly turning his horse, asked us in English where we were going?    <pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6843-00000007"/>    
               <pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6843-00000008"/> "     MY ADVENTURE ON A FROZEN LAKE. o'clock in the forenoon, during which time we consulted as to the fu- ture. Thompson seemed perfectly sanguine that we would yet make our escape in safety; but the incipient thirst and gnawings of hunger nearly dispirited me.. ,Antmad a jl ties b' 6tkw4di 'oircumstances, how- ever, Thompson continued'as buoyant in spirits as though he were oIsDA rti .,    .; ..dito.      ... for a moment, beforehim.  It was the dreard of the pain, liis, for a moment, before him. It was the dread of the pain He#xs    <pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6843-00000009"/> O      . HMY ADVXNTURB ON A tODB! LAK.  MY ADVENTURE ON A FROZEN LAKE.       17 We examined our guns and found that all was right, in ease they should be called in requisition. We jutmped over the fence and cau- tiously prceeded toward the'humble habitation. Before arriing at the door, I told Thompson tolet me do the talking,- and above ill, I urgpd that he should not, on any consideration, commit any rash act, unless compelled to do so in selfldefense; I made mention, too, that persuasion would, in most cases, accomplish more than the sword and the baycnet combined. In answer he told me to go ahead, forhunger's sake, and stop my moralizing; and declared that thp moment we got on the American side I might preach. and he would lisntewith all earnestness, and not only that. he would advertise in the papers my abilities as an expounder of the "moral cod ."  - Our business now," he continued, "is fighting - not preaching." However,- he finally agreed that I might go in the lead, and he would follow. my direotions. Arrivimg at the door, we waited a short -time, and lis. tened. We could hear a low conversation. I gave the door two or three smart raps, and all remained silent. We heard the chair move, heo ever, and then all was silent again. "Give anoter rap," .said Thompson, in a low whisper. I then gave the door another rap or so, but rather louder than be- fore; and presently a voice within demanded , Who's there?" A flock of six or eight geese kept up such a squalling that I could scarce ly hear or be heard. At this Thompson struck one old goose wlich stood niear by, and knocked it nearly stiff, and that served to make the others squall the louder, if any thin;;. At this the door opened about ten incnes or so. and the head of a somewhat aged femnale protruded but the instant she saw us, jammed it to again. We stood a moment more, waiting for her to open again. but all'was still withln. I rapped once more, and a vo ce within asked, ".What do you want!" She spoke in the Irish brogue. I remarked that I would thank her if she would give us a drink of water. WA ho are you?" was further demanded I told her that we were' friends, and were going down to Windsor, to join Her Majesty's army. "', A devil of a pretty pair of friends we are," said 'Thonpsonl, in a low, undertone of voice. " lFell ihem we are live Yankees and to open the door, or we will open it for them," be continued in the sanre low tone. I motioned to him to be quiet; but it was like preaching Christianity to the Turks. Presently a voice within remarked, in rather an angry tone, bid, ding us begone, and telling us, at the same time, that we were our. selves, rebels; and furthermore, if we did not clear immediately out, they would set the dogs on us, or scald us with hot water. Sht said, too, that we dese:ved to, be poi.-oned; and ether like epithets fol- lowe d in rotation. This raised Thom ,son's passions to the highest lch. "   1 'II be d---d," said he, " it I don't see the inside of that lou se ;" and passed oat to the wood-pile, near byr and taking up 'a large "  mall, as we Yankees term it, returned with it in his hand, and in a drawn manner.    <pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6843-00000010"/> 16      MY ADVENTUR\E ON. A FROZEN LAKE. I asked him what he intended doing?"If you will watch a little," said be,!"I will show you what I intend to do," and at the same instant let drive at the door full vengeance, and literally de- molished it. He struck with such force that the "r mall " passed out of his hands, and landed about midway of. the house. I do not know whether his shooting the sentinel at the barracks caused any-more of an uproar than did his affair at the door of the log cabin. Another such a screaming and crying among the in- mates I never heard. There were three women, and I should think at least a half a dozen young ones, all of whom screamed at the top of their voice. I tried to persuade Thompson to act a little more civil, but all to no purpose -he only raved the more. Thompson passed immcdiately in, and just told them in plain Eng- lish, that if they did not stop their d --d yelling he would cut the throats of every one; and suiting the action to the word, commenced flourishing a large knife at them, as though he intended killing them the next instant. This only made them scream the worse, if any thing; and I was for leaving, but Thompson told me that i' I did not stand by and help him kill them, he would kill me. This, of course, was said merely to try to bring them to terms. He then told them that we were, indeed, rebels, but if they would give us what we asked for, we would pay them for it. But all was to no purpose. As a last alternative, he sat three chairs in a row, and told the women to set down or he would kill them instantly. They paid no attention to his order, and for a while I was really afraid that he would carry his threats into execution. His better judgment, however, kept the ascendancy, and did them no harm. All this time, I was at the cupboard, which stood in the cor- ner, helping myself to such provisions as I could find. On a large pewter platter was a large quantity of cold boiled pork and potatoes, besides a large quantity of other articles of a miscellaneous kind, such as boiled turnips, boiled cabbage, &amp;c., and on another platter was cold corn bread. I took every thing I could lay my hands upon, and tying it up in a large cotton handkerchief, told. Thompson we had better leave. Before departing, I offered the wo- man who appeared to be head one, two half dollars, as compensation money; but she refused in the most obstinate manner to touch it. I immediately threw it down on the floor, and told her she might re- ceie it ,or not, just as she pleased, and at the same time started off. She picked up the two pieces of money,ran to the door, an I threw them at us in the most indignant manner, accompanying which was a roll of oaths equal to those o! an old, enraged sailor. Thompson stopped and picked up one of the pieces, and while looking around for the other, the old woman let drive at him a billet of wood, and the other women commenced throwing other missiles. By this time 1 was ten rods off, and after calling two or three times, induced Thompson to come on. When Thompson overtook me, he said I was too chicken-hearted on such occasions. He said that he   MY ADVENTURE ON A FROZEN LAKE       19 never intended hurting them, but he knew that unless we went to work in good earnest, our chance for a dinner was a poor one. One thing is sure, I would':not have,exchanged that lot of provisions for one-half of the wealth of t6e kingdom of Great Britain. Much as I despised robbery, I could not help giving utterance to a spirit of exultation for the " forage" obtained in the old cupboard.     ,             @  *        <pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6843-00000011"/> CHAPTER 'IV. We penetrated back into the forest quite a distance, before ven- turing to stop and refresh ourselves on our store of provisions. In an hour's travel we came to a suitable location, and struck a fire and then ate our fill. There was a tin cup in the cupboard, and I took the precaution to retain that in my business of abstraction; and with this we were able to procure our water, by the melting of snow. The weather continued extremely cold, but our feast had so regaled our spirits that we did not suffer as much as on the previous even- ings. Many were the surmises which we made touching our visit to the cabin. We were confident that it would be the means of arous- ing a spirit of revenge, and that if we were ever arrested, death was our portion. However, we passed the night as comfortably as could be expected, all things considered, each taking our turn in watching. We did not start. as was o)ur previous intention, very early the next morning on our journey. While sitting by our fire, in a somewhat unguarded manner, we were suddenly surprised by the sharp report of a rifle, the ball of which struck the log within a few inches of where Thompson was seated. We instantly sprang to our feet, seized our guns. and put out to the top of our sp, ed. Following the reiport was raised a most rightful yell. Looking back, we discovered three In- dians coming after us at full speed. Both of our guns were loaded at the time; but the sudden approach of the savages had, for the time. completely unmanned us. We ran, I should judge, about a mile, and I began to feel fa;int, when Thompson ordered a halt, and swore he would let the devil have him, before he would retreat an- other inch - declaring at the same time that in all his life he had never acted so cowardly. I told him that cowardly or not, I was not going to give battle, single-handed. against a troop of Indians. He declared that he could whip out the whole posse, himself. As in the case of the man n ar Windsor. we thought it best to wait their approach, and give them a " leaden pill ;" that is, if a chance presented itself. Examining our guns, we found them in go d order. We then stepped behind a large monarch of the forest, ftor which that part of Catiada is noted, and commenced a look out for the whelps. We had not remained long before one of the number came in full sight, having all the contour of native elasticity, and looking as fierce as a tiger. The moment lie came to a pause, Thompson fired on him, and. as on former occasions, with that same deadly precision. The savage gve a loud % hoop, and jumping at least two feet from the ground, fell at full length. Critical as was our situation, I could not help giving a real loud   MY ADVEtTURE ON A FtOZEN tAKE.      2, hurrah, more particularly, as Thompson turned his dark, glain-ag eye toward me, and giving one of his knowing winks, as auch as to say, "What think you, of that, old shipmate?" He beckoned me to come to him; and again taking my gun, started in the direction of his- what he called "game.", I told him not to be too venture- some, as I was confident that the other two were lying in ambush, but that made not the slightest diffeience with him; his only answer was, "* load up, and come on, and examine our game." I loaded the- gun with all possible dispatch ; keeing, at the same time,  good look out for the other two Indians'; but nothing was to be seen or heard of them; still I was confident that they were not far off, and would come up' to make discoveries.. We had not proceeded to excee.4 ten paces, before the other two Indians appeared in view, and a savage looking couple they were, too. Both of us immediately brought our guns to our faces, and I was in the act of pul!ng trigger, when Thomp son discharged his. Simultaneously with the report of his gun was the report of one of the Indiatns. I heard the whistle of his ball, and that was all the dam. age effected. For the first time, too, Thompson failed in his aim. The Indians, seeing that they had 'accomplished nothing, wheeled and fled; and Thompson seized my gun, :made arter them, giving at each bound a scream, and every now and then uttering a most terrible oath. They were soon out of sight. I continued motion- less as Lot's wife; what to do I did not l:now. I looked first one way and then the other, fearing to stir, taking the precaution, however, to reload. Presently, in the distance, I heard the report of a gun, and from the sound I was quite confident that it was Thompson's. After the spa e of fifteen minutes, back came Thompson, puffing and blowing like a porpoise. In answer to my inquiry, he said that 'they out. stripped him; and finding that he could not overtake them, he fired at randon, but in the direction of where they were last seen.  " We then went to the spot where our supposed dead Indian lay, and to our surprise found that he was still alive; that instead of be. ing dead, he was only badly wounded. The ball had taken effect. in his right groin, and the blood was protruding from it quite profusely. He seemed to be suffering intensely from pain; and occasionally he would roll over, -from one side to the other, giving, at the same time, a sort of mournful groan.  I will never forget the savage appearance of "his countenance, when I put my foot on his side, for the purpose of making -him lay still. All that he wanted was the strength necessary to plunge his scalping knife, whi-h was in his belt, into my heart. Thompson was for kicking him to death; but I finally persuaded him that such an act was entirely useless - that the fellow was wholly in our power, and that if he wished to kill him, why,' he could (shoot him.' While I was thus expostulating with him, Thotnpson drew his pistol, and placing the muzzle close to the Indian's head, discharged    <pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6843-00000012"/> 22      MY ADVZNTVUN ON A FJLOZBN LAKBi. the contents into his brain. It literally tore his head to atoms. I cannot say that the sight affected me in the least; on the other hand, it would have imparted more than ordinary satisfaction to have been able to dispatch the others in the same manner. This bding the third life which he had taken within four days, made him one of the most desperate mortals conceivable. It was by the utmost persuasion, anJ even the threat of parting with him, that I prevented him following on after the remaining Indians, for the purpose, as he said, of giving them battle, single-handed; stating, too, that he would gladly have his days shortened five years, for the glorious privilege of meeting them in single combat. He even went so far as to curse himself lor running when attacked in our camp, and so raving did he become, that he actually turned, and giving a spring with all his might, struck his heels with tremendous force into the breast of the dead Indian. I found that it was of no earthly use to say any thing, so I passed it off by telling him that I guessed the devil was dead now. He then declared that if I would return with him to the house of the women, he would cut the throats of every one of them; stating that he knew that it was they who put these "hell hounds" after us. I have no doubt but that it was them : for they caine from that direction. However, Thompson had heard to me in nearly every particular, and the idea was, at length, totally abandoned. The Indian was well armed, among which his rifle was the article I most coveted; but Thompson thought a musket was a much better weapon for our use; and the only thing that we took from him was his tomahawk; this done, we left him. We endeavored to find our camp again, in order to secure the balance of our provisions# but after an unsuccessful search for at least two hours, we were obliged to abandon it as a fruitless endeavor. Taking our course in What we supposed to be a north-easterly direction, we wandered all that day, without meeting with any incident worthy of recording. The weather through the day had considerably moderated, from what it had pre- viously been; but the night continued extremely cold. Having noth- ing but the open sky to shelter us, it was a matter of impossibility to keep any thing like feeling comfortable. Near night-fall we again came to a halt, built us a fire, preparatory to another night's tarry -not rest. Hunger returned; and being extremely wearied from the fatigues and excitement of ithe day, ren- dered the period such a one to me that nothing but a total annihila- tion of memory can ever obliterate from recollection. Sad thoughts, despite all the resolution I could muster, would occasionally come over me ; and this coupled to the reflection that our footsteps were marked by blood, brought from my breast many a desponding sigh. The prospect before us, in the morning, was any other than propi- tious. The weather was intensely cold, and the air filled with frost. I certainly thought we would perish. Our only alternative was to proceedS We determined to stop again at the first dwelling we come   MY ADVENTUEB ON A FROZEN LAKE.      23 to, and try to procure us a breakfast. Starting out, we directed out steps toward the shores of the Lake; and about ten o'clock we come to a clearing, which bordered on the shore. About a mile to our right was a house and outhuildings, which, from appearance, was the home of plenty. I then told Thompson that if he would promise me not to exhibit his indomitable spirit of rashness, . would follow him thither and try our fortunes toward getting something to eat; but if he did not make that promise I would not go. He accordingly promised that if we were not actually attacked, he would let me do all the managing; " but," 'said he, " if there is the least disposition made to take us prisoners, or disturb us in any way, I will defend myself to the cost of my life.', To this, of course, I consented, and we started out. We proceeded directly on toward' the house, with as much non- chalance as though approaching the dwelling of a friend, and met or saw no one on the way. Passing through the gate, I approached the door, and giving two gentle raps, a voice within bade us enter. There were sitting before a large, cheerful fire, three men, two wo-. men, and some four or five children, ranging from five to twelve years of age, I immediately gave the usual salutation of " how-do- you-do, gentlemen?" and received in exchange a friendly answer; at the same time they rose and proffered us a seat. We immediately passed to the chairs and sat down. Nothing was said for nearly a minute, when I broke the silence by saying: "I think, gentlemen, you are not natives of Canada?" One of them replied that they were not - that they were formerly from Vermont. No one knows how welcome. the word "Vermont" fell on my ear. I then told them, unequivocally, who we were; also, related the many privations through which we had passed since the morning of the battle at Windsor. I further stated that I did not think they would, on any account, betray us; to which they replied that they were friendly to the cause of Canadian freedom ; but such was their precarious situation that they could not, in a direct manner, lend their strength to its support. The man spoke with such em- phasis and force of feeling, that it made my heart bound with glad- ness. It brought back to my bosom, as by the power of magic, the blessed influence derived from the communion of minds which soar above and beyond the shackles that bind to the dungeon walls ot ig. norance, the progressive spirit of republican intelligence; and for a moment, I forgot the unfavorableness of our unhappy lot. I then informed them that we had been without food for the past twenty-four hours, and the good lady immediately set to work pre- paring us a repast. We were informed that it would be necessary thr us to keep secreted, for such was the hostile feeling of the au- thorities, that should one of the rebels be found in a house, not only the rebels, but the entire inmates might be put to immediate death. While we remained, one of the number kept watch out at the gate, in order to give, if necessary, the alarm of danger. The meal being e           A,     .    <pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6843-00000013"/> 24      MY ADVENTURE ON A FROZEN LAKE. prepared we set down; and it has rarely entered into the heart of man to conceive how well it relished to our nearly famished stomachs. We had not been long seated, before the man came in and said that two of the British Patrole were coming at full gallop on horse- back, and thought it best for us to secrete ourselves, and that, too, in the utmost haste. Immediately in front of the fireplace was a trap door, which opened into the cellar. I raised it and told Thompson to pass down, which he did, and I followed. The horsemen, how- ever, passed on without calling, and we were soon again at the table. I made proposals to the man to permit us to remain with him for a time, but he said that he could not, in justice to his family, listen to such a proposition. He said that the spirit was willing, but the flesh overruled. Having finished I offered him pay, but he refused to receive one cent of compensation. He told his wife, such, at least I took the woman to be, to put us up some provisions, and urged the necessity of our immediate departure. R:is kindness forbade my urg- ing him to let us stay, and we again set out into the world of dreari- ness, refreshed in body, but with dejected spirits. As usual, we repaired to the woods, and penetrated back a considerable distance, as we were informed by our hospitable friends that, in that region was an Irish settlement, and that the majority were republican at heart. We followed on all that day without meeting with a single individ- ual, or making any favorable discoveries. The weather again changed from sunshine to one of cloud and gloom; and the moaning of the wind too plainly told us that a storm of snow was brooding. It was evident that if we did not find a place of safety that day, our doom was sealed. We finally came to a halt, with an idea of starting a fire; and while consulting, I told Thompson to listen, that I could hear the strokes of an axe. We paused in breathly silence, for some time, and as the wind lulled at intervals, our belief was confirmed. We lost no time in proceed- ing in the direction from which the welcome sound came. After traveling a little over a half mile, to our joy, we came to a clearing, which contained about twenty acres, and on the further side was a dwelling. The men were at work; one was drawing wood with a yoke of cattle, and the other one was chopping. We listened, in or- der to hear their language, but their voices were so indistinct that we could not perfectly satisfy ourselves what countrymen they were. Resolved, at length, to proceed immediately to them; we scaled the fence and approached the dwelling boldly, and with a somewhat quick pace. They did not discover us until we were directly upon them. On looking up, one of them saluted us with, "Yer servant, Sir." I responded in the usual terms, and asked him if he would have the kindness to let us have a drink of water?"Certainly," said he, walk in, and may wife will help you." His brogue told me that be was an Irishman, and I felt quite safe; that is, if he did not belong to the what is called "Orangemen." In order to explain a   MY ADVENTURE ON A FROZEN LAKB.       25 little to the reader, I will merely remark that, in Canada there are two classes of the Irish population: the "Orangemen," who are sworn enemies to the principles of ,Freedom, and the Protestants who are Republicans, and are, without exception, among the noblest people in the world. Our only fears were that we might fall into the hands of the former; and in that event nothing short of killing, or being killed, was the consequence. We walked in, as he requested us to do, and found the woman sitting by the fire, surrounded by her four small children. Room was immediately made for us, and- the cup of water furnished. We then seated ourselves, and at this in- stant the two men came in. We immediately rose to our feet, and Thompson told the man who we were. and stated further, that if they wished to take us prisoners, they might make the attempt; but that we would defend ourselves at the expense of blood. One of them told him not to get alarmed be- fore he was injured; that they had no desire to molest us, and what was more, they, themselves were in favor of Canadian Liberty! but reiterated what others had told us, that their situation wag such as forbade them rendering any assistance. He remarked, too, that on the following day, both were obliged to go to Windsor, and join the militia, having been drafted. We then asked them if they were willing to let us have something to eat? to which they replied in the affirmative,; and the woman, than whom a mother could not have displayed more feeling for us, immediately set to work, preparing us a supper. During this time we related to them the sufferings through which we had passed, and their whole sympathies seemed enlisted in our behalf. They said, as did the man with whom we last stopped, that it was death by the law, -  to give comfort to any of the rebels; but that we should have a sup- per, at all events. One of the men consented to keep watch out at the door, lest some of the neighbors, of a hostile feeling; might come in. The meal ready, we sat down, and had scarcely began -eating, when our sentinel came in, and said that a man - calling him by name-was coming, and being an inveterate enemy of the rebels, it was essential that we secrete ourselves with all possible dispatch. There was a small loft to the house, and the woman proposed that we climb up there, and we did so. We had scarcely got still before the man came in. In order to allay suspicions, the whole family set down to the table, and went through all the forms of a meal, and during the time, a tirade of abuse was showered on the audacious rebels. The whole family joined in with the fellow ; and after near- ly an hour's tarry, much to our joy, he departed, carrying with him the curses-of both Thompson and myself.    ,    <pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6843-00000014"/> CHAPTER V. No sooner was the door closed on the fellow, than we come forth, like two coons, from our hiding places. We all had a, hearty laugh at what had happened; and Thompson took his watch from his pocket, worth perhaps, fifteen dollars, and made a present of it to the woman, for her faithfulness. As may be supposed, it had a ben- eficial effect, and, in reality, it welded the last link in our chain jof safety. While we were eating, I proposed to the men, that we remain there until they returned from Windsor, and as a compensation, we would allow them three dollars each a week, for our board, and fur- thermore, we would advance them twenty dollars of the money then. The only question was, where we could remain during the time, and not be discovered. There was only one room in the house, and the only place in which we could remain secreted, was either to repair to the little, low loft, over-head, or in the cellar, which was only about six feet square, and not over four feet deep. After talking the matter over, it was finally decided that a straw bed should be placed in the loft, and we remain there until they returned, which would probably be within ten days or two weeks. For the first time, the glimmering rays of Hope beamed on our vision, since the day of the battle. I was quite confident that, by proper watchfulness, we could, in due time, make our escape. The men promised to lend us all the assistance in their power; and while gone, they would make discoveries, if possible, by which to gain the Michigan side of the lines. We were then eighteen miles from Wind- sor, and about six miles to the east of the shore of Lake St. Clair. Such was our seclusion, that we could not have selected a better place, in point of safety, within the borders of Canada. It finally being decided upon that we should remain during their absence, we paid them the twenty dollars in advance, and our quar- ters was accordingly prepared. We retired early, and a better night's rest was never enjoyed, than was that night by us. In the morning, after breakfast, the men prepared for their departure - promising that if the river should chance to freeze over, one or the other, or both, would endeavor to procure a furlough, long enough to come home, and give us the information -that being the only apparent chance by which to insure us a probable safe escape. All things arranged, the men started, and we 1" went aloft." For the three first days, we did not venture, during the day, to even come down. After eight o'clock in the evening, however, we would venture to go out, and exercise by walking in the field. The time passed heavily, and every hour was ladened with anxiety. The tenth day passed, and no tidings were received of the men, or any news in relation to affairs.   MY ADVENTURE ON A FROZEN LAKE.      27 On the night of the fifteenth day after they left, about nine ia the eveninfg, and white we were out in the field, the men arrived. Learn. ing that we were out, they thought to have a joke; accordingly they watched for our return, and before coming in, they hid themselves under the bed. We came in, as usual, and after seating ourselves by the fire, in an unconcerned manner, I chanced to cast my eye round, and to my astonishment, beheld two men standing behind us, and each had our guns. Not recognizing them, I sprang to my feet, seized my chair, determined to sell my life at as dear rate as pos- sible. Thompson, too, did the same, and was in the very act pofdash- ing it at them with all his might, when the woman stepped in between them, and unfolded the actual state of affairs. Their long beards and dirty appearance, made so by exposure, had completely changed their mien. -After a hearty laugh, we exchanged the accustomed tokens of friendship, and then sat down for a long talk, in relation to affairs. They brought us the only news on which much reliance could be placed, in relation to the final termination of the battle. They made mention that a man had been found in the woods, belonging to the Volunteers, who had been murdered by sohe of the rebel party, and that a reward of one hundred and fifty dollars had been offered, by the Government, for the villian or villians who committed the deed, They told about the Indian affair, too. We put on an air of wonder '= at all that was said, as though we knew nothing in relation to it. In fact, at no time, did we ever say one word to any of the family, re- specting our exploits. But what exceeded every other pleasure, connected with their re- turn, was a letter from a valued friend at Detroit, and who, too, was in the engagement at 'Windsor, but effected his escape on the same day of the battle, in company with Gn. Bierce and others, by means of small boats, first to Hog Island, and then to the American shore, by the ice. Our host had been in Detroit quite a number of times, and on one occasion, chanced to form the acquaintance of this young man, at the hotel near the ferry, and communicated to him the intel- ligence of my being at hid house. He accordingly consented to bring me a letter; and in order to give the reader some insight into the manner in which things were managed, I will give the letter at length. It cannot fail to prove interesting, although it does not properly be- long to our story. Still it is connected with it, and what is more, it is true to the nicest point in truth. I will give it without abridgment, bat shall reserve the name of the writer, from motives of which the public have no care about. DETROIT, December 20th, 1838. DEAR H--  : You are little aware what pleasure it yielded me, on learning from Mr. S-- of your safety, and that you was in com- fortabje quarters. H had g'ven you up as dead, and had written to your brother that such was the case. Robinson, who made his escape the eighth day after the engagement, told me that he was quite sure    <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6843-00000015"/> that he saw you among the dead, in the orchard; and hearing no tidings to the contrary, that belief was about confirmed. "You maycuare to know something how affairs proceeded with us, in our retreat up the river, and the manner in which myself and some thirty others, among whom was Gen. Berce, made out escape, and if you will bear patiently with me, I will relate it minutely, and in detail. After our separation at the barracks, and the division to which you was attached. commenced the action in the orchard, Gen. Bierce found th tt we were completely cut off from the support of Gen. Putnam, by a company of bri'ish Regulars; who had manraged to get in between us; and learning, too, that a large reinforcement of the enemy was near at hand, from the fort at Maiden, ordered a re- treat up the river. We would not have retreated so soon, however, had we not ascertained that the enemy was supported by a Frass "4 six pounder," and that, under the manaement of skillful artillery- men. This gave them a decided superiority and to contend against them, would exhibit a want of sense and rea- on. Pievious to our retreat, however, Gen. Bierce sent word to your division, or rather, to Gen. Putnam, to fall back to where we were, but the poor fellow, James Riley, (you knew lim) was met by a company of the enemy, and shot down. We waited a long time for his report, before we learned his fate. "Gen. Bierce then order d that the prisoners, which we had taken at the barracks -twenty-six in number I think it was,- to be placed on the right flank, so that should the enemy overtake us, they would be obliged to kill their own men first. In this manner we retreated up the river, in the utmost order. When - bout three miles from the town, we were overtaken by another scout, who communicated the fatal intelligence that Gen. Putnam had fled to the woods in the wild- est confusion, and that a large number of his men had been 1 illed. i"I cannot inform you the shock which this intelligence gave me. What to do, was a question none could properly answer. General Bierce, however, remained rerfectly calm, and told us that fear never y t effected success; and thinking that a ruse might be made use of to ndvaniage, he tuined to Col. Scott, and remarked in a somewhat more than common audible manner, and in the presence of the pris- oners that, Gen Plutrnam had made the retreat a; he had 'directed, to the woods, where the two regiments were quartered in ambush, and he was really in hopes that it would be the means of inducing the enemy to follow them. "In that case," said he,-" we can fall upon their rear, and completely cut them to pieces." "The Colonel, understanding the matter, coincided at once, with Gen. Bierce, but expressed much fear that the enemy could not be in- duced to follow. There was one of the prisoners who complained mtl( h, or in other words, pretended sickness, and begged hard to be released before we left Windsor. He belonged to the Essex Militia. b hile we were standing there, he kept begging to be released, and finally the General told him that, if he would promise not to take *   MY ADVENTURE ON A FROZEN LAKE.       29 Up arms again, he might go, and off he started for Windsor, at full speed. "t he plan worked precisely as Gen. Bierce anticipated; for no sooner did he make the ann,uncement to tha enemy whom he met, respecting the two - by the way -" imaginary Regiments," than they return3d back to Windsor, which gave quite a number of us a chance to make our escape to Hog Island, and there on the ice to this land of Freedom. "We had nearly as much to fear from Gen. Brady, of the Ameri can Army, as from the enemy. He was in command of the steam- boat "Erie," which was plying up and down the river, and every chance which offered itself, he made prisoners of those who were en- deavoring to escape in' small boats to Hog Island. I4 so happensed that I got over in the first, and in company with Gen. Bierce; but the British. finding that there was no 'Regiments, in ambush,' returned back to where our men were crossing, and immediately opened a tre. mendous tire of grape and canister sheot on them. In one instance COpt. Armstrang had his arm completely out off, and Capt. Douglass, too, was knocked overboard. Bradey sqcceeded in taking quite a number of our men, while endeavoring to cross, and at night they were arll lodged in the jail at Detroit. On my arrival at Detroit that evening. the whole city' was in tt e most intense excitement. It was  feared that the British would fire red hot balls in the city and lay it in a-hes. "Some ten or fifteeen of the influential citizens of the city went over to Windsor during the day, and the stories which they related on their return, was enough to make humanity shudder. A lar e number of the dead lay nearly stripped of their clothing, andin one or two instances, the hogs had mutilated them in a horrid manner: The daughter of Gen. Putnam went over to beg the body of her dead father; but that inhuman monster, (ol. Prince, refused to co(nrpy, and st 'ted that he was sorry that he was dead, as he wished the priv; ilege of hanging him alive. "' Nearly every one taken previously to the first. day, was barbar, ously put to death by Plir ce, without the slightest trial, and it made no difference whether taken with or without arms, death. was their portion. For a week after, reports came over of large numbers being found in the woods frozen to death. Those who were' spared, are now at Maiden, confined in the hull of an old vessel, suffering every privation. Tthey are shortly to b- taken to the London District, and then the gallows will hsave plenty of work, I suppose. "There is scarcely a day passs, but what some one effects their escape to this side, and a sad spectacle they present. Their ema- ciated forms and sunken eye, too plainly indicate that the hand of misfortune has been laid heavily upon them; and so common has it become to see them, that the citizens are rather indifferent about the matter --so that many, after they land here, find little to yield them a necessary relief.    <pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6843-00000016"/> "I do not give you this dark side of the picture, dear old friend, in order to dishearten you, by no means. I am confident that you feel anxious to know the reality of affairs, and I write accordingly. Mr. S--  says that no pains shall be wanting to render you all the assistance in his power. He is a noble-hearted Irishman, and no mistake. I have just purchased him a barrel of flcur, for your sake - although, he informs me, that you have already paid him quite liberally. I do not know that Mr. Thompson, which Mr. S-- speaks of, and whom he informs me, is with you. He must be of the ' right stripe,' however, or you would not companion with him. Now, then, Mr. S--  and myself have hit upon this plan for your escape, and it is the only one that [ know of, which will prove successful, and we have thought and talked the matter all over, from Alpha to Omega,' and it is this: "The weather is getting intensely cold, and I think that the river will freeze ,over, so as to be able to cross on it, by to-morrow morn- ing; but such is the vigilance kept up by the Government officers on the other side, that it would not do for you to attempt to come so far down, and make a crossing. Besides that, you are well known in the vicinity of Windsor, and it is intimated that you was the one who shot Dr. Hume, the British Surgeon. But I know better than that, for I saw G--  M-- when he did it, and he has now got his watch, and a valuable one it is, too. This, however, is not telling you about the said escape.  "I went up to Lake St. Clair, yesterday, and so far as my eye could reach, it was one field of ice, and after mature reflection, I think it will be best for you to wait until, say the 25th inst. (Christ- mas night,) when there will be a moon, and in the evening come to the lake and cross over at the point opposite where you now are. It will be a herculean undertaking, for the Lake is twenty-one miles wide; but such is the precarious situa ion in which you are placed, that it will require an extraordinary movement on your part, to be. come, once more, a citizen of the land of the 'stars and stripes.: "Mr. S-- informs me that he leaves for home day'after to-mor- row, and he says that he will take observations of the lake on that side on his return, and if it is frozen, will inform you of it. I; have spun my letter to a much greater length than I anticipated ; still, I have not told you one-half that I wish it was in my power to tell. Take hold of my project, for your liberation, resolutely, and as sure as rises yon sun in the eastern sky again, so sure, old friend, will we greet each other, once more, as friends ever desire to meet, ' face to face.'         "Forever Thine,    O. C--." The sensation which this letter produced on my mind, " will de- scend with me to the grave." I read and reread the letter, w ith in- tense interest, but the idea of venturing to cross the lake, on the ice, when it was twenty-one miles in width, seemed too visionary, and withal too hazardous. Thompson, however, liked the scheme, and said that, so far as he was concerned, he was perfectly willing to   MY ADVENTURE ON A FROZEN LAKE.       31 make the trial. It being late when the men were at the lake, they could not tell whether it was frozen or not, but said that on the fol- lowing day, they would, go down, and on their return, something definite could be determined--upon, in relation to the matter The men, agreeable to arrangement, went down the next day, and on their return, brought the somewhat welcome news that, as far as thewcould see, nothing but a frozen world was presented. The idea did-not strike the men very favorably, as it was a feat thay was never before attempted, in any emergency. A something told me that a fatal result would be the issue; still, it was wholly out of the ques- tion for us to remain where we were much' longer, as all who were drafted were daily being discharged from Service, and the final' on- sequence, would prove our discovery and detection.- I pondered anid weighed the subject in all its bearings, and in every conclusio, -the same result presented itself-namely, a fatal terminations Summoning, at last, all the resolution of which I was earthly pos- sessed, I agreed that, on the next night, if the weather was not too boisterous, we would launch our destinif s on a frozen lake. During the whole of the night, the idea haunted my imagination with a ghost-like horror, despite every thing I could do, to give the scheme a favorable constructicn. Thomrson lay and slept as soundly as though the morrow was the harbinger of a promised good, and his future days to be long and full of propitious fortune. Naturally possessed ol a terperament which never permitted any reverses to cloud his serenity of feeling, he could sleep as soundly and dream as pleasantly, M ith a battle-field for his bed-chamber, and a corpse for his pillow, as could Innocence in a gar- den of roses. His equal so far as regards danger, I have never yet met with. On the other hand, I was as timid as I was cautious- daring, however, to do any thing where there appeared the slightest probability of success, which made us as unlike each other, in nearly every respect, as an acid and an alkali. Among the wisest dispensations in the ordination of Providence, is the keeping folded of those mystic curtains which shut the future from our gaze, arid never permits them to be drawn aside, however fervent may be our prayers to the contrary. We can often look back with philosophic calmness, and contemplate the many hazardous events which have, at different periods, checkered our lives with momentous concern, and in many instances with regret; but were it poseible for us to know and discern the multiplicity of trials which are laid up in store for uss and which in the process of time, we shall be called upon to encounter, how many noble hearts would bleed with anguish, and how incessantly would our eyes be suffused with tears. Under the weight of care and anxiety, which such a state of existence would produce, the world which now presents so much beauty and happi- ness, would be converted into a "wilderness of wo," and make man, now lord of Creation, the offspring of mourning, the pupil of trouble, and the ultimate victim of sorrow and remorse.    <pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6843-00000017"/> CHAPTER VI. Agreeably to the arrangement made, the next night, which was Christmas eve, at a little after dusk, we prepared for a departure. The better to elude detection in case we should chance to meet with any one on the way, the oxen were yoked to a large sledge, on which was placed a quantity of loose oats straw, and in this we were to con- ceal ourselves. The moon, at the time of our starting, was riding in her full splendor; but before we arrived at the Lake shore, thin hazy clouds, swept occasionally over her surface. It was near nine o'clock, when we "came to the beach," and a rather strong breeze was blowing from the American side of the Lake, and in the precise direction which was pointed out to us, where to proceed, and which, if we were fortunate enough in gaining, would take us within ten miles of Detroit. All things arranged, we bid them adieu, and with their blessing on our heads, we started. Thompson proposed, that I should take the lead, which proposition I readily accepted. I told Thompson, after we had got out a mile or some such a matter, on the ice, to take particular notice how the wind struck us, as that was our only guide by which to steer. The breeze was fresh but steady; and I knew if it changed to any other point of the compass, it would be preceded by a calm. The ice ap- peared perfectly solid, and at times it was so glare, that it was with the utmost difficulty we could keep our feet; and sometime when we were in the middle of one of these glare places, of the space of ten acres, perhaps a gust of strong wind would strike us, and-drive us back with much force, to its outer edge. The weather, too, seemed to change with the moments nearly. At one time, the moon would appear in unclouded majesty, and in less than fifteen minutes, it would be hid from the gaze, behind dark clouds which drove across the sky in a frightful and hurried manner. To add to the wildness of the scene, the air occasionally would be filled with flying snow, or frost, accompanied by a dismal roar, like the distant rumblings of a coming earthquake. The ice, too, was almost incessantly giving forth a sharp loud cracking s und, in short, no description, can portray, in anything of a graphic manner, the appearance of the dreary frozen aspect that surrounded us. We continued, however, to proceed with all possible dispatch, and when out to the distance of perhaps eight miles, we came to an opening in the ice, and from appearance, the opening was about a half a mile in width, and stretched each way as far as the eye could reach. This as may be expected, induced us to think our chance for pro- ceeding further, a hopeless one. To return we knew was akin to certain death; and to proceed was impossible, that is, in the right direction, and what to do we could not satisfactorially determine. I   MY ADV3NTUft' ON A FROZBN LAKE.       3 told Thompson that we would make an effort to find an end to the opening, and we accordingly started up the lake, in a horizontal line with the water. For some distance it appeared about the same uniform width, but at last it began to narrow down to only a few rods in width, and at length it tapered out in a sort of oval shape, and we passed round it. This gave a new impulse to our 'feelings, and I then remarked to Thompson' that we, had better return as near as possible to the spot opposite from whence we started, and then emerge out once more in the world of ice. . . We did so, and after proceeding five or six miles furtheri to our astonishment and deep regret, we came to another, but still' wider sheet of water, and what was worse, as the moon peeped through the dark clouds, each and every way, to the very extent of ourvis- ion, a gloomy, watery waste was prezented. , The wind continued to freshen, and-in:its eddying gusts, it would nearly take our breath. There are situations in life, in which a person can be placed, when the fears which accompany the thought of death,' is lost -in the mighty vortex of despondency and indifference. At such a period, his frozen and palid touch is welcomed with emotions of calm re- signation, and even joy. And such were my feelings in that season of doubt-and dismay. Death, in any form, short of the horrors of sui- cide, would have been courted with a smile of fervor; still, a some, thing, a sort of inward monitor, which rarely forsakes us in "times that. try men's souls," seemed 'to sustain and prompt me to brave, with manly fortitude, the ordeal of the hour:, and I therefore re. solved to brave my fate, let whatever might betide.  We thought ithest, as in the forrher case, to make the trial, and see if an end to the opening could not 'be found. Thompson re- marked that it would not do for him to remain standing much longer, as he was nearly chilled to the heart. We. then set out,' as before, up the lake, and in a horizontal line with the water. The wind, if any thing, increased in force the further we got from the shore; and by. this time, the whole air was one continual Aloud of snow and' frost. The moon, too, was fast sinking to the :horizon, adding gloom and desolation to all around. We -promeededi however, as best we could, for two miles or more, and to our joyful surprise, we found that, like the other sheet of water, it terminated in the same kind of oval shape. Passing around it, we attempted to return the same distance we had come, but in this we were foiled. So strong' did the wind- continue to blow, that itwas a matter of impossibility for us to stem the current. Time, and again, did we make the attempt to proceed down, but all to no purpose ;- and we finally set our faces American- ward, and startedoff dwith all the speed possible.  -We had' not gone far, .hdwerer,whei- Thominpsnstopped uite suddenly, and remarked to me, that wewreeturned round, and go. ing the wrong way; that is, we were makingto ur Wa .baek the Canadian shore, and, stated; too, thatwe must-immediately chage 3    <pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6843-00000018"/> our course, or our fates were forever sealed. I told him that such was not the case, as the wind, in that event, would be to our back, instead of striking us, as it had done ever since we started, in our faces; and begged him, in the most urgent terms, to come on. We started on again, but he, instead of keeping up with me, as he had - formerly done, begun to lag behind, and every now and then, I would stop and urge him to proceed faster. He finally came to a dead stand, and declared in the most emphatic manner, that he would not proceed one step further in the direction we were then going, and even went so far as to turn round and start back. I immediately ran and overtook him, and feelingly requested him, by all that was dear and sacred, not to prove stubborn, and that if he would pause awhile, I thought I could satisfactorily convince him of his error. He accordingly stopped, and I made use of every argument in my power, to convince him, but all proved unavailing. He then began to exhibit an uncommon degree of fretfulness, and was impatient to be moving on. Complained most piteously of cold, and declared that he had stood by me, in every emergency, and now I was unwilling to comply, for the first time, with his wishes. H'o persuasion to be permitted to follow his own inclination, affected me in the highest degree; but so certain was I that he was laboring un- der a mistake, that I was determined not to yield to-his misdirected mind. He again turned his face toward the Canadian shore, and bidding me farewell, started off, I stood a moment, and thought I should be obliged to abandon him; but friendship still bade me cling to him. I overtook him once more, and brought him again to a halt. We held a lng parley; during which time he complained most bitterly of being cold. He stated, however, that under no consideration, could he be induced to go any other than his own way. I could not harbor the idea of leaving him; but my persuasions proving a use- less expenditure of time and words, I was on the eve of leaving him in good earnest. He spoke and said that he was tired, and said that he must set down and rest awhile, In a short time he complained of feeling sleepy, and even went so far as to propose taking a short nap. It was then at once evident to me that he was freezing; and I made use of every stratagem to rouse him up, by telling him that I saw a light on the shore, and requested him to get up and look, too; but all tat I said was of no earthly purpose. He then complained that his legs were cramping, and begged me to rub them. I complied with his reques and rbbed them as hard as I could. I had, myself, stood so long that I was chilled nearly through, and the cold continued to increase, and the darkness con- tinued to increase with the cold. Thompson kept muttering over some indistinct words, and for the purpose of endeavoring to rouse him, I commenced taunting him; and occasionally I would give him a slight kick, hoping by this means to get him angry. Finally I told him I believed Iwas wrong, and that if he would come on, I would /   nr aV*wu   O A BOtXzw Uas      35 follow him.- AU this, however, failed to have any effet; h on begged me the maore:piteously to let him alone, na not disturb him Whenever'he lay down I woud sit him lup, and made sayeal efforteA to raise him tohis feet, but his strength as well as powers offsensi bility, were so far exhiusted by cold, that I at once saw he was forever beyond the reach of any beneficial assistance on my pa. e Lookinginathe distance, as the moon began to disappear beIQw the  horizon, I was quite confident that I could discover the "1loom of the land," and the better to satisfy myself that such was actuallythe case, I walked to and fro for some considerable space, in order to make observations. From what I could discover, I was confident that I was not deceived, and the land did not appear over six or eight miles off. I then turned my attention once more to Thompson and such was the darkness that it took some time to find him. On approaching him, he lay at ful length on the ice, ith his rmside from fainting. 1 became so much agitated that my whole frame shook with violent convulsions, and for a time, I became-alarmed for my own safety. .    . I finally recovered myself a little, and spoke a few word, to him, by asking him how he felt; but the only answer I received in ex' change, was an occasional groan, companied by a long breath. I drew my glove and felt of his pulse, and no beat was perceptible.  then unbuttoned his coat and vest, and placing iiy hand on the fie- gon of his heart, found that it continued to throb very slightly. i immediately buttoned up his coat again, and made an effort traise him' up, but the rigidity of death was on him. Plaing: 'ycheek close to his mouth, I could feel, or fancied I could feel his- Wb e v If - waited with him some ten minutes longerperhaps, and when it was apparent that he was dead, I turned lhis fet in the directionOf th east, placed his hands across his breast, gave his departd siit my ouls best blessing, and his body a forever farewell! What my feelings were, in that hour of solemnity, is a point in my history I shall not be able to convey ---whe thus leaving one in the cold embrace of Death, and one too, who in every exigency of danger, was my warmest and truest friend. - Such wa :his doy deo tion to me, that had it been necessary, during our wanderin in the land of the enemy, to have sacrificed life in ' my defense lie would have offered it up 'a eely as doe0s the truly peete his mornt and evening prayers. With all the vciousuess of spirit, asexhibited on the several eceasins -hichI hae already narrated, t shall never forget with what warmth of timent he often spoke relation to his widowed mother and oher relatives, as we s at before oursolitary camp-fire, in thewinhospitable wilds of Canada.    -  ime and again, would he tell me, when I expresised any seiots doubts of ever making good our escape, that despondency -in adverse circumstances, was the sure indication of a cowardice of the lowest    <pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6843-00000019"/> 36      MY ADVExTUBE O A .RZi*  , AdIo. order; while a buoyancy of heart, and incessant firm resolves to rise superior to the troubled circumstances which chanced to sur. round us, was the highest evidence of philosophy and real heroism. As proof of what he, said, he called to mind the innumerable in- stances which are recorded on the pages of history, of the mighty ends which had been attained, and propitious results accomplished, by making such examples a standard and rule of conduct. -"Many a time and oft" would I have given up in loneliness of heart and anguish of soul, but for those sustaining words which he was so wont to pour in my almost ear of dumbness; and the conse. quence was, he had become endeared to me, in many ways, by the establishment of a friendship as deep and abiding as the real auties of life are vast and momentous. We are often prone to praise those deeds, which at the moment of their being transacted, we abhor and condemn, and vice versa. Leaving the corpse, I journeyed on toward the shore, and in the same direction to which I was the hour before tending, and made my way in the best manner possible, through the midnight darkness. The ice was not so glare as it had been, but it was extremely rough, and in some places, in consequence of being jammed by the winds and the waves, it was piled up in long winnows, some eight or ten feet high, which rendered my progress very difficult. . I kept a con- stant look out for the land, but after an hour's hard traveling, nothing but the same frozen scene appeared before and around me, and I be- gun to think that I was, in reality, making my course in the wrong direction. Determined, however, to know the worst of the matter, I contin- ued to proceed. and within two hours after I left the dead body of Thompson, and without perceiving it, I came suddenly to a high, bluff bank, and what it was, whether land or a large mass of ice- it being covered with snow- I could not tell. 1 examined it forsome time; but could not satisfy myself what it was. One thing, I saw it to be inaccessible. I resolved to know something in relation to it, and commenced following it up the lake, and had not gone far before I found a place by which to scale it, and on ascending, to my aston- isliment, 1 found it to be the shore. Near by stood an old wind-mill, and on the opposite side was a large orchard. By this-time, the day began to dawn; and about a quarter of a mile to my left, I heard the barking of a dog. I was quite undetermined in my mind, how- ever, whether it was the Canada or the, American shore. I knew if it was the former, it was then too late to retreat, and if the latter, I was in the arms of safety. In eithercase, was determined to enter some building, and abide the consequences. I proceeded in the direction of the noise, and came, at length, to an old French mansion, which had all the air of contentment, and walking up to the door, gave it two or three loud raps, and a voice within answered me, but it was in French, and I could not under stand it. I spoke in English, and said that I wished to come in; and   MY ADVThTtfkE ON A fMOZBN'/LAt.      37 after' a long time, the door was opened, and an old Frenchiman stood before me. I walked immediately in, and he kept up a-sort of mut- tering, not one word of which could I understand. 1, too, kept talk- ing, as he was endeavoring to start the fire, and he Was as bad off as myself; he could not understand me. After the fire was built, * young man, whom I afterwards learned was his son, came in the room, in a half dressed condition, and I asked him if he could speak the English? to which he replied in the affirmative. He spoke the English plainly. I asked him how far it was to Windsor? being yet in doubt as to whether I was on the right shore. He told me that it was twelve miles to Detroit, and that Windsor was on the opposite side. This at once banished all my fears and I then told him that I had just at that moment made a" landing " from the lake, having crossed it on the ice, and thus escaped from the jaws of death. I told him that I had been wandering in the woods for nearly three weeks; in short, told him the whole of my troubles. He then communicated my story to the rest of the household, who by this time had assembled, and they looked at me with an air of astonishment. Every attention necessary to my comfort, was then extended to me; and I remained with them the whole of that day and night, and on the following morning, after making me a present of a change of under garments, the first change which I had made in a little over five weeks, the young man put his horse before his "carryall," and took me down to Detroit. I made a still younger brother of the man, who seemed to take quite a fancy to the Queen's piece," (gun) a present of it; and he said that it never should go out of the family possession; that is, that it should be kept as a kind of family heir-loom. On my arrival at Detroit, I found the two men with whom I had tarried while in Canada, awaiting our presence. Never did a man receive a more heartfelt reception than was extended to me. I com- municated to them the unhappy intelligence of the fate of our mutual friend, Thompson. Every demonstration of sorrow and regret was manifested by them at the event. I told my friend 0. C--, who was present at the same time, to make no mention of it, as it would only be distorted by the newspaper press, and the mournful tidings of cruelty and suffering which was constantly being published from day to day, touching Candian matters, had nearly, or quite turned the mind of the public from its legitimate pursuits - serving only to keep alive a relentless spirit of animosity between the two countries, and from which no ultimate good was to be gathered. The battle of Windsor was the last struggle made by the "Revo- lutionary Patriots," in relation to the Fresdom of Canada; and was, in fact, the termination of all the hopes of its friends of both sides. Finding myself once more free, I immediately turned my attention to the plucking of those fruits which grow along the paths of peace -being perfectly satisfied, or rather "satiated" with that "con- scious glory" that is said to attend the soldier, when contending on    <pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC6843-00000020"/> 38      MY ADVBNTURE ON A FROZEN LAKEB the field of blood, for those "I inalienable rights," which the "Laws of Nature and Nature's God entitles him ;" but which, alas I is too often debarred from his enjoyment, by the potent power of unholy usurpation and despotic tyranny. /           THE MASSACRE AT OWEGO' AN INDIAN TALE. The recent opening of the New York and Erie Rail Road calls many a traveler through a section of country, which was once the scene of daring events, and bloody deeds,- and among the most prominent tragedies which occurred in the early days of Indian life, was the Massacre At Owego. Few, however, of the present day, are acquainted with the details of this thrilling incident, and the writer is, in a great measure, indebted to the blessings of a more than ordi- nary retentive memory, for the materials which make up this really Historical Sketch. It was related to him, many years since, by an aged and respected friend, whose father had it from the lips od an old Indian, who was a prominent actor in the drama. About one hundred and fifty years ago, there existed in the vicinity of the now thriving villages of Owego and Binghampton, in the State of New York, two powerful tribes of Indians, known by the renowned titles of Tiogas and Susquehannas. Both tribes were nearly equal in point of strength, and numbers, which caused an incessant spirit of hatred and jealousy to exist between the chiefs of each tribe. They often had skirmishes, in which some favorite Indian, or squaw, fell a victim to the poisoned arrow, or the. more dreaded tomahawk.' As the tribes increased in age and numbers, ambition and jealousy burned more fiercely in the breasts of their leaders, until, at length, it became a matter of extreme danger for one or the other of the tribes to be out on a hunting excursion alone; for he seldom returned, without being fired upon, and either receiving a wound, or being taken prisoner, and carried to his enemies' wig- wam, there to undergo all the excruciating tortures of savage invention.        l This unrighteous business awakened, at length, in the minds of the respective chiefs, all the bitterest feelings of animosity. Revenge, the darling passion of savage and civilized man, stood foremost in their minds, and a gratification of this spirit, was either to be satiated by an open declaration of war, or quenched by the proceedings of a council for a general amnesty. Kewasko, the leader and chief of the Susquehannas, gave notice to his councillors, that, on a certain day, a question of a grave and important nature would be discussed- and being assembled, he related to them the fatal results which would inevitably come to pass, if the then existing rankling jealousy between    <pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC6843-00000021"/> 40         THE MASSACRE AT OWEGO. them and the Tiogas was not immediately quelled by mutual con- sent. It was, therefore, resolved that a deputation of young war- riots should be sent to Owanko, the leader and chief of the Tiogas, with a request that they all meet at some convenient place, and there bury the hatchet of discussion, and smoke the Pipe of Peace. Consequently, the four young warriors were selected, and being rainted in all the majesty becoming their mission, started with in. structions to implore their inimical brothers to accede to the proffered terms. In due course of time, they returned with the welcome tidings that Owanko was extremely anxious for the interview. On the following day, they were sent back to Owanko's wigwam, with a solicitation for him to point out the spot where, and name the time when, the Council should be held. He accordingly selected the site where now stands the village of Owego, (from whom the town de- rives its name,) and which at that time was the emporium, or rather, trading point, it being the most central place, on account of the Cat- elant, which flows from the north, and there empties into the Sus- quehanna, and thus they could descend in their canoes from that region, and from the east and west, by the Susquehanna river. The joyous intelligence spread with the rapidity of fire on an untimbered prairie among the two tribes; strict injunctions were made on both sides, not to commit any act which should, in the slight- est manner, endanger the good feeling that was fast gaining strength, and the prospect continued to brighten, as the time for the council drew nigh. The omen of better days was every where discernible. It was on the first day of the new moon that the armistice was agreed upon, and the middle of the month was set apart as the day they were to assemble. In a short time the Susquehanna was dotted with the birchen canoes, all leaving for the destined post, where hos- tilities were to find a grave in the harmony of generous sentiment. The morning of the 15th of June saw all that portion of the Indian world assembled at Owego. Their tents were pitched in a uniform line, and at every convenient spot, groups of the different tribes were seen sitting in their accustomed posture, smoking, and relating their various adventures after the deer and elk, for which the country was then noted. The squaws were busily employed in preparing their coarse fare, and peace and contentment were the handmaids of the encampment. As the morning sun walked up his path of azure, the vapors van- ished, and nauoght but the smoke from the camp fires obscured the calm atmosphere above. A beautiful grove, near by, which had been the theatre of many a military plot, by the fathers of those assembled, was neatly swept, as the spot where the chiefs were to gather and debate upon the future plans of mutual friendship. A breathless anxiety pervaded the minds of all present, and save the hum of the wild bee, or the song of a bird from a neighboring tree, the silence was profound. The signal for the final gathering, was made by the beat on a large   THB MA4SAOUR AT OWISGO,        41 drdm of rough, Indian structure. The two chiefs, with their subal- terns, immediately moved in the direction of the selected spot, in all the pomp and majesty of savage life, and painted in the most hideous, as well as the most fiwtastic manner possible, each with their hair profusely decorated with the feathers of different birds, and according to their rank and station in office. Each of the chiefs appeared at the head of their staf assuming the most ferocious look, and eahi "clothed upon" with a large bear skin.  Their tents having been pitched in an opposite direotipn, the two, companies met at one and the same moment at thehgrove, where h consultation was to be held. s .the two chiefs approached in sight of each other, their eyes flashed with all their Wonted fire of lie;, still, the importance and solemnity of the occasion, forbade them showing, either by look or deed, the least feeling of a hostile nature., Each party was attended by a Prophet, whose duty it was to officiate in the rites and ceremonies necessary for the council. When they had arrived to within forty paces of each other, a halt was made by both sides, while the respective Prophets walked forward, and met.- ing saluted each other, according to the terms of peace and concord. This being the signal for the two chiefs to come forward, and ex- change sentiments of good will, the warlike monarchs stepped forth in all their native pride, and after shaking each other heartily by the hand, proceeded to the spot where seats had been prepared for them, covered with the moss of the mountain-rock-an emblem of age and reverence. It needed no artificial aid to shut out the rays of tXe sun from their devoted heads, for the dense boughs of the beech, maple, and broad-spread hemlock, formed a most delightful shade. It was, indeed, a monotonous period; for, although there were assembled on an area of, perhaps, ten acres, nearly three thousand Indians, one would have scarcely believed that a human being was in existence. In the far-off thicket, was occasionally heard "The twittering cry of some fugitivebird," and this, with the monotonous song of the locust and other insects, was the only noise to disturb the quiet of the scene. In slow, array, the Indians came marching toward the grove in long files, and seated themselves in a circle, leaving the center of the grove unoccupied, as the place where the speeches were to be delivered, and the other pro- ceedings perfected. In the course, of an hour, all became seated, and every necessary arrangement being accomplished, Kewasko ad- vanced with a firm step, to the center of the grove, and throwing back his head, delivered the following animated address: "THE GREAT SPIRIT, my brethren, has called aloud on Kewasko, to arouse the people committed to his care and keeping, from the wicked deeds of cruelty, to which they have fallen; like- wise, to implore his august and powerful brother Owanko, to accept the terms which I am now about to propose. In accordance with the promptings-of a truthful conscience, therefore, I sent to my    <pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6843-00000022"/> ,4.2e       THE MASSACRE AT OWEGO. brother Owanko, to meet me, and smoke the Pipe of Peace. He, as a noble and worthy brother should do, has nobly accepted the invi- tation, and we now present a spectacle which the Great Spirit looks down upon with pleasing countenance. Such a spectacle, my brethren, was never before known in the history of nations. Never before has so large a body of brave Indians been assembled, on an occasion so full of interest, as the present. For a long period, I have warred my brother Owanko, and, in nearly every instance, when an occa- sion presented itself, have put his soldiers to a death, the most horrid which Kewasko could devise. I have destroyed Owanko's corn fields, laid waste his fine forests by fire, spread desolation and terror, by acts of cruelty and blood. And whathas all this been perpetrated for? "Not for wrongs which he has personally done me; but for the purpose of satisfying the cravings of an unrighteous ambition, devoid of bounds. Kewasko wishes to put an end, and that too, forever, to this wretched state of affairs. He wishes to take Owanko and Tidga by the hand, and welcome him and them as children of his own tribe. He wishes to see all dissensions driven from each and every breast. Are we not all heirs of one common parent? Did not the Great Spirit make the broad earth for Owanko and his children, as well as for Kewasko's? Then, why bathe our arrows and tomahawks in the blood of our kindred? From this, henceforward, let us act as rational beings, and not like the fierce animal, whose skin I now wear, to denote its rude nature in me. Our forests abound with game suitable to the adventurous chase. Then let us abandon the destruc- tion of one another, and thus show to our children that the detest. able practice of murdering our friends, displeases the Great Spirit, at whose bidding we could be struck. dead, at a moment's time. It is my desire to preserve my dignity and station in the nation I guard and protect; and I equally desire that Owanko should preserve his. We each know the limits of our country, which are marked by our hunting trails. "Let the people of Owanko be contented to keep within their own bounds, and the people of Kewasko shall do the same. When we meet a Tioga, instead of hurling the arrow at his breast, let us meet him with a hearty smile; and if weary with the heat and burden of a sultry, summer day, invite him to the wigwam of our squaw, and share with him, even the last piece of venison; so that, when we meet in the country beyond the mountains of the Great Susquehanna, we may meet, not covered with scars made in battle, but in the cos- tume and painting which gives the Indian pride and nobleness of feeling." Thus closed the patriotic and soul-stirring speech of the warrior and chief of the Susquehannas. He was cheered by the shouts of all who heard him; for every word he uttered was listened to with profound attention. Every syllable had its desired effect. His commanding appearance and gestures, served to make his words strike sympathy to every Indian heart.   THE MASSAORE AT OWEGO.         43 Kewasko returned to his seat, and was met by Owanko, who passed the usual salutation of respect, due Kewasko's rank and sta- tion. He then proceeded to where Kewasko had made his speech, and folding his arms closely upon his breast, in turn began; "Friends and Brethren: My distinguished brother of the powerful Susquehannas, has awakened such an emotion of feeling in my breast, that I am at a loss for words to express my own sentiments in relation to the importance of the occasion. He has givehi a true picture of the cruelties which we have exercised' toward one another; and if, as he intimates, this unholy business of butchering our brethren is not soon ended, when a few more moons shall have rolled over our heads, not a remnant of all our vast number will be left to tell the heroic deeds of our fathers and ourselves. Our lands will be overrun by the pale faces, our beautiful hunting grounds laid open, and made subject to their own convenience; our rivers impeded by their dams; our wigwams removed or destroyed; and as for Owanko, he desires peace, he wishes to see tranquility restored; and, moreover, he wishes to live on terms of friendship and intimacy with every Susquehanna. Any reasonable sacrifice which Owanko can make, consistent with right and reason, shall be freely extended. Owanko delights to see so many of his own and Kewasko's brethren assembled for the fulfilment of such a glorious cause as the present exhibits. The Good Spirit is present with us all, to-day; not an' Indian in mine and Kewasko's nation, but feels to rejoice in the pro- ceedings of this glorious day. Even the beasts which roam our forests, seem to despise the act of unnecessarily taking the life of each other; and shall we, who can count the stars, and navigate the great rivers, and in secret talk with the Great Spirit, who made all, and rules over all -shall we, I say, do that, which even the wild beasts scorn to commit? Owanko rejoices for the privilege of thus expressing his sentiments, not only to his, but to Kewasko's people. He prays from the inmost depths of his heart, that the pro- ceedings of this day will forever put a stop to the further shedding of each other's blood.  / "If Owanko has offended, either by word or deed, one Susque- hanna present or absent, he now offers his hand in friendship, and his speech, in asking pardon. And if tears, yea, even the bitterest tears of deep and abiding regret, could wash out and reconcile the painful recollection of the past, Owanko would weep, as when a child in his mother's arms. His prayers, however, night and morning, shall hereafter be, Union, BHarmony and Good Will, with the noble Tiogas, and the no less generous Susquehannas." The latter clause of this animated speech was given with all that emphasis of tone and meaning which gives sublimity as well as solemnity to language. The wood again resounded with their patriotic shouts, which plainly indicated that the links in the chain of friendship were riveted by the bonds of peace, and never again to be torn asunder. Owanko was welcomed back to his seat by Kewas-    <pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6843-00000023"/> "        THE MASSACRBE AT OWEGO. ko, with the enthusiasm so peculiar to the Indian character. The excitement having somewhat subsided, a council fire was made on the spot where the two chiefs had delivered their speeches. In a few moments, the Prophe ts of the respective tribes were seen approaching it, side by side, each bearing a large pipe, filled with tobacco. They seated themselves by the fire, opposite to each other, and simultaneously lit them at the blaze. The two Chiefs then pro- ceeded arm in arm, and seated themselves beside the Prophets- and they at the same time handed them the lighted pipes. After taking two or three puffs, the pipes were handed back to the Prophets, who immediately exchanged them with each other, and this was the token that peace had found a resting place in the bosoms of the two tribes. Preparations were then made to have a dance in the grove. They chose their partners, each, however, taking a squaw of their own tribe. When the music commenced-which was nothing more than a beat on a kind of drum, and the shaking of numerous strings of beads -the celebrated dance began. The two Chiefs, with their Prophets, and other distinguished men, did not join them ; but sat as spectators, and viewed with cheerfulness the merriment of the scene. While enjoying all the pleasures of the moment, the proceedings were interrupted by the screams at a short distance, of some one in distress. A general rush was made in that direction, by nearly all the Indians, and the utmost consternation prevailed. On their arrival at the place from whence the noise proceeded, they found two squaws in a fight, uttering the most hideous words, and covered with blood. It appeared, upon inquiry, that one of the little children of the Tiogas had caught a large grasshopper, which the Indians of that day ate, and considered as their most delicious food; and that another, but still larger child of the Susquehannas, on seeing him catch it, ran and took it away from him. This making the mother of the little Tioga angry, she ran and struck the Susquehanna with a large club; and this, as a matter of course, urged on the other mother. The sight of blood drove immediately from their minds all the good feeling which had existed for the two previous weeks, and then commenced one of the most appalling massacres ever known in the annals of Indian History. Both sides claimed the right of the matter. Some were for parting the squaws, while others were determined they should fight it out. Owanko, seeing his squaw about to be overpowered, gave the signal to one of his men to advance and sink a tomahawk into her antagonist's head, which was instantly obeyed. The next instant found the same Indian stretched lifeless on the earth, for his audacity. Kewasko now became fierce at seeing one of his number killed, gave a long, loud and piercing yell, such as he ever made when he wished to rally his men, and in a few moments, his forces were marshaled in battle array. Owanko also made preparation for the approaching conflict, but before he could form his men in line, the Susquehannas rushed upon    THE MASSACRE AT OWEGO.        45 him with their tomahawks and war clubs, amid the most fright- ful yells. The scene of slaughter was one of fearful extermination, more particularly with the women and children, fcr they were des- patched as fast as found. The Tiogas, however, stood their ground with heroic fortitude, determined to sell their lives at the dearest possible rate. In the course of an hour they gave way, and fled with the greatest precipitation toward the river. To the west of the battle-ground lay a large swamp, to which many fled for safety, but in the hurry and excitement many were mired in the mud. The Susquehannas pursued them, and wherever a Tioga could be found with his head above the surface, he met an immediate death Owanko and his staff fled in the direction of their ill-fated brethren, determined, if possible, to assemble them again, and either revenge himself, or see every man lie dead upon the field. Kewasko took advantage of this movement, and sent a reinforce- ment down to a ford of the Catetant creek, where he knew that Owanko would pass, and they arrived in time to attack him and his devoted followers. Not the least daunted, however, Owanko cast off his bear skin, and drawing his tomahawk, met his combatants with the ferocity of a tiger.* Every blow left its, evidence, but being over. powered by numbers, he at last received a blow from an unexpected quarter which severed life's golden chain. Those with him, on seeing their beloved!chief fall, became panic-stricken, and without fur- ther resistance, yielded themselves a sacrifice to their merciless captors. While this was in progress, the scene of carnage was not stayed in the least at other points. In some instance&amp; the Tiogas remained firm, and were in the ascendancy; still they wanted the presence of their chief, to instil in them the fires of vengeance. The moment they came in possession of the news of his death, their courage for- sook them, and death or flight put an end to their energies. By this time it was near night-fall, but the work of blood ceased not with the going down of the sun. The Susquehannas, when they had slain all they could overtake in the flight, returned, and com- menced the most inhuman butchery of those who lay weltering in their gore. The ground for acres was covered with the dead and the dying. Many of the Susquehannas lay among them, but these were selected out, and the necessary assistance rendered them, which their situation demanded. Kewasko, who had throughout the whole struggle been on the alert, at this moment arrived on the spot where the heaviest of the battle had been, and on beholding his men butch- ering those who still retained a consciousness of life, ordered them immediately to desist, and the order was promptly obeyed. As the sun sunk behind the hills which. then bound the Indian world, the moon rose in full splendor, and shed her pale beams on that unhappy spot. The din and confusion of the strife had, in a measure, become still; and naught, could be heard save the moans of the wounded and dying. Kewasko then ordered sentinels to be stationed at every accessible spot where an 'assault could be effected, ^      r   e    <pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC6843-00000024"/> ;. ;  at aw'.rljpur^g            - . *t e, f    * zo g :. -? " .-   dingly Itheseiitise is eritationed,. and the survivo S :  e&amp;: each a plane. o'e., on :  he same ground .whefe thE - t - - evieus it a thyhla  hi1ed each  ther as friends iand hre  Kewrasko, toghout te Oniht was res te, and eemed mu  afflicted at ithat, had: takin ,$c: - 'ti!, the thought t'.at he:hact come off c queror, gave smeig  f  spinrt of anin4o^hi - feelings.- Early the net 'ior.:gt e dim was beat, an: d tlhe:ah ering made. Great rnmibers came fowariimaimed: and wounded, while thers felt azious to foqluoup fi  -quest. It was fou 'that, two hundred of theMuSu eaan ns were misiing, and the greatei part of thaatnumberwere sleeping the d.,gniies lees,: The10os on the. part of the Tiogas was 'more :tman o1 taibij t::'t um .;aht fiveltundred, together with their ehief', d-f^J"ei' ,5A conultation was held, andawithougl4best tht    4 -gathered aud thrown in the -ived, dithewioundedirive h t --are bestowed upo them.  , lt  Oirv h    as * were too far gone, shold be  di0i dipatheddwhich- o was carried into. execution, :anad i hhe'spce oLsix o howthe-ground wascleared of every ,co se andsuevere. -h river,for ees. r presented a sad spectacle to; the atives who lived on the ban he loW'- for, in a few days,. the bodies rose to' :the s ,andiiib ited their bloated forms to the rays of0 a  Sr  , thfe st frightful to contemplate, and causing the grea st costerntio to the tribes, as -no. aecurate idea could- be oarmed b respeoting : he -cause of this a   irue  ..;umsta rce"' The:bodies t0owsefe. for monthslitheiprey of id b.astsand .car. - ni'vepus birds,' ndth/ stenoh arising fromthim, efitted he atmos- ph'eee-or miles around' From .this isastroussi shck,' the Tioga never afterxecovered.- T hose whosrived the butchery, returned back to their homes in straggling groups, but being robbed of their beloved and sagacious leader, they wandered from pace to place, -and in a few yearsdwindled dwnto a mere party.' The usqte. hannasb owever, flushed by this decisive victory, soon pushed their -conquests into the country, and finally became and retained their sit7 'Uation as mastes of all that region, until the wmarch of civ lization made its  s a'pearace among thein, by the "pale es," w ,hen they, like the Tioa,'; withered and became extinct before the benign,yet piermng beams of Christianity.            g  y' e - Theol-yrremaining object at the present day, which stands as'a, - living witness of this memorable struggle, 'S a large and stately elm tree, which stands 'a short distance th theWest, but in thi" uburbs Wof te Village. -This relic of antiuity, which. the villagers ;have .pre. sevd awith more of the :spirit of veneration, than 'a thing of  beitA ., seems in the language of nattire to repeafi tothe cuiots  's  traveler these w0is':, 'Near ts spot was ac   -    .      </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>