<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6057">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Claremont, or, The Undivided Household </title>
            <author>Anonymous</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC6057</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-0530</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                    participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Claremont, or, The undivided household</title>
                  <author>Anonymous</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>206 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Parry and McMillan</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Philadelphia </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1857">1857</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="AEL Data" when="2003-03-03">Finished transcription and SGML encoding</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2003-10-13">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-04-22">Converted document from SGML to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-04-22">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6057-00000001"/>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>CLAREMONT;</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">OR, THE UNDIVIDED HOUSEHOLD.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>PHILADELPHIA:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>PARRY AND McMILLAN.</publisher>
            </docImprint>
            <docDate when="1857">1857.</docDate>
         </titlePage>
         <pb n="iii" xml:id="VAC6057-00000002"/>
         <div type="fly_title">
            <bibl>
               <edition>Entered according to the Act of Congress, in the year 1856, by PARRY AND McMILLAN, in the Office of the Clerk of the District Court of the United States in and for the Eastern District of Pennsylvania.</edition>
               <pubPlace>PHILADELPHIA:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>T. K. AND P. G. COLLINS, PRINTERS.</publisher>
            </bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <head>A Tribute</head>
            <p>TO THE MEMORY OF LOVED ONES,<lb/> ABSENT; BUT NOT LOST.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="iv-v" xml:id="VAC6057-00000003"/>
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE unpretending little volume herewith committed to the public, was not originally designed for publication; but was written to relieve the tedium of the sick chamber, where the author was confined for months, laid aside from the active duties of his profession.</p>
            <p>After being restored to health, in deference to the judgment of friends, who urged its publication, it is now sent forth on its humble mission.</p>
            <p>As the recalling of the scenes of other days proved both interesting and instructive to the writer, he trusts that, by the blessing of God, the charms of piety, and its worth in afflictions, as exemplified in the case of the family<pb n="vi-vii (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC6057-00000004"/> of Claremont, may tend to establish the Christian in his most holy faith—direct and encourage the sincere inquirer after the truth as it is in Jesus—and persuade those, who have not the grace of God, to seek it as for hid treasure.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="contents">
            <head>CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>CHAPTER I. The hallowed influences of home—Sad impressions on leaving it—College life—First visit to Claremont—A happy household—Reflections. <ref target="VAC6057-00000006" rend="right">9</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER II. God's covenant faithfulness—His goodness to the family of Claremont—The happy communion—Mrs. E.'s cup of joy full. <ref target="VAC6057-00000014" rend="right">26</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER III. Beginning of troubles—Young Edgar's illness—The struggle—The triumph of faith—Resignation and peaceful death—Reflections. <ref target="VAC6057-00000024" rend="right">45</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER IV. Religion the chief source of domestic happiness—How?—Why? <ref target="VAC6057-00000033" rend="right">64</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER V. The church of Glendale—Its early history—The revival of 18-6—Its fruits. <ref target="VAC6057-00000045" rend="right">87</ref>
               </item>
               <pb n="viii (Table of Contents) -9" xml:id="VAC6057-00000005"/>
               <item>CHAPTER VI. The Sabbath school institution—Its importance to the church—What is necessary to its effectiveness—The duty of the church to her children, what?—Of parents and teachers, what? <ref target="VAC6057-00000054" rend="right">105</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER VII. Mrs. Edgar's indisposition—Premonitions of death—The solemn interview—Counsels to surviving friends—Her last hours—Character of her piety. <ref target="VAC6057-00000060" rend="right">118</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER VIII. God's hidden ones—The church's indebtedness to these—Encouragement to labor for Christ—The revelations of the day of judgment. <ref target="VAC6057-00000071" rend="right">139</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER IX. The desolate home—Miss Edgar's indisposition—Mental depression—Its removal, and her resignation to the will of God—Death and funeral—Mr. Edgar's last days. <ref target="VAC6057-00000081" rend="right">160</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER X. The family of Christ—Of whom composed—How divided—All the members are tending homeward—The general reunion—A glorious undivided household. <ref target="VAC6057-00000094" rend="right">185</ref>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Claremont, or, The undivided household</head>
            <head>CLAREMONT.</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The hallowed influences of home—Sad impressions on leaving it—College life—First visit to Claremont—A happy household—Reflections.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>HOME! Who is not charmed with the music of that word! Who has not felt its magic power! Who can calculate the influence of a rightly constituted home! How many sacred associations cluster around it!</p>
               <p>The tender and pleasant reminiscences of the home of our childhood are so deeply engraven upon our hearts as not to be obliterated. There is earnest poetry in this period of our life. At times, when in a melancholy mood we muse upon by-gone days, how the thoughts of our early home will crowd upon<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6057-00000006"/> us! The power of these to touch the heart, though softened and sobered through the medium of the past, is not in the least impaired.</p>
               <p>It is not strange that the youth—called by the voice of duty to leave the parental roof, either for the pursuit of business or the seclusion of college life—should be, to use a common phrase, <emph>homesick,</emph> and be so depressed in spirit as to refuse, for a time, to be comforted. Than this, there is not in the life of a youth a more critical period. Every circumstance connected with it becomes important. Because that which is apparently the most trivial, may decide his character and destiny for time and eternity.</p>
               <p>There is, at such a time, within the soul a sense of emptiness, as if a part of itself had been torn away. Engagements and pleasures are for awhile forgotten, inaction of body, abstractions of mind, and a sealed spirit cleave to him. Unable long to endure such evils, he must go in quest of new objects and new associates to supply the place of the lost ones. Inexperienced and unsuspicious, he readily selects as his friends those who sympathize with him in his troubles, and cheer him in his lonely hours.</p>
               <p>Happy the youth who, at such a time, meets with friends as kind, hearts as true, and forms attachments whose influences are as favorable as those in the case of the writer. He will ever remember with gratitude the dear family of Claremont. For the many acts of kindness done to a stranger, this humble tribute is paid to the memory of that goodly household, now removed from the society of kindred and friends on earth, to the holier and happier fellowship of the saints above.</p>
               <p>After the necessary arrangements were made—such as purchasing books, clothing, and all the little comforts which mothers seem instinctively to know their sons may need—the writer left home to prosecute his studies at the College of M., an institution rendered illustrious by the many revivals of religion which it has enjoyed, and which has furnished the church with more ministers, in proportion to the number of its alumni, than any other college in the land.</p>
               <p>The preparations for the departure of a son<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6057-00000007"/> for college are full of interest. What care is taken by the mother to have every article in its place! Nor is the pocket Bible ever forgotten. It is safely deposited, with the prayer that her boy may take heed to his ways according to its holy precepts. Then comes the last evening for all to be together. As they kneel before the mercy-seat, fervent prayers are offered in behalf of the son who is to depart on the morrow. With the morning dawn all is astir. Every moment is improved in giving some needful caution and good counsel, rendered impressive by the tears of affection that accompany them. Then comes the hurried parting. The mother's fond token of affection, and the blessing of a revered father are received.</p>
               <p>As the lightning speed with which the iron horse now travels was then comparatively unknown, to move at the rate of six miles an hour was regarded as worthy of the highest commendation. And while ignorant of the better way, with due submission we endured all the inconveniences of the stage-coach and rough roads, which are destined ere long to be known only as things of history in this age of human skill and progress.</p>
               <p>After a journey of three days—the tedium of which was greatly relieved by the beautiful and sometimes romantic scenery constantly presented to view, while crossing the Alleghanies—the village of Unionville was reached, which, aside from the college, presents nothing inviting to a stranger.</p>
               <p>The following day, the college term of the winter of 18-4 was opened, and the village of Unionville was all life. Every arrival was watched with great anxiety. Every new comer excited much interest. Old friendships were renewed, and new acquaintances were formed. At the appointed hour, the old college bell summoned the students to the place of meeting. The President, venerable with years, conducted the morning devotions in his own inimitable manner, simple, impressive, fervent. All who ever heard him addressing the throne of grace, must have been persuaded that he had power to prevail with God. He delivered an appropriate address to the students; after which the classes were arranged, and their studies assigned<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6057-00000008"/> ed them by the professors, in their respective departments, and thus the day passed most pleasantly.</p>
               <p>The novelty connected with the opening of a new term at college, keeps the mind fully employed. Soon, however, the scene changes. All settle down to their studies. The noise and tumult are passed, and quiet reigns over all. Then come the thoughts of home and absent friends. Then you are disturbed by night-dreams, ay, and day-dreams too! It is soon pretty evident that you are <emph>homesick.</emph> If at such a time you escape the ridicule of your less considerate companions, and meet with some kind heart to sympathize with you, and cheer your gloomy spirit, you might deem yourself quite fortunate. Such was my good fortune, as the sequel will show.</p>
               <p>One morning soon after entering college, being in a most melancholy mood, holding converse in thought with absent friends, my classmate R——, with his characteristic cheerfulness, entered my room. Looking me full in the face, which was then considerably elongated, he exclaimed: "What! Is it possible sible that you are homesick! Come, come! it will never do for you to sit here and mope over your trouble. You must stir about and cheer up. I called to ask you to take a walk this evening a few miles into the country. I wish to introduce you to a charming family of my acquaintance. I know it will be of service to you."</p>
               <p>Most gladly was the kind invitation accepted, for the imprisonment of a few days had become almost intolerable.</p>
               <p>At the appointed hour we left the college campus and directed our steps towards Claremont. It was a beautiful evening in autumn; the air was balmy and invigorating; the forest was attired in her mantle of varied hues. To a mind of a somewhat melancholy cast, nature arrayed in her autumnal garb possesses peculiar charms. We reached Claremont in time to witness a most beautiful sunset, which alone repaid us for an hour's walk. There is not a more enchanting sight than a clear sunset, except it be sunrise, when all nature is astir to chant her Maker's praise.</p>
               <pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6057-00000009"/>
               <p>The Claremont homestead was an ancient unpretending structure, built upon the brow of a hill, commanding an extensive view of a charming, picturesque landscape.</p>
               <p>The lawn was laid out; the trees, the shrubbery, and flowers were arranged with much taste. Everything suggested the idea of repose, and comfort, and refinement.</p>
               <p>How surpassingly lovely did the country then appear! How cheering to my spirits was the sight of <emph>a home,</emph> which reminded me so fully of the home of my childhood! How deeply are the scenes of our early years engraven upon the tablet of memory! We love to recur to them often, and we seem to live them over again. Each scene stands out distinctly before us—our sprightly walks over the fields; the cool repose amid shady groves, vocal with the notes of nature's inimitable warblers; the murmuring stream, where we were wont, in our rambles, to slake our thirst; the lowing of the herds; the humming of bees; the monotonous song of the night-bird—as these soft memories steal over us, we are compelled to weep, despite all efforts to stay the trickling tear.</p>
               <p>The introduction to the family; the cordial reception; the entire absence of mere formality; the kind wishes expressed for the welfare of a stranger; the family board; the chitchat of the evening; the family altar—all this was adapted to recall the past, to dispel the gloom of the present, and reconcile the mind to the separation from home and its sweet endearments.</p>
               <p>How strong and enduring are friendships formed at such a time! Never can the kindness of my friend R——, who led me to that sweet retreat, be forgotten. It will ever be regarded as a special favor, that it was permitted me to form the acquaintance of that goodly household, so early in my college course, and to share afterwards in their joys and sorrows.</p>
               <p>An introduction to the members of the family of Claremont may be acceptable to our readers.</p>
               <p>Mr. and Mrs. Edgar were a venerable couple, then considerably advanced in years.<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6057-00000010"/> Mr. Edgar, having accumulated some wealth by strict attention to business, had retired from the noise and bustle of the city to enjoy the peace and quiet of the country. He purchased a small plantation, sufficiently large, however, to keep him employed: for he knew full well that to be unemployed would be a source of misery rather than of peace and comfort.</p>
               <p>For one of his years, he enjoyed to an unusual degree the society of his friends. He had been a keen observer of men and things, and was well informed on all ordinary subjects. His judgment was generally correct, and his disposition kind and generous. At the time of our first acquaintance, he was not professedly a Christian, though his sympathies were strongly on the side of religion.</p>
               <p>Mrs. Edgar possessed peculiar attractions of character. Of her it might have been truly said— <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"Her might was gentleness; she won her sway</l>
                        <l>By a soft word, and by a softer look.</l>
                        <l>Sweetness was her attribute;</l>
                        <l>By that she reigned."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>It was evident that she had been a child of affliction, as her countenance wore the marks of grief; yet withal there was a sweet smile upon that face which betokened a heart submissive to the will of God, and a blessed consciousness that all was well. The rare beauty and grace of manners which she must have possessed in early life, had, in a measure, given place to the more permanent and superior charms of eminent piety. This rendered her in old age esteemed and beloved by all who knew her intimately.</p>
               <p>Their family consisted of a son and two daughters. Of these, one was not, for God had taken her. After a lingering illness of several months, she gently fell asleep in Jesus, leaving her testimony to the faithfulness of Christ to succor all who trust in him, and to cause them to rejoice and triumph in death. It was a severe stroke to the aged mother. At the time of our first visit the family were clad in the weeds of mourning.</p>
               <p>The surviving daughter was the centre of attraction to a large circle of friends. Nature had endowed her with great personal charms.<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6057-00000011"/> Her countenance betokened intelligence, strength of character, and a disposition frank, confiding, and benevolent. She was highly accomplished in all that is truly valuable in female education. Miss Edgar wielded her pen with ease and vigor, and for good ends. Her poetic effusions possessed considerable merit, many of which were published in a literary journal of some note at that day. With all her rich endowments, she, alas! lacked the chief ornament of female character, true piety. She knew not the Saviour. But she was not far from the kingdom of heaven. How could it have been otherwise with one nurtured by a mother whose life was a constant testimony for Christ; who walked with God, and abounded in prayer for the salvation of her household?</p>
               <p>At the time of our first visit to Claremont, the son was absent prosecuting his studies at a distant college. He was expected home shortly, bearing with him the honors of the Institution. With pleasure his return was anticipated by the family. The mother evidently looked forward to his future career with anxiety, and yet with high hopes, that his life might be long and honorable. But neither had he, amid all his acquisitions, obtained true wisdom—the knowledge of Jesus Christ, which is eternal life.</p>
               <p>Such was the family of Claremont; how happy in each other! How full their cup of joy! Removed from noise and strife, surrounded with all that heart could wish, surely a benignant Providence had highly distinguished them. As we traced our steps next morning toward the college, our ardent prayer ascended to heaven for that favored household. Long, long may they be spared to each other; far from them be the day of darkness and adversity! But how transitory and uncertain are all things earthly! No condition in life is exempt from trouble; none are secure from the arrows of the destroyer! But more of this anon.</p>
               <p>We must say a word to our young readers, ere we close this chapter.</p>
               <p>Have you a home where God's name is revered, and the sweet incense of prayer and praise ascends to heaven morning and night?<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6057-00000012"/> Prize that home highly. Give good heed to the warnings and counsels of your pious mother. For if you improve them aright, they will be your guardian angels in after life, to keep you from the snares of the destroyer. When allured by the voice of the tempter to wander from God and happiness, in the crooked ways of sin and ruin, the fervent prayers of your revered father will not let you go astray, without many an inward struggle. When your companions bid you taste the forbidden cup of pleasure, and cast off the love of virtue, the form of your loved mother, in all its winning charms, will rise before you—her warning voice will ring in your ears, and her tears of affection will plead with you, to shun the paths that lead to death—walk in wisdom's ways, and drink the cup of salvation. It will bid you strive to attain to true worth and excellence in life, and to the enjoyment of glory and felicity hereafter. A mother's love—what so pure—so faithful—so wholly disinterested! <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"Oh! in our sterner manhood, when no ray</l>
                        <l>Of earlier sunshine glimmers in our way,</l>
                        <l>When girt with sin, and sorrow, and the toil</l>
                        <l>Of cares, which tear the bosom that they soil—</l>
                        <l>Oh! if there be in retrospection's chain,</l>
                        <l>One link that knits us with young dreams again;</l>
                        <l>One thought so sweet, we scarcely dare to muse</l>
                        <l>On all the hoarded rapture it reviews,</l>
                        <l>Which seems each instant, in its backward range,</l>
                        <l>The heart to soften, and its ties to change,</l>
                        <l>And every spring, untouched for years, to move,</l>
                        <l>It is—THE MEMORY OF A MOTHER'S LOVE."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Parents, do you wish your children in after years, when separated from you, to remember with gratitude the home of their childhood? Spare no pains to make that home—what God designed every home should be—a miniature of heaven. Let the name of God be honored. Lead your little ones to the mercy-seat. Early teach them to lisp the name of Jesus.</p>
               <p>Never can we forget the winter evenings when, with our little brothers, we gathered around our dear mother, to hear the Bible stories which she related to us, at the same time drawing from each the moral lessons they suggested, and which were impressed upon the conscience with the earnestness and persuasion which mothers alone can employ. Our cheeks were often bedewed with tears,<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6057-00000013"/> while we listened to the thrilling story of Joseph, of Samuel, of David, and other worthies of the Old Testament; but above all of Him who came to save the lost—who took in his arms the little ones, and blessed them. The scenes of his birth—his life of toil—the garden—Pilate's hall—and Calvary, were all so vividly set forth, that the impressions are retained to this hour in all their freshness.</p>
               <p>Mothers! your influence over your children the first years of their life—a period above all others when the heart is susceptible of deep and lasting impressions—is beyond all computation. It is yours to give the first bent to the mind which is immortal. To distil into hearts, not yet in contact with a corrupt world, lessons of heavenly wisdom.</p>
               <p>We have ample testimony of the influence of a mother's early lessons of wisdom, and fervent prayers, upon the after life of men.</p>
               <p>John Randolph, the eminent but eccentric American statesman, once said: "I should have been a French atheist, had it not been for the recollection of the time when my departed mother used to take my little hand in hers, and make me say on my bended knees, 'Our Father who art in Heaven.'"</p>
               <p>Mothers! To you, above all others, God has committed the destiny of your children. If, by the grace of God, you are faithful to your trust, your memory will be most sacredly embalmed in the hearts of your offspring—the world will be the better through your influence—the church will bless you—and God will crown you with his favor.</p>
               <p>But oh! if faithless—</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6057-00000014"/>
               <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>God's covenant faithfulness—His goodness to the family of Claremont—The happy communion—Mrs. E.'s cup of joy full.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THAT God hears prayer is a truth most explicitly taught in the Bible. "O thou that hearest prayer, unto thee shall all flesh come."</p>
               <p>What varied and strong expressions are employed by the Holy Spirit to set forth the faithfulness of God to his engagements. How well adapted to rebuke our unbelief, to remove every doubt, and confirm our feeble faith. And how consolatory to the believing parent, when interceding with God in behalf of his son or daughter.</p>
               <p>We are warranted in believing that the instances of God's answering the prayers of the pious, for the conversion of their offspring, are more numerous and wonderful now, under the dispensation of the Spirit, than in the period when the volume of inspiration was written. We also believe that there are mothers in these latter days, who, like the mother of Samuel, are at times so carried away with their earnest wrestling with God, that, were they seen by some formal priest of modern times, they would be charged with folly, but who might rebuke their reprover in the words of Hannah, when falsely charged with inebriation: "Count not thine handmaid for a daughter of Belial. I am a woman of a sorrowful spirit; for out of the abundance of my complaint and grief have I spoken, and poured out my soul before the Lord."</p>
               <p>The occurrences in the family of Claremont during the summer of 18-5, furnish an illustration of the truth of God's faithfulness and willingness to answer prayer. Mrs. Edgar enjoyed intimate communion with God, and lived near the throne of grace. It was natural for one of such deep piety to be concerned about the spiritual welfare of her aged partner and beloved children. Her solicitude was evinced by the affecting manner in which she would at times refer to the subject.</p>
               <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6057-00000015"/>
               <p>The son having returned to his friends with the tokens of honor to which his diligence and application, during his collegiate course, entitled him, concluded to rest awhile and enjoy the repose of home, before entering upon the study of law, which profession he had already chosen. This course was rendered necessary by the state of his health, which had been somewhat impaired by too close study.</p>
               <p>Amid the quiet of home and of rural life, the conduct of young Edgar was evidently changed for the better. No situation could have been selected more favorable for reflection. Removed from the distraction, the strife and dissipation of college, under the genial influences of home, is it strange that there was a marked improvement in his general deportment?</p>
               <p>It was clearly shown, by the events of the ensuing summer, that God was thus preparing the way for answering the many prayers which had been presented in behalf of that beloved youth.</p>
               <p>The links in the chain of events which bring about the conversion of a sinner, considered sidered separately, may be very trivial, but viewed connectedly, and traced to their legitimate results, they become of vast importance. The most casual occurrence has often started a train of reflection which, by the blessing of God, has led to the salvation of an immortal soul.</p>
               <p>A youth, who was wont to frequent the theatre, was entering one evening. His eye rested upon the inscription over the door, "<hi rend="i"/>Entrance to the Pit." As he passed in he involuntarily repeated the words, "<hi rend="i"/>Entrance to the Pit." The words stood out in living characters before his mind's eye. He could not dismiss the subject. It haunted him. It disturbed his conscience, and compelled him to leave the place of amusement. The truth came home with overwhelming power that he was standing upon the brink of the precipice of ruin, and was hastening towards the awful pit of woe. His heart was pierced by the arrows of conviction. He paused; he considered, and resolved, by the grace of God, to shun the paths of vice and death, and thenceforth to walk in wisdom's ways.</p>
               <pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6057-00000016"/>
               <p>By the most unlikely means, God does at times bring about his gracious purposes so as to illustrate most clearly that the excellency of the power is not of man, or in the instruments, but of himself.</p>
               <p>The leisure and social intercourse of the winter of 18—4 had a most happy influence upon young Edgar's mind, and prepared the way for the moral change which he was about to experience. Early in the following spring there were indications of God's presence manifest in the congregation of Glendale. Meetings for prayer were well attended; Christians began to feel a deep solicitude for the salvation of the youth of the church; everything betokened the dawn of a better day. The Spirit was poured out, and that parched hill of Zion was blessed with a copious shower of divine grace.</p>
               <p>A number of young persons were led to renounce the world, and seek in earnest the salvation of their souls. Among these was Miss Edgar found. The Spirit of God arrested her attention. She saw herself as a lost sinner, and felt her need of an interest in the atoning blood of the Lamb. In her perplexity, she naturally sought the aid and counsel of her pious mother, who had long wrestled with God in her behalf. She was directed to the cross, and there found peace by believing. How happy must have been that devoted mother, when she witnessed the hopeful conversion of her daughter!</p>
               <p>The daughter, which had accompanied her a little while in her pilgrimage, had been removed to a higher sphere, and she had been journeying alone towards the celestial city. But now her surviving daughter had renounced the world and cast in her lot with the people of God. This encouraged the mother greatly, and led her to plead with God for the conversion of the other members of her househould.</p>
               <p>The charms of piety, when added to the many excellencies of character which Miss Edgar naturally possessed, rendered her exceedingly attractive. There was an earnestness of spirit, a depth of feeling exhibited by her as a Christian, that touched and won the hearts of those who knew her. It was not<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6057-00000017"/> strange that one of her character, when she found the Saviour, should have felt a deep interest in the spiritual welfare of her revered father, and only brother, who were not yet Christians.</p>
               <p>Is there ought purer than a sister's love! Its influence is felt even in manhood. The heart that has grown cold by contact with the selfish world, will warm and thrill with pure and holy joy, as some incident reminds it of a sister's devoted love. How often has a wanderer, wooed by the gentle influence of such reminiscences, abandoned a course of life which warped and false philosophy had reasoned into expediency, and sighed for the calm and pure pleasures of his early years!</p>
               <p>Under such influences the finer feelings of young Edgar's heart had been developed. He loved that sister sincerely; and his love was returned by the most affectionate and anxious solicitude for his soul's salvation. She resolved to speak to him on the subject which occupied so much of her thoughts and prayers.</p>
               <p>Finding her brother one evening alone in the parlor, she resolved to seize the opportunity then offered to introduce the subject. Having seated herself on a low chair by his side, with trembling voice she told him what she had experienced of the goodness of God; of the Saviour's love; of the peace of the Christian, and of the hope of glory. In the most persuasive manner she pressed upon him the claims of Christ, and entreated him no longer to resist the Holy Spirit. Her effort was not in vain. Perceiving that there was hope, and drawing strength from the advantage already gained, she plied skilfully the weapons of truth and love. She kindly and pointedly asked him, "Why, dear brother, why do you refuse to accept the rich grace of the gospel? How can you reject such a Saviour as I have found?"</p>
               <p>At first there was evidently a struggle between his native pride and the convictions of truth, and he endeavored to conceal his state of mind; but it was in vain. He now opened to her his heart, and said that for days the subject had occupied his attention, but that he could not summon sufficient courage to introduce<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6057-00000018"/> duce the subject, or reveal to any one the workings of his heart. That since the change had taken place in her condition, his mind had been more deeply impressed. He often hoped she would introduce the subject, and was almost tempted to speak to her on the great theme; but his heart would fail him. For a short time he had been seeking the Saviour, and had a faint hope that he had found him. This revelation was wholly unexpected, and her soul was filled with joy. She embraced him as a brother in a new relation, and felt bound to him by ties stronger and holier than ever before. That evening the tidings were imparted to her mother, and they together mingled their tears of joy and gratitude, for the son and brother who was dead was now alive, he who was lost was now found.</p>
               <p>But Mrs. Edgar's joy was mingled with sorrow, because her aged husband was not yet a Christian. She viewed her children as now safe with her in the ark, and hoped to meet them at the right hand of the righteous Judge. But how could she bear the thought of being separated from her husband in that dread day! Oh! it could not be!</p>
               <p>Encouraged by the goodness of God in the conversion of her children, she wrestled more importunately at the throne of grace in behalf of her partner. Her intercessions were not in vain. God heard her supplications, and willing more abundantly to show his long suffering, had compassion on her aged husband, and received him at the eleventh hour into the vineyard. At the following communion, Mr. Edgar sat with them at the Lord's table.</p>
               <p>The manner in which Mr. Edgar's mind was awakened to the claims of religion, as related by him to the pastor of Glendale, when applying for admission to the privileges of the church, was interesting and instructive. He stated that he had been under deep and poignant convictions frequently during the last forty years of his life. He was at times almost persuaded to be a Christian; but, alas! he had stifled those convictions. Being present at the communion when his children were admitted into the church, the Holy Spirit sent an arrow into his heart. The wound could<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6057-00000019"/> not be healed save by the peace-speaking blood of the Lamb. As the family left the pew and took their seats at the sacramental table, he was seized with terror at the bare possibility that the separation then taking place might foreshadow the eternal separation between the righteous and the wicked—between those who serve God and those who serve him not. Lest God should swear respecting him: "Thou shalt not enter into my rest," he solemnly covenanted no longer to delay, but, by the help of God, to take the yoke of Christ upon him, and, at the next communion, to unite with his family in celebrating the Redeemer's dying love.</p>
               <p>This is one of the many instances in which the administration of the Lord's Supper has been blessed to the salvation of souls. Is there no reason to fear that this ordinance is not made as prominent as it ought to be in our churches? In our anxiety, as Protestants, to avoid everything that may seem to attach any inherent saving efficacy to the sacraments, or lead to superstitious reverence for them, is there no danger of erring in the other extreme, by attempting to divest the solemn ordinance of the Supper of its impressiveness? Is not the hurried manner in which it is too often administered calculated to lessen its influence on the minds of participants and spectators?</p>
               <p>The practice of preaching a long discourse at such seasons, is of very doubtful propriety. The strength of the preacher and the patience of the hearers are wellnigh exhausted. At a late hour the ordinance is administered in a manner wholly inconsistent with its solemnity and importance. No time is allowed for reflection and the due improvement of the occasion.</p>
               <p>The testimony of a pastor, who, during a ministry of some length, has uniformly dispensed with a sermon on sacramental occasions, fully establishes the correctness of our remarks. The practice has met the approbation of the pious, and secured a much larger attendance than is usual on such occasions.</p>
               <p>After the usual introductory exercises, instead of a sermon, the words of the institution are read, a few pertinent remarks are made touching the ordinance, and the sacrament is then administered. Ample time is thus<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC6057-00000020"/> afforded to address the several classes of persons present. There is no fatiguing of the aged and feeble, who are found in all congregations. Nor is there any interfering with the ordinary domestic arrangements of the people. The Lord's Supper is so simple, so impressive, so eloquent, that the convictions produced by its proper observance are, by the blessing of God, generally deep and abiding. It is Christ's ordinance, instituted by him under circumstances solemn and exceedingly trying. "<hi rend="i"/>The Lord Jesus, the same night in which he was betrayed, took bread." It should be permitted to speak to the heart in its own peculiar language.</p>
               <p>But to return: that must have been a happy communion Sabbath to the family of Claremont. It was the commencement of a new era in its history—a day never to be forgotten. Mrs. Edgar's joy abounded. She remarked to a friend, on leaving the house of God that Sabbath: "How can I doubt the Lord's goodness towards me! We are now an undivided household—all having hope in Christ, and rejoicing in the glorious prospect of being united forever in heaven."</p>
               <p>Many pious mothers, like Hannah, have devoted their sons to God from their birth, to serve Him at the altar. Such was the case with Mrs. Edgar; with many tears she had prayed that the offering might be accepted. Though her son had chosen the law for his profession, yet her faith wavered not. She humbly but confidently hoped that his life would be spent in the more honorable calling of preaching Christ crucified.</p>
               <p>Whether the question of a change of profession had been presented to him by any of his friends or by the indications of the providence of God, we have now no means of knowing. It is certain, however, that soon after his conversion, the subject engaged his thoughts, and caused him much anxiety to know what was the path of duty. Whatever motives led him to devote himself to the profession of the law, when ignorant of Christ, they were not sufficiently cogent to satisfy his mind now. With talent of a high order, with family influence on his side, and with persevering<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC6057-00000021"/> severing industrious habits, he would doubtless have obtained a commanding and distinguished position in that honorable profession. But duty called him to a different and a nobler field of labor. After a most impartial and prayerful consideration of the subject, he resolved to consecrate his life and all his acquisitions to Christ, to serve him in the ministry of reconciliation.</p>
               <p>Such were the occurrences in that goodly family during the summer of 18-5. The son, who had returned home from college, ambitious of worldly distinction, was resting awhile to regain strength, ere he would enter upon his career of gain and glory. During this period of rest, God in His infinite mercy adopted him as a son. He was enabled to heed the warning voice of the gospel, to bow to the Redeemer, and make an entire surrender of himself to His service.</p>
               <p>The daughter, now possessing the chief ornament of her sex—true piety—her career for time and eternity changed. She immediately began to work for Christ. All her sympathies were enlisted in the great interests of the church. Her influence was felt for good in the Sabbath school, and in connection with the benevolent operations of the church.</p>
               <p>Also an aged man brought into subjection to the authority of Christ—made to rejoice in the hope of the gospel, when the shadows of the evening were lengthening apace, and the sun of life had wellnigh set.</p>
               <p>Dear reader, is it too much to say, that the family of Claremont were now truly blessed? As you read our brief description of their beautiful residence, possessing all the charms of ease, and rural refinement, and comfort—as you beheld the favored inmates happy in each other's society, secluded from the folly and excitements of city life—did you not almost envy them? In a worldly point of view, we could scarcely imagine anything that could add to their happiness. But in the judgment of angels, in the judgment of God, they were not all blessed. Oh! no—as the contents of this chapter prove most abundantly. All of the members, save the aged mother, were without an interest in Christ, consequently, their prospects were gloomy indeed. Had death<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6057-00000022"/> entered that circle and called any of them away, ere they had passed from death unto life, no believer in the Bible could have pronounced them blessed. But when they obtained the hope of the gospel, they were truly blessed; as they possessed that "godliness which is profitable unto all things, having promise of the life that now is, and of that which is to come."</p>
               <p>Unalloyed happiness, however, is not a plant of earthly origin and growth; it cannot bud and blossom in such soil, and in an atmosphere so foul. It would wither and die at the touch of earth's nipping frosts. It is a plant that grows in the Paradise of God, and blooms under the genial rays of the Sun of Righteousness. Permanence is not written on any earthly enjoyment. And though it might have been said of the family of Claremont—"They are happy, and their sky is comparatively serene," yet troubles and days of darkness then awaited them.</p>
               <p>How often it happens, that God grants special tokens of His favor to those of his children who are to pass through deep waters of affliction. The experience of families is often like the days of autumn—the morning may be bright and beautiful, but ere noon the sky is overspread with clouds, and by evening-tide the terrific storm may howl and rage most furiously.</p>
               <p>The years 18-5 and 6 were to the Edgar family a season of sore trial. And had they not been sustained by the consolations of religion, sad indeed would have been their condition. To the eye of sense all was gloom; but the eye of faith could clearly see light and peace in the midst of darkness. Blessed be God for the hope of heaven! If in this life only we have hope, we are of all men most miserable. There is a hereafter! There is beyond the tomb, <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"The life of perfect love, the rest</l>
                        <l>Of immortality."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>In closing this chapter, we would ask, do not its contents illustrate and establish the glorious truth, that God heareth prayer? "He will keep His covenant forever. Holy and reverend is His name." That devoted mother and wife had prayed long and fervently for<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6057-00000023"/> the conversion of her household. Her faith must have been severely tried; yet she persevered, and was permitted to witness the conversion of all its members. No wonder that she exclaimed on that memorable communion season, when they all sat together at the Lord's table, "How can I doubt God's goodness and faithfulness?"</p>
               <p>This narrative may encourage earnest Christians to persevere, under present discouragements, in seeking the salvation of their friends and relatives. The house of Jacob shall not seek God in vain. He treasures up His people's tears, and their prayers are recorded in His book of remembrance. <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"It sha'n't be said that praying breath</l>
                        <l>Was ever spent in vain."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The tears of faith shall not be lost, but shall be as seed sown, which shall germinate and bring forth fruit, though it be after many days. The prayer of faith will bring down answers in return, though they may seem to tarry. It is ours to wait patiently, cheerfully—for they will surely come: they will not tarry. "The effectual, fervent prayer of a righteous man availeth much."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Beginning of troubles—Young Edgar's illness—The struggle—The triumph of faith—Resignation and peaceful death—Reflections.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IN our anxiety to know what awaits us in life, we are unwilling to abide God's time. Were it permitted us, we would lift the veil and know what is appointed for us to do, to suffer, and enjoy.</p>
               <p>But God in infinite wisdom conceals from us all our future allotments. Our evil days will come soon enough, when God sends them. It is ours to receive our evil things submissively—to enjoy our present good with gratitude—to pray that both the evil and the good may be sanctified to us—and that we may be better fitted for the unalloyed felicities of eternity.</p>
               <p>How it would have embittered their cup of<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC6057-00000024"/> joy, had the dear friends of Claremont foreseen the trials and sorrows that awaited them? But the Lord deals mercifully with His children. He proportions His grace to their trials—His strength to their day.</p>
               <p>When young Edgar returned from college, his health, as before intimated, was impaired; but it excited no alarm at the time, as it was attributed to his close application to study. His friends were confident that relaxation from literary pursuits, and the pure country air, would soon restore him to perfect health. Ah! they knew not that the seeds of disease were already sown—that the deceptive foe, consumption, had marked him as its prey.</p>
               <p>The combined influence of the quiet and comforts of home, and of the moral transformations which the grace of God had effected, contributed greatly to the general improvement of young Edgar's health. For the change which is produced by conversion, imparting to its subject new views, new motives to action, new hopes, and new and glorious prospects, must be decidedly favorable to health and physical enjoyment.</p>
               <p>Our young friend regarded himself as sustaining new and important relations to his fellow-men. His talents and acquirements, which were once devoted to the world and self, he now laid on the altar as a free-will offering to God; his highest ambition was to go forth to make known to dying men the grace and love of the Saviour. All this infused new vigor into his languid frame, and he longed ardently to enter upon the study of theology, preparatory to the work of preaching.</p>
               <p>Deeming it unwise to enter the seminary until his health was fully established, he improved the opportunity for visiting some friends in the West. Soon after he reached his friends, whose society he greatly enjoyed, their fears were excited by the unexpected appearance of certain premonitory symptoms of consumption. Medical aid was sought, in hopes of arresting the disease, but in vain. So rapidly did the disease develop itself, that, after some rest and partial recruiting of strength, he had to take leave of friends, and return home, not to gain strength, but to lay<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC6057-00000025"/> aside his armor—to enter into his rest, and receive the crown of life.</p>
               <p>Never can we forget our first visit to Claremont after his return. What a change a few months had wrought! Emaciated and enfeebled by disease, and greatly dejected in spirit, he was silent and reserved. His former flow of life and joyousness was gone. There was evidently a fearful struggle within that soul. How terrible, at such a time, the conflict between life and death!</p>
               <p>Marvel not that our young friend was cast down, and even morose. Having already made considerable advancement in his preparations for life, standing on the very threshold of usefulness, with the most flattering prospects of success, he was suddenly called to bid adieu to all he held dear on earth. With the strong love of life, which is natural to us all, warping his judgment, he could not realize that infinite love had ordained the cutting off, in the midst of his days, all his hopes and prospects; consequently he could not at once lie submissively under the mighty hand of God.</p>
               <p>How truthfully is the inward conflict of one brought suddenly from the midst of life and all its bright promises to the verge of the grave, set forth in the words of the King of Israel, when he was bidden by the prophet to set his house in order, for that year he would die and not live. "I said in the cutting off of my days, I shall go to the gates of the grave: I am deprived of the residue of my years. Mine age is departed, and is removed from me as a shepherd's tent: I have cut off like a weaver my life: He will cut me off with pining sickness: from day even to night wilt thou make an end of me. Like a crane, or a swallow, so did I chatter; I did mourn as a dove: mine eyes fail with looking upward: O Lord, I am oppressed; undertake for me. What shall I say? He hath both spoken unto me, and himself hath done it: I shall go softly all my years in the bitterness of my soul. The living, the living, he shall praise thee, as I do this day: the father to the children shall make known thy truth."</p>
               <p>The failing health of her son was a heavy affliction to the aged mother, and it was a great trial of her faith. How could she give<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC6057-00000026"/> him up! who, by baptism, many tears and earnest prayers, had been devoted to God; for whose spiritual welfare she had importunately interceded with the Lord; over whose conversion she had been permitted to rejoice; whose dedication to the glorious work of the ministry she regarded as an answer to her many prayers, and the realizing of long cherished hopes? That son, in whom were centred her chief earthly expectations, she was now called to resign to the God who gave him, and follow him to an early grave. It was a bitter cup to drink—a burden too heavy for her to bear, in her own strength.</p>
               <p>But God was her stay. In the hour of darkness and despair she resorted to Him who was her refuge, and her rock of defence. Often had she turned thither in the day of adversity, and found safety and consolation. How sweet to the afflicted saint are the touching words of the poet:— <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l rend="ti-1">"Come, ye disconsolate, where'er ye languish,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-2">Come to the mercy-seat, fervently kneel;</l>
                        <l>Here bring your wounded hearts, here tell your anguish;</l>
                        <l rend="ti-2">Earth hath no sorrow that Heaven cannot heal."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Mrs. Edgar's faith was strengthened. She clearly saw that it was a father's hand that smote her, who, though he afflicts, yet afflicts not willingly. All murmur ceased, and peace and comfort ensued. The devoted mother, having experienced this blessed change in her own soul, naturally turned toward her disconsolate son. Her heart yearned over him, and she most earnestly sought for him divine interposition.</p>
               <p>The good pastor of Glendale visited our young friend often during his trouble, endeavoring to pour light on his path, and cheer his drooping spirit. He cited many touching promises suited to the case of the troubled in spirit. "As a father pitieth his children, so the Lord pitieth them that fear Him." "Whom the Lord loveth He chasteneth, and scourgeth every son whom He receiveth." These and similar promises were repeated, but they gave him no relief. All the while, unbelief rested like a heavy burden upon his soul.</p>
               <p>After a long night of darkness, the day of peace dawned upon him. His heart was<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC6057-00000027"/> enlarged. He was enabled to acquiesce in the Divine will. He bewailed, most bitterly, his own unbelief and perverseness in refusing so long to be comforted. He spoke of God's distinguishing mercy in granting him deliverance from the oppression of the enemy. Were it the will of God, it would have rejoiced him to live to preach Christ, and labor to save souls; yet he was willing to commit his <emph>all</emph> to the hand of his heavenly Father.</p>
               <p>This blessed change was cheering to his friends, to whom his mental distress had been a source of anguish. It was now a privilege to sit by his couch, and hear him relate what God had done for his soul. The sweet smile that was wont to play upon his countenance while in health, returned again. God was now to him, "as the light of the morning without clouds; as the tender grass springing out of the earth by clear shining after rain."</p>
               <p>How deceptive is consumption! How stealthily it coils itself around its victim! How it blinds him to his danger! Often its death pangs are regarded as premonitions of returning health and life. As death casts its dark shadows over the soul of the dying, it alarms him; but he soon recovers from the shock, as the hope of life returns. Thus it was with young Edgar. The best medical aid was obtained; but to no purpose. The decree had gone forth, "This year thou shalt die."</p>
               <p>The painful task of communicating the tidings of his approaching dissolution was intrusted to his pastor. It was done with great judgment and tenderness. The dying youth received the announcement with some agitation. It startled him, as though assailed unexpectedly by a cruel foe. Ah! our nature instinctively shrinks from the thought of dying. And though death is to the child of grace a vanquished foe, yet we dread him. How wilt thou do in the swellings of Jordan? is a question that often disturbs us fearfully. And though the voice of Him that was dead and now liveth, speaks to the timid, trembling soul, "Fear not, for I am with thee; be not dismayed, for I am thy God," yet, <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"Tim'rous mortals start and shrink,</l>
                        <l>To cross this narrow sea."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC6057-00000028"/>
               <p>We cling to life, and are slow to depart, when our faith is weak.</p>
               <p>The struggle in young Edgar's bosom was but momentary. His faith triumphed. After a brief pause, he said calmly, "THE WILL OF THE LORD BE DONE." The hope of glory beamed into his soul with divine radiance. "This is the victory that overcometh the world, even our faith." "Thanks be unto God who giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ." How great its power! By it the gloom of death is dispelled—the dying saint is enabled to look through the dark portals of the tomb, to eternity, and to the judgment seat, undismayed, clad in the righteousness of Emmanuel.</p>
               <p>The death-bed scenes of that young Christian were deeply instructive. There was no ecstasy; but divine peace filled his soul. Well assured anticipations of Heaven cheered his dying moments. He would often address his weeping mother and sister in words of affection: "<hi rend="i"/>Weep not for me." "Would you detain me here in this vale of sin and suffering, while rest from all that pains me now is just at hand, and the crown of life awaits me?"</p>
               <p>It reconciles us to the loss of loved ones, to be assured that they have exchanged sufferings, tribulation and sin, for eternal health, ineffable joy, and celestial glory.</p>
               <p>And while we shed the tears of grief under our bereavement, we are enabled to sing— <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"Thou art gone to the grave; but 'twere wrong to deplore thee,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Since God was thy ransom, thy guardian and guide:</l>
                        <l>He gave thee, and took thee, and soon will restore thee</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Where death hath no sting, since the Saviour has died."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>As the weeping friends stood by the open grave of the departed, the words of the Son of God—repeated by the pastor—were as precious ointment to their stricken hearts: "I am the resurrection, and the life: he that believeth in me, though he were dead, yet shall he live." As he referred to the bright prospects which were once before the departed—to his conversion—to his consecration to the service of his Master—to the sudden change—to the terrible struggle through which he passed—to the gracious interposition of<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC6057-00000029"/> God, by causing the light of salvation to break into his soul—to the peace of mind, and the bright anticipations of glory he enjoyed in his dying moments—and finally, to the blessed resurrection morn, "when the trump of God shall sound, and all the dead shall rise; when this mortal shall put on immortality"—all were deeply moved, and felt the power of the world to come. And sure we are, that the oft repeated prayer ascended that day from many a throbbing heart: "Let me die the death of the righteous, and let my last end be like his."</p>
               <p>Another breach in that once happy family—many tender ties were broken—the light of that house was dimmed—and its members were again clothed in the weeds of mourning. Thus the attractions of earth were losing their power, while those of Heaven were growing stronger apace. It was evident that the trial of the faith of the surviving friends was working in them the peaceable fruits of righteousness, by which God was preparing them for other afflictions yet awaiting them.</p>
               <p>What lessons of wisdom are taught us by the preceding narrative! Is it not well adapted to teach us that God is a sovereign, who giveth no account of His doings? "Clouds and darkness are round about Him, righteousness and judgment are the habitation of His throne." The aged sinner is spared, whose life has been a continued scene of iniquity—his influence has been a blight, a curse—yet he is permitted to live. We are tempted to ask, Wherefore do the wicked live, become old: yea, are mighty in power?</p>
               <p>On the other hand, the talented, the learned, the good, are brought to the grave in the morning of life. Behold a youth, whose early years were spent in close study—whose mind was well stored with precious materials for future usefulness—with the ardor and enthusiasm of youth—a heart burning with love to Christ and perishing souls—in whom are centred the hopes of many friends—such a youth is just entering upon the duties of life: when, lo! he is stricken down suddenly by the fell destroyer, and is no more. These things perplex us; such problems are too hard for us to solve—it is vain to attempt it. We must refer<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC6057-00000030"/> them all to the good pleasure of God. "Even so, Father, for so it seemeth good in thy sight."</p>
               <p>The Rev. Thomas Spencer, while yet a youth, was called to an important pastorate in Liverpool, England. He was a youth of rare attainments. Learned—pious—eloquent—richly furnished for his work, both by nature and by grace. In a little while his fame spread far and wide. Thousands thronged to hear him, and were moved and agitated by his powerful appeals, and clear exhibitions of divine truth. For the purpose of invigorating his exhausted frame from the fatigues of the Sabbath, he went early one Monday morning to bathe in the river Mersey. In a few minutes he was seen leaping into the stream. The effect was most exhilarating, and under the excitement he leaped again in the midst of the waters. Those who were with him in the stream were suddenly startled, for he had disappeared. But, lo! he rises again. Hark! he gives signs of distress—he cries for help—he sinks again—to rise no more! Thus young Spencer perished beneath the waters of the Mersey. The tidings spread rapidly through the city. Multitudes hasten to the fatal spot, to gaze upon the cold, ghastly features of him who, but yesterday, thrilled their souls with hope and joy, as he set forth the worth of the Saviour, and the glories of the celestial city. Of a truth, <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"God moves in a mysterious way,</l>
                        <l>His wonders to perform!"</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The sad story of the cruel death of the devoted Lowrie is familiar to our readers. Possessing a mind of the first order, a ripe scholar, richly furnished for every good work, he was eminently qualified for the position in which he was to be placed. He was always hopeful, ardent, cheerful, yet discreet. In judgment, sound, clear, discriminating. In disposition, amiable, conciliatory, yet conscientiously firm and decided. In short, he possessed such characteristics as would fit him to be a pioneer, a leader of the host of God, in that benighted region to which he was sent to labor.</p>
               <p>He occupied a prominent and most important post in that field. He girded himself for<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC6057-00000031"/> his work, and well and manfully did he perform it. The eyes of Christian friends were fixed upon him with intense interest and high anticipations of future usefulness. Though young, yet his co-laborers had the most entire confidence in his superior judgment and scholarship, and intrusted to him important interests. Returning from Shanghai, where he had been attending to some business of the mission, the vessel in which he had sailed was entered by a ruffian band of pirates, by whom the young missionary was cruelly murdered. Ah! what a sudden breach in the missionary ranks. How many hearts were pierced by the sad tidings that the <emph>devoted, the beloved Lowrie</emph> was no more!</p>
               <p>By these mysterious dispensations God designs to impress us with a due sense of his sovereignty—to repress our impatience to comprehend His infinite purposes. It is our duty to bow reverently before the Judge of all the earth, who will do right; to wait till, in the light of eternity, we shall behold all things in perfect harmony. "What I do, thou knowest not now: but thou shalt know hereafter."</p>
               <p>Dear young reader, what a solemn lesson is taught you by the preceding pages! You may be looking forward to life with bright anticipations; but you may never realize those pleasant dreams. You may not reach maturity. For aught you know, the seeds of disease may be sown already in your system; and inexorable death may have marked you as his prey. We would not needlessly alarm you; but oh! that we could awaken you to serious reflection, and lead you <emph>now</emph> to prepare to meet your God.</p>
               <p>Was not young Edgar in <emph>your</emph> judgment wise? Was he not right in seeking the favor of God—in becoming, by the aid of the Holy Spirit, a Christian? Had he postponed attention to the interests of his soul till too late, how painful would have been his death-bed scenes! How keen would have been the anguish of surviving friends, at the bare possibility of his having died without Christ! But behold the dying youth calmly awaiting his last change, when he would be forever with the Lord. What a halo of glory surrounds the<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC6057-00000032"/> couch of the dying Christian! Were you called to-night to lie on a bed of sickness and death, are you prepared? Could you cheerfully resign all, and look upwards to the judgment-seat without fear? Ah! think not that you will be able to ward off death by forgetfulness of God, and indifference to spiritual things. Be not deceived: God is not mocked. Tell me—why are you not yet a Christian? Why yet without hope? Surely you cannot plead ignorance; for you know your duty. Nor can you say that you have not been warned, counselled, entreated. You may have had a pious mother, who prayed for you, and with tears besought you ofttimes to pause, and consider your ways, and seek an interest in the Saviour.</p>
               <p>The church is praying for you—ministers are seeking your salvation, and would rejoice to counsel, and guide, and encourage you in the way of life. Christ died for you. His agonies in the garden—his wounds, and dying pangs—his precious blood plead with you, and call upon you to repent, to believe, and trust in Him for life eternal. The Spirit is striving with you. The Father, with infinite compassion says unto you, "My Son, give me thine heart." Turn ye, turn ye, for why will ye die? <emph>Oh! sinner, why?</emph>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC6057-00000033"/>
               <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Religion the chief source of domestic happiness—How?—Why?</p>
               </argument>
               <p>BEFORE noticing the dealings of God with the family of Claremont, during the year 18-6, let us pause, and inquire what lessons of wisdom are taught us by the preceding narrative.</p>
               <p>It clearly teaches <emph>that religion is an essential element of domestic happiness.</emph> Whatever may be to us a source of enjoyment, which does not view life as it is—with its sunny and shady sides—is essentially defective, and must fail us in the hour of need. Religion takes human life as it is, a mixture of good and evil. It takes into account all that is allotted us to suffer and enjoy, and provides for them all.</p>
               <p>Mutual love, peace, health, and worldly competence, are important ingredients in human happiness. Piety does not lessen their power for good, but regulates them, making them subservient to our higher interests. We are also exposed to trials, reverses, disease, and death. Religion has its supports—its consolations for the day of trouble, for death and eternity.</p>
               <p>In order to establish more fully the proposition, that religion is an essential element of domestic happiness, we must ascertain what benefits it confers—what is its influence upon the domestic relations—what its effects. It qualifies the members of a household for the discharge of their respective duties, leading each to seek the good of the others, and thus strengthens the ties of nature, and cements all hearts together.</p>
               <p>How differently do the domestic affections operate, when under the control of religion, and when not sanctified by the grace of God! What principle in nature is so strong, so purely disinterested, as maternal love! A mother's toils, and watchings, and anxiety for her off-spring, during infancy, childhood, and even through life, are cherished with grateful love, by every one whose heart is not seared and<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC6057-00000034"/> dead. Yet <emph>even this</emph> may be perverted and exerted for evil, when not under the influence of Christianity.</p>
               <p>A near neighbor of the Edgars—Mr. Mercer—was a man of considerable wealth. His wife was an amiable woman, but wholly devoted to the world. She possessed all the strong and delicate impulses of a woman's heart, but she was not a Christian.</p>
               <p>They were blessed with one pledge of mutual affection, a daughter, upon whom the mother lavished the riches of her love. The child was her idol. When the little one began to prattle, the fond mother commenced to impart her first simple lessons. But being herself a stranger to the truth as it is in Jesus, and the sweetness of his love, she taught not her little one to lisp his name.</p>
               <p>When Clara attained the age of girlhood, every wish of her young heart was gratified. With what delight did the mother behold in her child the early buddings of promise. No expense was spared in her education; the useful; the ornamental; all that could adorn the female character, were secured. Her mind which was naturally vigorous, had been highly improved by education. Her disposition was amiable, her beauty of person and grace of manner invested her with great power to please and attract, so that it was not strange that she was flattered, and her society courted by the young and the gay. But alas! her training, and all her accomplishments, had reference to this life <emph>only.</emph> That devoted mother regarded not her child as an heir of immortality, as possessing a soul to be educated for God and heaven.</p>
               <p>Amid the gayeties of life, and all the charms of early womanhood, Clara was taken suddenly ill. No immediate danger was apprehended, however, till the morning of the fourth day, when the disease assumed an alarming form. The attending physician vainly endeavored to conceal his anxiety from the mother. After preparing some medicine for his patient, and giving some necessary directions, he left the room. Mrs. Mercer, following him to the hall, asked him, with great earnestness, "Is there any danger in her case, doctor?" "I hope not, madam," was the unsatisfactory reply.</p>
               <pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC6057-00000035"/>
               <p>"I hope not; but she must be kept <emph>perfectly quiet.</emph> I shall see her again in the evening."</p>
               <p>His reply convinced her that there <emph>was</emph> danger. That day was to her one of great mental suffering. She anxiously waited the doctor's return. When he came, he was evidently ill at ease. He expressed a wish to have another physician called in for consultation, as the disease had assumed a form somewhat unfavorable, though he hoped not dangerous.</p>
               <p>The result of the consultation was to confirm the worst fears of the afflicted parents. The mother was almost distracted. She gave utterance to her mental distress in terms most painful to hear. "<emph>I cannot give her up! How can I part with my darling child! Oh! it is too much! I never thought it would come to this! Oh! I cannot give her up! I can-not!</emph>" Poor distracted mother, whither could she turn for strength—for consolation, at such a time!</p>
               <p>Though not a Christian, Mrs. Mercer had a vague impression that it was necessary to have a minister to pray for the dying—that some preparations must be made, in order to a peaceful and happy death. As her maternal affection tion led her to seek the welfare of her child, she ventured to suggest to her the propriety of sending for the good pastor of Glendale.</p>
               <p>Clara, as if awakened from a dream, was greatly startled by the strange suggestion, and asked her mother what she meant? What did <emph>she</emph> want with a minister? Was there any danger in her case? Suppressing the rising emotions of her heart, she replied, "You are <emph>very</emph> sick, my daughter." The tone, the manner, more than the simple words, revealed to the young sufferer the dreadful truth she was about to die! Ah! now, for the first time, the thought of dying entered her soul.</p>
               <p>To the young and hopeful, death is ever an unwelcome messenger, even when they can repose in humble trust upon a Saviour's arm. The young heart clings to this bright and beautiful world, so replete with untried joys. But, when not supported by the love of Jesus, death must be to the young, the King of Terrors. Clara was greatly alarmed and distressed about her condition. The early religious impressions she had received in the Sabbath-school were now revived with freshness and<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC6057-00000036"/> power. She had learned something of Jesus and his salvation. She felt the need of counsel. She tried to pray. She asked her mother to pray for her. Alas! that mother could not; for she had not been taught by the Spirit of God to pray.</p>
               <p>That evening the fever returned with great violence, probably aggravated by the mental excitement to which she was subjected during the day. She became delirious. Amid all her incoherent expressions were clearly revealed the workings of a soul keenly alive, even in delirium, to its fearful condition. "<emph>I must not die! Where are you, mother? Save me, oh! save me! I cannot leave you! I am not ready to die! Why, oh mother! why did you not teach me to love the Saviour? But now I cannot! It is too late!</emph> TOO LATE!"</p>
               <p>Thus the poor girl continued for some time, in alternate cries for help, and upbraidings of her heart-stricken mother. Soon after she sank into a troubled sleep, lingered till morning, and then—died! The bereaved mother was overwhelmed with grief. In her deep agony of soul she had no solace, no refuge whither to flee.</p>
               <p>But did she not love her daughter? No mother was ever more devoted to her offspring. Her maternal impulses were strong and constant; but they were not regulated by the word of God—not sanctified by the influences of the Holy Spirit. She lived for the present only, and trained up her child for this world, regardless of eternity and all its momentous interests. An immortal soul may be ruined by maternal love! How awful the thought!</p>
               <p>Compare with this the case of Mrs. Edgar. She recognized, as every mother should, her children as lent her to be her comfort, to be trained up, not for the world, but for God and eternity. Her love being under the control of religion, led her to seek for her offspring a better portion than this world. They were given to God in baptism, accompanied with many tears, and fervent prayers that they might live before God. No expense was spared in the education of her children. As she beheld in her daughters the buddings<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC6057-00000037"/> of promise, she experienced all the satisfaction a devoted mother could feel.</p>
               <p>But she rejoiced most of all, because she saw that they possessed the priceless ornaments of piety. As her son advanced toward manhood, giving signs of future usefulness and honor, her heart swelled with joy and hope; but all this did not satisfy her, while he continued disobedient to the calls of the gospel. When he was led to the Saviour, and chose the ministry of reconciliation as his future work, then her cup of joy was full to overflowing.</p>
               <p>Was she called unexpectedly to give up that son to God? The struggle was severe; but faith triumphed. She was enabled to resign him with calm submission. There were no chidings, by the dying son, of that faithful mother; nor were her sorrows increased, in that trying hour, by the remembrance of neglected duties. She had a refuge from the storm. She was comforted by the assurance that with him <emph>all was well.</emph>
               </p>
               <p>Which of these mothers, think you, dear reader, acted the more wisely? And why the difference? The answer is obvious. One was under the influence of the grace of God, the other knew not its power—felt not its charms.</p>
               <p>In the case of Miss Edgar, we have an illustration of the workings of the fraternal affections, when renewed and sanctified. What deep and tender solicitude she felt for her brother, when she regarded him destitute of hope! How fervently did she plead with God for his salvation! Most skilfully did she ply the weapons of truth and love to the citadel of the heart! How eloquently did she set forth the claims of Christ, and the blessedness of pardon! Her joy was great when, in response to her earnest appeals, he revealed to her the state of his mind, and told her that he had been seeking the Saviour, and had some hope that he had found Him.</p>
               <p>We have also seen in that family the blessed effects of piety upon filial affections. When the son had found peace by believing, it was natural for them to turn with solicitude to the aged man, who was all a husband and father could be without the influence of Divine grace. They could not rest till he also was<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC6057-00000038"/> led to the refuge of salvation. They unitedly besieged the mercy-seat; and He, who is rich in mercy, honored the faith, and accepted propitiously the pleadings of sanctified affections.</p>
               <p>That religion is an essential element of domestic happiness is evident, because of its influence upon worldly prosperity. How prevalent the impression that religion is adapted only for the day of adversity! And when this is said, it is deemed sufficient homage paid to its power and excellence. To intimate that it is needful as well for the time of prosperity, excites their surprise.</p>
               <p>Many view piety as inimical to all worldly enjoyments—that it lays an embargo upon the use of the good things of this world. They think that the religious should always wear a demure face, and bow down his head like a bulrush. But how would they construe the following passages of holy writ? "In the day of prosperity be joyful." "Go thy way, eat thy bread with a merry heart; for God now accepteth thy work." "Live joyfully with the wife, whom thou lovest, all the days of the life of thy vanities." "Godliness is profitable unto all things, having promise of the life that now is, and of that which is to come." They could scarcely believe that these were the dictates of religion, so perverted are the judgments of men, and such their prejudice against the truth. What foul aspersions have been cast upon Christianity by its foes!</p>
               <p>The Christian may extract purer, sweeter enjoyments from prosperity than the worldling. Behold one who has been prosperous in business, and has accumulated considerable wealth; his home is cheered by the presence and smiles of one devoted to his interests—the sharer of his joys and sorrows; he is blessed with children "who are like olive plants around his table;" with his portion of this world, he has, moreover, in heaven a more enduring substance. Is not his enjoyment of the good things of this life increased by the assurance that they are the gifts of God, <emph>his Father,</emph> reconciled to him by the blood of Emmanuel? Is not he, who with his riches enjoys the favor of heaven, happier than his equally prosperous neighbor, who is without God in the world? <emph>He</emph> may also be surrounded by loved and loving<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC6057-00000039"/> ing ones; but, being a stranger to the power of religion, he cannot look forward to the future without the most gloomy apprehensions. It must embitter his cup of domestic bliss, to feel that the wife of his bosom, or his children, may at any moment be snatched from his embraces; or that he may be driven from his possessions, and all the sweets of home, by relentless death.</p>
               <p>The family of Claremont had abundance of this world's good. Was their happiness lessened when the salvation of God entered their house? Did they not enjoy their prosperity as much? Was their joy in each other not as pure, and real, when they were rejoicing in the love of God, and animated by the hope of heaven, as it was before their conversion? In the experience of Mr. Edgar, all things became new, when grace entered his heart. Even his fields wore a fairer aspect, and his faithful wife and children were dearer to him than when he was a stranger to the peace of God that passeth all understanding.</p>
               <p>If these remarks be true, it is manifest that were our days to be always unclouded—were our tabernacle to remain in peace; even then religion would be essential to our happiness. But <emph>change</emph> is written upon all things earthly. Sorrows and joys—days of darkness as well as of light await us all. He who, in his calculations of life, has overlooked this fact, is doomed to suffer sad disappointments and bitter sorrow.</p>
               <p>Are we in the midst of competence, and in the enjoyment of worldly comforts to-day? Riches may make for themselves wings and flee away. Reverses in business are not of rare occurrence. Messengers of evil may come in quick succession: one by one our comforts may leave us; our sun may be darkened at noon, and our heart may fail us for fear of the evil to come. Though the dear friends of Claremont were greatly favored by Providence, yet they were not exempt from all evil. Disease invaded their happy circle, and the pride and hope of the family is first assailed, and in all his vigor, and in the midst of the brightest prospects, he falls a prey to death.</p>
               <p>The servant of God is called sometimes to witness the most trying scenes in the chamber<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC6057-00000040"/> of sickness. A parent is called suddenly to die. An interesting group of children may be there, clinging to the dying parent; and in turn the parental affection entwines itself around the loved ones. How reluctant to give each other up! All before them is doubt and darkness. No ray appears to cheer the dying, or support the living. The minister of truth may tell the dying that God's mercy is free and infinite, that peradventure he may be found. But he cannot bid the survivors to dry their tears, and look forward to eternity in the joyful hope of a blessed reunion. What can he say to cheer them! The voice of prayer was never heard there. The counsels, promises, and the encouragements of the word of truth have always been unheeded. In all their domestic arrangements there had been no provision made for the day of trouble. But the evil day came—death entered that house, and made a wide breach in that family circle.</p>
               <p>How awful, at such an hour, to have no God in whom to trust; no mercy-seat whither to resort; no Saviour on whose almighty arm to lean; no refuge wherein to hide ourselves, and no hope of future blessedness to dispel the gloom of death! The final separation of friends is painful under the most favorable circumstances, but vastly more so when there remains a doubt concerning the safety of the departed. On the other hand, if we have a comfortable evidence that our friends, who have been torn away from us, are at rest in the bosom of Jesus, it alleviates our grief. Though we weep, we sorrow not as those who have no hope.</p>
               <p>But it might be asked, how does religion produce such wonderful effects? what is the <emph>secret</emph> of its power?</p>
               <p>The grace of God leads us to recognize the hand of the Lord in all our affairs, governing and directing all according to His infinite wisdom and goodness; that all we possess and enjoy are the gifts of His bounty; that when He takes these away, He is only recalling what is his own. Without such views and feelings, we cannot enjoy our prosperity, or submissively yield up all our comforts, and endure afflictions.</p>
               <pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC6057-00000041"/>
               <p>Talk of bearing the ills of life as a philosopher! It is sheer folly. We may blunt the sensibilities of our nature, but only by suicidal acts most cruel. And this boasted stoicism is, at best, the sullenness of the brute. How well does one of the most strenuous advocates of this philosophy express its practical workings in his own experience! Referring to the infirmities of age, and domestic trials, he says:</p>
               <p>"Shall I tell you that I bear this melancholy situation with that meritorious constancy and resignation, of which most people boast? No: for I really <emph>cannot</emph> help it. I bear it, because I <emph>must</emph> bear it, whether I <emph>will or not.</emph> I think of nothing but of killing time the best way I can, now he has become my enemy." What a commentary upon that heroism, so much extolled under the false name of philosophy! How unreliable its supports! How incomparbly superior is the philosophy of Christianity!</p>
               <p>The Christian loves his family most ardently, and enjoys the sweets of domestic life; he also feels keenly the calamities which befall him, the loss of friends, and other sore afflictions tions. But he is enabled to resign his comforts, when it seems good in the sight of the Lord to recall them. As they are taken away one by one, he says: "What! shall we receive good at the hand of God, and shall we not receive evil? The Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away; blessed be the name of the Lord!" "Although the fig-tree shall not blossom, neither shall fruit be in the vine; the labor of the olive shall fail, and the field shall yield no meat; the flock shall be cut off from the fold, and there shall be no herd in the stall: yet I will rejoice in the Lord, I will joy in the God of my salvation." And, even when stripped of his all, faith enables him to triumph and exclaim—"Though he slay me, yet will I trust in him." It is comparatively easy to endure trials, when persuaded that "Whom the Lord loveth He chasteneth, and scourgeth every son whom He receiveth." If, in the midst of danger, we hear the voice of God saying, "Fear not, for I am with thee: be not dismayed, for I am thy God: I will never leave thee, nor forsake thee," what need we more to arm us<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC6057-00000042"/> for the conflicts of life, or patiently to endure all its trials!</p>
               <p>But religion does more than reconcile us to our trials; it also sanctifies them to us, causing "all things to work together for good to them that love God, to them who are the called according to his purpose." Many a household will bless God forever for their trials. When all was well, folly and fashion reigned. In their prosperity they said unto God, "Depart from us, for we desire not the knowledge of thy ways. What is the Almighty, that we should serve Him? And what profit shall we have if we pray unto Him?" God sent to them a messenger bearing evil tidings. Reverses of fortune befell them—disease entered their dwelling. In the midst of their gayeties, the voice of music and mirth was hushed, and in its stead, the voice of weeping and mourning was heard. In their trouble, they were led to seek the Lord. A most blessed change was produced. Now an altar is erected in that house, and morning and evening they gather around the mercy-seat, and mingle their voices in the family devotions.</p>
               <p>To them the cup of sorrow has been made the cup of blessing. Verily, their afflictions yielded to them the peaceable fruits of righteousness. An individual having met with an accident, which was the means under God of awakening him to a sense of his lost condition, was wont to say, with more pith, perhaps, than elegance, that he would have reason to praise God to all eternity for his afflictions. "For," said he, "when I was posting my way to hell, Christ met me in my mad career, and broke my limb, to save my soul."</p>
               <p>The fruit of all the Christian's trials is to purge away sin. His afflictions, be they ever so painful, have nothing penal in them. They are like fire to the gold, pruning to the vine, medicine to the patient, correction to the child. Christ "sits as a refiner and purifier of silver: and he shall purify the sons of Levi, and purge them as gold and silver, that they may offer unto the Lord an offering in righteousness." It is easy to bear the rod, when we know that "our light afflictions, which are but for a moment, are working out for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory."</p>
               <pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC6057-00000043"/>
               <p>Above all, religion bears up its possessors under the vicissitudes of life, by imparting to them the glorious hope of heaven. To court tribulation and death is fanaticism. Religion teaches us to shun dangers. "Do thyself no harm," is its language. But when they are sent upon us, it arms us with strength to endure them, assuring us of final triumph. No man, not even the best, seeks death for <emph>its own sake.</emph> "We that are in this tabernacle do groan, being burdened: not for that we would be unclothed, but clothed upon, that mortality might be swallowed up of life." They are willing to be stripped of the garments of corruption, in order to be attired in the robes of light and glory.</p>
               <p>What can reconcile us to leave all the endearments of home, all the sweet fellowships of kindred and friends? The glorious anticipations of heaven. The sure hope of being admitted into the goodly fellowship of angels and saints, and, above all, of Jesus the Mediator. Faith robs death of his power to harm, by uniting the soul to Christ, who destroyed him who had the power of death, and has delivered livered them who, through the fear of death, were all their lifetime subject to bondage. Trembling believer! do you ask <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"How you may meet your conflict yet,</l>
                        <l>In the dark narrow way?"</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>We answer:— <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"Through Him—through Him that path who trod!</l>
                        <l>He proved them all—the doubt, the strife,</l>
                        <l>The faint perplexing dread,</l>
                        <l>The mists that hang o'er parting life,</l>
                        <l>All gathered round His head."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q> Through Christ we are made more than conquerors over death and the tomb.</p>
               <p>If religion gives to prosperity its true worth—fits us for the day of adversity—makes our trials conducive to our spiritual good—renders that which is in itself a curse, a rich blessing, and reconciles us to privations, sufferings, and death—it must be an essential element of true happiness. "Length of days is in her right hand, and in her left hand riches and honor. Her ways are ways of pleasantness, and all her paths are peace."</p>
               <p>Dear reader, are you a stranger to the grace<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC6057-00000044"/> of God? Oh, be persuaded to seek religion <emph>now.</emph> Why deprive yourself of present peace, and expose yourself to eternal ruin? Are you, under the common prejudices of unbelief, ready to ask, "Can any good come out of Nazareth?" Is religion worth anything? "Come and see." "Oh, taste and see that the Lord is good: blessed is the man that trusteth in Him."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The church of Glendale—Its early history—The revival of 18-6—Its fruits.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE old church of Glendale, with its spacious burying-place—a spot rendered sacred by many precious reminiscences—we deem worthy of more than a passing notice, especially as it is so intimately connected with our narrative. It was the spiritual birth-place of three of the members of the dear family of Claremont. In its communion they lived and rejoiced—for its welfare they labored and prayed—to it was bequeathed the fragrance of their piety, and the influence of their happy and triumphant death—and in that graveyard their sleeping remains will rest, until the general resurrection.</p>
               <p>We regard with great interest, indeed with feelings bordering on veneration, ancient<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC6057-00000045"/> church edifices, which are so many links connecting the present with the past. Their style of architecture, their internal and external arrangements, convey to us very accurate impressions as to the peculiar customs of olden times, and the modes of worship our fathers adopted. When we witness the demolishing of one of these structures, in order to give place to another more in keeping with modern tastes and improvements, we experience emotions akin to such as are excited by the death of one rendered venerable by age and extensive usefulness.</p>
               <p>The church of Glendale was a venerable structure situated in a beautiful grove, on a hill, which commanded a full view of an extensive valley highly cultivated, and bearing the marks of thrift and skill in husbandry. Often did we watch the people wending their way through the prosperous vale beneath, toward the sanctuary. At such times, we were forcibly reminded of the words of the Psalmist: "I was glad when they said unto me, Let us go into the house of the Lord, whither the tribes go up." What comparable parable to a bright Sabbath in the country! By its influence the devout mind is calmed and cheered, and fitted for sweet communion with God.</p>
               <p>Rude seats were arranged in that pleasant grove under the shade of ancient trees, which had looked down for almost a century on the Sabbath visitors, and seemed to greet them kindly as they returned statedly to the hallowed spot. There the people met, and exchanged the salutations of the seasons, and rested awhile before the morning services. At an early hour the good pastor was there. And as a father among his family, he might be seen passing from group to group of his parishioners, greeting them with a smile, and words of kindness—never omitting to take by the hand the little ones of his flock. He was greatly beloved by his charge. At the appointed hour, he would direct his steps towards the sanctuary, which was the signal for all to assemble in the house of God.</p>
               <p>Their place of worship was substantial, commodious, and sufficiently attractive to please people of rural habits and tastes, who relished<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC6057-00000046"/> the plain wholesome truths of the gospel, and had no itchings after gorgeous temples and attractive ceremonials.</p>
               <p>As the congregation was considerably scattered, instead of returning home after morning service, the people were accustomed, during an hour's intermission, to partake of refreshments brought with them for that purpose. After this primitive repast, a second service was held; while the evening of the Sabbath was devoted to meetings for prayer in the several districts of the congregation.</p>
               <p>The modern innovation of praising God by proxy was not in vogue in the congregation of Glendale. The time-honored practice of congregational singing was still adhered to—the united voices of all the people sweetly harmonizing in the songs of praise, ascending as a pleasing offering to the throne of God. Doubtless there were some jarring notes: the hypercritic, who regards artistic effect of more importance than the melody of soul which God approves, could easily have detected frequent violations of the rules of musical criticism. But still there is in the singing of the praises of God by the whole congregation, an inspiration of soul, an elevation of heart to heaven, which all the so-called "<emph>improvements</emph>" in church music could never produce.</p>
               <p>From these remarks, it might be inferred that we are unfriendly to all reforms in sacred music. Not so, however. What we condemn, is the practice of <emph>hiring artistic performers</emph>—in many cases not even professedly Christians—to do the singing of God's praise <emph>exclusively.</emph> Hence tunes are sung, or rather "compositions are rendered," of such a character as effectually to exclude the uninitiated from uniting with them, however much their hearts may be inspired to sing the Lord's praise. How foreign to the spirit of devotion! How utterly at war with the design of devotional singing! Such may be suited to the concert-room or the opera; but are wholly inadmissible in the house of God. Let all the improvements of the science be applied to church music; let the aid of instruments be called in, if necessary, so as to make this part of divine worship acceptable to the most refined Christian taste; let all be done that can be, to<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC6057-00000047"/> elevate and advance pure church music: but let it <emph>be church</emph> music—let it be a full, heart-felt union of all voices in congregational singing.</p>
               <p>In order to secure for the church this most desirable state of things, in this department of devotional worship, let the children of the church be taught the science of music; let congregations feel it to be their duty to adopt and sustain such measures as shall secure to them all the benefits of the science; let singing be regarded as an appropriate part of Sabbath-school instruction; let all the youth be enlisted in the work—and a better day will dawn upon us. The good old tunes to which our fathers were wont to sing the songs of Zion—held sacred by many pleasing associations of home and church—will ere long be sung in sweeter strains than are now heard in our churches.</p>
               <p>But to return to our story. Not far from the old church there stood a rude structure, which deserves a passing notice. It was so unique as always to attract the attention of strangers, and led to the inquiry, "For what purpose was it erected?"</p>
               <p>It was a venerable relic of olden times; preserved with care by the present generation, associated as it was with the sweetest recollections of their youth. In the early settlement of the western frontiers—when the population was sparse, churches far apart, facilities for travelling imperfect, and Christian intercourse not easily enjoyed—sacramental seasons were regarded with peculiar interest. At these blessed times, those living far apart would meet and spend several days together in religious exercises. An immense concourse of people would thus be brought together to some of the most central points. The church edifices were too small to accommodate the vast throng of people that would collect together on such occasions. Convenient places in groves and woods were selected, where logs and rough boards were arranged as seats. The pulpits at these places of assembly were usually erected with care, and preserved for future use. Such was the structure of which we are speaking—a pulpit in which had stood<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC6057-00000048"/> many of those mighty men of God, whom Providence raised up and qualified for great and noble purposes.</p>
               <p>Many a pleasant hour have we spent seated near that antique structure, listening to some of the old men of the congregation recounting the deeds of those noble-hearted men, and telling us of the glorious exhibitions of God's presence, which they had witnessed in their boyhood. The scenes of other days, as they were thus revived, often affected us so deeply that we almost envied the sturdy oaks under whose genial shade the gathering throng assembled, to listen to the thrilling eloquence of those goodly men, whose names even to this day are held in veneration by the church. From morning until eventide, with but a brief intermission at noon for refreshment, the people heard with joy the words of eternal life. On the Sabbath, the great day of the feast, they commemorated the dying love of the Redeemer. Those were days of gladness and triumph to the church. Oh! that we were permitted in these days of formality and spiritual declension, to witness such times of refreshing from the Lord! such tokens of His presence in the sanctuary!</p>
               <p>What a contrast between the Christians of that day and their children! What an effort it is for us to sit in our cushioned pews an <emph>hour</emph> or <emph>two</emph> to worship God! We deem it a great sacrifice of comfort, and a high compliment to the preacher to bear with him that space of time. Should the transcendent importance of his theme cause him to forget himself, and pass beyond the accustomed hour, he may deem himself fortunate if some of his kind-hearted parishioners do not, from a tender regard for his reputation, admonish him of the disastrous consequences of <emph>long sermons.</emph> Should a slight protraction of the morning exercises occur, the less considerate show their disapprobation by absenting themselves from the house of God in the evening. Should you reason with them concerning the sinfulness of such a course, their reply would be, "<emph>We cannot abide long sermons.</emph>"</p>
               <p>Far be it from us to advocate all the practices of our fathers. We also are "progressives," when true progress can be made.<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC6057-00000049"/> It must be admitted that, owing to change of circumstances, many of their customs would be wholly inexpedient at the present time. But we should not speak lightly of their peculiarities. There is much in the manner in which they endured privations and sufferings for Christ, in the character of their piety, to excite admiration, and well worthy of our imitation. Are the Christians of the present day as mighty in the Scriptures as our fathers? Do we place as high an estimate upon the ministration of the truth and ordinances of the church? Do we love the sanctuary as devoutly? Are the fruits of our piety as manifest? And are the triumphs of the gospel as wonderful, and the accessions to the church of such as should be saved, as numerous as in olden times?</p>
               <p>The church of Glendale had been blessed with several precious revivals at different periods in its history. We have already referred to a precious season, which was enjoyed during the summer of 18-5. Among the fruits of that revival, Miss Edgar and her brother, with their aged parent, were found. Early in the spring of 18-6 there were some favorable indications of the presence of God among the people. Meetings for prayer were well attended; the people looked for a revival of the work of grace, and earnestly prayed for it; the good pastor seemed to preach with special reference to it. The people thought he preached with more unction than was his wont; which very probably was the case, as they evidently <emph>prayed</emph> for him more fervently.</p>
               <p>Ah! it is a sad task to preach to a people who heed not the injunction of the Apostle: "<emph>Brethren, pray for us.</emph>" Let the people pray more for their pastor—in secret, at the family altar, and in the social circle, and they will be the gainers. How it cheers the faithful shepherd in the midst of his toils and trials, to know that he lives in the affections of his flock! He studies better, preaches more effectively, and works with more delight.</p>
               <p>It is a sure sign that the time to favor Zion, yea, the set time, has come, "when the servants of the Lord take pleasure in her stones, and favor the dust thereof." When the people say, "For Zion's sake will we not hold our<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC6057-00000050"/> peace, and for Jerusalem's sake we will not rest, until the righteousness thereof go forth as brightness, and the salvation thereof as a lamp that burneth;" such was the state of things in the church of Glendale in the spring of 18-6. The gentle rain of grace descended upon that hill of Zion. Christians were revived, and rejoiced in God's salvation. Doubtless, the death of young Edgar was the means of producing much seriousness among his late youthful companions. Most of those who became hopefully pious were pupils of the Sabbath-school, for whom unceasing prayer had been offered to God. Some of them were very young—mere children.</p>
               <p>The character of that revival deserves special notice. All the circumstances connected with it proved it to be of God. The people longed for a revival of religion. It came not with observation. There was no undue excitement. The preaching was earnest, the truth was presented with clearness, and direct appeals were made to the consciences of men. But there was no noise or tumult. The stillness of death reigned during the public services vices. Earnest heed was given to the truth. The silent tear might be seen trickling down many a cheek unused to weeping, but there were no sudden or violent outbursts of feeling. All were fully conscious of the Divine presence; Christians were led to exclaim: "How dreadful is this place! This is none other but the house of God; this is the gate of heaven."</p>
               <p>Nor can we overlook the fruits of that revival, for the genuineness of revivals is to be tested chiefly by their fruits. Things falsely called revivals have often proved most disastrous in their consequences. They have been succeeded by dissensions and divisions in churches. Their subjects were proud, full of conceit, censorious, borne away by fanaticism to all length of extravagance, and finally led to embrace most ruinous errors.</p>
               <p>Such, alas! have so often been the fruits of these misnamed revivals, that many good men, and conscientious Christians, have spoken unadvisedly of all occasions of the kind, and look with suspicion upon all extraordinary interest or unusual excitement on the subject of religion, and have openly condemned all efforts<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC6057-00000051"/> to promote genuine revivals in the church. While it must be admitted that there have been spurious excitements on the subject of religion, it is certainly true that many genuine revivals have been enjoyed. Their blessed fruits are yet seen in the church. The full extent of their influence will be known only in eternity. It is unfair to confound the <emph>true</emph> with the <emph>false.</emph> "What is the chaff to the wheat? said the Lord."</p>
               <p>In this day of darkness and rebuke, would to God our churches were permitted to enjoy the pentecostal seasons, which our fathers witnessed, and which are connected with our earliest recollections; when the arm of the Lord was revealed, and multitudes were brought into the kingdom. Ere the church shall be able to execute her high and holy mission, in the spread of the gospel—in the overthrow of the dominion of sin and Satan, and in the full establishing of the throne and authority of the Prince of Peace—must there not be witnessed another pentecostal day? Must not the church experience anew the baptism of the Holy Ghost? Otherwise, how are her deep death-slumbers slumbers to be broken? How is the standard of piety to be elevated, and self-consecration to the service of Christ to be attained? The great heart of the church must be enlarged and inspired, so that its outgushings shall be a faint type of the outgushings of the heart of Him who gave Himself a ransom for His people.</p>
               <p>But what were the fruits of the revival of 18-6 at Glendale? A new and better spirit was infused into the church. The people sympathized more deeply with the benevolent operations of the day; felt a deeper interest in the spiritual wants of a dying world. Their hearts were enlarged, and their hands were opened to contribute more freely and cheerfully of their means to sustain the enterprises of the church. They also manifested more liberality in the support of their faithful pastor. All these are sure signs of a heartfelt and abiding interest in the cause of Christ.</p>
               <p>At the communion, in the fall of that year, there was gladness in God's tabernacle. Many a harp that had for months hung upon the willows, was strung anew, and songs of salvation<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC6057-00000052"/> were heard in their dwellings. When the Lord turned again the captivity of Zion, their mouth was filled with laughter, and their tongue with singing: saying, "The Lord hath done great things for us, whereof we are glad."</p>
               <p>As the subjects of that revival were for the most part from the Sabbath-school, it might be asked was there any special interest in the school previously, and were the teachers engaged in that good work? For months previous, the teachers had been in the habit of spending a short season in social prayer on Sabbath morning before entering upon their work, for the outpouring of the Holy Spirit upon the school. All seemed anxious to do good, and to instruct their pupils, so as to secure the blessing of God upon the school.</p>
               <p>Of the many interesting incidents connected with the work of grace in that Sabbath-school, we shall give one example. It was the case of Miss Edgar. One Sabbath evening, as she was walking home from prayer-meeting, in company with the superintendent, her mind was evidently troubled. She told him that she had concluded to resign the charge of her class, assigning as a reason her conscious unfitness for such a responsible work. She feared that she was the Achan in the camp, preventing the blessing of God upon the school. Being asked how that sense of unfitness affected her mind, she replied—"It leads me to search my own heart, and scrutinize my motives in engaging in the service of Christ. I endeavor to prepare myself by prayer, and the careful study of the Bible, for my duties. Yet I return home every Sabbath, ashamed of my feeble efforts to instruct my class. I seek forgiveness, and strength to be more faithful. But I feel such a sense of responsibility as to be almost too painful for me." The superintendent very properly said: "<emph>You cannot resign.</emph> You <emph>cannot</emph> be spared. <emph>Yours</emph> is the state of mind in which we should enter upon every good work, having for its object the salvation of souls, and the glory of the Redeemer. Would that we all felt as you do! Then we might look for a day of gladness to dawn upon our school, and the revival of the work of the Lord in the church."</p>
               <p>The deep interest which the teachers of the<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC6057-00000053"/> Sabbath-school felt in the spiritual welfare of their pupils, which led them to pray and labor for their salvation—the conversion of a number of the pupils during the revival of 18-6, as the result of the efforts, and in answer to the prayers of those teachers—suggest important reflections, which will furnish materials for our next chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Sabbath school institution—Its importance to the church—What is necessary to its effectiveness—The duty of the church to her children, what?—Of parents and teachers, what?</p>
               </argument>
               <p>"WOULD to God we all felt as you do! then we might look for a day of gladness to dawn upon our Sabbath-school, and the revival of the work of the Lord in the church." These were strong expressions. Their correctness might be called in question by those whose sympathies are not deeply enlisted in the Sabbath-school cause.</p>
               <p>But he was right. There is no more potent auxiliary to the church than a Sabbath-school, rightly conducted and cared for by all who sustain an intimate relation to it—teachers, parents, pastors, and leading members and officers in the church. And yet there is one fact in connection with this subject which<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC6057-00000054"/> deserves to be seriously pondered: the number of conversions among the pupils of Sabbath-schools is lamentably small. What is the cause? Where lies the fault? Is it in the institution? Is its foundation defective, or are any of its essential elements positively bad? The basis of all the instruction imparted is the word of God. The mode of teaching is catechetical—giving line upon line, here a little and there a little. The libraries attached to all well regulated schools consist of works pre-eminently suited to illustrate and enforce the precious truths of the gospel. The teachers are mostly professing Christians. The pupils are for the most part the children of piety, for whose proper instruction the church is responsible. There are also to be found in the Sabbath-school the children of parents who lack either the ability or disposition to instruct their offspring. These poor unfortunate ones are sought out and brought under the influence of the truth as it is in Jesus. Such is the Sabbath-school institution, such its aim, its end, and such the means employed to accomplish these ends. And is there aught in all this positively wrong, and tending to evil? Far from it. The institution is preeminently adapted to be effective for good.</p>
               <p>We bless God for the American S. S. Union—an institution which deservedly stands high in the estimation of every patriot and philanthropist. Who can fully compute the counteracting, elevating, and saving influence of the religious literature this noble society has published, and scattered throughout the length and breadth of the land! Strongly biased by prejudice must be the judgment, and cold must be the heart of <emph>that man</emph> who can view with indifference such an institution, or can assail its integrity by word or deed.</p>
               <p>The record of membership in our churches; the host of active pious laymen; the ranks of the ministry; the many interesting memories of children who were savingly impressed by the instructions of faithful teachers, and died rejoicing in Jesus; all yield blessed evidence of the effectiveness of Sabbath-schools.</p>
               <p>As the institution cannot be charged with the fault, that the number of conversions among the pupils is so small, we must trace it<pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC6057-00000055"/> to some other source. We think the fault rests partly with the church, partly with Christian parents, and partly with the teachers. Do Christian parents practically believe in the conversion of their <emph>children?</emph> Does the church act upon such a belief? While many of the declarations and promises of the Bible imply the conversion of children, while there are examples in the sacred volume of some being sanctified from their birth, as Jeremiah, John Baptist, and others, of some also who were called in early childhood by the grace of God, as Samuel, Josiah, Timothy, yet the faith of the church is exceedingly feeble, and the views of many Christian parents strangely vague on this subject.</p>
               <p>If perchance, during a season of revival, some very young children be awakened to a sense of their perilous condition, does it not often excite surprise, a feeling akin to incredulity? There have not been wanting instances when the genuineness of their conversion was beyond all doubt, and yet friends have opposed their admission into the church, and church officers have been slow to welcome these tender lambs into the fold of Christ.</p>
               <p>Take one example which came to our knowledge a few years ago. It was the case of a young person who was admitted to the church in her fifteenth year. It was soon manifest that her piety was of no ordinary stamp. She became an object of great interest to her pastor, who watched over her with care, and rejoiced to witness in her the rapid development of the life of faith, and a great promise of future usefulness. But God, who is wise in counsel, was pleased to transplant that beautiful flower from his garden on earth to bloom in the paradise above.</p>
               <p>After her decease, it was our privilege to peruse a diary kept by her from early childhood. We were surprised to find a form of covenant drawn up in her own hand-writing, in which was a solemn consecration of herself to Christ, made in her eleventh year. This led us to seek some explanation of the matter. We learned that during an interesting season of revival in the church of which her friends<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC6057-00000056"/> were then members, she was awakened and became hopefully pious. The pastor regarded her case with great favor, and urged the propriety of admitting her to the privileges of the church. But it was deemed best to defer her admission into the church on account of her extreme youth. It was at <emph>that period</emph> she drew up the form of covenant to which we have referred. For maturity of thought, clear views of truth, and propriety of arrangement and diction, the document would have done credit to any one twice her age.</p>
               <p>Christian parents must at times be greatly concerned for the salvation of their offspring, and fervent supplications must be ascending to God that their children may live before Him. Yet when these prayers are heard and answered in the early conversion of their children, these parents are taken by surprise! The conversion of very young children is regarded as the <emph>exception</emph> rather than the general rule of God's great plan of gracious operation: and that which would be regarded, in persons of mature age, as sufficient evidence of thoughtfulness, is often treated lightly in the case of children, as mere transient impressions which will soon pass away.</p>
               <p>Good impressions are doubtless often made upon the minds of the young, which might result in permanent advantage, were they properly treated and cherished, but which are often lost through the influence of those who above all others ought to regard them most tenderly. If the Spirit operate through the truth upon the mind and heart of the child, its views of the truth must be those of a child; it must think as a child; it must speak as a child. And though its impressions are not as mature as those of a man, yet they may be as real; its love to the Saviour as pure, and its exercise of faith in Christ be as genuine.</p>
               <p>As the faith of the church is imperfect as regards the subject of early conversions, the people of God are not sufficiently alive to the importance of the Sabbath-school institution. In her plans of operation, the church does not embrace as fully as she ought the interests of this institution—does not spread over it her protecting wing—nor are her sympathies sufficiently enlisted in its behalf.</p>
               <pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC6057-00000057"/>
               <p>Were an entire stranger to the existence of such an institution to enter the majority of our churches on the Sabbath, and our weekly social meetings, and listen to the intercessions of the church, could he infer from the prayers of pastors or people, that there existed an institution, in connection with the church, whose sole object is to promote the religious instruction of her children; to train them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord, and in due time to bring them to the fold of the Redeemer? If this be so—and we leave our readers to judge—is it any marvel that the good fruit from this source is not more abundant? The interests of this institution must be nearer the heart of the church, ere its fruits are as plentiful and the number of conversions among the youth as manifold, as the promises of God would encourage us to expect.</p>
               <p>In the preceding pages we have endeavored to represent the matter as fairly as possible. No one can call in question the truth of the assertion that the church has not come up to her duty to her children, and that the faith of Christian parents, touching the conversion of their offspring in early childhood, is very imperfect. There are many bright examples of congregations doing their duty towards this class. Their little ones are brought to Jesus, that he might bless them. And what is the consequence? The work of the Lord is prospering, the youth are numbered among the followers of the Lamb, and the children of the church are "like olive plants around her tables." All such examples tend only to confirm our assertion. Let the church be faithful to herself, extend her fostering care to her little ones, and out of the mouths of babes and sucklings God will perfect praise. According to her faith, so shall it be to the church.</p>
               <p>But we have said that the fault of which we are now speaking rests partly with those who are engaged as instructors in our Sabbath-schools. Is it so? Far be it from us to cast the least reflection upon that worthy class in our churches, who cheerfully devote a portion of their time to instruct the ignorant and those who are out of the way. Many of them, like the good Harlan Page, are accomplishing<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC6057-00000058"/> a vast amount of good, and deserve the gratitude of the church for their work of faith and love. Many of these have been richly rewarded for all their toil by seeing some of their pupils brought early to the Saviour. The faithful teacher has his witnesses now on earth, and his record on high: because multitudes of little ones are in glory, clothed in white, following the Lamb whithersoever. He goeth, who were led to Jesus through his prayerful exertions.</p>
               <p>The ties which bind together the teacher and the taught, how tender, yet how strong! What an influence for good the teacher may exert! It is his to instil the first lessons of Divine truth into minds and hearts not yet warped through the influence of vicious habits, not yet blinded through unbelief; whose consciences may be easily impressed, to whom the simple story of the love of Jesus possesses peculiar charms. The child we know has inherited a depraved nature, opposed to spiritual things. It is as true of the child as of the man, "that the carnal mind is enmity against God: it is not subject to the law of God; neither indeed can be." But its opposition to the truth is more feeble, its enmity to God less inveterate, and the power of sin over the heart not as strong as in after years. Consequently, it may, by the help of the Holy Spirit, be led more cheerfully and readily to the obedience of the gospel.</p>
               <p>Are Sabbath-school teachers conscious of the importance of their work, of the weight of responsibility resting upon them, and the power for good which is intrusted to them? In their preparations for the Sabbath, in their intercessions with God for their pupils, in their manner of imparting instructions, and in their intercourse with them, teachers too seldom feel and act as if in expectation of their immediate conversion, of being themselves the honored instruments of leading them to the Redeemer. They rather view their instructions as preparatory. They sow the seed which is to germinate hereafter. To bring the pupils into the kingdom, is regarded as instrumentally the work of the pulpit, and to be effected at some future time.</p>
               <p>These are not mere surmises. They are,<pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC6057-00000059"/> alas! the records of our own sad recollections of past delinquency and want of faith. With shame we recall the many opportunities of doing good which have passed unimproved, and the many indications of seriousness which might have resulted favorably, had we had faith to believe that God was willing to render our feeble efforts effectual in opening the hearts of those who were committed to our charge, to receive the truth, and be saved.</p>
               <p>The foregoing observations and suggestions are made in the spirit of kindness, in the earnest hope that they may be productive of good, in awakening attention to the subject in the minds of Christians. Some may censure us for speaking thus openly. But, when we consider the importance of the early conversion of her sons to the welfare of the church, that the ranks of the ministry may be supplied with men of mature judgment and experience, and who shall consecrate the vigor of their days to Christ; and that those who are to carry onward the enterprises of the church, may be men of enlarged views, stability of character, and strong faith; when we also consider the untiring ing efforts of our enemies to allure, ensnare, and ruin the young; and when we consider the strong temptations thrown in the path of the youthful aspirants to seek gains, and worldly distinctions and pleasures, and thus harden their hearts, that they should heed not the claims of God and eternity, we are constrained to speak with plainness, with earnestness, and yet in the spirit of love.</p>
               <p>Oh! that the church would hear attentively and believingly the words of the Master, which, on the eve of His ascension, He addressed to His fallen, but penitent, and returning disciple, when he had obtained from him the thrice-repeated assurance of love—"FEED MY LAMBS."</p>
               <p>Such is the will of Him who carries the lambs in His bosom—who took the little ones in His arms and blessed them, saying, "Suffer the little children to come unto me, and forbid them not; for of such is the kingdom of heaven."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC6057-00000060"/>
               <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Mrs. Edgar's indisposition—Premonitions of death—The solemn interview—Counsels to surviving friends—Her last hours—Character of her piety.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE good people of Glendale, as we have said, were much engaged in the work of the Lord, and rejoiced in the manifestations of His power and grace.</p>
               <p>The influence upon the health and spirits of Mrs. Edgar was very favorable. It was natural that a person of her deep piety, so devoted to the interests of the Sabbath-school, who labored and prayed in faith for the conversion of the children of the church, should have been deeply interested in the revival of the work of grace in their midst. Her domestic afflictions, and late sad bereavement, seemed for a time forgotten. Her whole energies were given to the work of encouraging those who labored there, in leading the young to the Saviour. The tidings of the conversion of one and another caused her joy to abound, and the sweet smile that was wont to play upon her face returned. The change in her general appearance was such as to encourage the friends to hope for the re-establishing of her health, and the lengthening of her days; for there were many strong ties uniting her to her family, and the church of Glendale could not well spare one who was truly a mother in Israel.</p>
               <p>But the Lord orders all things wisely for His people's good, and His own glory. Notwithstanding these flattering signs of returning health, it was evident that Mrs. Edgar was ripening apace for heaven. She viewed death as near at hand. Her friends were bidden not to deceive themselves, as her end was drawing nigh. She regarded herself as a weary traveller, who, having been long tossed by tempests, was earnestly longing for the haven of rest.</p>
               <p>To long for entire freedom from the trammels of earth and corruption, is not inconsistent with due submission to the will of God. It affects not the soldier's courage and fidelity,<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC6057-00000061"/> that amid the roar of cannon, the clash of arms, carnage and death, he should be weary of such sounds and sights, and should sigh for the safety and repose of home. Nor is it an evidence of impatience, that the child of God, surrounded by enemies, should earnestly pant for deliverance and eternal rest in the city of God; where there are no foes to dismay, no trials and sorrows to endure, for God shall wipe away all tears from every eye. "There remaineth a rest for the people of God."</p>
               <p>Mrs. Edgar had tasted of the bitter cup of affliction. She had learned the instability of earthly things, and her thoughts were turned to the permanent pleasures and the happy society of heaven. There was nothing extravagant in her views. Hers was the experience of one well versed in the Scriptures, whose communion with God and sanctified afflictions had imparted peculiar lustre to her piety, and rendered every circumstance connected with her illness and death deeply interesting.</p>
               <p>Dear reader, has it ever been your privilege to witness the death of a Christian? Have you listened to the words of one whose face shone brightly with the radiance of divine glory? If not, you have much yet to learn of the worth of the grace of God. Enter with us the chamber of a dying saint, and learn how to die. As you behold the sufferer emaciated and enfeebled by disease, yet calm and cheerful, patiently awaiting the coming of her Lord; you may also learn the preciousness of the hope of the gospel, and be led to seek clear evidence of acceptance with God, through the Redeemer.</p>
               <p>When the pleasant excitement connected with the revival at Glendale had in a measure subsided, and the summer was passed, early in autumn Mrs. Edgar's health became very feeble, and she was confined to her chamber. Her sufferings were comparatively light at the beginning of her sickness. Her mind was clear, and her soul was kept in perfect peace. Every stroke was sanctified to her, and while her feeble body was tending to decay, the soul was daily renewed. <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"The head that God breaks with affliction's stroke,</l>
                        <l>Oft, like the flower when stricken by the storm,</l>
                        <pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC6057-00000062"/>
                        <l>Rises from earth, more steadfastly to turn</l>
                        <l>Itself to heaven, whither as a guide,</l>
                        <l>Kindly though stern, Affliction still is leading,</l>
                        <l>Even to the home of endless joy and peace."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>On our return to college, after the fall vacation, we received a message from Claremont that our aged friend was not long for this life, and was anxious to see us before her departure. In company with an intimate friend of the family, we hastened to the dear spot, which we visited two years before, almost to the day, for the first time. But how changed the scene! Then we met as strangers, and health and gladness and peace were there. Now it was the house of sorrow; death had entered, and taken away a beloved son, and the devoted wife and mother was laid low by afflictions, and all the tender domestic ties were soon to be broken, and the surviving friends were to be clad again in the weeds of mourning.</p>
               <p>What a commentary upon earthly instability and man's immortality. <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"The air is full of farewells to the dying,</l>
                        <l>And mournings for the dead."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The interview of that evening is among the most precious reminiscences of our life. As we approached the couch of the dying saint, she extended her feeble hand, and, summoning all her remaining strength, she said: "I am very glad to see you, as I wish to leave with you my dying testimony, which may be useful to you hereafter. We have often spoken of the preciousness of the hope of the gospel. I want to tell you now what I know, what I feel at this trying hour. <emph>My end is nigh; my hope of heaven is firm and bright. Death is robbed of his sting, and has no terror for me. I have been a child of affliction, but the haven of eternal rest is in sight. I long to depart and be with Christ, which is far better.</emph>"</p>
               <p>It was a solemn season to all present. We all knelt before the mercy-seat, and there poured out our prayers and tears.</p>
               <p>With our prayers we also offered the sacrifice of praise and thanksgiving for the rich consolations enjoyed by her, who then stood on the verge of the tomb. Oh! the triumphs of faith. How glorious the hope of the Christian!</p>
               <pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC6057-00000063"/>
               <p>Her aged partner, naturally a man of great resolution and self-control, was bowed down under the heavy trial. To give up the chief object of his earthly affection—the wife of his bosom, was a sore affliction. It agitated his whole frame. <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"Man may bear with sufferings; his heart</l>
                        <l>Is a strong thing, and godlike in the grasp</l>
                        <l>Of pain that wrings mortality; but tear</l>
                        <l>One cord affection clings to—part one tie</l>
                        <l>That binds him unto woman's delicate love,</l>
                        <l>And his great spirit yieldeth like a reed."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Observing him greatly moved, she addressed him: "Dear husband, we have toiled together for many a weary day. God has greatly blessed us. We have lived most happily. We must part, but only for a little while. I hope soon to welcome you to heaven, where we shall spend a long eternity together."</p>
               <p>Her maternal affections were strongly drawn out towards her surviving daughter, who was overwhelmed with grief at the prospect of parting. How tender the ties that bind an affectionate mother to a loving daughter! How keen the anguish of separation! Turning ing to her daughter, she said: "This stroke falls heavily upon you, my child; may God support you. Be of good cheer. Live near the cross. Hold on a <emph>little while,</emph> and the victory will be yours too."</p>
               <p>The doctrine of heavenly recognition, which we fully believe to be clearly taught in the word of truth, has been always full of comfort to the pious heart. It has its difficulties, we know. It might perplex many a sincere soul to give a clear and satisfactory statement of the ground of his belief; yet it is so inwrought into his faith, that he could not for a moment question it. It seems as an intuitive truth. The bereaved Christian dwells upon it with delight. It casts a ray of light over the darkness of death and the tomb. Our friends are absent, but not lost. We shall meet them, and be united to them by holier, stronger ties, than those of life! To Mrs. Edgar this truth was most precious; she would often refer to it after the death of her son with great satisfaction. But it was now a theme that engrossed much of her thoughts. Referring to the members of the family who had already departed<pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC6057-00000064"/> parted, she said: "I expect to be hailed, on reaching the gates of the celestial city, by my dear children, now in glory. Oh! to meet there an undivided household." For a moment she remained silent, and evidently absorbed in thought; then, with a sweet smile upon her face, said: "One thing I know, I shall behold Him who is the chief among ten thousand. Then shall I be satisfied, when I awake in thine image."</p>
               <p>That night was to her one of wakefulness and pain. It was evident that the clay tabernacle was soon to be dissolved, and her spirit be released, and as an uncaged bird, would flee away and be at rest. Approaching her couch, in the morning, she whispered, as her strength was almost spent: "I expected to have commenced this day in paradise. But I murmur not; His will be done."</p>
               <p>Mrs. Edgar was a great admirer of the beautiful in nature, and communed much with God in his works. Having revived a little during the early part of the morning, she asked to be raised, and the curtain drawn aside, that she might gaze once more upon the beauties of nature, which had so often delighted her. As though the anticipations of heaven imparted greater loveliness to earth, she exclaimed: "How beautiful! Oh! how beautiful! My Father made them all. If earth, the abode of sin, be so lovely, how transcendently glorious must heaven be, free from all the blighting effects of sin!"</p>
               <p>The Bible had been our aged friend's constant companion. She had her favorite portions, which she often perused. And what Bible-Christian has not? He is to be pitied who has no favorite spots in the green fields and beside the quiet waters of the Scriptures, where he may repose in peace. Oh! what could we do in times of trouble, had we no pavilion to which to resort and hide ourselves, till the tempest be overpast.</p>
               <p>One of her favorite portions was our Saviour's intercessory prayer. She requested that it should be read that morning at family worship. She afterwards remarked: "That has been a precious legacy to me all my pilgrimage; but it is far more so now at its close. What a glorious intercessor is Jesus! Who<pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC6057-00000065"/> need fear to commit their all to his gracious care! What an Almighty Saviour we have! What could I do now without him?"</p>
               <p>The last interview with a dying friend is always affecting. Every expression is treasured up as a sacred legacy. It is like a messenger sent from the eternal world, to counsel and encourage surviving friends. We witness, at such times, the earnestness of a soul in sympathy with the world of spirits. There is no trifling—no artifice; all is truthful and convincing. Such was our last interview with Mrs. Edgar. In the most solemn manner, she gave us her parting blessing and dying counsel. "You have been called to preach the gospel; you have a great work to perform. May God make you faithful and successful! Preach Christ crucified; let him be your constant theme. You can never speak too highly of His love. Be not afraid of exhausting the subject. Could you see things as I now see them, and know what I now know of the worth of Christ, you could never lose sight of Him in your sermons."These were solemn words indeed. They are too deeply engraven on the heart ever to be forgotten.</p>
               <p>It is an inestimable privilege to be permitted to witness the triumphs of faith in a dying hour. Thence Christianity draws some of its strongest defences. We have seen a timid female, when brought to the verge of the grave, by the power of what we call faith, enabled to look death, the king of terrors, in the face undismayed; awaiting the summons to leave all that was dear to her on earth, in a cheerful frame of spirit. There was nothing in the unknown future to alarm her. There are those who would call this power, by which the dying saint triumphs over death and hell, delusion, and the volume which sets before us the high honors and felicities of eternity, a falsehood!</p>
               <p>But they too often betray doubts and misgivings respecting their own faith. They are forced—though reluctantly—to confess that their so-called philosophy fails utterly to account for the heroism of the dying Christian. And where, we would ask, are the proofs of the genuineness of their religion? How do its chief advocates, its champions, take leave of the<pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC6057-00000066"/> world? We have heard that some of these heroes, at the close of life, entertained their friends with pleasantries, and conversed jocosely of death, and hereafter. Even their own associates being judges, their conversation was not such as became the hour of dissolution—such as should have fallen from the lips of those passing into the great unknown—their jests and laughter were forced, and betrayed a fearful disquietude of the inner man—and that their end was not worthy of the heroism they assumed in their lifetime.</p>
               <p>What a libel on their creed; or, rather, what a truthful commentary on its hollowness, were the scenes of the closing hours of some of the chief advocates of infidelity!</p>
               <p>How did Hume, and Voltaire, and Paine, and others of that class, meet their fate? Was it in a manner creditable to their faith? We challenge the friends of this heartless system to show us, in the annals of the world, one <emph>single</emph> instance of an infidel resting calmly upon the hopes and anticipations which <emph>his</emph> religion furnished, and dying submissively, tranquilly, joyfully. The example cannot be found. It cannot, in the nature of things, ever exist. While, on the other hand, we ask them to produce an example of a Christian, possessing the hope of the gospel, the assurance of God's favor, whose death was a libel on his faith.</p>
               <p>During our last interview with the dying saint, the children of the church, for whose spiritual welfare she had always manifested great concern, were not forgotten. She intrusted us with her dying counsels to them. The Sabbath after her departure was a memorable day in the history of that school. It was a sad and solemn season. Even strong men, unused to weep, were bathed in tears. God, who had often answered the prayers of that devoted Christian, encouraged His people to believe that the tokens of love bequeathed to the children of the church, on that occasion, were not in vain. Impressions were then made on many a heart, which were never lost.</p>
               <p>The day of her burial was a sorrowful day to many. But no one seemed to feel the loss more than the good pastor of Glendale. He had lost a friend whose kindness and sympathy had been a source of great comfort to<pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC6057-00000067"/> him, whose prayers and counsels had often cheered him in the arduous labors of his calling. A large concourse of people assembled to follow to their last resting-place the mortal remains of one who had lived usefully in the church and the community. It was a tribute of love and esteem paid to true worth and eminent piety. Oh! the sweet savor of grace. It is like the fragrance of most precious ointment, reviving the drooping spirit—speaking to the heart most convincingly, of the excellence of religion to sustain the believer in all his tribulations! "He being dead, yet speaketh," is true of every Christian who lived worthy of his high and holy vocation.</p>
               <p>It is evident from the preceding pages, that the piety of that beloved Christian was not only genuine, but eminent. To ascertain, as far as we are able, the cause of the depth and power of her religion might be interesting and instructive. To say that she had been a child of affliction will not suffice to account for this. True, trials are designed to promote sanctification. Saints often come out of the furnace as gold tried, and fitted for the Master's use. The experience of many Christians is that of the Psalmist: "Before I was afflicted I went astray; but now I have kept thy word." Mrs. Edgar's frequent and severe trials contributed much to her growth in grace; but we must look beyond this for the secret of her deep piety. It is also true that her intimate communion with God, and delight in the Word of Life, imparted lustre to her Christianity. They who breathe the pure atmosphere of devotion must enjoy spiritual health and vigor. They who meditate in the law of the Lord, shall be as trees planted by water streams, which bring forth fruit in their seasons; whose leaves also shall not wither. While all this is true, yet we are persuaded that there were circumstances connected with the early training of Mrs. Edgar which gave peculiar tone and character to her religious life.</p>
               <p>Take an individual whose early training was defective, whose conversion was effected, instrumentally, under preaching though in the main sound, yet lacking fulness and clearness. The piety of such a one, though genuine, will<pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC6057-00000068"/> necessarily be feeble, and subject to inconsistencies and decays; while the piety of one who is rooted and grounded in the truth as it is in Christ, who was brought into the kingdom under the ministry of one mighty in the Scriptures, and skilled in the art of giving to each his portion in due season, will be scriptural, vigorous, stable, symmetrical, and his "path as the shining light, that shineth more and more unto the perfect day."</p>
               <p>It cannot be justly inferred from these observations, that we attach too much importance to the means employed, the truths proclaimed; and do not sufficiently exalt the agency of the Holy Spirit in the sinner's conversion. God forbid that we should utter a syllable that would cast dishonor on the Spirit's operations in the work of regeneration and sanctification. It is the Spirit's prerogative to enlighten and sanctify; but this is accomplished by and through the truth. "Sanctify them by thy truth: thy word is truth." A person's attainments in Divine life, and the character of his piety, will correspond with the extent and accuracy of his knowledge ledge of the gospel. A man's knowledge may exceed his piety; but his piety cannot exceed his knowledge of the truth. Else we must adopt the absurd doctrine of Rome: "Ignorance is the mother of devotion!"</p>
               <p>We think that by applying the foregoing observations to Mrs. Edgar's case, we may discover the secret of her eminent piety.</p>
               <p>Her early religious training was under the ministry of one of those devoted men, who as pioneers carried the gospel, the seed of divine truth, over the Alleghanies, and planted it with faith and prayer in what was then the far West. They were men who had been themselves trained in times that tried men's souls. Driven from the North of Ireland, on account of their steadfast adherence to the principles of the gospel and Protestantism, they came to this country, and proved a rich blessing to the church. Men of strong minds, warm hearts, of earnest life, they left their impress on everything they touched. They imparted their own high character to the churches planted by them, and which has not been lost amid the changes and convulsions to<pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC6057-00000069"/> which they had been subject. It was under the ministry of one of these godly men Mrs. Edgar received her religious training. She was brought into the kingdom during the extraordinary season of revival enjoyed by the church throughout Western Pennsylvania, Virginia, Kentucky, and some of the Southern States, which has been so truthfully and graphically described by the late venerable Dr. Alexander, of Princeton.</p>
               <p>Trained under such ministry, and born into the kingdom at such a time, it was not strange that Mrs. Edgar's views of the doctrines of grace, and the covenant relations between Christ and his people were clear, comprehensive, and discriminative, that her faith was vigorous and unwavering. In the darkest hour, she calmly and securely trusted in God. In her experience there was no presumption, no boasting, no self-trusting; but an humble child-like faith in the Redeemer as her reconciled God and Father, an unshaken confidence in the immutability of God's gracious purposes, and the indissoluble union between the believer and Christ. Such piety has its foundation dation, not in feeling and good frames of mind, as it is sometimes termed, which are ever fluctuating, but in deep settled principles. Such faith magnifies the grace of Christ, glorifies the Holy Spirit, and imparts true worth to the Christian character and example.</p>
               <p>Such, dear reader, is a brief sketch of the life and character of a beloved Christian, which is set before us for imitation. Her submission to the will of God under her trials; her constant desire to glorify Him in life and death; her efforts to promote the cause of Christ in the salvation of souls, and her composure in the immediate prospect of dissolution—all was a rich legacy bequeathed to her friends and to the church. Oh! that we may have grace to tread in the footsteps of the saints who served their day and generation by the will of God—whose death was peaceful and triumphant.</p>
               <p>Dear reader, our prayer is that you may <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"So live, that, when thy summons comes to join</l>
                        <l>The innumerable caravan, that moves</l>
                        <l>To that mysterious realm where each shall take</l>
                        <l>His chamber in the silent hall of death,</l>
                        <pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC6057-00000070"/>
                        <l>Thou go not like the quarry slave, at night,</l>
                        <l>Scourged to his dungeon, but, sustained and soothed</l>
                        <l>By an unfaltering trust, approach thy grave</l>
                        <l>Like one who wraps the drapery of his couch</l>
                        <l>About him, and lies down to pleasant dreams."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>God's hidden ones—The church's indebtedness to these—Encouragement to labor for Christ—The revelation of the day of judgment.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT is a sore trial to the earnest pastor to lose from his charge the devout and the faithful. Such may be overlooked by the formalist and the faithless; but they are highly prized by the man of God, who labors to win souls to Christ, and believes that the effectual prayer of the righteous availeth much.</p>
               <p>Amid the discouragements incident to the work of the ministry, how cheering to know that the prayer of faith is daily ascending to God in his behalf! The trials of the servant of Christ are peculiar. He often concludes his efforts are all in vain. How little success, comparatively, attends his labors! How small the number of the truly pious! Regarding<pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC6057-00000071"/> himself as standing alone, he is almost ready to abandon his post, and give all up for lost.</p>
               <p>We are giving articulation to the fearful struggles which most, if not all, the servants of Christ endure in the course of their ministry. Much of this is the work of the great adversary, whose interest it is to fill the hearts of the standard-bearers with gloomy apprehensions, that thus they may be shorn of their strength, and driven from their steadfastness.</p>
               <p>The prophet Elijah was thus assailed, and for a time yielded to the power of the tempter. When his life was threatened by his enemies, he fled like a coward, and hid himself in a cave. In his impatience and distrust of God, he desired to die. In his place of concealment, the Lord sharply rebuked him, saying: "What doest thou here, Elijah?" To justify himself, he answered and said: "I have been very jealous for the Lord God of Hosts, because the children of Israel have forsaken thy covenant, torn down thine altars, and slain thy prophets with the sword, and I, even I only, am left, and they seek my life to take it away." But he was bidden to return to his post, and labor faithfully, and not judge Israel so severely. "For I have reserved to myself," saith God, "seven thousand men who have not bowed the knee to the image of Baal."</p>
               <p>God has never left himself without witnesses. In every age He has had His hidden ones. How sad the condition of the church in the days of the prophet Malachi! The priests, the prophets, and the people, had corrupted their way before the Lord. Infidelity and profanity were rife. Yet even then there were found those "who feared the Lord, and spake often one to another. The Lord hearkened and heard, and a book of remembrance was written before Him, for them that feared the Lord, and that thought upon His name." These things were recorded for our admonition and encouragement. We should not judge the Lord too much by appearances, nor be too hasty in our conclusions; but be willing to labor faithfully and perseveringly, and leave results wholly with the Lord.</p>
               <p>Though God has had a people in the world, who were dear to Him, even as the apple of His eye, yet they have been often wholly unknown<pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC6057-00000072"/> known. The world has not known them, even as it knew not their Master.</p>
               <p>The reasons why they are unknown, are very obvious. The world's standard of merit and that of the word of truth, are essentially different. That which stamps worth upon character in the sight of God, is overlooked by the world, and regarded even as valueless. Though the world may profess great esteem for Christian virtues, yet these are for the most part despised, as exemplified in the life of the pious. In its persecutions of the church, and opposition to the cause of true religion, the world has always disavowed any hostility to true piety. False names were applied to all Christian virtues, ere the saints were opposed and maltreated. The meekness of the gospel was called "pusillanimity," "conscientiousness," "Pharisaism;" steadfast adherence to truth and righteousness, "obstinacy;" devotion to the cause of the Redeemer, and solicitude for the salvation of immortal souls, "fanaticism and hypocrisy;" strict attention to equity in all the details of life, "being righteous over-much." While, on the other hand, the chief excellences of the world are worthless in the sight of God. We are forbidden to adopt its maxims, to imbibe its spirit, or to follow its ways. Even its wisdom must be contemned. "If any man seemeth to be wise in this world, let him become a fool, that he may be wise." It is not strange, then, that God's hidden ones are unknown to the world. The springs of their joy, the sources of their grief, the elements of their victory over sin and self, and their peculiar beauty and glory, which is the beauty of holiness—these are things the world cannot understand or appreciate. Hence, the more eminent in piety a person is, the nearer he approaches to the standard of perfection, the greater the opposition of the world to him.</p>
               <p>Who ever endured such contradiction of sinners against Himself as the Son of God, who was the perfection of all goodness! His whole life was a continued sacrifice of Himself for the good of others; yet He was reviled and persecuted. The worst crimes were laid to his charge. His enemies, whom He came to seek and to save from eternal woe, thirsted for His blood; nor did they rest until they<pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC6057-00000073"/> accomplished His death. They knew Him not; they beheld not His glory, though it was "the glory of the only begotten of the Father, full of grace and truth."</p>
               <p>If the world knew not the Master, it is not strange that it knows not His disciples. For the servant is not above his Lord. "If they have persecuted me," said He, "they will also persecute you." "If the world hate you, ye know that it hated me, before it hated you."</p>
               <p>Should not this reconcile the Christian to all his trials, and suppress his impatience? What though his motives be impugned, his character injured, and he be neglected and despised, let him remember that man's judgment, being subject to prejudice and caprice, is often false; but God's judgment is according to truth. This neglect and opposition are needful to try his faith. Were all things fair and prosperous—were he fully known, there would not be the same necessity for implicit trust in the sure word of promise, which teaches that our feeblest efforts may be effectual for good—that actions lightly esteemed by the world, are pleasing in the sight of God. To labor and pray earnestly for the world's good, when opposed and contemned, needs the exercise of strong faith, patience, and deep-rooted charity—that charity which "beareth all things, is not easily provoked, thinketh no evil, seeketh not her own."</p>
               <p>It is easy to work under the stimulus of public excitement, while receiving the applause of multitudes. But to toil for years unnoticed and apparently to little purpose—to weep, and pray, and labor for the salvation of those around us, when no eye beholds, no ear hears but that of Him "who seeth in secret," there needs be a full persuasion of the power and willingness of God to make our feebleness redound to His glory. <emph>Patient continuance in well-doing, is the fruit of the precious grace of faith.</emph>
               </p>
               <p>Although the great majority of God's hidden ones are unknown, yet who can calculate the world's indebtedness to them for its richest blessings? Silently and unostentatiously they go on their way, doing good, like their Master; giving bread to the hungry; clothing the naked; visiting the widow and the fatherless<pb n="146-147" xml:id="VAC6057-00000074"/> in their afflictions; carrying the Word of Life to the abodes of ignorance, poverty, and wretchedness; scattering tracts in the path of the careless and the wanderer, those blessed leaves from the tree of life, which are for the healing of the nations. These deeds of benevolence are not heralded before the world. Indeed, the world cannot fully appreciate them, nor understand the motives of these benefactors. But these deeds are not the less praise-worthy because done in secret. Such persons seek not the empty praises of the world. If God approves, they ask—they desire no more.</p>
               <p>The church also owes much to those who are least known among its members. How much do those who occupy the high places of trust and influence in the church, depend upon their more retired brethren for support and success? No tongue can tell. As Aaron and Hur sustained Moses's hands, while Israel was in conflict with their enemies, so these, by the prayer of faith, cheer the hearts and feed the waning strength of the leaders—the standard-bearers of the hosts of God.</p>
               <p>The mutual dependence of the members of the household of faith upon each other, is most beautifully set forth by the apostle, under the metaphor of the human system: "God hath set the members every one of them in the body, as it hath pleased him. They are many members, but one body. The eye cannot say to the hand, I have no need of thee. Nor, again, the head to the feet, I have no need of you. Nay, much more; those members of the body which seem to be feeble, are necessary. God hath tempered the body together, having given more abundant honor to that which lacketh. That there should be no schism in the body; but that the members have the same care one for another."</p>
               <p>To whom, under God, is the church indebted, for some of its brightest ornaments, its noblest champions for the truth? To whom does it owe many of its most devoted ministers, its most useful missionaries, dead and living, who carried the messages of peace and salvation to the benighted and perishing; planted the standard of the cross on the banks of the Ganges, the plains of India, in the heart of populous China, and on the shores<pb n="148-149" xml:id="VAC6057-00000075"/> of Africa? Is it not to the devoted mothers in Israel, whose faith rendered their prayers and tears prevalent with God? To these, the church owes a debt of gratitude it never can discharge. They devoted their sons in early life to the service of the Redeemer, and that dedication was followed by suitable efforts. They sought for their sons, not riches or worldly distinctions, but the highest honors within the reach of man, that they might become the heralds of the King of kings. They strive not to make them skilled in the wisdom of this world, which cometh to naught, but they labor to make them wise to win souls. In the quiet retreats of humble life, they trained their offspring in the ways of piety; they instilled into their tender minds the simple lessons of divine truth, and made them to know the name and grace of Jesus, the children's friend. They strove to exemplify, by their walk and conversation, the precious instructions they imparted. Trained with such sedulous care, taught in such a <emph>thorough, practical, and orthodox school,</emph> it is not strange that they should be mighty in the Scriptures, apt to teach, strong in faith, and able to "endure hardness, as good soldiers of Jesus Christ."</p>
               <p>Mrs. Edgar consecrated her son, when a child, to the service of God in the ministry. Her prayer was heard and her offering was accepted. Although her son was not permitted to preach the gospel, yet it was in his heart thus to serve Christ, and the will was accepted for the deed.</p>
               <p>What a rich blessing such persons as Mrs. Edgar must be to a church and community! They are God's hidden ones, who sigh and cry for the desolations of Zion, and who, by their spirit of kindness and deeds of charity, win the heart, and conquer the opposition of many to the gospel. The devoted pastor knows the worth of those women who labor with him in the gospel. He should not think, or treat lightly, any class in his charge, as each has its peculiar influence and sphere of labor. The servant of Christ, who is indifferent to the approval and co-operation of the rich and influential portion of his flock, curtails his usefulness, and is acting in a manner wholly unworthy of the spirit of the gospel. Nevertheless<pb n="150-151" xml:id="VAC6057-00000076"/> theless, the humble, retiring, praying, active spirits in his charge are most highly prized by him, for they wield a mighty influence. They have power not only with men, but also with God, in whose hands are the hearts of the children of men. It augurs sadly for a minister to have no praying mothers in his charge, to intercede for him at the throne of grace, to whose abode, though it may be humble, and not attractive to the gay and thoughtless, he often resorts for Christian converse and prayer, and where, in the hour of gloom and despondency, he is often refreshed and encouraged, and his faith in God strengthened. How rich in grace are many of the humble poor!</p>
               <p>In the vicinity of M. College, there lived an aged colored woman of eminent piety. Many of the pious students were in the habit of resorting to her humble dwelling for Christian conversation and prayer. Though illiterate, yet her views of divine things were clear, her Christian experience was Scriptural, and her conversation was truly edifying. No one could listen to her without admiring the grace of God, which makes the simple wise.</p>
               <p>As we were leaving, on one occasion, her humble dwelling, we met one of the professors of the college entering. Having exchanged the usual salutations, we passed on. Meeting him a few days after, he alluded to the above circumstance, saying, "I often visit that aged pilgrim, who seems to live by prayer. She is so rich in Christian experience, so full of the love of God, so strong in faith, that I have often laid aside my books, and have paid her a visit. I have been blessed, and greatly refreshed in spirit, and been led to admire the grace of God, who conceals the wonders of His love and redemption from the wise and prudent, and reveals them unto babes." "Even so, Father, for so it seemeth good in thy sight."</p>
               <p>How wonderful will be the revelations of the day, when the secrets of men shall be judged! Christ will then acknowledge and honor, before the assembled universe, those who were faithful in their lot. Each will be rewarded, not according to the number of talents received, but according to the improvement made of those intrusted to him, whether few or many. The disclosures of that solemn day will be<pb n="152-153" xml:id="VAC6057-00000077"/> surprising, <emph>even to the redeemed.</emph> "Then shall the King say to them on his right hand, Come, ye blessed of my Father, inherit the kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world." Then will follow an enumeration of their righteous deeds, which will be so amazing as to excite the inquiry, from each and all, when and how had they performed such deeds so pleasing to the King? Then will be announced the great principle, according to which all actions must be weighed—the ruling motive must be their reference to Christ and His cause—"Inasmuch as ye have done it to one of the least of these my brethren, ye did it unto me." What marvellous grace to poor earth-born creatures, many of whom were contemned and persecuted! What surprising glory to receive from the august Judge, the God of all, the plaudit, "Well done, thou good and faithful servant! Thou hast been faithful over a few things, I will make thee ruler over many things; enter thou into the joy of thy Lord."</p>
               <p>Then will be exhibited to the saints the great panorama of time, arranged according to the infinite wisdom of Him "who knoweth the end from the beginning;" "who doeth all things according to the counsel of His will." Every event therein set forth will appear important or otherwise, according to its connection and bearing upon the work of human redemption. The glorious central point in that great plan will be Mount Calvary, which was the scene of the greatest achievement of time. The Cross will be the radiating point towards which all the transactions of time will converge, from which they will borrow all their weight and worth. The relation of each of that vast throng to the Cross of Christ, will be clearly seen. How far each lived and acted under its attractive power—the nature and extent of the influence each exerted to win the lost to safety and peace through Him who died for man—how that influence continued increasing and widening for ages after its author had entered into rest. In the light of the cross, transcendent worth and glory will be attached to the sighs, the tears, the prayers and efforts of the faith of the feeblest of the saints. From that point of observation, there will be seen, in a light infinitely clearer than it<pb n="154-155" xml:id="VAC6057-00000078"/> could be understood in time, how God caused the foolish things of the world to confound the wise; and the weak things of the world to confound the things which were mighty; and the base things, and things which were not, to bring to naught things that were. Then it will appear that many who were wholly unknown in the world, whose pious acts were not heralded abroad, had accomplished more for Christ and His cause, and consequently were more exalted in glory, and would have brighter gems in their crowns of rejoicing than many who received the applause of men, and the record of whose deeds filled ponderous volumes. Whose works, however, because composed of wood, hay, and stubble, were burned; but they themselves, because their hope was resting upon the true foundation, were saved, yet so as by fire. For "many that are first shall be last, and the last shall be first."</p>
               <p>Nor will such public exhibition tend to lessen, but rather to enhance the bliss of the redeemed. For pride, and envy, and jealousy shall never enter the new Jerusalem, the city of God. "There shall in no wise enter into it anything that defileth."</p>
               <p>The love and friendship of the holy brotherhood will be perfect, even as God is perfect!</p>
               <p>Ye humble disciples of Christ! behold your encouragement to labor, and your great reward! What though your influence be limited, and your strength be small? All that is required of you is fidelity in your lot. "Be thou faithful unto death," is the command of the Lord of life and glory, "and I will give thee a crown of life." Your sighs, and tears, and prayers, are all treasured up! not one of them shall be lost. Your feeble efforts, of which perhaps you are now ashamed, and which escape the notice of men, even <emph>these,</emph> the King regards approvingly. What amazing grace that sinners, who are children of wrath by nature, should be made partakers of the favor of God! But how much more amazing the condescension of heaven, to permit men to be co-workers with Christ, in doing good! That He should notice approvingly their deeds of faith and charity! Did He not commend the act of her who anointed<pb n="156-157" xml:id="VAC6057-00000079"/> Him, before his burial, with precious ointment? And regarded the widow's mite of greater worth than the gold and silver of the rich and the great? Surely, He will not despise any effort to promote his cause, and show forth His praise. "Whosoever shall give to drink unto one of these little ones, a cup of cold water only, in the name of a disciple, verily I say unto you, he shall in no wise lose his reward." Cease not, then, ye followers of the Lamb, cease not your exertions to do good, and labor for the salvation of those whose spiritual interests lie near your heart. Per-adventure God will bless those efforts, and save the lost. But whether or not, your labor shall not be in vain. Your reward is sure—your record is on high—you shall receive the crown of life!</p>
               <p>"Whosoever shall give a cup of cold water in my name,"—what wondrous words! How they rebuke the slothful, and sweep away all excuses, which are wont to be pleaded, when urged to labor for Christ! "We cannot do much:" "Our influence is limited:" "There are so many whose means are greater, whose influence is more extensive, who have opportunities and leisure to engage in deeds of benevolence." What if all this be so, it does not affect the case, nor excuse you. Have you used the means you have, to advance the glory of the Redeemer? You are not accountable for not doing that which you had not the time, nor the opportunity, nor the ability of doing. Your responsibility is commensurate with your ability. Have you prayed as fervently as you ought for the salvation of your friends and relatives? You may have a husband who is not a Christian,—can you bear the thought that he should perish! Suppose he should be torn away suddenly from your side, could you then feel that you had wrestled earnestly and unceasingly for his salvation? You may have a son or a daughter gay and thoughtless—suppose he was laid on a dying bed, could you lift your hands to God, and say, I am clear from his blood! I warned and entreated him, and prayed for him! Look around you, and see if there is ought for you to do in the community, and in the church. There is a<pb n="158-159" xml:id="VAC6057-00000080"/> luxury in doing good. Oh! how pure—how sweet! Would that you knew its worth: then you would need no arguments to rouse you from your sloth, and gird you for life's duties. Do you not covet the honor of living usefully, to occupy a place in the church so important that you will be missed when death shall remove you hence? So to relieve the orphan and cheer the widow in her afflictions, that as the widows stood by Peter weeping, and showing the garments which Dorcas made while she was with them, so the fragrance of your piety may be most precious to the children of sorrow, who were made partakers of your benefactions, and through you, were made to know the grace of God.</p>
               <p>Dear reader, God has His hidden ones, who are most precious in His sight. They may be poor, obscure, wholly unknown, yet they are the salt of the earth, the light of the world. And though their deeds may never be recorded in the annals of the world, and they may receive no honors, no reward from men, yet "They shall be mine, saith the Lord of hosts, in that day when I make up my jewels; and I will spare them, as a man spareth his own son that serveth him." Are you of the number? Then all is well.</p>
               <p>Wealth, and influence, and social position, are deemed of great moment in the world. Religion does not contemn them. Nay, it enjoins upon us the use of all proper means to secure them. Christians should not feign to despise them, for they are important talents to be used in doing good; but they are not the chief good—they are lighter than vanity, when compared with the favor of God. "A good name is rather to be chosen than great riches, and loving favor than silver and gold." Of what avail would the kingdoms of this world, with all their glory, be in the day of trial, and in a dying hour, if God be our enemy! What if esteemed by the world, while not recognized by Christ! The highest distinction attainable on earth is to be numbered among "God's hidden ones." And to be meet to receive a crown of righteousness, which the righteous Judge will give to all those who love His appearing, will be the highest bliss and glory of eternity!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="160-161" xml:id="VAC6057-00000081"/>
               <head>CHAPTER IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The desolate home—Miss Edgar's indisposition—Mental depression—Its removal, and her resignation to the will of God—Death and funeral—Mr. Edgar's last days.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>HOW true the proverb, "troubles come not alone!" By some strange affinity, they cluster together, or follow each other, in quick succession. Why it should be so, is not for us now to know. All will be revealed hereafter, when the events of time shall be seen in their true bearing, and in their infinite harmony.</p>
               <p>Though we know not the reason of this, yet that it is so, is too evident to be denied. Families that had long enjoyed peace and outward prosperity, have been unexpectedly visited by sad reverses, and sore trials. The home that once rung with the merry songs and sweet voices of young and loving hearts, full of peace, and light, and promise, has been left desolate. Those glad voices were hushed in death; those loving hearts have ceased to beat. Those tender flowers which had enjoyed the culture and watchful care of maternal affection, were suddenly touched by the nipping frosts of disease, and one by one they drooped and perished. Such occurrences are not rare, and must be familiar to our readers.</p>
               <p>An instance of this we now readily recall, though twenty years have elapsed since it occurred. It was a happy household. The parents had been blessed with a large family of children—nine in number. There was not one feeble or diseased among them; but all rejoiced in the bloom of youth and health. How the long winter evenings, we spent among the happy circle, were enlivened by their sweet music, a talent which they inherited from their mother. She, with all the enthusiasm of a lover of the art, led the song, and all their voices would join in the chorus of praise. But, alas! such happiness was too pure to continue long uninterrupted. Most unexpectedly, disease entered that abode, and in the short space of one month, six of that number were<pb n="162-163" xml:id="VAC6057-00000082"/> snatched away. What a breach! What a void! Though that mother knew the worth of grace in affliction, yet <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"The heart of Rachel, for her children crying,</l>
                        <l>Would not be comforted."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Such sad changes are common to all classes and characters—the rich and the poor, the evil and the good. "All things come alike to all: there is one event to the righteous and the wicked; to him that sacrificeth, and to him that sacrificeth not. There is one event unto all."</p>
               <p>The history of the family of Claremont is an illustration of the expression "Troubles come not singly." At the time of our first visit to that sweet retreat, we regarded them as greatly favored, and truly happy in each other. And those who murmur at the allotments of Heaven, and judge of things in the light of sense, and not of faith, would have looked upon them with an envious eye, and coveting heart. But ere two years had elapsed, there remained but one of that once happy circle, desolate and sorrowful. Though it be painful to pass through such scenes of grief and bereavement, yet it is profitable withal. "It is better to go to the house of mourning than to the house of feasting, for that is the end of all men; and the living will lay it to his heart." The spirit of our holy religion teaches us to weep with those that weep, as well as to rejoice with those that do rejoice.</p>
               <p>The evening of the day of Mrs. Edgar's funeral was spent most profitably in the house of mourning. We saw more clearly than ever that it was right—nay more, most merciful—that man also knoweth not his time:" for a knowledge of our future days of darkness would unfit us for present duty, and overwhelm us with sorrow before the time; while a view of the sunshine of our life would unduly elate our spirits, and render us impatient to abide God's time. The prayer of the Christian, indited by faith, will always be: "If there be appointed for us a cup of suffering and sorrow, let us receive and drink the cup our Father gives us, with filial resignation. And if it be His good pleasure to bid the sun of prosperity shine upon our tabernacle, and<pb n="164-165" xml:id="VAC6057-00000083"/> cause us to repose in peace under His shadow, may we have grace to be humble and thankful to Him, who, with these earthly blessings, gives Himself as our chief portion."</p>
               <p>During the evening to which we have referred, Mr. Edgar sat sad and silent, for his heart was too full for utterance. He conveyed an expression of his grief only by the pressure of the hand, and the trickling tear, by which the workings of the soul are revealed, when too strong to be uttered by words. <emph>Twice,</emph> nay <emph>thrice,</emph> God had smitten that aged man. And now the light of his eyes being extinguished, he sat in his house, not sullen, but dumb. "He opened not his mouth, for God had done it." When an individual has met with some fearful accident, he is stunned by the sudden shock, and is seized by mental as well as physical paralysis. He wonders what has happened—what means the tumult and confusion around him. Thus it was with Mr. Edgar. He was utterly at a loss to understand the dealings of God with him. Another stroke! Wherefore sent! What shall the end be! When our friends are unable to see the hand of God, in their trials, and cannot bow submissively under the rod; instead of censuring, we should rather sympathize with them in their afflictions, and earnestly pray that light may shine upon their path, and that their mourning be turned into singing.</p>
               <p>Miss Edgar was also in the sitting-room when we entered, with a few of her intimate friends, which had called to condole with her in her bereavement. As she spoke to us, we caught a glance of her eye. It startled us, for there was something about her face that was ominous. It was very much flushed; there was an unnatural lustre and wildness of the eye, which contrasted strangely with the languor of her delicate frame. She conversed but little during the evening. There was evidently great mental abstraction. The heart was far—far away in communion with the absent. Excusing herself on account of indisposition, she retired at an early hour. As she took leave of us, giving her aged father the token of affection, he was greatly agitated, as though some prophetic vision of coming sorrow had cast its shadows on his soul. Not<pb n="166-167" xml:id="VAC6057-00000084"/> a word was spoken for some time. After a while, he resumed his wonted composure. We endeavored to shake off the strange impressions on our mind. We would ask ourselves, what does it mean? It may be only the reaction of the anxiety and fatigue resulting from long watchings during her mother's illness, and the grief an affectionate daughter must suffer by the loss of one so endeared to her. The repose of a few days will remove all this, and she will be herself again. Or can it be that there is in store for the aged man another severe trial? In addition to those already snatched from his fond embrace, is this one—so well qualified by nature and by grace to solace him in his declining days—to be taken from him? Has death marked her as his prey—and must he gain another conquest ere he retires from this abode? Such were the sad musings of that evening, forced upon us by what we saw.</p>
               <p>Strange to say, two weeks had scarcely elapsed ere it was announced that Miss Edgar was seriously ill. The symptoms greatly alarmed her friends. Alas! the sad surmisings ings of that evening at Claremont were too true. The family physician could not conceal his anxiety; though the more sanguine of her friends regarded these fears as unfounded, and the alarm premature. Not so, however, thought Miss Edgar. She spoke from the first of her disease as sure to terminate fatally. She often referred to the strong ties that bound her to her affectionate father. For his sake she was willing to remain; though for herself she had no desire to live, but longed to depart and be at rest. From the day her sainted mother's remains were committed to the tomb, she had evidently lost all attachments to earth, and sighed after a glorious reunion with those she loved so well, so purely.</p>
               <p>Her delicate frame, already enfeebled by the toils and vigils through which she had passed, sank rapidly under the attack. One feature of her disease was very distressing. She suffered fearfully from mental depression. At times she was quite delirious. Indeed, we are persuaded there was far more truth in the vague, yet strong impressions of that memorable evening at Claremont, than we were<pb n="168-169" xml:id="VAC6057-00000085"/> willing to believe. There was awakened in that soul a strong sympathy with the departed, wholly inexplicable.</p>
               <p>We are no spiritualist. We regard the "spiritualism" now in vogue as a fearful delusion, which God in judgment permits those to embrace, who have long contemned His word, and treated with derision the revelation of the Holy One. As they would have none of His counsels, and would not believe Moses and the prophets, God has delivered them over to strong delusion to believe a lie. Let these sceptics, these restless spirits seek unto them that have familiar spirits, that peep and mutter; let them seek for the living to the dead, and glory in their revelations, if they will: <emph>we</emph> will go to the law and the testimony. We are satisfied to render devout thanks to God who has given to us, "the more sure word of prophecy, whereunto we do well to take heed as unto a light that shineth in a dark place, until the day dawn, and the day star arise in our hearts." While we have no sympathy with these errors, yet we cannot resist the belief that the soul is at times permitted to hold communion in thought with the spirits of the glorified, as real as the fellowship of friend with friend on earth.</p>
               <p>During Miss Edgar's illness there were some lucid moments; but even these were overcast with gloomy doubts and fears, which was a source of anguish to herself and friends. She could not say with exulting joy, "I know that my Redeemer liveth."</p>
               <p>One evening, as her pastor sat by her couch, having engaged in fervent prayer in her behalf, she, weeping bitterly, said to him: "Oh! that I could know that I am indeed a child of God! But I cannot believe that I love the Saviour, else I would have served Him more faithfully, and could not requite His love with such ingratitude." He replied, in his peculiarly tender manner: "Well, we grant you have no love to the Saviour, and no hope in Him for salvation. Answer me one question: would you be willing to forsake Him, and return again to the world?" Her countenance brightened, as though a ray of hope had been kindled in her trembling soul; raising herself a little on her couch, she said, with peculiar emphasis:<pb n="170-171" xml:id="VAC6057-00000086"/> "Forsake Christ? <emph>No, never!</emph> No, NEVER!" What a triumph over unbelief! What a happy moment was that to the friends present. She found peace in that hour. Many prayers had been offered in her behalf by those who were deeply moved by her mental distress. In great mercy, God heard those prayers, and removed her depressions.</p>
               <p>Her reply to her pastor deserves particular notice. Though had she not given such clear evidence of her faith in the Redeemer, none who knew her could have questioned the genuineness of her piety. Her exemplary walk, her efforts in the Sabbath-school, and exertions in behalf of the benevolent operations of the church, were her witnesses. But is not her answer, which is recorded above, the strongest proof of the existence of grace in the soul? Is it not the essence of true saving faith? Is it not the same in substance with the reply of the disciples to the Son of God, when he asked that touching question, "Will ye also go away?" "Lord, to whom shall we go? thou hast the words of eternal life."</p>
               <p>While we are persuaded that Miss Edgar's distress was owing in a great measure to her disease, which caused a derangement of the nervous system—but that was not the sole, nor even the chief cause of her mental anxiety, as her remarks to her pastor clearly reveal—we think it meet to dwell on this for a moment, because it often, greatly and unnecessarily, perplexes many a timid but sincere Christian. Why did Miss Edgar doubt her own piety? Because she could not discover much love in her heart to Christ, and had done so little for Him. Though this, as we shall presently show, is a sure evidence of grace, yet the remains of legality and self-righteousness, which are so deeply rooted in us, turn to the worst purposes what would otherwise be a source of strong consolation. We look into our dead hearts for some native goodness, which might be a ground of boasting. We are slow to believe that in us there is no good thing, save what the Holy Spirit has wrought there. What, then, is the course to be pursued in reference to those who may be laboring under this error? What means did the good pastor of Glendale use in the case before<pb n="172-173" xml:id="VAC6057-00000087"/> us? Having discovered the secret of the evil, and having entire confidence in the genuineness of her piety, he endeavored to draw her mind away from herself, and direct it to Christ. The moment the eye of faith rested upon Him, His glory filled her soul with light. A view of his infinite love instantly enkindled her love, and revealed the strength of her attachment. "Forsake Christ! my hope, my trust, my refuge, the high tower of my defence, the rock of my salvation, my glory, my all! <emph>No, never! no, never!</emph> 'Whom have I in heaven but thee? and there is none upon earth that I desire beside thee.'"</p>
               <p>Child of God! are you filled with fear and trembling, because all within is gloomy? Because, in your judgment there is no grace, no goodness there! Look away from yourself; cease your search after aught that is trustworthy or praiseworthy in your dead heart; look to Christ and see if the view of His grace will not warm your cold heart, and excite your love and give you peace.</p>
               <p>Ere you are aware of it, your darkness will be turned to light, and you will be able to exclaim without fear: "My beloved is the chiefest among ten thousand. He is altogether lovely. My beloved is mine, and I am His." And you will sing with joy— <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"Thou, O Christ, art all I want;</l>
                        <l>All in all in thee I find!</l>
                        <l>Raise the fallen, cheer the faint,</l>
                        <l>Heal the sick, and lead the blind:</l>
                        <l>Just and holy is thy name,</l>
                        <l>I am all unrighteousness,</l>
                        <l>Vile and full of sin I am,</l>
                        <l>Thou art full of truth and grace."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The fact that you are not satisfied with your love to the Redeemer, that you are ashamed of your devotion to His cause, and bitterly lament your great distance from Him, is an evidence of the life of grace in the soul. Are you troubled because you do not love one who is an entire stranger, and has no particular claims to your esteem? But it pains you to do so little to requite the kindness of a benefactor, who rescued you from peril, who succored you when in trouble, who delivered you from some pressing want, and to whom you were united by the strong ties of affection. The unbelieving are not much concerned<pb n="174-175" xml:id="VAC6057-00000088"/> because they do not love Christ. They regard their attendance upon the means of grace and their benefactions to His cause as sufficient returns for all they have received, and as possessing some merit in the sight of God. But talk of zeal, and good works, and sacrifices to the believer who has seen the Redeemer's glory, who has experienced His pardoning grace, tasted His love, enjoyed the sweet fellowship of the saints, and has the hope of eternal life, through His blood, and he would blush at the thought that anything he has ever done should be once named as a ground of boasting. He would bitterly bewail his want of love to one so worthy. <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"Dear Lord! and shall we ever live</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">At this poor dying rate,</l>
                        <l>Our love so faint, so cold to thee,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">And thine to us so great?"</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>This is the real sentiment of every sincere believer.</p>
               <p>Instead of the darkness which had so long enveloped her mind, Miss Edgar now had light and joy; she could lie submissively under the rod, and lean upon the everlasting arm of Jesus, and there find repose. A few days after this blessed change, her spirit, mellowed by afflictions, and sanctified by the grace of God, was released from its prison of clay and corruption, and, we feel assured, admitted into the companionship of the spirits of the just made perfect.</p>
               <p>The community was filled with gloom when the sad tidings of her departure were known. There was a large circle of friends who were attached to her by many tender ties, and who were deeply affected by her death. When the tidings reached us, the scenes of the last evening we spent by the dying couch of her sainted mother were brought vividly before our minds. Were not the words she addressed to her weeping daughter that evening prophetic? "We must part. Live near the cross. <emph>Hold on a little while longer,</emph> and the victory will soon be yours." In a little while the daughter reached the goal, exchanged earth for heaven, the armor and the conflict for the crown of life—the rest of immortality.<pb n="176-177" xml:id="VAC6057-00000089"/>
                  <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"Thou wert too good to dwell with clay;</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">For sin too pure, for earth too bright;</l>
                        <l>And Death, who bore thee hence away,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">Placed on her brow a gem of light."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The burial services were very solemn and instructive, as the pastor of Glendale was skilled in the art of healing the broken in heart, and comforting those who mourn. In a brief, but touching manner, he referred to the change death had wrought, in so short a time, in that household. He alluded to the repeated evidences given in the experience of those who had departed, of the preciousness of Jesus to the dying, to the happy reunion of the departed in the New Jerusalem. He poured into the heart of the disconsolate husband and father the oil of consolation, bidding him trust in God, though all earthly comforts fail.</p>
               <p>He urged upon all the necessity of seeking a refuge, ere the evil day should come; to listen to the solemn admonition addressed to them from the tomb and eternity. "Be ye also ready; for in such an hour as ye think not the Son of man cometh."</p>
               <p>The closing scene of that hour was one of intense interest. The mourners gathered around the coffin to gaze for the last time upon that lovely face, then cold in death. There is in that ceremony something painfully impressive. It is the tearing asunder of the last tie binding the living to what is mortal of the dead. The mourners retired one by one; but the aged father lingered. The thoughts of other days, when all was peace and gladness, and of his present desolate condition, came over him like the shadow of death. The contrast was too much for him. Gazing intently upon the form of his beloved daughter, he fell athward the coffin. He gave a shriek, which even now rings in our ears, while we pen these lines. Then in broken accents he said: "<emph>Oh! this is too much! I cannot give her up! This is too</emph>"—and the words died upon his lips.</p>
               <p>There was an awful stillness in that chamber. The stoutest heart was moved with pity. His grief, which seemed to have been pent up in his heart, was now dissolved in copious tears; he grew calm. Then he said in trembling tones: "Pardon me, pardon me, my<pb n="178-179" xml:id="VAC6057-00000090"/> friends! The thoughts of my loneliness came over me: it was too much for me to bear!" No one could have found in his heart to censure him. Though naturally a man of great fortitude, the repeated waves of sorrow which had rolled over his soul, had unnerved him; they had broken and crushed his strong spirit.</p>
               <p>Though he had learned to regard the over-ruling hand of God in these trying providences, yet he was constrained to say: "The purposes of God are too deep for me to fathom: His ways I cannot comprehend." We must not speak harshly of those who in affliction cannot always acquiesce in the dispensations of God. If one of Jacob's tried and abounding faith, charged God foolishly, in the hour of temptation, it is not strange that men of weaker faith should, in the day of adversity, when the objects of their affections were torn from them, speak unadvisedly with their lips.</p>
               <p>Ah! it was desolate indeed, that late delightful house of Claremont! Its lights had gone out one by one. The aged pilgrim stood alone in the midst of his sorrow. Grief weighed heavily upon him, and so affected his spirits that he never regained his former cheerfulness. He survived his family only a few years. He was evidently a stranger upon earth, looking with earnest longing for another and a better country. Earth was to him void of attractions. While he exhibited a spirit of quiet submission to the will of God, yet it was very evident that to depart and be present with the Lord, was regarded by him as far better than to remain here. He would often speak of the dear friends in heaven, and of his readiness for the hour of release, when he should join them in glory. The evening-tide of his life was cheered by a well assured hope of heaven, and he would turn from the perplexities of life and sin to that blessed region where there is no night; but one high eternal noon.</p>
               <p>As a shock fully ripe for the harvest, after a short illness, he was gathered into the garner. Death was welcomed as the voice of Jesus to call him home. His mortal remains were laid by the side of his family. How peacefully they slumber there! In life they were united, and in death they were not long separated.<pb n="180-181" xml:id="VAC6057-00000091"/> How hallowed is that spot! How precious the dust there deposited! Should you ever visit the church of Glendale, a venerable relic of olden times, forget not to enter the old graveyard. On the left, as you enter, in a beautiful spot beneath the spreading branches of an ancient drooping willow—a fitting place of rest for such loveliness and piety—you may see inscribed upon a marble tablet the names of our departed friends, whose quiet and happy home we have described, whose joys and sorrows, whose trials and triumphs of faith we have briefly set forth in these pages. They are absent but not lost! The golden ties that bound together the members of that godly household, were not subject to the changes of time. In life and death they were an undivided household. Over them might be written the inscription— <q>
                     <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>"A household tomb!</l>
                        <l>United once they were,</l>
                        <l>All in fond love and hope,</l>
                        <l>One household still.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>Together they shall sleep,</l>
                        <l>Together they shall rise,</l>
                        <l>And sing their morning song,</l>
                        <l>One household still."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Dear reader, our task is almost done. It is a voluntary offering, an humble tribute paid to departed worth. It has been our aim to instruct as well as to please. We have endeavored to tell our story faithfully, the story of grace in connection with the household of Claremont. We have occasionally wandered from our path to pluck some flowers from other fields. But these, we trust, were not unacceptable. The reminiscences of the church of Glendale, with its relics of olden times, the scenes of divine power and glory witnessed there, and the blessed fruits of the revivals of religion in their midst, were doubtless interesting even to strangers. But to us they all seemed to be essential parts of our story. Has it never happened to you, when some one has accidentally hummed some notes of music, fragments of a half forgotten song of your early days, connected with which there are many hallowed associations, that you instantly caught the strain? One note suggested another, and another still, until you had all the parts of the sweet old melody, though as yet in scattered fragments. By a little effort, however, you<pb n="182-183" xml:id="VAC6057-00000092"/> gathered and arranged these, and soon could sing in sweet strains the old familiar song.</p>
               <p>Thus it was with our story; one incident would suggest another—all seemed to fall in our way most naturally, and were necessary to throw light upon it.</p>
               <p>Our picture is not all darkness. It has its lights and shades, which are essential to all true pictures. It may appear overcast with dark shades, when viewed by the eye of sense in any, even the brightest earthly light. But viewed by the eye of faith, in the light of revelation, it appears pleasing and attractive. Even its darkest shades add to its perfection, and are illumined by rays of grace and glory.</p>
               <p>The members of that dear household were enabled to justify the ways of God towards them, here in this vale of sin, when they could see only through a glass darkly. Their views of the infinite wisdom and goodness of God in their trials must be much clearer now, when they know even as also they are known. Doubtless their communings together are most sweet, as they recline in some heavenly bower under the spreading branches of the tree of life, recounting the perils, trials, and wonderful supports and deliverances they experienced in their earthly pilgrimage. What they knew not here, they now know perfectly. They see clearly that every cup they had to drink, every trial that befell them, every stroke of the rod that was laid upon them, that all these were needful to their sanctification and ultimate salvation. The tearing asunder of the tenderest earthly ties was necessary in order to unite them together by the holier, stronger ties of eternity. And as they trace the wonders of redemption displayed in their salvation, commencing in grace here, to its consummation in glory, they strike anew their golden harps, and sing unto Him that loved us and washed us in His own blood, and made us kings and priests unto God the Father, unto Him be glory and dominion for ever and ever. Amen!</p>
               <p>Dear reader, have you hope in Christ; is He formed in you the hope of glory? Can you look to heaven as your final rest? Have you felt its attractions? Is it a theme on which<pb n="184-185" xml:id="VAC6057-00000093"/> you delight to dwell? Then you are prepared to accompany us a little longer, while we gather a few more gleanings that yet remain, before we close.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The family of Christ—Of whom composed—How divided—All the members are tending homeward—The general reunion—A glorious undivided household.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>"OH! to meet an undivided household in glory," said Mrs. Edgar, on leaving the sanctuary the Sabbath they all sat for the first time at the communion table. That prayer has been answered. A whole household in heaven! A whole family removed by death—not a member remaining, to perpetuate its name and memory! The places that knew them, shall know them no more. How solemn the thought! What a fit emblem of the instability of earthly things, and of our condition! Such is the destiny of all families, when their end is accomplished.</p>
               <p>There is but one household, which, as to its essential relations, is to continue forever—unaffected by the changes of time—its members<pb n="186-187" xml:id="VAC6057-00000094"/> are bound to each other, and to their glorious Head, by indissoluble ties. "For neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things present, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, shall be able to separate us from the love of God, which is in Christ Jesus our Lord." We need not tell our readers that we refer to the household of faith—the family of Christ.</p>
               <p>How often is the church represented by the Holy Spirit, under the metaphor of a family! It is one that appeals to our holiest affections; it affects all hearts, combining as it does, in itself, so many excellencies, so many touching associations.</p>
               <p>The church—God's great family—is now divided; but all its members are tending homeward; it is scattered now over the face of the earth; but there is to be, ere long, a general reunion, a grand family gathering, when all will be presented to God, a glorious, undivided household in Christ.</p>
               <p>The household of faith, how numerous! Though bigotry will have it that the number is but small, including only a fraction of mankind kind, while the great majority are delivered over to the power of the Prince of Darkness. Cursed bigotry—how cold its charity! How niggardly its spirit! Its benevolence is the chill of death! Compared with this, how enlarged the benevolence of Christianity—the teachings of the oracles of truth! The apostle John, while an exile at Patmos, being favored with a vision of the end, saw the whole family gathered together on Mount Zion. After seeing the thousands of Israel, which were numbered and sealed: "I beheld," says he, "and lo, a great multitude, which no man could number, of all nations, and kindreds, and people, and tongues, stood before the throne, and before the Lamb, clothed in white robes, and palms in their hands."</p>
               <p>This household consists of two general divisions, with Christ as their glorious head, "Of whom the whole family in heaven and earth is named." The branch in heaven is composed of "an innumerable company of angels, and of the spirits of just men made perfect." The saints of all ages, from righteous Abel to the believer who has just been released from the<pb n="188-189" xml:id="VAC6057-00000095"/> trammels of sin and mortality, and clothed in the robes of light and glory. The character, condition, and employments of the members of the branch on earth, are clearly set forth in the word of truth. Explicit, however, as are its declarations, what disputes and quarrels have arisen, touching this subject. Strange as it may appear, some have arrogantly assumed the name, and claimed for themselves an exclusive right to all the immunities and honors of the family. They have uttered their anathemas against any who would dare to question the validity of their claims. They have even persecuted to the death many of the legitimate children. They have contemned the laws and regulations of the family, setting up their own, in opposition to these. They have clearly shown by their spirit, and temper, and actions, that they neither knew nor loved the Master.</p>
               <p>The word of God teaches that the members of the household on earth are not of any particular class, or of one nation, or of one period; but composed of those of all classes, of all nations, and of all times, who call upon the Lord in sincerity and truth. The legitimate children—who have a right to the privileges of the family—are those "who are born, not of blood, nor of the will of the flesh, nor of the will of man, but of God."</p>
               <p>Whether or not we are the children of God, is a question which involves interests of infinite moment: "For if children, then heirs, heirs of God, and joint-heirs with Christ!" Yet, alas! how reluctant are we to sift the matter thoroughly, and honestly do the work of self-inspection, though we are bidden to give all diligence to make our calling and election sure. Notwithstanding all this, many live in carnal security, vainly flattering themselves that, to assume the name, and adopt some of the more common phrases and observances of the family, may entitle them to its privileges. Having a name to live, while dead, they continue in their delusion through life. Clinging to their false hope until too late, they shall meet with the stern reply from the Master, "I never knew you: depart from me, ye workers of iniquity!"</p>
               <p>Touching a question of such moment, one that involves our safety and present peace of<pb n="190-191" xml:id="VAC6057-00000096"/> mind, we might safely conclude that the teachings of eternal truth would be most explicit. It gives no uncertain sound—it makes the matter so plain, that he who runs may read it. And what are the marks of sonship, set forth in the Scriptures? Let us notice a few of the leading evidences.</p>
               <p>The first and most important of these, is <emph>love to God.</emph> "We have received the spirit of adoption, whereby we cry Abba, Father." These are the breathings of love. This holy principle may not be equally strong in all, nor of equal strength, at all times, in the same individual. They who behold the unveiled glory of God, the Redeemer, love Him, constantly, perfectly. Their love burns with a perpetual flame. Christ in God is the chief object of their contemplation—the key-note of their songs—the chief attraction of all the glories and beauties of Heaven. But all who are born of God <emph>do</emph> love Him, though they have only the imperfect eye of faith to look upon His face. How are we to know whether or not we love Christ? They who love Him, bitterly lament their distance from Him, and the feebleness of their affections towards Him. They delight to hear His voice, and desire to enjoy His constant presence. They love to read the records of His grace, to hold sweet converse with Him at the mercy-seat, and meet in the assemblies of His saints. In every time of trouble, they draw nigh to Him with freedom, and in the darkest hour, their implicit confidence is in His promises to succor and deliver them that trust in His name. How clearly and beautifully was all this exemplified in the character and experience of Mrs. Edgar! In the midst of trouble, she calmly and cheerfully leaned upon the arm of Omnipotent love, knowing that greater was He that was for her, than they who were against her. Let those who have these desires, however faint, take courage, for if sincere, He who will not break the bruised reed, nor quench the smoking flax, will not despise them, but will regard them with favor. Cherish these feeble desires, and use all proper means to bring them to perfection.</p>
               <p>
                  <emph>Fraternal love,</emph> is another important test of sonship. "We know that we have passed<pb n="192-193" xml:id="VAC6057-00000097"/> from death unto life, because we love the brethren." "If we love one another, God dwelleth in us, and His love is perfected in us." This affection must extend to all the saints. To be attached to our own party, is no sure sign of grace. Though it is natural to be bound more closely to those whose views of truth harmonize with our own; yet our fraternal love must spring from a different source than party feeling. We must love the saints, chiefly, because they are the children of God. "He that loveth Him that begat, loveth him also that is begotten of Him." Moved by this principle, they "bear one another's burdens, and so fulfil the law of Christ." With what emphasis did the blessed Jesus utter the command, "<emph>Love one another.</emph>" "By this shall all men know that ye are my disciples, if ye have love one to another." The beloved apostle John, who caught most of the spirit of the Master, reiterates and enforces the injunction by the most cogent reasons, and in the most persuasive terms, placing the obligation on the highest possible ground, even that of redeeming grace: "Beloved, if God so loved us, we ought also to love one another." It is impossible to read his epistles, without being touched and deeply moved by their attractive power.</p>
               <p>
                  <emph>The children of God are interested in the welfare of the household.</emph> How near our hearts lie the interests of our families! We share in their weal and woe—in their joys and sorrows.</p>
               <p>Christians cannot be indifferent to the welfare of the church. When Zion is in adversity; when her enemies triumph, and general declension prevails, they mourn, because the heritage of the Lord is desolate. When the church is prosperous; when wanderers are reclaimed, enemies reconciled, Christ exalted, and the name of God glorified, their tears are dried, and the voice of triumph and praise is raised. The imagery by which the saint's attachment to the church is set forth, shows the strength and activity of this principle. Multitudes have evinced the sincerity of their love and devotion, by cheerfully sacrificing ease, prosperity, and even life itself, to promote the<pb n="194-195" xml:id="VAC6057-00000098"/> honor of Christ, and the prosperity of the church.</p>
               <p>These are the chief links in the chain of evidences of our Divine sonship. If these be wanting, all others are worthless. <emph>These are essential.</emph> Love to God is the spring whence all the others flow. We love the saints, because they are born of God. We love the church, because it is <emph>God's</emph> church—because it is the channel through which salvation is to be conveyed to the perishing—the instrument by which the world is to be regenerated, and become like the heaven to which we aspire.</p>
               <p>The household of faith, as said before, is divided into two great parts, the one in heaven, and the other on earth, whose members are in a state of pupilage, until the time appointed of the Father. Would to God the church had never known any other division. But the family on earth has been divided and subdivided, and thus it has been shorn of its strength; its progress impeded; its glory obscured; its exalted Head dishonored; and the Holy Spirit grieved. The causes of these divisions are endless. They all may be traced, however, to one source, the imperfect attainment of the church in grace. Her members have too often forgotten the simple rule—"<emph>In essentials, unity; in non-essentials, liberty; in all things, charity.</emph>"</p>
               <p>It ill comports with our present theme to dwell upon the mournful scenes which have been witnessed in the church. It has often been the arena of strife, leading to schisms, separating very friends. Her enemies have exulted over her, torn by divisions, and have deridingly exclaimed: "Behold, how these Christians love one another." But let us turn to a view of the subject more in harmony with our present purpose—the <emph>oneness</emph> of the household of Christ. Amid all that tends to disunion, there is a general unity on all vital questions. The same spirit of truth dwells in them all. There is a sense in which believers of all ages form one vast and compact temple, of which the Holy Spirit is the living soul, cementing, animating, and pervading all. He operates in them as the Spirit of Truth, that they may consult His dictates as their living oracles. He is engaged to sanctify<pb n="196-197" xml:id="VAC6057-00000099"/> them, to heal all the breaches sin has made, and to bring them into closer fellowship, until the intercessory prayer of Christ shall be fully answered in them—"That they all may be one, as thou, Father, art in me, and I in thee. I in them, and thou in me, that they may be made perfect in one: that the world may know that thou hast sent me, and hast loved them, as thou hast loved me."</p>
               <p>
                  <emph>The people of God are tending homeward.</emph> The church above is daily receiving new accessions. The hour of release to the pious, though solemn, will be the fulness of the day of redemption. There is a fearful conflict between nature and grace. Nature dreads dissolution; but grace longs to be free. The distempers of the body sadly interfere with the activities of the soul. Does it attempt to soar aloft, and commune with the Holy One? How its wings are clipped, its visions dimmed, and its enjoyments cloyed, by its relation to clay and corruption! But death dissolves this relation. The body returns to dust; but the spirit returns to God who gave it.</p>
               <p>It humbles our pride to think what these bodies are to be, the moment our spirits leave them. They are fit only for the grave. They say to corruption, "Thou art our father;" and to the worm, "Thou art our sister and brother." But are our bodies to remain forever under the power of death? Is the soul to enjoy its happiness alone? Can its fruition be complete without the body? Though the soul be in the enjoyment of pleasures peculiar to its own nature, yet it cannot be consummately happy while the body remains under the dominion of death.</p>
               <p>"If a man die, shall he live again?" is an inquiry which has been pressed in vain by generation after generation passing to the tomb, who had not the Word of Truth. For no system of religion of man's devising has been able to give a satisfactory response. The doctrine of the resurrection is so sublime, transcends so far the power of man, that even the wisest in this world's lore, scouted it as the climax of absurdity; and called him who preached Jesus and the resurrection in the chief seat of science and philosophy, "a babbler, a setter forth of strange gods."<pb n="198-199" xml:id="VAC6057-00000100"/> Christianity alone solves the perplexing problem. It was its high mission to bring to light, life and immortality. It places in our hand a lamp, which dispels the gloom of death. It casts a halo of glory around the tomb. It whispers in the ear of the mourner—standing by the open grave of a beloved one—"Be of good cheer, thy friend shall live again." "This mortal shall put on immortality."</p>
               <p>
                  <emph>There is to be a general reunion.</emph> Family reunions on earth, how sweet! Its members, after a long separation, all meet. How cordial the greetings! How delightful to recount the toils and trials of the past! All cares, all troubles, are dismissed—forgotten. Such family meetings are, however, often saddened by by the absence of some loved one. The thought of separation embitters the bliss of the hour. The last sound that falls upon the ear, is the sad "farewell." How infinitely superior will be the reunion of the saints! Nothing will occur to interrupt the enjoyment, or mar the felicity of that blessed meeting. All family differences will be adjusted. There will not be found among that happy throng, one feeble or diseased. No heart burdened with corroding cares, or overwhelmed with grief; no heart-burnings to destroy the peace and harmony of the saints. No member will be absent. No thought of separation to mar the pleasures of their intercourse. And the sad farewell will never be heard there, for their meeting shall be eternal. "They shall go out no more forever."</p>
               <p>But it is asked, when shall be this blessed reunion of the saints? We answer, when God's purposes of mercy, in reference to this world of sin and death, shall have been accomplished—when the last heir of salvation shall have attained to full maturity. It will be at the time of the restitution of all things—at the resurrection of the just—when the scattered dust of the members of Christ's great household shall be collected, remodelled, and reanimated by their glorified spirits.</p>
               <p>Speculation has been busy in her conjectures relative to the resurrection of the dead, attempting to lift the veil, and bring to light things which God has concealed from men and angels. Faith is satisfied with the revealed truth, "The dead shall be raised, and the world<pb n="200-201" xml:id="VAC6057-00000101"/> be judged in righteousness, by the man Christ Jesus." The time, and all the circumstances of the awful day of reckoning, it meekly leaves with Him who is wise in counsel, and mighty in working.</p>
               <p>Though the glorious doctrine of the resurrection be clearly revealed in the Old Testament, it remained for the Son of God to clothe this truth with its own attributes, and to show its relation to the other cardinal truths of revelation. It is so inwoven with all the vital doctrines of the gospel, that to deny it, would be to destroy the integrity of Christianity. "For if the dead rise not, then is not Christ raised: and if Christ be not raised, your faith is vain, and ye are yet in your sins."</p>
               <p>What a lamentable scene does the earth present to holy and benevolent beings! A charnel-house—an aceldama, filled with the trophies of death, erected in the forms of tombs and sepulchres! "Jesus wept," when His compassionate eye surveyed the gloomy scene. He resolved to dethrone death; He assumed our mortal nature; He experienced all the pangs of death; He was led as a captive to the dark domains of the grave. But He was the death of Death, and having conquered him in his own region, He burst the bars of his prison, and walked forth to life and immortality, in the greatness of his might. By lying in the grave, he stripped it of its terrors, he perfumed it with the fragrance of His love, and made it the sacred depository of the sleeping dust of all His people, until the time appointed for the redemption of their body. Jesus will then stand at the gates of death, and repeat the glorious truth, "I am the resurrection and the life." His voice shall peal and echo through the gloomy region of death, causing his throne to tremble to its centre. "Then, in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye, at the last trump: for the trumpet shall sound, and the dead shall be raised incorruptible, and we shall be changed." From the ruins of every believer's grave, shall be raised a living structure to the praise of Omnipotence.</p>
               <p>Then shall the church be presented by Christ without spot, or wrinkle, or any such thing, a glorious undivided household, to the<pb n="202-203" xml:id="VAC6057-00000102"/> Father, saying, "Behold, I and the children which thou hast given me!"</p>
               <p>Thus far we have been guided in our inquiries by the light of revelation. And are they not sufficiently explicit to satisfy our faith? Whether the last trump shall wake the dead, and change the living <emph>to-night,</emph> or a thousand years hence, is not for us to know. It is ours to have our lamps trimmed, and be habitually ready, and looking for the Bridegroom's coming, and be meet to enter and sit at the marriage-supper of the Lamb.</p>
               <p>In the preceding pages, we have described the family of God—the church, in its various stages. Its divisions, its tribulations, its imperfections, its progress towards entire freedom from all that mars its beauty, and the final reunion of all its members before the throne of God. In our meditations, we have adhered closely to the word of truth. But shall we attempt to portray the glory and felicity of the redeemed above—the church of the first-born?</p>
               <p>Ere we can describe the transcendent glory of heaven, we must have an angel's tongue; ere we can sing its songs of triumph, and chant its hymns of praise, we must have an angel's golden harp; and ere we can conceive the happiness of the saints in light, we must have an angel's heart. Ay! and even then all these must remain things unutterable!</p>
               <p>Speculation has also been busy in her inquiries as to the place of meeting. Where is the palace of the Great King, and where the city, in which the ransomed of the Lord shall forever dwell? In the Apocalypse, we have descriptions of the final abode of the glorified. The New Jerusalem is portrayed in most gorgeous colors. Its gates are of pearls; its streets are paved with fine gold, as it were transparent glass; the river of the water of life, clear as crystal, proceeds evermore out of the throne of God, and of the Lamb. "There shall be no night there, and they need no candle, neither the light of the sun; for the Lord God giveth them light, and they shall reign forever." In the Apocalyptic representation of the city of God, "heaven and earth have been emptied of their richest imagery, and there has been gathered from all their provinces<pb n="204-205" xml:id="VAC6057-00000103"/> vinces whatsoever is beautiful and splendid." The moral glory of that city "shall make the sun and moon grow pale," and its moral beauty "will make pale and dim the beauty of the heavens, and the lustre of the earth." What a glorious abode! What an august assembly! Composed of the choicest spirits of the universe. To be permitted to hold converse with the wise and the truly renowned on earth, with the imperfections of mortality clinging to them, is deemed a great distinction. But how much greater honor, how much greater the happiness to be admitted into the society of the saints above, divested of every imperfection, with all their moral and intellectual powers in vigorous exercise! There holy friendships shall be formed, never to be interrupted! Every bosom shall glow with Divine love; every face shall beam with heavenly benignity; every heart be filled with rapture; and every tongue shall swell the anthem—"Blessing, and honor, and glory, and power, be unto Him that sitteth upon the throne, and unto the Lamb forever and ever!"</p>
               <p>Dear reader, we have probably detained you too long with our story. It has been to us a most pleasing work. May we not hope that the perusal has not been wholly without interest to you. Our theme was so captivating, that we could not resist its attractions. Have you in heaven any who were endeared to you on earth—<emph>a father—a mother—a husband—a wife—a child—a brother—a sister?</emph> Then heaven must possess to you peculiar charms, and you can understand why we have lingered so long on the blessed theme. "Where the treasure is, there the heart will be also." And is not your treasure in heaven? Is not God your Father there? Does not Christ your Saviour there unveil His glories to the saints, and stand revealed in all the fulness of the Godhead bodily? Are not your treasures there?—the treasures of your household, the treasures of your heart?—those whose souls were united to your own, by the strong ties of sympathy, in sorrow and in joy? Oh! blessed privilege, to dwell now in thought with those in whose cares, and toils, and anxieties, and griefs, we shared—whose last interview was the death-bed—whose last looks were tears!<pb n="206-207" xml:id="VAC6057-00000104"/> Oh! glorious hope, to be forever with the dear treasures of our hearts—and, above all, to be with Jesus, our elder brother! <q>
                     <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>"Sweet bonds that unite all the children of peace,</l>
                        <l>And thrice precious Jesus, whose love cannot cease;</l>
                        <l>Though oft from thy presence in sadness I roam,</l>
                        <l>I long to behold thee in glory at home.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>"I long, dearest Lord, in thy beauties to shine,</l>
                        <l>No more, as an exile, in sorrow to pine;</l>
                        <l>And in thy dear image to rise from the tomb,</l>
                        <l>With glorified millions to praise thee at home!"</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <closer>THE END.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <pb n="208 (Advertisement)" xml:id="VAC6057-00000105"/>
         <div type="advertisement">
            
            <head>PARRY AND McMILLAN</head>
            <head type="sub">PUBLISH THE FOLLOWING INTERESTING AND INSTRUCTIVE WORKS.</head>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>The Book and its Story:</head>
               <p>Being a most charming History of the Bible. Illustrated with numerous cuts. $1 00</p>
               <p>"It ought to be in every family and congregational library. Its perusal must profit every man who glances over its pages."—<title>Reform Banner.</title>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>The Six Days of Creation:</head>
               <p>A series of Affectionate Letters from a Father to his Children, developing the progressive advances of Creation during the Six Days; in which the Natural History of Animals, Plants, Minerals, Celestial Objects, &amp;c., and their uses and relations to man, are treated with particular reference to the illustration of Scriptural truth. By W. G. RHIND. With numerous illustrations. $1 00</p>
               <p>"We cordially commend this beautiful book to all readers, especially the young.—<title>New York Observer.</title>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>The Ocean.</head>
               <p>By P. H. GOSSE. With fifty-two illustrations. $1 00</p>
               <p>CONTENTS.—Introduction—The Shores of Britain—The Arctic Seas—the Atlantic Ocean—The Pacific Ocean—The Indian Ocean.</p>
               <p>"Teaches lessons which are calculated at once to instruct the understanding and improve the heart."—<title>Presbyterian.</title>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>Evenings with the Prophets:</head>
               <p>A Series of Memoirs and Meditations. By Rev. A. MORTON BROWN, LL. D. $1 00</p>
               <p>"The chapters resemble great historic paintings; each prophet stands as the centre, and around him gather the pomp and circumstance, and grandeur and desolation of ancient monarchies, the shadows of Israel's doom, and the rising splendors of Messiah's Kingdom."—<title>London Evang. Magazine.</title>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>Mornings with Jesus:</head>
               <p>A Series of Devotional Readings for the Closet and Family for every day in the year. By the late Rev. WILLIAM JAY. $1 25</p>
               <p>"There is a peculiar freshness about these pages which gives them a charm superior to almost any other of the productions of Mr. Jay."—<title>N. Y. Observer.</title>
               </p>
               <p>Sent by Mail, postage paid, on receipt of price.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>