<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6500">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Gertie's Sacrifice, or, Glimpses at Two Lives </title>
            <author >Gage, Frances Dana, (1808-1884)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC6500</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >Gertie's sacrifice, or, Glimpses at two lives</title>
                  <author >Gage, Frances Dana, (1808-1884)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >189 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >National Temperance Society</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1869">1869</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-04-13">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2005-07-13">Finished TEI conversion</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <front> 
         <div type="frontis"> 
            <pb n="Illustration (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6500-00000001"/> 
            <p>
               <figure> 
                  <head>THE SKATING POND. Page 11. GERTIE'S SACRIFICE.</head> 
               </figure>
            </p> 
         </div> 
         <titlePage xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
            <pb  n=""/> 
            <docTitle> 
               <titlePart>GERTIE'S SACRIFICE;</titlePart> 
               <titlePart type="sub">OR, GLIMPSES AT TWO LIVES.</titlePart> 
            </docTitle> 
            <byline >BY <docAuthor xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">MRS. FRANCES DANA GAGE.</docAuthor>
            </byline> 
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>NEW YORK:</pubPlace> 
               <publisher >National Temperance Society and Publication House, <address> 
                     <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">58 READE STREET.</addrLine> 
                  </address>
               </publisher>
            </docImprint> 
            <docDate>1886.</docDate> 
            <pb  n="3" xml:id="VAC6500-00000002"/> 
            <docEdition>Entered, according to Act of Congress, in the year 1871, by J. N. STEARNS, In the office of the Librarian of Congress, at Washington, D. C.</docEdition> 
            <docImprint>
               <publisher >JOHN ROSS &amp; CO., PRINTERS. 27 ROSE STREET, NEW YORK.</publisher>
            </docImprint> 
         </titlePage> 
      </front> 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Gertie's sacrifice, or, Glimpses at two lives</head> 
             
            <head>GERTIE'S SACRIFICE;</head> 
            <head type="sub">OR, GLIMPSES AT TWO LIVES.</head> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <head>I.</head> 
               <p>"THERE they are, spread out before you; and now tell me, dear, demure little Puritan as you are, in which of those gorgeous costumes your humble servant, who is to be the bright, particular star of this, the most momentous of all evenings of the nineteenth century, is to array herself?"</p> 
               <p>"The bright, particular star must choose her own light in which to twinkle and glow."</p> 
               <p>"Ah! if she only could! But you see how it is; there is that darling old uncle of mine, that anticipates every want, and more than answers every wish,-until I am almost disposed to be miserable from the want of a want,-has placed them both before me at<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC6500-00000003"/> the same moment, this <foreign xml:lang="FRA">chef-d'uvre</foreign> of the skill of Madame Demorest, the very queen of mantua-makers, and Madame Le Blond, her rival, If I had but the one, now, do you see, how happy I should be!"</p> 
               <p>"Truly, my dear Gertie, you have ray sympathy, and, if I knew how to settle this intensely important question, I should do so with the greatest pleasure. But to think of deciding the destiny of a young lady whose whole and sole trial is the choice of a dress, is a responsibility too formidable for my nerves."</p> 
               <p>"Make sport of me as you please, my sweet friend, this thing perplexes me; and do you know I sometimes fancy that I am made more unhappy by possessing too much than I should be by possessing too little, and being obliged to think and act more for myself."</p> 
               <p>"Very possibly it may be so. Striving for an object gives it value. But about these dresses. This silver-colored moire antique, with its sparkling border, is superb; while this rose-tinted satin, with its soft leaves falling like snow-wreaths about it, is magnificent. If they were both mine, I should not have a moment's trouble, for if I courtesied to his Excellency Beaumont Fletcher to-night in the rose-"</p> 
               <p>"There, you have chosen-you said rose first," exclaimed the owner of the garments, coloring to her temples. "Rose you have said, and rose it shall be." And she turned to hide the confusion that a name carelessly spoken had produced, to the relief of a casket that lay upon her toilet, which she opened and held up to her companion's admiration.</p> 
               <p>"Was there ever the like of that uncle of mine? See! diamonds-the purest and best I Now, is it not enough to turn my silly head? Aren't they nice?"</p> 
               <p>"A very tame word, I am thinking, for anything so bewitchingly brilliant; not <emph>nice,</emph> surely, Gertie, but splendid; and now thank me for helping you out of your trouble, by coming out with me into the garden. There is a glowing sunset which these stone walls and shaded chambers do not permit us to see. Your diamonds are brilliant, but I love the stars and the clear blue sky and the auutmn leaves better than them all. <q>
                     <l>"'So come into the garden, Maud.'"</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC6500-00000004"/> And the speaker trilled a strain of a sweet tune, as she returned the diamonds to their owner, whose eyes sparkled even more brightly in her exuberance of joy.</p> 
               <p>"Indeed, indeed, Nell, I can't spare one moment for any such rational purpose this night. See, it is already six; we have no time to lose. Let me kiss my thanks, and away to my hair-dresser. How shall I ever repay you for your kindness in helping me out of this great difficulty?" And the belle of the evening floated out of sight.</p> 
               <p>Melonie Thorne stood a moment looking out at the green hills skirting the horizon in the far distance, and thinking of the goodness of God, and wondering, as she thought, whether it were possible that her friend might, as she had hinted, be more truly happy, if she had a want, something to care for, to strive for, to live for.</p> 
               <p>And as she thought, her eye seemed not taking in the pine-clad hills, with the paling sunlight upon their tops, nor yet the scarlet and gold of the dying oaks and maples; nor the far-off spires, or the uprising blue mist that hung over the great city where almost a million hearts were beating <q>
                     <l>"Their funeral marches to the grave."</l>
                  </q>
               </p> 
               <p>She, was looking at the past. The long years of sorrow and poverty, the hunger and cold, the bitter pangs of contempt and scorn, and, more than all, the dark midnight hours of heart-ache, when, as a child, too weary and sad to sleep, she had lain awake to think and weep, because she could hear and feel her mother weeping by her side, and knew that her father might come-ay, listening for his footstep with quaking-and in a moment intensify all their suffering, and make all that suffering agony, by his brutality and passion.</p> 
               <p>Thus thinking, is it a wonder that tears started from her eyes unbidden, or that she should drop upon her knees even there, between those two magnificent dresses, and pour out her heart in the fulness of prayer to Him who numbers the hairs of our heads and marketh the sparrow's fall, that she might have strength to resist temptation, strength amid her altered circumstances to keep firmly and truly on in her way of self-denial, and to<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6500-00000005"/> resist the pressing influences that were closing around her; that she might remember the poor, and do good to the needy, and let no sun go down without being able to say in the gathering twilight. "I have not lived this day in vain"?</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
                
               <head>II.</head> 
               <p>MELONIE THORNE rose from her knees, her heart subdued and made more calm and joyful by the utterance of her prayer, and proceeded, unaided, to arrange her own dark folds of hair into neat braids; thinking, as she stood before the mirror, not of herself, but of the great problem of life that lay before her.</p> 
               <p>The lithe little figure that stood before her, with its rounded arms lifted up, and the small white hands so busy with those long braids, was not her or hers just at that moment. And only when the work was done, and the tea-bell summoned her to take her place with the family below, did she seem to come back into her own self, and realize the glitter and glare of her surroundings, or the part she was to act for the evening.</p> 
               <p>While these two young girls, nearly of age, and just entering the great whirlpool of<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6500-00000006"/> fashionable metropolitan life, sip their tea, let us introduce them to our readers.</p> 
               <p>Gertrude Manning was the only daughter of Henry Manning, who, sixteen years before the beginning of our story, had stood a prominent and successful barrister at the New York bar, winning bread and something more for a young wife and two children,-Harry, his eldest born, a lovely boy, and Gertrude, the subject of our sketch.</p> 
               <p>Mr. Manning was induced to take a trip to California at a time when speculation and trade were at their highest, and the ship in which he embarked was lost in a gale while rounding the Cape. Only a few souls escaped, and he was not one of them.</p> 
               <p>Simon Eliot, Mrs. Manning's brother, a bachelor, gave the widow and her children a home. While we are about it, we may as well introduce him, too, a little more specifically to our readers.</p> 
               <p>He was a bachelor, not exactly from his own choice, but because at twenty "he loved not wisely but too well." How could he help it, when he went skating in the winter days, and met that little loving beauty, Kate Vaughn, who asked him, with her red pouting lips, to fasten on her skates; who shook her glove at him and cried, "Now for a race; who'll follow?" How could he help falling in love, when, as the pleasant skating days wore on, and he had met her every evening for a month, and glided hand-in-hand with her over the glassy floor, listening to her musical laugh and cheery jest, and watching the ingenious evolutions made by her pretty feet, cased in the neatest of gaiters, as she dodged him or; led him in the game or chase?</p> 
               <p>Ah! if there is a place in all the world to fall in love, it is on the ice; and the "colder the hands the warmer the heart," becomes a truth not to be doubted.</p> 
               <p>Simon was a brave young fellow, tall and good-looking, and a noted skater. No wonder that pretty Kate Vaughn, the daughter of a tradesman, should like him; and no wonder that, when "the ice grew thin and she fell in," he should plunge after her, and, at the risk of his own life, bring her to the surface and restore her to her friends.</p> 
               <p>And no wonder that when he talked to her a few evenings after, "walking in the moonlight<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6500-00000007"/> light alone," she should have accepted his rhapsody of love, and declared herself, in her girlish simplicity, eternally and unalterably "his own Katy," in spite of all the world.</p> 
               <p>The old people were not pleased with the attention of the, young mechanic. The mother declared "Katy was only a baby, and the whole thing must be put a stop to."</p> 
               <p>But, somehow, the more father and mother tried to put a stop to it, the (as is usually the case) less they succeeded. Katy was true to Simon, and Simon was true to Katy. Her black eyes were his inspiration as he bent over his task, under the hand of his master, who had but-one desire in an apprentice,-that he should work well for him.</p> 
               <p>There was one thing Simon liked only less than Kate Vaughn, and that was his trade. The former was his angel of light and joy; the latter his angel of good, through whom he expected to win all things for her that he loved.</p> 
               <p>Three years went by, and still he loved only the sweet little girl that he saved from the deep waters of the skating-pond. His trade was learned, or at least that part of it that his "old boss" could teach; and now, in an unpretending shop, upon -- Street, with an unpretending sign over his door,-"Simon Eliot, Locksmith,"-he was earning, day by daft, the means which should enable him to take Katy into his home as his own dear little wife. He was twenty-three, and his lady-love just five years his junior, and three years of blissful anticipation had filled his whole being with the beautiful image at whose shrine he was pouring out all his youthful devotions.</p> 
               <p>"But we are not going to write out this romance, only to glance at it and its effects.</p> 
               <p>Katy had been gone two years, finishing herself, at his suggestion, in a Boston seminary, for a mechanic's wife.</p> 
               <p>Did we say Katy was pretty? To be sure we did; and men love pretty women mostly, at least John Crooker, the millionnaire, did. Moreover, he had lost his wife, and wanted some one to fill her place, to sit at the head of his table, to manage the servants, and, most of all, to take charge of the children and relieve him and them of the presence of Aunt Jerusha, who never was pleased except when<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6500-00000008"/> somebody else was remarkably displeased. Then she felt in duty bound to be amiable, and to remind them, by certain twirling of the thumbs and rolling up of the eyes and long sighs, how little they had to be troubled about; setting forth her own virtues as no one else <emph>would</emph> or could have done it for her. So, to get a pretty woman to sit at his table, a house-keeper to manage his servants, a maid to look after his children, and especially somebody to rule Aunt Jerusha out of his palatial residence, what should he do but offer himself, heart and hand, bank stock, California mines, wholesale house on Broad-and all, to Miss Katy Vaughn, who, somehow, lost sight of the skating-pond, the souse under the ice, the vows of years, and all the cherished hopes of the past, and became Mrs. John Crooker, of Fifth Avenue. The only uncommon thing about the romance is that millionnaires are uncommon; not that pretty young girls should break troth with a poor lover if a rich one offers.</p> 
               <p>Simon Eliot received a blow from which he never recovered. He did not fall or sink down, but through every fibre of his frame there was a shock of intense pain that weakened his trust in woman, and made him feel as if he were left more alone with God.</p> 
               <p>Being a Christian in the truest sense of the word, he prayed for strength to bear the trial imposed, and resolved that no life should be rendered useless by the treachery, weakness, or unworthiness of another. Pitying Katy as he had never pitied any human being before, pitying her because he knew by the yearnings of his own soul what she had lost, he turned to his other mistress, his trade, waiting in faith for the revelation that should show him, by and by, that this disappointment was for the best. Just at this time his sister, Mrs. Manning, came to him for help, and his heart and home opened to her, and she entered in and dwelt with him and he with her.</p> 
               <p>Harry and Gertie were some time in his new home which he had built with loving care for another, who had shrouded it in gloom. Mrs. Manning was a loving, indulgent mother, a member of the church, living up to all its requirements, and striving hard to keep the commandments; at least she thought so. To<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6500-00000009"/> her loving heart, "Thou shalt have no other God before me," meant except Harry and Gertie. "Thou shalt not make unto thee any graven image, nor bow down to them and serve them," was not intended as an interdiction of her love to those who were now her all.</p> 
               <p>Oh, how many such idolaters there are to-day in the world!</p> 
               <p>Mrs. Manning's life had but one central idea,-that of making her children happy; bowing down to them and worshipping them; giving two thoughts to them to one to her God, through all her sixteen years of widowhood.</p> 
               <p>Simon, whom we left but now struggling against a great disappointment at twenty-three, struggled on through the next seven years, he finding at last that he was a genius, and had not known it; nay nor he never would had he been happy with Kate Vaughn by his side. The long evenings might have been spent with her in social ease, at the church, concert, or lecture-room. His hand, with ready skill in his trade, would have secured a competence. Would not that have sufficed? Now the long hours spent alone in his little back-office must be filled up, so he thought and invented, and his hands executed what his brain arranged; and, before he knew it himself fully, he had, by an improvement in mechanism, lifted a burden from millions of hands, and care from millions of hearts.</p> 
               <p>One invention leads to another, and Simon Eliot went on blessing the nations, who in their turn blessed him, till, at the age of thirty, John Crooker, of Fifth Avenue, stood as a poor man-poor in gold, and poor in honors-in comparison with him who was cast aside seven years before because he was poor.</p> 
               <p>Still Eliot had two loves. Now his art stood first; and his lovely niece, who had filled every tillable gap of his heart for seven years, the second.</p> 
               <p>Too much engrossed with his business to look very closely into the details of either the education of his nephew or niece, or perhaps feeling that her mother was the most proper person to attend to that, he paid the bills unquestioningly, only too happy in being so unselfishly loved. He knew Gertrude loved<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6500-00000010"/> him, and that she was the most radiant, beautiful, and happy child he ever saw; that she kissed him at his coming and at his going, played and sung for him when he was weary, teased him when he was sad, robbed his pockets of all his surplus change, and made him sure, by the bills sent in, that his money was being used. If a thought of Katy Vaughn now and then obtruded itself, it was only to make him feel more sure that a wise Providence had guided his destiny. So things continued through all the sixteen years, and now at forty we introduce him to our readers.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
                
               <head>III.</head> 
               <p>GERTRUDE went from her boudoir to meet her hair-dresser. The mention of the name of Beaumont Fletcher had set the warm blood of her heart into more rapid flow, and flushed her cheeks.</p> 
               <p>"Ha! ma belle reine! "exclaimed Madame Broseau, "what is the matter? what makes the cheeks so rosy and eyes so radiant? Mademoiselle in love?"</p> 
               <p>And she patted the chin of her patron with her jewelled fingers, in a way to inspire and win confidence.</p> 
               <p>Startled and vexed that a secret she had not known herself for ten minutes should have been revealed by her telltale blushes already to her hair-dresser, she threw herself into a chair, with an air of offended dignity, while the rebellious blood, which had performed its mission, receded, and left her pale, as if about to faint.</p> 
               <pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6500-00000011"/> 
               <p>"Mon Dieu!" exclaimed Madame Broseau, "my ladie too much excite." And she gave her a fan, and vigorously rang the bell, which was promptly answered by Kathleen, her Irish maid. "Wine for mamselle!" exclaimed Broseau, theatrically.</p> 
               <p>"No, no, no!" said Gertrude, starting to her feet; "don't go for wine; you will frighten mother out of her wits if you go to her for the key. There is nothing the matter."</p> 
               <p>"Is it the drinks as is wanting? Sure, thin, there's the brandy in the pantry, standin' there this blessed day. It's niver a drop that's been touched sin' Master Harry was hurted that time."</p> 
               <p>"Just the thing!" said Madame Broseau. "A little hot water, sugar, nutmeg, and glass, and we'll bring her round at once."</p> 
               <p>"And is it sick is the mistress?" asked Kathleen, her eyes half starting from their sockets.</p> 
               <p>"No, no, Kathleen, I am not sick, only a little tired; go get the things as madame tells you."</p> 
               <p>Kathleen now returned, and the hair-dresser mixed a strong brandy sling, of which Gertie supped a few swallows and felt revived.</p> 
               <p>Kathleen noticed that madame emptied the glass; and on returning to the kitchen thus reported herself to Aunt Cynthia, who was busy with the arrangements for tea:-</p> 
               <p>"And sure for ye, Aunt Cynthe, it's two words for hersel' and one for Miss Gertie the Frenchwoman was spaking, bad luck to her. She's used to the likes of that. Didn't she be smacking her lips though! and Miss Gertie sending the carriage, and she axin' three dollars the job for spoiling the beautiful hair of her. If I'd my way she'd come no more coaxing a beautiful young lady to be taking the sling. Sure for ye now her breath will be smelling the whole evening, it will."</p> 
               <p>"What are you talking about, Kathleen?" asked Aunt Cynthia, who was arranging the rows of bread in methodical order for the family meal. "Who has been taking brandy-sling in this house?"</p> 
               <p>"Miss Gertie, mum."</p> 
               <p>"She haint neither," responded Aunt Cynthia, with indignation.</p> 
               <p>"And faith now, it's the truth I'm spaking<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6500-00000012"/> to ye. That Frinch Magpie, that twists up my leddy's beautiful hair, rings the bell, and orders me to be bringing the brandy and sugar and hot water and nutmegs, and with the two eyes of me I saw her bidding Miss Gertie, the darlint, to drink the stuff, not fit for hersel, forby a Christian leddy of the likes of Miss Gertie."</p> 
               <p>"Did I ever hear the like of that?" said Aunt Cynthia, shaking back her cap-strings, as she stood in astonishment, knife in one hand and bread in the other. "If you hadn't seen it yourself, Kathleen, I'd never a' believed one word on't."</p> 
               <p>Aunt Cynthia had lived in the family from Gertie's infancy, and, if possible, loved the dear young lady better than mother or Uncle Simon. Poor old soul, she had no one else to love now; but there had been a time when husband and child warmed up the current of her life. God took them, and Gertie and Harry came to her also, comforters amid her solitude and affliction.</p> 
               <p>Aunt Cynthia was honest, patient, and enduring, always at her post, and skilled in the culinary art. She could not talk or read French, but she knew how to spell out the text at church, and, as she expressed it, "read the road to heaven."</p> 
               <p>Strong drink in any shape was her aversion and it was rumored that her widowhood came of the bottle. But Aunt Cynthia kept her own secrets. Be that as it may, she was decidedly a teetotaler, except, as she would say, "in mince-pies."</p> 
               <p>"It stands to reason that a body must have a little then, just to give it a flavor; that much would not hurt a mouse. But f touch not, taste not, handle not/ as the pastor says, that's my rule." "And did she really git her to drink sling?"</p> 
               <p>"Sure, thin, and she did."</p> 
               <p>"And you saw her do it?"</p> 
               <p>"I did thin, with my own two blessed eyes."</p> 
               <p>"Oh! my, my, my! What will come next?" soliloquized the good woman, turning to her slices of bread.</p> 
               <p>Kathleen might as well have put her fingers into the very eyes of Aunt Cynthia, as to have intimated that her darling Gertie, upon whom she had exhausted the fire and energy<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6500-00000013"/> of a truly noble heart for eighteen years, had been guilty of an error-and of such an error. Just now, of all other times, it could not be borne. So she worked away nervously and quietly, making ready the little, tea in the library where they were all to meet presently and refresh themselves for the toil of the approaching evening.</p> 
               <p>She could have soolded the beautiful creature herself, could have reproached her until she brought tears, half of sorrow, half of indignation, into the eyes she loved so well; and then, with as many cooings and comfortings as a fond mother could have given, have calmed down the turbulence she had created. But, to have another find fault, and, above all others, Kathleen, the servant girl, who, only a year ago, had been brought in from the pavement, dead drunk, at midnight; whom Aunt Cynthia, aided by Gertie, had, with infinite pains and care warmed into life; and who had been then taken into service at Gertie's earnest request, was quite too much.</p> 
               <p>To be sure Kathleen had been to hear Father Mathew since, and had taken the pledge, and been as sober and steady from that day to this as the old family clock that stood at the head of the hall stairs; but still, what right had she-Here Aunt Cynthia's fingers failed her, and down went the plate which she held in them, scattering her cakes far and wide over the pantry floor.</p> 
               <p>"Och! but what's happened yez, Miss Cynthia? Sure it's the witches, as yez called them, that have got into the house this day. Niver the likes o' that happened yez before sin' I set foot in this blessed place!"</p> 
               <p>"Dear! dear! dear! nearly every one of them is broken smash in two!" ejaculated the good woman, as they both stooped to gather up the fragments.</p> 
               <p>The two women had found a matter large enough to entirely turn the current of their unpleasant thoughts. The branded linking and Kathleen's impertinence were, for the time, forgotten.</p> 
               <p>Thus it is. A very little circumstance, so trifling as to cause only a smile, may often come in the guise of a mishap or blunder, and turn aside the pressure of some trial which, without this timely aid, might have borne down a tried and weakened spirit, and<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6500-00000014"/> have unfitted it for some higher and nobler duty. Especially is this so in the lives of many women. Born to the heritage of brains, with faculties for planning and organizing, and powers for executing that might, with sufficient and judicious culture, have fitted them for spheres of action as wide and deep as the world offers to the human soul; with the resistless, indefinite longing of these repressed powers to be used to the utmost limit of their capacity,-a longing seldom satisfied in any degree,-discontent becomes habitual.</p> 
               <p>Aunt Cynthia might be said to be habitually discontented, and the spilling of a plate of cakes was a momentary relief, like the friction given a paralyzed limb that needs yet cannot take its own exercise. Had this good woman been blessed through all her years by the continued life of her husband, and the care of a household of restless, healthy children been her portion, she would have filled her whole measure of duty, and would doubtless have sent out into the world the noblest specimens of men and women that her great, generous-hearted motherhood, in its uncultured state, could have trained and educated. And this is the world's best work.</p> 
               <p>Love-the love of a mother-would have been her teacher, and, in her struggles for their development, she would have found ways and means for the advancement of her own mental and moral powers. But no such fate came to this lone heart, so full of great possibilities, which for the most part slumbered and slept, waking only at longer and longer intervals to cry aloud with a hunger that was never appeased, save by complaints against society and the world.</p> 
               <p>In all probability, but for this little windfall of an accident, Kathleen would have received a "scolding" which she would have felt sore over for days, finally carrying her grievance to Miss Gertie; and Miss Gertie would have gone to her mother, and the length and breadth of the household quarrels no one can measure.</p> 
               <p>The cakes were picked up and set aside for the poor woman who came every morning for the broken bits. Fresh ones supplied their place, and Aunt Cynthia, in her self-accusa<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6500-00000015"/> tion, forgot wrong done her darling Gertie.</p> 
               <p>Let us now take, a peep princely mansion of the Eliot's. It is not the beautiful cottage of years ago, when Simon Eliot's head and heart were full of the bright eyes and rosy smiles and rippling laughter of the fairy bird that deserted the nest he had built for her. Oh, no!</p> 
               <p>A new residence, palatial in all its proportions, was to be christened upon this evening to the use of her whose birthday was the occasion of all the preparation we shall see, as we look through a few of its brilliantly lighted rooms. Pictures, statuary, chandeliers, carpets, furniture,-all arranged by the most cultivated taste, lay beneath the brilliance of gas-light, while flowers from tropic climes, vines from mountains, and blooms from garden and forest, shed their loveliness and fragrance over all, until the whole glowed and burned and dazzled on the gaze like a bright Elysian dream.</p> 
               <p>The banquet-rooms were one blaze of sparkling brightness. The wealth of Italy's glowing suns, the choicest vintage of France, the treasures of the isles of the sea, hoarded for a century; rum and brandy that had ripened long before Toussaint l'Ouverture bad broken the chains of the slaves that distilled them, or the bloody plains of Waterloo had decided the fate of the tyrant who crushed out his noble life, here glanced and gleamed and intensified the light. All that wealth, art, or skill could group together of the rare and beautiful were here in lavish profusion; but the rarest and most beautiful picture of all was the uncle and niece, who stood in the midst of this magnificence, gazing closely at its details and general effect, and asking each other if anything were wanting to complete the gorgeous display.</p> 
               <p>"No, darling uncle, mine, not one thing. Oh! it is so beautiful! so grand!" And the young girl, blushing in her rose-colored satin, her dark curls floating about her like a drapery, her diamonds flashing light upon her cheeks, glowing with excitement and happiness, twined her fair arms around the sturdy workman's neck and kissed his cheek, whispering:-</p> 
               <p>"Dear uncle, more than father, I will love<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6500-00000016"/> you always. It is all that I can do." And, in spite of herself, a great sob burst from her over-full heart, and tears gushed from her eyes.</p> 
               <p>"Hut! tut! tut!" exclaimed Uncle Simon, "what's all this about? Spoiling your eyes with tears and bursting that tight bodice with sobs I Come, Gertie, come! away with your sentimentalism! Here, pet, taste this old St. Croix rum. 'Twas sent me when you were a baby by old Captain Goodrich, who had made ninety trips from Connecticut to the West Indies, and never lost a sail. He said it was a hundred years old when he shipped it, and I have been keeping it for your eighteenth birthday. Come, pledge me now; for when those roysterers come, they'll not leave a drop."</p> 
               <p>And, suiting the action to the word, he poured a glass and held it to her lips. At that moment Melonie Thorne glided to the side of her friend, like an angel of light, in her white robes, with one pure white lily, as her only ornament, pendent in her hair.</p> 
               <p>"Why, Mell," exclaimed the beauty, "how sweet you are! Just in time to help me pledge dear Uncle Simon in this preserved sunshine of a hundred years ago. Only think of it!</p> 
               <p>"Yes, only think of it!" answered Melonie. "Only think of it; but don't touch it, dear Gertie."</p> 
               <p>"Why?" exclaimed Gertie, alarmed by the expression of her friend's face.</p> 
               <p>"Only that these words come to me now with prophetic warning: 'Every inordinate cup is unblessed, and the ingredient is a devil.'"</p> 
               <p>"Oh! fie, fie, fie!" gayly answered the young girl; "what a Puritan you are!" And, raising the glass, she continued, "Here's health, long life, and happiness to the best of uncles, and may he never want a warmer love than mine to cheer and comfort him."</p> 
               <p>And she sipped the odorous beverage, and handed it to him. Barely touching the glass to his lips, he replied, with choking emotion, "God bless you, my love!" and left the room.</p> 
               <p>Gertie threw her arm around Melonie, asking, with a troubled expression:-</p> 
               <pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6500-00000017"/> 
               <p>"What can be the matter with Uncle Simon?"</p> 
               <p>"I do not know, Gertie; but something has evidently stirred him deeply." Then, looking around, she exclaimed, after a troubled pause:-</p> 
               <p>"How beautifully everything is arranged! Not one thing to wish or to want."</p> 
               <p>And amid the rich aroma that floated from the beverage just tasted, the two young girls sought the parlors, arm in arm, to receive their guests.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
                
               <head>IV.</head> 
               <p>"WHAT is the matter with Uncle Simon?"</p> 
               <p>Well might the belle of the evening ask that question; but had Uncle Simon heard, he would have answered, "Nothing! "telling that strange falsehood that so many thousands tell when sudden emotions overcome them, or great gusts of passion sweep through the open portals of the soul, stirring from their old-time places a thousand memories of the past.</p> 
               <p>Uncle Simon would have said, "Nothing;" but we who have passed into the elegant parlors, the beautiful library, the unrivalled conservatory, the banquet-halls, and the drawing-rooms, may, perhaps, peep behind the curtain of a good man's heart, and tell a tale of what we see there, without violating any law of friendship or honor.</p> 
               <p>About twenty years before this memorable night, on the memorable one that had con<pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6500-00000018"/> summated the betrothal of Simon Eliot and Katy Vaughn, his first and only love, an incident occurred which had been shaping, in a greater or less degree, the destinies of all the parties concerned in our story.</p> 
               <p>There is, perhaps, never a moment of more ecstatic happiness to a pure and true-hearted young man, than that which secures to him a cheerful promise of fidelity from the young maiden who has given him already her love and trust.</p> 
               <p>Buoyant with happiness, and breathing forth earnest, heartfelt thanks to God for the precious boon that had been granted him, Simon was hurrying through the inclemency of a winter night, at a late hour, toward his lodgings, in one of the great thoroughfares of the city, when he was suddenly startled by the cry of a child. It was a low, wailing sob, that seemed to come from some exhausted sufferer. It required but a moment to bring the tender-hearted young man within the enclosure of a park near by, and threading its walks, guided by the sound, he soon found the object of his search, which proved to be a little boy of some five or six years of age. A fair-haired, beautiful child, clad in poor but tidy garments, who had been sent out earlier in the evening, doubtless, had strayed into the park and fallen asleep under a bush, and now awakened stiff and cold and frightened, yet had not been discovered by the policemen.</p> 
               <p>"What is the matter, my little fellow?" asked the young locksmith, gathering the child close to him. "How came you here?"</p> 
               <p>"Mamma sent me," answered the boy, "to ask some lady to come and see her."</p> 
               <p>"What did she want some lady to come for?"</p> 
               <p>"Because, sir, she is sick and very hungry, and has nobody but me."</p> 
               <p>"Would no lady go?"</p> 
               <p>"No, sir; they only said, 'Go away! Don't touch me!' and I stood by the gate until I was too cold, and then I crawled under this bush to wait for more ladies to come, and went to sleep."</p> 
               <p>Simon picked the poor, chilled little thing up in his arms, and, wrapping his cloak about him, hurried away to a police-station to warm him and satisfy his hunger, before he tried to<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6500-00000019"/> find his home. This done, with an assistant by his side, he set him down, and, taking his hand, by the aid of the lamplight he led them to the vicinity of a long row of wretched tenements in an obscure alley; and here, groping in and out, and down a flight of stairs, they came at last to the place which this artless, half-frozen child called "home."</p> 
               <p>"Don't go in, if he's there," whispered the little fellow.</p> 
               <p>"Who?" asked his companions.</p> 
               <p>"Papa. He'll strike if you do; and oh! he swears so. Mamma says it's wicked to swear. Is it?"</p> 
               <p>Simon did not heed the remonstrance of the prattler, but, pushing aside a broken door, he stepped into a scene of misery new to his young eyes.</p> 
               <p>On a bit of ragged quilt, in one corner of the damp cell, lay a dying woman, with a starved and dying babe clinging to her shrunken and empty breast. On the floor, almost barring the entrance to the apartment, was the prostrate form of what had once been a good-looking man. Now, with a jug by his side, he lay in the last beastly stage of imbecile inebriety; and as the officer and Simon rolled him out of the way, he opened his glued lips and uttered a scathing curse on the poor dying creature in the corner, and then rolling back upon his face, he fell into a deeper and more deadly stupor than before.</p> 
               <p>Another policeman was called, and the man was borne away by Simon's orders, to be cared for when he should awaken.</p> 
               <p>The young man applied himself to the task of reviving the mother. With eyes almost starting from their sockets, she watched them bear out the form of her husband, and, clasping her hands over her heart, she whispered feebly, "Gone, gone, gone! O God! for Jesus' sake, pity him, forgive him! He knows not what he does."</p> 
               <p>Then, turning to those who stood near her, she caught sight of her child, and, almost starting upright, she stretched forth her arms for her boy.</p> 
               <p>"O sir! where did you find him? O Beau, my babe, my darling! I am almost gone, sir; and I sent my child last night to see if in all this great city there was one to come to the dying mother and her child.<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC6500-00000020"/> Oh! how I have prayed,-prayed the good Father for <emph>him,</emph>"-and her eye sought the door,-"prayed for my beautiful boy. But he did not seem to hear. O sir! does God ever forget? My faith grew weak; I was so hungry, and he did not come. I had nearly gone into his presence doubting his love and mercy. O Jesus, forgive me! thou only knowest how weak I am."</p> 
               <p>A terrible spasm of coughing compelled her to pause. The policeman drew a flask of brandy from his pocket, and, pouring a little into a broken cup, said:-</p> 
               <p>"Take a sip of this, madam; it will help you."</p> 
               <p>The smell seemed to revive her; but, starting back with horror, she exclaimed:-</p> 
               <p>"No, no, no! 'Every inordinate cup is unblessed, and the ingredient is a devil.' Yes, yes, I know it now! So my father said when he told me not to marry him. No, no, let me die; but do not ask me to taste of that which is carrying his once noble soul to hell!" And, sinking back with a shudder, she closed her eyes, gasped, and her lips whispered, "Jesus, I come," and died.</p> 
                
               <p>Simon Eliot stood alone in the presence of a double death, for, stooping to remove the' babe from her breast, he found that the little spirit had already passed beyond.</p> 
               <p>It is not our purpose to tarry long by the wayside. The woman was decently buried, with her babe by her side; and they who in life had known little joy slept well, we trust.</p> 
               <p>All that could be gathered of the history of these people was from an old crone or two who lived in the adjoining basements The woman had come there, very feeble, a month or two before; had gone out in the daytime and sought work, and thus supplied herself and boy with food.</p> 
               <p>"She was a real lady and mighty pious, and had her Bible to read till he took it from her and sold it for liquor; and then she only prayed; but her prayers were as good as the-priest's any time." They did not know her name. Her husband had called her "Jule," and she had called him "Beaumont." He was always drunk, took away her clothes, her shoes, and everything. When her baby was born, he did promise to bring her something<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC6500-00000021"/> thing to eat, but he only came home drunker than ever.</p> 
               <p>They tried to give her a crust, but he beat them from the door, and so they left her the morning before, hoping to get something for her; and when they came at night, he had shut the door, and sat with his back to it, shouting and singing until he could shout and sing no more, and then all was still. And thus it ended. This was the brief, heartrending story.</p> 
               <p>"A hundred such every year," said the kind-hearted policeman. "This great city is full of them, and must be while the city council and law-makers manage things as they do now."</p> 
               <p>Mr. Eliot disposed of the boy, and then sought the inebriate father; but rum had done its work. Raving in delirium tremens, he had no coherent thoughts; but his language, tone, and sentiment all proclaimed a man of education, character, and ability. A lordly sacrifice to the demon of strong drink, he, too, died, and was buried by the side of his wife by the kindly care of Simon Eliot.</p> 
               <p>"What did your mamma call you?" asked he of the child as he held him on his knee and tried to soothe his cries for his mother.</p> 
               <p>"She called me her little boy Beau, sometimes, and when she called me on the street, she said 'Beaumont Fletcher;'" and so the little tongue lisped the name that his mother gave, and kind strangers calling him "little Beau," and striving to make him happy, soon won him from his grief. His cheek grew round and plump; his blue eye danced with light and joy, and all the neighbors said that little Beau Fletcher was the smartest and prettiest child that ever was seen.</p> 
               <p>Simon Eliot soon loved the boy, and longed for the time to come when he could shelter him in his own home, and train the little heart each day in the ways of wisdom. In the mean time he was sent to school, and made great proficiency, winning hearts and prizes wherever he might be.</p> 
               <p>Hitherto the child had been in the care of good Mr. Welkins, the foreman in Mr. Eliot's shop. Having no children of their own, he was to this good man and his wife a light and joy. They loved him with great love, and taught him gently and kindly.<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6500-00000022"/> Sabbath school and day school welcomed the beautiful boy, and he grew in grace and knowledge, loving God and keeping all the commandments laid upon him by the good Grandsire and Grandma Wilkins, as they had taught him to call them.</p> 
               <p>When the great disappointment of Mr. Eliot's life fell upon him, Beau was a solace to many a lonely hour, and it was a long conflict Simon had between his love and his duty, before he relinquished the idea of taking Beau home when Mrs. Manning and her children domiciled themselves in his house.</p> 
               <p>"Better not, better not, Master Eliot," said Grandsire Wilkins. "The boy is wonderful smart, but he is somebody else's boy, you know. Mrs. Manning has her own to love, and women ought to love their own the best, and mostly they do."</p> 
               <p>"Yes; leave him with us, Master Simon," pleaded grandma, imploringly. "I couldn't have him anybody's second best. No, no, Master Simon; let us bring him up to be a man."</p> 
               <p>So Mr. Eliot yielded, and Beau lived with the good mechanic and his wife, attending the city schools, until West Point, six years after, opened its doors to the orphan boy, <foreign xml:lang="FRA">proteg</foreign> of the rich inventor.</p> 
               <p>Do you ask now why Simon Eliot turned away with such emotion from the two lovely girls? Those words of Melonie, which had a history for her too, had struck a chord in that bereaved heart which thrilled in that hour of pride, pomp, and splendor, as keenly even as twenty years ago it thrilled responsive to the touch of Katy's fingers.</p> 
               <p>The dead mother of Beau seemed to have reiterated her dying words in the ear of his niece to warn her of her danger.</p> 
               <p>Was he warned? No. He felt a thrill as the recollections of other days swept over him, and in the library, leaning his head against a beautiful statue, he gave way to weakness, as men call it, for a moment, and let tears course their way down his manly cheeks.</p> 
               <p>"What would he do if anything should happen to Gertie?" Such seemed to be the question that his yearning heart was putting to some invisible power. Dropping upon his knees, the strong man prayed that her life<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6500-00000023"/> might be preserved and her love kept pure; that prosperity might not pervert and destroy, or lead either himself or his child to forget God; or grow arrogant or selfish in spirit. It was a humble, earnest prayer,-not eloquent in neatly rounded periods or elaborate sentiments, for they were not his gift; but fervent, as coming from a heart that felt the goodness of the all-Father, and believed in his wisdom and power.</p> 
               <p>The ringing of the door-bell and the bustle of incoming guests called him to stand by the side of his niece and sister, to receive the five hundred friends who had been called to grace this birthday festival, and his emotion which was but momentary passed as a breath of autumn wind.</p> 
               <p>Oh, if Simon Eliot could have apprehended the relation between cause and effect-morally, as easily as he could do mechanically; could he have seen how little things jai and despoil the machinery of social life, as he would have seen the discrepancies caused by one unfinished or imperfect cog or wheel in his wonderful inventions; how easily could he, with one wave of his hand, have removed the evil that was threatening to mar and destroy all the joy, happiness, and peace of every soul connected with his household!</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC6500-00000024"/> 
               <head>V.</head> 
               <p>BUT this good man did not see. He believed-yes, conscientiously believed-that wines daily upon his table, and strong drink upon his sideboard, in the presence of those children, would be no detriment, but rather a benefit.</p> 
               <p>At the time of which we write, in 1854, the Temperance subject was perhaps more fully before the world than it had ever been before since the redeeming work began.</p> 
               <p>"Total abstinence," he would say, "is not temperance. Temperance is 'moderation in all things,' says St. Paul, and I want my household to be governed by self-denial and self-control. What safety is there for a boy whose only protection is simply a promise that he will not touch the thing?"</p> 
               <p>The church stood with him and aloof from the great swelling surge of popular reform, that swept like an overwhelming wave over the middle classes of the people, moving them in all parts of the United States to form societies and associations to enable them to make due resistance to the almost superhuman efforts of men engaged in the traffic in alcoholic beverages.</p> 
               <p>"Let those who can't stand alone join hands; but for me and my house, our faith is in our own common sense and self-denial, not in a promise," Uncle Simon was wont to say when besought to give his aid and influence to the good work. He argued it as a scientific question, quoted the learned doctors, and gave the example of wine-drinking countries, and, believing he was right, he persisted in the habit of his youth.</p> 
               <p>"There is no better or more consistent man living than Simon Eliot. Grand and strong intellectually, true to every interest of society, no good thing is done that he does not help to do it. He builds churches, asylums, homes for the widows and orphans, I houses of protection, tenement-houses full of comfort and cleanliness, visits the jails and the workhouses, gives labor to the strong and charity to the weak, and in every way<pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC6500-00000025"/> fills his whole measure of duty as a citizen, a neighbor, and a Christian man; and do you, sir, pretend to tell me that such a man's influence in society is dangerous because he indulges moderately in beverages that other people choose to use to excess?"</p> 
               <p>Such was the reply of a fashionable liquor-dealer when remonstrated with by one who felt that, for the masses of mankind, there was safety but in total abstinence.</p> 
               <p>Many people sustained the liquor-dealer's argument, and the moderate drinker forgot the sublime prayer, "Lead us not into temptation;" forgot that every drunkard was once but a moderate drinker; forgot those terrible words, "Cursed is he that putteth the cup to his brother's lips;" and that most awful of all truths, "No drunkard shall enter the kingdom of heaven."</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
                
               <head>VI.</head> 
               <p>"IT'S all over," exclaimed Gertie, as she threw herself into a chair and leaned her head against the yielding cushion, regardless of diamonds and drapery.</p> 
               <p>"It is all over! This one great gala-day of my life, talked of, thought of, dreamed of, for months and years, is consummated in a few short hours, and gone."</p> 
               <p>"No, not gone, Gertie-only finished, as you finish an elaborate piece of crochet-work, or embroidery, or drawing. Finished to be laid aside for the present, or hung up on memory's walls to be examined hereafter; but always yours while reason and life last,' said Melonie.</p> 
               <p>"No, it is not gone, Mell. Shall I tell you? Will you laugh at me? I must, or I cannot sleep to-night. Beaumont Fletcher has proposed to me."</p> 
               <p>"And what answer did you give?" asked<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC6500-00000026"/> Melome, turning upon the speaker with a start.</p> 
               <p>"What answer?" and the heiress held up her fair hands and leisurely unclasped her diamonds and laid them on her lap. "Such an answer as a foolish girl of eighteen in the first flush of her first womanly conquest might be expected to give to Such a wonderfully splendid fellow. Blushed, stammered, and let silence give consent.</p> 
               <p>"Mell," she exclaimed, excitedly, "there is no other such man living as Beaumont Fletcher. I have known him always. He has been like a brother; but I never knew until to-day how much I-There! How foolish I am. I am tired. I'll not say another word."</p> 
               <p>She rose hastily, broke into a little snatch of song, and commenced rudely and rapidly throwing off the elegant trifles that had made her so gorgeously brilliant during the evening.</p> 
               <p>"Why, Gertie, dear, how excited you are! Let me help you. You will tear that beautiful lace."</p> 
               <p>"Don't care if I do. That old goose of an uncle is rich enough to buy more."</p> 
                
               <p>Her eyes were flashing, her cheeks burning with bright-red spots, and the young heart throbbing, not with fresh, pure happiness, but with the fitful, unsteady spring of unnatural stimulants.</p> 
               <p>Melonie Thorne saw it all at a glance. A pang shot through her heart that paled her cheek and almost brought her to fainting.</p> 
               <p>"Let me help you undress. You are tired, love, and the sooner your head is on your pillow the better. See, it is after three."</p> 
               <p>So, carefully soothing and aiding, she soon disrobed her friend, who, without her usual prayer, without the loving good-night kiss to either uncle or mother, threw herself upon her bed and fell into a deep stupor, which was not broken until the sun rode high in the east, and the parlors below were well-nigh cleared of all the glittering pageantry of the previous evening.</p> 
               <p>The great party and its magnificence were the talk for a day or two. The dailies found numerous paragraphs necessary to satisfy the public demand. For what do ladies order magnificent costumes, if not to be<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC6500-00000027"/> heralded in the <title>Herald?</title> For what do modistes labor and toil to gain the eclat of having got up the most elaborate and unequalled toilets of the occasion? Shall Stewart import, and not have it known? Shall Lord &amp; Taylor dazzle, and only their shop-windows tell the tale?</p> 
               <p>Little do the usual readers of a daily paper in a great city like New York comprehend the complicated machinery that is put in motion by commerce and trade, art and industry, speculation and intrigue, to give note and <foreign xml:lang="FRA">clat</foreign> to such a party. The unseen wires which are pulled, run down deep into a thousand hearts and households, and ring changes on thousands of lives, unseen and, unfelt in the great whirl of fashion and folly that dance their round upon the surface.</p> 
               <p>A great festival party in New York, or any other large city, is not, cannot be simply a festival party. It is far more than we dream in our wildest imaginings. From the silk-winders of Italy, the ivory-hunters of India, the marble-chisellers of Florence, the lace-weavers of Valencia, through every ramification of trade, in every item that helps to make up the glittering display, down to the poor seamstress who tacks the trimmings on the dresses, and the ebony waiter at the hall-door, who bows graciously as he receives the stylish card upon his silver salver,-all these patient, humble workers are linked to these festivals by bands of common interest and common labor, and are made better or worse, happier or otherwise, by the rise and fall of the tide of popular favor, that gives work to their hands, and through their work furnishes money for their needs.</p> 
               <p>"What right," asks the moralist, "has one to engross and spend thousands of dollars when another is only able to spend dimes?"</p> 
               <p>Can we answer such questions? Shall we ask what right has God to endow Simon Eliot with powers so vast that, by their use, he may create under his hand an agent so superhuman that, with bones of wood and muscles of iron and nerves of steel, it can do in one hour the work of a hundred men, taking from their strained bones and muscles the load that was bearing them down and racking them with pain; thus giving him the means of gathering immense wealth; while<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC6500-00000028"/> to another he gives only the plodding brain, that toils and delves and lifts itself no higher through threescore years and ten, and dies at last no wiser than at the beginning?</p> 
               <p>He who grinds the faces of the poor; he who by wily arts obtains from others what he should not have; he who selfishly grasps, may be questioned; but he who puts a million wheels in motion, and, by his own inherent strength, using the talents God has given him, helps to give bread to a million waiting mouths; if he injures no man, and owes "no man anything but love to one another," should not be too severely censured or criticised.</p> 
               <p>But, while we have been moralizing, the day has worn almost to the meridian, and Gertie Manning has wakened from her long, feverish stupor, and rung the bell for Aunt Cynthia, who answers with a readiness that through years of devotion has never failed.</p> 
               <p>"O Aunt Cynthia! where is my mother? I am so sick. My head will burst. Oh! what will I do?"</p> 
               <p>"My, my, my!" exclaimed Aunt Cynthia. "I knew something would happen when I let them there cakes fall. "Why, Gertie, child, what is the matter? What makes its head ache so? There, darling, lay its head right down on aunty's shoulder. A plague take them miserable old parties!"</p> 
               <p>The poor, sick girl writhed and groaned in very agony.</p> 
               <p>"It's the brandy that's at the bottom of it, it is," said Kathleen. "Sure and don't I be knowing? It's meself that's had the aching head and the vomiting, many's the time from that same, before Father Mathew give me the pledge. Och! but it's a bad thing!" And, crossing herself devoutly, she ran for hot water, and to send Sandy for the family physician.</p> 
               <p>Madame Broseau had given Gertie brandy: Uncle Simon had pledged her in rum one hundred years old; old Father Frazier, whose pet she had been from childhood, had asked her to drink a glass with him; Harry, just home from the East Indies, whom she had not seen for two years, said:-</p> 
               <p>"Come, pledge me, sister mine, in this wine which I have brought for you from the far-off isles of the sea." Last of all, Beaumont<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC6500-00000029"/> mont had touched glasses with his beautiful betrothed.</p> 
               <p>Need we wonder! need we exclaim! Is it only young men, strong and brave, full of vigorous health and bounding life, that may fail when thus tried; when temptations multiply, and the loved, the trusted, the true, set the snares for their guileless feet?</p> 
               <p>Who, in all that throng of worshippers at the shrine of beauty, wealth, and fashion, had dared to say to Gertie Manning, "Beware!" Not one; no, not one; and there she lay, prostrate, wild with pain, and craving what she dared not ask for-a stimulant.</p> 
               <p>Was it the first time she had erred? No; far from it. For ten years, day by day, had this sweet-tempered and happy-hearted maiden been sipping, sipping, sipping, in the presence of her mother, in the presence of her uncle, yet no one thought of evil.</p> 
               <p>More than once she had said, "I took too much wine yesterday. It made my head ache." Yet had she said, "I took too much cake, or ate too many oysters," it would have elicited as much attention.</p> 
               <p>The habit was forming. The wily serpent was coiling around her life, and drawing its deadly folds closer and closer over that noble heart. When Dr. Steadman made his appearance,-the family counsellor as well as physician,-what should he have done in a case like this?</p> 
               <p>"He should have told her the truth in regard to herself," you will answer. But did he? Ah! no. He only felt her pulse, looked into her swollen eyes, gave her a lotion, and comforted the almost distracted mother by telling her that it was only the effect of nervous excitement, pouring into her ear fulsome compliments, and then ordered a powder and a quieting draught, and withdrew; only too glad that the doting eyes of the mother had been too blind to see what Aunt Cynthia and the humble, loving Kathleen knew but too well.</p> 
               <p>The victim slept again, but wakened in the evening twilight to full consciousness. She called the faithful Kathleen to assist her to rise and dress.</p> 
               <p>"Bring me a glass of wine, Kathleen. It will steady my head."</p> 
               <p>"Och! Miss Gertie, darlint, I wouldn't<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC6500-00000030"/> now. Let me be bringing yez a cup of tea, It will do you good."</p> 
               <p>"I tell you," answered the sick girl, petulantly, "I want a glass of wine."</p> 
               <p>"Sure now, don't I know that?" replied Kathleen; for she was alone with the patient. "It's meself, Miss Gertie, dear, that knows just what yez bes wantin', askin' yez pardon a thousand times over; but if I die this blessed minute I must spake.</p> 
               <p>"Miss Gertie, it's drunk ye was last night. Drunk from the brandy sling and the wine, and all of it ye got. Don't Kathleen know? Didn't yez bring me round that awful night with yer own hand? Och ohone och! ohone! Let me spake; let me spake. It's I as knows all about it. I have been dhrunk in the shanty I've been dhrunk at the dance! I've been dhrunk at the wake! I've been dhrunk on the cellar-doors I've been carried dhrunk to the prison; dhrunk to the work'us; been bound down on the frame with the delirem tremlies! and is it meself that don't know?</p> 
               <p>"Och! darlint, let me say my say. Don't be calling for the wine. Don't be touching it, or tasting it any more; or yez may come to the streets, and the perlice, and the work'us, and the jail-forby the lady that ye are! Don't bid me be bringing ye the wine. Don't darlint, don't. Turn me in the strate, keep me wages, hate me if ye will; but I'll not get it for yez, and, God forgive me, that I answered the French madam yesterday, and put the brandy to yez sweet mouth."</p> 
               <p>With such terrible vehemence had Kathleen poured forth her appeal, that Gertie, overwhelmed, had no power to check or stay the current of her prayer until it was ended, and the poor creature had thrown herself on her knees by the bedside, sobbing and moaning convulsively.</p> 
               <p>"Drunk!" said Gertie, slowly. "Kathleen, what have you said? That I was drunk?"</p> 
               <p>The girl could only sob.</p> 
               <p>"Get up," said Miss Manning, raising herself to a sitting posture. "Get up and leave the room. I can wait upon myself."</p> 
               <p>"Och! Miss Gertie, don't now-"</p> 
               <p>"Leave the room this instant," was the reiterated command, and Kathleen passed out, leaving the pet of the household alone.</p> 
               <pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC6500-00000031"/> 
               <p>"Drunk!" she exclaimed again. "Yes; I know it all now. My God! my God! and only that poor humble soul could be brave enough and true enough to tell me; and I have driven her out to repeat the tale to my mother; perchance to bruit it to the other servants in the kitchen." And, springing from her bed in wild dismay, she rang the bell, and again summoned the sobbing Kathleen to her side.</p> 
               <p>Weeping and wringing her hands, she reappeared and stood humbly at the door, Gertie sprang to her, and, throwing her arms about her, cried out in a voice of suppressed agony:-</p> 
               <p>"O Kathleen! I know it. I see it all. Don't tell mother. Don't tell Aunt Cynthia. Forgive me, Kathleen, and I will not touch or taste again. Never, never, never."</p> 
               <p>"Forgive yez, darlint. It's not for a poor wicked sinner like me to be forgivin' yez, Ask it of Jesus, and sure yell get pace." And so at the end of the festival stood the humbled, penitent heiress, and the exalted, purified servant, who had ceased to do evil and learned to do well, face to face, and heart to heart, as equals.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
                
               <head>VII.</head> 
               <p>"HAVE you heard the miserable gossip that is floating about in regard to Miss Manning?" asked one of the heads of a firm on Broadway of his partner, as they watched the folding away of the rich goods that had been piled upon the counter in answer to that young lady's call.</p> 
               <p>"I have not. I should as soon expect a gossip about the Virgin Mary as to hear the fair name of Miss Manning used rudely."</p> 
               <p>"One would think so. But at our club last night it was asserted that, on the evening of her birthday festival, she became actually intoxicated."</p> 
               <p>"Goodwin, don't repeat it. Why did you not cowhide the rascal who said so?"</p> 
               <p>"Because I have myself, more than once during the last year, noticed the breath of Miss Manning as she leaned over the counter to whisper her commands. I tell you, Jones,<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC6500-00000032"/> this thing is more common than you think; and, terrible as the suspicion maybe, it is not so terrible as the startling fact that, among our Fifth Avenue upper crust, ladies are sinking under a vice that formerly was supposed to be the peculiar propensity of men. The fact is awful, but nevertheless true."</p> 
               <p>"God help us!" ejaculated Jones, thinking of his own lovely wife, whom he had more than once suspected of indulging too freely in wine, when, after evening entertainments or wedding feasts, he had found her prostrate and irritable, passing through the same symptoms that marked his own excesses of like nature.</p> 
               <p>"After all," he resumed, "is it to be wondered at, if the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">lite,</foreign> the fashionable, the leaders of <foreign xml:lang="FRA">ton,</foreign> set liquors and wines before our wives and daughters, that they, supposing they are to be used, should fail to know just where and when to stop?"</p> 
               <p>"We do not; that is certain," responded Goodwin, emphatically. "And this fact is every day before us, that the highest and noblest among us fall, and we need not expect weak-headed young girls, or silly-brained women, as we are apt to call them, to be braver and more self-reliant than ourselves."</p> 
               <p>"That is so! My two girls are just on the point of entering society, and I feel tempted to institute a reform in my own house by forbidding the use of all intoxicating beverages at our reunions and receptions."</p> 
               <p>"I will join you."</p> 
               <p>"Good! Let us shake hands on that." And with a hearty, friendly grasp over a good resolution, the two parted for the time, each with sadder thoughts than he had uttered; each trembling for himself and for the safety of his own household, under the pressure of a habit that was slowly but surely gaining influence over them all.</p> 
               <p>We are so in the habit of associating the idea of intoxication with the poor and the unfortunate, with the working, delving classes of men and women, that we are shocked when it enters boldly into our parlors and takes its seat at our tables. But, should we go down among those who inhabit the purlieus of our cities, who revel in bar-rooms, and hide their awful lives of debasement in underground saloons, and trace the course of<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC6500-00000033"/> these victims of this great American scourge back through the frightful labyrinth their stumbling, erring feet have trod, we should be more shocked and humbled still to find, too often, that the lowest and vilest of them all had once stood, like ourselves, at the entrance of that gate which we will call "Moderation," firm in their faith that <emph>they,</emph> though all others might fail, could walk with steady steps even unto the end.</p> 
               <p>So had thought and reasoned the father of Beaumont Fletcher, when, as a young man, the pride of his father's house, the heir of immense wealth, the genius of the college, the life, the spirit, the soul of the literary circle, of the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">bon vivants</foreign> of London, he had sipped his wine and called for his brandy.</p> 
               <p>Had any one whispered to him, as he stood by the side of the accomplished Julia Raymond at the altar, "You will die a drunkard, and your wife will perish of want in a cellar" would he have believed? would he have denied himself an "inordinate cup," or have tried to restrain one desire that was overmastering him?</p> 
               <p>The history of thousands answers, No! and the shrieks of those lost in the past centuries torture our ears with their woes; and yet the burning stream rolls on. The same arguments, the same sophisms, the same delusions, lead us and our loved ones into the same paths, to walk through the same fiery furnace, to grovel, to blaspheme, to riot, to die, leaving the place we have occupied to be instantly filled by another as wretched and as lost.</p> 
               <p>O people of America! O men and women of this nineteenth century! are ye asleep? O fifty thousand ministers, standing in fifty thousand pulpits! you who have wrapped about you the robes of Christ, why are your voices so silent oh this damning sin? Can you fold your arms, and smile complacently, and teach doctrines to hungering and thirsting souls, while a quarter of a million of human beings are falling into line, and marching, to the enticing music of moderate drinking, with sure and steady steps to the fate of Beaumont Fletcher? while hundreds, who sit beneath your teaching, are waiting only for the earnest, prayer, "Lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from evil," to fall from your lips,<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC6500-00000034"/> to save themselves from the snare that entangled the feet of Gertie Manning, and left upon her fair name, from the night of her birthday festival, forever and forever, the Withering blight?</p> 
               <p>Oh! for the voice of an archangel to convince those who are like Simon Eliot, or Parson Ludlow, or Dr. Steadman, that the only safety for all is to become as the Rechabites of old, promising before the Lord of hosts:-</p> 
               <p>"We will drink no wine all our days; we nor our wives, nor our sons, nor our daughters."</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
                
               <head>VIII.</head> 
               <p>IN our last we made allusion to the early life and parentage of Beaumont Fletcher. While yet a student at West Point, an English traveller, visiting that institution, had heard his name and looked into his face, and, recognizing the familiar features of an old college friend, had made inquiries concerning the home and friends of the young man. He learned simply that he had been entered there through the influence of Mr. Simon Eliot, of New York, a wealthy and influential gentleman, who seemed to have sole supervising care over him, who paid all his bills, and often visited the institution, seeming very much attached to the young man.</p> 
               <p>Obtaining the address of Mr. Eliot, the stranger called upon him on his return to New York, and learned from him the fate of Beaumont Fletcher, senior, and his wife, and gave in return a circumstantial account of the<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC6500-00000035"/> early life and connections of this talented but misguided young man.</p> 
               <p>This account we have already sketched sufficiently for our purpose. It was but a reiteration of the tale that may be told of thousands, ay, millions, wherever civilization has trodden paths for the feet of man.</p> 
               <p>Not that civilization has made the world worse; but it has not yet taught all men the high and holy truth so impressively as to withhold and restrain the sensualism that has its roots within.</p> 
               <p>"Will these lessons ever be learned?" is the question asked by the doubter and sceptic. It is not for us here and now to attempt to answer that question by elaborate argument, or refutation of doctrines which lead to the continuance of practices resulting in the downfall of such noble natures as was Beaumont Fletcher's, and the consequent sacrifices of such women as the pure-hearted Christian wife who, with her child, starved to death-far from parents and home, a stranger in a foreign land-in a cellar in Five Points.</p> 
               <p>It is enough for us to know that abstinence from all that will intoxicate never, no, never brought man or woman to such a fate; that habits of strict temperance in a household will help to make the same habits more fixed and complete in the families that shall go out from that one, spreading their influence through coming generations.</p> 
               <p>Knowing this, need we know more? The simplest of all truths is the best truth; and while we see and know that those who never cultivate the habit of using, even in moderation, those beverages that lead to inebriety never fall, is it not strange that the wisest, truest, purest, and best men and women in the country will still tamper with such dangerous agents, still indulge <emph>in such fearful experiments?</emph>
               </p> 
               <p>We are writing a glimpse of two lives, and must now bring into more bold relief the life and character of Melonie Thorne, As already hinted, her early years had borne the withering blight of intemperance. Her father had gone down with thousands of others; but her mother, strong in her womanly nature, and buoyed up by that sublime faith which we have already witnessed in the prayer of the young girl in the midst of the<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC6500-00000036"/> glitter and excitement that surrounded her, though bruised and broken and panting by the way, had found the good Samaritan in Simon Eliot, a distant relative. On the outskirts of the great city lay the old family residence of the Eliots. Once a farm, four miles from the Battery, gradually surrounded by the growing population, lot after lot had been clipped off, until there was left of the one hundred and sixty acres, which the great-great-great-grandfather had bought more than a century ago, only a large garden of some two or three acres, with its plain old redbrick house, its ancestral elms and great maples and chestnuts, its overgrown hedges and countless variety of tree and shrub, saved because Simon's father and mother had planted them.</p> 
               <p>Into the shrubbery, in the midst of a bustling, growing addition to the city, Mrs, Thorne chose to retire, and to take with her, and educate herself, her only daughter Melonie. Her education, above the average attained by women of-her day, and great skill and taste as an artist, enabled her, by teaching a few young ladies in French, German, music, and drawing, to earn enough to relieve her from a feeling of entire dependence. All that Cousin Simon persistently bestowed besides, she accepted gratefully.</p> 
               <p>Mr. Eliot had, as the people said, some queer crotchets, and one of these was that "Cousin Eunice," who had received her education in Europe, should be Gertie's teacher, He had a horror of boarding-schools, of flimsy courses of study, of the drillings of fashion; and so furnished every possible appliance to make The Elms, as it was called, attractive, and fitted in every way for the improvement of the young ladies, who put themselves for a few hours each day under the care of Mrs. Thorne.</p> 
               <p>Thus growing side by side, studying the same books, drinking from the same fountains, under the same fostering care, it was no wonder that the two girls became as sisters, though widely different in tastes and habits. With line upon line and precept upon precept, drawn from the bitter fountains of her early experience, had Mrs. Thorne fortified her own child against all the excitements of vice. But how could she interfere<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC6500-00000037"/> with the daily habits of social life in that other household, where her benefactor centred his affections? Of course it did not seem to her necessary, and it was not done.</p> 
               <p>Now these young girls stand on the threshold of that destiny which comes in some shape to every girl of eighteen.</p> 
               <p>After the birthday party, the usual routine prevailed. Beaumont Fletcher was ordered by the government to the far West. Harry, his mother's petted darling, was in the navy. His furloughs had been few and far between; but Melonie had, from early boyhood, been his "bright, particular star," and the engagement between them had been the work of years. It could hardly be told how it began or how it was consummated. It was; and Melonie was happy and trusting, waiting quietly for the hour when she should assume the duties of a wife.</p> 
               <p>In the mean time she was carrying out a plan of her own, which, like the compass of a ship, kept her course steady, and brought her every day nearer and nearer to the goal she desired to reach, a fitness for the sphere of life she had consented by and by to fill.</p> 
                
               <p>The Elms lay near one of those open spaces of land around the city where the offal of its streets and the sweepings of its lanes and alleys are deposited day by day, to fill up the hollows and bring the land into marketable condition. Passing this spot very frequently on her way to and from the city, Melonie could not be blind to the poverty and misery she saw there. Men, women, and children, with tattered garments and forms emaciated by starvation, came by tens and twenties, to turn over this garbage and delve amid its filth for bits of coal, splinters of wood, old rags and papers, bones, or whatever might or could be converted into a penny to support or destroy their wretched lives.</p> 
               <p>Blear-eyed, haggard, profane, most of them, yet human still, were the mothers. But the children-were they not, even in all their penury and wretchedness, such as Jesus gathered into his arms when he uttered that sublime saying, "Suffer little children to come unto me, and forbid them not; for of such is the kingdom of heaven"?</p> 
               <p>Often, as Melonie picked her way daintily from the station-house to The Elms, only a<pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC6500-00000038"/> block or two, a dozen little blue, cold hands would be held out imploringly, and a dozen little tongues, trained to deception and falsehood, would utter whining lies to win her coppers.</p> 
               <p>One cold wintry morning in November, a few days after the birthday party, Simon Eliot was startled in his office by the entrance of Melonie, glowing with the exercise of a rapid walk and the excitement of her errand.</p> 
               <p>"What's in the wind now?" exclaimed Uncle Simon, and laying down his papers, and stretching out both hands to the entering guest, he caught her half-frozen fingers in his, and drew her down upon his knee.</p> 
               <p>"Why, Uncle Simon, your question is quite to the point. There are twenty poor miserable children in the wind,-this cold, bitter wind,-with tattered garments, and half of them with bare feet, starved and wretched as they can be. They are upon the common, hunting bones and chips and bits of coal, and begging and swearing and fighting. O Uncle Simon! can't we do something for them?'</p> 
                
               <p>"Aren't their mothers there with them, pet?"</p> 
               <p>"Why, yes, I suppose so."</p> 
               <p>"And they all have homes or hovels somewhere, haven't they?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, I suppose so."</p> 
               <p>"Well, what can we do? If we feed them to-day, they will be just as hungry to-morrow."</p> 
               <p>"I know that, Uncle Simon."</p> 
               <p>"If I should give you cash to buy a comfortable outfit for every one of them this morning, they would half of them post into the city, and before night sell their garments for rum, and be in the Recorder's court to-morrow morning."</p> 
               <p>"I know that."</p> 
               <p>"Then what does my rosy-cheeked darling propose that <emph>we</emph> shall do?"</p> 
               <p>"Uncle Simon, you know that on the back corner of our garden, which is nearest the common there is an old brick building, with large rooms and good chimneys and great windows, and all that. Now the gardener and his wife only occupy two or three of the back rooms that open into the garden. You<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC6500-00000039"/> wanted to give me diamonds the other day. You remember I said, 'No; wait till I want something.' Now I want something. I want that house fitted up, those rooms put in neat order, their walls hung with cards and pretty object-pictures. I want chairs and tables,-yes, Uncle Simon, I want a large schoolroom; and I want another woman in the other great room that will keep house, and make soup, and get one good meal ready every day for twenty boys and girls; and then, Uncle Simon, I want to pick out the worst, the very worst of all those children, and take them in and teach them."</p> 
               <p>"Teach them what?"</p> 
               <p>"Teach them of Jesus; teach them to be good; teach them by loving-kindness to be loving and kind; teach them to read, by reading them pretty thoughts and true thoughts; teach them, by actual contact therewith, that there is a happier, purer life, even in this world, than that they are now living. And, Uncle Simon, if this can't be done, then is our faith vain, and we are mocked; which I don't believe."</p> 
               <p>"Well, darling, you shall have it all your own way. When shall <emph>we</emph> begin?" And the great inventor emphasized the "we" a little provokingly.</p> 
               <p>"We will begin now, if you please. I want one thousand dollars,-less than half the value of that set of jewels which I did not want. I don't want for myself, but for God's poor." And, putting her small, rosy fingers each side of the smiling, generous face, hiding them in the iron-gray beard, she drew his beloved head toward her, and kissed the furrowed forehead.</p> 
               <p>"Trust me, Uncle Simon. 'He that giveth to the poor lendeth to the Lord.'"</p> 
               <p>"I will trust you, my darling." And the money was put in her hand.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC6500-00000040"/> 
               <head>IX.</head> 
               <p>TIME'S swift wing has moved us with irresistible force two years beyond the point at which we left our little friend Melonie Thorne at the close of our last chapter. It is not to be supposed she has been sitting on that kind knee, and drawing her rosy fingers through that grizzling head, all this time.</p> 
               <p>"Of course not. But how did she succeed with her school?" There, gentle reader, I knew you was longing to know the ultimate success or failure of such a unique proceeding. She succeeded admirably, because she resolved to succeed,-to give her heart to her work, and her prayers to God. True, she had some dark days, some sad trials; but Melonie Thorne had too much sense to suppose that children born in sin, reared in the streets, and educated upon the garbage heaps of New York city, could be transformed to saints by the wave of her pretty hand, or even the potent influence of a few thousands a year from Uncle Simon, made more by now and then a donation from the rich and kindly disposed that loved her and believed in her. She had faith-faith in the power of truth and right to overcome falsehood and wrong-that if she failed in ten cases out of twenty, were not the ten helped worth the effort?</p> 
               <p>So she asked her heart with every disappointment, and the answer was always in the affirmative. If she could have had those little ones all to herself; if she could have cut off the influence of the home life, then she would have found the gems that a few years' polishing under her sunny kindness have wrought into jewels for the lory. But that could not be. Home life and home love could not be severed. So she wrought patiently, enduringly, lovingly, and hopefully; and she was rewarded by seeing some of her proteges reformed, and some mothers made willing and anxious, in order to save their children from temptation, to give up even the claim to them, that the little one might be removed to a purer atmosphere, and escape the snares<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC6500-00000041"/> of city life that were set for them. And now at the end of two years we find the young enthusiast grown the staid, sober, thoughtful woman, and, though but twenty, seeming to have lived thirty years. 'With a shade upon her brow of care, and, mayhap, perplexity, she sits by the window, holding in her hand a letter which she has apparently just read. Out on a playground, only a few rods away, thirty children are at play. Slowly her eye scans them, one by one, and then turns to the letter, as it fills with tears, and, bending her head over it, they drop upon the paper.</p> 
               <p>Harry has written her. He shall soon be home; and when he comes, he shall claim the promise of two years ago, that she will be his bride. It is a long letter, full of love, and stirs her heart with wild flutterings.</p> 
               <p>But who will take care of <emph>them?</emph> Those thirty helpless ones who for two years have shared her anxieties and prayers, and helped to still the longings of her spirit for him who was tossing on the wild waves of the ocean? She must give them up. No wonder the tears fell and blotted the love-freighted missive she held in her hand, or caused the deep sigh while yet the flushed cheek and fast-beating pulse told of the more intense joy that was surging in her bosom. She read his letter again and again; and, as she read, the greater love absorbed the less.</p> 
               <p>"I must get somebody to fill my place," she said to herself at last, aroused from her blissful dream by the ringing of the bell that proclaimed the hour when these thirty children were to go out to the squalid places called homes; for the night.</p> 
               <p>How bright and happy they looked on the playground! Now, as they came in to be disrobed, and again put on their street-garments, there is scarce one that is not sad. As the "good-nights" are said, and as they pass out one after another, you can almost read the resolve in the faces of the elder ones: "We will try to be good, to learn to read and work, so that one of these days we will have good clothes all the time, and earn for ourselves good bread and meat."</p> 
               <p>For so had Melonie Thorne, in her sweet, quiet way, been teaching them to think and hope for the future; teaching them that they could only be made better by their own good<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC6500-00000042"/> resolutions, habits, and wills; by loving God and keeping his commandments. And now Melonie was alone. There was time to read that letter once more ere the tea-bell should ring, and again her eager eyes traced every word.</p> 
               <p>It would have been hard to tell which preponderated, pain or pleasure, in the mind of the usually calm, quiet maiden. Pleasure there certainly was, for Harry would be home in a month or so,-Harry whom she had loved so long and trusted so implicitly. Then she mused: " He must be strangely changed. What expressions he uses!" Just such as Will and Ed used to use when she first took them in from the street. But then he was with rude men and sailors all the time; so far from home, too, <emph>poor Harry!</emph> It was so hard for him to be so long away from friends, and only on shipboard with men; and so, while the pain was yet keen from something that her sensitive nature felt rather than read, she folded the letter, tucked it under her bodice and went to tea.</p> 
               <p>As the pendulum swings back and forth, so must we swing back again to the time when Melonie first began her good work; good and beautiful, but curious for a fair maiden of eighteen.</p> 
               <p>One bitter cold morning of February, 1857, just after the great financial crisis that sent such desolation, sorrow, and want into households and homes hitherto blessed with affluence, and, consequently, poverty almost amounting to starvation into the hovels of the poor, a boy of fourteen, yet very small of his years, might have been seen standing against the east wall of Cooper Institute.</p> 
               <p>His long, bony, soiled hands were thrust deep into his ragged, empty pockets. An old white hat ran up to seed, with half the rim lost, covered his head. His old jacket, or rather jackets,-for they were the remnant of two or three,-were only "ventilation garments," that let in the wind, and let out the warmth of his poor starved little body.</p> 
               <p>The wind, as it rushed up the avenue, pierced him to the heart. His old pants were, if possible, worse than his jacket, and let in the sunlight he seemed to be trying to woo to his naked person, which, though dazzlingly<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC6500-00000043"/> zlingly bright, brought no warmth, nor stirred one dripping tear from the icicles that glittered like diamonds from every point. That day sun nor wind had pity for the poor.</p> 
               <p>Had any one passed the child and noticed him, the only expression that would have fallen from the lips would have been, "<emph>Poverty, rags, and sin.</emph>"</p> 
               <p>The little fellow supported his back against the wall, stood upon the right foot, while he drew the toe of the left up into the redundant bundle of tatters that hung under the left knee, and nestled it there in hope to thaw it out, making every fluttering fragment do its best.</p> 
               <p>Oh, what a picture of wretchedness was Willie Saxton then and there! the tear which the wind, not his own misery, had forced from his great blue eyes, actually frozen upon his soiled, sallow cheeks; the deep brown hair uncombed, and full of dust and ashes from the heap where he had curled up last night, would kink and curl in spite of all opposition.</p> 
               <p>"I can't stand it much longer," he muttered; "she might have let me stayed. If I was starving, I didn't do no harm to that old board-wall and ash-heap, and they'd a kep' this awful wind off a little, and may be a fellow would 'a' had to gone up. Don't I wish somebody here would tumble down and break a leg or two, so I could get a handkercher, or glove, or something! I can't stand this much longer. Now, Mr. Left Toe; you must come clown in the world, and let your brother, Mr. Right, take a chance in the rags. 'Now I've got to steal or starve. Come, Mr. Left Toe, clown you go, in the ice and snow. Granny used to sing, 'This pig went to meeting and that one stayed at home;' but there aint no meeting nor home nor the por-'us now'-days."</p> 
               <p>So saying, the frozen toe went up and the half-frozen one went down, while the boy almost broke into a sob; the thought of his grandmother and of a time long ago pierced him more keenly than the wind.</p> 
               <p>"All <emph>his</emph> fault," thought Willie. "How <emph>he</emph> did use us, though, when he was drunk! Poor mother and granny! Well, I'm glad they're both dead!"</p> 
               <p>"Hallo there! Tarbox, is that you? What's up?"</p> 
               <pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC6500-00000044"/> 
               <p>This was addressed to the boy by another so exactly the counterpart of Willie himself in the outward that you might have guessed them twin brothers. The boy addressed as "Tarbox" looked up with keen eyes from a bit of bread he was munching, and immediately came and' took his place by the wallflower we have been describing, and also accosted him familiarly:-</p> 
               <p>"I say, Yellowtop, you're kind o cool now, aint you? As blue as a tatur. What's up with ye?"</p> 
               <p>"Where'd you git that bread? I hasn't had one bite since night before last, and that I fought a dog for that run out of a cellar-door. He stole it, and then I partook with the thief. Couldn't jug a fellow for that, could they?"</p> 
               <p>"Here, Yellowtop, just help yourself," replied Tarbox, whose name had its derivation from an immense shock of black hair, as had the nickname Yellowtop from the once golden curls of Willie Saxton.</p> 
               <p>"Here, help yourself, and don't be bashful now."</p> 
               <p>Half-frozen, dirty hands extended a crumb of hard bread, a half-frozen biscuit, and a bit of cold pork.</p> 
               <p>"Where'd you get' em?"</p> 
               <p>"Now, you just look here! Don't you go for to ask me questions. It's none of your business, and this child won't go for to be telling lies when it won't pay." And the boy turned his head half away, as if it were more than he could do to divide his meagre store with the hunger gnawing at his own vitals. Yellowtop took the crumbs and munched them down, while the great, beautiful eyes looked their intense gratitude.</p> 
               <p>Tarbox pressed a little nearer, and the two helped to keep each other warm, while in a low tone they talked of the prospect before them.</p> 
               <p>"I say, Yellowtop," said Tarbox (whose real name was Edgar Willard), "I'm not going to starve and freeze with that ere shop full of cakes and bread over there before my eyes, and all these fires a-blazing about."</p> 
               <p>"What will you do, Ed-"</p> 
               <p>"Don't you go for to call me <emph>Ed,</emph> and taking the heart out of me on such a day as this, That makes me think of her."</p> 
               <pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC6500-00000045"/> 
               <p>What a flash shot from those dark eyes! What a spirit gleamed over that young face, once so pure, now distorted by want and crime!</p> 
               <p>"What'll I do? I'll put my fist through that big glass, with a brickbat in it, or something; then the police will take us to the lockup, and we'll get warm once anyhow."</p> 
               <p>"No, you won't, Tarbox!"</p> 
               <p>"By-I will!" And the boy sprang forward, dragging Yellowtop with him toward the shop-window, and was about to put his threat into execution, when Yellowtop's old suspender gave way, as with a jerk, meant to free himself from his impetuous companion, he drew back, and at once denuded himself, of his upper garment. The rags fairly fell from his shoulder in the hands of Tarbox, while his release from the grip of Yellowtop precipitated him forward, and he fell headlong, striking his temple upon the curbstone, stunning him into unconsciousness. Tarbox fell prostrate upon him with a wild cry. The boy sprang forward to regain what he had lost.</p> 
               <p>Tarbox, who with desperate resolution had rescued his companion with a force not at all necessary for the strength of the old clothes, was thrown, when they gave way, headlong on the curbstone beyond, with a stunning power that left him for a moment senseless, the blood gushing from his temples, while Yellowtop tumbled over him in the effort to regain his rags.</p> 
               <p>A policeman immediately seized upon both boys, and was about to hurl them off the sidewalk, when he discovered that one was entirely unconscious in his hands.</p> 
               <p>At the same instant, a lady passing by was met by the gathering crowd; and, seeing the apparently dead boy, pale and bleeding, in the hands of the police, and the naked shoulder of his companion in that piercing wind, naturally stopped and asked, "What is the matter? "Yellowtop, though frightened, gave her the information.</p> 
               <p>"He was jerking me across, mem, and my gallowses they gave way, and down we went, both on us, and Tarbox-no, mem-Ed, I mean-he struck hisself on the rock, that's all."</p> 
               <p>"Where do you live?"</p> 
               <pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC6500-00000046"/> 
               <p>"Nowherea."</p> 
               <p>"Where do your father and mother live?"</p> 
               <p>"Haint got none."</p> 
               <p>"Neither of you?"</p> 
               <p>"No, mem; both our governors died of drink long ago, and some says our mothers went of the trouble; and we lives in the street, and we're both pretty nigh froze and starved."</p> 
               <p>Possibly nothing short of the immense fright Yellowtop had received at seeing what seemed the dead face of Tarbox before him, could have knocked such an expression of truth out of Yellowtop. But out it came as if a death-bed confession. Do you wonder? Was not the child more than half dead?</p> 
               <p>Melouie Thome-it was no other-for a moment forgot her lady-like sphere, and, stepping up to the policeman, inquired:-</p> 
               <p>"Is the boy dangerously hurt, sir?"</p> 
               <p>"I think not, miss; only stunned. He'll be all right as soon as he comes to, and will be off like a quail just out of its shell. He's a regular case. I know him. He'll be stealing the supper off somebody's table before their eyes before sundown. Can't kill such a chap as that."</p> 
               <p>Just then Edward Willard gasped, opened his eyes, and struggled to escape from the policeman, but staggered and fainted, and again fell back.</p> 
               <p>Melonie beckoned to a hackman passing who reined up to the pavement.</p> 
               <p>"Take these two boys in, and drive us to No -- street, as soon as possible."</p> 
               <p>"But, miss, excuse me. I will see to this case," said the policeman.</p> 
               <p>"Excuse me, sir," replied the young lady springing into the coach. "Lay that wounded boy on this buffalo. Jump in," said she to the half-naked figure who was pulling his rags about him; and Yellowtop obeyed. "Drive on."</p> 
               <p>The coachman mounted his seat, and away whirled his carriage, the horses' feet striking fire from the ice at every bound.</p> 
               <p>"She shall pay for this," he muttered, as he brought his gloved hands together to keep them from freezing.</p> 
               <p>Once inside the carriage, tumbling over the stones, Tarbox breathed again. Melonie tied<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC6500-00000047"/> up his head with her scarf, rolled the two boys in the furs and knee-blankets, and at last, in her solitude, took no note of time until they drew up at her school-room door.</p> 
               <p>The two boys were taken out, ushered into the warm, glowing kitchen, the driver paid his exorbitant fare without a word of remonstrance, and then Melonie, throwing off her hat and furs, addressed herself to her duty. The wounded boy was now fully conscious, and looked about in strange bewilderment.</p> 
               <p>"Lie still," said Melouie, with authority, as she covered him warmly and put his bleeding head upon a pillow on the sofa.</p> 
               <p>"Tom, go for Dr. Price." A coat was wrapped round Yellowtop. "Margery, take off those old boots, and put his feet in a bucket of cold water; the boy is nearly frozen."</p> 
               <p>We need not follow Melonie Thorne through all the minutiae of that afternoon's rescue. At nightfall Tarbox and Yellowtop found themselves in a neat, clean chamber in the attic of the school-house, well-fed, clean and comfortable, brushed and dressed, wondering how it all came about; for Yellowtop bad fainted long before he was removed, and Dr. Price asserted that one hour more upon the street would, in all probability, have given the local reporter the next morning an item running thus: "Froze to death; found dead. Two boys, usually known as Yellow-top and Tarbox, vagabonds about town," etc.; and then would, in all probability, have followed a comment on the necessity of a home for such children, which everybody will admit as true, and nobody put in practice, said the sententious doctor, as, late in the evening, he came in to look after his patients.</p> 
               <p>"Come, Miss Melonie, let's see what we have got. If they turn out pretty bright, we must take care of them; if not, let 'em go when morning comes." And, lamp in hand, the Charity Doctor, as he was called, ascended to their chamber, followed by the fair young girl. Fast asleep lay the two.</p> 
               <p>"Handsome chaps, both of them," said the doctor, after a moment's examination; "pretty nigh starved, though. Don't feed them too much, Miss Melonie. Isn't this golden-haired fellow a beauty? See what a classic face-that clear-cut line-that nose has<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC6500-00000048"/> power in it. This one is a genius. It staggers a man's faith, Miss Thorne, to look at such boys as these, and remember they are vagabonds."</p> 
               <p>"Our faith in man, not in God," answered Melonie, with that clear, penetrating voice of hers that always carried conviction in its tone.</p> 
               <p>"Right, miss, right! What would this world be without women's enduring faith and tender love?"</p> 
               <p>Tears stood in the old doctor's eyes, and were likely to dim his sight, so he brushed them away hastily and started for the door.</p> 
               <p>"Don't feed 'em too much. Look out for 'em, or they'll be off before you're up, and with all your blankets, if you don't watch. Good-night! Good-night! If ever there were angels of mercy, you're one of 'em." And the doctor bowed himself downstairs.</p> 
               <p>Melonie was alone with the waifs God had drifted into her hands. How mildly they slept! Were there deep sin-stains upon their young souls? If so, whose fault was it? "Both our fathers died drunkards, and mothers went of trouble." "Poor, dear boys!" sighed Melonie. "They shall have a home, and, if not fathers and mothers, friends."</p> 
               <p>And, kneeling by the bedside, she prayed for them, that they might be made as brands snatched from the burning, and saved for the higher and nobler life. And, rising from her knees, she descended to the kitchen, leaving the children in charge of Margery and Thomas, with strict injunctions not to allow them to leave in the morning without her seeing them, and, weary with her day of excitement and fatigue, she soon retired and was at rest. On the morrow she sought her charges at early breakfast time.</p> 
               <p>The black-head (as Tom called Edgar) had been restless and moaned some, and the other had wakened and cried with his feet before morning. Both invalids had frozen feet, and had no desire to leave such comfortable quarters. They were boys of fourteen years of age, had been "knocking about," as they expressed it, for years, sometimes in the House of Correction, once or twice at reform schools; everywhere subject to abuse, everywhere wicked, but always<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC6500-00000049"/> keeping soul and body together until this terrible winter. They had not known each other long, and only the night before had they come to the awful extremity. The deep snow had covered the garbage, the cold had chilled and benumbed them. Melonie had found them, and had saved them. Tarbox and Yellowtop became the Edward Willard and William Saxton, of whom Miss Thorne spoke in our last chapter.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
                
               <head>X.</head> 
               <p>"STOP, stop!" shrieked out Aunt Jerusha, as she seized the hand of Kathleen, who was striking her right palm with unnecessary force on the bottom of the pepper-box, and sprinkling the pile of nicely-browned buckwheat cakes, instead of the steak that stood beside them.</p> 
               <p>"Whatever has got into you, Kathleen? Yesterday, what should you do but put the cream into the teapot, and now you are peppering the cakes." And Aunt Cynthia stood transfixed with horror.</p> 
               <p>"Och, ohone! och, ohone! It's gone daft I am, Miss Cynthia. It's meself that's not fit to be doing the likes of this at all." And Kathleen crossed her hands on Aunt Cynthia's shoulder, and, laying her head upon them, burst into a fit of weeping and sobbing that well-nigh sent the house-keeper daft with her.</p> 
               <pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC6500-00000050"/> 
               <p>"What is the matter, Kathleen? Why, me, me, me! Don't, now! I never saw you this way before. Come, now, child! Uncle Simon is waiting. And the cakes are burned as black as the stove.5' And the good woman sprang from the sobbing Kathleen to the griddle; while the latter, left standing alone, dried her eyes and choked down her sobs, and went deliberately to throw away the spoiled cakes, followed closely by the elder matron with the burned ones. Kathleen was first to speak.</p> 
               <p>"Let me be putting the breakfast before them now, Miss Cynthia, and I'll be telling yez all about it when it's fitting. My heart is almost broken."</p> 
               <p>And so the breakfast was carried in, and the bell rang, and Kathleen performed her duty as if no sorrow lay at her heart. All day long the two women worked on together with subdued and quiet thoughts. There was no more weeping, no more jokes, no more laughter. Kathleen's usually bright and happy face-and it was a handsome face, too, now that good habits and pleasant thoughts were wearing out the deforming lines of the past-wore a deep and very unusual shadow of care and trouble.</p> 
               <p>"Whatever can it be?" Aunt Cynthia asked herself again and again as the day wore away. "It must be something serious to make her act so."</p> 
               <p>"Why didn't I think of it before? It's just because Miss Gertie's going to be married next week. Me, me, me! but it will be lonesome here without her, when she and Miss Mell both go off to Europe, and her mother getting so kind of queer and nervous. How she did cry t'other day when she told me about it, and all about Kathleen's going to take care of Miss Mell's school while she was gone, and-what shall I do without Kathleen? Me, me, me! I never! thought of that."</p> 
               <p>And now the good nurse found it her turn to cry; and, slipping into the little room where she spent her evenings with Kathleen when their work was done, she sat down by the grate to indulge herself in a little season of sadness and sorrowing.</p> 
               <p>Kathleen came in presently, and found her, with her apron over her head, sobbing<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC6500-00000051"/> as violently as she herself had done in the morning.</p> 
               <p>"What is it now. Miss Cynthia? Sure, I've come to yez this blessed night for comfort from the black trouble that's been breaking my heart all the day, and ye're worse off than meself. Tell me, now, what is it?"</p> 
               <p>"O me, me! Kathleen, I never thought about it till this evening, as sure as I sit here. I just thought all the time it was so nice to have Beau and the Lieutenant, as Uncle Simon calls our Harry, both a-coming, and then such a nice wedding, and they all a-going off over the sea. I thought it would all be so grand, and I was so glad that you was going to be the lady over at The Elms, and take care of Miss Melonie's nice boys and girls, and Uncle Simon going to put Willie Saxton and Ed Willard to school, and they such nice chaps too. Me, me, me! you see I never thought how I was going to be left alone, and you gone, and everything. I don't wonder you cried to think of it. I can't bear it neither."</p> 
               <p>All this had not been said without many a sob; but, at the end, she broke out more sadly disconsolate than before.</p> 
               <p>Kathleen saw at a glance the drift of her woe, and waited a moment for its intensity to pass. Then, seating herself beside her friend, and resting her elbow on the table, and her head in her hand, she said, at length:-</p> 
               <p>"Miss Cynthia, it's very different things you and me cries about. Sure I hate to part with them; but it's worse than that that's putting out the light of Kathleen's eyes, you may be sure."</p> 
               <p>Her deep and solemn tone, the almost entire freedom of her speech from the brogue she was fast learning to suppress, seemed at once to calm Aunt Cynthia's grief; and, drawing down her apron and wiping her eyes vigorously, she cleared her throat and managed to say:-</p> 
               <p>"Kathleen, what is it?"</p> 
               <p>"Aunt Cynthia" (Kathleen forgot the Miss), but she could go no further, and there was a dead silence. Then again she essayed: "Aunt Cynthia, it's you sits at the table with them every day, and sees what is going on." She paused.</p> 
               <pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC6500-00000052"/> 
               <p>"To be sure I sit at table. Why shouldn't I? I am of just as good a family as any of them, and better too, for that matter. It would be very mean if I didn't sit at their table, and when it copies that I can't I'll go. Me, me, me! what are things coming to?"</p> 
               <p>"Sure for you, Aunt Cynthia, how you go off! It's not that at all. It's going to ask you, I am, if you see anything queer these days about Miss Gertie?"</p> 
               <p>"About Miss Gertie?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, now, about Miss Gertie."</p> 
               <p>The matron lifted her spectacles to her reverence bump, turned her full-frilled cap-border away from her jet-black wig, and looked out of her tear-swollen red eyes in wild affright at Kathleen.</p> 
               <p>"About my darling Miss Gertie! You don't think, now, she is getting consumption or anything? Don't tell me anything like that!"</p> 
               <p>"Consumption, is it?" exclaimed Kathleen, with an indignant flush. "If it was only that."</p> 
               <p>"Only that! She haint got diphtheria, now? O me, me! if anything happens to that child, my old heart will break."</p> 
               <p>"It's taking the wine she is again," said Kathleen, springing to her feet, and bringing the startling secret to Miss Cynthia's ears in a hissing whisper that told how terrible the secret had been to her heart, and how like strain beyond her strength was this effort to relieve her mind of its burden.</p> 
               <p>"Is that all to scare a body about so?" And the idol-worshipper, as Aunt Cynthia might have been called, relieved of the startling apprehensions which the tortured expression of Kathleen's face produced, seemed now to become vexed, and, settling back in her chair, she demanded of the excited girl before her, in an authoritative voice:-</p> 
               <p>"What of it?"</p> 
               <p>"Is it of me ye are asking 'What of it?' Meself that ye picked up out of the clutch of Satan, and brought back into this beautiful world under the blessing,-me that has taken the vow that I'll never taste it, never, never, never! And didn't she do the same after that awful night? Och! it angers me, and grieves me, Aunt Cynthia, to hear ye<pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC6500-00000053"/> asking as if the soul of her was nothing,-not the value of a straw,-and the body was all of her; and she promised me that very night, with her head on my bosom, that she'd never, no, never, touch it more. And ye ask ' What of it?' Och! when ye see her past herself, when she goes out on the street with bloated face and red eyes, when she travels among the police-Och! Miss Cynthia, in them days, neither ye nor Mrs. Manning nor Uncle Simon will be sitting asking 'What of it?' The very hearts of ye will die in your living bodies for grief of her,-the kindest and best,-and the drink making a beast of her entirely."</p> 
               <p>"Shut up, now!" exclaimed the indignant nurse, "or I'll go straight and tell Mrs. Manning the very words you say. Do you think we are going to have you-you-Kathleen-talking such things about Miss Gertie, and she just going to be married to the nicest and handsomest man in the land?"</p> 
               <p>"Och! Miss Cynthia, don't be vexed now, because I spoke the truth to you," answered Kathleen, starting up, proudly and resolutely confronting the old house-keeper. Her eyes flashed,-those great, round, blue eyes, in whose depth there lay a mighty power yet undeveloped: a power growing and striving, as yet half awake; in itself, when once aroused, capable of performing deeds of strength, but waiting, like a huge mastiff, the need and the call, to attack the direst enemy. Kathleen was tall and graceful; her form a model for a sculptor's chisel; her complexion as fair as Miss Gertie's; hardened a little by exposure, yet still the envy of the would-be belles and beauties who met her on the streets and in the market, and sighed that nature should have made such a sad mistake as to give such eyes and complexion, such teeth, and such magnificent auburn hair, lying in wavy bands and heavy braids about her face, to an ignorant servant-girl.</p> 
               <p>As Kathleen stood in her plain, neatly fitting calico wrapper, her cheeks glowing with the excitement of her own daring, and the indignation caused by the words of her companion, she was superbly beautiful.</p> 
               <p>Matters had now come to a crisis, in that little basement sitting-room, between the two presiding powers. It was the first quarrel or<pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC6500-00000054"/> disagreement; and Kathleen, with her earnest convictions of right, her deep love for, her young mistress, and gratitude to her for her own salvation, having now given utterance to the appalling fact that had been opening to her for months, could not recede. She must go on.</p> 
               <p>"Yes, it's to be married she is; and oh! the black sorrow of that if this other goes on. Married, as you say, to the nicest and handsomest man in the land. Tie is all that, and more. He is sober, and a Christian, which is far better than being beautiful or having money.</p> 
               <p>"What'll he be taking in his loving arms, when he comes from his long journey? It's God's living truth I am telling ye this night. It's six years this very night since Miss Gertie found me dying upon the street,-do you think it's for the like of Kathleen to forget? And this very night, Miss Cynthia, now, now while you are telling me not to speak, the beautiful creature, that I love more than any but my God above, lies moaning there from the very same reason that she did the day after her birthday party.</p> 
                
               <p>"It's meself, Miss Cynthia, that braids her hair. It's meself that fastens her brooch. It's meself that hooks and buttons her dresses; and it's meself that has watched with grieving and weeping, for six months or more, the bad that was coming. Night after night she comes home as no lady should, with her eyes all alight and her tongue a-running. Och! Aunt Cynthia, should you or her mother hear the words she says, sure you would not be keeping still.</p> 
               <p>"Last night it came to the worst, and I spoke to her, and then she struck and cursed me. Swore-och! yes, she swore-she would drink as she pleased; and then she rushed to the bureau and took out the brandy before my very eyes, and drank it clear from the bottle, and laughed and sang, and it was only when she grew stupid like that I got her to bed; and this whole blessed day she has not been up.</p> 
               <p>"Do you bid me 'Shut up!' now? Do you wonder I put the cream in the teapot, or the pepper on the cakes? O God! help me! I would die for the darling-but to see her so-"</p> 
               <pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC6500-00000055"/> 
               <p>Aunt Cynthia could bear no more. Lifting her hands above her head, with a wild shriek, the poor old nurse fell to the floor.</p> 
               <p>Kathleen sprang to her, and, lifting her up, laid her upon the lounge in the position she had heard was best for a swoon; then, dashing a cup of cold water in her face, the good woman soon opened her eyes, and came back to her new-found sorrow.</p> 
               <p>Rubbing her hands, wiping the water from her face, cooing over her like a dove to its brood, this young girl controlled her own frightened nerves until she had restored Aunt Cynthia to full consciousness. To have rung for help, to have summoned Mrs. Manning or Uncle Simon, or the other servants, would, in all probability, have disclosed the secret which Kathleen was not yet ready to trust beyond the care of the loving heart of the old nurse and house-keeper, who seemed as near to Miss Gertie as her mother.</p> 
               <p>Aunt Cynthia came out of her faint, calm, but stricken as with a palsy.</p> 
               <p>"O Kathleen! have I been dreaming? Did you tell me my darling baby, my child, swore, and cursed and struck you, and drank brandy? Did you tell me, or have I dreamed it?"</p> 
               <p>She did not raise her head or lift a finger, but looked up with eyes in whose expression lay immeasurable depths of woe. Kathleen stooped and kissed her.</p> 
               <p>"You fainted, Aunt Cynthia, dear, while I was telling you. But don't take it too much to heart. It's the truth; and I was telling you that we two might plan a way to make it better. There, now, don't greet." And she laid her white, beautifully formed hand on the wrinkled brow, and smoothed back the silvery hair, from which the wig and cap had fallen.</p> 
               <p>Her kind words and gentle ways seemed to soothe; and, without moving, Aunt Cynthia closed her eyes, and seemed to sleep while Kathleen sat beside her in silence.</p> 
               <p>"We must tell Uncle Simon. Why didn't we think of that before?" she said, after an hour's quiet, speaking in a low voice, as if not a moment had elapsed since the terrible disclosure had been made. Then wearily opened her eyes, whispered her oft-repeated, "Me, me, me!" and, rising to her feet, went<pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC6500-00000056"/> deliberately across the room, and, putting her lips to the tube communicating with the library, called, "Mr. Eliot!" Applying her ear, the answer came:-</p> 
               <p>"Here."</p> 
               <p>"Kathleen and I wish to speak with you. Shall we come to you, or will you come to us?"</p> 
               <p>"I will come to you."</p> 
               <p>So long had Aunt Cynthia been one of the household,-back to the days when' Uncle Simon was a boy; back to the days of his poverty and struggles; back to the days when she was the companion and friend of his hard-working and care-worn mother,-that she occupied almost the place of a mother to all in the household, and Uncle Simon never demanded of her to take a step beyond her own wish and will.</p> 
               <p>Dropping his pen and pushing aside his papers, he was with the women in their sitting-room, before Kathleen had found time to remonstrate, or suggest any other course of action.</p> 
               <p>"Good-night, Aunt Cynthia! What's up?" said he, carelessly, as he swung himself self in and turned to close the door. "Water-pipes out of gear? Stove-plates burned out? Jack on a spree? or is the house to be pulled down and made over again?" And, advancing to the middle of the room, he fixed his eyes first upon one woman, then upon the other.</p> 
               <p>"Good heavens! what is the matter?" he exclaimed, as he caught the expression of their faces.</p> 
               <p>"Mr. Eliot," said Kathleen.</p> 
               <p>"Mr. Eliot! What's got the woman? Am I not Uncle Simon any more? You look like two dead folks standing there. What is it? What has happened?"</p> 
               <p>"And please, Uncle Simon, will you take a seat?" asked Kathleen, from whose cheek all the rose had fled, but to whose tongue the servant brogue returned in the presence of her employer.</p> 
               <p>"Sure, it's a sad tale we'll have to be telling ye, since Miss Cynthia has called ye. It's Miss Gertie, sir, we've been talking about. She is falling into bad ways, the darling."</p> 
               <p>"Bad ways! Our Gertie! My beautiful child! You cannot with truth say anything bad of her. What do you mean, girl?"</p> 
               <pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC6500-00000057"/> 
               <p>"Och! sir, it was a sad thing when ye coaxed her to drink the wine at your table, and tempted her into the taste and love of it; and now, sir, it goes beyont-"</p> 
               <p>The blood rushed up to Uncle Simon's temples. He stood as one confounded, struck dumb for an instant; then, bringing his clinched fists down on the table, and speaking in a voice of thunder, he exclaimed:-</p> 
               <p>"Woman, what do you mean? Speak out!"</p> 
               <p>"I mean, sir," and Kathleen blanched whiter and whiter, "that Miss Gertie gets drunk; and is, this very hour, in her room, not able to get up, from the wine and brandy she drank last night at the great party.</p> 
               <p>"I've spoken, sir, and I've spoken the truth. Turn me out of your house, do with me as you will, but save Miss Gertie!"</p> 
               <p>Simon Eliot staggered back with a groan, as if stricken by some powerful blow, and, covering his eyes with his hands, he cried out:-</p> 
               <p>"My God! My God! how blind I have been! I see it all now,-why she refuses to sit on my knee, why she escapes my kisses, why I am losing the love of my child. O Kathleen, Kathleen! why did you not come to me before?"</p> 
               <p>"Sure, sir, how could I bring this trouble to you?" answered the maiden, with a voice soft and gentle, and full of loving pity.</p> 
               <p>The strong man rose and gave a hand to each.</p> 
               <p>"Watch her, Kathleen. Let me think tonight. Aunt Cynthia, go to rest, my good friend. It is not yet too late to save her. Say nothing until I see you to-morrow. Good-night!" And he passed from the sitting-room of his servants to his own gorgeous apartments, in a state bordering on distraction.</p> 
               <p>He saw it all-all! How blind he had been! How the habits of his house had been doing their work! Another truth flashed upon him,-Mrs. Manning! Was not she, too, tarrying too long at the wine? Now he remembered strange scenes, and her constant evening headaches, her weak eyes, her exclusion from society, her apparent want of care for Gertie, her petulance, so unlike her m other and younger years.</p> 
               <p>The revelation made by Kathleen had<pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC6500-00000058"/> fallen like a thunderbolt. What was to be done?</p> 
               <p>Hour after hour he paced the spacious library with a woe he had not known since the blight fell upon his young heart long ago. Had not he himself put the cap to lips he so loved? Had he not laughed down scruples and sneered at arguments? Had he not perverted the word of God, and said, "Take a little wine for your stomach's sake, and your often infirmities," heedless of the solemn warning, "Wine is a mocker, and strong drink is raging, and he that is deceived thereby is not wise"? If two-two of the purest and best that knelt at his household altar, and offered with him, at morn and eve, their prayer to God, "Lead us not into temptation "-had fallen under his very eye, and he so blind as not to see it, might not others have been led into the forbidden paths? And, as he thought, he remembered Harry, his darling boy: how freely he poured the wine when last at home; how jolly, piquant, and agreeable he became at the late dinners; how reticent, almost morose, and often late at breakfast. Then he remembered the extravagant agant bills sent in under the plea of expenses in India. And then the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">blas</foreign> style in which some of his last letters had been written; and he groaned and walked, and walked and groaned, until the daylight illuminated the apartment.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC6500-00000059"/> 
               <head>XI.</head> 
               <p>IT was Uncle Simon's custom to breakfast with his family. Aunt Cynthia had for quite a number of years occupied a seat at his left hand, while his only sister sat opposite him, dispensing the good gifts of the coffee and tea urns.</p> 
               <p>Kindred, friends, strangers, business men, often spent days in his house. It was one of the delights of his life to entertain those whose companionship he enjoyed. After breakfast the family would repair to the library, and join in family worship.</p> 
               <p>Kathleen, through her faithfulness and gentle ways, had grown into great favor with all; and, as years fell upon the head of the old house-keeper, almost unconsciously she had allowed Kathleen to take the weight of all responsibilities upon her strong, young shoulders, while she still believed, as old people are apt to do, that without her presence ence all would go wrong, that she was still the pendulum of the great family clock that kept the machinery in motion. Kathleen never disturbed the satisfying thought. Why should she?</p> 
               <p>The most unkind thing that can be done to those whose footsteps are walking toward the sunset is to force upon them the conviction of uselessness. In every part of that mansion, the earnest industry and care of Aunt Cynthia's past years of strength and activity had given out their healthful glow. Every member of the regular household loved her, and all came to her in their troubles.</p> 
               <p>Kathleen relieved her cares without withdrawing one beam of kindly affection. In fact, she seemed the Penate of the household. She had never sat at meals with the family, and for the last two years had been excused from waiting upon the table. As maid to Miss Gertie, as one to be called on in all emergencies, as manager of the departments, she was loved and trusted, but yet, in other respects, fully occupied the place of a servant.</p> 
               <pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC6500-00000060"/> 
               <p>Melonie's time being taken up by her self-assumed cares, she spent but few days now with her friend and her godfather; but she had been instructing Kathleen with great zeal for the last two years, and her efforts had been warmly met and appreciated by the ambitious girl.</p> 
               <p>Harry and Beau had been gone two years. Mrs. Thorne went from home less and less. Gertie had been much away. Her large circle of friends-for beauty and wealth, hollow though they may be, always attract them-drew her for weeks at a time away from the elegant home that Uncle Simon called hers. Mrs. Manning, more engrossed in her love for Harry than for her daughter, found solace for his absence in her round of fashionable calls, and in her deep devotion to her circles and charities; while Uncle Simon, more and more absorbed in the great thoughts and inventions of the time, was unconscious of the changes going on.</p> 
               <p>He lunched at Taylor's, and dined at home at half-past seven. If the ladies went out, he sometimes attended them; but more frequently enjoyed the society of his friends in the library, or an occasional <foreign xml:lang="FRA">fte</foreign> in the parlors.</p> 
               <p>Kathleen had aroused him, as from a dream, to a frightful reality. He compassed the whole at a glance. No wonder that all night he paced his library. Slowly, imperceptibly, had the serpent been creeping into his paradise, and with throes of agony he asked himself again and again luring that long, horrible night:-</p> 
               <p>"How many souls have I been the means of ruining?"</p> 
               <p>"Woe, woe unto him that putteth the cup to his neighbor's lips!" rang in his ears. How many hundred young men he had treated to wine at his restaurant lunches,-young men who had said:-</p> 
               <p>"Excuse me, sir. I am not in the habit of taking wine."</p> 
               <p>Yet, when he had pressed them, and laughed at the scruples implanted by good mothers, and affirmed that temperance consisted in moderation, not in total abstinence, or any other fanaticism, and cited his own hale and hearty condition as proof of his own theories, they had yielded to his persuasions, and put<pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC6500-00000061"/> an enemy into their mouths to steal away their brains.</p> 
               <p>His great, searching, closely scanning mind, now that it was turned into this channel, saw as clearly how one wrong begets another, moving out into wider and wider circles, as it could comprehend the force of levers, pulleys, and cams. In the loneliness of his night-walk, he resolved from that hour henceforth to give his aid to the temperance reform, and to begin from that day a new system in his own life; for, after all, was it only others that had been wronged? The question startled him anew.</p> 
               <p>"I, too, am a victim!" he exclaimed. "I am so wedded to my wine that even I feel the want,-ay, and indulge that want when I am weary and perplexed. Only yesterday I left my work to treat myself, and by so doing was led to treat that young man from the West, who told me he had once taken the pledge.</p> 
               <p>"From this hour I will abstain from all that will intoxicate," was the solemn vow of his heart in the presence of God; and, as he had knelt two years before, when Melonie's warning had so stirred him, he knelt again, and prayed for strength to keep that vow.</p> 
               <p>When the breakfast-bell, rang, he answered the summons in his usual ready manner, with a pale and weary, but resolute face.</p> 
               <p>The breakfast-room was deserted. He seated himself as usual, and leaned his head upon his hand, awaiting his sister and niece; but they came not. The servant brought him his coffee.</p> 
               <p>"Send Kathleen to me, Bridget," said he, without lifting his eyes.</p> 
               <p>She came in a moment, asking her master's wish.</p> 
               <p>Mr. Eliot raised his forehead out of his palms, and looked up with a start, as if her voice had frightened him.</p> 
               <p>"Where is Mrs. Manning?"</p> 
               <p>"She is not well this morning, sir."</p> 
               <p>"And Miss Gertie?"</p> 
               <p>It is asking to be excused she is, sir."</p> 
               <p>It was strange, but Mr. Eliot's voice had a power to make Kathleen forget herself and the ways of her people, save when he spoke of Gertie. Then the old tide of love, all the tenderness of her child-life came rushing<pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC6500-00000062"/> back, as if the sluice-ways of the years when she had first known and loved her had been opened, and the old brogue dropped all unexpected from her tongue.</p> 
               <p>"And what is the matter with Aunt Cynthia?"</p> 
               <p>"Nothing at all, sir; but she was wakeful all night, and is not yet up."</p> 
               <p>Mr. Eliot asked no more questions, pushed his coffee from him, left his plate unturned, and quitted the table. As he was leaving the room, he said, in a husky voice:-</p> 
               <p>"Kathleen, say to my sister, to my niece, and to Aunt Cynthia, I wish to meet them all at dinner."</p> 
               <p>Without looking back or showing his haggard face to his servant, he passed into the street, a weary, heart-sore man.</p> 
               <p>After he had left the two women the night before, no words had passed between them upon the subject that was such a sore distress to both.</p> 
               <p>"I am so tired!" sighed Aunt Cynthia. "Me, me, me!"</p> 
               <p>"Let me help you, Miss Cynthia." And Kathleen put her arm around the stricken woman, and led her to her chamber, and, after seeing her snugly in her bed, kissed her goodnight, and went back to Gertie, whom she found searching in the bureau for the brandy which she had revealed to Kathleen the night before. It was not there. Not yet sufficiently recovered from her last night's debauch to feel her own position, or shrink, as she would have done a few hours later, she accosted Kathleen angrily:-</p> 
               <p>"Have you been to this bureau?"</p> 
               <p>"I have, thin, Miss Gertie, dear."</p> 
               <p>"And you've been after my brandy that the doctor ordered me to use for my nerves."</p> 
               <p>"Miss Gertie, dear-"</p> 
               <p>"None of your dealing me! You're breaking your pledge. You're taking to your old ways. That is the reason my bell was not answered last night. Now, Miss Kathleen, you,-I vow, if you don't behave yourself, out of this house you go, bag and baggage."</p> 
               <p>The poor, trembling creature sank again on the bed, and burst into hysterical weeping and wailing.</p> 
               <p>Kathleen knelt by the bed, and, putting her arm over her, soothing her gently:-</p> 
               <pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC6500-00000063"/> 
               <p>"It's sick ye is, my pet. There then, let Kathleen comfort ye. Och! but it's the awful headaches ye have, sure now."</p> 
               <p>Gertie's shallow emotion, the result of over-excitement and exhaustion, soon found vent, and, as she became quiet again, she fell into a doze, and Kathleen ran down to the kitchen, prepared and brought up some coffee and steak. She had eaten nothing for twenty-four hours. Roused by Kathleen, and quieted by her manner, she began to recollect herself, drank her coffee, and ate as if nearly famished; then slept till morning. In the morning, while Kathleen was assisting her to dress, she was silently planning to got out and gratify her craving for brandy. This Kathleen resolved she should not do.</p> 
               <p>At last her toilet was completed and she spoke:-</p> 
               <p>"Kathleen, how is mother?"</p> 
               <p>"It's poorly she is, indeed."</p> 
               <p>"What's the matter?"</p> 
               <p>"The same as ails yourself, darling."</p> 
               <p>"Nervous headache?"</p> 
               <p>"Just such as you have yourself, Miss Gertie, and from the same cause."</p> 
                
               <p>"What do you mean?"</p> 
               <p>"Don't get angry, darling. It was myself that saved you once, and I'll do it again, with God's help. Miss Gertie, 'tis the late parties, the wine and brandy, that's killing you both. Och! my pet, that I should have to say it, and you to be married in ten days,-and you,-it's truth I'm speaking to you,-you was drunk last night, and cursed me, and tore my hair, and scratched me here. See the prints of your nails. Shall I tell <emph>him?</emph>" she added, slowly.</p> 
               <p>"O merciful God!" exclaimed Gertie, and, before Kathleen could prevent her, she had fallen on her knees at the feet of her maid, in the wildest affright and desperation.</p> 
               <p>"Kathleen, don't tell him! For the love of Heaven, don't tell him! O Beau, Beau, my darling Beau! Only a week and he will be here, and see what I am. O Kathleen! my red eyes! my bloated face! What shall I do? Yes, I was drunk. That awful wine! I will never touch it again, never, never, never!" And with wild, hysterical sobs this poor child of affluence and indulgence moaned again in the arms of her faithful attendant.</p> 
               <pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC6500-00000064"/> 
               <p>Gertrude Manning had been running a wild career for a few months. The watering-places had exhausted their resources for her enjoyment. Constant open-air exercise, sea-bathing, horseback riding, evening dances, boat-rowing, climbing mountains, roaming forests, all out-door sports, had kept the glow of health upon her cheeks, and screened from the casual observer the effects of the growing habit of wine-drinking.</p> 
               <p>Her wonderful beauty, enhanced by her wonderful health, strength, and courage, united to an entire independence of character and scorn of all conventionalisms, drew around her a crowd of admirers that almost worshipped her. Loving Beaumont Fletcher with the entire devotion of her noble, womanly nature, she let it be fully understood that she was his affianced bride, and thus saved herself from all unpleasant importunities.</p> 
               <p>On, on, on, in her wild career, she had gone without a thought or fear. She read and studied, met in social intercourse with gentlemen of the highest culture, constantly improving her mental powers, and adding to her literary resources. Her letters to Beau were freighted with a wealth of description of the rich, varied life she was living, and assurances of her truth to him.</p> 
               <p>But her habit of drinking wine was gaining strength with each day of indulgence, as it is sure to do in nine cases in ten, slowly undermining all these foundations of purity and beauty; and when she returned to the city, late in the season, to commence preparations for her marriage and a year's absence in Europe, life seemed suddenly vapid and dull, and unconsciously she sipped more and more whenever she felt weary and dispirited.</p> 
               <p>Her mother, too, seemed estranged and very fretful, especially in the morning hours of family intercourse. Dear Cousin Mell was so busy, and Uncle Simon's head, she declared, was so full of cogs and wheels and pulleys and piston-rods, there was not room for a bit of common sense in it.</p> 
               <p>She grew ill; felt nervously prostrate and weak; was advised to take small doses of brandy three times a day, and did it, nothing loath.</p> 
               <pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC6500-00000065"/> 
               <p>Need we follow her further? 'Tis the oft-told tale of the fate that has overtaken millions in the long years of the past, millions of the brightest and best.</p> 
               <p>The fate of Mrs. Manning differed in degree, not in kind. It had taken a decade of years to do for her what a half-one had done for her child, and both were now approaching the culminating point of ruin and disgrace. The active mind of Gertie, now aroused by the sharp, blunt words of her maid, took in at once the whole horrible picture. Only one week until her marriage-Beau expected every hour. No wonder she cried out in despair:-</p> 
               <p>"What shall I do? O Kathleen! Kathleen! what shall I do?"</p> 
               <p>And why had not Kathleen spoken sooner?</p> 
               <p>Because she had never before fully realized the condition of her mistress. Gertie had been sly; often stolen to her brandy-bottle to quiet her nerves after the faithful Kathleen had gone to bed; waited more upon herself, as she had done in her journeyings, and kept herself more aloof from her uncle. She was ever half conscious of her wrong, but ever half bewildered by her wines and brandies, and without power to act. She had had neither wine nor brandy for a day and a half,-Kathleen had hid it all,-and now, faint as she was, she was enabled to think.</p> 
               <p>Kathleen let the sobbing have its way, and, when her charge grew calm, said softly in her ears, as she passed her hands over her head, smoothing out the masses of rich, tangled hair, and thereby infusing somewhat of her own healthy magnetism:-</p> 
               <p>"There, darlint, don't cry any more now."</p> 
               <p>"Oh, tell me, Kathleen, what shall I do?"</p> 
               <p>"Get up and bathe your face in clear, cold water, and then lie down and rest, and we will think. Uncle Simon wishes you all to meet him at dinner. He did not eat one bit of breakfast. It's breaking his heart yez all are. It made my own tears run to see him there at the beautiful table all alone."</p> 
               <p>"I will do as you say; but, Kathleen, promise me you will not tell Beau. Oh, what if he should come? Promise me, prom<pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC6500-00000066"/> ise me! I will say I am sick. Will you say I am sick?"</p> 
               <p>"Miss Gertie, is it yourself that's asking me to <emph>lie?</emph>" answered Kathleen, proudly rising.</p> 
               <p>"No, no, no! not a lie; but I am sick, sick unto death, from the crown of my head to the soles of my feet. I am sick. O Kathleen! I would give the world this minute for one drink of brandy, if it were right to take it; but for the world I would not accept it now, not if I knew I should die before nightfall. I will not ask you not to tell Beau, I will tell him myself. He shall know all, and then-then, O Kathleen! if he spurns me, you shall help me to live, or 'help me to die.'"</p> 
               <p>Kathleen put her arm around the wretched girl, and forced her to lie down, folded a wet bandage over her forehead, and sat by her, soothing and comforting her until she fell asleep.</p> 
               <p>That evening, as requested by Uncle Simon, the family met at the dinner-table. The three women and their condition I leave to be pictured by the imagination. Mr. Eliot had, in the morning, resolved to dismiss wine from his table; but on further consideration he had asked himself, "Have I any right to thus impose a rule upon others? My sister and her child are capable of deciding for themselves. To attempt compulsion might ruin all."</p> 
               <p>The dinner hour passed without its usual cheerfulness. Mrs. Manning, who knew nothing of the disclosures that had been made to the rest, tried to be merry, and in part succeeded, though the pale face of her child disturbed her.</p> 
               <p>The time came for the wine to be passed. It was refused by each of the ladies. Mrs. Manning had already learned to prefer a stronger beverage, and had made her brother believe that she did not "look upon the wine when it was red." There always comes a time when the use of strong drink involves deceit and hypocrisy.</p> 
               <p>Uncle Simon had always taken his glass boldly. Now, when it was offered him, he looked bravely in the eyes of his household, and spoke thus:-</p> 
               <p>"Sister Manning, Aunt Cynthia, and my<pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC6500-00000067"/> beloved Gertie, I want each of you to witness to-night my vow. I refuse this wine, and, before God and you, whom I love next best to him, I pledge myself to total abstinence from all that intoxicates. I leave you to your own convictions; but I will never order it upon my table again, nor have it brought to the house. I wash my hands clear of it, and, if these glasses and decanters ever appeal-before me again in this house, it will be by the command of one or the other of you three ladies.</p> 
               <p>"One week from to-day, sister Manning, will be the wedding-day of our daughter, to a man who, from childhood, has withstood all temptation. I have been blind to his and our own interests. The wedding must pass also without wines, unless you yourselves order it."</p> 
               <p>He rose, kissed his sister and niece, and went to the library. The three women looked at each other in surprised silence, and, without a word, rose from the table and went each her way.</p> 
               <p>An hour later found Gertie kneeling at the bedside of her mother, making a full confession sion of her follies, and repeating her vows of total abstinence. Mrs. Manning was not in a frame of mind to take the matter into serious consideration. The prayers and tears of her child fell upon her ear as do the pleadings of a mother upon her half-inebriate son.</p> 
               <p>"Don't take on so, Gertie! What's the use? Suppose you have taken a little too much once in your life, child,-you need not do it again. Be more careful. I am sure God intended wine to be drunk, or Christ would not have turned water into wine at the marriage feast. Your Uncle Simon is very foolish. It's always the way with him. There, go to bed, or you'll be down sick."</p> 
               <p>"O mother, mother, mother!"</p> 
               <p>"Go to bed, child, I'm tired of all this. It's ridiculous. Go at once! You'll be ashamed of all this to-morrow."</p> 
               <p>As soon as Gertie had left her, she rose and took a deep draught of brandy, and then threw herself again upon her bed.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC6500-00000068"/> 
               <head>XII.</head> 
               <p>GERTIE retired from the bedside of her mother to her own room, utterly unnerved. Her mother's harshness, and the evident cause of it, her blindness to the terrible effects of intoxicating beverages, even upon herself, filled the daughter's heart with new fears and new sorrows.</p> 
               <p>Her own misdeeds were well-nigh crushing her, now that they lay plainly before her, and, weak and almost fainting from want of stimulants, longing, ay, almost frantic with her thirst for strong drink, she could not have resisted her desire to rush to the sideboard and supply the want, but for Kathleen, who stood beside her like a guardian angel. Good and beautiful! How her new position ennobled her! By her heroism, she walked among them in a <foreign xml:lang="LAT">rara aura</foreign> that penetrated the consciousness of every one in the household.</p> 
                
               <p>"How beautiful and good you are, Kathleen!" exclaimed Gertrude, as she lay panting and quivering on the lounge in her room, while Kathleen read to her from the Testament she always carried in her pocket.</p> 
               <p>"No, Miss Gertie, darling; it's neither beautiful nor good is your poor Kathleen. Ye forget what meself was when ye first saw me." And, choking with emotion, her tears fell and blinded her, so that she could not proceed with her lesson.</p> 
               <p>"O Kathleen! you have reformed, and God has pardoned your sins. How can you still go back to them, 'and weep over them, beside such a wretch as I?"</p> 
               <p>"Miss Gertie, I feel that God, for Jesus' sake, has forgiven me; but it's meself that can never forgive; meself that knows the pain; meself that can never shed tears enough to wash out the stain that my own weakness put upon my own soul. The sears once made, darling, stay with us."</p> 
               <p>"And does it not give you peace when Father McVay forgives your sins?"</p> 
               <p>"It does not, thin, Miss Gertie; and, since ye ask me, I will spake ye the whole truth.<pb n="136-137" xml:id="VAC6500-00000069"/> I go no more to him. Not for six months have I confessed to him. It's only to the good God and the dear Jesus I confess now, since Miss Melonie has been teaching me so much. I have joined the church where she goes, up at The Elms; and I am happier now than ever I was before." Gertie covered her face, with a great sob.</p> 
               <p>"O Kathleen! what a saint Cousin Melonie is; and I so wicked-so wicked!"</p> 
               <p>Kathleen drew close to the weeping girl, and, taking both her hands in her own, led her mind from herself and all her suffering, by telling of her own life and of Ireland, with an uninterrupted flow of low, monotonous sound, that chained the attention while it soothed the nervous irritation of the poor girl until she fell asleep. The next morning she was suffering with fever, and unable to leave her room for three days after, while Mrs. Manning seemed not in the least aroused by her daughter's illness, but went out as usual, and returned, as Kathleen and Aunt Cynthia said, each day more irascible and excited.</p> 
               <p>During these few days Aunt Cynthia had grown old and bowed, and almost imbecile, and could do little but wring her hands and exclaim:-</p> 
               <p>"What are we coming to? Me, me, me! If it's the Lord's will, I'm ready to go now!"</p> 
               <p>"Not yet, Miss Cynthia; we'll be having things all right by and by. Put your trust in him. It's our Gertie, the darling, that will be strong to help us with poor mother when Mr. Beau comes."</p> 
               <p>And Beau came and found his dear Gertie an invalid, barely able to meet him with tottering steps in the parlor, pale and trembling. He was shocked; but her protestations that she was better reassured him. The crisis of her self-denial was past. She talked with him long, and fully confessed her folly, offering to release him from his obligations to her. He spurned the idea, and she then begged to postpone the wedding. It was to be a private affair, witnessed by a few friends, and then, with Harry and Melonie, they were to spend the year of Beau's furlough on the continent.</p> 
               <p>Beau folded Gertie more closely in his arms. "No, Gertie, no. I see how in your<pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC6500-00000070"/> innocence you have been tried and tempted. How, without a mother's warning, you have been led into deeper self-indulgence than was wise. We will speak of it no more. Bless you, my own Gertie, that you have told me this. I have never tasted, touched, or handled the accursed thing. The dying look and words of my mother, and the awful fate of my father, have been ever before me; and the constant, loving counsel of my foster-parents planted my feet on the rock of self-denial. Leaning hereafter, love, on my arm for protection, this will never occur again. We are already married, dearest, in heart and soul. No form of the law can make my obligation to you more sacred to my own heart, and I long to reveal it to the world, and recognize my own dear wife beyond the world's dispute or control."</p> 
               <p>Thus reassured, Gertie's strong, 'buoyant nature rallied so rapidly as to give promise that she would be as radiant as usual before the morning of the wedding-day.</p> 
               <p>As Gertie had promised Kathleen and her uncle that she would herself tell Beau of her transgression, they kept entire silence on the subject, and he supposed that her enthusiastic nature had magnified her fault, and made an unintentional mistake, caused, in part, by the physician's advice, into a fearful sin. Oh, fearful delusion!</p> 
               <p>We must not forget Harry and his affianced. One day, after the "lightning train" had brought Major Beaumont Fletcher from his regiment in the far West to the home of his adopted father, a vessel, bearing Lieutenant Manning, from his two years' cruise in the Pacific seas, sailed into New York harbor. He flew in irrepressible haste to meet his betrothed, whose heart had been tremulous with joy ever since the morning telegram had announced the in-coming ship.</p> 
               <p>"Two years on board a man-of-war, away from all woman society," so she thought of him, and so, with loving heart, she had said. "I will keep me all pure and true from every taint and passion for him, who, in his country's service, is making such self-denial."</p> 
               <p>O sweet Melonie! could you have seen the gay Harry Manning in all his vagaries on sea and shore, it would have given you many a pang. Like his sister, he had been taught<pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC6500-00000071"/> by precept and example to indulge freely in intoxicating beverages. The commander of the squadron was a rollicking old fellow, and the captains, though stern disciplinarians on shipboard, were each debauchees on shore. Harry, as has been hinted, had been living a very free and easy life. He had money without stint, for he had always with him checks on his uncle that could be cashed in any port.</p> 
               <p>Two years, from twenty-one to twenty-three, had wholly transformed him. The youthful, beardless face, always closely shaven of its downy growth, was now enveloped by a heavy, becoming beard that concealed the somewhat sensual mouth and chin from observation. The once compact figure, developed by manly exercise, began to show the flabby bloat of selfish indulgence; for Harry, if the truth must be spoken, was almost a drunkard. His puffing cheeks, the glare of his eyes, told the tale; and, though he had been striving with determination, as he thought, to restrain himself and put himself into condition to meet Melonie and hide his shame, he had only partially succeeded.</p> 
                
               <p>They met. Who shall describe that meeting? Folded in his arms, there were a few moments of delicious joy. Harry, her dear Harry, whom the twilight had not revealed, was with her again. She felt his beating heart, heard the same voice, only grown more manly, that had thrilled her since her infant years, and she was happy. Was he happy? Answer for yourself, dear reader. Happiness is not of sin.</p> 
               <p>An hour passed ere the lighted gas revealed him. With one sweep of her eyes over the face and form of Harry Manning, Melonie Thorne read her doom. The bacchanal laugh that broke out all unawares, the half-spoken, half-suppressed phrase of the club-room, the mirthful manner in which he alluded to their coming marriage,-the most solemn and sacred event of life to her,-filled her with such agonizing fear as only a nature lofty and noble as her own could ever know.</p> 
               <p>Harry quailed before her searching glance. He felt that those pure, keen eyes were reading him as an open book. Suddenly, as if shaken from a deep sleep, the blissful hopes of years glided out of sight, as a sweet dream<pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC6500-00000072"/> before awakening consciousness. He grew uneasy; they could not converse. She arose, at length, on some pretext, from her seat by his side, withdrew her hand from his, and, when she returned, took a chair at a distance from him.</p> 
               <p>"I must see my mother and Gertie," said he, rising and rallying his native manliness and gallantry. "At ten I must report on board; but after to-night, dear Mell, for one year, I shall be my own man, to report when, where, and how I please. So farewell for the night." And, stepping forward, he was about to embrace her; but she drew back, only giving him her hand, and, looking him directly in the face, she said just what she had been used to say when they were children:-</p> 
               <p>"Good-night, brother Harry. Give my love to mother and Gertie."</p> 
               <p>Harry felt the full force of the rebuke, and it stunned him. He left her without another word. He knew that he was unfit to mate with such a pure and beautiful woman as Melonie Thorne; and being, for that evening, duly sober, he left the house. The rush of feeling that passed over him when he found himself inside the carriage was maddening.</p> 
               <p>"Drive to the ship," was his command to the coachman. "No mother, no Gertie tonight. God! what have I done? Fool, fool, fool! Why didn't I know better? I may as well hoist all sail at once, and let her rip! But, I love her. Yes, I love her! And this is what you brought yourself to, Harry Manning!"</p> 
               <p>So exclaiming, so pouring out his maddened and really agonized soul as the coach rattled over the pavements of New York, and shouting to the coachman to drive faster, Harry was soon landed at the dock, and pulled by the waiting crew to his ship, where, joining a few of his companions, who had called in some old friends and were resolved to make a night of it, he soon drowned his sorrows in the brandy-bottle, and before midnight was the maddest, drunkest reveller of them all.</p> 
               <p>Beaumont Fletcher and Uncle Simon had hurried to the ship on her arrival, and had passed Harry, who in his hot haste had left the ship before she had anchored. They returned and waited for him at home.</p> 
               <pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC6500-00000073"/> 
               <p>"Oh! why don't he come?" exclaimed Gertie again and again.</p> 
               <p>"Forgotten his mother!" petulantly responded Mrs. Manning, who had appeared in the parlor that evening to await him. Better than any other living creature, Mrs. Manning loved her son. Slowly the evening wore away, and still he came not, and the grieved and disappointed mother retired to her room and drank more freely than usual of her brandy.</p> 
               <p>Beau comforted Gertie; while Kathleen had, perhaps, the hardest task of all in reconciling Aunt Cynthia to forego a sight of her darling for the night. Uncle Simon again walked his library in lonely sadness, the only one besides Melonie that had dreamed of this great sorrow that was to fall upon them.</p> 
               <p>Nights of pain and suffering as well as of pleasure come to an end, and so did this, Melonie went to her chamber, prayed fervently to God for strength to sustain her through coining trials, and lay down upon her bed to think, not to sleep.</p> 
               <p>The family met at breakfast, all disappointed again at the unexpected absence of Harry. Uncle Simon had sent the carriage early to The Elms. He was not there. Then to the ship. His servant went to call him, and returning announced to the messenger who carried Uncle Simon's note that Lieutenant Manning was dead drunk, and could not be aroused. He promised to hand him the note when he came to himself.</p> 
               <p>The servant's arrival called Uncle Simon to the library to receive his message. When he returned, he was pale with emotion; and, still standing, leaning over the back of a chair he announced the reason why Harry could not come, in a choking voice.</p> 
               <p>"My punishment is greater than I can bear. O God! be merciful to me a sinner! My Harry, our Harry, dead drunk!"</p> 
               <p>Beau caught Gertie in his arms, and was about to hurry her to the parlor, when all were attracted by the changing countenance of Mrs. Manning. She uttered a deep groan, stretched out her arms imploringly, and fell forward, without a word, into the arms of Aunt Cynthia and Kathleen, who had just entered the room.</p> 
               <p>All thought was now centred upon the wretched mother, who was laid upon the sofa<pb n="146-147" xml:id="VAC6500-00000074"/> senseless. In five minutes her heart was still forever. She was dead. Uncle Simon dried his tears,-the first he had shed for many years. Gertie rose in the strength of her grand nature to meet the emergency, and bore the shock of her mother's death with unexpected womanly firmness. Aunt Cynthia went about, pale, silent, and weeping, while faithful Kathleen, calm and collected, seemed more than ever the spirit of the household.</p> 
               <p>As soon as Uncle Simon could be spared from the house, he went again and alone for his beloved nephew; but he was not on the ship. He had gone ashore with all his baggage about noon. Driving at once to The Elms, he learned that Harry had not been seen there. The coachman was found who had been employed, and reported that he had driven the young gentleman to a steamer about to sail for Cuba. A short note to his uncle, through the post-office, came soon to tell the tale.</p> 
               <p>"Gone, gone, gone! and with him all the bright hopes of the past," exclaimed Melonie, as she read the note, which ran as follows:-</p> 
                
               <q>
                  <floatingText xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
                     <body > 
                        <div type="letter"> 
                           <p>"DEAR UNCLE SIMON:-I am an ingrate and a fool, unfit to enter the presence of my sainted mother, or pure, sweet sister. I cannot, I dare not, meet them, lest I kill their love at a glance, as I have that of my darling Melonie. If I can ever be a man again, I will come back to you; but, until I am, you will never again be annoyed by the presence of your profligate and drunken nephew,</p> 
                           <closer>
                              <signed>"HARRY MANNING.</signed>
                           </closer> 
                        </div> 
                        <div type="letter"> 
                           <p>"P. S-Do not try to track me. I will not, cannot marry Mell. She is too pure, too good.</p> 
                           <closer>
                              <signed>H. M."</signed>
                           </closer> 
                        </div> 
                     </body> 
                  </floatingText>
               </q> 
               <p>As Uncle Simon had done years before, Melonie resolved to do now,-to live for God and humanity; and, pledging herself anew to her duties, she folded her great sorrow in her heart, and arose and went her way, drawing solace from Him who alone can give strength.</p> 
               <p>The day appointed for the wedding was the day of the funeral of Mrs. Manning. Six weeks after, Gertie became the wife of Beaumont Fletcher, wedded amid a circle of household friends. Her failing health made<pb n="148-149" xml:id="VAC6500-00000075"/> Beau feel that this was best. They departed, as had been intended, for Europe. He had duties for his government that demanded his attention in London.</p> 
               <p>The household now seemed broken, the house desolate, and, at Uncle Simon's earnest request, Mrs. Thorne and Melonie came to fill the places left vacant by Gertie and her mother. The school at The Elms went on with Melonie's supervision, under the care of two excellent sisters whom she had found ready for the work.</p> 
               <p>Kathleen took her place as a beloved one in the household, and by earnest care and study gradually fitted herself to fill every position with grace and dignity.</p> 
               <p>Melonie's new life helped to blunt the keen edge of her disappointment and grief. In hospitals, homes of the friendless, in jail and prison, her ministration was seen and felt; and the liberal hand of Uncle Simon did its work more efficiently through her. Sunbeams of love and gratitude, from bruised and stricken hearts lifted up and comforted by her, fell upon her own darkened pathway, lighting and warming it, till flowers of hope and beauty in a year or two began to spring up by the wayside that had seemed so cold and dead on that expected wedding-day.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="150-151" xml:id="VAC6500-00000076"/> 
               <head>XIII.</head> 
               <p>IT is in the month of May, 1861, that we introduce our heroine, now Gertie Fletcher, to our readers,-a fair and blooming matron, with her two babes, flying, under the escort of a friend, from Fort Leaven-worth to the North for safety.</p> 
               <p>Major Fletcher cannot leave his post, and his wife goes to the home of her childhood to receive the kindly welcome of Uncle Simon, Mrs. Thorne, Melonie, and Kathleen.</p> 
               <p>Aunt Cynthia has passed away. She never ceased to moan for her beloved Harry, who has not been heard from except as he still draws upon his uncle's bankers wherever he may chance to be, for Simon Eliot's kind heart cannot deny him the privilege.</p> 
               <p>In Cuba, then in Smyrna, a year after in Rome, spending immense sums, but not to be tracked or heard of in any other way than by the bills aforesaid.</p> 
                
               <p>Willie Saxton and Edgar Willard, grown into brave, earnest young men of nineteen, were among the first to enroll themselves for the service of their country in the First New-York Volunteers,-"Tarbox and Yellow Top" no more. Oh! how grateful to God for his mercies to her was Melonie Thorne; for none more grateful than for the gift of these two precious children, these "hard cases," made "hard" by the wickedness of intemperance, and brought to her as if by a miracle.</p> 
               <p>The great, gathering army had not in its ranks two braver and truer souls than these, whose fathers "died drunk," and their mothers "from trouble." That one short sentence as to their antecedents told volumes. Women of coarse, hard, imbruted natures do not die of trouble. It is only those whose purity and love are still strong that sink to the grave under such pressure.</p> 
               <p>These tried and suffering women had perhaps given life to those boys in days of joy and gladness, ere the wily tempter had stained their husbands' lives with vice and shame.</p> 
               <p>Gertie arrived safely among her friends,<pb n="152-153" xml:id="VAC6500-00000077"/> and the merry shout of childhood rang through the half-desolated house once more, and blunted and softened even the harsher sounds of war.</p> 
               <p>Eliot was a darling little fellow, and crept into Uncle Simon's heart and nestled there so snugly that he might well have filled it full, if the country and the Union had not claimed precedence. The little Lulu laughed and crowed and made amusement for them all.</p> 
               <p>No officer in the army seemed to have a more arduous place than Major Beau, as he was familiarly called at home. Gertie's anxiety and care preyed upon her, and she grew pale and seemed to be failing. Her babe engrossed her time, and she had little strength or desire to go forth actively in the work that claimed all the leisure hours of Melonie and Kathleen. Her husband and children were all in all to her. How could she think or feel for others, with so much anxiety and care for them?</p> 
               <p>The months wore slowly away. At the battle of Shiloh, Major Fletcher was wounded, and for his gallant conduct promoted to the rank of colonel.</p> 
                
               <p>"Do not come to me," he wrote; "I shall Boon be up again. Remember, I command you to stay with the children." Had he not so often enjoined it upon her, she could not just then have left the cradle of her babe, whose life hung for weeks on the verge of the grave.</p> 
               <p>Poor Gertie! she was failing in strength and courage, and the doctor insisted she should daily take a few spoonfuls of medicated wine, which he had prepared for her. She yielded. The old overpowering taste did not leap at once into active life; but, day after day, as the sickness and watching and weariness continued, the same prescription made out was added to strengthen, and it was taken until the craving became almost insatiable.</p> 
               <p>The little one recovered, and at a year old was healthy and strong. But was the wine-bottle set aside? No. By stealth Gertie perjured her own soul. Now that the child was well, and Gertie grew rosy again, Melonie and Kathleen were away in the hospitals. Often Melonie was not at home for weeks, ever seeking out and finding the place<pb n="154-155" xml:id="VAC6500-00000078"/> of greatest need, and watching faithfully while the need continued.</p> 
               <p>Kathleen had a position on the Potomac. Thousands of our men, saved by her care, will bless her and teach their children to reverence her name.</p> 
               <p>Late in the autumn of 1862, Colonel Beaumont Fletcher came, with a wounded arm, and spent a few days with his wife and children.</p> 
               <p>"Why, Gertie, you are growing fresh and fair," he laughingly said to her. "You will soon outweigh me, and be 'fat, fair, and forty,' if you live long enough." But not a gleam of suspicion crossed his pure mind as to the cause of her altered appearance, so entirely had she deceived him as to her habits. Mrs. Thorne had suspected; but it was only suspicion; no positive evidence appeared.</p> 
               <p>As soon as his sword-arm could be used, the gallant colonel left his wife, to join his regiment on the Mississippi, and thence was soon ordered into Texas.</p> 
               <p>The two weeks of imposed self-denial had well-nigh driven Gertie mad. She excused her paleness and languor as being the effect of her anxiety for him.</p> 
               <p>How could he leave her? she moaned; yet she knew he must go, and, loving him as she did, still she almost longed for his departure, lest her courage should fail, and she should be induced to drink ere he went. Her period of self-denial was ended at last. Her husband was gone. Uncle Simon accompanied him to the West, and Mrs. Thorne went to Washington to visit her daughter, and assist her in the arduous hospital duty in which she was engaged.</p> 
               <p>Gertie had now no restraint, and the night after her husband's departure she was wholly imbecile from the effects of brandy. The nurse, thinking her sick from grief, did as she was bid and kept the children out of the way.</p> 
               <p>Day by day she grew worse and worse. At intervals conscience goaded her almost to madness, and she wept and groaned in her terrible suffering. "What should she do when they came back?" was the cry of her tortured soul.</p> 
               <p>"I cannot meet them," she exclaimed to<pb n="156-157" xml:id="VAC6500-00000079"/> herself. "The first moment Mell's eyes rest upon me, she will know that I have fallen. And Uncle Simon's voice will kill me. Oh! what shall I do? what shall I do? "Sometimes she almost resolved to write and call Kathleen back, and then, shuddering with horror, she would cry out, "No, no, no! I will not meet them. O God! help me; I cannot reform now. I am lost-lost-</p> 
               <p>"I will take my children and go away. I will pretend to go to the mountains. I will dismiss Blair and Anna, pay them well, and leave them in the city. I will die alone. I will die, I will not live; and when he comes, he shall only find his innocent children. He shall never know what became of his perjured wife. O Beau, Beau! May God bless you even as I have cursed you!</p> 
               <p>"If only Kathleen were here," she went on, often when her drunken madness had relived itself in tears; "she might save me once more. No, I will not be saved. I cannot; I am a drunkard, made a drunkard by my mother and Uncle Simon." And, pouring down another and another glass, she would blunt the stings of conscience, that pierced her sober moments, and sink again into the insensibility of intoxication.</p> 
               <p>All this time she was able to keep up appearances by day, and lock herself in her chamber by night. She soon began to carry her desperate plans into operation, dismissed her nurse and waiting-maid, and told the other servants that she was going to the mountains to spend a few weeks, and recruit her health; and with such indefinite information she left her home.</p> 
               <p>She took lodgings in obscure rooms in the heart of the city, disguised her little ones in garments befitting the children of common day-laborers, resolved never more to be found by her friends.</p> 
               <p>She had taken her trunk on board a boat, and registered her name for Providence, leaving letters for all her friends. Late in the evening she slipped on shore and did not return. She placed her jewels and money on deposit, and thus secured herself against danger of want.</p> 
               <p>The intense determination which had taken possession of her soul had kept her almost sober for a few days; for she was as yet only<pb n="158-159" xml:id="VAC6500-00000080"/> such a drunkard as we see by thousands in the other sex, filling posts of honor and trust in our country, men who are beastly drunkards to-day, yet to-morrow will be received with loud acclaim by gathering multitudes,-men, who, by constant perversion of the moral law, have taught themselves to believe that it is not so wicked for a man to drink as for a woman.</p> 
               <p>"Look at Major-General --," said Gertie to herself one day, while dining at Delmonico's. "He is reeling drunk, and yet, in ten days, he will take charge of fifty thousand men. But who considers him disgraced? He will, perhaps, sacrifice a battalion of his soldiers in some coming conflict. Who will call him to account? Is it any worse for me than for him?</p> 
               <p>"I can't do half the harm that he has it in his power to do; and my mother has told me a thousand times that my father loved wine and brandy too. What right have these men to claim all the enjoyment of the convivial cup?"</p> 
               <p>Suffering at all times the goadings of conscience and the agonizing dread of discovery, she thus endeavored to reassure herself, forgetting, while using such arguments in her own favor, that neither man nor woman is justifiable in committing sin.</p> 
               <p>The boat that bore away Gertie's trunks, packed with valueless materials, encountered a storm that night, foundered, and, in attempting to escape in boats, several of her passengers were lost. As Gertie had written to her friends of her intended departure from the city, and mentioned the time and mode of going, it was with intense joy that she read in the morning paper the announcement of the wrecking of the ship, and the supposed loss, with other passengers, of the wife and children of Colonel Fletcher, now in Texas. Accompanying this joy was a fearful pain at the thought of the grief she was bringing upon all that loved her.</p> 
               <p>She had written to Beau a letter full of tenderest regrets for his trials, and prayers for his safety, every word a truth, while yet she was planning with the falseness of a demon to destroy his happiness and blight his life. To ease the terrible remorse that now seized upon her, she left her children in<pb n="160-161" xml:id="VAC6500-00000081"/> care of her newly hired servants, went to a hotel, called for a room, and, drinking deeply from the bottle in her satchel, soon sank into stupid slumber and remained for hours. Late in the evening she aroused herself and attempted to go to her boarding-house. Staggering, weak, and bewildered, she, of course, sought relief from her bottle again, and soon fell upon the pavement, where she remained until found by the police, and was carried to the station-house, where she passed the night in drunken unconsciousness. Thence she was taken to the recorder's court, fined and discharged, with a severe reprimand from the judge. Hiding her features all the time in a coarse veil, she was not recognized.</p> 
               <p>The policeman had taken her bottle from her, and, thus deprived of her usual drams for ten hours, she had become somewhat sobered, at least enough to allow her again to become fearfully agonized with accusing thoughts. With desperate energy she formed another resolve.</p> 
               <p>Seeking a school for orphans, she asked to enter two poor children that she had taken a few months before, intending to keep them as her own. Now she was called to join her husband in the army, and for safe-keeping wished to leave them with the "Sisters of Mercy" until her return.</p> 
               <p>Depositing an ample sum of money, she was allowed to bring them, and, bestowing on them fictitious names, she left them with great apparent distress and solicitude. Little Eliot, not yet five years old, was not easily reconciled to his new name of Thomas Winn, and stoutly asserted that he was "Major Elly, grandpa's boy."</p> 
               <p>Some things seemed strange to the matrons; but the large amount of money left for their use stifled all inquiries if not suspicions.</p> 
               <p>Now, wholly released from restraint, the course of Gertie Fletcher tended downward with fearful rapidity. With her own hands she cut the beautiful hair from off her own head, leaving an uneven and ragged deformity.</p> 
               <p>"I will never be recognized by those who have known me. They shall think that I am dead and buried away in the deep blue sea. They shall mourn me as one lost in her<pb n="162-163" xml:id="VAC6500-00000082"/> purity, taken from them by the hand of God."</p> 
               <p>Sometimes she would threaten to present herself to Uncle Simon in all her hideousness. "He deserves it," she would say. "Didn't he make me a drunkard with his arguments about moderation?</p> 
               <p>"Moderation! O hell! your pits are filled with such moderation! The canting hypocrites! the miserable, whining fools! What do I care for them?" So she raved.</p> 
               <p>We cannot follow the wretched creature through her vagaries. Not a month after she had left her home, she was robbed of all her money by a young man who had watched her and spent a few evenings in her room; for she was already fallen so low as to be seeking companionship in her wild carousals.</p> 
               <p>Selling her clothing, everything that would buy brandy, she was soon reduced to the last extremity. She dared not show herself to her bankers, or to those with whom she had made deposits, as that would prove her still among the living, and reveal her still deepening and already terrible depravity.</p> 
               <p>Maddened and desperate, she stole a bit of rich lace from a shop door, intending to buy with it a few drams from some low grogshop. But she was not adroit enough. The act was seen, and she sent to the lock-up, thence to prison for six months.</p> 
               <p>O miserable mother of two fair children! O Gertie Fletcher! once the beautiful, elegant, accomplished Gertie Manning, condemned to six months in the penitentiary! With returning enforced soberness came not resolution to reform, but to endure, lest she should be discovered, and her awful crime and shame brought to light. Suffering in every fibre of her nature, she moodily filled her place, and gave no evidence to any living creature of her past life or condition.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
               <pb n="164-165" xml:id="VAC6500-00000083"/> 
               <head>XIV.</head> 
               <p>Six months in a prison! Surely, surely, repentance and reform would come, ere all those days, slowly following one upon another in dreary isolation and bodily weariness, could creep through their inevitable succession!</p> 
               <p>Surely the woman, the wife, the mother, in that once noble nature, would assert themselves in her heart and bring her back, pleading and penitent, asking mercy and forgiveness of those whom she had so wronged,-asking mercy and forgiveness of her God.</p> 
               <p>Did you ever trace the course of a clear stream flowing from the hills and winding through shaded forests, and clean farms, and fertile valleys, or dashing its way through rocky glens and falling over miniature precipices? Oh! is it not a beautiful thing, sparkling in its unsullied purity, giving out freshness and life as it speeds onward toward the absorbing grandeur of the sea? Suddenly denly its course joins with that of some larger stream, and the rills of purity begin to mingle with the waters of pollution. For a time they are able still to dance and sparkle; but, as they roll on, sewer after sewer, drain after drain, disgorge their filth and poisons, and mingle drop by drop with that which once was pure, until it becomes an on-flowing stream of disease and death, sending up day and night its deadly stench and miasm.</p> 
               <p>Could its drops be distilled and purified by nature's holy and gentle agencies, could they be sent again through fields and forests, they might again sparkle and grow lovely, and bestow blessing instead of cursing.</p> 
               <p>O crushed and broken soul! O Gertrude Manning! Shall we call thee "a victim"? Did thy young heart ever dream of such a fate? To every such question the answer from every one implicated would have been "No." Yet was not such ignorance of probable results culpable? Could Uncle Simon, or the mother, or the guest that sat at the table and sipped wine with them, or the physician, who prescribed as a medicine<pb n="166-167" xml:id="VAC6500-00000084"/> the infuriating draught,-could they be excused?</p> 
               <p>What right had they to lay such temptations in the path of one so young, so fair and impulsive, so trusting, yielding, and kind? They had seen like experiments tried in like cases, and too often result in ruin and death; not one of them all but had thus seen and known this evil. Had not the wretched father of Melonie fallen before them? Had not Beaumont Fletcher's father gone down under their hands? Had not Simon Eliot and his sister, Mrs. Manning, felt in their childhood the grindings of poverty, and writhed under the scorpion lash of intemperance, as visited in the iniquities of fathers upon their children to the third and fourth generation of them that forget the commandments of God?</p> 
               <p>Yes, they knew it all; and yet they led the young soul like a lamb to the slaughter. And there she sits before us upon the cold stone floor of her prison-cell, her long, graceful arms clasped about her knees; her short hair uncombed, and still made as frightful and uncouth as possible, till it might well be said, "every hair stood on end;" her garments soiled and loose;-there she sits singing ballads, in her own inimitable style, for twenty or thirty of the abandoned creatures about her.</p> 
               <p>Even the jailer pauses, as he passes, to listen, entranced by the sweet sounds which even sin cannot destroy, and a twinge of conscience pains him as he whispers, "Sing away, and I'll give you a dram to-night; keep them quiet; it does 'em good."</p> 
               <p>And so, protruding first one baked foot and then the other, making believe to touch the keys of her piano, now springing up and whirling a waltz or a schottisch, then repeating some passage in sad and solemn mockery from a favorite author, travestying it to suit her purpose, she makes the gloomy room ring with frenzied laughter, and the crushed, guilty souls around her forget, in their mirth, their degradation and shame, and half take courage to plunge still deeper, should they ever have opportunity, because one so gifted and strong has made even prison-life so grand.</p> 
               <p>What did Gertie herself think? Only this one thought engrossed every moment of her life,-if we may call that life which has sunk<pb n="168-169" xml:id="VAC6500-00000085"/> so low,-the one all-absorbing secret, not to be discovered, not to have one glimpse of her present dark, polluted life ever brought within the recognition of her friends. Night and day the thought was present with her that Beau must never know; her children must never know and bear the odium of their mother's crime and shame.</p> 
               <p>The jailer, a man of the common kind, large, strong, uncultured, and fiercely animal in his propensities, drinking and eating, swearing and smoking to excess, marked this young, still beautiful, and bright-eyed woman as his prey; and, though intoxicating drinks were strictly forbidden in the prison, he, the trusted officer of the government, fed the flame that might have died in six months.</p> 
               <p>The six months were passed, at length,-passed as months do to women in those awful prisons,-and our heroine came forth to the world tenfold more a child of sin than heretofore. And now we lose her in her downward career until 1865.</p> 
               <p>In the mean time, the clarion note of war has ceased. General Fletcher, who has not visited the North since his wife and children have been supposed to sleep the sleep that knows no waking, still lingers, by government orders, on the turbulent fields of Texas, but writes that he will visit New York in July of 1865.</p> 
               <p>Melonie Thorne, worn with her labors in camp and field, has left the hospitals, where there is no longer extreme need, and is trying to recruit in Uncle Simon's home. Kathleen has added freshness and beauty to face and form with each passing year. The rough bit of marble that Gertie picked from the streets so long ago has been chiselled by those unapproachable artists, Love and Purity, into a superb statue fit to adorn the brightest niche in any palace or home.</p> 
               <p>What could these two noble girls do now? They could not come out of such a conflict and be content to fold their hands. Oh, no!</p> 
               <p>"Work, work, work!" was their motto; and, as Uncle Simon had made fabulous additions to his wealth, and gave them almost unlimited freedom to spend it, they took the strange and almost unheard-of notion into their heads of looking about home for somebody needing comfort and material aid. They<pb n="170-171" xml:id="VAC6500-00000086"/> visited the prisons, the homes of the friendless, orphan schools and asylums, and soldiers' homes, scattering blessings broadcast through the city of their adoption, and gaining love from all.</p> 
               <p>It was late in June of 1865, nearly two years after the time the Sphynx was lost, with her precious burden (as was supposed) of women and children, when these two noble sisters of charity, as they really were, chanced to visit the orphan school where Gertie had left her darlings.</p> 
               <p>It was a day of examination and display, and the two little ones were on one of the lower forms, and directly in front of Melonie and Kathleen. From the moment when they had been seated, Kathleen had seen none but these two children, more richly dressed than any of the others. The heavy purse left with the "sisters" was not yet exhausted, and the principals had never dared to neglect their especial duty to these pupils, lest at some unexpected moment they might be claimed, and themselves called to account for the trust reposed in them.</p> 
               <p>As soon as the exercises had closed, Kath leen stepped up to the little boy, and, trembling in every nerve, called him-using the pet name of former years.</p> 
               <p>"Elly!"</p> 
               <p>"That isn't my name, ma'am. It used to be Major Elly, 'grandpa's boy,' now I am Tommy Winn; and this is Lulu Winn, my little sister."</p> 
               <p>"Who brought you here?" asked Kathleen, quivering with excitement.</p> 
               <p>"I thought it was mamma; but she says," pointing to the matron, "that it was a lady, and that mamma is dead."</p> 
               <p>"What did you call the lady? Do you remember?"</p> 
               <p>"We called her mamma; but Uncle Simon called her Gertie, and so did papa when he came home from the war; and aint you Kathleen?" And the sweet child looked up into her face, and, with his simple words, swept all mystery as to his parentage out of the way.</p> 
               <p>Melonie, who was in another part of the room, was called, and the boy recognized her at once as "Aunt Mell."</p> 
               <p>The ladies of the school knew nothing<pb n="172-173" xml:id="VAC6500-00000087"/> more than has already been told, and this was soon communicated.</p> 
               <p>With hearts almost bursting with joy and grief, Melonie and Kathleen flew home to Uncle Simon. There could be no doubt that Gertrude herself had placed the children there. The time of their coming was later than the shipwreck.</p> 
               <p>What could it mean? Was the mother still alive? Joy at finding the children was almost crushed beneath the dread suspicion that flashed into every mind.</p> 
               <p>"May I speak?" asked Kathleen, with a face ashen white, while her tongue gave out only a moaning whisper.</p> 
               <p>"Let us hear. We have borne much, dear Kathleen; we can bear more, now these are found."</p> 
               <p>"Gertrude Manning has, in our absence, been overtaken by that power stronger than all earthly influences, her love of strong drink, and she has hid herself from our sight. Either she has committed suicide, or she may be found."</p> 
               <p>"My God! my God!" shrieked Simon Eliot, as he clasped a hand of each of the girls in his own. "Oh, a thousand times better that they should all have perished in the sea!"</p> 
               <p>"Simon Eliot," said Kathleen, "God knows best. His will, not thine, be done. Let these little ones come to us; we must care for them, for of such is the kingdom of heaven."</p> 
               <p>Clasping his hand in her own, and winding her arm about him so as to draw his drooping head upon her shoulder, she pressed her pale lips upon his forehead, and whispered:-</p> 
               <p>"Now I will yield to the importunities of years. Now I will become your wife, and these shall be our children until we find their father and mother. My beloved, be comforted."</p> 
               <p>Melonie glided from the room and left them alone together.</p> 
               <p>"O my good and beautiful Kathleen!" exclaimed Mr. Eliot; "I will be comforted; and, in the light of your purity and love, guided by your wisdom and truth, I will try to lift the fallen, redeem the enslaved, and remove the temptation from the path of the weak and unwary. If the remainder of my<pb n="174-175" xml:id="VAC6500-00000088"/> life can atone for the wrong done, it shall be freely given."</p> 
               <p>He clasped her in his arms, and then, kneeling together, they poured forth the fulness of their hearts into His ear who hears the earnest cry of all his children.</p> 
               <p>Mr. Eliot arose the next morning with renewed strength, and lifted up his head that the sunlight might kiss his seared forehead, while with every step of the familiar road to his office he blessed the name of the Lord, who had given back into his hands the children of his beloved Gertrude; and not for that alone. More than for all else did he offer thanks that Kathleen, who had woven herself into the minutest fibre of his being by years of the most unswerving duty and kindness, and who had resisted all his importunities until now, had at length yielded, and consented to bless his home and heart.</p> 
               <p>This morning his first business was to call upon the chief of police, to describe, as minutely as possible, his niece, as she was in the beginning of her mad career, without giving her name. It was supposed that, if living, she would linger somewhere near her children. He had not fully finished his description before the stern features of the officer relaxed, and a sad gloom settled upon his usually imperturbable countenance.</p> 
               <p>"I know the lady, sir. She has, for the last two years, been repeatedly in our charge. We have never learned her real name. She calls herself Moll, nothing more. Beautiful as an angel, sir, when I first knew her."</p> 
               <p>"Where is she?" gasped Mr. Eliot.</p> 
               <p>"We brought her over two weeks ago from a year's confinement on Governor's Island. In less than a week she was found on the street, raving in delirium tremens. She was sent to the hospital. The doctor says she can never recover."</p> 
               <p>"Take, me to her!" was all Mr. Eliot could utter. And together the two went, one on the saddest errand of all his life, the other on one so common to him as scarcely to move him with an emotion.</p> 
               <p>Bound to an iron bedstead with broad straps of leather, lay the wreck of his former pride and love, the once proud, cultured, Christian woman, now the unholiest Magdalen of them all, shrieking, screaming, laughing<pb n="176-177" xml:id="VAC6500-00000089"/> ing, singing, cursing, praying. Her hands also were bound, for she tore and raved with a strength that would have destroyed everything about her.</p> 
               <p>"Will you speak to her, sir?" asked the woman who was in attendance.</p> 
               <p>"No," was the answer. And the lips that spoke seemed turned to stone.</p> 
               <p>"Perhaps she will know you, sir; she raves for some one she calls Kathleen, and for her children, and for her husband, whom she calls Beau. It is pitiful to hear her, sir, and she must die soon. Maybe, sir, you could comfort her."</p> 
               <p>Uncle Simon summoned all his manly resolution, and, going to her side, looked down upon the prostrate form. She was Gertie still. The beautiful hair, with two years of growth, lay in wavy masses over the coarse pillow. The attendant (during her stupor, produced by opiates) had smoothed it out in sheer pity.</p> 
               <p>Long confinement had restored the fair complexion of her girlhood, and a year of entire restraint from liquor and vice, under better regulation than in her first prison life, had somewhat renewed the beauty of the past.</p> 
               <p>Uncle Simon stooped and laid his hand upon hers, and in a low, touching tone spoke her name.</p> 
               <p>"Gertie Manning!"</p> 
               <p>"Gertie Manning!" she shrieked. "Who speaks that name here? Avaunt! It was Uncle Simon. I have killed him, and he's shouting my name down into hell from the battlements above. Take them off! take them off! don't let them kill me!" And, with a power that seemed superhuman, she wrenched her hands asunder, and tore them from his grasp; she uttered yells and imprecations that turned his blood to ice, and then, with eyes staring at the wall, she begged for Kathleen.</p> 
               <p>"O Kathleen! why don't you come? Come, come, come! You said you would. Come and take away these snakes! They are crushing me!-crushing my heart out! O Kathleen! don't tell Beau! Uncle Simon, Melonie, don't tell Beau! Where are my children? Help, help, help! Kathleen, you lied; you said you'd come, and now the<pb n="178-179" xml:id="VAC6500-00000090"/> devils are killing me! O Kathleen! come, come, come!"</p> 
               <p>Mr. Eliot could bear no more. He rushed from the room, sought Kathleen, and told her all.</p> 
               <p>"O Simon! let us save her."</p> 
               <p>"Can you go to such a place, my love?" he asked, in his tenderness, of his newly affianced bride.</p> 
               <p>"Can I go?" answered Kathleen, springing to her feet. "I thought you knew me better than to ask such a question as that. Can I go? O Simon Eliot! down to the very depths, lower than mortal foot has ever trod, would I go to help the once pure angel, who picked <emph>me</emph> up from the street, and, under the hand of God, made me all that I am I Yes, let us go."</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter"> 
                
               <head>XV.</head> 
               <p>WHEN Mr. Eliot and Kathleen arrived at hospital, they were informed by the matron that Gertie had entirely exhausted herself by her ravings after his departure, and that a powerful opiate had been administered to reduce her to quiet.</p> 
               <p>"It is more than likely' said the woman-"that she may die without becoming con, scious again. If she come to at all, she may be more calm. She has lived about as long as is usual with that awful disease, unless they obtain sleep. That she sleeps now is a favorable sign."</p> 
               <p>Kathleen stationed herself beside that iron bedstead. There lay her benefactress, prostrate, bound hand and foot, drugged to unconsciousness, the darkened gloom of prison walls and grated windows still shadowing the features once so radiant with life, love, and purity. Kathleen watched and waited,<pb n="180-181" xml:id="VAC6500-00000091"/> nerved for the fearful awakening,-nerved for the fearful death, if it should come. But oh! to have her die now, and thus, with the muttered curse and imprecation yet upon her lips!</p> 
               <p>Mr. Eliot sat in another apartment, bowed with anguish. The hours went slowly. The physician went his usual round, looked at her, and shook his head.</p> 
               <p>"She may awaken calm and conscious, madam, but I think her nervous system is past restoring;" and then, with a sigh, he whispered in Kathleen's ear, "Her friends may feel thankful if she dies. One like her could never live possessed of sufficient reason to enable her to look back over the past two years of her own awful life. Pray God to forgive her, and be thankful when her hands are folded to rest."</p> 
               <p>A fallen angel she seemed, indeed, as she lay hour after hour, her white, worn face upturned in the dim light, framed in its clustering curls; the beautiful features no longer distorted with fear and anguish, but calm and quiet and peaceful, as if some ministering spirit were soothing the guilty, tortured soul, and fitting it for its entrance into that world-beyond, upon whose threshold she seemed but lingering a moment ere she would vanish away.</p> 
               <p>O men, O women of this land! How many such souls have ye, by sins of omission, if not of commission, sacrificed upon this direst and darkest altar of idolatry that the world has ever known! What argument of "moderation," of "use without abuse," can stand before such a living, breathing, yet dying fact as this before us? A woman, a wife, and a mother, passing to the presence of God-drunk! Will his all-seeing eye remember her offences alone?</p> 
               <p>One, two, three, four, five hours. Oh, such hours! Kathleen sat with Gertie's two hands clasped in her own, with her eyes fixed upon that darling face, that she might catch the first awakening expression and be prepared for the recognition.</p> 
               <p>"How sweetly and calmly she sleeps!" whispered the matron. "I never saw the like before, and I've seen hundreds of 'em."</p> 
               <p>Was the magnetism of Kathleen's healthful and noble life filling this agonized frame with<pb n="182-183" xml:id="VAC6500-00000092"/> peace? It might be! "Was her gentle and loving spirit already healing the wounds and soothing the pain? Who can answer?</p> 
               <p>After five hours of perfectly calm, and, to all appearance, sweet sleep, Kathleen felt the slender fingers clasp more closely around her own, and a warm moisture soften the palms. Remaining perfectly quiet, she waited on. Then came a quivering of the eyelids, followed by a slight tremor of the body; the lips moved as if in effort to enunciate. At first no sound came. By and by the almost inaudible words, breathed rather than spoken, reached the strained, listening ear:-</p> 
               <p>"Kathleen, you've come; you said you would. Don't let go my hand; don't leave line. The devils are only outside; I see them; I hear their howls. They won't come where you are. You won't go, will you?"</p> 
               <p>Kathleen stooped and kissed her, and answered:-</p> 
               <p>"No, Gertie darling; your own Kathleen will not leave ye. There now, lie still and sleep again, my pet; it's meself will watch and see that ye are safe."</p> 
               <p>"O God! for Jesus sake forgive me!" prayed the wretched woman, as a glow of satisfied hope spread over her pallid face, and again she slept, still clasping Kathleen's hand tightly in her own. Again the hours slowly, slowly glided by. The day died out. The night, scarcely more dark and gloomy than the day in that horrid grated room, passed, and the dawn of a beautiful June morning threw its light and glory over the world.</p> 
               <p>The effect of the opiate was gone, and Gertie awoke to full consciousness, but so weak and bewildered at first as scarcely to be called alive. She expressed no surprise at the presence of her friends.</p> 
               <p>"I know it all!" she whispered. "I saw it all in my dreams."</p> 
               <p>"Be quiet, darling, don't talk; the doctor says you must not."</p> 
               <p>"You are my doctor; I have no other."</p> 
               <p>Kathleen kissed her lips gently. "Then be quiet."</p> 
               <p>Uncle Simon had walked the halls of the hospital in torturing suspense through all these hours, and, knowing the suffering and suspense of Melonie, as soon as Gertie awoke went home to tell her of the condition of the<pb n="184-185" xml:id="VAC6500-00000093"/> patient. Another shock of mingled pleasure and pain awaited him.</p> 
               <p>Beaumont Fletcher met him at the gate. The two men clasped hands in speechless emotion, and went in together, and Uncle Simon soon told all he knew.</p> 
               <p>"Let me go to her," was the first cry of Beau's heart.</p> 
               <p>"It would kill her at once. Her pleading and prayer through all her terrors has been, Don't tell Beau! Oh, don't tell Beau!' You must wait."</p> 
               <p>"God give me strength to wait; to bear this crushing pain for her, this overwhelming pleasure at finding my babes! O merciful Father! even when I thought the sea had destroyed them all, it was not an hour like this."</p> 
               <p>The strong man, who had braved death in a thousand forms without blenching, sank upon a chair, and, calling for his new-found children, clasped them to his heart to help him bear his seemingly insupportable burden of woe.</p> 
               <p>Kathleen did not leave the patient for an hour. She even slept with Gertie's hand in her own. If she passed out the door for but a moment, Gertie's terrors returned, and the shrieks of the poor soul recalled her. But each day she grew more calm. The bands were removed. Careful hands lifted her into a litter, and she was tenderly carried and laid down in her own home, in a room that she had not known,-not an article in which could recall a recollection of the past.</p> 
               <p>The physician expressed wonder at her prolonged life, and began almost to hope for recovery. She was calm, but seemed to gain no strength, and was sustained by tonics and opiates. After a week she asked for Beau, and expressed joy that he lived, yet begged Kathleen, still, with terrible earnestness, to promise never to reveal to him her awful fate. Then in whispers, and at long intervals, and with agonizing contrition, she told Kathleen all she could remember of her life after they left her alone with the children. With great caution, and only when concealment was no longer possible, they told her that the children had been found and brought home.</p> 
               <p>She seemed too weak to wish to see them, or to truly realize a mother's love. Oh, that<pb n="186-187" xml:id="VAC6500-00000094"/> holy love, trampled upon, extinguished by degrees, by the liking of strong drink! Could it ever truly live again? Her love for Beau had outlasted and outlived all.</p> 
               <p>"I am dying, Kathleen. It is best I should die. God will forgive me for Christ's sake; for I have prayed day and night during all that last year I was in prison. How I came drunk again I do not know. O Kathleen I to be turned loose from a prison, and know myself the vile, hated thing that I was! I knew that, like Magdalen, my devils had been cast out; but I knew, too, that, though God had spoken peace, the world would not. I remember standing alone by the ferry. My eyes grew dim and the sunlight turned to darkness. O Kathleen! I fainted, and they gave me brandy. They always do. How can such poor souls as I reform? And then I was mad,-for one drink will craze me,-and I knew no moment of consciousness until I awoke in your loving and careful hands. Oh, if I could see Beau only one moment; hear him say,' I, too, forgive you, Gertie!' then I could die."</p> 
               <p>Kathleen told her a letter had been received ceived saying he was coming. She bore it well, and asked, "When will he be here?"</p> 
               <p>Cautiously a time was fixed, and she seemed to wait with patient, trusting hope and courage.</p> 
               <p>At last the hour came. Alone Beaumont Fletcher entered the room that seemed to him the chamber of resurrection, not of death; for she had been dead to him, and now she lived.</p> 
               <p>As he approached her, she lifted her arms, and, clasping them around his neck, with a low cry uttered the words:-</p> 
               <p>"O Beau, Beau, Beau! Say you forgive me before I die!"</p> 
               <p>"I do forgive you," sobbed the stricken man. "O my darling, I do forgive you!"</p> 
               <p>"I have waited only for this," said she, feebly. "Now I will go away and trouble no more the hearts that love me."</p> 
               <p>Still holding her in his arms, still sobbing forth the pent-up agony of months, with his lost wife pressed to his true heart, General Fletcher did not notice the relaxation of the clasp of her arms until they seemed to drop for support. Thinking she was overcome,<pb n="188-189" xml:id="VAC6500-00000095"/> and perhaps fainting, he laid her back upon her pillow.</p> 
               <p>She was dead!</p> 
               <p>She had waited only to hear his "I do forgive you," and passed beyond, where temptations never come, and where sin and sorrow are no more.</p> 
               <p>"God is merciful," said Melonie to the bereaved husband, a few hours after. "He has given the tried and tempted soul the rest she prayed for. His will be done."</p> 
               <p>"God is merciful. His will be done," was the humble response of the stricken husband and father.</p> 
               <p>Let us draw a veil over the events of the next year and a half.</p> 
               <p>Kathleen Eliot is worthy of all the love and honor that greet her to-day, and Uncle Simon feels that the last year of his life has been the truest and best of all his days; and he is never happier than when bending over the little life that Kathleen has added to his own, and which they have consecrated already to higher purposes than he knew in his earlier years.</p> 
               <p>General Fletcher has won from Melonie the promise that she will be ere long in reality, as she is now in act, the mother of his children.</p> 
               <p>The death of Harry in Paris, from dissipation and fever, was both a sorrow and a relief.</p> 
               <p>Willie Saxton and Edgar Willard are nature's noblemen, and filling, as such men should, places of honor and trust.</p> 
               <p>Here endeth our "Glimpse of Two Lives."</p> 
               <p>Melonie Thorne is everywhere bright and beautiful, giving forth the aura of love and duty, blessing and blessed; while the other, with equal power, equal purity of intention, gave her husband, her children, her home, her fortune, her life, for an injurious self-indulgence, and died the victim of fashion, custom, and law.</p> 
               <p>Gertie's sacrifice was the sacrifice of herself.</p> 
            </div> 
            <closer>THE END.</closer> 
         </div>
      </body> 
   </text>
</TEI>