<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6967">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >The Last of the Buccaneers </title>
            <author >Buntline, Ned, (1822 or 3-1886)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC6967</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >The last of the buccaneers</title>
                  <author >Buntline, Ned, (1822 or 3-1886)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >97 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >Garrett</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1856">[1856]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-10-01">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="Pacific Data Conversion Corp." when="2002-03-20">Finished transcription and SGML encoding</change>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-05-20">Finished TEI conversion and final editing</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <front> 
         <titlePage xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
            <pb  n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6967-00000001"/> 
            <docTitle> 
               <titlePart>THE LAST OF THE BUCCANEERS:</titlePart> 
               <titlePart type="sub">A YARN OF THE EIGHTEENTH CENTURY,</titlePart> 
            </docTitle> 
            <byline >BY <docAuthor xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">NED BUNTLINE,</docAuthor> AUTHOR OF <choice>
                  <sic>MYTERIES</sic>
                  <corr>MYSTERIES</corr>
               </choice> AND MISERIES OF NEW-YORK; B'HOYS OF NEW-YORK; THREE YEARS AFTER; LIFE YARN; EDWARD CARROLL; ETC. ETC.</byline> 
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>NEW-YORK:</pubPlace> 
               <publisher >GARRETT &amp; CO., PUBLISHERS, <address> 
                     <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">18 ANN STREET</addrLine> 
                  </address>
               </publisher>
            </docImprint> 
         </titlePage> 
         <div type="preface"> 
            <pb n="" xml:id="VAC6967-00000002"/> 
             
            <head>PREFATORIAL.</head> 
            <p>These sketches were written when I thought "the world" was smiling kindly upon me; they were written light-heartedly-came from one upon whom trouble had only began to leave its impress. They were <hi rend="i"/>written to amuse my friends; now they are published to <hi rend="i"/>benefit myself, and my old friends, the publishers.</p> 
            <closer>
               <signed>EDWARD Z. C. JUDSON.</signed>
            </closer> 
         </div> 
         <div type="dedication"> 
            <pb n="" xml:id="VAC6967-00000003"/> 
             
            <head>DEDICATION.</head> 
            <opener>
               <salute>GARRETT &amp; CO.-</salute>
            </opener> 
            <p>Individually, I knew your trio, before you were united. That our acquaintance is not regretted by me, and that you are the only publishers of my works, suffices to tell the public that my hand and heart as American publishers is with you.</p> 
            <closer>
               <signed>EDWARD Z. C. JUDSON.</signed> 
               <dateline>NEW YORK, May 17th, 1856.</dateline>
            </closer> 
         </div> 
      </front> 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The last of the buccaneers</head> 
            <pb n="" xml:id="VAC6967-00000004"/> 
             
            <head>THE YACHT:</head> 
            <head type="sub">A SERIES OF ORIGINAL TALES.</head> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <head>NUMBER ONE.</head> 
               <head type="sub">The Pirate of the Gulf.</head> 
               <p>SUMMER in the Gulf-stream-what a season it is! Now calm and sultry-then, quick as thought, up springs a storm; now not a cloud in sight, and yet in ten minutes your ship may be scudding wildly before a white squall, or lay, a dismantled wreck, upon the foaming yeast of angry waters. But to my story.</p> 
               <p>Twenty years ago, a large ship was drifting along with the current, close in to the Florida reef, abreast of the Island of Matacumbe. She was from New Orleans, laden principally with cotton, and bound to Boston.</p> 
               <p>There was scarcely a breath of wind to fill her sails; the sea was smooth as it well could be. The crew were "laying off" in the shadiest places they could find about decks-the mates and captain were aft on the quarter-deck, looking in toward the low range of islands on their larboard hand, with the only spy-glass aboard.</p> 
               <p>We will go down in the cabin, reader. There were but two passengers on board. One was a white-haired old man, the other, a beautiful girl-his daughter. The father was pale and thin, looking indeed as if Death had placed his seal upon him. Reclining upon a sofa, he presented a sad contrast with the lovely girl-the womanly creature, who, kneeling by his side, with a fan, endeavored to cool the heated air of the sultry place. How like an angel she seemed while thus employed!</p> 
               <p>"Don't weary yourself, Emily; don't weary yourself with fanning me!" murmured the old man.</p> 
               <p>"I am not tired, dear father," replied the girl; "but I wish this voyage was over.<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6967-00000005"/> We have been twelve long, tiresome days at sea, and yet not one-third of the distance is passed! I do want to reach our own home; you will grow better, then, dear father!"</p> 
               <p>"No, child! I am almost worn out!" murmured the father. "I <emph>hope</emph> to live to lay my head once more beneath the dome where you were born, and where your poor mother died: yet it will be a mercy if God spares me so long. This last voyage, and our disappointment in not finding James, has been too much for me. Could I have found and reformed him, then I could have died in peace; for I should have known that a protector was left for <emph>you!</emph>"</p> 
               <p>"Father, do not talk of dying-do not, <emph>dear</emph> father!" murmured the daughter, tearfully.</p> 
               <p>"It is best to speak and think of it, child; for it <emph>must</emph> be, and we make death more dreadful than it is by holding thoughts of it in silence and awe!" replied the father.</p> 
               <p>The daughter made no reply, but drew a miniature from her bosom, and after kissing it fervently, gazed upon it with a look expressive of fervent love. The old man noted this, and with a sigh, said:</p> 
               <p>"You may well kiss her picture, child; many is the time she kissed you so, when you were a babe!"</p> 
               <p>"Dear-dear mother! thou art now in Heaven!" murmured the girl, sadly; and again she kissed the picture.</p> 
               <p>At this moment, heavy footsteps passing hurriedly to and fro were heard upon the deck, and an instant afterward the captain came hurriedly down into the cabin, and entered his state-room.</p> 
               <p>"What is the matter? Why are you arming?" asked the girl, as she saw the captain hurry out, with a cutlass in one hand, and a brace of pistols in the other.</p> 
               <p>"Nothing is the matter, Miss Emily; be calm!" he replied. "I am only preparing for evil if it <emph>should</emph> come. A vessel, looking like a pilot-boat, or a <unclear>wrecking-schooner is</unclear> bearing off toward us, with a light land-breeze, and I think, as we are in a rather bad latitude, we had best be on our guard!"</p> 
               <p>"Captain, you are pale and tremulous!" cried the old man; "if there is danger, <emph>say so</emph>. I am old, but I've borne arms! Ah, Emily! if your brother James was with us! he <emph>was</emph> wild, but he was <emph>brave!</emph>"</p> 
               <p>The captain had not waited, but had hurried on deck; and Emily, who saw by the captain's manner that there <emph>was</emph> danger apprehended, would have followed, if she could have left her father, who was too weak to rise.</p> 
               <p>The sound of hurrying feet above-orders from the officers, and a motion of the vessel, as the wind from the land filled her sails, was all that served to give the maiden an idea of what was coming. Suddenly, however, the boom of a cannon was heard-then, in a few moments after, a crash in the hull of the vessel, and quickly after, another deafening report, told that the <emph>danger</emph> was <emph>near</emph> and terrible.</p> 
               <p>"Let me go on deck, father, and see what this means!" cried the girl.</p> 
               <p>"No, child-no; I cannot go with thee! Trust to the gallantry of <emph>Whittaker</emph> and his crew; if they cannot defend thee, in God alone is thy aid!"</p> 
               <p>"Hark! hark!" moaned the girl. "I hear strange shouts! Ah! a crash-another vessel is beside us! We are boarded-God help the crew! God help me and my poor father!"</p> 
               <p>A rush-a sound of clashing steel-a pistol-shot now and then-shouts and curses were heard-then, for a moment, all was still!</p> 
               <p>Oh, terrible suspense! dreadful moments of anxiety! Yet they did not last long.-Down into the cabin rushed a man, clad in a strange attire. His face was stained with powder and blood-his sword was dimmed with gory stains.</p> 
                
               <p>"Ha! ha! a petticoat and a beauty!" he shouted, madly, as he descended the stairs, followed by eight or ten rough-looking men-"and a grey-beard too! To hell with the one, and to my cabin with the other!"</p> 
               <p>"Oh, spare-spare my dying, father, if ye are <emph>men!</emph>" shrieked poor Emily, folding her father's form to her breast.</p> 
               <p>"Take <emph>her</emph> aboard the Reckless; let <emph>him</emph> stay where he <emph>is!</emph>" shouted the leader.</p> 
               <p>His orders were obeyed almost as quickly as they were uttered. The slender form of the lovely maiden was raised in the rude arms of the fiendish pirates, and fainting she was hurried from the side of her poor old father.</p> 
               <p>"No money aboard; only cotton; and the market's as dull as continental money was during the revolution!" cried the leader, as he came on deck after the maiden was borne off. "Set fire to the old hulk-let her light herself to glory!"</p> 
               <p>Horrible-yet it was so. The fiends, after they had slain many, and disabled <emph>all</emph> the crew of the ill-fated merchantman, set her on fire, leaving the sick and helpless old man to perish with the wounded and dying. The beautiful daughter, unharmed as yet, had been borne aboard of a "long, black, rakish schooner," which was hove-too close aboard.</p> 
               <p>To her we will now glance for a few moments.</p> 
               <p>The ruffians who tore poor Emily from the side of her father had conveyed her aboard the schooner, and when she awakened from the swoon of terror into which she had fallen, she found herself alone in a cabin strangely but richly furnished. The ceilings were garnished with rich weapons and strange pictures; the floors were carpeted with silks of damascene; rich hangings and gilded ornaments were all around her.</p> 
               <p>"Where am I?" she murmured. "Where is my poor father?"</p> 
               <p>"Ha! ha! a beauty, by my love for the sex!" cried a rough, discordant voice; and as she glanced up, the poor girl saw the terrible face of him who had burst into the cabin of the packet ere she had fainted.</p> 
               <p>Involuntarily she sunk to her knees, breathing a prayer to God for protection!</p> 
               <p>"Come, come! Look up, lady! Let's see what you're like!" cried the same rough voice; and she felt a heavy hand laid upon her shoulder.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, God! have mercy on me! Kill me-but do not wrong me!" she moaned, in her utter agony.</p> 
               <p>"Look up, look up, and don't make a fool of yourself!" cried the pirate. "I'm not the man to wrong a <emph>woman;</emph> I love the whole breed!"</p> 
               <p>There was something in his voice which forced her to look up; she could not help it, and, as she did, she took the miniature from her breast, raised it toward him, and shrieked:</p> 
               <p>"James-James Armstrong! My <emph>brother!</emph>"</p> 
               <p>"<emph>Brother!</emph> Ah! my mother's picture! Emily, is this you-is <emph>he</emph>, our father in that burning ship?" shouted the pirate, as he tore the miniature from her grasp. "My <emph>father, not</emph> too late!" and, as he yelled these last words, he rushed from the cabin.</p> 
               <p>Minutes-and they seemed as <emph>hours</emph> to her-passed on, and that poor girl moved not from where she had knelt when the pirate bent over her. Minutes had gone by, and she heard slow steps approaching.</p> 
               <p>"Emily!" <emph>moaned</emph> a voice beside her.-"Emily, my <emph>sister!</emph>"</p> 
               <p>She raised her eyes; the pirate was there, but oh! how changed! His face, save where it was stained with powder and blood, was pale as if death had laid his frosty hand upon it! His form trembled from head to foot.</p> 
               <p>"<emph>Emily!</emph>" he murmured.</p> 
               <p>"James, where is <emph>our</emph> father?" was her reply.</p> 
               <pb n="10 (Illustration) -11 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6967-00000006"/> 
               <p>
                  <figure> 
                     <head>PIRATE OF THE GULF.</head> 
                  </figure>
                   
                  <figure> 
                     <head>THE MONUMENT ERECTED IN MEMORY OF THE FATHER OF THE PIRATE.</head> 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
               <pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6967-00000007"/> 
               <p>"Oh, God! I am his murderer! The ship is but a mass of flame; all on board are lost; I am his murderer, a <emph>pirate</emph> and a PARRICIDE!" groaned the wretched man.-"God forgive me-none other can!"</p> 
               <p>"My father!-alone-<emph>all</emph> alone!" moaned the wretched girl.</p> 
               <p>"No; as God hears me, you, Emily, shall be saved from all harm! I have erred-damned myself here and hereafter-but I will set you safe on shore in our native place, and then I will <emph>die!</emph>" cried the pirate.</p> 
               <p>"James-James, our father! Oh! my brother, this is <emph>worse</emph> than death!" moaned the girl. "Yet are you my <emph>brother!</emph>"</p> 
               <p>"Yes; and bad, vile, lost as I am, will do a brother's duty to thee, Emily!"</p> 
               <p>Reader, a brief explanation may lessen its <emph>romance</emph>, yet it will explain the <emph>reality</emph> of this story. The brother of Emily Armstrong, rendered desperate by intemperance, and associations and losses with gamblers in his native town, had broken the laws of the land and fled; he had taken refuge in New Orleans there had joined a remnant of the <hi rend="i"/>Lafitte band, and had become a pirate. His widowed father and only sister had followed him to New Orleans, in hopes of reclaiming and saving him; failing to find him there, and the father's health rapidly declining, they started to return to their native place. The reader knows the rest. The brother did take his sister safely home, but on that self-same night he committed suicide over his mother's grave, and became another of the lost victims to GAMING and INTEMPERANCE.</p> 
                
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="14 (Illustration) -15" xml:id="VAC6967-00000008"/> 
               <head>
                  <figure> 
                     <p>FLOWER OF THE DESERT.</p> 
                  </figure>
               </head> 
                
               <head>NUMBER TWO.</head> 
               <head type="sub">Lalla Zara-the Flower of the Desert.</head> 
               <epigraph> 
                  <q>
                     <lg type="quotation"> 
                        <l>"Lovely is the Arab maiden,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Leaning thoughtful there;</l> 
                        <l>While the languid gale of evening</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Lifts not her black hair.</l> 
                        <l>Purple is her broidered caftan;</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">And the golden band</l> 
                        <l>"Tells she is a chieftain's daughter</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">In that eastern land."</l> 
                     </lg>
                  </q> 
               </epigraph> 
               <p>OH, beautiful is "Beled el Jerid," or the "Land of Dates"-beautiful as the blue sky mixed with the fleecy clouds of summer,-beautiful as that eastern sea which boasts its Archipelago of lovely isles-beautiful because its desert is interspersed with many a green and flowery oasis. God, when he made the world, placed this garden of Nature between the bleak heights of the Atlas Mountains and the vast waste of the great Zahara; and midway between Morocco and Tripoli was the home of LALLA ZARA-she who was known far and near among the tribes of the Berbers, as THE FLOWER OF THE DESERT. Her father was the Chief of the Gadams-a small but warlike tribe, who owned no master save Gazzim, their chief, and who would fain have repudiated the tribute which he yearly yielded to the Bey of Tripoli. But Gazzim, though brave, was politic, and withal prudent; he knew that his tribe was too weak to wage successful war against <unclear>so</unclear> powerful a foe, unless united with the <unclear>other</unclear> tribes; therefore, he gave ten camels and six female slaves yearly as a tribute to the Bey of Tripoli. But all this has little to do with this story.</p> 
               <p>Lalla Zara had lived seventeen summers; and as she was the pride of her tribe, so was she the star of hope and joy to her father; for she was his only child. Five wives had he-yet all save one, his <emph>own</emph> ZULEIKA, had proved barren, and she, his first love and his last, had given him this child; and in the same glad, yet <emph>sad</emph> hour, had <emph>died!</emph>
               </p> 
               <p>Shall I tell how the dark clouds of misery wrapped around his heart; how his dry eyes burned with the desert-fire of that grief which the dew of sympathy may not soften? No, no; let the veil of merciful kindness hide all that which would but sadden the reader.</p> 
               <p>Seventeen summers had Lalla Zara lived; and who so beautiful as she could live so long without a lover! She had <emph>many</emph>-yet, as <emph>ever</emph>, there was but <emph>one</emph> unto whom she turned her heart, as the sun-flower daily turns its face unto its god. Hassan Ben Ali was poor, but he was brave and handsome; and he was the loved of Lalla Zara, and, in turn, the loving. The father did not frown upon their love-yet he cared not to part with his daughter; and he would not yield his oft-entreated consent to their union. And thus passed things, until the day and<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6967-00000009"/> hour which our artist has selected for giving the portraiture of our heroine.</p> 
               <p>It was evening; the hot sun was low in the west, and the maiden went, as was her custom, to the well for water; and she lingered there, for seldom had she to bear the brimming pitcher back to her father's tent. Hassan was ever near to perform that duty.</p> 
               <p>While yet she lingered by the well-side, she saw the turbaned heads, and the bright spear-blades of a troop of horsemen, sweeping toward her from a distant point, where the palm-trees made a cape out into the desert; but as she saw the main body pass by at a distance, and but <emph>one</emph> of the warriors ride toward the well, she had no fear. On came the single warrior, mounted on a jet-black steed, whose mane glistened like silken thread in the rays of the setting sun; and as he reined-up beside the well, the rider sprang lightly to the earth, and advancing, cowed low, as he said:</p> 
               <p>"Lady, I thirst; wilt thou give me to drink?"</p> 
               <p>The maiden only replied by actions; for she reached to him the brimming pitcher. He drank; and then, with an eye which, though bright, seemed to her almost too warm and bold, he gazed upon the lovely maiden.</p> 
               <p>"Thou art beautiful, lady! Hast thou a lover?" he cried, in a tone bordering upon insolence</p> 
               <p>"Thou wilt soon know, if thou dost tarry!" replied she, pointing to the form of one hurrying across the sands.</p> 
               <p>"So, so! One of the boors of a poor Berber tribe is thy lover! Thou art too beautiful for <emph>that!</emph>" said the <emph>insolent</emph>.</p> 
               <p>The maiden did not reply, but the blush of proud indignation mantled her cheek, rendering her even more beautiful than ever. Emboldened by her silence, perchance mistaking the meaning of her blushes, the stranger cried:</p> 
               <p>"Come, lady, wilt thou not fly with me? I have a palace which would shame yon Berber tents, as the stars of night shame the poor glow-worm's light!"</p> 
               <p>"I ask nothing that I have not; leave me, stranger!" said the maiden, in reply.</p> 
               <p>"Thou dost carry thyself proudly! I've a mind to humble thy pride!" cried the stranger, with a sneer.</p> 
               <p>"Ah! my father is coming hither!" cried the girl, as she saw four or five horsemen riding from the direction of her father's tents. "Stranger, if thou dost place value on thy <emph>life</emph>, go to thy own people! Go, and I will not repeat what thou hast uttered. Stay, and the peril be thine!"</p> 
               <p>"I go, <emph>but</emph> to return!" said the stranger, bitterly, as he leaped into his saddle, and sped swiftly away.</p> 
               <p>The maiden gazed at him with a sad and thoughtful, yet half-pleased air. She was pleased that now she was safe; glad that her friends were near;-yet there had been that in the look and tone of the stranger, as he left her, which filled her heart with fearful misgivings and strange forebodings. And with his head half-turned toward her, the stranger rode away, and joined his troop, already far distant.</p> 
               <p>Soon Hassan was by the maiden's side. He found her pale and trembling. A single tear hung like a pearl below each of her great black eyes; her bosom lifted her thin robes with the waves of emotion.</p> 
               <p>"Who was he that rode so swiftly away, love, when I approached?" cried Hassan; "and why this agitation? Has he insulted or offended thee? If so, by Allah-"</p> 
               <p>"No, no!" cried the girl, placing her hands to his lips, and interrupting him, "He did but ask for water, and pay me a foolish compliment, which fluttered me! 'Twas nothing-I cared not; for, <emph>dear</emph> Hassan, I saw thee coming!"</p> 
               <p>Short stories require sudden changes. So in this.</p> 
                
               <p>Three moons had filled and waned over that flowery spot in the desert; a fourth lifted its pale, slim crescent in the sky, and then went down early in the night, leaving all in darkness and quiet. Lalla Zara slumbered in her couch, in the inner tent of her father's camp, and blessed dreams of her loved Hassan made her heart warm. Suddenly a rush of steeds-the sound of voices-and then the quick clash of arms, broke upon her slumbers. Ere she could speak to the terrified women who were near-ere she could express her own alarm in words, or ask what was the meaning of this strange alarm-a band of rude men rushed into the tent, and she was seized, and borne quickly from the spot. In vain she screamed for aid-in vain she called upon the name of Allah-in vain she shrieked her lover's name; she was borne forth, lifted up before a horseman-and she fainted as she found herself carried with the speed of the wind away from her father's tents; and they, too, were on fire, lighting up the path of those who bore her away.</p> 
               <p>Another change. Within a garden attached to a palace, such an one as can only be seen in the Golden East, was a beautiful scene. The garden was filled with bowers and lovely plats of flowers. Here and there bright fountains cast their glittering treasures in the air. Groups of richly-dressed women were scattered around, but near them armed black slaves kept a careful and watchful guard. Around this garden a low wall of marble was built, and beyond it groves of oranges lifted their green heads, bowing with the weight of golden fruit.</p> 
               <p>Near the wall, alone and pensive, on a bank cushioned with flowers, sat a young female. Her face was pale-her head bowed down-her long hair strayed carelessly and unconfined over her bare shoulders. Gay were those around her-yet <emph>alone</emph> did she seem among them all. Suddenly the sounds of gaiety ceased. "He comes! he comes!" was whispered from mouth to mouth. The women ceased their dances-the slaves bowed their heads-and a richly-dressed man, armed and girded as nobles only were in that land, passed on He approached the side of the female who seemed so sad and lonely, but she lifted not her head. He paused before her.</p> 
               <p>"Zara!-flower of my soul!" he murmured.</p> 
               <p>"Ah!" she sighed with a start and a tremor from head to foot. "My <emph>master!</emph>"</p> 
               <p>"Nay: rather say your slave-for am I not bound in the shackles of <emph>love!</emph>" cried the noble.</p> 
               <p>"Mehemet, thou art powerful-I am thy slave!" sighed the pale girl-<emph>our</emph> Zara, for it was she.</p> 
               <p>"If so, why dost thou avoid me? Why sit here like the drooping flower day by day, and refuse to raise the 'broidered handkerchief which I cast at thy feet!" said the chief.</p> 
               <p>"Thou art the Bey. Thou art my <emph>master!</emph>" sighed the girl.</p> 
               <p>"No, Zara! Ever since I beheld thee at thy father's well, I have been a slave to love of thee. Thou hast been chosen as my favorite-then why dost thou act thus?"</p> 
               <p>"Cage the young dove, and if its eye grow dim, ask it wherefore! Bind the antelope-if it sicken, ask it wherefore! Unmate them both-then bid them be happy, ere you bid me smile!"</p> 
               <p>"Foolish child-did I not love thee I should be angry!" said the Bey, with an ill-concealed air of impatience. Then, after a slight pause, he added: "I will leave thee one night more for consideration, Zara-and hearken, girl; <emph>but</emph> one! Thy fate must be decided by thyself! Be mine willingly on the morrow, or the bow-string is thy fate!"</p> 
               <p>"Then wait not for the morrow! Let<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6967-00000010"/> the decision be made at once!" cried the high-spirited girl.</p> 
               <p>The Bey smiled haughtily, but turned away, and returned to the palace without replying.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, Allah! save me for the sake of poor Hassan! Take me to thyself!" murmured the wretched girl. Tears gushed from her eyes as she spoke-and her bosom heaved up and down with the tempest of agitation, as the lily heaves on the wind-stirred lake.</p> 
               <p>Ah! she starts to her feet! What is the cause? Close before her a single tress of glossy hair bound to a pebble is thrown! She bends down and picks it up! She gazes eagerly upon it. "It is my own!" she murmurs. "<emph>Hassan!</emph> Oh, can he be near? To him I gave this tress when our troth was plighted in the blessed Beled el Jerid!"</p> 
               <p>Eagerly she strained her eyes around. Ah! there, just beyond that wall, in the shadow of the orange groves-beneath the low bending branches she sees a crouching form. She moves toward the wall. With body bent close-very close, to the ground, the person beyond glides toward her. The guards do not see him-now he is by the wall.</p> 
               <p>"Blessed be Allah! It is thee, Hassan, come to die with me!" murmurs the poor girl.</p> 
               <p>"No, Zara-no; but to <emph>save</emph> thee have I come!" whispered the voice of her own true love. "In the shadows of yonder grove thirty of our own brave Berbers stand beside the swiftest steeds of our tribe. Their lances are left behind; but a bare scimetar without a sheath is in each one's hand. We have come to take thee home or to die in the trial. Wilt thou go?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes-or die!" murmured Zara.</p> 
               <p>"Then boldly leap the wall! I will take thee in my arms-one moment, and we are in the grove; then, once mounted, and away upon the steeds of Berber, pursuit is vain."</p> 
               <p>The glad girl wanted no second bidding. With a wild bound she cleared the low wall-the next instant was in her lover's arms. and before the astonished slaves could yell out their alarm, she was within the shadows of the nearest orange grove. But one instant later, and a band of horsemen dashed out and sped toward the desert. In their centre was one who bore before him the lovely form of his rescued bride-LALLA ZARA, "the Flower of the Desert."</p> 
               <p>The Bey Mehemet did not order a pursuit. He knew well how fleet were the Berber steeds-how dangerous it was to awaken the wrath of the Bedouin tribes, and then pursue them into their own haunts; and without an effort he resigned the lovely maiden to the husband of her heart. And when once more the Chief of the Gadams pressed his child to his bosom, and heard how boldly she had been rescued by the brave Hassan, he did not withhold his consent to the union, but blessed it, and adopted Hassan as his successor, and the future Chief of the tribe.</p> 
                
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="20 (Illustration) -21" xml:id="VAC6967-00000011"/> 
               <head>
                  <figure> 
                     <p>THE GRECIAN WIFE.-See page 21.</p> 
                  </figure>
               </head> 
                
               <head>NUMBER THREE</head> 
               <head type="sub">The Grecian Wife.-A Tale of the Archipelago.</head> 
               <epigraph> 
                  <q>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"And sad beneath that dark browed sky,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">By lightning flashes shown more dark,</l> 
                        <l>I watch with onward straining eye;</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">For, oh! behold yon Grecian bark,</l> 
                        <l>Where stoutest hand scarce holds the helm,</l> 
                        <l>'Mid whirling waves that rush to whelm."</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"That bark to aid, a torch's light</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Is gleaming through the troubled air</l> 
                        <l>
                           <emph>She</emph> lifts it there! In wild affright,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">A Wife-a Mother-lifts it there,</l> 
                        <l>For him, who, spite of coming wreck,</l> 
                        <l>In calmness treads his splitting deck."</l> 
                     </lg>
                  </q> 
               </epigraph> 
               <p>"OH, God, guard my brave Albano!-the God of Heaven save him in this fearful night!"</p> 
               <p>Thus moaned a lovely woman, whose age could not be more than twenty. Why need I pause to say that she was beautiful, or to contemplate that which my readers may discover at a glance, by looking at the artist's engraving?</p> 
               <p>The wife was standing at the latticed window of a cottage which nestled in a little gorge of a hill, close on the shore of the rock-bound Isle of Naxio, and so close, too, that the wild roar of the breakers even drowned the shrill whistle of the gale.</p> 
               <p>Back, in the centre of the room, was an older female, engaged in sewing; and by her knee stood a little urchin of some four or five years old, playing with the ball of thread in her lap. The Greek mother turned from the window, and as her tearful eyes glanced upon her young boy, she sprang to his side, raised him to her lips, and as she kissed him fervently, she murmured:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, that thy father were here also!"</p> 
               <p>"When will father come home, sweet mother?" lisped the little one.</p> 
               <p>"Hark! Was not that a gun?" cried the mother.</p> 
               <p>"Yes." said the servant-woman. "Yes I heard it plainly!"</p> 
               <p>"Hark! Again? No, 'twas thunder!" cried the Greek wife, hurrying to the window.</p> 
               <p>As she gazed out into the pitchy darkness, she saw another flash; and then, in a few moments, she heard another report.</p> 
               <p>"It is Albano!" she cried. "Boy, it is thy father! Irene, quick-light a torch; we will hurry down to the cross, by the sea-shore, where the poor Santorinio's were buried; for, in this fearful darkness, he cannot enter the narrow port, I fear!"</p> 
               <p>The servant hurried to obey, and in a few moments a torch was lighted, and the mother, child, and nurse hurried out in the storm, wending their way down toward the shore. In a short time they stood close by the sea-shore, in a spot where several old columns, marble slabs, &amp;c., were strewed upon the earth, and where a large cross of<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6967-00000012"/> grey marble was firmly set in the ground. And as they stood there, the flaring torch, enlivened by the wild gale, lighted up the pale cheek of the mother, and showed her plainly, as she leaned there, like an angel against the emblem of faith, imploring God's mercy on him whom she loved;-and it also showed the terrified servant, cowering near her feet, gazing out to seaward, and shielding, all she could, the form of the young boy from the cold spray-gale that swept in from off the wild sea.</p> 
               <p>"Why is all so dark? Oh, God! this is terrible! If he sees my light he will surely find the harbor!" cried the wife, as she waved the flaring torch-light above her head.</p> 
               <p>Suddenly, a long quivering flash of lightning darted across the clouded sky. And as the wife gazed eagerly to seaward, she saw plainly the white glance of a sail, flying over the dark mass of water, even as the white-winged gull skims the surface of the sea. And while the flash yet lighted sky and sea, she noticed that it, like her husband's craft, was a three-masted, lateen-rigged vessel.</p> 
               <p>"It is Albano!" she cried; "Oh, God save him!"</p> 
               <p>"Ah!" she added, as, farther out at sea, a bright flash, quickly followed by the loud boom of a gun, was seen; "Ah! there must be another peril beside that of the storm!"</p> 
               <p>Another, and then another flash, each followed by a report, was seen; and then again a flame of lightning opened the sky, and illuminated the sea. Then plainly could the poor woman see that a large vessel was close in the rear of the first, and that the cannons were fired from the larger, which was evidently in chase of the other.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, God, this is terrible! The Turks must be following poor Albano! Human enemies are even more cruel than the warring elements!"</p> 
               <p>To understand this scene, we must place ourselves on board the Greek vessel at the same moment when the Greek wife first glanced out from the window of her little cot.</p> 
               <p>On the deck of that vessel were twenty men all armed with yataghans and pistols-men who looked fit to cope with any foe! Close by the helm, speaking in a low tone with the helmsman, stood the captain, now glancing back over the wild waste of waters; then looking at the compass in the binnacle, and then again asking the leadsman, who was sounding as they sped on, what depth of water he had.</p> 
               <p>"Twenty minutes more, and we will be in the cove, and darkness will save us from the pursuit!" muttered the captain; and as he spoke, a flash-the hiss of a shot thrown close by the mark, and the quick following report of a cannon, showed the nature of the pursuit he alluded to.</p> 
               <p>"What water?" he asked of the leadsman.</p> 
               <p>"By the dip, four!" was the reply</p> 
               <p>"Ha! shoaling so fast? Luff up a point!" he cried to the helmsman.</p> 
               <p>"Luff it is, sir!" cried the obedient sea man, bringing the vessel up closer to the wind.</p> 
               <p>'There, so, steady. North-east, half east will be sure to take us in-keep the lead going lively!"</p> 
               <p>"Aye, aye sir!" replied the leadsman.</p> 
               <p>"Light ho! A light on our lee bow!" cried a man from forward, in the vessel.</p> 
               <p>"Curses!" muttered the captain-"curses on such folly! The infernal Turk will follow us in if that beacon is kept alight."</p> 
               <p>"It will be impossible for him to strike the channel!" said the pilot at the helm. "It was a chance that we could get in without yon friendly light, which, if I err not is at the cross by the sea-shore."</p> 
               <p>"Aye-my poor Haidee has brought it there, thinking to serve me! Little does she dream of the peril which is worse than the storm-a peril too near, for in that Moslem ship there are five hundred men, and all ready to contend with my scanty band."</p> 
               <p>"Bear away two points!" he added, to the pilot. "We must go in-and if they follow us, the peril be theirs!"</p> 
               <p>The seaman shifted his helm slightly, and on, swooping over the great waves, bore the beautiful little craft, now heading in nearly toward the beacon-torch, held aloft by that fond and faithful wife. Her masts bent like reeds before the gale, for all of her canvass was set, but still when the lightning flashed, not an half-mile astern could be seen that large ship, also covered with canvass, looking like a fierce hawk in pursuit of a white-winged dove. The Greek captain looked first towards the torch on shore, then towards the ship in chase, and muttered:</p> 
               <p>"That torch will ruin all! I might have escaped him before, but if his pilot knows the coast at all, he too will gain the harbor!"</p> 
               <p>He gazed a moment longer, then turned again to his helmsman. "Keep away for yonder light!" said he.</p> 
               <p>"It will run us ashore!" said the pilot. "The light is by the cross; but a cable's length beyond, and we are safe in the cove!"</p> 
               <p>"Safe!-Safe with that vulture astern, coming down upon us?" cried the captain. "No, Luigi, we must beach the boat and run the risk of defending my cottage; for the vile Turk shall never place foot on <emph>this</emph> deck!"</p> 
               <p>The pilot made no reply, but at once shifted the helm, and with a free sheet the fated bark bounded on towards the shore.</p> 
               <p>"Secure your arms-you will soon need them!" cried the captain, and then as he passed forward, he gave all a caution to prepare for the shock, when the keel of the vessel struck.</p> 
               <p>So near now were they that they could plainly see the terrified faces of the little group on shore. The next moment by a rough, harsh shock-they knew the keel was on the rock; then as a surge swept them madly on, the strained bark struck heavier yet, the over-burdened masts snapped in twain, all was wreck and confusion. But the Greek captain had not thrown his vessel in a place to endanger the lives of his crew. She was of light draught, and the third surge threw her high up on the land. The crew, one by one, hurried out of her, and soon they stood on the shore with their weapons, gazing at the ship which had so closely followed them.</p> 
               <p>"She has a pilot on board! See, she enters the channel-there, she luffs up to gain the cove, where she may anchor in safety!" cried Luigi, the pilot.</p> 
               <p>But the Greek captain was now in the arms of his tearful, yet happy wife-happy that he had gained the shore with life. As she saw his loved form springing through the spray toward her, she dropped the blazing torch, and with a wild cry of joy rushed forward to meet him. With her glad kisses, she, for a moment, kept him from speaking, and then as she paused, cried:-</p> 
               <p>"Oh, I thank God and the Holy Mother for thy safety, Albano. I had feared thou wouldst never reach the shore on this terrible night!"</p> 
               <p>"We have no time for words, loved one, we must hurry up to the cottage-for see, there sweeps a foe who knows no pity-to whom mercy is a stranger. In ten minutes more he will be safe in the harbor, and then-"</p> 
               <p>The Greek did not finish his remark-but as he looked at his fair wife, and at the boy who was now clinging to his legs, and calling him father, an ashy paleness, betokening<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6967-00000013"/> ing the agony of his brave heart, overspread his face.</p> 
               <p>"Up, men-to the cot-up quick, and arm for the strife! Follow me!" he cried; and rapidly ascending the hill, carrying the boy in his arms, the father hurried. In a few moments they were all in the cot, and a large trap-door was raised from the centre of the room, disclosing beneath, an armory filled with weapons. The crew seemed well acquainted with the contents of this place, for one or two stepped down the little staircase, and at once commenced passing up guns and pistols, with supplies of ammunition.</p> 
               <p>"Load every weapon! We may have need of all!" cried the Greek.</p> 
               <p>What a strange scene was that! In their singular, but picturesque dress, twenty men were busy in preparing weapons of destruction; scarce a word uttered amongst them; but on the face of each that calm determination which speaks plainer than words-</p> 
               <p>"<emph>We will do or die!</emph>"</p> 
               <p>And there, pale, yet with her love-lighted eyes bent upon her husband, stood the Greek wife; and he was by the window listening and looking forth into the darkness beyond.</p> 
               <p>"Be hasty, men! I see lights yonder on the shore-they are landing!" cried the captain. Glancing toward his wife, he added:</p> 
               <p>"Dear Haidee, take the child and Irene, and go down into the vault. You will be safer there!"</p> 
               <p>"I will not leave thee, Albano! Irene, carry the boy down, and stay with him!"</p> 
               <p>"But, Haidee, you are exposed to unnecessary danger here. A chance shot might destroy thee!"</p> 
               <p>"I have shared thy pleasures-why should I hesitate to share thy danger?"</p> 
               <p>"But it is useless, love! Thou canst not aid us!"</p> 
               <p>"Can I not? See if I know not the use of these weapons-Ah! look there!" As she spoke, she pointed to flaring torches, down near the sea-side, and by their motion it was plain to see that the bearers were hastening toward the house.</p> 
               <p>"Out with the lights-bar the doors, and be silent as death!" cried the Greek.-"Come hither to the window, six of you, and rest your pieces on the sill, so that they may cover the path up the shore. Be ready to take up other guns! All depends upon beating them back with a close fire. Remember Bozarris, and fire low!"</p> 
               <p>Without a word he was obeyed. He drew back slightly, and again urged his wife to descend into the armory. At last she did so. Then, for a few moments, all was still, except the loud howling of the storm without. Then a confused murmur was heard; then, in a few moments, the sound of voices, and the tread of many feet.</p> 
               <p>"Hold your fire! Be calm till I give the word!" said the Greek.</p> 
               <p>The advancing party reached the little plain in front of the cot and here paused, as if to hold consultation before commencing the attack.</p> 
               <p>Then a single one seemed to advance; for a heavy tread was heard on the plain, while all the rest were silent. A rough, loud voice cried:</p> 
               <p>"What, ho, there! Albano, surrender to thy masters!"</p> 
               <p>"Oh, God! 'tis the voice of Murika, the Renegade!" cried Haidee, who had crept up again to her husband's side. "It is the voice of that dreadful man-it is for me that he has come!"</p> 
               <p>"No wonder, if 'tis Murika, that he knew the channel so well!" muttered the old pilot.</p> 
               <p>Meantime, the large form of Albano was trembling from head to foot. Not with fear, but with wrath; for a foe whom he hated more than all the Turks in the world-a <hi rend="i"/>renegade Greek, was before him-one who had, in earlier years, attempted to win his Haidee from his side.</p> 
               <p>"Stand by the door, ten of you!" he whispered; "cock your guns-loosen your yataghans in their sheaths-and when the word is given, fire! Then let steel do the rest. Haidee, love, stay within doors-stay for our child's sake!"</p> 
               <p>"No answer?" cried the voice outside. "Perchance the dog is not at home. But his fair wife should vouchsafe a reply.-What, ho! fair Haidee! 'tis an ancient lover of thine calls to thee!"</p> 
               <p>"Speak to him-put him off his guard!" whispered the Greek.</p> 
               <p>"Who is there?" cried Haidee, with her shrill voice.</p> 
               <p>"Thy friend, fair Haidee! Where is thy husband? We have come to sup with him-I and my friends!"</p> 
               <p>"Thou shalt not be disappointed!" cried the brave Greek, then as he unbarred the door, he shouted, "<emph>fire!</emph>" Quick as thought a deadly volley was poured in upon the dense crowd-then as he drew the bright steel from its sheath, the Greek, close followed by his crew, rushed upon the astonished foe, shouting-"Bozarris! remember Bozarris!" as they went. For a moment, the Turks fell back-and that moment was a terrible one to them, for not a Greek was wounded as yet, and they mowed down their turbaned foes by the dozen. But the Renegade was as yet unharmed-and led on by him they recovered, and joined by fresh forces from below, they made a bold front. Now, the small party of Albano began to suffer. In a moment, two were so badly wounded that their comrades bore them back to the cottage. And now the angel <emph>woman</emph> in Haidee appeared. Fearless of the rattling shots, fearless of the terrible sounds of warfare so near, she calmly lighted her lamps, and then bent down to aid the wounded! Tearing the linen scarf from her waist, she bound up their bleeding limbs, and now Irene, her servant, came to her aid. And her boy, brave as he was beautiful, knowing, too, that danger was near, had seized a sabre, and there he stood, his great black eyes flashing, ready to defend, so far as he could, his noble mother.</p> 
               <p>But outside, where the battle raged, only when the red lightning glimmered across the sky, could the combatants plainly tell where and how their leaders were placed. Though trying to reach each other, they had not been able for several minutes after the combat commenced, and when at last their eyes met, it was in the verge of a pale light cast from the lamp which poor Haidee had lighted, that she might assist the wounded. And when their eyes met, both seemed to feel that on themselves the issue of that battle depended. Bounding toward each other, their swords crossed.</p> 
               <p>"This for thy treachery!" cried Albano, as he aimed a heavy blow at the turbaned head of the <choice>
                     <sic>renagade</sic>
                     <corr>renegade</corr>
                  </choice>.</p> 
               <p>"And that for thy bride, who soon shall be mine!" replied the villain, as he parried the Greek's blow, and returned it with one which would have been fatal, had not the wily Greek sprang back from its reach.-Quick as lightning then were interchanged their blows and parries, and all of the combatants paused as if to see what was to be the result of this combat. Blow after blow rapid pass, and still swifter parry,-a pause now and then as the panting combatants watched each other with fierce eyes, and still neither seemed to gain any advantage.</p> 
               <p>But ah, fatal moment! Haidee had bound up the wounds of those who had been brought to her, and approaching the window to see how the combat went on, she saw her own Albano face to face with the dreaded Murika. She could not repress<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6967-00000014"/> the scream of terror which rose from her heart to her lips. Recognising the well known voice, Albano turned to see if some insolent foe had not seized her, that moment left his breast unguarded, and the fiendish Murika drove his sabre home to its very hilt, in that noble bosom. In vain the Greeks rushed on to avenge their leader, in vain they strove to stem the tide of swollen numbers. One moment of terrible slaughter, one moment of fearful action, and not one Greek barred the path of Murika to the cottage door. He entered the cottage, and two dying Greeks near the door, were its only defenders; two blows of his red blade finished them.</p> 
               <p>There on the far side of the room, with unbound and disheveled hair, holding a torch in one hand, and clasping her boy with the other, knelt poor Haidee! Her dark eyes were wildly bright, not with terror, but with desperation, for she had witnessed her husband's death. Close behind her, with clasped hands, face distorted with terror, stood the pale-faced servant.</p> 
               <p>"Ah ha! lovely bride of Albano! So fair Haidee, mine at last!" cried the wild renegade, with a mocking laugh, as he stood near the threshold.</p> 
               <p>The Greek wife uttered no words. Her eye glanced once down into the armory, then with a smile-yes, a smile-she beckoned him toward her.</p> 
               <p>Followed by a crowd of his fiendish followers, he <emph>did</emph> advance; she waited until he had almost reached her, then with a wild cry, she said:</p> 
               <p>"Albano, I come!" Before the words had reached the ear of the renegade, she dashed the lighted torch down into the vault beneath, and in a second all was fire, smoke and <choice>
                     <sic>defeaning</sic>
                     <corr>deafening</corr>
                  </choice> thunder.</p> 
               <p>Few of the Turks regained their vessel. All who were in that cot were scattered around with its shattered timbers. The Grecian wife, pure in death as life, had fired the magazine, and joined her dead husband, while she avenged his death. Would that wives were as pure! and as brave in these modern days!</p> 
                
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="28 (Illustration) -29" xml:id="VAC6967-00000015"/> 
               <head>
                  <figure> 
                     <p>BIANCA'S BRIDAL EVE-See page 35.</p> 
                  </figure>
               </head> 
                
               <head>NUMBER FOUR.</head> 
               <head type="sub">Bianca's Bridal Eve.-A Tale of Venice.</head> 
               <epigraph> 
                  <q>
                     <lg type="quotation"> 
                        <l>"Stand here! Now let thine eyes drink in the sights</l> 
                        <l>Of Venice.-Wonder upon wonder, strewn</l> 
                        <l>Like jewels on the wild floors of the deep;</l> 
                        <l>Innumerable; disordered. Spoil on spoil,</l> 
                        <l>Wrung from the Candiote or the Moor. Behold!</l> 
                        <l>Those columns, mouldering with the touch of time,</l> 
                        <l>One stood on Grecian earth, perhaps once slept</l> 
                        <l>(All virgin marble) in Athenian caves,</l> 
                        <l>Till some rare sculptor wrought them,-for what end?</l> 
                        <l>Alas, but to he lost!"</l> 
                     </lg>
                  </q> 
               </epigraph> 
               <div type="part"> 
                  <head>PART FIRST.</head> 
                  <p>STREETS paved with glittering water-rich in the light of the sun as molten gold; bright beneath the pale moon as liquid silver-such are <emph>thy</emph> pathways, oh, Venice, even <emph>yet "Queen of the East."</emph>
                  </p> 
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="i"/>Bianca di Clari!</p> 
                  <p>READER, would you know who she was? Yea? Then read on! She was the fairest flower that ever bloomed in Beauty's garden! She was the last scion of the noble-blooded Clari. Born the daughter of a Doge of that proud city-from his haughty blood, mingled with that of her mother, <unclear>Iqusa</unclear> Alfieri-came the beauty and the pride of her who is the heroine of this story. At fourteen she was an orphan. Her father fell by an assassin's hand; her mother died in six short weeks afterwards, with a broken heart. And then Bianca was the last scion of the <hi rend="i"/>Clari family. She became the ward of Giovanni Alfieri, her mother's only brother-who, though her uncle, was her senior by only ten years. He was a noble-a ducal coronet was emblazoned on his shield. He had wealth-a palace in that city of palaces, which vied proudly with all others. And to the palace of her bachelor uncle, young Bianca was removed, at the date of her bereavement; and there until the hour selected by the artist for the picture annexed to this story, she resided. But I will here pause to describe her as she looked at that hour. Her age was but seventeen years, yet had she arrived at the full perfection of womanhood; for, in those sunny climes, the human form, like the flowers of the land, buds, blossoms, and, alas! <emph>fades</emph>, ere, in our more temperate clime, the season of girlhood is passed. Bianca was tall-yet every limb, her small hands, delicate feet, full bust, were in such perfect proportion as only a sculptor's dream could picture. She was <emph>queenly</emph> in form as she was in manner. Her proud soul flashed at times through her great black eyes-then again her dreamy, loving, voluptuous heart seemed to nestle in their liquid depths. And the silky-looking lashes drooped so modestly over them, you could hardly deem nature had bestowed them there, but that they were some exquisite invention of art, placed there to but half-conceal; and thus with contrast, add to the beauty, expression, and<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6967-00000016"/> brilliancy of the soulful orbs beneath. Her features were <hi rend="i"/>Italian-such as Canova left in marble, and Angelo transferred to canvass. Have you gazed upon the ripened pomegranate-seen its lovely rind, thin and transparent, hued brunette, by the warm sun, its little juicy veins seen beneath? Such was her cheek. Have you seen a brow white as alabaster, without its oily gloss-looking warm, yet like the uncrusted snow that drops unstained upon the hill-side-a brow not <emph>too</emph> lofty, yet arched by jet black hair? Such was hers. Have you seen lips that parted with the breath, just revealing a row of pearly teeth, showing whiter than pearls, because contrasted with lips full, plump, and red as the bursting cherry-lips which <emph>spoke</emph> without motion? Such were hers! Have you gazed at some mad painter's creation, who dwelt in an ideal world of loveliness and transferred the beauties of <emph>all</emph> his creations into one, and then <emph>died</emph>, with the wish to go to the world where <emph>she</emph> was to be found? Then fancy that Bianca di Clari was even <emph>so</emph> gloriously beautiful.</p> 
                  <p>Though secluded from the world by her uncle, never allowed to go abroad unveiled, yet, thanks to the tongues of sundry indiscreet duennas and serving-maids, the fame of her extraordinary beauty got abroad, and ere the time when this story opens, many an offer came from noble families, to the uncle-from those who wished to ally sons with wealth and pure blood, enhanced in value by surprising beauty. But Giovanni Alfieri received them all coldly-gave them no reasons for so doing; but haughtily declined all offers. If asked why he did not permit his ward to attend <foreign xml:lang="FRA">fetes</foreign> of the nobility, why he veiled her so closely from the world, he replied, that it was her own choice. But we soon will see whether he spoke truly.</p> 
                  <p>"I cannot sleep to-night!" murmured Bianca. "Though it is now midnight, my eyes are not weary, nor my soul at rest, so that I may pray to my Holy Mother, and lay my head upon my pillow!"</p> 
                  <p>She was all alone in her chamber, but when, one moment later, a guitar was heard beneath the window, a female hurried into the room.</p> 
                  <p>"Music-lady! I hear music on the Lagune!" said the duenna.</p> 
                  <p>"Yes-some passing revellers, probably!" sighed the lady, carelessly.</p> 
                  <p>"No!" said the attendant. "Hear, they are beneath the window!'</p> 
                  <p>"Hist! let me hear the words of that song!" murmured Bianca, as a rich, strong voice rose in notes louder than the accompanying guitar, which had opened the</p> 
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
                        <body > 
                           <div type="poem"> 
                              <head>SERENADE.</head> 
                              <lg type="stanza"> 
                                 <l>"List, lady, list to the song of</l> 
                                 <l rend="ti-2">The gondolier,</l> 
                                 <l>Hark, lady, hark to his words</l> 
                                 <l rend="ti-2">Without fear;</l> 
                                 <l>He sings of love, <emph>true</emph> love and pure.</l> 
                                 <l rend="ti-2">Then lady hear;</l> 
                                 <l>And with the light of thy dark eyes,</l> 
                                 <l rend="ti-2">His vision <unclear>cheer</unclear>
                                 </l> 
                              </lg> 
                              <lg type="stanza"> 
                                 <l>Though proud hearts are thine, lady mine,</l> 
                                 <l rend="ti-2">None can there be</l> 
                                 <l>More true than mine is unto thine</l> 
                                 <l rend="ti-2">Linked tenderly!</l> 
                                 <l>Each day I think, and ev'ry night</l> 
                                 <l rend="ti-2">I dream of thee;</l> 
                                 <l>And now, my love, when others sleep,</l> 
                                 <l rend="ti-2">I sing to thee!</l> 
                              </lg> 
                              <lg type="stanza"> 
                                 <l>Then listen, listen to my lay,</l> 
                                 <l rend="ti-2">Oh, lady fair,</l> 
                                 <l>For I've worshipped thee in silence,</l> 
                                 <l rend="ti-2">And wild despair</l> 
                                 <l>Until the weight of woe, I could</l> 
                                 <l rend="ti-2">No longer bear;</l> 
                                 <l>Then, lady, list to the song of</l> 
                                 <l rend="ti-2">The Gondolier!</l> 
                              </lg> 
                              <lg type="stanza"> 
                                 <l>Pure as the wave beneath the moon,</l> 
                                 <l rend="ti-2">His love for thee,</l> 
                                 <l>True as angels unto Heaven,</l> 
                                 <l rend="ti-2">He'll ever be;</l> 
                                 <l>His heart, his hand, his knightly word</l> 
                                 <l rend="ti-2">From falsehood free,</l> 
                                 <l>He gives this night, and forever</l> 
                                 <l rend="ti-2">To thee-to <emph>thee!</emph>"</l> 
                              </lg> 
                           </div> 
                        </body> 
                     </floatingText>
                  </q> 
                   
                  <p>"<emph>Knightly</emph> word, he said!" murmured Bianca; "Who can he be?"</p> 
                  <p>"Some gay gallant, who has heard of thy beauty, lady!" said the duenna, carelessly.</p> 
                  <p>"Hark-hist! he sings again!" whispered Bianca. "How melodious is his voice; and yet how sad! I am sure he is unhappy!"</p> 
                  <p>"Lovers are always unhappy, lady; at least they say they are, in order to excite the pity of those whom they love-knowing that pity is akin to love!"</p> 
                  <p>"Hist, hist! let me hear those words!"</p> 
                  <p>After a brief prelude, the singer again raised his manly voice, in a verse different from the half-prosaic stanzas he before had sung: <q>
                        <lg type="quotation"> 
                           <l>"Oh, am I heard, lady-love,</l> 
                           <l rend="ti-1">Heard by thee, adord?</l> 
                           <l>If so, a boon, lady-love,</l> 
                           <l rend="ti-1">By me implord;</l> 
                           <l>Oh, east forth a single token</l> 
                           <l rend="ti-1">Down upon the sea!</l> 
                           <l>Oh, drive me not, hopeless,</l> 
                           <l rend="ti-1">Far away from thee;</l> 
                           <l>I am thine, and thine only,</l> 
                           <l rend="ti-1">Be merciful to me!"</l> 
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                  </p> 
                  <p>"What would you do, lady?-do not; 'tis rash!" cried the duenna, as the fair girl snatched a scarf of crimson satin woven with gold, from her own neck, and cast it from the window.</p> 
                  <p>"Rash, slave? He asked a token-he has it!" said Bianca, proudly.</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, and I fear me harm may come of it," sighed the attendant. "If my master knew of it-"</p> 
                  <p>"But, Sylvestra, you will not tell him of it-see, there is a ring-a rare jewel; put it on thy finger, and remember that <emph>silence</emph> is a great virtue in <emph>woman!</emph>"</p> 
                  <p>The eyes of the woman glittered with pleasure's light, as she glanced at the costly gift, but as a knock was heard at the door, she exclaimed:</p> 
                  <p>"It is our master! Ever jealous, he has heard that music, and-"</p> 
                  <p>"And what?" said Giovanni Alfieri, entering the room, unbidden.</p> 
                  <p>"Nothing-Signor!" murmured the woman.</p> 
                  <p>"Go! I wish to speak to my niece, alone!" he thundered.</p> 
                  <p>The servant obeyed, and then, with a dark and threatening look, Alfieri turned toward Bianca.</p> 
                  <p>"Why art thou up so late?" he asked.</p> 
                  <p>"Because I did not feel like sleeping."</p> 
                  <p>"<emph>No</emph>-of course not, when thou couldst listen to drunken revellers who spend their days in dissipation, and their nights in running over the Lagune, singing love-songs!"</p> 
                  <p>"It is not <emph>my</emph> fault, uncle, if they come and sing to me. You never give me an opportunity to see cavaliers, and I cannot invite them to serenade me."</p> 
                  <p>"Art thou so fond of music?"</p> 
                  <p>"I have a <emph>heart</emph>. Who that has one can live and not be fond of music?"</p> 
                  <p>"Well-well, girl! But I have serious matters to talk of to thee! Sit down here by me, and listen!'</p> 
                  <p>The fair girl took the seat, for she thought she heard the plash of the gondolier's oar as he rowed away.</p> 
                  <p>"Bianca!" continued Alfieri-"Bianca, this is a strange world!"</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, uncle, but thanks to God, there is another and a better to come!"</p> 
                  <p>"Poh! I wish not to speak of that!-Listen to me. Society-men-<emph>fools</emph>-have made many rules which are not sanctioned by <emph>Nature</emph>. They have in their insensate ideas of social necessities invented relationships and rules, which are as far from Nature's laws as the sun-girdled equator is from the icy north!"</p> 
                  <p>"I do not comprehend you, uncle."</p> 
                  <p>"Then I will try to explain, Bianca. You are now a <emph>woman</emph>-I am as a <emph>man</emph> but a little in advance of your perfection. I am said to<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6967-00000017"/> possess manly beauty: I am but ten years thy senior, and full of all life's strength and fervor.'</p> 
                  <p>"Well, uncle!' said Bianca, "what of all this?"</p> 
                  <p>"What of <emph>all</emph> this, child?" cried he; "Listen, and I will tell you! It is much, very much, to us! Do you believe in all these silly customs?"</p> 
                  <p>"My mother did; and she has gone to Heaven!" replied the girl.</p> 
                  <p>"It is of earth, and of heavenly pleasures <emph>on</emph> earth, that I would speak!" replied he, "Hearken to me, Bianca-I <emph>love</emph> you!"</p> 
                  <p>"<emph>Uncle!</emph>"</p> 
                  <p>"You need not gaze at me in surprise, Bianca, or start back in horror. I love you-would wed you!"</p> 
                  <p>"You are my <emph>uncle!</emph>"</p> 
                  <p>"Aye? who made me so. I am a man and you a woman-born not of our own request and consent, but thrown together by fate; and I <emph>have</emph> loved, and <emph>do</emph> love you!"</p> 
                  <p>"Uncle, do not speak so. You fill my soul with horror. Leave me-please leave me!"</p> 
                  <p>"Never, girl, never, until you promise to be mine!"</p> 
                  <p>"Signor, this is too much. You presume upon my helplessness-think me in your power!" cried the lady, drawing up her form proudly. "But, sir, I have my mother's pride, and my father's courage. Leave me-I <emph>command</emph> you!"</p> 
                  <p>The look of fondness in the Venetian's face changed to a dark flush of anger.</p> 
                  <p>"Girl!' he cried; "thou shalt choose between these; either consent to be mine, or I will bestow thee and thy fortune within the dark walls of a convent!"</p> 
                  <p>"Then slight change will there be, for even here am I a prisoner-caged like a captive.-<emph>Ah!</emph>"</p> 
                  <p>A sweet note of the guitar, again sounded on the Lagune, and as she made the single exclamation, Bianca sprang to the open window and looked out. She saw a gondola gliding away, and a tall figure in its prow held aloft the scarf she had cast from the window. Giovanni also saw this, and he recognised in that scarf a gift that he had made his niece but a few days before.</p> 
                  <p>He uttered no word when he saw this, but his dark eyes reddened with madness, and he bit his lips until the red blood gushed from them and trickled down upon his beard. Raising his clenched hand, he shook it menacingly toward the distant gondola, and then strode heavily from the room.</p> 
                  <p>In the ante-room he found Sylvestra, pale and trembling too; for she saw how fearfully angered he was.</p> 
                  <p>"So! This is the watch you keep!" he muttered between his grinding teeth. "What cavalier was that, to whom she gave the scarf?"</p> 
                  <p>"My lord, I know not!" murmured the woman-her words almost inarticulate from terror.</p> 
                  <p>"Fool, do not try to deceive me; speak, who was he-speak, or this dagger shall find a home in thy heart!"</p> 
                  <p>"My lord, as heaven hears me, I do not know! He sang beneath the window and she cast out the scarf. She does not know him-nor do I!"</p> 
                  <p>"Then she will seek to know him, and-" The noble paused, and seemed to endeavor to calm his mad passion down into thought. "Yes, woman-like, she has been charmed by a voice-she will seek to find him out. Come with me, Sylvestra-come, I have business with thee!"</p> 
                  <p>The Venetian led the way to another apartment, apparently his study, and entering it, closed the door as Sylvestra followed him in.</p> 
                  <p>"Now, woman, I shall give thee a part to play," he cried; "but beware of the fate which will reward treachery, if thou dost deceive me!"</p> 
                  <p>Opening an escrutoire, he pointed to a pile of glittering ducats.</p> 
                  <p>"If thou art true to me, <emph>there</emph> is thy reward! If <emph>false</emph>, this shall be thy payment!" and he laid his hand upon the broad dagger which rested in his girdle.</p> 
                  <p>"My lord, I will not deceive thee!" replied the trembling woman.</p> 
                  <p>"No, thou darest not! Now hear thy lesson. I have quarrelled with thy lady, and she will seek, perchance, to know the cavalier who serenaded her to night. She will be apt to hire thee to seek him-"</p> 
                  <p>"I will not, my lord, I will not!"</p> 
                  <p>"But you must! It is my <emph>order</emph> that you obey every whim and wish of hers-but take not one step without informing me of it. Let her go on; I will thwart her! Now wilt thou be faithful to me?"</p> 
                  <p>"I will, my lord."</p> 
                  <p>"Kneel down and kiss the crossed hilt of this dagger-swear!"</p> 
                  <p>"I do!" said the woman, kissing the cross.</p> 
                  <p>"Now go; and be silent as to that which I have told thee. Be faithful, and wealth is thine-deceive me, and I will slay thee, even if thou shouldst seek refuge at the holy altar's foot!"</p> 
                  <p>Still trembling from head to foot with fear, the woman turned and left the room.</p> 
                  <p>"If she cannot be mine she never shall be another's!" muttered Alfieri fiercely, "and a convent-no, I would not let her vast fortune go to a convent. She shall be mine-or die!"</p> 
                  <p>When the duenna returned to the chamber of her lovely lady, she found her seated by the window, gazing forth upon the Lagune, her eyes brimming with tears.</p> 
                  <p>"Poor lady!" sighed the woman.</p> 
                  <p>"<emph>Poor?</emph>" echoed the lady, haughtily, turning around and looking at her, half-angrily. "Am I <emph>pitied</emph> by thee!"</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, dear lady. How can I see the tears on your cheeks, and not feel sad, that one so rich and kind and beautiful should be unhappy?"</p> 
                  <p>"It matters not-I am not <emph>very</emph> unhappy," sighed the girl. "His was a sweet voice who sung to-night."</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, lady-he was doubtless some brave knight, who has heard of thy beauty, and now he will wear thy scarf, and love thee, even though absent!"</p> 
                  <p>"Do you think he will wear it, Sylvestra?" cried the maiden eagerly, as the red blood rushed up into her cheeks.</p> 
                  <p>"Surely, lady, if he is as I think, a noble and chivalrous knight-aye, and vow that his lady is the fairest and purest in the world; and do battle for her if needs be!"</p> 
                  <p>"Sylvestra, a thought has come unbidden into my heart; but it is there. Can I trust thee?"</p> 
                  <p>"<emph>Trust</emph> me!" echoed the woman, in a tone of sadness, as if her heart was wounded by the implied doubt.</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, I know I can. Go on the morrow, and if you can seek out that knight, tell him who I am-what is my fate here-that I am persecuted and helpless!"</p> 
                  <p>"What else, lady?"</p> 
                  <p>"Nothing-if that knowledge do not gain a reply from him, then I wish to hear no more of him, never to gaze upon his face; and yet-and yet he sung <emph>very</emph> sweetly!"</p> 
                  <p>"Lady, I will strive to serve thee!" said the woman. "If I can find him, I will!"</p> 
                  <p>"Do so, Sylvestra! here is a gift for thee!" and the lady took from her finger a beautiful emerald, and gave it to the other.</p> 
                  <p>"Thanks, my noble, kind lady!"</p> 
                  <p>"No matter-leave me now; I will try to compose my mind and retire!"</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="part"> 
                  <pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6967-00000018"/> 
                  <head>PART SECOND.</head> 
                  <p>GIOVANNI ALFIERI was again in his cabinet, and one week of time had passed by since we last saw him there. He was deathly pale; did not seem like the same being we saw before. His eyes were sunken-his face expressive of settled malignity, and of suffering also. He paced up and down the marble floor, every now and then glancing impatiently toward the door, as if expecting a visitor. One came; it was Sylvestra; and her face wore a look of pleasure.</p> 
                  <p>"Well?" cried Giovanni impatiently.</p> 
                  <p>"The gold will be mine!" she cried. "All is right! Forese Admiari-he who is known as 'The Knight of the Iron Hand'-is the lover; and when I told him that my lady pined like an unmated dove in an iron cage, he swore to set her free!"</p> 
                  <p>The noble smiled bitterly as he heard this.</p> 
                  <p>"So! Forese Admiari is my rival! How often have I met him in the tournament!-and there he was <emph>my</emph> master; but now-we'll see-we'll see! Revenged on both! Has thy lady heard of this?"</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, my lord, and sends this gage!"</p> 
                  <p>"What! that diamond? I gave that to the ungrateful girl on her last birth-day; and now it goes to a lover whom she has never seen!"</p> 
                  <p>"But she has heard of him, my lord; his name is on the lips of half our gondoliers, and often in their songs on the Lagune his praise is uttered!"</p> 
                  <p>"Aye, curses on the name! But, good Sylvestra, what message did your lady send?"</p> 
                  <p>"She bade me tell him, that if she was worth the winning, to bear her away from this, her prison. And that she would be ready this night, as the bell of San Michael strikes twelve, to go with him wherever he pleases, if he would pledge his knightly word to do no dishonor!"</p> 
                  <p>"Go then, Sylvestra; but make the time in thy message one half-hour later! Tell him that the lady sends no pledge, but that she will be on the marble steps at the hour you name! Then hasten back to thy lady; tell her that the knight will send a trusty gondolier to bear her to the house of a priest in Padua, where he will wed her; that the gondolier will wear the ring she sent as a token of his trust. Haste thee now, and then return to me; I have yet one more piece of work for thee, and <emph>then</emph> the gold is thine!"</p> 
                  <p>As soon as the woman had left, the noble rung a small bell, and a man entered.</p> 
                  <p>"Nicolo, I want a gondolier's dress, a mask, and a swift-rowing gondola. Let the boat be at the private gate of the palace at the hour of eleven this night! And send a message to Ruotti, the keeper of my private stronghold on the Isla Notti, that I will be there, ere the day dawns, with a <emph>prisoner!</emph> Tell him to be prepared for my coming!"</p> 
                  <p>The attendant bowed, and hurried away to fulfil his orders. In an hour more, Sylvestra returned.</p> 
                  <p>"All is arranged, my lord!" she said. "He bade me say to my lady that he would be here in his gondola, alone, at the hour, and would bear her to the convent Francesca, and there his sister would await them with a priest. What more do you wish, my lord?"</p> 
                  <p>"Have you carried the message to your lady, that I gave you to deliver?"</p> 
                  <p>"I have, my lord!"</p> 
                  <p>"Then you have but one more duty. There is the gold I promised-take it. Here is a letter. Envelope yourself in one of your lady's shawls, after I bear her off in the gondola, and await the coming of her knight. When he springs forward, supposing thee to be the lady Bianca, hand him that note! Speak not, but retire!"</p> 
                  <p>All things were now ready for the final scene in the life-drama. The bell told the hour of <hi rend="i"/>twelve, and as it did, a gondola glided out from beneath the shadows of a palace, and the next instant it paused before the <unclear>steps</unclear> of the Alfieri palace. A single gondolier, a tall and well-formed man, wrapped in a mantle, with a mask over his face, stood at the oar, and as he saw the queenly form of Bianca di Clari step out in the moonlight, he lifted a single finger upon which an immense diamond glittered, and she felt sure that all was safe! She stepped timidly on-reached the water-side, and the gondolier handed her to the curtained-room in the middle of the boat. Here he seated her on cushions of silk and down, and placed in her hand a guitar; then, without uttering a word, he stepped to his place, pushed off the boat, and with a strong arm, urged her out into the bright Lagune.</p> 
                  <p>Bianca, though timorous, was happy-for she was flying, as she thought, from danger and from a prison. She took up her guitar, and sung this song,-words written by a poet whose fame is as eternal as the sea he loved to praise: <q>
                        <lg type="stanza"> 
                           <l>"Gondolier, Gondolier!</l> 
                           <l>Bear me o'er the waters clear,</l> 
                           <l>And a lady's thanks and a purse of gold</l> 
                           <l>Shall into thy palm be truly told,</l> 
                           <l>As soon as on Padua's ground I stand,</l> 
                           <l>Safe by my knight of 'The Iron Hand.'</l> 
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="stanza"> 
                           <l>"Gondolier, Gondolier!</l> 
                           <l>Hast thou a child or a mother dear?</l> 
                           <l>Hast thou a wife or a maiden true,</l> 
                           <l>That watcheth thy boat o'er the waters blue?</l> 
                           <l>Ah, think 'tis she whom thou dost now bear</l> 
                           <l>To a firmer land and a freer air!"</l> 
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                  </p> 
                  <p>On swept the boat swiftly, while she sung; soon it was beyond the Lagune's banks, which she so well knew, and was stretching out in the Adriatic toward Padua.</p> 
                  <p>Again a change to the scene. Not more than ten minutes after the gondola departed, which bore Bianca away, another approached the Alfieri palace-for <emph>true</emph> love is impatient, and counts time rapidly. The gondolier wore no mask who stood upon her deck. He was a noble; his face alone told that. He was clad richly, in an embroidered suit of velvet, and a sword, inlaid and hilted with solid gold and sparkling jewels, was girded on his thigh. He had not long to wait ere a female form, hurried-not by love, but by terror and avarice, (for Sylvestra wished to escape with her gold,) came out from the palace, and staggered down its steps.</p> 
                  <p>"Is it thee, oh, lady fair!" exclaimed he of "the Iron Hand," as he sprang to the shore.</p> 
                  <p>The only reply was an extended hand which reached him a note. With haste he opened it.</p> 
                  <p>"What does this mean?" he asked in surprise. But the female had vanished. He read the note aloud.</p> 
                  <p>"<emph>Thou hast tried a fine game-but thy master, Giovanni Alfieri, cannot always be conquered. If thou wouldst find thy intended bride, fellow her to the bottom of the Adriatic!</emph>"</p> 
                  <p>"Oh, God! what can this mean?" he groaned. "I know who wrote this. Ah! I saw a gondola glide down the Lagune not an half-hour since! Could she have been in it?"</p> 
                  <p>Without speaking again, he sprang into the gondola, and with a strength that seemed almost superhuman he sent her quivering frame through the waters, and dashed out toward the Adriatic. Palace and prison, church and castle, were passed as swiftly as winged birds could fly; on-on madly he darted. Soon the open sheet of water was before him, and there, truly, a mile or more ahead, could be seen a speck on the glittering water-evidently a gondola.</p> 
                  <p>"The boat bears off for Isla Notti, his prison-house. I <emph>know</emph> that <emph>she</emph> is in it!" cried the knight, and swifter still his boat shot along the tide.</p> 
                  <pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6967-00000019"/> 
                  <p>And now back to the side of Bianca. With a glad heart she gazed out on the waters as they foamed up by the side of the swift gondola; but when she saw that instead of bearing off toward Padua, the boat steered for a single island out in the bay, upon which a dark, grey-towered castle stood, she spoke:</p> 
                  <p>"Why dost thou steer toward that isle? The course to Padua is on our left!" she cried.</p> 
                  <p>The gondolier made no reply, but with a vigorous arm he dashed on. The lady wondered at this, and though she said nothing for a few moments, strange fears and doubts began to rise in her mind.</p> 
                  <p>She arose, and looking forth from the curtained room, upon the form of him who impelled the boat, she noticed that the mantle had been cast aside, and that a rich and costly dress, such as would be worn by no common gondolier, set off the fine figure of the boatman. The mask, however, disguised his face-and though she almost <emph>hoped</emph> it was her expected husband, she feared to ask.</p> 
                  <p>But she saw the form of the man heave with sudden agitation. She saw him glance back in their silvery wake, and discovered that another boat was on the same track, and that with renewed exertions her boatman seemed to labor.</p> 
                  <p>For a little time she gazed-and this time she saw that the rear-most boat was fast closing with that in which she was standing</p> 
                  <p>"Who are you?-what means this?-where do you bear me?"</p> 
                  <p>"To your home-this is your <emph>bridal</emph> eve, lady!" said a mocking voice.</p> 
                  <p>"Oh God! my uncle!" screamed the hapless girl, and with a full conviction of her misery, she sunk back on the cushions, senseless.</p> 
                  <p>How long she lay there, she did not know, but a kind of confused dream, of hearing angry voices, and clashing steel came over her senses-then a shriek of agony, a groan-and then she was awakened from that dreadful dream, by one who passionately kissed her cold lips, called her by her name and pressed her to his breast.</p> 
                  <p>"Where am I?" she murmured-"Oh, Holy Mother, where am I?"</p> 
                  <p>"Safe-on the blue bosom of the Adriatic, but safe with one who loves thee as only <emph>he can</emph> love!" said a manly voice.</p> 
                  <p>She opened her eyes, and saw that a young but noble-looking man was supporting her. At a short distance, she saw another gondola-it was the one she had been in. She saw a dark mass upon its prow, she saw a ghastly face, turned up toward the moon, then when she glanced at him who was by her side, she understood all. She had been rescued by "The Knight of the Iron Hand"-and was <emph>free</emph> and happy! Her tyrant uncle, who would have added incest to his crimes, was no more!</p> 
                  <p>Reader, does this story require any more finishing? If you think so, do it yourself!</p> 
                   
               </div> 
            </div> 
            <div type="poem"> 
               <pb n="38 (Illustration) -39" xml:id="VAC6967-00000020"/> 
               <head>
                  <figure> 
                     <p>CIRCASSIAN SELLING HER DAUGHTER.-See page 63</p> 
                  </figure>
               </head> 
                
               <head>NUMBER FIVE</head> 
               <head>A Circassian Mother selling her Daughter.</head> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>I.</head> 
                  <l>A MOTHER sell her child? Oh, can it be</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">That such may live and breathe God's air?</l> 
                  <l>That parents, with cold hearts of stone, may yield</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Their blood to shame and to despair?</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>II.</head> 
                  <l>Alas! alas! There is a sunny clime,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Where crystal rivers gently flow;</l> 
                  <l>Alas! alas! there is a lovely land</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Where Beauty's fairest flowers grow:</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>III.</head> 
                  <l>And o'er that land where love <emph>should</emph> dwell-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Where God has made all fair and bright,</l> 
                  <l>Save human hearts alone, there rests a dark</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And vile-an ever-damning blight!</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>IV.</head> 
                  <l>Behold! See, in yon picture's lights and shades,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The history I would unfold;</l> 
                  <l>A heartless mother shows the beauties rare,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">That she would sell for yellow gold!</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>V.</head> 
                  <l>The Turk will bear them to his Moslem lord,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And they will yield them to their lot;</l> 
                  <l>But, though they live beneath a palace dome,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">They'll envy <emph>love</emph> within a cot!</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>VI.</head> 
                  <l>And even here, in Freedom's boasted land,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">
                     <emph>Too often</emph>, human hearts are sold,</l> 
                  <l>And fairy forms, and warm and gentle souls,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Are bartered off for sordid gold!</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>VII.</head> 
                  <l>Age, with a gilded chain, to youth is bound-</l> 
                  <l>Youth withering beneath the touch-</l> 
                  <l>A very mockery made of gentle Love,</l> 
                  <l>His flowers hung upon a crutch!</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>VIII.</head> 
                  <l>Oh, God, why is it so? Are <emph>hearts</emph> so scarce</l> 
                  <l>That half the world have none at all?</l> 
                  <l>Oh, wretched Eve-why didst <emph>that</emph> apple eat,</l> 
                  <l>And thus cause man from bliss to fall?</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>IX.</head> 
                  <l>And yet, when woman shares the pain and woe,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Why should <emph>we</emph> venture to condemn?</l> 
                  <l>E'en if that act caused misery and pain,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">She's still the <emph>happiness</emph> of men!</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>X.</head> 
                  <l>Then I'll bless thee, woman-bless thee still,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Tho' oft thou leadest man to evil;</l> 
                  <l>And I'll believe thee-<emph>think</emph> thee <emph>angel</emph>.</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Tho' oft, with men, you play the devil!</l> 
               </lg> 
            </div> 
            <div type="poem"> 
               <pb n="40 (Illustration) -41" xml:id="VAC6967-00000021"/> 
               <head>
                  <figure> 
                     <p>IRENE, THE GREEK SLAVE.-See page 42.</p> 
                  </figure>
               </head> 
                
               <head>NUMBER SIX.</head> 
               <head type="sub">Irene, the Greek Slave.-A Romaunt of the East.</head> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>I.</head> 
                  <l>WHERE Lemnos rears its rocky crest</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Above the gean wave</l> 
                  <l>An isle, whose daughters all are fair,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And sons are warriors brave,</l> 
                  <l>There dwelt in bygone time, a girl,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">No lovelier e'er was seen,</l> 
                  <l>The daughter of a noble sire,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The Lemnian's pride-IRENE!</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>II.</head> 
                  <l>Her form, of rare Venesian mould;</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Her eyes, cerulean blue;</l> 
                  <l>Her cheeks like inner rose-leaves were,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Her lips of coral hue;</l> 
                  <l>A being made to grace the earth,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">As lovely flowers are:</l> 
                  <l>Alas! how often woman proves</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Like them, as <emph>frail</emph> as <emph>fair</emph>!</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>III.</head> 
                  <l>Sixteen years had come and gone, since</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Irene saw the light,</l> 
                  <l>And o'er her path the star of peace</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Shone quietly and bright.</l> 
                  <l>But clouds <emph>will</emph> rise in earthly skies,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And <emph>ev'ry</emph> lot has woes:</l> 
                  <l>In vain the hope that life's long dream</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">May be a sweet repose!</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>IV.</head> 
                  <l>The Moslem came with fire and sword</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Amid the gean seas,</l> 
                  <l>And shout and shriek, and groan and cures</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Were borne on ev'ry breeze,</l> 
                  <l>As one by one Greek warriors fell;</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The Moslem hordes were strong,</l> 
                  <l>Oh, what could valor do to stem the tide</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Of such a mighty throng?</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>V.</head> 
                  <l>As with the storm the strong tree bends</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And creaks and writhes-at last</l> 
                  <l>Bore down by powers beyond its strength,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">It yields unto the blast;</l> 
                  <l>So reeled and shook their serried ranks,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And one by one they fell,</l> 
                  <l>As branches from the storm-lashed tree-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The victors shouts their knell!</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>VI.</head> 
                  <l>Thus Lemnos fell! Her sons were slain,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Her daughters captive made,</l> 
                  <l>And borne afar-a weeping band</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Of merchandise for trade!</l> 
                  <l>Yet was there one who wept not then,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Nor heaved a single sigh:</l> 
                  <l>Though she had seen her father slain,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Both eye and cheek were dry!</l> 
               </lg> 
               <milestone n="* * * * * *" unit="typography"/> 
               <pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6967-00000022"/> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>VII.</head> 
                  <l>Irene had not a tear to shed,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The fountain of her grief was dry,</l> 
                  <l>Her loved were numbered with the dead,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">All useless then the sob or sigh.</l> 
                  <l>But not in vain one cherish'd thought-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">A thought e'er constant in her breast-</l> 
                  <l>Their victory should be dearly bought,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Before a Moslem's couch she press'd.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>VIII.</head> 
                  <l>Her captors were not rude-they knew</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Too well the value of the prize</l> 
                  <l>They bore across the waters blue,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">To glad the lustful Sultan's eyes:</l> 
                  <l>They knew Mehemet's chests of gold</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Would ope when charms like hers were seen,</l> 
                  <l>And be her weight in sequins told,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">For Lemno's pride-the fair Irene</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>IX.</head> 
                  <l>The moon rolled o'er its spangled grath,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Not e'en a cloud obscured the sky,</l> 
                  <l>To bode the tempest or its wrath,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Or omen give of danger nigh;</l> 
                  <l>And just as calm and all serene,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Amid the bloody Moslem crew,</l> 
                  <l>Stood the helpless maid Irene,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Gazing o'er the watery blue.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>X.</head> 
                  <l>Thought she of the loved and lost,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Fallen 'neath the Moslem swords-</l> 
                  <l>Thought she of the distant coast,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Ravaged by their cursed hordes-</l> 
                  <l>The land receding to her view</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Where she had lived and loved so long:</l> 
                  <l>Thought she of these as on she flew</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">With her accursed captor throng!</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XI.</head> 
                  <l>Or did the fate they had in store</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Come sweeping o'er the fair girl's mind,</l> 
                  <l>As shadows cast a sign before</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Which startle, although undefined?</l> 
                  <l>If so, no sign nor look she gave</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">To tell the thoughts within her breast,</l> 
                  <l>As placid as the gentle wave</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">When the breeze has sunk to rest.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XII.</head> 
                  <l>But thought the sky above was clear,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And though the sea beneath was still,</l> 
                  <l>And not a sign of danger near</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The Moslem hearts with fear to fill,</l> 
                  <l>Azrael from his ebon throne</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Had looked on them with angry frown,</l> 
                  <l>And marked the pirates for his own</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">While gazing in his anger down.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XIII.</head> 
                  <l>For soon both moon and stars were hid</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">By storm-clouds rising dark and fast,</l> 
                  <l>And on the Moslem vessel sped</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Before the fierce impetuous blast.</l> 
                  <l>In vain her crew exert their skill,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">In vain the fools to Allah cry;</l> 
                  <l>She leaks and fast begins to fill-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Despair is seen in every eye.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XIV.</head> 
                  <l>In every eye but <emph>one</emph>-for bright</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">As were the stars before the storm,</l> 
                  <l>Shone Irene's glance of light,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And proud arose her queenly form,</l> 
                  <l>And haughty was her look of pride;</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">For sooner in the angry sea</l> 
                  <l>Would she her peerless beauty hide,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Than e'er the Sultan's victim be.</l> 
               </lg> 
                
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XV.</head> 
                  <l>"On-on to death!" she wildly cried;</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">"The storm-king has ye in his grasp;</l> 
                  <l>On, on to death, ye pirates ride-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Azrael your cursed forms would clasp;</l> 
                  <l>On, on to death!-you go to meet</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The victims of your cursed steel:</l> 
                  <l>On, on to death!-revenge is sweet,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And that revenge, thank God, I feel!"</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XVI.</head> 
                  <l>But hark! a cry of wild delight</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Bursts from the Moslem Chieftain now:</l> 
                  <l>A familiar beacon is in sight-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">A harbor booms before their prow;</l> 
                  <l>And those who deemed themselves as lost,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And hopeless bowed them in despair,</l> 
                  <l>Now gaze upon the friendly coast,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And look for safety there.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XVII.</head> 
                  <l>And her whose eyes were erst so bright,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And whose pure bosom knew no fear,</l> 
                  <l>Who looked on death with calm delight,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">When it for friend and foe was near,-</l> 
                  <l>Now stands a statue of despair,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">With pallid cheek and tearful eyes,</l> 
                  <l>While Moslem shouts ring thro' the air,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">As towards the haven they fly.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XVIII.</head> 
                  <l>And now the boasting Chieftain turned</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And gazed upon his pallid prize;</l> 
                  <l>His eyes with a fiendish lustre burned</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">As he listened to her woeful sighs.</l> 
                  <l>"The Sultan <emph>soon</emph> will see his slave,"</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The <choice>
                        <sic>pircte</sic>
                        <corr>pirate</corr>
                     </choice> cried in demon glee;</l> 
                  <l>"His arms are warmer than the grave,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And soon they will <choice>
                        <sic>enaircle</sic>
                        <corr>encircle</corr>
                     </choice> thee."</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XIX.</head> 
                  <l>"No!" she cried-"By all I loved before</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">You tore me from my native shore-</l> 
                  <l>By those whose memory I love,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And whom I hope to meet above-</l> 
                  <l>Thy Sultan ne'er shall touch the form</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Which I'd have given to the storm,</l> 
                  <l>Nor shalt <emph>thou</emph> live to boast again</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Of the victims thou hast slain!"</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XX.</head> 
                  <l>A poinard keen was in his belt,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">She snatched it from its crimson sheath,</l> 
                  <l>An instant more-that blade he felt,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And sank upon the deck in death.</l> 
                  <l>Then turning to the Moslem horde,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Who stood in mute surprise-</l> 
                  <l>"Go tell your cursed Sultan lord</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The fate of him who yonder lies</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XXI.</head> 
                  <l>I scorn his power and force,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And spit upon his cursed name,</l> 
                  <l>E'en as I do upon this corse-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">This recreant lump of shame.</l> 
                  <l>Tell him a maiden struck the blow,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And sooner than his mistress be</l> 
                  <l>Her own heart's warm blood shall flow:</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Thus-<emph>thus</emph>, Irene herself will free!"</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XXII.</head> 
                  <l>E'en as she spoke the crimson blade</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Was buried in her bosom's snow,</l> 
                  <l>While a look of triumph laid</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Like a halo on her brow.</l> 
                  <l>Her spirit pure had gone to rest,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">All free from guilt and stain,</l> 
                  <l>To the mansions where the blest</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Are free from anguish and from pain.</l> 
               </lg> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6967-00000023"/> 
               <head>Washington Crossing the East River.</head> 
               <p>THE skillful and daring retreat of the American Army across the Delaware, under Gen. Washington, has so often been delineated by the historian and the painter, as to be quite familiar to every person in the land. Not so, however, with Washington's retreat from Long Island, August 28, 1775, the day after the disastrous battle of that name, and less than two months after the Declaration of Independence. From the second volume of Irving's Life of Washington, just completed, we take the following sketch of this important strategic movement. It will serve as a specimen of the graphic style in which Mr. Irving describes military operations:</p> 
               <p>Never (says Washington Irving) did retreat require greater secrecy and circumspection. Nine thousand men, with all the munitions of war, were to be withdrawn from before a victorious army, encamped so near that every stroke of spade and pickaxe from their trenches could be heard. The retreating troops, moreover, were to be embarked and conveyed across a strait three-quarters of a mile wide, swept by rapid our-rents. The least alarm of their movement would bring the enemy upon them, and produce a terrible scene of confusion and carnage at the place of embarkation.</p> 
               <p>Washington made the preparatory arrangements with great alertness, yet profound secrecy. Verbal orders were sent to Colonel Hughes, who acted as quarter-master-general, to impress all water craft, large and small, from Spuyten Duyvel on the Hudson, round to Hell Gate, on the Sound, and have them on the east side of the city by evening. The order was issued at noon, and so promptly executed that, although some of the vessels had to be brought a distance of fifteen miles, they were all at Brooklyn at eight o'clock in the evening, and put under the management of Col. Glover's ambitious Marblehead regiment.</p> 
               <p>To prepare the army for a general movement, without betraying the object, orders were issued for the troops to hold themselves in readiness for a night attack upon the enemy. The orders caused surprise, for the poor fellows were exhausted, and their arms rendered nearly useless by the rain; all, however, prepared to obey; but several made noncupative will, as is customary among soldiers on the eve of sudden and deadly peril.</p> 
               <p>According to Washington's plan of retreat, to keep the enemy from discovering the withdrawal of the Americans until their main body should have embarked in the boats and pushed off from the shore, Gen. Mifflin was to remain at the lines with his Pennsylvania troops, and the gallant remains of Haslet, Smallwood, and Hane's regiments, with guards posted and sentinels alert, as if nothing extraordinary was taking place; when the main embarkation was effected, they were themselves to move off quietly, march quickly to the ferry, and embark. In case of any alarm that might disconcert the arrangements, Brooklyn Church was to be the rallying place, so as unitedly to resist any attack.</p> 
                
               <p>It was late in the evening when the troops began to retire from the breastworks. As one regiment quietly withdrew from the station on guard, the troops on the right and left moved up and filled the vacancy. There was a stifled murmur in the camp, unavoidable in a movement of the kind: but it gradually died away in the direction of the river, as the main body moved off in silence and order. The youthful Hamilton, whose merits had won the favor of Gen. Greene, and who had lost his baggage and a field piece in the battle, brought up the rear of the retreating party. In the dead of the night, and in the midst of this hushed and anxious movement, a cannon went off with a tremendous roar.</p> 
               <p>"The effect," says an American who was present, "was at once alarming and sublime. If the explosion was within our lines, the gun was probably discharged in the act of springing it, and could have been no less a matter of speculation to the enemy than to ourselves."</p> 
               <p>"What with the greatness of the stake, the darkness of the night, the uncertainty of the design, and the extreme hazard of the issue," adds the same writer, "it would be difficult to conceive a more deeply solemn and interesting scene."</p> 
               <p>The meaning of this midnight gun was never ascertained; fortunately, though it startled the Americans, it failed to alarm the British camp.</p> 
               <p>In the meantime the embarkation went on with all possible dispatch, under the vigilant eye of Washington, who stationed himself at the ferry, superintending every movement. In his anxiety for dispatch, he sent Colonel Scammel, one of his aids-de-camp, to hasten forward all the troops that were on the march. Scammel blundered in executing his errand, and gave the order to Mifflin likewise. The General instantly called in his pickets and sentinels and set off for the ferry.</p> 
               <p>By this time the tide had turned; there was a strong wind from the north east; the boats with oars were insufficient to convey the troops; those with sails could not make headway against wind and tide. There was some confusion at the ferry, and in the midst of it, Gen. Mifflin came down with the whole covering party; adding to the embarrassment and uproar.</p> 
               <p>"Good God! Gen. Mifflin," cried Washington, "I am afraid you have ruined us by so unreasonably withdrawing the troops from the lines."</p> 
               <p>"I did so by your orders," replied Mifflin, with some warmth.</p> 
               <p>"It cannot be!" exclaimed Washington.</p> 
               <p>"By G-d, you did!" was the blunt rejoinder.</p> 
               <p>"Did Scammel act as aid-de-camp for the day, or did he not?"</p> 
               <p>"He did."</p> 
               <p>"Then," said Mifflin, "I had orders through him."</p> 
               <p>"It is a dreadful mistake," rejoined Washington; "and unless the troops can regain the lines before their absence is discovered by the enemy, the most disastrous consequences are to be apprehended."</p> 
               <p>Mifflin led back his men to the lines, which had been completely deserted for three-quarters of an hour. Fortunately the dense fog had prevented the enemy from discovering that they were unoccupied. The men resumed their former posts, and remained at them until called to cross the ferry. "Whoever has seen troops in a similar situation," writes General Heath, "or duly contemplates the human heart in such trials, will know how to appreciate the conduct of these brave men on this occasion."</p> 
               <p>The fog which prevailed all this time seemed almost providential. While it hung over Long Island, and concealed the movements of the Americans, the atmosphere was clear on the New York side of the river. The adverse wind, too, died away; the river became so smooth that the row-boats could be laden to the gunwale, and a favoring breeze sprang up for the sail-boats.</p> 
               <p>The whole embarkation of troops, artillery, <choice>
                     <sic>amunition</sic>
                     <corr>ammunition</corr>
                  </choice>, provisions, cattle, horses and carts, was happily effected; and by daybreak, the greater part had safely reached the city, thanks to the aid of Glover's Marblehead men. Scarce anything was abandoned to the enemy, except a few heavy pieces of artillery. At a proper time, Mifflin, with his covering party, left the lines, and effected a silent retreat to the ferry. Washington, though repeatedly entreated, refused to enter a boat until all the troops were embarked, and crossed the river with the last.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="46 (Illustration) -47" xml:id="VAC6967-00000024"/> 
               <head>
                  <figure> 
                     <p>THE BUCCANEER'S DAUGHTER.-See page 50.</p> 
                  </figure>
               </head> 
                
               <head>NUMBER SEVEN.</head> 
               <head type="sub">The Buccaneer's Daughter.-A Tale of the Southern Seas.</head> 
               <p>"SPARE her-oh, father, spare her for my sake! Do not do her harm-do not leave her to the mercy of your crew-remember my <emph>mother!</emph>"</p> 
               <p>What a contrast! A tall, dark-skinned, bearded man, whose head was already turning grey, and whose rough face bore the wrinkles of care, as well as the scars of violence, stood before a small hut, which was one of a cluster, built upon the secluded banks of the Canima, a small stream emptying into the bay of Matanzas, on the north side of Cuba.</p> 
               <p>And before him, holding one of his great rough hands between her own delicate <choice>
                     <sic>finfiers</sic>
                     <corr>fingers</corr>
                  </choice>, stood a young girl, lovely as the flowers which decked her jetty hair. Rich jewels were strung around her neck, yet brighter far were two pearly tears which trembled in her eyes-as she looked up imploringly and pale into his face.</p> 
               <p>Her dress was simple, suited to that wild, delicious clime. No bonnet shaded her brunette complexion, a simple girdle confined her white dress, and her delicate feet and ancles were bare. But the man was armed to the teeth. She looked mild and gentle as an angel; he, fierce, cold, bitter as a fiend. And yet she called him <emph>father!</emph>
               </p> 
               <p>"Spare her, oh father!" she pleaded-"spare her, for my sake! Do not do her harm-do not leave her to the mercy of your crew-remember my mother!"</p> 
               <p>"Your mother, Ignsa! Why do you speak of her?" muttered the man, stamping his foot angrily, and flushing up in the face.</p> 
               <p>"Because, dear father, you are gentler when you think of her! You <emph>loved</emph> her!"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, child, yes, I did!" and the lip of the man trembled as he spoke.</p> 
               <p>"Then, for the sake of her memory, father, spare this lady!" and the girl kissed her father's hand as she spoke.</p> 
               <p>"I have told you that she is the wife of the governor, he who is even now sending forth his bloodhounds on my track-who, if he could, would string us all on a gibbet ere another sun rose o'er the ocean!"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, father, but <emph>she</emph> is not to blame! Am <emph>I</emph> guilty of anything which <emph>you</emph> do?"</p> 
               <p>"It matters not, Ignsa, her fate is sealed! I can never have a better revenge than this!" muttered the man, trying to take his hand away from hers.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, father, are you a <emph>man</emph> to be revenged upon a <emph>woman!</emph> Oh, do not be so vile, so <emph>cowardly</emph> as that!" she cried, her dark eyes flashing the while with excitement.</p> 
               <p>"Cowardly, girl! Beware!-do not anger me! Begone to thy room!"</p> 
               <p>"Never, my father, never, until you listen to my prayer!"</p> 
               <p>"<emph>Why</emph> do you plead for <emph>her?</emph>"</p> 
               <pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC6967-00000025"/> 
               <p>"Because she looks as did my poor mother! Because she is a lone and helpless woman! Because your rude men, with cruel violence, have torn her away from those she loved! Oh, father, would I be so treated if-"</p> 
               <p>"Hush, child! hush! Some of the crew come this way!"</p> 
               <p>"I do not fear them, father! Are you not their chief, and I <emph>your</emph> daughter?"</p> 
               <p>"They come to bear her away! They know my determination!" said he gloomily.</p> 
               <p>"Then!" cried the young girl-"then shall they learn mine too!"</p> 
               <p>As she spoke she reached out her tiny hand, and snatching a pistol from her father's belt, sprang to the door of the hut, and placing the barrel at her own heart, she cried:</p> 
               <p>"The first step that approaches this door will be echoed by my death-shot! Now come on if ye wish <emph>me</emph> to die!"</p> 
               <p>"Madness! Madness, girl!" cried the Buccaneer, starting as if to advance.</p> 
               <p>"One step, and I die!" cried the girl, her finger pressing hard on the fatal trigger.</p> 
               <p>The pirate paused. He waved his hand to the men who were advancing.</p> 
               <p>"Back-keep back!" he cried. Then turning to his child, he added:</p> 
               <p>"Give me back that weapon, Ignsa! 'Tis folly in thee!"</p> 
               <p>"A noble folly then!" said the girl, bitterly; "a folly which my sainted mother would have gloried in!"</p> 
               <p>"Child! child-do not speak of <emph>her!</emph>"</p> 
               <p>"I will, my father, for it is the only unbroken chord in your heart!"</p> 
               <p>The man trembled. Memory seemed to strike that chord. He groaned-in bitterness of memory, he groaned. When again he spoke, a tear was in <emph>his</emph> eye-his voice was low and tremulous.</p> 
               <p>"Ignsa, you have conquered! She shall be safe!"</p> 
               <p>"She must be more than safe, father; she must be taken in safety to her home!"</p> 
               <p>"It shall be so!" murmured the man.</p> 
               <p>"Swear by my mother's soul that it shall be so!"</p> 
               <p>The man trembled yet the more, but he swore.</p> 
               <p>"Bless you, oh, my father, bless you!" cried the girl. "One act of mercy-one noble deed-blots out a hundred evils!"</p> 
               <p>He replied not-but the workings of his large frame-the quivering of his lips, showed that his spirit was struggling with excitement. While he stood there, the girl passed into the hut, where upon a rude couch reclined a lady, whose pallid face and downcast eyes, her hands clasped over her bosom, made her look like one whose spirit had passed away. Yet her lips moved, for she was praying.</p> 
               <p>"You are safe, lady, safe!" cried Ignsa.</p> 
               <p>The lady arose, and springing forward to the lovely girl, cried:</p> 
               <p>"Angel of heaven, I thank thee! I have heard all-have listened, and trembled at every word-oh, girl, God will bless thee!"</p> 
               <p>"I ask no thanks-but hasten to leave this place. Dangers lurk around; even my father will find it hard to master and keep in check the lawless spirits of his band; yet you have his oath-he will bear thee safely home!" replied Ignsa.</p> 
               <p>"Oh, that <emph>I</emph> could take thee with me! This is no place for one so good and pure as thou art!"</p> 
               <p>"Thanks, kind lady-this place is all in all to me. Down where the bright Canima laves the pebbly shore is my mother's grave. I go there each day, for my soul communes with hers, when I linger where she went to sleep! You must go-my father waits-<emph>farewell!</emph>"</p> 
               <p>"Oh, what may I do for thee? Would that I had a gift-ah, I think! But one relic have the robbers spared. Here is a miniature-the likeness of my only boy, one of the noblest cavaliers that ever blessed and honored a mother!"</p> 
               <p>Ignesa took the picture and pressed it to her lips, as she did also the hand which gave it. The likeness was that of a young and very handsome man;-at least he appeared very handsome to her who had only been accustomed to gaze upon the rude and revolting followers of her lawless Sire.</p> 
               <p>"Has he never <emph>loved?</emph>" she asked <hi rend="i"/>naively, while she looked upon the portrait.</p> 
               <p>"Not that I know of, except to love me, his mother, dearly; but why do you ask that question?" said the lady.</p> 
               <p>"Only-I-I hardly can say why. If he never loved any one, and I, who never have loved any one but father and <emph>you</emph>, dear lady, were to meet, we <emph>might</emph> love. At least <emph>I</emph> might love him, and God help poor me if he did <emph>not</emph> love me. But lady you must leave. Forgive poor Ignesa, she loves you!"</p> 
               <p>"God bless you, my <emph>daughter,</emph> for like a daughter you seem to me. I will love you. But rest assured we will meet again. Is there any favor I can grant thee?"</p> 
               <p>"But <emph>one,</emph> dear lady. If ever my father is taken, do not let him be slain. For my sake he has spared you from worse than death;-save him, if his fate darkens and he falls into your husband's power!"</p> 
               <p>"I will Ignesa. Bless you, child-farewell-but remember we will meet again!"</p> 
               <p>"Heaven grant we may," sobbed the girl. Both wept as they parted. How easily women do cry. Happiness is illustrated with tears, and how pretty they look when they cry for joy-just like flowers bending under a load of dew at sunrise-<hi rend="i"/>pearl and <hi rend="i"/>crimson all in spots. And when grief-rain comes, cold and icy like a hail-storm, how they bend like an over-laden willow.</p> 
               <milestone n="* * * * * *" unit="typography"/> 
               <p>Only a week after the lady had departed, the look-outs on the cliffs of the Pirate's Isle descried a vessel approaching. She wore the gaudy banner of Spain. What her business was, venturing so boldly into the pirates haunt, was a puzzle to the father of Ignesa Perchance he thought that his late leniency had worked in his favor, and that the Spanish Governor had sent to arrange a treaty of peace. But his thoughts can better be judged by his actions. He had one of his heaviest vessels instantly manned and got under way. Standing out of the harbor, he hoisted the red flag, and bore directly for the stranger. Though smaller than his own vessel, and not so fully manned, her commander showed no disposition to avoid combat, and she was the first to open fire. But before the first gun was fired, the vessels were within pistol shot of each other, and in a moment after the firing commenced, they were side by side.</p> 
               <p>There was no time for questions. "Board her, my men!" shouted the father of Ignesa, at the same time dashing himself aboard the Spaniard. Then followed a rush-shouts and curses, mingled in fearful din with the crash of cannon, cutlass met cutlass, pike met pike, and all were hand to hand. Ignesa's father, as ever, was foremost in the fray, and picked the commander of the strange vessel for his mark. At last, over the dead bodies of many of their respective followers, they met. Both were skillful, both were brave, but the experience of the elder <emph>told</emph>. In a few minutes he disarmed his opponent, and when he did so, the Spanish vessel lowered her flag, and was carried by the pirate crew, into the harbor, with shouts of triumph, and of derision at the foolhardiness of the Spanish commander in thus bearding their <choice>
                     <sic>Captian</sic>
                     <corr>Captain</corr>
                  </choice> in his stronghold.</p> 
               <p>And now I can only say that the father of Ignesa treated his captive as a foe who had been his equal.</p> 
               <p>The author has not room here to carry out all his wishes-he is, by necessity, drawn<pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC6967-00000026"/> into very narrow bounds. He is forced to leave much to the imagination of his reader; much is he obliged to leave to the fancies of those for whom he caters. Therefore, dear reader, we'll let another month slide by on the incline plane of time. The young prisoner had so far recovered from his wounds, that he could walk down by the side of the Canima, and there for hours would he sit and tell Ignsa of things which he had seen in old Spain: of the legends which there he had heard, about the time when the star of chivalry shone brightest above proud Castile. And he told the simple maiden stories of love, which often made her own warm heart dream bright dreams.</p> 
               <p>It seemed strange that her father, who loved her so tenderly, and guarded her so carefully, should be so willing to leave her continually with his prisoner, for he could not but see that she, at least, was already fondly and passionately in love. But he did so-yet not carelessly. No motion of theirs was unseen-no word they uttered unheard-no step they took, but was followed.</p> 
               <p>On a balmy eve-one of those quiet, drowsy afternoons, so dreamily beautiful-the couple were again wandering along the banks of the stream, when they came to a little arbor which Ignsa had entwined with her own hands; the young man complained of being weak, and they seated themselves.</p> 
               <p>"Are you not very lonesome-very tired of being a captive?" asked Ignsa, plucking a flower from a branch overhead, and commencing to pick it to pieces.</p> 
               <p>"I think I could never be lonesome where you are, and would not pine if I were only <emph>your</emph> captive!" he replied.</p> 
               <p>A blush rushed up into the maiden's cheek-she did not reply for a moment, but the poor flower was utterly annihilated by her trembling fingers. At last, though, she murmured:</p> 
               <p>"You will soon be well, then my father will ransom you, and you will go to those whom you love-to your noble mother!"</p> 
               <p>The youth sighed.</p> 
               <p>"She is a noble mother!" he said. "I would, Ignsa, that you could see and know her! You would <emph>love</emph> her!"</p> 
               <p>Little did the young man dream that poor Ignsa had already <emph>known</emph> and <emph>loved</emph> her! Little did he dream that she had his picture in her bosom at that very moment, for she, with all of woman's delicacy, had concealed all this from him. She had not told him why she had begged every favor from her father for him; why she had nursed him through his illness, explained the manner in which he had been left on board the pirate when his own vessel and the Buccaneer's were in contact, and assured him that he should be ransomed and depart in safety.</p> 
               <p>"I do love your noble mother!" murmured the girl, "and oh, how I wish that I could see you in safety by her side! You must go from here-it-it is dangerous for you to stay!"</p> 
               <p>"Have I not your father's word that I am safe?"</p> 
               <p>"Yes-but still I pray you to go; your poor mother may be dying, for she loves you tenderly, and when she hears of your capture-or perhaps they will report your <emph>death</emph>-it will break her heart!"</p> 
               <p>"I would fly this instant, if <emph>you</emph> would go with me!"</p> 
               <p>"I?-I? oh no, never! I cannot leave my father, I cannot leave my mother's grave: no-no, it cannot be!"</p> 
               <p>"Oh, Ignsa, what is a father's love and a mother's memory, to the love I bear for thee! Oh, be mine, and fly with me from this spot; I cannot leave you here alone!</p> 
               <p>"I shall not be alone when you are gone -I shall remember you-I shall be contented!"</p> 
               <p>"Then I will not go!"</p> 
               <p>"It is your <emph>duty!</emph>"</p> 
               <p>"Love makes us all undutiful!"</p> 
               <p>"So it would seem!" said a low, sweet voice, close behind where they were seated.</p> 
               <p>Both started to their feet, and as they saw two figures standing outside the arbor, they knew that they had been overheard. Angry blood mantled the cheek of the young man, as he stepped forth to confront the intruders; but a cry of delight escaped his lips in place of angry words, as he saw who was there.</p> 
               <p>"Mother-oh, my mother!" he cried, and the next instant he was in her arms.</p> 
               <p>Stern and calm the Buccaneer stood and looked upon this scene, nor did his countenance change, until he saw the high-born lady press his child to her bosom, kiss and bless her as the preserver of her son. Then a tear quivered in his eye, his bosom heaved with a suppressed sigh, and he turned his face away to conceal his emotion.</p> 
               <p>And now, a hurried explanation was given by the lady to account for her presence there. She had heard of her son's capture-had heard a description of the vessel, and had at once concluded who was the captor. Trusting to <emph>his</emph> honor, she had laden a small vessel with gold for ransom, and with a small crew, under a trusty officer, had at once come boldly to the pirate's home. She had at first sought an interview with him-the reader knows the rest-no, not all the rest. The Comtessa asked for the miniature. The blushing girl drew it forth, but with tears in her eyes begged to be permitted to keep it.</p> 
               <p>"Would you not prefer the original?-he loves you!" cried the lady, "and though he might wed more noble-born, he could never bring to me a daughter whom I could so love as thee!"</p> 
               <p>Could the Pirate believe his ears! His only hopes and wishes had been for the welfare of that child, and now when neither she or her lover could speak, the stern man turned his brimming eyes toward the noble lady, and said:</p> 
               <p>"You have done what all your husband's armed force could never do! You have conquered <emph>me!</emph> From this day, the <hi rend="i"/>Pirate of the Canima sheathes his blade and furls his flag!"</p> 
               <p>And so it was. The Comtessa returned to Havana, obtained a full pardon for him, and then, unknown to the people of the city as a pirate, he returned thither. His vast riches, and the beauty of his daughter, soon made him an object of attraction, and his house was crowded with visitors. The most constant of these was young D'Ancona, who soon became the husband of <hi rend="i"/>Ignesa, THE BUCCANEER'S DAUGHTER!</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC6967-00000027"/> 
               <head>The Battle of Red Bank.</head> 
               <p>SOON after the war commenced between the Colonies and England, the Americans turned their attention to the mouth of the Delaware River. To prevent a British fleet from capturing Philadelphia, extensive fortifications were erected at various eligible points along the river shores. On a low reedy island, where the beach was only a foot above tide, stood Fort Mifflin, a strong fortress, built of earth, stones and huge logs on the Jersey shore; just opposite, was Fort Mercer, a similarly constructed fortification, armed with heavy cannon. Further down the river were other works, while under the lee of small islands, floating batteries commanded the river in every direction. Nor was this all, for in the main channel the Americans sunk huge <foreign xml:lang="FRA">chevaux de frize</foreign>, or frames of timber filled with stones and logs. Upon these principally the patriots relied for the protection of Philadelphia.</p> 
               <p>Soon after the battle of Brandywine, Sept. 11, 1777, Sir William Howe, with a large fleet of frigates and storeships, appeared in the mouth of the Delaware River and opened fire upon the first line of batteries. Being able to bring many heavy guns to bear upon the American works, he soon silenced them, and taking advantage of a strong wind, sailed in one night nearly to Billing's Island. Under cover of a heavy fire from the ships the British labored to break a passage through the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">chevaux de frize</foreign>. By great exertions a channel eight feet deep and just wide enough for a light frigate, was delved out, and six vessels sailed through. Meantime, the British army, which had defeated Washington at Brandywine, rapidly neared Philadelphia, and in fact, received stores from the six ships which broke through the sunken obstructions. With a determination to destroy Forts Mercer and Mifflin, Howe sent Col. Donop, with 1200 picked men to make an attack by land, while the fleet assaulted a large flotilla of American batteries, gallies, gun boats and schooners, which caused the British vessels much annoyance. The fleet was also to bombard Fort Mifflin.</p> 
               <p>Fort Mercer, commonly called "Red Bank," was garrisoned by the regiment of Rhode Island troops under Col. Green, and Fort Mifflin by two regiments of Marylanders, under Col. Smith. Col. Donop, with his brigade, left the British camp on the morning of October 21, 1777, and the first night rested at Haddonsfield, New Jersey, for several hours. Getting under arms about midnight they marched briskly across the country, and at 4 o'clock on the morning of the 22d, came within cannon shot of the Fort. They were discovered by the sentry about day-light, slowly forming in the edge of a belt of forest. The garrison was instantly under arms, and preparations made to resist until the last. Although Col. Greene had only four hundred men, he declared that Fort Mercer should never be surrendered. With only fourteen pieces of cannon, the brave officer, heartily supported by his gallant men, hastily made ready for battle. Soon a stir was observed in the British ranks, and an officer, riding up to the intrenchments, protected by a white flag, made a proclamation:</p> 
               <p>"The King of England orders his rebellious subjects to lay down their arms; and they are warned that if they stand battle no quarter will be given!"</p> 
               <p>To this insulting message, Col. Greene nobly replied:-"We ask no quarter, neither will we give any!"</p> 
               <p>The officer retired, and very soon a party of artillerists commenced the erection of a battery within easy cannon shot of the fort. The works of Fort Mercer consisted of a strong citadel, loopholed and supplied with embrasures for cannon. The citadel was surrounded by ramparts, flanked with batteries; there was also a ditch and abatis. Besides these defences, a strong masked battery occupied an angle of the ramparts, its guns completely raking the abatis and approaches.</p> 
               <p>The battery being finished, a rapid fire opened on the American works. The patriots replied for a time, but gradually slackened, and the men withdrew in small parties to the citadel, leaving a company to manage the masked battery. Col. Donop, believing the enemies' guns dismounted and his men dismayed, ordered an assault from his whole force, in two columns of six hundred men each. The column which first advanced cleared the outworks with loud shouts of derision under the impression that the Americans had abandoned the whole fortress; but their dreadful mistake was soon evident. As the Hessian soldiers climbed up the ramparts in great numbers, a vivid fire of cannon and musketry opened <choice>
                     <sic>puon</sic>
                     <corr>upon</corr>
                  </choice> them from the citadel. It is said that nearly one hundred men fell at the first volley. A storm of grape and chain shot swept the glacis, while from every loophole there poured a stream of musket-balls.</p> 
               <p>As the enemy staggered back, <choice>
                     <sic>astonishd</sic>
                     <corr>astonished</corr>
                  </choice> and dismayed, the masked battery suddenly opened, and at point-blank range cut down the disorganized enemy, until the glacis was covered with the dead and dying. The columns of Donop assaulted the south side of the works just at this instant. Charging at the head of his men, Donop led them over the abatis, across the ditch, and even upon the walls of the fort. Here Donop fell, badly wounded, and his soldiers, unable to endure the terrible carnage made by every volley from the citadel, turned and fled. As they wheeled, Col. Mingerode, the second officer in command, received a mortal wound. The Hessians, panic struck, fled at once, nor did they a moment halt until several miles from the scenes of defeat. Under the ramparts of Fort Mercer they left over four hundred dead and wounded men, while the patriots only numbered eight men killed and twenty-eight wounded.</p> 
               <p>As a party of Americans, under the order of a French engineer, were removing the wounded, a faint voice from under a heap of slain and mangled men, called out, "Whoever you are, draw me hence!" It was the voice of Col. Donop. He was taken to a neighboring house and kindly cared for, but his wound defied human skill. In three days he died. A few hours before his death he said: "It is finishing a noble career early, (he was thirty-seven,) but I die a victim of my ambition and the avarice of my sovereign!"</p> 
               <p>The attack on Fort Mifflin by the fleet began at the moment of Donop's assault. For several hours a severe cannonade was kept up from six British frigates, upon the American fleet and fortifications. It was returned by the Americans in such a skilful and rapid manner that very soon two of the frigates were set on fire by hot shot, and two others badly crippled. Finally the English commander abandoned the attack and retired beyond cannon-shot.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="54 (Illustration) -55" xml:id="VAC6967-00000028"/> 
               <head>
                  <figure> 
                     <p>THE TREASON OF GOMEZ.-See page 57.</p> 
                  </figure>
               </head> 
                
               <head>NUMBER EIGHT.</head> 
               <head type="sub">The Treason of Gomez Arias.-A Tale of Man's Perfidy.</head> 
               <epigraph> 
                  <cit> 
                     <q>
                        <p>"Triste acuerdo! que rendida en los brazos que creia ser principio de mis dichas, halle en ellos, e la perfidia."</p>
                     </q> 
                     <bibl>SEGUEDILLA.</bibl> 
                  </cit> 
               </epigraph> 
               <p>[BEFORE commencing this story, it is just for me to state, that I take the plot from a beautiful poem of the same title, written by J. R. Chorley, an English writer of genius and celebrity, and that I claim no credit, save that of partially telling the story in prose, which he has immortalised in verse.]</p> 
               <p>IT was noon-the year 1490-a time when the Moors and the Spaniards were fighting with alternate success; the one party to regain their long-lost land, the other to keep their blood-bought possessions.</p> 
               <p>It was noon. Along the sunny side of a gentle slope midway among the mountains of Asturias, three persons rode. The two first rode side by side; one a lady, of tall and queenly form and mien, mounted on a horse of snowy white, which, though travel-worn, seemed proud of his lovely burthen. By her side rode one whose armor, spurs of gold, and crested shield betokened him a knight: whose arched brows long, curling hair, proud features, and light complexion, told that his blood was purely Spanish, and as yet untainted with that of the hated Moors.</p> 
               <p>An armed servant rode behind them. The heat was oppressive. Not a breath of air lifted the wilting leaves of the shadowy trees which grew on either hand-not a zephyr's sigh fanned that lovely lady's burning cheek.</p> 
               <p>"I am faint, dear Gomez-faint with heat and fatigue!" said the lady. "When will we reach your castle? You said yesternight, that ere the noon of this day we would be there!"</p> 
               <p>"Aye, dear Blanche!" he replied; "but in taking this route to avoid danger and pursuit, I fear me I have lost the way! It is indeed time that I saw <hi rend="i"/>Guevera's towers; but I fear me that I took the wrong gorge as we passed the Capella range of hills!"</p> 
               <p>"It matters not, dear Gomez! Thou art with me; and with thee so near, the mountain or the vale, the palace or the desert, were alike to me a Paradise!"</p> 
               <p>With all of love's fond pleasure that lady's eyes flashed as she spoke; yet as flashes the warm sunlight on a peak of snow, so fell the light of love on the pale face of that Spanish knight. With a kind of forced courtesy, he bowed, and with words which he seemed to measure and weigh, so cold were they spoken-he replied:</p> 
               <p>"Thou art a fair flatterer, lady. We have been wedded but five days!"</p> 
               <p>"Wedded!-aye, by Nature!-but I cannot be happy till the holy priest has blessed our marriage, and made us that before the world which we <emph>are</emph> before God!" sighed the maiden.</p> 
               <pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC6967-00000029"/> 
               <p>A kind of sneer-a flitting shadow-seemed to pass over the Spaniard's face; but a moment after, as he glanced far along to wards a distant mountain toward which they were riding, his color heightened and his eye flashed with a new light. He-and he alone-saw the glitter of arms; he, and he alone, saw the flash and glitter of a golden-webbed flag, and knew that the foes of his land were before him. And did his eye flash because he panted to meet them in battle? Ah, no!-for what could he do with his scanty force-two arms alone-against an array that might outnumber him ten to one. That hour commenced the "Treason of Gomez Arias!"</p> 
               <p>"Turn aside, dear Blanche," he said, "we will rest for an hour or more beneath the shade of yonder lofty tree. Thou shalt slumber awhile, <choice>
                     <sic>and and</sic>
                     <corr>and</corr>
                  </choice> then refreshed we will proceed!"</p> 
               <p>Followed by the servant, they turned from the road, and beneath the shadowy branches dismounted. From a case borne by the servant the knight hurried to draw a flask of wine; but he turned his back on the others as he poured it out in a small golden cup; for into the same cup he dropped a single drop of liquid from a little flask drawn from beneath his own vest.</p> 
               <p>"Here, dear Blanche, drink this, and then lay thee down upon my cloak!" he said, as he handed her the cup. "An hour of rest will renerve thee for our ride!"</p> 
               <p>The wearied lady drank, and almost as soon as it had passed her lips, her lovely eyes closed in sleep.</p> 
               <p>Then the knight smiled, and calling to the servant, bade him tighten the girths on his horse.</p> 
               <p>"She is lightly off my hands!" he cried, "I'll now hie me off to fair Seville, and look for another prize-and learn with her to feel once more that charm which cloyed passion cannot know!"</p> 
               <p>The groom heard, yet scarcely understood. The lady was one of the proudest of her native land. Her family had opposed her union with Gomez Arias; yet, trusting all to him, <emph>unwedded</emph>, yet as his wife, five days before had she fled from Cadiz. Why should he now desert her? Let his own words, just written above, account for it. The servant saw then, at scarce a mile distant, the gleam of arms and the flash of banners. One long, eager look, and he cried:</p> 
               <p>"The Moors! my master-the Moors! We must wake the lady, and fly!"</p> 
               <p>"Let the lady sleep!" was the stern reply of the knight. "Mount, Garcia-mount! Our road lies down the hill!"</p> 
               <p>"But, my lord-the lady! Holy Jesu-she ill will bear to wake with Moslem foes around her!"</p> 
               <p>"Slave, obey! Mount, and away!" cried the knight.</p> 
               <p>The groom glanced once at the lovely lady, as she slept, then at the angry face of his master; and with a trembling hand, tightened the girth, and then mounted his horse and rode away-following his master, who at headlong speed dashed down the road he had so lately passed over.</p> 
               <p>The sleeping lady had a dream. She dreamed that with her loved Arias she had reached his proud ancestral halls, and stood on Guevera's heights. She was happy.-But suddenly, rude hands were on her-shouts of rude voices came like rolling thunder on her ear. She woke-woke to find herself a bound captive-a captive, too, to those who never spared the honor of the Christian ladies. One wild scream of terror-one moan of unutterable woe-one cry:</p> 
               <p>"Gomez! Gomez Arias, art thou slain?"-and she was lifted senseless to the steeds of one of the captors.</p> 
               <p>Oh, little did she dream of the foul treachery of him who had left her there a prey to the worthless Moors!</p> 
                
               <p>High on a lofty hill, not far from Seville, there was a stronghold, called Guejar, held by one Zegri, a Moorish chief, famed for his wealth and bravery. Like the eagle's eyrie, his lofty castle was perched in safety. It could only be gained by a difficult and tortuous path, where no more than two or three could pass abreast; and therefore, nought but treachery, or a siege, could ever cause its capture. But famed as was Zegri for wealth, more famed was his child, young Zorayda, for her peerless beauty.-Christian knights had turned false to their creed and land to win her hand-but all in vain. Moslem chiefs had fought and died to win a renown which could gain that prize; but her bridal-veil was not woven.</p> 
               <p>To this castle was poor Blanca carried-to the harem of this chief was she borne. He saw, admired, and loved her. He endeavored to make her the queen of his harem-the "<hi rend="i"/>favorite" of his choice. But tears and moans were all that she gave in return for proffered kindness. She mourned for her lost Gomez-she pined for her heart's choice. In vain did Zegri lay the costliest gifts before her-in vain did the fair daughters of Circassia, or the dusky Arab girls, dance their sprightliest steps-in vain did the music of the East fall on her ear. She would not be comforted.</p> 
               <p>But when the fair Zorayda listened unto her sighs, and with gentle words and kind caresses strove to comfort her, then did poor Blanca pause in her sobs, for she felt that a <emph>sister</emph> was near. And when Zorayda pleaded with her father to spare the Christian captive, for a time at least-though a cloud covered the warrior's brow, still he listened and spared her.</p> 
               <p>Time passed on. Zorayda and Blanca were as sisters. Zegri still loved his captive-but, restrained by the entreaties of his child, treated her more as a guest than as a captive. But his guard was close upon her. Zorayda was permitted to sail upon the beautiful lake which lay in the bosom of the vale below the castle; she was permitted even, with a chosen attendant to wander along its flowery shores-but poor Blanca was not allowed a greater pleasure than to gaze down from the grey battlements. Thus things passed for a few weary weeks, and then change came.</p> 
               <p>One eve-a calm and pleasant afternoon it was-Zorayda returned from a trip on the lake,-and seeking Blanca; in a hurried tone, her countenance flushed, her bosom heaving, her whole manner betokening agitation-she said:</p> 
               <p>"Would you be free, lady?"</p> 
               <p>Blanca could scarcely speak, so surprised was she with the question, and with the manner of Zegri's daughter. But recovering from her surprise, she replied:</p> 
               <p>"Captivity is not pleasure to me!"</p> 
               <p>"I know well it is not!" said Zorayda. "I will set thee free-aye, and go with thee!"</p> 
               <p>"What means this? Can I believe thee? Why is this?"</p> 
               <p>"Christian-I have learned to <emph>love!</emph>" replied the Moorish maiden. "A knight of thy own race has wooed, will win me. Thrice on yonder lake we've met-this night I've vowed to be his own! Say, wilt thou fly with us?"</p> 
               <p>"Will I? Oh, bless thee, Zorayda-bless thee! Now I may return to my home to die!"</p> 
               <p>Night came on. Scarce had its shadows closed, and the pale stars crept out in sight, when Zorayda, having placed one of her own attendants at a private gate, passed out from her father's castle. The Spanish lady was with her. What a contrast in their looks! The one tall, fair, queenly, and yet timid as the frightened deer. The other small, exquisitely formed-dark in eye, hair and hue, yet brave and warm-blooded as her sire.</p> 
               <p>Out from the castle gates they passed-down the steep and narrow pathway, yet<pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC6967-00000030"/> ere they had reached one half the distance, they heard the alarm given. They were discovered! The troops of Zegri were called to arms, and far ahead of all, the chief himself rushed madly down the dangerous path.</p> 
               <p>"We are lost! We are lost!" murmured Blanche.</p> 
               <p>"No-no! See yonder boat dashing across the lake! My lover comes! He will save us-bear us hence beyond all danger!' cried Zorayda. "On, lady, on, and do not look back!"</p> 
               <p>With trembling limbs and tearful eyes on fled the noble Blanca and the lovely Moor; close behind were heard the steps of their pursuers; but onward still dashed the boat toward them o'er the lake. Its prow at last touched the beach, and, with a scream of joy Zorayda pointed to a noble-looking cavalier standing foremost in it, and cried:</p> 
               <p>"See!-see!-my lover!-my lord!-my Gomez!"</p> 
               <p>Ah! why stops Blanca on the shore, as she sees that knight?-why does she pause? The Moorish girl tries to urge her on. One moment she stands motionless, then with a wild shriek of joy she sprang forward. She saw her once faithful servant Garcia there-she saw Gomez Arias-and, almost mad with happiness, screamed:</p> 
               <p>"Oh, God-my thanks to thee! Gomez Arias-I am spared for thee!"</p> 
               <p>The Spaniard frowned. He had not dreamed of this, or known that the betrayed Blanca was near. With a husky voice, he cried:</p> 
               <p>"Quick!-to the boat-quick!-the foes are close upon ye!"</p> 
               <p>But now the Moorish maiden drew back, and as her dark eyes flashed like fire, she turned to Blanca.</p> 
               <p>"Lady! have you known and loved him before?" she asked.</p> 
               <p>"He is the lover from whom your father's band tore me-him whom I have mourned as dead!" cried Blanca.</p> 
               <p>"And he is the lover with whom I was to flee-he whom I have loved-oh, Allah! how have I loved him!"</p> 
               <p>Before the knight could say more, he saw that the Moors in heavy force were closing fast upon them; and, determined to save his prize, he sprang to the beach and strove to seize Zorayda. But she darted from him and fled toward her father. With a curse, Gomez Arias leaped back to his boat; and Blanca was already in, and by her side stood Garcia, the servant who had witnessed the "treason" of the knight.</p> 
               <p>Arias ordered the boat shoved from the shore; but as she moved beyond the reach of the pursuer, a new-and oh, God! how vile a thought-rushed into his heart!</p> 
               <p>"Ho, Moor!" he cried. "If thou'rt as gallant as thou'rt brave, say what thou'lt give me for this Christian slave?"</p> 
               <p>"Whate'er thou wilt, so that she be mine. The Zegri ne'er was scorned before!"</p> 
               <p>"Wilt give thy child?"</p> 
               <p>"Zorayda?-No!-ten thousand curses, no! But if her weight in solid gold will serve, that shalt thou have, in zechins!"</p> 
               <p>"'Tis well!-I ll trust to thee-behold, I come!"</p> 
               <p>As he said this the recreant knight bade his boatmen row in to the shore. And now let the poet speak: <q>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"Oh! had you then the maid beheld!</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">As if her heart must break;</l> 
                        <l>How wild amaze her spirit held,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">And flushed and blanched her cheek!</l> 
                        <l>Such grief and fear her bosom swelled,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">And vainly strove to speak;</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"Till passion through lament, that strove</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">For utterance, struggled forth-</l> 
                        <l>'Thou false to God, and truth, and love,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">And stain to knightly worth!</l> 
                        <l>Thus canst thou dare, though Heaven should bear</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Such crying sin on earth?</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                         
                        <l>"'Oh, lost! for mercy must I call</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">To thee-to whom I gave</l> 
                        <l>Heart, honor, trust-my life, my all</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Oh! give me but a grave,</l> 
                        <l>And sudden death, that I may fall</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">
                           <emph>Thy</emph> victim-not a slave!</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"'O Gomez! choose some lesser guilt-</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Reject me-let me roam</l> 
                        <l>Alone, degraded, as thou wilt,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Back to my darkened home!</l> 
                        <l>But spare me this-so saints in bliss</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Forgive thee!-Woe! they come!'"</l> 
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p> 
               <p>Yes, they came! Garcia the servant. alone dared to remonstrate; but with his gauntletted hand the knight smote him senseless, and ere he came to, the Moor had borne his captive to his castle; the knight received his price. But Garcia made a vow of vengeance then-and well he kept it. Soon as his foot pressed the shore, he left his traitor lord, mounted horse, and sought one whom he knew to be blessed of God with a pure and noble soul-she who first smiled on the patronless man who gave this land its birth-right in the world-land which for his memory should be called <hi rend="i"/>Columbia. But I shall now let the poet close the story, for no words of mine could give it half the beauty which he has done: <q>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"Still Garcia spurred, nor drew his rein,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">But sped in wild <unclear>deray</unclear>,</l> 
                        <l>Until he reached the dappled plain</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Where Darro winds his way-</l> 
                        <l>'Twas all the pride of Christian Spain</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">That round Grenada lay.</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"Outspake the Queen, bright Isabelle,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">The Queen of high Castile,</l> 
                        <l>When at her feet the henchman fell</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">That treason to reveal-</l> 
                        <l>'So God my trust to me be just,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">As I with him shall deal!</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"'Arouse ye, knights!' To horse arrayed</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Ten gallant thousands leap;</l> 
                        <l>'The cause is mine, a sister's aid.</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Nor will I kneel where prayers are prayed</l> 
                        <l>Nor solace take, nor sleep,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Till I have freed that ruined maid</l> 
                        <l>From out the Moorish keep'</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"And ere five daily suns from heaven</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Had chased the morning star,</l> 
                        <l>Around the mountain post was driven</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">A storm of sudden war:-</l> 
                        <l>The wall is ta'en,-the flag of Spain</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Is waving on Guejar!</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"The Queen hath kissed the captive's cheek,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">And whispered words of cheer;</l> 
                        <l>Few words and strange did Blanca speak.</l> 
                        <l>Her wandering eye, that seemed too weak</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">To bear a starting tear,</l> 
                        <l>Strayed evermore,-it seemed to seek</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Or shun a sight of fear.</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"And now our Lady of Castile</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Had reached the leaguer's ground,</l> 
                        <l>When fording through the clear Xenil</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Was Gomez Arias found.</l> 
                        <l>Straight to the Queen, with willing zeal,</l> 
                        <l>They brought the wight, and bade him kneel</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Before her, strongly bound.</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"Close at her side the mournful dame,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">With heaving bosom, stood;</l> 
                        <l>Their eyes have met-dismay and shame</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Have chilled the traitor's blood.</l> 
                        <l>The Queen commands-the priest he came,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">And bare the blessed rood.</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"'That lady's honor,' spake the Queen,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">'Hath won thee special grace;</l> 
                        <l>False, thankless, vile, as thou hast been,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">And base beyond the base-</l> 
                        <l>That spares thy life, to make her wife,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">One treason to efface.</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"'Go, join their hands.' False Arias bowed,-</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Nor said the damsel, nay;</l> 
                        <l>The ring is given, their plight is vowed,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">In coldness and dismay;</l> 
                        <l>The bride had better worn her shroud,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Than seen that wedding day.</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"Now ended all the church's rite,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">The Queen she frowning said-</l> 
                        <l>'Go, carry forth, and shrive the wight,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">The axe awaits his head;</l> 
                        <l>And ere yon cloud, that veils the light</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Pass eastward, do him dead!'</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <pb n="60-61 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6967-00000031"/> 
                        <l>"Loud sobbing knelt that Ladye fair,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">And clung to the Queen's knee;</l> 
                        <l>"Oh, spare his life! my husband spare-</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">He injured only me!</l> 
                        <l>As I forgive, so let him live,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Or mine his sentence be.'</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"Great pity shook the Queen, for sore</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">That sweetest Lady prayed,</l> 
                        <l>And eyes that never wept before,</l> 
                        <l>And rugged cheeks with tears ran o'er,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Such piteous suit she made;</l> 
                        <l>Till failed her breath, it seemed in death,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">As trampled violets fade.</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"The cloud has passed athwart the sun,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">The grass with blood is red;</l> 
                        <l>The foulest deed that e'er was done</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">Still brands the traitor dead.</l> 
                        <l>Though years be gone, yet never one</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">For him a mass hath said.</l> 
                     </lg>
                     <lg type="stanza"> 
                        <l>"But still, on Darro's banks of thyme,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">The dreaming virgins tell,</l> 
                        <l>Or sing of Gomez Arias' crime,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">And Blanche, that loved so well.</l> 
                        <l>As sad a theme, for tale or rhyme,</l> 
                        <l rend="ti-1">As e'er in Spain befel."</l> 
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
                
               <head>
                  <figure> 
                     <p>ZULEIKA, QUEEN OF THE HAREM.</p> 
                  </figure>
               </head> 
               <pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC6967-00000032"/> 
                
               <head>NUMBER NINE.</head> 
               <head type="sub">Zuleika, Queen of the Harem.-A Brief Story of the East.</head> 
               <p>"ALLAH, il Allah! Great is Allah, and Mahomet is his prophet!" cried an officer of Ali Achmed, the Sultan, bowing low before his lord.</p> 
               <p>The Sultan took a long whiff from his chibouk, raised his eyes languidly, and asked:</p> 
               <p>"What does the slave want?"</p> 
               <p>"To serve his great master, the Sultan!"</p> 
               <p>"Thou <emph>art</emph> my servant!"</p> 
               <p>"Yes, thanks be to gracious Allah! But my lord, I have journeyed afar to serve thee!"</p> 
               <p>"Well, what hast thou done?"</p> 
               <p>"In a Persian garden I saw a flower, rare as 'twas beautiful! That have I brought unto my master; and ere 'tis unfolded, would I pray the sunlight of his eyes to rest upon it!"</p> 
               <p>"'Tis well! Bring it forth!"</p> 
               <p>The officer departed, and in a few moments returned, and led in a veiled female. The Sultan smiled, and half arose from the cushions on which he reclined.</p> 
               <p>"Let me look upon her?" he said.</p> 
               <p>The officer lifted the veil; and well had he named her a "<hi rend="i"/>flower" who stood there. Bright were her shadowed eyes as stars which cluster in the skies; and red her lips of coral hue, as is the rose which drinks the dew; the lily on the lake was not more fair than she; and golden was her glossy hair! Her form was all that sculptor could for model ask; and hard indeed that poet's task who'd dare to picture all her beauties rare!</p> 
               <p>The Sultan sat amazed, and in deep silence for a moment gazed. Three hundred women in his harem dwelt; Circassia's maidens, Georgia's daughters, even <hi rend="i"/>Frankein maidens knelt whene'er he scanned their ranks; yet ne'er had Achmed seen such beauty as Zuleika then unveiled.</p> 
               <p>"Thou shalt be my harem's queen!" he cried.</p> 
               <p>Alas! that word! <emph>it</emph> was her doom! Quick through the harem was it spread, that LEILA, long the pride and favored one, was to be displaced; that a new and yet more beauteous one, had come to fill her place. And what did the Circassian maid? Did she bow to her lord's stern decree? Aye, as in a modern tale: "woman stoops to conquer!'</p> 
               <p>"Achmed is my master!" she murmured. "His will is mine-I <emph>love</emph> him!"</p> 
               <p>But as she spoke, Leila's eyes flashed like fire, and the red blood rushed up to her very brow. The Sultan's mandate passed. The stranger was his queen and favorite-and Leila, <emph>once</emph> the loved, was Zuleika's slave.</p> 
               <p>"Give me to drink of the iced sherbet. Let me cool my lips with the nectar-drink<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC6967-00000033"/> which proud Mohammed loved!" said the new made queen.</p> 
               <p>"Thy will, oh, lady, thy will is mine!" said Leila; and she hastened forth to obey.</p> 
               <p>Soon she returned, and as she did, a female slave also came from the Sultan with a casket of jewels-a present to the new favorite.</p> 
               <p>"Stand back!" said Leila. "My gift first-then let her wear the jewels!"</p> 
               <p>Had Zuleika noted then the paleness of Leila's cheek-the anxiety in her glance-the nervous quivering of her hand-she would not have taken the sherbet. But from the hands of the kneeling girl it was taken, and Zuleika's lips sipped its cool contents.</p> 
               <p>"It is a blessed beverage!" she murmured.</p> 
               <p>Leila moved not, spoke not, until the golden cup was drained. Then springing to her feet, her dank eyes flashing wildly, she shouted to the astonished slave who had brought the jewels:</p> 
               <p>"Go to thy master-to Achmed-and bid him hasten to the arms of his favorite. Ah, the fire begins to flame; 'twas a <emph>blessed</emph> beverage! Ha! ha!"</p> 
               <p>Even while she spoke, a deathly pallor passed over the face of Zuleika. With a faint moan her lips opened-her lovely form quivered with a terrible pang; she knew her fate. She had been poisoned!</p> 
               <p>In a moment the harem was alarmed. Forgetting his usual slow and stately dignity, the Sultan rushed to the side of the dying Zuleika.</p> 
               <p>"Whose is this accursed deed?" he cried.</p> 
               <p>"Need Achmed ask?" replied Leila, proudly, as there she stood with her arms folded on her heaving breast, gazing calmly upon the agony of her victim.</p> 
               <p>"Ah! was it thee, vile slave? What ho! Guards!-the bow-string!"</p> 
               <p>"I spare them that trouble!" said the haughty woman. "In losing thy love, oh, Ali Achmed, Leila lost <emph>all</emph> for which she lived!"</p> 
               <p>Then, quick as the lightning leaps from the thunder-cloud, she drew a shining blade from beneath her robe, and buried it in her bosom.</p> 
               <p>"It is well!" said the Turk. "Bear away her corse; bury the two side by side! Thanks to Allah, there are more flowers on earth! Bring me my pipe, a cup of sherbet, and let the dancing girls be summoned!"</p> 
                
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="66 (Illustration) -67" xml:id="VAC6967-00000034"/> 
               <head>
                  <figure> 
                     <p>THE WABINGA QUEEN.-See page 68.</p> 
                  </figure>
               </head> 
                
               <head>NUMBER TEN.</head> 
               <head type="sub">Wanesa, the Wabinga Queen.-A Legend of the Forest.</head> 
               <div type="part"> 
                  <head>PART 1.</head> 
                  <p>I HAVE but a simple tradition to tell, or a tale that was told me by an old man, who dwelt at the head of the Delaware river, where I was born. He told it in a plain and simple style-so will I give it to my readers.</p> 
                  <p>Many years ago there was a powerful tribe of Indians known as the Wabingas, whose hunting-grounds were extended from the banks of the Hudson across the mountains, to the Susquehanna. They were, when this country was first discovered, very numerous; but, being at war with nearly all of the eastern tribes, especially with the Mohicans, they were almost entirely annihilated before the commencement of the second half of the last century. Of them, or rather of their Queen, is this story told.</p> 
                  <p>When the first white settlers came to this country, the tribe was under rule of Chihocki, an aged warrior and king, who died shortly after the settlement of the country, leaving his only child Wansa, queen of the tribe; but acting under a council of chosen chiefs and warriors, much as Victoria Regina acts through her parliament and ministers in England, at the present time.</p> 
                  <p>Wansa, who was very young when the eagle coronet was placed upon her brow, was ever very kind to the whites, and sought their society much. Her presents were rich and frequent, and of course her reception was ever kind among the strangers. And among these strangers none was more marked in attentions none more generous in presents, than HERBERT LOVELACE, a young and dashing Englishman, the only son of a gentleman of fortune, who had taken it into his head to settle on the banks of the Hudson, far up, somewhere near where the town of Hudson now stands.</p> 
                  <p>Wansa was at first pleased with the beauty of the gallant stranger, then captivated by his rich presents and his ardent attentions, and she <emph>loved</emph> him. Unknowing <emph>our</emph> forms of etiquette and cold-hearted ceremony, she did not attempt to disguise her love; but <emph>purer</emph> than those who often stand so <emph>much</emph> upon form and etiquette, her love was free from <emph>passion</emph>. She wished to <emph>wed</emph> the noble-looking Herbert, but it was in vain that he strove to win her except <emph>as</emph> a <emph>bride</emph>. This he did not desire; and it was in vain that she offered him the chieftainship of her braves-that she besought him to become her lord, and join her tribe. At last he became wearied of his fruitless exertions to dishonor her, and threw off the specious veil which had disguised his black heart. He openly laughed at Wansa's love, scorned her advances, and drove her from his father's house.</p> 
                  <p>She went-not weeping, or sobbing, or sighing, as our deserted maidens would;-<pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC6967-00000035"/> she went with anger in her eye, revenge in her heart, a curse against his perfidy on her lips.</p> 
                  <p>Months passed away-she came no more to the settlements-Herbert thought that all was over.</p> 
                  <p>About this time, a beautiful young lady, the daughter of a retired officer, came over with her father and settled near the Lovelace estate. The young lady, Constance Merley, was of the same age as Herbert's only sister, Blanche; and a more beautiful being never trod the flowery carpet of God's footstool. She was tall, her figure rather slight, set full enough to be perfectly graceful. Her hair was a dark brown, approaching very nearly to black; her eye-brows arched her eyes a dark blue; her features classic and beautiful. And yet, even above her beauty, there seemed a charm in her manner-a fascinating simplicity and <hi rend="i"/>naivette, which won admirers on every hand.</p> 
                  <p>Having no companion of her own age and sex in the settlement, except BLANCHE LOVELACE, CONSTANCE was thrown much in her society, and of course often met Herbert. These meetings of two handsome, young, and loveable persons soon caused a ripening friendship; and but a brief period passed ere that friendship ripened into love. To make the story short-a year from the time when Wansa left the white settlements, Herbert Lovelace and Constance Merley were married.</p> 
                  <p>It was a dark and stormy night when they were wedded-yet within the rude walls of Mr. L's dwelling all was brightness and gaiety. Though the wind roared without, the laugh was merry within; though the thunder rolled deep and solemn through the clouded sky, no clouded brow was there; though the lightning flash was bright without, brighter was the cheery fire and brilliant lamp within. With song and dance the eve was whiled away-the festive board was spread, red wine brought from afar o'er the sea was quaffed, and all was gaiety and joy. At last the midnight hour arrived, and then Constance, attended only by Blanche, left the festive room.</p> 
                  <p>They had been gone but a few minutes, yet the guests now began to leave. Suddenly a piercing shriek was heard-then another-and another, loud, shrill-shrill as terror could make it! One instant of surprise-an involuntary pause-then, Herbert leading the way, the <unclear>male</unclear> portion of the company rushed toward the bridal chamber, whence the screams had issued.</p> 
                  <p>But when they reached it, it was empty. An open window, a yell of savage exultation, the whoop of an hundred Indian warriors, sent back in mockery told the story. The Indian Queen had been well avenged had she seen that wretched husband stagger forward, and with a groan of agony sink helpless to the floor.</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="part"> 
                  <head>PART II.</head> 
                  <p>IT was night. In the deep shade of some lofty oaks was a tableau fit for any painter to picture or poet to describe. In the background, around a blazing fire, a party of warriors danced and chanted their wild war-songs. Here and there, amid the rough-barked trees stood warriors grim and silent. They were sentinels. In the foreground, dressed in the queenly costume of her rank, reclining against a rock, the tomahawk and knife by her side, was Wansa. In her hand she held the miniature of Herbert Lovelace, which had just been taken from the neck of Constance.</p> 
                  <p>Constance, with an air half of despair, half of dignity, stood upright, gazing upon her; while poor Blanche, her garments rent by the rude savages as they had borne her over many a rocky precipice, and through tangled forests, crouched trembling by her side. The fire threw its ruddy light on the scene. Then as Constance gazed on the dark, yet beautiful face of Wansa, she saw great, bright pearly tears coursing down her cheeks.</p> 
                  <p>"The white warrior is beautiful!" she murmured. "Yet, he has been like the changing wind, which, coming worm from the south, brings the flower to life; then, changing to the north, comes icily and kills it; such has he been to Wansa! Now Wansa has triumphed! His wife is in her power his virgin bride is in her grasp! What shall be her fate?-the torture?"</p> 
                  <p>The dark-freed Queen paused; she looked again upon the portrait; she raised it to her lips; she kissed it! The great tears streamed in torrents down her cheeks. Constance, in surprise, gazed upon her, yet knew not why she wept. Dreading the worst, poor Blanche only wept and trembled.</p> 
                  <p>Wansa at last arose. Passing close to the side of Constance, she paused, and looking steadily into her blue eyes for at least a minute before she spoke, said, holding up the portrait:</p> 
                  <p>"The <unclear>lily</unclear> who came over the great waters has chosen this white warrior for her lord?"</p> 
                  <p>"Yes!"</p> 
                  <p>"Does she love him?"</p> 
                  <p>"She would never have married him had she not."</p> 
                  <p>"Wansa loves him too."</p> 
                  <p>"Who is Wansa?"</p> 
                  <p>"<emph>I!</emph>" cried the Wabinga Queen, her face darkening, while her eye brightened. "I am Wansa."</p> 
                  <p>And we are your prisoners!" sighed Constance.</p> 
                  <p>The Queen made no reply. Again she paused, looked down upon the miniature, and then kissed it once more.</p> 
                  <p>"Wansa is alone!" she murmured. "The flower of her heart has perished-the spring of her soul is dried up! The bride of her deceiver is in her power!-shall she die? No!-<emph>she</emph> has not wronged Wansa-it is <emph>he!</emph> 'He shall be punished!'</p> 
                  <p>She gave the portrait back to Constance.</p> 
                  <p>"Keep it, Lily!" she said. "I will not punish thee, but <emph>him!</emph>"</p> 
                  <p>That night the two maidens slept in the lodge of Wansa; and it was their first night of rest since three nights before they had been torn from their home.</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="part"> 
                  <head>PART III.</head> 
                  <p>IN vain had Herbert Lovelace and his friends searched the forest, and traversed hill and dale, woodland and riverside, to gain tidings or find a track of his lost bride and sister. Not a trace had he found. Seven days had passed, and almost maddened by despair, he had returned to his lonely home. The afternoon was sunny and clear-bright, as if mocking the darkness of his misery.</p> 
                  <p>Suddenly he heard shouting and cheering. Springing to his feet and hurrying to the door, he saw the well-known faces of Blanche and Constance; and between them, leading them on, came <emph>Wansa!</emph>
                  </p> 
                  <p>"Accursed hag!" he cried, as he sprung towards her, "It was thou who robbed me of my bride!"</p> 
                  <p>And as he dashed on, he drew a dagger from his breast. The Indian Queen paused-folded her arms on her bosom-and with a low, calm voice, said:</p> 
                  <p>"Strike, Herbert, strike! It will not be the first or most cruel blow!"</p> 
                  <p>He <emph>would</emph> have struck her! The unmanly wretch raised high his hand-he would have struck that defenceless-noble woman, but ere his hand could descend, Constance, his <emph>wife</emph>, stood before her.</p> 
                  <p>"Herbert Lovelace!" she cried-"husband<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC6967-00000036"/> band by <emph>form</emph>, but not in <emph>heart</emph>, since I have learned thy treachery, forbear! Strike her, but not until my heart's blood has reddened thy blade!"</p> 
                  <p>He paused; he saw through all in a moment. His bride unharmed-his sister uninjured-had been restored by the wronged Wansa! That moment, in his remorse she was again avenged. But doubly, when a moment after, Constance turned, and pressing her to her noble bosom, vowed to live a virgin bride forever, rather than exist by the side of one who had pretended love but to destroy-who had crushed the heart which nature had stamped noble.</p> 
                  <p>In vain did Herbert Lovelace sue for par don-in vain did he threaten the law of husband's right; he was scorned by her whose love he had won by his beauty, and lost by his perfidy.</p> 
                  <p>The story is told. Reader-be thou male or female-take a lesson from it.</p> 
                   
               </div> 
            </div> 
            <div type="poem"> 
               <pb n="72 (Illustration) -73" xml:id="VAC6967-00000037"/> 
               <head>
                  <figure> 
                     <p>LUTI'S WOE-See page 73.</p> 
                  </figure>
               </head> 
                
               <head>NUMBER ELEVEN.</head> 
               <head type="sub">Luti's Woe.-A Romance of the Ganges.</head> 
               <epigraph> 
                  <cit> 
                     <q>
                        <lg type="quotation"> 
                           <l>"When the light perisheth</l> 
                           <l>That from thee issueth,</l> 
                           <l>Our life evanisheth."</l> 
                        </lg>
                     </q> 
                     <bibl>TENNYSON.</bibl> 
                  </cit> 
               </epigraph> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>I.</head> 
                  <l>THEY stand beneath the midnight,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Beside the river-sea,</l> 
                  <l>Whose water sweepeth white around</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The shadow of the tree.</l> 
                  <l>The moon and earth are face to face,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And earth is trancd deep;</l> 
                  <l>The wave-voice seems the voice of dreams</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">That wander through her sleep!</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-4">The river floweth on.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>II.</head> 
                  <l>What bring they 'neath the midnight,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Beside the river sea?</l> 
                  <l>They bring that human heart, wherein</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">No nightly calm can be-</l> 
                  <l>That droppeth never with the wind,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Nor drieth with the dew;-</l> 
                  <l>Oh, calm it, God! <emph>Thy</emph> calm is broad</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">To cover spirits too.</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-4">The river floweth on.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>III.</head> 
                  <l>The maidens lean them over</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The waters, side by side,</l> 
                  <l>And shun each other's deepening eyes,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And gaze adown the tide:</l> 
                  <l>And each within a little boat</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">A little flame bath lit;</l> 
                  <l>If bright it move, the loved doth love-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And love doth fail with <emph>it</emph>.</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-4">The river floweth on.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>IV.</head> 
                  <l>The stars are strong above us,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">To symbolize the soul;</l> 
                  <l>Whereby a tempest-wind may rush,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Nor dim them as they roll.</l> 
                  <l>And yet the soul, by instinct sad,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Doth stoop to symbols low-</l> 
                  <l>To that small flame, whose very name,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Breathed o'er it, shakes it so.</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-4">The river floweth on.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>V.</head> 
                  <l>Go, little boats-go softly,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And guard the symbol spark!</l> 
                  <l>The little boats go soft and safe</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Across the waters dark.</l> 
                  <l>And Luti's eyes have caught the fire</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">They watch; and unawares,</l> 
                  <l>That blessed while, she lets a smile</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Creep silent through her players!</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-4">The river floweth on.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>VI.</head> 
                  <l>The smile-where hath it wandered</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">She riseth from her knee;</l> 
                  <l>She holds her dark, wet locks away-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">There is no high to see!</l> 
                  <l>She cries a quick and bitter <emph>cry</emph>-</l> 
                  <l>"Nuleeni, <choice>
                        <sic>lauch</sic>
                        <corr>launch</corr>
                     </choice> me thine!</l> 
                  <l>We must have light abroad to night,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">For all the wreck of mine!"</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-4">The river floweth on.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WRIGHT2-1430-NOTE001" n="*"
                     place="foot">
                  <p >Confident that I could write nothing so beautiful to illustrate the accompanying picture, I borrow this beautiful <unclear>poem</unclear> from the gifted pen of Miss E. B. Barret-one whose name is as familiar in America as it is in her <unclear>own land</unclear>.-NED.</p>
               </note> 
               <pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC6967-00000038"/> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>VII.</head> 
                  <l>"I do remember watching</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Anear this river-bed,</l> 
                  <l>When on my childish knee was laid</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">My dying father's head.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WRIGHT2-1430-NOTE002" n="*"
                           place="foot">
                        <p >The Hindoos carry their dying friends to the banks of the Ganges, believing in the after blessedness of those who <unclear>die there</unclear>.</p>
                     </note>
                  </l> 
                  <l>I turned mine to keep the tears</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">From falling on his face;-</l> 
                  <l>What doth it prove, when Death and Love</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Choose out the self-same place?"</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-4">The river floweth on.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>VIII.</head> 
                  <l>"They say the dead are blessed,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The death-change here receiving.</l> 
                  <l>Who say-ah, me!-do <emph>any</emph> say</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Where blessed are the living?</l> 
                  <l>Thy boat, Nuleeni!-look not sad-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Light up the waters rather!</l> 
                  <l>I weep no faithless lover where</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">I wept a loving father."</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-4">The river floweth on.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>IX.</head> 
                  <l>"My thought was of his falsehood,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Ere my flame had waxed dim;</l> 
                  <l>And though I closed mine eyes to dream</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">That one last dream of <emph>him</emph>,</l> 
                  <l>They shall not now be wet to see</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The shining vision go.</l> 
                  <l>From earth's cold love, I look above</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">To the holy house of snow."<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WRIGHT2-1430-NOTE003" n=""
                           place="foot">
                        <p >The Hindoo heaven is <unclear>localised</unclear> on the summit of Mount Meru, one of the mountains of the Himalaya, or Himmeleh, which signifies, I believe, in Sanscrit, the abode of snow, winter, or coldness.</p>
                     </note>
                  </l> 
                  <l rend="ti-4">The river floweth on.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>X.</head> 
                  <l>"Come <emph>thou</emph>-thou never knewest</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">A grief, that thou shouldst fear it;-</l> 
                  <l>Thou wearest still the happy look</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">That feels another's near it!</l> 
                  <l>Thy humming bird is in the sun,<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WRIGHT2-1430-NOTE004" n=""
                           place="foot">
                        <p >
                           <unclear>Himadeva</unclear>, the Indian God of Love, is imagined to wander through the three worlds, accompanied by the humming bird, cuckoo, and gentle breezes.</p>
                     </note>
                  </l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Thy cuckoo in the grove;</l> 
                  <l>And all the three broad worlds, for thee,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Are full of wandering love."</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-4">The river floweth on.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XI.</head> 
                  <l>The little maiden cometh-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">She cometh shy and slow</l> 
                  <l>I ween she seeth thro' her lids,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">They drop a-down so low!</l> 
                  <l>Her tresses near her small, feet bare-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">She stands, and speaketh nought;</l> 
                  <l>Yet blusheth red, as if she said</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The name she only thought.</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-4">The river floweth on.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XII.</head> 
                  <l>She kneeled by the water-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">She lighted up the flame;</l> 
                  <l>And o'er her youthful forehead's calm</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The trembling radiance came.</l> 
                  <l>Go, little boat-go, soft and safe,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And guard the symbol spark!</l> 
                  <l>Soft, safe doth float the little boat</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Across the waters dark.</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-4">The river floweth on.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XIII.</head> 
                  <l>Glad fears her eyes have blinded-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The light they cannot reach;-</l> 
                  <l>She turneth with that sudden smile</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">She learnt before her speech.</l> 
                  <l>"I do not hear his voice; the tears</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Have dimmed my light away;</l> 
                  <l>But the symbol light will last to-night-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The love will last for aye."</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-4">The river floweth on.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XIV.</head> 
                  <l>Then Luti spake behind her-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Out spake she bitterly:</l> 
                  <l>"By the symbol light that lasts to-night</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Wilt vow a vow to me?"</l> 
                  <l>She gazeth upward in her face;</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Soft answer maketh she:</l> 
                  <l>"By loves that last when lights are past,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">I vow that vow to thee!"</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-4">The river floweth on.</l> 
               </lg> 
                
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XV.</head> 
                  <l>An earthly look had Luti,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Tho' her voice was deep as prayer.</l> 
                  <l>The rice is gathered from the plains,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">To cast upon thine hair.<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WRIGHT2-1430-NOTE005" n="*"
                           place="foot">
                        <p >The Ganges is represented as a white woman, with a water lily in her right hand, and in her left a late.</p>
                     </note>
                  </l> 
                  <l>And when <emph>he</emph> comes, his marriage-band</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Around thy neck to throw;</l> 
                  <l>Toward his gaze thy bride-smile raise,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And ask of . . . . <emph>Luti's woe</emph>."</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-4">The river floweth on.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XVI.</head> 
                  <l>"And when, in seasons after,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Thy young bright-faced son</l> 
                  <l>Shall lean against thy knee, and ask</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">What deeds his sire hath done?</l> 
                  <l>Press deep adown thy mother-smile</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Upon his ringlets long-</l> 
                  <l>View deep his pretty childish eyes-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And tell of-<emph>Luti's wrong!</emph>"</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-4">The river floweth on.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XVII.</head> 
                  <l>She looked up in wonder,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Yet softly answered she:</l> 
                  <l>"By loves that last when lights are past,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">I vowed that vow to thee!</l> 
                  <l>But why glads it thee, that a bride-day be</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">By a word of wo defiled-</l> 
                  <l>That a word of wrong take the cradle song</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">From the ear of a sinless child?"</l> 
                  <l>"<emph>Why?</emph>" Luti said, and her laugh was dread-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Her laugh was low and wild;-</l> 
                  <l>"That the fair new love may the bridegroom</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And the father shame the child!"</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-4">The river floweth on.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XVIII.</head> 
                  <l>"Thou flowest still, O river!</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Thou flowest 'neath the moon,</l> 
                  <l>Thy lily hath not changed a leaf,<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WRIGHT2-1430-NOTE006" n=""
                           place="foot">
                        <p >The casting of rice upon the head, and the fixing of the band or tall about the neck, are parts of the Hindoo, marriage memorial.</p>
                     </note>
                  </l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Thy charmed lute a tune!</l> 
                  <l>
                     <emph>He</emph> mixed his voice with thine-and <emph>his</emph>
                  </l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Was all I heard around!</l> 
                  <l>But now, beside his chosen bride,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">
                     <emph>I hear the river's sound!"</emph>
                  </l> 
                  <l rend="ti-4">The river floweth on.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XIX.</head> 
                  <l>"I gaze upon her beauty,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">I feel her happy breathing:</l> 
                  <l>The light above thy wave is hers;</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And mine, the rest beneath them</l> 
                  <l>Oh! give me back the dying look</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">My father gave thy water!</l> 
                  <l>Give back!-and let a little love</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">O'erwatch his weary daughter!"</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-4">The river floweth on.</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>XX.</head> 
                  <l>"Give back!"-she hath departed-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The word is wandering with her,</l> 
                  <l>And the stricken maidens hear afar</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The step and cry together.</l> 
                  <l>O symbols!-none are frail enow</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">For mortal joys to borrow.</l> 
                  <l>While bright doth float Nuleeni's boat,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">She weepeth, dark with sorrow!</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-4">The river floweth on.</l> 
               </lg> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC6967-00000039"/> 
               <head>Chased by a Bear.</head> 
               <p>"You've heard of bear fights, boys! Now try every fellow here, just hold your tempers, and hear your uncle say a word or two, on that subject."</p> 
               <p>"Go it, Uncle Bill! and if it's first rate we'll treat," exclaimed half a dozen listeners, drawing their chairs closer to the old veteran who had proposed the "yarn." We had often listened to the tales of the old settlers, and with our usual interest excited took a seat. The bar-room was soon in a quiet state-even the bar-keeper leaned forward over the counter, to hear the old settler.</p> 
               <p>"Uncle Bill," as he was familiarly termed by all who had seen him more than once, was a curious specimen of human nature; no one had ever learned from whence he came; whether he had been married, or anything else personal. He would talk with you all day long about the "Injuns," and the days he had fought under Harrison, but if you asked him further, his answer was either so evasive that you became convinced it was none of your business, or he turned it off in a hearty joke, and a queer, comical look of his left eye, (he had lost his right in an "Injun" fight) which was equal to the words, "Who'd you say was green.'</p> 
               <p>So much for the narrator; and pulling his old rabbit-skin cap tolerably well over his eyes, and after sundry twistings about in his chair, he proceeded to amuse the young men by telling them some of his experience.</p> 
               <p>"When I was a small chap, say, about the size of Jack Benson, there, my father lived near Wheeling. He was one of the early settlers of that region, having made, although the Indians bothered him a heap, considerable improvements, that is, people thought them so, in them days. He had, by the assistance of his boys, (I was the likeliest of the family.) cleared about twenty acres and put in crops. He had the nearest log-cabin about, two rooms below, and a loft where we stowed away all the lumber in one corner, while the end which had a window in the gable, was taken up as a sleeping room for me and a younger brother.</p> 
               <p>"The old man always had an idea that I was cut out for an etarnal hard kind of a chap, and kept me at work, as he said, to keep me out of mischief; but the old fellow wasn't smart enough for his son,-for if there was to be a buskin', quiltin' match, coon hunt, or a general spree among the young 'uns, I'd lay perfectly still, till I thought the old man was asleep and then-you understand-my brother was afraid to tell-he'd catched one of the awfullest lickens that any chap ever dreamed of.</p> 
               <p>"Well, one night, the Widow Jackson, about three miles from our house, give out that she'd have a quiltin, and wanted all the young folks to come and help her out of a drag. They fixed them things in them days just as they do now. You see, the young fellers had no idea of quiltin' but the gals wanted some one to go home with them-just as if they had no big brothers that came with them. When supper was over, I picked up my cap and made for the door.</p> 
               <p>"Bill," said the old man, "Bill, where are you a goin' this time of day."</p> 
                
               <p>"To Widow Jackson's quiltin," said I, just as <unclear>unconsarned</unclear> as if I didn't care nothing about it.</p> 
               <p>"You can't go, Bill; I don't want to be waked up in the night to let you in."</p> 
               <p>"Well, dad, I'll stay at home!" for I saw I had to play 'possum.</p> 
               <p>"The old 'uns soon went to bed with the impression that I was there also, and sound asleep. About the right time I was off, and soon reached the quiltin'. All the boys for four or five miles around was there. But what took my eye was a chap named Tom Phelps strutting about in all of his glory. Half of the gals in the room was trying to get him to look at them. I knew something was in the wind, so I walks up to him, says I, "Tom, how d'ye do."</p> 
               <p>"First rate," said he, "only I'm mighty tired; he was a hard fellow to upset, but I done it for him."</p> 
               <p>"Who do you mean?" says I, for I didn't understand him.</p> 
               <p>"You didn't hear of the bear, then, that I killed to-day!" And so he sets down and tells me all about it. You see he was out hunting and came across a bear. As good luck would have it, he took first rate aim and upset the black varmint at one shot. He skinned the old feller, and now he calculated that he was one notch ahead of any chap in the settlement. And that was what all the fuss was about. He'd killed a bear, and every gal in the room thought he was a real snorter.</p> 
               <p>"Just to please him, I acknowledged the corn. I could whip any boy about, fair fight-but I had not killed a bear. But, thinks I to myself, without saying anything-if I don't kill a bear 'fore a week, then I'm switched, or else there aint none about.</p> 
               <p>"I didn't sleep much that night, when I went home, for I was thinking of glory, and shining among the gals.</p> 
               <p>"Two or three days after, there was a general understanding that there was bears about the neighborhood, and the neighbors set upon a day to turn out and give them a chase. The night before I cleaned out my rifle, and prepared myself in all respects. We were to start off at day-break. Setting my rifle by my bed-side, I hopped into bed, but found, it hard work to sleep for a long time, and had hardly got in a good snooze, when I heard a low, savage growl not far off. I was up and dressed before you could wink-out and ready to show fight. The moon was shining as bright as day, and not far from the house, I saw the old feller making tracks for the woods. 'Not so fast!' says I, 'old feller, I've a word to say to you-I would like to know where all of your friends are.' But he didn't stop; and I after him, as fast as my heels could carry me. I guess I chased him about a mile when the old feller wheeled about, and seemed disposed, as the Indians say, to have a talk. He reared himself upon his hind feet, and showing his teeth, seemed to say 'Come on!'</p> 
               <p>"Drawing up my rifle, I took aim with a rather unsteady hand, and cracked away. The old feller gave a most tremendous growl, and started towards me, limping a little, and showing his teeth in a manner that would have scared the best of you. I commenced to retreat in a slow manner, and felt for my powder horn, but in my hurry, when dressing, I had forgotten it, and then I was in a trying situation. Boys, if you could only have felt for about two minutes as I felt just about that time, you'd have the fever and ague shakes as long as you lived, and could recollect anything about it, but you know that in such times a feller don't stop to think of anything but which is the best track home, and how to keep clear of the bear. The long chase had made me tired, but I took to my heels as the last resource in time of danger, bracing every nerve. Logs were no obstruction, and gulleys which had looked rather broad at other times, I got over as easily as you would hop over a twig, and close after me growling in a hungry tone came the bear. The sweat poured down my face, although it was winter and cold enough. I could hear the steps of the bear close behind me, but had not enough courage to look back, for that was not the object with me; I was trying to get over the ground ahead as fast as I could. I heard his steps closer and closer, till it seemed to me that he trod almost on my heels. I felt like dropping down and giving up at once, but then I thought that Dad would grieve himself to death to think what had become of me, for I had hooked out.</p> 
               <p>At last I felt his fore paw brush against was my<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC6967-00000040"/> foot. I felt like saying my prayers; but raising all of my courage at one lick, I turned suddenly round and gave him a thundering blow over the head with my rifle, which slipped from my hand with the action. It didn't hurt the old fellow much though, for he after me again, but I had gained about fifteen feet on him, which was considerable in such a fix as I was.</p> 
               <p>We were both tired, and moved along slowly, but doing our best licks. As I was now within about one quarter of a mile of the house, three or four times I yelled as loud as I could, but it did no good, and the varmint was gaining on me slowly. The blow which he had got had raised his spunk, and he yelled twice as loud as he did before. I could hear him gritting his teeth, and the flesh trembled on my bones. How I wished for my rifle again to hit him another lick over the head, or a knife, for then I might have closed in with him and put an end to the matter; but there was no assistance at my hand. You may think it strange that a feller could think of such things, but it's so. Why I recollected every time I had hooked out of the gable window, every orchard and water-melon patch I had helped to rob when a little shaver; and if you'll believe me, boys, I even thought of what Tom Benson and the other chaps would say, when they found out that a bear had come the giraffe over me.</p> 
               <p>Again the varmint was close upon me, and I tried to redouble my speed, and even then I thought we were a long time running a quarter of a mile. It seemed as long as a year to me. But one hope still remained: I was now about thirty yards from the fence around the cleared field, and I knew that if I got over that, all was safe. But it was very high, and my only salvation could be gained by clearing it at one jump. I didn't believe I could do it, but I was bound to try at all events. The bear was close to me, and still gaining; the fence was high; was there no other way? I looked around to see if a rail was down in any place; twice I screamed aloud, hoping to wake up the dog. I looked one way and another; the fence was thundering high, and if I should fail and fall, all hope was passed. When within about thirty feet of it, I felt that it was my last and only chance, so heaving myself till it seemed to me that my sinews would crack, I gave a despondent shriek and sprang into the air."</p> 
               <p>Uncle Bill seemed overcome with emotion, and he buried his head in his hands. I heard a suppressed sigh break from him. The stillness was broken at last by all of us enquiring in a low tone what was the result of the leap. He raised up his head, and, drawing off his cap, brushed back his gray hair, and said slowly:</p> 
               <p>"Do you see that scar?" pointing to what had once evidently been a deep gash; "I shall carry that," he continued," with me to my grave. With that mark I was kept in bed with a brain fever, and it was some time before I went out again to hunt bears."</p> 
               <p>"But how did you escape?" said I.</p> 
               <p>"I'll explain; you know that we had to put up rough pine limbs for rafters in our log-cabins."</p> 
               <p>"But what has that to do with the story?"</p> 
               <p>"Keep cool, my young friend; you understand what I said. My bed was close to the low roof. When the bear was after me, you must be certain that I wasn't thinking of anything except jumping. Well I jumped-it was a terrible jump. I leaped at least three feet from the bed and found myself lying on my back."</p> 
               <p>"But what were you doing in bed?"</p> 
               <p>"Dreaming of bears, and you see like a fool I jumped up, and came near butting my brains out against the rafters."</p> 
               <p>"Now, Bill!"</p> 
               <p>"It's a fact, by hokey! don't you believe it ask my mother," said he putting on his queer comical look.</p> 
               <p>We treated.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="poem"> 
                
               <head>NUMBER TWELVE.</head> 
               <head type="sub">The Wounded Patriot.</head> 
               <byline>BY CHARLES SWAIN.</byline> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <l>NOT where the Dorian song arose</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Triumphant o'er the bold and brave,</l> 
                  <l>Twould shake the dead from their repose;</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">No! tread not near their dust, thou slave!</l> 
                  <l>For, where the Spartan swords have shone,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Where glory's banner met the breeze,</l> 
                  <l>Each field should be a Marathon!</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Each warrior a <unclear>Mihiades</unclear>!</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>II.</head> 
                  <l>Think, think of that heroic time</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">When Thebes sent forth her Sacred Band!</l> 
                  <l>And is it not the same proud clime?</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The same beloved, immortal land?</l> 
                  <l>Oh, this should be a thought to speed</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Her fettered sons to freedom-<emph>this</emph>
                  </l> 
                  <l>Might call a <emph>spirit</emph> forth to lead,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Like that which led at Salamis!</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>III.</head> 
                  <l>Yet hark! a voice from shore to shore</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Now swells and gathers like a tide;</l> 
                  <l>The swords are drawn, which never more</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Shall rest, till Moslem power hath died!</l> 
                  <l>The reddening sun of morning glows</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">On spear and banner, crest and shield;</l> 
                  <l>The shock and shout of battling foes</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Burst like a whirlwind over the field!</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>IV.</head> 
                  <l>But, ah! the stirring sounds, that move</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The warrior's soul to proud emprise,</l> 
                  <l>Turn faint the watching hearts of love;</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Make dim the fond and anxious eyes:</l> 
                  <l>The stormy close-the sever'd line-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The bickering sabres' deadly sweep-</l> 
                  <l>Rifle the rose from beauty's shrine;</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And matrons tremble while they weep!</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <l>Fast, fast the turban'd tyrant quails</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Before a youthful leader's might;</l> 
                  <l>Till 'neath the bolt of combat falls</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">That arm-the beacon of the fight.</l> 
                  <l>Whilst round the wing of conquest scars-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Whilst fame and freedom nerve each band.</l> 
                  <l>Oh, how his gallant soul deplores</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">His useless sword-his powerless hand!</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>VI.</head> 
                  <l>A mournful wife before him kneels-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">A sister's love his arm entwines;</l> 
                  <l>But not, oh, not for <emph>these</emph> he feels-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">His heart is with his banner'd lines!</l> 
                  <l>Nor wife-child-sister-yet may turn</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">His thirsting spirit from that goal;</l> 
                  <l>No tears may quench the fires that burn</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Deep in his young and patriot soul!</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>VII.</head> 
                  <l>From <emph>all</emph>, with one "farewell," he speeds,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And bears within his last brave hand</l> 
                  <l>The hallowed cross for which he bleeds-</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The standard of his native land!</l> 
                  <l>Still foremost! Still on high it rose!</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">Till far and wild the clarion blown,</l> 
                  <l>Told Hellas' triumph o'er her foes,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And Turk and crescent overthrown!</l> 
               </lg> 
               <lg type="stanza"> 
                  <head>VIII.</head> 
                  <l>With myrtle bind the warrior's brow,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">And bid Olympic garlands wave;</l> 
                  <l>Let wine the wreathed goblet flow,</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">In honor of the young and brave!</l> 
                  <l>And sound the lyre, as when of old</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">It sang the conquests of the free!</l> 
                  <l>The <choice>
                        <sic>anbient</sic>
                        <corr>ambient</corr>
                     </choice> pans of the bold!</l> 
                  <l rend="ti-1">The glorious meeds of victory!</l> 
               </lg> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="80 (Illustration) -81" xml:id="VAC6967-00000041"/> 
               <head>
                  <figure> </figure>
               </head> 
                
               <head>NUMBER THIRTEEN.</head> 
               <head type="sub">Fatal Curiosity, or the Abstracted Letter</head> 
               <head type="sub">A SIMPLE STORY OF REAL LIFE.</head> 
               <p>THERE were few, if any, prettier women in the county of Kent, in England, than Sarah Wimsett, the only daughter of Thomas Wimsett, an old farmer of Kent; and there were few more mischievous girls than her lively cousin, Alice.</p> 
               <p>Sarah was in her eighteenth year, and was, at the time I date this story, engaged to the son of a neighboring farmer, named Frank Lonsdale. Frank was of age, and like the other young men of the neighborhood, often came over to her father's farm in harvest time, to help him get in his grain-the Lonsdale farm being used almost entirely as a grazing farm.</p> 
               <p>Frank Lonsdale was very handsome, quite a favorite among the girls, but a very steady and honorable disposition, and was really much attached to Sarah, who in turn loved him <emph>devotedly</emph>.</p> 
               <p>But Alice was not quite so <choice>
                     <sic>luckly</sic>
                     <corr>lucky</corr>
                  </choice> in getting a handsome lover-and partly through fun, and partly through envy, she determined to play a trick which should pay Frank off for some of his slights, and also give her cousin a little uneasiness. She had a good opportunity to execute her plan-for each day during the harvest-time the two girls carried out the dinners of the harvesters, and remained with them while they partook of the noon-tide meal, beneath the cool shade of some old oak.</p> 
               <p>Having got her plot all ready, Alice accompanied Sarah, as usual, to the field, and after having left their basket and ale-jug with the harvesters, the two girls walked on to the other side of the large tree where the harvesters were seated, and where, when they commenced their work in the morning, they had cast off their jackets.</p> 
               <p>"Let's examine Frank's pockets, and see what's in 'em," whispered Alice, catching up his coat, as she sat down.</p> 
               <p>Thoughtlessly, Sarah caught it up, but then a thought of wrong rushed into her mind, and she dropped it, turning her head quickly toward Frank, as if fearful that he would see her.</p> 
               <p>Fatal moment! It sufficed to do all that Alice wished. Quick as thought she drew a letter, already prepared, from her bosom and slipping it, unobserved, half-way into the pocket of the jacket, exclaimed:</p> 
               <p>"There's a letter there, Sarah! Let's look at it!" And as she said this, she snatched it out, and glancing at the superscription, said: It's in a woman's hand: have <emph>you</emph> been writing to him, Sarah?"</p> 
               <p>"No-no-never!" said the young girl, turning pale.</p> 
               <p>"Oh! I fear he is a coquette; I always did!" said Alice. "May be this letter will prove it. Let us read it!"</p> 
               <p>Sarah took it in her trembling hand,<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC6967-00000042"/> glanced at the beautiful hand-writing on the back, then seeing it was sealed, she murmured:</p> 
               <p>"It is sealed-I cannot open it!"</p> 
               <p>"Pshaw! You're a ninny! Why, you're almost as good as married to him-you've a <emph>right</emph> to open it!" said the temptress.</p> 
               <p>"No-he'd never speak to me if I did! He would not open a letter of mine," replied Sarah.</p> 
               <p>"He would if <emph>you</emph> gave <emph>him</emph> cause for jealousy!" replied Alice.</p> 
               <p>"Oh! you don't think he loves another?"</p> 
               <p>"I know what I know; and think what I <emph>think!</emph>" said Alice; "but if I was you, I'd read that letter before I was one minute older!"</p> 
               <p>"I dare not open it," sighed Sarah.</p> 
               <p>"Pah! I'll break the seal, if that's all, and you can read it while I keep watch!" said Alice; and before the other could reply, or interfere to prevent her, the wilful girl had the letter open.</p> 
               <p>"There now, read it, coz, and tell me what's in it," said the fair hypocrite.</p> 
               <p>The temptation was now too strong to ba resisted, especially as "<emph>Dearest</emph> Frank" was seen on the first line, and Sarah began to read it. Scarce a second, however, had elapsed, before, with a piercing scream, she sprang to her feet, still holding the letter in her hands.</p> 
               <p>The scream brought the harvesters, with Frank foremost of all, in an instant to her side, and he was the first to ask what was the matter.</p> 
               <p>She glanced first at him, then at the letter, then murmuring, "lost-ruined-deceived-O God-<emph>too</emph> much-<emph>too</emph> much!" she sank fainting to the earth.</p> 
               <p>"What does this mean? Sarah, what is the matter?" exclaimed Frank, raising her from the ground.</p> 
               <p>She began to recover. Again she glanced at the letter, then at him, and as she gathered strength, she cried:</p> 
               <p>"Frank Lonsdale, you are a perjured wretch! You would have ruined me-begone-begone from me forever!"</p> 
               <p>"But, Sarah, hear me. What do you mean?"</p> 
               <p>"Nothing, sir, nothing! Go from me-go-go to her!"</p> 
               <p>"To <emph>her?</emph> To who? You bewilder me! What does this mean?"</p> 
               <p>"It means that you are a villain! You've got a wife!" cried Alice.</p> 
               <p>The young man looked at her for a moment in silent surprise-then the flush of anger mounted upon his cheek, and in a stern and bitter tone he turned to poor Sarah, who was weeping bitterly, and asked:</p> 
               <p>"Do you believe that of me, Sarah?"</p> 
               <p>Her sobs were her only replies.</p> 
               <p>"Once more, I ask, do you believe it?"</p> 
               <p>"Leave me-leave me!" she sobbed.</p> 
               <p>"I will-yes-and forever!" cried the young man.</p> 
               <p>At that moment a drum was heard, and at a short distance, passing along the highroad, was seen the gay colors of a recruiting party. England was then at war with France, and her army was filling up to follow the "Iron Duke" to battle. Frank heard the drum, saw the colors, and without uttering another word, raised his jacket, put it on, and hurried to the sergeant of the recruiting party. In less than five minutes he was an enlisted soldier.</p> 
               <p>Alice now began to realise the mischief she had done. With a pallid cheek, and eyes filled with tears, she conjured Sarah to call her lover back.</p> 
               <p>"No-never! He may go to her he is wedded to!"</p> 
               <p>"He is <emph>not</emph> wedded! Oh! Sarah, forgive me! I only did it for a joke! The letter was written by <emph>me!</emph>"</p> 
               <p>"By <emph>you?</emph> Oh! Alice-Alice-you have done that which will kill me' Do you see what he has done? He has enlisted, and my last hope of happiness goes with him!"</p> 
               <p>"No!" cried Alice-"I will go to the Duke himself and pray for his discharge! I did not mean to do this great harm. Dear Sarah, I shall never forgive myself,-oh, if I was only a man, I would go in his place!"</p> 
               <p>"There is no hope!" sighed Sarah; "my fate is sealed! I feel that he is lost to me for ever!"</p> 
               <p>Alas! her foreboding was but too true. All efforts to get his discharge were made in vain because he would not request it himself. In a few weeks later the battle of Waterloo was fought, and Frank perished on that bloody field. Not quite a year elapsed before poor Sarah was carried to the village church-yard Alice never smiled again!</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
               <pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC6967-00000043"/> 
               <head>NUMBER FOURTEEN.</head> 
               <head type="sub">The Last of the Buccaneers.</head> 
               <head type="sub">A YARN OF THE EIGHTEENTH CENTURY.</head> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER I.</head> 
                  <p>OVERSHADOWED by the sombre pall of midnight, the inhabitants of Mariel, a little town situated on the sea-coast, about sixty miles west of Havana, were reposing in quiet and security. The gentle sea-breeze bore the breath of orange, citron and palm through their open lattices, and fanned their heated brows, whispering olian accompaniments to the maidens' dreams.</p> 
                  <p>Suddenly, a heavy, booming sound came moaningly on the breeze from the seaward; and then another and another came sharper and louder, arousing the wondering and half affrighted slumberers, and causing strange commotion among the quiet-loving denizens of the village. Whence came, and what meant these ominous thunderings of war? Spain was then at peace with all nations-the sound could not come from the brazen throats of the Moro.</p> 
                  <p>The awakened inhabitants, half-robed and anxious, had crowded down upon the rocky heights which overlooked their little harbor, and were stretching their eyesight in the gloom to sea-ward, which was every now and then for an instant illuminated by the fitful flash of the cannon, whose booming roar we have already noted. It was evidently an engagement between vessels at sea, but the darkness shrouded the combatants, so that it was impossible to discover their force or nation. With impatience the villagers awaited the approach of day-light, which would aid in revealing the mystery which had aroused them from their dreams.</p> 
                  <p>A low bank of black ragged clouds fringed the northern horizon, at which the old pilots on the "Torre" looked with anxious eyes, for to them it was evident that the combatants would soon have to battle with the fierce and unsparing storm-king.</p> 
                  <p>At last Aurora's blush was seen to tinge the dark cloud-bank, as she slowly arose from the couch of night, gradually lifting the mist-woven veil from the scene, and revealing spar by spar in the dim distance, the vessels whose thunderings had so early enlivened the neighborhood. They were two in number, a corvette and small fore-top-sail schooner, both nearly yard-arm and yardarm, each pouring forth a perfect sheet of flame and shower of shot at the other. As Sol came up from behind the high hills east of the town, and threw his bright light upon the belligerents, their colors told their country and their calling. From the peak of the corvette, the ensign of St. George shook its broad proud folds, while from each mast-head of the schooner, small red streamers danced out upon the breeze, like the flaming tongues of enraged serpents; and a broad red flag, with two swords crossed in its centre, told that she was one of the "rovers of the bloody hand," the oaken home of the Buccaneers Though hove to, the vessels were gradually borne nearer to the shore by the inward heave of the sea, and the tendency of the breeze, so that the combat was visible to the astonished spectators on shore.</p> 
                  <p>The fight was very unequal, as the English man-of-war seemed to be double the size of the schooner, and her guns far out-numbered the pirates' battery, which however was well worked, though by a more scanty crew. As the vessels had drifted in within a mile of the shore, it was apparent that the battle must soon end. The pirate, which till now had lain with her main-top-sail aback, almost yard-arm and yard-arm with her enemy, was seen suddenly to brace around her yards, set top-gallant sails, and haul up on a bowline, as if to try to outwind her opponent. The manuvre was tried too late; escape to seaward was impossible: but two ways were left for them-one, to fight till victory or destruction crowned their efforts-the other, to make the land and find a refuge in the mountains. The pirates, by their next movement, seemed to have adopted the last plan; for, failing in her stretch to windward, she squared off before the wind, and headed directly in for the port, using only her stern chasers. The Englishman followed close in her wake, with a cloud of canvass bellying from her yards, belching forth fire and iron, making the hills resound with his loud thunder.</p> 
                  <p>The harbor of Mariel is but a triangular nook in the coast, and is principally formed and only rendered safe by a large island which lies in its mouth, serving as a breakwater against the ocean surf. The north western channel leading into the harbor, is broad and deep, while the other though deep, is narrow, extremely crooked, and is fringed and broken by dangerous coral reefs. The best pilots rarely venture through this channel, even in calm, clear weather, and never, when the sky wears the aspect of a storm.</p> 
                  <p>The vessels were rapidly scudding in towards the harbor, while the astonished citizens gazed upon them in almost stupid wonder. The cruelty and overbearing disposition of the English nation, had created such strong prejudices against them among the Spaniards, that in the present case, there was little danger that the good people of Mariel would aid them by opposing the landing or escape of the Buccaneers.</p> 
                  <p>The schooner reached the entrance of the port, she swept swiftly along the sandy shores of the island, another moment and she will ground upon the main shore and her crew will fly to the - but ha!- she rounds the inner point of the island and bracing her yards sharp up, heads for the narrow, the impassable channel: bold and fearless must be the hand that guides her now, for one false turn of the wheel, one varying flaw of wind and she is helpless. Her course lies directly under the edge of the cliff upon which the villagers have crowded, and she flies along beneath them; they gaze with shuddering hearts and half-averted eyes, down upon her gory, death be-ridden decks. They see here a headless body, a shattered, crushed and quivering trunk; there a bodiless head, with set teeth and glaring eyes; an arm with sabre still grasped in death-a leg, or on the red bulwarks the dark ooze of brains. Here lies one whose eye, wide glaring, lips compressed, and hands clutched in the death agony, tell how dreadful are his sufferings, though pride, that conqueror of agony, forbids a groan; there another, whose anguish, beyond all human endurance, breaks out in mad yells and shrieks, that rise even above the roar of the breakers, and the loud flapping of torn canvass, or the battle shouts of pursued and pursuer. Oh it was dreadful to look upon!<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC6967-00000044"/> language nor the pen may say how dreadful! The pencil, with nature as a color mixer, the sky for an easel, and eternity for the task, could never do it full justice. Why, oh why should man, after seeing such sights, yet strive to write GLORY with his blood-stained fingers upon death's pale brow!</p> 
                  <p>Fast following, the sails of the corvette loom over the island; her guns have ceased to fire. A moment more, however, and she will be too late, for a few fathoms ahead, and the pirate will have gained the open sea. But ha! look! hark!-heavens! the schooner's keel grates upon the sharp rocks-she trembles-crash go her top-masts over the bows!-she stops-she's lost!</p> 
                  <p>The schooner had grounded upon the last reef in the channel, and now, half dismantled, she swung slowly around broadside on-her battery bearing full upon the mouth of the channel, which the corvette had already gained.</p> 
                  <p>On the deck of the schooner stood a tall old man, whose long white locks streaming upon the wind, contrasted strangely with the red spots of blood and gore which spotted it. From his head and body the blood of many wounds streamed down upon the deck, yet like a crippled lion at bay, he stood leaning upon his long sword, glaring defiance with his blood-shot eyes upon the advancing foe. Around him clustered all that were left of his band, like him, worn, wounded and bleeding, but fierce, silent and fearless, ready alike to die or win the dear-bought victory.</p> 
                  <p>The corvette bore down swiftly and noiselessly. On her forecastle clustered her crew, their numbers ten to one of their foes, confident of an easy victory. Her captain stood far out upon his vessels bowsprit-pride, daring and confidence beaming from his face. As he nears the Buccaneer, waving his bright sword in glittering circles <unclear>above</unclear> his head, in tones that ring clear and loud through the air, he shouts,-"Surrender, dogs! down with arms and colors! Surrender you hell-hounds, or not a soul shall live to tell your fate, and stretch our English hemp!"</p> 
                  <p>"Hear your answer!" yelled the old Buccaneer, as he waved his blade in the air, and shouted "Fire!"</p> 
                  <p>One instant the gunners glanced along the dark tubes-the next, even as the head spars of the corvette touched the schooner's rigging, there burst upon her one blinding sheet of fire, one deafening burst of thunder; the tall cliff trembled to its base; the roar of the guns was echoed by one shrill sky-piercing shriek, and then all was still as solitude, save again the surf roar, and now and then a gurgling cry from beneath the black cloud of smoke which veiled the spot where the vessels were last seen. Slowly the smoke-cloud arose: just beyond the reef, with shattered spars, rent sails, half dismasted and nearly sinking, was the schooner, working against the rising wind, and with difficulty gaining an offing; but where was the corvette, a moment before so beautiful and proud, with her tall spars decked in snow-white canvass, from their thin peaks gay streamers dancing upon the breeze, looking like some proud and beautiful woman, attired for the ball-where was she now? Just above the surface of the water, three mast-heads, with a drooping flag flying from each, could be seen: they told the fate of the corvette and its gallant crew. The shock of the vessels' meeting had forced the pirate over the reef into the open sea, while the broadside of the latter had not only driven in the bows of the corvette, but the concussion had forced her back into the channel, where she had filled and sunk, even before the smoke of that dreadful broadside had cleared away.</p> 
                   
                  <p>Of her crew, a few dark specks, seen struggling for a moment amid the foaming and whirling waters, and then gone from mortal sight forever-they were all!</p> 
                  <p>The inhabitants of Mariel left not the cliff until the last glimpse of the pirate craft had vanished in the distance to seaward; and when at last they turned away, they crossed themselves, and shuddered, as they thought of that day's sights. They shuddered too as they felt the rising storm, and thought them of the sea-tossed mariners, while they looked up at the swift sweeping black clouds that came from seaward-'twas like to be a fearful night upon the waters, But what would storm and tempest betide the fallen, those who lay beneath their waters-'twas for the living they should pray.</p> 
                  <p>Death is terrible, when with warning voice and slow but certain steps it creeps upon the aged; terrible when he vanquishes the young and powerful; terrible when he renders colorless nature's finest tints on the cheek of beauty, and dries the pulses of earth's fairest creatures; terrible when in its budding loveliness he freezes the veins of the tender infant; but oh, doubly terrible when at one fell swoop he hurries hundreds into his cold dark kingdom, unprepared, uncoffined, and unknelled.</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER II.</head> 
                  <p>It was the night following the day of the battle, and the storm had broke upon the Guerrera. She had been refitted as well as she could be at sea, and was now hove to under her fore-try-sail, with a fair chance of weathering the gale, if it did not continue too long for the offing which she had gained.</p> 
                  <p>From her deck the blood stains and black marks of battle had been carefully washed away, her rent sails had been supplied with new ones, and her spars either replaced or scarfed and refitted. The watch on deck were at their stations, and the only thing that would have reminded the spectator of the terrible part they had but lately enacted, was that here and there, amongst them, one would be seen with an arm suspended from his neck by the surgeon's sling, or a plastered cheek, or a gashed brow; for the dead were far down in an ever-quiet grave; quiet, though above roared in sweeping wrath the hurricane, and ploughed the maddened bark; and the wounded were in their uneasy hammocks below decks. In the cabin of the schooner lay the old captain, with his tide of life on its last ebb. The rich curtains of crimson velvet that hung in ample folds above him, threw a ruddy hue over his sallow brow, but his wandering eye, bloodless lip, and the large stiffened drops of sweat that hung glistening on his temples, told how near his last mooring grounds he lay. Beside the couch of the dying man stood one, whose features similar, and look of deep anxiety betokened consanguinity with its occupant; yet in his high clear brow, soft dark eye, and woman-like mouth, there was little to account for his apparent calling, little to explain why <emph>he</emph> was found in a pirate's home, with a pirate's crew; yet so it was. Hark! the sufferer speaks and beckons attention to him who watches by his side. "Eduardo," murmurs the dying man, "Eduardo bend down thine ear, I have much to tell ye, and but little space to speak it in. My anchor's apeak boy; I'll soon go-oh, God! I'll soon go to meet <emph>her-her</emph>-the only being in the wide world beside thee, who has ever proved true and faithful even to death; all else have been cold, heartless, selfish, deceitful, cowardly or treacherous. <emph>She</emph>-oh curse on the dogs! the cursed nation that beggared <emph>me</emph>, drove <emph>her</emph> to ruin. in<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC6967-00000045"/> famy and death, made <emph>thee</emph> a <emph>pirate's</emph> son! Eduardo I die, but oh, I leave you a heritage, a bloody heritage! Vengeance! Vengeance for those who drove me from wealth, peace and happiness, upon the ocean, a remorseless destroyer, a leader, aye the chiefest of a band of devils. Follow them, my boy-circle the boundless ocean, sweep the broad seas-tinge the blue waters, rest not nor stay helm or brace till the bark's last plank yields to the wave and the worm; away with boyish qualms and love-sick mercifulness; away with all but the thought, the damning thought, that my mother died a - oh God! boy I see her yet-thee a feeble wailing infant, thy tiny fingers playing with the silken threads that drooped over her glassy eyes, there cold and motionless; hair torn and dishevelled, lips through which in the last agony, her pearly teeth had forced themselves: oh God! Boy, then-there-I knelt me down beside thy murdered, worse than murdered mother, and vowed to live but for revenge! Revenge! ha, ha-I've had it. I vowed to rest not nor stay my hand till <emph>his</emph> blood had foamed upon my blade, and that done, to follow his cursed nation even till death; and <emph>thou</emph>-thou my son, shalt take mine oath; thy heritage is blood! I go Eduardo, I go to meet <emph>her</emph>, the pure, the holy, the spotless, <emph>thy mother!</emph> And to meet <emph>him</emph>, the destroyer, to gaze on him, to see him quake beneath the sentence of eternal perdition, and to follow him even to the lowest pit of hell to taunt him in his agony. Boy take the schooner, she's a brave bark; stout hearts and strong hands have preserved her; she has borne me through many a hard fought day; take her, and while one plank of the old craft sticks to another, leave not her flag; let her ever be as now, the scourge of the ocean, her flag the warning, her cannon the knell of every foe. I weaken boy-bear me on deck-I would again gaze forth upon the blue waters; <unclear>I would look</unclear> upon the blue shroud that curls for my shattered hulk; I would speak to my crew, and tell them that thou, thou, Eduardo, art my choice! thou'rt theirs-they thine. Bear me on deck!"</p> 
                  <p>They bore him upon the deck-for a moment he looked forth upon the black angry waters and smiled defiance as the rough blast roared above his head, and roughly tore the covering from his weak limbs. "Call aft my crew," he cried, "I'd spin my parting yarn." They came, slowly and sadly, and eyes that never before felt nature's softening moisture, glistened with a light they never before had known. They cared not for death; 'twas not that which pumped up sighs from their unfeeling breasts; no, they had faced the King of Terrors in all his varied and most ghastly shapes; they trembled, not that in his presence they stood; it was that he who for many a blood-recorded year had led them through danger and excitement; led their battles and shared their revels, felt their hardships and known their troubles, should now slowly but surely depart from amongst them. Had he died in the heat of battle they would not have felt so much the loss; but now, and thus, most keenly they felt that he their chief was lost to them forever. Eagerly they crowded around him to hear his last words, and breathless stood the throng, that not a sound should pass unheard. Supported on the shoulder of his kneeling son, he looked upon them and feebly spoke. "I go, my men, on a long strange cruise, I wish that ye might not part company; but it's luck, that's all. I leave ye the craft, a brave, good craft she is too. I leave ye her, and I leave ye my boy for a leader; he will keep up her name and fame, and I bid ye stand by him; yield not the craft whilst ye or he live, for she and ye belong to him and vengeance!" The old man was failing fast, and as he ceased, he sank feebly back, his eyes closed, his lips seemed to move as if in prayer, if one like him <emph>could</emph> pray. The crew broke forth in angry mutterings that rose on the ear of Eduardo like the low murmur of a coming storm. He had ever been unpopular with them; his heart too merciful, his hand too sparing, he illy suited those bloody men for a leader. Their murmurs reached the ear of the dying chief, it aroused the expiring man, and with strange fierce energy, unaided he started to his feet, his yet bloody sword sprung from its scabbard, and while he flashed forth the lightning of his angry eye, he shouted in tones that mocked the tempest's roar, "Dogs! dare ye dispute my will? dare ye murmur at my bidding? Down villians, ere I curse ye!" Even then, in his last dying agony, that fierce old man caused those fearless men to shrink in awe and silence back into calm obedience; they shrunk away and murmured no more. He sank again into the arms of his son, and in a low tone gave his last instructions. While he was speaking, the clouds flew swiftly by overhead, ragged, black and threatening. The spars though disencumbered from the weight of canvass, bent like hoop-poles before the force of the gale, and the rigging served as strings whereon the hurricane piped its wildest tune. Oh, it was a fitting night and place for a sailor to die. Above him shrieked the storm-king, him with whom he so oft had battled; around, all was foam and flashing waters, the air teemed with maddening excitement, all seemed leaping madly, racing with the coursers of destruction. Oh, it was madly, grandly, majestically yet fearfully beautiful. In such a scene, at such a time, oh let my soul burst from its worn-out hull and spring out upon the flapping wings of the hurricane, amid the rushing clouds, the roar of wind and waters, and the shriek of Petrel and Albatross. While the old man spoke, his eye sought the heavens above-a small white cloudlet seemed to rest quietly above the vessel, while above and around it flew the black heralds of the storm with inconceivable rapidity. He gazed wildly for a moment upon it, and then, with the energy of a strong man's last agony, burst from the arms of his son-one moment with arms outstretched as if to grasp some unseen form, and eyes up-glaring at the cloud, he shrieked, "It is she, Eduardo! it is she-my own Monona-I come, my bride, I come!" and with one wild bound he cleared the bulwarks-a flash upon the waters, a gurgling eddy, and he was gone forever, unshrouded, uncoffined, and unmarked. The vessel sped madly on before the gale, but with a sad and quiet crew</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER III.</head> 
                  <epigraph> 
                     <q>
                        <lg type="quotation"> 
                           <l>"And his wife by turns she wept and smiled</l> 
                           <l>As she looked on the father of her child,</l> 
                           <l>Returned to her heart at last."</l> 
                        </lg>
                     </q> 
                  </epigraph> 
                  <p>The Guerrera has gained her harbor, and Eduardo has pushed from her side, for on the shore there is some tie that draws him from his noisy mates. Alone, in a light skiff he steers his course up the Canima's tide, and none know or ask whither he is bound or when he will return. None dared to question him while his father lived,-all fear to do it now.</p> 
                  <p>Far up the beautiful Canima is a large cavern,<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WRIGHT2-1430-NOTE007" n="*"
                           place="foot">
                        <p >Unto this day known as "La Cueva de los Piratas." The writer has spent many an hour in exploring its dark and gloomy passages, and gathering rich specimens of crystal branch and congealation. It is only about five miles from the city of Matanzas.</p>
                     </note> only accessible by a steep and narrow path which wound up the face of the almost perpendicular cliff, from which grew a sort of fringe-like covering of flowering<pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC6967-00000046"/> shrubs, which were nourished by many a little rippling fountain, which rolls in connected bubbles down its rough side.</p> 
                  <p>Upon the out-reaching crag, which jutted forth from the cavern's mouth, stands a form with head bent enquiringly down the stream. It is Eduardo's wife; she watches for the homeward bound. O how beautiful she appears as she poises herself on the narrow peak of black rock; the clear sky, moon-lit and cloudless, serves as a back-ground against which the graceful outline of her figure rests. The moon glistens on her long tresses of ebon silk, and the breeze half lifts the gossamer folds of her mantilla, revealing beneath, an infant sweetly sleeping in the only heaven an infant knows, its mother's breast. But see, her large black lustrous eye beams with joy-light, see, her white hand waves the banner of welcome, her tiny feet twinkle on the narrow peak as if she would spring into the silvery waters beneath, the sooner to meet <q>
                        <lg type="quotation"> 
                           <l rend="ti-2">-"the father of her child</l> 
                           <l>Returned to her heart at last."</l> 
                        </lg>
                     </q> But there speeds his boat along the glassy waters, her wake like a fountain of boiling silver sparkles and bubbles up brightness; now its prow touches the rock, swiftly he clambers up its steep side and mother and child are clasped in his fond embrace. Burning kisses meet his lips, she spoke not, but would press him to her beating heart, and then arching back her graceful head would gaze upon his dark face, as if to see if it was indeed <emph>him</emph>, or to mark what change time and exposure had wrought in the mirror of her happiness. Again and again the low sound of her lips' fond pressure stirred the air, and at last she spoke: "Mine own Eduardo, is it you at last, come again to shine upon the darkness of my solitude? Yes you have come, never, O never again to leave me! Have you not, my husband? Speak O speak the words, the blessed words for which my heart so long has yearned, 'twould fall like heaven's music song of welcome to my ear."</p> 
                  <p>"It cannot be <emph>yet</emph>, my bride, but soon, O soon I hope for freedom, and then for thee and happiness, our child and heaven,-but how is the little innocent, Seberina, how fares our gentle Carlos?"</p> 
                  <p>"The child is well my husband," answered the young mother, sadly, "but you have not answered,-you go forth again upon the ocean? Oh go no more, Eduardo! go no more forth amid perils and dangers, forsake the wild life which leads you away from my clinging arms and sorrowing heart, into dangers that are ever pictured in hues of blackest horror to my terror-chilled soul. Thou needest not gold; leave thy blood-stained carnage-loving comrades, and fly with me to some peaceful secluded vale, where none but us and our happy babe may live in the palace of nature's chosen purity, innocence and joy hovering over us with sunny and untiring wings. Come-come my life, and look, Eduardo-see, our little Carlos wakes and smiles upon the happy thought: Oh think, 'tis an approving God, who throws his glorious light upon our infant's face, as thence most easy to reach a parent's heart."</p> 
                  <p>The stern dark-browed man leaned his head upon his fair bride's neck and wept; ay, he whom danger could never blanch, <emph>wept</emph>, while his infant leapt and crowed gleefully in its mother's arms, and even dabbled its tiny fingers in the large drops that coursed down its father's swarthy cheek. Its bliss was in its ignorance.</p> 
                  <p>"Seberina, I cannot leave my fate; it is too late, forever too late! my father has fought his last fight, he has slipped his cable, and now <emph>I-I</emph> am his successor. He has left me a dreadful heritage. I hear him yet-"Blood! Vengeance! Vengeance <unclear>for</unclear>
                      a murdered, worse than murdered mother's wrongs."</p> 
                  <p>"No my husband," interrupted the imploring and tearful wife, "no, you are not bound to that dreadful life, you are to good, too merciful to lead a ruthless band of robbers, they even now as ever murmur at your goodness, you are yet pure, innocent, and free from blood, go forth with me into the sunny world and claim a peaceful home and biding place."</p> 
                  <p>"No! hence! it is too late, I am an outcast, we are hunted by the whole world's blood-hounds, and I though innocent as that babe of crime, would be the first to meet with scorn, infamy and disgraceful death."</p> 
                  <p>"No, O no my husband, they could not, would not harm thee; I would plead thy cause, I'd tell them that your sword had never been extended but to save the helpless, thy shout had ne'er been heard but to call back the destroyer; I'd tell them how you saved me from worse than death, when the faithless elements had cast me lone and helpless into the hands of those dreadful men, that horrible Manuel; Oh they would not harm thee."</p> 
                  <p>"No my Seberina, it is too late, thou knowest them not, those men of chilling dignity, who sit in judgment upon their less fortune-favored brethren; with them justice is but a harsher name for death, severity their motto; Mercy, too fair and gentle for their ever-biding winter, blooms not in their presence, but shrinks away like a withered, blighted, unseen flower. They would spurn thy pleading form from their footstools, wert thou to tell them that a <emph>pirate's son</emph> could live and be guiltless of crime. No, my bride, that fearful heritage! those sepulchral tones-"blood! Vengeance for thy murdered mother's wrongs!" they ring yet in my ear."</p> 
                  <p>"No Eduardo, it is <emph>not</emph> too late; we will go forth hand in hand with our infant, into some unknown and peaceful clime and who shall dare to say that guilt or infamy is linked with hearts that love like ours? But come, my love, the night is chill and the damp dews gather on your raven locks, come within."</p> 
                  <p>They entered the cave, the inner luxury of which strongly contrasted with its rough and gloomy exterior. The narrow entrance, guarded by a single huge rock, which turned on a pivot, opened into a large saloon, lofty and spacious. It was hung around with silken tapestry, carpeted with the softest wools of Turkey, and ornamented with rich paintings and beautiful statues. From a long crystal stalactite hung a silver lamp whose rays reflected from a thousand glistening points, cast a rich mellow light over the whole apartment.</p> 
                  <p>Upon a silken unpressed couch, lay an unstrung Guitar, where the watchful bride and mother left it when she went forth to look for her beloved. A small table, inlaid with the richest mosaic work, bore wine and refreshments, but they too were untouched.</p> 
                  <p>"Rest ye now my Eduardo, while I call my sleeping maidens to prepare our supper," said the young wife disappearing in the interior of the cave, leaving the little duplicate in the arms of its father. We will now return to the Guerrera and her wild crew.</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER IV.</head> 
                  <p>At the mouth of "El Rio Canima," now overlooked and guarded by a Spanish fort, which pours its clear waters into the beautiful bay of Matanzas, is a small basin or lake, surrounded by high hills, and only approachable from sea-ward through a narrow winding channel, the mouth of which is so completely<pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC6967-00000047"/> masked by thick overhanging mangroves, that few in passing would notice it. The lake, clear and transparent as the cloudless sky which it mirrors, looks as if nature in some warm luxurious mood had scooped it out from its rocky base to serve her as a bath.</p> 
                  <p>Around the lake spread a perfect flower-wreath, which served to perfume air and water; while, to one fancifully inclined, the high, thickly wooded hills seemed to have been thrown up as a veil, to hide the favorite moods of the lovely Dame, whom we have already named, from the ever curious eye of a peeping world. The merry birds, with praise, song and many a varied note, seemed to hail this spot as sacred to Nature alone.</p> 
                  <p>In this basin, where she had been warped for concealment, lay the Guerrera; her crew impatiently awaiting the return of her new commander. She had been so refitted as to leave no trace of battle or tempest, and the delicate shadows of her tall, slender spars, and her thin, black rigging, lay wavingly on the gently rippling waters, like the scattered threads of woman's glossy hair when cast adrift in a blaze of sun-gleams. Some of her crew were lolling about her decks, enjoying the breeze from aloft, or reclining beneath the forecastle awning; others were on shore, wandering among the flowers and sparkling rills, that bounded like childhood's sunniest hours adown the rocky hill side; watching the flight of pretty birds, or the playing of the silver streaked trout, that side by side with foamy bubbles, darted to and fro in the waters.</p> 
                  <p>Upon the highest peak of the hill, walked a sentinel, who from his elevated post could command a view of the bay and surrounding country.</p> 
                  <p>Two persons were pacing up and down the quarter-deck of the schooner, engaged in earnest conversation. The elder, who, from his manner, seemed to be in temporary command of the craft, was a weather-beaten, time-marked man, whose quick, flashing black eye, small mouth, compressed lips, and brow contracted with a kind of ever-hiding frown, told of energy and resolution; had apparently seen much hard service, judging from many a scar which seamed his sun bronzed face. Though his appearance was rough and forbidding, there was a something in him which gave tokens of honesty and confidence. His companion was younger by some years, and of an entirely different cast of countenance. His eye was small, grey, and ever twinkling up and down, now here, now there, continually restless; in short one of those eyes which can never be mirrored in another eye, and of course is productive of suspicion wherever you meet it. His thin lips, curved downward when they closed, betokened courage and firmness; but there was a sneering, forbidding manner about him, which would cause one to fear if not to dislike him.</p> 
                  <p>The elder seemed more open and honest, while the younger, in physiognomy at least, would have served as a painter's model for a likeness of Judas.</p> 
                  <p>"No, Manuel, it must not be!" said the elder, in answer to a proposal made by the other, to sail without awaiting the return of Eduardo: "His father formed this crew, built this schooner, by his own courage sustained and brought us through many a hard fought battle, and not a week since, when he cut adrift from this world, left the vessel to the boy, and <emph>he</emph> shall have and command her. What fault find ye with him? True he is rather merciful and milk-and-waterish now, but by-and-by he will be as terrible as his sire. <emph>You</emph> cannot say that he is cowardly, especially after you bring to mind the affair off Cazadores."</p> 
                   
                  <p>"The affair off Cazadores! Ha, you again throw that in my face," muttered the other through his grinding teeth; "I have the memory of that morning rankling in my heart yet-but the time is coming, the hour is drawing nigh when the memory of that scene shall be drowned in blood. Aye, you do well to remind me of him, the blow yet tingles on my cheek, but he shall know that a true Solano forgives-never! Let him look to himself: he little thinks that I know of the secret cave, that I have traced him to the nest where lies his dove of beauty. He has won her, true; but if I live, he has a dear price to pay for his prize."</p> 
                  <p>"Pshaw! there are more wenches than her, boy," rejoined the elder. "You had better give up all thought of her, she's meet for your master, go look for as fair and more willing than she, you'll not seek in vain, and for him-"</p> 
                  <p>"What!" interrupted the fiery youngster; "You, one of the 'bloody hearts,' preach to me, forgetfulness of damning insult? Tell me to give over the chase of her who scorned my love, and him who snatched her from my grasp, when she was mine by all our rights? No! that girl is mine. I first saw her, as I stood on the look-out, I first claimed her, and were it not for that faint-hearted recreant, she would now be mine, or else under the blue water, looking for the mermaids in their shell-built homes. She <emph>loves him-scorns</emph> me. It is well! very well! I'll 'bide my time. I'll learn her yet to kneel at my bidding, to lick the dust at my feet, to pray for my smile. She yet shall learn to prize my favors! Pablo, determine at once, I'll wait no longer; either make up your mind to take the schooner out upon a cruise, or <emph>I</emph> will. <emph>He</emph> cannot sway the crew if we are once under weigh; come, old boy, which shall it be, you, or I?"</p> 
                  <p>"Neither, Manuel; you, I, and all of us, swore by the bloody flag, that we would obey and support <emph>him</emph>, even as we had obeyed his father's will; <emph>I'll</emph> not turn traitor to him! I'll not break my oath!"</p> 
                  <p>"Then go to the -, <emph>I will!</emph> and you, Don Pablo, you may look out for - but what is that? there's something in sight, the signal is flying, the look-out is coming in, there's something in the wind, or that fellow would not leave the hill." There was evidently something wrong. The sentinel had set the alarm signal, and was bounding down the hill-side toward the vessel. In a moment he gained the shore and springing into a boat reached the vessel. His errand was soon told. The lurking place of the pirates was discovered. A large fleet of armed boats were even now entering the pass. At once the crew were summoned on board, and active preparations made for defence, for from this spot there was no retreat for the schooner, except by sea, and the assailants approached from that direction. A few moments of intense anxiety were passed, and then the foremost of the boats came out from beneath the mangroves in the entrance, followed quickly by the rest.</p> 
                  <p>On board the vessel, the crew had been busy; the boarding nettings were triced up, the guns double shotted with grape and canister, and all was prepared for the conflict. Again the serpent-tongued streamers and the broad red flag waved high in the air, while a dead silence reigned on the deck beneath; the silence which ever presages a storm. The boats bore Spain's royal standard, which with its folds of red and gold waved heavily over the quiet lake.</p> 
                  <p>So far as numbers were concerned, the buccaneers were in a desperate situation. Their foes numbered more than treble their own force, but yet there was hope, as the assailants fought not for life so much as for their King and his bidding.</p> 
                  <pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC6967-00000048"/> 
                  <p>After the boats had all cleared the pass, they formed into two columns, one of which headed for the bows, the other for the stern of the schooner. With loud cheers, which echoed strangely over the lake and through the hills, the boats dashed for the vessel. An instant of rapid rowing, an instant of almost unbroken silence, and then thick as flakes in a snow-storm flew shot and splinters among the boats. Some were at once shattered and their crews left struggling in the water, but there was no time for the vessel's guns to be reloaded, the foe were alongside. One short moment of desperate effort, in which man after man who had gained the bulwarks was hurled backward, dead into a watery grave, and then the decks were gained, though but a scanty space was made. Bravely did the pirates hold their own; step by step only did they give, and that was measured by death. Surrounded and almost hidden from daylight by the number of their foes, they fought on, not for life, but for its value, revenge. All but a few had fallen: among these, foremost stood Pablo and Manuel, both covered with wounds, yet each silent and firm, giving and parrying blow for blow as if yet confident of victory. It was an awful sight. No shouting, no cries of pain or shrieks of agony; nought but the clash of steel against steel, and pistol shot were heard. At times the gnashing of teeth and panting breath of the combatants could be plainly distinguished. The serried circle kept slowly shrinking and narrowing down, until a fresh arrival of boats with their united crews dashed on board. Then-as the snow-flake melts before a drunkard's breath so passed away the last of the buccaneers. No-not the last, for one struggles still, it is Manuel; a thousand wounds pour from their gaping mouth his life blood, a thousand points are aimed at his heart, when he cries-"Hold! save me-our Captain-a secret cave." The weapons were stayed, and officer sprang forward, it was the commander of the victorious force.</p> 
                  <p>The wounded pirate gazed at him for a moment, and then his eye lighted up with increased fire. He muttered to himself, "It must be her-the likeness is strange! oh! I have it now-revenge-revenge! <emph>thou</emph> art mine at last!" and then raising himself to his feet, he spoke to the officer. "Dost thou command His Catholic Majesty's forces here?"</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, fellow, but what said you of your leader? speak, or your death has been but stayed for a paltry moment."</p> 
                  <p>"Another question first, noble captain; hast thou not a sister?"</p> 
                  <p>A look of indescribable anguish swept over the young officer's face, as he responded-"I had one once, now she rests in heaven. She was lost at sea."</p> 
                  <p>"She rests not in heaven, without heaven is in a pirate's cave, and the attendant angels are pirate's paramours!"</p> 
                  <p>"What?" gasped the officer, "my own Seberina yet living? False! false!</p> 
                  <p>"I saw her sink beneath the gurgling waters on that dreadful night, when the Polacca was lost, even in sight of our happy home on the heights of Cazadores. I saw her sink, and cursed my fate that I too could not die, but on a single mast I was swept on shore. Thou liest, dog! she lives not."</p> 
                  <p>"I tell but that which is true as heaven; she was saved. We picked her up at sea upon a slender raft of spars and now she is the chosen of our Captain's harem. I know her, for she is your counterpart. She looks a twin being with yourself."</p> 
                  <p>"She was-oh, God of Heaven! would that she had sunk beneath the whirling wave, rather than have lived to float upon this gulf of infamy!"-groaned the young officer, and then with maniac-like energy he shouted "man the boats! you say you know of a secret cave where rests the captain of your craft, where <emph>she</emph> my-lead on! lead on! and life with gold enough to make it a curse, shall be yours! Away! and guide me true."</p> 
                  <p>The boats pushed from the schooner's side and swiftly rowed on up the Canima. One lingered later than the rest, and when she turned away from the bank, a black cloud arose from her decks-she was on fire. Ere the boats were out of sight an explosion that shook the very hills was heard, and then the lake was still and quiet as before; nought but a few blackened spars specking its bright bosom. Gone forever was the Guerrera, the beautiful, the swift-flying, oaken home of the roving buccaneers.</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER V.</head> 
                  <p>They were sleeping-the father, mother and child, all clasped in one embrace, all smiling, perchance over dreams of their own happiness. The moon looked in through the vines which clustered over the entrance of the cave, casting a clear, cold light upon the up-turned faces of the sleepers; while the thickly woven vines, as if jealous of the moon's rays, threw flickering, net-like shadows over the scene, as the gentle zephyr moved them slowly to and fro.</p> 
                  <p>Seberina, was even beautiful: beautiful when her large dark eyes sparkled with her heart's true feeling; beautiful when her red lips opening showed the pearls within, and gave birth to gentle words, which would come like the soft sounds of flute-music, as it floateth from afar over still waters; but now in her calm sleep, she looked like heaven's brightest angel in a swoon. One of her rounded arms pillowed the head of her sleeping husband, his jetty hair in clustering curls embracing it, as if to clasp it in its silken bands. Her other arm encircled her infant, which like a lily afloat on a gentle lake whitened by moon-light, lay sleeping on her bosom, rising and sinking with her gentle breathings. It was a beautiful sight, one over which the poet and the painter might luxuriate. But, ha!-a shadow darkens the entrance-another and another-it is the traitor Manuel and the party which he has guided to the cave. With <emph>her</emph> brother at their head, they stealthily enter, and approach the sleepers. Half awed by the pure beauty of the scene, they looked, and broke not the silence. Even the traitor trembled, his eye-lashes drooped and hid the hellish fire within, a stranger blush found a frozen home on his swarthy cheek. "Back! all of ye, back!" whispered the young officer, motioning his party toward the shadowed walls-"back into the gloom take yon traitor, I would test my only sister ere I slay <emph>her</emph> and <emph>him</emph>. She must be innocent. Guilt never thickened the veins of a Marin, and it cannot be that she, our sainted mother's second-being, could be the first to bring ruin on our fame." He approached her side and kneeling, whispered his own name in her ears. As he did so, a smile played upon her features, and she murmured, even in her dreams, his name linked with those most dear to her. "Enrico-my dear Enrico, lost-but in heaven with my husband and my Car"-"Her husband! did she say husband?" muttered the brother, and as he spoke he raised himself and gazed upon the sleeping man-long and earnestly he looked, and then again breathed forth his thoughts. "It cannot be that he who thus sleeps calmly by the side of youth and innocence, is criminal. He cannot be the pirate chief whose name, the watchword of terror, is blackened with murder's foulest stain; every<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC6967-00000049"/> feature is marked with the unerring stamp of nature's honest nobility. And she called him <emph>husband!</emph> O, I knew it-neither she, nor one of our proud race would stoop to be a monarch's leman. I will not slay them as they sleep; fair and open trial shall be theirs, and if yon traitor's tongue has played me false-he'll curse the hour which saw him enter on a life doomed to end in hellish agony-ha! Seberina! my sister, awake.'"</p> 
                  <p>She started at the well known tones-she opened her dark eyes-one quick glance-one piercing shriek of mingled joy and woe, and she sank senseless in her brother's arms. Aroused by that cry, quicker than the ragged lightning leaps from its bed in the storm cloud, Eduardo sprang to his feet-and as he rose, his sabre waved in the air, but it was too late, he was seized, disarmed, and pinioned. One glance told him all; there stood the traitor Manuel, his eyes gleaming with the infernal joy-light of satisfied hate. A withering sneer sat upon his lips, as he looked toward the senseless wife, whom her brother was endeavoring to recover, and shouted, "Ha, Don Eduardo! now is <emph>my</emph> time, noble captain! <emph>We</emph> are pirates, the sole survivors of the Guerrera-and yon lies a <emph>pirate's leman</emph> in that noble Spaniard's arms. Now is she <emph>yours? mine?</emph> or am I revenged? And you bastard son of thy mis"-have you ever seen the tall oak bowing, writhing and groaning in the strong arms of the whirling hurricane, at last from the firm, rock-belinked earth leap madly to its last resting place, casting in its fall ruin and burial upon all beneath it?-so for one instant Eduardo swayed to and fro in the strong arms of his captors, as his ear burned with the maddening taunts; the next-they were hurled from him, and with one tiger-like leap he alighted beside the dastard traitor, and as his feet touched the rock, his hand clenched the villian's throat. Manuel grew black in the face, blood spouted from his eyes, nostrils and mouth-his limbs trembled-an instant more, Eduardo's hand relaxed its grasp-the traitor was dead. Then his wrath was past, he turned submissively, even meekly to his captors, but looked only on his wife and child. Seberina was recovering from her swoon. The infant half enveloped in the silken folds of the couch, looked with a wondering, but not affrighted eye, on the glittering throng of armed men. As strength and recollection came to the mother's mind, aided by her brother, she arose to her feet and looked around. Her eye first met the livid corpse of the traitor. Shudderingly she turned away, and then she saw her husband. Glancing upon his bounden hands she comprehended all-"Tear those manacles from my husband's arms, Enrico! he is innocent, as yon babe, of crime-tear the slavish symbols from his noble form! As free from guilt as thou, and fitting to be the husband of the last woman of thy race-oh! my brother release him-save <emph>him</emph>"-cried the fond wife as she sunk to the earth stifled with tears and sobs-oh! save the father of thy sister's child! my God-given husband!" "Be calm, my sister, my duty must be done, all must be investigated; he must meet the governor and then if he be guiltless, he shall still be thine. Don Rodrigo is just, I have his favor-fear not-he will go free if guiltless-and if not"-"Oh what?" shrieked the poor girl-her brother bent his head to her ear-she rose with a sweet, sad smile of satisfaction on her heavenly face.</p> 
                  <milestone n="* * * * * * *" unit="typography"/> 
                  <p>In Florida on the banks of St. Augustine Bay, a few miles only from the city, stands a neatly beautiful cottage, embedded in the centre of a grove of orange, lime and palmetto trees. Situated on the side of a gentle tle elevation which slopes gradually up from the water side, it is known as the prettiest spot in St. John's county, nay in the entire territory. The building is composed of the singular shell stone, which is found in only two places in the world, the island of Anastasia which fronts St. Augustine, and the island of Sacrificios, lying off Vera Cruz, on the coast of Mexico. Its interior resembles the disposition of a ship cabin, and judging from a flag staff which rises from the gable end of the cottage, and a "look-out" formed from a tall fine tree, rigged after the manner of a sloop's main mast, I should suppose the whole either to belong to, or have been designed by a sailor.</p> 
                  <p>Reader, if you ever go to St. Augustine, in the course of this life's varied cruisings, visit "<hi rend="i"/>Casa Pulla" and gather the conclusion of the foregoing history. It will not be traced on the page of sorrow, wilted down by tears; but perchance you'll come away with a light heart and a joyous countenance, after hearing from one <emph>deeply</emph> interested, the remainder of the "<hi rend="i"/>last of the Buccaneers!"</p> 
               </div> 
            </div> 
            <closer>THE END.</closer> 
         </div>
      </body> 
      <back> 
         <div type="advertisement"> 
            <pb n="98 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC6967-00000050"/> 
            <head type="sub">Garrett &amp; Co.'s List of Publications.</head> 
            <head>Ned Buntline's Celebrated Novels.</head> 
            <div type="advertisement"> 
               <head>THE MYSTERIES AND MISERIES OF NEW YORK.</head> 
               <p>A book of the Strangest and most Mysterious Adventures that ever took place in the New World, giving the reader details of more genuine New York life than can be found in print anywhere else, or can be heard of in any ordinary circles.</p> 
               <p>In this book you may find out all the curious dodges of the flash, the fancy, and the light-fingered gentlemen who parade Broadway and the Bowery and of society in high life, low life, and life around town. It is complete in two large volumes of about 200 pages each, and the price is 50 cents per volume, or One Dollar for the complete work. We send it free of postage.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="advertisement"> 
               <head>THREE YEARS AFTER.</head> 
               <p>A Sequel to the Mysteries and Miseries of New York; and a continuation of the same sort of curious and entertaining reading-wherein Ned enters into the spirit of the thing, and tries to make his readers satisfied that he really can tell a good and exciting story if he sets about it. This is a book of 175 pages, and we send it free of postage for 50 cents.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="advertisement"> 
               <head>THE B'HOYS OF NEW YORK.</head> 
               <p>Being a final conclusion of the "Mysteries and Miseries," and of "Three Years After."</p> 
               <p>This is a book of 194 pages: and, as the first plot deepens and ends, it becomes very spicy and interesting. We believe this is really the end of the main story Either this book or the other two are complete by themselves; so you can buy one or all, as you please, and be satisfied. This series is the best of Ned's efforts. They will please every reader. Price 50 cents, and we send the book free of postage.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="advertisement"> 
               <head>NED BUNTLINE'S LIFE YARN.</head> 
               <head type="sub">A thrilling Story of the Sea.</head> 
               <p>This is a book of 102 pages, and is about the best book Ned ever wrote. Price 50 cents, and the book sent free of postage.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="advertisement"> 
               <head>THE CONVICT; OR, THE CONSPIRATOR'S VICTIM.</head> 
               <p>A story founded on facts, and written in prison. This is probably Ned Buntline's <choice>
                     <sic>verson</sic>
                     <corr>version</corr>
                  </choice> of an incident in his own life. It is a book of near 300 pages. Price 50 cents, and the book sent free of postage.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="advertisement"> 
               <head>THE WHITE CRUISER; OR, THE FATE OF THE UNHEARD-OF.</head> 
               <head type="sub">Price 25 cents.</head> 
               <p>The author's early career was spent upon the ocean; and as a naval officer he has had opportunities of gaining a nautical knowledge which peculiarly fits him to excel as a writer of Sea Novels. His naval career was distinguished by active service in the Gulf, and among the kegs and bags of Florida during the Seminole War; and in this, his last, beat work, we find proofs that he has not forgotten his early education.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="advertisement"> 
               <head>THE WHEEL OF MISFORTUNE;</head> 
               <head type="sub">OR, THE VICTIMS OF LOTTERY AND POLICY DEALERS.</head> 
               <head type="sub">A Yarn from the web of New York Life. Price 25 cents.</head> 
               <p>This deeply interesting work speaks in plain language of the Lottery and Policy Dealers. It also exposes the many gambling houses that infest this metropolis, showing the various cheats and tricks that are daily practiced on the inexperienced dupes who frequent these "hells." The characters are all drawn from real life, and will be readily recognized by all those familiar with New York scenes.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="advertisement"> 
               <head>THE MYSTERIES AND MISERIES OF NEW ORLEANS.</head> 
               <p>Price 25 cents.</p> 
            </div> 
            <div type="advertisement"> 
               <head>NORWOOD; OR, LIFE ON THE PRAIRIE.</head> 
               <head type="sub">A thrilling Tale of Western Adventure. Price 25 cents.</head> 
               <p>This is one of those wild romances of the rambles and adventures of an adventurer in the West-one of those uneasy personages who braves death and danger from a love of novelty alone, and to see how near a man can go to the edge of eternity without falling off.</p> 
               <p>Copies of the above books sent free of postage.</p> 
            </div> 
         </div> 
      </back> 
   </text>
</TEI>