<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6934">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Harry Tempest, or, The Pirate's Protege </title>
            <author >Hazel, Harry, (1814-1889)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC6934</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >Harry Tempest, or, The pirate's protege</title>
                  <author >Hazel, Harry, (1814-1889)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >vi 103 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >H. Long</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1853">[1853]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
            <language  ident="spa">Spanish</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="AEL Data" when="2003-04-01">Finished transcription and SGML encoding</change>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2003-08-05">Finished TEI conversion</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text > 
      <front> 
         <titlePage xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
            <pb  n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6934-00000001"/> 
            <docTitle> 
               <titlePart>HARRY TEMPEST;</titlePart> 
               <titlePart type="sub">OR, THE PIRATE'S PROTEGE.</titlePart> 
               <titlePart type="sub">AN AMERICAN NAUTICAL ROMANCE.</titlePart> 
            </docTitle> 
            <byline >BY <docAuthor xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">HARRY HAZEL,</docAuthor> AUTHOR OF "THE KING'S CRUISERS; OR, THE REBEL AND THE ROVER," "FLORINE; OR, THE BUTINEERS," "MIDDY OF THE MACEDONIAN," "MAD JACK," "THREE PIRATES," "YANKEE JACK," &amp;C.</byline> 
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>NEW YORK:</pubPlace> 
               <publisher >H. LONG &amp; BROTHER, <address> 
                     <addrLine xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">121 NASAU-STREET.</addrLine> 
                  </address>
               </publisher>
            </docImprint> 
            <pb  n="iii" xml:id="VAC6934-00000002"/> 
            <docEdition>ENTERED, according to Act of Congress, in the Year One Thousand Eight Hund and Fifty-three, by H. LONG &amp; BROTHER, in the Office of the Clerk of District Court of the United States, for the Southern District of New York.</docEdition> 
         </titlePage> 
         <div type="preface"> 
             
            <head>PREFACE.</head> 
            <p>THE story of "HARRY TEMPEST" is not a production of the imagination alone; indeed, its most remarkable incidents actually occurred; and were we disposed, we might mention the real names of the Buccaneer Chief, his Lieutenant, and our interesting and brave young hero, Edward Duvalle. But we prefer to leave it to our readers to exercise their memory in regard to the leading events narrated, and the real characters will naturally present themselves, especially to the minds of those who were upon the stage of life twenty years ago.</p> 
            <closer>
               <signed>HARRY HAZEL.</signed>
            </closer> 
         </div> 
         <div type="contents"> 
            <pb n="iv-v (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC6934-00000003"/> 
             
            <head>CONTENTS.</head> 
            <list> 
               <item>CHAPTER I. A calm on the Atlantic-The "Sparta" and her crew-The strange Passenger-His Interview with Fanny Floyd-Daring Feat of Edward Duvalle-His Mysterious Conduct-A quiet Love Scene. <ref>7</ref>
               </item> 
               <item>CHAPTER II. A sail descried-Her suspicious Appearance-Captain Wingate and the mate of the Sparta-Alarm of the Latter-Interview with Edward Duvalle-His corroboration of the Captain's opinion in regard to the chase-The boxes of Muskets-The strange Sail a Pirate! <ref>15</ref>
               </item> 
               <item>CHAPTER III. The clipper Vision alias Spitfire-A Frigate is descried-Captain Ringbold and his Lieutenant, De Soto-Elegant Costume of the Latter-The Mutinous Pirate! <ref>25</ref>
               </item> 
               <item>CHAPTER IV. Sanguinary Punishment-Ringbold's plan to capture the Merchantman and escape the Frigate. <ref>28</ref>
               </item> 
               <item>CHAPTER V. The conduct of the Pirate accounted for-Preparations for Defence-The boats of the Schooner heave in sight-Are hailed by the Captain, and a musket ball returned-The first gun from the Sparta, and its terrible Execution-Dismay of the Pirates-A portion of them gain the deck of the Sparta-A desperate Conflict-Conduct of Duvalle-Single combat, in which De Soto is defeated by Edward Duvalle. <ref>33</ref>
               </item> 
               <pb n="vi (Table of Contents) -7" xml:id="VAC6934-00000004"/> 
               <item>CHAPTER VI. Hailing the Schooner-Glee of the Pirates at their golden prospects-Success of the Ruse-Consternation and destruction of the Second Detachment of Pirates-Duvalle and fifteen men prepare to embark in the boats for the purpose of attacking the Spitfire. <ref>43</ref>
               </item> 
               <item>CHAPTER VII. Embarkation of the Sparta's crew under Duvalle-They board the Spitfire-Confusion of the Pirates-A desperate Encounter between our hero and the Buccaneer Chief-The latter is defeated and made a prisoner-A part of the Mystery is Unravelled-The Prize arrives alongside of the Ship-Joy of the Victors. <ref>52</ref>
               </item> 
               <item>CHAPTER VIII. Interesting conversation-Departure of the Prize-She is chased by an English Frigate-Escape and arrival at Havana-The Prize is boarded by a Revenue Officer-Queries promptly answered. <ref>63</ref>
               </item> 
               <item>CHAPTER IX. The Governor and his family-Duvalle visits the Palace, and relates his recent Adventures-The letters-Generosity of His Excellency-Florencia is introduced to Duvalle-Arrival of the British Naval officer-He demands the Vision as his Prize-Refusal of the Governor, His Anger-Interference of Duvalle-The British Officer makes his exit with a flea in his ear-Conclusion. <ref>70</ref>
               </item> 
               <item>TRE ROSE OF MATANZAS, IN TWO CHAPTERS. <ref>85</ref>
               </item> 
            </list> 
         </div> 
      </front> 
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Harry Tempest, or, The pirate's protege</head> 
            <div type="part"> 
                
               <head>HARRY TEMPEST:</head> 
               <head type="sub">OR, THE PIRATE'S PROTEGE.</head> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER I.</head> 
                  <argument> 
                     <p>A calm on the Atlantic-The "Sparta" and her crew-The strange Passenger-His Interview with Fanny Floyd-Daring Feat of Edward Duvalle-His mysterious Conduct-A quiet Love Scene.</p> 
                  </argument> 
                  <p>IT was a calm and beautiful night in the year 182-; there was no moon, but the stars shone out from the blue vault above with that brightness which can only be seen in the tropics, almost supplying the deficiency of light caused by the absence of the queen of night. Not a breath of air rippled the mighty waters of the Atlantic, which seemed like a vast mirror of burnished steel, reflecting with peculiar clearness the diamond-studded canopy above.</p> 
                  <p>Upon the glassy sea a noble ship was becalmed, and she lay as motionless and majestic as a palace founded on a rock. Her canvas was all set, but it hung loosely from her yards, and the helmsman paced to and fro the quarter deck, deeming that, under such a pacific state of things, a constant attention at the wheel was quite unnecessary. Still he did not entirely desert his post, but remained near it and occasionally looked over the taffrail and watched the sportiveness of myriads of porpoises and dolphins about the sides and stern of the vessel.</p> 
                  <pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6934-00000005"/> 
                  <p>The ship was the "Sparta," of and from Baltimore, and bound to the Rio de Plate; and though she had been twenty-five days at sea, her passage was not yet half completed, owing to a protracted calm; it having already lasted ten days, and during the whole time the ship had not made three degrees of latitude; and she would have made less, had not the boats been out towing the ship slowly along for three or four days of the calm.</p> 
                  <p>A group of merry hearted seaman were idling away the evening watch, upon the forward deck, spinning yarns, singing songs, and indulging in other diversions peculiar alone to those who follow the trackless ocean.</p> 
                  <p>"Come, my hearties, can't you whistle us up a breeze?" said Bill Rattlin, an active looking tar, to a group of sailors, as he came forth from the forecastle.</p> 
                  <p>"For my part," replied one of the number, "I'm blow'd if I've got breath enough in my body to blow out the binnacle light."</p> 
                  <p>"Captain Wingate 'll have the boats out again to-morrow, sure." resumed the first speaker; "if we don't prevail on Boreas to stir up old Neptune, and get the Sparta out o' this dead calm."</p> 
                  <p>"Captain Wingate be d--d!" replied an athletic seaman, in a gruff voice, as he ejected a huge quid of tobacco from his mouth with sufficient force to lodge it between the bright twinklers of the black cook, who was seated upon a coil of rigging, quietly listening to the conversation.</p> 
                  <p>"What's dat? Who frow'd dat ar?" demanded black Pete, with frowning indignation, as the nauseous masticated weed came in contact with his flat organ of smelling.</p> 
                  <p>Pete's inquiry was not taken the slightest notice of, and the sailors continued their conversation supposing that from his apparently mild, and forgiving disposition he would not resent it, as he had often been made to subject himself to indignities of a like nature, which he could not or dare not avenge. But Pete's character was not so well understood by his shipmates as it was by himself; and he was well assured who it was that committed the ungentlemanly outrage upon his person; but he assumed ignorance, as he did not deem that that was an opportune time to repay the insult. A time would come he inwardly resolved, when he should return it fourfold, particularly upon "Big Tom," as the burly sailor was denominated by the ship's crew. With a sullen and dogged air the negro left his unpleasant associates and entered his caboose, where we shall leave him brooding over his afflictions.</p> 
                  <p>It was not yet ten o'clock, and while a portion of the ship's crew still remained in the vicinity of the windlass, two persons came forth to enjoy the beauties of the night, who require from us more than a passing notice, as they are destined to act something more prominent than supernumerary character in our romantic narrative, and perhaps deserve the appellation of hero and heroine. The latter was leaning somewhat timidly upon the arm of the former, as they came upon the deck, and they seemed to be well satisfied with each other's society, as may be supposed from the fact that one was a gentleman of about twenty-two years of age, of prepossessing appearance, with an expressive and intelligently marked countenance, while the other was a charming young lady just verging into womanhood, graceful as a Sylph, and lovely as the goddess of Beauty. Fanny Floyd-for by this name our heroine is to be known-was the daughter of a rich planter residing near St. Inigoes, in the State of Maryland, who with her father had embarked on board the good ship Sparta, as passengers for Rio Janeiro, where they intended to spend some months with connections of Mr. Floyd, he having married a Spanish lady in that city, some twenty years previous, and the only issue of their union was the fair Fanny-her mother having died while she was yet in her infancy.</p> 
                  <p>Mr. Floyd, at the time we are writing, was an invalid, and his great inducement in visiting a more salubrious climate, was that he might escape the unhealthful effects which another nothern winter might have upon his constitution. It was at the suggestion and the solicitation of Miss Fanny that she was permitted to accompany him, and the invalid father had already<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6934-00000006"/> felt the comforts of her ministering hand, during the time they had been at sea. They had brought with them two faithful slaves, one a female and the other a male, which had been reared upon Mr. Floyd's plantation, in Maryland, and who devoted themselves assiduously to the wants of their master and young mistress.</p> 
                  <p>The young man, whom we find on terms of intimacy with Miss Floyd, was an agreeable and intelligent gentleman, and had booked his name among the list of passengers of the Sparta, as Edward Duvalle. Father than this, concerning him, was unknown to any of the ship's company, except that his pleasing and winning manners had gained him the esteem of all on board; and farther than this will not be divulged to our readers, at this time, trusting that they will have sufficient patience to follow us through the incidents of our tale, in the course of which his character will be clearly developed. It may appear singular to some, under these circumstances, that he should be found so intimate with Miss Floyd, all of which too, was well known to her father. The cause of this may be explained in a short narrative which had but recently occurred.</p> 
                  <p>At the time of the Sparta's departure from the wharf, Mr. Floyd's family, unfortunately, was not on board, but before the ship had got beyond hailing distance, a carriage drove down to the wharf, a signal was raised, and the vessel backed her topsails, and hove to, for the purpose of taking on board her tardy passengers. The wind at the time was blowing almost a gale from the north-west, and some difficulty occurred in procuring a suitable boat to put off with the newly arrived passengers, and a large quantity of baggage. One of inferior size was at length obtained, and so great was the turbulence of the waters when the boat reached the ship's side, that it was with the greatest difficulty that they were enabled to assist Mr. Floyd (being, as we before stated an invalid) on board the ship. Fanny, in attempting too hastily to follow her father, lost her footing, and was precipitated into the waves. A piercing shriek was heard above the raging elements, and the word was quickly passed along the deck of the ship that a female was overboard, and amid the confusion the weak voice of Mr. Floyd was heard in lamentable and heart-rending tone, saying,</p> 
                  <p>"Save, oh save my beloved daughter!"</p> 
                  <p>The old man in spite of the resistance of several of those standing by to prevent his rushing to certain destruction, would have thrown himself over the ship's side in the vain attempt to save her, had not a young man who was standing near, anticipated his intentions in rushing past him and leaping into the water to rescue the drowning girl. In one short moment, he would have been too late-he however, seized her by her flowing hair, and held her above the surface with one hand while with the other he was enabled to keep himself up until a rope was thrown him, which he contrived to fasten to his body, and was thus drawn toward the ship, and finally to the gangway, which he ascended with the exhausted Miss Floyd in his arms.</p> 
                  <p>This remarkable and daring feat of humanity was the chief topic of conversation on board of the ship, and when Miss Floyd had entirely recovered, she begged to see her noble preserver, and to acknowledge to him in person, her grateful thanks. Edward Duvalle was accordingly conducted to the cabin, where the lady and her father improved the opportunity of making their acknowledgements. As he was about to retire, Mr. Floyd begged him to tarry one moment, and to excuse him for a temporary absence. He presently returned and offered him as a token of his regard a magnificently jeweled watch, which Duvalle positively refused, averring that he had been amply repaid for the attention which they had shown to one who must continue a stranger to them.</p> 
                  <p>"At least," said Fanny, taking from her finger a ring with a large vignette attached to it, "you will accept this little token for my sake."</p> 
                  <p>The manner in which this was said and done, was irresistible to the susceptible feelings of Duvalle. He graciously took the ring, placed it upon his finger, and said,</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, for your sake I cannot refuse."</p> 
                  <pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6934-00000007"/> 
                  <p>After this incident, Edward and Fanny first met occasionally upon the deck of the noble ship. As each day passed away they seemed more in each other's company, until at length it was rare that one could be seen minus the company of the other.</p> 
                  <p>In this relation matters stood upon the evening mentioned at the beginning of this chapter, and it is therefore not strange at all, that they should cherish towards each other sentiments of the highest esteem, if not of affection. Some insight in regard to opinions held by each may be gathered from the annexed singular conversation which took place as soon as they had seated themselves in a somewhat retired position upon the quarter deck of the vessel.</p> 
                  <p>"Tell me, Edward," said she, "why it is that you seem so melancholy since we have become acquainted? During our fitst interview you were as happy as I could ever hope to see you."</p> 
                  <p>"Do I seem unhappy now, Fanny?" asked he in tones of sober earnestness, and while there was no animation or joy visible in his countenance.</p> 
                  <p>"Indeed you do; and the serious tones of your voice, so pleasant but a few days ago, now almost chills me."</p> 
                  <p>"I confess, Fanny, as it is useless for me to dissemble, that there is good and abundant cause for grief."</p> 
                  <p>"You surprise me," said Miss Floyd, as she looked up into his face with a startled but timid expression. "What possible event could have occurred within the narrow limits of this ship that should give you one minute's pain?"</p> 
                  <p>"Nothing-yes-much!" he stammered in reply.</p> 
                  <p>There was a pause for several moments, and the young man seemed deeply affected when he saw that Fanny's eyes were wet with tears.</p> 
                  <p>"Let me be plain but brief, Miss Floyd."</p> 
                  <p>"Nay, nay, not brief. Let me know all, but pardon my inquisitiveness," said she; "and do not, I beseech you, Edward, address me in terms of coldness."</p> 
                  <p>"God forbid that I should ever have cause so to do; but in reality I do you a serious wrong when I address you with language better befitting a lover than a stranger."</p> 
                  <p>"Why will you persist in calling yourself a stranger. Have not the many hours which we have been permitted to be together, been sufficient at least to rank me as one of your acquaintances? And did not you save my life at the imminent risk of your own?"</p> 
                  <p>"Say no more of that Fanny," replied Duvalle. "I grant dear girl, that in the common acceptation of the term, we are intimate acquaintances and friends; but that implies not that you know him who appears before you as Edward Duvalle."</p> 
                  <p>"Not know you? How, Edward? What can you mean?" questioned Fanny, with mysterious apprehension.</p> 
                  <p>"I mean that he whom you know as Edward Duvalle-who has passed many happy hours in your sweet society-who will confess boldly and freely that he loves Fanny Floyd with all the warmth of his affections-is yet and must ever be a stranger to you."</p> 
                  <p>"Oh, heavens!" exclaimed Fanny; "I cannot understand; and yet I fear--"</p> 
                  <p>"Yes; and you have good grounds for fearing that Edward Duvalle is not the character which has been assigned him by this ship's company. Lady, would to God I could unfold to you my true standing in the world, but that at the present time is impossible. Should I ever be so fortunate as to make good one resolution I have formed, then, and not till then, will I appear before you and the world in my true person."</p> 
                  <p>Fanny burst into tears. "I can trust you. I can have nothing to fear from one like you," said she sobbingly.</p> 
                  <p>"I would not, my sweet girl, give you one moment's pain; nor would I be guilty of using the slightest deception in gaining your esteem. I can only regret that I did not sooner put you upon your guard, but since I first saw you I have been indulging in your sweet smiles until I have become intoxicated with an ardent passion. Indeed, I am bound by a spell of fascination. But I have yet power to break it, though my heart be sundered in the effort. Ere many days we shall<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6934-00000008"/> part-in all probability, never to meet again, but I shall never forget the happy moments I have passed in this ship-and I shall likewise cherish in my memory the bright being who has caused me so much felicity."</p> 
                  <p>"Nay, nay, Edward, talk not thus. Surely in you there can be no guile."</p> 
                  <p>"I know, sweet Fanny, your confiding and generous disposition. I know your purity and inestimable worth; and would to God that I was worthy of the sentiments you have revealed to me; and that I might here bend the knee and offer you my heart and hand, and feel that I was not imposing upon the good and virtuous. But this precious boon is denied me; and were the mysterious veil, by which my true character is concealed, be raised, you would regard me with indignation, if not horror; therefore, gentle creature, this had best be our last interview, and although there is a possibility of my remaining on board of this ship some days longer, our pleasant intimacy had better be discontinued. If I am right in my information and conjectures, an event will ere long take place which will not only separate us for ever, but reveal to you facts startling indeed, and which may serve to unfold to you the reason why I cannot, with any degree of propriety seek to cultivate an intimacy so happily begun, but which, alas, if persevered in, must lead to unpleasant if not to disastrons results."</p> 
                  <p>Duvalle uttered these words with all the complacency that he could command, but it was evident from his quivering lip, his forced utterance and energetic manner, that he was deeply moved. Fanny trembled like an aspen leaf, and tears gushed copiously from her eyes. She looked up into his face but her heart was too full to speak.</p> 
                  <p>"Go, Fanny, to your father," resumed Duvalle; "tell him that I am unworthy of your regard."</p> 
                  <p>"No-no-Edward, this must not be," replied she sobbingly. "One so noble and frank and generous as yourself, cannot be other than he seems."</p> 
                  <p>"And yet to be more plain, I am allied to that which is ignoble, base and criminal; and, oh, that the time might come when I could forever be disenthralled from a dreadful alliance which weighs my very soul to the earth. Perhaps that time may come, but the path before me looks dark and gloomy, and in that path lurks danger, terrific and bloody."</p> 
                  <p>Duvalle could say no more; but taking the hand of the beautiful Fanny, he led her to the entrance of the ladies' cabin, and bidding her "good night," retired to his own stateroom.</p> 
                  <p>At this time the group of sailors forward, had mostly dispersed, and none were left upon the Sparta's deck except those who kept the first night-watch.</p> 
                  <p>Duvalle again for a few moments appeared on the quarter deck of the ship, bearing a night-glass in his hand, and after surveying the sleeping sea in every direction, and discovering nothing, he returned to his quarters, where we shall leave him for a few hours, not in a state of repose, but brooding over a dreadful event, which he believed was near at hand.</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER II.</head> 
                  <argument> 
                     <p>A sail descried-Her suspicious Appearance-Captain Wingate and the mate of the Sparta-Alarm of the Latter-Interview with Edward Duvalle-His corroboration of the Captain's opinion in regard to the chase-The boxes of Muskets-The strange Sail a Pirate!</p> 
                  </argument> 
                  <p>THE night wore away and the calm continued, and there was as little prospect of a breeze as there had been on the preceding morning. The mate came upon deck and issued orders to man the boats as soon as the crew had partaken of their meal. This caused, as might be presumed, from the remark of Big Tom on the night previous, no little dissatisfaction among the sailors; and it is not certain that almost a mutiny would have been raised had not the cry of-</p> 
                  <p>"Sail ho!" from the look-out on the fore-topsail yard, at<pb n="16-17 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6934-00000009"/> that moment interrupted the progress of dissension and disobedience which evidently increased among the foremast men.</p> 
                  <p>"Where-away?" sung out the mate.</p> 
                  <p>"On our lea-quarter, sir," answered the man from aloft.</p> 
                  <p>"What do you make her out to be?"</p> 
                  <p>"A large clipper-built schooner."</p> 
                  <p>"What is her course?"</p> 
                  <p>"She is now almost directly in our wake following us, she has two boats out fully manned."</p> 
                  <p>The strange sail at the time she was descried, was about six miles distant, and in less than half an hour she had approached near enough to prove to the captain and crew of the Sparta, that it would be good policy to avoid so suspicious a looking craft. The boats were accordingly manned and at snail-like pace the heavy merchantman was dragged along at the rate of one knot per hour, while it was apparent that the schooner gained upon her sufficiently fast to be broadside to her before the sun could pass the meridian.</p> 
                  <p>"Mr. Cooper," said Captain Wingate, addressing the mate, apart from any of the passengers or crew, "I wish to create no unnecessary alarm, but I am fully confirmed in the belief that you schooner making towards us is a pirate."</p> 
                  <p>"It cannot be possible. A pirate has not been seen in these latitudes for many years."</p> 
                  <p>"True; but I will give you the reasons for my belief," continued the Captain. "I have been watching her steadily for the last hour through my glass, and if my eye does not greatly deceive me, that is the clipper built craft called "The Vision," which three months ago attracted so much attention in the harbor of Baltimore, and which was reported to be bound on a private expedition to Europe."</p> 
                  <p>"I recollect her well," answered the mate; "but you must bear in mind that the clipper "Vision" was painted green, with a bright scarlet streak from stem to stern, while this craft is black and has a double white streak instead of a scarlet one."</p> 
                  <p>"You are correct; but it is an easy matter to alter the complexion 
                     <figure> 
                        <head>DE SOTO, THE CORSAIR LIEUTENANT.</head> 
                     </figure>
                     <pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6934-00000010"/>
                      plexion of the hull of the vessel. Do you perceive the singular shape of her top-gallant sail?" asked Mr. Wingate.</p> 
                  <p>"It is peculiar, indeed."</p> 
                  <p>"Well, sir, when I was having the Sparta's canvass overhauled and refitted in Baltimore, I saw that very sail upon the floor of the sailmaker's loft. I recollect distinctly making some remarks upon the singular manner in which it was cut, to the man who was at work upon it. He told me that it was intended for the clipper Vision and it was cut in accordance with her Captain's orders. Now, I never saw since I followed the sea, which is about thirty years, but one sail which corresponded with that; and if that does not prove to be the same one, I will never risk my judgment upon such a matter again. This, together with the fact of her being in the latitudes, repainted, and also from the number in the boats, and upon deck, being four times the complement she sailed with, convinces me that she is a pirate!"</p> 
                  <p>"She certainly looks suspicious," replied the mate showing symptoms of alarm; "but what's to be done?"</p> 
                  <p>"Nothing, without my orders," said the Captain, sternly; "and on your life create no unnecessary alarm among the passengers or crew. We have two guns that can be brought to bear upon the schooner, and if our hands are not all cowards, we can make at least a show of resistance. When I give the signal, clear away the guns and bring our small stock of ammunition upon deck."</p> 
                  <p>"It will only exasperate the pirates if they are really such, if we make the feeble resistance that you propose," said the mate, almost trembling with fear. "We fare better to let them have their own way."</p> 
                  <p>"Go to your duty, and remember my positive orders;" said the captain, in tones of authority.</p> 
                  <p>The mate left the captain and went forward to incite the men in the boats to extra exertion.</p> 
                  <p>Captain Wingate, with the aid of his glass, continued to watch the suspicious craft, as she slowly gained upon the ship.</p> 
                  <p>"It is a pirate! I am positive!" exclaimed he, in tones sufficiently<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6934-00000011"/> ficiently loud to be heard by Edward Duvalle, who was pacing the deck near him.</p> 
                  <p>"That is my opinion," said the youth, stepping to the captain and saluting him.</p> 
                  <p>"And upon what grounds do you hazard such an opinion?" inquired the Captain.</p> 
                  <p>"Every thing indicates it, sir."</p> 
                  <p>"I hope that opinion is not now prevalent on board of the ship."</p> 
                  <p>"I have heard no one but yourself give utterance to that belief, sir."</p> 
                  <p>"I am glad to hear it, and I would not have a single person yet entertain the belief that it is possible we may soon be attacked by pirates."</p> 
                  <p>"I hope that you intend to make resistance," remarked Duvalle, with apparent concern at the Captain's tardy movements.</p> 
                  <p>"Yes."</p> 
                  <p>"But, sir, they will be upon us before we are prepared to receive them," said the young man, impatiently.</p> 
                  <p>"We have but two guns, which can be got in working order in five minutes, and if my crew and other able-bodied men on board do their duty, we can at least sell our lives dearly!"</p> 
                  <p>"Excuse, me, sir, interfering at all in the affairs of your command, but a moment is approaching when more than the resources of this ship will be necessary to be brought into action to repel the fire which you will shortly have to contend with. Now, sir, you will recollect among the luggage which I sent on board of your ship there were two heavy boxes?"</p> 
                  <p>"Perfectly well."</p> 
                  <p>"They contain a dozen muskets each. Another box contains several hundred rounds of cartridges with balls. They are at your service. Distribute them among the crew, and I will arm the passengers."</p> 
                  <p>"You surprise me!" exclaimed Captain Wingate. "How fortunate! I will have them hoisted upon deck immediately. Halloo, there, forward! Open the main hatch, and rig the tackle."</p> 
                  <p>"Ay, ay, sir!" was the quick response, and the forward hands went about the duty with alacrity.</p> 
                  <p>The boxes of arms, fortunately, were among the last parcels of freight received, and being easily got at, were in a few moments hoisted upon the deck. As the boxes were opened and found to contain guns, the crew looked first at the weapons then at the strange sail, and the whole truth burst suddenly upon them. In one minute every person on board of the ship knew the character of the schooner, and every preparation was quickly made for action.</p> 
                  <p>Edward Duvalle busied himself in examining each musket, and distributing them together with cartridges, alike to passengers and sailors; while at the same time the two six pounders which the ship carried on her quarter-deck were brushed up, and loaded heavily with grape and canister.</p> 
                  <p>At this particular juncture, as if providence intended to favor them, a gentle breeze sprung up, and the sails which had so long been useless began to fill away. The boats which had been sent ahead to tow the ship, were ordered in and the Sparta again under an easy press of canvas, was moving through the water at the rate of five knots an hour. The captain's face brightened once more, for he thought it possible that, as the Sparta was a fast sailer, he might keep beyond the reach of the schooner's guns until night, and under its cover make his escape. Not so thought Edward Duvalle; he knew the superior qualities of the chase, and as he saw that her last sail was set, and that the wind now favored her, she would soon be alongside.</p> 
                  <p>"It is useless, Captain Wingate, to attempt to escape her," said Edward, energetically. "Let us prepare to meet her like men."</p> 
                  <p>"You seem to know more of this vessel than one could possibly learn by a few moment's look through a spy-glass."</p> 
                  <p>The youth turned to conceal his suddenly suffused cheeks, which this remark caused; but re-assuring himself, he thus replied,</p> 
                  <pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6934-00000012"/> 
                  <p>"I have seen her once before."</p> 
                  <p>"Where?" questioned the captain, eagerly, with suspicion lurking in his countenance.</p> 
                  <p>"In Baltimore;" replied Duvalle, promptly.</p> 
                  <p>"Ah! you know her commander?"</p> 
                  <p>"Question me not now, for the love of heaven, Captain Wingate. You will know all soon! I have sworn to assist you in repelling the furious villains! and I will keep the oath! They know that you have a large amount of specie on board, and will make a desperate attempt to obtain it!"</p> 
                  <p>The bold and ingenuous manner of the strange youth almost confounded the captain. Still he felt that he, could trust him, for he had been a witness of his noble prowess in saving the life of Fanny Floyd.</p> 
                  <p>"Your language fills me with amazement," said he, as he regarded him closely for several moments before speaking.</p> 
                  <p>Before Duvalle could reply, a shot was fired from the schooner, which, however, fell short of the ship; at the same time a black flag with a red dragon emblazoned upon it, was unfurled on board of the piratical craft, as she proved now to be.</p> 
                  <p>"Mr. Duvalle," said the captain, seizing the youth by the hand; "I feel that I can place implicit confidence in you. There is no time to be lost. To what station shall I appoint you?"</p> 
                  <p>"Give me a complement of fearless men, and charge of one of the guns upon the quarter-deck."</p> 
                  <p>"That will be the post of danger."</p> 
                  <p>"Then I have the greater reason for preferring it."</p> 
                  <p>"Do as you will; my first officer shall take charge of the other; while I will give orders to the crew and passengers who are armed with muskets."</p> 
                  <p>Everything was prepared for action without the least confusion. The musketeers were ordered below to wait until the pirates should attempt to board the ship. The female passengers, of whom there were several, were entreated to go below, and on no consideration to expose themselves during the impending conflict. With reluctance they left the deck for the lower cabin, which, comparatively was a place of safety from the shot of the enemy.</p> 
                  <p>"Captain Wingate," said Duvalle, in a low tone; "you have a dangerous man among your ship's crew."</p> 
                  <p>"Impossible!" exclaimed the commander, with increased surprise, as his eye sought out each man upon the deck. "There is but one on board who has not sailed with me before."</p> 
                  <p>"True; and he is now below."</p> 
                  <p>"You mean Big Tom."</p> 
                  <p>"The same."</p> 
                  <p>"To my knowledge he has shown no symptoms of insubordination!"</p> 
                  <p>"Still I repeat he is a dangerous man; and would, were it in his power, deliver your vessel into the hands of the bloody demons who sail under yon piratical flag."</p> 
                  <p>"You amaze me!"</p> 
                  <p>"Take my advice, and while he is sleeping below, order his arrest, put him in irons, and stow him away in the hold. Be cautious, too, how you approach him; he has loaded pistols concealed about his person, and will make desperate resistance."</p> 
                  <p>"Ah!" exclaimed the captain, "a light breaks in upon me. He is in some way connected with this craft, and you-"</p> 
                  <p>"Say nought of me!" interrupted Duvalle; "I am bound by a voluntary oath to serve you, and let this day's events corroborate my sincerity."</p> 
                  <p>"I will trust you, and be guided by your advice, whatever your motive may be; and will immediately order the confinement of Big Tom," said the captain, as he turned upon his heel to put his resolve into immediate execution.</p> 
                  <p>"Stay," said the youth; "I must not be known to him in this business. No good and much harm may result from it."</p> 
                  <p>"Your wish shall be regarded," said the captain, as he left Duvalle, went forward and called three of his trusty crew into his state-room. Here he made known to them the duty they had to perform, and instructed them on no condition to alarm<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6934-00000013"/> the crew or passengers upon the deck; and also gave them to understand that he would be near them in case an emergency should require any assistance from another. He then gave the chief man hand-cuffs and chains, which he first carefully wrapped in a handkerchief that they might be concealed from the crew, as they passed along the deck from the state-room to the forecastle.</p> 
                  <p>This precaution Captain Wingate deemed essential, as he was not a little suspicious that Big Tom might have caused a seditious influence among some of his crew.</p> 
                  <p>The men went forward and entered the forecastle, where Big Tom and his companions were quietly sleeping away their watch below. At the same time the captain had made his way through the piles of freight and luggage which were stowed between decks, and took his place beside a secret pannel, affording an entrance into the forecastle if desirable.</p> 
                  <p>The heavy report of a gun from the chase at this moment caused Big Tom to start from his berth, when he was immediately seized by three sailors. But his immense strength proved too great for them. With his athletic arms he threw them from him as if they had been children, and drawing two pistols from beneath his jacket, he stood in an attitude of defence, with one in each hand!</p> 
                  <p>"I'll send the first man to h-ll, who dares approach me!" exclaimed he in a tone of defiance, and with a stentorian voice.</p> 
                  <p>The sailors shrank from him with fear, for although they knew his immense strength, he had never appeared to them so formidable and terrible before. The noise had awakened the other sleepers, who leaped from their berths suddenly, but seemed undecided how to act; it had also reached the ears of Black Pete, who rushed down the forecastle steps, and perceiving Big Tom with his pistols levelled, he leaped with the quickness of a cat upon his back, and seized the barrel of the pistol in the sailor's left hand, which was discharged and the contents lodged in the ceiling above. The heavy stroke of the sabre from an unseen hand caused the other weapon to drop to the floor, while his right arm now hung powerlessly by his side. This last blow was struck by the captain, who, perceiving the desperate state of things slipped the pannel noiselessly aside, and thus decided the affray. The powerful sailor made no further resistance, but submitted to his captors' will. They heavily ironed him, and placed him in a secure place in the hold.</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER III.</head> 
                  <argument> 
                     <p>The clipper Vision alias Spitfire-A Frigate is descried-Captain Ringbold and his Lieutenant, De Soto-Elegant Costume of the Latter-The Mutinous Pirate.</p> 
                  </argument> 
                  <p>THE clipper Vision (for this in reality was the name of the chase) was the identical vessel that Captain Wingate had seen in the harbor of the monumental city but two or three weeks previous. She had, since leaving port, been entirely repainted, and a dark strip of canvas nailed upon her stern with the word "Spitfire," painted upon it, now successfully concealed her real name from view. As the captain of the "Sparta" had predicted, she was truly a pirate. He would hadly have suspected her when she first hove in sight, had not the tell-tale top-gallant sail, together with the sudden radical change in her appearance, struck him as not being altogether consistent with the common course of things.</p> 
                  <p>The Spitfire, as we shall now term the corsair, was one of the finest models of naval architecture of her class then upon the ocean. Her hull fore and aft was of the most graceful symmetry; and her long tapering masts and spars were finely proportioned to the hull. She was about one hundred and seventy tons burthen, and had sailed from Baltimore with fifteen men, but her force had since been augmented to sixty, and they were as fierce a looking set of fellows as ever trod the deck of a corsair. She carried eight brass guns, four on each side, each of six pounds calibre; four small pieces aft, and two long eighteens forward. She had been in pursuit of<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6934-00000014"/> the Sparta for several days, and on the morning when the merchantman was descried from her lookout, her boats were ordered out and every exertion used to overhaul their intended prize. Their exertions were continued until about ten A.M., when a large vessel hove in sight directly astern, which the captain of the pirate, after gazing at her carefully through a superior telescope, made her out to be a large double-banked frigate, but she was too far distant to enable him to discern to what nation she belonged; and so far distant from the Sparta that she had not as yet been descried by that vessel. The pirate captain immediately resolved to retard the speed of his vessel which was now under full sail, until nightfall, when he should be enabled to board the merchantman without being observed by the frigate; and at the same time to keep a respectable and safe distance from the latter craft. This expedient worked successfully, and the three vessels in a line, were now moving through the water at about an equal speed. Consequently on board of the pirate there was but little to do, except to keep a good look out for the frigate, and to vary the speed of the craft as circumstances required.</p> 
                  <p>On the quarter deck of the Spitfire stood the pirate captain, whose name was Ringbold, conversing with his first lieutenant, a swarthy visaged Spaniard, whom the captain addressed as De Soto. The former was a muscular looking man of about forty-five years of age, with huge whiskers and shaggy eyebrows; the latter over-arching a pair of twinkling eyes. His complexion was florid, and were it not for a rigid and severe expression which rested upon his countenance, he would have been called by many, a noble looking man. His manners and accent were evidently English; and his bearing was commanding and dignified. His dress was wholly unlike that of a Pirate, but nearly resembled the undress uniform of officers of rank in the British navy. His only weapons were a jewelled hilted rapier which hung by his side, and a small pair of pistols were placed in his belt directly beneath his right arm; while his men carried heavy cutlasses, pistols and knives.</p> 
                  <p>De Soto, the Spaniard, was richly and elegantly attired; he he sported a crimson cap, of the style worn in the days of Louis XIV., with plumes fastened in a socket of precious stones; a light, gold embroidered tunic, and a waistcoat with various devices elaborately wrought with gold, silver and other threads. Upon his shirt bosom sparkled a brilliant star, formed of diamonds of immense value. A richly embroidered scarf around his right shoulder, and its gold bullion ends hung gracefully upon his left side. He also wore a diamond-hilted sword, and gold buckles set with emeralds and rubies. His jet black and glossy hair curled in profusion about the neck, which was laid almost bare. His complexion was dark but clear, and when he smiled, displayed a set of teeth of which he might well have been proud, so perfectly and regular and white did they appear. He was pleasing and gentlemanly in his manners, and affable in his conversation; and he seemed better fitted to grace the drawing rooms of a king's court, than the deek of a bloody corsair. But De Soto was a perfect demon in the hour of battle, but apparently calm and pleasing as a child when the strife was over and the victory won. He was ambitious in the extreme, and more than one unsuccessful attempt had been made to forever silence Captain Ringbold, that he might become monarch of the fleet then under the orders of his captain, and which were ploughing more than one ocean in search of plunder. But fortunately for him his attempts to supplant his superior had never been discovered, otherwise he long since would have been dangling at the fore-yard arm.</p> 
                  <p>"Haul down the black flag!" shouted the captain, the moment the frigate was discovered.</p> 
                  <p>"Ay, ay, sir;" answered one of the men, who promptly executed the order.</p> 
                  <p>"Captain Ringbold," said the lieutenant, as he came aft, after ordering the gunners to cease firing, "we are in an awkward predicament; if we run away from the frigate we shall lose the prize that we have been so long in search of."</p> 
                  <p>"The frigate be d-d!" replied the captain.</p> 
                  <p>"She is a match for two or three just like us."</p> 
                  <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6934-00000015"/> 
                  <p>"Were she a match for the d-l himself I would not make an effort to escape until we had transferred the golden treasures of the Sparta to the Spitfire."</p> 
                  <p>"Then we had better crowd on all canvas and board the ship as speedily as possible," said De Soto.</p> 
                  <p>"When I give orders to that effect see that they be promptly executed, but I require no dictation or advice," replied Ringbold, with severity.</p> 
                  <p>"But I merely intended to suggest--"</p> 
                  <p>"Your suggestions, Mr. De Soto, are entirely superfluous. I have my course marked out and shall follow it, though a dozen frigates were after me. The Spitfire is sailing just fast enough."</p> 
                  <p>The lieutenant finding the captain in ill-humor, thought it wise not to oppose him, though he thought he must be insane to allow the craft to sail at no greater speed than the heavy merchantman, after which they had so long been in chase.</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER IV.</head> 
                  <argument> 
                     <p>Sanguinary Punishment-Ringbold's plan to capture the Merchantman and escape the Frigate.</p> 
                  </argument> 
                  <p>THE wind was increasing each moment, and the Spitfire, evidently began gaining slowly upon the Sparta.</p> 
                  <p>"Forward, there!" shouted the captain. "Down with the foresail!"</p> 
                  <p>"Ay, ay, sir!" shouted one of the men, and the order was executed with promptness.</p> 
                  <p>This order not only surprised the lieutenant, but the men forward could not penetrate the design of their chief in taking the very means to place their lives in jeopardy. Though they felt dissatisfied with the commander's course, they dared not utter a word of complaint so that it might reach his ears. But when the lieutenant found occasion to go forward he was questioned by the men on deck in regard to Ringbold's singular conduct.</p> 
                  <p>"We shall be blown to h-ll!" exclaimed a ferocious looking sailor, addressing the lieutenant. "If we allow that black looking frigate to bring its double-tiered battery to bear upon us, we may reconcile ourselves either to become food for sharks, or dangle in the air with a bit of rigging about our necks."</p> 
                  <p>"That's just what I think," responded another sailor; "and the sooner we can show the frigate a clean pair of heels the better."</p> 
                  <p>"Captain Ringbold thinks otherwise," remarked De Soto. "I must confess that I do not like so close an approximation to so formidable an enemy."</p> 
                  <p>"And why do you not tell him so?" asked one of the men.</p> 
                  <p>"I have done so; and he not only scorned my words but insulted me," replied the lieutenant.</p> 
                  <p>"Then I'll take the responsibility of hoisting this rag up again!" said the sailor who first spoke, when he saw the captain had gone below.</p> 
                  <p>It required more than the efforts of one to hoist the heavy sail, and there was not another on deck who dared to assist in this mutinous act. The sailor having great strength had succeeded in raising it two thirds up, when Captain Ringbold suddenly appearing on deck, demanded if any of the officers had given orders to the man to hoist the foresail. On receiving a negative answer, he drew forth from his belt a pistol-a report followed, and the foolish mutineer lay weltering in his blood upon the deck!</p> 
                  <p>"Throw him overboard!" ordered Ringbold. "Such shall be the fate of all who disobey my orders."</p> 
                  <p>The command was promptly obeyed, and order was again restored, though more than one pirate swore inaudibly, revenge upon their sanguinary commander.</p> 
                  <p>The lieutenant again rejoined Ringbold upon the quarter deck. The latter was now in better humor, since he had an opportunity of venting his spleen upon the disobedient sailor,<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6934-00000016"/> and treated his first officer with less sullenness than he had done a few moments before.</p> 
                  <p>"Take a cigar, Mr. De Soto," said Ringbold, as a negro boy came forth from the cabin and placed a box of fine Havanas before him.</p> 
                  <p>"With pleasure," replied the lieutenant, as he helped himself, and took a seat near the captain.</p> 
                  <p>"We shall have a dull day after all," remarked the captain; "but the evening will prove a busy one."</p> 
                  <p>"It will indeed, if the frigate in pursuit, overtakes us," replied De Soto.</p> 
                  <p>"There is but little danger of that so long as we can carry a rag of canvas. We can run her hull down in half an hour."</p> 
                  <p>"Then what possible danger is to be apprehended from overhauling the merchantman, securing our booty, and then showing the frigate a clean pair of heels?"</p> 
                  <p>"The danger is this, Mr. De Soto; I am not sure that the commander of the merchantman will do all in his power to resist us. At any rate there will be a sufficient delay to enable the frigate to heave in sight of him, if he has not already discovered her. If we should board the Sparta in sight of the man-of-war, the character of our vessel would be instantly known, and we should be dogged by her from one ocean to another."</p> 
                  <p>"May I ask if your plan is fully matured?"</p> 
                  <p>"It is. You will perceive that for the last two hours the frigate has not gained upon us; nor has the merchantman, although both are under every rag of canvas that they can carry; while we are walking through the water with equal speed, under two-thirds of ours."</p> 
                  <p>"True-I have noticed it."</p> 
                  <p>"Now, my intention is to incite the merchantman to press forward as fast as possible, at the same time to show the frigate that we have no anxiety in regard to her proximity. As soon as it is sufficiently dark I shall crowd all sail and overhaul the Sparta, obtain her treasures, and when morning dawns to be far out of sight."</p> 
                   
                  <p>"Excellent! Excellent!" exclaimed De Soto. "I admire your judicious plan. I will never again be alarmed. I confess that I considered your strange movements dangerous if not foolish."</p> 
                  <p>"Mr. De Soto," resumed Ringbold; "I would, if possible, have the ship captured without the firing of another gun. To effect this I have an important duty for you to perform."</p> 
                  <p>"I shall feel proud of any appointment whereby I may show my zeal in your service."</p> 
                  <p>"As soon as it is dark, man the cutter and gig with fifteen men each, and pull with all speed for the ship. Be sure that they are well armed. Should you meet with more resistance than you can cope with, display a signal light, and the schooner shall be run alongside with all possible dispatch. In all probability, the two guns on the ship's quarter will be found spiked at the time they have most need of them. Drive the passengers and crew into the hold, and fasten down the hatches. Harry Tempest, if he has done his duty faithfully, will disclose to you where the ship's treasures are concealed. Have everything ready to transfer to the Spitfire the moment she ranges alongside."</p> 
                  <p>"Your orders shall be strictly obeyed," replied the lieutenant. "What disposition shall be made of the ladies if any are on board."</p> 
                  <p>"Secure them in the lower cabin: or, rather leave them to the disposal of Harry. He is fond of the fair creatures, and as he has already, without doubt, made himself very agreeable to them, let his humor be indulged."</p> 
                  <p>"I trust their influence over him will not cause him to turn traitor."</p> 
                  <p>"No danger, not the slightest. Although Harry was not cut out for a free rover, yet he has never deceived me, and I would trust him on an enterprise like the present as soon as I would trust myself. He is a noble fellow, and knows no master or sire save me."</p> 
                  <p>"I have heard that there was some mystery connected with his birth, but I never learned the particulars."</p> 
                  <pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6934-00000017"/> 
                  <p>"They will all be brought to light in due time. I, alone, possess the great secret, and when I have done with his services his true position in life shall be divulged."</p> 
                  <p>"I have been told that he has refused promotion even under you."</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, uniformly. I have offered him the place you now fill; and even tried to persuade him to take command of a clipper which I would have procured and equipped for him in the most efficient manner. No, he prefers executing my orders, rather than to take the responsibility of a command himself. He does not lack courage, for he is ever upon deck in the hour of battle, though I never saw him brandish a cutlass or discharge a pistol, except by way of amusement. Yet there is no duty on board of a vessel that he is not fully competent of performing."</p> 
                  <p>"Have you no fears that he will ever prove treacherous to you?"</p> 
                  <p>"None; for well he knows that then his hopes of penetrating the mystery which hangs over him would perish for ever. With my own hands would I destroy the last trace which stands between him and an exalted station in society."</p> 
                  <p>"Surely you have him secure enough."</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, and as he has done me good service, I can't help liking the youth, notwithstanding I strongly suspect he despises our roving profession."</p> 
                  <p>It was now five o'clock in the afternoon, and the officers of the Spitfire were summoned to the cabin to dinner, leaving the deck in charge of the second lieutenant, with proper instructions as to her course, speed, &amp;c.</p> 
                  <p>The merchantman and pirate were within four miles of each other, while the frigate was eight or nine miles astern of the schooner. At seven o'clock, Captain Ringbold and his lieutenant again appeared on deck. The latter immediately made preparations to execute his commission, and when the pirate crew ascertained that there was a prospect of having something to do, they gave three loud huzzas, and went about their duty with alacrity.</p> 
                   
                  <p>The sun had disappeared, and the shades of evening had veiled the frigate from view, when the captain exclaimed in thundering tones:-</p> 
                  <p>"Haul the foresail! up with the topsail and top-gallant sail. Set the gaft-topsail! There she walks through it gloriously!" continued Ringbold, as he looked over the side of his trim craft. In the meantime two of the boats had been lowered from the davits, and thirty picked men, well armed, were ready to push off at a moment's warning. "All ready, pull away, my hearties!" exclaimed De Soto, as he leaped into the stern of the gig.</p> 
                  <p>The remainder of the crew on board gave them three hearty cheers, which was returned by the men in the boats. They now plied the oars and shot ahead of the schooner rapidly, notwithstanding he was under a pretty good headway. In half an hour they had so far distanced the Spitfire as to lose sight of her altogether.</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER V.</head> 
                  <argument> 
                     <p>The conduct of the Pirate accounted for-Preparations for Defence-The boats of the Schooner heave in sight-Are hailed by the Captain, and a musket-ball returned-The first gun from the Sparta, and its terrible Execution-Dismay of the Pirates-A portion of them gain the deck of the Sparta-A desperate Conflict-Conduct of Duvalle-Single combat, in which De Soto is defeated by Edward Duvalle.</p> 
                  </argument> 
                  <p>IT had been a day of fearful anxiety on board the Sparta. The apparent lack of exertion on the part of the pirate, and the hauling down of the foresail did not escape the observation of Captain Wingate, yet he was at a loss how to account for the strange movement.</p> 
                  <p>"The pirate has taken in her foresail," said the captain to Duvalle, as soon as he had reached the deck, after the arrest of Big Tom. "This looks strange."</p> 
                  <pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6934-00000018"/> 
                  <p>"It is unaccountable to me," replied Duvalle, "unless, perchance, they are not yet fully prepared to attack your ship."</p> 
                  <p>"Or perhaps they may imagine that we are too strong for them," added the captain.</p> 
                  <p>Duvalle shook his head, as he thought how little Captain Wingate knew of the terrible power contained within that graceful craft.</p> 
                  <p>"It is my opinion," said he at length, "that the pirate chief does not intend to make the attack until after dark."</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, yes-that's his game, without doubt," responded Wingate; "and I thank you for giving me an insight into his design. But we'll be on the lookout, and when the bloody devils do show themselves they'll be sure to be warmly received. But I must go below and inform the ladies that there is no immediate danger, for if they find out that I am hencooping them up without a reasonable cause, they'll be down upon me like a white squall after a calm."</p> 
                  <milestone n="*   *   *   *   *   *   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/> 
                  <p>It was now evening. The bright constellations were reflected from the deep, and the noble ship with majestic and graceful motion was slowly breasting the long rolling billows. The wind was light and steady, and there was a perfect silence maintained on the Sparta's deck. The captain and first officer, together with Duvalle, stood on the quarter deck, their eyes kept to leeward, and they carefully listened as if expecting every moment to catch some sounds from the pursuing vessel, which became utterly imperceptible soon after the sun had sunk beneath the western wave.</p> 
                  <p>Every man, with the exception of Mr. Floyd (including the crew and passengers), were now upon the deck of the merchantman, and altogether they numbered thirty-five-but little more than half the number on board of the chase. They had been harangued by the captain to some effect, and every one uttered a resolve that they preferred to die fighting manfully, than to be murdered in cool blood, by devils wearing the semblance of humanity! All of them were armed with muskets, with the exception of a small detachment to man the guns. Each one was ordered to preserve the utmost silence until the captain's orders were heard. Thus were the entire resources of the ship judiciously arranged, and the men put under proper instructions. It is true they had but little hope in repelling the piratical crew, yet they vowed to sell their lives dearly.</p> 
                  <p>"Hark!" exclaimed Duvalle to the captain; "I hear the sound of oars!"</p> 
                  <p>In another moment, clapping his night-glass to his eye, he continued, "I perceive two boats, fully manned, rowing with all their might towards us!"</p> 
                  <p>"Sure enough," said the captain; "the devils will be under our heels in fifteen minutes. How many do you make out their number to be."</p> 
                  <p>"Not upwards of thirty," replied Duvalle.</p> 
                  <p>"Not more than thirty?" reiterated Wingate; "our number exceeds that."</p> 
                  <p>"You must consider that they are all fighting men."</p> 
                  <p>"But have we not the advantage of them?" asked the captain regaining confidence. "Pooh! they mistake our strength! We can send half of them to Davy Jones, before one can gain a footing upon the Sparta's deck! I really like the shape they come in, and quite relish the little brush that is about to come off."</p> 
                  <p>Saying this the animated captain went along the deck to raise the hopes and spirits of the men.</p> 
                  <p>"Cheer up my hearties!" said he; "they are coming in gig loads, instead of administering doses of hot shot from their eighteens into the ribs of the old Sparta! How I should glory in capturing this schooner. It would be a good joke to tell of when we get into port-how an old merchantman, with a handful of men and passengers, captured a fast sailing piratical craft heavily manned and armed! Keep cool my lads, when the boats come within musket shot. Fire not a gun until you hear the word of command, and then take sure aim and blaze away!"</p> 
                  <p>The boats could now be discerned with the naked eye.<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6934-00000019"/> Captain Wingate took his station on the quarter-deck, and through his speaking-trumpet, vociferated aloud,</p> 
                  <p>"Boat ahoy!"</p> 
                  <p>No answer was returned, but the men plied their oars more briskly than before.</p> 
                  <p>"Boat ahoy!" again shouted the captain.</p> 
                  <p>A flash and a sharp musket report was heard, and an ounce ball pierced a hole through a speaking-trumpet which Captain Wingate held in his hand.</p> 
                  <p>"The devils are sharp-shooters!" exclaimed he to Duvalle, as the ball whistled through his instrument.</p> 
                  <p>"Shall I give them a salute from this six pounder?" asked Duvalle.</p> 
                  <p>"Wait until you cannot fail of your mark!"</p> 
                  <p>"In a minute more they will be so near us, that it will be impossible to depress the piece sufficiently to bear upon them."</p> 
                  <p>"Take a good aim and let them have it! Mind the heave of the sea."</p> 
                  <p>"Stand by, my boys!" exclaimed Duvalle, while he directed the piece. "All ready! Fire!"</p> 
                  <p>The match was applied-the sea for a moment was illuminated, and amid the booming of the cannon-a crash was heard!-and shrieks and oaths from dying men fell upon the ears of those upon the Sparta's deck!</p> 
                  <p>The smoke cleared away, the roar of the gun echoed in the distance, and with it were hushed the groans and curses of the wounded and dying! The foremost boat was crushed, and no less than ten men had found a watery grave! Those who miraculously escaped were picked up by the lagging boat, which retarded her progress but for a moment. De Soto, the lieutenant, was on board this boat, and when he saw the fate of so many of his brave men, it only increased his desperation, and muttering awful curses and damnable oaths, he ordered his men to fire a volley upon the quarter deck of the ship, and then to pull heartily and board her, where they would have an opportunity amply to revenge the fate of their fallen comrades!</p> 
                   
                  <p>"Can't you give them another dose!" said Wingate, as he saw the effect of Duvalle's well-directed fire, and just as the shot of the pirates pattered like hail about them.</p> 
                  <p>"No-they will be under our stern in one moment," answered Edward. "Now's the time for the musketeers!"</p> 
                  <p>The men were now all ordered to the quarter-deck, with their guns cocked and primed, awaiting the word of command.</p> 
                  <p>"Ready! Aim! Fire!" ordered the first mate, who now acted as captain of the raw marines.</p> 
                  <p>"Bravo! Bravo!" exclaimed the captain, as he saw three or four of the men fall.</p> 
                  <p>The muskets were again loaded, and another volley was poured upon them, but the execution was not so great as at the first fire, the pirates being now nearly under the stern of the ship. In a moment more they began clambering up the ship's sides, but many were beaten into the water with the butts of muskets, and but few gained a footing upon the deck. These fought with all the fury of madmen, and made considerable slaughter among the ship's crew! De Soto and three or four others had gained the quarter deck by means of the davits tackle, and here a most desperate combat ensued! Duvalle had shot the first that gained a footing, and disarmed him of a heavy cutlass, with which he kept the others at bay. Captain Wingate with one or two others rushing to his assistance, succeeded in engaging and beating down with such weapons as they could find, all but the leader, who was in the meantime in deadly combat with Duvalle!</p> 
                  <p>"Traitor!" exclaimed the enraged pirate lieutenant. "Thy hour is come."</p> 
                  <p>"Pirate! murderer! merciless wretch!" returned Duvalle, in thundering tones. "This moment is worth living a whole life for! God be praised that he has spared thy miserable life thus far through this scene of carnage, that I may perform one good deed ere I die!"</p> 
                  <p>"Prate no more, vile traitor. Think not, because we are partially defeated through your damnable treachery, you or<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC6934-00000020"/> this ship's crew are safe. Ere midnight, every one of you will be weltering in your gore!"</p> 
                  <p>"If my arm fails to let out your savage blood, think not to escape."</p> 
                  <p>"Shall I blow his brains out?" ejaculated Captain Wingate, after the strife was quelled on the other parts of the deck.</p> 
                  <p>"No; he must die by my own hands. Let no one interfere. He is the pirate De Soto, second in command to the devil, Ringbold!"</p> 
                  <p>"And what art thou, then?" questioned De Soto, "but the devil's own son?"</p> 
                  <p>"Ringbold is not my father, and thou knowest it, villain."</p> 
                  <p>"Then thou'rt worse. An illegitimate foundling. Picked up upon the sea, where thou had'st been cast up by thy unnatural mother!"</p> 
                  <p>"Liar! I'll hear no more!"</p> 
                  <p>Their blades crossed. Both looked upon each other with the ferocity of tigers. It was an anxious moment. The lieutenant evidently was Duvalle's superior in strength, but the latter could boast of greater skill in handling the cutlass. Blow after blow was struck, but not a drop of blood was yet drawn. Owing to some blood upon the deck Duvalle slipped as he was parrying a blow, and his weapon was knocked from his hands. De Soto was about to cut him down, when, in an instant, the weapon was restored to him, and in time to enable him to ward off the powerful stroke, which the pirate aimed at his head. Duvalle regained his feet, and renewed the fight with more eagerness than before. It was for sometime doubtful how the contest would end. They seemed evenly matched. But Captain Wingate watched every movement with the eagerness of a cat, resolving if Duvalle again labored under a disadvantage, to blow out the pirate's brains at once. This, however, was not destined to be the result. De Soto's power began to fail him, and his antagonist, acting with greater coolness, began now to press him hard, and seizing an opportunity, by a dexterous movement of his arm, the cutlass flew from the pirate's hand. In another moment his headless trunk lay weltering in purple gore!</p> 
                  <p>"Bravo! huzza!" shouted Captain Wingate, and a hearty response was heard from all on board.</p> 
                  <p>The decks were now cleared from the dead bodies of the pirates, and thrown over board. One of the foremost men of the ship's crew was found among the slaughtered. This loss, with two or three others who were slightly wounded, was all that the ship's crew sustained in this well fought but desperate contest.</p> 
                  <p>The ladies having been informed that the pirates were defeated, came upon deck, and witnessed the single combat between Duvalle and De Soto. It was none other than Fanny Floyd who picked up Edward's sabre when he was by accident disarmed, and quickly placed it in his right hand. The captain was a witness of the heroic act, and applauded her openly for it, and afterwards informed Duvalle of the circumstance.</p> 
                  <p>"Your gallant deeds and noble bearing during our desperate conflict with the bloody devils, deserve more than our warmest thanks," said Captain Wingate to his heroic passenger. "I hope yet to have an opportunity to manifest it by a more substantial token."</p> 
                  <p>"I have done but my duty, sir."</p> 
                  <p>"The honor of the victory we have achieved belongs solely to you."</p> 
                  <p>"Remember the victory is not yet won."</p> 
                  <p>"I do not think one has escaped to tell of their defeat."</p> 
                  <p>"True, sir; yet, notwithstanding we have killed a score or two of the merciless buccaneers, there are enough left on board of the corsair to man every gun that she carries, and with one or two broadsides, she might easily sink your ship."</p> 
                  <p>"Perhaps they will send another detachment to look after their comrades. If they do they must share the same fate."</p> 
                  <p>"They will not do that," replied Duvalle; "it is my opinion that we shall not see the schooner again before midnight, though I should recommend the strictest look-out to be kept;<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC6934-00000021"/> and the men be prepared at a moment's warning. It is customary on board of the corsair, when boats are sent on any expedition in the night, to carry with them a signal-light to display if they need further aid from the vessel. Here is a lantern which one of your men has taken from the pirate's gig, now alongside, which confirms me in my belief that it was brought with them for this very purpose. If no signal is discovered by the corsair captain, he will, of course, presume that the ship is captured and now in possession of his crew."</p> 
                  <p>"That being the case, what's best to be done?" asked Captain Wingate, musingly.</p> 
                  <p>"We cannot escape her nor capture her, unless by a <foreign xml:lang="FRA">ruse,</foreign>" replied Duvalle, "but it will prove a desperate and bloody one."</p> 
                  <p>"So much the greater glory," answered the captain, with enthusiasm. "This is the first time I ever did any fighting in my life, and now that I have got a taste of it, and had an opportunity to prove myself whether I am a coward or not, I could enjoy a battle with these sea-robbers every morning by way of getting up an appetite for breakfast."</p> 
                  <p>"Then, be assured, if we engage these fellows again, you will require more than a double allowance to-morrow morning," replied Edward, facetiously.</p> 
                  <p>"Come, let's hear your plan for a ruse, and I'll follow it. Although I'm monarch of this deck, yet under the circumstances I am willing to listen to your dictation or direction."</p> 
                  <p>"In the first place I propose that the clothes which were stripped from the bodies of the slain pirates be distributed among your men, with orders to disguise themselves therewith immediately, so far as they will go. Let the disguised men be stationed near the gangway, and order all the others below until a signal is given for them to reappear upon the deck."</p> 
                  <p>"Excellent, I see it all!" interrupted the captain, rapturously.</p> 
                  <p>"Then back the main-topsail, and bring your ship to,"--</p> 
                  <p>"What? and allow the devils to board us at once?" ejaculated the commander somewhat staggered at this latter suggestion.</p> 
                   
                  <p>"It is the only course to save the vessel and your lives."</p> 
                  <p>"Then our chance is indeed a small one."</p> 
                  <p>"Not so; you have not heard my whole plan."</p> 
                  <p>"Well, go on. I'll listen with all my ears."</p> 
                  <p>"With De Soto's wardrobe I intend to disguise myself, and by calling into aid a little imitative talent that I fortunately possess, I shall be enabled to personate him whom I have just slain, with tolerable accuracy; at any rate sufficiently so to deceive the corsair chief. When the schooner heaves in sight, I will hail her and tell him that he had better not run her alongside, as there is danger of an explosion, giving him to understand that there is fire in the hold, but to send another boat, with a full complement of men to assist us in putting out the fire and getting the treasures upon deck.</p> 
                  <p>"Should the pirate chief put off in the boat for the ship, by all means let him be taken alive; I have an account to adjust with him before he dies.</p> 
                  <p>"On no consideration let a gun be fired, but silence the pirates with swords and cutlasses; otherwise the report of muskets would alarm the schooner, and we would be fired upon at once. Have no lights burning about the ship, that our proceeding be discovered by those on board of the corsair. Should we succeed in this, I will again hail her to come alongside, as no further danger may be apprehended from the pretended fire. The moment she comes up, and with her grappling-irons is made fast to the ship let that be a signal to board her at once. Station half your force at the gangway for defence and I will lead the other half on board of the pirate from the ship's quarter deck. In ten minutes after that our fates and the contest will be decided."</p> 
                  <p>"Bravo! bravo! gives us your hand! You're the boy for me!" exclaimed the captain in raptures. "You deserve to be the admiral of a whole fleet. If ever I step my foot on <foreign xml:lang="LAT">terra firma</foreign> again, I'll see that your name shall go down to posterity with the best of 'em. You shall be immortalized, if brave deeds can give a man immortality."</p> 
                  <p>"Thank you, captain, but I have no ambition for such<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6934-00000022"/> distinction," replied Edward. "On defeating the pirates and taking their chief alive, depend all my hopes for the future; and since I find you have good and brave men on board of your ship, there is a possibility of your becoming the victors. Your chance is more than half equal if I can deceive them by my <foreign xml:lang="FRA">ruse.</foreign> But, Captain Wingate, before we again go to our duty I have one request to make."</p> 
                  <p>"Had you a thousand to make they should be granted, my friend."</p> 
                  <p>"Should I fall in the contest, I wish not to leave an ignominious name behind me. It is true, I never harmed the least of God's creation except in defence; yet should I die without penetrating the awful mystery which keeps me from a knowledge of myself, a bloody pirate's name would live after me!"</p> 
                  <p>"A pirate! You a pirate! I'll never believe it."</p> 
                  <p>"And yet more than half of my life has been spent in the company of pirates; in their haunts upon the land, and in their vessels on the sea; but for all this I deserve not this murderous appellation."</p> 
                  <p>"I believe it,-every word you utter."</p> 
                  <p>"Now should it be my fate to fall, you will find among my papers a detailed account of my own life and actions, since I was a child, much of it, indeed, written from memory, but nevertheless correct in particular. Give this history to the one whose address it bears."</p> 
                  <p>"Your request shall be faithfully attended to, should you possibly meet the fate you apprehend," replied the captain. "May God spare your life, and bring you many days of happiness and comfort."</p> 
                  <p>"Should Ringbold fall, I claim his person and private papers," resumed Edward. "For in his possession the secret of my birth is carefully kept. He has often asserted, in my hearing, that when he falls,-should I prove treacherous to him,-for ever dies the mystery. On this account I would have him taken alive."</p> 
                  <p>"Cheer up, my young friend," said the captain, as he observed that Edward looked despondingly. "I feel that upon you the lives of all on board of this ship depend."</p> 
                  <p>"Then, may Heaven assist me, and nerve my arm for the impending conflict."</p> 
                  <p>Saying which Edward and the captain went about their duty; the former to prepare for the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">ruse</foreign> he intended to play upon their sanguinary foe, and the latter to rouse the ardor of the passengers and the ship's crew.</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER VI.</head> 
                  <argument> 
                     <p>Hailing the Schooner-Glee of the Pirates at their golden prospects-Success of the Ruse-Consternation and destruction of the Second Detachment of Pirates-Duvalle and fifteen men prepare to embark in the boats for the purpose of attacking the Spitfire.</p> 
                  </argument> 
                  <p>IT was about midnight, as Duvalle had predicted, when the Spitfire hove in sight. She was yet a mile and a half distant, but could be distinctly discerned through a night glass. Captain Wingate, with great coolness and intrepidity, gave orders to take in all the small sails, heave the ship to, and await the coming up of their fearful enemy. All the instructions and suggestions of the young active passenger were implicitly followed; the men then upon deck wearing the garb of the pirates that were killed in the first contest, and Duvalle fully equipped with the arms and gay attire of the corsair lieutenant; while the remainder of the crew and passengers were waiting below with beating hearts the summons to the fearful and bloody battle in anticipation. Not many minutes after the ship was hove to, the Spitfire had come within hailing distance, when Duvalle mounted the taffrail of the ship, with the captain's speaking-trumpet, and with a loud but assured voice, hailed,</p> 
                  <p>"Schooner ahoy!"</p> 
                  <p>"Halloo!" was the response a moment or two afterward. "What ship is that?"</p> 
                  <pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6934-00000023"/> 
                  <p>"The Sparta! Lieut. De Soto! of and from Baltimore, bound to Rio Janeiro, with a rich cargo! What schooner is that?"</p> 
                  <p>"The Spitfire, Captain Ringbold, on a cruise. Shall we run alongside?"</p> 
                  <p>"No!" replied the assumed De Soto. "Send a boat, we need another to remove the specie! Besides the ship is on fire, and there is no time to lose!"</p> 
                  <p>"Ay, ay!" returned the corsair chief.</p> 
                  <p>All was now animation and glee on board of the Spitfire. The crew shouted and danced for joy at the golden prospects before them! Their supposed prize they had watched and dogged for several weeks, and to obtain so easy a victory was a matter of congratulation, particularly to several novices in the profession, which had been enlisted since the schooner left Baltimore.</p> 
                  <p>"Comrades!" exclaimed the pirate chief, rubbing his hands with exultation. "Launch the long-boat, and pull for the ship with all despatch! The prize is ours-and a golden one she'll prove to us! De Soto has done up the business bravely! Work briskly, my lads! bear a hand, every one of you!"</p> 
                  <p>"Ay, ay, sir!" shouted all the crew; and in a few moments the heavy long-boat was afloat.</p> 
                  <p>Twenty men were despatched in this boat under the command of the third officer; the captain and ten men remaining in charge of the schooner.</p> 
                  <p>The exulting shouts of the pirate crew reached the ears even of those on board of the ship. But instead of having a disheartening effect, it emboldened their hearts and nerved their arms for the fight. The captain and Duvalle for a few moments awaited with fearful anxiety the success of their project; but when they heard the loud "heave-oh!" of the pirates, the latter knew that they were getting out the long-boat for the purpose of coming on board to assist in removing the treasures of the ship, and therefore, thus far the trick had proved successful.</p> 
                  <p>"It is my opinion, Captain Wingate," remarked our hero, "that this boat's crew can be captured without the firing of a gun!"</p> 
                  <p>"Without the firing of a gun?" ejaculated the commander. "Impossible!"</p> 
                  <p>"It is quite possible, sir," continued Duvalle.</p> 
                  <p>"How so?"</p> 
                  <p>"They come as victors for the spoils which they suppose already theirs. And therefore, it is my opinion, they will leave, at least, their fire-arms behind them!"</p> 
                  <p>"True! you're right. We'll spoil the devils!"</p> 
                  <p>"If they can be destroyed or taken without the firing of a cannon or musket, our efforts will be crowned with success;" continued Duvalle. "Should firing be heard by the pirate chief, he will suspect that all is not right, and before we know it he will be pouring his grape and canister into us. Even with half a dozen men he might blow the ship into atoms! On the other hand, by capturing or destroying them with cutlasses and swords, their fate will not be known to Ringbold until it be too late to revenge the slaughter of the crew. As soon as this can be accomplished, with as many men as can be spared from the ship, we can man three boats, run alongside of the schooner, and before we are suspected, gain possession of her deck, where I hope not only to avenge the wrongs I have suffered, but to discover the secret of my birth, now only known to the pirate chief!"</p> 
                  <p>"Your plan is all important, I perceive;" replied Captain Wingate, "and I will forthwith enforce upon the minds of the men, the necessity of achieving our next victory by the sword alone. If they are not armed with muskets, we can silence half of them while clambering up the ship's side; and then we must be poor, weak soldiers indeed, if we can't conquer the remainder in the same way. But we have no time to talk! There they come exulting fiercely over their supposed prize!"</p> 
                  <p>"Sure enough, and they will be under our stern in five minutes."</p> 
                  <p>"Remember, my dear friend" resumed the captain; "if we<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC6934-00000024"/> capture the pirate, you shall have the command, and the largest share of the prize money."</p> 
                  <p>"I want neither," replied Duvalle; "but I shall deem it a special favor if you will allow me to lead those who will be despatched to capture the schooner!"</p> 
                  <p>"By all means; you're just the man! I wouldn't trust another on board the Sparta. I wouldn't trust myself, though from this day henceforth I shall consider myself a fighting man, lacking neither courage nor strength."</p> 
                  <p>After this laudatory remark of the captain, spoken half seriously, and half jokingly, he went among the men on deck, and stationed most of them near the gangway with cutlasses, swords, handspikes and such other weapons as the ship afforded, with the exception of fire-arms, which were removed to a convenient place in case they should be required.</p> 
                  <p>The long-boat of the Spitfire was now half a cable's length distance, when Duvalle (dressed as De Soto) mounted the gangway ladder, where he could be seen by the pirates. They gave him three loud and hearty cheers. He, in return, waved his hat in acknowledgement, and returned to the station he had chosen upon the deck!</p> 
                  <p>"Everything favors our cause," said he in a loud voice to those around him. "It appears that they have brought no weapons except their side arms with them. Wait, comrades, till the signal for attack is given. Strike not a blow until half a dozen at least have reached the deck, and as many more are upon the gangway ladder."</p> 
                  <p>All resolved to adhere closely to Duvalle's instructions, and for a few moments the utmost silence reigned upon the Sparta's decks. The long-boat came thumping against the ship's side; the pirates, impatient and eager to be on the deck of their supposed prize, crowded up the gangway steps in confusion, while many clambered up the ship's side, clinging to whatever they could find. In this way eight or ten reached the merchantman's deck at once; and among them was the second lieutenant of the Spitfire, who, first perceiving him whom he supposed to be De Soto, ran towards him to congratulate him with extended hand. Instead of taking it, he gave him such a blow with his heavy sabre as nearly to sever his head from his body, and the pirate officer's dead body rolled upon the deck!</p> 
                  <p>So quick was this done, that the pirates, not yet comprehending the snare that had been so ingeniously set for them, looked on the dead body with wonder and amazement. The first impression which thwarted across their minds, was that De Soto had taken this opportunity to avenge himself for some injury that his fellow officer had done him. But precious few moments did they have to investigate what appeared to them such a profound mystery!</p> 
                  <p>"Now's the time!" shouted Duvalle, in tones of thunder.</p> 
                  <p>"At 'em, my boys!" added Captain Wingate. "Down with the bloody villains! Show no quarter but to those who fall upon their knees and beg for it."</p> 
                  <p>Eight or ten had already fallen by the effectual onslaught made by the crew and passengers, before they began to comprehend the fatal situation in which they found themselves. It was now too late for a retreat. Every man had been brought into the snare, and to fight was all that could be done. Should they sue for mercy on board the ship and obtain it, they well knew that on shore that quality would never be shown to pirates, whose bloody deeds had already chilled the hearts of a multitude. With a desperation and fury, amounting to madness, drew their cutlasses, and rushed upon their foe. One of the number, recognizing Duvalle in De Soto's attire, exclaimed aloud,</p> 
                  <p>"Ah! we have been betrayed by Harry Tempest, the captain's son!" and singling out Duvalle, he strove with all his might to cut him down, but the pirate found more than his match-at the third blow his skull was split in twain. Those who had been waiting below for further orders, where now summoned to the combat. Seeing a large body of men rushing upon deck, the pirates were dismayed and disheartened. They fell back before their new antagonists. Several tried to jump overboard, but all who attempted it, received a blow<pb n="48-49 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6934-00000025"/> which sent them to their last account! So well had everything been contrived to meet every possible emergency, that Duvalle had stationed several men along the ship's side, to prevent any one's escaping alive to give the alarm to those left on board of the schooner.</p> 
                  <p>The pirates fought with desperation and fury unparalleled. They did not ask for quarter. They did not expect it. But so long as they had life in their bodies, they continued to make resistance. At length, the last one of those who had left the Spitfire in such high glee, was run through the body with a two edged sword, and fell upon the deck with curses in his mouth!</p> 
                  <p>The Sparta's crew had fought nobly their second contest; but five of them were lying among the slaughtered, and several received severe but not mortal wounds, and were immediately taken below.</p> 
                  <p>Captain Wingate also received a deep sabre cut upon the left arm, but he would not be persuaded to leave the deck, "so long," to use his own expression, "as there was a live pirate upon it."</p> 
                  <p>"Your plan thus far has succeeded to admiration;" said the captain to Duvalle, as soon as the conflict was over.</p> 
                  <p>"You are severely wounded, Captain Wingate," remarked our hero, as he saw the blood gushing out the sleeve of his coat. "You had better go below and get it dressed."</p> 
                  <p>"There is more important business first to be attended to. In the first place, among the dead bodies upon our deck, are several of our brave men,-they must be separated. I can't bear the thought of leaving them lying promiscuously together. No-the pirates must be thrown overboard, and our brave but fallen heroes must have Christian burial!"</p> 
                  <p>"In the meantime, captain, shall we board the schooner? Delay is dangerous."</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, my brave friend, and to you shall the honors of these successive victories be ascribed;" replied the captain. "Run up alongside as soon as you have conquered her. I want to see what that craft is made of."</p> 
                   
                  <p>
                     <figure> 
                        <head>RINGBOLD, THE CORSAIR CHIEFTAIN.</head> 
                     </figure>
                  </p> 
                  <pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC6934-00000026"/> 
                   
                  <p>"But should I fail, captain?</p> 
                  <p>"Fail! Hang me if I believe you would if she were a hundred-and-ten gun ship!"</p> 
                  <p>"I think the chances are now decidedly in our favor, but I must have a picked crew."</p> 
                  <p>"Take whom you please, and be sure you select a sufficient number."</p> 
                  <p>"Thank you. I have observed who are the best fighting men of all the ship's company, and I can easily make a selection. Fifteen are all that I require. Should I meet with more powerful resistance than I anticipate, a signal lantern shall be lighted by one whom I will leave in one of the boats for that purpose. You can then despatch me as many more as you can spare, leaving a sufficient number to man your guns, for in them lie your only hope if this expedition fail!"</p> 
                  <p>The captain promising to comply, Duvalle went forward to select his men, leaving it however, to the choice of each one not to go unless they wished it. Fortunately, among the fifteen chosen there was not one who did not feel honored at the distinction. They all attired themselves in the garments of the pirates and quickly manned the boats, ready for any order from their heroic leader. Duvalle went aft and took the captain's hand.</p> 
                  <p>"Farewell!" said he, "for the present! If we ever meet again in this world it will be this night. Within this hour will be decided my fate, my hopes, and happiness; ay, even life itself."</p> 
                  <p>"God be with you, and protect you!" said Captain Wingate, as the tears moistened his eye.</p> 
                  <p>"Everything is prepared; and everything seems to favor our enterprise. The men are getting impatient. Again-farewell!"</p> 
                  <p>"Farewell!" responded the captain, as our hero left him and jumped into the boat which was to take the lead. It was ordered that as they neared the schooner, each boat's crew should continue to board her simultaneously and all rush to the quarter deck, and secure its possession, where they were<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC6934-00000027"/> to await further orders. They were more than once cautioned not to take the life of the pirate chief, but to take him prisoner and confine him securely beneath the hatches.</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER VII.</head> 
                  <argument> 
                     <p>Embarkation of the Sparta's crew under Duvalle-They board the Spitfire-Confusion of the Pirates-A desperate Encounter between our hero and the Buccaneer Chief-The latter is defeated and made a prisoner-A part of the Mystery is Unravelled-The Prize arrives alongside of the Ship-Joy of the Victors.</p> 
                  </argument> 
                  <p>THE boats now being fully prepared, pushed off from the ship, and as silently as possible the men rowed leisurely for the schooner; as they had been instructed not to waste their strength in making useless haste. As they neared the pirate, Duvalle began singing a buccaneer's song, a favorite of De Soto's, and which the latter often sung for the edification of Ringbold. So perfectly did he imitate the defunct lieutenant, that the pirate chief, who was watching the approach of the boats from the taffrail, did not for a moment suspect that it proceeded from any other than De Soto.</p> 
                  <p>Without the least confusion, and with apparent moderation, the three boats ranged alongside of the schooner; and although the jolly boat, Ringbold noticed did not resemble any that belonged to the Spitfire, yet he thought nothing of it, since he was so fully persuaded in his own mind that the Sparta was really his prize. He was just giving orders to his men to assist in taking the treasures on board (for his eye had a moment before, discovered several boxes and casks in each of the boats, which had been purposely put there to make the deception the more complete), when the boarders almost simultaneously gained the schooner's deck. Some half dozen of the pirates who were about to execute the captain's orders in regard to the specie, met their foe face to face, and recognizing nizing strangers instead of their own comrades, started back in dread alarm; but before they could gain a defensive position, they were most of them struck down by the quick movements of the boarders!</p> 
                  <p>"To the quarter deck!" exclaimed Duvalle, who saw Ringbold standing in an attitude of amazement, with one or two of the pirates beside him, equally amazed. As some dozen of the boarders rushed towards him, the pirate chief drew his pistols from his belt and presenting them, commanded in bold and authorative tones,</p> 
                  <p>"Stand! Approach me not! the first who disobeys dies!" There was a halt.</p> 
                  <p>"What means this sudden mutiny? You are mad! De Soto, speak?" demanded Ringbold.</p> 
                  <p>"Fear not the bloody monster!" exclaimed Duvalle, as, with sword in hand, he rushed towards him, followed by his men who only waited to hear his commands.</p> 
                  <p>"Ringbold levelled one of his pistols, but fortunately for Duvalle, it missed fire; he raised the other, but ere he could pull the trigger it was knocked from his hand by our hero's sword.</p> 
                  <p>"Stand back, my men," exclaimed he, as several came to his assistance. "He is my prize! Make sure of all the rest of the bloody villains on board, for this one I'll be accountable!"</p> 
                  <p>"Traitor!" exclaimed Ringbold, as he now for the first time recognized his captor; and drawing his two edged sword, he attempted to make a defence, by a heavy blow from Duvalle's cutlass his sword-arm fell powerless by his side.</p> 
                  <p>"Now, merciless monster, I have thee! It is my turn to triumph!"</p> 
                  <p>"You have triumphed by treachery most foul."</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, and saved a noble ship's crew from being massacred by your bloody hell hounds! Thank God they have all met with a severe retribution."</p> 
                  <p>"All! did you say?"</p> 
                  <p>"Ay, all but thee; the last and the <emph>worst!</emph>"</p> 
                  <pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC6934-00000028"/> 
                  <p>"Do I deserve all this from thy hands, Harry Tempest?"</p> 
                  <p>"Ay, and much more wilt thou receive! Have you not denied me a father; a mother; a brother; a sister? Have you not endeavored to train me to a life of bloody deeds? Have you not sent me on missions of treachery, far greater thon this, which I consider the best, the noblest act of my life? Have you not given out that I am your son?"</p> 
                  <p>"Is that a crime?"</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, in my view the greatest of crimes! Now, Ringbold, Tempest, Burke, or whatever your name may be, give up all that appertains to the secret of my birth."</p> 
                  <p>"Spare my life;" said the pirate chief, sinking upon his knees; "and you shall know all."</p> 
                  <p>"I will answer for myself and for those under my command. Farther than this I cannot promise you."</p> 
                  <p>"Enough! lead me to my cabin, where the secret shall be disclosed, and the proof placed in your possession."</p> 
                  <p>Duvalle, knowing the danger of allowing Ringbold the use of his limbs, ordered him to be pinioned and conveyed to the cabin. He submitted to the execution of these orders without a murmur.</p> 
                  <p>The victory on board of the schooner was complete, and she was now nearing the Sparta under a light breeze. Meanwhile our hero and the pirate chief were below continuing the conversation which was began on deck.</p> 
                  <p>"I have always been told by you that I was found at sea," resumed Duvalle.</p> 
                  <p>"And such is the fact."</p> 
                  <p>"What were the circumstances?"</p> 
                  <p>"Be patient, and I will narrate the particulars so far as my memory serves me. I was then a young man of thirty years of age, first lieutenant of a corsair brigantine. We had been chasing for a number of days a Spanish galleon, belonging to Havana, which was bound to Cadiz, with a large amount of specie on board. In the early part of the night we overhauled the galleon and succeeded in boarding her, after a desperate resistance, in which our chief received a mortal wound, and I was immediately, by acclamation, promoted to the command. I had not been long enough in the roving profession to acquire a decided taste for blood; and when I saw as in this instance, men and women upon their knees, crying for mercy, and at the same time our merciless crew singling them out, and literally hacking them to pieces, my heart sickened within me, and I commanded them to desist from their bloody work. Among those who were saved by the little spark of mercy which then inhabited my soul, were a noble Spanish gentleman about the same age as myself, and his wife, a beautiful young lady, not more than twenty years of age. Notwithstanding I promised that their lives should be spared, they seemed more grieved than before. The lady was indeed frantic with grief, and all my efforts were exhausted in endeavoring to calm her. On inquiring the cause of her singular conduct, I learned that but a few moments before I ordered that their lives should be spared, they had committed to the mercy of the wind and waves, a little boy not more than two years old! He was placed in an open box, wrapped carefully in blankets, and lowered out of the cabin window by his parents, who preferred thus to sacrifice their darling child, rather than to see him hacked to pieces before their eyes by the piratical savages, as they termed us.</p> 
                  <p>"As we now wished to remove the treasures of the galleon to the brigantine, and to destroy the other by scuttling, I gave notice to the few remaining passengers whom I had spared, that they must quit the vessel, and offered them the galleon's long boat, with provisions and water for five days. This proposition was eagerly embraced, and ere half an hour more had elapsed they cast off from their captured vessel which went down soon after they and our own crew had left it.</p> 
                  <p>"When morning dawned the long boat was out of sight, but one of our men espied a box floating upon the waves, which he thought looked peculiar. On taking my glass and looking at it for a few moments, I saw distinctly the head of a child. I gave orders to lower the jolly boat and despatched four of my crew to pick it up, not doubting that it was the<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC6934-00000029"/> child who was set afloat on the night previous from the captured galleon.</p> 
                  <p>"My conjectures were correct. In half an hour the boat returned bringing back with them a bright and rosy cheeked boy, together with the box in which he had been so miraculously preserved. The boy, indeed, smiled and prattled as if nothing had happened, until an hour or two had passed, when he began to cry for his mother. I easily appeased his grief by placing within his reach many curiosities which I had gathered in various parts of the world. In a few days he had quite forgotten his parents, and I resolved to adopt him as my own, and called him Harry Tempest, a <foreign xml:lang="FRA">nomme de guerre</foreign> by which I was then known to the brigantine's crew.</p> 
                  <p>"Among the contents of the box which had been carefully supplied with pillows, clothes, etc., for the comfort of the little lone mariner, I found a bag of gold, a casket of precious stones, together with sundry other articles of no inconsiderable value. I also found a scrap of paper within the casket, which I have ever carried carefully concealed in my bosom!"</p> 
                  <p>"And is it there now?" interrupted Edward Duvalle, eagerly.</p> 
                  <p>"It is," answered the pirate, as with his left hand he drew from his bosom, a small greasy black wallet, made of calfskin. "I have always kept it in this," he continued, handing him the wallet, "and you will find it there now."</p> 
                  <p>With trembling hands Edward opened the wallet, and took therefrom a slip of paper written in the Spanish language, it being the only article it contained, and translated into English, read as follows:</p> 
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
                        <body > 
                           <div type="letter"> 
                              <opener>
                                 <dateline>"At Sea-on board Spanish Galleon, SAN GERMANO, July 10, 1805.</dateline>
                              </opener> 
                              <p>"Holy mother of God! protect the innocent child whom we now consign to the mercy of the winds and the waves. The galleon has been attacked by pirates, and already they have commenced butchering the passengers and crew. Our hour is near at hand! Should, perchance, the child be living when picked up, rear him as the means accompanying will allow. Should he be dead, give him Christian burial, and may Heaven bless thee for it. Oh Heaven, who can describe our agony in this our last but deliberate act!</p> 
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>(Signed,) EUSTAQUIO SAN MALO,</signed> 
                                 <signed>CONSTANZA SAN MALO."</signed>
                              </closer> 
                           </div> 
                        </body> 
                     </floatingText>
                  </q> 
                  <p>"The child herein mentioned, you would have me believe-"</p> 
                  <p>"Is yourself," interrupted the pirate.</p> 
                  <p>"Are my father and mother yet living?"</p> 
                  <p>"Of that I cannot inform you. Whether the long boat in which they embarked, ever reached land, I never could ascertain, although I have made frequent inquiries."</p> 
                  <p>"What proof have I that you are not now deceiving me?"</p> 
                  <p>"In that iron chest," answered Ringbold, "which you have so often seen; it contains, beside a mine of wealth, the identical casket of jewels and the bag of gold."</p> 
                  <p>"Even with this evidence I may be deceived!"</p> 
                  <p>"You will also find in the chest a package of papers which fortunately fell into my hands, when the passengers' luggage was overhauled. Among the papers are the marriage certificate of the persons whose names are appended to the slip of paper which you have just read, a registry of their boy's birth, and a passport signed by the authorities of Cadiz. Here are the keys," continued the pirate; "I have considered the chest and the wealth which it contains my private property; I now transfer it all to you."</p> 
                  <p>"I shall receive nothing from your hands except that which rightfully belongs to me," replied Duvalle, proceeding to unlock the chest.</p> 
                  <p>He was somewhat astounded on opening it, to behold the vast amount of ill gotten wealth it contained. By direction of Ringbold, he easily found the package of documents, the casket of jewels and the bag of gold, which he declared rightfully belonged to our hero; and upon perusing the papers, he found that they corroborated the assertions of the pirate.</p> 
                  <pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC6934-00000030"/> 
                  <p>It was now morning; the schooner, which for the last fifteen minutes had been bearing down for the ship, had now arrived alongside.</p> 
                  <p>Duvalle concealed the papers and casket in his bosom carefully, and placing the pirate chief under the charge of a guard, hastened upon the deck. He was first met by Captain Wingate, who first leaped from his own vessel as she came alongside, while the crew and passengers at the same time gave three hearty cheers.</p> 
                  <p>"Huzza! Huzza! my brave boys; you have conquered!" exclaimed the captain of the merchantman, as he embraced the youth.</p> 
                  <p>"In the presence of all here assembled, I hereby declare that the three successive victories we have achieved over the pirates, were accomplished through the bravery of this youthful stranger who stands before you!"</p> 
                  <p>The air again resounded with cheers; and the ladies who stood upon the quarter deck of the Sparta waved their handkerchiefs in token of their gratitude.</p> 
                  <p>"To him, then, are we indebted for our lives and our property!"</p> 
                  <p>"No!" answered Edward, falling upon his knees, and stretching forth his hands. "To God alone should we render thanks for guiding us safely through the perils of this night!"</p> 
                  <p>They all fell upon their knees and a silent prayer was offered from every heart.</p> 
                  <p>Duvalle now went on board of the ship, and each one of the crew and passengers took him by the hand, and spoke their gratitude. Mr. Floyd, supported by his daughter, came tottering towards him. Edward perceiving them, advanced a step or two to meet them, when the old man, in fervent language, gave him his blessing. Fanny, beautiful as the morning, stood trembling and blushing by her father's side-she could not speak-but extended her delicate hand, which he took and pressed warmly to his lips. Who can describe the sensations which at that moment agitated her bosom? The youth whom she so fondly loved, and who had so recently caused her to shed bitter tears, in consequence of his parting words, again stood before her with an unclouded brow and a look of hope beaming from his dark eyes. She understood the meaning of his ardent gaze-she recollected his ominous words at their last interview-the mystery of which he spoke-the "dreadful alliance" at which he had hinted; and which she had but vaguely comprehended. She believed that the time had now come when he would no longer condemn himself; and that the events of the last night, in which he had been the chief actor, were but the fulfilment of that of which he had hinted.</p> 
                  <p>"I did not believe, Miss Floyd," said Edward, "that I could again meet thee with pleasure. But the mysterious veil which kept me from a knowledge of myself I thank heaven, is no longer before my eyes. I owe this disenthralment from a life of misery to the victory we have achieved; and should we again have an opportunity to confer alone, I will give you an account of my eventful history, including my recent discoveries. But I have a great duty yet to perform. I must seek out my father and mother if they are in the land of the living. If dead, seek out the tombstone which covers their mortal remains, that I may kneel in affliction before it."</p> 
                  <p>Mr. Floyd, hearing the frankly spoken words of our hero, and thinking that perhaps his presence might not be agreeable to the lovers, he gave his arm to one of his black attendants, and tottered towards the companion-way.</p> 
                  <p>"Oh, Edward," replied the blushing girl, looking into his manly countenance; "I thought that we should never meet again, and yet one spark of hope dwelt with me. Say, shall I not now see thee often?"</p> 
                  <p>"Not on board of this ship. Captain Wingate will give me the command of the prize, and I must carry her safely into port. My next duty will be to travel in search of my parents. Should success crown my efforts, but few months will elapse before I shall meet thee again. Should I fail after one year's diligent search, then Fanny, will I come to thee and crave<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC6934-00000031"/> that boon which I feel assured you will not refuse me. My hand-my heart, my fortune, will I lay before thee."</p> 
                  <p>"And must you leave so soon?"</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, before the sun reaches its meridian, the schooner and ship must part company, to sail in almost opposite directions. Believe me, Fanny, were it not my duty I would never leave thee."</p> 
                  <p>"I do-I do believe thee, Edward," replied the lovely maiden, with energy. "Go-my love shall not stand between thee and thy duty. Your purposes are truly noble, and I should feel guilty were I to endeavor to avert the course you have marked out."</p> 
                  <p>"Generous creature, you give me happiness. Your last words will comfort me during my absence."</p> 
                  <p>Their conversation was here interrupted by the approach of Captain Wingate, who desired to speak with Duvalle for a few moments on an urgent matter.</p> 
                  <p>"Big Tom," said the captain, "who was arrested at your suggestion, desired to speak with you; he says that he is dying."</p> 
                  <p>Edward went below where the burly sailor was confined, and the moment that he saw him he was convinced that he was not long for this world.</p> 
                  <p>"Ay! I am glad you have come," said the dying sailor; "tell me, has the Spitfire been captured by this ship?"</p> 
                  <p>"It is indeed so."</p> 
                  <p>"I am happy to hear it. Oh, God! that I had lived any life but that of a pirate, I might die in peace! What has become of Ringbold and the crew?"</p> 
                  <p>"He is our prisoner-the crew are all dead!"</p> 
                  <p>"And why do you let him live?"</p> 
                  <p>"To wring from him the secret he possesses in regard to myself."</p> 
                  <p>"And has he divulged anything?"</p> 
                  <p>"Yes-much. I have learned something of my own history."</p> 
                  <p>"I could have told you of that, and intended to before I died, that it might have earned for me thy forgiveness."</p> 
                   
                  <p>"You can now narrate the story-the full corroboration of Ringbold's statement is what I most desire."</p> 
                  <p>"Thank you-thank you," said the sailor; "I am glad that I can do the least good for you; for I have done you evil enough."</p> 
                  <p>Big Tom gave Edward a detailed account of the galleon's capture, corroborating every particular of the statement as given by the pirate chief, but he could give him no knowledge respecting the long boat which was set adrift with the passengers. In continuation he said, "All I have told you is true, so help me Heaven!"</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, I believe it, for it agrees with all I have heard from the villain Ringbold."</p> 
                  <p>"And now," resumed the sailor, in low and feeble voice, "remove the gold chain which encircles my neck."</p> 
                  <p>Edward did as he was requested, and to his surprise he found attached to the chain a locket, set in diamonds, and containing a finely painted miniature of a lady of surpassing beauty and loveliness.</p> 
                  <p>"That chain with my own hands I removed from your neck, before you were brought into the presence of the pirate chief. I was helmsman of the boat that picked up the box in which you were saved, and I bore you in my arms, while the men were rowing for the brigantine. I took it and concealed it about my person without the knowledge of my comrades, and have worn it constantly from that hour to this."</p> 
                  <p>"Whose likeness do you suppose it to be?"</p> 
                  <p>"It is your mother! I had one look at her before she left the ship, and I know I cannot be mistaken; besides I have always thought how much resemblance it bears to you."</p> 
                  <p>"And can this indeed be the semblance of my dear mother?" ejaculated Edward, rapturously, as he gazed upon the picture and kissed it. "My mother-and yet so young and beautiful! Scarce seventeen summers could have passed over her head when she sat for this picture. There is a smile resting upon her cherry-colored lips; and her large lustrous eyes beam lightly with hope and affection. Can it be true that so fair<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC6934-00000032"/> and pure a being could have been the mother of one like me? And yet I cannot doubt! Oh God!" continued he, clasping his hands and looking upward, "I trust that thou hast in thy divine wisdom, spared her life. Oh, lead me to her that I may love and bless her!"</p> 
                  <p>"May heaven grant your desires;" exclaimed the dying man with a feeble utterance. "Forgive me-oh, forgive me; and I die content."</p> 
                  <p>The sailor reached out his hand, which Edward took kindly-"I do forgive thee;" he replied.</p> 
                  <p>"God bless you!" were the last words of the dying mariner. His breathing grew short, and his pulse grew more feeble each moment,-soon the death rattle sounded in his throat, and he expired!</p> 
                  <p>The Captain was immediately summoned below, and he ordered, at Duvalle's request, that his body be prepared for burial in a like manner with those of the ship's company who had fallen in battle!</p> 
                  <p>Silently our hero and Captain Wingate went upon deck. The sight of a corpse of one who had died a natural death, seemed to effect them more than the sight of all the bodies of those who were slain in the heat of battle. They retired to the cabin, where Duvalle made know to the captain his discoveries in regard to himself, as are already know to our readers. But there is one matter slightly enveloped in mystery, and which perhaps, may be made clear through a portion of their conversation, which will be given in the course of another chapter.</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                   
                  <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head> 
                  <argument> 
                     <p>Interesting conversation-Departure of the Prize-She is chased by an English Frigate-Escape and arrival at Havana. The Prize is boarded by a Revenue Officer-Queries promptly answered.</p> 
                  </argument> 
                  <p>"YOUR noble actions have convinced me," said Captain Wingate to Duvalle, in continuation of their interview, "that your plans were all matured before you registered your name as passenger on board of this ship."</p> 
                  <p>"It is true," replied Duvalle; "and this accounts for the muskets and ammunition which I sent on board with my luggage. I did not resolve to betray the pirates until after months of previous reflection. When I did resolve, I swore that it should be done the first opportunity that offered; and at the time Ringbold revealed to me his designs in regard to this ship, I eagerly accepted his proposition; viz: that I should engage a passage in the Sparta, and that Big Tom should ship as foremast hand; and, we were also instructed not only to contrive to render useless your ammunition but to spike your deck guns, that you might become an easy prey to the blood-thirsty and merciless hell-hounds, which with the aid of heaven, we have exterminated!"</p> 
                  <p>"It was a perilous undertaking," remarked the captain.</p> 
                  <p>"It seemed to me perfectly desperate; but there was a silent monition within me, which bade me go on! It was irresistible, and I obeyed, not dreaming that my plans could, by any means within my control, have proved so completely successful! I had two great objects in view; one was to rid the seas of its greatest terror-the other to penetrate the secret which the pirate chief has in his keeping concerning myself, which I had often entreated in vain to gain from him."</p> 
                  <p>"And you deserve honor and reward from the whole world<pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC6934-00000033"/> for your great and glorious achievement;" said Captain Wingate.</p> 
                  <p>"Without your personal aid," replied Duvalle, "I could have done nothing."</p> 
                  <p>"Pooh! don't mention me again, only as one of the invincible thirty-five. But to return to business-how many men do you require to run the prize into Baltimore?"</p> 
                  <p>"Eight, if you can spare so many."</p> 
                  <p>"You shall have them. Here are letters to my employers, together with the slight instructions necessary. I can trust everything to you. I shall hasten my voyage with all possible despatch, and I hope the return voyage may be completed, so that I may be with you at Baltimore in sixty or seventy days at the farthest."</p> 
                  <p>"By this time all must be in readiness on board of the schooner, and I would not lose a minute unnecessarily. What shall be done with Ringbold?"</p> 
                  <p>"Let him be removed to the ship; we can take care of him till we again reach home, when he shall be given up to the United States authorities."</p> 
                  <p>A list of the men who were drafted to man the schooner was now handed to Edward, by the captain, when they both went upon deck and superintended the completion of the preparations for parting.</p> 
                  <p>All was now in readiness, and Edward had taken leave of all on board, save one, a servant of whom now appeared on deck and gave him a slip of paper. It was a billet from Fanny Floyd, begging to see him one moment in the cabin with her father. He quickly obeyed the summons, but without breaking in upon their privacy, we shall merely say that the parting was an affectionate one, and whether the old gentleman really consented on this occasion to their union, shall be known hereafter.</p> 
                  <p>The sails were hoisted-the helmsman stood at his post, and the order was given to cast off. As the two vessels separated, the crew cheered each other heartily, and so long as the signal could be discerned, they were made with white handkerchiefs from the quarter decks of the two vessels-we need not say by whom.</p> 
                  <p>In three hours the Sparta and Spitfire were not within view of each other; every exertion being made on board of both vessels to make their respective ports of destination as speedily as possible.</p> 
                  <p>It was ten o'clock, while the schooner was on her larboard tack, and going at the rate of eight knots (the wind having increased considerably) that she was hailed by a large frigate which suddenly hove in sight, and which was bearing down, with the wind on her quarter, towards the captured corsair. Duvalle, who was then below, suddenly appeared on deck, and espying a double banked frigate, with an English ensign hoisted, within half a gunshot of him, he hesitated for a few moment how to act. The pirate vessel had been so often described, he doubted not that she would be readily recognized by the frigate, and that, if he should allow her to be boarded by the British officers, all his asseverations to the contrary might not convince them that she had within a few hours been captured by an American merchantman, and had been ordered home as a prize. Everything on board of the Spitfire was the same that was there before her capture, and no change was visible except in her crew. Our hero, although he knew that ultimately the truth could be ascertained, yet was satisfied that if once taken possession of, by the Englishman, he and his crew would be subjected to much inconvenience, perhaps cruelty, and months in all probability, would intervene, before the necessary evidence could be obtained to free them from a charge of piracy. With these views he resolved to escape from her if possible, though her immediate proximity placed the schooner in a most hazardous position. One broadside well directed, from the frigate's double battery, would inevitably disable her.</p> 
                  <p>A second time the schooner was hailed, and no answer was received. Duvalle knowing that a shot would come next, ordered the long eighteens to be manned, that he might return the fire, and at the next moment to wear ship, in order to<pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC6934-00000034"/> avoid the effects of a whole broadside which he reasonably anticipated, after setting the man-of-war at defiance. The sea around for a moment was illuminated and the thirty-two pound shot whizzed over the deck of the Spitfire, doing no injury in its flight. The fire was quickly returned, and the fore-top gallant-mast of the frigate fell by the board, and in another moment the Spitfire had borne away and now showed her heels to the enemy. But this manuvre did not prevent Johnny Bull from pouring from his double row of black teeth a full broadside upon the supposed corsair, and the shot flew over her deck like hail, doing some mischief to her upper spars and sails, which her young officer ordered immediately to be repaired as far as possible. The schooner gained fast upon the frigate, and an incessant fire was kept up between them without doing much damage to either. Before midnight the Spitfire had managed to get beyond the reach of most of the frigate's guns; and as the chase had compelled him to run before the wind, and directly out of his course, Duvalle gave orders to brace up the yards and bring the schooner into the wind. This movement brought her again within range of the enemy's guns, but her intrepid officer trusted to the superior sailing qualities of his craft for escape, and at the same time to be nearing his port of destination. The frigate at first changed her course, only a point or two, but perceiving that her constant fire upon the schooner had not the desired effect, she, too, hauled up into the wind and endeavored to keep the weather gage. Her long thirty-two's were now put in requisition, and did considerable damage to the spars and sails of the schooner, and until repairs were made, they materially lessened her speed, yet notwithstanding this she gained slowly upon the chase.</p> 
                  <p>At sunrise the following morning, the Spitfire had gained sufficiently upon the pursuing vessel, so as to be entirely out of the reach of her longest guns. The frigate however, continued the pursuit, and as they were now nearing the West India Islands, Duvalle resolved, that under the cover of the next night, he would run into one of the Spanish ports, where he hoped to find some American vessel of war, to whom he might surrender the schooner, or ask for a convoy to the United States.</p> 
                  <p>Accordingly as soon as the shades of night entirely concealed the English frigate from view, he ran into the port of Havana, and moored her among the thickest of the shipping in the harbor.</p> 
                  <p>At daybreak, on the subsequent morning the schooner "Vision" (the name of the Spitfire having been removed during the night) was lying amid a fleet of vessels of almost every nation before the city of Havana. The Yankee flag was waving from her main truck-her sails were neatly furled, and everything about the craft presented a neat and trim appearance. About nine o'clock she was boarded by a revenue officer, as much from curiosity to examine the exterior of the beautiful vessel, as from a duty which he was bound to perform.</p> 
                  <p>Duvalle was looking over the taffrail when the revenue boat came alongside, rowed by four men, the officer sitting in the stern acting as helmsman. As soon as he came upon the deck of the "Vision"-for by this name we shall henceforth call her-he approached our hero, and inquired, in the Spanish tongue, for permission to see her commander.</p> 
                  <p>"I have that honor, sir," replied Duvalle.</p> 
                  <p>"You, Senor?" ejaculated the Spaniard, in surprise. "I took you rather for a cabin boy than the master."</p> 
                  <p>"Notwithstanding, sir, I am for the present commander of this schooner."</p> 
                  <p>"Whither bound?"</p> 
                  <p>"To Baltimore."</p> 
                  <p>"Where are your subordinate officers and crew?"</p> 
                  <p>"They are all upon deck, sir, as you will perceive."</p> 
                  <p>"What, an armed schooner and only eight men? Impossible!" said the officer, as he cast his eyes searchingly about the deck.</p> 
                  <p>"I have spoken the truth, sir."</p> 
                  <p>"How is it that your men wear not the uniform of the United States naval service?"</p> 
                  <pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC6934-00000035"/> 
                  <p>"The schooner belongs not to the United States Navy."</p> 
                  <p>"Not to the United States Navy?" reiterated the officer, casting his eyes aloft and regarding our national ensign waving proudly from her masthead. "What means that flag?"</p> 
                  <p>"Simply that she is an American vessel, sir!"</p> 
                  <p>"Incredible! a private vessel, and carrying ten guns in time of peace;" exclaimed the revenue officer.</p> 
                  <p>"It is, however strange it may appear, true."</p> 
                  <p>"You will pardon me, Senor, for being inquisitive; but being the revenue officer of this port, it is my imperative duty to ascertain more concerning this vessel. I would not be too officious, but it is so unusual to see an armed vessel of this class sailing under yonder flag on mercantile account, that I must make further inquiries. Is she a privateer?"</p> 
                  <p>"No, sir."</p> 
                  <p>"Is she a slaver?"</p> 
                  <p>"No, sir."</p> 
                  <p>"Then I must demand of you to produce your papers."</p> 
                  <p>"I have none, sir, that I can produce with propriety. The only papers on board are those of a pirate, formerly used by the desperado Ringbold!"</p> 
                  <p>The name of this renowned corsair chief struck the officer with awe. He looked upon the open and ingenuous countenance of the young commander with doubt and perplexity. "Ringbold-the pirate? What mean you?"</p> 
                  <p>"Simply, sir, that but a few days ago, that bold buccaneer and sixty of his desperadoes trod the deck of this vessel. She has since been captured, and is now the prize of the American merchant ship Sparta!"</p> 
                  <p>The officer was more and more astounded.</p> 
                  <p>"What! a merchant ship capture this formidable craft and sixty men? With what, I pray?"</p> 
                  <p>"With thirty-five seamen and passengers, armed with muskets, and two pieces of cannon!" replied our hero.</p> 
                  <p>"It seems almost incredible! and yet from the appearance of your men and yourself, sir, I am bound to believe you. Can you show any proof other than the testimony of your men."</p> 
                  <p>"I have letters unsealed, from the first officer of the Sparta to his employers at Baltimore, which if you deem necessary to peruse, I will place them immediately in your hands."</p> 
                  <p>"This affair is so strange that I must ask you to go ashore with me and visit the Governor of the Island, and let him judge of the matter himself."</p> 
                  <p>"Thank you, sir, for your civility, and if you will allow yourself to be detained until I can prepare myself, I will accompany you with pleasure."</p> 
                  <p>Our hero immediately repaired to his state room, where he attired himself in a becoming suit for an audience with His Excellency, and in the course of half an hour he re-appeared on deck, and signified to the official dignitary that he was in readiness to accompany him.</p> 
                  <p>"My duty compels me to leave one or more men on board of your vessel, until further orders from the Governor."</p> 
                  <p>"Your precaution, though unnecessary in this case, sir, I fully appreciate; the vessel may be considered under your surveilance until I have satisfied His Excellency that I have represented correctly everything in regard to her."</p> 
                  <p>The revenue officer having instructed one of his subordinates in the duty of ship keeping until further orders, went on board his barge with Duvalle, and they were quickly rowed ashore, and proceeded directly to the palace of the Governor.</p> 
                  <p>Before entering, however, the booming of heavy cannon was heard, and on learning the cause it was found that an English man-of-war had just arrived in port, and was firing a salute. Our young commander was apprehensive that this might be the frigate from which he had run away; but as he was in a Spanish port, he would seek protection from its authorities, if the Englishman attempted to attack him.</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC6934-00000036"/> 
                  <head>CHAPTER IX.</head> 
                  <argument> 
                     <p>The Governor and his family-Duvalle visits the Palace, and relates his recent Adventures-The letters-Generosity of His Excellency-Florencia is introduced to Duvalle-Arrival of the British Naval Officer-He demands the Vision as his Prize-Refusal of the Governor, His Anger-Interference of Duvalle-The British Officer makes his exit with a flea in his ear.</p> 
                  </argument> 
                  <p>THE Governor of the Island of Cuba, at the time of which we write, was a noble gentleman of the old Castilian race, and if he were considered somewhat despotic and arbitrary in the administration of the laws made for the Island by old Spain, he certainly deserves much credit for his impartiality and magnanimity. He was a man of six feet in stature, finely proportioned, and possessed a noble and dignified bearing, especially in the presence of his subjects. He was about forty-five years of age, though he appeared somewhat younger-his hair being of a glossy black, and his eye retaining all the fire and expression of youth.</p> 
                  <p>The wife of His Excellency was some five years younger, of remarkably light complexion, and large lustrous eyes, and although forty years had passed over her head, she yet retained much of the beauty which she could boast in her more youthful days. She was a native of Louisiana, and was married in New Orleans, where her husband first made her acquaintance. They afterwards moved to the land of his nativity, and some years afterwards, being noble by birth, and possessing every qualification for any responsible station, he was appointed by his King, Governor of the Island of Cuba, whither he removed soon after his appointment. They were blessed with one child, a daughter about seventeen years of age, of great beauty and sweetness. Florencia, for this was her Christian name, resembled her beautiful mother, in a great degree. She was at once the joy and pride of her noble parents, and commanded the love and admiration of all who enjoyed her acquaintance. Florencia, on the morning of which we write, was standing with her mother in the balcony of the palace which overlooked the picturesque and animated harbor of Havana. The sun was shining brightly, but the cool and invigorating breezes from the sea rendered the atmosphere less oppressive than usual. Hundreds of flags and streamers of various nations, were waving from the masthead of the shipping, and the "yo, heave oh!" of the sailors broke merrily upon the ears of the two females who regarded the scene with sensations of delight. Florencia and her mother had been remarking upon the more beautiful vessels of the great fleet which was spread out before them, and the symmetrical proportions of the schooner with the star-spangled banner flying at her mast-head had not escaped their attention, when the Governor joined them upon the balcony. His eye immediately caught sight of the American, when he exclaimed:</p> 
                  <p>"By San Iago! yon clipper looks like a Baltimorean! It is a rare sight to see one of that class of vessels in our harbor. She must have been sent here for an especial purpose. Hand me my glass, daughter, I must have a clear view of her."</p> 
                  <p>Florencia with fawnlike step ran to obey her father's wishes. In a moment she returned bearing the telescope which the Governor placed to his eye, and for a long time scrutinized the vessel.</p> 
                  <p>"She carries ten guns, and yet I can perceive but eight men upon her decks, besides a youth who is looking over her side. The men are dressed like common American sailors, and she therefore cannot belong to the Navy."</p> 
                  <p>"A boat is approaching her," said Florencia.</p> 
                  <p>"It is the revenue boat," replied His Excellency; "and if I mistake not, Senor Garcia, himself, our first revenue officer, has charge of her. Yes, he has boarded the American, and is now talking with the young man aft. I never saw a more perfect model of a sailing craft in my life," continued he laying aside his glass. "I cannot imagine what she is, or for what purpose she is here."</p> 
                  <pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC6934-00000037"/> 
                  <p>"Perhaps she bears despatches for the United States consul," replied the Governor's wife. "Surely she comes on no hostile errand with a handful of men."</p> 
                  <p>"It is very probable," replied His Excellency. "Our indefatigable officer will soon inform me."</p> 
                  <p>While the Governor and his wife were conversing upon the loveliness of the morning and the gay and animated appearance of the harbor, Dona Florencia was looking through the telescope, watching every movement on board of the schooner. She had observed the young man go below, and as the revenue officer tarried upon the deck, she thought he had gone to call the commander of the schooner. When the young officer again appeared on deck, genteelly attired, he became an object of interest to her, inasmuch as she thought he must be the captain of the craft, for he seemed to be giving orders to his men, and had evidently prepared himself for accompanying his official visitor to the shore.</p> 
                  <p>"Father," said she, in sweet and gentle tones, "the young man whom you saw, is the first officer of the handsome vessel."</p> 
                  <p>"How know you that, my daughter?" interrogated the Governor.</p> 
                  <p>"He has been giving orders to his men; and is now coming ashore in company with Senor Garcia."</p> 
                  <p>"Ah! then they will be here shortly. My word for it, daughter, he is not the commander; most likely the owner's son."</p> 
                  <p>"Then why did he give orders?"</p> 
                  <p>"How is it possible that you should know that he did? Your sense of hearing certainly cannot be sufficiently acute to enable you to hear a distance of at least two hundred rods."</p> 
                  <p>"Oh! but then you know I could tell by his gestures. I saw him making motions to his men, and could almost see his lips move."</p> 
                  <p>"Then, I dare say, daughter, you have already discovered whether he is good or ill looking?"</p> 
                   
                  <p>"Yes, father, he is decidedly handsome," said Florencia, frankly, and with a smiling countenance. "I never saw a more graceful figure, unless it be your Excellency's!"</p> 
                  <p>"Tut, tut, Flora," said her mother archly, "You will make your father vain in his years of manhood, if you pay him such compliments."</p> 
                  <p>"There is little danger, madame," said his Excellency; "but if you had complimented my person so highly twenty years ago, it would undoubtedly have added considerably to my pride. We must keep an eye on our daughter, she is fast loosing her heart through a telescope."</p> 
                  <p>"No fear, father," answered the Senorita; "I have only magnified the young man's perfections."</p> 
                  <p>Meanwhile the boat was fast approaching the shore, and shortly after Senor Garcia and Duvalle had landed, they were announced to His Excellency, the Governor.</p> 
                  <p>"Shall we not be present at the interview, father?" inquired Dona Florencia.</p> 
                  <p>"No, daughter, should I require your services, I will send for you," replied His Excellency, as he left his wife and daughter, and repaired to the audience chamber of the Palace.</p> 
                  <p>"<foreign xml:lang="SPA">Buen venido,</foreign> Senor Garcia!" exclaimed the Governor, as the revenue officer entered the room, followed by Duvalle.</p> 
                  <p>"<foreign xml:lang="SPA">Muchas gracias!</foreign>" replied Senor Garcia. "Senor Duvalle, commander of the American schooner Vision," continued he, introducing our hero.</p> 
                  <p>"Welcome, stranger!" said the Governor, approaching him and taking the youth by the hand. "You are young to have the command of an armed vessel."</p> 
                  <p>"The command is but a temporary one," replied Duvalle. "I am merely commissioned to carry the schooner safely into the port of Baltimore."</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, your Excellency," added Senor Garcia, "the schooner which he has the honor of commanding, is a prize to an American merchantman."</p> 
                  <p>"A prize?" interrupted the Governor; what mean you?"</p> 
                  <pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC6934-00000038"/> 
                  <p>"You will perceive by these letters, which I have deemed prudent to place in your hands for perusal, that this vessel is none other than the one fomerly commanded by the terror of the ocean,-the Pirate Ringbold!"</p> 
                  <p>"<foreign xml:lang="SPA">Santa Maria!</foreign> and has the bloody monster met with his just deserts?" ejaculated the Governor, looking with intensity upon the noble countenance of the youth.</p> 
                  <p>"His crew have to a man been destroyed!" answered Duvalle; "and he himself is a prisoner on board of the merchant ship Sparta. He will be taken to the United States, where he will most undoubtedly meet with his just reward."</p> 
                  <p>"No, by San Iago, such a devil cannot be punished this side of the infernal regions!" said the Governor in an agitated manner. "None have better reasons than myself for wishing the bloody hell-hound the worst of punishments! would to God that it was left to me to inflict the pains he deserves on earth! There could be no torture invented too keen for the monster's body; and though I never beheld a punishment in my life, when I did not feel a pity for the person on whom it was inflicted, yet, I could rejoice heartily to witness this horrible and merciless villain writhing in all the agonies of the most extreme torture!"</p> 
                  <p>While the Governor was speaking, big drops of sweat stood on his noble brow, and his form quivered with the violence of his feelings. At length, partially composing himself, he said,</p> 
                  <p>"Excuse me, gentlemen, for allowing my indignant feelings to gain a momentary ascendancy over me."</p> 
                  <p>Saying which he bade his visitors to be seated, and commenced perusing the letters and other documents, which had been brought from the schooner.</p> 
                  <p>"The account of this capture is truly as astounding, as the conflict was bloody," at length said the governor, rising and addressing Duvalle, "and I perceive that to you belongs the honor of this almost incredible capture! I feel proud of your acquaintance," continued he, taking the hand of our hero; "None have greater reasons for gratitude to you than myself, and how shall I show the sincerity of my feelings?"</p> 
                  <p>"Your Excellency is kind," answered Duvalle; "but none have gained so much by this victory as myself, and therefore your approval of my conduct, as well as the world at large, will more than repay me."</p> 
                  <p>"By <foreign xml:lang="SPA">San Diego,</foreign>" exclaimed His Excellency; "I cannot let you depart without bestowing upon you a slight token of my <emph>gratitude</emph> and esteem."</p> 
                  <p>"You have already done me greater honor than my merits deserve," replied our hero, as the Governor left the apartment.</p> 
                  <p>After an absence of a few moments he returned, bearing in his hand a magnificent Damascus sword, the hilt enriched by gold and precious stones. His daughter followed him, who was instantly introduced to the handsome young stranger. There was something in the countenance of the graceful Florencia, which sank deeper into the heart of Edward Duvalle, than its surpassing loveliness. Was it love? Had she, too, as well as the beautiful Fanny Floyd struck the chords of affection? or were the sensations which the sight of the Spanish maiden produced in his bosom, of a different, of a lofter, of a holier nature? There was a powerful feeling pervading his whole soul, of which he was conscious, but for which he could not account! His eyes were riveted upon the maiden with glowing intensity, nor did he remove them until the Governor again approached him, and broke the spell by which he seemed bound for many moments. Said His Excellency,</p> 
                  <p>"Allow me, my brave youth, to present you with this sword, in token of the great service you have rendered, not only the Spanish nation, but all the civilized commercial nations of the earth!"</p> 
                  <p>Our hero was so embarrassed by the presence of Dona Florencia, that he almost disregarded the words of the Governor. He received the magnificent present, in silence, when she came forward, and taking from her neck a massive gold<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC6934-00000039"/> chain, to which was appended a small gold cross, studded with diamonds, she wound it around his neck, and bade him wear it, as a testimonial of her esteem for the great service he had done her father.</p> 
                  <p>With a modest grace he bowed his head, while she bestowed the gift upon him, and placed his hand upon his heart in token of his gratitude, for he was too much overcome to utter a single sentence.</p> 
                  <p>Had custom permitted, he would have folded his arms about the beautiful creature, and pressed her to his bosom! Strange as it may appear, it was a pure and holy impulse that prompted the desire! What was it? We shall see anon.</p> 
                  <p>The audience now being at an end, Duvalle prepared to take his departure, not however before extending an invitation to the Governor, and to his family, if they desired it, to visit and examine the piratical craft. Just as Duvalle and the revenue officer were extending a parting salute, the door opened, and an English naval officer was announced, who entered the room abruptly and in great excitement. As Duvalle mistrusted that it was the commander of the frigate who had chased him, he tarried to make explanation if necessary.</p> 
                  <p>"Your Excellency will pardon me;" said he, "for my business is of an urgent nature. I am commander of his Britannic Majesty's frigate Thunderer, and have been for several days in chase of a piratical schooner, which is now moored in sight of your palace! I ask permission to take possession of her as a lawful prize, in the name of His Majesty, George Fourth!"</p> 
                  <p>"You forget, sir stranger, that this is a Spanish port," replied the Governor, calmly.</p> 
                  <p>"Nevertheless, and with all due respect to your Excellency, I claim her as the prize of the frigate Thunderer. She but last night escaped us and took refuge immediately under the guns of your castle!"</p> 
                  <p>"I cannot grant your request," said the Governor, with the utmost coolness; not liking the blustering airs of the Englishman.</p> 
                   
                  <p>"What, sir, do you positively deny my request?" said the British captain in menacing tones.</p> 
                  <p>"Most positively!"</p> 
                  <p>"And allow your port to become a place of refuge for every bloody corsair who desires to enter it?"</p> 
                  <p>"I know my duty and shall follow it."</p> 
                  <p>"And I know mine," added the Englishman, "and shall immediately forward despatches to my government giving information of this monstrous violation of the laws of nations."</p> 
                  <p>"You have my permission to do that, and also permission to leave my palace!" said the Governor, unable longer to restrain his indignation at the officer's blustering manner. "If you have any other business with me, let it be done through a substitute, who can demean himself with becoming propriety."</p> 
                  <p>"Your insolence is insufferable!" replied the Englishman, his face livid with rage.</p> 
                  <p>"Will you allow me to explain this matter?" asked Duvalle of the Governor, in a courteous and persuasive manner.</p> 
                  <p>"Certainly! I cannot refuse, as you are probably somewhat interested in this matter."</p> 
                  <p>"Do I address," said Duvalle, approaching the angry Englishman, "the first officer of a double banked English frigate, which for the few past days has been in pursuit of a small schooner, carrying ten guns and only eight men?"</p> 
                  <p>The officer looked upon the interrogator with surprise.</p> 
                  <p>"I have been in chase of a formidable pirate vessel," said he, "under the command of the noted Ringbold, and it is said that he has under him sixty men!"</p> 
                  <p>"And did your ship sustain the loss of a fore-top gallant-mast by a shot from the pirate!" again questioned Duvalle.</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, besides the frigate sustained considerable injury in the hull from the incessant and well directed fire of the schooner."</p> 
                  <p>"Indeed! I trust you lost no lives?"</p> 
                  <p>"Not a man," answered the Englishman, wondering at the inquisitiveness and knowledge of the handsome young stranger.</p> 
                  <pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC6934-00000040"/> 
                  <p>"It is well," answered Duvalle; "and now to prevent any difficulty between his Excellency, the Governor and yourself, I will confess that the schooner you speak of I have the honor to command."</p> 
                  <p>"You?" ejaculated the frigate's first officer.</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, you have deceived yourself in regard to the present character of the schooner. That she was once the vessel you believe is very true, but sir, owing to the good fortune and bravery of the crew and passengers of an American merchantman, mounting but two guns, the formidable pirate has been captured, and I have been commissioned to carry her into port."</p> 
                  <p>"Incredible!" exclaimed the Englishman.</p> 
                  <p>"Wonderful!" added the Governor, ironically, "that the schooner with only eight men, should have made a successful resistance, and afterwards succeeded in making her escape from His Britannic Majesty's frigate Thunderer, under the command of such a valorous officer."</p> 
                  <p>The Englishman felt the keenness of the Governor's remark, and without making a reply, he bit his lip, turned upon his heel and left the palace.</p> 
                  <p>"Stay one moment," said the Governor to our hero; "what, did you really engage with this chop-fallen braggadocia Englishman, and shoot away the frigate's fore-top gallant-mast?"</p> 
                  <p>"We did, your Excellency."</p> 
                  <p>"By San Iago! I like you better for that deed. Then the saucy fellow tried to capture a prize instead of a pirate?"</p> 
                  <p>"He did, your Excellency; but the fellow thought he was doing his King service."</p> 
                  <p>"Why did you wish to escape him?"</p> 
                  <p>"I feared that he might doubt me, and carry me into port," answered Duvalle. "At all events, I preferred rather to trust to the superior sailing qualities of the Vision, than to the doubtful clemency of one of these British ocean monarchs."</p> 
                  <p>"And you did well, my brave youth!" exclaimed the Governor. "I shall do myself the honor to visit your vessel this afternoon."</p> 
                   
                  <p>"The honor will give me great pleasure," replied our hero.</p> 
                  <p>"Shall I not accompany you, father?" asked Dona Florencia, who began to feel a greater interest in the stranger than could have been supposed at first sight.</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, my daughter."</p> 
                  <p>"And mother, too?"</p> 
                  <p>"If it be her pleasure."</p> 
                  <p>Duvalle again bidding them good morning, took his departure and repaired immediately on board of the Vision; and in anticipation of the Governor's visit, gave orders to have the beautiful craft put in the best possible trim, and to make reparation for the proper reception of their illustrious visitor.</p> 
                  <milestone n="--" unit="typography"/> 
                  <p>It was a lovely afternoon in the month of September, the sun was yet about two hours above the horizon, when the signal was given for the departure of the Governor from the quay. As if by magic, the beautiful clipper Vision was dressed in the flags of every commercial nation; and from her guns a salute was fired which made the welkin ring with their roar. The beautiful silken canopied barge of the Governor, propelled by twelve oarsmen, soon came along-side; and his Excellency, with his wife and daughter, was received with due courtesy by the young and gallant officer of the Vision, and escorted to the magnificently furnished cabin of the schooner, when the Governor introduced to him his wife, and the lovely Senorita, whom he had seen at the Palace, gracefully saluted him.</p> 
                  <p>The same impulses which had agitated our hero on first seeing Dona Florencia, now moved him as before, and on beholding the face of her mother, it was increased. He seemed confused beyond measure, and was at a loss how to act.</p> 
                  <p>Attributing the young officer's apparent bashfulness and confused manner to the presence of ladies, the Governor talked rapidly concerning the beauties of the vessel, of her remarkable capture, the richness of her cabin, and other matters for<pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC6934-00000041"/> the purpose of dispelling the embarrassment which so suddenly overcame him.</p> 
                  <p>Duvalle was not the only one who was moved by impulses, the cause of which they could not divine. The wife of His Excellency, on first beholding the form and features of our hero, gazed abstractedly upon him; her daughter, too, Dona Florencia, with an interest, amounting to admiration, watched his every movement. The Governor's affability and openness of manner, soon partially dispelled this unknown influence, and each recovering in a degree their wonted confidence, entered into conversation with increased animation.</p> 
                  <p>Duvalle gave the whole history of the capture of the pirate, and of the chase of the frigate, keeping himself, however, as the chief actor, far in the background. He then commenced showing them many valuable articles, which formerly belonged to the pirates; and among other things he took from the iron chest the casket of jewels, of which we have before spoken, and opening it before them displayed its riches.</p> 
                  <p>"<foreign xml:lang="SPA">Santa madre de Dios!</foreign>" exclaimed the Senora, extremely agitated; "what do I behold! Look! Do you not recognize these, Your Excellency," said she, directing his attention to the jewels.</p> 
                  <p>"<foreign xml:lang="SPA">San Diego!</foreign>" exclaimed he; "they look like the jewels that were--"</p> 
                  <p>"They are the same!" interrupted the Senora. "I pray you, Senor Duvalle, tell me; know you more of these jewels than the mere fact of their being taken from the pirates?"</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, madam; I know much; they nearly concern me."</p> 
                  <p>"Concern thee!" reiterated the Senora, "you name is--"</p> 
                  <p>"I am at present known by the name of Edward Duvalle," he interrupted. "Of my true name I am not positive, but I believe it to be San Malo."</p> 
                  <p>"And these jewels?" ejaculated the Governor regarding him with wonder.</p> 
                  <p>"Are mine! They were taken from me when a child; together with this chain and miniature," replied Duvalle, taking them from his neck and handing them to the Senora.</p> 
                   
                  <p>"He is! he is! my son! my long lost darling boy!" screamed the Senora, and fell overcome with joy into the arms of Duvalle.</p> 
                  <p>"My mother! my dear mother! I thank God that I have found thee at last!" exclaimed Edward. "And thee, too, my father! Oh, my God! can this be true? or am I dreaming?"</p> 
                  <p>"My son! my son!" added the Governor, "my brave-my noble boy! By what miracle have we found thee at last?"</p> 
                  <p>Dona Florencia stood regarding this scene amazed in perplexity and doubt. She had been told when a child that she would have had a little brother had he lived, and a faint reminiscence of that knowledge still lingered like a long remembered dream in her mind. That he should be still among the living was a miracle too wonderful for her comprehension; yet she had heard her parents' wild exclamation, had seen all that had passed, and she stood trembling like a leaf uncertain how to act.</p> 
                  <p>The first ebullition of joy having subsided, the elated youth encountered the fair Senorita, who stood before him, when His Excellency with joy exclaimed,</p> 
                  <p>"Florencia, your brother! Eustaquio, your sister!"</p> 
                  <p>"My dear sister!"</p> 
                  <p>"My dear brother!" were the only exclamations of the son and daughter, as they embraced and kissed each other with all the fervency of a holy passion.</p> 
                  <p>Mutual explanations were now entered into, and before the whole party had left the schooner for the palace, each was acquainted with the history of the other.</p> 
                  <p>Our hero accompanied his father and mother to the palace, and after remaining three weeks, enjoying more happiness each hour than he had experienced during his whole life, he told the Governor that he had made a promise to take the prize into Baltimore; and until he should fulfill it, there still remained something unaccomplished to complete his happiness.</p> 
                  <p>His Excellency reluctantly permitted him to depart; but out of regard to his safety, he despatched an armed brig after him with instructions to act as a convoy to the prize, without allowing<pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC6934-00000042"/> lowing his son to know it, and to remain in the port of Baltimore, until it was his pleasure to return, and then solicit him to take passage in the brig.</p> 
                  <p>In eleven days after the Vision sailed she had arrived in the harbor of Baltimore.-Her commander immediately reported himself to the owners of the Sparta, who were amazed at the contents of the despatches, nor could they realize the truth of them until they visited the prize in person. For several days our hero was toasted and lionized by those interested, and by the few to whom the whole affair had been known.</p> 
                  <p>The brig, which had been sent as a convoy to the prize, or rather to her young commander, although a tolerably fast sailer, was far outstripped by the schooner in their passage from Havana, and she was not reported in the harbor of Baltimore until eight days after the Vision had been moored before the city. The captain of the brig immediately reported himself to San Malo and informed him that the brig was subject to his orders.</p> 
                  <p>On the fifth day after the arrival of the convoy, our hero was rejoiced to see the Sparta moving majestically up the Chesapeake Bay. His impatience would not permit him to await her arrival to the anchorage ground, he therefore procured a boat, and was soon alongside the noble old ship, for which he had quite an affection. He was joyfully greeted by Captain Wingate, and by those who were on board at the time of the victory over the corsair. They narrated to each other a history of the incidents that had transpired since their parting-that of young San Malo is already in the possession of our readers; that of Captain Wingate's was marked by nothing particularly interesting except that Mr. Floyd and the beautiful Fanny had both unexpectedly returned, the former having partially recovered his health.</p> 
                  <p>It having reached the ears of Fanny Floyd that our young hero was actually on board of the ship, she adjusted the curls of her beautiful hair, and other trifling matters of the toilet, and made her appearance in the main cabin, from her state room, just as he entered from the deck. If possible she looked more blooming and beautiful than ever. They being together for a moment or two alone, it is not to be marvelled at, nor is it a matter at all reprehensible, that they rushed into each other's arms, and snatched from each other's lips the first kiss of love. There must, of course, in all these matters be a first time, and why not, very properly, on this occasion. It would have all done very well had they been satisfied with one embrace, or one kiss, but they, like all indiscreet lovers, repeated it, I know not how many times, until they were surprised, in the very act of kissing each other, by Mr. Floyd himself, who suddenly appeared in the cabin to the utter confusion of both.</p> 
                  <p>Mr. Floyd approached the young man, gave him his hand and evinced great pleasure in seeing him again.</p> 
                  <p>"Come here, you little minx," said he to his daughter, playfully. "I have observed enough to satisfy me; you love this noble youth, do you not? Now, you might as well confess it, and not blush so."</p> 
                  <p>"Why, papa, I--"</p> 
                  <p>"Come, come, no mincing the matter, you might as well out with it, frankly and boldly at once."</p> 
                  <p>"Well, papa, I suppose I must say-say-yes!"</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, you jade, you couldn't have said any thing else if you had tried-no, it would have choked you. And you love my daughter?" continued he, addressing the young man.</p> 
                  <p>"With all my heart!" he replied.</p> 
                  <p>"Spoken like a man!" said Mr. Floyd, as he took Fanny's hand and placed it in that of her lover's. There, take her. She is a good girl, and I have got a fortune in reserve for her. God bless you. May you ever be happy!"</p> 
                  <p>In two weeks after this scene on board of the Sparta, we noticed the following marriage in one of the papers:</p> 
                  <p>At St. Inigoes, Md., on the 24th inst., by Rev. Thomas ---, CARLOS EUSTAQUIO SAN MALO only son of the Governor of the Island of Cuba, to Miss FANNY MARIA, only daughter of Hon. Francis Floyd, of St. Inigoes.</p> 
                  <pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC6934-00000043"/> 
                  <p>Captain Wingate and the commander of the Spanish armed brig were the only guests present at the solemn ceremony of the marriage of his young friend, other than the near relatives of Floyd. In the course of a week after the marriage, the young bride and bridegroom embarked on board of the Spanish vessel which His Excellency had sent out as a convoy.</p> 
                  <p>There was great rejoicing on their arrival at Havana. The Governor gave a magnificent Levee in honor of the occasion, which was attended by many hundreds of the noble and aristocratic of the Island.</p> 
                  <p>The bloody pirate Ringbold, was tried, condemned and executed in the city of Baltimore, and his body was afterwards given up to the surgeons for dissection. We understand his skull can be seen at the Museum of that city, among the other "thousand and one" curiosities which are there on exhibition.</p> 
                  <p>Thus ends the romance of "HARRY TEMPEST, the Pirate's Protege;" and should any of our readers affect to disbelieve its main incidents, the author stands ready to substantiate them.</p> 
               </div> 
            </div> 
            <div type="part"> 
                
               <head>THE ROSE OF MATANZAS:</head> 
               <head type="sub">OR, DIABLETO, THE GULF PIRATE.</head> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER I.</head> 
                  <epigraph> 
                     <q>
                        <lg type="quotation"> 
                           <l>She sighs and smiles, the color comes and goes,</l> 
                           <l>While the eloquent language of Love</l> 
                           <l>From her ruby lips softly flows.</l> 
                           <l>From her eyes beams the exquisite feeling</l> 
                           <l>Of Love, which gently o'er her heart is stealing.</l> 
                        </lg>
                     </q> 
                  </epigraph> 
                  <p>AS the sun raised its resplendent face above the horizon on a spring morning in 1823, there might have been seen a fine barque-the Relief, of two hundred tons burthen gaily ploughing her way on the dancing waves, as she sped on her rapid course. It would have made an old tar's eyes glisten with pride and delight to view the finely modelled hull, her clean and tapering spars, her taught rig, and her white and trimly cut canvas, which stretched to the wind, caused her gaily adorned prow to dash through the rough waters like the mighty war-horse of yore amidst the surging tide of battle. She moved most gracefully upon old Neptune's cradle, and as she rose and fell, she seemed to look down with pride upon her symmetrical form reflected upon the blue waters below, as though conscious of her utility and beauty. Truly, there was utility and beauty and grace also combined in this elegant pieces of mechanism. Her decks, like those of all West Indiamen, were encumbered by a large caboose-house on deck, and a large disproportioned quarter deck, which answering also for cabin, was neatly furnished with every convenience.-The lumber which frequently litters our first class vessels, was absent, and everything gave positive evidence of cleanliness and discipline. Her standing rigging was set up taut, while the running was all tautly belayed, and neatly coiled upon its belaying pin. There was also placed at intervals along the well-cleaned deck those small tubs in which the old salts expectorated the<pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC6934-00000044"/> superfluity of saliva naturally collecting from the use of pig-tail tobacco. She had four six-pounders aboard, two of which poked their noses out for'ard, while the remaining twins were placed aft on the quarter-deck, to use only in case of emergency; for, at the time of which we write, some of the most daring freebooters scoured the sea, in defiance of the united navies of the United States, England and Spain.</p> 
                  <p>The Relief was from Matanzas, homeward-bound to New York. Her crew consisted of the master, first and second mates, and twelve fore-mastmen; there were also three passengers aboard, Mr. Markman, son and daughter; who were wealthy residents of Matanzas, about returning to New York, Mr. Markman's place of nativity.</p> 
                  <p>His son, a fine youth of eighteen, who delighted in the honored cognomen of Nelson, could boast of a very prepossessing countenance and an excellent education; his person was very slender and apparently delicate, almost to effeminacy.</p> 
                  <p>His sister, two years his junior, was endowed with the sweet appellation-Rosa, and I assure you, kind reader, the name was well applied; for in beauty she even excelled the blooming rose. When she addressed one, her silvery voice would thrill to the heart with that pleasing and exhilarating influence that one experiences while inhaling the balmy breeze of spring, laden with the odor of that delicate and most perfect emblem of nature's beauty. The most skilled and experienced sculptor could discover no fault in her delicate and graceful form. No! but he would gaze with pleasure-excessive pleasure, and mentally exclaim: "Truly, nature's sculptor excels the almost perfect skill of man," for she was the perfection of loveliness and beauty; her form, the gods might say, "this is our handiwork," and smile at the vain attempts of man to imitate this god-like nature. From her countenance shone forth the stamp of innocence, truth, and intelligence that might have set the most skilful slave of the palette musing, while he would cast from him his pencils in dismay; for then, and then only, would he become sensible of his inability to portray nature upon canvas. How interestingly beautiful she appeared, as she stood upon the quarter-deck, a light crape shawl of the finest texture thrown carelessly over her snowy shoulders, and confined about her graceful neck by her delicate hand; while her mild but expressive dark blue eyes gazing into the dreary depths of the water below, seemed to lend the brilliant hue it fain would steal. A smile playing upon the sweet face discovered the most pearl-like set of teeth that ever adorned the pouting, ruby lips of the fair sex; and her dark brown hair which, neatly separated upon her marble-like forehead, fell in luxurious clustering curls upon her shoulders and finely formed bust, gave her the most perfect likeness to the inconceivable beauty of an angel.</p> 
                  <p>I will now endeavor to describe another person who is destined to play a very conspicuous part in this sketch from life. This was Arthur Ashford, an athletic and finely built young man of nineteen or twenty years of age. He was not what we term handsome, but manliness was too plainly depicted upon his countenance not to be detected at a glance. He was habited in a sailor costume of the most costly materials; nor was there presumption in his assuming that garb, for he was acquainted with every particular of his profession, practically and theoretically; being the first mate of the Relief. Well might the men be proud of such an officer. He possessed a fine head, and a high commanding forehead; such a one that invariably impresses the beholder with the belief that there is no small quantity of brains encased therein. His nose was of an aquiline mould, that is, his intimations of relative and personal defence were perceptibly developed. His mouth gave token of courage, firmness of purpose, and pride; in short he possessed the physiognomy of a man; not the effeminate beauty of a woman. At the time when we introduce him to the reader's attention, he was standing about midway between the top and the bulwarks on the main shrouds; with one hand he firmly grasped the ratline, while in the other, which hung negligently down, reposed the glass. He had been aloft sweeping the horizon, a duty he never failed to perform at sunrise. And now he paused and gazed upon the sylph-like form of Rosa in silence-the silence of adoration.</p> 
                  <p>A smile of pleasure which slightly parted his lips, exposed to view his white and regular teeth.</p> 
                  <p>Arthur experienced excessive pleasure in contemplating this being so beautiful. In her he beheld all that his vivid and prolific imagination ever had created.</p> 
                  <p>"Oh!" murmured he, "what joy-what bliss would it be to exist forever within the hallowed circle of thy supernatural presence! with what untiring diligence could I toil for the maintenance and pleasure of so fair a being, so that I might exist within the charming influence of thy angelic smiles, and my heart drink in the celestial music of thy sweet voice! oh! it would be joy unknown, happiness unrivalled!" He felt at this moment that he loved-yes, even idolized that creature so artlessly beautiful.</p> 
                  <p>A cry of "Sail-ho!" in the gruff tones of the look-out at the mast-head, awoke him from his trance of pleasure, and Arthur was beside him in a moment bearing with levelled glass upon the distant object. He was hailed from the deck by the master in a peculiar squeaking tone, as follows:</p> 
                  <p>"How doth she stand, Mr. Ashford? what dost thou make of her?-Thou shouldst quickly speak, for verily my patience ill brooks so much procrastination."</p> 
                  <p>Arthur, still viewing her attentively through his glass, at length replied, much to the benefit of the master's placidity of temper: "It is a fore and aft topsail schooner, shaping her course about abaft the starboard beam, and bearing down directly for us." Then leaving instructions with the look-out to inform him when the vessel raised her hull, he descended to the quarter-deck and joined the master.</p> 
                  <pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC6934-00000045"/> 
                  <p>Now, it is necessary to inform the reader that the worthy master of the Relief was a quaker; one of those genuine, spirit-moving, corpulent-bodied, short-legged, peace-loving christians, one who, as though to show the distinction between mind and matter, was as long in deliberation and motion, as he was short and obese in person. He was subject to nervousness, too, and his system had sustained no little injury from the copious draughts of wine with which he was wont to refresh and strengthen his inner man; also was he inclined to the grievous sin of gluttony; he always endeavored to do justice to the get-at-tables that covered his inviting board. I wish the reader to understand that everything was get-at-able to our little master; a nod or a grunt at a desired article, and in a moment his attentive <hi rend="i"/>seneschal gave him a dish full. The commander was above the delicacy of changing plates, that was a useless waste of time that by no means suited him; for what cared he, all food went the same way; in short we feel sagely inclined to the opinion that our little master was a-a-a swine!</p> 
                  <p>"Well, Mr. Ashford," he inquired in a very anxious manner, his hands hanging down at full length, while, with his fingers interlaced, his thumbs performed a rotary motion, one around the other, "Mr. Ashton, what dost thou make of her? think'st thou her intentions are hostile, as may be inferred by her rapid course toward my peaceful craft? and <emph>dost</emph> thou suppose it can be a vessel of those lawless, ferocious Buccaneers?" The nervous master expended three gasping respirations in his effort to pronounce that terrible appellation; and then to disguise his weakness, he tremblingly caressed his double-decked chin, and endeavored to appear quite composed. But the effort was ineffectual. Arthur's quick eye instantly detected the subterfuge, and a smile for an instant illumined his placid countenance as he replied, "I can ascertain no more at present than that she is a fore and aft schooner; but it is my opinion that we shall have an opportunity, and that in a remarkably short period of time, too, of judging what she is, and what may be her object; for she brings a nine knot breeze with her and is overhauling us at a fine rate, as without difficulty you may perceive."</p> 
                  <p>"Thou speakest truly, Mr. Ashford, for already may'st thou observe her topsails looming over our starboard quarter; I fear she is an unlawful trader."</p> 
                  <p>"Most likely, Mr. Parker," replied Arthur coolly, "and in my opinion 'tis the most probable thing in the world, for I think I have seen her before; still, I do not see the necessity for alarm; as yet, we know not her character, nor intentions, and I am as liable to be in error as all men are; however, if my suspicions should prove correct, and she really be a pirate, (here the master's fear visibly augmented) why, sir, we have four guns aboard, and a large quantity of small arms; with them and our gallant crew, on whom I am confident we may rely, we'll be able to give them a warm reception; at least, we can sell our lives as dearly as possible, and as our passengers demand our protection as well as does the property intrusted to our care, we must defend them and it to the last, or we prove ourselves unworthy the position we now hold."</p> 
                  <p>"Verily, Mr. Ashford," exclaimed Mr. Parker in great trepidation, "thou art truly blood-thirsty! Thou dost, I perceive, exult in the fearful carnage of war, which verily is terrible for me to contemplate. Knowest thou not that I am <emph>not</emph> a man of blood, and that I hold not to the godless struggle of life for life? Dost thou comprehend, sir, that I place no trust in those terrific engines of heathenish warfare? No! for the sight of them doth chill the warm fluid coursing through my veins, and disturbs my nervous system amazingly. We should not think of those fearful weapons of devastation which God hath forbidden, but rather leave this fearful aspect behind; therefore I hold it meet that we clap on all sail aloft and alow, place our <emph>faith</emph> in God and our <emph>trust</emph> in a good pair of heels, and flee from this wicked companionship."</p> 
                  <p>As the little master delivered his heroic sentiments, the treadmill-motion of his thumbs increased in velocity, his eyes rolled up in their sockets until their sights were scarcely visible, and his head acquired a fidgety movement as though prepared to dodge the first shot.</p> 
                  <p>"But, Mr. Parker," urged Arthur, "should we not make preparations for the worst? We must struggle hard for life, if not for duty, and I do not think (should they take the barque) but that the narrow plank or the keen knife awaits us all. Consider, sir," he continued, smiling slily, "how unpleasant such proceedings would be to yourself-a man so very sensible to external impressions."</p> 
                  <p>The master's spirit moved him with a vigor, mentally and corporally, that was truly surprising.</p> 
                  <p>"Mr. Ashford," he said, sawing the air with his arms in an agitated manner, never before witnessed in him, "I am thy Captain, and by the authority invested in me, I command thee forthwith to make all sail without delay; I order that those reefs be shaken out of the topsails, and that skysails be sent aloft; also that studding-sails be rigged aloft and alow, and that we endeavor to show a clean wake instanter to those Buccaneers."</p> 
                  <p>"Immediately, sir," and turning away to give the orders, he encountered Rosa, who had been a silent spectator and overheard their whole conversation. This greatly depressed Arthur's buoyancy of spirit, for he feared that her delicate nature could scarce sustain the sanguinary warfare which he knew would ensue. She seemed to await an opportunity to address him; and it was between the delivery and execution of one of his commands, that the timid maid enquired:-"Is there any actual danger to be apprehended from our pursuers, Mr. Ashford? do not equivocate, I pray; I would have you speak frankly, and if it really exist, tell me its true extent." The fair girl paled as she spoke, and Arthur, stammering, answered; "Well-that is-I mean-well to be frank with you, Miss Markman, I am compelled to say that I know that they have no good intentions, in chasing us in that manner."</p> 
                  <p>"You know!" exclaimed Rosa, as a dread suspicion crossed her mind.</p> 
                  <pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC6934-00000046"/> 
                  <p>"Yes, Miss, I know them well, for I once had the honor of forming one of the--"</p> 
                  <p>"Mr. Ashford," she interrupted, turning deadly pale.</p> 
                  <p>"Excuse me, Miss Markman," returned the young man, his manner evidently confused; "it was involuntary on my part, I assure you, do not unjustly accuse me-even in thought. It was the height of folly for me to make such an uncalled-for assertion; I hope you will not allow your mind to dwell upon those unthinking words of mine, Miss-say you will not, and you'll relieve my mind greatly, you will indeed."</p> 
                  <p>His earnest manner aided by an honest fervor lifted a weight from his fair hearer's heart. "Why, Mr. Ashford," she said, smiling mischievously, "you really excite my suspicions; you will almost compel me to believe you are one of their confederates. 'Twill be necessary that you give me a full explanation at some future period, or I cannot, or will not be answerable for any hasty conclusion at which I may arrive. But pardon me, sir," she continued, the color once more fading from her cheeks, "can we not escape from our inhuman pursuers? The issue is fearful to dwell upon, should we not."</p> 
                  <p>"I will only say we must hope for the best, Miss Markman, and as the master wishes to get out of harm's way as soon as possible, we will endeavor to escape them; I would again like to request, Miss,"--he hesitated, "well, that you dismiss the recollection of the few hasty words a wandering mind gave utterance to; at some future time I pledge my word to clear up all doubt or suspicion, which this morning may have existed."</p> 
                  <p>At this moment the look-out hailed him according to instructions, informing him the schooner had now raised her hull. Arthur was soon aloft and had the craft in the field of his glass. He examined her long and then said, addressing the look-out, "It is just as I expected, Harry, there's an old friend of ours."</p> 
                  <p>"What say, sir? do you think as 'ow you knows her?"</p> 
                  <p>"Why Harry! is it possible you do not recognize that schooner? you must have certainly lost your eye-sight."</p> 
                  <p>"Can't be-oh, gammon-beg pardon, sir, but it can't be she! yes-no, it's impossible, yes it am she too, why who'd a thought it, sir? The worthy old salt was evidently perplexed, for he took off his tarpaulin, scratched his half bald pate, and gave other signs of surprise and astonishment.</p> 
                  <p>"I will have you relieved, Harry," coolly remarked Arthur as he prepared to descend, "I think we shall have a very disagreeable consort presently, who, if he does not fail in overhauling us, will give us some warm work for awhile. <emph>We</emph> know, Harry, that he is not one to mince matters."</p> 
                  <p>The Relief was standing on before a stiff sou'west breeze, with every stitch of canvas she could bear; but in comparison with her pursuer she was but a poor sailer, as was very evident, for the schooner soon raised her hull even on deck, quite destroying all prospect of escape. At two bells (nine o'clock) she-at the most extravagant calculation-could not be more than two miles distant. There was not now the least shadow of doubt concerning the nature of the schooner's character remaining in the minds of those on board the barque. Had there been, it would soon have been dispelled, for when within some two hundred fathoms, they discharged a swivel, rigged amidships, and at the same moment the black flag waved at her peak, a fearful potent of her bloody calling. Then came the iron messenger, rattling and crashing through the spars and hamper of the barque, parting in its lightning flight the sling of the main top-gallant yard, which came on deck with a run.</p> 
                  <p>All this intimated in a very marked manner that the barque must heave too, and that to without the slightest delay.</p> 
                  <p>The Master, Rosa and Arthur stood upon the quarter-deck. Each was deeply excited by the chase-but though the excitement was in every case produced by the same object, the sensations brought in play were widely different. For instance-although novel anxiety agitated the timid Rosa, to Arthur one of the ordinary phases of a brave sailor's life presented itself; and the prospect of coming strife gave it the zest it else would lack. But then the little master.-Truly, his spirit was moved, and he felt great fear for his personal safety. The color departed even from his beet-like nose, leaving his countenance quite livid. He fidgeted about, apparently feeling himself one too many on board the vessel; not knowing what to say or do, and giving vent to his miserable sensations in short and grunting sighs.</p> 
                  <p>Arthur observed this, and knowing the trepidation which pervaded his soul, generously resolved to free him from his not to be envied situation. Accordingly, following the bent of his inclination, he stepped up to him, and respectfully addressing him, said-</p> 
                  <p>"Would it not be advisable, sir, to hand Miss Markman into the cabin? This is hardly a suitable place for a female."</p> 
                  <p>"Verily, Mr. Ashford, thy question teems with judgment and discretion. Yea, thou speakest and actest like a man of mature years. And now thou shalt behold how quickly I will repair the error that thou, in the goodness of thy heart, hast reminded me of. And, Mr. Ashford, in my absence I leave the deck in thy charge; for, peradventure, I may linger awhile that I may appease the fears of Miss Markman, who, I perceive, labors under the weight of a great anxiety."</p> 
                  <p>He then very unceremoniously-to Rosa's great annoyance-seized the little hand and hurried her within the cabin; nor did he again appear until all sounds of strife were gone.</p> 
                  <p>"If I can be of any service, Mr. Ashford, you may command me," said a voice; and turning he beheld young Markman. "I desire to participate in this defence you are preparing to make. My family, in days of yore, were considered quite a race of fire-caters, and I wish to learn from experience if I have degenerated. I can use a sabre, sir, and if you have an article of that description aboard, I haven't the slightest doubt but that I can give some of those human fiends a practical proof of the fact."</p> 
                  <pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC6934-00000047"/> 
                  <p>"But you must remember, sir, that you have a father and sister who love you dearly."</p> 
                  <p>"I do, indeed, Mr. Ashford, and that fact will nerve me in the coming fray-so say no more, Mr. Ashford, for, God willing, and with your permission, I'll fight the good fight this self-same day."</p> 
                  <p>"You are a man, Mr. Markman," exclaimed Arthur, grasping his hand; "and forgive me if I offended by offering the remark I made. I misjudged your character, sir, but my intention was good, and merits pardon."</p> 
                  <p>"Say no more, Mr. Ashford. Let us now turn our attention to our enemies here. We will find sufficient to contend with without the disagreeable addition of feeling personal enmity upon our own deck."</p> 
                  <p>Arthur's hand-shake followed, and a friendship sprang up that lasted for ever after.</p> 
                  <p>"Now, my lads," cried Arthur to the assembled crew, "that schooner contains a band of pirates; you know their customs, and they have given us some evidence of their intentions. Now, men, if we do not repulse and drive off those rascally lubbers, before the sun sinks into the sea Johnny Shark has our bones for supper. Courage, then, and be active, and with the assistance of the invincible hand of God, which always helps the just cause, we may hope to overcome them."-Then turning to Harry, he continued:-"Distribute the weapons you find in the arm-chest among the crew, and then see that the guns be charged to the muzzle with grape, and throw into each a quantity of the copper nails you'll find in the carpenter's locker.-Away, sir! Now, lads!" and then followed the orders to shorten sail and heave to. Helm a-lee, and she brought to by the wind. "Down with the foretopmast staysail-haul up and furl foresail-hoist lower staysails-in with fore and main topsails," and she was hove to.</p> 
                  <p>The crew were then well armed with sabres, handspikes and pistols, and superior to all else with that armor of proof-courage. A stern resolution to defend the vessel to the last gained a place in the bosom of the hardy tars.</p> 
                  <p>Now Nelson appeared accompanied by his father; to which latter Arthur addressed many remonstrances. Vainly did he endeavor to withdraw him from the theatre of coming strife. The old gentleman firmly persisted in his determination of remaining, and at the same time begged him to desist and reserve his breath and fine words for a more fitting occasion.</p> 
                  <p>"All's ready, your honor," said Harry; and so it was. The larboard gun was placed beside its mate upon the starboard side, and the twins protruded their gaping muzzles over the quarter-rail. All silently awaited the approach of the schooner. One could read a determination depicted upon each weather-beaten visage, as each arm was raised and cutlass grasped by hands of living oak. With senses alive to the keenest power of perception, and an eye awake to the smallest incident, Arthur stood. He noticed upon the distant horizon a small white speck, which to him was an augury of promise. He observed too the rapid course of the schooner which carried on as though a few moments would mark the passage of its jib-boom through the bulwarks aft-and finally he noticed that the barque gently forged ahead-and when about twenty fathoms apart, he in a low voice said-"Lay the helm to port; so, so," which gave the advantage for which he waited. By this manuvre the Relief gained a raking position, and as the guns were brought to bear upon the schooner's deck the word was given to "fire!"</p> 
                  <p>Oh! that discharge was well directed; that is, if one might judge by the mingled cries and curses that arose from the pirate vessel, which returned the compliment by a ball from their swivel; this entered the bulwarks aft and laid one poor fellow low. Still the barque held steerage way and as, she broached to, a bow gun was brought to bear upon her opponent and showered its contents among her crew, with a fearful effect; instead, however, of repulsing, this warm reception seemed to increase the ferocity of the pirates. The little schooner's helm was laid hard to port as she gracefully rounded to, down came her fore and main-sails and jib, and the next instant her jib-boom interlocked with that of the barque.</p> 
                  <p>"Boarders away," yelled the pirate captain, as he led on a ferocious crew of desperadoes.</p> 
                  <p>"Stand by to repel boarders," cried Arthur in a clear distinct voice. He had anticipated this movement, and accordingly had mustered his entire force upon the forecastle. "Stand firm, my lads, and make every blow tell," then turning to the faithful Harry, he continued in a rapid tone, "run the larboard gun that isn't discharged just abaft the wounded yard," which still remained as it had fallen athwart ship, "and direct it for'ard, then leave it in charge of the mess-boy with directions to fire the moment I give the word, and not before, away."</p> 
                  <p>During this interval the pirates came pouring over the bulwarks forward like a pack of blood-hounds; but they were received with that cool courage characteristic of the yankee tar. Opposing their calm bravery to the headlong rush of bull-like desperation, Arthur and Nelson led on the small but hardy crew; then the combat became hand to hand.</p> 
                  <p>"The Lord have mercy on your souls," cried Arthur as he sent one of his opponents to overhaul his log and report both good and evil to the great master above.</p> 
                  <p>"I don't like to cheat the hangman, but here goes," shouted Nelson, and he clove a sturdy buccaneer to the chin.</p> 
                  <p>"Take that, you long-shanked, black-hearted abortion; and the world'll thank me for riddin' 'em of ye;" and Harry brought a gigantic pirate to the deck.</p> 
                  <p>The fight waxed warmer: every man was engaged with one or more; and some even with three, the sharp report of the pistols, the ringing clash of the sabres as blows were given and parried-the agonized shriek of pain-the grovelling curses of anger and anguish<pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC6934-00000048"/> -the yells of defiance and despair-the taunting bravadoes and energetic repartees-all mingled in one terrific din. It was life for life, no quarter asked or given, but each intent upon his opponent's destruction; oh! man, how degenerate is thy nature. How is it that thy heart becomes so void of all feeling-how is it that remorse does not visit thy inmost soul, and whisper mercy to sweet humanity? Oh! how is it possible that you can thus destroy the boon of life-murder thy fellow being without compunction or regret? Gradually the small crew began to waver and fall back, for the pirates were thrice their number, and fought with demoniac fury, at length the dauntless crew were separated in the centre and were hemmed in between the bulwarks and their merciless foe. Arthur, whose dripping sabre told of well done work, saw that for which he had waited had arrived. This undischarged gun, as we have stated, had been placed abaft the yard in a position to rake the deck forward. The pirates occupied the centre, and completely covered his men from the fiery tempest about to break. Now was the critical moment; "Ready there, fire!"</p> 
                  <p>Sickening was the sight that met the wild gaze of the combatants, as the drowsy smoke arose and showed the bloody carnage done. Loud was the shout, and smacking of triumph too, that rose from the yankee crew; and deep was the yell of despairing rage that the disappointed villains gave vent to as they commenced their retreat. As Arthur's men followed up their advantage, driving the invaders in wild confusion from the barque, Diableto (little devil), the pirate captain; was engaged with Nelson. Fortune appeared in favor of the latter, until a treacherous blow from behind laid him senseless upon the deck. A shrick resounded through the air, and the delicate form of Rosa interposed to shield her brother from the uplifted weapon. For a single moment he hesitated, and then with an unearthly smile, he rushed upon her. He stooped and rudely encircling her waist with his muscular arm commenced his retreat fighting at every step. In vain were weapons levelled-in vain did arms of steel attempt to slay him; for the inanimate form of Rosa shielded him from lead and iron, and he laughed with bitter scorn; the vessels separated and the girl was a captive. Mr. Markman was almost wild with despair and rage at beholding his dearly loved daughter torn from him by the human monster, and his valiant son lying apparently dead upon the deck.</p> 
                  <p>"Lost! lost to me forever;" cried the frantic old man, "Oh! God, give me strength to bear this fearful misfortune-this terrible calamity will lay my head with sorrow in the grave." He fell upon his kness and with extended hands implored the pirates to return his daughter, "miscreants, fiends, demons of blood, give me back my child. Oh! Almighty God, restrain the winds-dry up this great body of water that I may again embrace my child; even now I hear her call. Yes, Rosa child, I'm coming, dear, I'm coming."</p> 
                  <p>He would have leaped overboard had not Arthur with the assistance of several of the crew prevented him, and by exerting their strength to the utmost succeeded in securing him in the cabin. He was a maniac. But Nelson was not dead. No, he was to awake to a full realization of his dreadful loss.-His poor helpless sister carried off to suffer unknown torments, and perhaps, nay, most likely-degradation worse than death. It was horrid; the very thought almost maddened him; and then his brain-sick parent; Ah! Nelson, thine was a heavy burden.</p> 
                  <p>The schooner had hauled off and those who were watching her movements perceived an uncommon haste and bustle on board of her. It will be remembered that about the commencement of the action, a speck upon the horizon was a harbinger of hope to the attentive Arthur. Unobserved by all until now, the pirates discovered in this whilom speck, a sail; and hence the confusion so apparent; far they had no desire in the present condition of the vessel and crew to remain in the neighborhood of so dangerous and unwelcome a visitor. The stranger was now within four miles' distance from the scene of action. The schooner's huge sails filled to the wind and she stood off on the larboard tack.</p> 
                  <p>Arthur felt the loss of Rosa extremely, but still he was not one who submitted to the despotic sway of overpowering despair. No, for a bright ray of hope was within his heart that set the dark demon at defiance; and spoke of a means by which he might repair an error or retrive an unlooked-for loss. So it was with joy he beheld the approach of the sail, which his practised eye soon discovered was a brig of war, and his delight was unbounded when he contemplated the possibility of recovering the lost one through this medium.</p> 
                  <p>The little captain when he found the din of battle had subsided, made his appearance for the first time since he conducted the unfortunate maiden to the cabin.</p> 
                  <p>It was obvious from his demeanor that the stings of humiliation and shame assailed him, as he viewed the mutilated bodies of six of his own crew, and the huge piles of mangled human flesh that had been their opponents; thinking meanwhile of his dastardly conduct to that of the heroes dead. He stood with his eyes downcast, his thumbs rolling around each other; and the stifled grunt (his substitute for a sigh) told that the feeling of his littleness had penetrated to his inmost soul. Even the crew looked upon him with contempt, and had not the respect which they paid to his office prevailed, an open expression of disgust would have saluted him; a low murmur did indeed arise as he at length walked aft to muse upon the disagreeable situation in which his cowardice had placed him.</p> 
                  <p>Upon examination, the bodies of the two and twenty of the assaillants told of the determined resistance made by the crew during this short but sanguinary struggle. They were indiscriminately cast overboard, and with the exception of the six corpses of the noble defenders, for whom more ceremonious obsequies were intended, matters commenced to wear a more orderly appearance. The stars and stripes were changed union down, a signal of distress to attract the attention of the brig of war; which shortly after coming within<pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC6934-00000049"/> 
                     <unclear>hail,</unclear> a gruff voice from the main shrouds enquired the name and destination of the barque.</p> 
                  <p>A hasty statement off affairs, and the request for a supply of hands to replace the dead sailors, was the reply.</p> 
                  <p>"Immediately, sir," returned the same hoarse voice, as the brig tacked, and hove to. Soon after a twelve-oared cutter came alongside, and after a little delay, a young officer came tumbling up on deck, whom Arthur went forward to receive; they both started, and an expression of surprise and joy overspread their features; in a moment they were in each other's arms and in another they fell to shaking hands and clapping each other on the shoulder most energetically.</p> 
                  <p>"By Jove, Arthur, is this you?" exclaimed his visitor, "or is it some spectre conjured up by an over-heated imagination?" (Here he threw himself into a theatrical attitude.) "Why, my dear boy, I thought you were dead. How is it I find a passed middy of the United States Navy, upon the deck of an old tub of a West Indiaman like this? By Jove, my boy, I hope you are not a deserter in reality. Come, let's hear all about it, and if you really are a delinquent," (here he winked) "why--I'll go aboard the old brig again, and not a soul shall be the wiser, ay! not a word, though I should confoundedly hate to part with you again."</p> 
                  <p>"It is a long, yarn, Stuart, and we must not delay the brig a moment longer than is necessary; for the pirates have abducted a young lady from this vessel," (Stuart gave a prolonged whistle) "whom we must rescue at all hazards. See, that is her brother so bitterly upbraiding the captain for permitting her to leave the cabin."</p> 
                  <p>"Why; yes, by Jove, and now he is about to choke him. Why, the man is desperate, Arthur; and we must separate them, or he'll be the death of him."</p> 
                  <p>They both hurried to the assistance of the captain who was crying for help in a very unquaker-like manner. He was seized around the waist by Stuart, while Arthur stepped in between, loosening his vice-like grasp with which Nelson had almost choked the unfortunate man to death.</p> 
                  <p>"Mr. Markman! Mr. Markman! you must be bereft of your senses," said Arthur in an impressive tone, "to choke a man in that manner. I am sure you don't wish to murder him; and if you did, it would be no recompense for your loss. Be rational, my friend; think what you were about to do, and you will then see your folly."</p> 
                  <p>"But did not that livid-faced coward permit my sister to throw herself in the hands of that pirate? why did he not prevent her? tell me, you pusillanimous villain, why did you not prevent her?" and the desperate Nelson endeavored to break away and seize upon the trembling captain, who looked the perfect picture of despair.</p> 
                  <p>"Verily I could not," answered the little man as soon as he regained the power of speech.</p> 
                   
                  <p>"You could not!--could not; thing! Unhand me, Mr. Ashford, that I may crush his detestable carcass not fit for earth; oh! God, how can I sustain this stupendous bereavement! It will break my heart-it will crush my soul to the very dust, and make death a pleasure to be courted." As he paused his head fell upon Arthur's shoulder; and tears, the quintessence of sorrow drawn from his inmost heart, flowed from his gushing eyes. Indeed it is a solemn thing to see a man weep; for, generally the sterner sex have the power to mask all external show of sorrow even while it burns with a devouring fury within their breasts, like unto a choked and smothered volcano; he shows no sign visible to the eye, for his pride, his spirit, and sometimes the fear of ridicule forbid it; therefore it must be an utter loss of spirit-a prostration of pride, or an entire investment of his soul by recklessness and despair that can cause him to permit the burning tear to roll upon his cheek, and his heart to be agitated and troubled with depth of feeling. Thus it is grand and fearful to behold.</p> 
                  <p>"Despair not, Nelson," said Arthur in that kind persuasive manner which at once wins the heart and confidence of an auditor, "but weep on, it will relieve you of the weight of sorrow, my friend, which has accumulated. Still, lad, you need not quite despair, take courage, man, here comes your father whose eyes glisten with hope as he looks towards the brig which may afford a means to restore our-I mean your sister; so cheer up, for now is the time to act with determined resolution and activity. Come, be a man once more."</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, yes; your words inspire me with renewed hope," exclaimed Nelson energetically; "my strength seems revived, and I feel as though I could perform prodigies that might astonish even myself. Tell me what is to be done-how shall we proceed? be quick, for every moment now I value as a year of my life!"</p> 
                  <p>"Take your father and hasten below, select what articles you meet may need, and then return and make preparations to go on board the brig of war which will pursue the enemy, and with heaven's help you may soon clasp your sister in your arms."</p> 
                  <p>Without a word the father and son hastened below, and Arthur, turning to the captain, (who stood in speechless surprise listening to the proceedings,) remarked with a calm manner that he would tender his resignation, being compelled to return to his duty on board the brig, also that he claimed the discharge of Harry Hawser who belonged to the United States Navy, and was under his command.</p> 
                  <p>The captain raised his heavy eyes, and his thumbs twirled with unexampled rapidity as he replied; "Verily, Mr. Ashford, I suppose thy departure must take place. I marvel not now that thou didst display such courage, nor that thou didst so well understand the use of those destructive implements of war; for verily, thou art by profession a man of blood, and therefore, thy mind and heart are callous to all the tender feelings that form the core of my effeminate nature. Yes, Mr. Ashford, my consent is freely given, and thou<pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC6934-00000050"/> mayst go to any quarter of the globe thy thirst for blood may lead thee."</p> 
                  <p>"So this worthy nonpareil of a quaker, this unbeliever in the necessary spilling of blood, is your captain, hey? I am under the impression that one would have to cut pretty deep into that deep-sea carcass of his to find anything like blood," said Stuart with a boisterous laugh. "But come, my boys, if you are going to leave this valiant skipper alone in all his glory, and go aboard the brig to hunt up the pirates, you had better have your traps passed into the cutter as quickly as possible, for I see they are signalling for my immediate return."</p> 
                  <p>Shortly after, Mr. Markman, Nelson, Arthur and Harry, were seated in the cutter with their effects, and leaving sufficient men to assist in taking the bark to Portsmouth, and bidding those they left behind a hearty farewell, they gave way and soon reached the brig.</p> 
                  <p>Cheers from the crew, and a hasty welcome from the commander and officers, greeted Arthur upon his appearance. Mr. Markman and Nelson received the heartfelt sympathy so soothing to the anguish-stricken mind. They were also consoled by the reliable assurance of the commander that the lost one would be soon delivered from captivity, for that he intended to exert himself to the utmost to punish the ferocious buccaneers.</p> 
                  <p>Harry had to grin and bear the vice-like grip bestowed upon him by his warm-hearted mess-mates; after which some who were off duty hurried him between decks to hear a recital of Arthur's and his own adventures since they left the brig at Havana.</p> 
                  <p>The old salt felt happy as a king, as, seated between the two forward guns and surrounded by his old messmates, who were anxiously attentive, he commenced his narrative in the following style:</p> 
                  <p>"Well, messmates, ye remember that dark night we lay off Punto Castle at Havana? That dark night when I 'spose as how ye missed me and master Arthur?"</p> 
                  <p>"Aye! aye! we recollect it."</p> 
                  <p>"Well, do you see, there was a kinder of a plot in the horizon as hadn't yet risen to view between our skipper and master Arthur. It was all along o' that rakish schooner as hexcited our s'picions at Havana; do yer remember?"</p> 
                  <p>Another "aye, aye."</p> 
                  <p>"Well, do you see, our skipper thought as how she might be a pirate or a slaver, or some such thing, so to be sure on it he axed master Arthur as how he wouldn't like to go and find out whether things was all right or no. Of course ye all know what master Arthur would say-why "yes" to be sure.-The skipper then axed him if he wouldn't want some handy lad in whose courage and good sense he could trust. (Harry could pipe a little for himself occasionally.) Well, master Arthur in an off-hand way, said "yes," an' as how I was jest the lad he wanted, for he could trust me in any perzition he might be placed in. An' he was right there, mates! afore I know'd this he hove along side o' me, an' axed me if it might be pleasurable for me to desert with him. Ye might know, mates, that <emph>that</emph> took me all aback, being, as I said, green in the thing. So I told him as how I hadn't 'zactly thought o' sich a thing jist, but on the hull I didn't think as how I'd do it, no how-meaning no disrespect to him though. Then he kinder laughed an' took me by the flipper, an' said as how I was a brave, honest lad; an' then he up an' told me all about the plot. He said that our captain perticklarly 'quested me to accompany him; that we must swim to the schooner-make believe we were deserters, (that is, tell <emph>them</emph> so) an' then we could find out all about it, do you see?"</p> 
                  <p>This Harry delivered with emphasis, for he wanted all the points of the game to be plainly understood; and the old salts in the way of acknowledgment, gave their quids a significant turn in their capacious mouths, applied each a finger to the side of the nasal organ, and at the same time closing the larboard headlight, nodded sagely. This peculiarly mysterious diagnostic of comprehension having been performed with all due solemnity, Harry continued:-</p> 
                  <p>"Well, do ye see, we finished the 'rangements in this way, if she was a pirate or anything o' that sort, we were to sling our ducks aloft with a handkercher spliced to the legs of 'em; and if she wasn't, why all we had to do, was to tell the master what we came aboard for, and ax him for the loan of his yawl, an' go back to the brig agin.-Now that was all very well to talk about, mates, as ye'll see afore long. Well I agreed in course; an' master Arthur unshipped his uniform, an' shipped a pair o' my ducks.-Overboard we went, an' was soon alongside o' the schooner.</p> 
                  <p>"Hello, on deck there," said master Arthur in a loud whisper, "just throw us the bite of a line, will ye?"</p> 
                  <p>"Who are ye, an' what do ye want?" said one of the watch, sticking his head over the bulwarks.</p> 
                  <p>"We want the bite of a line now, maty, an' we'll tell you the rest when we get on deck;" I answered.</p> 
                  <p>"Heave 'em a line, my lad," spoke a somebody in the main rigging that we had'nt seen afore, I then began to think as how he might a see us go overboard, but the rope came an' we was on deck in a twinklin."</p> 
                  <p>"Who are you?" repeated the same voice from the main riggin'."</p> 
                  <p>"We are deserters from the man-o'-war brig layin' off your quarter; we were used so hard in her, that we thought as how we would desert-ship in some merchant-man or other an' do most anything for half pay, on'y keep their graplin' irons off us, an' our fare arterwards aint muck consekence," said master Arthur.</p> 
                  <p>"Well, my men, you've jest come aboard in time, for I'm jest goin' to weigh anchor an' foot off." I was taken all aback, an' had jest prepared my lips for a good long pipe, when a nudge from master Arthur's elbow came like a twenty-four pound shot against my ribs and cut it off short in the bud.</p> 
                  <p>"What are you whistlin' for, you lubber," says main-riggin' to me,<pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC6934-00000051"/> "Oh that's a tickler way o' saying he's glad;" says master Arthur, before I had time to ketch my wind agin."</p> 
                  <p>"But maybe he whistles when he aint glad," says he rather 'spiciously, "I guess I'll take a squint at that chap."</p> 
                  <p>"We're in for it, Harry, my lad," says master Arthur.</p> 
                  <p>"Keep a good heart an' never say die, says I. Well the long an' short of it, messmates, was, that they thought it reasonable to throw us in irons and stow us away below. Now that was kinder unpleasant, but howsomever, they did it, and there's no use sayin' how many hard words I made use of for the three blessed days we were stowed away. When we did come to daylight though we were far enough away from Havana. But it was the beautifullest place you ever laid your peepers on; we were in a little bay with banks kivered with fine green trees of all sorts, on which the birds were piping away at the rate o' twelve knots an hour. Polls jabbering and monkeys chattering,-oh, it 'ud a' done your heart good to 'a seen it, messmates, arter bein' stowed in a dark hole, as long as we had."</p> 
               </div> 
               <div type="chapter"> 
                  <head>CHAPTER II.</head> 
                  <p>"WELL, when we was brought afore the captain-yes, an' a bloody pirate captain he was too, mates, he wanted to know what he should do with us; he was considerin' some time, an' at last he says; "you thought you'd get to the windward of me my lads, but you didn't; but I'm willin' to forgive you all if you choose to jine with a hearty good will; if ye don't, why there's a plank or so aboard, an' I guess we might manage to rake up a few thirty-two pound shot.</p> 
                  <p>"This was all right, so to smooth all 'spicions we shipped ourselves, an' turned into bloody pirates. What do ye think o' that, mates?</p> 
                  <p>"Well, the captain seemed satisfied with this, an' said, we must do our duty like men an' fight like devils, all o' which we 'greed to an' then turned round to take a squint at the crew. They were the most savage set o' ruffians I ever seed; most all Spaniards and cooly Molattors, who looked as if they'd cut a throat for a glass of grog, any day, or Sunday either. Well, that day we broke bulk, for they'd made a good haul somewhere, an' master Arthur an' me was put in a long boat, that was brought from shore to carry the goods-silks, satins, laces, an' shawls of all kinds, to the store-house, as they called it, but bless ye we found as how this store-house was nothin' less an' a re'lar built fort. When we seed this, master Arthur sed to me; 'jest note this down in mem'ry's log book, Harry, for it may come useful arter this.' Well, we lay in the bay two days, an' at sunrise on the third we towed our schooner out through a small river that first run east-north-east, then sou west an' a little later due south. This river was a matter of a mile long, when all of a sudden we came smack on the ocean; we there dropped the line, went aboard, packed on all sail, an' soon left the little island far to the north-east. For about three days we cruised standin' towards sundown, an' it was early daylight on the fourth when we raised the port of Matanzas on our larboard bow; master an' I bein' in the mornin' watch; as near as I remember it was about two bells when master Arthur comes up to the side o' me an' in a low whisper says: "Now's our time, Harry my lad, we must make a heffort now or never; I've got a pocket compass, an' I've the bearin' of the port of Mantanzas, an' I've put a stout pair o' sculls in the yawl that's on the quarter davits; so all we've got to do is to stop the pipes of the rest of the watch and be off like winkin."</p> 
                  <p>"All right, says I, I'll stick by you till death.</p> 
                  <p>"Now, mates, do'ye see, there was two besides ourselves, an' the man at the helm too, so that we had to be right active like, about the silencen' of 'em; well, we went to work an' got some stout marlin an' a couple o' marlinspikes, an' then says master Arthur to me; "You go aft an' hengage the man at the wheel in conversation, an' when I whistles you must knock him down-clap your hanker-chief on his jawin' tackle-seize up his grapples behind him an' then belay all, then get ready the yawl an' wait till I come."</p> 
                  <p>"I done jest as he told me, went aft an' spoke to the man at the wheel, presently I heard the whistle so I right away knocked my man on the side o' the head, an' laid 'im hout for operation. I mighty soon had his grapplers seized up an' mouth stuffed full o' silk, an' presently master Arthur comes aft an' said he'd silenced the tother two beauties an' all was right. He then laid the helm to port till she headed nor-west when he lashed it amidships; then we launched the yawl-jumped in-cast off the tackle an' away we went for Matanzas, where we arrived after a hard pull of thirty hours.</p> 
                  <p>"Now if I should tell you how we waited at Mantanzas to hear from the brig, till we were tired-how master Arthur shipped on board of the Relief as first mate, an' I as able seaman-how we were four days out, when them diabolical cutthroats tackled us, an' how we drove 'em off, would not benefit the main yarn a bit; so all I've got to say is, that we didn't get none the worst o' the trip, an' that here I am all safe an' sound as the rock o' Giberaltar."</p> 
                  <p>"Tip us your flipper, mate," said an old tar, as he gave his indispensables a hitch up; "now that's what I call an adventure o' the brilliantest kind."</p> 
                  <p>Here the conversation ended abruptly.</p> 
                  <p>Arthur had appeared on the quarter-deck habited in a fine uniform, which improved his appearance greatly; and was now being questioned by the captain (Mr. Coleman,) in relation to the strong-hold of the pirates. The schooner was standing on with a fine S. S. E. breeze, distant about six miles from the brig, which was under a heavy press of canvas overhauling her fast.</p> 
                  <p>After coasting a considerable distance they entered the mouth of<pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC6934-00000052"/> quite a large river, where they found twelve fathoms of water, the tide of which was setting up; so they continued some two miles further and dropped anchor with sufficient room to swing with the tide.</p> 
                  <p>"We can proceed no farther with the brig, gentlemen," said the captain, addressing his officers who were assembled on the quarter deck. "The remainder is for boat-service. At bright dawn I propose sending away the three cutters to board and carry the schooner, and then destroy whatever other works they may have in their retreat. Mr. Justice, (the first lieutenant,) you will command the first cutter, Mr. Stewart the second, and Mr. Ashford the third. Now then, get your volunteers-arm and equip them well, for you will have tough work of it. Wait though until the men have break-fast, for it's hard fighting on an empty stomach."</p> 
                  <p>All being anxious to enter on the expedition, there was no lack of volunteers; and the only difficulty the officers experienced was the denial of the overpowering numbers desirous of accompanying them.</p> 
                  <p>After proceeding some distance up the intricate river, they were fired upon from a concealed battery. Arthur's plan of proceeding was formed in an instant. He landed his men a short distance below the battle's raging point, and scrambling over rugged declivities and through the tangled underwood that obstructed their way, they at last succeeded in reaching the scene of action, and a formidable one it was.-There were three fields-pieces planted upon a bank, in a position to rake the whole channel; but the fire was now directed entirely upon the first cutter, the crew of which was gallantly advancing to the attack in front. The pirates, fifteen in number, armed with sabres and muskets, were so intent upon the combat waged in their front, that their rear was left exposed and open to the attack of Arthur's valiant command.</p> 
                  <p>"My gallant lads," said the young officer, after he had arranged his men, "thus far you have behaved with unrivalled courage and discipline, and I thank you, one and all, as our countrymen, in fact, the whole world will when they hear of your exploits. We have now found the stronghold of these heartless renegades, which we must capture and destroy. I say we <emph>must,</emph> for if we do not subdue them now our previous efforts go for naught, for they will still be at liberty to rove the waters, to plunder, burn or murder, just as their vicious inclinations may dictate; and should not this fact be sufficient, there is another reason that should appeal to your chivalry and the most refined feelings of your natures. There is a fine young lady, an admired and esteemed resident of Matanzas, who is now their prisoner. She pleads for succor to each manly heart. Need I say more, my gallant men? No. Then be each man a hero, and receive the thanks of her friend, her brother, and her weeping father."</p> 
                  <p>"Yes, an hundred dollars to the man who returns me dear Rosa," shouted Nelson, highly excited.</p> 
                  <p>Then the fight commenced with the utmost courage and even fury on both sides. Victory for some time was doubtful, but at length the pirates were discomfited and fled, and Rosa was saved by Arthur himself who tore her from a burning building which the pirates in their vengeance had fired.</p> 
                  <p>The result is easily told. Rosa and Arthur well knew their own love for each other, and at Rosa's request, her lover made known his love to her father and asked his permission to wed his daughter. The old gentleman hesitated. Arthur was but a passed midshipman, and he thought him unable to support a wife. At length it was arranged thus. Arthur should remain in the navy until he had attained the rank of Post Captain, when he might claim his pretty bride. To be sure this measure appeared an enormous procrastination to the enamored twain, but as the decision was irrevocable, they concluded to make a virtue of necessity and endeavor to live through it.</p> 
                  <p>In the remarkable space of four years, Arthur by his zealous exertions and the powerful influence of Captain Coleman, was enabled to read his commission upon the quarter-deck of a fine frigate; soon after which he resigned. In the mean time Rosa's beauty had increased, and in possession of his lovely bride, and the consummation of his ambition being attained, he felt that his cup of happiness was full to over-flowing.</p> 
                  <p>On the night of their nuptials, another couple who had acted as bridesmaid and groomsman entered into the holy state of matrimony.</p> 
                  <p>These were Nelson Markman and Isabel Ashford; who becoming acquainted with each other's excellent qualities, made the necessary preparations, and caused a double wedding to be celebrated.</p> 
                  <p>Harry Hawser acted as chief gunner at the time of Arthur's resignation, but it was the last time he acted in that capacity. He was attached to, and longed for, the society of his young commander, and to reward his fidelity Arthur caused to be built for him a splendid yacht. And many a time and oft, with a sparkling eye has he doffed his tarpaulin to receive the two fair brides and their loving husbands on board the gay craft--The Rose of Matanzas.</p> 
                  <p>The Relief with her little captain arrived safely in New York harbor where he surrendered the command of said vessel on the plea of age and nervous debility. Soon after the poor man sank to rest, upon the softest portion of a chair, before a table loaded with the choicest viands, at his own fine residence. He rested in peace surrounded by his neat quaker family, were no fearful Buccaneers could destroy the equilibrium of his nervous system, nor compel him to cooperate in the "Godless struggle of life for life."</p> 
                  <p>Captain Coleman, and Lieutenants Justice and Stuart attained eminence and distinction in the service of their country.</p> 
                  <p>And now, kind reader, hoping the disposal of the characters may meet with just approval, and also that you have succeeded in whiling away a pleasant hour, I take, I hope, your friendly hand a warm adieu</p> 
               </div> 
               <closer>THE END.</closer> 
            </div> 
         </div>
      </body> 
      <back> 
         <div type="advertisement"> 
            <pb n="104 (Advertisement) " xml:id="VAC6934-00000053"/> 
            <head type="sub">HARRY HAZEL'S NEW SEA STORY.</head> 
            <head>RED KING, THE CORSAIR CHIEFTAIN.</head> 
            <head type="sub">A ROMANCE OF THE OCEAN.</head> 
            <p>
               <figure> </figure>
            </p> 
            <p>BY HARRY HAZEL, AUTHOR OF "YANKEES IN JAPAN," "YANKEE JACK," "THREE PIRATES," "GALLANT TOM," ETC.</p> 
            <p>One of the best Sea Stories that have appeared since the days of Cooper and Marryatt. Tales of the sea always engross the attention of the reader. Everybody feels interested in the wild, reckless, yet often generous career of the sea rover. Harry Hazel will add fresh leaves to his laurels by this story, which is beautifully illustrated.</p> 
            <p>NEW YORK: H. LONG &amp; BROTHER, 121 NASSAU STREET.</p> 
            <p>PRICE 25 CENTS.</p> 
            <list> 
               <head>Just published, the following Sea Tales:</head> 
               <item>THE THREE PIRATES. By Harry Hazel. Illustrated Price 25 cts.</item> 
               <item>BEN BRACE, or The Life of a Sailor. Illustrated 50 cts.</item> 
               <item>ADVENTURES OF PAUL PERIWINKLE. Illustrated 50 cts.</item> 
               <item>JACK ARIEL, of Life on board an East Indiaman 25 cts.</item> 
               <item>GALLANT TOM, or The Perils of the Ocean 25 cts.</item> 
               <item>FLYING DUTCHMAN, a Mysterious Tale of the Sea. Illustrated 25 cts.</item> 
               <item>SYLVIA SEABURY, or Yankees in Japan. Illustrated 25 cts.</item> 
            </list> 
         </div> 
      </back> 
   </text>
</TEI>