<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6540">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >Christmas at Under-Tor </title>
            <author >Gordon, Clarence.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC6540</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >Christmas at Under-Tor</title>
                  <author >Gordon, Clarence.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >47 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >Mohun Ebbs &amp; Hough</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1864">1864</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-05-04">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text >
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Christmas at Under-Tor</head>
            <p> 
               <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6540-00000001"/>  CHRISTMAS AT UNDER-TOR. An American Christmas Story. NEW YORK: MOHUN, EBBS &amp; HOUGH, BOOKSELLERS, PUBLISHERS, AND IMPORTERS, 189 BROADWAY. 1864.    <pb n="" xml:id="VAC6540-00000002"/>  Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1864, by MOHUN, EBBS &amp; HOUGH, in the Clelk's Office of the District Court of the United States for the Southern District of New York. POLHEMUS.&amp; DEVRIES, PRINTERS, No. 66 Courtlandt street,'N. Y.    CHRISTMAS AT UNDER-TOR. CHAPTER I. ONCEr upon a time-near the Christmas Time, the 22d December, 1S6--I sat in my studio, up four flights of stairs, next to the roof of a building in New York. The big northern window gave plenty of light to a canvas, but no view or amusement to a dreamer or idler. And just then- between four and five P. 3I.-wasD no time to work, and moreover, I was rather low-spirited and dreamy. The hard coal fire had smouldered down to white ashes, and the- gray-shod twilight settled like a fog through the window, outlining, in indistinct dreariness, stilt-like easels, unfilled frames, half-finished pictures; the three-legged stool supporting a palette, a cold pipe, its ashes emptied beside it, and the draped lay-figure with its outstretched arm. Altogether, my surroundings were not conducive to cheerfulness; and yet I enjoyed it in that style in which the age of twenty-four likes to make itself poetically dark and comfortably miserable. So I shut the door leading into the bedroom, put a blanket about my shoulders, filled and lighted the meerschaum that had now had an hour's rest, threw myself into the rocking-chair, and mounting my feet on the elephantine-legged table, felt-splendidly mor- bid and reveristic. There was a brown church spire to be seen, its weathercock swinging north and south, east and west, in a very excitable mazed state over the gusty wind. There was a roof, too, as foreground, a precipitous, soot-    <pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC6540-00000003"/> I .4 dyed roof, where I once knew two pigeons, of a soft spring morning, to light and coo-now it was swept and rattling in the December gale, and the spits of smoke from its tall gaunt chimney were dashed and whirled here and there by the reckless frolicsomeness of the young winter evening; for background, there was a slaty merciless sky. Those features composed my pleasant prospect, but I enjoyed it grimly, trying desperately to believe myself a poor unap- preciated genius in a garret, recalling all the sad hopeless verses I had ever heard or read, and chewing, with appre- ciation, the only real cud of bitterness or disappointment my life had ever known--the fact that a cramped and somewhat deformed left hand disabled me from an active part in the war. Giving play to what a certain philosophical young lady of my acquaintance, from Boston, would call the sympathy of nature in mysterious elective affinity with the different molecules of matter in the gathering storm and deepening twilight, I had to forget the reality of my being a very lucky young man, with health, strength, good looks, no knowledge of want, and with a neat little for- tune in perspective; with a good education, friends, a pro- fession which I loved, and a mother most dear- "But these are luxuries of woe Jove's banquet could not move." We know how children, with all the warmth and glory of a summer day about them, delight to find a dark crevice in the rocks, and there, in contrast to sunshine and laugh- ter, imagine themselves hiding from brigands, or lost and starving in a terrible cave; and that strange contrariness of youth reproduces itself again and again after childhood. We ofttimes see those to whom the world is the kindest and brightest, loving to imagine and seek out its shadows. But let me leave myself for a few moments in the dark- ening room and thick tobacco smoke, and lowering fancies,   and accidental nap perhaps, while we unloose a string or two that might hinder the clear unrolling of this little nar- rative. My father had been dead four years. He left five chil- dren, and a fortune of between fifty and sixty thousand dollars to each of us; but providing in this odd manner for us three boys-that we should not receive the inheri- tance until thirty-five years of age each. We had all been educated liberally; we had been permitted to make our own choice of a profession; but from the moment of entering upon the practice of the vocation chosen, we re- ceived nothing from my father while he lived, nor from the property in trust after his death, until each might reach the age of thirty-five, except an annuity of five hundred dol- lars during the intervening time. The payments of the inheritances finally were so conditioned (and the strict exe- cution of these conditions was most strenuously provided for) that-to 'take my own case as an example of all-I could only receive the entire amount of sixty thousand dol- lars in case I had never drawn the annuity, and provided also that I could solemnly swear that my total indebted- ness, legal or illegal, formal or understood, did not exceed fifty dollars. For every year the annuity had been drawn, three thousand were to be deducted from the property; and if my indebtedness should exceed fifty dollars I would forfeit the entire amount. Wise and charitable provision was made for the disposal of the amount or amounts forfeited. What, you may ask, were the reasons for such peculiar disposition of an inheritance? Simply these: My father wished us to start in the world with a generous education and an honorable name-those he had given us-and then he wished us to make our way by our own independent in- dustry and talent. He wished our years of youth and en- terprise to be free from the coils of wealth and idleness.  <pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC6540-00000004"/> 6 Time was given in which to show that we deserved suc- cess; and then, in proportion as we had proved ability to do by our own independent efforts, in the same proportion should we be rewarded. The deed setting aside these properties in trust, had been made when my eldest brother Harry, who had followed the sea from the age of twenty-one, entered on his profession- my father allowing his choice, opposing it neither with arguments nor commands; but insisting upon the post- ponement of its adoption as a business and means of livelihood until his twenty-first year, and until he had been educated in the most thorough manner, mentally and phy- sically, for the career of a sailor. Of him, much to my mother's grief and anxiety, nothing had been heard in nearly three years' time. My brother George had wished to be a soldier; so, after his education at West Point, he had been made a brevet second lieutenant at twenty-one. He was the second son, and had been in service now ten years. In the late fight at --- he had been painfully wounded and had won a majority. We were expecting him to be soon released from hospital and on furlough. Next in male order was the artist, who, from the necessity of the story, was obliged to intrude himself first on the stage. I had come of age the year my father died, but had only, at the date of these events, been settled in my pro- fession a short time, as at my father's wish I had passed two years of study at Rome. We all launched on the busi- ness of life, knowing our father's provision and hopes for the future: carefully too had that father's counsel and ad- vice striven to prepare us for its temptations and dangers. Indeed he had always been to us our closest and dearest friend. His abhorrence of debt--that tempter to extrava- gance-that fetter on the limbs of advancement-was writ- ten up before us in the most important clause of the instru- ment providing for our future. My dear mother lived in   7 the city with my married sister Emily. My sister Ade- laide, the pet of the family, was just entering her twentieth year, and a more beautiful girl I had never yet seen. I suppose that I did fall asleep, for when I heard a step on the stairs I was conscious that my room was as dark as Egypt; that my pipe lad fallen from my hand, and that I felt very bewildered generally, and wanted to rub my eyes, which I did, besides stretching myself and knocking something off the table as my feet were kicked out. The steps kept on their way towards my floor. How those great bare stairs would creak on a cold night! The tin roof opposite was still rattling, and the wind continued its blowing and wailing; not exactly in a melancholy tone, but as if it was bound on a desperate sort of a make-mis- chief spree; as if it would like to lift off a roof, or clatter a chimney down in a rataplan of bricks, or tear off a sign and leave it face down in the nud, or whisk off the breeches Holmes once sang of. No, not that either. It was after something more serious; say-split a mainsail, or capsize a schooner. Singing, while it tore about, "What care I for life? I love destruction-strife. Get out of the way- phew-whoop! Hurray! What a gay bender. Hi! Jolly December!" There were no rooms beyond mine, and yet the steps came on. Rap-rap. "Oh, dash it, I don't know where the matches are, but come in. Come in!"The door opened: a low, pleasant laugh: "Why, Earnest, my dear fellow, are you in this very thick blackness, and can't find a match? Wait-I think I can furnish one." "Uncle Minot, is that you?"-as I rushed for his hand, and skinned my shin on a chair-"Thunder! Why, Uncle Minot, how did you ever discover this den of mine?" Colonel Minot was striking a wax light on the door- panel. When he had given it to me to find my lamp with,    <pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6540-00000005"/> he took my disengaged hand in both of his with the kindly grip of real warm affection. "Well, my young artist, things here have a Bohemian aspect. In a more cheerful light, no doubt, the disorder would be picturesque.-No, Earnest, I cannot take a chair, for I have but a moment to stop. I dined with your mother and Mr. and Mrs. Blaire, and from them I learned how to find your quarters. Your motler, and Emily and her husband, and little Bessy have promised to return to Under-Tor with me in the morning. So my visit to town is but a short one, having only come down this afternoon; and my sole object is to make up a large family party to take Christmas cheer with me, and I depend upon you, Earnest, as one of my lieutenants. You must bring up our clergyman cousin, Stuyvesant, and his wife, and your sweet second-cousin, Lucy, the governess. The Holmeses can probably spare her at holiday time. You had better get Oscar Mare, too-the relationship is not very close, but it ought to be, for he is a fine young man. I tell you that one who, with those crippled limbs, has preserved a dispo- sition so sweet, and advanced, too, so rapidly in his pro- fession, has good metal in him-the very best. Adelaide, my sweetheart niece, must come under your wing, too. Then George-but I had forgotten, in my haste, to tell you that he arrived at Emily's just as I was coming out with a fortnight's furlough in which to recruit strength. George will conle up with Eben Hardie. George is rather fond of mly friend Eben's daughter, is lie not? Hardly a fair question to put to you, eh? Well, he ought to prove irresistible with his arm in a sling. Mr. Hardie will also bring the two pretty Misses Rodman. Earnest, you would like to be in that party. Ha! ha! No matter, my dear boy, you can be with Miss Titine all the time atUnder-Tor; but is it Miss Titine or Miss Fanny? The Rodmans are not even connected with our family, but they are so inti-   9 mate with Alice Hardie, anc are such fine girls themselves, that I thought you would not object to their being of the party. Am I unmerciful to you to-night? Never mind, nephew, we will make it up at Under-Tor. John Hardie may get from Cambridge in time to come up with thein, and then you may have a rival." I was so delighted with the prospect of such a jolly time that I did not interrupt Uncle Minot's programme, but I grew somlewhat uneasy when he insinuated that I was-that I was-well, I mean when lie expressed that I more than admired( Miss Titine. However, I turned it off with a Taugh, and told him what a splendid Christ- mas time he was arranging for us. "Is that snow on your coat, uncle?  Yes?  Well that's fine. Do you think there will be sleighiing before the 25th, for as sure as there is I sliall take up my party in a sleigh." Yes, I think we are in for anl old-fashioned Christlnas -cold, snow, sleigh-bells, crackling fires, &amp;c. &amp;c.; but I must be off now, for I want to take tea with the Hardies, and arrange how tlhat brigade shall be brought to the field." "Wait one moment, uncle, for me to slip on my coat. I would like to walk along with you. I want to run round to Mr. Blaire's and welcome George, and have a cup of tea, too, with motler and Emily." Colonel Minot was my mother's brother. Ite was a hale and handsome old ge: tleman of over seventy years of age, but cheerful-spirited, and as active as a boy. Dur- inlg nearly thirty years lie served in the army ; for one period of six years being superintendent at West Point. He had resigned twenty-five years ago, and since then lived on his farm in Rockland county. His possessions there included also some rich tracts of iron ore, for which reason he had started, just as the war commenced, furnaces  <pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6540-00000006"/> 10 and foundries, and was now turning out some of the best cannon furnished to the government. He was a bachelor, and my grandmother--a bright, sweet old lady of nearly ninety five-presided over his household. That ititle-" perfect gentleman "-which should be the preeminent distinction, ennobling supremely among men the union, as rare as beautiful, of spotless honor, noble breeding, wholesome education, and a great and charitable heart-has become such a cant term, such a suit of jargon to be fitted, by every one who cannot understand it, on every one they would approve or flatter, that I hesitate in thereby binding together the lofty qualities of my uncle's character: manners so sweet and easy, yet full of dignity; nobleness of mind and simplicity of heart; honor so beau- tiful, guarded so reverently; and the setting-blending these virtues harmoniously and confirming thenm-the prac- tice of a brave, cheerful, charitable Christian life. They say no man of character lives without enemies. Uncle Minot's were very few. Many friendships of the 1" auld lang syne" were not, of course, surviving about a seventy-third year; but those who could call themselves his fiiends, mentioned him always with an affection like that some- times pleasantly existing between ingenuous and warmly attached youths-speaking thus to or of hiln "My dear colonel ; " "Give my love to Colonel Minot." As we stepped into the street, I took my uncle's arm, and a!; the pace necessary such a cold night we were soon crossing Madison square, the snow flurrying about, and the gas-lamps twinkling like stars through the winter veil. "What a pity," said Uncle Minot, " we cannot have Harry with us at Under-Tor. I have no fear that serious harm has come to him, for out of each of his countless ad- ventures heretofore he has managed to get some honor or profit. I have great faith in that nephew. What a brave   " act that of his very first voyage before the mast, when he volunteered with only three others to save the poor fellows on the foundering "Ocean Queen," and he did it-did what his captain said he himself would Hever have dared to attempt. The next year, when the yellow fever killed all the officers and half the crew of the California barque, laden with specie, he, by knowledge of navigation and un- daunted energy, took the vessel safely into Liverpool; and did not the merchants give him a testimonial, and the owners make him mate and quarter owner of their new ship, the ' Vestris?' When she was burned at the wharf in San Francisco, and he was out of place for a time, you remember, Earnest, he took a whale boat, and with  Lieutenant Manare, cf the navy, and some seamen, made a practical survey of all the north coast of California. For that and the valuable discovery of' the fine harbor of Trinity Bay, the Navy Department sent him a letter of thanks. There was his shipwreck and bondage to those black savages of the Dutch government, off the east coast of Africa; he turned that to account too. Oh, I tell you that Harry is a brother for you to be proud of. He'll turn up all right in a few months, depend upon it. Where was his last letter written?" "At Madeira, sir; but that is three years ago, or it will be three years in August next. He was waiting for some ship which he did not name." "He is knocking about somewhere, cheerily enough, be assured. I want to hear, Earnest, how you are getting along this first year working on your own account." "Well enough, uncle. You saw the picture I painted in Rome, that I called ' A scene of '48?' It hung in the Academy this fall, and was sold to Mr. Bertrari for one hundred and seventy dollars. And the little sketch you liked, of the black nurse and blonde child, a Boston lady bought, offering me sixty dollars for it-much more than I would    <pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6540-00000007"/> 12 have asked. And I have been illustrating for the Har- pers lately; they pay well and the work is light. So, as my expenses are small, I intend to hire a pair of spank- ing horses, and drive up to Under-Tor in style, if there is sleighing." Why, my boy, that is thirty-five miles. However, you know the road. Get the best team you can find, Ear- nest, and let the bill come to me. Not a word Here we must part. I shall turn up Sixteenth street to Mr. Har- die's. Remember to be at Under-Tor with full ranks to- morrow evening or the next morning. I want you fresh for Christmas eve. Good night!" "Good night, and a Merry Christmas to you!" He had gone some distance from me when I shouted out the "Merry Christmas." The intervenifng flo cks of little white imps seemed to catch the hearty words, and toss them about in gusts and spirals of fun and welcome.   13 CHAPTER    II. THE wind retired before the patience and gentleness of the snow-flakes. Large and small, drops and crystals, the innumerable white army of heaven came on in muffled march to earth. A peaceful army; an army robed in white, to preach of home joys, and fireside circles, and love and charity; covering with those robes the rugged- ness and homeliness of the winter world; adorning skeleton-like boughs with grace; leaf-stripped hedges and jagged fences with pleasant outlines; the humblest un- painted cottage with cosiness and beauty-as if to say to man, "Do thou likewise-let your hearts give charity to cover the faults of others and your own discontent. Let love come and make more beautiful parents, friends, and little ones." At some of the German watering-places, you awake in the morning to the softened tones of an orchestra playing sa- cred airs-wake gradually and deliciously, as if floating out from a dark cavern on a beautiful stream, sunny, rippling; wake not as metaphysics tells us we arouse to noises- because the soul, alarmed, calls up the senses to make in- quiry of the cause. But wake because the soul is enjoy- ing, and the senses-sympathizing at first unconsciously- kindle slowly to the full happiness of the soul. So always seem the mornings whenl the first snows are fall- ing. The usual discordant noises are all hushed, and in their place is a pleasant muffled movement-like a very distant rustling of leaves-a hollow gentle murmur. The senses emerge from their oblivion to a sensation of delight, and then we look out on the infinitude of beautiful, chang- ing, floating atoms, and the work they are accomplishing so delicately-the fairy-like transformation of what was be- fore dull and forbidding to what is brilliant, soft, and pure; and we lie motionless to catch the whispered sounds-the    <pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6540-00000008"/> " indistinct poetry-th-at soughing of an unvoiced song-as if nature was humming to herself in happiness. It was nearly three o'clock in the afternoon when-after the tedious winding through crowded streets-we sat in our sleigh on the Hoboken ferry-boat. I suppose sisters, however sweet, must be true to the womanly articles. Faithful at least to that one, "always keep people wait- ing," Adelaide had delayed our departure two hours. The ladies took that opportunity on the boat to settle their hoops and tuck their furs snugly about them. My reverend cousin, Stuyvesant, and I, on the driving seat, looked over the snow-crested wheelhouses at the gray, velvety surface of the river-the rugged Palisades, edging it in brown outline above, and below a forest of fiosted -masts puffing tughoats; the smooth, flat islands with their fortress crowns. The horses impatiently swung their necks, jingling in jerks the full strings of bells. We were ashore, soon past the Elysian Fields, ice- cream and oyster saloons, an the pretentious villas of Ho- boken-all the countrfywrapped in snow. "Ger-lang, step out colts." Jingling with such evident merriment to the movement, the bells (I had taken care to secure plenty of them,) brought appreciative curves of sympathy about every mnouth. So plainly was it expressed as we instinct- ively glanced at one another, there was no need to speak it all at once-"How nice!" Mrs.! Grayson, Stuyvesant's wife, Cousin Daisy (a name j she had won in infancy) we all called her, asked, after we had all enjoyed in silence for awhile the delightfully soothing motion! and sounds, "When will we get to Under-Tor?" "Between eight and nine, probably," I answered. "Sleighing" said Oscar Mare, who  sat behind with the ladies, his crippled limbs requiring the warm of the many robes there, "is like first love. The quick, dreamlike advance to the musical jingle of   15 pleasant sounds-tender words and flatteries; the com- mon-place realities of the world silenced and forgotten in the new element. Folded in the warmth and plenteous. ness of the ' grande passion,' the happy ones recline in Cupid's car, which, like our sleigh, noiselessly wears tracks in the hitherto unfurrowed, unsullied expanse, that the thaw of after wisdom, or tears, or a succession of flirta- tions-the sun, rain, or following vehicles-finally oblite- rate." "What pretty nonsense," laughed Mrs. Grayson, " don't some first loves end in matrimony?" Hers had-and she looked up tenderly at her dear reverend, but the impres- sive blue eyes only met the back of his turned-up fur col- lar. ' So do some sleigh rides," answered Oscar. "But," continued Mrs. Grayson, " true love never runs smooth." "Mrs. Grayson," replied Oscar, " first love is not always true love; and moreover, are sleigh rides always without adventure, and who know what obstacles await this?" Oh," said Adelaitle, " to think that I should have for- gotten it until now! Whom do you think Uncle Minot took up with him besides those he expected?" We could not imagine. "Gulie Clifford!" "Gulie Clifford! our Georgia cousin!" we all exclaimed, and then came a heavy rain of feminine questions-how she got North; why she came North; did you see her; how did she look; etc., etc. The information surprised me into hitting the near horse a lick when there was no neces- sity for it, and Stuyvesant turned round in most unru- brical astonishment for a high church-man. *' Well, please don't pull the furs entirely off me," said Adelaide, " and I will tell you all about it. For the benefit of Lucy and Oscar, to wholm Gulie's further remove of relationship may occasion bewilderment, I will explain that Aunt Isabella, mother's only sister, married Mr. Grantley Clifford,    <pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6540-00000009"/> 16 a rice planter in Georgia, and that all her children were brought up and educated there, except for a period when their father was Charg6 at Vienna; but the year Guilie came out, her parents traveled north with her to spend the summer; that was five years ago, and the summer be- fore Aunt Isabella died. They stayed at our house for a week-a sort of return for the splendid winter George and Earnest once enjoyed on their plantation." "Yes it was," I added, " one of the pleasantest times in my life. Her brothers, too, were noble fellows, and with Gulie I was terribly smitten then." "Well, three of those brothers, Gulie says, are now in the Southern army, and the fourth, Horace, was killed at the first Bull Run battle. Edwin, a captain of cavalry, was badly wounded in a skirmish, and brought a prisoner to Washington-that was in October. Gulie soon heard of his misfortune, but in an exaggerated way-that his wound was mortal-and with characteristic energy determined to try to reach him. She got the necessary passes and arrived at Washington, and there received permission to be with him; that girl, only nineteen, nursed her brother amid all the horrid surroundings of a hospital, and through his ex- cessive suffering. Two weeks ago he was exchanged and sent south, but the authorities could not allow any females to go until they were sending a large party by flag of truce, which will not -e until the first week in January. In this dilemna, alone and her money nearly expended, Gulie, who had in the excitement and occupation before forgotten to write to mother, wrote a touching letter, and arrived at Emily's last night, a few hours after her messenger. You may imagine how warmly she was welcomed, although a rebel, and how beautifully kind Uncle Minot was, when he met her this morning. He prevailed upon her to pass Christmas With us at Under-Tor, where as Uncle said,   17 her Federal relations might have an opportunity of hold- ing as prisoner a real rebel.'" "Is she pretty?" asked Lucy, our poor relative, the governess. Pretty! Why, Lucy, she is perfectly beautiful." "Look here, soldiers" said Stuyvesant, " there are to be no more rebel victories." We sped on, chatting and laughing, and at one time Os- car Mare sang a beautifil little thing he called Hans Andersen's "Winter Song." At about half-after-four, the sun, ruddy after its Decem- ber day's work, shone in patches through a bunch of low cedars in the west. Its red rays skimmel across the white spread fields-glistened in the frost drops on the bushes and trees, and flashed on the small windows of an old Dutch farm-house on our right, as if they weie plates of burnished metals. The three cows lowing in the barn- yard had their red coats polished in the glow, and the fowls, seeking a roost on the boughs beneath the house eaves, cackled "good-night" as the last streaks shot to them and disappeared. Some miles ahead appeared a part of the Tappan Zee. Above, streaks of gray clouds fleeced the fading sky. It had been thawing for hours, but now, quickly, at the night's signal, it grew cold-cold and colder fast. A crust formed on the snow's surface, which the sleigh parted with a gentle crunching noise. Night settled fast, and now the roads in some places were entirely unbroken. "Come steeds, walk up this hill, and then settle to your work. Come, Hi-up!" It was very dark, or would have been but for the snow. In that, the innumerable silver spangling above had its reflection. Otherwise there was only the occasional pass- ing glimmer from a farm-house. A dog here, and another miles off, gave melancholy mouth to the electric atmos- 2    <pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6540-00000010"/> 18 phere. The wintry country night was bitterly cold, and magically undefined in starlight and snow. Behind, they talked and laughed, taking no account of time. At length I missed the rzad. That was not told to Stuyvesant until I was sure of having regained it. Notwithstanding furs and merriment, the cold made entrance, and growing dis- comfort found expression in embarrassing questions. At length, I had to confess that the roads had grown very heavy, and therefore the horses had to be humored; that we had at one time missed the way ; and finally, that it was eight o'clock, and those lights to the northeast were in Nyack. I did not know whether Upper or Lower Nyack; but we ought to have passed both two hours ago. The effects of my confession were dispiriting to the sur- prised aiid somewhat alarmed ladies. On we went for another hour, our progress slower and slower; the horses tired ; the roads worse; and I not sure of the direction. The full extent of the cold Stuyvesant and I felt, and we had to change the reins every few min- utes. Behild, the fun had subsided, except Oscar's, who fed the drooping spirits with courageous witticisns, and snatches of song; but the ladies muttered speculations and occasional complaints. Could it be possible?-as by the match with which Stuyvesant and I lighted our ci- gars, we saw my watch--ten o'clock! Stuyvesant," I whispered, " we are in for an adventure sure enough. I don't know exactly where we are, and the horses are about used up-; and tlen I ami fiozen, ain't you?' He turned and boldly told the party our situation, trying to make it out as a jolly good joke. The ladies did not ap- preciate it, except little Lucy. She did not say much, but evidently thought it a most delightful experience of roman- tic reality. Adelaide and Mrs. Grayson were really alarmed, and I am pretty sure that, as we drove on again, I heard l I   19 Cousin Daisy repeating parts of Eastman's "Snow Storm :" "But cold and dead by the sunken log, Are they who came from the town." We pushed on for another half-hour, which seemed a whole night time, and then pulled up before a farm-house, in which the inmates were a long while under blankets. A rascally cur screeched and yelped at us. That, how- ever, and our united voices calling for about ten min- utes, aroused some one, for we heard a sash fiostily resist lifting, and a male nlight-mare full voice say, "What in the devil do you want?" Stuyvesant asked, in a voice as if he were reading the collect, for the necessary information, and we learned that we were twelve miles from our desti- nation, and four from the nearest village. The window dropped with a bang, but a word reached -me, too, some- thing like " jam," or " slam," or " ram." On we strllggled, with what expressions of confort and cleer we could find for the ladies. "Look here, Stuyvesant," said Oscar; by Mrs. Gray- son's permission, we shall have to pitch you out in the snow. Sailors hate to sail with a clergyman on board. What is a sleigh but a land-ship, and you but our Jonah? The interior of a white whale snow-drift would, for the glory of Trinity Church missions, preserve you, I am sure, for three days--sty until the twenty-sixth of Decenmber, and then give you up to clay roads and a brisk walk." "Ho! Halloo!" sang out Stuyvesant in alarm, " where in the mischief are you driving, Earnest? Here we are over the runners in a drift." The fact is, I had my eyes on a dark, irregular building just ahead, and I was trying to make out if it was a poor- house or a jail. We had to get out of this position, how- ever. "Gee-up-I tell you ger-lang!" and I cut the horses with the whip. A jump and a crash! A whiffle-    <pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6540-00000011"/> 20 tree broken! A dainty little shriek chorus, and there we were.  Scene: Indistinct snow-drifts-a jagged fence-a dark low, looming building. Time : Eleven o'clock, of a biting cold winter night. Characters: Three ladies and three gentlemen. Anxious to avoid the reproaches and consler- nation of my charge, I handed the reins to Stuyvesant, and jumping from the sleigh, started to make a reconnois- sance of the cause of our accident, which I hoped might also prove a sielter in our extremity. It was evi- dently not inhabited. The second story had been destroyed by fire. The charred boards and beamls hung over the lower story. I tried the door, whose step was an im- mense mill-stone. I had to lift to open it, for it hung by but one hinge. My matches quickly showed me the inte- rior of a mill; wheels, belts, and grain-bins; and I heard the stream which had once urged it, rushing beneath. Another door opened into a medium-sized room, which had apparently been used as a store-rooml for grainl but whichl must lhave been originally intended for the miller's family, for there, to gladden my eyes, was a large open fire-place. Something more was necessary. I hurried out and went around the building. Piled against one side were several cords of wood, and there-an out-house large enough to shelter mny poor horses. I picked up the bro- ken boards and splinters that lay in it, and then loading myself with sticks from the wood-pile, hurried with them to that altar of our night's comfort-the great fire-place. The only paper I had was Halrper's Weekly, and that with a Christmas sketch in it which I had preserved for my little niece. Nevertheless it must go. As I stooped to arrange the fire, I heard my disconsolate party calling from the sleigh. I answered by holding a match to the kindling. In a moment a red, sportive flame shot up. As I ran to the sleigh, I turned to see the windows of our ark illu-   21 minated in welcome. Oscar's lame legs would serve him but poorly in the untramlpled snow. As I wanted him to assist immediately at the mill, I bid him get on my back- in that way had wte made many a Saturday's excursion in our boarding-school days-and tellinll Stuyvesant to make up all the sleigh-cusions and robes in bundles, and to get the ladies ready to move, I trotted off again to the mill. "Now, Oscar," said I, putting him down in the bright wood-lighted room, " keep that fire roaring; Stuyvesant will bring in wood enoughl: and above all tlings, strain your wit to keep the ladies up to brave, good spirits." Hardly had I finished speaking, before Stuyvesant's brigade mnarched in. All! how their faces changed (as they saw the crackling fire--snapping, fizzirng, anll blazing-- throwing rays and sliadows on the lheavy beams and joists overhead, and making silvery threadls of manly an ancient spider's home. Yes, the rosy cheeks and lips were now set off by smiles and eyes sparkling with appreitation of the comfortable scene. In a imomeniit, with the quickness of feminine enthusiasm, tlhey were turnling boxes and barrels into seats, and voting the dventure " splendid." Stuyve- sant hlad gone out for an armful of wood, and as I left them--for I had determined to take one of the horses and seek for a house where I might find provisions for both man and beast-six pretty feet were toasting before the fire, and Oscar's humor was finding a deliglited audience. The most tired horse I unhlarnessed and lut into the out- house. On the other dI started at a brisk trot up the cold, dark road. When I had gone about three-quarters of a mile, I descried a light ahead. Yes, some one was up, for when somewhat nearer to the house, I saw the figure of a man walking up and down a room. He heard my approach, too, and came to the window, and, seeing ime stop, came out to the door. I told him of our accident,    <pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6540-00000012"/> 22 and that I was in want of feed for my horses, and whatever I could get to make a meal or two for my party. "Why, that's my mill, stranger, and you are durned wel- come to its shelter. Got the old chimney going, too, eh? That's good. Women folks putty cold, I guess. That ar mill cotched fire last month, and I haint used it sence. Fact is, I sot up thinking, as I smoked my pipe, when I could get the old place going, and now, by jingo, it's let for a 'otel. Ha! ha! Oh, yes, I guess I can help you some i Come around to the barn and hqlp yourself fol the horses." He got a lantern, and when we reached the barn he gave me an immense bag to stow hay and feed in. And then my new acquaintance said, "Hitch your horse there and come in. The old woman has gone to bed, but I guess we can stir up something to eat." So he did: a couple of pumpkin pies, a loaf of bread, a saucer of but- ter, and a slice of cheese. These he packed in a basket, chatting with me all the while as if we were old friends, adding, at my suggestion, some plates, cups, knives and steel forks; doing it all just as if it was a matter of course that I should come along at midnight under those circuin- stances, and that he should do his best to oblige me. Ah, he was an old trump! He promised, as I rode off after my successful forage, to bring us a roast turkey and some cof- fee for breakfast. It took me but a few minutes to get back to the mill. The horses were soon comfortably fixed for the night, and then I entered our hotel, where the laughter was sounding merrily. Two shawls, hung from the centre beam, parti- tioned off a ladies' room. They were draped up now and showed couches of cushions and furs. An improvised plank table was the chief article of furniture in the gen- tleman's apartments. The elegant starch-box and barrel easy-chairs and fauteuils were occupied about the fire. My arrival, loaded with provisions, was enthusiastically   23 greeted. I had a bottle of whiskey in my valise. We pre- vailed upon the ladies to take some of that, warm, in place of the tea they missed, and now I very much doubt whe- ther V6ry or Delmonico could furnish a meal that would be attended with more real good humor and merriment than that supper at midnighllt in the deserted mill. The Rev. Stuyvesant Grayson came out splendidly, quite eclipsing Oscar for a time. A true devoted Christian cler- gyman, when he is a natural man, always shines in crises like that. They appreciate, with a keener zest thant lay- men, real harmless, sinless pleasures of this world, and at such times, off among fiiendls-equal and respected-free from the formalities and requirements of their flocks, .they are delightful companions, pure in merriment and spark- ling in their relish. An earnest clergyman I always think as necessary an element at a pic-nic or gcntlemans dinner party as lemon in a toddy-adding flavor while it imper- ceptibly takes the cloy from the suglar and the fire from the spirits. After our jolly little meal the ladies dropped their wall, and we thereafter only heard their whispers. Our blankets were limited, but we could lie near the fire, which had to be ftd all night. And that was done faitlhfully, though we all got good shares of quiet comfort-full slumber. I woke in the morning to the sound of the mill-stream flowing coldly beneath us, and to the trill of a sweet laugh behind the partition of shawls. Stuyvesant was out already; but Oscar lay coiled up in a second sleep, with the additional comfort of the robe our companion had deserted. I heard the outside door creaking, and hurried out. There stood my friend of last night, true to his promise, with a basket of eatables, and in one hatld a tin wash-basin and a kettle. "A bright morning to you, sir. My old woman thought of several things your women folks might want. There '*     <pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6540-00000013"/> 24 war'nt much in the house, but she did just as good for you as she could," said the good Samaritan, putting down his load. ' And I have rigged up a new whiffle-tree for you. Lord! that'un was kind-er smashed. By gorry, I guess you didn't know that our snow drifts is hindersome like. Ha," shooting off a laugh like a delighted pistol, and then wiping his mouth with a sweep of the back of his hand, "and I have seen, too, that your horses are fed and all comfolrtable." Well, my friend," said I, "( are there many mien like you in this country, for if there are I would like to settle among you." That speech set hin off into a file-filring sort of laughing, that promised to shoot any remnant of bad luck straggling about that mill. I got my whiskey bottle and a couple of cups before he had recovered himself, and begged him to take a drop with me, which he did. "Thank you, sir," said he, smacking his lips. 'Thunder, that is good.  Well, to-morrow is Christmnas, so I wish you and your party a tremendous 'Merry Christmas.'" In an hour more we were stowed in the sleigh again, and on our way. Our commissary and mill-owner thought that tenh dollars greatly overpaid him for his trouble and contributions, but we forced it on him. The night's ex- perience had not given a cold to any of the party. In- deed, the ladies seemed fresh and radiant-yes, Tadiant as the young morning sun that silvered the whole country. Some little snow-birds hopped along the fences and tweetered a low response to our sleigh-bells. The scene was beauti- fully exhilarating, and the sleighing now grew excellent, so that in less than an hour we were climbing up the south side of the mountain range, which sweeps down to the river, half a dozen miles north of Rockland Lake. And as we reached the top-the funnel mouth of the des- cending Clove-how brilliant and inspiriting was the pic- ture below us! The fi'ozen river, from the feet of the piled-   25 up mountains near West Point, dotted here and there by a few skaters, looking like ants on white sugar, thp cedar- clothed land spears, like Stony Point, piercing the river course now and then.  A few more quickly traveled miles, and we were trotting up the avenue of Under-Tor. There, right before us, was that architectural embodilllnt  of hospitality-my Uncle Minot's house-large, cheerful, straggling, shlleltering, many and diverse its lines and angles, sulnny surfaces anld shadowing gables rightly pro- portioned, and its visage venerable and full of protection. Dear comfortable old Under-Tor! And hearing the sing- ing, jingling, increasing bells, Colonel Minot, tall and erect, the silver hair blowing about his head, comes to the door, smilingl affliction and cordiality, to bid us "Weicome to Under-Tor."     <pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6540-00000014"/> 26 CHAPTER III. "But when the bare and wintry woods we see, What then so cheerful as the holly tree?"'-SOUTTIEY. ALL through the day there were silky rustlings on the great stairs and through the hall, and a rattling of balls in the billiard-room. A committee of ladies was adorning the lower part of the house in Christmas dress, and the gentle- men were trying to keep out of the way and yet amuse themselves. Having made my toilet, and gotten a bite of a second breakfast, I was on my way to the billiard-room, where John Hardie and George awaited me, when I came face to face with a female figure coming from a side hall-the rebel cousini Gulie Clifford was tall, and ler figure perfect-having the agreeable plumpness which tall women generally lack. Her complexion was a clear tlhin olive; one of those deli- cate envelopes of sensitiveness and susceptibility, beneath which the blood courses visibly at every word or thought; taste and kindly humor, charmingly lined beauty of mouth; the large tender steady black eyes, shaded by long cur- ling brown lashes, were full of expression; head and fea- tures no sculptor could surpass; her soft brown hair was gathered to a comb behind, and then fell in ringlets on her neck. High-spirited, high-bred, with a manner so full ef style, courage, and graceful gentleness, she would have been admired with plain features and ordinary figure; without any charms of person, her voice alone would have made her attractive. As it was, she was beautiful, very beautiful. In admiration I stood before her motionless. For fully half a minute I remained staring with apparent rudeness, obstructing the passage and not saying a word. Uncon-   '27 sciously, perhaps, I felt as if I had the right to gaze so at a cousin I had not seen in many years; but the fact was, that an arrow of instantaneous love in that moment pierced through my heart. Like a lightning bolt, it seared across my Past, making it as nothing now in my eyes, and con- suming to dust former fancies or passions. Guhe had not recognized me: she had waited, thinking that this apparent stranger had, perhaps, been sent with some message to the ladies busy' on Christmas wreaths and adornments. She was one of those, but as I uttered not a word, she attempt- ed to pass on. That movement brought me to my senses, but my words came as if I were emerging fromn a long dive. "Why, Cousin Gulie, do you not remember me, Earnest Grayson?" Her face lighted with surprise and pleasure, and she gave ime her hand. "Are you really Cousin Earnest? Yes, I see it now: how glad Igam, yet how strange it seems, when I think that when we knew each other before, it was on the dear old plantation-you a boy and I a little girl in short dresses. I have been look- ing for you since yesterday afternoon, when uncle thought you would arrive, but, although expecting you, I never would have known you, so much have you changed. Earnest, that shadow can go again, for I nmeant it as a coln- pliment." All that time her hand lay in mine. As she withdrew it, I turned and walked with her to the foot of thie stairs, and stood talking with her there until John Hardie, cue in hand, almost ran us down. "Ah! Miss Gulie, making acquaintance with another cousin? I don't wonder that Earnest forgot his appointment with me at twelve : it is now one." We parted until dinner, when all of uncle's guests did not appear. The ladies of my party were lying down, so as to dismiss the fatigues of last night and be fresh for Christmas Eve. The sweet old lady of ninety-five sat at tie head of the table. On my Uncle Minot's left was little    <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6540-00000015"/> 1;      28 Bessy, the great grand-daughter. Nearly a century divided the extremes of our family party. During the afternoon, most of the gentlemen were nap- ping, but I wandered about in the hope of meeting Cousin Gulie, but in vain. Every footstep was a disappointment. Sunset came. On the soft cushioned seat of the library win- dow, I watched the pale pitlk regrets it left fade from the sky, anrd enjoyed the soft vagueness twilighu lent to the white-clothed country, until I fell asleep, only waking in time to dress for the evening. When I came down stairs again, the house was brilliantly lighted, and there hung in vines, wreaths, and festools everywhere, beautiful combinations of ivy, Christmas gi;ejn, red belqiies, and laurel. The wainscoting and heavy carv- ing, all in walnut, in the immense hall--the house had been built in many respects, to repeat the features of my grandmother's home before her marriage, in England- drank up greedily the warm light flashing froml the pile of hickory logs blazing in the great fire-place. The grotesque heads sculptured in walnut over the fire seemed, in the flickering of the flames, to be grinnilng heartily at the pre- paratio's for Christmas Eve. Only six or eight paintings Colonel Minot possessed; those were glorious ones. They all hung in the hall. One-the only one whose history and artist's name was not known-which always greatly impressed me, and, I believe, sowed the first artist seed in my mind, represented an improviscatore sitting on the stone border of a fountain. It was the graceful figure of a hand- some boy of sixteen. The right leg, the foot of which rested dn the left knee, supported the guitar. A short cloak was thrown back froml the shoulders, displaying the arms, wlhich held the instrument with evident tenderness. The inspired expression of the upturned face was most beautiful--so sad, so lost to everything but his theme, and so \vonderfully had the artist rendered the act of sing-   29 ing, that, really, when you first beheld the picture, you waited to hear the song. There was mnore poetry than in a dozen of B1urns's songs, and more music than many a con- cert evening could give. That painting hung over the fire-place. In one of the heavy old-fashioned sofas drawn beside the fire, sat my mother, Colonel Minot, and my niece Bessy. Bessy was standing on his knee, smoothing and plaiting her grand-uncle's white hair. As I stopped and sat down by my mother for a few minutes, I heard little Bessie ask, "Gran' uncle, vy did 'oll never get ma-yied?" The ques- tion struck me, for it had never occurred to me before, and evidently affected Colonel Minot; but he kissed Bessy and told her that little children's questiomns could not always be answered, and so lie would tell, her a story instead. George was walking up and dowln the hall with Alice Hardli and Titine Berg. I joined them, and we went all together into the parlors. At a glance I saw that Cousin Guhe was not there. Fanny Berg and Adelaide, who both sang well, were, with the assistance of Mr. Blaire and John Htardie, and with Oscar Mare at the piano, giving an improvised opera. Oscar played wlhatever lie pleased, and its success depended greatly on the variations from one to another musical style, and also upon hi^ manner of rendering the airs. For instancc, just, hen, nodding his head at Adelaide (the singers standing in d(ifferent parts of the room, but watch- ing the orchestra, and ready at his sign to take any part), he played "I1 Segretto," to which Adelaidee sang "Old Mother Hubbard, she went to the cupboard."  At the last word "c none," Oscar cried, "All, chorus!" and to the same air they adapted the word "none" under all pos- sible conditions as a chorus. At the close of that, Oscar played a dirge-like movement, interrupted by the rolling    <pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6540-00000016"/> 30 of thunder, which was produced by Mr. Blaire, who at proper intervals drew his hand across the strings and sounding-board. At a nod to John Hardie, the dirge and thunder-storm disappeared in a tragic rendering of "Oh, poor Robinson Crusoe." Pushing on Mr. Blaire, in the Lady Macheth style, to the garroting or some other ill usage of "Senior Robinson Crusoe," John Hardie, his hair on end and his knees knocking together all the while, urged the unwilling tool, "Don Blairo," to make short work of the poor victim, supposed to be sleeping some- where in the back parlor. But, at the chorus-when Oscar would make the air intensely lively-the assassins forgot their dark intentions, -nd immediately commenced dancing to and from each other in the Chinese fashion, with bent knees and upraised thumbs. So the nonsense went on, perfectly ridiculous, yet for that reason, and be- cause it was done with such spirit, it provoked shouts of laughter from the audience, composed of my dear old grandmother, down whose cheeks the mirthful tears ran, the Rev. Stuyvesant and Daisy, Lucy Estwood and Mr. Eben Hardie. But in a few moments I was again in eager search for Cousin Gulie. In the library, where was no light but that of the coal fire, I heard her voice and sister Emily's. There were two " libraries," so called, to the house at Under-Tor. This one, which was a library but also a general " sitting-room," and another, called "Colonel Mi- not'sl library," into which latter room none then in the house, except my uncle, my grandmother, and nother, had ever entered. It was one of the few fancies my uncle indulged in, to have a place sacred to himself, his papers, and his quiet moments, where, as he said, he could go as to a ifar country. But there was another reason which but few of us suspected, why that library was so secluded.   3J I learned it from -the question which had echoed in my thoughts since little Bessy had suggested it, and which I, a few moments after finding Cousin Gulie and my sister, put to Emily, "' Why was Uncle Minot never married?" "Shut the door, Earnest, and I will tell Gulie and you," said Emily, "; the story of uncle's library. It will explain why he never married. Grandmother told me, and it has never crossed my lips, but, somehow, this Christmas Eve here at Under-Tor, it seems right that I should tell you, who are both as near and dear to uncle as I. When uncle was twenty-seven, he was stationed at some western fort, where he made the acquaintance of his senior officer's daughter, Millicent Barnard. She was eighteen, and very beautiful and accomplished. She was Col. Barnard's only child, and her mnother was dead. They became engaged, but her fatler did not wish her to marry within three years. After eighteen lmonths, uncle was ordered on other duty near New York, and not long after, Colonel Barnard was killed in a fight with the Indians. Millicent then came to live with an aunt in New York, where grand- mother made her acquaintance, anld sool became very fond of her. She often had her at Under-Tor on long visits in the summer, and sometimes she was here for awhile in the winter. The three years had nearly gone by, and uncle was thinking of resiguing and marrying. Grandmamma had a Christmas party at Under-Tor that year-of course Millicent was there, and your uncle, then Captain Minot, had a furlough, so as to enjoy the festivities. What is uncle's library now, was then an unfinished room, where were boxes, and books, and old pieces of furniture. I don't know why it was left in that state. But Millicent took a great fancy to that room, the bay-window of which looked out under the arches of a little grove of spruces and hem- locks, and commanded, too, a glimpse of the bold red-    <pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6540-00000017"/> 32 rocked Tor side, as it does now. That little picturesque bit was very pretty at sunset always, when the light would flush all over the Tor, and then creep higher and higher, leaving rocks and crevices in the shadowof advancing night Because not only sunset and twilight were so pleasant in that room, but because it was so warni and sunny all day, and the birds in winter loved to shelter themselves in that evergreen grove, and also, I suppose, because it was such a quiet, retired place, and had a char- acter so quaint, with the packed boxes, and piles of unar- ranged books, and the medley of ancient furniture, Milli- cent loved that room, and when uncle was away, sat there all day, absorbed in old books, and perhaps in \lew delici- ous dreams. Grandmamma says that no affection she ever knew or read of, equaled the devotion of those lovers; that uncle watched her always, as if his eyes were on some, perfect passing vision, and that his attentions toMil- licent were as chivalric as tender. He loved her, too, dearly. Christmas passed off gayly. The day after, it snowed heavily, and then there was fine sleighing. Uncle was very fond of horses, and drove beautiful animals. On the 28th of December, he and Millicent went out for a long sleigl-ride. While they were riding, a furious gale sprang up as suddenly as in summer, and with the fierceness of a tornado. On their return, about four in the afternoon, when half a mile from Under-Tor, in driving beneath an old oak that the lightning had struck a year or two be- fore, it fell, instantly killing the horse, and a brancl strik- ing Millicent, knocked her from the seat senseless. Uncle, half crazy, bore her in his arms toward the house. She opened her eyes when nearly here, and said, ' Dear Guy, take me to the Tor room.' He did so. Doctors were sent for, but as the setting sun, glowing on the Tor, flashed back, illuminating her face with a heavenly radi- ance, Millicent said her last sweet words to her dear G0uy,   33 and with a prayer to God for him  and herself, she breathed her last as twilight turned to night." Emily's voice trembled. Gu!e's face was turned toward ;he window. We halD no time to make remark before the door-knob turned, and Mrs. Grayson came in. "( Ah, here you are, the lost ones--uncle wants us all in his own library-think of that-the unknown room! He thinks it will be so pleasant, so social, for us to gather together there, in a snug family circle, this Christmas Eve." Strange, that the bit of romance our hearts had not  ceased to baat to, should be so immediately succeeded by a summons to the scene of' its action. We joined the laughing and merry-chatting ones who were on their way, through the hall, from the parlors to uncle's library. Little Bessy had fallen asleep before the big hall fire, her head in my mother's lap. , Come, sister," said Colonel Minot, "and we must bring the baby too; she can continue her sleep, but we must have all of our family party to-night; I can lift her quietly and place her just as comfortably in my library." He went ahead, his charge in his arms, her long golden ringlets hanging over his shoulder. A short side passage, and a double door-a heavy walnut door, and an inside one of green baize--opened into uncle's library. It was lighted fully by the burning logs of the second open fire-place at Under-Tor. Colonel Minot laid Bessy gently on a couch and covered her with , plaid. That couch was a strange-fashioned, ancient piece of furniture, and stood, as if it had been drawn there only for a time, nearly in the centre of the room. [n a moment I knew that, on that couch, and standing exactly as it did now, had Millicent taken her farewell of Guy. Only a very few of us had heard the story of that place, and yet it seemed to me as if all entered with i reverent respect to the beautiful memories consecrating it. Their spirit dwelt there and called forth an uncon- 3    <pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6540-00000018"/> 34 scions recognition from those who came within its circle- an influence evoking neither sadness, gloom, nor heavi- ness, but thoughtfulness and gentle sentiments. The hours of that Christmas Eve were full of glad, quiet hap- piness-a soft, pervading cheerfulness. It has abided in memory with me since, as the tranquil atmosphere of an Indian summer; as if an angel were among us-or as if we were in a mystic time and place, where ties of affection, pleasant memories of the past, and bright trust for the future, were strengthened and pure. "Oh, uncle," said Cousin Daisy, as soon as we were in *the library, "let us have no other light but that of the fire;, see how bright and genial that is-just the warm, tempered brightness I like to talk and listen in, don't you?" "Yes, I like your suggestion; we can feed the fire with pine-knots when it does not come up to our requirements." We were in a long low-ceiling room, its atmosphere pregnant with retirement and dreamy comfort; one could hardly imagine harsh wordsor unkind thoughts finding place there. Chastely carved bookshelves occupied all one side, except a window-place, over which they met in an arch. The fireplace, study table, and lounges filled two other sides, on the walls of which hung beautiful proof engravings simply framed. That over the mantle-tree was Millais' "Huguenot."  The soft India matting was covered here and there by fur rugs, an immense bearskin being spread before the fire. In one corner stood an old-fashioned clock, its quaintly carved case reaching from floor to ceil- ing, singing always, always with low silvery voice, a rhyme to every step of time: what an even, patient friend, aid, and sympathizer in study or reflection! The great bay- window entirely filled one end of the room, its cushioned recess partly shaded by draped blue curtains; but the fire- light spread through these, throwing a glistening yellow   35 on the snow beyond, and flickering on the ice-drops pen- dent from the evergreens. Conversation soon flowed on like a deep pleasant river, joined and freshened here and there by tributary streams' that, springing from the thickly dotted plains of recollec- tion or the hidden shaded dells of thought, came to empty their fullness into the main current. Grandmother told us some pretty incidents of the days of her courtship in Eng- land; my mother described the old times at Under-Tor be- fore we were born; Colonel Minot related thrilling scenes of Western frontier life forty years ago; and Major George was called upon to tell of his late battle, and how he got his wound, which he did with a brave man's modesty, and with most affectionate and delicate respect for Cousin Gulie's position; and then Cousin Guhe was questioned about her experiences before she left home and afterwards in the hospital; she answered with the deep emotion the questions excited, telling of her brother's death at Bull Run; of the family's exile from the devastated plantation (but all with not a word or imputation to wound the most ardent patriotism), and with quivering voice and blanched cheeks she repeated some hospital scenes, until tears of sym- pathy crept from our eyes. Next we talked of Harry-at the thought of whom, of where he might be this Christmas Eve, I know sweet Lucy Estvan's heart throbbed with as much anxiety as his mother's, and Uncle Minot chased away our fears with assurances that we would soon, he felt sure, hear good of him. So our talk ran from one to ano- ther: ' We spake of many a vanished scene, Of what we once had thought or said, Of what had been, and might have been, And who was changed and who was dead ;" -until the proposition was made that Cousin Lucy should sing us a ballad, and so she went to the piano in the    <pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6540-00000019"/> 36 next room, leaving the door open between, and after touch- ing the keys awhile, as if for inspiration, she sang-and ah ! how sweetly-Longfellow's " Footsteps of Angels." Lucy knew not the story of Millicent Barnard, and little suspected the tide of feeling that must have flooded uncle's heart at the verse: "And with tham the Being Beauteous, Who unto my youth was given, More than all things else to love me, nalA is now a saint in heaven." He sat in the shadow, so there were no witnesses of the emotion, hat may have suffused his countenance. The Christmas Eve was nearly ended. As Lucy finished her song and returned to the library, we waited silently to hear the distant village clock strike twelve. Grandmother asked Stuyvesant to read the record of that event which made the whole civilized world commemorate it in thank- fulness and joy to-night. Lights were brought, and he read that first part of the second chapter of Luke, shutting the book as he concluded with those words of glorious beauty and everlasting import: "And suddenly there was with the angel a multitude of the heavenly host praising God, and saying, GLORY TO GOD IN THE HIGHEST, AND ON EARTH PEACE, GOOD WILL TOWARD MEN." And then we all sang With hearts and voices: ' iIHark I the herald angels sing,. Glory to the new born King I'eace on earth," etc. -the village bells clanging out with our song their joy- ous peals; and Christmas Eve was numbered with the happy hours past of the receding year. We left grandmother, mother, and Colonel Minot in the library, and all ran in a burst of mirth to the dining room. Perhaps in the confusion of the chase, I stepped on   Cousin Gulie's dress tearing it, and-is it only a dream, or did I really?-apologizing for my awkwardness, perhaps, as she repaired the harm, I seized her fair soft hand and detained her in the hall until she had granted my passion- ately expressed petition that she should give me the camellia in her belt, which I had hated all through the evening, but vowed now to love if she but granted my request. Sur- prised, but laughing at my outburst, she released her hand, and disengaging the flower, hurried to the supper-room. What a racket, laughing, and popping of champagne  Oscar! Oscar ! how can those young ladies swallow a mouth- ful unless you stop your nonsense. Ah,Stuyvesant, rever- end cousin, you are altogether too attentive to Miss Fanny Berg, and what jollity for a priest's countenance to wear! There-smash I    * oh, bull in a china shop !* * You have knocked over the ice-cream pyramid into your wife's plate, and a champagnebottle into Hardie's bosom ! "Ha! ha! ha !" Miss Titine has forgotten me-ah ! then there no hopes are blasted-perhaps she was never conscious of my tenderness. How she is entrancing John Hardie-the champagne notwithstanding-and firing side shots at Oscar Mare, too! i  Cousins, cousins," exclaimed Mr. Grayson, "do let's have tableaux and charades to-morrow night." "Splendid idea," was the unanimous answer; ': we will -we will."  Christmas had begun as merrily as ever it did-what fun ! Oscar Mare, in a solemn voice, cried out: "I would propose a very serious toast, and I excuse all those who may have conscientious scruples, fiom drinking it.  It is"-and the most glorious merriment and good- will burst into his countenance like a sunrise--" It is a Merry Christmas to all!'"  " Merry Christmas !" ( Merry Christmas !" and the girls set to hugging and kissing one another, as if this was their first meeting after years of separation. Merry, Merry Christmas!     <pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC6540-00000020"/> 38 "Then wreathe old Christmas' face about, Down to his glowing chin; No pleasure spare, no pastime shun, Each roof with social clouds be curled - 'Tis well; for once beneath the sun There rolls a happy world '1" A noisy, gay, busy house was that of Under-Tor on Christmas morning. The great hall was to be turned into a theatre. Carpenters were erecting a stage at one end. What a combination of sounds-laughing, sawing, talking, hammering! Figures hurrying in and out; groups on the stairs and the floor; some one busy in some way every- where; ladies preparing costumes; ladies stitching up the long widths of green baize for a curtain; ladies all busy and chatting together over piles of prints and illus- trated papers; the "Dresden Gallery" on the floor; the "Verion Gallery" open on a sofa; over the "Costumes of Italy," Stuyvesant tripped and nearly bumped his nose on a high-back chair. Oscar Mare-and what a guest to be valued was he; what a living spring of fun and good spirits; what an influence of sunshine; so bright, so abounding in projects and expedients; so thoughtful for others, so unconscious of himself-Oscar Mare, proposing and elucidating charade-words in a circle of ladies, was almost bewildered by impossible suggestions, by assents and obstacles. There was stage-manager Hardie among the carpenters, explaining and directing. Major George, one arm still hung in the bandage of glory, leaned ten- derly over Alice Hardie and the prints she held; but why was it necessary to sit so far from the others, and why must George look so pitiful and talk in whispers? and why should Alice bend at times so closely over that one picture, which has already occupied nearly half an hour's time- and why, pray, the blushes that hurry over the fair face? Ah! well-the sweet old, yet always young, passion has its slaves everywhere under the sun. I had a recess for a ^  ^   39 studio, where I sketched and dashed colors on the big frames of scenery: that was a rough chance for enjoying my favorite art, and I should have been constant at it; but no, every few minutes I had to rush to where cousin Gulie sat, and urge with eager, trembling words that she should accept such or such a role offered to her in the tab- leaux-this goddess, that queen. Finally she told me "Earnest, I shall not take part in the tableaux." "( Why? why?" "Now, not so fierce, cousin, and I will tell you my reason if you will not repeat it: I will not expose my- self deliberately to such bribes to vanity. Besides, what pleasure would you take in making pictures you could not see. No! I delight in looking at tableaux, but I never have and never will appear ill one-anything, requisite in charades I shall be glad to attempt." Well, I hope they may give you a long, tough word- let's see-extraordinary, for instance!" "Oh! that is easy enough: I appear sitting alone on the stage-beholdl " ordinary:"You enter-I find that to be "extra!" "Yes, Cousin Gulie, you are severe: you have made me feel often in the last twenty-four hours how easily you can dispense with my society!" "Nonsense, cousin, why talk with such seriousness and vehemence. That is extra-uncalled for: pit some of it in your canvass and you'll insure fame!" "The hint art should thank you for, Miss Clifford: allow me as its representative to do so. For the remainder of this day feel assured your wishes will be respected." Even that Christmas sky had its cloud-a cloud I had bloiwn myself, yet in its shadow was misery. However, good sese iln half an hour brought me relief: I went con- trite and smiling once more to Cousin Gulie, who stood looking from one of the hall windows: she was alone-,    <pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC6540-00000021"/> 40 "Cousin Gulie, I am subject to fits of irritability at times when-when I sit up too late at night. Do pardon and forgive." "Did you think me angry, Cousin Earnest?"Had wo- man ever such a voice-so incomparably sweet?  "I have nothing to forgive; I wish it was as easily understood as forgiven." Just then, John Hardie came up to take Cousin Gulie to where her opinion was immediately re- quired on some arrangement under discussion. The Programme for the evening's amusement com- menced with tableaux and charades; then dancing, and af- ter that, supper. The preparations crowded the day with busy pleasure, and for the evening we expected any amount of jollity. There are islands in life,-wild, beautiful, vine-hung, flower-adorned islands,--the bridges to which fall in ruins when our happy feet have passed over; and when the re- gretful travelers, having abided their time, depart into the world again on others, those too disappear in the thirsty gulf of the Past. In those spots, a sweet illusive, magical light throws romantic charms about the acts and person- ages of their brief histories. The numbered assemblage of inhabitants who have journeyed thither with the same aim -Happiness,-isolated for awhile from the world, and in- dependent by mutual interest and affection, and the re- sources they yield, give themselves up to dreams and delights as the Lotos-eaters; and those tenures of felicity are the sweeter because, being contrary to the world's edict of ceaseless work and constant labor, they are stolen as it were. Like conditions have given fascination to the stories of the "Decameron ;" to that of the "Swiss Family Robinson ;" the "Annals of Arcadia :" and because of some similarity of circumstances, we have read with mysterious interest and almost envy the journals of the   " pastimes gf men and women shut in some beleaguered fort by troops of surrounding savages, and of those, too, of ships' companies imprisoned by the rigors of Arctic winter. But when the circumstances-isolation and dependence one upon another-giving interest, happily imprison in an old hospitable country-house a party in the mid-day of Youth-their Island of Delight cut off fronm a world they would escape for awhile, by such gulfs as cold and snow- which they almost wish were impassable floods ; then, truly theirs is an island of fairest hues and foliage, somewhat aside from and above too the common-place pleasure-tracks of the world. The smoke of their many little individual social fires wreathe up to the near sky in fairy-like clouds, that their happy eyes believe enchanted forms. Unknown, or perhaps suspected virtues or talents ; personal histo- ries, romances, or peculiarities; governing passions-all in- terweave themselves strangely and most engagingly about a commonrlife and movement. Were the converging and clustering together of frost-rays into ice-crystals allowed in the world, its great lake would soon be frozen over: there- fore are the unconscious self-formed and self-executing laws of the world disturbing, tossing, and dashing into waves, those waters. All must be in motion ; no shaded indolent pools to spread ice or stagnation. In a retreat like ours-an unfrequented by-street-dear old Under-Tor, no gensd'armes of the great world's police intruded with fixed bayonets, shouting, " move on, Messieurs! quick! move on!" It seemed to me that uncle's dogs kept up a tremendous barking that afternoon. About sunset, some one wanted Adelaide to take her place in a rehearsal of "' Faust and Marguerite"-the third tableau on the list. She could not be found. They searched the parlors and libraries. Then I went up stairs and knocked at her room door: not there.    <pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6540-00000022"/> 42 So I got a lady's maid to look in the different rooms, but she was not up stairs. I went down again, and out on a side piazza, where I could see if she were tramping about anywhere in the trodden paths of the hillside. I was about to go in again, when I heard the shutting of a door -the door of a small brick wing where uncle once had a sort of office. There I saw Adelaide, turning the key in the lock. I ran up to her before she had got it in her pocket. Her face was radiant with pleasure, but it changed when she saw me. "Why, Adelaide, what in the mischief is going on out here?" "No matter, Earnest-I shall tell you nothing about it. Just be quiet; and pro- mise me, dear Earnest, that you will not say one word about this"-and she took my arm in the insinuating way sisters have when they are determined to make you yield -" promise me, now-and that you will not mention where you found me: Earnest, do you hear?" "Yes, Addie, but you are at some of your mysteries, and I should like to ferret it out. However, I promise- there." We went in, and none asked very troublesome ques- tions. At half after seven everything was arranged in our theatre. Those actors who would soon be wanted had retired to their green-rooms, and the audience came in. Besides the members of our household, all the servants in- cluded, there were guests invited from the village: the doctor and his family, a sickly-looking boy and girl, who appeared so well charged with mercury that I instinctively examined them for some indication of the temperature of the theatre-room : the care-worn clergyman of five hun- dred a year, and his laughing wife and nine children. The state senator, the pompous Hon. Patrick Henry Eel, and his thin aristocratic daughters. "Quite a brilliant scene!   43 H'm! Colonel? It renews an evening I once enjoyed at the Villa Ariadne-the Countess Fontandi's at Florence. How handsomely the elections went last month." The theatre-bell was just ringing for the raising of the curtain, when the dogs commenced barking again as furi- ously as they had during the afternoon. Then came a rapping at the main door of the hall. My uncle was near and opened it. There stood a tall, stooping oldqian, sup- porting himself with a cane; his hair and long beard were almost as white as the snow; a long cloak was wrapped about his figure. He removed his hat and spoke to Colo- nel Minot in a hoarse, trembling voice: "Good evening, sir; I anm a stranger in the village, but hearing of the festivities here, I have made bold, with only this social time for an apology, to ask that I may be a looker on to-night." Certainly, my good man, we are happy to see you; do walk in.' I was among the audience and watched with much interest the man, whose old limbs took hm slowly to a seat against the wall and beneath the shadow of the stairs. The tableaux went off perfectly. The last, "Christ- mas, " a picture Oscar suggested, was strikingly beautiful, and as effective as the greatest hit at Wallack's. Then came charades; some of them, particularly those where Titine Berg and George had parts, were full of wit. The audience shouted with laughter, and when they could not guess the words, called for a repetition. During the cha- rade before the last, I looked to see how our old gentle- man was getting on, but he was nowhere to be seen. I had not time to ask questions or express surprise, before I was called for the last charade. In the first syllable "Sur," I was required to be extremely pressing in my attentions to a very pretty bar-maid, Lucy Estvan ; she reproved and repulsed the attentions of the impolite young dandy with    <pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6540-00000023"/> " an energetic and constant use of "Sir! Sir, you astonish me!l-Sir, I shall not permit you flatteries," etc., etc. The following syllable, "prise," was added, when a press- gang burst into the room and bore me off a prisoner. The bar-maid's relief, and yet her pity for " the poor young fellow lugged off so suddenly to sea," were sweetly acted. The curtain fell, and for the whole word I was to appear again, a full-blown sailor, after a long absence, to the astonished eyes of my admired bar-maid. I was soon ready, having quickly slipped on the white pants, volu- minous blue shirt, and natty hat with long neatly-ironed riband of the dramatic sailor, when, greatly to my aston- ishment, Adelaide ran up with'resistless impetuosity, and clapping a hand over my mouth, pushed me, before I was aware of what she was about, into the green-room (a large closet with a window on a piazza), and turned the key on me. I could not stand tlat patiently, but jumped through the window, and was in a moment at the hall door, suspect- ing some stage-joke of Adelaide's. Ding-die ding-dle-ling! The curtain rolled up; Lucy was seen dusting out the bar- room, soliloquizing, too, at her work, and bustling about with charming by-play. The stage door opened, and there en- tered-I was never in my life so astonished; what in the mischief did it mean?-the old gentleman whom uncle had admitted an hour ago to witness the performances. Lucy's stage manner was gone in an instant. She was evi- dently as much amazed as any of the audience. "Ah " said the old cracked voice, bringing out the words slowly, "Ah-I thought--I would come up here-to-to wish you all-a merry-very merry Christmas!"   In the twinkling of an eye his figure straightened, the cloak was thrown back, the white wig and beard thrown across the stage: a delighted shout from a score of voices spread excitedly, joyfully through the hall. "Harry? Yes! Yes!   45 it is Hairy!" Lucy fainted, and would have fallen, but that happy faced, robust, handsome sailor, caught her in his arms and pressed a kiss to her forehead. Adelaide took her from him quickly, and he sprang with one bound among the audience. My mother had advanced from her seat, tears of great joy filling her eyes. In a moment the restored son was clasped to the mother's bosom, kisses pressed on his bronzed features, and two thankful hearts beat close to one another. A few minutes, and then uncle, brothers, sisters, all,' surrounded Harry: arms around his neck, hands squeezing his; kisses, sobs, laugh- ter! Thle mother, whose joy forbade words, silently thanked her God for this blessed, blessed Christmas. And all felt beyond expression the overflowing happiness of that merry Christmas. *    *     *    *    * The baize of completion rolls down on the stage of my story, and an impatient printer's devil would extinguish the lights. "Stop, you little imp! stop, I say! What in thunder are you about? Hark! don't you hear the yells and stamping? They want something; can it be a speech? Pull back the curtain. Let me get out, quick!" "Ladies and gentlemen, deeply impressed by such a . . such a . . deeply impressed, I say . .impressed . . I . I  . .thejfct is, I can't make a speech . . but . .this is Christmas night, 1S64! On the 2d January last year, Harry Grayson offered himself to Government. She had lovers enough, and refused the sailor, so he turned about and begged Lucy Estvan to accept him, and she did. How many were the gifts of his New Year-mother, relatives, and an overflowing welcome, the proof of a pure heart's love, and, least of all, a fortune of sixty thousand dollars. He is now a happy landsman, a thankful husband. But-    <pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC6540-00000024"/> " he seems somewhat anxious lately, I don't know why- perhaps another Christmas present. What can it be this time? The major went back to his regiment. He has become a colonel, and married charming Alice Hardie. And now, ladies and gentlemen " '"Go on! go on! More! more!" "What more? What can I say? O-h, yes! Colonel Minot took his niece as far as Washington on her return to the South. It was the sixth of January, a dreary, slushy, overcast day, when I waited in the Philadelphia depot in Jersey city to see them off. Soon. they came, and Cousin Gulie being seated ill the car, Uncle Minot left her to look after the baggage. I bent over her while my iheart seemed choking me, and said: "Gulie, dear Gulie, I love you. Do say that I may. Say something to lift me from my despair in losing you." "Dear, kind Cousin Earnest, how proud and yet how very sorry I am  to hear those words. I cannot love you yet: we have known each other for but such a short time. Dear cou- sin, let us think no more of this until after the war. Then we shall see each other again - and - until then we can remember and hope." The whistle screeched, and the cars commenced to move. "Good-by, dear Cousin Ear- nest, good-by!?' I hurried her unresisting hand to my lips. "t God bless you, dear, dear Gulie; I shall remember and hcope." On the platfi rm I ran by the cars and waved a good-by to Uncle Minot. Gulie opened her window, smiled a sweet, sad smile, and threw me a fiesh green piece of one of our Christmas evergreens. Two years ago! And this is Christmas. '64! God grant that before the end of another year we may, North and South, enjoy in one great, strong Union an honorable, endurable peace. Peace! peace to restore the blessings now withheld; to soothe and comfort   47 thousands of hearts now worn sore with watching and fears; peace to bring back to us the brave, noble hearts we love so dearly! Can we not catch a reflection from its beautiful white wings now, as with overflowing heart we say, "A merry, merry Christmas to all?" </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>