<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6928">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Flying Artillerist, or, The Child of the Battle-field </title>
            <author>Hazel, Harry, (1814-1889)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC6928</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-1385</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                    participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The flying artillerist, or, The child of the battle-field</title>
                  <author>Hazel, Harry, (1814-1889)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>90 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>T. B. Peterson</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Philadelphia </pubPlace>
                  <date from="1800" to="1899">[18--]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="AEL Data" when="2003-03-20">Finished transcription and SGML encoding</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2003-06-05">Finished TEI conversion</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-08-04">Converted document from SGML to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-08-04">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6928-00000001"/>
         <titlePage>
            <titlePart type="series">THE CELEBRATED 'HARRY HAZEL' SERIES!</titlePart>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>THE FLYING ARTILLERIST;</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">OR, THE CHILD OF THE BATTLE-FIELD.</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">A TALE OF MEXICAN TREACHERY.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>BY <docAuthor>HARRY HAZEL.</docAuthor> AUTHOR OF "GALLANT TOM, OR THE PERILS OF THE OCEAN," "THE BRIGAND, OR THE MOUNTAIN CHIEF," "THE REBEL AND ROVER," "KING'S CRUISERS," YANKEE JACK, OR THE PERILS OF A PRIVATEERSMAN," "THE THREE PIRATES, OR THE CRUISE OF THE TORNADO," "THE FLYING YANKEE," "RED KING, OR THE CORSAIR CHIFTAIN," "SYLVIA SEABURY, OR THE YANKEES IN JAPAN," "THE FLYING DUTCHMAN," "THE DOOMED SHIP," "JACK JUNK," "HARRY HELM," "HARRY TEMPEST," "SWEENY TODD," "GALLOPING GUS," "THE GOLD SEEKERS," "RALPH RUNNION," "OLD PUT, OR "DAYS OF SEVENTY-SIX," "THE YANKEE MIDDY," "VALDEZ, THE PIRATE," "REBEL BRIDE," "PIRATE'S SON," ETC.</byline>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>Philadelphia:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>T. B. PETERSON &amp; BROTHERS, <address>
                     <addrLine>306 CHESTNUT STREET.</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </publisher>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
         <div type="contents">
            <pb n=" (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC6928-00000002"/>
            <head>CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>CHAPTER I. The Retreating Regiment. <ref target="VAC6928-00000004" rend="right">1</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER II. The Battle of Coletta. <ref target="VAC6928-00000009" rend="right">20</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER III. Santa Anna's Sanguinary Mandate. <ref target="VAC6928-00000016" rend="right">33</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER IV. The Prisoner of Vera Cruz. <ref target="VAC6928-00000024" rend="right">47</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER V. Defeat of the Mexican Lancers. <ref target="VAC6928-00000030" rend="right">61</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER VI. Puebla and the Convent of San Ursula. <ref target="VAC6928-00000033" rend="right">67</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER VII. The General and the Friar. <ref target="VAC6928-00000038" rend="right">75</ref>
               </item>
               <item>CHAPTER VIII. "All's Well that Ends Well." <ref target="VAC6928-00000040" rend="right">79</ref>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The flying artillerist, or, The child of the battle-field</head>
            <pb n="5" xml:id="VAC6928-00000003"/>
            <head>THE FLYING ARTILLERIST.</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE RETREATING REGIMENT.</head>
               <p>THE year 1836 will ever be as memorable in the annals of Texas, as any period of her history; for, during this year, her forces met with more reverses in her great struggle for independence than throughout her war with Mexico. It might properly be called the dark era of her revolution, because of the unparalleled sufferings of her soldiers, through famine, battles lost, imprisonment in antiquated castles and loathsome dungeons, and merciless barbarities of her treacherous enemy.</p>
               <p>It was but a few weeks subsequent to the fall of the Alamo, where one hundred and eighty Texans, under the command of Colonel Travis, held out for thirteen days against eight thousand Mexicans under Santa Anna, that a body of armed men, principally on foot, might have been seen passing a narrow barranca, which led towards the prairie of Coletta, an open space of about three miles in diameter, surrounded by a thick forest.—The commander of this band rode a somewhat jaded horse, and immediately following him was a young, gallant officer, belonging to the staff, leading a mule, on which was mounted a<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC6928-00000004"/> female, who, despite that anxiety of mind so strongly expressed in her countenance, was as lovely a specimen of her sex as the Anglo-Saxon race can boast of at the present day. In her arms she bore an infant, over whose head a single summer had not yet passed; it was a bright, rosy-cheeked child, in whose tiny lineaments could be distinctly traced a semblance of him who led the plodding beast of burden which conveyed them along the rough pathway.</p>
               <p>"Be of good courage, my love," said the gallant officer, addressing the young matron, "if that half Indian guide has not deceived us, we shall reach the prairie an hour or two before sunset."</p>
               <p>"I'll skin him alive, if he has," muttered a tall, athletic Kentuckian, by the name of Dick Keen, who trailed a long rifle in his hand, and carried a bowie knife in his belt. Dick marched on the left side of the mule, a sort of self-constituted body-guard for the lady and child.</p>
               <p>"Better send a Kentucky pill into his carcass," answered Field, the first surgeon of the regiment, a short thick-set Yankee, from Charlemont, Massachusetts.</p>
               <p>"Well, Dock, I'll leave skinnin' and all d—d surgery op'rations to you; for juss now I've got a pertickler case in hand. D'ye see that cussed, swarthy spy on top o' that knoll? May I never see old Kaintuck again, if I don't make him swally this pill in a different place from that which he's used to swallyin' med'cin!"</p>
               <p>All eyes were now turned in the direction the Kentuckian pointed. It was a long distance where the Mexican was skulking; but Dick knew his rifle, and he cracked away.—The Mexican was seen to leap a few feet in the air and then fail. Keen had shot him through the heart.</p>
               <p>"There, cuss yer, take that!" said Dick, as soon as he saw the effect of his shot. "That makes juss five out o' the hunderd I've sworn to shewt on Davy Crockett's account!" and he drew a strip of shingle from his pocket, on which he cut a notch with his bowie-knife.</p>
               <p>"Your pills are quite effectual!" remarked the surgeon.</p>
               <p>"Yer right, Dock; unlike pottecary's pills, they're a damn sartin cure for every complaint, and a speedy cure, too! I'd like to hev a few more patients to-day; fer I feel as ef I could do somethin' desprit—I'm kinder cattymount like—that raw ration of buffalo meat has consid'rably stirt up my meat. I ken see further, aim straighter, and kill surer to-day, then since we started on this Mex'can hunt."</p>
               <p>"If my judgment is correct," said Colonel Fannin, who had fallen back to the party concentrated around the lady; "you'll have an opportunity to avenge poor Crockett's death before night. There are plenty of the enemy near, or that fellow you've finished wouldn't have been skulking up yonder."</p>
               <p>"Sooner the better, Kurnel!" replied Dick; "then I shall be a'ready fer another job; but I don't like wastin' a whole charge o'ammunition on each one on 'em—I want to take the creturs rakeways. I reckon my 'Joe Manton' (the name of his rifle) would send a slug through a four inch plank—and if that aint tougher than any ten Mex'cans, you can skeer up, then my name's not Dick Keen, and I'm no Kaintuck. Yes, Kurnel, gin me a fair shot at a dozen on 'em, and I'd send 'em all to Kingdum cum, a little quicker than ye can say Jack Roberson! Oh, I'm a rip-staver—raal Kaintuck grit—so's my father—so's my mother—so's Davy and John—so's Kate and Mira—so's all the little crop o' Keens growing up at hum!"</p>
               <p>"Your family is rather extensive," remarked Colonel Fannin, somewhat amused with the sharp-shooter.</p>
               <p>"I reckon we are some—there's sixteen on us in all and more 'spected, besides the old man and old woman. We orter to tuck the premium at last cattle-show!"</p>
               <p>"And are all your brothers so expert with the rifle?" asked the colonel.</p>
               <p>"Every mother's son on 'em; we can all spile a bull's eye at hunderd yards. As fer Mira, she's as good a shot as any on us. I seed that gal blaze away at a bald-headed eagle, arter Davy had two shots at it, and may I be swallyed by an allygator if the didn't spile the bird's windpipe!"</p>
               <pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6928-00000005"/>
               <p>"Practicing the rifle, then, I should judge is a good part of the business of your family?" queried the Colonel.</p>
               <p>"We don't do any thing else, and we've got to be pretty fore-handed. We hunt in the summer for buffaloes up the Kansas; in the fall we kill beavers, bars, deer, and sich small game; in the winter, we stay about hum, hev a good time, go to all the corn-huskings, and all the turkey-shoots, and make money out o' that; and airly in the spring we start off on a trappin' tramp."</p>
               <p>"And this year you have volunteered on a Mexican hunt," remarked Fannin; "and I fear you'll not find it quite so profitable."</p>
               <p>"I don't 'spect to," said Dick; "I reckoned I've listed in the cause of Texas and Liberty! and vengince on the murd'rers of my old friend and canderdate for Congress, Davy Crockett When that is done, I'll be satisfied to go back to old Kaintuck without a cent in my wall't, or a rag to my back! bare-footed, bare-headed, and bare-backed! barked, bruised, and battered! Yes, Colonel, I'd even be willin' to stump it through the world on a game-leg, and have only one eye to aim my Joe Manton with, ef these things will come to pass."</p>
               <p>"I trust you may not be disappointed," said Fannin. "If I had five thousand such men as you, Keen, I could march to the Mexican capital, and plant our bright star on its ramparts!</p>
               <p>"Ah, Kurnel, don't salve me. I ken stand any thing better than that, from a bar's hug to an allygator's grip! If we're going to hev a bit of a brush with the Mex'cans, I may as well clean up Joe Manton for she's precious foul; and if <unclear>yer've</unclear> no objections, Kurnel, I'll straddle that foremost gun while I do it for I don't want to be laggin' ahind when there's prospect of a fight ahead!"</p>
               <p>"Certainly, Keen, you have my permission," said the colonel Dick ran forward and mounted the cannon, which was a four inch howitzer, and commenced the operation of swabbing out his rifle, and rubbing up the ornaments, of which he was excessively proud.</p>
               <p>"That's a noble fellow, Mrs. Woodland," said Fannin addressing the interesting lady, to whom we have before al luded.</p>
               <p>"Indeed he is, Colonel," she replied in the sweetest voice imaginable. "Henry and myself find his company exceedingly agreeable."</p>
               <p>"That we do, colonel," added Woodland, the young officer, who led the mule. "He appears to know no fear; and he does much towards animating the drooping spirits of some of our men."</p>
               <p>"Colonel," resumed the lady, "are we near the prairie?"</p>
               <p>"An hour's brisk march will bring us there, so the guide informs me," answered Fannin. Then turning to Woodland, he said, "after a night's repose, Woodland, your lady will be able to undertake the journey to the hacienda of my old friend, where she and the child will have sure protection until the approaching crisis is over. She shall have a strong escort and a faithful guide."</p>
               <p>"Thanks, colonel," replied Henry Woodland.</p>
               <p>Fannin politely raised his chapeau, and spurring his jaded animal, he rode to the head of his column.</p>
               <p>Before we proceed further we may as well relate to our readers some interesting facts touching the young officer and his still younger wife, and how it happened that they, at this critical period, should have been attached to this expedition.</p>
               <p>Henry Woodland was the son of a highly respectable but somewhat indigent professional gentleman, who resided in the metropolis of Massachusetts. Henry had received a semi-military education at the Norwich Military Academy, but subsequently commenced the study of law in the office of a distinguished counselor of the Suffollk bar. Chance threw him frequently into the society of Sabra Sherwood, the only daughter of a wealthy gentleman of the same city, who had but recently renounced Protestantism, and become a zealous adherent of the Romish Church.—An intimacy between Woodland and Miss Sherwood was by no means agreeable to the young lady's father, and although he at first made no open opposition, yet he contrived as frequently as possible to prevent and disturb their<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6928-00000006"/> interviews. But all in vain; their attachment had become too strong to be easily broken; they vowed eternal love and fidelity to each other, and this approach to a climax was promptly made known to Mr. Sherwood by Sabra herself, in a loving, gentle, confiding manner. But not so the answer of the stern, iron-hearted man, who regarded money as his God, and the Pope as his Idol! His first exclamation to his daughter, was:—</p>
               <p>"This young Woodland is but little better than a beggar, and rather than own him or any other protestant as son-in-law, I would follow you, indiscreet girl as you are, to an early grave!"</p>
               <p>"Dear father," she replied, while tears flowed from her dark, sparkling eyes, "I love none but him—we have exchanged vows of affection and eternal constancy—and——"</p>
               <p>"Then forswear your vows!" he harshly replied. "To do so will be no sin in the sight of Heaven, for he is a heretic!"</p>
               <p>"Does the father whom I love advise his child to perjure herself?" she asked, with astonishment.</p>
               <p>"No more of this!" he commanded, evading her question; "but listen to what I say, and what I MEAN! You shall never become Woodland's bride! I have other views in relation to you, much more eligible—much more agreeable to my feelings and WILL! You must espouse our friend and frequent visitor, Carlos Dumiger. You are aware that his expectations are great, for he is the son of one of the wealthiest grandees of Spain.—When on his first visit to this country, he solicited from me your hand in marriage, and expressed in sincere terms his ardent love for you. I pledged him my word that nothing should be wanted on my part to meet his earnest wishes; and his present visit to this city is for no other purpose than to make you his bride! He shall not be thwarted! This is my irrevocable determination! Marry him, and be happy! Refuse him, and you are no longer child of mine!"</p>
               <p>"I hate this Dumiger, father!" said she, her eyes flashing with indignation; "his very sight is loathsome to me!"</p>
               <p>"Then let it henceforth be your task to learn to love him!"</p>
               <p>"That is impossible!"</p>
               <p>"Well, then, marry him you hate!"</p>
               <p>"Never! so help me, Heaven. Ere I'll enter his bridal chamber, I shall cease to exist!"</p>
               <p>"Then by Heaven! you shall eke out your remaining life in a cloister."</p>
               <p>"That is preferable. God forbid that I should ever break my willing vows to Henry Woodland!"</p>
               <p>"Rash girl! that you should ever have dared to make such a vow without first consulting me!"</p>
               <p>"My heart prompted me to it! My soul forbids that it should ever be revoked!"</p>
               <p>"Then prepare to become the bride of Heaven!" exclaimed Mr. Sherwood, angrily. "You must renounce the world and its pleasures—enter the Convent of Sacre Cœur—never to return to the world—ungrateful child!"</p>
               <p>"Oh, father, call not the child that honors and loves you ungrateful, for I shall obey you."</p>
               <p>"Then consent to marry Charles Dumiger?"</p>
               <p>"No! not that—any thing but that, father! My soul shudders at so horrible a thought!"</p>
               <p>"Then, the cloister!"</p>
               <p>"Right willingly."</p>
               <p>"A packet ship sails for New Orleans on the coming Thursday—prepare to take passage in her. You will need but a scanty wardrobe. Silks, satins, laces and jewels, you will no longer require. The Sisters of the Sacred Heart will take care to furnish you with the uniform costume of the convent."</p>
               <p>"I shall be in readiness," said Sabra, firmly, disregarding the half-sneering manner in which her father uttered these last sentences.</p>
               <p>"Mr. Sherwood made no further reply, but left the parlor muttering to himself, and quite enraged at what he called his daughter's obstinacy. Perhaps in his calmer moments the strong-willed man would not have forced upon her an alternative, which, notwithstanding his Catholicism, his own heart revolted at infintely more than did that of his daughter. But now it was too<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6928-00000007"/> late—he had decided!—she had decided! No concession or compromise could be made by such inflexible spirits—and none was sought.</p>
               <p>At the appointed day and hour Sabra was prepared. She bade an affectionate adieu to her stern-hearted parent, and her only brother. She had a beautiful sister, who had married a French gentleman a twelve-month previous, and who, at this time, resided in Paris. Sabra had never known a mother's love—for she was but a year old when Mrs. Sherwood died. The carriage which was to convey her to the vessel drove up to the door. She cast a last lingering look at the noble mansion, where she had passed her childhood's years, was handed into the carriage, and in fifteen minutes afterwards was on board of the packet ship, where she was placed under the protection of a catholic priest, who had promised Mr. Sherwood to deliver his daughter safely into the hands of the Lady Abbess of Sacre Cœur.</p>
               <p>The weather was propitious, and a fair wind soon wafted the vessel into the wide Atlantic. On the second day of the voyage she, for the first time since their starting, appeared on deck. Great was her surprise to encounter, in the first person that she met, the hateful Spaniard, Dumiger, who was the real source of all her sorrow. The thought that this was a plan of her cruel father, to give the Spaniard an opportunity to cause a change in her feelings, readily occurred to her mind, and she as readily made up her mind how to act. He at once, in the most courteous manner that he was master of, paid his addresses to her, but she repulsed him with as much contempt as she was mistress of.</p>
               <p>There was another passenger who had entered an assumed name on the passenger list, and who was a stranger to all on board excepting herself. This was none other than her faithful lover, Henry Woodland. Sabra, during the interim of her father's decree and the hour of departure, had contrived to in form him of her destination, without suggesting any course for him to pursue; but, nevertheless, she was not altogether surprised prised to find him on board of the packet. During a fifteen days' passage, they met frequently upon the deck, and conversed openly upon all matters except those which lay nearest their hearts, reserving these for meetings when their whisperings could not attract the attention of any of their fellow passengers. The priest, as well as Dumiger, contrived every possible means, without appearing rude to the stranger, to prevent these frequent interviews, although they had not the slightest suspicion that he was a lover. Before the vessel arrived at New Orleans, Dumiger's jealousy and envy had reached their highest pitch, and in his anger he let drop rather an insolent reflection, touching the honor of his fellow passenger. Woodland retorted with equal severity, and an open rupture of the most malignant character, was the consequence.</p>
               <p>In due time the ship arrived at her port of destination, and Sabra, with her priestly protector, together with Woodland and Dumiger, repaired to the St. Charles Hotel, the former two intending to remain one night only, when they were to set out for the convent of Sacre Coeur, situated a few miles' distance from the Crescent City.</p>
               <p>They had no sooner arrived at the hotel than Woodland received a sealed note, which proved to be a challenge, designating time and place of meeting. It was instantly accepted, and at sunset they met without seconds, or without agreeing upon any preliminaries. They fought with rapiers.—Woodland was the victor, having severely wounded his antagonist in the sword arm and pierced his breast. Dumiger fell, and Woodland ran to procure a surgeon, and related some of the circumstances of the affair without implicating himself. He guided him to the spot, where the Spaniard was lying insensible from the loss of blood. The wounds were examined and pronounced not fatal by the surgeon.</p>
               <p>Overjoyed that he had not killed his belligerent rival, he left the bloody scene, and hastily repaired to the hotel, where he obtained an interview with Sabra, and acquainted her with the duel in which he had been engaged.</p>
               <pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6928-00000008"/>
               <p>Meanwhile a rumor ran through the city that an assassination had been committed, and officers were sent on the alert to hunt up the assassin. These rumors reached Woodland's ears, and he instantly determined to flee from the city lest he should be arrested, and for want of evidence for defence, made to suffer for a crime of which he was innocent.—Again he sought to see and to take a last farewell of his beloved betrothed, for he deemed it not prudent to remain another hour in that city.</p>
               <p>"Then I will fly with you!" declared Sabra, as soon as he made known to her his intention.</p>
               <p>"There would be great danger, my love, in such a step," replied Woodland.</p>
               <p>"I will brave any danger to be near you, Henry!" said she, "Take me with you, lest I never behold you more. Tomorrow, be well assured, if I remain, I shall be as far beyond your reach as if I were laid in my grave!"</p>
               <p>"It shall be so, dearest!" exclaimed Woodland, clasping the fond maiden to his bosom; "but how shall we elude the vigilance of that bigoted priest?"</p>
               <p>"He has but now gone abroad to visit the catholic bishop; he will not probably return until the evening is far spent!"</p>
               <p>"Then surely now is our time and opportunity, for if either should remain longer, our escape would be cut off, owing to that indiscreet matter which I could not well avoid."</p>
               <p>"Whither shall we go, Henry?"</p>
               <p>"To Texas!" was his prompt reply. "If we can once get aboard of one of the many vessels constantly plying between this port and Galveston, our chances for escape will be in our favor."</p>
               <p>Woodland went forth to make his preparations, and, if possible, secure a passage for himself and Miss Sherwood. He found, on visiting the levee, that a small steamer was to sail that very night for Galveston. He went on board, secured berths, and then hastened to the St. Charles to communicate to Sabra the happy intelligence.</p>
               <p>Before twelve o'clock that very night, the steamer, with our oving couple aboard, glided down the Father of Waters, at a twelve knot speed: and in due time landed her passengers safely at Galveston.</p>
               <p>Many days had not elapsed, when the priestly protector of Mrs. Sherwood, in company with a constable of New Orleans, made their appearance in this place in quest of the fugitives, the one to take Miss Sherwood to her original destination, the other to arrest Woodland as an assassin, and convey him to the calaboose of the city where the crime was purported to have been committed.</p>
               <p>But Woodland, in due time, got wind of their arrival, and fled with Sabra immediately to La Bahia de Goliad, at which place they arrived after a fatiguing journey of several days. No sooner had they arrived, than they went to the house of the only protestant clergyman in the place, and were privately married. They afterwards travelled from place to place, and finally found a secluded refuge at a ranch near Gonzales, on the Gaudalupe river, where they remained for some fifteen months. Hearing that Col. Fannin was making a retreat towards Victoria, he determined to join him, for their more safe conveyance towards San Jacinto, where he determined, if necessary, to claim the protection of the provisional government of Texas.</p>
               <p>The revolutionary party was in want of soldiers, and when Woodland arrived in camp, with his wife and child, and related his story to Colonel Fannin, he promised them all the protection he could afford, and being pleased with Woodland's address and spirit, he offered to send his wife and babe to a secure retreat, if he would accept a subaltern's commission in his army. This after due deliberation and consultation with Sabra, he acceded to.</p>
               <p>Early next morning the army re-commenced their retreat, and it was but two days after this that we find them on the road leading to the prairie of Coletta.</p>
               <p>The terrible scenes which were here enacted we reserve for a new chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="16-17 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6928-00000009"/>
               <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE BATTLE OF COLETTA.</head>
               <p>THE Texan troops had nearly passed the dreary barranca, and, contrary to the expectation of Col. Fannin, without meeting the Mexican force, which, he had intelligence through a spy, was to have been dispatched to cut off his retreat. The road here diverged from a straight course almost at right angles, and after marching on for about a fourth of a mile he ordered the column to halt, for the purpose of refreshing his troops, from the fatigues of the march they had endured that day. A half an hour elapsed, when a few stragglers came running up, in breathless haste, and reported that a large body of Mexican cavalry was in their rear.</p>
               <p>Fannin immediately ordered the artillerists with their how-itzers to the left of the column, and then resumed the march at a rapid pace, hoping to reach the prairie before an attack could be made.</p>
               <p>"Blast their yellar picters!" exclaimed Dick Keen; "they'd better not come within reach o' my Joe Manton! Ef they dew some on 'em 'll git peppered, snake me of they don't. I've got the critter in fust rate workin' order, and all I want now is a good mark to let drive at. Kurnel," he continued, addressing Fannin, "if yer've no perticler objections, I'll take my persition long o' them brass-barkers in the rear. I reckon I can't dew the execution they, can, but I'm a thunderin' sight surer!"</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>A COMPANY OF FLYING ARTILLERISTS IN ACTION.</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6928-00000010"/>
               <p>"That is now the post of honor," said Fannin "and if it is your choice to take it, you have my leave; and I wish I had a hundred just such sharp-shooters to send with you."</p>
               <p>"Thank ye, Kurnel," resumed Dick; "perhaps now I'll git old Joe leveled at one or two o' them laced-coat chaps; ef I dew, well, I'll make 'em smell-powder! I've reckoned about one gin'ral, a brace o' kurnels, and a score o' captins and leftenants in my hunderd on poor Davy Crockett's account."</p>
               <p>Delivering himself of this speech, Dick stepped out of the ranks and stood by the road-side until the rear of the little army came up. He had no sooner done so than the Mexican bugle sounded a charge, and the heavy tramp of horses was distinctly heard in the distance.</p>
               <p>"That cussed Mex'can bewgle agin!" said Dick Keen to the artillerists. "Were in fer it now, boys! So let's gin em a few straks o' lightenin', a smart clap o' thunder, sprinkled with an old fashun Yankee hail storm!"</p>
               <p>The howitzers were charged with grape and canister, and the men were ready, with fusees burning, for the enemy's approach, yet moving steadily on. Soon the Mexicans were seen turning the angle in the road, and at the moment they espied the retreating force, they all shouted and yelled like so many wild Camanches; for they anticipated an easy victory over the vastly inferior numbers of the Texans. The General, Urrea, cautioned his subordinates not to waste a single pistol shot upon them, but to ride over and cut them down with their lances and sabres, without giving quarter to the 'd——d Northern Vandals,' as he was accustomed to term the Anglo-American invaders.</p>
               <p>Onward they came at full gallop—the front rank with lances poised. The road was narrow, allowing not more than six or seven to ride abreast.</p>
               <p>The Texan artillerists waited until the enemy approached within musket shot distance, and the word was given to halt and fire! The two rearward howitzers simultaneously belched forth a sheet of flame and a shower of iron hail, which sent death and destruction among the foremost ranks of this flower of the Mexican cavalry! They received so sudden and so appalling a check, that the whole road became chocked up by those, who, with all the impetuosity of a charge, were galloping on.</p>
               <p>The moment the two howitzers were discharged, they were dragged forward, and before the smoke cleared away, the two others (there were but four pieces of cannon in all) were brought to the rear and discharged, not giving the enemy sufficient time to recover from the horrible and confused dilemma in which they were placed. The carnage was awful. So many men and horses were killed and wounded by the effective fire of the Texans, that they formed an impassable barricade for cavalry, between the pursuers and pursued. Indeed so great was this heap of commingled human and beast flesh, that in one or two succeeding discharges of the howitzers, it actually was the means of saving the lives of many more Mexicans.</p>
               <p>As soon as it was possible, the lancers turned to the right about, and after retreating beyond the reach of the deadly shot of the little army, they came to a halt, and Fannin's column moved on to the prairie.</p>
               <p>Urrea, stung with mortification and anger at this unlooked for disaster, determined to take summary measures, to redeem his acknowledged reputation, won in the field, as a skillful strat egist and as a brave commander. Under him was a force of eighteen hundred lancers, well mounted, and well armed and equipped; they had been tried in many a well-fought battle and were deemed invincible; indeed they were regarded as the flower of the armies of the republic. Urrea, therefore, well knew, if he allowed a force of four hundred raw, undisciplined foot-soldiers, badly equipped and armed, to cope successfully with his brave army, he could never more be regarded worthy of his high rank in the armies of the "magnanimous Mexican nation."</p>
               <p>As soon as it was considered prudent, he ordered his troops to march. When they came to the barricade of slain men and<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6928-00000011"/> horses, the general was obliged to detach a company of men to drag aside the dead bodies, that the army might pass. Urrea cast but one look upon the heterogeneous mass, and turned from it, for his heart sickened at the sight!</p>
               <p>The work of clearing the road caused a full half hour's delay which gave Fannin's troops time to reach the prairie, where they immediately commenced the work of entrenching themselves, with whatever means they had at hand. The guns and heavy baggage-wagons had been dragged by Mexican oxen, while the lighter vehicles had been drawn by mules. The animals were forthwith detached from the wagons, and strung together by a long chain, which was fastened to posts driven at equal distances. These formed a quarter section of a circle Behind the mules and oxen were stationed the infantry and sharp-shooters. Opposite, at a distance of eighty or a hundred yards, were ranged the wagons, turned broadside, while, intervening, was piled up all their bulky baggage. These formed another section of a circle. The other quarter-sections were formed by earth and turf, which the men threw up, breast high, in an incredibly brief space of time; for on their exertions at this critical juncture, they well knew, depended their lives. At these points, were stationed the artillerists, with two pieces of cannon at each. Thus entrenched, they went to work and pitched their tents near together in the centre of the area, and made other preparations, anticipating that here they were to be besieged by a vastly superior force; and here they were resolved to fight to the last, unless, peradventure, honorable terms of capitulation should be offered.</p>
               <p>It was now well nigh sunset, when from that 'cussed Mex'can bewgle,' as Dick persisted in calling it, came a blast, sounding shrill and clear upon the ears of that little band of patriots; and every man was now made aware that he must surely fight before he could eat, notwithstanding the rations were nearly ready; for the Mexican cavalry, in full strength, filed out of the forest, and arrayed themselves in full view of their intended prey. They certainly presented a most formidable and splen did appearance, compared to the little band which they resolved to overwhelm and demolish at one dread onslaught.</p>
               <p>"I reckon, leftenant,"said Dick Keen, (who was allowed to fight on his own hook,) addressing Woodland, who commanded the battery in the road slaughter, "ef your barkers dew their hull dewty as they did in the woods, we shall spile the good looks o' them hansum lookin' red feathered varmints."</p>
               <p>"We shall do all that men can do!" replied Woodland.</p>
               <p>"Then we shall lick 'em, sure's thunder. But I say, leftenant, you made such a smoke, and piled up the varmint so in the woods, that my Joe Manton was no more use to me than would ha' ben a Kaintuck corn-stock."</p>
               <p>"True," replied Woodland; "there would have been about as little sport for you to have fired into that body of Mexicans we repulsed, as there would be in your practising rifle-shooting, with the broadside of a church for a target!"</p>
               <p>"May I be chawed up and spit out by a hungry alligator, of I didn't think so myself," said the Kentuckian. "But, I say, leftenant, you gin them yellar gingerbread varmint partickler thunder, didn't yer? I reckon you aint so all fired green in mileterry matters as you pertented to Kurnel Fannin, when he gin you a commission. Whar d'ye come from, leftenant, of that aint axin to much of a gentleman?"</p>
               <p>"Do you know where Bunker hill is?"</p>
               <p>"I reckon that's the hill the Britishers marched up and didn't march down agin, coz they had to roll down!"</p>
               <p>"Something like that, Keen," replied Woodland. "Well, the room I was born in, looks out upon that proud eminence."</p>
               <p>"May I be struck by a thunderbolt, ef I didn't think you were raised somewhar down thar! Nex to old Kaintuck boys, gin me them from the Bunker Hill diggins! I've seen strangers from them parts afore to day; I've seen the critters in our diggins at hum, and they're as kewt at a long rifle distance, as they be in honin' a razor or sellin' a wooden time-ticker! My old dad bought one once, and the way that clock would travel hrough her days work was no ways lazy. It beat the sun<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6928-00000012"/> every day by two hours and a half; the world would na' come to an eend long afore this, ef the old man had'nt sent off down to Louyville for a clock maker. Davy did the errand, and may my head be used for a gun-swab, ef the critter didn't bring home a book which Mira said, and she can read, was called the "Clockmaker." We laughed at Davy, and sent him back for a reg'lar clock tinker and not a thing to read! Next time Davy was right, and the chap he brought overhauled the time-ticker, and arter he'd fixed it and gone, we found it travelled too slow fer Kaintuck human natur to bar. The thing was conterery as a wild hog—it went so slow arter that we use to set up all night, coz the clock said it warn't time to go to bed. That was the smartest and the laziest clock in the hull township. One day I was outside our log hut long o' Mira; sez I, Sis, don't the time-ticker git enny better. Sez she—no, Dick—it's slower than wet powder. Then sez I, I'll just fix the obstinate critter's flint in about a few seconds. So I raised Joe Manton, and aimed, atween two logs of our hut, right at the critter's phiz. Sez Mira, be keerful Dick—mind yer eye, and don't hit Davy and Kate, for they're in there skinnin a panther; Never you mind them, sez I, I won't hurt a hair o' their heads, but I should like to take that high horn comb out o' Kate's topknot, just for sarvin' me the trick o' shootin' that panther, after I had hunted the varmint a hull mornin' and treed him. I waited half a minit, and I soon got a sight o' Sis's topknot, right in range o' the mug o' that Yankee clock. I let old Joe blaze away—the shot spiled Kate's horn comb, and that clock aint ticked since; but the way that Sis o' mine did pitch inter me for spilin' her topknot arrangement was like a wild-cat pitchin' in inter a litter o' young pigs. That gal is smarter than a she cattymount. Ef Mira hadn't taken my part, there wouldn't ha' been much meat left on my bones. Yes, that——Hello!" he exclaimed, suddenly changing the subject, "that cussed Mex'can bewgle agin! Now old Joe, (addressing his rifle,) yer master specks you'll dew yer dewty. Ef yer don't I'll swap ye off for one o them patent critters, what fires six times with ony one loadin'!'</p>
               <p>Thus finishing his unique speech, Dick took a position, which he had assigned himself, while Lt. Woodland summoned his artillerists to the guns.</p>
               <p>The Mexican cavalry were now seen to deploy to the right and to the left, stretching off evidently for the purpose of forming one great circle around the entrenched force, and thus, whenfully prepared, to make one grand charge on all sides.</p>
               <p>It was, truly, a singular military spectacle to behold that little body of Texans, entrenched in a circle, in the center of a vast field, and beyond, in a more extended circle, their merciless foes, ready for the word to rush down upon them, with the barbarous command to give no quarter.</p>
               <p>Soon the Mexicans commenced moving towards their intended prey at a moderate gait, and as they approached their files thickened, until they were formed eight deep, without a break. The order was then given to continue increasing the files in a like manner, after the final order to charge should be given.</p>
               <p>Colonel Fannin, mounted upon his horse, viewed this strange manœuvre with astonishment; and being satisfied that they intended to attack upon all quarters at the same moment, he rode around his encampment to prepare his men to give the Mexicans a hot reception. He saw that if he had a dozen pieces of cannon, instead of four, he could with such tactics on the part of the lancers, annihilate their whole host. As it was, great odds were against him. The alternative seemed only—to conquer or die!</p>
               <p>Presently the loud and clear notes of the enemy's bugle, sounded the charge; onward they came with their accustomed impetuosity, threatening to over-ride every obstacle in their path.</p>
               <p>The Texans reserved their fire until they could almost distinguish the features of the lancers, when simultaneously each howitzer, aimed in four different directions, was discharged, and the terrible effect of each was seen, by the avenues cut through the moving masses. Still the unbroken portions of the circular column galloped on, closing up the gaps as they neared their<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6928-00000013"/> enemy. When within five or six rods of the entrenchment, the order was given for the infantry and riflemen to fire. The musketry rattled and the rifles cracked irregularly, but with astonishing execution. It seemed as if every Texan had picked his man, and that for every shot a lancer fell from his steed.</p>
               <p>Our intrepid Kentuckian, Dick Keen, had mounted an empty baggage wagon, where he loaded and fired his Joe Manton with wonderful rapidity. He took good care not to waste his ammunition on single targets—unless the target was epauleted, and more than a trio of these fell beneath the deadly aim of his rifle. Whenever he got his sight ranged on three or four of the rank and file—or "takin' em rakeways' as he termed it—he was most certain of having the satisfaction of seeing a portion of them reel and fall from their saddles.</p>
               <p>Riderless steeds were seen galloping over the plain in every direction, adding to the confusion and terror of the besiegers. The lancers retreated in great disorder, but having no pursuers the bugle's call soon concentrated them in a solid phalanx a one point, beyond the reach of the galling fire of the Texan howitzers.</p>
               <p>Urrea, finding that his grand original manœuvre resulted only in immense loss and an inglorious repulse, determined to charge, with his whole force concentrated, at one point. The one selected for another grand onslaught, was that occupied by Lt. Woodland's command. Judging from the position now taken by the lancers, that the brunt of the battle was to fall upon his command, he ordered the two howitzers to be double charged with grape and cannister, resolving to give them such a reception as the enemy did not dream of. To support his gallant and heroic lieutenant, Fannin ordered two companies of infantry, and the rifle corps, to station themselves at the right and left of the artillerists.</p>
               <p>The bugle was again heard sounding the charge, and onward came the dense body of lancers at a flying speed and in a fearful array. The tramp of this heavy troop came upon the ears of the Texans, like the rushing of a mighty whirlwind across the prairie. It was now the critical moment of the little band of patriots. All was hushed into awful silence throughout their lines, awaiting to hear the orders of their leaders. Every soul was nerved to the contest, and every soldier felt that his life was pledged upon the issue. Not an order was given—not a word was spoken—not a shot was fired, until the front ranks of the lancers had approached within reach of the muskets of the infantry.</p>
               <p>Fannin's first word of command, given with the voice of a Stentor, rung loud and clear in the ears of every man within the entrenchment. The howitzers first poured forth a most destructive fire, which would have checked any but maddened, infuriated men; but still the great masses pressed on, when volley after volley of bullets from the infantry and riflemen were poured upon them, making terrible havoc in the enemy's ranks. Scores and scores of lancers fell beneath their destructive fire. Gap after gap was closed up and the Mexicans finally reached the breastwork, and many had the daring to leap their horses over it, when commenced a fight, hand to hand with sabres, pistols and other small weapons. The riflemen, following the example of Dick Keen, mounted the wagons, and did terrible execution, for every shot was death to one Mexican at least.</p>
               <p>In the thickest of the deadly fight, Lieut. Woodland was seen to fall—he was struck by a lance which inflicted a severe wound. He was stunned by the blow, and fell apparently lifeless. A moment or two afterwards his devoted wife, who had witnessed his fall, ran to the fatal spot. She uttered a heartrending shriek on beholding his ghastly and frightful wound; and in the agony of her despair, she snatched the sword, reeking with gore, from his grasp, determining if necessary, to sacrifice her own life in avenging his death. She singled out the lancer, whom she had seen strike her husband, she darted towards him and plunged the sword into his vitals, and he fell from his horse a corpse! Suddenly a thought of her child, whom she had left at the entrance of the tent she occupied, rushed upon her mind, and she ran back lest harm should befal<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6928-00000014"/> the exposed little innocent, but to her utter horror and dismay it was gone! She looked about her, and beheld a monkish looking individual, in cowl and cassock, hastening from the scene, bearing the child in his arms! She followed, despite the dangers she had to pass. A dismounted lancer raised his sword to strike the almost frantic woman, but with her husband's bloody weapon, which she yet clung to, she parried the blow, and run him through. Drawing the sword, she continued on, in all haste, in the direction the priest had taken. Simultaneously they reacned the wood together.</p>
               <p>"My child! my child!" shrieked the afflicted mother.</p>
               <p>"Santa Madre!" ejaculated the monk, halting, and peering with his gray eyes from out the holes of a mask which covered his face, "The dam followeth her young—I knew it would be thus. The infant, then, is thine?"</p>
               <p>"'Tis MINE! so help me Heaven!" exclaimed Mrs. Woodland. "Why did you—holy man as you appear, steal my child?"</p>
               <p>"Hold! rash woman!" returned the monk; "I am what I seemeth, a holy man, and cannot do that which thou darest impute to me. Have I not exposed my own life to bear from that scene of bloody strife, thy infant? for I now know, as I gaze upon its tiny features, and upon thine, it is truly thy offspring."</p>
               <p>"Pardon! pardon! holy man, I pray!" cried the young mother; "I wronged you—my mind was so distracted, I scarcely had thought of what I was saying."</p>
               <p>"Thy petition is granted," said the monk; "Come with me—I will be thy guide from these scenes of sanguinary strife to a refuge of safety. Not far from this, the sisters of St. Marie have their abiding place. Thyself, fair but afflicted lady, and thy child, shall have their protection."</p>
               <p>"Thanks—oh, thanks!" cried the grateful lady.</p>
               <p>"Thy husband has fallen in the battle?" said the monk, inquiringly.</p>
               <p>"Alas! he is slain! he is slain!" she cried in agonizing tones. "Let us hasten on, and secure my child's safety, then will I go back to bury the body of my husband!"</p>
               <p>"Nay, lady; thy life will be in imminent peril."</p>
               <p>"If I lose my poor life, I shall meet him in heaven!"</p>
               <p>"And thy child?"</p>
               <p>"Alas! I cannot, I must not leave my child, I must live for is sake."</p>
               <p>"That is rational, lady," said the monk; "the child will be a solace to thee in thy affliction, and a blessing hereafter."</p>
               <p>Twilight shades were now deepening; and after a walk of fifteen minutes, through a winding path of the forest, they emerged into an open space, and stood beneath the walls of a dark, sombre, antiquated looking edifice, not unlike a baronial castle in its appearance. It was the convent of St. Marie. The monk pulled a bell-knob—the door swung on its rusty hinges, and they entered an arched passage, which having gone through, they entered the chapel of this sacred cloister, upon the altar of which was dimly burning several candles. The monk here threw off his cowl and mask, and displayed the features of the identical priest, under whose protection she had once been placed by her father, and who had promised, as our readers will remember, to be answerable for her safe delivery into the hands of the Abbess of the Convent of Sacre Cœur!</p>
               <milestone n="——" unit="typography"/>
               <p>But to return to the battle-field. The stife was over for that day, and the indomitable Texans remained masters of the field. When evening came, the lancers had withdrawn from the contest. On mustering the men and calling the roll, it was found that upwards of four hundred men were killed, and three to four hundred were wounded, while the Texans had but about a dozen killed, and but twenty or thirty disabled from duty. Among the first conveyed to the surgeon's tent, was the gallant Lieutenant Woodland, whose deeds of valor on that memorable day, commanded the admiration of every fellow-soldier. The wound was an ugly one, but to the inquiry of Colonel Fannin, Surgeon Field replied that it was not mortal. The flowing of blood was staunched and the gaping wound was dressed. He<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6928-00000015"/> soon breathed freely, and consciousness was restored to him. He inquired for his wife and child, but no satisfactory information could be imparted to him. Fears of their death for a time well nigh distracted his thoughts, but the confident assurance of Fannin and Field, that no harm had befallen them, other than that they had been taken prisoners by their enemies, who could not, with all their reputation for barbarity, do harm to a defenceless mother and her innocent infant.</p>
               <p>A terrible night, notwithstanding victory sat perched upon the banner of the 'lone star,' was passed in the camp of the Texans. The wounded, as well as those who were not, suffered much from the want of that greatest of all necessaries, water, which was impossible to obtain in the prairie, and it was not deemed prudent by the colonel to venture forth to obtain it.</p>
               <p>That long night at length passed away.—The sun arose upon that field of blood, displaying heart-sickening signs of the terrible slaughter of the evening previous. The enemy had borne from the field their helpless wounded during the night; but not so the dead—for scores of mangled corses were scattered over the plain, stripped of their habiliments, and in many instances, lying side by side with carcases of dead horses.</p>
               <p>Ere the sun had been an hour above the horizon, the enemy again appeared on the skirts of the forest, marshalling themselves in battle array, apparently with the intention of renewing the scenes of the previous day.—It was evident that they had been reinforced; for on the left of the lancers, were now displayed two heavy pieces of cannon. One of these was dragged forward several rods, and fired a heavy hall completetely over the entrenched forces. This was thrice repeated, when, following, a white flag simultaneously was displayed by each of the forces. The two commanders walked forth and met at a proper distance from their respective armies.</p>
               <p>"Colonel Fannin," said General Urrea, embracing him, "yesterday we fought; but to-day we are friends."</p>
               <p>Capitulatory articles were then proposed by Urrea, and agreed to by Fannin, after a brief consultation with his officers and then were committed to writing, with signatures and the accustomed formalities. In these articles, the Texans agreed to surrender, and in consideration the Mexicans agreed to ensure their lives, restore their personal property, and in all respects to be treated as are prisoners of war by the most civilized powers of the world. Furthermore, there was a verbal promise given, to send the prisoners to the nearest port of Mexico, within eight days, thence to be transported to New Orleans, or some other port of the United States.</p>
               <p>In the afternoon of the same day the main body of the prisoners were marched to the fort at Goliad, the wounded of both armies, together with the surgeons, encamping on the field until the next day, when they also were conveyed to the fort.</p>
               <p>The events, which succeeded the capitulation, are worthy of a new chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6928-00000016"/>
               <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
               <head type="sub">SANTA ANNA'S SANGUINARY MANDATE.</head>
               <p>NINE days after the battle of Coletta, two Mexican officers sat in the verandah of a genteel residence; which overlooked the fort at La Bahia de Goliad. The eldest of the two, a tall, swarthy-complexioned gentleman, was splendidly attired in the full dress of a General of the Mexican republic. His companion was about the medium height, careless in his person, having a good-natured physiognomy, and he was attired in a shabbygenteel suit of a Colonel of Lancers. The one smoked a lady's cigaritto, in the most delicate manner imaginable, while the other puffed forth large volumes of smoke from a huge chibouk; the one was a nice, delicate-mannered sort of a gentleman, just the proper model for a lady's drawing-room—the other a bluff, sturdy-looking soldier, with "rough-and-ready" manners, and just the man for storming a fortress, or charging upon an open battery; the one was General Urrea, the other was Colonel Halsinger of the Lancers.</p>
               <p>"Our courier, methinks, should have been here ere this,"said Urrea; "these prisoners are but a curse to us; for they exhaust our provisions, occupy the fort, and are a hard set of men to deal with."</p>
               <p>"By San Iago! we had better let them loose at once, general; when the supply of black-beans is exhausted, they will either create a famine or die from actual starvation."</p>
               <p>"But do you not mean to abide by the terms of capitulation?" asked Halsinger.</p>
               <p>"El demonio!" exclaimed Urrea; "what has so disturbed your usual good sense, colonel, as to make such an inquiry as that?"</p>
               <p>"Simply, that it was agreed to send them to the nearest port of the country."</p>
               <p>"What of that?"</p>
               <p>"A matter of honor—nothing more," replied Halsinger, with a significant expression and a look full of meaning.</p>
               <p>"Honor with barbarian invaders!—you're mad this morning, colonel! Do we not consider it fair game to entrap the Camanches and other savages, when they make incursions among us?"</p>
               <p>"Mentira! that is true; but do you rank these brave men with wild Indians?"</p>
               <p>"In what respects are they better?—answer me that."</p>
               <p>"They appear to be intelligent."</p>
               <p>"Curse their intelligence!"</p>
               <p>"They profess Christianity."</p>
               <p>"Heretics—every devil of 'em!"</p>
               <p>"They are educated, enlightened men.</p>
               <p>"Then is there less excuse for their audacity in entering our territory."</p>
               <p>"They are brave, and in the field behave not like savages!"</p>
               <p>"They behave even worse."</p>
               <p>"I grant you, if the way they served us at Coletta is any criterion," said the colonel, in slightly ironical tones.</p>
               <p>"No more of that, Halsinger!" said Urrea; for that battle was a sore subject to this popinjay general.</p>
               <p>"I feel a little ashamed of that affair myself," replied Halsinger; "but a truce to that—what do you suppose Santa Anna's orders will be, as regards the disposition of the rebels?"</p>
               <p>"He will agree, I have no doubt, with my advice in the matter."</p>
               <p>"Prithee, what is that?"</p>
               <pb n="32-33 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6928-00000017"/>
               <p>"To shoot every cursed rebel!" answered Urrea, with the utmost sang froid.</p>
               <p>"Heaven forbid! that the President of the boasted magnanimous Mexican nation should issue such a horrible mandate as that!" replied Halsinger. "It would be sufficient to disgrace him in the eyes of the whole civilized world!"</p>
               <p>"I think it would be a greater disgrace to set these wretches tree!"</p>
               <p>The conversation was here interrupted by loud huzzas from the little plaza of Goliad, and in a few moments a courier, mounted on a fleet charger, dashed across the open space, and halted before the mansion occupied as the head-quarters of General Urrea. The rider dismounted, took a packet from his chaqueta, and leaving his horse to the care of a groom, he hurried to the general's apartment, when he was met at the door by Urrea himself.</p>
               <p>"Welcome, Giberto, to Goliad!" said the general, receiving a packet from the hands of the courier. "By your appearance you have ridden hard to-day! What news at Bexar?"</p>
               <p>"Your letters and dispatches will give you information of a startling character," replied Giberto, as he bowed himself out of the apartment.</p>
               <p>"What news, General?" inquired Halsinger, entering after Urrea had finished perusing the contents of the packet.</p>
               <p>"As I anticipated."</p>
               <p>"That is sufficiently indefinite for the most cunning non-commitalist," answered the colonel, slightly piqued.</p>
               <p>"Extermination is the word!"</p>
               <p>"I understand that a <emph>little</emph> better, though it is somewhat ambiguous."</p>
               <p>"Well, colonel, to be plain with you, since you are somewhat dull of comprehension to-day, we have, in the first place, to shoot all the Coletta prisoners!"</p>
               <p>"Shoot them?" ejaculated Halsinger, with a look of amazement.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>THE FLYING ARTILLERIST MEXICAN</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6928-00000018"/>
               <p>"I said—shoot—all—the—Coletta—prisoners!" said Urrea. emphasizing each syllable. "Do you understand now?"</p>
               <p>"I do—and I do not hesitate to say that it is horrible to contemplate!" replied Halsinger; "but you will not execute the merciless mandate?"</p>
               <p>"As certainly as I hope to enjoy a good dinner to-day!" answered Urrea, with the utmost complacency.</p>
               <p>"Does this order proceed from his Excellency the President?"</p>
               <p>"It does—and I heartily approve of his judgement. Santa Anna is none of your mealy-tongued officials; there is none of the imbecile Bustamente about him."</p>
               <p>"No—in this affair, he has shown himself a monster!" replied the colonel.</p>
               <p>"Come, come, colonel—such language is treasonous!"</p>
               <p>"Call it what you will; it is an honest opinion, freely and fearlessly expressed."</p>
               <p>"Well, well, colonel," said Urrea, "here is the mandate, and it must be obeyed. To-morrow-morning, at a sunrise, see that it be duly executed!"</p>
               <p>Halsinger stared Urrea in the face for nearly a minute, as if doubling, whether he clearly understood his last sentence.</p>
               <p>"What did I understand you to say, General?" he inquired.</p>
               <p>"At sunrise, to-morrow-morning, see that this mandate, which you perceive, contains the great seal of the executive, be executed!" said Urrea emphatically.</p>
               <p>"Who?"</p>
               <p>"You!"</p>
               <p>"What, me?"</p>
               <p>"I—said—you!"</p>
               <p>"If the mandate contained the great seal of St. Peter himself, I'd not obey it!" replied Halsinger.</p>
               <p>"What, disobey orders?"</p>
               <p>"By all the blessed saints! I swear, that sooner than issue this murderous command, I would see you, Santa Anna, and all Mexico sunk in the lowest depths of the regions of his Satanic Majesty!"</p>
               <p>"Colonel—colonel—this will not do!" said Urrea, trying to aim the temper, into which he had thrown Halsinger. "Thus far, between us, have ever existed the most amicable feelings. You do not perceive the consequences of refusing obedience to orders!"</p>
               <p>"General," replied the colonel, "when I accepted a commission in the Mexican army, I made myself liable to its regulations. If this be one of them. I know the penalty of disobedience, and therefore, will throw up my commission. I will fight for the Republic in honorable warfare! but on my reputation as a soldier, I will not lie, steal or murder for this or any other nation!"</p>
               <p>"Upon my word, colonel, you regard this insolent, vandal crew too highly!" said Urrea. "They deserve neither love, sympathy, or clemency from us!"</p>
               <p>"But they do demand that the terms of capitulation shall be complied with! Our honor, your honor, General, the honor of the Mexican nation, will be compromised, if this matter is pushed to extremities!"</p>
               <p>"Then you have resolved not to obey?"</p>
               <p>"I have—I'll die first!"</p>
               <p>With this emphatic answer, Colonel Halsinger bade the general good morning, and strode out of the apartment.</p>
               <p>In the course of the half hour following, Urrea received the resignation of Halsinger, as colonel in the Mexican, army, accompannied by his commission.</p>
               <p>"Halsinger is a fool!" exclaimed Urrea, "and—"</p>
               <p>But before he could finish the sentence, Major Olente was announced, and in walked or rather strode, a swaggering, thickset Mexican officer, who had as villanous a countenance as ever smiled upon a murder.</p>
               <p>"Ah, Major Olente, you're the very man I most desired to see, and was on the point of sending for you. Be seated."</p>
               <p>"What's afoot now, general. Anything desperate to be done?" asked Olente.</p>
               <p>"Those four hundred barbarians must be shot at sunrise, tomorrow morning!"</p>
               <pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6928-00000019"/>
               <p>"That's all right, and just as it should be," said the major, "the wretches are a nuisance in the fort."</p>
               <p>"I wish you to execute the mandate," said Urrea.</p>
               <p>"With all my heart," replied Olente; "the job will give me a good appetite for breakfast!"</p>
               <p>"Perform it expeditiously, and it may gain you promotion. How would you like Halsinger's place?"</p>
               <p>"I might want until doomsday and not get it."</p>
               <p>"There is a fair prospect of it, for Halsinger has resigned."</p>
               <p>"The devil he has! Then there is a hope indeed! But how's this?" asked the delighted Olente.</p>
               <p>"He preferred to throw up his commission rather than execute the mandate of Santa Anna, to shoot the vandals!"</p>
               <p>"I ever surmised there was a soft spot in his skull," remarked the major</p>
               <p>"Which you can now turn into profit," added Urrea. "Obey the order—do it well—and I shall commend you to the general's favor in my next dispatches. Spare only their surgeons—we have need of their services for a few days longer, and then they can be dispatched."</p>
               <p>"Rely upon me, general," replied Olente, and with an additional swagger to his usual gait, he retired from the presence of his commander.</p>
               <milestone n="——" unit="typography"/>
               <p>After the conditional surrender at Coletta, Doctors Field and Barnard, the surgeons attached to Fannin's command, were ordered to leave their own sick and wounded, and attend upon several wounded Mexican officers, and while the former were thrown promiscuously into open carts like so much useless rubbish, the latter were conveyed in carriages, to the fort at Goliad, and behind these carriages the Texan surgeons were compelled to walk, so as to render any assistance that the officers might require, notwithstanding there was a large surplus of horses and mules without riders or any other burden.</p>
               <p>After a tedious march they reached Goliad, (which olace had previously been in possession of the Texans,) and here the most decent apartment within the walls of the fortress—this being almost destitute of comforts—was allowed to be occupied by the Mexican officers, the patients of their foes. The two surgeons, however, did all their watchfulness and professional skill could do to alleviate their sufferings. Indeed, so faithful were they to their trust, that they gained their implicit confidence and their favor. A few days subsequent to their arrival, Dr. Field, at his earnest entreaty, gained permission of these officers to allow Capt. Brooks, one of the most severely wounded of the Texan prisoners, to be brought into their apartment, that he, also, might receive the advantage of the professional services of his own countrymen. The captain was brought in, and the only blanket in possession of the surgeons was placed over him, he having been stripped of almost every article of covering, as were most of the prisoners, by the merciless Mexicans.</p>
               <p>On the afternoon of the same day that Major Olente had received from his general, the mandate for a general massacre, this swaggering fiend obtruded himself, with a file of soldiers at his back, into the presence of these wounded officers, not because of the least solicitude on his part touching their health, but merely for the vain purpose of acquainting them with the additional dignity he had acquired in his commission for shooting some four hundred men in cold blood, and his ultimate prospects of promotion to the rank of colonel.</p>
               <p>"By San Jago! we're to have rare sport!" said the bully major, addressing Lieutenant Mendoza, one of the invalid officers.</p>
               <p>"What's on foot now?" inquired Mendoza.</p>
               <p>"The dam'd ragged barbarians are to be shot at sunrise, tomorrow morning!" said Olente, whispering in his ear. "Will you not be able to hobble forth to see the fun?"</p>
               <p>"Are you in earnest, Major?"</p>
               <p>"By our holy faith, I am! and I can boast of the honor of being selected to superintend the business!"</p>
               <pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC6928-00000020"/>
               <p>"You're jesting?"</p>
               <p>"When you hear the morning gun, come forth and see," insisted Olente.</p>
               <p>"Still I think you're imposing upon me!" continued Mendoza.</p>
               <p>"The general would not dare——"</p>
               <p>"His Excellency, however would. But to show you your own incredulity, behold that!" and he unfolded and displayed to his astonished gaze, the sanguinary mandate, with the signature and seal of His Excellency General Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna, President of the Republic, etc. etc.!"</p>
               <p>"I am amazed!" exclaimed Mendoza.</p>
               <p>"The cursed vandal crew will be!" added Olente. "But, Mendoza, you will be well enough to come and witness the pastime. It will be a better entertainment than a dozen bull-fights together!"</p>
               <p>"No. Señor Olente!" answered the lieutenant, emphatically: "and if I had the free use of all my limbs and faculties I should be loth to witness even the execution of a single man, unless he were a spy or a traitor! We shall gain nothing but the curses of the whole world by such a diabolical outrage!"</p>
               <p>"Out upon you, Mendoza, for such an opinion!" exclaimed the major, angrily. "By the blessed Virgin, I swear that I wish there was as many thousands as there are hundreds of them!"</p>
               <p>"Better, Major, swear by some infernal deity, and not thus desecrate the name of the Holy Virgin!"</p>
               <p>"No by all the Heavenly Host I speak my soul's truth!" returned the blasphemous butcher. "I tell you, Mendoza, they are but fit food for powder and ball! It will be an act of charity to put an end to the existence of the suffering wretches. Their ragged and half-famished condition proves it!"</p>
               <p>"Are all to be shot?" ejaculated the lieutenant.</p>
               <p>"Every devil of them!"</p>
               <p>"Are NONE exempt?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, I had forgotten—the surgeons are for ultimate disposal."</p>
               <p>"No officers? not even their colonel?"</p>
               <p>"There is no distinction to be made—all must fall together."</p>
               <p>"Horrible!"</p>
               <p>"Excellent, say I—ah! who have we here?" ejaculated Olente, espying the Texan captain, who had been suffered to be removed from a filthy, noisome dungeon to comparatively less uncomfortable quarters. "This, by his white-livered looks should be one of the miserable barbarians!" and, seizing the blanket, he had partially dragged it from the body of the suffering man, when surgeon Field darted forward, and snatching it from the hands of the ruffian he replaced it!</p>
               <p>"Ah, miscreant!" he exclaimed, drawing his sword; "I have the power to annihilate you at a blow!" and again seizing the covering, he succeeded in dragging it away.</p>
               <p>Field remonstrated, and would again have defeated the attempt, despite the major's threatening aspect, had not Lieutenant Mendoza begged him not to offer any opposition, lest he should be slain on the spot.</p>
               <p>"Seize this Texan dog!" commanded Olente, addressing the soldiers behind him, and pointing to the prostrate Capt. Brooks; "drag him into the court among his fellows. We'll soon make carrion of these vagabond invaders."</p>
               <p>This inhuman order was obeyed, and as they dragged him over the rough stone floor, from the apartment, he cast a last farewell look of resignation at Surgeon Field, who was sobbing like a child at this cruel specimen of Mexican barbarity!</p>
               <p>"You're a surgeon?" asked Olente, addressing Field.</p>
               <p>"I can vouch for that," answered Mendoza. "I should have been now food for worms, but for his skill."</p>
               <p>"And you also are a surgeon?" inquired Olente of Barnard.</p>
               <p>"For him, too, I'll vouch," replied the lieutenant.</p>
               <p>"Are there any more leeches belonging to this vandal host?" asked the major.</p>
               <p>"I have an assistant who is wounded!" said Field, a lucky thought flashing across his brain, that he might, by an excusable deception, be of essential service to, and even, perchance, save the life of young Woodland, who he understood from<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC6928-00000021"/> Mendoza's servant was confined in one of the subterranean dungeons of the fort.</p>
               <p>"Follow me, you d——d Yankee leech, and point him out" commanded Olente.</p>
               <p>Field was escorted by this brutal officer through the courts and dungeons where the prisoners were confined. Having surveyed nearly all without finding the object of their search, they came to a trapdoor which opened into a large, dark dungeon, where nearly a score of prisoners were immured. These, however, had fared better than the prisoners above ground, their subterraneous situation protecting them from the thieving propensities of the Mexican soldiers; therefore, they had escaped thus far from having their covering stripped from their backs.</p>
               <p>"Is Woodland here?" cried Field, when the trap was thrown open.</p>
               <p>Woodland, hearing his name, answered affirmatively.</p>
               <p>"He is here?" said Field to Olente.</p>
               <p>"Then let him come forth," said the major.</p>
               <p>"Woodland, you have permission to come forth," said Field, "I will come down to assist you."</p>
               <p>But Woodland's wounds had nearly healed, and he at once clambered up the mouldy and damp steps of the dungeon without assistance.</p>
               <p>"You're a surgeon, I am told?" said Olente to Woodland, inquiringly.</p>
               <p>He hesitated for a moment, but a significant glance from the dark, intelligent eye of Field, caused him to give an affirmative answer.</p>
               <p>"Then you're a lucky fellow!" said Olente. "Surgeon, take this man to the quarters; but if I detect either of you giving the least comfort to any prisoner, I'll have you quartered and hanged!"</p>
               <p>This threat being given, accompanied by a most profuse volley of profane epithets, Olente went to make preparations for the sanguinary business of the morning, and Field and Woodland repaired to the apartment of the wounded Mexicar officers.</p>
               <p>Ere the sun had risen on the following morning, the prisoners were mustered in squads of a score, and after stringing each squad together like a drove of horses, they were marched forth into an open field, under strong guards, without communicating to them the least intimation of the bloody business at hand Most of them supposed that they were thus to be driven from the country, while others believed that they were to be escorted to the nearest seaport, as was verbally promised at the capitulation, thence to be transported to the United States.</p>
               <p>When all the squads had reached the field, they were drawn up in a single line, and facing them at a distance of four rods, were paraded upwards of a thousand Mexican infantry, in files, two deep. At right angles, on the right and left, extending from the wings of both parties, were marshalled two companies of lancers, for a purpose easily to be conjectured by the reader.</p>
               <p>Prancing to and fro on a high mettled charger along the Mexican lines, and swelling with importance, could be seen the bloodthirsty Major Olente, giving orders, in a low tone of voice to his several subordinates.</p>
               <p>When all was prepared, the sun, like an orb of molten fire, arose from above the horizon. A heavy gun boomed forth the dread signal from the fort, and ere its echoes had died away, the voice of Olente, raised to a cracked pitch succeeded.</p>
               <p>"Ready!—Aim!—Fire!" were the words which were belched forth from his rough throat.</p>
               <p>Three successive volleys of musketry were fired at intervals of not more than three seconds! The cries, shrieks, groans and yells of dying and wounded men was too horrible to relate—i beggared all description. Nearly half of the prisoners were shot dead, and as many more wounded! A few only had escaped the shower of bullets, only to be cut or trampled down by the lancers, as they vainly endeavored to escape from the massacre!—Those who had one spark of life visible in their bodies, were either bayoneted by the infantry, or pierced by the lances of the cavalry.</p>
               <p>In less than fifteen minutes the last of this most appalling<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6928-00000022"/> tragedy was finished!—this great act of Mexican treachery and barbarity was consummated, in a manner highly gratifying to Olente, and to Urrea, and to their tyrannical master, the infamous Santa Anna!</p>
               <p>The Mexican forces were immediately marched back to the fort, to partake of an unusually palatable banquet, which had been prepared for them, as a reward for their morning's butchery. Two Mexican soldiers were left on the blood-stained field to guard the dead, or rather to observe that none came to life. If such a miracle should occur, their orders were to dispatch them at once.</p>
               <p>When the first volley of musketry was poured upon the defenceless prisoners, our old friend, Dick Keen, received a slight wound in the neck; but he fell as if killed outright, and took good care to besmear his face with blood and dirt. He then stretched himself out, and by the time the smoke cleared away, he seemed as much like a corpse as any one of his comrades, who were not so fortunate in having an opportunity to sham; yet when he deemed it prudent he took occasion to peer out of one eye, to observe the situation of affairs.</p>
               <p>After the troops had marched from the field, he observed that the two sentinels, instead of watching the corpses, commenced the work of ransacking their pockets, for tobacco, knives, and such other matters as had not been filched from them while living.</p>
               <p>One of these human vultures approached the Kentuckian, and began to rifle his pockets. Dick had a half eye open upon the fellow, and when he got one hand fairly into his breeches pocket, he suddenly seized him by the throat, with a tiger-like grip, rolled him over upon the earth, and pressing his fingers firmly about the windpipe, he strangled him to death in less than thirty seconds, without noise and with but a faint struggle from his victim. Dick then donned the fellow's hat and coat, took his musket, and after making sure of the strangled Mexican by running the bayonet through his body, he began creeping about among the slain, seemingly committing the same petty depredations that he had discovered in the individual he was now endeavoring to personate.</p>
               <p>All this was accomplished while the other sentinel, in another portion of the field, was busily engaged in providing himself with a tolerably good suit of garments from the corpse of a murdered officer, and who was entirely ignorant of the incident which had just occurred.</p>
               <p>Dick commenced a slow oblique movement towards the busy sentinel, taking good care not to expose his phiz. He managed, finally, to get to the rear of his enemy, within the distance of a couple of rods; and while the fellow was in a stooping position over the dead body, Dick suddenly charged bayonet upon him, and run him completely through the body.</p>
               <p>The Kentuckian was now master of that field of dead, and he gazed with tearful eyes and sorrowing heart upon the remains of his late comrades. He was the only survivor of all who had been led forth that morning to execution; but there was solace to his mind that they were better off than they had been since the day of the capitulation; for if ever human beings suffered in this world, Fannin's men suffered; they were cruelly, brutally, mercilessly treated from the hour of their surrender until the hour of their most foul murder!</p>
               <p>Dick's sorrowful reflections were put to an end, by the appearance of a file of soldiers from behind an angle of the fort.</p>
               <p>"May eternal vengeance light upon this treacherous nation! May God spare my life to revenge my comrades' death!"</p>
               <p>Thus prayerfully soliloquizing, Dick escaped, unobserved, from the field, and with an old Spanish musket and bayonet, instead of trusty "Joe Manton," he penetrated into the forest, and after encountering almost insurmountable difficulties, he succeeded in getting out of the Mexican country. In a few days he reached the camp of the main body of the Texan army, and reported himself to General Houston, to whom he communicated the details of the sad fate of Col Fannin's command.</p>
               <p>The battle of San Jacinto was fought a few days afterwards, in which our brave Kentuckian bore a conspicuous part, and<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6928-00000023"/> was one of those notable characters who "treed" Santa Anna and carried him a captive into the Texan camp.</p>
               <p>It was certainly a great act of forbearance on the part of the Texans, and will ever be so regarded by the world, that Santa Anna's life was spared by the Taxans, when the tale of Mexican treachery and butchery was so fresh in their ears.</p>
               <milestone n="——" unit="typography"/>
               <p>In the course of ten days after the massacre, Surgeons Field and Barnard, including Woodland, contrived to effect an escape from the fort. They were permitted to go to a spring, for water, outside the walls of the fort; and on one occasion, from some unknown cause, there was no sentinel on duty, which fact was discovered by Field, and by him immediately communicated to his companions. They forthwith improved this opportunity, and sallied forth without discovery and gained the forest, where they remained concealed until night, when they recommenced their perilous flight; and after wending their way for several nights through dense woods and chapparals, fording creeks and swimming rivers, and wading through miry swamps, they reached the Taxan camp, where they corroborated the story of the general massacre as related by Keen, who, of course they were surprised as well as pleased to meet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE PRISONER OF VERA CRUZ.</head>
               <p>WE here take a romancer's license, and pass over a period of eleven years, with a brief allusion to several important events which meanwhile occurred, and also to the whereabouts and position of several of the most conspicuous characters, who figured in the introductory chapters of this well-authenticated tale.</p>
               <p>The independence of Taxas was achieved by such brave spirits as fought at the Alamo and at Coletta, and she, as an independent nation was acknowledged not only by several great powers of the world, but by her unscrupulous foe, Mexico herself. Subsequently the "lone star" of Taxas was admitted into the bright constellation of states, which compose our Federal Union; and, in a few years following, and army of occupation was sent to the Rio Grande, which led to some occurrences intimately touching the most prominent characters already introduced to the reader.</p>
               <p>After Taxas had gained her independence, our hero, Henry Woodland, resigned his commission in the army of the Republic, and returned to the United States. The loss of his wife and child, whom he supposed dead, bore heavily upon him, and his friends believed that there was great danger of his sinking under the affliction. Time wore on, and he partially recovered his health and spirits, and by urgent request he was then in<pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC6928-00000024"/> duced to accept a lieutenant's commission in the army of the United States, thinking that a life in the camp might, perhaps, drive away his melancholy altogether. He was, after a year's discipline in an infantry corps, transferred to a company of Flying Artillerists, which was under marching orders for Corpus Christi.—On the arrival of his company at the post, he was surprised and pleased to meet with his old friend, Dick Keen, the eccentric Kentuckian, who came into camp with no other companion than a second "Joe Manton" upon his shoulder.</p>
               <p>Woodland recognized him at a glance. No wonder, for no other man ever moved with a pair of legs like Dick Keen's. He wore, too, that same peculiar roundabout; the identical cap, and a pair of breeches of the same cut and material, that he wore in the Texan campaign. The lieutenant approached him and said:</p>
               <p>"If my eyes do not deceive me, your name is Keen, from Kentucky?"</p>
               <p>"Stranger, you're right," said Dick; "Keen is my name, and one mought jest as easy mistake a bar for a wild-cat, as to mistake me for any thing but a Kentuckian. But, stranger, I hope to be barked if I hain't seen your target afore. Who mought you be?"</p>
               <p>"My name is Woodland—one of the few survivors of Fannin's command!"</p>
               <p>"Steamboats and alligators! May I want a mother's bless'n if I didn't begin to think so!" exclaimed Dick, eagerly. "Gin us your paw! I'm happier to meet you, than if I'd met Mira or Davy out here. I ain't forgot that time you gin it to the cussed Mex'cans in that cord'roy road, with them barkers o' yourn. How you did pile 'em up! But, my friend, I reckon by your 'quipment, you've got to be one o' Uncle Sam's reg'lars."</p>
               <p>"Yes; I am now attached to a company of Flying Artillerists."</p>
               <p>"And them I take to be your little pocket pieces, out thar?" said Dick, inquiringly, and pointing to the battery. "If we'd ony had a dozen o' them out on that infernal prairie, I reckon we shouldn't ha' gi'n them black-hearted cutthroats a chance to trap us as they did. My blood biles when I think o' the treach'-rous rascals."</p>
               <p>"If we had all been as wise as yourself, my friend, the offer of capitulation would never have been accepted. Agreeing to it proved a most fatal mistake; but our Colonel thought he was treating with a foe, claiming to be somewhat better than savages!"</p>
               <p>"Cuss the varmint!" resumed the Kentuckian; "I and Old Joe fixed about two hundred o' their flints for 'em, but we're worse off than afore. I reckoned that we avenged Uncle Davy Crockett's death. Now we've got to pay 'em off for shootin' so many on us at Goliad. I think not less than the blood of a thousand Mex'cans will pay 'em off for that job!"</p>
               <p>"Then you anticipate a war?" inquired Woodland.</p>
               <p>"That's the idee we've got up in Kaintuck. We heard that Taylor had been ordered to the Rio Grande, which I reckoned was 'quivalent to a brush with the cussed Mex'cans; so I shouldered Joe, and here I am."</p>
               <p>"What corps are you attached to?"</p>
               <p>"None."</p>
               <p>"Do you desire to enlist?"</p>
               <p>"No—I leetle prefer campaigning it on my own hook—Joe and I."</p>
               <p>"Then it appears you have got your Joe Manton back from the Mexicans?"</p>
               <p>"Not exactly; I had my hands full to get away myself from he cussed yellar skins; I had to strangle one—the other I spitted as I would ha' sarved a wild-cat! But this rifle is one o' the same sort—a leetle keener at a long shot—I call it Joe, Junior—coz I've had a sort o' presentiment that I should see Old Joe again. By the way, lieutenant—beg pardon, perhaps you're a captain?"</p>
               <p>"Only a lieutenant"</p>
               <pb n="48-49 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6928-00000025"/>
               <p>"I was about to inquire o' you, if the wife and little un was ever heard from?"</p>
               <p>"Not a syllable, my friend," replied Woodland, while tears glistened in his eyes.</p>
               <p>"That was a strange affair."</p>
               <p>"It would be great satisfaction, whether living or dead, to know in what mysterious manner they disappeared from the camp."</p>
               <p>"It's my 'pinion, though 'tain't wuth much, that the monk story had some truth in it."</p>
               <p>"And what is that, pray?" eagerly inquired Woodland. "I know of no story about a monk."</p>
               <p>"I heard of it first when we were hived up in the Goliad prison; I didn't believe it at the time; but Dr. Field said arterwards in Texas that he hadn't much doubt of it."</p>
               <p>"Well, what does it amount to?" asked the lieutenant, impatiently.</p>
               <p>"After you had fallen, an old monk somehow or nuther got into the camp, picked up your little 'un, and run away with it; then the mother was seen running arter both—The riflemen would ha' put an ounce or two o' cold lead into the monk's carcase, had they not feared to harm the child."</p>
               <p>"Merciful Heavens!" exclaimed Woodland; "this intelligence gives me one faint gleam of hope that they yet may be in the land of the living! But it is strange, indeed, that I never heard a lisp of this before!"</p>
               <p>"None of us b'lieved it at the time," replied Keen; "besides, you were separated from the main body of the pris'ners."</p>
               <p>"You said it was a monk?"</p>
               <p>"So I was told."</p>
               <p>"A monk should be a holy man!" said Woodland, as if soliloquizing.</p>
               <p>"I'd like to trap a holy Mex'can—he'd be a nat'ral curiosity, just the thing to show in a menagerie."</p>
               <p>"But the monks in Mexico are nearly all Spaniards, and there must be some good men among them."</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>WOODLAND FREED FROM THE DUNGEON. See p.44.</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC6928-00000026"/>
               <p>The interview between these two survivors of Fannin's command, was here interrupted by the trumpeter's call for a parade of the Flying Artillerists.</p>
               <milestone n="——" unit="typography"/>
               <p>Thirty days subsequent to Dick Keen's arrival in camp, the "Army of Observation" had reached the Rio Grande, and hostilities immediately commenced. The battles of Palo Alto, Resaca de la Palma, and the occupation of Matamoras, were the most important events which followed in rapid succession; in all of which, none of equal rank bore a more gallant part than Lieut. Woodland, and for his bravery he was breveted to a captaincy, and upon him soon devolved the command of the corps. After the siege of Monterey, where he also distinguished himself, his company was ordered to join Scott at Vera Cruz. The brilliant achievements of the Americans in bombarding and capturing this stronghold of the Mexicans, are matters of history, and need no comments from us.</p>
               <p>The victorious Americans had been in possession of San Juan de Ulloa and the citadel but a few days, when Woodland was commissioned to visit the great prison of the city, and set at liberty all persons who were therein confined for political offenses. Accompanied by an officer of subordinate rank, and a file of soldiers, he commenced his task. He questioned each one as to his name, rank, and offense for which he suffered imprisonment, and each story was either corroborated or falsified by the records of the prison.—In one of the dungeons last entered, was discovered a dignified-looking man in age somewhat past the prime of manhood, with a long, bushy beard hanging over his breast, and a countenance emaciated evidently by suffering long endured. He arose, and stood in a commanding attitude when Woodland and his party entered.</p>
               <p>"Americanos!" he ejaculated, somewhat surprised.</p>
               <p>"Si, Senor," replied Woodland.</p>
               <p>"You are conquerors?" he said, inquiringly.</p>
               <p>"We are in possession of your great castle and the citadel."</p>
               <p>"Then all is lost! alas! my poor, ill-fated country! he said, while sighs and sobs interrupted his speech. "My prediction is fulfilled! But why should I complain? The miscreants in power have brought me to this! My advice and admonition were construed into treason, and for it I have suffered eleven long years within these adamantine walls! therefore, for your wrongs and mine, let vengeance light upon the heads of the whole tyrannical host!"</p>
               <p>The prisoner's eyes gleamed wildly while he spake, and he increased in eloquence and vehemence as he went on, dilating upon the narrow, imbecile policy of the Mexican rulers.</p>
               <p>Woodland listened to the sensible remarks of the prisoner with much interest; and more than once the thought occurred to him that the voice was not wholly unfamiliar to his ears, and that he had somewhere looked upon that commanding figure before. When and where he could not remember.</p>
               <p>"Did I understand that you had been incarcerated here for eleven years?" inquired Woodland.</p>
               <p>"It is true, Senor," replied the prisoner. "Ever since the night after the brutal massacre at Goliad, my eyes have not gazed upon the blessed sun! I have been here caged, like a wild beast, and fed scantily each day by my keeper, who is either deaf and dumb, or refuses, with unparalleled stubbornness, to reply to a single question, or give me a sign or a look that I can comprehend! He comes and goes like an automaton; and this, too, have I endured for eleven long years!"</p>
               <p>"The massacre at Goliad, did you say?" ejaculated Woodland.</p>
               <p>"Si, Senor."</p>
               <p>"Then all who were concerned in that diabolical atrocity deserve even greater torments than you have endured!" declared Woodland, vehemently. "A life-time of lingering torture should have been the fate of the butchers!"</p>
               <p>"True, SenorAmericano!" resumed the prisoner, "but torture was reserved for those only who sympathized with the Texans who were murdered, and for those who declined, officially, to make themselves murderers. Those who obeyed orders to take<pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC6928-00000027"/> part in the sanguinary business, have been rewarded by the tyrants in power. Santa Anna, I accidentally heard, is again at the head of the affairs of the nation. Urrea, that dandy general, still holds his place in the army, and has had high civil honors bestowed upon him. That fiend incarnate, Olente, who executed the barbarous mandate, has received a general's commission; and even the meanest of the officers under him, have been rewarded either by civil or military honors; while Lieut. Mendoza—a braver young officer never held commission in the Mexican army—was executed, on the charge of having in some way or another assisted in the escape of three young Texan surgeons. The charge was substantiated only by an oath of Olente, which I should have regarded with as little faith, as I would in the oath of the arch-fiend himself!"</p>
               <p>"As little would I, in that matter," murmured Woodland to himself.</p>
               <p>"As for myself, I committed, in the eyes of my superiors, a somewhat less offense," continued the prisoner. "I then held the rank of Colonel in the Lancers, and was the first man to refuse to become a government murderer! and immediately sacrificed my commission, rather than to sacrifice my soul. But the resignation of my place did not satisfy the rapacious, blood-thirsty monsters who misruled our nation. I was accused of being a dangerous man to be at liberty—then boldly charged with being a traitor to the government—I was arrested, arraigned, and after a species of mock trial which I did not understand, I was declared guilty, and sentenced to be immured within these dungeon walls during the remainder of my existence, which, I thank God, must soon close. The vapors of this cell, together with the unwholesome food furnished me, have already begun to make inroads upon my health, and will soon put me beyond the casualties and torments of this world! During the long, long period of my incarceration, I have not looked upon the faces of my beloved wife and children, (who I doubt not, believe me dead,); neither have I seen a friend, nor any human being, unless my non-descript keeper can be so termed, until this visit which you have honored me with—for what purpose I have not yet been informed?" he said with an inquiring and piercing gaze.</p>
               <p>"That you shall quickly learn!" said Woodland, almost affected to tears. "I think you said that you were a colonel?"</p>
               <p>"Si, Senor—a colonel of lancers."</p>
               <p>"Did you witness the slaughter which you have alluded to?"</p>
               <p>"Thank God, my eyes were spared that horrid spectacle!"</p>
               <p>"Were you at the battle on the prairie of Coletta?"</p>
               <p>"I am quite ashamed to confess that I commanded a regiment of lancers on that occasion," replied the prisoner. "It was the most disgraceful affair to Mexican arms that ever I was engaged in; but we did all that men could do, under the orders of an imprudent, imbecile commander. We were eighteen hundred strong, had advantage of position, &amp;c., and yet we were beaten by four hundred undisciplined Texans; but a braver little body of men never fought! They mowed down our troops as if they had been but so many spears of prairie grass, ready for the sickle!"</p>
               <p>"Deem me not impertinent," said Woodland, "if I ask your name?"</p>
               <p>"Rodriguez Halsinger!"</p>
               <p>"Halsinger—Colonel Halsinger—I remember the name distinctly." remarked Woodland.</p>
               <p>"You, Senor?" ejaculated the prisoner, with surprise.</p>
               <p>"I am one of the four who escaped the massacre!"</p>
               <p>"You?" queried Halsinger with an incredulous look. "It was said that but three escaped, and they were surgeons, whose execution was put off only because our wounded required their services?"</p>
               <p>Besides the three surgeons, one who feigned dead on the field of execution, finally made his escape."</p>
               <p>"God be praised that one more escaped!" exclaimed Halsinger. "It was the avowed intention of the butchers that not one should survive to tell the barbarous tale to the civilized nations of the earth! But, let me look at your face." Continued<pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC6928-00000028"/> the prisoner, approaching Woodland. "Were you in that desperate conflict on the prairie?"</p>
               <p>"I was."</p>
               <p>"An officer?"</p>
               <p>"A lieutenant—my name is Woodland."</p>
               <p>"I remember that name well—but, methinks, he was a surgeon."</p>
               <p>"Only an assistant at the fort. I deceived my captors, and saved my life; but it grieves me to know that Mendoza had to suffer because of our escape. He was entirely innocent of having connived at it, nor could he have been apprised of it until after we had fled. The truth was, there was no sentinel on duty at the point of egress, and we availed ourselves of his absence."</p>
               <p>"Just as I thought," said the prisoner; "I believed that Mendoza suffered innocently. How many more deaths have been caused by the treachery of men in power at that time, it is difficult to ascertain. Our unhappy country would have been spared much misery if the terms of capitulation at Goliad had been fulfilled to the letter."</p>
               <p>"Then I presume, you well remember the terms?" inquired Woodland.</p>
               <p>"When I forget all that transpired from the first terrible havoc your guns made upon our front in the road leading to the prairie, up to the time of the massacre, I shall have lost my memory entirely. Those events are indelibly impressed upon my mind; and I hesitate not to declare that, to that one great act of treachery, may mainly be attributed the immense evils which are constantly afflicting this ill-starred nation, and for which, in the future, she will have to pay penance for. Santa Anna, Urrea, Ampudia, Olente, and their unscrupulous minions must be annihilated, ere the nation can have peace for any considerable period."</p>
               <p>"Does your memory serve you sufficiently well to retain the more trifling incide its of the battle of Coletta?" asked Woodland.</p>
               <p>"It were impossible to forget any thing that I was an eye witness of."</p>
               <p>"Saw you a man, on the field that day, in cowl and cassock?"</p>
               <p>"A monk, do you mean?"</p>
               <p>"So his exterior indicated?"</p>
               <p>Halsinger paused for a few moments, and then with a look of confidence replied,</p>
               <p>"I did!—I did!—I recollect it well—let me think—it was Padre Francis, a monk attached at that time to the convent of San Marie, which establishment was situated but a short distance from the prairie. I saw him hastening from the field with something in his arms, which I afterwards learned was a child he had rescued from the perils of the conflict! Following him, at a few rods distant, was a female, who appeared to be also seeking a refuge of safety."</p>
               <p>"This is, truly, a corroboration of the story of the Kentuckian!" said Woodland to himself. "Is this Father Francis, of whom you speak, known to you?" he inquired, after a short pause.</p>
               <p>"Not personally—I had seen him prior to the time of the battle, and had heard him frequently spoken of."</p>
               <p>"Know you anything of his character?"</p>
               <p>"Nothing—except that he was formerly a priest of the Catholic church—had but recently attached himself to the Convent I have alluded to—and I believe he came from New Orleans."</p>
               <p>"Indeed!—was he an American?"</p>
               <p>"That question I cannot answer," replied the prisoner "Why I knew he came from New Orleans, was from the fact that he came in company with a young Spanish nobleman, who had just recovered from a severe wound he had received from the hand of an assassin in New Orleans."</p>
               <p>"Can it be possible?" reflected Woodland. "It must be so, else the coincidence is very singular. The priest—the Spaniard—the charge of assassination!" These and other thoughts<pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC6928-00000029"/> resolved quickly in his mind. He felt that he had got a clue to the mystery, and Hope again reanimated his heart.</p>
               <p>"Come, my friend," said the hopeful man, addressing the prisoner; "for I must esteem you as such, though I fight against your nation—come—this abode befits not a man of your noble nature."</p>
               <p>The prisoner stared at Woodland, as if he did not com prehend the meaning of the singular words which had fallen upon his ear.</p>
               <p>"Come, my friend, you must go with me," continued Woodland, taking the old man's arm within his own, and urging him along.</p>
               <p>"You will not take me to a darker prison? You will not bind my limbs with chains?" queried Halsinger, as he moved his stiffened limbs slowly along.</p>
               <p>"Dark dungeons should be made only for tyrants! chains should only bind the limbs of the traitorous murderer! Patriots should breathe the pure air of heaven, and have free use of all their faculties."</p>
               <p>"Dios de Cielo!" exclaimed the old man, as he moved along each moment with firmer step; "Santa Madre de Dios! may the glimmer of Hope, which warms and revivifies my sunken soul, deceive me not!"</p>
               <p>"If your soul pants for Liberty, hope on—you shall be free!"</p>
               <p>"Heaven be praised! and God bless him, who sets the innocent captive at liberty!" exclaimed the happy Halsinger; "I did not anticipate freedom from the invaders of my country. But am I truly to be set at liberty?"</p>
               <p>"Such is the order of our commanding officer!"</p>
               <p>"God bless your general! And I shall see the glorious sun again?"</p>
               <p>"The moment we emerge from this gloomy passage!"</p>
               <p>They descended the stone steps and reached the outer door of the prison, when Halsinger halted, and looking steadily into Woodland's face, said:—</p>
               <p>"Are there any conditions to my release? I would not to purchase my freedom, fight against my poor, bleeding country!"</p>
               <p>"We could not thus impose upon you," replied Woodland.</p>
               <p>"Your release is without condition; yet, you would do me a favor, if you would partake of the humble hospitalities of my quarters for a few days."</p>
               <p>The released prisoner acquiesced with a grateful bow, and arm in arm they repaired to the place designated, where Woodland provided him with a suitable wardrobe, and bestowed upon him every comfort in his power. In a few days he was enabled to walk with the martial dignity of other years; that sickly hue left his complexion, and he no longer had that emaciated appearance as when he was first seen by Woodland in the dungeon he had so long occupied.</p>
               <p>Many were the hours, which Woodland passed in private conversation with his intelligent and noble guest. Each related to the other the prominent events of their whole lives. Each could sympathize with the other in matters pertaining to those they held dearest their hearts. Halsinger took the liveliest interest in Woodland's romantic history, and pledged himself to use his utmost endeavors to learn the fate of those, from whom he was separated at an untimely hour.</p>
               <p>On the day prior to that when the brigade, to which Woodland's company of Flying Artillerists was attached, marched from the city of Vera Cruz, a man with a long, greyish beard attired in the habiliments of a holy friar, and mounted upon a mule, was permitted to pass out of the city gates unquestioned. He took the road leading towards the Puente Nacional.</p>
               <p>After riding a few miles he was stopped by a party of Mexicans, but to all their queries concerning the enemy, he professed to know nothing, and they allowed him to proceed on his doubtful pilgrimage.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC6928-00000030"/>
               <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
               <head type="sub">DEFEAT OF THE MEXICAN LANCERS.</head>
               <p>THE famous city of Puebla de los Angelos, (the city of the Angels,) is one of the richest and most magnificent places in the republic of Mexico. From any high position commanding a view of its public edifices and white-roofed dwellings, it looks like a cluster of gems lying in the bosom of the Cordilleras, and seems to the beholder really worthy of its celestial title; but in reality, if it were called Puebla de los Demonios, it could not be a much greater misnomer than is the one it now bears. It might have been, when it gained the appellation indicating the abode of angelic beings, all that could be desirable in a terrestrial abiding place—for nature never lavished her beauteous gifts more bountifully upon any spot of earth,—but at the period of which we write, its charms were only upon the exterior;—within, vice and wretchedness, in their most loathsome and hideous forms, stalked openly, hand and hand, both by day and by night.—Yet the amount of wealth in this degraded city, perhaps, exceeds that of any other of its size in Mexico, but it is in the possession of the comparatively few, who pass away their hours in idle luxuries or lazy sports, and no more heed the ragged, emaciated, dirty masses, than they do the mud beneath the wheels of their gilded chariots. There is scarcely a redeeming trait in any class of its inhabitants, whether rolling in wealth and magnificence, or wallowing in filth and squalid poverty—all are vicious; all are degraded and criminal. Drunkenness, licentiousness, robbery, assassination, were deeds of daily and nightly occurrence. Chastity, in either sex, or in any grade of society, was "more honored in the breach than in the observance." Crimes, especially among the affluent, go unpunished. Occasionally a wretched wreck of humanity, who filches from the nabob sufficient to keep him from starving for a day, is put beyond the miseries of this life by means of the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">garotte</foreign>, the guillotine, or infernal machine of the Mexicans.</p>
               <p>But a righteous judgment soon visited this sinful city; and we trust that the scourge has had the effect, in some degree, to improve their despicable condition. But this is somewhat of a digression from the course of our story, and we therefore resume it.</p>
               <p>It was a bright and lovely morning on the 14th of May, 1847, that a division of Scott's army, headed by General Worth, was seen moving on towards Puebla. This portion of the army, notwithstanding its glorious achievements but a day or two previous on the heights of Cerro Gordo, was in fine condition, so far as arms and ammunition were concerned, but the soldiers were fatigued, jaded and battleworn, but they moved on as if determined on conquest after conquest, until they should reach the great city of the Aztecs, and stack their arms finally in the Plaza Major.</p>
               <p>They continued their march until about seven o'clock in the morning, and had reached a place called Amasoque, about twelve miles from Puebla on the Vera Cruz road, when the column was ordered to halt.</p>
               <p>At eight o'clock, a meek looking friar—the identical individual we saw leaving the gates of Vera Cruz a few days previous—rode along the American lines, as if confident that his holy vocation would shield him from injury or insult. To be sure, some of the more facetious of the soldiery, made some light remarks reflecting upon the raw-boned, long-eared animal that he rode, and which he urged along by the constant application of a heavy raw-hide. As he passed along his keen eye scrutinized the features of each commissioned officer. He reached<pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC6928-00000031"/> a company of Flying Artillerists, and perceiving an officer standing apart from the soldiers, intently surveying the scene of grandeur before him, he rode up by his side ere he was observed.</p>
               <p>"Buenos Dies, Senor!" saluted the friar.</p>
               <p>"That voice!" ejaculated Woodland, as he turned suddenly to the right-about. "Ah! my——"</p>
               <p>"You forget my vocation!" interrupted the holy man, raising his fore-finger to his lips.</p>
               <p>"I beg pardon, HOLY FRIAR!" said the officer, slightly confused, and emphasing the pious appellation.</p>
               <p>"Three thousand lancers will be upon you anon!" said the strange individual, in a hurried manner. "Prepare for the attack, and instantly!—you have no time to lose!"</p>
               <p>"But, holy father," said Woodland, "have you learned anything concerning——"</p>
               <p>"Question me not! I have no time for answers! Soon I hope to meet you again!—Till then farewell!"</p>
               <p>With these unsatisfactory expressions, the monk continued on his way for a few rods, when he entered a by-path and disappeared.</p>
               <p>Woodland, for a moment, was quite bewildered; but, suddenly recollecting himself, he beckoned his groom to bring his steed, and giving a few hurried orders to his first lieutenant, he sprung into the saddle, and galloped off to the head of the column. Here he found the gallant Worth, and communicating the information so strangely received, he rode back to his company.</p>
               <p>The shrill notes of the trumpet now quickly summoned every man to his post, and the whole column again moved forward, and with a brisker pace than before. They reached a favorable position, just as the loud notes of a bugle proclaimed that the enemy was approaching.</p>
               <p>"That cussed Mex' can bewgle agin!" exclaimed Dick Keen, to Capt. Woodland, as he marched alongside of that officer, with his Joe, Jr., at a trail, in his hands. "I should know that town, if I should hear it in a camp-meetin' on the old Stampin Ground! I'll lay a hundred that's a body of lancers!"</p>
               <p>"You are right, Dick!" replied Woodland; "and I'm inclined to believe that the old devil himself is in command!"</p>
               <p>"What! old timber-leg?"</p>
               <p>"I mean Santa Anna!"</p>
               <p>"So do I! And would'nt I like to get my young Joe on his cussed picter once! Mebbe he would'nt go to kingdom come, quicker'n a Kaintuck flash o' lightin."</p>
               <p>The American troops, with a promptness worthy of veterans, were drawn into battle array. Woodland's battery occupied the right flank. The enemy appeared in full force, and with unparalleled impetuosity charged upon the Flying Artillerists, and it seemed as if they would be overwhelmed by the superior numbers sweeping down upon them; but, a well-directed fire from the entire battery, supported by a heavy volley of musketry from a regiment of infantry, staggered the foe, and they retreated, leaving many a lancer upon the field. Thrice they rallied, and repeated the charge, but were repulsed without causing the loss of a man of the American force.</p>
               <p>Hostilities ceased for a time, when Worth led on his troops to a more commanding position, in spite of the determined resistance of the Mexicans, when he had reached the brow of a hill, overlooking a plain, but which was accessible on all sides.</p>
               <p>The Mexican general had conceived the plan of making a mock assault upon the Flying Artillerists, draw their fire, and then to charge upon the infantry and riflemen in position on the left. This design on the part of the enemy, flashed suddenly across the mind of Woodland, and as soon as they commenced moving forward, he ordered his whole battery to be discharged, notwithstanding the enemy were too far distant to be reached by the small shot with which the guns were charged. Under cover of the smoke, one of the heaviest pieces was ordered to make a circuit of the hill, and take a position on a little rocky bluff to the lef, of the infantry. The cannoniers mounted, and at full gallop followed Woodland to the commanding point he<pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC6928-00000032"/> had discovered. <hi rend="i"/>(See engraving p. 17.) This movement was executed with such rapidity that it was scarcely observed by either of the contending armies. The lancers, as he apprehended rushed forward towards the battery, but suddenly changing their course, dashed on towards the infantry. A volley of musket and rifle balls was showered among them. This fire, though severely galling, was well sustained. It checked them for a moment only; they recovered, and pressed on towards the infantry, who began to fall back. It was inevitable that, if the left flank was turned by the enemy, victory would be extremely doubtful.</p>
               <p>At this critical juncture, from an unexposed position, and almost concealed from view, a heavy piece of ordnance, charged with grape shot, was opened upon them, and threw terror, dismay, and death into their serried ranks. Another and another discharge was fired from the same gun, before the now flying enemy could get beyond the reach of its deadly aim!</p>
               <p>The lancers in great disorder made a precipitate retreat towards Puebla, leaving their dead and wounded behind them. The Americans continued on their march, and on the next morning, without meeting with any farther resistance, entered the city of Puebla.</p>
               <p>An hour previous, Santa Anna, with his discomfited lancers, together with several regiments of infantry, had marched out of it, not daring to risk another battle until he was still further reinforced.</p>
               <p>It is, indeed, one of the most remarkable facts in the history of modern warfare, that two or three thousand men of an invading army, fatigued with fighting and a long, tedious march, harassed on all sides, even suffering from the want of food and water, and badly clothed and equipped, should be suffered to march into a hostile city, containing sixty thousand inhabitants, and to stack their arms and pitch their tents, without even saying "by your leave," in the great plaza of the city. And when night came, to lie down for rest and sleep, without the slightest apprehension that the enemy would have the temerity to attack them, notwithstanding the fierce and surly looks cast upon them by every inhabitant.</p>
               <p>Praises of Captain Woodland were upon every tongue, for the skillful manner in which he turned the tide of battle at Amasoque, and he was afterwards breveted to the rank of Major for his part in that victory.</p>
               <p>With Dick Keen it was the absorbing topic of conversation. Said he to Woodland:</p>
               <p>"May I be scalped if I don't think Young Hickory ought to gin you a brigadier's commission, or, at the lowest notch, a colonel's. I seed the hull bizness; and oh, tornadoes and thunderbolts! how you did pepper'em! I thought Joe, Jr. and I had made a few extra button-holes in their cussed green jackets, but you cut 'em down as fire duz prairie grass! There was no fun for me, so I ordered arms and looked on."</p>
               <p>Thus would Dick run on for an hour if Woodland would listen to him; he was much too lavish of his praises for the modesty of the gallant captain to bear. Keen was a great favorite of Woodland, who always checked his garrulity, when the theme was flattering to himself.</p>
               <p>On the day after their occupation of Puebla, detachments of the Americans took possession of the adjacent heights of San Juan, Gaudalupe and Loretto, on the former of which they planted a battery.</p>
               <p>At sunset that evening, the friar again appeared to Captain Woodland, and led him to an occupied house, where they spent nearly an hour in earnest conversation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="64-65 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6928-00000033"/>
               <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
               <head type="sub">PUEBLA AND THE CONVENT OF SAN URSULA.</head>
               <p>A HALF hour's ride from Puebla de los Angelos, in a northerly direction, through a narrow road, scarcely wide enough for two cavaliers to ride abreast, brings the traveler to the Convent of San Ursula, a large, modern-built structure, with high stone walls completely encompassing it, the only egress being by means of opening a heavy iron door, of such narrow dimensions that not more than one portly person could make his exit at a time. This gate was guarded at all times by an Irish porter, who had some years prior been brought into Mexico by a rich gentleman who settled at Puebla. The Spaniard died, and Mickey Mahoney, who was deemed an honest fellow, and a true catholic, obtained the situation of porter to the great nunnery of San Ursula.</p>
               <p>A few nights previous to the battle of Amasoque, a monk, in company with an officer attired in a splendid suit of cavalry uniform, though concealed by a light Spanish cloak, stopped at the Convent gate, and summoned the porter by ringing the bell. Mickey appeared, and on learning that it was Father Francis and his friend, opened the gate, and allowed them to pass in. Ten minutes had not elapsed when another officer, a bloated-looking Mexican, also applied at the narrow door, and making himself known, was admitted. Soon afterwards, a fourth individual<figure>
                     <head>CAPT. WOODLAND'S ADVANTAGEOUS POSITION AT THE BATTLE OF AMASOQUE. See p. 65.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC6928-00000034"/> vidual apparently a friar, rode up to the door and dismounting from a poor, jaded beast, demanded admission.</p>
               <p>"Who are ye?" asked Mickey.</p>
               <p>"I'm a stranger just arrived from Vera Cruz," was the reply,</p>
               <p>"Then, by the holy Saints! you'd bitter be afther thravelin' back again," said the Irishman; "yer don't understand the rigilations o' this paceful retreat of the blissid young ladies"</p>
               <p>"I am sure they are not such as would shut out an humble friar, with a commission to Padre Francis."</p>
               <p>"Ah, by my sowl! that althers the matther, indade! It's a holy friar that ye are?" queried Mickey. "Are ye quite shure of that same, now?"</p>
               <p>The stranger gave an affirmative reply.</p>
               <p>"Thin, by all the swate sisters! ye are entirely wilcome the likes iv ye can always inter; but yer riverince's holy basto can't folly ye; tie yinder post to his halter, and by the faith of an 'onest Irishman like meself, he'll stand like any gudu Christian."</p>
               <p>The mule was disposed of in the manner suggested, and the friar was admitted inside of the convent walls without additional ceremony.</p>
               <p>"This way, yer holy riverince," said Mickey, escorting the priest towards the visitors' apartment, a small room in a front wing of the edifice, adjoining which was the library, separated only by a partition with folding doors which were locked.</p>
               <p>"Wait here, yer riverince, while I inform my holy misthress of yer riverince's pious prisence. Och! by my sowl now. I had forgot to ax yer holiness's name inthirely?" said Mickey.</p>
               <p>"Friar Valdez," answered the stranger.</p>
               <p>The porter retired, and soon announced that his "holy mis thress was thin ingaged in pious duties with the swate sisters." but, if he had patience to wait, she would meet him in the course of half an hour.</p>
               <p>To this the friar assented, and to while away the time, he commenced examining the pictures upon the walls, and the sculptured images of saints placed upon brackets in the cornera of the room, and upon the mantel. Passing the folding doors, he heard the sound of male voices speaking in subdued tones.—Two individuals appeared in earnest conversation, and, overhearing some words which riveted his attention, he knelt down and put his ear to the key. The voice of one of them he instantly recognized, although he had not heard it for years; but once listened to, it was ever to be remembered. It was that of the infamous Olente, the Mexican butcher, a general in the service of the republic. The other individual was Padre Francis, the monk who, our readers will recollect, was seen, in years past, flying from a field of carnage, with a child folded in his cassock. The friar intently listened, and heard the following:</p>
               <p>"'Tis useless, general," said the monk; "thy suit is hopeless the lady will not listen to thy love protestations. She is but a poor, heart-broken creature. Ever since I separated her from that bright-eyed angel of a child, she has been inconsolable."</p>
               <p>"But she is still beautiful," remarked the wretch, Olente.</p>
               <p>"What can her beauty be to thee, when her best affections are buried in the grave of him who, you declare, was shot among the four hundred at Gol—"</p>
               <p>"I tell thee, monk," interrupted Olente, "I'll listen to no obstacles you can invent or suggest. I have set my heart upon the possession of this fair creature you have tempted me to obtain: and all the host of Hades shall not deter me from my purpose! I gave thee a large sum of money for gaining me an interview, and although I made little impression upon her inflexible spirit, I will now offer thee double that sum for another interview. Since then, you know, I have been promoted to the highest grade in the army short of Commander-in-chief, and I hold likewise an enviable place in the cabinet of the Executive. Then I was comparatively poor. Now I am rich and have influence."</p>
               <p>"Happily would I grant thee what tnou desirest," said the monk; "but again, I assure you, it will be of no avail."</p>
               <p>"That shall be my fault—no thine"</p>
               <pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC6928-00000035"/>
               <p>"Thou wilt remember that my part in this will subject me to the severest censure, should it be discovered," said the monk.</p>
               <p>"There is no danger of its being known. Besides, good Padre, the gold that I will give thee makes thee rich."</p>
               <p>"How much gold?" inquired the monk, his eyes gleaming with avarice.</p>
               <p>"One hundred Spanish doubloons!"</p>
               <p>"For one more interview?"</p>
               <p>"Si, Padre! but remember, without interruption, or any interference whatever; for her stubborn soul must be bent to my will!"</p>
               <p>"And what for possession?" inquired the impious monk.</p>
               <p>"Three hundred!"</p>
               <p>"And thou wilt swear to defend me against any charge that may be preferred against me for assisting thee to accomplish thy unholy purpose?"</p>
               <p>"Summon all the saints in the calendar, or all the demons that reign in hell—prescribe the oath, and I will swear by any or all of them!"</p>
               <p>"Enough!" said the monk. "To-morrow night I will lead thee to her chamber-prison. But, be sure thou providest thyself with the gold."</p>
               <p>"I have it already here, and would see her this very night!" said Olente, producing two bags of gold.</p>
               <p>"It is impossible!"</p>
               <p>"Why impossible?"</p>
               <p>"I cannot tell thee why. Perhaps the Lady Abbess can."</p>
               <p>"Curse the old hag!—she looks not kindly on me," replied Olente. "I would not even have her know of my presence here. I offended her once, because I happened to have a little love affair with a sweet little Nun—a pet of hers—just before she removed from the old Convent of San Marie."</p>
               <p>"The Abbess herself is with the fair American to-night, for the purpose of persuading her to renounce the world. Tomorrow evening be here one hour after Vespers, and thy wish shall be gratified."</p>
               <p>"Curse this delay!—it is provoking! but I suppose I can be patient twenty four hours, longer," said Olente, concealing his bags of gold, and rising to depart.</p>
               <p>"Good General, there are robbers prowling in the vicinity," suggested the avaricious Padre.</p>
               <p>"I carry a weapon, you perceive,' returned Olente, tapping the hilt of his sword.</p>
               <p>"Yet it is unsafe to bear so much gold at night!"</p>
               <p>"No, no, my good Padre," said the general, twinkling his eye significantly. "I comprehend thy gentle hint."</p>
               <p>"It will be perfectly safe in my iron chest."</p>
               <p>"I tell thee, monk, that not a piece of my gold shall touch thy fingers until I have access to my fair inamorata."</p>
               <p>With the accustomed "buenos noche!" Olente, with his usual swaggering gait, retired from the convent, and being allowed egress through the outer wall, and placing a small coin of gold in Mickey Mahoney's extended palm, he went on his way towards an encampment of Lancers situated about a quarter of a mile distant.</p>
               <p>But to return to Friar Valdez. He still maintained his humble attitude at the key-hole; for no sooner had the relentless Mexican butcher closed the door behind him, than Padre Francis gave audible vent to the following soliloquy.</p>
               <p>"Ha! ha! lucky he's gone, for I expect his more successful rival down each moment! This lady has proved herself a perfect treasure—a mine of wealth to me! Four hundred doubloons more from this brutish general, together with three hundred mulcted from Captain Carlos Dumiger, make a goodly sum. Verily, my pious vocation is profitable. This is not all—her father (who believes his daughter dead,) writes me that he will guarantee the payment of two thousand dollars, as soon as his grandchild, the beautiful little Ninette Woodland, is found and conveyed safely to the United States. My duty is fulfilled, and if I have intrusted her to safe hands, I shall receive my reward in due time. True, I must part with a portion of the<pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC6928-00000036"/> golden fees to old Magdalena, but I <unclear>shall strive to extort more</unclear> from Dumiger—I have pandered to his wishes much too cheap."</p>
               <p>His soliloquy was interrupted by the abrupt entrance of him whose name was the last upon the monk's tongue.</p>
               <p>Carlos Dumiger, our readers will remember, was the young Spaniard, to whom Mr. Sherwood had promised his daughter Sabra's hand. He had accompanied Padre Francis into Mexico, after recovering from the wound he had received at New Orleans in his encounter with Woodland Losing all trace of those of whom he was in pursuit, he separated from the monk, and knew nothing of Sabra's whereabouts until accidentally meeting with Padre Francis at a recent date. Dumiger, during the past ten years had been a resident of the Mexican capital, and in a dissolute course of life he had disposed of his entire fortune, which he had drawn from Spain.—Thus reduced from affluence to poverty, he sought for and gained a captain's commission in a squadron of Lancers belonging to the division of Olente. He vas well aware that if he could gain the hand of his American flame, who was in the power of Padre Francis, he should at once repair his broken fortunes; and he still cherished a violent passion for the lady. But he had resolved, if she persisted in her refusal to wed him, to commit a ruffianly deed, which, in the most enlightened nations of the earth, is punishable by an ignominious death!"</p>
               <p>Dumiger entered excited almost to a frenzied state. He stamped his feet, and strided rapidly to and fro the room uttering groans, as if writhing under extreme torture!</p>
               <p>"What's the matter, Senor Captain?" asked the monk.</p>
               <p>"Hell's furies! I have been thwarted!" exclaimed the enraged Dumiger! "At the very moment I thought her in my power, she drew a poniard, which was concealed in her bosom, and with it dealt me such a severe blow on my left wrist that I fear I shall lose my hand! Is not this a horrid spectacle?" said Dumiger, as he unwound a handkerchief from his wrist and displayed the bloody gash. "I should have stabbed her to the heart, had not a sudden faintness overcome me! giving her an opportunity to escape to the range of apartments occupied by the nuns, in one of which she is now concealed. But I swear to be revenged! This desperate, stubborn beauty I'll conquer or die in the struggle!"</p>
               <p>"What wouldst thou do now?" inquired the monk.</p>
               <p>"Drag her from her convent prison to a more secluded place I wot of," replied Dumiger! "There will I glut my desire and my vengeance!"</p>
               <p>"The Lady Abbess will not permit her departure!"</p>
               <p>"Gold will accomplish much with the old hag!"</p>
               <p>"True; but she will require a large sum."</p>
               <p>"How much?"</p>
               <p>Three or four hundred doubloons!"</p>
               <p>"I'll give it!"</p>
               <p>"And how much more for my services?" asked the monk.</p>
               <p>"You have been well paid already!"</p>
               <p>"And I have thus far fulfilled all I promised thee!"</p>
               <p>"A hundred doubloons in addition I offer!"</p>
               <p>"Make it three, and you have my zealous services!"</p>
               <p>"Enough! I accept your offer!"</p>
               <p>"When do you wish to carry your purposes into effect?"</p>
               <p>"Of that I will hereafter inform you," answered Dumiger.</p>
               <p>"This ugly wound must first be attended to. On your life, reveal not how I received it, and if, perchance, I lose my hand, I may be enabled to turn it to some account."</p>
               <p>"On my confidence thou canst rely," replied the Padre.</p>
               <p>Here ended this second interview, and the monk and captain departed from the nunnery together.</p>
               <p>The whole of the conversation here recorded fell distinctly upon the ear of the friar through the key-hole. Though startled at the import of what he heard, he was exceedingly gratified at the important intelligence he had by stealth so unexpectedly gained.</p>
               <p>The Lady Abbess, an emaciated, vixen-looking piece of female antiquity, soon afterward entered the visitors' apartment, to receive the stranger; and the only apology she plead for her<pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC6928-00000037"/> delay in appearing, was, that she had company in an adjoining room. This the friar well knew to be a falsehood, for although persons had been in there, she had been elsewhere, and only tarried that they might know there was a strange friar in the Convent.</p>
               <p>The friar placed in the hands of the old lady, a letter of introduction purporting to be from the Bishop of Vera Cruz.</p>
               <p>"Thou art welcome, worthy Valdez, to our Convent. As for the lady alluded to in that note, I assure thee that she is not among the Sisters of St. Ursula!" was the false answer of the Abbess.</p>
               <p>"It was said that she had never taken the veil; and was detained here by one Padre Francis with your consent."</p>
               <p>"The story is false, worthy friar. It must be some other convent in which she is confined," replied the Lady Abbess, "for I allow no female, who has not irrevocably renounced the world, within the precincts of these sacred walls, with the exception of my servants."</p>
               <p>"Then is my errand here fruitless, worthy Abbess, and I will at once depart; but, methought I heard a voice from the adjoining room, which vibrated upon mine ear very like unto that of the holy Father Francis."</p>
               <p>"That indeed," answered the Abbess, somewhat confused, "but—certainly—it was not that son of the church to whom you have alluded."</p>
               <p>"Verily, thou wouldst not deceive me, and, therefore, I will go hence on my weary pilgrimage."</p>
               <p>Thus speaking, the friar bowed reverently and took his departure, satisfied beyond his hopes as to the information he had elicited, and also of the hypocritical character of the Lady Abbess and of Father Francis.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE GENERAL AND THE FRIAR.</head>
               <p>LOVELY indeed was the evening subsequent to the remarkable revelation that accidentally fell upon the ear of the unknown friar at the Convent of San Ursula. The heavens were resplendent with innumerable stars, and the atmosphere was bland and delightful, scented with a thousand fragrant flowers blooming in the forest and in the garden of the nunnery. The round, full moon was just peering over the eastern hills, gilding with her silver beams the golden cross of the Convent tower, when a solitary individual, clad in an undress military suit, pursued his way, with as rapid strides as his gouty limbs could carry him, throug the leafy path, which led to the retreat of the Ursulines. He emerged from the thicket into the open space, within full view of the edifice, when a dark form, from beneath the shadow of a palm-tree, suddenly obtruded itself in his path, and raised a hand as a warning for him to proceed not another step forward!</p>
               <p>The officer started back with dismay, as if the arch-fiend himself, or the ghost of one of his victims had risen from out the earth to intercept him in his way.</p>
               <p>"Quien vive?" demanded the officer, in tremulous tones.</p>
               <p>"A lowly man, as thou perceivest by my habiliments," said the friar.</p>
               <p>"Then stand aside and let me pass!"</p>
               <pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC6928-00000038"/>
               <p>"No, no, Señor Olente," resumed the other, 'thou canst I.O advance. Between thee and me there is a deadly hatred!"</p>
               <p>"Stand aside! or, by hell, I will cleave thy skull in twain!" and Olente clutched the hilt of his sword.</p>
               <p>"Move not! or that instant thou diest!" threatened the friar; "I know thee well, thou base poltroon, and thy errand, too! But thou enterest not within the walls of that cloister, to-night, alive!"</p>
               <p>"Darest to threaten me?"</p>
               <p>"Ay, Señor General," said the friar, in tones of bitter irony "and spit upon thee, too, with as little fear as I would upon a cur! I tell thee, most powerful! the fair American is not for thee! Fie upon thee!—for shame! thou hast a wife at Perote, and children, too! Wouldst thou disgrace them still further, by adding another to thy long catalogue of hellish crimes!"</p>
               <p>"Peace! vile calumniator, or by——"</p>
               <p>"Peace, thyself!—coward, perjurer, adulterer, murderer, in human monster!"</p>
               <p>"I'll hear no more from thy slanderous lips, be thou angel of devil!" cried Olente.—"I am not the craven-hearted wretch to stand here and be berated by some vagabond, clad in holy garb!"</p>
               <p>The angry general drew his sword, and, rushing forward with tiger-like ferocity, aimed a blow at the friar's head; but quicker than thought another blade gleamed in the moon's light, and the sword of Olente was twisted from his hand, as readily as if it had lost all its power to wield a weapon.</p>
               <p>"Ha, ha!" laughed the friar;" thou hast not thy boasted skill! Pick up thy sword, for I scorn to take advantage of a disarmed foe, though he be the veriest wretch in Christendom."</p>
               <p>The discomfited officer picked up his sword, and turned as if to retrace his steps.</p>
               <p>"Hold! or by San Pedro, I'll run thy vile body through!"</p>
               <p>The trembling coward obeyed.</p>
               <p>"Move not," continued the friar, while I hold up a mirror to thy gaze that thou may'st view thy hideous deformity! I remember well the time when thou wert esteemed a valiant officer. Thou were promoted to a colonelcy for executing a horrid, cold-blooded butchery at Goliad! Thy former friend—one Colonel Halsinger, who refused to commit four hundred murders—and whom thou didst succeed in office, wast betrayed by thy perjuring tongue! he was cast into a noisome dungeon to linger in torments until death should relieve him from misery unparalleled!"</p>
               <p>"And there he deserves to remain for his treason against the state," said Olente, his anger giving him assurance to speak.</p>
               <p>"Lying dog! he was no traitor! and well thou knowest it!"</p>
               <p>"And what can all this be to thee?" asked Olente.</p>
               <p>"In me behold Halsinger's dread avenger! and if thou hast a tittle of thy boasted prowess, thou wilt surely consent to cross blades with one who maketh no pretensions to courage!"</p>
               <p>"What! I fight with a friar?" ejaculated Olente. "Never! Never let it be said that Olente disgraced his sword by fighting with a man in holy garb!"</p>
               <p>"I tell thee thou shalt fight me!" returned the friar. "Draw, thy weapon again, and defend thyself! Do one courageous, manly act ere thou diest! thy whole career shows thee but an assassin! an adulterer! a very beast!"</p>
               <p>"By hell's tortures!" exclaimed Olente, angered to desperation, uncontrollable. "Be thou man, saint or devil, I'll listen to thy envenomed tongue no longer;" and he drew his weapon, and put himself in an attitude of defiance.</p>
               <p>His antagonist threw off his outward, holy habiliments, and displayed to the dismayed Olente the commanding and noble figure of Rodriguez Halsinger, the late prisoner at Vera Cruz.</p>
               <p>He was clad in the full uniform of a Colonel, and never before displayed such terrible dignity as he did on this occasion.</p>
               <p>"Halsinger?" ejaculated the amazed general.</p>
               <p>"Ay, Halsinger! Senor Olente's deadly foe! Oh! how oft, in the solitude of that dark, dreary dungeon have I prayed for this hour!—I may say, this HAPPY hour!—the hour of sweet revenge. Monster! fiend! murderer! come on! Thou deservest to die by the <foreign xml:lang="FRA">garotte,</foreign> but on my soul I will be magnanimous<pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC6928-00000039"/> and spare thee that ignominy.—Thou shalt die by a sword that never was unsheathed save in a just cause! Put all thy skill into thine arm!—nerve thy hellish soul for the contest, for I would not slay thee as I would a butcher's dog!—in honorable combat only let my pure sword be tarnished! Come on!"</p>
               <p>The blades clashed. Olente, amazed at the unexpected appearance of him, whom he thought was still wasting away in prison, trembled like a guilty thing while he spoke, but now he nerved himself to the combat, and despite his well known cowardice looked like a formidable foe! With desperation, truly wonderful in one of his besotted and loathsome habits, he cut and thrust most lustily; but they were parried by his cool adversary with a skill worthy of a professional swordsman. Being tired of acting only on the defensive, Halsinger now began to exercise his power in dealing blows! He struck but twice, and the head of the brutal Olente rolled in the dust!</p>
               <p>After contemplating for a few moments the corse of his bloody foe, he knealt over it and drew from his belt sundry papers which he concealed in his own bosom. Searching for more, he discovered two bags of gold.</p>
               <p>"Ah!" thought Halsinger, "this will relieve my suffering family from the poverty, which thy remorseless hand hast caused them;" and he concealed them about his person.</p>
               <p>Dragging the headless trunk into the thicket, and tossing the gory head after it, he resumed his cowl and cassock, and in the course of half an hour, he sat alone in an unoccupied house in Puebla, and by the dim light of a taper was perusing dispatches, and other papers he had taken from his foe! Before daylight, the next morning, he mounted his mule and rode on to meet the American force then approaching Amasoque.</p>
               <p>His brief interview with Woodland, and subsequent events, have already been described in the fifth chapter!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
               <head type="sub">"ALL'S WELL THAT ENDS WELL."</head>
               <p>On the evening following the occupation of Puebla by the ever victorious invaders, it will be remembered that the pseudo friar led Captain Woodland to a deserted house, where they remained in conversation some hours. Halsinger related his visit to the Convent, and all the information he had there accidentally gained; also, his encounter with and death of the barbarous Olente. With an impatience, which knows no bounds, Woodland leaped to his feet, and declared he was ready to proceed to the nunnery that very night and batter down all opposing obstacles to his entrance!</p>
               <p>"Be patient, my friend, or you will ruin all!" replied Halsinger. "Be governed by my advice and all will be well! Remember you have a dear one to save, and enemies to punish!"</p>
               <p>"Who to punish?"</p>
               <p>"As base a pair of wretches as ever escaped strangling! The time to strike will soon approach; that, however, depends upon circumstances!"</p>
               <p>"Let no circumstances debar me from rescuing my long lost one from the clutches of her accursed persecutors! Why not to-night, or to-morrow night?" eagerly questioned Woodland.</p>
               <p>"To-morrow night," repeated Halsinger, thoughtfully; "perhaps<pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC6928-00000040"/> haps. At all events, you may be prepared; and meet me here half an hour before the rising of the moon, with a brave and rusty friend!"</p>
               <p>"Ah! such an one I have now in my mind," replied Woodland. "But will not an escort of soldiers be necessary?"</p>
               <p>"That is well thought of, my friend; for Capt. Dumiger may take the same precaution. Yes, an escort may be required."</p>
               <p>"Dumiger," repeated Woodland. "Is this the name of the Spanish captain you have spoken of, in connection with this criminal monk?"</p>
               <p>"Ay, Captain Carlos Dumiger," replied Halsinger.</p>
               <p>'The coincidence is remarkable, or this must be the man! remarked Woodland.</p>
               <p>"What man?"</p>
               <p>"The Spaniard—my rival in years gone by—he whom I fought in New-Orleans, prior to our fleeing to Texas!"</p>
               <p>"I remember," said the colonel, "in relating your history while I was in prison, you mentioned the name of Dumiger. Without doubt, this is the man!"</p>
               <p>"Then I trust to Heaven my hour of triumph is near at hand!" said Woodland, "for now a light breaks in upon me—I think I see it all!"</p>
               <p>"Then go to your quarters at once—retire to rest, that you may be refreshed for this enterprise which will need all your tact and all your energy! Remember the time—half an hour before the rising of the moon!"</p>
               <p>"Thanks for your counsel, my kind friend!" said Woodland, clasping the friar's hand. "Be assured, if ever impatient lover was true to time and place I shall be here! Adieu, till then!"</p>
               <p>"Adios, Señor," returned Halsinger, as his American friend retired from the apartment, and left the lonely dwelling.</p>
               <milestone n="——" unit="typography"/>
               <p>Padre Francis, and Magdalena, the Lady Abbess of San Ursula, sat together in the Library, on the evening following the interview just narrated.</p>
               <p>Their conversation related chiefly to the non-appearance of general Olente, on the night appointed.</p>
               <p>"This is awkward business," remarked Padre Francis; "for I have received a note from Dumiger, informing me that he will, at all possible hazards, be here this evening; now, if it should so happen that the general makes his appearance too there may be trouble."</p>
               <p>"They must not see each other," returned old Magdalena "I'll manage that; but their gold we must secure!"</p>
               <p>"Dumiger writes that he will bring us ample security; that, in the conflict of Amasoque, in which they suffered defeat, they lost all their baggage, containing money, clothing, etc."</p>
               <p>"Ay, the security must be as good as the gold!" said the old withered hag, shaking her head.</p>
               <p>"Och! murther! thunder and ouns! bludy murther! Padre Francis! houly mither of all the saints! murther! murther!"</p>
               <p>These exclamations from the lungs of the Irish porter, Micky Mahoney, as he came making rapid strides towards the convent door, fell startlingly upon the ears of the Abbess and her unscrupulous confederate, the monk.</p>
               <p>"Holy mother of God!" exclaimed the old Abbess, crossing herself and repeating Ave Marias, as she hurriedly counted the beads of her rosary.</p>
               <p>"There must have been a murder committed!" exclaimed the monk.</p>
               <p>"Ye may well say that, and spake as big a truth as iver ye wur guilty ov!" said Mickey, bursting into the room, and displaying a human head to the astonished gaze of his master and mistress. "Arn't that a bludy murder now?"</p>
               <p>The head presented so ghastly a spectacle that the old woman suddenly grew faint and fell upon the floor.</p>
               <p>"Some water, Mickey, quick!" said Padre Francis.</p>
               <p>"Och! thunder and thurf! the houly mither is ony frightened!" suggested Mickey.—"The head is too murtherous for her sensibilities; though by my throth, I thought the critter could stand any thing from the corpse of a nun to that same of a robber!"</p>
               <pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC6928-00000041"/>
               <p>"Begone! don't stand there prating! bring some water!" commanded the monk.</p>
               <p>"Yis, yer houly riverence!" answered the Irishman, dropping the head, and running to do the monk's bidding.</p>
               <p>In a few moments Mickey returned with a full bucket.</p>
               <p>"Bathe her temples, while I apply the salts," said the monk.</p>
               <p>"Yis, yer riverence," answered the Irishman, as he raised the bucket, and splashed the entire contents with full force into the old woman's face!</p>
               <p>"What the dev—"</p>
               <p>"Yer holy riverence should'nt call upon that jintleman's name! Och! shure, the cowld bath has done the thing jinteelly. See, she begins to come too! How is it with yer houly saintship?" he asked, as the monk raised her to a sitting posture.</p>
               <p>But the old Abbess was yet too faint to speak. A glass of water, however, soon revived her. Her female attendants soon appeared, and supported her to her private apartments.</p>
               <p>"Where did you pick up that head, Mickey?" inquired the monk.</p>
               <p>"In the woods, yinder! I sthumbled my fut against it when I wur coming hame from seeing Misthress Snorar Inez Isabella Amalia Mahony, shure!"</p>
               <p>"Is that your wife's name?"</p>
               <p>"Part of it, yer riverence."</p>
               <p>"It's a long one," suggested the monk.</p>
               <p>"Yes, yer riverence, and bad 'cess to her for that same; but it's the same with all the dare crathurs in this counthry. Now, if it wur ony Bridget—thare's a swate name for ye—or Mary, or Ellen, or ony o' the likes, by my soul I should like her arl the betther for it."</p>
               <p>"Remove that head," said the monk, tired of Mickey's presence.</p>
               <p>"Yis, yer riverence.</p>
               <p>"Tarry a moment; let us see if its features can be recognized."</p>
               <p>Mickey held it up by the hair at arm's length.</p>
               <p>"By my soul, I've looked upon that oogly mug before." said the Irishman.</p>
               <p>"By San Iago! I know it well!" exclaimed the monk. "It is the head of General Olente! Ah! by hell! he has been robbed and murdered! Poor Olente! had he taken my advice, his gold would have been safe and his life spared! I now understand the cause of old Magdalena's sudden faintness. She recognized Olente's features at the first glance."</p>
               <p>The porter's bell of the convent now rung, and Mickey ran to conceal the head, and then hastened to ascertain who demanded admittance.</p>
               <p>"Friar Valdez!" answered a voice outside, to Mickey's inquiry, "who's there!"</p>
               <p>"Ye're inthirely wilcome, yer houliness!" said Mickey, opening the door, and admitting not only the pseudo friar, but another individual, whose real character was likewise concealed under a meek garb of sanctity.</p>
               <p>"We would speak to the Lady Abbess!" said Valdez.</p>
               <p>"Thin, by St. Pathrick, ye must wait till the marnin," for as thrue as that houly jintlemin druv all the sarpints out o' Ireland, she's frightened almost out of her sinses. Och! yer riverince, there's been bludy murdherin' bizness hereabouts!"</p>
               <p>"Indeed?" ejaculated the friar, with feigned surprise.</p>
               <p>"Faix, I tell ye but the truth," resumed Mickey. "A great jinral has been murdhered, and the very sight of the head, which I showed to the ould lady tuk away her sinses inthirely, and she'll sae nobody as thrue as I hope to resave the blissins o' holy St. Pathrick."</p>
               <p>"Is there no one at home?"</p>
               <p>"Shure, and there is. There's all the dear nuns—the darlint wate crathers—thin there's the beautiful leddy what's always cryin' out o' the windy o' yon tower; but it's agin the rigilations o' this blissed retrate for sthrangers to step fut beyant the door o' the hall. D'ye mark that now?"</p>
               <p>"We desire not to intrude," replied the friar.</p>
               <pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC6928-00000042"/>
               <p>"Thin yer riverinces are thrue jintlemin, ivery inch ov ye, from the souls of yer heads to the crowns ov yer futs."</p>
               <p>"Thanks for thy compliments; but tell me, is there a holy man within called Padre Francis?"</p>
               <p>"No, yer riverence," replied Mickey. "May the saints forgive me for tellin' that lie," said he to himself.</p>
               <p>"Should any one call here for Friar Valdez, admit him," said the frair; "we are somewhat wearied with a long walk, and will tary for a brief period in the visitors' room."</p>
               <p>"Walk in, yer riverences, and make yer holinesses inthirely comfortable."</p>
               <p>The two visitors walked on and entered the room alluded to. A few minutes only had elapsed, when the porter's bell again rung, and Captain Carlos Dumiger was admitted, and escorted to the library where the monk was enjoying a brief repose. He had previously instructed the porter that he was at home to no one but the captain.</p>
               <p>Again the porter was summoned, and some one inquired for Friar Valdez. Mickey opened the door, and in stalked at exceedingly lengthy individual, muffled in a monk's cassocl which scarcely reached below his knees.</p>
               <p>"Walk in, yer riverence!" said Mickey, politely; "yer holy frinds are in waiting for ye!"</p>
               <p>"Thank ye, old hoss!" replied Dick Keen, for he, indeed, it was; "may I be shot thro' the gizzard, like a shootin'-match turkey, if I don't think you're an Irishman!"</p>
               <p>"Thrue as gospil, and Mickey Mahoney's my name, at yer riverince's sarvice."</p>
               <p>"Then, p'rhaps you can't give a man, who's dry as a birch-bark, a horn o' whisky?" asked Dick.</p>
               <p>"Whiskay!" exclaimed Mickey, smacking his lips. "<unclear>Did</unclear> yer riverince say whiskay?"</p>
               <p>"I said whisky!"</p>
               <p>"Thunder and thurf! whiskay! Divil o' bit o' that delightful crathur will ye be afther findin' in this counthry! Och wouldn't I like jist a wee drap for the sake o' the conshence Ould Ireland, why did I lave ye for a counthry that had no whiskay!"</p>
               <p>"Take a swig from this flask, and then say if you can, wha sort o' liquor it is!" said the Kentuckian, producing from beneath his awkward covering a large hunting-flask.</p>
               <p>Mickey put it to his lips and took a long draught.</p>
               <p>"Whiskay! by all the holy Saints of swate Ireland!" he exclaimed. "A thousand blissin's on yer riverince's head! (Mickey takes another draught.) May yer riverince live a thousand years! (another draught.) May yer sowl pass through purgatory without gettin' a single hair of yer holy head scorched!—(another draught.) May yer riverince have a seat between St. Pathrick and the next best saint! (another draught.) May ye niver lack a gude drap o' Irish whiskay there, ither!"—(another draught, and a long one.)</p>
               <p>Mickey then gave the empty flask to the Kentuckian.</p>
               <p>"May I be swallyed by an alligator, if you hav'n't emptied the bottle!"</p>
               <p>"Blissin's on yer (hic) riverince! Yer sowl is saved, if Mick (hic)ey Mahoney can save any body! Yer a jintleman! ye (hic) can come and go whiniver yer (hic) holiness plazes! That whis(hic)kay has got into my (hic) head! If I didn't know I (hic) was n't drunk, I should say I was dam (hic) drunk! Ould (hic) Ireland foriver! Whis(hic)kay foriver! (hic)."</p>
               <p>These were the last words uttered by Mickey Mahoney on that night of promised events. He staggered backwards, and fell upon a huge Maguay plant which grew near the path.</p>
               <p>Presently the porter's bell again rung. Dick inquired in good Spanish:</p>
               <p>"Quien vive?"</p>
               <p>"Soldats! Dumiger!" was the answer.</p>
               <p>Instead of admitting them, he applied a whistle to his lips, and blew one shrill, prolonged note. Ere its echo had died away, a party of Americans had rushed upon Dumiger's followers and overpowered them. Keen came forth, and giving the American sergeant a lasso, ordered the captives to be<pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC6928-00000043"/> strung together after the fashion he had once experienced at Goliad. They were then led at a short distance, where the end of the cord was secured to a tree. Among the arms taken from them was an old American rifle, which attracted Dick's attention.</p>
               <p>"May I be singed, boys, if that isn't my old 'Joe Manton! he exclaimed in joyful tone, and embracing his old rifle as affectionately as he would have hugged his sweetheart had he met her in that strange place.</p>
               <p>"Old yellar-skin," said he, addressing the Mexican from whom his rifle was taken, "whar did you get that weap'n?"</p>
               <p>"Goliad, Senor."</p>
               <p>"Then I s'pose you had a hand in that shootin'?"</p>
               <p>"Si, Senor."</p>
               <p>"And you?"</p>
               <p>"Si, Senor."</p>
               <p>This question was put to each, and all gave an affirmative answer.</p>
               <p>"Oh! you infernal cussed butchers!" said the Kentuckian. "Unlucky's the hour that you fell into the hands of one of the suff'rers! Sargeant, said he, "keep these yellar-skins fast trapped. Let not one on 'em escape. Every skin is my game!—food for powder!"</p>
               <p>Giving this caution, he re-entered the Convent grounds, to guard the outer door.</p>
               <milestone n="——" unit="typography"/>
               <p>Let us now look into an apartment of the edifice before us, apart from the rooms occupied by the nuns. Seated at an ironbarred casement, gazing fixedly upon the rising moon, was a lady, apparently twenty-six or twenty-seven years of age. A care-worn and sorrowful expression rested upon her transcendently beautiful features. Yet, hope gleamed in her lustrous, heavenly eyes, and courage was stamped upon her firmly compressed lips. She had been weeping, ay, praying, too—not before fore a crucifix—not before an idolator's image—but praying to the one, invisible, omniscient, omnipresent Being.</p>
               <p>Presently, she was startled by the unlocking of her prison loor, and turning, her eyes fell upon him she despised in her girlhood's days, and who had recently renewed his persecution. The intruder strode boldly across the room, and seized her rudely by the arm.</p>
               <p>"Dumiger! monster! begone!" she cried, releasing her arm from his grasp.</p>
               <p>"No, no, my beauteous fair one!" he replied, with an air of confidence. "At length you are in my power! Yield and treat me kindly, and I will not take that revenge which I should, for what I have suffered from the cruel wound you inflicted upon me."</p>
               <p>"Whatever be my fate, Carlos Dumiger, never can I look upon thee other than as a fiend, a brute, a loathsome creature. Take thy revenge by plunging thy sword into my heart. Death has no terror for me!"</p>
               <p>"Then thy death would be but poor revenge," answered Dumiger. "No, no, my charmer; such an event will not suit my purpose. I have provided for thee a most luxurious abode in Puebla, where we shall live, and love, and be happy. Go with me quietly, and every attention shall be paid you.—Resist, and by Heaven you shall be dragged thither by brutal soldiers! Remember, no power can give you aid. I cannot be thwarted again."</p>
               <p>"Merciless wretch! I scorn thy threats, as I do thy base propositions!" she replied.</p>
               <p>Hereupon the wretch again seized her by the arm, and stamping his foot, the monk came to his aid, and seizing the other arm, they succeeded in dragging her partly across the room, when a loud voice exclaimed:</p>
               <p>"Hold! monsters!"</p>
               <p>Releasing their victim, who had fainted under their rudeness they turned and beheld two individuals, with naked swords confronting them.</p>
               <pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC6928-00000044"/>
               <p>"By H—ll. we're thwarted!" cried the impious monk.</p>
               <p>"Draw, villains! and defend your lives!" exclaimed Halsinger, as he rushed upon the monk, while Woodland crossed swords with Dumiger.</p>
               <p>The contest was a desperate one on both sides, but it lasted not long. Victory was on the side of the right. The vile Dumiger, and his impious confederate fell almost at the same moment.</p>
               <p>Woodland now knelt over his long-lost bride, who was lying prostrate on the floor. Oh, God! how his heart beat with joy, as he felt her soft breath upon his cheek, and saw her open those heavenly orbs of light. He gently raised her exhausted form to his arms, and imprinted burning kisses upon her bloodless lips. She was pale, yet looked smilingly, and he fanned her cheek with his hand.</p>
               <p>"Merciful Heavens!" was her first feeble exclamation "this is a beautiful vision—in it I again look upon my husband—I am in his arms—I feel the warm pressure of his hand—ah! he kisses my cold lips. Hush! let me not awake—let me die in this happy, delightful dream!"</p>
               <p>"Ah! my sweet dove! this is no dream!" said Woodland, fearing lest her mind was diseased. "I am, truly, thy Henry! Sabra, look upon me!"</p>
               <p>"Hark! I hear his voice! he speaks in those loved and familiar tones!" she again essayed.</p>
               <p>"This is no dream—this is reality—awake, Sabra, and behold thy long absent husband, who comes to bear thee from thy vile pesecutors!"</p>
               <p>She smiled incredulously at his first words, but when he alluded to her persecutors, she roused herself, as if from a dreamy state, and gazing for a moment into her husband's face, and then upon the bloody corses of her enemies, she threw herself into her husband's embrace, exclaiming:</p>
               <p>"Oh joy!—it is no vision! Thou art truly my own dear, dear Henry!" and the tears gushing from a happy heart's fountain, rolled profusely down her beauteous cheeks.</p>
               <p>They both wept, and so did the veteran soldier, who could not look upon this proof of affection without emotion.</p>
               <p>With the assistance of Halsinger, Woodland bore his be loved from that sacrilegious temple to his quarters at Puebla. Two happier beings slept not in Mexico on that eventful night.</p>
               <milestone n="*   *   *   *   *   *   *   *   *   *" unit="typography"/>
               <p>Other incidents of that night, however, remain to be told. To our eccentric friend, the Kentuckian, was entrusted the disposition of Dumiger's soldiers, whom he had taken captive. At his own request, the American soldiers returned to quarters as escort for Captain Woodland and his bride.</p>
               <p>There, in the stillness of the night, with the moon shining brightly and serenely their heads, with no human eye upon them, stood Dick Keen, confronting his six captives, and gazing upon them with as much delight as he would have done upon a herd of buffaloes within reach of his rifle. He approached them closely, and will all the dignity of a western stump orator haranguing an audience, he addressed them as follows;—</p>
               <p>"Prehaps you don't know who I am. My name is Dick Keen. I'm a full-limbed, full-blooded. Kentuckian by birth and by nater, and I'm reckoned the best shot in our parts. You all know the time when four hunderd on us were strung together at Goliad like so many sheep. Prehaps you don't, but I do. I was one on 'em, but I escaped to avenge their foul murder! and consid'rable luck I've had in the bizness. I reckon I've killed a thousand Mex'cans since then—but what's the vally of a thousand of sich yellar, cut-throat lookin' chaps as ye are? Ye're hardly fit for power, but I am bound to do my duty. So, down on yer marrow bones and say yer prayers, for I reckon you won't have another chance—and that's more'n you 'lowed us at Goliad. I'll be magnanimous, and gin you a speek of a chance to escape being bored by one o' my bullets—I grant each on you a run for life, and I won't pull trigger till you get at a fair turkey-shot distance!"</p>
               <p>The culprits mumbled over their "Aves," but with little<pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC6928-00000045"/> sincerity, for they imagined that there was more than an equa chance of saving their lives.</p>
               <p>Dick pointed out the direction they must run, threatening that, if they diverged to the right or to the left he would fire fortnwith.</p>
               <p>"Now, Mexy, number one," said Dick, freeing one of his captives, "vamouse!—legs again 'Jos Manton'—go it!"</p>
               <p>The captive started, and after running a distance of one hundred yards, Dick leisurely raised his rifle to a level, and fired! No. 1 fell as suddenly as if he had been stricken by a thunderbolt!</p>
               <p>Dick reloaded his weapon and released number two. He ran no farther than his dead comrade, when "crack" went the rifle, and No. 2 measured his length upon mother earth.</p>
               <p>Numbers three and four were served in the same manner Numbers five and six were set free from the cord at the same moment, and they run for dear life in separate directions.</p>
               <p>The Kentuckian leveled "old Joe" at one and brought him to the earth. Then turning suddenly about, he seized "Joe, Junior," and its swift-winged messenger penetrated the heart of his last captive!</p>
               <p>Dick coolly reloaded both of his rifles, and placing one upon each shoulder, he marched off to the camp of the Americans, to the tune of "Hail Columbia, happy land," which he whistled all the way!</p>
               <milestone n="——" unit="typography"/>
               <p>Woodland, with his bride, a day or two afterwards, left Puebla at the head of his corps, for the "Halls of the Montesumas," and distinguished himself in every important conflict on the route, even to the very gates of the capital.</p>
               <p>The brave and generous Halsinger, who had already accomplished so much for the hero and heroine of our story, reassumed his holy habiliments, with the ardent hope of doing another favor for the man who had given him liberty and life He had found papers in the possession of the monk, indicating that Ninette Woodland, the sole child of Henry and Sabra Woodland, with an escort, had but recently left Puebla for some port on the Mexican coast, thence to be sent to Boston, U. S. A., by the first vessel thitherward bound. Woodland obtained a passport for his friend, and he started off on the identical mule we have before seen him astride. He had not travelled more than six leagues when he fell in with a large body of American troops, from whom he learned that the identical escort, together with the darling object of his pursuit, had been intercepted, and that they were in their hands.</p>
               <p>Delighted beyond measure, our pseudo friar sought an interview with the commander of this force, and laid before him his passports and other papers which he had obtained for furthering his intentions. The result was that the pretty Ninette was placed under his care, and he retraced his steps under the protection of this division of the army.</p>
               <p>On the very day that the "Star Spangled Banner" first waved in triumph over the Mexican capital, a carriage halted at Capt Woodland's quarters, and from it alighted Halsinger. He then took Ninette from the vehicle in his arms, just as Woodland made his appearance.</p>
               <p>"Joy, my friend! for I have the felicity of restoring to a father's arms his long lost daughter!" said Halsinger as he transferred his smiling happy little charge to the overjoyed captain. "See—she is the perfect image of your wife!"</p>
               <p>Woodland was too happy for reply. He kissed her sweet lips an hundred times, and wept like a child. The mother now appeared, and the child flew to her embrace. It was a happy scene—too happy for description, but one easily imagined.</p>
               <p>Upon the battle-field, in the midst of carnage and death, Ninette was lost to her father. In the conquered capital, after the final conflict was fought, and after a lapse of eleven long years, Ninette was restored.</p>
               <p>Santa Anna and his minions had fled.—"Peace was conquered." The American General treated with a new <foreign xml:lang="FRA">regime,</foreign>
                  <pb n="90" xml:id="VAC6928-00000046"/> and the brave but maltreated Halsinger, having exposed Mexico's misrulers, was called to a high position in the councils of his nation, which place, we learn, he still retains.</p>
               <p>Woodland, with his family, returned to the United States with the victorious army. His father-in-law, Mr Sherwood, having but recently died intestate, he in behalf of his wife, came into the possession of an ample fortune, which, we are pleased to add, they are now enjoying in a manner befitting their station. He has resigned his commission as Lieut. Colonel in the corps of Flying Artillerists, to which rank he had been promoted for distinguished services in the Mexican campaign.</p>
               <p>Reader, should you, in your rides or rambles in the vicinity of Boston, chance to pass by a large and noble mansion, of Gothic architecture, with beautiful grounds laid out with exceeding taste, with flowering shrubs and fruitful trees, with here and there a statue of marble or an appropriate group, with fountains and arbors, and every luxury desired about a country villa, you may rest assured that Henry Woodland is the proprietor.—And should you chance to see a sweet, bright eyed, cherry-cheeked girl of scarcely fifteen summers, culling flowers, or playing with a cherub boy of two years old, you may at once exclaim,—that is Ninette Woodland, "THE CHILD OF THE BATTLE FIELD!" And should you chance to see a gentleman, of commanding, dignified bearing, mounted upon a noble charger, which he rides with consummate skill, you cannot mistake him for any other than the hero of our story, "THE FLYING ARTILLERIST!"</p>
            </div>
            <closer>THE END.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>