<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6602">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Something to Wear </title>
            <author>Doesticks, Junior.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC6602</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-1076</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Something to wear</title>
                  <author>Doesticks, Junior.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>67 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>F.A. Brockway</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Brooklyn </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1857">1857</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
            <language ident="deu">German</language>
            <language ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-05-28">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Nick Homenda" when="2013-10-21">Mass transformation to fix page breaks, update schema, and update project information.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Something to wear</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6602-00000001"/>  SOMETHING TO WEAR,   AND SOME OTHER THINGS.  BY DOESTICKS, JUNIOR.  BROOKLYN: 181 FULTON STREET. 3185 ,    <pb n="0" xml:id="VAC6602-00000002"/>  Entered according to Act of Congress in the year 1857, BY HARLAN  P. HALSEY, In the Clerk's Office, of the District Comrt of the United States for the Southern D'strict of N'ew-York.   SOMETHNG TO WE R. AN EPISODE OF CITY LIFE. ouisa McPHEogoN was lovely and fair, Always gay and cheerful with something  to wear; Her eyes were dark blue, and her forehead was high, Her hair glossy black while her complexion did vie; '.With the most brilliant tints of Elly and rose,    <pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC6602-00000003"/> 6    Something to Wear. Her teeth, with the whiteness of Alpian Snows; With features quite handsome, and voice soft and sweet, Always ready to sooth, cheer, welcome and greet. Possessing one winning, agreeable grace, A sweet peaceful smile that illumined her face, And speaks of a spirit contented and pure,  The possessor of strength enough to endure Patiently, the sore trials and ills of life,' And a calmness amidst bickerings and strife. In demeanor modest, in manners refined, And lively in motion, contented in mind, , These qualities so pleasing, all had a share   Somethingg to Wear,.       7 In causing contentment, with sometaing to -wear. } Her father a merchant of lucrative trade, His bills when presented most cheerfully paid , And never before " three" goes " skinnqing around, On the " borrow," to make a bank account \   sound. His family was large just nine, when all told, And order was the first law of his -house; hold; w .                      .  .              J^    <pb n="8-9 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6602-00000004"/> 8   ' Something to Wear. His mirthful daughters all were beautiful queens, Enjoying bright hours, and just in( their "teens ; And in their good sense, had certain de- fences, Against young squirts, bereft of their senses, In other words, conceited, dressy donkeys, Apes in their appearance, in manners- monkeys. Those whom nature most certainly intended By their great length of ears to be defen- ded From the grave charge of possessing com- mon senset Or even ordinary intelligence..   ! "x                   , Apes in their appearance, in manners monkeys. [See page 8. [5,pae8    <pb n="10 (Illustration) -11" xml:id="VAC6602-00000005"/> ----.. Sit and smirk and smile and grin Until some unsuspecting maid is " taken in." [See page   Something to Wear.     11  Vain puppy's that smirk, and smile, and grin, Till some unsuspecting maid is "taken in," But thanks to training, Louisa, lovely girl, Could not be dazzled by fashions dizzy whirl. Having been rejected by Flora the gay, From her door in disgust I turned sad away; Declaring all women both giddysand light, And ready from fashion to fashion to flight Forgetting that life is a serious state, Dizzy rounds of pleasures they never abate; But glory in Parties, and companies gay,.    <pb n="12 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6602-00000006"/> 12   Something to Wear. And the dear treasures of health flitter away. In winter, in gauzes and laces go bear, Instead of possessing something warm to wear. Quite ready to chatter, and titter, and smile, And hours for sleep in excitement beguile. But Louisa, sweet girl, never wasted her nights, In pleasures which the strength of health- fulness blights; And never indulged in blank irritation, Or e'er whined the foolish reiteration; Oh! dear, its too bad, I have nothing to wear: Its really tyranic and I do declare If Papa dont buy me a darling new dressl   C I' Quite ready to chatter and titter and smile, And hours for sleep in excitement beguile. [Seepage 12.    <pb n="0-13" xml:id="VAC6602-00000007"/>   Something to SWear.     13 I shall die with a silken chronic distress.  No, no, sweet Louisa rejoiced in good health, And never felt colds crawling on her by , stealth;  And never her duties, and-so-forth, put off, Because of some fierce alarming   hectic- cough: Never complained  of fever, headache or pains, A lack of silk dresses and 'mouslin de'lanes, Her ward-robe was always abundantly fill'dl With waistes, skirts and basques, most elegantly frilled,  And her father never complaining  could say, Unreasonable sums for dresses I pay.    <pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6602-00000008"/> "   Something to Wear. She had fine clothes in which to walk and to ride, And even some dresses were left to be dyed, Yet always to parties she went richly dress'd, And dresses once dyed looked as good as the rest. Oh, ladies! dear ladies! lovely and fair, If you would be happy, have something to wear, Possess cheerfulness, and contentment of mind, And real comfort, peace, and happiness find,   P* OO'1 Something to Wear.      15 Oh, cultivate a disposition with care, That will teach you with a cheerful mind to bear With patience all the trials and ills of life, Put on an armor prepare for the great strife Against fashion and fashionable nonsense, So deadly to peace, affection and conscience, Then pray forgive me, on this a wJhile I dwell, And the balance of my experience tell With Miss McPherson of whom I have written; Though not at first with my poor person smitten, Without the power or will of prevention,    <pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6602-00000009"/> ) 16   Something to Wear. Received with great grace, my trifling attention. While these I was paying, I was wispering beware, Lest she shoild turn out with ' nothing to wear," Thus I determined carefully to study Day in, day out, whether pleasant or muddy, Her character, the difference draw with care,   Something to Wear.     17 'Twix't those who have "nothing" or "something," to wear;  And prove how that insignificant trait To some others more important doth relate And show how those ladies with clothing enough, Can battle with fortune either smooth or rough, How this one little "straw" conclusively shows, The channel in which their real ambition flows; That a "Miss" who has "something to - wearl Of a habit of idleness will beware, 2    <pb n="18 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6602-00000010"/> 18   Something to V ear. And not her life in sheer indolence pass through, With such senseless complaints as "nothing to do ; Nor when married, her husband's wishes defeat With excuses4f having "nothing to eat ;" Nor from his caresses turn moping away ,Unable to smile and with " nothing to say," And drive him wretched along toward ruin's brink, 'Till he drowns his sorrows in "something to drinkl,"           r Or go gaddilg and shoping from day to day 'Till her papa bursts np With " nothing to pay."     ,  Oh, yet it is a most lamentable truth    And drive him wretched along towards ruin's brink, 'Till he drown his sorrows in something to drink. [Sce paqe 18. [    <pb n="-19" xml:id="VAC6602-00000011"/> I r 4 1j A. I   Something   to Wear.   19 That -the majority of our female youth Possess all these hard faults of ivhic:l I sing, And when rui - upoa their Papas they bring, With pining and tears lament their affliction, And use sour language without r3 rliction; While poor Papas, of every cent bereft, Discover the fact when there's 'nothinog left"' That they must endure contempt and de- rision, Be blamed for waste and indicision- Or a husband through the wiles of such a wife, Feels severely that there's "nothing sweet in life." 88630    <pb n="20-23" xml:id="VAC6602-00000012"/> 20   Something to Wear.  But excuse me dear reader, I promised you That I would carry my poor rhythm right through, And frankly, fairly and truthfully state The difference between a one" and the "other" trait, And as I proceed, oh, glory ye bright fair, That from your ranks came one " with something to wear  Who lost not her character or position, And fulfils on earth a real useful mission, And yet retains a sufficiency of pride As " charity" and "fashion" can be alied; The goddess of fashion so hardly reviled, Around many an artist's hearth oft hath smiled Ft   Something to Wear.    23 With the coveted gift of " something to do," To produce from his genius "something quite new; Although proud fashion each mere whim will obey,  Worshippers at her shrine generously pay. The worst sin of fashion consists in the fact That 'tis not fashionable to do a good act. But I hope reason and sense will prevail While I proceed on with the pith of my tale:    <pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6602-00000013"/> 24   Something to Wear. One drear winter night I sat in my arm chair And gazed in the fire with a meaningless stare, Indulging in dreamy thoughts of future days, Picturing bright hours illumined by rays Of happiness reflected from the bright eyes Of her who in my heart had kindled a flame As pure and true as any that e'er did rise In the heart of mortal, such a love to claim Was sweet indeed, while thus I sat and mused   Somethiingto Wear.    25 My sight grew dim and my mind became confused, When lo, suddenly, a "change came o'er my dream," And I assumed a light spiritual form, My mortal frame no longer a weight did seem But on the fierce wind though the fierce howling storm, I floated as a spirit, and yet in human shape, Dark clouds fringed the sky as with a mourn- ing crape. The rain pelted down, the wind whistled dreary Around an old barn some miles from the city,    <pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6602-00000014"/> 26   Something to Wear. Where dwelt a lone soul of life's burden weary; Unblessed with life's comforts or human pitye In the fire-place there smothered an unfed On the floor stood a table, upon it no fare Wherewith to quench a stomach s cra -ing desire, And nothing to cheer a poor mortal was there. In the corner upon a pallet of strat Was stretched a poor shrunken, wasted hu- man form, A mortal that much happier days once saw   Something to Wear.     27 And in comfort was shelter'd from wind and storm; Shivering with the cold the poor sufferer* groaned As more hoarsely without the cutting wind moaned. Groan followed groan, and painful sighs struggled up As the sufferer quaffed from life's bitterest cup, No soothing voice was near, no low mur- tnured prayer Arose from that poor suffering being there So cold the once proud leader of fashion lay    <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6602-00000015"/> 28    Something to Wear. Bereft of earth's splentdors unable to pray. Into this lone room I slowly descended Seemingly invisible to mortal eye And beheld poverty and fashion blended In this forsaken soul about to die, Gliding beside her bedside there I stood, And gazed in the sufferer's pallid face, I saw features pinched by care and lack of food AWhich once were crowned with happy, grace. A moment I gazed, when oh, my God, I saw Surrounded by filth, groaning, suffering there;   Something to Wear.     29 She  who had acknowedged as first fashion's law Who when blessed with plenty had " no- thing to wear. Memory  recalled her when in youthful pride, Crownedl with splendid beauties she sat at my side; She raised her head on her cheek, there fell a tear, She spoke; I leaned me forward her worda to hear.    <pb n="30 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6602-00000016"/> 30   Something to Wear. SOLILOQUY OF A DYING "WOMAN OF THE WORLD.  Neglected, left alone to die, There's no kind friend now near The fierce wind rushes howling by And all is sad and drear. Where are those many, many friends, That used to court my smile, The wind an answering echo sends I hear it all the while. Thy friends, aha, you'll find them now In fashion's lighted hall,   Thy friend, ahla! you'll find them now In f;ishion's liglhtedt hall, 'Neath the same lighlt which on thy brow Some days ano did taill.     [See p 'e '. 2"    <pb n="0-31" xml:id="VAC6602-00000017"/> I i I -             .   Something to Wear.     31 'Neath the same lights which on thy brow Some days agone did fall. There smiling now as thou once smild, Heedless of future care, Conscience by pleasures bright beguiled No time for thought can spare. Oh, where are those who pledged their love Enduring as the hills, As lasting as heavenly vows above 'Midst happiness or ills. Again an answer finds my ear Sends to my heart a chill, In fashion's Hall they yet appear, N And vow affection still. 3    <pb n="32" xml:id="VAC6602-00000018"/> 32   Something to Wear. Oh! where are all the precious hours That I so much enjoyed How was my time when cast 'midst flowers Continually employed, They're gone, forever fed and gone, And flittered all away; Oh when I reach that final bourne Ah! then what can I say. And what is now my fate, my lot, An answer reason begs Of wealth bereft, by friends forgot, I'm quafling now the dregs.    <pb n="Illustration-33" xml:id="VAC6602-00000019"/> a  ^  Falshon, nashiwn, I itttelil. , fai/ ,  3e^,tiler of time, deadler of ctee Jcstz over of feeli ngx tAse. p^  ]'etroyer or' feig, C;epq::,   Something to Wear.     33 Fashion, glittering, flashing and fair, Bitterness concealing Beguiler of time, healer of care, Destroyer of feeling. Allured by thee, time I squandered; The future I forgot! After thy bright bubbles I wandered Charity heeding not. While worshipping at thy bright shrine Life indeed was sweet, Kind friends and fortune all were mine Among the gay elite,    <pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6602-00000020"/> 34   Something to Wear. But now, how changed, I'm dying fast, Oh time, pray linger now, Time for repentance it is past, Death's written on my brow. Demons linger around my bed,  Their calling spirit come, Memory, reason, all have fled, My tongue is stricken dumb.   Something to Wear.     35 She ceased to speak, yet from her bright glassy eye Maniac glances shot forth, reason had fled, And there s he tossed and moaned, who among the high; The richest, and proudest, of this gay world was bred: Powerless to move, I watched, she breathed her last, And upon her face was stamped a ghastly smile, Death-shadows around her shrunken form were cast, And all was over, earth's pleasures and trials:    <pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6602-00000021"/> 36   Something to Wear. Motionless I stood, upon the body gazed When lo, a dazzling light around me blazed, I saw a form clad in garments as bright And shining as the brilliant, dazzling noon-day light. Holiness and peace illumined his calm face; And stamped him as being of a heavenly race, ie spoke, his heavenly voice was sweet and clear And fell like seraphic music on the ear; "Fashion was the god of that departed soul,"   Something to uWear.     37 No higher aim was her's while enjoying life, In wealth and luxuries she struggled to roll And join in fashion's glittering, dazzling strife. At religion's warning voice she loved to scoff, And of her ye now behold the end thereof; Fashion, her first god, has left her dying there, And too bitterly, with " nothing to wear.' Oh! Son of Earth! thou hast witnessed a scene Which unto thy soul a lesson should teach,    <pb n="38-41" xml:id="VAC6602-00000022"/> 38   Something to Wear. Yon stiffPing mortal's life from childhood hath been Disturbed by yearnings for joys beyond her reach. Death now has vanquished all her- earthly hopes Her spirit has left this darkened world of care, And brighter scenes unto her vision ope's Yet she can find no peace or solace there. But, come thou mortal, visit with me a room From whence another spirit will soon- depart,   Something to Wear.     41 Though shadowed in clouds of sadness and gloom, Hope there still lingers to gladden the heart. Again I floated through the gloom of night, The storm had cleared away and -stars shone forth, Afar I beheld Aurora's great light /   Illumining the horizon in the north, Presently, o'er a strange city we sailed Where noiselessly into a house descending, We entered a drear room in sorrow veiled, Where a soul its struggles on earth was ending.    <pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6602-00000023"/> 42   Something to Wear. On the bed she lay beautiful and calm, Her weeping friends she gaily sought to cheer, And sweetly smiled, as if a Heavenly Psalm Fell soothingly upon her listening ear; Her glance was clear, no furrowed lines of pain Were traced upon her calm and peaceful brow, Seemingly with nought to lose, all was gain To her bright pure spirit forever now; My guide in shining clothes turned and said, Mortal! behold yon cheerful happy soul   Something to Wear.     43     b There are no trembling signs of fear or dread,  And no fearful terrors around it roll. That dying maiden, once lovely and fairy    i In life had many pleasing traits of mind, Was always cheerful, had "something to Wear."                   i To those about her was gentle and kind, Her days were fraught with contentment  and peace; And hope is hers' now life's about to cease  She speaks, and now, oh mortal man attend Her words unto thy soul will comfort send.    <pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6602-00000024"/> "   Something to Wear. SOLILOQUY OF A DYING "A CHLD OF GOD Y Life is departing slowly, surely, Oh, still my friends, don't weep, I've tried to serve my Maker truely, And as I've sown I'll reap. Oh, how sweet, how cheering the thought, hen now about to die; That Christ by his dear blood hath bought A home for me on high. Grim death can cause me but few pangs, In separation, friends, For hope around that sorrow hangs'l And comfort to me sends.   Something to Wear.     45 Through life, a pleasure "twas to give To needy ones around, Mine was a pleasant one to live, In death, strong hope I've found. My friends, farewell I I'm fainter now, M[y strength is failing fast; Death is settling on my brow, My time has come at last. Oh, yet -I'm ready now to die; 1 have no wish to live; One hour of time I would not buy, For life one asking give, 4    <pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC6602-00000025"/> "   Something to Wear. Farewell! farewell! we'll. meet again I Beyond this world of care, When we'll be free from every pain, Have something bright to wear. My memory's fading, my pulses cease And sight has left me too, A moment will my soul release Farewell! Heaven I view, She spoke no more her spirit with a smile Forsook the faded, shrunken form of clay, And free from impurity, wrong, or guile, Toward the bright realms of Heaven sped away.   Something to Wear.     47 I turned to address the angel by my side, WNThen a glorious vision I beheld, To rise, to speak, to move, I vainly tried, Upon the scene to gaze I was compelled. The Heavens were illumined by floods of light Rivalling in brightness the noon-day sun, And on a great throne that dazzled my sight, I saw the Omnipotent UHoly One." There kneeling at the throne was the young maid Who upon the low bed of death had laid,    <pb n="48-51" xml:id="VAC6602-00000026"/> 48   Something to Wear. And I beheld her clothed with glory there NWho while on earth had " something to wear.^ I strove again to speak, but seemed t(o choke, -When suddenly to consciousness I awoke And discovered that all' which real did seem WAas nothing but a passing, fitful dream. In a comfortable house on Avenne C, In a room gathered around a bright blazing fire; There's assembled a family from trouble quite free,   Something to Wear.     51 Surrounded by all comforts that heart can desire, Happinesss in that house has built a throne, On pillars of purity, contentment, kindness and truth, Where sour words and angry replies are unknown Only health and pleasure, contentment and youth. By the hearth-stone ensconced in an ample arm-chair, Is Louisa, who always had  " something to wear."    <pb n="52 (Illustration) " xml:id="VAC6602-00000027"/> 52   Something to Wear. On the floor engaged with his children at play, Is he, once rejected by Flora the gay. Hard times are darkening many happy homes, In hideous shape among the poor it roams ; But frugality did this family prepare And now they have plenty to " eat and tao. wear.' To the poor quite cheerfully have " some- thing to say," And around the face of poverty cause smiles to play;    ..... :- But frugality did this family prep rc Aild now they have plenty to cat aid to wear. [Sepcage 2. [Seae 2    <pb n="-53" xml:id="VAC6602-00000028"/>  Something to Wear.    53 And along our back streets fearlessly go through, So in cheering the poor find ";something / -to do." And now while the cry of ' hard times" around us rings, We'll change our subject to, SOME OTHER THNGS. In this day when "Nothings" are flooding the trade, By which into Books dull manuscripts are made;    <pb n="54" xml:id="VAC6602-00000029"/> 54   Something to Wear. There are some "Nothings" deserving of mention Which claim their full share of public at- tention; There are "Nothings" so mean, and stingy and small, That truthfully speaking, there's just " no- thing at all ;" Nor even of nothing the one-millionth part In manners, or actions, or reason or heart, But simply slick-walking, breathing forms of clays Resembling an Ass between stacks of hay, They get between two heaps of public plunder,     <pb n="Illustration-55" xml:id="VAC6602-00000030"/> -4. Now too, a lawyer remains above par 'YCL;;  [eepae 5   Something to Wear.     55 And bray before a people lost in wonder; Judges, lawyers, mayors, police and all, Are at the present day just " nothing at all." on a jury; Hearing nothing but counsels quarrel like fury, And now  too, a lawyer remains above par, Whether he practices, or drinks at the bar; And murderers, and much   worse mur- deresses, A right good chance of getting clear pos- sesses; ,   <pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC6602-00000031"/> 58   Something to Wear. While an innocent person runs a good chance In open air 'twixt heaven and earth to dance. For pure justice lawyers no longer plead But old dusty volumes of precedents read ; Law cases argued sometimes in the year one, In some far off barbarous land beneath the sun, Or else for hours and hours they will jaw About some dirty "technical point" in lasw; Charging their-clients with the precious time they waste   1 Something to Wear.     d9 In vile slang by which a beast would be disgraced. Soulless thieves may steal the cash for which they lust, And go scott-free on the "Point"Breach of Trust But if it prove that they have been too rash And certainly pilfered, aye, stole the cash, Then  if they have of their stealings sufficient left; Great justice of her sword can be bereft, An habeas corpus catch and seize 'em Can quickly be procured, forsooth, to please 'em.    <pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC6602-00000032"/> 60   Something to Wear. Judges each other's decisions embarrass, And often their several proceedings harrass. In dignity they now no longer take pride, Politics, not justice, their cases decide ; Republican thieves may be sentenced for years, AWhile thieves Democratic are free from all fears Unless tried before a RepuDlican judge, Then they probably towards States Prison may trudge. Laws are not recognized now   by their intent   Something to -Wear     61 But all hangs upon the way a phrase is bent; Thus liquors on Sundays can be sold no, more But the Law don't mention a "Grog Shops' Back Door." All private cases are kept out of Court While over great public cases' lawyers sport; The people endure foul, health-destroying streets While waiting  to see which demagogue beats. 5    <pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC6602-00000033"/> 62   Something to Wear. A vacancy occurs the Governor appoints, And thereby weakens the Mayor in his joints; And he on the strength of his own dis- cretion By force puts another man in possession And the moneys of the Public have to pay For what lawyers and judges all "have to say!" Oh, patient public! you're dazzled by the glitter, Justice Is dead! its pearls away they fritter, And ye get "nothing!" aye, "nothing at all,"   Something to Wear.     63 Yet on thee, for your encouragement they call, Returning you neither their love nor pro- tection And  forget all their oaths right after election! Pick-pockets and rowdies preside at the polls         ,  And the colnting ofvote', se c., controls, NVhile payers of' taxes;" asessments and tithes *   '. ,  Are exposed to the risk of getting black eyes; And if some foul "rough" their ballot opposes,  -            <pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC6602-00000034"/> "   Something to Wear. They're plone to give in to save broken 10oses. Our highest officers, when they're elected, In some bold  plunder scheme become 'connected; And our modern maLyors, in this' age of reason,  Are boldly :gilty obf thl foulest treason. And   brave  sliegislsature' and 'courts of appeal In locusts and slung-shots extensively deal, The public are even deprived of police, To guard and protect, and insure certain peace;   Something to Wear.      65 'While at the same time they're forced to pay, As if they were guarded through the night and day. 'This is at present the city's position, Because there's a row in the "Police 0Cn- mission.." But it is little that these gentlemen care, As long as they have " something to wear ; And nothing so pleasant to   them, it is true, As this little "Nothing"--just " nothing to do."    <pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC6602-00000035"/> "   Something to Wear. Reader, these are frightful, dreadful times, Owing to the scarcity of " stuff" called dimes; Business Firms are Failing! Banks are Breaking! And  some more unfair advantage are taking! And your obedient's chance has a very bad- look In regard to the sale of this Little Book. But as these are really very poor rhymes, Their chance is better, considering the times. Farewell! and if this only returns me some cash   Sornething to Wear.     67 I'll be glad to see it suspend and smash; But as probably we'll soon find ourselves minus, I'll abruptly close with a sweet little FINIS.     </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
