<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
   xml:id="VAC6522">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gertrude Morgan, or, Life and Adventures Among the Indians of the Far West </title>
            <author>Anonymous</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC6522</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-0999</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                  copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction
                  project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                  University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is granted
                  to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                  contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                  educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                  inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University
                  Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
               Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gertrude Morgan, or, Life and adventures among the Indians of the far
                     West</title>
                  <author>Anonymous</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Barclay</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Philadelphia </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1866">1866</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
               Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
               website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and has
               been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
               Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-04-16">Finished OCR, rough
            encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="Pacific Data Conversion Corp." when="2001-12-27">Finished transcription and
            SGML encoding</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2002-04-18">Finished TEI conversion
            and final editing</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-08-04">Converted document from SGML to TEI
            P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-08-04">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents
            and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n="Illustration (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6522-00000001"/>
         <div type="illustrations">
            
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>Oh, what a horrible sight was it to see those stalwart powerful men reeling,
                     stumbling, and wrestling about, each endeavoring to gain the advantage.—Page
                     16.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>GERTRUDE MORGAN:</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">OR, LIFE AND ADVENTURES AMONG THE INDIANS OF THE FAR
                  WEST.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>PHILADELPHIA:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>PUBLISHED BY BARCLAY &amp; CO 602 ARCH STREET.</publisher>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
         <pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6522-00000002"/>
         <div type="fly_title">
            <bibl>
               <edition>Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1866, by BARCLAY &amp;
                  CO., In the Clerk's Office of the District Court of the United States, in and for
                  the Eastern District of Pennsylvania.</edition>
            </bibl>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>Gertrude Morgan, or, Life and adventures among the Indians of the far West</head>
            <head>GERTRUDE MORGAN.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THE experience of this accomplished lady, a native of New York City, during the
                  past eleven years, nearly all of which time she has lived among the Indians of the
                  Far West, by whom she was captured in 1855, is, perhaps, one of the most thrilling
                  and romantic that has ever been given to the public. The narrative, the
                  reliability of which is unquestionable, is written by Mrs. Morgan herself, and has
                  just been put, by the fair authoress, into the hands of the editor, who, with the
                  exception of here and there introducing an explanatory paragraph or sentence, has
                  made no alteration whatever in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>A full detailed account of my early history would, as far as the object of this
                  narrative is concerned, be of no consequence to the general reader, and I shall,
                  therefore, pass it with but a casual allusion.</p>
               <p>Born of wealthy parents in New York City, I experienced, from the time of my birth
                  up to my twentieth year, none of those ills, or vicissitudes, or trials, which
                  fall to the lot of so many. My doting father and mother, who had no other child
                  but myself, lavished upon me all that heart could wish for, and yet guided my
                  inclinations and disposition so gently and skillfully in the right direction, that
                  I escaped the result so generally brought about by parental indulgence, that of
                  becoming a spoiled child. At the time of which I speak, however—my twentieth
                  year—the cloudless, azure sky, that had hitherto smiled so brightly upon my life
                  path, suddenly became obscured. My father, by an unfortunate speculation, failed
                  in his business, lost all he had, and in a single day became a penniless man.</p>
               <p>This fearful reverse of fortune so deeply affected my mother, that in a very short
                  time after its occurrence, we were called on to follow her to the tomb, where,
                  thank Heaven, worldly trouble at last terminates. My father never looked up from
                  that day out, and in less than a year from<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6522-00000003"
                  /> the time that the green sods were placed on my mother's grave, I laid him
                  beside her, whom he had so dearly loved. Of all the hosts of friends who had
                  smiled upon me when <choice>
                     <sic>surronnded</sic>
                     <corr>surrounded</corr>
                  </choice> by affluence, there was only <emph>one</emph> who then, in the moment of
                  my adversity, stood with me and wept over my father's coffin, as the attendants
                  lowered it gently in its dusty resting place: and this one friend was William
                  Morgan, who had, for several years, been my father's confidential clerk.</p>
               <p>For sometime previous, there had existed between us a mutual feeling of affection,
                  which had continually increased in strength until this sorrowful day, on which we
                  vowed to live only for each other. In about two weeks after my father's funeral,
                  William obtained a situation, at a moderate salary, and we were, soon after,
                  united in the holy bonds of wedlock. Although reduced to such humble circumstance,
                  when compared to those in which I had passed the previous part of my life, yet I
                  was very happy—happy as the day was long, in the love of my dear husband, whose
                  unalloyed affection for me seemed to grow more and more intense.</p>
               <p>We had been married about nine months, when the California Gold Fever reached such
                  a height that thousands were emigrating to the new El Dorado, with brilliant
                  expectations of untold wealth. For a long time William had resisted its influence;
                  but at length he became so imbued with the idea of building up a speedy fortune,
                  that he obtained my consent to his departure for the land of gold, concerning
                  which, the papers were daily giving such dazzling accounts.</p>
               <p>It did not occupy him more than a week to make the necessary preparations for his
                  journey; and on the 7th of May, 1850, he bade me farewell, and started for the
                  modern Ophir. Until the beginning of June I received letters from him nearly every
                  day, each one dated father and farther West, until at last he wrote me, that when
                  I should get another letter he could not tell, as he was just about to plunge,
                  with a party of companions, into the boundless, prairie wilderness that laid
                  between him at Chouteau's Landing, or Station, and the Rocky Mountains. Chouteau's
                  Station was about twelve or fifteen miles west of the Missouri, and close to the
                  right bank of the Kansas river.</p>
               <p>Once more before he reached California, I heard from him, and after that I got no
                  word for many long months: in fact I had begun to have misgivings whether or no he
                  was alive, when I received an epistle, crumpled and stained with travel, but oh,
                  how welcome, informing me that he was not only still living, but in capital health
                  and spirits, and making money rapidly. In it he stated that his realizations had
                  already nearly equalled his utmost hopes, and, as an earnest of this, informed me
                  in what manner to dispose, to the best advantage, of nearly five hundred dollars
                  in gold dust, which would arrive some three or four weeks later. The next message
                  I got, he was doing an extensive and lucrative business in Sacramento. This time
                  he sent word also to his brother James, in Philadelphia, to come out and join him
                  the next summer. He had now been absent four years, and did not expect to return,
                  even on a visit, for some three years yet.</p>
               <p>This seemed a long, long time to be separated from my dear husband, and, as I
                  perused his letter over and over again, a new idea sprang to life within me: why
                  could I not go to him? True, there were dangers to be faced, hardships to be
                  encountered, and obstacles to be surmounted in the execution of such an intention,
                  but I feared them not, and, ere I closed the letter, my resolution was fixed.</p>
               <p>The next day I went on to Philadelphia and had an interview with my
                  brother-in-law, James, who, upon learning my intentions, endeavored to dissuade me
                  from such an hazardous undertaking, but in vain. Upon finding my determination
                  unalterable, he consented that I should accompany him the following May, (1855) at
                  which time we accordingly started to join William.</p>
               <p>In due season we arrived in St. Louis, where we were detained a few days waiting
                  for the arrival of some six or eight adventurers who were to fill up our little
                  company to its full number of forty, including, beside myself, two other females,
                  one of whom, like me, was going out for the purpose of joining her husband in
                  California. When thirty-eight of the party had arrived, it was unanimously agreed
                  to wait no longer for the other two, but to push forward immediately.</p>
               <p>This being decided, we were soon steaming up the mighty highway of the West, and
                  after a voyage of about four hundred miles, we reached, without accident,
                  Chouteau's Landing. Here we rested two days for the purpose of completing all our
                  arrangements before committing ourselves to the wilderness.</p>
               <p>At dawn of the day on which we commenced our journey we were aroused, and, after
                  taking breakfast, we struck off into the deep forests that belt the Kansas river.
                  During our progress through these forests we often came upon cultivated farms and
                  clearings, many of which belonged to Indians. We were guided by one of these
                  Indian farmers for thirty or forty miles until we emerged upon the prairies. The
                  latter came in view just at sunset of the third day, and of all the scenes or
                  scenery that I ever beheld, that which then burst upon my view was the grandest I
                  ever contemplated.</p>
               <p>From our feet the ocean of grass swept far, far away Westward, in beautiful,
                  swelling billows of verdure, that, moving gently to and fro in the evening
                  breezes, and, being gilded with the deep rays of the descending sun, looked like
                  moulten gold and emerald. Rooted to the spot in which I stood, I gazed in
                  admiration until the sun sank out of sight among the distant grassy waves, and a
                  melancholy, bluish mist rose over the boundless prairie, like an almost intangible
                  vail. And even then, as the starry host overhead came glistening into the
                  firmament, I continued my wrapt contemplation<pb n="16-19"
                     xml:id="VAC6522-00000004"/> templation until aroused by James, who, with a joke
                  and a laugh, passed my arm through his and led me away to our tent for supper.</p>
               <p>We resumed our journey the next morning about seven or eight o'clock, all the time
                  between that hour and daylight being consumed in grazing the animals we had with
                  us, and obtaining our own breakfast. Halting an hour or two at noon for rest and
                  refreshment, we again set forward and camped before sunset on the banks of a
                  romantic stream. We soon reached the dangerous locality of hostile Indians, and
                  thenceforward our little party was subjected to almost military regularity and
                  discipline. Every night the horses and mules and oxen were driven in and picketed,
                  and our wagons so arranged as to afford us a shelter or barricade, from behind
                  which we could repel any attack that might be made upon us.</p>
               <p>Three or four of the party in turn were also detailed each night to perform the
                  duty of sentinels, and thus prevent us from being surprised. At first we journied
                  along the regular Santa Fé Trail, but learning that the savages were likely to be
                  more numerous and troublesome than usual in this direction, our leader, who had
                  crossed the plains in 1842 with Captain (now General) John C. Fremont, determined
                  to turn aside, reach, and advance over the former route of that indefatigable
                  officer.</p>
               <p>Up to the third week in June we met with nothing calculated to discourage us, but
                  about this time a circumstance occurred that threw a gloom over our little party
                  and inaugurated a series of mishaps and disasters which subsequently took
                  place.</p>
               <p>Two men, relatives of each other, went a little distance up the banks of the
                  Vermillion river for a hunt or excursion. They remained away but a short time, and
                  on their return resumed a quarrel that had sprung up between them just after
                  setting out. Awhile before we took up our afternoon march they became so incensed
                  that blows were exchanged.</p>
               <p>In an instant more each drew his knife, and clenched in mortal combat with his
                  adversary. Oh, what a horrible sight was it to see those stalwart, powerful men
                  reeling, stumbling and wrestling about, each endeavoring to gain the advantage.
                  How it curdled the blood to see their deadly weapons cutting and slashing each
                  other's flesh, and now and then plunged with strange, shuddering quiver deeply
                  into one another's body. It was impossible, without much peril, to interfere with
                  the combatants, and so the contest continued until both men, cut, hacked and
                  stabbed literally to pieces, fell dying to the turf which was already crimsoned
                  with their blood. And even now it required the united strength of several men to
                  tear them from their deadly embrace.</p>
               <p>The one who was most badly injured died within a few minutes, and his livid
                  features were distorted with a scowl of agony and rage, with a curse on his lips,
                  his soul was ushered into the presence of that Being whose law he had so broken.
                  The survivor lingered until sunset, and then died with words of contrition and
                  sorrow upon his tongue, crying to be forgiven for the fearful deed he had
                  committed.</p>
               <p>The next morning we buried the two dead foes side by side in a wild ravine,
                  through which dashed a small but turbulent stream. To prevent the wolves from
                  tearing out their bodies and devouring them, a huge red sandstone boulder, of
                  which numbers were lying around, was rolled upon their graves, and on it was
                  rudely graved their names and the date of their deaths.</p>
               <p>This sad duty performed we once more moved on our way, but not in our usual good
                  spirits. A deep gloom settled upon us all, and more than one predicted "bad luck"
                  throughout the rest our journey. I never was, nor can I say that I am now, a
                  believer in "luck," either good or bad, but a singular fatality, that attended our
                  steps from that day forth, seemed to bear out the superstitious predictions made
                  on the occasion. Our oxen died suddenly, as did also several of our horses, three
                  or four of our wagons broke down, and finally, after being mended again and again,
                  had to be abandoned with nearly all their contents.</p>
               <p>By the time we were about to leave our course along the left or Northern bank of
                  the Little Blue, we found ourselves in the most deplorable condition. Still we
                  pushed onward, fervently hoping the while for some propitious change of fortune,
                  and we had nearly reached the Platte or Nebraska river, when we met a party of
                  four hunters or trappers, who brought us the startling intelligence that a large
                  war party of Pawnee Indians were in the neighborhood. After a hurried and
                  immediate consultation it was resolved that, as it would be impossible for us to
                  advance with any hope of success, we should forthwith return in company with our
                  new companions, who were bound for St. Louis. We, therefore, retraced our steps
                  until we reached our last night's camp, situated on the margin of the Little
                  Blue.</p>
               <p>Here we remained until the next morning, when we were in motion by seven o'clock,
                  but had only travelled about two miles, when we were thrown into a terrible
                  excitement by the shout of "Indians! Indians!" I can scarcely describe my
                  feelings, as, after listening to the blood-curdling stories of the trappers, who
                  had joined us the preceding afternoon, I now heard that wild cry of alarm. My
                  eager eyes ranged up and down the luxuriant valley, through which the stream ran,
                  and then over and along the verdant slopes of the hills. Not seeing any living
                  thing, with the exception of a few antelopes that were bounding along in the
                  distance, I was beginning to congratulate myself that the alarm was a false one.
                  But I had scarcely arrived at this partial and too hasty conclusion, when, over
                  the crest of a ridge, about three-quarters of a mile distant, I beheld a party of
                  savages, stripped to the waist, and mounted on fleet horses, dash into sight.</p>
               <p>As they discovered us, they uttered a deafening yell, and halted, apparently<pb
                     n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6522-00000005"/> rently to reconnoitre our position and
                  strength. A moment more, and several other companies of our dusky foes, galloping
                  over the hill-tops, joined their companions, when they all proceeded to hold a
                  council of war. But while I was gazing, horror struck, upon the enemy, the
                  gleaming of whose guns and spears chilled my blood, I felt myself lifted quickly
                  from the ground, and was carried to one of the wagons in which I was hurriedly
                  placed for shelter during the coming battle. It was my brother-in-law, James, and
                  one of the four hunters who had thus cared for my safety</p>
               <p>"Be calm, Gertrude," said the former, in a low, anxious tone, "be calm, and do not
                  attempt to get out until I come to you. I think we can beat them off yet."</p>
               <p>With these words the speaker turned away to assist in the general defense. The
                  wagons had been quickly arranged, so as to afford our party a barricade, from
                  behind which they might defend themselves to the best advantage.</p>
               <p>The expected attack was not long delayed, for the savages, having soon decided
                  upon their plan, came dashing down upon us with the most deafening yells and
                  whoops. But our men stood nobly to their work, and a volley from their deadly
                  rifles emptied several saddles and caused the foe to retreat. There is no doubt
                  also that had the Indians, notwithstanding their vast superiority in numbers been
                  armed with only their regular weapons—bows and spears—they would have been
                  speedily and effectually repulsed; but nearly half of them carrying rifles, they
                  were enabled before withdrawing, to return our fire, and with such effect, that
                  two of our force fell dead on the spot, while fully six or eight were more or less
                  wounded.</p>
               <p>I have often read glowing accounts of parties of three, four, or half a dozen
                  white men defeating fifty and even a hundred savages at once, but never took into
                  consideration the fact—generally omitted also by the authors—that the savages
                     <emph>were without fire arms</emph>, while the whites carried both guns and
                  pistols. Experience has taught me, however, that a long Missouri rifle, in the
                  hands of an Indian warrior, makes him entirely the equal, nay, oftentimes his
                  superior.</p>
               <p>The Indians now divided into three companies, and while two of these prepared for
                  a second charge upon us, the third passed out of view behind a wooded ridge,
                  doubtless intending to make a circuit and come in upon our rear. In this
                  emergency, our leader determined to cross the stream at our side, and reach if
                  possible, a position on the opposite bank where we could better offer battle than
                  in our present exposed situation. At a given signal, therefore, the wagons, of
                  which we had three left, suddenly wheeled, and started at full speed into the
                  water. Before the Indians recovered from their astonishment at this bold and
                  unexpected manœuvre, two of the wagons gained the other bank in safety, but the
                  third, in which I was, had no more than reached the middle of the stream, when the
                  savages, galloping within range, fired upon the mules by which it was drawn. Both
                  animals imals sank down into the water, struggling in their death agonies, and the
                  wagon of course became stationary. Several times subsequently my friends, headed
                  by James, attempted, with the most desperate valor, to save me, but were each time
                  repulsed by the foe, and found themselves obliged at last to retreat close into
                  the position that they had selected for their final stand.</p>
               <p>As had been suspected, the third party, that had disappeared over the wooded
                  ridge, reappeared some distance down the valley, and were doubtless much surprised
                  as they came dashing up on the other side of the stream, to find that we had
                  changed our position. Our stratagem amounted not to much, however, for while the
                  strongest party crossed the river to attack my friends, the other captured the
                  wagon in which I was, and, dragging it ashore, after cutting the traces of the
                  dead mules, commenced the work of overhauling its contents.</p>
               <p>Of course, of these latter, I being the most prominent, was the first seized, and
                  was violently jerked out upon the ground by a tall, powerful fellow, who instantly
                  drew his tomahawk, and was about to finish my earthly career, when he was
                  interrupted by a companion, who succeeded in persuading him to give me up to him.
                  Regardless, however, of my own fate, I kept my gaze fixed anxiously upon the
                  combatants on the other side. Volley succeeded volley; first from one and then the
                  other of the contending parties, but those of the whites grew fewer and fewer,
                  until at last only two men were left alive, who, seeing the utter hopelessness of
                  their situation, surrendered to their foes. The latter, however, instead of
                  showing them the mercy always due to a valiant but conquered foe, instantly
                  tomahawked and scalped them.</p>
               <p>As I beheld the fearful finale of the horrid butchery, I sank groaning to the
                  earth. Of all the company, men and women, that had set forth in such high hope
                  from St. Louis, I was the only living person left, and how long I might be spared
                  I did not know.</p>
               <p>Our wagons and their contents were a rich booty for the savages, who were so well
                  pleased with their success, that they resolved to return without delay to their
                  towns, some three or four days' journey to the southwest of the Big Blue. Before
                  setting out, however, they dragged all the bodies of their victims to a deep
                  ravine among the hills and threw them down into it, and, after holding a council
                  concerning the wagons, resolved to burn two of them and load the remaining one
                  with what plunder they could. The corpses of their own slain were all buried in a
                  beautiful spot on the north bank of the river. The pains they thus took to conceal
                  their diabolical work were induced from the fear they entertained, that some
                  future white travellers, discovering the bodies of their murdered countrymen,
                  might carry information thereof to the forts, and cause a detachment of soldiers
                  to be sent out to avenge their deaths. And of the <emph>military</emph> power of
                  the government all the Indians have a wholesome dread.</p>
               <pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6522-00000006"/>
               <p>After they had completed, as far as they were able, the concealment of their
                  butchery, the Pawnees set forward, as I have already said, for their village,
                  three or four days' journey to the Southwest. My captor, or rather he to whom my
                  captor had given me, forced me to mount a half wild horse and ride beside him.
                  This, thanks to the fact that I was a good horsewoman, I accomplished without
                  having my neck broken by the restiveness of the vicious animal I rode.</p>
               <p>At the moment that I had seen the last of our party fall before their dusky
                  murderers, I resolved to force my captors to take my life also; but, strange as it
                  may seem, a hope at that very instant sprang up in my breast that I might some day
                  or other again see my husband. I resolved, therefore, to live if possible, and
                  ever afterward, even when my trials and tribulations thickened darkest about me,
                  this hope, with its concomitant feelings, grew more and more intense.</p>
               <p>On the evening of the third day we reached the Pawnee village, situated on a large
                  stream of water, that I subsequently learned was an affluent of the Republican
                  Fork of the Kansas river. The spot where the lodges were pitched was chosen with
                  that taste for romantic scenery so inherent in the Indian breast. According to
                  some custom or ceremony my captors did not enter the village that night, but
                  remained out on a bluff on the river bank until morning; when all the village was
                  aroused by runners to prepare for their reception. All being in readiness, the
                  chief of the returned war party gave the required signal, and his braves moved
                  forward to meet their friends who were awaiting them in a body. The scene that
                  followed beggared all description, even the dogs joining in the noisy welcome. All
                  were elated with the valuable prize that had been taken and the number of
                  pale-face scalps that dangled at the belts of the victorious warriors.</p>
               <p>I, being the only prisoner, soon became the centre of all observation, especially
                  with the women, who universally bestowed on me nothing but the most malignant
                  scowls. As I was, however, the captive of the second chief in the nation their
                  demonstration reached no farther than this. To the lodge of this chieftain, whose
                  euphonious name was <hi rend="i"/>The Buffalo Horn, I was soon taken, or, more
                  properly speaking, driven by two of his wives into whose charge he had given me.
                  These termagents, after shaking their fists in my face and brandishing knives over
                  me, to intimidate me what my fate would be should I attempt to escape from my new
                  quarters, left me and went out to join in the festivities that were proceeding. Up
                  to this time my pride had forbidden the exhibition of any grief or fear on account
                  of the perilous situation in which I was placed, but now that I found myself
                  alone, and yet in the midst of relentless blood-thirsty enemies, I gave full vent
                  to my feelings in a flood of tears. I compared my present condition with what it
                  had been but a few years before, and oh! what cruel, terrible changes had been
                  wrought upon me during the intervening years of sorrow.</p>
               <p>While in the midst of these sad contemplations, I was suddenly startled by the
                  report of a gun, which was followed by the screaming and crying of women and
                  children, and a trampling of many feet. These sounds also came nearer and nearer
                  to the lodge in which I was, and, a minute or so later, the body of a man was
                  borne carefully into the lodge and deposited upon a rude pallet of skins. At a
                  glance I recognised him as my captor, <hi rend="i"/>The Buffalo Horn. The
                  unfortunate chief laid writhing in great agony for full a quarter of an hour
                  before the doctors, or "<hi rend="i"/>Medicine Men," made their appearance. The
                  latter had been thus detained in attiring themselves in their Medicine dresses, an
                  indispensable operation to their success. The chieftain's wound, which I afterward
                  learned was caused by the accidental discharge of his own piece, was directly
                  through the right lung, and, of course, apparently fatal. Yet, nothing daunted,
                  the Indian doctors set themselves to work, and, strange to say, succeeded for two
                  or three days in keeping their patient up. But about this time a change for the
                  worse took place and <hi rend="i"/>The Buffalo Horn began to sink with alarming
                  rapidity.</p>
               <p>At this juncture an idea struck me that perhaps his life might be saved in the
                  same manner as was that of an American General, who, during a battle in the
                  Mexican war, received a wound of the same nature.<ref rend="super"
                     target="#note_001" xml:id="return_001">*</ref>
                   To several of the chief's friends, who could understand English, I
                  therefore, immediately communicated my thoughts, which were by them made known
                  without delay to <hi rend="i"/>The Buffalo Horn himself. The latter ordered that I
                  should be allowed to make the attempt. Until this moment what I had read
                  concerning the manners, customs and disposition of the Indians never once crossed
                  my mind, but it all occurred to me now, and I trembled at the thought of the
                  danger into which my temerity and pity had led me. But to withdraw at this crisis
                  was to seal my doom with certainty, for the superstitious and revengeful "<hi
                     rend="i"/>Medicine Men," whose medicines had been pronounced "no good," would
                  then, without doubt, accuse me of causing the death of the chief. So, without
                  further delay, I began my hazardous task, I am free to confess I did so with much
                  trepidation.</p>
               <note place="foot" xml:id="note_001">
                  
                  <p><ref target="#return_001">*</ref>Mrs. Morgan doubtless refers to the case of General James Shields, who,
                     during an action, was struck by a copper ball, that entered his breast, and,
                     passing straight through his body, came out at his back; so that "daylight
                     shone through him." After being given up by all his own army surgeons, his
                     life was preserved by the skill of a native physician.—ED.</p>
               </note>
               <p>Among several articles which my enemies had left in my possession was a white,
                  India silk hankerchief, which had been presented to me by a sea captain years
                  before. After making all the preparations I deemed necessary, I took this
                  handkerchief, and, wrapping it in a peculiar manner about a thin willow wand, from
                  which the bark had been stripped, I insinuated it into the wound, and gently and
                  gradually worked it completely through. Upon drawing it forth there came with it a
                  mass of coagulated blood, and at this moment, to use a common expression, "<hi
                     rend="i"/>daylight shone through the wounded man's body." Immediately after
                  this I applied the preparations I<pb n="26 (Illustration) -27"
                     xml:id="VAC6522-00000007"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>A tall powerful Indian instantly drew his tomahawk, and was about to
                        finish my earthly career.—Page 21.</head>
                  </figure> fornia. Some little time elapsed ere these preparations were completed,
                  and then the band of warriors, headed by my patron, <hi rend="i"/>The Buffalo
                  Horn, departed upon their marauding journey. I endeavored to obtain leave to
                  accompany the expedition with the expectation of being enabled at some time to
                  escape, but was steadily refused, and finally obliged to retire to my lodge.</p>
               <p>This was a sad and bitter disappointment to me, and for a few days I was much
                  depressed, but my hopes soon began to revive again; why, I could not tell, for my
                  chances of getting away from my vigilant friends, if I may use that term, seemed
                  to grow less every day. Yet hope I did, and with a strength and <choice>
                     <sic>bouyancy</sic>
                     <corr>buoyancy</corr>
                  </choice> that astonished even myself.</p>
               <p>During the last week in June there were but a few warriors left in the village,
                  the rest being all absent in the expedition to which I have already referred.
                  Among those that remained was a third chief of the tribe, who, however, was not an
                  Indian, but a mulatto slave that had escaped from Missouri or Arkansas, and
                  managed to make his way to the haunts of the savages. Among these latter he had,
                  by reason of his prowess and daring, raised himself thus, and it is likely that,
                  but for the event I am about to relate, he would have finally gained the position
                  of first chief. This occurrence happened on the thirtieth day or rather night of
                  June, and for awhile produced the wildest excitement in the village.</p>
               <p>On the night in question, a messenger came to my lodge, and said that <hi rend="i"
                  />The Yellow Face—the fugitive's name among the Indians—was very sick, and wanted
                  to see me immediately. Of late I had noticed <hi rend="i"/>The Yellow Face casting
                  upon me leering glances and looks, that made me tremble, and now I felt a chill
                  come over me as I heard his ominous message. But I feared to disobey, and,
                  accordingly, with the utmost trepidation, I repaired to his lodge, where I found
                  him reclining upon a rude but comfortable couch of skins and robes. For some
                  moments he did not take any notice of my entrance, nor in fact until I spoke. This
                  roused him, or more properly seemed to, for that he was acting a part I now felt
                  fully convinced, and, as he fixed upon me his black, basilisk eyes, he said:</p>
               <p>"<hi rend="i"/>The Yellow Face is very sick, and has sent for the <hi rend="i"
                  />White Medicine, because her medicine is good."</p>
               <p>The look that accompanied these words only enhanced my fears, and I was unable to
                  utter a single word in reply, so occupied was my mind with thoughts of how I might
                  best escape from my dangerous companion. After a moment or so of silence, <hi
                     rend="i"/>The Yellow Face rose and stepped toward me, saying, in his own
                  natural voice and language:</p>
               <p>"Don't be afeard, Missus, I'ze not agwine to hurt you. Yah! yah! I jes want you to
                  come and be my wife; now won't you?"</p>
               <p>With these words the ignorant and sensual brute sprang between me and the entrance
                  of the lodge, and then, drawing a huge scalping-knife,<pb n="28-29"
                     xml:id="VAC6522-00000008"/> grinned a mocking smile, as coming towards me
                  again, he said, in low, chuckling tones:</p>
               <p>"Look yere, Missus, you'd better not make no noise now, else you's a dead woman,
                  dat's all!"</p>
               <p>The diabolical intention of the villain was instantly revealed, or rather about to
                  be consummated, for its revelation had been cotemporary with my entrance into the
                  lodge. Yet what availed my puny strength in the grasp of such a giant, or what aid
                  would my shrieks bring me? None whatever; for the Indians were too used to hearing
                  the outcries of the women when beaten by the men. All this rushed through my mind,
                  and guided my ensuing action, which was not a moment too soon, for, just as I
                  sprang to the opposite side of the lodge, my foe was in the very act of clasping
                  me in his foul embrace.</p>
               <p>"God of mercy, save me!" I breathed in almost a whisper, as I bit my tongue and
                  lips in an agony of fear and suspense, and kept my wildly staring eyes fixed upon
                  the mulatto.</p>
               <p>The latter, enraged that I had thus escaped him, scowled fiercely upon me, and,
                  with a bitter oath, made a fresh attempt to grasp me. But again I managed to elude
                  him, and bounded close to a frame of willow boughs on which were hung his shield
                  and trappings, and against which leaned his spear and bow. With demon-like rage
                  the monster, on finding himself thus foiled twice, leaped toward me, with an
                  agility that precluded escape.</p>
               <p>At this critical moment, however, and just as I gave myself up for lost, a thought
                  struck me like an electric flash, and almost involuntarily I seized the
                  keen-pointed spear that stood within my reach, and presented it at the breast of
                  my antagonist. Both of our motions were so sudden and equally timed, that the
                  following instant the spear head was plunged up to the pole directly in the heart
                  of my lecherous foe, who, with a deep groan, sank dead at my feet.</p>
               <p>Never, never shall I forget, nor shall I ever be able truly to describe, the
                  feelings that seized me as I looked down upon the silent and now harmless giant,
                  whose herculian arms could, a moment previous, have crushed my life out with a
                  single effort. For an instant a pang of sorrow wrung my heart, and then followed
                  that peculiar sensation, or self-conviction, of having shed the blood of a fellow
                  being. As though fascinated, I continued to gaze down upon my dead foe, the handle
                  of the avenging spear in my hand and the blade in his bosom. From this fearful
                  reverie I was at last suddenly aroused by a wild scream, and, starting back, I
                  beheld the dead man's favorite squaw rush into the hut and cast herself wildly
                  down upon the corpse.</p>
               <p>I waited no longer; the spell of horror was broken, and, uttering a stifled
                  shriek, I bounded from the lodge, and, with flying steps gained my own, where I
                  shut myself up, expecting every instant to be dragged forth and torn to pieces by
                  the infuriated friends of the deceased.</p>
               <p>I thought my hour had come when about ten minutes later a crowd commenced yellow
                  and hooting and screaming outside my retreat. My eyes were closed, and, bowed to
                  earth, I commended my soul to its maker. Minute followed minute, however, and hour
                  succeeded hour, and yet, though the clamor seemed to increase, no one ventured to
                  enter the lodge in which I sat trembling and despairing. Matters continued thus
                  until the next morning, when, about two hours after sunrise, the savages who were
                  collected around my wigwam, suddenly, and with a loud shouting, started away to
                  some other point, and silence reigned profoundly for sometime after. Then came a
                  scarcely audible murmur of human voices at a distance, which sound gradually
                  increased in volume until I became convinced that the savages were returning. They
                  had been, as I subsequently learned, summoned away to meet the war party of <hi
                     rend="i"/>The Buffalo Horn, who had come back at that juncture from his
                  marauding expedition in the plains.</p>
               <p>I knew the revengeful dispositions of my wild companions, and I was moreover aware
                  of the celebrity of the Chief whom, in defence of what was far dearer to me than
                  life, I had, God knew, <choice>
                     <sic>unintentially</sic>
                     <corr>unintentionally</corr>
                  </choice> slain. And, in this connection, I deem it only justice to the Indians,
                  to say, that in their primitive state, far removed from the frontier, the crime of
                  ravishing captive women, so common and hellish a vice among civilized nations,
                     <emph>is entirely <choice>
                        <sic>unkown</sic>
                        <corr>unknown</corr>
                     </choice>
                  </emph>. This statement may dissipate the romance many writers have imparted to
                  their stories of the Indians and beautiful white captive maidens, but it is
                  nevertheless a fact. An American savage will mercilessly butcher white women, but
                  a wild and <choice>
                     <sic>chivalous</sic>
                     <corr>chivalrous</corr>
                  </choice> honor deters him from ravishing or scalping them.</p>
               <p>It must have been noon when at last my anxiety was somewhat relieved by a crier or
                  runner of <hi rend="i"/>The Buffalo Horn, who announced to me that that chieftain
                  wished to see me. The name and order of my friend seemed instantly to revive my
                  spirit, and, strangely enough, I immediately began to hope. I was soon in the
                  presence of <hi rend="i"/>The Buffalo Horn, who questioned me concerning the
                  tragedy, in the manner rather of an old practitioner of law, than that of an
                  untutored savage. I stated the whole matter simply and truthfully from beginning
                  to end, confident that there was no other or better cause I could pursue.</p>
               <p>How the doom that I had so fully expected would meet me, was ever turned aside, I
                  never learned, but the following morning <hi rend="i"/>The Buffalo Horn told me
                  that the friends of the deceased were satisfied, and that I was, therefore, in no
                  further danger. Upon hearing this I fell upon my knees, and thanked my Heavenly
                  Father that even far away in the wilderness, and in the midst of barbarous
                  enemies, He had not forgotten me, but had thus far mercifully preserved me, and
                  brought me safely through all dangers and tribulations. Oh, what a holy unction to
                  the soul is the confidence of the humblest Christian, in the goodness and mercy of
                  God. It is<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6522-00000009"/> a well of pure water in the
                  desert, and the shadow of a great rock in a dry and barren land.</p>
               <p>My mind had no sooner became freed from the terrible suspense which had hung over
                  me than I immediately began to devise new plans for my escape. It was a strange,
                  wild idea that had taken possession of me, was this idea of escape, and it is
                  certain that had I been fully informed of the fearful perils attending the
                  attempt, I should never leave had the courage or temerity to put it in execution.
                  But, at the time, I thought to myself that all I had to do was to steal away from
                  the village, get safely out of sight of my foes, and then ride along until I fell
                  in with some caravan or other crossing the plains to California.</p>
               <p>My long wished and prayed for opportunity at length presented itself, and, one
                  morning, just after sunrise, with a few necessary articles secured about my
                  person, I mounted a splendid horse belonging to a noted warrior, and, giving him
                  the whip, dashed away from the village with lightning speed. What emotions took
                  possession of me as I swept over the swelling prairie, or through a woodland
                  glade, it would be impossible for me even faintly to describe. I felt free, and
                  yet it seemed as though an invisible arm was continually stretching forth to seize
                  and drag me back into captivity.</p>
               <p>The astonished groups of squaws and children through whom I rode, gazed at me in
                  mute wonderment, as I flew onward, and never seemed to be aware of my intentions
                  till I had cleared the last row of lodges, when at once comprehending all, they
                  raised a terrible clamor, which, being borne on the wind to my cars, told me what
                  I might now expect.</p>
               <p>Desperation lent calmness, and, with a firm, steady hand, I guided my horse in the
                  best directions, and kept the while a sharp look out in front, behind, and on
                  either side of me for any outlying or pursuing parties of my dusky captors. Thank
                  Heaven, none appeared, and I was beginning to congratulate myself that all was
                  going well, when I dashed into a piece of woodland which, though open at first,
                  immediately began to get thicker and more difficult. The long branches and limbs
                  of the trees, as the wind imparted motion to them, seemed to reach down and snatch
                  at me as I stooped close to my animal's neck to avoid or escape them.</p>
               <p>Twenty minutes thus riding at speed through a forest is an extremely dangerous
                  undertaking, for the horseman may in a twinkling be swept from the saddle, and
                  left bleeding, perhaps killed, in his own track. I was fortunate, however, and
                  with many hard brushes and several narrow misses of the leafy arms that
                  continually grasped at me, I at length emerged into a stretch of open plain, and
                  once more sat easily on my flying steed.</p>
               <p>For several hours I rode forward, hoping every instant to see wagons, and white
                  men who would, of course, rescue and protect me. But my eyes were strained in
                  vain. I beheld no sign of human or even animal life in any direction. All was
                  grand; all was beautiful; all was silent. Beneath me was the prairie with its
                  lakes and rivers of fragrant, beautiful flowers, and its rich, green grass. Miles
                  away behind me I could just catch glimpses of the forest that bordered the streams
                  in that direction. Miles away before me I beheld the same undulating lakes and
                  rivers of fragrant flowers and rich, green grass, while overhead was, what cannot
                  be more aptly termed, the <hi rend="i"/>prairie sky. There is a peculiarity in
                  this <hi rend="i"/>prairie sky, entirely cloudless as it often is, from the zenith
                  to the horizon, and lit up by the full blaze of the summer sun. The bright, dark
                  blue of the firmamental dome seems toned down somewhat by the whiteness, a barely
                  perceptible vail or film which makes the beholder think of spirit, fills his mind
                  involuntarily with ideas of the soul ideas of God.</p>
               <p>Thus I mused even in the midst of danger, not knowing at what moment my pursuers
                  might come in sight, and as I continued riding along at a slower pace in this
                  grand, wild solitude, my thoughts gradually turned upon my husband. How long I
                  remained in this abstracted mood I know not, but I was awakened at last from the
                  delicious reverie by the sudden stopping of my horse.</p>
               <p>In an instant I recovered myself, and scanned the horizon in all directions, but
                  saw no foe. My steed, feeling himself to be his own master, had halted to rest
                  himself, and drink of a little stream of water, that was here so narrow, that it
                  was completely hidden beneath the long, rank grass of the plain through which it
                  meandered. The action of the animal immediately reminded me of my own necessities,
                  and, dismounting, I proceeded to prepare a meal.</p>
               <p>Imagine my despair, however, on finding that the bundle in which I had wrapped up
                  my scanty supply was gone. It must have been swept from my back, to which it had
                  been secured or lashed by a strong pair of thongs, during my perilous ride through
                  the forest some hours previous. At first I gave myself up for lost; for I knew I
                  could obtain no food in the wilderness, and, as I had not yet met with the white
                  travellers I had expected to fall in with, I instantly went to the other extreme,
                  and decided that I never would.</p>
               <p>However, after taking a deep draught from the welcome stream, and bathing my face
                  and aching head in its cool waters, I felt much better, and praying to my Heavenly
                  Father to guide me safely, I once more mounted my steed, and set forward at a
                  venture. Just before sunset I espied at a distance a clump of bushes, and riding
                  up to it, I tied my horse, and threw myself down upon the grass to stretch and
                  rest my cramped and tired limbs.</p>
               <p>As I did so, my eyes were attracted by the glitter of something in the grass at
                  the edge of the clump. Upon reaching forth my hand to take it, I perceived it to
                  be a small pocket compass. I did not, however, touch it, for at that instant, I
                  discovered another fact, one which made my heart cease beating with horror.
                     <emph>The compass rested among the bones of a human</emph>
                  <pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6522-00000010"/>
                  <emph>skeleton</emph>, which, having been scarcely covered with earth when buried,
                  had become in the course of time thus partially exposed to view. It was now almost
                  hidden, at least to a careless traveller, by the rank grass and flowers of the
                  prairie.</p>
               <p>Shuddering throughout my whole being, I started up, seized the bridle of my steed,
                  and was just in the act of mounting, and speeding away from the fearful spot, when
                  a thought restrained me. The compass was an article of the highest value in this
                  vast wilderness; I had none. By its guidance I might reach friends; how, I could
                  not tell; but the disturbed idea floated through my mind, like a flitting
                  will-o'-the-wisp, that compasses led people in the right direction, guided them
                  wherever they wished to go. This to me was rescue, it was life, it was safety;
                  and, despite the chill of horror that crept over me at the thought of taking the
                  coveted prize from amongst the mouldering bones of an unfortunate human being, who
                  thus lay dreamlessly reposing in his shallow, prairie grave, I resolved to take
                  it.</p>
               <p>Quickly turning, therefore, I stepped back a pace or two, stooped down, and, with
                  great drops of perspiration falling from my brow, I seized the compass, thrust it
                  in the folds of the Indian blanket, which was wrapped about me, vaulted to the
                  back of my horse, and dashed away like one guilty of a sacrilegious act.</p>
               <p>The sun finally went down below the horizon, the twilight deepened into gloom, the
                  stars, one after another, twinkling forth in the sky, night stole gradually over
                  the prairie, and I was still a lost wanderer. Alone on the prairie! How much is
                  contained in that little sentence. So terrible were the feelings that oppressed
                  me, as I continued riding hither and thither, that I wished myself back a hundred
                  times with my wild and savage captors, the Pawnees. I had tasted no food since
                  daylight, and I began also to suffer extremely with thirst. But there was no help,
                  no food, no water! It seemed as though I was doomed to die of starvation.</p>
               <p>Exhausted and despairing, I at length dismounted from my nearly worn out animal,
                  and threw myself down upon the grass and fragrant flowers to sleep. And sleep I
                  did, soundly enough, until perhaps midnight, when I was suddenly aroused by a loud
                  clap of thunder. In an instant my eyes were opened, but fear prevented me from
                  rising, for immediately over my head, and glaring directly at me, were a pair of
                  huge eyeballs, and a hot, heavy breath came upon my face. I gave myself up for
                  lost; a wild beast had found me, and I was about to be devoured. Judge of my
                  delighted surprise, however, when, a moment later the horrid monster gave a whinny
                  of pleasure at finding himself successful in awakening me. It was the noble animal
                  which had borne me so faithfully during the day. Affrighted by the approaching
                  storm he had come thus to me for protection and companionship. I immediately arose
                  and remained awake throughout the night, gently carressing him, and cowering
                  behind him from the tempest which raged with fearful violence until daybreak.</p>
               <p>Famishing, wet and despairing as I was, I felt ready, as I gazed through the
                  falling rain over the prairie, to put an end to my miserable life. But once more
                  came that same old thought—I might yet see my husband—and immediately all ideas of
                  self-destruction were banished. But whither should I turn? I knew no path nor
                  direction in which to travel.</p>
               <p>In this dilemma I resolved to mount my dripping steed, and, leaving him to his own
                  instinct, allow him to carry me wherever he chose. No sooner was my resolution
                  made than it was put into execution, and, a few minutes later, the sagacious
                  animal, with the bridle lying loosely upon his neck, was cantering toward the
                  Northwest. By this time my hunger had become so intense, that I gnawed ravenously
                  at the raw-hide whip I carried, hoping thus to partially allay the fierceness of
                  my appetite.</p>
               <p>One fact struck me particularly, which was, that my horse swerved neither to right
                  or left, but kept steadily on in the direction he had first taken. His speed also
                  seemed to increase, as he progressed. A thrill of joy passed through me, as,
                  calling to mind all I had ever read concerning the sagacity of horses, I became
                  confident that the one I rode was bearing me to friends and rescue. Though ready
                  to fall to the earth with debility, the cheering thought <choice>
                     <sic>bouyed</sic>
                     <corr>buoyed</corr>
                  </choice> me up, and I continually swept the horizon in front with anxious eyes,
                  expecting every instant to catch sight of some friendly camp of whites.</p>
               <p>Late in the afternoon it seemed to me as though the more noticeable spots, past
                  which I had been riding for the last two hours, had a familiar look. Yet on I
                  went, entirely unsuspecting, until, just as I rose over a ridge of the prairie,
                     <emph>I came in full view of the identical Pawnee village from which I had,
                     with so much peril, escaped</emph>. With my crooked, devious travelling I had
                  only gone a distance away from it in a whole day and part of a night that my horse
                  accomplished in half the time, and going at a much slower pace. My heart sank
                  within me at the sight, and I felt ready now to curse the sagacity of my steed, or
                  rather my own stupidity, in supposing that when I left him to his own instinct he
                  would bear me to a white camp instead of back to his master's lodge.</p>
               <p>However, a crisis was before me, and my desperate condition forced me to put a
                  bold face upon the matter. So, without hesitation, I galloped straight into the
                  village, through groups of my dusky captors, who, to my utter astonishment,
                  received me with marks of joy and respect. My astonishment was immediately
                  followed by pleasure, as, by this manifestation, it became evident to me that the
                  savages looked upon my journey as <hi rend="i"/>"Medicine," or "a great mystery."
                  When on the day previous I had ridden forth into the wilderness, it was thought my
                  intention was to escape; but when the Indians saw me, as they supposed, thus
                  voluntarily returning, it was "<hi rend="i"/>Medicine."</p>
               <p>A terrible load was thus removed from off my mind, and, with a lightened heart, I
                  dashed up to my own lodge, turned my horse loose, and entered the humble, and I
                  must confess, at the moment, very welcome abode.</p>
               <p>My escape had been so narrow that I could not summon nerve enough during the
                  remainder of the summer to attempt another one, and, of course, it would have been
                  sheer madness for me to brave the rigors of the wilderness in winter. So, Fortune,
                  that fickle goddess, compelled me to remain a helpless captive until the following
                  summer, when I once more made an effort to gain my freedom, or, more properly
                  speaking, to reach some party of whites <choice>
                     <sic>jurneying</sic>
                     <corr>journeying</corr>
                  </choice> to California. This getting to California, that I might rejoin my
                  husband, was the only thought which had continual possession of my mind. As I sat
                  alone in my rude wigwam, it was before me, as I slept at night it haunted me in
                  dreams, and I could never banish it. It became a monomania. Often and often I
                  almost repeated to myself those beautiful, beautiful lines: <q>
                     <lg type="quotation">
                        <l>"No! the heart that has truly lov'd never forgets,</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">But as truly loves on to the close,</l>
                        <l>As the sunflower turns on her God when he sets</l>
                        <l rend="ti-1">The same look which she turned when he rose."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="34 (Illustration) -35" xml:id="VAC6522-00000011"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>The following instant the spear head was plunged up to the pole directly
                        in the heart of my lecherous foe, who, with a deep groan, sank dead at my
                        feet.—Page 28.</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>Before making this last attempt for liberty, I took every precaution so as to
                  insure my success, and, so far as effecting my release from my present captors was
                  concerned, my fortune was all that I could have desired. But the fate of the fish,
                  that leaped from the frying pan into the fire, was an exact parallel with my own,
                  for; after travelling eastwardly for several days, I fell in with a small party of
                  Kaskaskia Indians, who, though not exactly capturing me, as the term is usually
                  accepted, for they were just then on friendly terms with the whites, would not
                  suffer me to proceed in the direction I wished, but forced me to go along with
                  them to their village. This was built, or rather pitched, upon the north bank of
                  the Kansas river, one hundred and fifty or two hundred miles Southwest of Fort
                  Leavenworth.</p>
               <p>It was not long before I discovered that my fame, as "<hi rend="i"/>The Great
                  White Medicine," had reached my new captors, and, on apparently assenting to
                  remain always with the Kaskaskias, I was treated by them with as much respect, I
                  may say reverence, as I had been by the Pawnees. Still, however, the village being
                  in such close proximity to the border, the savages kept so strict a watch upon all
                  my movements, that I found it utterly impossible to make any successful endeavor
                  to escape. Several times indeed, I had every preparation made, but was each time
                  baffled by some unexpected circumstance or other. On the last occasion it seemed
                  as though Fate had sternly set her face against my ever regaining my freedom.</p>
               <p>At the time of which I speak I had been a prisoner among the Kaskaskias two years.
                  During the latter portion of these two years I had, as I fully believed, induced
                  my captors to place the fullest confidence in my intentions of remaining with them
                  during the rest of my life. It was not long after this that I determined to start
                  for Fort Leavenworth, where, could I only succeed in reaching it, I would be safe.
                  Since my first effort to escape from the Pawnees I had gained a vast amount of
                  information which it was necessary that I should possess to make success certain,
                  or at least to make it as nearly attainable as human events could be. How far I
                  succeeded the <choice>
                     <sic>sequal</sic>
                     <corr>sequel</corr>
                  </choice> will show.</p>
               <p>On the day I finally resolved to start for the Fort, I arranged the most minute
                  particulars of my future programme with the utmost precision. The weather favored
                  my design. Rain had been falling heavily all day, which had the effect of keeping
                  the Indians close in their lodges. To make assurance doubly sure, however, I
                  deferred setting forth on my perilous journey until nightfall. My hopes increased
                  as the day wore away without any abatement of the storm, and I felt certain of
                  success as, at midnight, I stole stealthily to where the horses were <hi rend="i"
                  />coralled, selected the best one, mounted him, and rode softly, slowly away until
                  I got at a safe distance from the town. Then, with a fervently breathed prayer to
                  that God, who watches the mighty, solemn wilderness with equal care as he does the
                  bustling metropolis, I dashed swiftly forward into the pitchy gloom. On I sped for
                  Fort Leavenworth.</p>
               <p>Soon after I had set out, it began to thunder heavily, and lighten frequently and
                  very vividly. Indeed, so terrific did the scene at length become, that I was
                  forcibly reminded by it of the plague sent upon the ancient Egyptians. From the
                  zenith, the livid glare would burst forth, and leap instantly and in all
                  directions to the horizon, while almost at the same moment, the bellowing thunder
                  would come booming and rattling down from heaven, and go rumbling away over the
                  prairie, only to be immediately followed by still more vivid flashes, and still
                  louder thunder claps.</p>
               <pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6522-00000012"/>
               <p>Oh! how strange did my situation at this moment seem, when I compared it to that
                  which I had occupied in the earlier part of my life. I, who was then a delicate,
                  puny girl, shrinking from airs too chilly, or sun-shine too warm; I, who then
                  trembled at the slightest peril, was now dashing fearlessly through a fearful
                  tempest, over a mighty prairie, with the blazing bolts of Heaven falling at my
                  very feet, the wind howling in my ears, and torrents of rain drenching me through
                  and through. Yet, I was not cast down, for my trust was in God, and I knew that if
                  it was His holy will to bring me safely through, nothing could prevail against
                  me.</p>
               <p>With this comforting assurance, I pushed on during the dreary night, until just
                  before I supposed the dawn to be at hand, when, coming to a stretch of timber, I
                  resolved to halt and give my good steed, as well as myself, some rest.</p>
               <p>As the sun came up, the storm began to break away, and, by the time the former had
                  been shining two hours, the sky was, with the exception of here and there a fleecy
                  bank, entirely clear of clouds. After making a frugal meal from some dried meat
                  and parched corn, I again hastened forward, confident that my trail from the
                  Indian village had been entirely obliterated by the heavy rain which had fallen.
                  Consulting the precious compass, mentioned in a former page, and which I had
                  preserved with religious care, I found that I was travelling in the proper
                  direction. Full of joy, I became light of heart, and I fear light of head also,
                  for I patted my steed lovingly on the neck, and addressed him in the most
                  endearing terms, promising him another rest at a stream which I knew to be only a
                  short distance ahead, from the line of trees within sight, growing on its
                  margin.</p>
               <p>Nearly a mile to the northward of where I was, I perceived a large band of
                  buffaloes, that, with furious bellowings, was rushing headlong in the same
                  direction as myself. This convinced me of two things, one of which at least was
                  far from agreeable. The first was that these buffaloes, or correctly speaking,
                  bisons, were crossing the scream beyond, and the second was that being so far out
                  of their usual range, they must have been pursued by Indians. This latter fact
                  rendered me uneasy, for I knew of no tribe in this section of country save the
                  Kaskaskias, and should I unfortunately fall in with any party of the latter I
                  feared that Fortune might not furnish me as good a plea as she had on the occasion
                  of my flight from the Pawnee village. But there was no time to waste in
                  calculations now. It was forward, forward with all speed to Fort Leavenworth, and
                  forward did I go.</p>
               <p>I reached the bank of the creek which I had seen, with the intention of resting
                  awhile on this side, and then fording it, continue my journey till sunset. My
                  feelings, however, may be imagined when, instead of a crystal, pearly stream, I
                  found a muddy, rushing torrent, roaring angrily, and bearing fiercely along on its
                  bosom, huge quantities of drift wood and trees, besides many an unfortunate bison.
                  These last had been swept down by the tremendous force of the current, and were
                  struggling frightfully, endeavoring to climb up on each other's backs, and hooking
                  each other's eyes out. Many also had been dashed against the opposite shore, where
                  they now stood panting, unable to climb the steep, slippery bank, and half
                  submerged in mud and water. The scene was appalling, and I shrank back as did also
                  my horse.</p>
               <p>But at this instant, and even while I was debating what I should do, I chanced to
                  cast my eyes back over the route in which I had come, and there, not far off, I
                  beheld a sight still more appalling than the rushing river; a score of naked
                  savages, mounted on half wild horses. As they noticed that I saw them, they set up
                  a fearful yelling, and galloped faster than ever to overtake me.</p>
               <p>Instantly my determination was fixed, and, with a wild and involuntary shriek, I
                  dashed my noble, high-mettled steed straight into the foaming torrent. A moment,
                  and then the angry waves were lashing about me, and causing my horse to snort with
                  terror. Yet on he kept, guided by my hand, until we had neared the opposite shore,
                  when all at once a fearful whoop resounded from the bank behind, followed
                  instantly by a ringing of rifles, and a whistling of bullets around us. But
                  neither of us, strange to say, was struck, although an unfortunate bison beside us
                  sank dead at the fire.</p>
               <p>We were close to the other bank, which, as I have said, was lined for some
                  distance down with half exhausted bisons, which, however, as they saw us
                  approaching, prepared to give us battle, fearful that we were going to push them
                  from their foothold.</p>
               <p>"Great God!" I gasped, as I saw this new danger, "even the wild beasts are against
                  me!"</p>
               <p>The words had scarcely left my lips before the noble steed, that had carried me so
                  faithfully, was forced directly against the horns of a huge bull, who, with a
                  bellow of rage, and a last effort at self-preservation, gored him, and actually
                  tossed him, with me still on his back, several feet into the air. All I remember
                  after that was pitching upward and forward, striking heavily on the bank, and
                  scrambling to a level spot out of danger of rolling back into the river. When
                  consciousness returned I found myself lying at the foot of a tree, and my hands
                  tied securely behind me with a long thong, which in turn was fastened around the
                  trunk of a tree.</p>
               <p>I saw in a moment that they were a roving band of Indians, who having recognized
                  and captured me, intended to carry me back to their village, from which I had
                  escaped.</p>
               <p>I will not dwell upon the rough treatment I received at the hands of these
                  savages, who, had I been a common prisoner, instead of "<hi rend="i"/>The Great
                  Medicine," would have soon tomahawked me; neither is it necessary that I should
                  minutely record the events of my subsequent life among them.</p>
               <p>Suffice it to say, that in the latter part of "1861" an agent from Albert Pike, a
                  man well known among the Indians, arrived at the village, and held several
                  conferences with the principal men of the tribe, the result of which was, that
                  nearly all the warriors prepared themselves to follow their chief to battle.
                  Obtaining an interview with this man, I related my story to him, and begged of him
                  to intercede with my captors. This he promised to do, expressing at the same time
                  great commiseration with me in my misfortunes. From him I learned for the first
                  time that a bloody war was being waged between the North and South. I could not
                  bring myself to believe it, and yet the preparations going forward indicated
                  something unusual. All I could do was to wait and see how matters would turn
                  out.</p>
               <p>Before the agent left, it was agreed between him and the Indians, that I should be
                  allowed to accompany them until reaching Arkansas, when I should be set free. I
                  named Fort Leavenworth to him, but he peremptorily refused to allow me to go
                  thither, why I did not realize at the time, but it has since become clear to me. I
                  was also too thankful for the privilege already granted, to complain of any
                  seeming inconvenience.</p>
               <p>From that time forward I looked anxiously every day for the departure of the
                  warriors, who were to march at a given signal into Arkansas, to join<pb n="38-39"
                     xml:id="VAC6522-00000013"/> an Indian army there under the command of General
                  Pike. This signal was not given until the beginning of February. There was,
                  however, no delay after that, and accordingly we soon found ourselves in Pike's
                  camp, where were already congregated a large number of Indians—some four or five
                  thou-and—gathered from many different tribes along the frontiers.</p>
               <p>It was during my stay in the rebel camp, that I fully learned the nature of the
                     <unclear>contest</unclear> that was going on, from a sick Union prisoner, whom
                  I tended.</p>
               <p>I could see that it was not intended that I should escape, as a guard was placed
                  at the opening of my tent, both night and day.</p>
               <p>I resolved to escape, if possible, at the first opportunity. I was informed that a
                  battle was about to take place between the Union and a portion of the Southern
                  army. At last the time for action came. It was the night before the battle. Who
                  could say, what the next day would bring forth?</p>
               <p>As I lay in the tent assigned me by the General, I thought I heard a sound, as if
                  some one was talking, yes, I was not mistaken; it was two guards, one of whom was
                  placed there to guard me, the other had come to relieve the first, I could hear
                  every word they said.</p>
               <p>"You know the captain said we must watch her well, cause you know she might give
                  us the slip," said one of the men.</p>
               <p>"Yes, yes," said the other, "but we can just slip over to Jim Carsons, and get a
                  little of his whiskey, the "gal's" sound asleep 'fore this."</p>
               <p>"Don't talk so loud," said the first, "she might wake up and hear you."</p>
               <p>"Well, here goes," said the second.</p>
               <p>I then heard their footsteps, as they silently left my tent.</p>
               <p>As I lay thus the thought entered my mind, that escape was possible. I might try;
                  if they did catch me, they would only bring me back, and guard me more securely.
                  Why not try it? My mind was made up instantly.</p>
               <p>I quietly arose and softly wended my way to the opening in the tent. I felt the
                  fresh air as it was gently wafted upon my fevered cheeks and brow. "Oh for liberty
                  once again!" I looked upon both sides of me, all was as silent as the grave. I
                  advanced a few steps, and then stopped. I trembled in every limb. I could not
                  move. I stood there like a marble statue. I stood thus for a few moments before I
                  could regain my composure enough to go forward. I had taken but a few steps, when
                  I heard the guards returning. I crouched behind some bushes which grew near the
                  place where I then stood. Having reached the tent, one of them looked in, saying
                  at the same time, "he supposed the 'gal' was all right."</p>
               <p>"Never fear for that," said the other.</p>
               <p>They then separated, one going towards his own tent, and the other having
                  stationed himself in front of mine.</p>
               <p>I dared hardly breathe, the guard lay within eight feet of where I was. None can
                  describe my feelings on that occasion.</p>
               <p>The guard would frequently drink of whiskey, which he had in his canteen. This
                  frequent pulling at the canteen (as the soldiers say) soon made him drunk.</p>
               <p>As soon as I was sure that he was too drunk to create any alarm, I quickly arose
                  from my painful position, and turned in the direction of the Union encampment,
                  which I reached two hours before sunrise.</p>
               <p>I was taken before the General in command, to whom I told a portion of my story.
                  After he had heard it, he informed me that I was very welcome, as I brought him
                  news of the Confederates, and that I might be of some use on the morrow.</p>
               <p>I was shown a tent in which to sleep. I laid down, and was soon fast asleep. I
                  awoke in the morning to hear the firing of cannon, and the cries of the
                  wounded.</p>
               <p>The battle had now began in earnest; it lasted three days. On the second, as I was
                  standing among the wounded in the rear, I beheld a Confederate, who had apparently
                  been leading his company, running and fighting his way through the companies in
                  advance of him, reached the Union army, his clothing perfectly riddled by bullets,
                  having also (as I learned afterwards) received several serious wounds.</p>
               <p>I saw them lift this man off of the ground on which he had fallen, and bring him
                  towards the sick and wounded. Yes, even towards the tent near which I then
                  stood.</p>
               <p>"Who is he?" I exclaimed.</p>
               <p>"We don't know, marm," said one of the men who had brought him. "We heard the Rebs
                  say that he was a traitor."</p>
               <p>"Traitor! who calls me a traitor?" exclaimed the wounded man. No one answering, he
                  said "No, thank God! The man who fights for that glorious ensign of American
                  Independence, is no traitor. I repeat it, is no traitor."</p>
               <p>The exertion had been too much for him; he fainted in the arms of a soldier, who
                  was holding him.</p>
               <p>As he was speaking, it seemed to me that I had seen that man before. Where had I
                  seen that face? It seemed strangely familiar to me, but I could not place it.</p>
               <p>They laid him on the couch that I had occupied before he came. As they did so, one
                  of the soldiers turning to me said, "Madame, we leave this wounded, perhaps dying,
                  man in your charge."</p>
               <p>They then left me, perhaps never to return again. I watched by the side of this
                  wounded soldier's bed for five long weary hours. At last he opened his eyes and
                  gazed upon me in a wild manner. He had a burning fever; he talked of fighting
                  Indians and digging for gold. At last his eyes were closed; he slept, and in his
                  dream I heard him talk of a wife whom he had not seen for years.</p>
               <p>One day as I watched, as usual by his bedside, I heard him utter the name of
                  Gertrude; I turned toward him, and his lips again uttered the name of Gertrude.
                  What could this mean? I uttered my thoughts aloud, which awoke him, he looked at
                  me in that same strange manner.</p>
               <p>"Those eyes! Where had I seen them before? They were my husband's. Thank God! I
                  knew him now."</p>
               <p>I told my story to the Doctor, who informed me, that if I valued the life of my
                  husband, I must keep out of the tent, as any sudden excitement would kill him.</p>
               <p>Thus for two weeks I waited. Oh, how long they seemed; it was almost as if two
                  years instead of weeks had passed.</p>
               <p>At last I was permitted to see him, and converse with him.</p>
               <p>I will pass over the joy of both, after having been separated so long. After I had
                  told my story, (which the reader already knows,) he related his, which I will give
                  in his own words. He began as follows:</p>
               <p>"After I left Chouteau's Station, I fell in with some hunters, and learning that
                  they were going in the same direction as I, we joined company.</p>
               <p>"I will pass over the many dangers encountered, and hardships endured by us, (as
                  it would fill a whole volume;) suffice it to say that we reached the gold regions;
                  and after having lived there nearly six years, (not having<pb n="40-41"
                     xml:id="VAC6522-00000014"/> heard from you all this time, except that you had
                  been-taken captive, I had long since mourned you as dead,) I started for home,
                  (having amassed a fair fortune.) I had come about half the distance, between
                  Chouteau's Station and the Missouri river, when I was captured by a band of
                  Indians. I supposed immediately, that my captors were a roving band of Kaskaskias,
                  whom I had thus accidentally fallen in with, and who, having captured me, intended
                  to carry me to their village. The event proved the correctness of the
                  supposition.</p>
               <p>"I need not dwell upon the rough usage I met with at the hands of the savages.
                  Suffice it to say, that in a few days we reached the village.</p>
               <p>"The day arrived for me to be burned at the stake, but an All-seeing Providence
                  prevented it. A terrible storm arose, carrying off every thing in its course. The
                  stake to which I was to have been burned was uprooted and carried away by the
                  wind; the lightning flashed, the thunder roared, and the rain came down in
                  torrents. The storm lasted three hours.</p>
               <p>"The Indians, being of a very superstitious nature, thought that it was an
                  interposition of their Great Spirit, or God, and from that time I was treated in
                  the best possible manner, for white man to be treated by the uncivilized Indians.
                  They looked upon me as a wonderful personage, though, at the same time, I was
                  guarded in the strictest manner.</p>
               <p>"I lived among these savages for almost five years. I joined in their sports until
                  I became quite an adept. One day, as I with several others was hunting near the
                  village, a runner came in, out of breath, from whom we learned (I had learned to
                  speak the Indian tongue) that a war had broken out between the North and South,
                  and that the tribe to which they belonged was offered very enticing inducements to
                  join the Southerners.</p>
               <p>"I will pass over the excitement which prevailed among those belonging to the
                  tribe; it having been decided that they should join the Confederates, I asked the
                  privilege of going with them, which was granted.</p>
               <p>"In due time we arrived at the confederate encampment, where I was selected as a
                  lieutenant of an infantry company. With seeming gladness I accepted the
                  commission, resolving at the same time never to fight against the Old Flag.</p>
               <p>"During the first day's engagement, I was too sick to join my company, but on the
                  second, the captain being killed in the first engagement the command, of course,
                  devolved upon me—therefore I was obliged to comply.</p>
               <p>"As I was apparently leading my company, I turned and fought my way to the Union
                  Army, where I am, 'thank God,' this day."</p>
               <p>I will pass over the events which occurred during our stay in the Union Army.
                  Suffice it to say, that after procuring a pass for New York, we reached that city
                  in due time.</p>
               <p>And now that my narrative is finished, dear reader, I would say to you, may you
                  never encounter the dangers or endure the hardships of Gertrude Morgan.</p>
               <closer>THE END.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <pb n="42 (Illustration) -43" xml:id="VAC6522-00000015"/>
         <div type="illustrations">

            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Yet on I went, entirely unsuspecting, until just as I rose over a ridge of
                     the prairie, I came in full view of the identical Indian village, from which I
                     had, with so much peril, escaped!—Page 34.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
