<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6650">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >The Russel Family </title>
            <author >Hastings, Anna.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC6650</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >The Russel family</title>
                  <author >Hastings, Anna.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >201 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >M.W. Dodd</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1861">1861</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-06-21">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text >
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The Russel family</head>
            <p> 
               <pb n="0 (Cover) " xml:id="VAC6650-00000001"/>   
               <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6650-00000002"/>   THE RUSSEL FAMLY. BY ANNA HASTINGS. NEW YORK: PUBLISHED BY M. W. DODD, No. 506 Broadway. 1861.    <pb n="0" xml:id="VAC6650-00000003"/> Entered, according to Act of Congress, in the year 1856, by M. W. DODI, In the Clerk's Office for the Southern District of New York. STEREOTYED BY S,     ,I PRINTED IYW THOMAS B. SMTh,           E  . J E .t K I N , 82 &amp; 84 Beekman Street.   PREFACE. A SKETCH of life is ever a page of truth. Its incidents may be even more startling than those that fancy weaves, as they pass before us, and we would turn dissatisfied away but that we are assured of the presence of truth-however disguised and concealed. This little volume is a sketch frdti real life. Enough of truth is woven in to form   a broad foundation for the lighter superstructure. In the gentle virtues of "Lottie"I have loved to trace those of an honored and beloved friend, and if, in the wild career and eventful life of "Malcolm," I have followed too closely that of her brother, who was left so many, many years to wander amid scenes as wild and strange as ever imagination    <pb n="iv-v (Table of Contents) " xml:id="VAC6650-00000004"/> iv        PREFACE. drew, she will, I am sure, attribute it to no other motive than a desire to present, in a real picture, the workings of the Christian "mother's influence" guiding and shaping the future course of her chil-  dren, and spreading, like the course of concentric  circles, until the ages of eternity receive their im- press.                     ! That the book may encourage the heart, and strengthen the hands of the praying Christian mother, is the earnest wish of the AUTHOR. FAiInIBLD, IOWA, Nov. 22, 1856.   PAGE I.-THE FAMLY      ............ .......... 7 II.--TmE CHASE....                19 "I.-THE MOTHER'S DEATH-BED. ..    ........ 34 IV.-THE REMOVAL ........................... 42 V.--THE VACATIONS .   . ...............48 VI.-THE SEPARATION ................  .... ...  61 VIL-.THE STRANGER .......................     74 rIII.-MALCOLM ................................ 85 IX.-THE FATHER'S DEATH-BED ................    95 X.--EDWARD ............    ................ 106 XI.-THE FRIENDS..... ...................... 120 XII.-THE ENEMY      ............     .. 133 "I.--THE NUNNER ........................... 141 [IV.-THE TUTOR   ................. 157 XV.-THE ESCAPE .    ........... .............. 168 VI.--THE TRADER   ........................ 183 VIL-THE RETURN.         ......      193    <pb n="vi-7" xml:id="VAC6650-00000005"/> K   THE autumn had come. Earth had donned her apron of sere, dead leaves, the tribute of the stately trees, so lately beautiful with the garnish of spring. The whispers of the summer zephyr had ceased, and there was a voice more sol- emn, which spoke to the soul in the fitful sighs of November's blast. The sun was slowly descending, and its last rays gilded the walls of the old fort at Prairie Iu Chien, deepened the shadows in the dense forest, and glanced smilingly upon a little group beneath the trees in the garden at- tached to the fort. A noble boy of fourteen stood with his hat n his hand, and the waves. of his dark ,hair blown carelessly over his head. His black eyes ,     <pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6650-00000006"/> THE RUSSEL FAMLY.   was lighted up with the earnest impulses of a generous nature. His sister, who might have been two years younger, sat by his side, reading. There was an expression of quiet peace anid sober thought beyond her years, marking her in strong contrast to the merry little elf, play- ing with Rover, the Newfoundlander, at a short distance from them. A pale, delicate boy of some nine years, completed the group. They were the children of Colonel Russel, who had long held the command of the fort, during a period when a military force was necessary to keep in check the neighboring Indians, and to protect the lives and property of the newly-arrived emigrants. He was a fine specimen of nature's noblemen--lofty and generous in his views and motives, his very soul scorned a mean action, and no one more jealously guarded his honor, or demanded a larger portion of esteem and respect from those under his command, or from those more closely connected to him by ties of affection. To maintain this character, and to live un- stained by vice or degrading avarice-to see   his family adopting the same model, and de&amp; serving the same meed of respect, and esteem from the world, this was his sole ambition. He forgot to render to God the homage of his gifted mind and noble soul. He practically denied the existence of Deity, and refused to acknowledge His claims upon him. His wife, however, was one of the most lovely of Christ's disciples. Her early life had been one of sorrow. When scarcely eighteen, she found herself alone in the world. She, with a brother and sister, had wept over the graves of their parents; then, with a heart still quivering with its first grief, she parted from them too, and went on her way, while they rested from all future sorrow. There is something soothing in the influence of a beautiful landscape, a living, breathing picture from our Father's hand. When the heart is burdened with grief, and weary with its life-struggles, we love to fill our soul with sublime indications of God's power, or grow calm, while reviewing His gentler footsteps. The storm had raged fearfully, and when it     <pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6650-00000007"/> 10     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. ceased in hollow murmurs, it left her a seared and blighted being, trembling before its part- ing breath.  Remqved to a distant home among strangers, she shunned society, and shut herself up, to be alone with her great grief. Then the gentle spirit-voices which breathe forth in the air, lulled the storm with- in to harmonize with the peaceful beauty around her. The soft air of summer had clothed the fields with grain, beautiful in its varied growth and coloring. The dark foliage of the forest trees, standing like eternal pillars supporting the blue arch of heaven, shaded many a flower of varied hue. The silver line of a murmur- ing rivulet gleamed from beneath the graceful willows on its bank, then mingled its waters with Erie's waves which sparkled in full view. She felt the influence of the gentle beauty of the scene, and it calmed the throbbings of her aching heart. The wild howlings of No- vember's blast had seemed a fit dirge to her mourning soul when. sorrow's darkling cloud had burst over her; the drear face of nature,    THE FAMLY.'       " arrayed in winter's winding-sheet, harmonized well, when she first arose to find herself alone. But in the softened twilight of summer, when all was still about her,- save the " whispering wind," or the music of the distant waterfall, she hushed the sad wailings of her lone heart and learned the lesson of meek submission. She trusted and loved. The soul was purified when it was prepared to say "Thy will be done." She eagerly longed to be at rest-to soar beyond the beauteous arch above her, to "Calmer seas, where storms shall cease, To purer skies, where, all is peace." But hers was a perfect sacrifice. Hence- forth she was " bought with a price," and she lived, not for herself, but for Him who had redeemed her with His own life. When she married, and removed to the far West, she found herself placed amid un- wonted scenes and new trials. But her in- telligent and refined' mind, sanctified by the purifying influences of religion, made her life    <pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6650-00000008"/> 12     THE RUSSEL FAMLY.       ! and conversation holy and beautiful. It ex- erted its usual influence upon those around her. The proud Colonel was content to listen quietly when the Holy Word was read by her sweet voice, and she was too tenderly beloved to suffer the slightest persecution for right- eousness' sake. The influence of her prayers was like that of incense, invisible, but pure, sweet, and gentle. None but her God knew the agony of her pleadings for her husband, her children, the officers and soldiers, and even the poor Indians, who each felt the influ- ence of the single Christian alone performing her duty. As yet her faithl was tried, and she wept as she sowed the seed, to believe that it lay un- fruitful still, and that it was denied her to bring home the sheaves rejoicing. Only for Charlotte, her eldest daughter, could she en- tertain the hope that she was a lamb of the Saviour. It was as a balm   to her aching heart, to trace, in her dawning love and child- like faith and trust, the footsteps of the Spirit, and to have the example before her of what   THE FAMLY.       13 the Saviour desired when He commanded us to become as little children. But to return to the little group beneath the trees in the garden. The children had been unusually quiet, and were seemingly soothed by the calmness and beauty of the scene. To Malcolm the season promised abundant game for the future hunt and chase, of which he was passionately fond. Charlotte found the sober quiet of evening harmonized well with the gentle turn her thoughts had taken from the perusal of her book. Nellie liked the night because it was so cool and pleasant for Rover and her to bound over the crackling leaves, while Edward found beauty in the glowing sunset, the quiet of the dim forest, and the murmurs of the wind, to satisfy his soul, al- ready indulging in the glowing fancies and earnest longings of the child of genius.. Oh, Nellie!" suddenly exclaimed Mal- colm, Cmy trap has gone!" Gone where, Mack?" Why, gone out of the garden, Puss, to be sure. You know you desired it set to catchk 2 <pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6650-00000009"/> "    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. the rabbits, or other offenders, that have I trampled down and destroyed your flowers. Something larger than a rabbit has carried off that trap, you may be sure, and I imagine 1 Master Reynard has carried off our bait and trap, too."       - "Now, Nell, what do you say to a chase after the rogue to-morrow morning?  Of  course he won't go far with that trap biting his foot with its iron teeth, and we can soon track him to his place of abode." "Oh, I should like that above all things, Mack, and I will ask mamma to give me some linen bandages to bind up the poor fellow's foot." "Yes, do, Nell, and take enough for his head, too.; for I imagine it will need it more than his foot., if I can only find the rogue. Yes, take along sonime bandages and some liniment too, and I will secure the services of i Doctor Rifle. Capital, Nell! We will form partnership, I will be doctor, and you, nurse to all the unfortunate foxes of Prairie du Chien. But let us go in and get some sleep, Nellie, for we must be awake early."   THE FAMLY.       15 They bounded lightly away, full of the bold project which the children of our front- iers alone have the boldness to plan or the courage to execute. When their last merry laugh had died away, and the darkness of night was fast gathering, Charlotte took her little brother by the hand, and led him into the fort. Mrs. Russel inet them at the door, and looking anxiously at the pale cheek and deep dreamy eyes of her youngest boy; she felt that he was indeed a pale and delicate flower, and her eyes dimmed as she pushed back his hair and imprinted a mother's kiss upon his brow. "Why so late, Eddie?  You should not let the night damp your head, my boy. But come, papa awaits us in the parlor ;" and she led the way to the room, where a warm tea and a cheerful fire awaited them. The family table was always a pleasant, social part of the colonel's household arrange- ments, where he met his wife and children alone, and entered without restraint into the sweet communion of affectionate hearts.    <pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6650-00000010"/> 16     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. His eyes rested with fond pride on the manly face and form of his first-born, and he felt that he was destined to fill some lofty and honored station in life. He was delighted to find the gentle graces and beautiful virtues - of his beloved wife, dawning with so much promise in their eldest daughter. Nelhe was like a sun-beam, bright, gay, and loving. Upon Edward his eye rested anxiously. He could little understand or appreciate -the in- tensity of the child's thoughts, which had so preyed upon his health. He only felt that he was a delicate child of a strange temperament, and his father's heart trembled when he thought it might be his lot to bury his beauti- ful boy.- The present was the end of his hopes. The thought that death might snatch from him some one of his darlings, or even lay his own proud form beneath the cold earth, this made the strong man quail. But forbidding the present weakness, he hushed the warning tone, and leaned proudly back upon his own strength.   THE FAMLY.       17 But the mother could not thus feel. Earn- estly had she studied the natures of each of her children. She knew that Malcolm  was generous and noble, high-minded and lofty in his impulses. But she trembled when she saw his dark eye flash, and his brow darken, when unholy passion resented the fancied wounds his honor might have received. She knew that proud heart would long refuse the humbling claims of the Gospel, and she fer- vently longed to see her noble boy sanctified by the renewing grace of God, and devoting himself to His service. She rejoiced that God liad given her hope of Charlotte, and in loving faith she trusted that He would guide this lamb to the fold of Christ. She even looked with anxiety upon her gay little Ellen, but hoped her early in- fluences would serve as a restraint upon her, and lead her to choose the path of right. But it was for Edward the mother's heart most yearned in tender solicitude. She knew what his sensitive nature must suffer, and how coldly would fall the sneers of unappreciative 2*    <pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6650-00000011"/> 18     THE RUSSEL FAMLY.  minds, when his own would thrill with images 1 of the beautiful; and how harshly would the mockery of life grate upon his gifted soul, filled with the imnusic of its own delicately- strung and sensitive harp. She longed to see her boy shielded by the Rock, and his soul fortified by faith and the hope of heaven, for its bitter trials. The mother's prayer was importunate that night, as "She kissed each fair sleeper's brow," while she rested her burdened heart upon the sure promises of the Holy Word of God. Night fell darkly over the wood, the fort, and its slumbering inmates.   Ministering spirits were watching beneath the Eye that "never slumbers nor sleeps." Silence settled over the busy scenes of day, and sleep visited every eye with its refreshing influence. \   II. HE morning sun arose brightly, and with its first rays, Malcolm and his brave little sister, as he called her, - were up and busy with their projected adventure. Mamma had smilingly given her consent that Nellie should accompany her brother, ex-9 acting the promise that they would be home before dark. The warm breakfast was pre- pared and eaten, then the lunch was laid in the basket, covered with napkins which Nellie proposed should take the place of the linen bandages. The rifle was thoroughly cleaned, powder-horn and shot-bag replenished, a warm cloak for Malcolm and shawl for Nellie, pro- vided by the careful mother, and the children sallied forth upon the chase.    <pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6650-00000012"/> The air was pure and bracing, the sun shone brightly upon the leaves, white with the breathings of the last night's frost. They struck off upon a tra leading to the woods, laughing merrily as th y ran on, now in full chase of some ticiid squirrel, and now gather-  ing their hands full ofthe nuts scattered  thickly over the ground, and pelting each other with the bright green hulls. At last, quite wearied, they sat down upon an old log  nearly covered with moss. Nellie with her' hands full of the brown autumn leaves, ar- ranged them into a wreath, which looked  I somber, even when laid among her sunny curls. X As if it had suggested a serious thought to her mind, Nellie looked up to her brother's face and said, "Mack, what are you going to be, when you grow up to be a great man, like papa?"   f  "Oh, I mean to study, and go to West Point and graduate, and be a colonel, and :ome back here and live in this dear old fort, mnd take care of you, Nellie, and dear mamma rnd papa when they are old." -   Nellie looked upon her brother with an af- 3tion not unmixed with reverence, and she i not in the' least doubt his ability to all that he had promised, and the hope the future brought a bright smile to her ce. cWell, Malcolm, I am so glad you will do at. But mamma said last Sabbath that all Lese dead autumn leaves ought to make us link of the time when we must die. Does ever seem to youlthat mamma can die? ie is so sweet and good." "Yes, mamma is almost an angel, I know, it I suppose she will die sometime, but not Atil she is a great deal older than she is now, ellie." "cOh, I hope not, Malcolm; but how often Le has told us we must die to. I wonder hat it is to die. I never saw any one dead it that old soldier, Somers, and poor Oskeish, ho froze to death last winter. Don't you member last spring when the gardener anted my flower-seeds, mamma said they ould swell and burst and perish; after that,    <pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6650-00000013"/> --- J- A-J L ijJJ ' ULl .J1 , jj *  the little green leaves would come up above  the ground and grow, and bear the beautiful I flowers. And that ugly worm, which she  brought on a leaf to the house, last summer; after a while the worm was gone, but she showed us a beautiful butterfly, and told us : it was the worm that had been thus changed.  . So after our bodies are laid in the ground they would all turn to dust; but, if we give - our hearts to the Saviour, He will make us pure, bright, holy angels. Would you not  X like to be an angel, Malcolm?" , Oh, yes, Nellie, if I could be one and not X die. I never get angry, or do any thing  wrong, but I think I would very much like to become an angel. But is is a dreadful thing  to die, I think. I suppose we can be good like mamma and Lottie before we die. Mam-n' ma says the reason why Lottie always does so nearly right is, because she asks God to help her, and because she has given her heart to f the Saviour." "I think that must be the reason, Malcolm, for do you not remember how often she used  K.   ) get angry? And once she spoke crossly to oor Eddie, and was even impertinent to dear iamma. And then, she used to be so idle, o00 and give so much trouble. Now she is so atient and good, and always tries to do right, nd if she does wrong, she is sorry and ready o ask forgiveness. I think Lottie is almost s good as mamma, don't you, Malcolm?" "Yes, and so are you a dear, good, little ,irl; and Eddie-I wonder if Eddie is a Christian! Mamma never said he was, but ou know, Nell, he never, does such naughty hings as you and I do, nor is ever reproved iecause his lessons are not learned. I often dish that you and I were as good as Lottie nd Eddie; then we should never see papa rown, or mamma's, eyes fill with tears. Oh, ellie, when I was angry the other day and ised that dreadful oath, it almost killed me o see mamma. She just looked at me so orrowfully, then went to that little room, vhere she has taken us so often to pray with is. When she came from there, and I knew he had been weeping and praying for me, I    <pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6650-00000014"/> 24     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. thought I could never get angry again or give mamma so much sorrow," Nellie looked wonderingly to see her brother brush away a tear, and her own bright eyes filled. So is it. The influence of the look, the tear and prayer of the Christian mother, how does it move over the heart-strings, and awaken many a better purpose, a high and holy resolve, that else might have slumbered forever! In the wakeful hours of night, or when we feel alone with our own heart-com- munings, comes home the sacred truth, im- pressed with the tender words and loving smile of a mother, and its impression is as lasting as eternity. Refreshed by their rest, the children re-  sumed their search, a little saddened by their late conversation. But soon discovering the irregular line left by the trap through the dead leaves, they eagerly pursued it, banish- ing their sadness in the excitement of the' chase. in the pure air. Malcolm thought the footmarks much too large for a fox, and examined well the condition   THE CHASE.       25 of his rifle, thinking he might have largei game to contend with. The track led them to a bluff near which they found their trap. "Ah, Nellie, the rogue has left the trap and made off, but I imagine he is not very far from here," said Malcolm, loading his rifle. "Now, Nellie, I am  going into that cave there, behind that rock, and I want you to stand at the opening to assist me if I need you." The children walked around, Malcolm shoul- dered his rifle ready charged, and fearlessly entered the cave. He cotuld not discover any object at first, but as his eye became more accustomed to the darkness, he thought he saw, at some distance however, the glaring eyes of some animal glowing like fire- balls. Approaching nearer, how  near he was not fully aware, he pointed his rifle directly at the glowing eyes of the animal, and fired. The shot took effect; but with a wild howl the animal leaped upward and forward in his death struggles, and being but a few feet from the bold hunter, his whole weight came    <pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6650-00000015"/> 26     THE RUSSEL FAMLY.        upon him. A short struggle ensued, when  the animal rolled over quite dead. The blow  had stunned Malcolm, and the claws of the animal had torn his face and arm, so that he I was becoming quite faint from loss of blood. From the first report of the rifle, Nellie  listened for her brother's call. When it came she was alarmed, for she fancied his voice 1 sounded weaker than usual. But she was a brave child, and too much accustomed to act, to hesitate now. ' "Did you bring the. linen, Nellie?" said Malcolm, as he met her at the entrance of the cave. Yes.  Does Master Reynard need it, Mack?" said Nellie; then in a moment ob- serving her brother's pale face and blood- stained clothes, she ran to him ih the utmost alarm.* "Dear, dear Malcolm, what has happened? Are you hurt? What can I do?" " No, Nellie, I am not much hurt. Now do not cry, but just be a dear little nurse, as yousa   ou know, not to the fox, but to the   THE CHASE.       27 'mighty hunter' himself. Bring the linen, Puss; how glad I am   you thought of it. There now, just bring me some water in my cap, and we will wash off these ugly stains." Calmed by the courage of her brother, Nel- lie brought the water and assisted him to bathe his face and arm, and bound them with the bandages in a manner creditable to her skill in her new calling. Refreshed by these little attentions, Mal- colm now considered what it was best for him to do. They were at least three miles from the fort, it was already late, and he was too weak and faint to go unassisted. He felt that to send his sister home alone through that  , dense forest, would be hazardous in the ex- treme, and to remain out alone after nightfall equally so. Their dinner-basket was as yet untouched, the creek near by furnished them water, the cave shelter, and the dry sticks scattered about would make a warm fire by the aid of powder and rifle. He determined to remain there all night. Nellie, assured of the right judgment of her    <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6650-00000016"/> 28     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. brother, helped to build the fire, divided their dinner, brought water to bathe his arm, and when night fell, they crept into the cave, and drew the body of the wolf across the opening as a protection from the cold, or wild animals. "Poor mamma!" said Nellie, as she looked out into the dark forest, lighted only by the fitful gleams of their fire. "How very anx- ious she will be about us, Malcolm." "Yes, Nellie, I know it, and that is harder to bear than the ugly scratches that old fellow gave me. But I think papa will send for us, so we will not be very anxious." Nellie dared not let her brother see the tears running down her face, so she retired to one part of the cave and prayed to God to take -care of them, with that faith in an all-power. ful Being, so innate with the child as with the older person in times of danger. With her head pillowed on her brother's knee, and wrapped warmly in his cloak, the weary child slept on her strange, unwonted couch. M Left alone in his strange position, the boy's heart almost failed him.  Weakened with   THE CHASE.       29 pain" and loss of blood, and chilled with the cold of the night, his mind wandered over'the busy scenes of the day. As he looked into the dense forest, already resounding to the cries of its wild inhabitants, he thought of the warm, well-lighted parlor, the cheerful tea- table, and the happy faces, now, alas! shaded by deep anxiety on their account. He saw his noble father pacing the room in sorrow, and his mother, retiring, as usual, to seek the unfailing Source of all her help. The boy wept, and learning his first lesson of dependence upon an all-controlling Su- preme Being, hle bowed his head to his moth- er's God, and prayed. Then resting his head upon the shaggy form of the- wolf, he slept. When the twilight had deepened into dark- ness, and the lamps wyere lighted, the supper waited for the rovers. Since sunset the mother had been most deeply anxious. True, it was no uncommon thing for the children to go off on such excursions; they had sometimes re- mained as late, the forest 'was well known to them, and Malcolm had promised to keep 3*    <pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6650-00000017"/> AudA AtUSSEL FAMLY.  near the trail, and to be home early. But it  was a drear night, and the rising wind seemed, to moan and sob around the fort, awakening, as it often will, sad forebodings.  Unable to rest, the mother had sent out the servants to look for them. But when nine  o'clock came, and still they tarried, she felt' sure that something had befallen them. Re- . tiring to her room, she left her sorrows with her God, while the no less anxious father aroused some of the soldiers to join the search. By the light of pine torches they searched- the wood during the greater part of the night, without striking their path. Toward morn- ing, however, the father and Lieutenant Ver-  non, who accompanied him, thought they saw the mark of Nellie's little foot. Following  the track, as they had wandered during their, morning's sport, they came to the old log, where lay a part of the wreath she had woven. Easily finding the path now, they arrived at the bluff just as daylight made every thing visible. The smoking fire guided them to. the cave, *  ' ,      -" . " *f As    1    '  I   where the first object that met the eye of the father was the form of an ugly wolf, asleep, as he supposed. But on drawing nearer, he saw his boy pale and disfigured, supporting his little sister on his arm, both asleep. The dead animal, the empty gun, and the stained clothes of the boy explained the story, and he shuddered when he thought of what might have been the consequences of the fearful struggle. The voices of the assembled party awakened Malcolm and his sister. Refieshed with his sleep, although stiffened and sore from his late encounter with the wolf, Malcolm joyfully welcomed his father, and prepared to leave his strange bed-chamber, while Nellie sprang sob- bing to her father's arms. A short time brought them  safely home. Malcolm, enveloped in his wolf-skin, which Manly, a soldier, declared his rightful spoil, made light of his wounds, but his lips trem- bled when he saw his mother's pale face and tearful eye, and realized how long and how weary must have been the night to her anx- ious, loving heart.    <pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6650-00000018"/> 32-    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. Deening the lesson a sufficient one to ensure more care for the future, Colonel Russel said nothing to his son, and his countenance beamed with proud joy as the evening lamp shed its soft radiance over all the members of his well- loved family. But the mother's words sank- deeply into the softened hearts of her children as she spoke tenderly of their late danger, the- nearness and certainty of death, and the pre- serving goodness of God.' Renewedly did she consecrate to God the precious gifts of His love, and long after sleep had closed the eyes of all the inmates of the fort, ascended still the prayers of this faithful Christian mother. How she longed, as she prayed, to draw aside the dim curtain of the future and know what would be the result of these anxious prayers and tears. But God has in mercy hidden from us the "Book of Fate."  It is ours to "fill the circle marked by heaven," to hope humbly, and " await the great teach- er, death." Had the future been laid open to her then, her heart now trusting and hoping, would have trembled with fear and dread.   THE CHASE.       33 How full of hope the thought that we know but in part; that our deeds of love and acts of charity are all known and remembered by the God who seeth in secret; that although often cast down, we are never forsaken. Let hope, then, cheer thee, Christian mother, however dark the prospect may seem. Your times are in the hands of One in whose sight "a thousand years are as one day, and one day as a thousand years." Rest in the sure word of promise, and labor on, marking the sands of time with footsteps, that may, at least, cheer some other sorrowing one in her path.    <pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6650-00000019"/> "I. * ^WO years have glided away. They L I have brought no marked change to J  the inmates of the fort. Again the autumn, with its rich coloring, has decked the forest. But now the wailing wind finds an answering echo from the bleeding hearts within the silent walls of the fort. The death-angel has spread his dark wing over the happy family, and chosen indeed a "shining mark." Upon her couch lies the idolized wife and devoted mother; her eye lighted by undying love as it rests upon the grief-stricken group around her. For weary dayso the hot breath of the fever had scorched and consumed her life-blood, and burned upon her brain, invading her reason, and filling it with vague but terrible dreams. With fond   THE MOTHER'S DEATH-BED.     35 care had the husband watched for one glance of recognition from the Wild eye, while the children wept as her voice fell upon, their ears in its unwonted ravings. But now the crisis was past-she must die. Awaking, as from a long sleep, she calmly received the grim messenger, and began to make ready to depart. Her inner house was all in order, but she must look out from it, while she nerved her soul for its struggle-for she must leave all these beloved ones. It was hers to tread Jordan alone. "Arthur, dearest!" The voice was a feeble one, but its tender tone reached the heart of the husband, who had buried his face in his hands, while his strong frame trembled beneath his burden of sorrow. He bent eagerly to catch the whis- perings of the beloved voice so soon to be hushed forever. "I am dying, my own Arthur. God calls me home. Mourn not too deeply, but ac- knowledge a Father's hand, and prepare to meet me there-in heaven.     You have    <pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6650-00000020"/> 36     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. smoothed life's thorny pathway, dearest, and gentle has been your love. My heart quivers with anguish in leaving you to- finish your pilgrimage alone. But I know that my Re- deemer liveth, and I will trust him. I could ask to be spared yet a few years, to guide our precious children over the shoals and quick- sands of life, but I can trust them to One who has promised to care for them, and to your own watchful love. "But Arthur, my precious husband, yield your heart to God. Let me be the blissful messenger to heaven of the glad tidings that you are one of Christ's redeemed. Yield not to despairing grief, but arise, and in God's strength meet your sorrows and your duties with a' firm heart. We shall soon be united, never again to know the pang of separation." The exertion of speaking so much had nearly exhausted her feeble strength; but as the flame of life flickered in its socket, it gleamed forth once more, with that mysteri- ous strength granted to many ere they close their eyes to enter the shady realm of death.   THE MOTHER'S DEATH-BED.    37 Then did the mother in that moment of life and vigor give her last instructions to her weeping children. To Malcolm she pointed out the peculiar temptations and dangers that would beset his future path, while she urged him, with earnest tenderness, to give his heart to the Saviour now, to take his mother's Bible for his guide and counselor, his mother's God as his everlasting portion. "Charlotte, my daughter, you must en- deavor to fill my place. Be a guide to your little brother and sister, and a comfort to your father. Seek strength and wisdom from God, darling, to prepare them for life and for death. May the blessed Saviour keep you from every hurtful snare, my dear child, and bring you to himself when life is over. "Nellie, my sweet one, kiss mamma. You must be a dear child, and love papa very much.  Mamma is going to live in those beautiful mansions. of which she has so often told you. Come and meet me there, Nellie, and be a pure, bright angel in heaven. "Where is Edward, my pooy boy?"    <pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC6650-00000021"/> 38      THE RUSSEL FAMLY. The boy arose from his knees, and took the extended hand of his mother,' while she spoke words of comfort and hope to his agonized heart. Pushing back the masses of brown hair from his fine forehead, with a gentle ten- derness, she breathed forth her blessing, a precious boon: sinking back exhausted, she motioned to her husband to raise her once more.  The farewell kiss was given, and after a short struggle, she slept peacefully, "As dies the wave upon the shoe." Colonel Russel laid her bac  gently upon the pillow, and clasping his youngest children to his heart, he mingled his tears with theirs. No stranger was there to mar the sanctity of that solemn scene.  Only the bereaved hearts that loved her best wept over the lost one. How beautiful she looked in that peaceful slumber. "There beamed a smile So fixed and holy from that marble brow'; Death gazed, and left it there; he dared not steal The ,signet-ring of heaven."   THE MOTHER'S DEATH-BED.    39 Ah, there is nothing terrible in death when the spirit is borne away so gently to the "pearly gates." We 'almost fancy we can behold the glories of heaven as they burst up- on her longing eye, while the faint echoes of heavenly music fall even upon our own sin- imprisoned souls, as ' she strikes her golden harp in unison with the angel band. Rest, sainted one. We can not wish thee back, although life will be dark unlighted by thy smile. The influence of thy holy life shall live after thee, and arouse many a better re- solve and lead to many a deed of love and charity. The bitter duties that follow death-'tis these that cause the heart the most of anguish. The carelessness and coldness of hirelings who clothe the lost treasure in the, garb of death, the narrow coffin and tomb. How gently would we fold the linen and lay her upon a softer couch. How does each jar, each mis- step make us writhe with pain, although we know the cold form can never suffer more. Then-most desolate of all-the rattling of    <pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC6650-00000022"/> 40     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. the first sod upon the coffin, that knell to our hearts, that tells us all is past. The return to the desolate home, and the long, dreary days and nights to watch and weep alone. Ah, it is easier to die than to live and mourn over the graves of those dearer than life to us. Life seemed all a blank to the bereaved husband. Each room of the fort, every flower in the garden, and every whisper of the forest leaves, seemed to speak of his lost one. She was buried among the flowers she loved so well, and already her grave was covered with the sere dead leaves of autumn. There came the husband and children to weep, and there stood the officers and soldiers to remember her- gentle teachings; and there, too, came many a dark-browed Indian to speak of the deeds of mercy and acts of love of the "White Dove" of the fort. But the stern duties of life must be met, and Colonel Russel roused himself for the conflict. When weakened by his great grief, he had bowed his proud head over the clay-   THE MOTHER'S DEATH-BED.    41 cold form of his idolized wife and prayed for the first time in his long life-prayed for sub- mission, faith to believe, and strength to serve his God for the remainder of his days. His prayer was heard. He daily petitioned for strength to meet every trial, while from the oracles of God he sought wisdom to direct him. His heart was comforted, and he arose from his sorrow " a wiser and better man." Men wondered to behold the haughty heart subdued and tender; the man of passion a man of prayer.  He who has' promised to "reward openly" remembered all the secret prayers of the righteous one now sleeping beneath the snow-wreaths in the garden. His promises are sure.     <pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6650-00000023"/> ALCOLM   RUSSEL was destined for the army. He was now sixteen years of age, and the time had come when he was to be sent to the Military Academy at West Point, to complete his education. He was a youth of much promise; and well might a father's heart swell with pride and hope for such a son. His face bespoke a noble soul, and in his dark eye slept a world of pas- sion. - e was generous, impulsive, and affec- tionate, the very nature to be swayed by the influence of others. At home this had been gentle and loving, and the boy had grown up almost unmoved by any other; so that, as yet, he had scarcely awaked to know his own powers or passions. Colonel Russel trembled   THE REMOVAL.       43 to subject him thus early to the influences of that world of which he knew so little. But as his natural taste was for a military life, he must be properly educated. The father trusted that the boy's early training, his own oft-repeated counsels, and the sweet influence of his mother's life and teachings would be-a safeguard to shield him from many a lurking danger. The other children, too, deprived thus early of their mother and teacher, must be placed where they could perfect the education she had begun. As no advantages offered here, they must be sent from home. These'consid- erations decided Colonel Russel to resign his command, and seek a home in the States, where he could more closely watch over and guide his children, and thus fulfill the sacred mission left him by his dying wife. Accordingly he removed with them to the State of Virginia, in the early spring. The precious dust of- his wife was disinterred and taken to their new home, for he could not leave her where only the stranger might point    <pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6650-00000024"/> "    THE RUSSEL FAMLY.- out her grave. It was a severe trial to leave the home made so dear by a thousand happy memories. Many silent tears were shed as they bade adieu to the haunts of their child- hood; scenes that must never again meet their eyes. Their new home was situated amid scenery full of beauty. The house built of dark stone much after the ancient castle style, stood upon a gentle eminence. Behind it, a forest inter- vened between it and the blue tops of the mountains marking the horizon beyond. The well-trimmed lawn in front sloped gradually down td the clear waters of one of our beauti- ful inland lakes; while art had vied with nature in adorning the ample grounds with all that could gratify a refined taste. Beyond the estate, stretched away a rugged country, full of wild, romantic scenery, while the gentle vale and lake slept peacefully below, as if secure in the protecting embrace of the giant mountains around. The house was furnished with elegance, that quiet elegance so congenial to minds taught by affliction to shrink from   THE REMOVAL.       45 the false glare and gaudy tinselry which de- light minds of coarser mold. Here Colonel Russel retired with his young- er children, devoting his time and thoughts solely to their education. Malcolm was placed in the Academy at West Point, and Lottie entered upon a course of study in one of our female seminaries at the East. Masters were provided for' Edward, and Colonel Russel endeavored in every way to fill the place of his lost mother to the sensitive boy. He was now nearly twelve years of age, and had grown to be quite tall; but his earn- est mind had worn upon his physical aevelop- ment; he was slender and very delicate. There was an almost spiritual beauty in his finely chiseled features, the expansive forehead just shaded by the wavy hair, and the eyes full of poetry and feeling. To his kindling fancy his beautiful home furnished food for many a musing hour. The lofty mountains beyond, bearing clouds upon their brows, now dark with the lowering of the storm-king, and now flooded with the    <pb n="46-47" xml:id="VAC6650-00000025"/> "     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. fall radiance of the rising sun, taught him many a lesson of sublimity and power. The vale, beautiful with its garment of emerald dotted with sweet flowers, the lake, sleeping -peacefully beneath the deep shadows thrown over its bosom, calmed himn, and inspired the purest and holiest thoughts. The ancient form of his castle-home carried him back into the dreamy past, while the pleasing mingling of the present in its adornments, jarred not by their want of harmony and grace. His poetry was of that order which seeks embodiment upon the canvas or the more lasting marble. His first efforts had excited the wondering admiration of the inmates of the fort, when his material was but rough wood, and the rude colors of the savage. But now his studio was adorned with the strangely beautiful conceptions of his soul, sculptured in the purest marbles the country afforded.' So intensely did he now pursue his favorite studies, that his health began to fail. His father immediately advised him to leave his studio, to engage in other studies, or the   THE REMOVAL.       47 sports and pleasures of boyhood. Accustomed from early childhood to a ready compliance with the wishes of his parents, Edward bade a reluctant adieu to his favorite pursuits. He soon became an eager student of the sciences, studying the hidden mysteries of nature, and tracing the footsteps of nature's God. He reveled, too, in the dreams of the poets of past ages. Riding upon his favorite pony, he would wander among the rocks and caverns, or along the streams of the country, peo- pling them with the mysterious gods and demi-gods of Homer and Virgil, or with the creations of his own wild fancy. Again, with the laughing Nellie, he would climb to the mountain-top, and crowning her with a chap- let of evergeen, install her the Naiad of the grove, and join merrily in her ringing laugh. The father's heart rested more quietly when he beheld the roses of health tinging, at last, the. pale cheek of his boy, and the delicate frame rounding to a fuller and healthier de- velopment.    <pb n="48-49" xml:id="VAC6650-00000026"/> V. thi  sae atio oitsu HE wheels of time move softly: three years glide away and we scarcely note their speed. And now the longr looked- for day has arrived.  Malcolm has received his first furlough; Papa and Eddie have gone to see dear Lottie receive her diploma and the first honors of her class, and then bring her home with Malcolm. How fuill of business was Nellie's sweet face on the morning of the expected arrivals. There was Papa's room to arrange, the gauze to remove from dear Mamma' portrait, always kept covered in Papa's absence; the mite of dust to be removed from his toilet-table and books; the curtains disposed to admit just enough of the bright sunshine to make the room cheerful, and to lighten the smile-that   THE VACATIONS.      49 strangely sweet smile, that Nellie could just remember-Mamma always wore, and which the artist had so happily preserved. Then there was Mack's room.   "Ah, I suppose Mack must be a splendid man now," mused Nellie, "with that beautiful black hair of his-and whiskers. Oh, I wonder if Mack does wear whiskers and a moustache! How funny he will look!" and Nellie laughed mer- rily as she glanced up to a portrait of her brother, when a lad of fourteen, at the fort. The little fairy moved about, making the most tasteful arrangement of books and fur- niture in Mack's room, and Lottie's and Eddie's. After every thing had been ar- ranged and rearranged to suit the capricious taste of the little coquettish mistress, she flew down for the sixth time at least, to tell Chloe to prepare a, nice dinner, and to see that Robert went with the coach to the depot precisely at one o'clock. The next moment she was with the gardener, culling her basket anjoarms full of flowers. Ah, Nellie was a very fairy among the 5    <pb n="50-51" xml:id="VAC6650-00000027"/> 50     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. flowers. She loved them, and used to think, simple child, that the roses and lilies and violets and daisies knew her step and nodded their pretty heads as she passed; and the little sensitive flower that Eddie had planted, did not shrink quite so quickly from her touch, she thought. Nellie sat down beneath a shading chestnut, and wove her garlands, and arranged her bouquets. A group of all varieties for the center-table; moss-rose buds and mignionette for Papa's vase; this pure white lily and sweet violets for Lottie's; passion-flowers and verbenas for Mack's; oak-leaf chaplets for Eddie's little statuettes, and these blue-eyed myrtles and forget-me-nots for the curious little vase upon which Eddie has carved an angel leading a child by the hand, and pointing toward heaven; and the angels face resembles so much M[amma's portrait. At last every thing is arranged, tho coach has gone, and Nellie pushes back the curtains to watch its appearance.   A short time elapses, then a cloud of dust announces the   THE VACATIONS.      51 approaching coach. They are borne rapidly to the door, and the happy child is clasped to the hearts of those she loves. Merry voices and gleeful laughs fill the drawing-room as the reunited falmily assemble together. "Why, Mack," said Nellie, when they were quiet, "you do wear whiskers, don't you? And this ugly moustache! Why, I can never kiss you on your mouth again, it will be so hard to find it!" "Why, Puss, you must remember that I am no longer Mack Russel, but an embryo lieutenant. Indeed, Papa thinks of leaving me to wear all his accumulated honors; while he retires to plain 'Arthur Russel, Esq.,' I am-or rather will be-' Colonel M. Russel,' at your service. To be sure, I must cover my youthful face with these black adornments, or people will never suspect I have been so highly promoted. Indeed, Miss Puss, most young ladies think these quite enchanting; I am shocked at your want of taste and discrimina- tion." "Well, Colonel M. Russel, allow me to 'em,    <pb n="52-53" xml:id="VAC6650-00000028"/> 52.    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. inform you that I, too, have been promoted, that I am no longer Puss, but-but-" "Well what? Miss Ellen Russel?" "No, no, Mack. Eddie, what was that queer title you gave me the other day?" "Ah, Nellie, have I wasted so many pretty titles upon you, and your giddy little head canenot retain one! I have installed you the Nymph of the Forests, the Naiad of the Fountains, and with that beautiful wreath of roses laid among your curls, I call you the Fairest of the Graces." "There, Colonel M. Russel, remember all my titles, if you can, and learn from me how to wear your honors." "I call my little Nellie my household fairy," said Papa, cc and now, dear, we will go to din- ner, and you may introduce Lottie to her new station as mistress of Papa's house." Lottie had been absent from home nearly three years, and had passed from a child to the full bloom of the maiden. As she ha&amp; grown older, the resemblance to her mother had become more marked; and now as she   THE VACATIONS.       53 sat opposite her father, in the place occupied for so many years by his lost Lucy, he was almost startled to observe how very like Lottie was to her mother' when at her age. ,It was always pleasant to recall the memory of the departed one, and many were the scenes recounted when she joined the circle and mingled her sweet-toned voice with theirs. It was a comforting and beautiful belief to them that her gentle spirit yet hovered around them and participated in their happi- ness. Dinner oveir, the whole estate must be vis- ited by Edward and Malcolm on horseback; Lottie must go with Nellie to each room in the house, shake hands with the servants, visit favorite walks and flowers, and talk of the busy past. Papa retired to his room to rest from the fatigues of his journey. When evening approached, the family gathered to- gether once more and discussed their plans for the future. "I have about concluded, my children," said Colonel Russel, "to send Edward to 5* :    <pb n="54-55" xml:id="VAC6650-00000029"/> 54     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. Europe next month.  The advantages af- forded here are not what he ought to enjoy. I have engaged Professor Benton of to attend him upon his journey, acting as his tutor while he travels two years, and, before leaving him in Italy, to provide him with the best masters and every facility for pursuing successfully the art he loves so well. Would you like that, my son?" "Oh, yes, Papa, better than any thing else, only--that I must bee separated so long from you all." (' It will be a hard trial, no doubt, to us all, but I feel more resigned to it, as I find my slender boy changing to the stronger youth. If you like the idea, I think you had better go. You, Malcolm, will return soon to your studies, and finish, I hope as honorably as you have begun, your course. It would be a ter- rible blow to my proud heart should you ever bring disgrace upon yourself and family. I can not advise you better than that you should fulfill the dying counsels of your sainted mother. ' Choose your mother's Bible /'   '       *    TlHE VAUCATIUON.       . for your guide, your mother's God for your everlasting portion.'"  - A shadow flitted over Malcolm's fine face, but it was unnoted. "' Charlotte, my daughter, you will now fill that mother's place. We must have your brother ready for his voyage next month; while we must try to tame this wild little  Nellie, and fill her head with more substantial   knowledge than the dreams the flowers whis- per in her ear." Colonel Russel pushed the clustering curls from off the fair forehead, and pressed a fond kiss upon it. Then followed a merry laugh, as Malcolm caught his little sister for his kiss, while music and stories about West Point, Hartford, and  home, made the hours fly swiftly until the bell struck for evening prayers. "Here are cards for -an evening-- party, Malcolm, from my old class-mate, Miss Lizzie Grant," said Lottie, a few  mornings after their return. "I have taken the liberty to accept them, 'without even :consulting you."    <pb n="56-57" xml:id="VAC6650-00000030"/> 56     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. "For what evening, Lottie?" "This evening. Lizzie is a very lovely girl, I assure you.  Her father is one of the wealthiest planters in Virginia, but I imagine he is somewhat tyrannical at home. I have seen but little of Mrs. Grant, but should judge her to be a quiet, lady-like woman. Lizzie was an intimate friend of mine at Hartford, and I am quite sure you will enjoy her society, should you make her acquaintance." "Very well, Lottie, I shall be happy to attend you to the party. We had better start early," replied Malcolm, as he went out to give orders to the coachman. When evening came, the brother and sister descended to the drawing-room, attired for the party. Malcolm looked very handsome, Nel- lie thought, in his cadet-dress, displaying well his manly form and graceful carriage. His raven hair was pushed off from his forehead and his eye shone with a merry light. Lottie's simple drapery of white became well her gentle beauty, while the tasteful choice and arrange- ment of the flowers was from Nellie. The   THE VACATIONS.      57 evening was mild and pleasant, and the ride promised to be a very delightful one. "Malcolm," said Lottie, "do you remember Lieutenant Vernon of the old fort?" "Yes, very well. He was a pleasant young man, and I believe Papa used to invite him to our parlor very often. But what of him now, Lottie?" "He has left the army. His father died quite suddenly, and he has returned to Hart- ford, where he resides with his mother and sisters. He called upon me soon after his arrival in the city, and spoke with warm af- fection of dear Mamma. He said he had im- bibed infidel principles while at West Point, but had been led by her holy and consistent life, to listen to her gentle reasonings, and search for himself the truths of God's word. He said, whatever peace of mind he now en- joyed, and the immortalf-opsthat brightened his future, he felt he owed to her, as the, means in God's hands. He recalled many scenes of our childhood that I had quite for- gotten."  I1F v    <pb n="58-59" xml:id="VAC6650-00000031"/> 58     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. Malcolm sighed deeply, scarcely seeming to hear Lottie's remarks. His memory was busy with the past, and it recalled with a bitter emphasis the lessons that sainted mother had taught him. They had fallen more and more faintly upon his soul since his first agony of grief, as he stood beside her death-bed. Her soft eyes looked reproachfully from the past, while the whisperings of his better nature bade him now to. turn and tread again the path of right from which he had strayed. But the proud heart rebelled. Hushing the warn- ing voice, he looked hopefully again upon his joyous present, and the bright future opening before him. "Well, Lottie, what more of Lieutenant Vernon?" he resumed, noting the thoughtful expression of his sister's face. "I received a letter from him, to-day," replied Lottie, blushing ; "you can read it if you wish." "Does' the brave lieutenant intend to be- siege your heart, sister, mine?" "He has expressed his interest in me,   THE VACATIONS.      59 in a very winning manner," replied Lottie quietly. "Have you told Papa of this?" "Certainly. Mr. Vernon begged permis- sion to visit us, and Papa wrote him to-day  that he would be very welcome." "Well, Lottie dear, I hope you will be very happy in your choice. As I remember Mr. - ernon, he is as worthy as any one I know of so precious a prize as my sister. Be very sure of my earnest sympathy and wishes for your future happiness. But here we are. Now, Lottie, you must assist me, for you know I am quite unaccustomed to other bright eyes than yours and Nellie's." The evening wore away pleasantly; Mal- colm was as much charmed with the lovely Lizzie Grant as his sister had anticipated. He even succeeded in bringing a smile upon the hard face of her father, by his joyous humor. When he parted, he obtained the promise of a welcome for future visits. The ride home was a silent one, for each was busy weaving the web of the future. Clouds mar-    <pb n="60-61" xml:id="VAC6650-00000032"/> 60     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. red not the fair prospect, but bright sunshine lighted the path, strewn with the fairest blos- soms of hope-that sweet charmer who cheers alike the- old and, young with dreams of a future good. . 8     VI. ddte fro oarat iou fa m HE short time that intervened before  Edward's departure from  home, was most industriously occupied by his sis- ters. Lottie, with a characteristic thoughtfulness, prepared many nice little articles for his comfort, while Nellie's busy fingers wrought various graceful devices upon his velvet slippers and the collar of his dress- ing-gown. But tears would dim her bright eyes when she thought of the long voyage, the four years' absence, and a little cloud hazed the bright prospect beyond, for Nellie remembered how many dear, loving brothers, just like Ed- die, were lying still and white down deep in the ocean-waves. "; Are n't you afraid to have Eddie go, Lot- tie?" said the child. 6    <pb n="62-63" xml:id="VAC6650-00000033"/> 62    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. "God will watch over and care for him as well there as here, you know, Nellie." "Yes, but Lottie, what if we should never see him again? What if he should be buried in the ocean, like poor Willie Seaton? Would not that be very dreadful?" "Very, Nellie ; but it is not right to make ourselves unhappy about imaginary evils. We must trust the results of all our plans to God's disposal, and go on hopefully. We must think how happy Eddie will be with his stud- ies, and in visiting the places which have so long filled his imagination; and then, perhaps he will come back, by and by, a great man, -and be all dear Mamma used to hope for him."  "Do you think Eddie is a Christian, Lot- tie?" "I am afraid not, Nellie, for he loves his art too absorbingly. But I think he will not soon forget all the lessons of truth that have been taught him. He never speaks of Mam- ma's last counsels and blessing without the deepest emotion. We must pray for him   THE SEPARATION.;      63 every day, Nellie, and that God will answer all Mamma's earnest prayers for us all." "Lieutenant Vernon will be here to-night," said Colonel Russel, entering the room with an open letter. Nellie's sadness was gone in a moment, and she danced gayly about, mindful only of present happiness.  She had but a slight recollection of Mr. Vernon, but her memories of the past were only happy ones, always bright and beautiful. The expected guest arrived that night. Time had produced less change in him than in the family of his former commander. It had silvered the hair, and bent somewhat the erect form of Colonel Russel, while a sad- dened and subdued soul shed a new and beautiful light over his once haughty brow. Lieutenant Vernon could hardly recognize his former little friends in the manly form of Malcolm, the graceful, womanly figure of his own Lottie, or the tall, slender contour of Edward's form. Nelhe had changed less-: the same artless, loving child, as of old. Memories    <pb n="64-65" xml:id="VAC6650-00000034"/> "     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. crowded thickly as the family gathered to- gether after tea. "How long since you left the fort?" asked the colonel. "About one year since. There have been many changes since you were there. Soon after Colonel Emery arrived to fill your com- mand, the Indians were removed to their reservation. As so large a force was no longer necessary, the detachment was ordered to other forts. But the old fort, the garden, the flowers, and walks, remain undisturbed. "The spot where Mrs. Russel was buried has been tastefully fenced in and ornamented. The Indians aver that the spirit of the ' White Dove' yet lingers around the spot; many of us feel that it does indeed. Hers was a gen- tle mission, and like an angel did she fulfill it." The silent tear and subdued countenances of the little group testified how fragrant was the memory of the departed one. ' Mrs. Russel used to speak of Edward with considerable anxiety," resumed the lieutenant, after a pause.   THE SEPARATION.       65 "His health is less delicate than formerly," replied the colonel. "I have concluded to send him to Europe to restore it more per- fectly, and that he may more successfully pursue his studies.  He will sail Monday morning, but must leave for New York the latter part of this week. Malcolm will return to his studies at the same time, and will re- main in New York until he sails." I am very glad you\ are going, Edward. We shall expect very much from you. How very few of America's sons of genius, sir, have wrought for- future fame. The spirit of the Money-king is all potent-it buys genius at a surprisingly low rate.  Be careful that it barters not for your soul, Edward." "I believe there is little danger, sir," re- plied the youth.  "My Father has kindly shielded me from want and the stern law of necessity." "In past ages, it was in want, and by this very stern law of necessity, the bards sang their loftiest strains. The most undying of the gems of art were completed to gain the 6*    <pb n="66-67" xml:id="VAC6650-00000035"/> "     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. few pence necessary to keep starvation from the door. The most hqavenly strains of the ancient masters seem like the wail of a soul trembling beneath its stern agony of the bit- ter conflict with life. But genius now seems devoted to pander to popular taste, however unworthy, or to the varied interests of party." "At present," replied the colonpl, " the times seem to demand the energy and labor of all, whether possessed of genius or otherwise, and, until our country has become older and more settled, we ought not to expect any marked national literature or advance in the fine arts." "That is very true, sir, particularly of our empire in the West. The varied elements which compose the western society, will re- quire time before they amalgamate sufficiently to form an entire and  separate character. Their lives and those of several generations, it may be, must be expended in the settlement of the country, the forming of social ties, and establishment of homes, amid the peculiar beauties of western scenery.  This, when   THE SEPARATION.      67 fully accomplished, will, no doubt, give rise to a style of literature, differing materially from that of the past or present, and possessing charms peculiar to itself. But ought we not to expect more from the gifted sons of New England, the middle States, and the sunny South?" "Undoubtedly, and I believe if each and every effort is met with proper encouragement we may expect to possess works of art that shall outlive the present, and to which we may proudly lay claim as emanating from our own country. But shall we not have some music? This little head of Nellie's will hardly hold any more of our concentrated wisdom. We must relieve it." Lottie seated herself at the piano, accom- panying it with her sweet voice; Malcolm joined his own rich bass, while Edward with the flute, and Nellie's guitar, completed the pleasing harmony. The evening prayers over, the happy family separated for the night. The moon shone out beautifully, and Ed- ward visited, as he often did, his mother's i    <pb n="68-69" xml:id="VAC6650-00000036"/> 68     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. grave. She was buried in a lovely spot, beneath the graceful branches of a droop- ing willow, which seemed to watch over the precious dust, and murmur a fit dirge over the gentle sleeper, as the wind rustled the leaves against the pure marble. The grave was covered with flowers, beautiful beneath the soft radianmce of the morn. The mound was a sacred spot to Edward, for it was near- est his mother's heart, upon which he so often longed to lean his weary head and feel its living influence. And now the past was before him : that gentle smother looked love again, down deep into his soul; her hand was on his brow, her kiss upon his lips. Her last blessing trembled upon his ear as he turned unwillingly to re- member the present. Soon he was to leave his home and beloved friends. The gentle voice that seemed to speak to his very soul from the grave of his mother, the soft eyes that beamed upon him from the starry heaven above, would, he find aught like these in foreign lands?   THE SEPARATION.      69 Then came his deep passion for his beauti- ful art, and he felt his soul quiet with the harmony of its own conceptions. Upon the altar of his heart did he then consecrate his genius to the memory of his sainted mother. To her should be dedicated all, and his im- aginings should be pure and holy in their beauty, like her who was to be his inspiration and guiding star. Ah, Edward! better would it have been had you consecrated your genius and powers to your mother's God. Beware lest you for- get the great Being who has thus endowed your gifted mind, and in the wild worship of the creature you forget to render homage to the glorious Creator. Your mother's, ran- somed soul would swell with a holier joy to see her boy thus honoring the God whom she delighted to honor, and thus fulfilling the in- structions with which she blessed your early youth. Friday morning dawned bright and beauti- ful. The trunks were ready in the hall, and the coach nearly prepared; Lieutenant Ver-    <pb n="70-71" xml:id="VAC6650-00000037"/> 70    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. non, Malcolm, and Edward were to leave this morning. Edward had arisen early to visit all his favorite walks, and knelt for the last time upon his mother's grave. Tears dropped fast upon the white lilies over the grave, for the boy's heart lived over again that terrible hour when he first bent over the tomb of his departed mother, and realized how bitter was sorrow's cup. As he arose, he remembered his vows of consecration and looked forward more hopefully. Charlotte, too, had arisen, and in her closet she fervently committed her brother to that kind care which had so guided and sustained them all. She remembered well her mother's last counsel to her, ana realized the responsi bility which rested upon her. Lovingly had she endeavored to fulfill that sacred trust, by gentle counsel and deeds of self-denial, but most of all, by constant and earnest prayer. Her influence was very pleasant, and she was most tenderly beloved by the family, who de- lighted to find in Charlotte's gentle mind and   THE SEPARATION.       71 lovely graces, so exact a counterpart of their lost household angel. Colonel Russel, also, had been earnest in prayer for his boy, that morning; and he af- fectionately besought him to take the Bible as his guide, and by watchful prayer to arrest the peculiar temptations that might befall him. Again was he reminded of his mother's last counsel, that he should not become a worshiper of art, but yield the homage of his soul to God alone, the Fountain of all Wis- dom, and the Source of the Beautiful. Nelhe had brushed away the tears very often from her bright eyes, while arranging beautiful bouquets for the travelers, commun- ing the while, with her own hopeful little heart of the time when they would return to be happy together once more. Change, dis- ease, death, darken not that fair picture with their poisonous breath. Malcolm, too, had yielded to most serious reflections, as he prepared once more to depart from his home. As he bent over his mother's grave, he felt that change must come, perhaps    <pb n="72-73" xml:id="VAC6650-00000038"/> 72     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. even disease and death might again invade their own loved circle., Again over his heart, came back the memories of the past, and the counsels and prayers of his mother.   Ah, well he knew his duty, but could he do it now?  No, he would hush this warning voice from the past, pursue yet further the bright phantoms of the preset, while the future-ah, that made his heart tremble a moment-but wherefore? all was sunshine now. And thus they partel. Tears dimmed their eyes, softly fell the murmered "May tlh Lord bless you," the farewells of loving hearts were spoken, the familiar scenes of home faded from their sight. Their paths were now to diverge. Will they ever meet again?  God knoweth.  The tide of time yet rolls onward swiftly. Lottie fills the important sphere of mistress of her father's house; teachers are provided for Nellie; while the colonel retires once more to the privacy of his library, or mingles with the circle of friends, whose congenial intercourse has beguiled many of his leisure hours. Let-   THE SEPARATION.      73 ters came frequently from the absent ones. Edward's spoke of the incidents of his voyage, the beauties of the various countries he visit- ed, his studies, friends, and the bright visions of the future. Malcolm  also wrote full of hope, and the proud ambition of his heart. These letters, full of affection, were a balm to the loving hearts at home, whose thoughts had followed the wanderers. But, lo! a cloud, no larger now than a man's hand, it may be; will it ever vail this glori- ous sky? Shall its darkness lower over this happy home, and its mutterings cause these gentle hearts to tremble? Our Father has promised us heavenly mansions; wisely does He send the bitter cup, though it may be ours to drain its very dregs. In love does He permit the false pleasures of life to crumble within our grasp; else should we live content with these earth-tenements, unmindful of the heavenly inheritance. 7    <pb n="74-75" xml:id="VAC6650-00000039"/> VII.  1p . i t r a I I  t r' /f NE afternoon, about six months after the departure of Malcolm and Edward, 1 a man dismounted before the door, and inquired for Colonel Russel. (' Walk in, sir," said the waiter, a moment after, "Colonel Russel will attend you in a moment." He was ushered into the drawing-room; the tasteful arrangements of the apartment brought a leer of satisfaction upon his ugly features. He was a rough, hardened man in his- appearance; although genteelly dressed, he was evidently as little at ease in a broad- cloth suit, as in the elegant room. There was a remarkably sinister expression about the eyes and mouth, while firmness and decision marked his every movement. He was evin-   THE STRANGER.      75 dently of that class who delight in any deed, however black or dishonorable, however dis- tressing to the feelings of others, provided only that it will pay well. "Did you wish to see me, sir?" asked the Colonel, entering the room. "Well, I did, Colonel.  I calculate you don't remember me?" "I certainly have no recollection of you, sir." "Well now, that's cur'us.  Why, don't you remember little Billy Sherman? I have been to school many a day with Arth. Russel in the old red school-house. You are Colonel Russel now, but I am old Bill Sherman yet. None the worse for that, you know," tapping the Colonel upon the shoulder with a rude familiarity. "Have you any business with me, sir?" said the colonel, drawing back haughtily. "' Well, yes, I have," replied the man, tak- ing some papers from his. coat, "but you neel not be so snappish to a fellow, Colonel. Be decent, now, for the sake of old times and    <pb n="76-77" xml:id="VAC6650-00000040"/> 76     THE 'RUSSEL FAMLY. treat." Let that spruce waiter of your'n bring in the wine, for my throat is dry, ain't your'n, old boy?" "Attend to the business matter directly, sir; and be more regardful of your behavior while in my house," retorted the Colonel, in- dignant at the fellow's low and insulting fa- miliarity. "You 'd better wait until you know it is your house, Colonel. It may be my right to these premises is better than your'n, and that I shall order you off in a hurry," replied the man, with a savage scowl. "Just give these papers your immediate attention, and you will require my assistance, I assure you." Colonel Russel unrolled the package; it was a motley collection of law-papers, the exact purport of which puzzled him to make out. ' You will perceive by these papers, Colonel, that your deed to this estate is a forged one, plenty of witnesses to prove that. So the sooner you leave these grounds, the better for   THE STRANGER.       " me, I calculate, for I happen to be the right- ful owner of them." The Colonel turned pale a moment, but commanding himself, he said, "You may leave these papers with me, sir, while I consult with my lawyer. I shall be able to attend you to- morrow at ten," and he left the room with a slight bow. The waiter appeared a moment after to show the stranger out. He went muttering threats of vengeance for the treatment he had received. Colonel Russel spent the remainder of that day and most of the night in anxious consult- ation with his lawyer. He had bought the estate of a man who professed to hold it in his own name, but it rightfully belonged to his brother, who spent most of his time travel- ing. His only son, who had followed the sea from an early age, was the present holder of these papers. Covetous of gain, the brother had forged the necessary papers, sold the estate to Colonel Russel, and then departed for a distant western State. 7*    <pb n="78-79" xml:id="VAC6650-00000041"/> 78     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. After a few years the rightful owner died in a foreign land, attended by his son. He revealed to him the perfidy of his uncle, con- fided to him the lawful papers, and by will made him his sole heir. He had now returned from sea, and recognizing his former school- mate in -the haughty bearing of the Colonel, he felt all the mean jealousy of a little soul, and knowing his power, he determined to an- noy and insuli him in every possible manner. He was present punctually at the hour ap- pointed, accompanied by a lawyer, and weary, anxious days were spent in examining the papers, and in unraveling the meshes of the law. "Who is that ugly man that comes so often to see Papa, Lottie?" said Nellie, one day after the- waiter had shown Sherman into the library. "I believe his name is Sherman; he wishes to see Papa on business. It must be very harassing, for Papa has scarcely eaten any thing these several days, and I often hear him pacing his floor until past midnight." a   THE STRANGER.      79 "c Well, I wish Papa would just send off that villain of a man. He looks very disa- greeably at me whenever I meet him. To-day he took me by the hand and said, ' My little dear, you'll not always keep such a pretty hand, I calculate; I'll make it work pretty soon.' I snatched it away, and ran to tell Papa, but he looked so troubled that I did not.' "That was right, Nellie; we must try to cheer and assist Papa all we can, for I fear he is deeply troubled." Weary days passed by. The case was a clear one ; it was useless to carry the investi- gation any further, the lawyers said. "Then I am ruined," groaned the Colonel, burying his face in his hands, while the stern eye of poverty stared full upon him. "Be kind enough," said he to his counsel, " to leave me alone. Assure Mr. Sherman that he shall have full possession of his estate in one fortnight. In the mean tine a rtertras- actions you will please attend to. I desire no further intercourse with him. I must be    <pb n="80-81" xml:id="VAC6650-00000042"/> 80     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. alone with my family to complete arrange- ments for the future." The lawyer bowed, and took his leave. Once more alone, Colonel Russel bowed be. neath his heavy trial, and through the long night did he struggle with his intense agony. As the morn threw an early ray into his room, he glanced up to the portrait of his wife. In a moment he remembered the Rock of her refuge, the Source of her comfort, and with his burdened heart, he sank before Him, and prayed with earnest fervor for strength to meet this new trial, for entire submission to the will of his God, and for wisdom to direct his future plans. At breakfast, although deathly pale, he was calm, even cheerful. Lottie hoped the cloud, which of late had seemed to threaten their peaceful home, had passed away.  Letters were read from the absent ones. Nellie noticed a tear trembling in the eye of her father, although the letters were, as usual, joyous and hopeful. After the meal was over, Colonel Russel called his children into the library, and   THE STRANGER.       81 told them all the truth and explained their future course. "What, Papa!"- exclaimed Nellie, must we leave our sweet home?" "Yes, darling, but we will be very brave, and not murmur or repine. You know it is God's will; let it be ours to acquiesce cheer- fully." "And is that ugly Sherman to live here in' our own home? Oh, what will poor Mack and Eddie do without our sweet home! Papa, will Mr. Sherman have all my beautiful flow- ers, too?" No, Nellie, you shall keep all you wish." c Mamma's grave-Papa?" said Lottie, who had listened with a pale face to the story of their wrong. "It shall be ever with us, dearest. Our furniture must all be sold to purchase a new home, and to send for your brothers to return. This is the bitterness of my grief, that my children must suffer with me. But I shall depend much upon your firmness, my daugh-    <pb n="82-83" xml:id="VAC6650-00000043"/> 82     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. ters, to meet this trial. We must do all we can, and trust results to God." Lottie knew her wealmkness, and retiring to her closet, she sought strength to assist her in this, her hour of earnest need. Then with the self-sacrificing love of a true woman, did she meet and perform  all the new and trying duties of her position. And so nobly did she fulfill them, and with so gentle a dignity, that the father blessed her in his heart, while he acknowledged that God had comforted him even in this sore trial. A small white house was purchased, and the scanty remains of the furniture removed to it. The house was embowered in shrubbery, and Nellie's favorite flowers transplanted. It was an humble home compared with their former one, but taste and affection still made it inviting.- But the end is not yet. Colonel Russel had become more delicate in health since his removal from the West. The anxiety attendant upon his late misfortune, and the discouraging prospect of the future, had so harassed his mind, that feeble nature   THE STRANGER.'      83 sank beneath its burden. He had scarcely removed to' his new home before he was stricken down with a brain-fever. Almost crushed beneath this new trial, Lottie learned to lean more heavily upon the Divine Arm, as she devoted herself untiringly to the care of her father. Letters were dis- patched to the absent brothers urging their immediate return. The fever raged wildly; the' physician said there was but little hope that he would ever arise from this couch of suffering. Nellie shrank back affrighted from the wild stare of his delirious eye, and his ravings, now stern and haughty, now pleading in agony, filled their hearts with keenest sor sow. A few days after he was taken sick, a letter came directed to Colonel Russel, and post- marked "West Point," but 'the: writing was not the familiar hand of her brother. Trem- bling with secret misgivings, she directed Nellie to watch beside her father while she went out to walk in the open air. Directing her steps to the beautiful spot where her    <pb n="84-85" xml:id="VAC6650-00000044"/> 84     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. mother still slept peacefully, she rested her throbbing brow upon the cold marble a mo- ment; then opening the letter, she read its contents. With a moan of deepest anguish she sank upon the grave, and oh, how she longed to rest there her aching heart to know no more of sorrow. "How can I endure this blow?" she mur- mured. "Oh God! help me to drink this cup, and say 'Thy will be done.'  Peace came after this hour of agonizing prayer, for He who " hath borne our griefs, and carried our sorrows," giveth sweet conso- lation to His chastened ones. Carefully de- stroying every vestige of the letter, she re- turned to her home, with an ashen cheek, and lips still quivering with the last sore conflict, but gentle, patient, and burying her griefs within her overburdened heart.   VIII. at I ait m. WHEN Malcolm first left his home and mingled with so many of his own age, he carried with him a heart comparatively guileless. Knowing but little of the world, beyond the loving ones at home, his mind had scarcely been tainted with its evils. After he entered the Military Academy he began to develop more rapidly the seeds of evil sown in every human heart. The. lessons of his early youth, the counsels and prayers of his sainted mother, would often make themselves heard, and sway his heart in its better moments with a resistless power. But he gradually learned to close his heart to them, while he listened to the silver-tongued voice of the world, but just beginning to fall upon his ear. 8    <pb n="86-87" xml:id="VAC6650-00000045"/> 86     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. A young cadet from  the South was his chosen companion,  Possessed of winning manners, fascinating address, and a cultivated mind, Louis Thornton was well calculated to acquire an influence over Malcolm's impulsive nature; while his selfishness and utter want of principle, fitted him to play a fearful game with the undeveloped passions and generous heart of his victim.  He was an infidel; but so artfully did he introduce his senti- ments, so polished were his arguments, and so unanswerable his scornful sneer, that, like a beautiful serpent, he. charmed even while inflicting the deadly blow. He treated Malcolm with the most cordial and marked affection, and never intruded his peculiar views but in  the most artful manner, clothed in the fascinating garb of a false philosophy. Slowly, but surely, he was doing his fiendish work. The influences of a sainted mother's earnest prayers and 'counsels, the fond hearts at home, and the gentle love of another dearer than life to the young man's heart-for Lizzie Grant had bestowed on him   MALCOLM.        87 the wealth of her confiding love-all these failed to repel the fatal poison which was corroding the heart of the beloved one. His mother's Bible was neglected; his mother's God despised and forsaken. The beautiful ship is entering unconsciously the fearful whirlpool. Will no hand stay its mad course? Alas, for its fate! alas, for the fond hopes dashed with it upon the fatal rocks below. Malcolm's high standing, social nature, and generous impulses, made him a favorite with his companions, and he was a welcome guest, whenever he chose to join them. As he began to neglect his Bible, he the more easily listened to the doubts and skepticism of many; nor was e startled even at the open and avowed infi- delity of others. The specious philosophy of Thornton attracted his attention. It pleased his fancy, while it afforded a resting-point for a mind but ill at ease. It served for a food wherewith he hoped to. satisfy the eternal longings of his soul. But it was long before he could join the Y   .          ;    <pb n="88-89" xml:id="VAC6650-00000046"/> 88     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. ribald laugh, or utter the sneering jest, against the Bible and its sacred doctrines. They had been too faithfully impressed upon his heart, by a mother who had calmly entered the icy gates of death, and landed fearlessly upon the dark and mysterious ocean of eternity, rejoic- ing in the hope of a haven of rest and perfect peace. It was long ere he could utter the fear- ful oath, or raise the wine-glass to his lips, or bend over the gaming-table, where lay staked interests of far greater value than the small heaps of gold scattered over it. For from the soft skies above him, gentle eyes looked reproachfully, and when in silence and solitude, the voice of conscience would still be heard. But as time passed on, he found it easier to tread the ways of sin. He could do all-and God only knoweth upon what terrible rock he might have been dashed, had not a hand of mercy interposed. True, it held the afflicting rod; true, the cloud which enveloped it was deep and dark; but it had a silver lining, though he knew it only after years of bitter anguish, weary of suffering and sorrow.   MALCOLM.        89 In a small, but well-lighted room, were a group of youth, surrounding a gaming-table. The half-emptied glaoses, the excited looks and words of the party petrayed the presence of evil spirits, who delight to frequent such scenes, to play their own fearful game with the souls of men. The issue of this game, by a singular turn, depended now between Malcolm and Thornton, while the others watched its progress with intense interest. With the- cun- ning of an experienced gambler, Thornton led on his victim, until he had staked all he pos- sessed of any value. Malcolm played with com- pressed lips and knitted brow, but so complete was his confidence in his friend, and so intense the excitement of his mind, that he took no notice of the artifice and tricks which were so surely robbing him of his property. But toward the close of the game, he looked up a moment and caught the unguarded movement of his antagonist, and read in the cunning and malice of his eye, how completely he had been his dupe. But it was too late, the game was over, and- he was robbed of all. 8*    <pb n="90-91" xml:id="VAC6650-00000047"/> 90     THE RUSSEL- FAMLY. Rising, with a pale cheek and flashing eye, he charged Thornton in plain terms of unfair- ness and intentional duplicity in the game. "I allow no gentleman to use such lan- guage to me, sir," said Thornton with a sneer, "much less shall I suffer it from you. The game was fairly played, sir." "You lie most basely, sir!" retorted Mal- colm, while his frame fairly shook with his concentrated passion. Thornton made no reply, but arose, and drawing his glove in a most insulting manner over Malcolm's face, he took the arm of one of the other young men and went out. Mal- colm followed a moment after, but as he was out of sight, he went to his own room. He immediately wrote a challenge, and sent it to Thornton, by a friend. He forgot, in this hour of passion, that in this act he had broken one of the well-known rules of the in- stitution. But as he became calmer, he paced his room all the night, agitated by the re- proaches of his conscience, and the fearful step he: had taken, the consequences of which   MALCOLM.        91 he now began to realize. Morning found him more. wretched than he had ever been before in his life. He hourly expected Thornton's' friend to arrange with his the preliminaries of the duel, but he came not. His suspense was becoming intolerable, when a note was put into his hand. Opening it hastily, he found a summons to appear be- fore the authorities of the Academy, to answer to a charge preferred against him by Cadet Louis Thornton. Malcolm now saw the preci- pice yawning before him, around which he had so long and idly played. His chosen friend had proved the viper which was now to sting him with its fatal fang. Thornton had in- closed the challenge, an unmistakable wit- ness of Malcolm's rash folly, to one of the officers. There was nothing in his trial that could extenuate or atone for his folly, and he was accordingly expelled, with disgrace, fromn the institution. He received, the blow with a de- gree of calmness, although his brain seemed on fire, and his heart bursting with its con- ,    *    <pb n="92-93" xml:id="VAC6650-00000048"/> 4 v 92   THE RUSSEL FAMLY. tending emotions. It was the first draught from the cup now placed to his lips, and he could realize how bitter it would become ere he had drained it. During the long agonizing night which followed his expulsion, his mind and heart were busy recalling the past, its sunny hours of comparative innocence, the, angel-hearts that had been sent to love and cheer him, over whose heaven of hope he had caused a cloud to settle forever. Then floated the vis- ion of his last and best-loved friend. Should Lizzie Grant, the innocent, the beautiful, ever share his disgrace? No! he could be brave to suffer alone. With a breaking heart he wrote to her, confessing all, and releasing her from an engagement to one no longer worthy. The letter from the authorities would reveal to his father the fatal truth: he could not in- sult him by a letter in his own hand. And now whither?  The world was before him. Home must be forsaken, for could he meet his noble father and beloved sisters, and see their heads bowed in grief and shame for him? He   MALCOLM.        93 who had been their pride and the hope of the future, could he show the " red hand," which had brought such agonizing sorrow to their hitherto peaceful home?  Ah! it would have brought no pang to that heart whose feeble throbbings are so soon to be stilled. No tear would have dimmed that eye, now wild with the delirium of fever. Better had it been for thee, erring one, hadst thou returned to thy father's house, that the tendrils of love might again have entwined about thy heart to lead thee back to peace, to happiness, and to God. But ere the message of sorrow from home reached him, he was a wretched wanderer, while miles of blue water were fast separating him from those who would have loved him through all. The sad news from West Point rankled only in the aching heart of the lovely watcher around the sick-bed at home, and in the bosom of her who had so freely lavished her early love upon the wanderer. Her hope seemed forever crushed, her life a dreary blank, A few years she wandered alone, quivering    <pb n="94-95" xml:id="VAC6650-00000049"/> "    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. before each blast of sorrow, then rested- where flowers may wave over her grave, but grief shall never again disturb the weary sleeper. \ . , *    IX. IK  fattheS    pttr's le ta X  a -HE midnight lamp burned dimly, }[ throwing a fitful light over the group in the sick-room. Colonel Russel was dying; the hot flush of the fever was gone, but there seemed little of life left in his- pallid cheek and sunken eye. The physician had exerted his utmost skill in vain, and now he had given his fatal message of the short- thess of his stay on earth, then departed to leave the stricken ones alone with their sorrow. They bent over the dying couch, clasping each a hand of their beloved father. Lottie was supported by the manly arm of Lieutenant Vernon. He had hastened to answer the message of grief from his betrothed one, who, until then, had bravely suffered alone. They bent together now over the wasted form of    <pb n="96-97" xml:id="VAC6650-00000050"/> 96     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. him who so lately had sank beneath the hand of the destroyer. He breathed so feebly that they feared life would depart iere they could have one look or word of recognition. But opening his eyes at last, he glanced anxiously over the group and around the room. He sighed deeply, for he missed the absent ones. It was a balm to Lottie's heart that his dying hour was not darkened, nor his last moments agonized by a knowledge of this last and most cruel blow. As if conscious of the shadowings of the dark cloud, he asked not for them, but addressed himself to the weeping ones around him. He was too feeble to speak much, and this in broken whispers. "I am ready to die-but I would that I could live for you, my dear children. God will care for you, my precious ones. My hope and trust is in Him alone. Your angel-mother will welcome me home to heaven. God has been gracious to me, serve Him faithfully and love the Saviour. His love lightens the dark valley of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil.. Tell Malcolm and Edward to love and   THE FATHER'S DEATH-BED.    '97 obey their mother's God, and to meet their parents in heaven.. "My soul is at p6ace. I would not live alway. Life is but a troubled dream, a tale of sorrow. Would that I had never misspent its precious hours! Follow the footsteps of your mother, my darlings, and may your last end be like hers." He was too weak to say more. With his last strength he joined the hands of Lottie and Alfred Vernon, and whispered his last blessing, committing to his care the helpless ones, now exposed to the cruel beatings of the storms of life, without a protector. The parting kiss of the loved ones was on his lips, their tears upon his cheek, their moans of anguish fell faintly upon" his ear, when the worn heart ceased its beatings and the icy hand of death closed the portals of life forever. To the departed soul has opened the mysteries of its eternal destiny. Thither we may not follow now, our mission is with the living still. Alfred Vernon prepared to fulfill the sacred 9 ( *    <pb n="98-99" xml:id="VAC6650-00000051"/> 98     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. duties bequeathed to him. Supporting the stricken ones with his sympathy and manly love, he breathed words of consolation and hope, while he assumed all those deeds of tenderness and duty to the dead which might cause their hearts, quivering with grief, to bleed afresh. A spot of quiet peaceful beauty was chosen, and there, side by side, were laid to rest the stilled hearts whicW had loved so well on earth. The evening zephyr shall whisper their requiem, the rustling leaf and waving flowers alone disturb the quiet of their sweet repose, until "the last trump" shall sound to awake the dead. Colonel Russel had a sister, Mrs. Sinclair, who resided in Baltimore. The children had never seen her, and knew but little about her, except that her marriage had been an unfor- tunate one, and that she was now a childless widow in affluent circumstances. But when a letter came filled with heartfelt and delicate sympathy, inviting them to come and find a home with her, they felt that a kind Prov- idence had already cared for them, and ac-   THE FATHER'S DEATH-BED.    99 cepted her gentle kindness. Lottie was to remain only until the time appointed for her marriage, for Alfred whispered "that it was his to love and protect his gentle one, and that their separation must be short." The scenes of their past joys, their beautiful home, where so many happy hours had flown unheeded by, the humble cot, where bitter tears had been wrung from anguished hearts, the sacred mound, where slept beloved ones- ah, it was hard to leave them all; again to try new and unwonted scenes. Lottie could but feel the desolateness of her lot, as with her little sister she visited each endeared spot, before seeking their home among strangers. The earnest cry of her heart was for entire submission, and for strength to endure all the will of God, while she acknowledged with gratitude that so many blessings were yet spared to her, and that she could still lean trustingly upon the Everlasting Arm. 'Tis sorrow brings us nearest heaven, from whence the bright beams of an immortal hope may lighten our dark despair.    <pb n="100-101" xml:id="VAC6650-00000052"/> 100     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. "No. 19 CarrToll-place," said Mr. Vernon to the coachman, as he handed Lottie and Nellie into a carriage at the landing at Bal- timore. The long ride through the brilliantly lighted streets, was pursued in silence, for each was busy with their own thoughts. Alfred had wished to take them to his own home, where as his cherished wife and sister, he might shield them, if possible, from all future sorrow. But he was too delicate to urge his wishes now, while he claimed it as his privilege to attend them to their future home. The coach drew   up before an old- fashioned mansion, shaded by a row of fine elms. The bell was answered by a young girl who, evidently expecting them, led the way to the parlor, saying, "Mrs. Sinclair will at- tend you immediately." She entered a few moments after. Nellie thought she had never seen any one so lovely. There was a shade of melancholy thrown like a vail over her ex- quisite features, while her dark, lustrous eyes, although marked by a peculiar expression,   THE FATHER'S DEATH-BED. were exceedingly beautiful. She advance rapidly toward Lottie, exclaiming: "Is this Charlotte?  How very like m sweet sister Lucia. You make me a chil again," she continued, her fine eyes fillin, with tears. "I was not older than Ellen when your dear mother became my sister, ana I loved her very dearly." "Ellen, my darling child, can you be happ2 with me? You are both very welcome t( my heart and home." She then received Mr. Vernon with a grace. ful courtesy, thanking him for his attentions to her brother and his family, during theii late afflictions. She invited him cordially to remain her guest, as long as suited his con- venience. "It is necessary that I return to Hartford, immediately, madam," replied Alfred, "but I hope to return soon to claim by bride, and-" "Not Ellen--indeed, my dear sir, I can not give them both up. Ellen is my child now," and Mrs. Sinclair drew Nellie to her affection- ately. "I shall take her from your influence 9*    <pb n="102-103" xml:id="VAC6650-00000053"/> 102    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. immediately," she added, playfully, and bid- ding him adieu, she left the apartment, lead- ing Nellie by the hand. Alfred drew Lottie closer to his side, and whispered, -"You will tell me, dearest, if you are not happy here?" "Certainly, Alfred, but, I believe I shall be very happy. My aunt seems a lovely woman, and I think I shall love her very much." "'The time will seem long before I can take you to my own home, dear Lottie. Be sure to write often, so that I may know you are well and happy." "My brothers, dear Alfred, will you inquire after them? Malcolm has never written since his terrible letter to Lizzie Grant, and Ed- ward, we have not heard from since we left our beautiful home." "I will do what I can, dear Lottie. But I fear Malcolm has already severed himself from us, while Edward may be nearing us every hour. Grieve not so sadly, dearest. Can you not trust -them with- God? Cast all your burden upon the .Lord, Lottie, for He has   THE FATHER'S DEATH-BED.   103 strengthened and supported you. But what of Nellie, dearest?" "I shall either place her in some school, or take her with us, or leave her here with Aunt, as she may prefer. I must do what will be for her happiness and best good, you know, dear Alfred, although I may be called to part from her for a time." "Remember my home is for you both, Lot- tie, if you think it best. But I must leave you now. May God protect and bless you, my own Lottie." He drew her fondly to his heart and pressed a kiss upon her forehead, then left her once more alone. In the quiet and peace of their new home, the summer glided happily away. The gen- tle sympathy and affection of Mrs. Sinclair healed the wounded hearts of the orphans, and although never forgetful of the loved and lost, they would have been happy but for the cloud of doubt and fear yet overshadowing the fate of their brothers. From them they had never heard one word since their father's    <pb n="104-105" xml:id="VAC6650-00000054"/> 104     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. first illness, and of their fate they were utterly ignorant. In the early autumn, Alfred Vernon came to claim his bride. Sorrow and affliction had purified her gentle spirit, imparting a new charm to her lovely character. There was an expression of calm trust and confiding love, as she stood up to plight her faith to the no- ble choice of her heart. In his love, she felt she had found again all that she had lost, and that she should stand no longer alone to buf- fet the waves of trouble. Mrs. Sinclair wept bitterly at parting with the lovely one, whose presence in her household had been as that of an angel. She had plead so earnestly that Nellie should be left with her, and the child seemed so happy, that Lottie had consented, although she felt it was severing the last link of their broken circle. She was well aware that Nellie's advantages with her Aunt would be superior to any she could afford her, and that her presence was essential to her happi- ness, for Aunt May's heart had been riven by peculiar and severe trial.   THE FATHER'S DEATH-BED.   105 "Nellie should visit her often," Aunt May assured her, and Lottie should ever be wel- come to her home. They parted with bitter tears, but no sad forebodings, for life had again opened only sunny paths. In the home of her husband, shielded by his fond love, the joy and light of his heart, the messenger of consolation and hope to many a weary one, struggling on life's journey, the days and years of Lottie's life shall pass lightly and peace- fully away. We leave thee, Lottie. May heaven's skies be bright above thee, and the dark storm of thy early life fade away in the dim past. When we return, may it be to find thee as peaceful as now,. fulfilling the \mission of woman, happy in the present and sustained by the immortal hopes of a glorious future. Turn we now an eye over the ocean-main to follow the path of another member of the broken family circle. \    <pb n="106-107" xml:id="VAC6650-00000055"/> X. ouluthb fa W   J 1 SHEN Edward left home, his father supplied him with funds amply sufficient for his expenses during the two years he had designed him to travel with his tutor. Professor Ben- ton was a young man of superior talents, cultivated mind, and firm principles. As yet he had no decidedly religious character. Al- though professing at all times a deep respect for the sacred rites of religion, he declined ac- cepting its claims as binding upon him at this early period of his life. Colonel Russel could hardly have chosen one better fitted to superintend the education of his son. His mind was of the highest or- der, and had been most carefully cultivated. Still thirsting for knowledge and a desire to   ,                   .   EDWARD.       107 travel, he had been induced to accept the proposition of his old friend, Colonel Russel. He could understand and appreciate Ed- ward's nature, and what he required; could sympathize with the glowing intensity of his thoughts, and the extremely sensitive cords, which grated so harshly when struck by a rude hand. But his judgment, too, was calm and decided, so that he preserved Edward from the dangers which threatened to destroy his health, and even his life, when the fever- ish activity of his mind would impair his still delicate body. For a time the letters from home were regular and frequent, and Edward pursued his travels and studies undisturbed by anxiety regarding the loved ones he had left. But at length a long time passed, and he received no letters. He read of accidents on land and sea, and supposing the mails might have been de- stroyed, he continued to write as usual to the home where, as he supposed, the happy family still dwelt, whom he had left but one short year ago. At each place where he failed of    <pb n="108-109" xml:id="VAC6650-00000056"/> 108    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. receiving the expected messages, he left orders to forward all his letters on to Rome. Then he rested quietly, ignorant of the cloud that had darkened and burst over his happy home. Although, at times, he felt deeply anxious, he suffered .no gloomy forebodings of evil to in- -terrupt his studies, nor the intense interest with which he mingled in the strange scenes and events of the various countries he visited. Thus after two years he landed at Rome, his health strengthened, and his mind stored with rich food, and prepared to enter with new zeal upon the lessons more particularly connected with his beautiful art. After pro- viding him with every facility for. his future comfort and education, Professor Benton took a reluctant leave of his pupil,'to whom he had become deeply attached, while he returned to England to remain another year before his re- turn home. Edward now entered with resistless ardor upon his favorite studies. He had stood al- most breathless before the works of the old masters, drinking in the spirit of their genius, I  .   EDWARD.        109 his whole being kindling with its deep emo- tions. But he felt that from his soul must come the imagery of its own conceptions. Thence should emanate such glorious imagin- ings of the beautiful, living and breathing from the marble, as should prove him no un- worthy disciple of the glorious old masters, at whose feet he had come to worship. His means were sufficient to furnish his; studio with the purest marbles, and to meet. his other expenses for one year. Still no. letters came from home. He would suffer in- tensely at times, when the misgivings of his, heart would whisper what might have been the fate of his loved ones. But hope still cheered him. The distance was so great, the means of conveyance so uncertain, and why should he fear that harm could befall hearts so gentle and guileless. He retired now to his studio where he lived amid the creations of his own genius. A rich drapery separated one portion. of -the room from the other, concealing a block of the finest and most beautiful marble. Here he 10    <pb n="110-111" xml:id="VAC6650-00000057"/> "O    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. came only when his soul was filled with the purest and loftiest conceptions. When the prose of life intruded to shade the delicate imagery that he felt was growing and expand- ing, within him, imbibing and feeding upon his very life, he would sculpture upon the coarser marbles, images, beautiful to the eyes of others, but failing to satisfy the desires of his own soul. There were days when no dis- cordant notes struck the sensitive harp; when its breathings filled his soul with harmony the sweetest and loftiest, then he secluded him- ,self from every object, often unmindful even of the demands of nature, to create upon the marble, devoted alone to this purpose, the in- spirations of his genius. And, as it daily grew before him, a creation of marvelous beauty, he was ready to worship the work of his own hands, the grand ideal of his soul, with a wild idolatry. He would stand unwearied before the marble, chiseling and molding the unshapen block, while the hot fever of his mind was consuming his very life-blood. No othpr eye profaned the sanctity   EDWARD.        1" of this altar, where were consecrated the powers of his body and' mind; ay, even the hopes of an immortal soul were fain to center in its cherished idol. Before it he forgot home and friends, he forgot his God, thinking only that this should be a fit offering at the shrine of his angel-mother. In the delirium of the fever of his soul, he believed her presence was near him to encour- age, to strengthen; that her soft eyes smiled approvingly from the cold marble before him. It was a wild fancy, but he knew, that, as his work advanced, and the embodiment of his idea became more perfect, more beautiful, it was warmed and made living by the actual presence of his/ mother. 'With awe did he then approach, for he believed that although her tenement of clay was moldering to dust, the immortal spirit could accept of another abiding-place, and meet and answer the long- ings of his soul, as when on earth., And when it was finished, and stood out before him, a beauteous image, the incarnation of the thought brought from  the very "passion-    <pb n="112-113" xml:id="VAC6650-00000058"/> "2    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. fountains" of his soul, he knelt before it and wept. The dream of his life was fulfilled, it was before him, and it filled him with a wild ecstacy. He saw not that sin had left its stain upon his soul and marred its beauty That God, before whom the works of men' hands are as nothing, He who has filled the universe with the foot-prints of wondrous beauty and power, has said to the sons of men "Give me thy heart." 'When this is withheld, He will in mercy snatch the idol away from the heart, and bring its broken bleeding tendrils to cling to Him, and He will give it new strength to grow for heaven. Thou hast forgotten thy God, Edward. Shrink not from the hand outstretched to take from thee thy cherished idol. He will, in great mercy, receive thee, when thou art ready to yield thy soul into His hand, and teach it to cry humbly, "Abba, Father." While Edward worked at his master-piece, he had sold the minor sculptures for a small sum, although they were remarkable for their beauty, to provide the necessary means for his   EDWARD.        113 support. The detail of business was entirely uncongenial to him, and he was totally unac- customed to it. - He thought of it only when his landlady, a coarse, passionate woman, de- manded the monthly payment of her bill. The day his statue was finished, while he knelt before it, she entered his room. Too much absorbed to notice even her heavy step, he was entirely unaware of her presence, until she rudely pushed aside the curtain, and in- truded her vulgar person into the place, so sacredly kept secluded from other eyes than his. She hesitated a moment, for the scene touched a chord even in her coarse soul. The statue, so wondrously beautiful, the frail youth kneeling before it, a bright flush tinging either sunken cheek, the hair shading his pale, damp brow, and his eyes full of a strange light. The sunlight shed a soft beam down from the statue, over the almost spirit- ual face, upturned to it, full of deep, ecstatic emotion. Mrs. Blake drew back; her better nature whispered this was no place for her. But a moment after, she glanced at her bill, 10*    <pb n="114-115" xml:id="VAC6650-00000059"/> "4    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. and then again upon the beautiful statue. Now, with a different spirit, she calculated its probable price, and a smile of deep cun- ning and avarice flitted over her hard features. Her plan was formed, it was a good one, and she prepared to execute it. Stepping forward she placed her hand roughly upon the should- der of the kneeling youth. The voice was harsh that first broke the stillness of the spot, where Edward's spirit had communed alone with its guardian-angel, the fancied presence of his lost mother. He sprang to his feet, his soul jarring harshly by so near a contact with the coarse and vulgar. "Why,are you here, madam?  You have no right to enter here." 4"No right in my own house, eh?  Pray, what right have you to curtain off a part of my house and fill it with your flummery, and then order me not to enter it?" "This room is mine, I believe" replied Ed- ward, more gently. "No, it ain't yours, when you don't pay for it. Here, sir, is your bill, and you must set-   EDWARD.       115 tle it or leave the room, and I 'll take charge of that pretty little piece of nonsense yonder." "Oh, you will not take that, dear madam! I can not give that up. I will pay you all, if you will but be patient." "Patient! I 've been that long enough. Just mind, Mr. Russel, every farthing of that bill must be paid this very night, or you will leave this house, and that thing there for my pay. I always mean exactly what I say," and Mrs. Blake stalked from the room, leav- ing Edward in an agony of fear and appre- hension. He roused himself to endeavor to procure the money. He had scarcely realized before how empty his room had become. The smaller sculptures were all gone. He had no marbles. He examined his wardrobe, it was scanty and well-worn. He could not borrow, for he was a stranger and friendless. All that weary day he paced the streets of the city, seeking some mode of raising the necessary amount. Once he had engaged himself as a private tutor for a mean sum, barely sufficient for his 4   )                 <pb n="116-117" xml:id="VAC6650-00000060"/> "6    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. present need. But when he demanded his salary in advance, he was turned away as a suspicious character. Thus was it all the day. It was agony for him to offer to pawn his soul for a paltry sum, to serve the coarse and vul- gar, from whom he instinctively shrank. But he felt strong to suffer all, that he might save the beautiful child of his genius, where was enshrined his holiest emotions. For how could he endure to see that exposed to the rude and unappreciative, its sanctity desecrated, its beauty degraded. Night brought a deeper darkness to his soul. It had ranged so long in the glowing fields- of fancy, been fed so long with the rich food of its own ideal, that this sudden contact with the real, the prose, of life, was indeed bitter and hard to be borne. He returned to his room, as the moon beamed in its full radi- ance. The acute sufferings, of the day, and the long and intense excitement of his mind, had wrought fearfully upon his frame. He sunk down before the beauteous statue, weak as a child.   EDWARD.       117 As he gazed upon it, a strange halo seemed to play over the head. He had seen it often before, but never so beautiful, so cheering. He had before believed his mother's spirit would visit him, living, and breathing in the cold marble, but now, it approached nearer. Her dear hand once more pushed the hair caressingly from his damp brow, the warm kiss was on his lips, and his aching, weary head, rested confidingly, hopefully, upon the loving heart. From out the cold marble shrine, nearer and nearer the spirit came. In the a cold moonlight, the statue was but a block of marble, the living essence, the grand idea was again his own. Again he felt it harmonizing and soothing his grieving soul. He arose to his feet as the landlady entered his room, accompanied by an officer. "Are you ready to pay my bill, Mr. Rus- sel?" "No, madam," he replied with a kind of desperate calmness. "Then you know I will do as I have said. You must leave this house, and that statue    <pb n="118-119" xml:id="VAC6650-00000061"/> "8    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. for my pay. If you refuse, this gentleman will give you a lodging-house better suited to your means, maybe." Edward made no reply to this coarse threat. He stood in a kind of stupor, while his statue, the work of so many weary hours, the center of so many fond, hopes, the fulfillment of the dream of his life, was borne away, he knew not whither. Left once more alone he glanced over the apartment, now desolate and lonely. A letter before unnoticed lay upon the table. He seized it with an eager hope. Perhaps here was the long-expected remittance, which should lift him from his present trouble, and restore the cherished work of his genius. Once more the cup is dashed from his lips, ere he quaffs the pleasing draught. The let- ter told only of sorrow, disease, and death. By a singular train, of circumstances, it has been delayed over three years, and he has but just learned the changes which time has brought to his peaceful home. As if the light of life had been suddenly and forever extin-   EDWARD.        119 guished, Edward sank to the floor in a death- like swoon. Ah, it was pitiful, thus to see the frail casket, within which sparkled the rarest jewel, crushed and broken, the sport of the blasts of adversity. When Edward revived sufficiently to real- ize any thing of the past, he had only the re- membrance that he must not stay there. He must seek another spot, where at least be might lie down and die. He tottered from the room, down into the street, out into the clear moonlight. He walked hurriedly, he cared not whither. His heart beat feebly, his soul was dark, hope extinguished. A heavy bur- den pressed him down to the very dust he' could not rise, he could not trust nor hope again. Wearily he paced the street, then laid his head down upon the cold pavement, and in his weakness, wished for an eternal rest from sorrow.    <pb n="120-121" xml:id="VAC6650-00000062"/> XI. W"-  HERE is a young man lying on - 1 the pavement near the street door, ] I husband."    '; lDrunk, I suppose." "So, I can not believe it. That is too beautiful a face to bespeak a besotted soul. Go out dear, with Walter, and see if he is not sick. What if it had been our own Walter? Do go, husband." Husband complied, went out, lifted the pale youth in his arms, and brought him to the house. "Walter, go for the doctor. Be quick; my son, for I think the young man has only swooned." Dear, motherly Mrs. Surrey, her kind heart beating only with love for all, bustled about)   NEW FRIENDS.      121 now bending an anxious face over the youth, lying so still and white on Walter's soft couch, and now asking Husband all manner of ques- tions as to the probable name and occupation of the poor young man. Notwithstanding her firm belief in his unfailing wisdom, Husband was entirely unable to enlighten the dark points. The Doctor came-may God bless all such doctors- his genial face a cordial in itself; he was evidently on good terms with the family, for he walked in, sans ceremonie. The sad and beautiful face of his patient touched a chord of sympathy in his kind heart. He thought he could read of sorrow in the delicate limbs, sunken cheeks, and transparent forehead. Surely this could be no street- brawler, he must be gifted with no ordinary mind, and he was sure he could not be of mean origin. After prescribing for him, he said: "You will nurse my patient, Mrs. Surrey?" "Shall I not, Husband?  You will not have him removed until he is quite well?" "No, not if your heart is warm enough for "    <pb n="122-123" xml:id="VAC6650-00000063"/> 122    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. us all, and you will not weary yourself too much." "Never fear; I should like to have some one be kind to our Walter if he should ever be so unfortunate as this poor young man." "Do you think the young man will live, Doctor?" asked Husband. "He is very ill. Some intense and long- continued excitement has worn upon his health; he is evidently of a feeble constitu- tion. He needs quiet, and most excellent care, and it may be he will rally again.' "I will attend to that, Doctor. lHe shall have the best of care. That is a very beauti- a ful face, Doctor. I wonder who he can be! Poor young man! he must have lain upon the col  vement all night. If Husband could only have seen him when he came home, but I suppose it was too early then. What if our Walter had been so unfortunate, Husband?" Mr. Surrey and his lady were of English origin, although they had resided for many years at Rome, engaged in some of the pur- suits which have so modernized the Eternal   NEW FRIENDS.      123 City. He was possessed of considerable wealth, and was a man of excellent attainments and undoubted piety. His wife possessed one of those happy natures, whose overflowing benev- olence creates a pure and genial atmosphere, beneath which stricken hearts delight to gather and rest. She loved her God with a simple trust and confidence, and rejoiced in the command, "Love thy neighbor as thyself." Nor did she ever hesitate, lest she might love her neighbor more than herself, although her hand might tremble or her head sink from very weariness. The never-failing incentive of her warm heart, while she ministered to the poor, the sick and perishing, was, "What if it was Husband or our Walter?" "Our Walter" was a fine lad of fourteen, who possessed, in a happy degree, 'the virtues of both parents. As their only child, he filled the whole horizon of love in their hearts, but as yet had seemed to escape the dangers that usually threaten the only son. He was a generous, high-minded youth, entirely content and happy in the circle of warm. loving hearts    <pb n="124-125" xml:id="VAC6650-00000064"/> 124 -   THE RUSSEL FAMLY. in his own home. He had developed an un- usual talent for music, which had been most assiduously cultivated by both parents. He had studied the grand works of the old masters of music, and, in a great degree im- bibed their spirit, so that his performances were not unworthy of them, nor their glorious genius.  So a kind Providence has given a safe and pleasant harbor to the frail little bark, so lately driven- at' the mercy of the winds and waves.. Edward slept peacefully upon a quiet couch; soft hands ministered to his wants, and gentle words answered his incoherent ravings. Disease made a child of him again; he would often take the hand of good Mrs. Surrey, call her' "Mother," ask pitifully why she had left him so long, and rain hot, scald- ing tears upon it. The good lady's heart yearned over him, and she would soothe him as one would soothe a moaning child, until he slept peacefully again, his wan cheek pressed closely to her hand, and the long lashes closed over the strange stare of his beautiful eye. ,                  ..   NEW FRIENDS.       125 "Poor young man," sighed the loving heart, "I will, indeed, be his mother, until he finds her again." One mild evening, Edward slept more quietly;. the good Doctor had ordered that he should be left alone and undisturbed, for his awakening would be to life and reason. So the curtains were drawn, that the beauti- ful starlight might shine into the room, and soft air play around the sick-bed. The gentle tread of the watcher was heard no more, he was alone. In another apartment, Walter sat before his piano, and the rich strains of Beethoven, with their strangely beautiful melody, floated out upon the still air. Like the faint echoes of the heavenly harps, it struck on the ear of the sleeping invalid, awaking him  with a thrill of pleasing emotions. He was too weak to think, he could only enjoy; he had no idea where he was, nor how he came there; the past was a blank, the future but little cared for. The glorious music filled Jhis soul, the cool air fanned his brow, he rested and was "i*    <pb n="126-127" xml:id="VAC6650-00000065"/> 126    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. happy. As the darkness grew deeper, he fell asleep again, and his slumber was gentle and refreshing. "Dear heart, he will soon be well again," and Mrs. Surrey drew the curtains and smoothed the pillow, the last office of love before seeking her own quiet rest. Edward gained rapidly, but he was long forbidden to speak of any thing but his present wants. As he lay in his quiet room, memory came back to him, slowly and painfully, until he realized all-the weary past, the helpless present, and the dreary future. Through the cloud he at last discerned the Hand that had led him along. His sufferings had not stilled the wild longings of his soul, and he felt that it could no longer be satisfied with the dreams and hopes he had indulged so long. "Have you a Bible, Mrs. Surrey?" he in- quired one day, as that kind lady sat by his bed-side. c Oh yes, dear Edward. Shall I read it to you?" "If you will," he replied feebly.   NEW FRIENDS.      127 She brought the Holy Word, and read of the, love of Jesus, that wondrous theme, so soothing to the bruised heart, so precious to the longing soul. Edward listened. Again he was back at his mother's knee, while the sacred Word fell upon his ear, and entered deep into his heart. Now he realized how far he had wandered and neglected to obey that mother's counsel to seek the rock of refuge. He had marked out his own path, set up an idol in his heart, before whose shrine he had wildly worshiped. His conscience reproached him loudly for his criminal neglect of duty, which had been so faithfully taught him. With deep penitence he hesitated, for still the wondrous love and mercy of Christ was read from his own holy Word: "Cast thy burder/upon the Lord, and he shall sustain thee." "Come unto me all ye that are weary and heavy laden, and I will give you rest." "Him that cometh unto me, I will in no- wise cast out." "Holy Father, I will that they also, whom    <pb n="128-129" xml:id="VAC6650-00000066"/> 128    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. thou has given me, be with me where I am, that they may behold my glory." Tears trickled through Edward's thin fingers as Mrs. Surrey closed the Bible. "Do you not love God's Word, Edward?" asked Mrs. Surrey, seriously. "My mother loved the Bible, and taught it to me; I wish to love it as she did." "'Where is you mother now, Edward?" ",She rests in heaven. She died when I was a boy of eleven years. She was my best and truest friend. Life has passed wearily  since they laid her to sleep in the cold grave. But my mother taught me of the Saviour and of heaven. I knew my duty when a child, for I can not remember when I was taught to say 'Our Father,' and told of Jesus' love." "And will you not love the Saviour, dear Edward?" "Teach me to love him, dear madam. I am a child in religion. Will you not pray with me?" The pious heart was full of warm desires, as she took the hand of the returning prodigal,   NEW FRIENDS.      129 to lead him back to his Father's house. The petition was simple, but the faith was all- comprehensive, the love earnest, that could take no denial. "Now, dear Edward, just let Jesus save you. Lean upon His arm, and let your eyes rest only upon Him. The fears, the sorrows and trials of life, will no longer harm your soul. His love will be your guide and your support through them all, and lighten even the dark valley of the shadow of death. Seek the Saviour now, will you, dear Edward?" " Yes, dear madam, I will try to trust. His love can reach even me, although my sins are vile, and my life has been one long act of dis- obedience an4 folly." "God is merciful to forgive us our sins. Trust him, Edward," and Mrs. Surrey left him alone. From the foot of the cross, his soul lifted a prayer of penitence and a plea for mercy. A peace, which he had never known before, rested upon his spirit. It was that " peace which passeth all understanding," with which    <pb n="130-131" xml:id="VAC6650-00000067"/> 130     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. a mighty God vouchsafes to receive His re- penting children. Now the time wore hap- pily away. Edward convalesced slowly, but his mind was at ease and his heart prepared to suffer all the will of God. The first day that he was permitted ta sit up, he made a solemn consecration of himself and all his powers to the service of his God. Well did he remember his first consecration, and the long, weary years of suffering it had brought upon him. But now, with the Holy Word for his guide and counselor, he was led to abhor himself, to resign all the idols of his heart, and accept the mercy of Christ as the only grounds of his hope. Henceforth, the powers of his mind, the energies of his renewed life, and the fruits of his genius, should be con- secrated a willing and unreserved offering upon the altar of his God. The dream  of his early life was all forgotten. He had no wish to know  the fate of his beautiful statue, that would but recall the agony of the past. This was the language of his soul, as it   NEW  FRIENDS.        131 parted its earth-moorings to plume its flight for heaven: "I 'll waste no more in idle dreams the precious hours of life, I wake to know my better self, to arm me for the strife: To invoke my noble purposes, abandoned all too long, Henceforth to holier themes I pledge myself, my lyre, my song. Oh still I know within my heart, upon the spirit's shrine, Still unprofaned by evil, burns the one pure spark divine, Which God hath kindled in us all; then be it mine to tend With purer thoughts and watchful care, the light that lamp may lend. I shut my eyes in grief and shame upon the dreary past, My heart and soul pored recklessly on dreams that could not last. The bark has drifted down the stream, at will of wind and wave, An idle, light, and worthless thing, that none had cared to save. Henceforth the tiller Truth shall hold and steer as conscience tells, And I will brave the storms of life, though wild the ocean swells. I know my soul is strong and high, if once I give it sway, I feel a glorious power within, though light I seem and gay. Oh laggard soul! unclose thine eyes. No more in luxury soft    <pb n="132-133" xml:id="VAC6650-00000068"/> 132      THE RUSSEL FAMLY. Of joy ideal, waste thyself Awake and soar aloft!  Unfurl this hour thy falcon-wing, fix on the skies thy sight, Then burst the thrall that binds thee down, prepare thy destined flight." 1    XII. HE twilight is fast setting over one of the vast prairies in the Far West. The night-wind moves over the tall yielding grass and flowers with a gen- tle whisper, which alone breaks the dread silence. The prairie rolls away like a vast emnerald sea, dotted with the most magnifi- cent flowers, until it seems a vast illimitable space. The stillness of the night, and the vast prairie, bathed in the light of the rising moon, would fill the soul with a sense of utter loneliness, if it could not acknowledge the omnipresence of God, and trace his footsteps even here. A single horseman appears upon a distant ridge, riding slowly along, now hidden, and then appearing again as he follows the path 12    <pb n="134-135" xml:id="VAC6650-00000069"/> 134    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. winding  over -the rolling prairie. He is mounted upon a superb horse, and is com- pletely armed. A rifle is slung to his saddle, pistols and a polished dagger occupy his belt. His dress consists of black leggins, a blouse open to the belt, displaying a shirt of finer material, and moccasins, elaborately adorned with an embroidery of beads and colored porcupine quills. A heavy beard covers the lower part of his face, while a broad sombrero shades completely the forehead and eyes. ' But as he raises his hat and the cool wind lifts the dark masses of hair from his fore- head, Memory starts to recognize the noble boy of the old fort, the youth of promise at West Point in the man before her. Time has not marked the white brow, nor silvered the raven hair. The form is still erect and manly, for scarce twenty-six winters have passed over him. But in the lines about the mouth, in the deep melancholy eye, we read an age of suffering, a wild abandonment to passion, and a fixed despair. Remorse has fed upon his  ,   THE ENEMY.       135 soul, and driven it to darker deeds to satiate its fierce cravings. This is an hour to still the storm of passion, to awaken the better nature, to listen to the' voices that speak to the spirit of man from each flower and blade of grass, or from the rolling spheres above him.  And Malcolm listens. His very soul loathes the husks upon which it has been fed so long, and once more utters its cry unchecked. Again is placed before him life or death, and once more he is permitted to choose. Bow thy soul, oh thou who art still beloved. Bring it with all its guilty stains to the fountain opened, for you may yet wash and be clean. A speck appears far off in the distance. Malcolm directs a piercing eye forward. The voice of mercy falls unheeded upon his soul. He replaces his hat, quickens the pace of his horse, examines his pistols, and rides forward. As he approached nearer he discovered it was a man, mounted, and riding leisurely along. He is but illy mounted and armed, apparently only as a traveler. Malcolm rides steadily to    <pb n="136" xml:id="VAC6650-00000070"/> 136    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. O meet him, his piercing eye fixed upon his countenance, his brow darkened, and his lips firmly compressed. He reined his horse in the very path, drew, and charged his pistol, and calmly awaited the traveler's approach. The stranger stopped and fixed a startled eye upon the stern man before him. Malcolm leaped from the saddle, and grasping the bri- dle of the other, threw off his hat and stood face to face with Louis Thornton. The poor craven paled before the dark, revengeful glare of the resolute eye, now pierc- ing into his very soul. "' Dismount, Louis Thornton!" The cold steel pressed against his forehead; trembling, he obeyed. A strong hand grasped the cringing form, which bent and knelt ab- jectly beneath it. The upturned face was white with fear, as he exclaimed: "Oh, for God's sake have mercy, Russell Do riot kill me here!" "For many a long weary year have I tracked your path, Louis Thornton, and longed for this day, when I could wreak on your black      <pb n="Illustration" xml:id="VAC6650-00000071"/> THE ENCOUNTER ON THE PRAIRIE Page 136.      <pb n="-137" xml:id="VAC6650-00000072"/>   THE ENEMY.      137 soul, the anguish you have brought on mine. Now you are in my power and you shall die!" The voice that pronounced his doom was fearful in its terrible calmness. "a Oh, say not so, Russel, I entreat of you. Spare my life! Think of the anguish you will bring upon my mother and sisters, who are dependent upon me." "Louis Thornton, it is you that have brought fearful desolation upon hearts as loving as ever throbbed for man'. You, who have dragged my noble Father to his grave in sorrow. You have sent bitter anguish to my gentle sister and brother; and you, foul fiend, have blighted the heaven of a guileless heart, and sent it moaning to rest in the cold grave. You have blasted my life, when it opened full of brightest prospects; taught me to destroy my own soul, and now, Thbrnton, for all this, you shall die. I shall delight to see your false soul depart, sent by my hand on its long journey. And when the screaming vulture feeds upon your craven heart, I shall rest content. My sweetest thought shall be that you feel the 12*    <pb n="138-139" xml:id="VAC6650-00000073"/> 138    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. bitterness of the anguish you have caused me to suffer these many weary years." The face bent over the prostrate wretch was terrible, darkened, as it was, by the foul spirit, Revenge. Almost paralyzed with fear, Thornton clasped Malcolm about the knees, and wept and moaned, while he plead pite- ously for life. "Oh, Russel, do not murder me! Forgive the past, I could not know the wrong I did you! Be merciful and forgive! I will serve you like a slave, Russel, if you will spare my life." "False wretch, say no more. You have just ten minutes longer to live. Do what you can to prepare for death in that time, then you shall try the realities of your philosophy, with which you once boasted you could die calmly."      ' Malcolm bound a handkerchief closely over the eyes of his victim, pressed the pistol against his forehead, took out his watch, and calmly counted the minutes, unmoved by the frantic cries and moans of his enemy. The   THE ENEMY.       139 appointed moment has arrived-Malcolm breathes faster as he places his finger on the trigger. A white hand is stretched out to save his soul from this dire sin of murder. A gentle eye looks tearfully, reproachfully, and points to the dreadful consequences of his sin. Overcome he listens to the voice of mercy that whispers of hop6 even for him. His hand ralaxes, the pistol is replaced i&amp; his belt, he mounts his horse, and is out of sight in a moment. From   the depths of his soul he could but cry, "Oh God, I thank thee that this man's blood stains not my hand, and that hope still remains for me." In the agony of his fear, Thornton could not believe that Malcolm really intended to spare his life. But as he arose and trem- blingly unbound his eyes, he looked cautiously around and found himself alone. A smile once more lit his face, while he muttered: "Poor fool! I knew he dared not kill me." He rode away rapidly, casting a furtive glance    <pb n="140-141" xml:id="VAC6650-00000074"/> "O    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. backward, to be sure he was not marked by a concealed foe.     ' But that God, whose name he had dishon- ored,' and whose being he had denied, followed his traqk with the arm of the Avenger. Far out on the green prairie, his bones whiten beneath the sun, while his gory scalp has long since swung in the wild war-dance of the savage.    XIII. -  '  flint gg1vtgit it IRS. SINCLAIR, with whom Ellen had found a home, was a person of extremely nervous constitution, a strong imagination, and poetic tem- perament. Her nature had been suffered to mature under circumstances unfavorable to' the development of a symmetrical character. Her life she would fain have made such a dream of beauty as her glowing fancy could easily paint. But she was to suffer much of the real, although she clung through life to her dreams of romance, and phantoms of hope. Her early marriage was contrary to the wishes of her parents, and, as is usually the case, it was a most unfortunate one. Her husband, a coarse, brutal man, watched her with the cruel eye of jealousy, while he in-    <pb n="142-143" xml:id="VAC6650-00000075"/> "2     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. vented every means of annoyance that a self- ish, tyrannical nature could suggest. Like a sensitive-plant, she drew back within herself those delicate tendrils, which, could they have found a firm support, would have developed a. healthier and more perfect flower. After her husband's death, his sister, a wid- owed lady, made her home with her for nearly three years. She was a Roman Catholic,-a sincere believer in all the dogmas and errors of that faith, and zealous for its advancement. Mrs. Sinclair found in her nature the conge- nial friend, she had long sought, while the beauty and mysteries of this religion of the senses attracted and fascinated her.  Father Le Fevre visited her often, eager to receive this new daughter into the church, for the value of her soul was greatly enhanced by the large property of which she was the sole heir. The serpent approached slowly: now arch- ing his beautiful neck, now raising his crested head, now displaying his brilliant eyes, but the deadly fang was kept concealed until long after she was bound in his fatal coil.   THE NUNNERY.       143 Every art was tried that learning could sug- gest or cunning devise. A fearful game was played with her intense nature, until, her senses captivated, her romantic dreams satis- fied, she yielded her soul to the charming but fatal delusion, and became one of the most devoted of Rome's daughters. Lottie knew  of this change in her aunt from her father, but she little realized that any danger could accrue from it to Nellie, else she could never have left her to be tempted. Mrs. Sinclair never intruded her views and opinions, and Lottie knew but little of the de- lusive power of that religion, whose beautiful exterior covers "a whited sepulcher, full of dead men's bones ;" and so Nellie, the sunny- hearted, susceptible child, was left to expand her undeveloped nature amid the deleterious influences of a false religion. She was placed in the c Nunnery of the Sacred Heart," to attend her studies. Mrs. Sinclair loved her with all the intensity of her nature, and lavished every advantage upon her that affection could devise, or wealth pro-    <pb n="144-145" xml:id="VAC6650-00000076"/> "4    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. cure, to educate her and make her life happy Nelhe was gifted with a brilliant mind, and soon made rapid advancement in her studies, while she won all hearts by her loving, earnest nature. In a handsomely furnished apartment of the "priest's house," Father Le Fevre sat in close consultation with another of the sons of the church. Father Le Fevre is a remarkable man, whose person would command reverence and confidence, but that an occasional gleam of a hard, avaricious spirit would overspread his placid face and startle one into the be- lief that even he could be a hypocrite. His brother in the craft is a feeble man, a mere tool in the hands of his superiors, but a de- voted and fanatical son of the church. We are likely to lose the wealth of Mrs. Sinclair, brother," said the latter in a confi- dential tone. "Why so?" "She has lately adopted an orphan niece, and intends, as she told Sister Aguace, to   /         THE NUNNERY.       145 make her the sole heir of her property, with some slight exceptions." "  But this is no reason why we should lose it, brother." Father Le Fevre lost none of his complacency at this announcement. It was no new game to play, he could easily do it again.' "We must bring this lamb into, the fold, also. I will instruct Sister Agnace to begin her education early. What is her age?" "A mere child, I should suppose. She canm not have seen more than twelve summers.. She is a fair child, with laughing eyes andL sunny curls." "The more acceptable will be her sacrifice, then. Now, brother, we might restore this child to the church, but we must win her back. I am  confessor to Mrs. Sinclair, and can easily manage her, while you must stand ready to act any part we may require. The church has need of the child and the property, and it shall have them." "But what if she refuse to be taught? What if the lessons are in vain, and the Aunt 13    <pb n="146-147" xml:id="VAC6650-00000077"/> "6    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. should die and place her property beyond her reach?" Father Le Fevre's brow darkened and the hard look gleamed into his eyes. , "It is enough, brother. The church has need of them, and mark me well, she shall have them. Now go to Sister Agnace and tell her I wish to see her immediately." The obedient brother went as he was de- sired to the convent, whither he was soon followed by Father Le Fevre. "Sister Agnace, you have a little daugh- ter here under your charge, the niece of our daughter, Mrs. Sinclair?" "Yes, father, a beautiful sunny-hearted child of thirteen years. ' What is your will of her, father?" "' Does she remain here all the time?" "No, father, she visits her Aunt each week and spends each Saturday and Sabbath with her." "This must not be, daughter. Win the child's love, and induce her to remain here contented. Let her Aunt visit her as often   THE NUNNERY.       147 as she wishes, but do not allow her to be long from your influence. That child must be de- voted to the church, and I shall expect you to educate her for it. You know the way. Be gentle, winning, and loving. It will be a sweet sacrifice to offer to God. Besides, daughter, her property--the church has need of it. y You understand?" Yes, Sister Agnace understood that signifi- cant look, understood her duty, and she was ready to perform it with a willing heart, for Rome had no tool more willing to serve her than that meek-browed, gentle woman, the lady-superior of the convent. The plot was laid, and now the game begins. Her studies were chosen to suit the poetry of the life she led. She saw nothing of open sin, scarcely of sorrow, save when the sisters bowed their heads in grief before the image of the Saviour, or performed their painful penance. Their conversation was, to her ardent temperament, heavenly, it was so pure and holy, while the consecration of so many lovely ones, seemed a beautiful act of faith. Her thoughts and feel-    <pb n="148-149" xml:id="VAC6650-00000078"/> "8    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. ings, her hopes and desires were soon taught to flow into one channel. She saw nothing of the world outside, which she was made to be- lieve one vast theater of sin and guilt, from, which, and the sorrow she had already begun to experience, she was now securely sheltered. The gentle teachings of Sister Agnace, the fond caresses of the lovely sisters, the air of - peace and love shed over every thing around her convent-home, the fervent blessing of the holy Father Le Fevre, all served to charm her fancy and captivate her heart. And so four years passed away like a happy dream. In that time she had often visited Lottie, but as little was said by either on that subject, Lottie knew nothing of the dangers which threatened the soul of her sister. She could only know that Nelhe had fulfilled all the promise of her childhood, and was bloom- ing into a lovely maiden, without losing aught of her artless grace and guileless love. She rejoiced that God had favored her with such advantages, and guided her path when He had taken both their parents to Himself.   THE NUNNERY.      149 Nellie always returned to her studies, and the charmed circle in which she moved, with a keen relish. As yet, the world had shown but one sunny period-her early childhood; and now, when all who had made her life happy were scattered and gone, a cloud rested over even that period, and she could only remem- ber the wave of, sorrow, which had deprived her of home and its loved ones. She returned the love of all around her with earnest warmth, while her plastic nature was thus the more easily molded. Her Aunt knew what would be the result of all this, but she was controlled by the cunning hand of the art- ful Father Le Fevre, and dared to think and act only as he directed. Her influence was alsc brought to bear in the same direction, and hei hand aided in forging the beautiful chain, de- signed to bind another in its galling bonds An incident occurring about this time, ex- erted a decisive influence upon Ellen's im- pressible mind.  She had just completed her seventeenth year when Louise Merton, her chosen friend 13*    <pb n="150-151" xml:id="VAC6650-00000079"/> 150    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. having finished her novitiate, prepared for the imposing ceremonies attendant upon taking the vail. Nellie often conversed seriously with her upon the subject, before the appointed day arrived. She would ask: "Why do you take this step, dear Louise? You are beautiful and accomplished, and have wealth at your command." "True, Ellen, but why should I desire to mingle longer in scenes that are abhorrent to my soul? I am older than you, and life has been so often agonized, that' I have hoped and prayed for death. Here I see no more of sin, no more of sorrow, for death has no terror here. He is but the angel bidden to open the portals of heaven, that the freed soul may enter. The folds of his dark robe are but the little clouds, above which are beaming in full radiance, the glories of eternity. It will be sweet, Ellen, to offer such a sacrifice to my God, to give up the baubles of life, and, per- form my mission on earth, like the Saviour, to go about doing good.'  "But, Louise, life must have a brighter   TILi bi' - U N A X. . B .- XJkL/ side. How can you resign it all now, in your early youth?" "The blessed saints sacrificed far: more than I am able to, and suffered the severest pen- ances.; but, oh, to be favored as they were, would more than compensate - for any loss or suffering. I can yield all I possess, and all I am, to be like them, to suffer like them, and to live and die like them." The beautiful dupe of a false religion thus sustains her fainting soul with its vain dreams and illusive hopes, led on by the smooth flat- teries of a designing priesthood. The evening appointed for the ceremony arrived. Elleir had seen but little of her friend during the past week, but Sister Agnace assured her, she was preparing to offer a more perfect sacrifice, by fasting and penance. That the soul must be pure when it became the bride9 of heaven. She repaired to the cathedral at an early hour, accompanied by her Aunt. It was dimly lighted by an open sash near the altar, and as the single ray glanced: ove .the :full-length    <pb n="152-153" xml:id="VAC6650-00000080"/> 152     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. portraits of the saints on either side, it caused them to stand out with a startling, life-like effect. The organ breathed forth a dirge-like tone, filling the soul with a strange awe. Ellen felt a chill creep over her, as she entered the silent room, and kneeled beside her Aunt, before the shrine of the Holy Virgin. She seemed no longer on earth, but transported to some other sphere, where she was surrounded by the company of saints, standing there so silent, their hands crossed over their pure breasts, and their soft eyes turned meekly toward heaven. Her heart subdued, shel be- lieved that she worshiped God acceptably, although bowing before an image made with men's hands. So completely was she fascin- ated, while the dangerous coil wound closer about her soul. The bell of the cathedral pealed forth a solemn tone, the music swelled to a- fuller harmony, as the sisters entered, and silently took their places. It was a strange sight. Many of them  were beautiful as they stood there beneath the mysterious light, clothed in   THE NUNNERY.       153 their long white robes and vails, their -eyes raised in silent prayer. The grand music swelled out with a fuller richness, a loud anthem  of joy and praise as the victim en- tered. Nellie started, for Louise looked so ethereal. in her beauty, so deathly was her pale brow, and cold the gaze of her fixed eye. She knelt upon a slightly-raised platform. Again the music sank to a low dirge, thrilling the heart with an undefinable emotion. Three sisters approached nearer, bearing torches, another the sacred emblems. The ceremony proceeded with the usual number of prayers and forms, and then the bride was arrayed for her terrible fate.. The rich robes were laid- aside forever, the dress of the order adjusted, the beautiful hair cut closely to the head, a white handker- chief bound closely over the pale brow, and the long vail-that fatal covering to a heart I  breaking with its blasted hopes, and trembling for its miserable futurity-was: thrown ovex the bowed head. The mournful ceremonies ended, the sisters    <pb n="154-155" xml:id="VAC6650-00000081"/> JLDy    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. filed out, leading their newly-consecrated one by 'the hand. As she passed, Ellen, whose whole soul had thrilled with new and con- tending emotions, felt that Louise had chosen the better part, that it was indeed a high and holy privilege to forsake the world and become a bride of heaven, to enter into a closer com- munion with saints and angels, to live with- out sin, and to do good. '"Dear Aunt May," she whispered, when they were alone, " how beautiful it is to be- come separate from the world, and live entirely consecrated to heaven." "Yes, darling. Would that I had taken the step, which the lovely Louise has just taken, when I was of her age. I should have escaped much suffering, and better fulfilled my destiny." "But can you not consecrate yourself even now, Aunt May?" "I must not, dearest, I must live in the world for you. You will need a protector and friend for many years." "But, dear Aunt May," Nellie's voice sank   THE- NUNNERY.-     155 to the lowest whisper, for her heart almost stood still, "why may I not forsake the world also, and live for heaven?" "How can I give you up, my darling child? My own Ellen, you have been the only hope and delight of my wretched life. To yield you up, would be to resign all of joy or peace that I ever knew. I had fondly hoped-but if it must be so, I will soon join you. I can not live in the world without you. To join your sacrifice shall be my holy duty." Did Aunt May observe the shadow of Fathet Le Fevre coming near them? And did it move over her heart, hushing the voice of nature, and bidding it obey the will of the church? From this hour Aunt May stilled her heart yearning over its loved one, and aided to strew the hidden path with flowers. Sister Agnace and the rest of the band united by soft en- treaty and gentle love, to win the beautiful maiden to tread their chosen way.  The tempted heart saw not the poison lying deep    <pb n="156-157" xml:id="VAC6650-00000082"/> 156    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. within the cup; it grasped- the bowl with a willing hand and pressed the sparkling draught to her lips. Ellen- has entered upon her novitiate.   XIV. Mb   tutor. HEN Edward had fully recovered his health, his heart turned with earnest longings toward his na- tive home. But he felt that he was deeply indebted to the kind hearts that had received him as from the very brink of the grave, watched over and cared for him, and above all, had taught him to seek his long-neglected Saviour; and that he must in some manner repay them for their deeds of love. One day while sitting with the family, Mr. Surrey asked him about his plans after his complete recovery. "I wish, first of all, to repay you for your kind care to me, sir, but I have not yet con- cluded what would be the best way of accom- plishing that end." "    <pb n="158-159" xml:id="VAC6650-00000083"/> 158    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. "You need not trouble yourself about that, Mr. Russel. We have done for you only what our Saviour has commanded us to do for all in His name. If we have been the means of restoring you to life and hope, He will'reward us, we ask no other." "No, Edward," chimed in the kind Mrs. Surrey. "Do for others as we have done for you, if you have the opportunity, aiyd we will rejoice, if but one more faint heart is refreshed through our influence. Providence may so order it that our Walter may suffer as you have, then I hope a gentle hand may be found read! to minister to him." "I have thought," Mr. Surrey resumed, "if you would like to undertake the education of my son, Walter, that I should be very much pleased. As yet, his education has been al- most entirely neglected, except in music. My plan would be, that you should remain with us the remainder of the year as his tutor, and when you return to America, take him with you. His mother and I, will soon follow. "I have watched the progress of your coun-   THiE TUTOIR.      IOy try with the deepest interest for many years, and would choose it above all others for my home, where we might spend the remainder of our lives peacefully, and near our son, amid Republican principles and Christian influence. I am convinced that in this country, we stand upon a terrible volcano, ready at any moment to burst out beneath us, and drag us down to destruction. I wish, as soon as possible, to flee far from it. "Poor, down-trodden Italy! The curse of God rests upon her classic hills and sunny plains. The besom of destruction will surely, sooner or later, sweep over this devoted coun- try, and great and terrible will be its fall. But what do you think of my plan, Mr. Russel?" "I accept it most thankfully. My heart yearns for home and its loved ones, but I shall be most happy to remain and do all for Wal-. ter that I could do for a dear brother. And I hope I may prove to you a grateful and affec- tionate son." "Enough then, Mr. Russel, you may enter upon your duties as soon as you are fully re-    <pb n="160-161" xml:id="VAC6650-00000084"/> 160    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. covered ;" and he concluded by offering him a - liberal salary. And so, for weeks and months, Edward faithfully led his pupil along :the paths of knowledge, now smoothing every rugged way, and now instilling his own lofty sentiments into Walter's plastic mind. And had he no longings for his beautiful art he had lately loved so well.? Often, but with a chastened desire. His eye was serene, his brow uncloud- ed, for he was now content to wait in the path of duty. But God's hand has been pre- paring the way, and He orders all things for good to those who love Him. While Edward. lay on Walter's couch, stricken by disease, his beautiful statue was placed in one of the. public galleries and of- fered for sale, at a price far below its real value, but exceeding by many hundreds the claim of Mrs. Blake. Crowds gathered about it, to admire its wonderful beauty, and to question as to the unknown artist whose lofty genius had conceived and executed so marvel- ous an embodiment.   THE TUTOR.       161 Among the number were a Mr. Lincoln and his daughter Florence, a fair girl of sixteen. Day after day she stood before the statue, drinking in the rich inspiration of genius, un- til the desire to possess it, became irresisti- ble. As her every wish was gratified, the beauteous statue was purchased and accom- panied them to their home in Washington. Here it attracted universal attention and ad- miration, while all were curious to unravel the mystery attached to it. Mr. Lincoln could only reply that he had bought it of a coarse, rough woman, in Italy, who refused to give any explanation, except that it belonged to an American youth, and that it had been seized for debt. She seemed particularly anxious to dispose of it quickly, at the highest possible rate. But Florence could not rest satisfied. She exaimined the statue most, minutely, hoping to find some clew to the mystery. At length, she thought she discovered in the folds of the drapery, as it fell away from the beautiful foot, a loosened portion of the marble. "*    <pb n="162-163" xml:id="VAC6650-00000085"/> 162    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. "Oh, papa!" she exclaimed, "I have found it!" "Found what, Floy? "The secret of my beautiful statue, papa," and she pointed the place to her father. With a small penknife, he removed the light substance from the marble, and there, traced in delicate lines, found- ," To MY MOTHER.  EDWARD RUSSEL." Florence was almost wild with delight, at the discovery, and her heart was filled with the thousand plans she had formed for the relief of the unknown artist. "Now, papa, you will write to poor Mr. Russel, won't you? Perhaps he may be in want. Poor fellow, to be obliged to sell this beautiful statue for so paltry a sum. ,You will write to :him, papa?" "Why, Flora, I have but little hope that a letter -can reach him now,. He may no longer be in Italy."  "Well then, dear papa,:, advertise. for his   THE TUTOR.       163 friends; will you? Perhaps, that ,may do some good." "Why, Flora, dear, why have you taken such a deep interest in this, unknown artist? He may neither be young nor handsome ;" and the fond father glanced mischievously down into the blushing face of his daughter. "I do not know indeed, papa, but I never stand before this statue, without feeling a sympathy for the artist, a premonition, if you like, that he needs sympathy and aid. At all events, papa, if he is an American, his genius should be encouraged for the sake of our country. Just to please me, papa, try to discover who he is." O"Well, you must .be gratified, I ppose. We will advertise and endeavor t.- d his friends."  Accordingly, the following advertisement appeared in nearly all the papers:. " If Edward Russel, an American artist, formerly residing at. Rome, or .any of .his friends' are now sin this -country, they will    <pb n="164-165" xml:id="VAC6650-00000086"/> 164     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. please communicate with the stibscriber at Washington, D. C. "F. J. LINCOLN." Lottie read this startling advertisement in her quiet home. By a strange fatality no letters had reached Edward, except the one received just before his illness. A few of his own had reached their former home where they had remained uncalled for. This, then, ,was the first intelligence she had received of her brother for three long, weary years. She thanked God that she might hope he was yet alive, while she immediately replied to the advertisement by the following letter: "HARTFORD, August 9th, 18-. "F. J. LINCOLN, ESQ. "SIR- I have just read 'your late adver- tisement. Edward Russel is my brother; he left home for Europe five years since, with his tutor, Professor Benton of this city, intending to travel and pursue his studies for four years. A short time afterward, we had the misfortune to lose our property in Virgidia; my father's   death occurring soon after, we left our former home for this city: since that time, we have heard nothing of my brother. If you can communicate with us in relation to him, you will bestow the greatest happiness on hearts who hiave long since mourned him as dead. "Please address c "MRs. ALFRED VERNON, Hartford." Mr. Lincoln read the letter to his daughter, and said: "There, Floy, you see we know but little more about your artist than before, after all." "Yes, Papa, but we have only commenced yet. I will write to this sweet Mrs. Vernon, and tell her what a splendid genius her brother is; and she will write to him, and then he wif come home and make us-.them, I mean-all happy again. And then, Papa, you will en- courage him to create other beautiful statues, and then people will admire them, his name will become known, and our government will employ him on some great work of art for his country." t    <pb n="166-167" xml:id="VAC6650-00000087"/> 166'    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. Florence could not touch a more agreeable chord than that of " our country," she well knew, for Mr. Lincoln was an ardent patriot. So, although Papa laughed at her fine air- castle, he indulged her in her whims, for in truth his own heart had become enlisted in the fate of the unknown artist, and he was always ready to encourage the sons of genius in his own land. Letters were written to Hartford, and from thence to Rome. Mr. Lincoln also wrote to "Edward Russel, American artist at Rome." These messengers of hope came to the pale- browed tutor a few weeks after he had com- menced the duties of his new station, dis- pelling the cloud which had apparently settled over his future career. Lottie wrote of the bitter past, marked by suffering and sorrow; of their happy present, clouded only by the fears for Malcolm. She told of the bright, beautiful Nellie, and her happy home; and finally, she wrote of her own happy circle, where loving hearts would rejoice to welcome home the beloved wanderer.   THE TUTOR.       167 Mr. Lincoln's letter told of the fate of his beautiful statue, its present admiring pos- sessor, and he encouraged him to commence some great national work, while he assured him of his constant assistance, should he desire it. Edward offered the grateful adora- tion of his heart to that God who had thus led him through the cloud out where the bright sunshine lighted his future path. The happy communion with the loved ones was now unbroken, while he devoted the inspira- tions of his lofty genius in creating a work of new and exquisite beauty.  But now  he wrought with a chastened heart, animated by higher hopes and holier motives. No wild idolatry mingled with the purpose of his soul, even when the marble, shapen by his hand, became a grand idea of the beautiful. .    <pb n="168-169" xml:id="VAC6650-00000088"/> XV. xgv ELLIE had nearly finished the first year of her novitiate, when her Aunt May was suddenly taken very ill. She immediately desired that Nellie should be permitted to watch by her sick-bed. Nel- lie hastened to her, and was shocked to observe what ravages the fatal disease had already wrought upon her Aunt's slender frame. The sunken cheek was tinged with a bright, hectic flush, while her eye shone with an unnatural brilliancy. Nellie took the hot hand of her Aunt, and bathed it with tears, while she asked, why she had not sent for her before? "I dared not, my child. Nellie, I am afraid I am dying-and, oh, how I fear to die! It must not-can not be. Life is too bright, too beautiful, I can not give it up now, and H   am unprepared to meet death. Can you not pray with me, my darling child?" ' Oh, do .not talk so, dear Aunt May., I hope you are not dying. Shall I not call Father Le Fevre to pray with you?" "No, Nellie," Aunt May whispered, with a shudder. "I do not wish to see him now- never again. I wish to see you alone. Are we quite alone, darling?" and she glanced nervously at the door. Nellie opened it, and looked out into the hall, they were quite alone. She closed the door, drew the curtains, and seated herself once more beside her Aunt's bed. "Nellie, bend closer to me, I must nor be heard. I know that I am dying, Nellie, and I have done you such a wrong I can not die, I can not be at peace until I save you from the snare which I have helped to spread for your soul. Flee from that, convent, darling, they are ensnaring and destroying your soul, as they have mine. That is a fearful place; it is a terrible religion, and you will only know it, when it is too late if you do not escape 15    <pb n="170-171" xml:id="VAC6650-00000089"/> 170    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. now.  I consented, though with agonized heart, that you should enter upon your novi- tiate, but I dared not do otherwise. Now I know the end of all their machinations, and it shall not be. My property, dear child, is what they most desire, and they hope to secure it by sacrificing you, for it is all yours. It shall not be; in that drawer--" A stealthy step in the hall checked the sentence, and sent the blood from the cheeks and lips of the invalid, while her limbs trem- bled with fear. "Open the door, Nellie," she said, faintly, "c it is Father Le Fevre." The hoary priest entered, a smile beaming from his venerable countenance, as he raised his hand in blessing over the- invalid and her watcher. "Return now to the convent, daughter. Sister Agnace desires your presence." Nellie glanced inquiringly at her Aunt. "c Go, darling, I wish to see Fathe Le Fevre alone," she whispered faintly. Bewildered with this strange and inexplic-   LnLL U4 Ji..t1arJmi.  6L 1 able conduct of her Aunt, Nellie obeyed. She saw not the dark frowning face bent over the invalid, stilling her heart, and moving her at the mysterious power of the crafty priest. She retired to her room in a kind of maze; she recalled the strange disclosures her Aunt had made, her warnings and evident fear of Father Le Fevre, at the same time she wondered at her subsequent reception of him. From that time she never saw her Aunt one moment alone, although spending the greater portion of her time near her. Aunt May seemed perfectly enthralled. She obeyed me- chanically the slightest wish of Father Le Fevre, or Sister Agnace, who hovered con- stantly around her, watching the poor victim incessantly, although under the specious pre- text of administering to her comfort and hap- piness. She yielded passively to their treatment, and although failing every day, she made no complaint, expressed no fear, except the wild, despairing look, when she drew Nellie toward    <pb n="172-173" xml:id="VAC6650-00000090"/> 172    THE 'RUSSEL FAMLY. her, and kissed her with a passionate tender- ness. The day that she died. Nelly was with her constantly, cheering her last moments by the gentle offices of love. But Aunt May was restless, watching the movements of both priest and nun, with an anxious eye. She knew that her hour had come, and the near- ness of death gave a new strength to her be- numbed soul. "Ellen, my child," she whispered, "I must see you alone." -Nellie glanced up into the face of the ven- erable priest, and was startled by its expres- sion. It was the first time she had ever noticed it, and it was gone in another mo- ment, but it fairly curdled her blood. Aunt May closed her eyes, and an expression of in- tense suffering overspread her countenance. She said no more until a few moments before the death-struggle began, when with an- other effort she pressed Ellen closely to her heart, and whispered in the lowest possible tone,   THE ESCAPE.      173 "Read the Bible, lmy darling child. Pray for me. Leave the nunnery, for God's sake!" It was a faint whisper, but it caught the quick ear of the priest. He drew Ellen gently aside and said, "Leave her, my daughter. She is raving. Your beloved Aunt will soon be at peace." The tone was gentle, the voice tender, but the stern eye glared into the poor soul, until it left its pale tenement to enter upon its eternal destiny. Ellen shuddered, for it was a fearful scene.  From that moment she was sensible that she was constantly watched, although treated with unusual and marked sympathy and affec- tion by all. But her Aunt's dying words rang in her ears. The agony of her dying hour', the paralyzing fear which had sealed her lips, and the unusual conduct of Father Le Fevre, were constantly before her, and filled her with conflicting and painful emotions. She contrasted the calm peace, and triumph, and faith, which had marked the death-beds of her father and mother, with the wild, - * .  15*    <pb n="174-175" xml:id="VAC6650-00000091"/> A174    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. -despairing agony of her Aunt's last hours. Vague doubts crept into her mind, as to the reality and efficacy of this religion, which had failed to soothe a dying hour. She remembered, also, the wild grief of a lovely woman, when she bent over the cold, dead face of her first-born. Whenw Ellen whis- pered of hope and heaven, she refused to be consoled. "Religionwas never meant to con- sole us," she moaned, "but for our discipline, and to prepare us for death." And this from the breaking heart of one of Rome's most de- voted followers. Ellen could remember that her mother had met every trial hopefully and cheerfully; her father resigned his property and life without a murmur; and Lottie bore a breaking heart for many weary days alone, sustained and comforted by religion. She thought, too, of the change in dear Louise. Her cheek had grown paler, her step more feeble. Could it be that- she was en- tirely happy,: when her soft eyes so often filled with tears, and her lips quivered with deep  X  .       .   THE ESCAPE.      175 emotion? For a long time, Nellie now re- membered, Louise had said nothing to urge her to follow her example, although the others were even more assiduous. Her Aunt's dying counsel, "Read your Bi- ble," often recurred to her and startled her. For five years she had not opened the Bible. She remembered how well her mother loved it, and the lessons of her early childhood came back to memory vividly, and fragrant with the holiest associations. But Aunt May never read the Bible, the Sisters never read it. And when she requested a Bible that she might read, no one possessed one, nor could assist her in procuring the Holy Book. Nellie did not know that it was a forbidden book, until she observed the horrified look of Sister Ag- nace-at her heretical demand. She now began to question whether she had not forsaken the rule her mother had chosen, and consented to be guided by the will of others. A strange fear possessed her when she observed how closely she was watched, and the desire to leave the convent, became    <pb n="176-177" xml:id="VAC6650-00000092"/> 176     THE IRUSSEL FAMLY. each day stronger. The vail was drawn, and she saw in a measure the 'e abomination of in- iquity" of this woman, " drunk with the blood of the saints," She felt that she was wander- ing in an unknown path, beset with dangers, with no one to guide her or protect her. In this hour she lifted her heart in prayer, not in senseless mummeries before the shrine of virgin or saint, but before God, in the simple words of the little prayer she learned beside her mother's knee. The prayer of the helpless one is heard and answered, and de- liverance is near at hand. "A gentleman wishes to see you, my daugh- ter," said Sister Agnace to her, soon after she closed the first year of her novitiate. She had not consented to enter upon the second, and every thing was made to appear as inviting as possible to win her back to them. She followed Sister Agnace to the parlor. As the door opened, she observed, a tall, deli- cate young man, standing before one of the "ne old paintings hung around the apartment. She gave one startled look at the face-that   THE ESCAPE.      1" was not to be forgotten. The same deep, dreamy eyes, the same broad, pale brow, the same waves of rich brown hair. "Edward!" "Nellie!" The brother and sister were clasped in each others' arms. "c Sister Agnace, this is my dear, long-lost, brother Edward, whom we have mourned so long as numbered with the dead." Sister Agnace received the stranger with gentle courtesy, but with an- uneasy and watchful countenance, for she feared his in- fluence at this juncture. "Where have you been, dear Eddie, these long, long years? Almost six years since you left our beautiful home, where we were all so happy together," and tears dimmed the eyes of the gay, laughing child of those days, now past forever.  ' My bark has drifted wildly, Nellie, but God has at last given it a safe and secure harbor. I landed in America only one week ago, visited Lottie and her sweet family, and    <pb n="178-179" xml:id="VAC6650-00000093"/> 178    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. then hastened to find my other sister. I left you a little girl, Nellie, and can hardly ac- knowledge this demure maiden as my merry sister, whom I left in our dear home." "You have changed too, dear Eddie, and grown older and more dignified-but I forget, you are no longer a boy, but a man, now; yet I have no trouble in tracing the resemblance of my brother, although six long years have passed since we were separated.: But tell me, dear brother, of all that has befallen you." "It is a long' story, Nellie, and I must have your company for a short ride, if this lady wilt consent, while we recount all the dealings of Providence with us." "May I not go, dear sister Agnace?" asked Nellie, eagerly. It was a forbidden pleasure, but it was dangerous to refuse Nellie's requests now; there was too much depending upon her being detained by gentleness and kindness, so Sister Agnace gave a reluctant consent. As Nellie passed through the hall, Louise passed her with a hurried step, crushing a !   THE ESCAPE.       179 paper into her hand, and then with one im- ploring look and passionate kiss, she glided away. Poor, suffering one! Rome's thousand eyes are on thee, and for this deed of love to thy friend, thy own heart shall quiver with bitter- est anguish. Eternity shall reveal the cruel deeds that have lacerated thy helpless soul. "Return soon, my sweet daughter," and Sister Agnace kissed the open brow of the now happy Nellie, and turned to meet the frown of Father Le Fevre, whose heart raged within him, as he saw his prey depart.  Nellie breathed freer when she found her- self by the side of her brother, and out of sight of her late prison. She unfolded the crump- led paper, she still held in her hand, and read: "Ellen, if you love your own soul, never enter these fearful walls again. I do this at the risk of my life. Pray for the hopeless soul of the wretched       LOUISE."' Ellen shuddered, and -clung closer to the protecting arm of her brother.       <pb n="180-181" xml:id="VAC6650-00000094"/> 180    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. "Dear Edward," she whispered, cC take me away from this fearful place. Take me home to Lottie." "Are you willing to go, dear Nellie?" said Edward, eagerly. "Oh, yes, I can not return there. But we must hasten. You will protect me, dear Ed- ward, and never let them drag me back into that terrible prison-house again." "They shall never harm you again, darling. But how came you there? Oh, Nellie, your do not know how my heart sank when Lottie told me you had finished the first year of your novitiate; I felt that I must come to you immediately to save you, and I thank God that He has rescued you from a fate far worse than death." Nellie's cheek paled, and her eyes filled with tears, as she lifted a grateful heart to that God who had so mercifully saved her from a life-long banishment from the sacred ties of affection and the loving hearts ready to make her happy. Then they recounted all the wonderful    THE ESCAPE.       181 dealings of a kind Providence with them, during their long separation, when a thick cloud had seemed to envelop the fate of the beloved wanderer, while they chatted cheer- ingly of their bright future. A quiet, peaceful home was purchased in a beautiful part of the city of Hartford, near their sister's residence. Here Edward found constant employment in his beautiful art; the last work of his genius, before he left Italy, having won for him the highest meed of praise from his admiring countrymen. Nellie's hours flew swiftly and happily by. In the quiet of her sweet home, the neglected flowers of affection struck a deeper root; and the memories and shades of the past, resumed their sway over her heart.  The Bible was read, studied, believed. Its beautiful doctrine when brought into contrast with the dark fables of Rome, convinced her intellect and subdued her heart. The sweet dove of Peace folded its wings, and rested upon the soul, which had strayed so long beneath the deadly upas shade, dis- 16    <pb n="182-183" xml:id="VAC6650-00000095"/> 182    THE aiUSSEL FAMLY. pelling the clouds of error which had dimmed its upward flight. Henceforth the beams of the "Sun of Righteousness" shall guide it over the dangerous shoals and quicksands of life, until it rests secure in heaven. ; .*.            *   XVI. X V   C X a &amp;c r. -AR up in our North-western border is a large trading-post, for the purpose of obtaining from the Indians, their rich collections of furs in exchange for English commodities, and often, alas! for the fatal "fire-water" of the whites. A fort is erected for the common safety, well supplied with arms, and each man is a soldier; for their warfare with the savages, often inflamed by the cursed " fire-water," is constant and cruel. Large fortunes are speed- ily accumulated here, but in consequence of the power of the habits they form, few of the traders desire to enjoy them amid the com- forts and luxuries of a more civilized life. They marry Indian wives, and live and die content, surrounded  by their dark-browed families.    <pb n="184-185" xml:id="VAC6650-00000096"/> 184    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. The commander of this trading-post seems younger than most of the rough men under him. He- can scarcely have reached thirty years of age; his form is lofty; his bearing haughty, and his manners reserved and taci- turn to those about him.' His stern eye pierces down into the very souls of those bold enough to cross his will, while his word of command awes the stoutest heart to submis- sion. He, too, has an Indian wife, a meek-eyed woman, lavishing all the intense love of a savage heart upon her white husband, and the little bright-eyed boy in her arms. It is hard to recognize the stern-browed man, moving among the traders and crowd of savages like a being of another sphere. But when we find him alone with his own circle, see hun take his first-born in his arms, gazing into the depths of his dark eye, the stern brow relaxes, the eye'softens, memory recalls the past, and Malcolm is once more before us. Wandering amid scenes of savage wildness for a few years, wretched, restless, and de-   THE  jDER        185 spairing, he accepted the command offered him of this trading-post. He was careless of the results, save to furnish new sources of ex- citement to his morbid soul. He married an Indian wife; unlike many of the leaders, he married her honorably, the ceremony being performed by a Romish priest, stationed as a missionary in these distant wilds. He could have no affection for her, as for one more equal to him, but he treated her with invaria- ble kindness, a sufficient reward to the simple heart, willing to live or die for him. But when Malcolm first took his boy in his arms, the long pent-up fountains of love were opened, and gushed forth resistless, refreshing his parched heart and rejoicing his weary soul. New desires and new motives possessed his heart and guided his future course. He toiled early and late to amass wealth-it was for his boy. He shrank from the contaminating intercourse with the' coarse and uncivilized about him. Thoughts of love and words of purity must alone mingle in the clear waters oft the opening fountain in his boy's heart. 16*    <pb n="186-187" xml:id="VAC6650-00000097"/> 186    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. He it was that taught the child the first easy lessons the heart must learn, and the gushing love and innocent prattle of his boy gladdened and cheered him. But he desired something more. He would have his boy taught the lessons in religion which had blessed his own infancy and boyhood. But who should teach him? The memories of his own childhood returned freshly to his heart, and the lessons of truth, that fell from his mother's lips, shone out in- delibly from the corroding rust of Ethe sinfuil past. The dying counsel of his mother fell upon his ear in louder tones than ever before. "Choose your mother's Bible for your guide, your mother's God for your everlasting portion." Once more the voice of mercy falls upon the sin-hardened heart. Will he now listen and obey? Yes, thank God! His grace is found sufficient to save even this beloved one, wandering for so many years far from his God and his own happiness. From the depths of a little package, pre-   THE TRADER.      1A7' served sacredly during all his wanderings, an old, worn-out Bible is drawn from its long resting-place. The dark-browed wife gazes in mnute aston- ishment, when she beholds the book raised reverently to the lips, and tears wetting, the page from eyes never softening,. save when they fell on her or their boy. And the bright- eyed child listens wonderingly, while his father clasps him in his arms and kneels be- fore, the book and prays in tones he was un- used to hear. The prayer was a broken and contrite plea for mercy and strength, to save him, even in this, the eleventh hour. Again; a God of long-suffering and tender compas- sion, vouchsafes to heari the prayer of the re- turning prodigal, and graciously receives him back to His mercy and love. The vail is withdrawn irom eyes so long blinded by the clouds of passion, and the suf- fering which sin brings to its slaves. Now he perceives the silver lining of the dark curtain which had obscured his path, above and be- yond which the beams of hope were yet shin-    <pb n="188-189" xml:id="VAC6650-00000098"/> 188    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. ing brightly. How else would his proud heart have been subdued and taught to return to its Father? Terrible had been his guilt before this God, but merciful the chastening hand so long held over him; but he had never realized this, but for the wondrous love of God, which can reach and save the most fallen and wretched of the sons of men. In the deep contrition of his soul,'Malcolm's only plea was,. "God be merciful to me a sinner ;" and when a holy peace calmed the storm that had raged so long within him, when hope, a glorious hope of immortality, beamed upon his worn heart, to speak of hap- piness and heav-en, he bowed his head, and praised the God of all mercy and truth, with childlike faith and joy. The lost is found, the wanderer has returned, and heaven re- joiced over the repentant soul. By a series of continued extortions and acts of petty tyranny among the savage tribes, who supplied the traders with their sources of wealth, they had become thoroughly exasper- ated. A deadly hatred of the whites settled   ,              .   THE TRADER.       189 darkly over them. A secret and well-con- trived conspiracy was formed for their total destruction, and the time appointed for its fatal execution was rapidly drawing near. Malcolm, although stern in his authority, had never wronged a savage by any dishonor- able dealings. He awed them but never in- vaded their rights. But' he was a " pale-face," and held command of the fort. This was suf- ficient to involve him in the general massacre projected. He had felt uneasy for some time, for he read of danger in the dark brows, low- ering in sullen wrath around him, and in the revengeful glarW of their savage eyes. He watched them narrowly, and took every precaution for defense against the threatening danger. He gathered the traders and' their families into. the fort every night, repaired the arms and defenses, and warned them all to be ready at a moment's warning. It was a dark, stormy night, when the fear- ful war-whoop sounded, arousing the sleeping band to encounter the most appalling danger that they had ever experienced. The stoutest    <pb n="190-191" xml:id="VAC6650-00000099"/> 190    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. heart trembled when the eye wandered over the swarm of determined savage men, pressing with hideous shouts around the devoted band at the fort. The resistance was as determined as the attack, and the bloody fight was con- tinued until daylight, for men fought for their lives. At least five hundred Indians surrounded the fort, manned by only fifty brave men. Their destruction would have been inevitable, but for the foresight and care of their watch- ful commander, who had placed the fort in the best condition for this terrible encoun- ter. And now he moved among them to strengthen and encourage them in their dif- ferent stations. : The savages met a most unexpected resist- ance, for at every blaze of the cannon the ground was strewn with swarthy corpses, while there seemed no permanent injury effected by the returning shots of their rifles, or their showers of arrows. They attempted to fire the fort, and several times succeeded in causing the dry, combustible wood, to catch and burn   THE TRADER.      191 fiercely for a few moments. But this danger was most promptly met and guarded against, and their savage yells of joy, answered by louder shouts of defiance from the unconquer- able band. Disheartened, the band drew off as daylight approached, dragging with them the bodies of their fallen companions. By some strange neglect, a small entrance to the fort was left open. This was unobserved by either party, un- til it caught the quick eye of Percy, Malcolm's idolized son, now a beautiful boy of four years of age. He saw the opening, and ran out in boyish glee to his accustomed sport, just as the dusky band were leaving the battle-field. Malcolm missed his son, and was horrified on looking over the rampart, to find him play- ing unconsciously, while two savages with stealthy tread, crept softly to seize his beloved boy. With one leap, Malcolm sprang over the wall just as one savage hand had grasped his child. By a well-aimed stroke of his dagger, the hand relaxed its hold, and the savage fell heavily forward to the ground. " *     <pb n="192-193" xml:id="VAC6650-00000100"/> JL. .  jlLrJ j I U D I LJi . iVJU L. 1. t But Malcolm must soon have followed him to the pale realm of death, had not his dark- browed wife, with one wild scream, rushed from the fort and thrown herself before the avenging hatchet of the other savage. Down deep it sank in the dusky forehead, releasing a soul of passionate tenderness and devoted love. Malcolm lifted the mangled corpse in his arms, and manly tears 'were the offering of gratitude to that undying love that could lay down life for its beloved object. Poor simple' heart! a faint light beamed upon thy benighted soul from the Holy Word, as it fell from the lips of him whom thou hast died to save. Let us hope that thy released soul rests forever in the heaven, which the Great Spirit has dimly foreshadowed to thy untutored mind. As thy redeemed soul ex- pands through all eternity, in learning what is "1 the length and breadth and height and depth of Jesus' love," we will adore:- that mercy that is able to save the poor and ignor- ant, as well as the most exalted, among the sons of men.   XVII. tHE old fort at Prairie du Chien-it *  stands deserted and silent, for the roar of its cannon and the tread of its sol- diers have long since ceased. A village has sprung up around the old fort, and chil- dren repeat its traditions with streaming eyes  and shortened breath. To them it is a haunted spot, nor have they dared these many years to sport among the tangled brush around the old moss-covered walls. One beautiful day in early summer, a trav- eler visited the old fort. :Curiosity prevailed over fear, and two of the bravest boys ventured nearer, to watch the mysterious movements of the stranger. He visited each room in the fort, and followed the broken wall, until it crumbled beneath his feet, leading by the 17    <pb n="194-195" xml:id="VAC6650-00000101"/> 194    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. hand a beautiful little boy, whose childish glee seemed quieted by the desolation around him. The walks strewn with rubbish were trodden slowly and carefully, while they rested before each tree and shrub, handling them with a gentle touch. , At last they bent over a spot which was carefully fenced in, although evidently but a mass of neglected shrubbery. The stranger's hat was lifted from his brow, the wind tossed back his raven hair, as it used to do when he' sported here, a gay and thoughtless boy, long years ago; his dark eye was raised to heaven, and over that sacred spot, where once rested the ashes of his sainted mother, Malcolm Russel took the solemn vows of his future life, to choose her Bible as his guide, and her God for his everlasting portion. There did he con- secrate himself, his beloved boy, and all he possessed, to the service of his God, and vowed from henceforth to live for His glory, and trust alone in His mercy. This done, he cast one long, farewell look around the familiar   scenes of his childhood, then left the spot and pursued his eastward journey. It was his design to return to the States, to find, if possible, the scattered members of their broken family-circle, and renew the sacred memories of his childhood and youth, where he might rear his boy to a useful and happy life. He wrote to Lottie at Hartford, scarcely daring to hope that the letter would ever reach her. But time has brought but few changes to Lottie's quiet home. The letter, the first tidings she had received of her lost brother for ten long, long years, was received with a heart overflowing with love and- grateful joy. It told of his speedy return, when they should know of all that had befallen each one during their weary separation. But a few days elapsed, and the brothers and sisters were clasped in the warm embraces of affectionate hearts. 'Tis not for stranger- eyes to intrude upon this sacred scene, where severed hearts are reunited. We leave them to repeat the varied scenes that have marked their    <pb n="196-197" xml:id="VAC6650-00000102"/> *LW     Ta. 'TE JUWDDEL FA AMLY  separation, and to shed undisturbed the tears of joy or grief, as they thus recall the past. But once more would we fain draw the cur- tain, and as they gather around one family- table, mark the changes which time has wrought. Alfred Vernon occupies the head of the table. He has indeed become the high-minded man, and devoted Christian, that his youth promised, and he is marking his life with the noble deeds of God's devoted servants, respected and beloved by all around him. Charlotte sits opposite. Time has dealt lightly with her. The hair is parted off from a brow, marked only with the sweet graces of a true woman. A matronly air has displaced the girlish lightness of former days, but it becomes her well; a sweet smile lights her face as she gazes upon her lovely children, which reminds Malcolm  of the smile that blessed his childhood, for Lottie resembles her mother more   closely as -she grows older. "Permit me, Brother Malcolm, to present j   to your notice, your namesake, Malcolm Russel Vernon, and his sister Annie." The children stepped forward to receive the warm  embra-e  of their Uncle, and surely never mother's eye rested on lovelier children than the manly boy and his fairy-like sister. On Lottie's right sits Edward and his bride. Edward's cheek is less pale, his slight form less delicate, his brow is unruffled, and his eye beams with the light of hope and happi- ness. His genius has created new forms of beauty to adorn the galleries in his own coun- try, or to administer to a refined taste. His name stands high among the gifted ones in Europe and America, and bright laurels are laid at his feet. But upon the, altar of his heart, "Still burns the one pure spark divine." The poor bless the unknown hand that re- lieves their need; while many a heart, broken and ready to perish, revives to listen to the high words of hope which fall from the lips of 17*    <pb n="198-199" xml:id="VAC6650-00000103"/> 198    THE RUSSEL FAMLY. the gentle stranger. His record is on high, and his life is one quiet deed of pitying love. Florence Lincoln has become his lovely bride. The genial frankness and gushing ten- derness of the maiden lives freshly in the wife, and she has become the sympathizing com- panion, and the beloved object of the rich love she has won. Nellie, or Mrs. Ellen Benton, sits, demurely for her, by the side of Edward's former tutor -and traveling companion, Professor Benton. He now occupies a high position as professor, in once of our colleges, and Nellie moves in her elevated sphere with quiet grace and dig- nity. We do not miss the innocent smile, or fresh, gushing love of little Nellie, in the wo- man before us; if we miss the gay laugh and mischievous twinkle of the eye, we shall re- find them in the blue-eyed Katie, peeping from under her golden curls at her cousin Percy. On. Malcolm's brow are graven the lines that care and sorrow leave. A sad expression has softened the bold, joyous one of youth,   THE RETURN.       199 but the eye splaks of inward peace, the mouth of chastened and holy desires. Percy closely resembles the boy who gayly sported at the old fort, except that his brow is shaded by his Indian blood. He moves among his fairer cousins, a bright, beautiful, and joyous child, although the father sighs as he watches him in his innocent glee. For in the depths of his dark eyes, he reads the same undeveloped passions whichkhave caused him so much of anguish, and he trembles lest he should suffer as he had. The meal over, the happy family gathered around the altar to offer the overflowing grat- itude of believing hearts to that God who had so wonderfully guided and preserved them all. Malcolm led the devotions, and most elo- quently did he recount the mercies and long- suffering compassion, that had led them along through so many varied scenes and dangers, to meet after years of separation and suffer- ing, an unbroken circle, in the high work of praising and honoring the God of all grace and mercy. + /    <pb n="200-201" xml:id="VAC6650-00000104"/> 200     THE RUSSEL FAMLY. The holy influence of the #cene softened each heart and filled every eye with tears of joy and happiness, while it rested on the young heads, bowed in prayer, all unconscious of suffering, subduing their childish mirth, and dimming even their bright eyes with the uncalled tear.       \ * The mother's mission is done. Like a silver cord has it drawn the beloved ones away from sin and danger into the one fold of Christ. For her prayers of faith and deeds of love were known before God, and have prevailed. Henceforth, through all eternity, the song of praise, and adoration, and glory, shall as- cend to Him, who siteth on the Throne for- ever, as, one by one, the earth-won jewels are placed in her crown of rejoicing. Then faint not, Christian mother, your mis- sion is a high and holy one: "Let not ymir heart be troubled." The blessing may long delay, but live trusting and die trusting: God is faithful, and will surely perform all His  promises, though it may be at the eleventh hour.   THE RETURN.       201 The words of Eternal Truth are these : "I will be thy God and the God of thy children after thee." Go on then and sow the seed with a faithful hand, and "in due season ye shall reap, if ye faint not." THE END.     </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>