<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6371">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Poor of New York </title>
            <author>Edwards, Henry, (1824-1891)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC6371</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-0840</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                    participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The poor of New York</title>
                  <author>Edwards, Henry, (1824-1891)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>96 [i.e. 46] p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Hilton</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1865">1865</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="AEL Data" when="2003-02-26">Finished transcription and SGML encoding</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2003-03-12">Finished TEI conversion</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-07-17">Converted document from SGML to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-07-17">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6371-00000001"/>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>THE POOR OF NEW YORK.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>BY <docAuthor>HENRY EDWARDS.</docAuthor>
            </byline>
            <titlePart type="desc">FROM THE PLAY OF "THE POOR OF NEW YORK."</titlePart>
            <docEdition>ILLUSTRATED.</docEdition>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>NEW-YORK:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>HILTON &amp; CO., PUBLISHERS <address>
                     <addrLine>128 Nassau Street.</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </publisher>
            </docImprint>
            <docDate when="1865">1865.</docDate>
         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The poor of New York</head>
            <pb n="3" xml:id="VAC6371-00000002"/>
            <head>THE POOR OF NEW YORK.</head>
            <head type="figure">
               <figure>
                  <head>GIDEON BLOODGOOD, THE BANKER.</head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE CITY BANKER.</head>
               <p>MR. GIDEON BLOODGOOD, the banker, was considered by the people of New York a wealthy and a happy man; his name stood high in Wall street; his business was extensive; and above all, he was blessed with a charming daughter bequeathed to him by a dear wife, who had died some few years antecedent to the date at which our story opens. Whether the general report with regard to his<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC6371-00000003"/> wealth was correct or not was best known, however, to Mr. Bloodgood. The business of the President of a bank is of so private a nature that it is difficult for the world at large to estimate the probable amount of such a man's income; still as Mr. Bloodgood's love—we had almost said adoration—of money was so well known, the good people could not help feeling convinced that he was an opulent citizen.</p>
               <p>We must also add that if Mr. Bloodgood's love of money was proverbial, it was at any rate actuated by the love he felt for his only daughter, on whom he was willing to expend all the riches he possessed. Some of his enemies—for like most men he had a few foes—said that his mode of business was similar to that suggested by the Quaker to his son, "Make money, John; honestly, if thou canst, but make money!"</p>
               <p>One cold, dreary November morning, the banker was seated in his private room at his office, with his desk covered with papers. On one of these he kept his eyes fixed for some time, and, half in thought, spoke to himself as follows:</p>
               <p>"Gold! gold!—I must have gold! Gold! the chief, the sole object of life. How strange the word sounds! Gold I must have! But if I die! Ah! who knows? Well, she will be rich. My child, my daughter, my darling Alida! But if I should not! Well, well!—patience, patience!"</p>
               <p>Then, after pausing for a few minutes, but still keeping his eyes fixed on the paper, he again spoke.</p>
               <p>"No, no, Bloodgood—courage, courage! Keep to the straight road; traverse slowly and patiently the path of honesty. Yes, yes, that's all very well, but the road is long and wearisome. No, I will act as best seems fit. Oh, heaven! shall I be the first, or shall I be the last? True, I shall be despised; but my gold will comfort me. When it lies before me I should be a fool not to pick it up. Well, well, we shall see—we shall see."</p>
               <p>The banker then locked up the paper he had been so long studying, and rang the bell.</p>
               <p>The door opened and the old gray-headed porter of the bank, Joseph, who had held the post for forty years, entered.</p>
               <p>"All ready, Joseph?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, sir; the carriage is ordered, and will be at the garden-gate at the hour you wish."</p>
               <p>"That's right; where is my daughter's servant?"</p>
               <p>"In Miss Alida's room, busy packing her things."</p>
               <p>"Good. Listen to me, Joseph. If by chance I don't return to-morrow, take this sealed packet to the Stock Exchange."</p>
               <p>Joseph took the packet, and quietly answered—</p>
               <p>"Yes, sir."</p>
               <p>"The clerks have been told, I hope, that the bank will be closed at twelve o'clock to-day?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, sir; they were informed that it was in consequence of Miss Alida being three years old to-day."</p>
               <p>"True, true. Have they all gone?"</p>
               <p>"All but one, sir. Mr. Badger is still here."</p>
               <p>"What, Badger?" exclaimed Mr. Bloodgood, somewhat astonished; "why he's the most unpunctual and idle of the lot. Humph, that's strange!"</p>
               <p>"He says, sir, that his books are in arrear, and he wishes to take advantage of this holiday to finish posting them."</p>
               <p>"Indeed! Perhaps I am wrong then, and he may be an industrious man after all. Tell him I should like to speak to him."</p>
               <p>Joseph left the room in search of this industrious young man.</p>
               <p>"I can't understand this man; he does not work when the others do, and yet works when they do not. I don't like these oddities," soliloquized Mr. Bloodgood.</p>
               <p>The private door opened and in walked Mr. Badger, calmly smoking a cigar. He leisurely made his way to the banker's desk, and fixed his eyes on the papers with which it was covered. As this "oddity" is likely to play an important part in our story, we must say a few words of his personal appearance. He was a tall, well-built, clean shaven man of about thirty. His thin lips gave him an air of determination; his cold, gray eyes were constantly peering about in all directions, in the hope apparently of seeing something which might prove of advantage to their owner. The lines on his face showed that he had lived a hard life, and the suspicious, scrutinizing manner in which he stared about wherever he went must have given any stranger an idea that he was like one of those men we read of in novels, who prefer living on a secret wormed from some rich criminal to earning their bread in an honest manner. After glancing quickly at the papers on the desk, he coolly threw his cigar into the fire, and quietly but boldly said—</p>
               <p>"You sent for me, sir."</p>
               <p>"Oh yes, Mr. Badger, I did," said the banker, looking up. "Are you not aware that I have given you all a holiday today? You don't always seem to be so diligent."</p>
               <p>"Perhaps not, sir; but you know we must all make a beginning."</p>
               <p>There was nothing respectful in his manner, yet nothing rude. He only kept his cold, gray eyes fixed upon the banker in such an unpleasant manner that Mr. Bloodgood almost winced beneath their gaze.</p>
               <p>"True, sir, true; but I would rather you deferred your sudden and strange conversion until to-morrow."</p>
               <p>"To-morrow, sir, is an ambitious word: we never know what may happen to-morrow."</p>
               <p>"Mr. Badger, I do not object to philosophy, at times, but I do not approve of it in my clerks."</p>
               <p>"Then, sir, you may probably be wrong," replied Badger, quietly; "for philosophy makes an employee forget the injustice and ingratitude of his master."</p>
               <p>"Now, sir, understand me, that I object also to idleness and dissipation," said the banker, sternly. "I may pass over faults, but vices I punish. I shall not require your services any longer."</p>
               <p>"I beg your pardon, sir."</p>
               <p>"Mr. Badger, you can leave."</p>
               <p>"Leave, sir? Why, what have I done," exclaimed the clerk, apparently surprised. "I can understand my services not being required in a house that goes on; but when that house is about to break, the formality of telling a clerk he is discharged does seem to me an unnecessary luxury."</p>
               <p>"Sir, I don't understand you," almost shouted the banker.</p>
               <p>"Oh, don't you? then I'll soon make my meaning clear," said Badger, boldly. "In business, sir, there are two ways of becoming rich; one is long, weary, and troublesome. This, sir, is called labor. It is a difficult road perhaps. On this point I won't contradict you, as we two are, I know, of one opinion."</p>
               <p>"What do you mean?" exclaimed Mr. Bloodgood, growing uneasy.</p>
               <p>"Allow me to finish," continued Badger, quietly. "The other way to make money is simple and easy, and only requires boldness and a pliant conscience. It is managed under the guise of morality. Thus people acquire confidence in such a man of business; but one fine morning this moral man runs off with the feathers of those credulous birds who have been caught in the bird-lime of his credit."</p>
               <p>"Be silent, sir!" shouted the banker, becoming enraged.</p>
               <p>Badger, however, taking no notice of this injunction, quietly resumed his seat, and said—</p>
               <p>"This road, sir, is, however, dangerous. It passes the court of justice and runs very close to the prison. Some people call it bankruptcy. He is a clever man who gets into the house at the end of this road, the keys of this which are kept by the creditors, who, on the promise of a dividend. Will offer it to you. Here you may find a bed to rest upon made, sir, by trade, and from underneath the pillow you can pocket thousands."</p>
               <p>"Sir! dare you imagine—?"</p>
               <p>"No, Mr. Bloodgood, I never imagine, I<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC6371-00000004"/> am always sure, or else I hold my tongue. For two years, sir, you have concealed your profits and exaggerated your losses. Your safe, sir, is empty, but your pocket-book is full. The former is intended for your creditors, and the latter for yourself. Am I right, sir?"</p>
               <p>"This is infamous!" shouted the banker, springing from his chair.</p>
               <p>"Exactly what I said when I came to the end of your book. Am I altogether wrong if I say that this morning you filed your schedule, and that this evening there will be a post-chaise waiting for you at the garden-door?"</p>
               <p>He had scarcely finished the sentence when the voice of Joseph was heard in the passage.</p>
               <p>"This way, sir—this way."</p>
               <p>The door opened, and the porter appeared, followed by a gentleman.</p>
               <p>"Badger, be silent," whispered the banker to his clerk.</p>
               <p>"Fear nothing, sir," was the cool reply. "I am dumb."</p>
               <p>The gentleman who entered was one of those bluff, red-faced, jolly-looking sea-captains so common to the mercantile marine. His frank, unsuspicious, open countenance, almost provoked friendship from some and roguery from others.</p>
               <p>"Do I address Mr. Bloodgood?" said he, taking the chair offered by Badger.</p>
               <p>"That is my name," replied the banker.</p>
               <p>"I have to apologize," continued the sailor in a rough, cheery voice, "for trespassing on your time on such a festive occasion, but, sir, the short time I have at my disposal must plead for me."</p>
               <p>"Do not mention it; I am at your service, sir."</p>
               <p>"Well, then, to business; but who is this gentleman?" asked he, pointing to Badger.</p>
               <p>"Oh, don't mind me," said the clerk. "Mr. Bloodgood and I have no secrets."</p>
               <p>"Now, sir," continued the sailor, whose name was Fairbrother, "I am a sea-captain, just returned from a long voyage. In fact, sir, it was but yesterday that I was driven into the harbor. You know, sir, that sailors are superstitious. <unclear>It is</unclear> perhaps for this reason that I do not care to trust my savings to the sea again."</p>
               <p>"Go on, sir; your story interests me," replied the banker, eagerly.</p>
               <p>"Well, sir, you I believe are the agent of Cazavan &amp; Co., of Martinique. I have the highest confidence in that house, and from them I have heard the name of Bloodgood of New York well spoken of."</p>
               <p>"I am glad to hear it, sir; I have large transactions with the honse you mention."</p>
               <p>"So superstitious am I, that my money makes me uneasy, and I feel that I should be more comfortable if I placed in your hands the money I intend to leave to my children."</p>
               <p>"You have a family, then?"</p>
               <p>"Ah, that I have, sir; I am indeed a happy man," said the sailor, smiling. "I am a lucky father, sir, longing to see all my relations—to see her, my own dear wife, the devoted and patient companion of the sailor, whose loving voice murmurs each evening a prayer for those men who are at sea, and my dear children—two little angels, sir; my little Antoinette, the younger, who rolls on the floor, and mutters 'Pa, pa,' a hundred times a day; and then my son—sir, my dear boy, Paul, who is so like me, that when I look at him I see myself. Oh, my darlings! why am I not with you? How happy we shall all be together! You will excuse me, sir, I know, for troubling you thus with matters that cannot interest you; but you know how a father likes to chatter about his children. For him, sir, there is but one thing in the world—in the whole universe—his children."</p>
               <p>"I can appreciate your joy, sir," replied Mr. Bloodgood, "for I, too, am a father. I have a daughter, sir, whom I love with my whole heart."</p>
               <p>"Ah, it's pleasant to talk about these things, isn't it? How happy and rich my darlings will be—bless them! Here, sir," said he, taking out an old pocket-book from his coat, "is their fortune, torn, as it were, from the waves, with which I have struggled so long. But I have conquered, sir, after much suffering. What matters that; it was for my darlings. Take this, sir," continued he, giving the pocket-book to the banker; "there are one hundred thousand dollars in notes. Give me a receipt for them; then I can step on board my vessel more at case with regard to the welfare of my darlings."</p>
               <p>Badger looked up quietly from the ledger which he had pretended to study, and muttered—</p>
               <p>"What a change would one word from me effect!"</p>
               <p>"Sir, you honor me by your confidence; and I need scarcely tell you that this money will be ready whenever you may require it."</p>
               <p>"Good, sir; now count it please."</p>
               <p>"Quite correct, sir," replied Mr. Bloodgood, counting the contents of the pocket-book; "Mr. Badger will write a receipt for it."</p>
               <p>The clerk went quietly to the table, and wrote as the banker had directed.</p>
               <p>"With what name, sir, shall I fill this out?"</p>
               <p>"Captain Fairbrother."</p>
               <p>Badger took the pen and wrote—"New York, 30 October, 1847. Received, on special deposit from Captain Fairbrother, one hundred thousand dollars."</p>
               <p>"Will you sign the receipt, sir?" asked Badger.</p>
               <p>The banker nodded his head.</p>
               <p>Mr. Bloodgood took the pen and calmly wrote his signature.</p>
               <p>"Wonderful!" murmured the clerk, "his hand does not even tremble. How perfect this robbery is!"</p>
               <p>As soon as the captain had placed the receipt in his pocket, he cordially shook hands with the banker. "Many thanks, sir; you have taken a load off my mind. I shall now go and have dinner with some of my old sea friends; and if the wind keeps south east, the brig <hi rend="i"/>Adventurer will soon be on its way. Good day, Mr. Bloodgood."</p>
               <p>The banker accompanied the captain to the door.</p>
               <p>As soon as it was closed, Badger, in his usual quiet, original manner, said—</p>
               <p>"How fortunate, sir, that I stayed; I can now enter the hundred thousand dollars in the cash book as a special deposit."</p>
               <p>"My dear Badger!" exclaimed the banker, in a conciliatory manner.</p>
               <p>"Well, my dear Mr. Bloodgood?"</p>
               <p>"Ah, Badger, I find that I have misjudged you. You are a clever fellow."</p>
               <p>"I must do what I can for myself."</p>
               <p>"True, true. Now, Mr Badger, whenever I commit an injustice I like to afford reparation as soon as I can." He then took him by the arm, and beckoned him to take a seat near the desk.</p>
               <p>"And now, my dear sir, accept these two thousand dollars as a slight reward for your past services."</p>
               <p>The clerk quietly pocketed the notes and then closing the cash-box, said in the most imperturbable manner—</p>
               <p>"And what about the present?"</p>
               <p>"True, true, Badger," replied the banker, smiling. "Well, my friend, I am going for a little trip in the country, and—"</p>
               <p>"Are you going in a carriage?"</p>
               <p>"Just so; therefore, before I start I'll leave you double the sum you have just had."</p>
               <p>"Humph!" murmured Badger, "only six thousand dollars altogether; but if I betrayed him I should get nothing."</p>
               <p>Just then the door opened, and Joseph, the porter, appeared.</p>
               <p>"Please, sir," said he, "Miss Alida will not allow the servant to dress her. She is crying bitterly, and says she wants you to be near her."</p>
               <p>"The dear child; I'll come directly."</p>
               <p>"If she shows so much spirit now, I wonder what she'll be like when she is twenty," muttered Badger.</p>
               <p>"And now, my dear sir, I think we understand each other?"</p>
               <p>"Perfectly, Mr. Bloodgood."</p>
               <p>"Well, then, I'll see you before I leave."</p>
               <pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6371-00000005"/>
               <p>He then left the room, followed by Joseph, in search of his daughter.</p>
               <p>"Not a bad day's work," said Badger, when the door closed. "Go to your daughter, Mr. Bloodgood, if you please, but recollect that your master is here. Rob, plunder, and ruin twenty families; acquire wealth with their misery; become happy with their tears; and give your daughter what she pleases. Daughter, indeed! Bah! my children are my passions, or rather what fools call vices. Spoilt children, ungrateful perhaps, that may after all bring their father to the workhouse."</p>
               <p>"I tell you, sir, that Mr. Bloodgood's not in," shouted Joseph, the porter, in the passage.</p>
               <p>"Don't talk to me, sir," shouted a strong voice. "I will see him, I tell you. Where is he—where is your master?"</p>
               <p>The door was burst open, and in rushed old Fairbrother, very excited.</p>
               <p>"Why, what's the matter?" quietly asked Badger.</p>
               <p>"Where, sir, is Mr. Bloodgood? I must see him, I must speak to him at once. Don't you hear me! Tell him to come at once."</p>
               <p>"But, sir—"</p>
               <p>"Well, then, take me to him—I must see him."</p>
               <p>"But—"</p>
               <p>"I tell you I must see him."</p>
               <p>The sudden appearance of Mr. Bloodgood luckily put an end to what would probably have ended in a violent altercation.</p>
               <p>"What's the matter?" said he, quietly.</p>
               <p>"I am glad you have come, sir," almost shouted Captain Fairbrother, evidently excited. "I have changed my mind, sir, and want my money back. Give it me at once, and take your receipt. I wish to invest my money elsewhere; so give me my money at once."</p>
               <p>"Do keep calm, sir," replied the banker, quietly. "You have a strange manner of asking for what is due to you."</p>
               <p>"I know that, sir; but I can't help it. I have given you all I have in the world. It's my wife's fortune and that of my darlings, Paul and Antoinette. It's their happiness, sir—it's their life. Come now, I'll be frank with you. Just now, at the hotel where I was enjoying myself with a few friends, the captain of a steamer came in with letters. There was one, sir, from the house of Cazavan &amp; Co., of Martinique—"</p>
               <p>"Well, sir, what has that to do with me?"</p>
               <p>"An instant, sir. In this letter it was stated that your credit was bad, and that doubts were entertained of your solvency. Here, take the letter, read it yourself."</p>
               <p>Mr. Bloodgood took the letter, and without reading it threw it on the desk.</p>
               <p>"What, sir, do you think I care for the libellous reports of the Messrs. Cazavan?"</p>
               <p>"Perhaps not, sir; but I do, and I will not compromise the fortune of my wife and family. So give me my money, and take back your receipt."</p>
               <p>"Don't you know, Captain Fairbrother, that my office is closed for the day? You must come to-morrow for your money."</p>
               <p>"But, sir, you did not object to take my money after business hours."</p>
               <p>At this moment the door opened, and Joseph entered.</p>
               <p>"The carriage is waiting."</p>
               <p>"Very well," shouted Bloodgood, cowering with rage at the interruption.</p>
               <p>"The carriage!" exclaimed the captain. He then rushed to the window, and, in his anxiety, let the receipt fall. "Ah, it was even worse than I thought. And so, sir, you were going to flee with the fortunes of some people and the hard-earned savings of others. Oh, my God! the villian." In his rage the poor man sank upon his chair and foamed at the mouth. Suddenly he tore open his shirt. "Oh, hold me. Help, help!" shouted he, "I am suffocated; still I am in time for my money. Give me my money, you villian."</p>
               <p>"Be calm, sir, do be calm," said the banker imploringly.</p>
               <p>"You said to-morrow. Wretch, and yet you were going to run away to <unclear>night."</unclear> He sprang up, and seizing the <unclear>unfortunate</unclear> banker by the throat, he shouted, "Give me my money, now, at once. Don't speak, sir, for I wont hear you. My money—give me my money, or I'll kill you as I would a dog or a common thief."</p>
               <p>Badger here interposed.</p>
               <p>"Be calm, Captain Fairbrother, I implore you."</p>
               <p>As soon as the infuriated man had relaxed his hold, Mr. Bloodgood spoke.</p>
               <p>"Now, sir, let's have no more scandal. You shall have your money."</p>
               <p>"Very well, then. If you don't give it me I'll kill you. Oh, my head, my poor head!" exclaimed the old man, with an expression of agony. "Come, sir, quick; give me my money. I wont leave till I get it. Oh heaven! what is the matter with me?"</p>
               <p>"Ah! he staggers," shouted Badger, rushing to him.</p>
               <p>"How pale the man looks!" said the banker, still holding the pocket-book in his hand.</p>
               <p>The poor man was indeed ill. He fell upon the floor and rolled about in great agony.</p>
               <p>"Oh, heaven! I am suffocated; I can't breathe—I can't see. What is this before me? Am I going to die? Oh no, I cannot die, I must see my darlings first. Water, water, I implore you. Oh, my wife, my darlings, where are you? Let me embrace them—let me—"</p>
               <p>Mr. Bloodgood rushed to the door.</p>
               <p>"Quick, help!" shouted he. "Badger, fetch a doctor."</p>
               <p>Instead of obeying him, however, the clerk knelt down by the side of the captain, and felt his pulse. "It is useless, sir. This man is dead. I see what it is—congestion of the brain, an apoplectic fit, brought on by rage and grief."</p>
               <p>"Impossible!" mechanically exclaimed the banker.</p>
               <p>"His heart has ceased to beat, Mr. Bloodgood," continued Badger, looking up, "and now you need not open the pocket-book, sir. Ah! what's this?" said he, quietly. "The receipt, signed by Bloodgood. Come, this may be useful. There is no knowing when it may come in play." He then placed it in his pocket, unseen by the banker, whose eyes were fixed upon the corpse at his feet, whilst his hands convulsively clutched the pocket-book.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
               <head type="sub">THE CAKE VENDER OF PRINTING HOUSE SQUARE.</head>
               <p>It must be owned that selling "coffee and cakes" in the street is not a very rapid manner of making a fortune. True, the exposure to the open air is conducive to health, but yet the return on these articles of merchandize is so very insignificant, that many hot cakes must be sold before even a sufficient profit can be made to permit the vender to indulge in breakfast upon his own goods. Still the trade of "Butter-cake Dick," as was nicknamed Mr. Richard Martin, the honest dealer of Printing House Square, although occasionally variable in consequence of the fickleness of some people's appetites, was, on the whole, in a flourishing condition. His wife, his old Mary, we must state, was the maker of these wonderful cakes, all hot, with which old Martin wished to astonish those natives who were fortunate enough to meet him between the hours of eight p.m. and five in the morning. Mary certainly was not a lazy woman, for she rose at five each morning, and after making as much hot coffee as she considered the public might require, she strapped a large vessel on her back, and started off in the hopes of meeting workmen and others whose affairs called them up at that early hour. Then as soon as she had gone a certain round, she usually met Martin, whose presence was sure to increase the sale of the coffee, whilst those who had sipped a cup of hot coffee were often led to increase the luxury of their repast by adding to it one of those hot cakes which her husband by the aid of pepper, had rendered so famous. As soon as all their comestibles were disposed of, the worthy pair posted home to get their own breakfast ready, as well as that of Tony, their son,<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6371-00000006"/> a sensible young fellow of twenty-two, who was endeavouring to ascend the ladder of fortune by the aid of the paint-pot and brush, with which latter article he was engaged in daubing the shop-fronts of the small tradesmen of that quarter. There also lodged in the same house as nice and as good a young couple as they could wish—a brother and sister, who had fallen very, very low in the world. Thus, unfortunately, they were rather backward in their rent, and this fact occasionally rendered the money due from them to their landlord, Mr. Bloodgood, not quite so regular as might have been desired.</p>
               <p>"Lor', Mr. Martin, where can that Tony be this morning? Perhaps he is working so hard that he don't know that his breakfast is ready. I'll just run out and fetch him in," said Mary, clapping on her bonnet and running off after her boy.</p>
               <p>"Flowers flowers! who'll buy nice fresh flowers? the very last this season," shouted a neatly dressed girl.</p>
               <p>"Oh, don't say that, Maggie," said a young painter, Master Tony, by-the-by looking down from his work, "they wont be the last flowers, as long as you have those roses in your cheeks."</p>
               <p>"You go on with your work, mister painter. My cheeks belong to me, and don't require any aid from paint."</p>
               <p>"Perhaps not, my dear; but you paint with the brush of nature, like peaches and raspberries."</p>
               <p>"Don't talk nonsense. Flowers, fresh flowers, who'll buy?" shouted the girl, running off, probably thinking that the compliments of the painter, although very pleasant, were not quite so profitable as the sale of her flowers.</p>
               <p>Soon Mr. Tony's worthy mother appeared upon the scene.</p>
               <p>"Here, Tony—Tony, why don't you come to breakfast?"</p>
               <p>"Well, mother, I was working so hard trying to get this shop-front finished to-day, that I scarcely thought of breakfast."</p>
               <p>"How much are these—seventy-five cents a pair?" said Mary, stopping before a stall.</p>
               <p>"Can't do it really, ma'am. A pair of beautiful pigeons like these are worth one dollar; but you shall have them for eighty cents, there."</p>
               <p>"Oh no, seventy-five is enough."</p>
               <p>"Doesn't mother know how to market?" muttered Tony, clapping his hands.</p>
               <p>"Well then, ma'am, take them for seventy-five."</p>
               <p>The shrewd woman took them up in her hands, and then replaced them, vowing that they were the thinnest pigeons she had ever seen.</p>
               <p>"Perhaps you'd like to have them trussed for your seventy-five cents?"</p>
               <p>"Oh, how jolly, mother!" said Tony, who was beginning to take an interest in the market operations. "What a nice supper we shall have to be sure."</p>
               <p>"Ah, my boy, these pigeons are not for you, I can assure you."</p>
               <p>"What, are they for our fine lodgers, the Fairbrothers? We get beef, while they have partridges. I shouldn't make such a fuss about them, I know. However, as it isn't my money you're spending I don't care; besides, after all, the Fairbrothers are not a bad lot."</p>
               <p>"Indeed they are not, Tony. Mrs. Fair-brother is a dear good creature. And then her two children, Paul and Antoinette, why she seems to live only for them."</p>
               <p>"Of course, mother, just the same as you live for me."</p>
               <p>"No, I don't, sir. You don't deserve anybody to care for you."</p>
               <p>"Well, mother, it ain't my fault if I am not such a fire-looking gentleman as Paul."</p>
               <p>"Never mind, Tony, you are a good-hearted fellow; but I doubt if there's any young man who loves and respects his mother as Paul does; and there's that dear Miss Antoinette. Why, if her brother is a little low-spirited, she's perfectly miserable. Oh, here's Maggie coming."</p>
               <p>"Good day, Mrs. Martin," said the young girl, embracing the good old woman.</p>
               <p>"How are you, my child?"</p>
               <p>"But, mother, I am not your child yet."</p>
               <p>"Of course not, Maggie dear," said Tony, looking lovingly at her; "but you know we can't be married in Lent."</p>
               <p>"Tony, that's what you have said for the last eight months; but mind, if when Easter comes—I hope you hear me—I say that if at Easter I am not—"</p>
               <p>"All right, darling, we will talk about then."</p>
               <p>"That he shall, Maggie; you shall be married then, I promise you."</p>
               <p>"Of course, Maggie; although, my dear, I think it would be better to wait till I had saved two thousand dollars."</p>
               <p>"You old miser, always thinking of your money. That is not the secret of happiness."</p>
               <p>"All right, Maggie! Good-bye, dear! Now, mother, we'll go to breakfast." The two people then walked off, leaving the girl to sell her flowers.</p>
               <p>It was about the hour at which people go to morning mass, so off the girl started to the chapel. She soon met a crowd of people on their way to church, most of them carrying their prayer-books in their hands. Among the groups was one which particularly attracted Maggie's attention as she saw in the members composing it the prospect of a customer. This party consisted of an elderly, lady leaning on the arm of a handsome young man, and supported on the other side by a very pretty girl. The strong family likeness existing between the three plainly indicated that the old lady was the mother of the young people.</p>
               <p>"Now, mother," said the young man, who was no other than Paul Fairbrother, "having brought you to church, I think I'll leave you."</p>
               <p>"Flowers, ladies—buy my sweet flowers," said Maggie, snowing the many-colored flowers with which her basket was laden.</p>
               <p>"Shall I buy you some?" said Paul to his sister.</p>
               <p>"Not now, Paul. Let's wait till we return from church."</p>
               <p>"I'd rather buy them now. Here, Antoinette, is a boquet for you, and here's one for you, mother."</p>
               <p>"No no, Paul, I'd much rather not have it."</p>
               <p>"Pshaw! mother, take it. It is only a trifle that I can easily afford. Now, my girl, what is the price of these boquets?"</p>
               <p>"Whatever you please, sir," said the sharp witted girl.</p>
               <p>"Here, then, take these two shillings."</p>
               <p>"Oh, no, sir, that's too much. It is indeed."</p>
               <p>"Never mind! you owe me some flowers for it."</p>
               <p>"The girl ran away laughing, evidently surprised at her own success.</p>
               <p>"Oh, Paul, do be more careful with your money. You know we have not much to spare," said his mother to him.</p>
               <p>"Indeed we haven't, Paul," chimed in his sister. "It's very kind of you, but I am sure that we could have done without these flowers."</p>
               <p>"Scold away, ladies," said the young man, laughing. "Blame me as much as you please, I'll love you all the same."</p>
               <p>"Ah, Paul, you are a good son."</p>
               <p>"And a dear brother," said his sister.</p>
               <p>"My own boy, you are growing just like your dear father. Often when I hear your voice, when I look at you, I fancy I see my poor husband before me, and then, my boy, the kisses of the son dry the tears which are shed by the mother."</p>
               <p>"Come, now, mother, cheer up, don't be sad."</p>
               <p>"My dear children! shall we never be happy again?"</p>
               <p>"I am sure we are happy enough now. We want nothing, do we, Paul?" said Antoinette.</p>
               <p>"Nothing at all," answered the young man.</p>
               <p>Well, good-bye, mother. I am going to have a quiet cigar." Paul then made his way into the tobacconist's.</p>
               <p>"The ladies were just on the steps of the church, when a tall, middle-aged<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6371-00000007"/> man, evidently very care worn, but still possessing a certain lurking sense of jolity, came up to them.</p>
               <p>"Charity, ladies," said he, in the usual whining voice of beggars.</p>
               <p>"My poor man, I have not much to give you, but what I can spare you are welcome to," said Antoinette, giving him a trifle.</p>
               <p>"Thank you, miss! bless you!" said the man. "You are the first person who has taken pity on me, although it isn't the first time, either. I recollect one Sunday, a long time ago, you gave me some money."</p>
               <p>"And I hope it did you good, my poor man. I am sure I often think of you," continued the girl.</p>
               <p>"Bless you, miss! Heaven bless you!" ejaculated the man, evidently moved. "How lovely you are, and happy, too, I hope! Ah, miss, your parents ought to be happy people."</p>
               <p>"Oh, I am sure I'm sorry I said anything about it, then."</p>
               <p>"Thank you again, Miss!"</p>
               <p>"Good day, my poor man. I shall see you on Sunday, I hope. Pray for us in the meantime."</p>
               <p>They then passed into the church.</p>
               <p>"Pray for you! Ah, young lady, my prayers won t do anybody much good." The beggar, who we may as well state was no other than our old acquaintance, Badger, walked off in search of prey in some other quarter.</p>
               <p>As soon as Tony had enjoyed a hearty breakfast, he returned to his task of painting the shop-front of a flourishing grocer near the church in which the Fairbrothers were taking part in the mass performed there. This Tony was a merry, hearty fellow, very much in love with his little Maggie, but still anxious to save a little money before he entered the bonds of wedlock.</p>
               <p>At the end of a verse of a comic song then in vogue among the boys of the town, he daubed the green paint on the wainscot of the shop and began to talk to himself.</p>
               <p>"I'm bothered if I know why I am not a gentleman, or perhaps I'd be contented if I was only a shop-keeper, or I ain't quite certain if I'd mind being even a shirt-maker. Oh, my! here's a swell with an eyeglass stuck in his eye! Well, I think I should like to change even with him!"</p>
               <p>"Hang you, lout! What the deuce do you mean by spilling your beastly paint over my coat?" shouted the stranger, a very aristocratic, good-looking man of about twenty-five.</p>
               <p>"Beg your pardon, sir, I am sure. I am very sorry."</p>
               <p>"Just then Paul came out of the tobacconist's shop, smoking a very large cigar.</p>
               <p>"Why Paul Fairbrother, old fellow, is it you?" shouted the stranger, shaking him heartily by the hand.</p>
               <p>"What, Livingston! Well, this is indeed a surprise. How are you, old fellow? And when did you arrive in town?"</p>
               <p>"I have been in the city but twenty-four hours."</p>
               <p>"Oh, indeed! This eye-glass swell is a friend of our lodger's." Tony then went on daubing the shop-front, while the two friends walked a little way off, to chat about each other's affairs.</p>
               <p>"Are you on your way home, Mark?" asked Paul.</p>
               <p>"Well, not exactly. You see, I have some business to transact in this part."</p>
               <p>"Delightful work! who wouldn't be a rich man?"</p>
               <p>"Bah! my dear Paul, I am not so rich as you seem to imagine."</p>
               <p>"Ah, that's what all you wealthy fellows say. It's the way to keep off a borrower, and acts as a lock to your treasure. Besides, Mark, old fellow, I am sure you are rich, for you're becoming proud."</p>
               <p>"Proud, indeed! Nothing of the sort, I assure you. Come now, to show you that you are mistaken, I'll invite myself to dine with you, as I used to do in old times."</p>
               <p>"Humph! my dear fellow that's rather unfortunate, for I am afraid that our cupboard's empty."</p>
               <p>"Oh, never mind that. I am not a great eater."</p>
               <p>"I can't say I am hungry, Livingston, for I have been breakfasting with the head of my office, who has just been honored with promotion. So, of course, he invited all us young fellows to christen his new place."</p>
               <p>"And how are you getting on at the office, Paul? Have you been promoted lately?"</p>
               <p>"No, Mark, just the same. I am still a supernumerary clerk; but, however, I shan't have to wait long, for I am at the head of the list. By-the-by. I can take a day's leave to-morrow; so suppose you come and breakfast with us?"</p>
               <p>"Well, I am afraid—" said Livingston hesitating.</p>
               <p>"Come, come, Mark," said Paul clapping him on the shoulder. "I won't take any refusal. Why, my mother will be delighted to see my old college chum."</p>
               <p>"All right, then. Whenever I stand before you, it seems like opening an old book again."</p>
               <p>"Why, Mark, when we first met, and took a liking to each other."</p>
               <p>"Ah! and we have stuck to each other, haven't we, old boy? But come now, how is Mrs. Fairbrother?"</p>
               <p>"She is very well, thank you. By-the-by, she's in the church now."</p>
               <p>"What, with Antoinette? Oh, I suppose I ought to say Miss Fairbrother now. I recollect, when we were children, how we used to meet each Sunday. I was a boy, alone in the city, and your dear mother was a mother to me, whilst Antoinette, bless her! called me her brother. Ah! that was a happy time, Paul."</p>
               <p>"Well, I don't know, Mark. I can't say I am sorry it has gone."</p>
               <p>"So much the better for you, my boy. Our first regret, mark you, is like the first grey hair—it announces others to follow."</p>
               <p>"Why, you are quite a philosopher, I <unclear>vow.</unclear> You have lost your <emph>gaiety</emph> altogether."</p>
               <p>"Gaiety, my friend, is a disease. Fortunately, however, it can be cured, but by patience only."</p>
               <p>"Well, well, poor fellow, I can understand this change. You have lost your father, and I know what a loss that is, but, however, you needn't despair. You have a good fortune, and are now a lucky fellow."</p>
               <p>"Of course I am. Hang it, how that fellow's daubed my coat with his paint!" said he, apparently anxious to change the conversation.</p>
               <p>"Why, who the deuce did that?"</p>
               <p>"Oh, some lout just now, who was painting a greengrocer's shop."</p>
               <p>"How is it that a rich fellow like you hasn't a great-coat on?"</p>
               <p>"Well, to tell the truth," answered Livingston blushing, "I don't like a great-coat, and besides, it isn't cold to-day."</p>
               <p>"Isn't it? I can't say that I agree with you."</p>
               <p>"Perhaps not, but you New Yorkers are such cold mortals." Then, as if anxious to turn the conversation, he exclaimed: "Curses on that painter!"</p>
               <p>"Come, come, Mark, you must be indulgent to poor people."</p>
               <p>"Poor people! who do you call poor people?" shouted Livingston, evidently excited.</p>
               <p>"I can tell you, Paul, that a poor man more often wears a black coat than tatters. The really poor man is the clerk with a family, who has to deprive his children of food in order to buy himself a coat. It is the painter in his studio, who has to pawn his colors and easel in order to buy bread. It is the poet who dreams of the blue sky of Italy, and yet is on his way to the alms-house. It is the gentleman whose pedigree dates from the landing of the Mayflower, and is forced to button up his coat to hide his tattered shirt. It is the lawyer with no brief and no money. The truly poor man is the doctor without patients, the actor without an engagement, the author who cannot get his plays acted, the journalist without a newspaper; and yet, Paul, all these people must live, be lodged,<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6371-00000008"/> and feed themselves. Ah me! what a lot of misery there is in the world about which we know nothing; and yet, my friend, the doctor, the lawyer, the clerk, and the poet, all dressed in the only suit of clothes they have, will often take the last cent out of their pocket and give it to some shivering beggar whose mattress at home is stuffed with gold. These are the men who hide their misery by charity, who smoke to lose their appetite, who laugh aloud whilst a serpent is gnawing at their hearts. These, my friend, are the poor of New York."</p>
               <p>"Dear me, Mark, how you fire up! My word! you have studied philosophy with a vengeance."</p>
               <p>"Yes, Paul, I do observe these things."</p>
               <p>"My dear fellow, I am really sorry that my mother and sister did not observe this burst of eloquence. How pleased they would have been to be sure!"</p>
               <p>"Nonsense, Paul! Drat that fellow! I'm sure he has spoilt my coat."</p>
               <p>"Well never mind, you can easily afford another; and now good-bye, Mark. We shall expect you to-morrow."</p>
               <p>He then shook hands with his friend, and walked off, humming a song, whilst Livingston went in the other direction, in order to transact his business to which he has already alluded.</p>
               <p>That very inexpensive luxury known as building castles in the air was one in which Tony was wont to indulge. When last we heard of him, he was contenting himself with the thought of being a shirt-maker, and now he was just contemplating with pleasure the thought of becoming a lawyer's clerk, when Badger left the position he had taken up by the church, for professional purposes, and sauntered towards him.</p>
               <p>"And so, my man," said he, patronizingly, "you'd like to be a lawyer's clerk. I'm bothered if I can see the good of wishing to be what you really are not."</p>
               <p>"Don't you, indeed?" replied Tony.</p>
               <p>"Why, because I should like to lord it over those who are in the same position as the one I now occupy."</p>
               <p>"Well, you are a charitable fellow: <unclear>you</unclear> think more of other people than yourself."</p>
               <p>"And what if I do?" answered Tony, scarcely relishing Badger's style of conversation. "I tell you what it is, my man If you have never thought of anybody but yourself, why, hang me if you have done well."</p>
               <p>"Why, what do you know about it? For aught you can tell I may be a millionaire. A man does not wear his best clothes in business hours—Charity, please," said he, as Maggie approached, probably to see what her lover was doing. The appearance of the young lady did not encourage Badger to repeat his question, nor did he very much regret the disappearance of the two lovers, particularly as a middle-aged man, of goodly mien and stout proportions, Mr. Glum by name, soon appeared upon the scene.</p>
               <p>"Please, sir, take pity upon a poor beggar," said he, in his business voice.</p>
               <p>"I never give anything to idle fellows," was the unsatisfactory reply. "If you wish to live you must work."</p>
               <p>"This old fellow must be a philanthropist," muttered the beggar aloud, giving up all further chance of getting anything out of him.</p>
               <p>He was just moving off in search of other plunder, when his attention was attracted by the appearance of a face he knew well. It was our old acquaintance, Mr. Bloodgood, on whom the fifteen years which had elapsed since last we met him had produced no worse effect than to whiten his hair, and to enable him to clothe himself in as fine broadcloth as money could procure.</p>
               <p>"Well, old friend Glum, and how are you?"</p>
               <p>"Well—well, thank you, my worthy sir. Ah, you model father; I'll wager now that you are going to church for Miss Alida."</p>
               <p>"You are right. By-the-by, isn't to-morrow the day on which you are going with Alida to the different houses in this district to beg money for the poor?"</p>
               <p>"It is. Will you tell her that I'll call at twelve? Good day."</p>
               <p>The philanthropist walked off, whilst Mr. Bloodgood sauntered about, waiting until service was over. Soon the door opened, and his daughter appeared, followed by a footman in gorgeous livery.</p>
               <p>"Papa, I'm very cross indeed," said the young lady as soon as she perceived her father. "Baron Giverny, who promised to meet me at the church, of course wasn't there."</p>
               <p>"Perhaps, my dear, you didn't see him in the crowd."</p>
               <p>"Don't talk nonsense, pa! He wasn't there, I'm sure; besides, it was his business to look for me. Never mind; here comes another young man who I am sure would have been more polite."</p>
               <p>"Good morning, Miss Alida," said Livingston, coming up.</p>
               <p>"Ah, Mark Livingston, the best waltzer of last season, is it you?"</p>
               <p>"Oh, so this is old Bloodgood's daughter," muttered Badger, who had been eagerly watching the group for some time. "I prophesied fifteen years ago what sort of a woman she'd turn out, and hang me if I wasn't right."</p>
               <p>"Why, Livingston, you seem to be out of the world altogether. We haven't seen you for an age, I vow," said Mr. Bloodgood, gaily.</p>
               <p>"Well, Mr. Bloodgood, since the death of my father I have been nowhere."</p>
               <p>"Now it's time to show myself," said Badger advancing. "Please to bestow a trifle upon a poor beggar, sir."</p>
               <p>"What a nuisance!" muttered Livingston, evidently annoyed. "I've not a farthing."</p>
               <p>"Go away, you beggar!" shouted Bloodgood, touching him with his cane.</p>
               <p>"What, don't you recollect me, Mr. Bloodgood?" asked the beggar, boldly, looking into his face.</p>
               <p>"Badger!" ejaculated Bloodgood, "here is a dollar piece for you."</p>
               <p>Mr. Bloodgood, Livingston, and the young lady took their places in their carriage, which Badger followed with his eyes until it turned round the corner of a street.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
               <head type="sub">WELL DRESSED POVERTY.</head>
               <p>IN a plainly furnished and very modest apartment a young girl sat at work on a ball-dress. She had evidently labored long at her task, for her fingers drooped, and her eyes looked red and weary. Perhaps it was in order to cheer herself that she requested Tony (who was of a musical turn), when he came into the room on some trifling errand, to sing a few verses of a song. Tony, although declaring that he had no voice, soon burst out into a song, the refrain of which seemed to be— <q>
                     <l>"Lucy, you're a darling."</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Before he had finished the door opened, and Paul entered.</p>
               <p>"What, Tony singing again!"</p>
               <p>"Yes. We must amuse ourselves. Let's try again— <q>
                     <l>"'Lucy, you're a darling.'"</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>He then fell into a violent cough, and vowed he had no voice at all.</p>
               <p>"Dear me, how well you embroider, Antoinette?" said her brother taking up the piece of work on which she was busy.</p>
               <p>"What, Paul!" answered the young girl, smiling, "how attentive you are to notice such a trifle!"</p>
               <p>"My dear sister, whatever you do is no trifle to me. Hallo! who has brought this newspaper?" said he, taking one up that lay on the table.</p>
               <p>"It is mine, sir; at least it belongs to my boss, but I subscribe to it by borrowing it from him when he has finished; so I get it cheap, you see," said Tony.</p>
               <p>"What's this?" read Paul. "A magnificent performance took place last Wednesday at the Italian Opera."</p>
               <p>"Yes, that's correct. I was there," answered Tony.</p>
               <p>"And yesterday there was a clever piece at the Winter Garden?"</p>
               <p>"I was there also."</p>
               <p>"What! at the Winter Garden?" said Antoinette, surprised.</p>
               <p>"To-morrow at Wallack's there will be a performance for the reappearance of Miss——"</p>
               <pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6371-00000009"/>
               <p>"Ah! I shall be there."</p>
               <p>"Why, Tony, you seem to see everything," said Paul.</p>
               <p>"And you nothing at all," rejoined Tony.</p>
               <p>"Well, my good fellow, I must own that our position does not allow us to indulge in such luxuries; besides, I can't exactly see how you manage it."</p>
               <p>"Well, I'll tell you. On the night of a new piece I stand about the doors, or get in by promising to applaud the piece, if it is good."</p>
               <p>"But if it is bad?"</p>
               <p>"Oh, then I applaud all the same, for you know we ought not to discourage others."</p>
               <p>"Well, you are a lucky fellow, I can tell you, Tony."</p>
               <p>"Oh, I'm all right, but I can tell you I shouldn't mind changing places with you, for I am sure that you could go to all the theatres if you chose. Here's Mrs. Fairbrother, I see, so I'll say good day."</p>
               <p>"Why, mother, how ill you look!" said Paul, leading her to a seat.</p>
               <p>"I'm not ill, my dear son."</p>
               <p>"But you look very pale, mamma," said Antoinette.</p>
               <p>"Nonsense, dear. Has our landlady been here!"</p>
               <p>"No, mother, but here she comes," said her son, as the door opened and the landlady made her appearance.</p>
               <p>"Here's a letter for you, ma'am," said the landlady, giving Mrs. Fairbrother a letter. "It's an official note, that has just been left for you."</p>
               <p>"Be silent, I pray," said the lady, in an undertone, as she read the letter.</p>
               <p>"What is it, mamma?" asked Antoinette.</p>
               <p>"Nothing, nothing, child, only a prospectus. By-the-by, Mrs. Martin, will you let us know what we owe you?"</p>
               <p>"Certainly, ma'am, but you don't seem to be aware that I have some money to pay you."</p>
               <p>"How is that?"</p>
               <p>"Why, ma'am, I bought you two pigeons for fifty cents, and as you gave me seventy-five, I owe you twenty-five cents.</p>
               <p>"No, no, Mrs. Martin, I am sure you are making a mistake; for I heard you say, not long ago, that you paid seventy-five for them," said Antoinette.</p>
               <p>"Did I indeed, Miss?" answered the old lady, turning very red; "then I made a mistake."</p>
               <p>"So it appears. I wonder how many mistakes like this you have made!"</p>
               <p>"Nonsense!"</p>
               <p>"Come, don't deny it, my good Mrs. Martin. I am afraid that you are robbing yourself for us."</p>
               <p>"Not at all, my dear madam," replied the good lady; "besides I recollect how kind you were to my boy Tony, when he was ill of a fever. I'm sure, ma'am, if it had not been for you the lad would not have been alive now."</p>
               <p>"But that's several years ago," quietly interposed Antoinette.</p>
               <p>"That may be, miss, but a mother's heart never forgets a kindness shown to her child. So come, let's say no more about these pigeons."</p>
               <p>"You are a good woman, Mrs. Martin," said Mrs. Fairbrother, shaking her cordially by the hand. "When misfortunes crowd thickly around us, when all our friends forsake us, to meet such a noble creature as you, it seems as a light sent from Heaven to guide us poor wanderers on our weary way." Poor Mrs. Fairbrother, as if overcome by the weight of her troubles, burst into tears and would probably have given greater vent to her feelings, had she not been aroused by Mark Livingston shaking her violently by the hand.</p>
               <p>"What, Mark! I am indeed glad to see you. Bless you, my second son!"</p>
               <p>"But didn't Paul tell you that I was coming to-day?" asked the gentleman, looking round and feeling rather surprised at no appearance of breakfast.</p>
               <p>"Not a word; but here he is to explain for himself."</p>
               <p>"That's right, Livingston, I am glad you are punctual. Mother, he is going to breakfast with us," said the young man gaily.</p>
               <p>The joyous expression upon the good lady's face at once vanished. Her poverty told her how hard a matter it would be to provide a breakfast, and her pride also let her know what a poor repast it would be when it was provided. Luckily there was a deliverer at hand; for Mrs. Martin, who had been standing in the room all the time, quite overjoyed at the pleasure which these people took in each other's society, particularly the furtive glance of love which her sharp eyes noticed pass between Antoinette and Livingston, nodded <figure>
                     <head>BLOODGOOD'S RESIDENCE</head>
                  </figure> significantly at Mrs. Fairbrother, and at once left the room in order to prepare a repast in which her coffee and those delicious cakes, all hot, of her husband were to play a good part.</p>
               <p>"I knew he'd come back," said Antoinette to herself, blushing with pleasure.</p>
               <p>"Ah! Antoinette, my dear little foster sister, what a beautiful girl you are now. To think that when I left you, you were a<pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6371-00000010"/> little girl in short petticoats, who played with Paul and me, and who used to come every night to her brother Mark to be kissed. And you, dear mother, how pale and thin you look! I hope you do not suffer bad health?"</p>
               <p>"Not at all, Mark; I keep pretty well, thank God," answered the poor woman, smiling, in the hope of concealing the grief under which she was suffering.</p>
               <p>"At what time have you ordered breakfast, Paul? I am as hungry as a hunter, I can tell you. Why, I think I've scarcely tasted food for fifteen hours: I've been so busy running about that I have not had time for anything."</p>
               <p>"All right, Mark, breakfast will be ready at the hour," said Mrs. Fairbrother, sinking down into her chair. "Oh, this agony is insupportable! I must go to Mr. Bloodgood again. Oh, heaven! have mercy upon us!" She then rose and leisurely put on her bonnet.</p>
               <p>"Hallo, mother, where are you off to?"</p>
               <p>"You are not going to leave us alone at breakfast?" asked Livingston, quietly taking her by the hand.</p>
               <p>"No, my son, I am only going out on business for a short time. I shall be back soon." Mark however, like a polite young man, took care to see the old lady to the street door, and then bounded up three stairs at a time, in order to have a long chat with his little foster sister.</p>
               <p>"Dear Antoinette," said, he, taking a seat beside her, "I am so very glad to see you. I really had no idea that you could have changed so much."</p>
               <p>"Indeed!" answered the young girl, blushing. "But come, Mark, how do you like this rose?" said she, pointing to her embroidery.</p>
               <p>"It's charming; but, Antoinette, if it were like the finest rose in the garden, it would not equal the blush on your cheek."</p>
               <p>As if to show that his simile was correct, Antoinette blushed deeper and deeper.</p>
               <p>Paul, who was naturally pleased at the interest his friend evidently took in his sister's society, now interposed in a mock respectful manner.</p>
               <p>"I say, Antoinette, you must mind what you say to Mark, for he is a gentleman now. He is the heir to several estates. H'm! I feel rather flattered at being able to entertain at my table such an accomplished guest."</p>
               <p>"Come, come, Paul, if you want to do me a favor, never allude again to my property," said Mark somewhat annoyed.</p>
               <p>"Well, your are a strange fellow!"</p>
               <p>"Not at all. Do you think I am stupid enough to feel proud of my lands? Why, it's only <foreign xml:lang="FRA">parvenus</foreign> who are so stupidly conceited."</p>
               <p>"Well said, Mark!" exclaimed Antoinette, glowing with pleasure.</p>
               <p>"The best property, Paul, is that which flows from the heart."</p>
               <p>"Of course, that's all very well; but still I think a little land does no harm."</p>
               <p>"Perhaps not," answered Livingston, desirous of an argument; "still property may influence and even impair the mind. You must not, however, think that it has that effect upon me. My character is formed. Ah, me!" continued he, sighing; "what is life? what are riches? as long as there is happiness for all of us in this world."</p>
               <p>"Yes, Mark; it's easy for a rich man to talk in that <unclear>strain</unclear>. Still I don't envy you."</p>
               <p>"You'd be wrong it you did."</p>
               <p>"In money matters, my dear fellow, I am as careless as you are. Why, I have never even asked my mother how much we have. A little more poverty wont make much difference, and yet I often wish we were a little richer, just for your sake, dear sister."</p>
               <p>"And I for yours," said the girl, smiling.</p>
               <p>"Well, never mind, we mustn't grumble, as we have enough to live on; besides, I shall work hard to make money; and as for you, dear, you have quite enough charms to get a husband. Hasn't she, Mark? Why, what are you blushing for?"</p>
               <p>"I wish you'd mind your own business, Paul, and not trouble about me."</p>
               <p>"Very well; now don't be cross. Of course you didn't blush. On the contrary, you were as pale as a sheet."</p>
               <p>"Oh, do be quiet, Paul!" said he, endeavoring to look cross. "What a nuisance brothers are, to be sure!"</p>
               <p>"You are not going to leave us, I hope?" asked Livingston, looking at her very affectionately.</p>
               <p>"Not for long; I shall be back soon."</p>
               <p>As he opened the door to let her out, Mark whispered. "Return as soon as you can, dear Antoinette."</p>
               <p>"Isn't she a nice girl, Mark?" asked Paul, when the young men were alone.</p>
               <p>"I should think she was. Why, your sister is—is—is—"</p>
               <p>"Well, what?"</p>
               <p>"Oh, never mind! a very nice girl, to be sure. Oh, cursed gold! foe to all true love!" exclaimed he, in a excited manner. "I wish I had none; but I've too much, for I am in debt. Well, never mind. By-the-by, Paul, may I wash my hands in your room."</p>
               <p>"Of course, my dear fellow. Do just as you please here."</p>
               <p>"Thanks. Will you show me the way?"</p>
               <p>Scarcely had the young men left the room when the door was opened, and their landlord Mr. Bloodgood appeared.</p>
               <p>"Humph! nobody here. Well, I'll sit down till somebody comes."</p>
               <p>After he had waited a few minutes Paul came in.</p>
               <p>"What is your business, sir?" asked he, surprised to see a man in possession of the room.</p>
               <p>"My business, young man, is to speak to the people who lodge here," was the gruff answer.</p>
               <p>"My mother, sir, is not in at present. Will you wait for her?"</p>
               <p>"My time is too precious to wait. However, I daresay I can talk to your mother's son just as well. I am the landlord of this house, in which I believe you have lodged for two or three years. Now, sir, I usually allow such matters to be arranged by my agent, but on the present occasion I have determined to manage the affair myself."</p>
               <p>"What affair, sir?" asked Paul; eagerly.</p>
               <p>"I have endeavored, young man, to arrange it as pleasantly as I can, for I believed your mother to be a woman of her word."</p>
               <p>"I really don't understand you."</p>
               <p>"Well, sir, your mother has not kept her word."</p>
               <p>"How?"</p>
               <p>"Listen, then. She promised that yesterday she'd pay a part of the rent. As I expected, however, she did not keep her word, and I shall therefore instruct my agent to proceed at once. Do you know, sir, that you owe me more than a year's rent?"</p>
               <p>"Is it possible?" exclaimed Paul, aghast.</p>
               <p>"What! hasn't she told you? Surely you are old enough to look after her affairs."</p>
               <p>"I don't believe it, sir. There's some mistake."</p>
               <p>"I can tell you, young man, I only wish there was," said old Bloodgood, smiling. "However, I've no more time to waste. So just tell your mother that if a part of the rent is not paid this evening, she'll probably see the constables to-morrow."</p>
               <p>"Have pity, sir, I beg!"</p>
               <p>"I wont, young man!" shouted he, fiercely. "How the deuce can I afford to lose money? I wish I had never bought these houses."</p>
               <p>So saying, he pulled the door open and walked down stairs.</p>
               <p>"Is it possible that my mother is in debt, and yet hasn't told me?" said Paul to himself. "It must be true, however or else this man wouldn't have come bothering here. What's this? Her desk. I'll see what is in it." He tore open the desk and rummaged for a few minutes. Suddenly sank back in his chair, exclaiming:</p>
               <p>"Pawnbrokers' tickets! We are ruined, indeed!"</p>
               <p>He buried his head in his hands and<pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6371-00000011"/> wept bitterly for some time. In a short time, however, he was aroused by a tap at the door. After brushing away his tears and upbraiding himself for his weakness, he called, "Come in!" and young Tony entered, followed by Badger, still in his business dress of a beggar.</p>
               <p>"Oh, Mr. Paul, this poor devil's been asking for you, so I thought I'd better bring him up," said Tony.</p>
               <p>"Well, and what do you want?"</p>
               <p>"Why, if you please, sir, it's this way. This morning, not having had anything to eat for a very long time, I was begging just outside the church, when by chance I found this prayer-book, and as I was told that it belonged to one of the ladies who lived here, I thought I'd better bring it back."</p>
               <p>Paul took the book and said, "Quite right; it belongs to my sister."</p>
               <p>"Then I am glad I returned it, because you see ladies generally value those things," said he, knowingly. "You wont forget a poor beggar who has been honest enough to bring back the book to you?"</p>
               <p>Paul fumbled mechanically in his pocket.</p>
               <p>"My good man, I've no change just now; call again another time."</p>
               <p>While Paul was searching his pockets in the hope of finding something to give the beggar, Badger was peering with his cold gray eyes round the apartment. Suddenly he beheld a portrait in oil of an old sea-captain. Starting back and trembling in every limb, he clutched Paul by the arm and shouted:</p>
               <p>"Whose portrait is that, sir? Quick, tell me!"</p>
               <p>"Why what the deuce, man, can that be to you?" said Paul, surprised at the sudden interest shown by the beggar. "It's the portrait of my father, if you wish to know."</p>
               <p>"Your father, sir; then your name is—?"</p>
               <p>"Paul Fairbrother; but what of that?"</p>
               <p>"That's the name," said Badger; "that's the name; and you are very like him, sir—very like."</p>
               <p>"What! did you know my father?</p>
               <p>"Not exactly, sir; but I've seen him.</p>
               <p>"Well, then, you old muff, what's the good of making this fuss and frightening a fellow for nothing?" said Tony, who had listened attentively to the conversation. "Hang it! you have given me quite a turn. Now come along, what are you waiting for? I suppose you want something for bringing back that book, eh?"</p>
               <p>"You must call again, that's all, for I've no change," said Paul, rather confused.</p>
               <p>"I wouldn't take a farthing from you, sir," was the beggar's answer.</p>
               <p>"Well I'm blowed, you're a pretty beggar, you are!" murmured Tony. "Come along, then, I suppose you've nothing else to wait for?" He dragged the beggar out of the room, the latter murmuring all the way down stairs, and speaking as if in a dream—</p>
               <p>"His son!—his son!—his son!"</p>
               <p>"It's very strange!" said Paul, when the door closed, "Whatever made that fellow turn so pale and tremble at the sight of my father's portrait? He says he did not know him."</p>
               <p>"Oh, Paul, our last hope's gone!" exclaimed his mother, rushing into the room. "We are ruined!"</p>
               <p>"Ah, mother, I fear we are!" answered the young man, sadly, taking his mother's hand; "for the man's been here. Have we any money, mother?"</p>
               <p>Mrs. Fairbrother rushed to her desk, but finding all the papers scattered about, she turned to her son and said:</p>
               <p>"Ah, Paul, I see you know all. My poor boy, we are beggars."</p>
               <p>"Mother—mother, why did you not tell your children about this before?"</p>
               <p>"Paul, my son," said the mother, her eyes full of tears, "I hoped to keep this grief to myself, in order to spare you the pain of it."</p>
               <p>"But, mother, I am a man now; it's my duty to comfort you."</p>
               <p>"Paul, you are a dear, good son, but what courage is equal to that of a mother! This sorrow, my boy, would have stopped your work; nay, it might have killed you, for at your age gaiety is the chief elixir of life. You would have sacrificed your future to the present, whilst I have no future to sacrifice."</p>
               <p>"But, mother, how could you have hidden this terrible existence from me?"</p>
               <p>"My boy, I neither hoped nor wished to do so. I hoped to drag on in misery until I could say, `Paul, I have sacrificed all to you. It is now your turn to watch over your mother.'"</p>
               <p>"That I would have done, and will now, dear mother, but what of Antoinette?—does she know of this misfortune?"</p>
               <p>"No, she does not."</p>
               <p>"Oh, mother—dear mother, how can I ever repay you for all you have suffered? Better become a common workman than drag on such a life as this."</p>
               <p>"My poor son, the joy and pride of your father! To think that the money which he saved and hoarded with so much care for you and your sister should be lost so strangely. The fit which killed him in a strange place when he was near us has brought ruin, perhaps death on us. Oh, my boy—my children! what have we done, how have we sinned, that we should be punished thus?"</p>
               <p>"Cheer up, mother—cheer up, I beg, for I can work; and mother, who knows but after all this reverse of fortune may not be for our good, and that happier days are yet in store for us? Come, dry your eyes, mother, for I hear Mark on the stairs, and we must not let our guest see in what a sad strait fortune has left us."</p>
               <p>"Now, Paul," said the young man gaily, as he entered the room, "I hope breakfast is nearly ready, for I'm devilish hungry, I can tell you. Hallo, old fellow—how pale you look! Why, what's the matter?"</p>
               <p>"Nothing—nothing at all."</p>
               <p>"Ah, I know you wan't your breakfast—so do I. Why, it must be nearly twelve o'clock."</p>
               <p>"Not quite; the church clock has only just struck half—past eleven," said toinette, as she came in.</p>
               <p>Livingston's hand mechanically went to his waistcoat-pocket for his watch. "Wait a minute, I'll tell you what time it is," said he. His search, however, was unsuccessful. Turning rather red, and looking uncomfortable, he peered round the room, in the hopes of finding something to talk about.</p>
               <p>"Why, Antoinette, my dear, how nice you look! There was no need to dress so smartly, because an old friend has come to see you."</p>
               <p>"Nonsense, Mark! I am not smart. Am I, ma?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, my darling, and you are a dear, good child. Come, now, here's Mrs. Martin with breakfast; so now, children, sit round the table."</p>
               <p>They then took their seats, and endeavored to do ample justice to the hot cakes and coffee provided by the good Mrs. Martin. In this praiseworthy object we regret to say that none succeeded except Mr. Livingston, who ate and chatted gaily in the hope of reviving the drooping spirits of the widow and her son. As for Antoinette, she was too happy in the contemplation of her foster-brother to care much for eating. Sad and dejected, however, as some of these good people were, they would have been yet sadder had they known that worse trouble was in store for them.</p>
               <p>Towards the end of the meal Tony knocked at the door.</p>
               <p>"Oh, Paul, here are the people who go round to collect money for the poor."</p>
               <p>"And they come to us," murmured Paul, sighing.</p>
               <p>"Yes, sir; there's a gentleman and a lady dressed so smartly, and now they're coming up stairs."</p>
               <p>The door opened, and in walked Mr. Glum and Miss Bloodgood, the latter holding a bag in which the money she had collected jingled in a manner very tantalizing to the people, whom she expected would soon increase the store it contained.</p>
               <p>"Ladies and gentlemen," began Mr. Glum, bowing, "there are many poor people<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6371-00000012"/> ple in this neighborhood who are almost without the common necessaries of life. Will you therefore subscribe a trifle in order to aid us in making these poor people comfortable?"</p>
               <p>"What shall we do?—what shall we do?" murmured Mrs. Fairbrother.</p>
               <p>"Mr. Livingston will give something I am sure," suggested Alida, smiling on him,</p>
               <p>This sign of recognition was not lost on Antoinette, who felt all the pangs of jealousy at the thought of her foster-brother and this fine lady being known to each other.</p>
               <p>"Of course, Miss Bloodgood, I shall only be too happy to do anything to oblige you."</p>
               <p>"You are very kind," said the young lady, holding the bag out to him.</p>
               <p>Mr. Livingston fumbled in all his pockets, but in vain. Endeavoring, however, under these somewhat embarrassing circumstances to look as calm as he could, he excused himself under the plea that he had left his purse at home.</p>
               <p>"It does not matter much, however," said he, "for I'd only fifteen dollars in it."</p>
               <p>"Allow me then, to lend you some money," said Alida, with a provoking smile, as she drew forth a purse laden to the top with gold pieces.</p>
               <p>"Many thanks, Miss Bloodgood. Please put five dollars in for me."</p>
               <p>The young lady did as she was requested, and then presented the bag to Mrs. Fairbrother and her daughter.</p>
               <p>The good lady nearly cried with shame and vexation.</p>
               <p>"Come, mamma dear, give something," said her daughter.</p>
               <p>Paul looked on in despair.</p>
               <p>"Oh, heaven! and we've nothing to give."</p>
               <p>"The lady, I am sure, will not refuse to give a trifle in charity," said Alida, smiling blandly.</p>
               <p>The poor lady blushed with shame and grief.</p>
               <p>"Here, Paul, put this gold dollar in for madam," whispered Mrs. Martin, putting one in his hand.</p>
               <p>"Of course, if it is objectionable, we wont press you any further," said Alida, somewhat contemptuously.</p>
               <p>"Not at all," was Paul's reply, as he dashed the coin into the bag. "All those who can afford it ought to give a trifle to the poor."</p>
               <p>The visitors then quitted the room, leaving the poor inmates to console each other, at parting with money which they themselves required for their own wants.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
               <head type="sub">DISHONEST WEALTH.</head>
               <p>THE house which Mr. Bloodgood inhabited was in the most fashionable quarter of the metropolis. The fickle goddess of Fortune had indeed smiled upon him, since fifteen years before he had entertained thoughts of tempting her in another land. The investments which he had made with the money acquired from the old sea-captain, had turned out so well that his capital had gradually increased, until what with investing his spare capital in stocks and lending it out at rather an immoderate rate of interest, he had managed to acquire an immense fortune. His ambition was now to make a wealthy match for his daughter, and it was for this purpose that he had taken a large house on the Fifth Avenue, as we have mentioned. A few days after we had met Miss Bloodgood on her journey of charity, she appeared in the drawing-room holding a letter in her hand and evidently in a state of great excitement.</p>
               <p>"It's infamous!—it's shameful!" she exclaimed.</p>
               <p>She then rang the bell loudly, and before the footman could have had time to answer the summons, she rang violently a second time, and on the appearance of the old butler Joseph, who had been in the service of the family many years, said:</p>
               <p>"What do you mean, Joseph, by not answering the bell when I ring? You are as deaf as a post."</p>
               <p>"But Miss—"</p>
               <p>"Hold your tongue," shouted the young lady, stamping her foot, "and go and tell my father that I want to speak to him at once."</p>
               <p>The servant bowed and left the room.</p>
               <p>"Whatever could have been the motive," muttered the young lady to herself, "of such a shameful insult; I'll make him suffer for it yet."</p>
               <p>Joseph here entered the room to tell his mistress that Mr. Bloodgood was very much engaged at that moment, but that he would speak to her later.</p>
               <p>"Go back to your master directly, and tell him that I insist upon seeing him at once."</p>
               <p>The servant endeavored to make an excuse, but a threat from the young lady that he should be discharged if he disobeyed her, made him hurry off to his master as fast as his old legs could carry him. In a few minutes Mr. Bloodgood returned, evidently annoyed at the rather peremptory tones in which the wish to see him had been conveyed.</p>
               <p>"Now, my dear, what is the matter?—I am very busy, and don't like to be interrupted."</p>
               <p>"Oh, you've come at last!" said the young lady.</p>
               <p>"Yes, my dear; so come and kiss me," answered the father in the affectionate tone which he found himself forced to use in the presence of his daughter, whom he loved so much.</p>
               <p>"Well, papa, now I'll tell you why I sent for you. I am young, rich—very rich, I believe, and—at least you have told me—many men are longing to marry me."</p>
               <p>"Yes, my dear, that's true."</p>
               <p>"Well then, papa, read this letter," and she handed him a note.</p>
               <p>The father took the letter and glanced at the direction. "Why, it is directed to me, Alida!"</p>
               <p>"Of course it is; that's why I opened it," was the quiet reply.</p>
               <p>"Now, let's see what this letter's about. Ahem! from the Baron Giverny, refusing an alliance with our family."</p>
               <p>"Yes, papa, he refuses me! This is the third time that your daughter has been thus insulted; this is the third time that my marriage has been arranged, and then broken off at the last moment. Now, if you were not a millionaire I could understand it; if my reputation were even doubtful I could also understand it; but under the present circumstances I cannot make out how it happens."</p>
               <p>"No more can I, my child; but I will try to ascertain the cause."</p>
               <p>"You can save yourself the trouble, papa" answered the young girl, bitterly; "I can guess the cause."</p>
               <p>"What is it, dear?" asked the father, eagerly.</p>
               <p>"Well then, papa, there are some people who are not satisfied with a fortune or the reputation of the girl they are about to marry."</p>
               <p>"Why, what else do they want?" asked the father, smiling.</p>
               <p>"What else? Listen to me. How have you made your money, father? People say it is by <emph>usury.</emph>"</p>
               <p>"Be silent, child!" exclaimed the banker, angrily.</p>
               <p>"As you please, papa; only if this goes on I shall never be married. But perhaps you don't care about that."</p>
               <p>"Alida, don't be so ungrateful. You know how I love you."</p>
               <p>"That's all very well, pa," answered the young lady, coolly; but I want the love of a young man."</p>
               <p>"Ah, my child, if ever you are blessed with children I hope they may never speak thus to you."</p>
               <p>"Oh, that's enough, pa; but come, isn't it annoying to think that this very morning I had engaged a young woman to embroider a coronet upon my linen?"</p>
               <p>The banker hesitated a minute before he replied, and then, as if suddenly struck by an idea, he said—</p>
               <p>"Come, come, my child; things are not so bad after all. I think I can get an estate for you. There's a young fellow who has just succeeded to a property, and who is, I know, dreadfully in debt. I believe that you are acquainted with him. Well,<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6371-00000013"/> he's <unclear>due</unclear> we to be here soon. If you like him, drop your handkerchief, and I'll lend him what <unclear>he</unclear> requires at a moderate rate of interest; if, on the contrary, he does not answer your expectations, I'll not lend him a farthing, and he and his estate go to the devil. His name is—"</p>
               <p>Before he could complete the sentence, the door opened, and the servant announced:</p>
               <p>"Mr. Mark Livingston."</p>
               <p>"As I thought: the bird has soon fallen into the trap. This is your husband, Alida," whispered the banker.</p>
               <p>"Good morning, Miss Bloodgood; allow me to discharge myself from your debt," said the young man; bowing gracefully, and presenting two pieces of gold to the young lady.</p>
               <p>"You are very punctual in your payment," answered Alida, smiling graciously.</p>
               <p>"What is it?" asked Mr. Bloodgood.</p>
               <p>"Oh, nothing, papa. But Mark, how is it you are in such a hurry; it's only three days since I lent you the money?"</p>
               <p>"How lucky I met an old friend who owed me a hundred dollars," said Livingston, aside.</p>
               <p>"You must know, Miss Bloodgood, that I came here for two purposes; the first was to see you."</p>
               <p>"And the other was—?" asked she eagerly.</p>
               <p>"To see your father."</p>
               <p>"Indeed!" said the old man, rubbing his hands.</p>
               <p>"Oh, very well, then I'll leave you two together," said the young lady.</p>
               <p>"Not at all; please don't go," said Livingston. "What I have to tell your father is no secret, all New York knows of it."</p>
               <p>"Please explain yourself," asked the banker, although he well knew what was coming.</p>
               <p>"Certainly, sir, I can easily do that. In three words, I am ruined."</p>
               <p>"Is it possible?" exclaimed Mr. Blood-good, simulating the greatest surprise.</p>
               <p>"It's quite true, sir. My worthy father mortgaged all his property, which was worth 100,000, for about half the amount; and if in a fortnight I cannot raise this sum, all the land will be sold without reserve. If, however, I can raise this money, I can pay off the mortgage, and save the property."</p>
               <p>"That's plain enough;" quietly said Bloodgood, taking a chair and requesting his visitor to be seated; "and I am sure that you can easily raise the money you require. I only wish you had applied to me a fortnight earlier, I would then have lent you the money with pleasure; but at the present moment it is really impossible—quite impossible."</p>
               <p>"As I expected," said Livingston, sadly. He then turned round hastily to pick up the paper which Alida had let fall. "I am sorry, sir, that my errand to you is unsuccessful. I can only apologize for taking up so much of your valuable time, and beg to offer you my best thanks for the good wishes you seem to entertain for me." He rose, bowed, and was making his way towards the door, when he was recalled by the banker.</p>
               <p>"Stop, stop, my young friend; don't be in such a grievous hurry. I knew your father well, and I assure you that I am ready to do all in my power to aid his son. Therefore I will see at once if I cannot raise the money for you. I must ask you to call here at eleven to-morrow morning, when we'll see what can be done for you."</p>
               <p>"Thanks, sir, many thanks!" shouted the young man, quite overjoyed. He then shook his hand heartily, bowed politely to the young lady, and rushed out of the room.</p>
               <p>As soon as the door had closed, Blood-good kissed his daughter, and said: "Then you choose this gentleman for a husband?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, pa; but now I want you to do something else."</p>
               <p>"Well, Alida, and what is it now?"</p>
               <p>"Come and sit down at this desk, and take this pen." The old man did as he was bid.</p>
               <p>"Now, papa, write to Mr. Livingston."</p>
               <p>"What for, my dear?"</p>
               <p>"To tell him that you'll lend him the <unclear>amount</unclear> he requires without interest."</p>
               <p>"No, my dear," said Bloodgood, smiling at the absurdity of the proposal, "I really can't do that; I must make a little profit out of the transaction."</p>
               <p>"Not at all, papa. Do as I tell you," said his daughter, firmly.</p>
               <p>"But, my darling, it's so absurd. You want—"</p>
               <p>"I want a gentleman for a husband, and am not going to let the present chance slip through my fingers."</p>
               <p>"Clever girl!" muttered her father, as he sat down and wrote a note informing Mark, that out of respect for his late father, he would lend him the money without interest, and begging him to call at his office for it on the following morning. As soon as the note was sealed, Alida rang the bell, and told the servant who appeared that he was to deliver it at once.</p>
               <p>Scarcely had the door closed when a noise was heard in the passage—"I tell you that you cannot see Mr. Bloodgood," said Joseph.</p>
               <p>"That's a lie!" shouted a man, bursting the door open, "for I see him now."</p>
               <p>"What, Badger!" exclaimed the banker. "You can leave the room," added he, as Joseph seemed disposed to linger, in order to get rid of the apparently obnoxious visitor.</p>
               <p>"Get out, slow legs!" shouted Badger, in order to quicken the retreating steps of the old servant.</p>
               <p>"I must apologize, my dear friend, for not calling before, but the fact is I had some difficulty in ascertaining your address," said the visitor.</p>
               <p>"Who is this man, papa?" asked Alida, not very well pleased with the stranger.</p>
               <p>"Oh, what a nice young lady," said Badger, quite at his ease. "Ah, miss, I dare say you forget that fifteen years ago, I nursed you on my knee many a time when I was head clerk in your father's bank!"</p>
               <p>"Pshaw! man, don't remind me of that. Do you want money?" added she, taking out her purse.</p>
               <p>"Not at all, my dear young lady. I have come to shake hands with you, to render you a slight service, and not to ask one of you. I have also called on a matter of business, as I wish to refresh your papa's memory."</p>
               <p>"We'll talk of that some other time," said the banker, anxiously.</p>
               <p>"As you please," was the cool answer.</p>
               <p>"Don't mind me. My father and I have no secrets," said Alida, quickly.</p>
               <p>"Haven't you. though? I know better. Hallo I here's old top," said he, as Joseph entered.</p>
               <p>"This way, young woman."</p>
               <p>The door opened, and Antoinette came in.</p>
               <p>"Who is this?" said Alida, haughtily.</p>
               <p>"The young woman, ma'am, whom you sent for to embroider some things,"</p>
               <p>"Why this is the young lady who came to our room this morning to collect money for the poor," said Antoinette to herself.</p>
               <p>"I think I know her face," added Alida.</p>
               <p>"My word, she's my young benefactress!" muttered Badger, recognizing in Antoinette the young lady who had so often befriended him.</p>
               <p>"Can you embroider, young woman?" asked Alida.</p>
               <p>"Yes, ma'am; and I am very much in want of work," answered Antoinette, modestly.</p>
               <p>"Poor thing! I wish I had a little money to give her," muttered Badger.</p>
               <p>"Well, then, young woman, I'll engage you."</p>
               <p>"Thank you, miss. I was told that you wanted me to embroider some handkerchiefs with a baron's coronet."</p>
               <p>"Not at all, young woman; I want a gentleman's initials. Come this way."</p>
               <p>The pair then left the room, to the great delight of Badger, who was anxiously waiting to explain the object of his visit.</p>
               <p>"What can the fellow want? I need not fear him," muttered old Bloodgood.</p>
               <pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6371-00000014"/>
               <p>"Poor girl!" said his former clerk, still thinking of Antoinette; "I thought she was rich when she gave me some money so often."</p>
               <p>"How is it, Badger, that you are so badly off?" inquired the banker, rushing into the breach at once.</p>
               <p>"I can't help it. You know what I told you. My passions are the cause of it. I spent all your little present in six months—went off to California, got into trouble, and came back much poorer than when I started."</p>
               <p>"Well, then, why don't you work?"</p>
               <p>"Oh, that's a good joke! I went once in search of a situation as clerk in a bank, but I couldn't get a character. Now, if I'd only met you a little earlier, I might have done something."</p>
               <p>"Well, well," said the banker, impatiently, "now what do you want of me?"</p>
               <p>"What! don't you know?"</p>
               <p>"How the deuce am I likely to know?"</p>
               <p>"Come, come, that's rather too good a joke. Oh, never mind, I'll soon tell you. However, I don't want to talk of your bankruptcy, which was very well managed. I know all about it—how you got your certificate, set up again, and at length came here."</p>
               <p>"Be silent, fellow!" shouted Mr. Bloodgood, in a rage.</p>
               <p>"All right, old boy, I'll soon come to the point, because I have not much time to spare myself, as I am going out to dine this evening."</p>
               <p>"Now then, be quick."</p>
               <p>"Well, what is the good of telling you what you know already? The sea-faring man died fifteen years ago, of apoplexy, and left you 100,000 dollars, which I believe did not appear in your bankruptcy. Perhaps you'll say that you gave me 4,000 of them. I don't deny it."</p>
               <p>"My good fellow, I don't know what you are talking about. Nobody ever fell down dead at my office, nor left me the money you mention."</p>
               <p>"You sly old fox!" shouted Badger, joyously, slapping the banker on the back; "<emph>I've got the receipt!</emph>"</p>
               <p>"It can't be true!" exclaimed Mr Bloodgood, terrified; "besides in your hands it is of no value."</p>
               <p>"Humph! that's true," said Badger.</p>
               <p>"For, my good fellow, this receipt can only be presented to me by the heirs of the old captain, and they are dead," rejoined Mr. Bloodgood triumphantly.</p>
               <p>"No they're not!"</p>
               <p>"What is their name?"</p>
               <p>"The same as their father's."</p>
               <p>"But we never knew that," said the banker, as a last chance.</p>
               <p>"You didn't, I know; but I, like a good man of business, took the precaution of ascertaining his name whilst I filled out the receipt. Good day, my friend; I shall return soon."</p>
               <p>"Why, where are you going?"</p>
               <p>"Only to find the son of the old sea-captain."</p>
               <p>Just as he was walking off in high glee, Joseph opened the door, and announced.</p>
               <p>"Mr. Paul Fairbrother."</p>
               <p>"My man!" chuckled Badger to himself. "Why, I've got the game in my own hands now, so I'd better stop and play my trump card as soon as I can."</p>
               <p>"Well, sir, and what do you want, pray?" asked Bloodgood, in an angry tone, as Paul bowed to him, whilst Badger quietly took a seat in an easy chair, and pretended to be absorbed in a book.</p>
               <p>"Oh, sir, the men have seized our furniture?"</p>
               <p>"Well, I suppose I had a right to do that?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, sir, I know you had," answered the young man, in a tremulous voice.</p>
               <p>"Come, this is retributive justice," said Badger, under his book. "Why, these two men ought to change places."</p>
               <p>"I've not come to dispute your right, sir," continued Paul, humbly;" but among our things is a portrait of my father, and as it can be of no value to you, I hope you will let my mother keep it, as I assure you we prize it highly."</p>
               <p>"Well, then, keep it, and now good day."</p>
               <p>"Thank you, sir, for my mother, and for my sister, too." He then took up his hat and was preparing to go, when Badger strode up and patted him on the shoulder.</p>
               <p>"Wait a minute, young man."</p>
               <p>Paul looked up, and was surprised to see the man who had returned his mother's prayer-book, and on whom the portrait of his father had produced so strange an effect."</p>
               <p>"My lad, I know the portrait you mention, and well remember the noble, open features of your late father. I believe, judging from his dress, that he was a sailor?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, sir, he was a captain, trading in the Indian seas."</p>
               <p>"A noble profession, young man, although a continual struggle with the elements. A sailor does not die in his bed." All this time Badger kept his eye fixed on Bloodgood, and gloated over the painful glance which the banker threw at him.</p>
               <p>"My poor father, sir, did not, however, die at sea," continued Paul, his eyes filling with tears. "He lost his life on his return from along voyage, of an apoplectic fit."</p>
               <p>"How sad! Isn't it sad, Mr. Bloodgood."</p>
               <p>Beads of perspiration stood on the banker's forehead. Instead of answering, he quietly rang the bell, and when the servant appeared he said:</p>
               <p>"Don't go yet, dear Mr. Badger. I have something else to say to you."</p>
               <p>"I can wait a few minutes," was the cool reply.</p>
               <p>"Well, I'll just finish with this gentleman. In the meanwhile, Mr. Badger, step into the next room. You will find luncheon there."</p>
               <p>"I'm agreeable, Mr. Bloodgood. By-the-by," said he, in an undertone to him, "this young man is the son of an old friend, so mind what you're about, as I've got the receipt. Now, Silvertop," said he to the servant, "show the way."</p>
               <p>A few minutes elapsed after his departure before Bloodgood could sufficiently recover his composure to speak. At length he said:</p>
               <p>"Young man, I fear you may have thought me somewhat harsh. However, your position, I own, grieves me, and I am willing to aid you as far as I can."</p>
               <p>"Oh, sir!" exclaimed Paul, joyously.</p>
               <p>"Wait a minute, sir. Don't thank me too soon. You must leave North America at once."</p>
               <p>"Oh, sir, for my mother and sister I'd go anywhere."</p>
               <p>"Mind, sir, you'll have to leave the country for a long time, perhaps for ever."</p>
               <p>"Sir, my country," said Paul, in a sudden burst of enthusiasm, "is wherever I can live with honor."</p>
               <p>"Listen, then, to me. One of my agents in South America, at Rio Janeiro, is in want of a well-educated young man as clerk. The salary is 1,000 dollars a year, and ultimately you will have a share in the business."</p>
               <p>"And when must I start?"</p>
               <p>"To-morrow, my young friend, in order to be on board the <hi rend="i"/>Elizabeth the same evening."</p>
               <p>"I am ready, sir," was Paul's cheerful reply.</p>
               <p>"That's good! I like promptitude; now go and tell your mother, bid her good-bye, and return as soon as you can for your letters of credit and the expenses of your voyage."</p>
               <p>"Oh, Mr. Bloodgood," exclaimed the young man, seizing his hand, "how I have misjudged you!"</p>
               <p>"I am sorry to hear it, sir. Be assured that I am actuated by motives of humanity."</p>
               <p>"Heaven bless you, Mr. Bloodgood; you have saved my mother's life." He then pressed his hand, and rushed out of the room half mad with joy.</p>
               <p>"Good! Well done!" said the banker to himself. "When this fellow has started, I've less to fear. As soon as he has gone I'll manage to send the old woman and her daughter to some distant part of the country. Here, Joseph!" added he, as the servant entered, "take this letter immediately." The servant bowed and withdrew. "And now, Mr. Badger, I am ready for you, and for anybody who dares<pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6371-00000015"/> to cross my path." He then left the room, banging the door after him.</p>
               <p>In a short time Antoinette entered the room, to get her basket.</p>
               <p>"To think," said she to herself, "that I should have to work thus for a living, and above all for the daughter of this rich, wicked man."</p>
               <p>"Well, this is the strangest letter I ever read," said Livingston, as he entered the room, bearing the missive that summoned him.</p>
               <p>"What, Mark, is it you?"</p>
               <p>"Antoinette, my dear sister, what are you doing here?"</p>
               <p>"Oh, Mark, I've come in search of work. Mamma is ill, and we know not what to do," said the young girl, mournfully.</p>
               <p>"Well, cheer up, Antoinette, for I've come for money, and if I succeed all will be well."</p>
               <p>They chatted together in this harmless manner for some minutes, forgetting, in the pleasure their society afforded each other, in whose house they were. At length the conversation was interrupted by the appearance of Alida, who started back with surprise at seeing Mr. Livingston in conversation with her embroideress.</p>
               <p>"And then, dear Antoinette, if fortune favors me, and I succeed, let us divide my wealth. It is too much for me."</p>
               <p>"Oh, Mark!" exclaimed the young girl, as her lover kissed her.</p>
               <p>"Mr. Livingston, my father wishes to speak to you," said Alida, coming forward hastily.</p>
               <p>"I'll wait upon him, Miss Bloodgood, at once," answered Mark, smiling at his little Antoinette. As soon as the door was closed Alida walked up to Antoinette and said harshly:</p>
               <p>"A word with you, young woman. That gentleman loves you."</p>
               <p>"Miss Bloodgood!"</p>
               <p>"Don't deny it," continued she, "I have guessed it, and have seen quite sufficient to justify my supposition."</p>
               <p>"Well, then, Miss Bloodgood," replied the young girl, her pretty face flushing with honest pride," there's one thing you have not heard, because I have not told him yet; there is one thing that I will tell you without asking—I love <emph>him?</emph>"</p>
               <p>"That's right! I like frankness," continued Alida, coolly. "Now it's my turn. Let me tell you that I am going to be his wife."</p>
               <p>"I wont believe it," shouted poor Antoinette, alarmed.</p>
               <p>"I don't want you to, my dear; but as Mr. Livingston is ruined—"</p>
               <p>"Ruined!" exclaimed the girl.</p>
               <p>"Yes, ruined, unless my father helps him. Well, one word from me, and the helping hand which my father has held towards him will be drawn back."</p>
               <p>"But you won't say it—I'm sure you won't say!" said poor Antoinette, in an ecstasy of grief.</p>
               <p>"We shall see. But come, young woman," continued Alida, in a patronizing tone, "you would not suit such a man as Mark Livingston. Now, if you renounce him at once, I shall probably do something for you and your family."</p>
               <p>"But he does not love you," said Antoinette.</p>
               <p>"That has nothing to do with it."</p>
               <p>"Oh yes it has," rejoined Antoinette, boldly; "because he <emph>does</emph> love me."</p>
               <p>"What of that?"</p>
               <p>"Everything, miss. He is going to be my husband," shouted Antoinette, wrought to a pitch of desperation.</p>
               <p>"I think, young woman, that a little more modesty would become you better," said Alida, freezingly.</p>
               <p>"Modesty, Miss Bloodgood! How can you talk of modesty, when you boldly say that you want my lover? You don't love <emph>him,</emph> I know—it's his rank in society you want."</p>
               <p>"But, girl, I'll make him rich. What <emph>more </emph> can <emph>you</emph> do?"</p>
               <p>"More?" shrieked the poor girl, "I'll make him happy. Hear me, proud lady—I'll never surrender Mark to you."</p>
               <p>"We shall see. Mind, it's your own fault," said Alida.</p>
               <p>Just then the door opened, and Livingston appeared.</p>
               <p>"Antoinette, dear Antoinette, do you see that lady? she is my guardian angel. To her I owe my good fortune. Mr. Bloodgood has told me all; and see, this letter is in her own handwriting. Now, let me confess, Miss Bloodgood, that, had I not been thus rescued from ruin, I had no other resource but a revolver."</p>
               <p>"Oh, Mark!" exclaimed Antoinette.</p>
               <p>"Yes, I had resolved. I could not endure the shame and despair which beset me on all sides. But come, let us not talk of such madness—let us only remember that I owe her my life."</p>
               <p>"And I mean to claim the debt," said Alida, in a low voice.</p>
               <p>"More than my life," continued Mark "I owe to her all that happiness which you will bestow on me."</p>
               <p>"Me—me, Mark? no, it is impossible."</p>
               <p>"Impossible!" re-echoed Livingston, starting back.</p>
               <p>"I cannot be your wife."</p>
               <p>"What mean you, Antoinette?"</p>
               <p>It was a hard task for the poor girl. Mustering all her courage with a supreme effort, she said:—</p>
               <p>"I—I do not love you, Mark."</p>
               <p>"You jest, Antoinette; but no—there are tears in your eyes."</p>
               <p>"Did I ever tell you that I loved you?'" continued she.</p>
               <p>"No, you did not; but your manner—your looks—I thought—"</p>
               <p>"You are not angry with me, are you?" asked she.</p>
               <p>"No, Antoinette, I love you too sincerely for that; and believe me I will never intrude again on your family, where my presence can now only produce pain and restraint; may I hope, however, that you will retain sufficient kindness towards me to persuade your mother to accept my friendship? It will soothe the anguish you have innocently inflicted, if your family will permit me to assist them. Have you the generosity to make this atonement? I know it will pain you all, but you owe it to me. Farewell, Antoinette! I hope you will be happy." The young man rushed into the street, and poor Antoinette fell into a chair, weeping bitterly.</p>
               <p>"He has gone," said Alida. "Poor girl! They really loved each other."</p>
               <p>"I am glad he will not die," said Antoinette, drying her eyes.</p>
               <p>"And now, young woman, as you have kept your promise, I will keep mine. He offered you money. I should prefer that my husband should not have pecuniary relations with you, at least not at present; so, as you are in want, here is some assistance." She offered her purse to the girl whose lover she had stolen. What was her surprise when Antoinette rose from her chair, and, in a voice full of indignation, exclaimed—</p>
               <p>"You insult me, Miss Bloodgood!"</p>
               <p>"How can an offer of money be an insult to anybody?"</p>
               <p>"You thought I sold my heart—no, I gave it. Keep your gold, it would soil my poverty. I have sacrificed my happiness for him, and you have made two fellow beings unhappy." The poor girl staggered rather than walked out of the room.</p>
               <p>"Why, what is the matter, Alida?" asked Mr. Bloodgood as he entered, for he noticed a tear glisten in his daughter's eye.</p>
               <p>"Nothing, papa. I shall be his wife after all," said she, aside. The banker then rang the bell. On the appearance of Joseph, he asked <choice>
                     <sic>htm</sic>
                     <corr>him</corr>
                  </choice> if he had delivered he letter which was given to him in the morning.</p>
               <p>"Yes, sir; and the answer," continued the servant, smiling, "is in another room."</p>
               <p>"Well, tell the man who is lunching in the next room that I should like to speak to him."</p>
               <p>In a few minutes Badger appeared, wiping his lip with a napkin.</p>
               <p>"Your cook is a perfect arttist, Mr. Bloodgood, and your wine quite choice. Hullo! where's our young friend?" asked he, pocketing the napkin.</p>
               <p>"In the next room."</p>
               <p>"Why, what's he doing there?"</p>
               <p>"He is making the necessary arrangements for his departure to South America."</p>
               <p>"Well I must see him before he goes.<pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6371-00000016"/> However, now let's to business, old Bloodgood," said Badger.</p>
               <p>"Very well, my dear sir," replied the banker, calmly; "it's time we understood each other," said he, ringing a bell.</p>
               <p>"But, I say, you don't wish to enter into particulars in the presence of this charming creature."</p>
               <p>"Oh, don't alarm yourself. Her presence will not in the least affect our business."</p>
               <p>"All right, old fellow. What proposition have you to make?"</p>
               <p>Badger, as he spoke, was standing with his back to the door, and did not notice that soon after the bell had rung Joseph entered, followed by two policemen.</p>
               <p>"Why, fellow," shouted the banker, eagerly, "I propose to give you into custody for an attempt to extort money by threats and intimidation."</p>
               <p>"You are our prisoner," said one of the men, tapping him on the shoulder.</p>
               <p>"What, arrested!" exclaimed Badger.</p>
               <p>"Let him be searched," shouted Bloodgood; "on his person will be found a receipt signed by me, which he purloined from my desk yonder."</p>
               <p>All this time Badger did not lose his presence of mind.</p>
               <p>"Well played, my dear Bloodgood," said he, convinced that victory was in his grasp; "but, knowing the character of the society into which I was venturing, I left the dear document at home. Good morning, Bloodgood. Miss Alida, yours. General, colonel, take care of me."</p>
               <p>He left the room jauntily, and had the gratification of seeing the banker sink down in a chair, muttering, "Foiled, foiled!"</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHARITY, IF YOU PLEASE.</head>
               <p>IT is a bitterly cold night. The snow is falling fast, and the square in which we shall meet with some friends is covered with snow. People are hurrying home as fast as they can out of the cold. Still those people whose vocation calls them out of doors must be at their post in order to get their bread. Thus our old friend "Butter-cake Dick" with his cakes all hot, but in consequence of the cold was not doing such a roaring trade as might have been wished.</p>
               <p>"Oh Lord, how cold it is!" said he, smacking his hands. "I do wish people would buy my cakes, I thought if I posted myself just here, so as to catch the grand folks as they go to the opera, they might fancy to take in a bite just by way of a treat during the performance. Hullo, here's the old woman. I wonder what cheer she's had." Mrs. Martin, well wrapped up in a thick shawl, and laden with her coffee can, here joined her husband.</p>
               <p>"Ain't you a nice man, Dick," said she; "for five hours I've been carrying your dinner; so now begin."</p>
               <p>"All right, mother, here goes," said Martin, taking the bread and meat which his wife had brought. "Stop a bit though. God bless us, and pity the poor of this great city."</p>
               <p>"Oh, father look at that poor fellow, lying in the corner, just under the chemist's shop. Suppose you spare a bit for him?"</p>
               <p>"Of course I will, mother. Give him this bread."</p>
               <p>The old womon took the bread, and placed it in front of the poor fellow, without walking him.</p>
               <p>In a few minutes, a gentleman appeared, followed by Badger, whose white hat trimmed with a black hatband, looked shabbier than ever.</p>
               <p>"Bill of the play, sir? Take a bill, sir? They'll charge you two-cents, inside, well, then, buy a box of matches—one hundred for three cents—warranted genuine," shouted he, as the gentleman dodged past him. "Come now, if you're short of cash, I'll lend you a shilling. Ugh! you want all you're got to pay your fare. Oh, crikey, ain't it cold? Oh my," added he, performing a short dance on the pavement, "I could play the banjo on my stomach, while my shivering anatomy would supply the bones. I say governor, let's warm myself at your cake machine!"</p>
               <p>There is always a free-masonry existing between the poor. Dick, therefore, allowed Badger to warm his hands, and at once began chattering with him on the badness of trade.</p>
               <p>In a short time, Mrs. Fairbrother, bowed down with grief, tottered along the square. "I cannot return to our miserable home without food for my children," sobbed she. "Each morning we separate in search of work, in search of food, only to meet again at night—their poor faces thin with hunger." She clasped her hands in anguish. "Ah, what's this!" she exclaimed, as she felt a ring. "Yes I must part with it. It's gold, and is sure to fetch something.</p>
               <p>"Hallo, what's that? Gold, she said!" exclaimed Badger, coming towards her. "Bill of the play, ma'am?" said he, by way of introduction.</p>
               <p>"Tell me, my friend, where I can buy a loaf of bread at this hour?"</p>
               <p>"All right, ma'am, there's a shop open in the next street. I'm sure she said gold."</p>
               <p>"Will they accept this piedge for some food?" asked she, showing Badger the ring.</p>
               <p>"Well, let's look at it," going to the chemist's window. "My word," muttered he, "here's a chance. I can easily make off with it,"</p>
               <p>"My children are starving, and I must part with it to buy them bread."</p>
               <p>Badger still keeping the ring, began to whistle. After hesitating a minute, he gave back the ring to Mrs. Fairbrother.</p>
               <p>"There, take it, go along and buy your children food, and mind you don't show that ring to anybody else. You deserve to lose it, for showing it to such a blackguard as I am."</p>
               <p>The poor woman hurried off, whilst Badger remained in the same place, in the hopes of getting a penny somehow. A rich quarry soon hove in sight in the shape of Mr. Bloodgood, on his way to the opera. As his house was close to the theatre, and as he did not like to waste money on himself, he chose to walk.</p>
               <p>"Bill of the play, sir? only one penny," shouted Badger, planting himself before him. "What, Bloodgood! exclaimed he, in astonishment.</p>
               <p>"Badger!"</p>
               <p>"Yes, my friend. A week ago I came out of prison, to hear that you had removed the Fairbrothers. I could not find a trace of them, but I got hold of my receipt again, and now I have got into business, old fellow. One hundred matches for three cents; try a box, And so you have sent young Fairbrother to South America?"</p>
               <p>"Ah, he doesn't know that the man refuses to go." said Bloodgood to himself.</p>
               <p>"And you have also disposed of the two women—I know that. But however, that don't matter at present. Now look here. Bloodgood. the receipt <unclear>of</unclear> the old sea-captain is worth a good deal to you, I know; so mind I am not going to stick at trifles, and if you don't come down handsome, I'll go to the police and say you murdered him."</p>
               <p>"Villian."</p>
               <p>"Oh, I don't mind your abuse," said Badger coolly.</p>
               <p>"Well, then, come to my house tomorrow, and bring the receipt with you."</p>
               <p>"Not quite, my good fellow. Once caught, twice shy; besides, you owe me a visit; so suppose you come to my house this evening at 19½, Cross-street—the fifth floor back."</p>
               <p>"All right."</p>
               <p>"Mind you be there in an hour."</p>
               <p>Very well." "Don't forget—fifth floor back. You'll see my name in chalk on the door."</p>
               <p>"In an hour I will be there."</p>
               <p>"That's right. Don't forget to present my compliments to your charming<pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6371-00000017"/> daughter. Sweet creature! The very image of her father. I hope you'll bring me her carte-de-visite the next time you come,"</p>
               <p>Bloodgood went into the theatre, and Badger started off in search of more plunder, Soon Antoinette appeared. "This is the place," said she; "I was told that I should find work at one of these shops, but I couldn't leave my mother before. Oh, Heaven be merciful to me, for this is the last hope."</p>
               <p>Some minutes later the poor fellow who had been crouching close to the chemist's shop woke up, and without seeing the bread which the good Mrs. Martin had placed for him.</p>
               <p>"How cold I am," muttered he; "I wonder how long I've slept there. I have tried in yain to get a place since I gave up Mr. Bloodgood's offer. I couldn't leave my mother and sister to starve. To starve, did I say? Ah! it may come to that, yet. Oh, my poor mother, my dear sister! were it not for you, I would lie down here and die in the streets. I wish I could work like a porter. I'll try; I have strong arms." In a short time a man came to a door and beckoned to Paul to carry a trunk for a gentleman to the railway station, close at hand. Before, however, he could drag his weary limbs to the place, a big, broad-shouldered porter rushed up; "Oh, I'll carry the trunk. Leave go, you young dandy with a black coat."</p>
               <p>"But he called me," gasped the half-frozen young man.</p>
               <p>"And is it the likes of you, that should be taking the bread out of the months of honest folks?"</p>
               <p>"God help me, friend! I have not tasted anything for two days."</p>
               <p>"Haven't you? Oh, very well then. You can take the trunk, and, welcome to it," good-humoredly said the other man, pushing the trunk towards Paul.</p>
               <p>"Now then, come along quickly, I don't want to lose the train," said the owner of the box, walking off. Paul tried to lift the trunk, but tried in vain. His long fast had deprived him of strength. Sinking down, overcome with exertion, he sobbed out: "I can't, I am too weak from hunger."</p>
               <p>"Look at me, then, young fellow. This is the way," said the strong porter, merrily, as he tossed the trunk over his shoulder. "All right, sir," and trotted off.</p>
               <p>"Merciful Heaven!" murmured the poor fellow, falling on his knees against a lamp-post. "You who have refused to me sufficient strenght to earn my bread, give me resignation to hear your will."</p>
               <p>Shortly afterwards Antoinette returned. Her errand had been unsuccessful.</p>
               <p>"No work," muttered she: "nothing to do but to starve or beg. Oh, if I could see some kindly face I would ask for alms!"</p>
               <p>After she had lingered about some time in vain, she noticed Mr. Glum hurrying along.</p>
               <p>"Sir, pardon me, will you," said she, scarcely daring to speak.</p>
               <p>"What do you want?"</p>
               <p>"Oh, sir, I—I," stammered she. "Which is the way to the Bowery, if—if you please."</p>
               <p>"Take the first turning to the right, and then keep straight on."</p>
               <p>As he hurried off, the poor girl muttered, "Oh, coward! coward! I have not even the courage to beg." She sank upon a doorstep and wept bitterly.</p>
               <p>The road from the pawnbroker's led Mrs. Fairbrother past the house upon whose doorstep her child was weeping, "They refused to take my ring," said the poor lady, "and said, perhaps I had stolen it. Dear, dear me! I can get nothing on it, unless <unclear>I</unclear> produce the marriage certificate."</p>
               <p>The darkness of the night which had now set in with all the customary soverity of winter prevented them from recognising each other, although they were all within a circle of twenty yards. At length Paul rose; "I will return home," said he, "to-morrow, perhaps, I can get work." Both the women saw the man dragging himself along.</p>
               <p>"Sir, sir, in the name of your own—give me bread for my children."</p>
               <p>"Sir, for pity's sake, give me the price——" He turned. "Mother! Antoinette!" shouted he in dismay, horrorstruck at the meeting. "I did not know that you poor women had come to this. How can I get a trifle for you? Stay! I recollect a few verses of an old song; then in a voice half choked by lears he sang the opening words of a popular air."</p>
               <p>"Poor man," said a passer-by, "I think I'll give him a trifle."</p>
               <p>"Now then! you idle fellow, move on. No singing here! shouted a policeman, pushing him along. He waited for a short time until the limb of the law had turned down another street. Then he began again, but nobody paid any attention to him. "Oh, this agony is more than I can bear," said he, as he sank down upon the pavement. "My boy!" "My brother!" exclaimed the women, as they knelt down, and mingled their tears together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
               <head type="sub">AFTER THE OPERA.</head>
               <p>The evening's entertainment at the opera had just concluded, and the rich people were waiting in the corridor for their cariages. Among these were Mark Livingston and his betrothed bride, Alida Bloodgood.</p>
               <p>"How strange Mark, that my father has not returned," said Alida to her lover, as they stood waiting for him.</p>
               <p>"It is strange. Allow me, however, to look for the carriage."</p>
               <p>"Do; I will remain here,"</p>
               <p>The young man seemed in no way loath to leave his destined bride, and at once darted off among the carriages, in search of that belonging to the wealthy banker.</p>
               <p>"At last I have won the husband I desire," thought Alida. "He is entangled in my father's debt; in one month I shall be the bride of Livingston. Our box is crowded with the cream of the aristocracy. The Baron still makes love to me, to which Mark appears quite indifferent. So much the better; when I am his wife, he may do as he likes, and so will I."</p>
               <p>Before Livingston returned, Paul had managed to squeeze through the carriages, until he had approached close to the young lady.</p>
               <p>"Ah! 'tis she. Alida Bloodgood," exclaimed he, as soon as he saw her.</p>
               <p>She also noticed him.</p>
               <p>"I wonder they permit such vagabonds to hang about the opera," muttered she "Oh, here is Mark."</p>
               <p>"Now Alida, come along, the carriage is ready. What, Paul, is it you?" claimed he, surprised at the tattered appearance of his friend.</p>
               <p>"Great heaven! in what condition do I find you."</p>
               <p>"Ah, Mark, we are poor; we are starving," answered the other mournfully.</p>
               <p>"Give the fellow a dime and come away," was Alida's generous suggestion.</p>
               <p>"Why, dear Alida, you don't know this is a school-fellow—an old friend."</p>
               <p>"I know, Mark you are keeping me in the cold. Ah! I see Baron Giverny on the steps yonder, smoking a cigar. He will see me home; don't let me take you from your old friend," said she, shrugging her shoulders, as she went to meet the baron.</p>
               <p>"Cold heartless girl!" muttered Mark Livingston. "Come, Paul, come quickly, take me to where I shall find your mother—your sister; stay, let me first go home and get some money. I will then meet you at your lodgings; where do you live?"</p>
               <pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6371-00000018"/>
               <p>"Number 19½ Cross-street, Mark Bless you. I will wait for you at the door."</p>
               <p>"In less than an hour I will be there," said his companion, walking off to his lodgings, and leaving Paul in a more equable state of mind than he found him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
               <head type="sub">NO. 19½ CROSS STREET.</head>
               <p>High up in one of those small houses which are to be found in the obscure quarters of all large towns stood a garret, in which the Fairbrothers were forced to take up their humble residence.</p>
               <p>The apartment was miserably furnished: one cupboard, two broken chairs, and a charcoal furnace formed the sum total of the adornments of the room. The small window affording only a view of the chimneys of the neighborhood, showed many broken panes of glass, which had been stuffed up with straw and old rags. The wall which separated it from the adjacent garret was scarcely more than laths and plaster. The paper with which it had been at one time adorned, had been almost entirely torn down by the lodgers who had at different times occupied the wretched place. True, there was a door between the two garrets, but this had always been kept fastened up, as no tenant had ever been found sufficiently rich to rent the two garrets at once. This door was so warped and rotten that at the top there was an aperture of at least a quarter of an inch, through which the wind howled and blew in a most uncomfortable manner.</p>
               <p>Mrs. Fairbrother and her daughter were seated in their lonely garret, huddled up in a corner in order to keep each other as warm as they could.</p>
               <p>"Nobody gave him anything, mamma, not even a penny," said Antoinette, nestling close to her mother.</p>
               <p>"My dear, Paul is <unclear>too ill</unclear> to sing well; besides, nobody listens when it snows. Oh, merciful Father! protect my poor children."</p>
               <p>In a short time the occupant of the adjacent garret, our friend Badger, entered his apartment, with several boxes of matches which he had not succeeded vending. He scraped one, in order to light a piece of candle which was stuck in a bottle. For some time he labored in vain. "One hundred of these fine matches for three cents. Hullo! here's one that condescends at last," added he, as he succeeded in lighting his candle.</p>
               <p>"Who says that days do not resemble each other now, mamma?" said Antoinette.</p>
               <p>"Ah, my child, that writer did not know what it was to be without bread.'</p>
               <p>"Canopy of rubbish,—palace of idleness, I salute you!" exclaimed Badger, as, in the best of spirits, he drew a large bottle from his pocket</p>
               <p>"Day after day goes by—no hope—the future worse than the present,—dark—dark. Oh, this load of wretchedness is too much to bear!" murmured Mrs. Fairbrother.</p>
               <p>"The candle is going out, mamma."</p>
               <p>"So much the better, my child. I shall not be able to see your tears, nor read on your face hunger and despair."</p>
               <p>As soon as Badger had placed his bottle on the table, he drew from his large pocket a slice of bread and meat, wrapped in a newspaper. "Here's my supper," said he, rubbing his hands. "Jane, lay the table-cloth. 'Yes sir,'" continued he, strutting to the end of room, and then marching back and spreading the newspaper over the table. "Jane! it's very cold here; there must be a draught somewhere. Jane! champagne. Thank you," continued he, drawing the cork out of the bottle, and taking a strong pull at the contents.</p>
               <p>"If Paul had only Antoinette to support," said Mrs. Fairbrother, to herself. "they <unclear>might live</unclear>—why should I prolong my life only to hasten their death?"</p>
               <p>"Oh Mark dearest Mark, I shall never see you again!" said Antoinette, half in thought.</p>
               <p>"Bother this draft!" exclaimed Badger, shrugging his shoulders. He then took the blanket from the bed, and wrapped it about his shoulders. "The draft comes from the wall. Oh yes, there are great chinks in it," said he, passing the candle before it. "Humph! I must see my landlord and demand repairs. A new family moved into the next room, yesterday. I wonder who they are."</p>
               <p>"Where is Mark now, I wonder? near her, perhaps!" sobbed Antointte.</p>
               <p>"Yes,—yes, I have lived long enough." thought Mrs. Fairbrother.</p>
               <p>"Now then, to business, continued Badger. "Jane, turn up the gas. 'Yes, sir.'" Lie snnffed the candle with his fingers. "Thank you, Jane. Ahem! old Bloodgood is coming for the receipt bequeathed to you by old Captain Fairbrother. What price shall we put upon it, Jane?"</p>
               <p>"They say that lovers are united in heaven. We shall meet this evening," said Antoinette. "When I am gone there will be one mouth less to feed. Paul will have but one care to provide for."</p>
               <p>"In this room we had some charcoal," said the mother. "There is enough left to bestow on me an easy death."</p>
               <p>"I think about $10,000 is near the mark," said Badger, between his bites. "Oh, what a prospect opens before me!"</p>
               <p>"I know how to die. One hour, and all would be over. What is mother doing now? Ah! she's lighting the pan of charcoal on which we prepare our food. Ah!" thought the poor girl, "if I could induce her to leave me alone, the deadly fumes of that fuel would soon bestow on me an easy death."</p>
               <p>Mrs. Fairbrother filled the furnace with charcoal. "It is there," said she. "Now! now! while I have the courage of despair!"</p>
               <p>"How shall I spend my money?" continued Badger. "I'll buy a large house and take in lodgers."</p>
               <p>"Mother!" "Antoinette!" exclaimed the two women together as they approached each other.</p>
               <p>"Dear Antoinette, I have just thought of a friend, from whom I may perhaps get assistance."</p>
               <p>"Go, then, mamma—go at once."</p>
               <p>"But, my child, I feel scarcely strong enough to go alone. Come with me, you can wait at the corner of the street until I come out."</p>
               <p>"Very well, mother, I'll go with you. And when we are out," continued she aside, "I can return alone and accomplish my purpose."</p>
               <p>"Instead of going to a friend, I can slip back unseen by Antoinette, and die alone," murmured her mother.</p>
               <p>"Come, then, Antoinette, let us be off. Wait an instant, child; kiss me once more, for my heart is cold."</p>
               <p>The two women embraced each other with all the fervor of love and despair, and then slowly left the room, while Badger went on steadily with his meal. "Hullo!" said he, "the bottle's nearly empty. I think they're smaller than they used to be. What's the news! Let us consult the tablecloth. Jane, you can clear away. Thank you, Jane," added he as he put away the remains on his feast in the cupboard, and sat down on his bed to read the newspaper. He had not sat there very long before the door opened and in walked his visitor.</p>
               <p>"Mr. Badger?"</p>
               <p>"Quite right, sir. Please to wipe your feet before you come in, as my carpet is new. I am glad to see you. Take a seat upon the sofa," added he, pointing to the bed.</p>
               <p>"Come, Mr. Badger, to business.<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6371-00000019"/> You have the receipt with you, I suppose?"</p>
               <p>"Of course I have. You know I've got it, or you wouldn't have come."</p>
               <p>"Well, well; how much do you want for it?"</p>
               <p>"Stay a minute. Short reckonings make long friends. You have had for fifteen years in your possession the sum of $100,000, the profits of one robbery. Now, calculating this at about 7 per cent., the sum will now be doubled."</p>
               <p>"Let me see the document, and then we can estimate its value.</p>
               <p>Badger took a tattered piece of paper out of his pocket, and placed it on the table. In an instant Bloodgood sprang forward. "Let me have it!" shouted he. Quick as thought, however, Badger seized the knife which was lying on the table and dug it into the paper, just in time to prevent it falling into the clutches of the banker. "Hands off, my friend!" There still remained another violent course of action, Quickly drawing a pistol from his pocket, Bloodgood represented it at Badger's head, exclaiming, "Give me the paper, or I'll blow your brains out?"</p>
               <p>"Oh, that's the way you pay your debts!" said Badger, calmly, edging towards the bed.</p>
               <p>"Ah, now you are in my power!"</p>
               <p>"Yes, of course—it's an old dodge, but ineffective. Come, no violence—I'll give you the paper."</p>
               <p>"Now then, be quick. A bullet is a good argument."</p>
               <p>"Yes, but two are better still" shouted Badger, drawing two big pistols from the bed.</p>
               <p>"Damnation!" exclaimed the banker.</p>
               <p>"Drop your hand, or I'll blow you into pieces! So you took me for a fool, and were wrong; but I, on the contrary, took you for a rogue, and was right. Never mind, this will only cost you a few more notes. So come, now to business."</p>
               <p>"Well, how much do you want?" asked the banker, surlily.</p>
               <p>"Only $25,000, that's all."</p>
               <p>"Come, come, that's too much."</p>
               <p>"I wont take a cent less. It will cost you more if I give you up to justice."</p>
               <p>"Well, then, be it so."</p>
               <p>"That's the way to square it, old fellow. Mind, I'll take it in notes; gold is too heavy."</p>
               <p>"You shall have the money to-morrow."</p>
               <p>"No, to-night; for I am off to Saratoga."</p>
               <p>"Very well; I'll return in an hour with the money. He has me in his power—I must yield." muttered he aside.</p>
               <p>"Let me light you out. Mind the banister; don't break your precious neck—at least, not to-night. No; go in front, will you? I prefer it."</p>
               <p>"What for?"</p>
               <p>"Oh, merely a fancy of mine," answered Badger, with a candle in one hand and a pistol in the other. "A want of confidence, in fact, pervades the community." They then left the room together. A few minutes later Antoinette re-entered her garret.</p>
               <p>"I took a cross street," said she, "and ran rapidly home. Now I am alone. The fumes of the charcoal will soon fill this small room. They say it is an easy death! but, let me no more hesitate, let me sleep the long sleep where there are no more tears—no more suffering."</p>
               <p>The poor girl then left the room for an instant in search of a light, in order to apply the torch which was to set in action the cause of her death.</p>
               <p>As for Badger, he was in rare spirits.</p>
               <p>"The old boy made me wake the porter," said he. "Never mind, I'll give him a trifle, for now I won't be under an obligation to anybody. I hope Bloodgood won't be garotted on his way home. Jane, bring me my hookah." He then took a short pipe out of his pocket, filled it with tobacco, lighted it, and then sat on his bed building castles in the air as to how he should spend the money he expected from the banker.</p>
               <p>In a short time Mrs. Fairbrother returned.</p>
               <p>"Poor Antoinette! I dared not look back upon her as we parted for ever. Despair hastened my steps. My poor children! I have given you all I had, and now I hope my death will serve you in your hour of terrible need. Courage! I must first stop up all the apertures." The desperate woman then proceeded to tear a part of her dress in pieces, with which she stopped up the apertures in the window and the key hole; she next applied a light to the charcoal, and sat as near it as she could.</p>
               <p>"Hullo!" shouted Badger, starting up, "I smell burning charcoal! Where can it come from? It must be my neighbors. And what's the matter with my pipe? 'Jane, why did not you clean it out this morning?" It's very odd—I've a strange feeling in the head. I think I'll lie down for a short time, and smoke my pipe."</p>
               <p>He drew the tattered coverlet over him and lay down on his bed.</p>
               <p>In a few minutes Antoinette returned with some matches.</p>
               <p>"I feel that the hour's at hand!" murmured the poor mother.</p>
               <p>"The moment has arrived," said Antoinette. As soon as she turned round, however, she perceived her mother. "Mother! mother what are you doing?" she screamed.</p>
               <p>"And you, my child," asked the old lady, pointing to the matches in her daughter's hands.</p>
               <p>"Don't ask. I see it all now. I know why you have fastened these apertures so closely. Like me, you wished to die."</p>
               <p>"No, no, my child!" shrieked the unfortunate mother, "you shall not die! My own darling, remember that life is before you,—hope—happiness. You are young yet."</p>
               <p>"What of that? I have no wish to live. The man I love will soon wed another. I have no future, and the present is a torture."</p>
               <p>"Hush, hush! my child; hush!"</p>
               <p>"Oh, mother! dear mother! let me die with you. It is better to die thus, than by grief or hunger."</p>
               <p>"But, my darling, you are too young and chaste to die yet. Ah, already my senses fail me," muttered she, sinking into a chair. "Dearest Antoinette, live—live!"</p>
               <p>"Oh no, mother, let us die together," said the girl, falling at her mother's feet. "Thus, mother, as I often knelt to you as a child, let us pray for those we love."</p>
               <p>"Oh merciful Judge in heaven," prayed the poor mother, "forgive my child—and let your anger fall—on—me—alone."</p>
               <p>"God bless my dear brother; and you, dear Mark, may you be happy!"</p>
               <p>The poor girl drew close to her mother, resting her head upon her lap. "Mother, dearest mother," sobbed Antoinette, "if ever in word or deed I have grieved you, forgive and bless me."</p>
               <p>"Oh my child, my child, rather forgive me, if I have not been able to make you sufficiently happy." She drew her child closer to her, and wept over her.</p>
               <p>In a short time Paul rushed up stairs and knocked loudly at the door.</p>
               <p>"Mother, mother, open the door; why is it locked? Mother, mother, open, mother open."</p>
               <p>He knocked again violently. Mrs. Fairbrother, in a sort of stupor, tried to reach the door, but failing, fell to the ground. At the same minute Paul burst open the door, and entered with Livingston. At the horrible sight within they started back in amazement. Mark's first impulse was to break the window-panes<pb n="38-39" xml:id="VAC6371-00000020"/> panes, whilst Paul raised his mother. "Too late!—too late!" he said: "they have committed suicide."</p>
               <p>"They live still!" exclaimed Mark. "Quick—bear them outside into the air." He raised Antoinette, and, preceded by Paul with his mother, dragged her out of the room.</p>
               <p>"Hullo!" shouted Badger, starting up. "How hot it is here. I cannot breathe. What a smell of charcoal! Have I drunk too much? Nonsense, I could drink a dozen such bottles. Let me try my legs a bit—where's the door? I can't see it—my head swims round. Come, Badger, no nonsense now. Heaven! I'm suffocating! Am I going to die, to die like that old sea-captain?".</p>
               <p>He flung himself out of his bed and tore off his neckcloth.</p>
               <p>"Justice of Heaven, I am strangling. Help! help! Bloodgood will return and find me helpless, and will rob me of the receipt, as I robbed the old sailor. I know him of old—he is capable of it, out he shan't have it. I'll place it in its nook if I have strength to reach it.</p>
               <p>He dragged himself along the floor, lifted up a loose board, and placed the receipt under it. "It's safe—safe—there," muttered he, sinking on the floor.</p>
               <p>Scarcely had he fallen down, when the door communicating between the two rooms was burst open and Paul rushed in. "I heard smothered cries for help—they came from this room, I think," said he, looking around.</p>
               <p>At the same time the other door opened and Bloodgood entered.</p>
               <p>"Here I am, Badger." He started back, almost suffocated by the charcoal. "Ugh, what a suffocating atmosphere. Where is he? Ha! intoxicated."</p>
               <p>"Is he dead?" said Paul, raising him.</p>
               <p>"What, Paul Fairbrother?" exclaimed the banker, starting back.</p>
               <p>"You here, Mr. Bloodgood?" said the other.</p>
               <p>"Ha! What names were those?" whispered Badger, raising his head. "Both of them here together. Listen, sir," said he to Paul, "while I have yet breath to speak—listen. Fifteen years ago that man robbed your father of $100,000.</p>
               <p>"Robbed!" shouted Paul.</p>
               <p>"How dare you say so, scoundrel?" exclaimed Bloodgood, threatening him</p>
               <p>"I have got the proofs," was the answer.</p>
               <p>"The proofs!"</p>
               <p>"Yes, Paul, I have got 'em safe. You'll find them, ah—ah—" He could speak no more, but fell back to appearances dead.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
               <head type="sub">RESPECTABLE BEGGARS.</head>
               <p>IN the garden of one of those little houses with which the environs of the Empire city are adorned, was seated a party quietly enjoying a nice cup of tea. This party, we must state, consisted of Mrs. Fairbrother and her son Paul at first, although in a short time it was joined by several people with whom we are also acquainted. The old lady looked, if not quite the picture of health, at least much better than the last time we saw her. She was quietly enjoying a cup of nice strong tea, whilst her son Paul, in a suit of new black clothes, was smoking a cigar at her side. In a short time, in expectation of further visitors, Mrs. Martin appeared at the door of the little cottage with a tea-pot in her hand.</p>
               <p>"Here's some more tea for you," said she, cheerfully. "Bless me, how hot it is to-day! who would think that we were in the month of February?"</p>
               <p>"Your husband is rather late to tea, Mrs. Martin."</p>
               <p>"Yes, ma'am, he is a bit late this evening. I suppose he's busy."</p>
               <p>"All right, Mrs. Martin, here he comes," said Paul, as the worthy cake vender, in a suit of new clothes, walked up the garden.</p>
               <p>"How is everybody? and above everybody, how is Miss Antoinette this morning?" asked he in a breath, at the same time taking a seat at the table.</p>
               <p>"All, poor child! her recovery is only slow," answered the young lady's mamma; the fever has abated, but she is still very weak."</p>
               <p>"Luckily, her life is saved," said Paul, "although for a whole month she hovered over the grave."</p>
               <p>"But how is it, Mrs. Martin, we never see our benefactor, Mr. Livingston?" asked Martin, apparently surprised at his absence; "he is like a good spirit—he showers benefits on all of us, and yet he never shows his face."</p>
               <p>"Ah, bless him!" said Mrs. Fair-brother. "After saving us from the perils of that dreadful night, he brought us back to this our old home, besides obtaining employment for Paul in New York."</p>
               <p>"Yes, Mrs. Fairbrother" added old Martin, whose mouth was full of bread-and butter; "and didn't he set me up again in my patent oven, and get me a contract for supplying the almshouse with bread?"</p>
               <p>"Ah, bless him!" chimed in Mrs. Martin, holding a cup of tea in her hands; "he's made of the finest flour that Heaven ever put into human baking; he'll die of over-bigness of the heart some day, I'll be bound."</p>
               <p>"Ah, Mrs. Martin," said Mrs. Fairbrother, shaking the old lady's hand; "while you praise Livingston, you forget yourself. What should we ever have done without your kindness?"</p>
               <p>"Oh, don't mention it, Mrs. Fairbrother. It's everybody's duty to do all the good he can," said old Martin, with a large piece of bread-and-butter in his hand.</p>
               <p>"I will tell you why Livingston <unclear>refuses</unclear> our society and avoids our gratitude," said Paul rising: "because my sister Antoinette refused his hand—because he has sold his hand to Alida Bloodgood, and has given us the purchase-money."</p>
               <p>This speech produced a silence of a few minutes; at length, while he was holding his fifth cup of tea in his hand, old Martin started up and said—"Look, here he is! Amongst those who have served us, don't let us forget poor Badger."</p>
               <p>"Why, they are talking of me," murmured that individual, as he came to the table. He look quite fresh and ruddy, and was clothed in the dress of a young countryman.</p>
               <p>"Forget him! Mr. Martin," added Mrs. Fairbrother, rising to make room for the new visitor. "Forget the man who watched Antoinette during her illness with more than the tenderness of a brother. No, a woman can never forget any one who has been kind to her children."</p>
               <p>"My sentiments to a hair," chimed in Butter-cake Dick.</p>
               <p>"And you sha'nt have cause to change them," answered Badger, probably feeling at that time a very worthy member of society.</p>
               <p>"Well, Badger, and have you succeeded in your errand?" asked Paul.</p>
               <p>"Yes sir. Congratulate me. I have been appointed to the police, and am appointed by chance to watch over the very street in which old Bloodgood lives. They think, it seems, that in that part dwell a good many bad characters."</p>
               <p>Thus the friends continued to chat, and to congratmlate each other on his good fortune. As soon as all the appetites were sated, Mr. and Mrs. Martin removed the tray into the kitchen, and Mrs. Fairbrother went upstairs to lie down for a short time.</p>
               <p>"Now, Badger, the news?" asked Paul eagerly, as soon as they were alone.</p>
               <p>"Bad, sir—bad. To-morrow Mr. Livingston is to be married to Alida Bloodgood."</p>
               <p>"Oh, my dear friend, what shall I do?<pb n="40-41" xml:id="VAC6371-00000021"/> I dare not accuse the banker of this robbery, unless you can produce the proofs which perhaps the wretch has destroyed."</p>
               <p>"No, Sir, I think not," replied the other calmly. "When I recovered from the effects of the charcoal, the day after my suffocation, I started for my lodging, but found to my dismay the house shut up and guarded by one of Bloodgood's servants. The banker had bought the place. However, I had the satisfaction of knowing that I had concealed the document very cunningly, for I am sure he has not found it."</p>
               <p>"But, Badger, knowing this man to be a felon, whom we may be able at any hour to unmask, can we allow Livingston to marry his daughter?"</p>
               <p>"Who mentioned my name?" asked Livingston, as he entered the garden. "How are you, Paul? I have come to bid you farewell, and to see Antoinette for the last time."</p>
               <p>The poor girl, still pale and thin, was led forward by her brother and Badger.</p>
               <p>"Farewell, for the last time, Paul," murmured she, softly.</p>
               <p>"Antoinette, dear Antoinette!"</p>
               <p>"Now, take care—sit down gently," said Badger, tenderly leading her to a seat.</p>
               <p>"Ah, my good kind nurse, you are always by my side."</p>
               <p>"Yes, Miss Antoinette, always ready with a dose of nasty medicine, aint I? Well, now I've got another dose ready. Do you see this noble, kind heart," continued he, pointing to Mark; "it looks through two honest blue eyes into your face. Well, tell me what you see there."</p>
               <p>"Oh, why do you ask me? said she trembling with emotion.</p>
               <p>"Come don't turn your eyes away," continued the Mentor: "The time has come, Miss Antoinette, when deception is a crime. Look in his face, and confess the infernal scheme by which Alida Bloodgood compelled you to renounce your love."</p>
               <p>"Alida!" exclaimed Livingston starting back in amazement.</p>
               <p>"Has she betrayed me?" asked Antoinette, in a low voice.</p>
               <p>"No, you betrayed yourself," answered Badger. "One night in the ravings of your fever, when I held your hands in the paroxysm of your frenzy, I heard the cries that came from your poor wounded heart—shall I repeat the scene?"</p>
               <p>Antoinette hid her face in her hands, and softly whispered.</p>
               <p>"No, no."</p>
               <p>"Paul, is this true—have I been deceived?" asked Mark, waking as from a dream.</p>
               <p>"Yes, Mark, you have: my sister confessed to me the infamous bargain extorted from her by Alida Bloodgood, and to save you from ruin she sacrificed her love."</p>
               <p>"Oh, Antoinette!—dearest Antoinette, look up!" shouted the excited young man. "It was for your sake alone that I accepted this hated union—to save you and yours from poverty; but whisper one word, tell me that ruin of fortune is better than ruin of the heart, and I——"</p>
               <p>Antoinette's lips moved as though she wished to speak. The attempt, however, was futile, and she was therefore obliged to answer her lover by throwing herself into his arms.</p>
               <p>"Hurrah:" shouted Badger. "I know a grand wedding party that won't come off. I shall make it my duty to be there to congratulate the bride."</p>
               <p>"Badger! Badger!" shouted the stentorian lungs of Tony, as he rushed into the garden: "where's my hat?—quick! there's a fire in the city."</p>
               <p>He then daited into the house, and soon returned with a telescope.</p>
               <p>"Yes, and there's a fire here, too, but one we don't want to put out," answered the nurse, calmly.</p>
               <p>"Now Mark," said Paul, "I can confess to you that documents exist-proofs of felony against Bloodgood, which may at any moment consign him to a prison, and transfer to our family his ill-gotten wealth."</p>
               <p>"Proofs of felony?"</p>
               <p>"I say, the fire is in Chatham street." said Tony, looking through the telescope.</p>
               <p>"Fifteen years ago," continued Paul, "he robbed my father of $100,000 dollars.</p>
               <p>"And I was his accomplice in the act; we shared the plunder between us," said Badger, laughing.</p>
               <p>"No it isn't in Chatham street," continued Tony. "I see it plainly, it is in Cross street."</p>
               <p>"Cross street!—where, where?" shouted Badger, growing alarmed.</p>
               <p>"If these proofs, these documents exist, where are they?" asked Livingston.</p>
               <p>"It is the tenement house, two doors from the corner," said Tony, still looking through the telescope.</p>
               <p>"Ha! it is our lodging!" shouted Badger. "You ask where are these proofs, these documents? They are yonder in that burning house, fired by Bloodgood to destroy the papers he could not find. Curses on him!"</p>
               <p>"Here's your hat, Tony, said his mother, coming out of the cottage.</p>
               <p>"Quick, Tony," continued Badger, "for our lives! Tony, the fortunes of Antoinette, of Paul, and of the old woman are in that burning house. I mean to save it, or perish in the flames.'</p>
               <p>"And I'll go with you," answered Tony.</p>
               <p>The pair then started off at full speed for the burning house.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER IX.</head>
               <head type="sub">FIRE! FIRE!</head>
               <p>THE exterior of No. 19½ Cross street was not very prepossessing in appearance. On the present occasion all the shutters of the house were closed, and the door guarded by a big watchman, who paced up and down as regularly as a policeman on his beat. A careful examination, however, of the place, would have discovered a light through one of the holes in the shutters of the upper windows. Presently a slight flame rose; then it was extinguished; and then it revived again slightly. The light was then seen to descend as the bearer of it passed down the staircase. Immediately after the door opened, and Bloodgood appeared. He ordered the watchman to go about his business, then looked round carefully, closed the door again and locked it.</p>
               <p>"In a few hours," muttered he with fiendish glee, "this accursed house will be in ruins. I have smeared the walls with petroleum in order to make the matter surer. The receipt is concealed there, and will be consumed in the flames." By this time the glow of fire had spread from to room. "Now Badger, do your worst—I am safe," said Bloodgood, as he quickly made his exit</p>
               <p>The flames now spread rapidly, and in a short time the house became completely enveloped in fire. Soon the cry of fire! fire! resounded through the district, until it was taken up by voices more remote, and spread as rapidly as the cause. The bells proceeded to ring, as they took up the alarm, until the roll of engines began to sound. Then a vast crowd, surging and rolling like the billows of the sea, made its appearance, to be restrained and forced back by a detachment of police which took up its position in front of the raging element. Next engines drawn by a throng of daring men dashed through the throng. The men sprang off, and at once drew out their ladders, began to rear them against the sides of the burning house, while men in the crowd volunteered in scores to work the pumps. Still the fire raged, and spread in spite of the<pb n="42-43" xml:id="VAC6371-00000022"/> efforts to stay it. Suddenly a noise was heard—"Clear the way," shouted a voice as Badger without coat of hat dashed through the crowd followed by Tony: the former tried the door, but in vain, it was fast; he therefore seized a bar of iron and dashed in the ground floor window, through which the flames were seen playing with terrible force.</p>
               <p>"Stop! stop!" shouted Tony, as Badger prepared to jump through the window. It was too late, Badger leaped in and disappeared. The mob huzzaed and shouted so loudly, that Tony jumped in also, but soon leaped out again black, burned so much that he staggered and fell, apparently overcome by the heat and smoke. Still the mob shouted, and still the water was poured in gallons upon the house, but yet it burnt, and great tongues of flame shot above people's heads, whilst ashes and tinder poured forth in showers, blackening every face in the neighborhood. In a short time the shutters of the garret fell in and discovered Badger in the upper floor tearing up a board. Then another shout arose from the crowd as a loud crash was heard, and Badger disappeared as if falling with the inside of the building. The shutters of the windows fell away, and the inside of the house was plainly seen, gutted completely by the fire. At the thought of the apparent hopelessness of poor Badger's escape, a cry of <unclear>horror</unclear> arose from the mob. Fortunately it was premature, for in a minute Badger dragged himself from the ruins, and fell across the sill of the lower window. In an instant Tony and two of the mob ran to help him forward, but were forced to recoil before the heat; at length they succeeded in rescuing the body, just as Livingston, Paul, and Martin rushed on. Tony at once knelt over Badger and extinguished all the fire which clung to his clothes. As soon as this was done, a shutter was procured, and he was conveyed to a neighboring house, where it was soon ascertained that his injuries were only slight.</p>
               <p>The house, however, in which stood the two garrets where formerly dwelt Badger and the Fairbrothers, was burnt to the ground, and in the morning nothing remained but the four walls and a huge mass of burnt beams and ashes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER X.</head>
               <head type="sub">JUSTICE.</head>
               <p>The drawing-room of Mr. Bloodgood's town mansion was brilliantly illuminated on the occassion of his daughter's marriage. The hour was nine, and all was in readiness for the arrival of the expected guests, while the sound of music in an inner apartment showed that a certain number of the early arrivals were devoting themselves to the worship of Terpsichore.</p>
               <p>Mr. Bloodgood, dressed in glossy black and a spotless necktie, soon made his appearance, looking as calm and collected as ever, and showing no signs of uneasiness with regard to the result of the deed he had committed an hour or two before.</p>
               <p>"This evidence of my crime is destroyed: no power on earth can reveal the past," said he, clapping his hands gaily. "Ah, Alida, my dearest child," continued he, as his daughter, dressed as a bride, made her appearance. "To-night you will leave this roof; but from this home in your father's heart, none can displace you," said he, kissing her fondly.</p>
               <p>"Oh, dear papa, do take care of my flounces," answered the affectionate daughter, "you men paw one about as if a dress was put on only to be rumpled."</p>
               <p>"I see that the rooms below are full of company. Has the bridegroom arrived?"</p>
               <p>"I did not inquire, papa. Baron Giverny is there, looking the picture of misery, while all my female friends pretend tend to congratulate me, although I know they are dying with envy and spite."</p>
               <p>"And do these feelings constitute the happiest day of your life?" said Mr Bloodgood, mournfully. "Alida, have you no heart?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, father, I have a heart; but it as like yours. It is an iron safe, in which are kept the secrets of the past."</p>
               <p>"The clergyman is robed, and ready perform the ceremony," said Joseph, as he entered, dressed in a new suit of livery for the occasion.</p>
               <p>"Very well! Let the bridesmaids attend Miss Bloodgood."</p>
               <p>The sumptuous red curtains, which concealed the saloon in which Alida and her father were standing from one equally gorgeous beyond it, were raised, and eight young ladies, dressed in white, who were to officiate as bridesmaids to Miss Bloodgood, made their appearance. In the mean-time the banker left the room, and soon returned with a number of ladies and gentlemen, who were to take part in the ceremony.</p>
               <p>"Welcome my kind friends," said the host, joyously, to the assembled guests. "Your presence fills me with pride and joy—but where is the bridegroom? has no one seen my son-in-law?"</p>
               <p>The large doors were at that moment thrown open, and the venerable Joseph announced—</p>
               <p>"Mr. Mark Livingston."</p>
               <p>"At last," said the host, shaking hands with him. "But, what a strange costume for a bridegroom!"</p>
               <p>Alida next came forward, and looking at her future husband somewhat contemptously, said—"Had I not good reasons to be assured of your sincerity, your appearance would lead me to believe that you looked upon this marriage as a jest, or a masquerade."</p>
               <p>In truth the dress and appearance of the gentleman was scarcely in accordance with the costume which is ordained by fashion to be worn by a bridegroom. His face and hands were black from the effects of the late fire. His coat was torn, and his collar was as brown as if he had worn it for a week.</p>
               <p>"As you say, Miss Bloodgood, it is a masquerade," he answered quietly, and with great self-possession; "but it is one where more than one mask must fall!"</p>
               <p>"What do you mean?" asked the banker amazed.</p>
               <p>"You speak in a tone of menace," added Alida, curling her lip. "May I—"</p>
               <p>"Perhaps I had better see Mr. Livingston alone; he may be under some misapprension," suggested Bloodgood, beginning to feel alarmed.</p>
               <p>"No sir, I am under none, although I believe you may be," replied Mark, as calm as over; "and what I have to say and do demands no concealment. I come here to decline the hand of your daughter."</p>
               <p>"You must explain this public insult," shouted the banker, in a violent rage.</p>
               <p>"I am here to do so," was Mark's ready answer; "but I do not owe this explanation to you—I owe it to myself and those friends I see here, whose presence under your roof is a tribute to the name I bear. My friends, I found myself in this man's debt; he held in pledge all I possessed—all but my name; that name he wanted to shelter the infamy in which his own was covered. I was vile enough to sell it."</p>
               <p>"Go on, sir, go on," shouted Bloodgood, boiling over with anger.</p>
               <p>"With your leave I will."</p>
               <p>"These matters you were fully acquainted with, I presume, when you sought my hand?" sneeringly asked Alida.</p>
               <p>"But I was not acquainted with the contents of these letters," said Mark, taking a bundle from his pocket, "written by you to Baron Giverny."</p>
               <p>"Dare you insinuate that they contain<pb n="44-45" xml:id="VAC6371-00000023"/> tain evidence derogatory to the honor of my child? exclaimed the banker.</p>
               <p>"No, sir; but I think Miss Bloodgood will agree with me, that the sentiments expressed in these letters entitle her to the hand of the baron rather than mine," said Mark, as he politely handed the letters to the blushing bride.</p>
               <p>"This man can go now, father," said Alida, with as much contempt as she could assume.</p>
               <p>"Not yet," rejoined Mark. "You forget that my friends here are assembled to witness a marriage, and all we require is a bride."</p>
               <p>"Yes, a bride who can pay your debts," sarcastically replied Mr. Bloodgood.</p>
               <p>"No, sir; a bride who can place the hand of a pure and loving maiden in that of a good and honest man," shouted Paul, as he entered the room, followed by his mother and Antoinette.</p>
               <p>"How dare you intrude in my house?" shouted the banker, livid with rage.</p>
               <p>"Because it is mine," was Paul's reply; "because your whole fortune will scarcely serve to pay the debt you owe the widow and children of Captain Fairbrother.</p>
               <p>"Is my house to be invaded by beggars like these?" exclaimed the old man, who had now lost all self-contro "Joseph, send for the police. Is there no law for ruffians?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, plenty; and here's the police," was the ready answer of Badger, who quietly entered the room in the uniform of a police-officer.</p>
               <p>"Badger!" exclaimed Bloodgood, aghast.</p>
               <p>"What's left of him."</p>
               <p>"Is this a conspiracy to rob me?" asked be, wildly.</p>
               <p>"That's it," replied Badger. "We began it fifteen years ago; we have been hatching it ever since; we let you build up a fortune; we tempted you to become an incendiary; we led you on from misdemeanor to felony—and that's what I want you for."</p>
               <p>"What do you mean?" asked Mr. Bloodgood, as he sank into a chair.</p>
               <p>"My meaning is set forth very clearly in an affidavit, on which the Recorder at this very late hour for business, issued this warrant for your arrest. Here, policeman, come in."</p>
               <p>He opened a door, and two of the guardians of the city stood there, waiting with their clubs, ready to arrest him.</p>
               <p>"Incendiary!" said the banker, in a low tone. "Dare you charge a man of my standing in this city with such a crime, without any cause?"</p>
               <p>"Cause! You wanted to burn up this receipt, which I was just in time to rescue from the flames."</p>
               <p>"Fiend!" shouted the old man, starting up nearly mad, and drawing a knife. "You escaped the flames here, now go to those hereafter."</p>
               <p>The banker, however, reckoned without his host; for Badger, whose cold grey eyes had never been taken off his enemy, grappled with him at once, and before a few minutes had passed, the banker was lying on the sofa with heavy manacles round his wrists. "Bloodgood, old boy, don't lose your temper," was all that his foe said.</p>
               <p>"Miss Bloodgood, this is no place for you. Let me lead you to your room," politely suggested Paul.</p>
               <p>The unfortunate girl went to the sofa: "Father, father!" murmured she.</p>
               <p>"Alida, my child!"</p>
               <p>"Is this true?" No one spoke, and she continued: "It is; I read it in your quailing eyes—on your pallid lips. And it was for this that you raised me to the envied position of the rich man's heiress; for this you roused my pride; for this you decked me in jewels, to be the felon's daughter. Farewell!" and the heartless girl was going to leave her father.</p>
               <p>"Alida, my child! it was for you alone that I sinned: do not leave me!"</p>
               <p>"What should I do in this city, can I earn my bread? What am I fit for, with your tainted name, and my own sad heart?" She snatched off her wreath and flung it on the ground. "I am fit for the same fate as yours—infamy," said she, as she rushed out of the room.</p>
               <p>"Baron, you had better see the lady out," suggested Badger, touching the latter on the shoulder. "Now, Bloodgood, allow me to introduce you to two friends of mine, who are anxious to make your acquaintance."</p>
               <p>"No, no, for pity's sake take me away! I have lost my child, my Alida; hide me from all the world!"</p>
               <p>"Stay," said Paul. "Mr. Bloodgood, in the midst of your crimes, there was one virtue; you loved your child; even now, your heart deplores her ruin, not your own. Badger, give me that receipt. Do you acknowledge this paper to be genuine?"</p>
               <p>"I do," answered the felon, faintly. </p>
               <p>Paul quietly took it and tore it in pieces: "I have no charge against you," he said. "Let him be released. Restore me to my fortune, and take the rest. Go, follow your child; save her from ruin, and live a better life."</p>
               <p>"Oh, sir! I cannot answer you as I would," said the old man through his tears.</p>
               <p>They were bitter tears of repentance, and as he walked out of the place, all felt that his heart had been touched, and that henceforth the old villain, who had been the cause of so much misery, would reform and die a good man.</p>
               <p>"That was nobly done, Paul," said Mr. Livingston, shaking hands with him. "Now, my friends, since all is prepared for my marriage, let the ceremony proceed."</p>
               <p>"But where is Mrs. Martin, Mark?"</p>
               <p>"Here they are, outside; but they won't come in," answered Badger.</p>
               <p>"Why not?" inquired Paul.</p>
               <p>"They say they are afraid of walking on the carpets," was Badger's answer.</p>
               <p>"Bring them in at once," ordered Mark.</p>
               <p>"That's soon done," said Badger.</p>
               <p>"Poor, good, kind people!" added Mrs. Fairbrother—"the first to share our sorrow, the last to claim a part in our joy."</p>
               <p>"Here they are. They wouldn't come, and so I was obliged to take them into custody," said Badger, as he appeared leading Tony, followed by old Martin, under the charge of a policeman, and the good lady assisted by another gentleman in blue.</p>
               <p>"Oh, mother, where's this?" was Tony's first question.</p>
               <p>"I'm walking on a feather bed," declared Mrs. Martin.</p>
               <p>"Why didn't you let me wipe my shoes?" asked old Martin, with a reproachful glance at Badger.</p>
               <p>"Come in," said Mr. Livington, shaking hands with them. "These carpets have never been trodden by more honest feet, these mirrors have never reflected kinder faces—come in—breathe the air here—you will purify it."</p>
               <p>"Oh, Tony, what grand folks, aint they?" said Mrs. Martin, in a low voice, "everyone."</p>
               <p>"I believe you, mother. Oh my! what clothes!" answered Tony in amazement.</p>
               <p>"And now, Antoinette, that we are all assembled, I claim your hand. All is ready for the ceremony," said Mark, gently taking his blushing bride by the hand.</p>
               <p>"You have seen the dark side of life—you can appreciate your fortune, for you have learned the value of wealth," morally chimed in Badger.</p>
               <p>"No, not of wealth, but we have learned the value of poverty. It softens the heart, Mr. Martin," said she, shaking hands heartily with him.</p>
               <p>Our story has now drawn to a close.<pb n="46" xml:id="VAC6371-00000024"/> and we mean to summarize the further events of this tale in as few words as possible. Antoinette became the wife of Livingston, and with her husband lived as happy a life as any mortal could desire. For a few years Paul dwelt with his mother in a comfortable house close to the larger residence of his brother-in-law. At the end of three years he, however, contracted a matrimonial alliance with one of the young ladies who had officiated as bridesmaid at the marriage of his sister. After this his poor mother lived first a few months with one of her children, and then with the other; and if there was one point upon which the brothers-in-law felt jealous of each other, it was as to the duration of the grandmother's visit. To the children of her own children Mrs. Fairbrother's visits were always anticipated with the highest glee, which was not altogether due to the toys and sweetmeats the good old lady brought with her. The Martins also found no cause to regret the kindness which they had shown to the Fairbrothers in their misfortune, for the many contracts for bread which the old baker obtained through the aid of Livingston soon placed him on the road towards the realization of a good fortune.</p>
               <p>In the course of a few years their son, Tony, married his old flame, Maggie. Thus Tony, who had formerly expressed his wish not to wed until he had scraped together a thousand dollars, got his way in the end, for when he married he was a master painter, doing a good trade, while Mrs. Tony Martin reigned supreme in an elegant fruit shop, the profits of which added considerably to the comfortable income of the young couple. Nor must we forget the reformed scapegrace, Badger. All our friends had cause to be thankful to him, and they showed their gratitude in a form highly acceptable to the clear-headed man. When last we heard of him, he was working his way up to the direction of one of the large national banks, and as he was industrious and persevering, there is little reason to doubt that his object would in time be crowned with success. We have left to the last old Bloodgood and his daughter. She married the Baron Giverny, and may be seen in the season, at most of the fashionable watering-places. We believe the region of Saratoga is not altogether unknown to her, and it has even been rumored that her husband one year won an enormous sum from a young Englishman, who had a taste for gambling, which he appeared willing to cultivate at the expense of his pocket.</p>
               <p>Mr. Bloodgood, the whilom millionaire and banker, did not go into business again. He chose a quiet little house in the neighborhood of Albany for his residence, where he lived the few remaining years of his life in comfort and repentance. His death was regretted by most of the poor people of the neighborhood, to whom he had on many occasions shown kindness in as substantial a form as his means would allow. Here we end. We hope that the sufferings depicted in this tale have touched the hearts of some of our readers, and have even caused tears of sympathy to linger in their eyes. We appeal to them! If, on their way through the busy streets, they should see poor creatures, let them extend their hands, and the blessings that will follow on their way will be the most grateful tribute they can pay to the POOR OF NEW YORK.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>THE END.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>