<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/vwwp/vwwp.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6865">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title >An Interesting Love Story Found in a Rebel Camp Ground </title>
            <author >Anonymous</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name >Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name  xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp >General Editor</resp>
               <name  xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher >Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address >
               <addrLine >1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine >Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno >VAC6865</idno>
            <availability  status="unknown">
               <p>2000, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Victorian Women Writers
                    Project participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Digital Library Program.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title  level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title >An interesting love story found in a Rebel camp ground</title>
                  <author >Anonymous</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent >12 p. </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher >[s.n.]</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York </pubPlace>
                  <date  when="1863">1863</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p >This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p >This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language  ident="fra">French</language>
            <language  ident="deu">German</language>
            <language  ident="grc">Classical Greek</language>
            <language  ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change  who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2001-08-16">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change  who="adamhoch" when="2012-12-21">Converted doc from sgml to TEI P5.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text >
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>An interesting love story found in a Rebel camp ground</head>
            <p> 
               <pb n="0 (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6865-00000001"/> AN INTERESTING LOVE STORY, FOUND IN A REBEL CAMP GROUND. WRITTEN BY A SOUTHERN SOLDIER, DRAFTED INTO THE REBEL ARMY, WHOSE SYMPATHES WERE WITH THE NORTH. NEW-YORK: 1863.      <pb n="0" xml:id="VAC6865-00000002"/>  A LOYE STORY. I suppose, as it is common, it is necessary to say something in the way of introduction or preface; however, as my story is short, it will only answer for the same itself. Most young men when, becoming acquainted with a young and beautiful girl, are rather bashful, and feel some- what confounded, and I, of course, not being very different from the rest of my sex, you may consequently imagine my feelings on that occasion. However, I mustered all my courage, and strained my nerves to their utmost, in or- der to meet that trying time. It was in the beautiful month of May, when first I saw the object of my story, and, on the first sight, I became smitten with her mild, modest and most interesting appear- ance-not saying a word about her beauty or accomplish- ments. She had all that Nature could give, with one exception, and I felt as if it were my duty to furnish that. In the first place an introduction was needed, and how to get it, I did not know. Ten thousand ways entered my head, but all were condemed. If there were to be any party or meeting she might go to, in the neighborhood, I would go and throw myself in her way-but no such chance-I would not allow any obstacle that might spring up, to pre- vent me from such an opportunity. I was for one month laboring under great mental agony, when, at last, an oppor- tunity presented itself, and I was determined to embrace it, let it turn out as it would. The little country school-house where my darling Catharine was preparing herself for Col,    <pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC6865-00000003"/> lege process, was situated but a short distance from my own humble dwelling. The grandeur and sublime appear- ance of that little log cabin (I) Beautiful College, did I say? Beautiful, I will acknowledge. I thought so. The reader may judge for himself, as I give a description of that dear little spot. The ;house wad made -of logs, and from its appearance, one would think it was Boone's first settlement in the North State. It was situated in a marshy country, surrounded by 'a Turpentine Plantation, without fence or garden; but still, to me it seemed beantiful-no spot on earth was so dear. When at work my mind was there. And I have often thrown the plow or shovel, or what- ever it might be away, for the purpose of harnessing old Charley-you may talk of fast and fine horses; but he beat all in these diggins-well he might, for he cost me Three Hundred Dollars in round cash. I have often sat behind him when the road was hard and smoothe, and imagined myself, going at the rate of a mile a minute, especially when passing that dear little romantic spot. Young men in thest parts are nowhere if they have not horse, buggy and harness. Consequently I provided myself with that necessity, as being a surety to a successful courtship and marriage. There was one thing yet in the way that blasted all my hopes for a while. The teacher of this little insti- tute was my bitterest enemy, though his intention was to make me believe he was my best friend, and would speak a good word for me on all favorable occasions. I soon feund him to be a "wolf in sheep's clothing," and for that reason I hated him worse than I did the very devil, I ask the reader if I hbdenft reasoi, Say yes. I know you would, This opportunity I spoke of, was on Tuesday, in in the latter part of July. It commenced raining in the fore part of the day, and continued incessantly, and therefore I could not bear to think that she being prized by me above all other earthly beings, should go home alone. No, I could   not-though I was not accquaind but now is  never. While in this state of meditation,  was in the barn with what few hands my father could spay', shell- ing corn for the mill. I came to the conclusion as it was- lanting season, to plant one crop, ad ot another would be quite unlike farming, so I resolved to go and see Cathar- ine, so I ordered Bill, a smart and intelligent negro boy, of nineteen summers to get my holjroady. I can't hold any longer, I x ant you to put the harness onCharley, and hitch him to the top buggy I am going to see that gal, if I get a worse kicking thain arn Jones got last week friom, Nancy Brown." What gal is dat,  ou going to See now massa?", None of your business, do as I have told you." "J knowed all 1the time dat Miss B'own didn't like Mr. Jones, kase she told me so." "Are you telling the truth, Bill?" "Did you ever know me to tell you a lie, Aassa John" "No, I did not; but I would like to know  how Miss Brown came to tell you that." "She told me a beep more dan dat, Massa: She told me who she loved; but I won't tell you, kase it might make you feel too funny;:" "Now Bill, no more of that; but go and do as I have told you: Now I must go to the house and-prepare myself for the occasion." And you had better believe I put oin all my best doings lhat evening, though I will assure you  felt very unpleasant in them as I had never wore them before. My pants didn't fit, my shoes and my coat were too large, and nothing pleased me. I believe I never felt so awkward in all my life, and almost abandoned the idea of going ; but I could not back out then. Now I hear the noise of Charley's hoofs coming to the door, and the sum- mons of the boy that all was ready. i brushed my hair and out I goes--charges Bill with his busine y hair and buggy- it up straight-guivesg my coat colla an extra pull, -'-1    <pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC6865-00000004"/> ana then I am off. Now my head is filled with a thousand ideas what to do or say, how can I excuse myself? she will think I am dead in love with- her, and I must acknowledge I am; but it will not do to let her know it. And now, there is that infernal teacher--I'd rather meet the devil than him. His very looks makes me feel miserable. I felt that he knew the thoughts of my mind O, what piercing eyes I He turns my heart inside out. Halloo! there is the school- house. Hark, I hear a bell. It is recess, by hookey! Now the children are shoving to the door, to see hlo can get out first. There they are, skipping, hopping, and jumping the rope, some one thing, some another. Here comes a larger crowd, of young ladies, and there, is my Catharine, she sees me-what must I do? I believe they- are going to the spring. Yes, there they go, running. Now is my chance, though I was mortally afraid I would not speak right--so here goes. I tied my horse to a tree, and, down I goes to the spring. I found Catharine in a sitting posture, face to. ward the spring, as if she were meditating upon human na- ture, gazing upon that crystal fountain, and as I came up in the sound of her voice, it fell on my ear like the sound of a death bell. My heart was in my mouth, they all looked up Tithl astonished faces, and seemed to be frightened to see me approach thfem, while sitting under the loving green they all looked beautifil. The large and majestic oak that sha- ded the spring, Land the dim reflection of the sun as it shone through the leaves, 'played upon their beautiful counte- nances, which added stillmore to their beauty. O, what a moment that wao to me. I felt as if there were a hive' of bees withinmy head, however, I made out to step up to Catharine, the object of my affections, and was about to excuse myself, when, my foot slipped, and in I went, up to my chin in the spring. O, what a laugh the young gils did have. It appeared to be the funniest thing they had ever seen; but now, I was so mortified, though   there was one that did not laugh, bnt seemed as much hurt at it, as I was myself-it was Catharine. Now these were the thoughts of my mind. O, here I am, dripping wet, from head to toe. What shall I do? How shall I excuse myself before the fair dame, this lovely girl of sixteen summers? She was beautiful, her hair hung in long black tresses over her shoulders, and her deep blue eyes, all, testifying of in- telligence and beauty. Although she was a loving picture, I had to take my leave of her. The sun was then setting in the Western horizon. I bid her good evening, with the hope of meeting her again, in the sunshine of her beautiful coun- tenance. It was indeed, an hour of deep meditation and love, though the sky was dark and gloomy, heavy clouds hung in dark, sullen masses over land and sea. The wind in pitiless agonies whistled and moaned around the cottage of my humble dwelling as I drove up. Bill, my servant boy was there, ready to take my horse. "Ah," says Bill, "it seems as if you had been put through the strouthes, massa." "Yes, but some people say 'bad beginning makes a good ending."' An old maid, speaking of marriage, says, " it is like any other disease, while there is life there is hope." "Well massa, what is hope." "  Well, Bill, some say it is one thing, and some another. It is said to be an anchor to the soul, it is the guiding star of our life; but who sahall be able to define all that. is con- tained in that little word, Hope. How thankful we ought to be for this little word called hope. It cheers us thiough all the vicissitudes of life, when one hope fails, we soon erect another to lean upon when we are sad and discourag. ed; hope comes as a glad messenger and cheers our droop- ing spirits." "Well, massa, 1 guess from what you have said, you haven't nothing to do but rest contented, and hope for better times-so pop goes the Weasel--come on Charley,    <pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6865-00000005"/> 8 let me give you a good rubbing down, and a good dry stable, where is a plenty of corn and fodder. Now Charley, eat hearty, for I expect massa will drive you soon, for he is dead in love with Rsoae gal." ChIarley paws and snorts as he chews his feed, enough to say, all right. But the storm cleared away, and Nature re-appeared in ' all her beauty and grandeur. The stars re-appeared in all their silent beauty, and as each constellation appeared, and disappeared, the night still slept on in beauty. Morning dawned, and as the stars disappeared, the sun arose in, unclouded brilliancy, aInd disappeared the gloom that lad so long overshadowed, as it was while approach- ing the school-house, there, I espied as I thought, the belle of the world, a morning glory, looked like a rose in its bloom, an angel form. Often, I would make it my business, to pass by the school house, and every time I did so, I would see my darling, sit- ting by the window, and I thought she was the prettiest thing under Heaven. The smile that floated on her rosy cheeks, looked so lovingly, and her sparkling eyes so charm- ing, that every time I saw her, my love would increase; at last it got to such a high pitch, I had to dress up, all in my best, to go and see Miss Catharine, the darling of my heart. Sire lives in Craven county--so off I goes, like a doctor to his patient, at a rate of a mile a minute-go along, Charly, what did I feed you for? So soon as I hove in sight of my loved one's house; and it seemed as soon, as I came in sight Charley was the proud- est fellow I ever saw, it seemed as if he tried to look over the house, he held such a high and gay head. Very often, I would take Miss Catharine behind Charley and go some fifteeen or twenty miles to church, or some oth- er place of enjoyment, and when I did, it seemed as if Char- ley was aware of it- For'he appeared more active then, and a prouder horse I never saw. Now, I had been in Miss   9 Catharine's presence several times before I popped the ques- tion. It was the hardest thing I ever attempted to do, in all my life; but after I mashed the potatoe, and began to talk 'lasses, it seemed to be the easiest thing I ever under- took to do. O, it was a lovely thing, a feeling of enjoy- ment, although a strange feeling, and an uneasy one, though I loved it, for the same reason I loved Kittie, and I believe Kittie loved me, for pretty soon we were engaged to be mar- ried. O, that infernal teacher, he was all the time laying stumbling blocks in my way, [and others would rise up against me, some on the left, and some on my right, and some in front, and some in the rear; but after all, she loved me, or she promised to go through weal or woe,let what come what may, she was mine, and I was hers. But the hardest thing I ever done, was to ask the old folks for her; but at last I raised ambition enough, and went to the house ; but not finding her father at home, I waited till I reached his plantation, about two miles from his house. When I found him, he was sitting behind the barn feeding some pigs. Well, we talked away for about two hours before I mentioned it, but at the same time wanted to do it ; but was afraid the answer would be No. So many had tried to break me up in this match. Some had said I was insolvent, and some say I were a rum-sucker, gambler, and a spendthrift, so every time I tried to ask him, it choked me, mv spittle woulld become ropey, and dry and thirsty as if I had been without water for several days ; but after a while I managed te get it out edgeways. "M r. Doublin, your daughter Catharine, has promised me her hand, providing you and her mother will condescend to sanction it." The old fellow hung. his head for about two minutes, and said, "I will give you *n answer in a few days." Now 1 was in a sweat, sighing and blowing, wishing Ibhad stayed back. Now we were moving in the direc-    <pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6865-00000006"/> tion of his house, I, trying to get his good graces. Now we are at his residence. I see my darling Kittie, I told her what the old man had said. She said, "its just like papa." I goes back again, but Kittie tells me her father wishes her, to go to school two or three years first, be- fore marrying. So I waited and waited, and kept by her side nearly all the time for two years. One more year yet, and our marriage will come off-But O, this war, this cruel war, between the North and the South has commenced. What shall I do, O, what shall I do. It will not do to marry now; and to be a Secessioner, is against my will. I am for the Union, and the Union alone. I am for the Country that our forefathers fought for. I am for the old Stars and Stripes. The flag I were cradled under, this flag, may it never be trodden under the foot of any 'man, and, to sum up the whole, may I see our Ccuntry yet united, and may my last breath be spent under the Star Spangled Banner. O, may our Country be as it once were. A Black Republican and a Secessionist, I do dislike. For freeing our negroes, and settle them in the midst of us, I am oppoosed to it; but if the Government will pay us for our negroes, and place them in a territory to them- selves, then, I am for'Emancipation. I am for a 'Gov- ersment that has no negroes in it. O, may the time soon come, when our Nation, re-united clear of the black race. May it be a Nation of white people. These are my sentiments, although I am in a rebel camp ground. I am a drafted soldier, and if these lines were to reach headquarters, and I in their reach; what would be the consequence, would I be shot, or would I be hanged? The last of poor Jack Skinner. My EVER DEAR LOVER: This will inform you that I am yet   " alive and quite well; but in low spirits. I guess you under- stand the nature of war by this time, as it has brought on many changes, such as is painful. O, what sorrowful times, indeed it makes me feel as if I were lost and ruined forev- er. Why so? Because you are not here by my side, O, this cruel war, when will it be over, so we can meet to part no more till death. I cannot say when I can come again, as times is so critical, it may be in a few days, and it may be M never; but if we never meet any more, this will be my wish to thee: May the blessing of God wait upon thee; may the sun of glory shine around thy head; may the gates of peace and plenty, honor and happiness, be always open to thee and thine; may no strife, distress thy days; may no sor- row distress thy nights; may the pillow of peace kiss thy cheeks, and pleasure of imagination atttend thy dreams. And when length of years make thee dreary of earthly joys, and the curtains of death, cling around thee to finish thy existence, may the angel of God take care that the expiring lamp shall not receive one rude bast to hasten the extinction and finally may the Savior's blood wash thee from all im- purities, and at last usher thee into a land of everlasting felicity. DOMESTIC HAPPINESS- There can scarcely remain a doubt in the minds of any, all the railing on the subject, to the contrary notwithstand- ing, that the true sphere of worldly happiness is decidedly to be found in the domestic circle, and that all, without it is flutterings, anxiety, discordant bustle, and heart-rending incertitude, Nature seems happily to have adaptedlthe connu- bial state to the feelings of wants and situation of man. Here, he not only finds a solace to his feelings-a supply for his wants; but an exemption from the many J- e en    <pb n="12" xml:id="VAC6865-00000007"/> temptations which surround him, that have a tendency to mar his peace, to undermine his health, and frustrate the purposes of his existence. Man, emphatically, needs some- thing to love, something upon which he may bestow his af- fections. Woman, lovely woman, was created to this end, and the situation in which this fact ought necessarially to place him, and the pledges, and the bond of the union thus effected, will give employment to, and call into exercise, those powers and affections which were bostowed by the All-wise-Being. And it is only under circumstances like these, that he can be truly happy; that he can enjoy that serenity of mind; that peace a]:d joy of the heart, which ever accompanies the performances of that duty. When, therefore, that time of life has happily arrived when this duty should be performed, and it should not be delayed too long, it should be one first and imperious care, to select a partner with whom we may reasonatDl expect to be hap- py. Love, in its common acceptation among young peo- ple, is a passion too sophistical and deceitful to be relied on altogether, though a portion is desirable if not necessary. But at all events, reason should go with us, and be with us in this all important choice. Beauty may inflame the pas- sion, but it cannot satisfy the mind It may be a necessary spurr, but it, should not be the governing principle. In corn- ming to a decision on this subject, we should be influenced and decided by the cultivation and powers of the mind, the virtues of the heart, and particularly by that affectionate kindness, ahd winning 'softness of mannt:rs which is endearing to the soul. This susceptibility, or rather sensi- bility of feeling, is the chief charms of a lovely woman, and is that which gives a zest to all of our pleasures--dis- arms affection and misfortune of their sting, and scatters the perenial flowers of affection and true love is our path through life. w    i     </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>