<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/lib/xml/tei/p5/general.xsd"
     xml:id="VAC6292">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Young Empress and the Reclaimed Deserter </title>
            <author>Doowrof.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Perry Willett</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Electronic Text Specialist</resp>
               <name xml:id="adamhoch">Adam Hochstetter</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="mdalmau">Michelle Dalmau</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1320 E. 10th St.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Bloomington, IN 47405</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno type="wright">VAC6292</idno>
            <idno type="wright2" n="previous">wright2-0763</idno>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>2013, The Trustees of Indiana University. Indiana University makes a claim of
                    copyright only to original contributions made by the Wright American Fiction project 
                    participants and other members of the university community. Indiana
                    University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
                    granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
                    contributions to this work claimed by Indiana University for non-profit
                    educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For
                    inquiries about commercial uses, please contact the Indiana University Libraries.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="s" type="project">Wright American Fiction: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The young empress and the reclaimed deserter</title>
                  <author>Doowrof.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>37 p.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>J. Lucas</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Baltimore </pubPlace>
                  <date when="1857">1857</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created as part of a project by the Committee on Institutional
                    Cooperation. Project description and participants are available at the project
                    website at http://www.letrs.indiana.edu/wright.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoding and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">French</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2005-05-30">Finished OCR, rough encoding and error checking</change>
         <change who="Perry Willett, Indiana University" when="2005-06-24">Finished TEI conversion</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-06-23">Converted document from SGML to TEI P5.</change>
         <change who="Siobhain Rivera" when="2014-06-23">Edited encoding to fix Table of Contents and title page.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n=" (TitlePage) " xml:id="VAC6292-00000001"/>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>THE Young Empress AND THE RECLAIMED DESERTER:</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">A TALE OF THE VICISSITUDES OF HUMAN LIFE.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>BY <docAuthor>DOOWROF.</docAuthor>
            </byline>
            <docEdition>PRICE TWENTY-FIVE CENTS.</docEdition>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>BALTIMORE:</pubPlace>
               <publisher>PRINTED BY JAMES LUCAS &amp; SON, <address>
                     <addrLine>Corner of Calvert Street and Lovely Lane.</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </publisher>
            </docImprint>
            <docDate when="1857">1857.</docDate>
         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <head>The young empress and the reclaimed deserter</head>
            <pb n="2-3" xml:id="VAC6292-00000002"/>
            <head>THE YOUNG EMPRESS AND THE DESERTER.</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
               <p>It was evening. The glorious luminary of day was just declining to his golden couch, surrounded by a brilliant array of bright delusions, and enveloped in a flood of radiance, while clouds of every hue were chasing each other with mimic rivalry through the heavens, and as the lingering sunbeams spread over land and sea, falling in light and shade over cloud capped mountain and flowery vale, over forest and streamlet, adding fairy-like beauty to each feature of the landscape, the scene was lovely to behold.</p>
               <p>Night was just about hanging her gloomy curtain over nature, and already the stars that gem the nocturnal diadem were faintly merging into vision, while far away in the Eastern sky, the silvery effulgence of the rising moon, was rapidly illuminating the gathering darkness, which was now robing the distant void in the dusky folds of midnight gloom.</p>
               <p>At the time of which I speak, in an apartment of a dreary looking mansion situate near the modern city of Genoa, sat an old man and his beautiful daughter. The brightly beaming, dark hazel eyes and broad high forehead of the old man, the noble contour of his form, indicated the position in which he acted. The peerless maiden by his side might have been nineteen years of age; her person was well rounded but delicate. She did not possess the raven tresses and the fierce glance of Spain's fair<pb n="4-5" xml:id="VAC6292-00000003"/> daughters, but the golden locks and sparkling eyes which are exceptionable in Italian beauty. Her complexion was clear, mingling the purity of the lily with the softened brilliancy of the rose. Her eyes, of the deepest, most radiant hue, were upturned to those of her companion, with a glance of fearful tenderness, which overspread the face of the old man with a flush of sincere earnestness.</p>
               <p>Her expression was sweet and seraphic, though now her cheek was tinged with the pale hue of sadness. She saw not the gorgeous sunset, nor the pale disk of the queenly moon rising in the reflected rose tints of the Eastern sky, nor did she hear the busy hum of retiring multitudes as they wended their progress homeward. But her thoughts were entirely concentrated on the interesting but mournful conversation that was going on between her and the old man.</p>
               <p>"Do you think you will go, father?" sweetly asked Eugene.</p>
               <p>"Yes, my child," replied the old man, "I feel it my duty to go. The Emperor of Austria has recently issued a proclamation for the purpose of forming a large army to serve in the impending struggle, and I, as one, have secretly dedicated my services, and my life, if needed to my country."</p>
               <p>"Well, father," resumed Eugene. "I suppose it will be of no avail to persuade you from your design."</p>
               <p>"Eugene," replied the old man, "I dislike leaving you exceedingly, for I fear there is no one in the wide world who will care for you when I am gone."</p>
               <p>"Yes father," replied Eugene, "there is one," but she blushed and paused.</p>
               <p>A shadow seemed to flit over the old man's face. "Henry Weston," he muttered, "that American soldier." To tell you the truth, Eugene, I have never liked him, but as God wills, so it must transpire; but look well into the matter, ere you bestow your hand; but I hesitate, for I have no right to instruct you."</p>
               <p>"Cannot instruct me father?"</p>
               <p>"Dear girl, I am not your father."</p>
               <p>"What!" exclaimed Eugene "you are not in earnest?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, child, I am? but I must be gone; here in this bundle is sufficient means to maintain you for many, years. Eugene, I shall never see you again; Farewell!" He glided out at the open door and was soon lost to vision in the thick gloom of night.</p>
               <p>The young girl could contain her feelings no longer, and uttering a heart rending and impulsive scream, she sank upon a sofa, overwhelmed with an exuberant suffusion of grief and tears.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
               <p>It is near midnight. We are no longer in Genoa, basking beneath the dazzling glory of a southern sun. The wind that sweeps fiercely and rude from the frigid North, is bitter and piercing, and drives before it the eddying snow like the white crested billows of the turbulent sea.</p>
               <p>A sledge drawn by six horses, harnessed three abreast, is dashing forward over snow and ice, with the velocity of a strong winged bird. It contains, beside the driver, two American deserters, who are quite snugly ensconsed within the vehicle. "Harvey," murmured his companion, "how far are we from the Black Horn Tavern?"</p>
               <p>"Only a few miles," resumed the other, who was apparently an officer.</p>
               <p>"Captain," said the soldier, "we have deserted from the army, and I fear we shall be overtaken, conveyed back, and perhaps meet an igominious death, and I am fearful that I shall never meet with her whom I love, yes love to distraction; she lives in Genoa, far away in the sunny peninsula of Italy. I intended to procure a permit as soon as expedient, and disposing of what few effects I possess, embark upon a vessel <foreign xml:lang="FRA">en route</foreign> to the city in which my dearest Eugene resides, but now my hopes are crushed, my expectations annihilated, and every bright anticipation frustrated, and all on your account; but as soon as I recover from the effect of this<pb n="6-7" xml:id="VAC6292-00000004"/> wound, I intend to return to the army and implore forgiveness. In about two hours, the party arrived at the Tavern, where help was immediately solicited to aid him into the house.</p>
               <p>Presently the inmates of the dilapidated Old Tavern retired to rest, amid a general huzza for Old England.</p>
               <p>The storm without grew wilder and more impetuous. The entire sky seemed mantled with the darkest habiliments of stormy wrath, while the snow, whirling angrily about, was swept by the irresistible blast, into huge avalanches of gigantic form. But at length day dawned, and the fleecy floating vapors that lingered playfully around the rising god of day, formed a fancied halo of circumscribed beauty, which seemed to smile on the emerging star of America as it twinkled transcendantly above the dizzy horizon of carnage and conflict.</p>
               <p>By the time the sun had reached meridian, the deserters were again wending their progress onward. The officer had determined to entice his comrade to Boston, where as speedily as possible, they were to sail from its harbor, bound for the nearest seaport of England. But long before they had traveled half the distance, they were surprised to observe a number of horsemen closely watching their actions and proceedings. The officer instantly communicated the discovery to the driver, who immediately turned the horses, driving them into a thick wood, which margined on the road. The officer and Henry alighted, and endeavored to screen themselves from view, by collecting a large pile of dry leaves and decayed branches, under which they crept, and huddling together bade defiance to discovery.</p>
               <p>Directly the cavaliers came up, the leader inquired of the driver if he had seen two disguised soldiers about the woods recently.</p>
               <p>The driver pretending misrepresentation of the question, pointed to the road and said, "I believe they passed here a few moments ago for one of them asked me the distance to Boston."</p>
               <p>"Onward, men?" shouted their leader, "to Boston? to Boston? if we catch the deserting rascals, we will receive a handsome reward from our General." No sooner had the sentence expired upon his lips, ere the furious horseman, encouraged and more determined, started off toward the city, shouting, "Huzza for the Young Eagle? death to the British and the deserters!" In the meantime, the hidden train remained silent and immoveable, but as soon as their pursuers had vanished, they sprung forth with elasticity and joy, immediately asking the driver, what the soldiers had said.</p>
               <p>Handley then informed them of the particulars of the interview as minutely and correctly as he could. They then shouted, "thank God? our pursuers have evaded us."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
               <p>It was morning. We are no longer in America, witnessing the escapes of the unfortunate deserters, nor are we in romantic Italy.</p>
               <p>The hyperborean tempest sweeps like some swift winged phantom of death over land and sea, and bears upon its icy breath the rain and hail of mid winter.</p>
               <p>A closely curtained coach, drawn by four snow white horses, is dashing onward over rough and smooth with swift and rapid haste.</p>
               <p>Within that coach is seated a gentleman and lady wrapped closely in furs, to protect them against the fury of the cold night wind.</p>
               <p>"Raphali," said the lady, "what was the meaning of that fearful cry?"</p>
               <p>"You must not ask me," replied her companion, and then speaking to the driver he added, "Theodore, spare not the lash as you value your life. We cannot be more than forty miles from Borodino." "That cry again!" cried Eugene, (for this was indeed the heroine of our story) "Raphali, I insist on knowing what it means." "It is the wolves, Eugene, "cried Raphali, pressing her convulsively to his breast, "but Theodore and I are armed, besides I trust in the speed of my horses; they are fleeter than the wind." Eugene pressed the hand of her companion and said, "Raphali, how cruel you are to tear me from my home, and convey me to another land;<pb n="8-9" xml:id="VAC6292-00000005"/> if Henry Weston knew this, oh! how his blood would boil with indignation."</p>
               <p>But again came those unearthly howlings borne by the fleeting wind, and casting her eyes back, Eugene saw by the star light, a dark cloud moving like a shadow over the crusted ground, and drawing near the coach with fearful speed. "Look, Raphali!" she shrieked, "they will surely be upon us."</p>
               <p>"She speaks the truth by Heaven," said Raphali. "Famine has certainly overcome their cowardly nature. What can we do?"</p>
               <p>"If I might offer an opinion," said Theodore, "I should say that we had better unharness one of our horses, and leave him to the wolves."</p>
               <p>"Good," cried Raphali, "be quick with your work."</p>
               <p>The serf sprang from his seat, and cut one of the horses loose from the coach, while his master held the reins of the others. The animal snorted with terror, as if aware of the fate that awaited him, but Theodore held him firmly by the bit with his left hand while with the right he drew a short sword and plunged it into the animal's heart. With a moan like the last cry of a dying man, the martyred beast fell lifeless.</p>
               <p>"Away!" cried Raphali, flinging the reins to the serf as he sprang to his seat. "This stratagem has saved us."</p>
               <p>On, on they flew, swifter than before. Cold as the night was, the horses reeked with perspiration.</p>
               <p>Raphali looked back, and beheld the ravening wolves quenching their thirst and satiating their appetite, with the blood and flesh of the slaughtered animal.</p>
               <p>The time thus gained was well improved, and just about midnight the coach entered the confines of a majestic park, surrounding a princely mansion, whose domes and spires of mingled Greek and oriental architecture, rose in loveliness and beauty against a star gemmed sky. The glow of fire and lamp light streamed from the huge windows, and along the avenue leading to the main entrance, stood men with lighted torches, whose ruddy glare threw a lucid flood of effulgence upon the gloom of the night.</p>
               <p>"Raphali, whose palace is this?" asked Eugene.</p>
               <p>"Mine," replied her companion proudly, "these are my slaves, and I am not the poor painter Raphali, as you supposed, but Count Alexander Bocaris, one of the wealthiest nobles of Russia."</p>
               <p>"You Alexander Bocaris!" exclaimed Eugene, "and I suppose, by thus changing your name, you think that I will consent to become your bride. No, never! rather linger out a thousand excrutiating deaths than to become the companion of one who is universally disliked."</p>
               <p>"Well pretty one, I shall see to that," replied Alexander.</p>
               <p>Presently they alighted at the entrance of the marble paved corridor; they passed through a long suite of apartments, furnished with a barbaric sumptuousness, which indicated wealth, without taste, and was characteristic of the early period of Russian history, when treasures lightly won by the sword, were scattered by hands unguided by refinement.</p>
               <p>Beautiful slaves waited to welcome them into the magnificently embellished parlor, in which, tired, and almost exhausted, they sat down upon a scarlet velvet divan.</p>
               <p>"Farewell," said Bocaris, as he arose to depart, "this is for the present your home; you must remain here till I return."</p>
               <p>He then departed, but on his way out he met Theodore, who, faint and weary, was wending his footsteps to his room.</p>
               <p>"Sit down, Theodore," said Alexander, "and let us converse awhile, and then you can retire."</p>
               <p>"Theodore," said his master, in a tone of despair, "I am a villain."</p>
               <p>The serf gazed upon his master with an inquiring look.</p>
               <p>"You are a slave," continued Bocaris, "but you are freer and happier than I. Your conscience is pure from stain, you are an involuntary bondsman, while I, Theodore, have committed one of the most fiendish crimes on record. I ruthlessly tore that young and lovely maiden from her own fireside, and have had her borne here within the very walls of my own mansion. These cursed walls, glittering with riches, robed with magnificence, are but the walls of a gilded prison. These stars and orders that blaze upon<pb n="10-11" xml:id="VAC6292-00000006"/> my breast are the badges of my infamy. I serve, 'tis true, an imperial mistress, but an humble despot would be less exacting. Theodore, if you ever sigh for freedom, remember Alexander Bocaris, the slave of the Czarina of Russia."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
               <p>We will now return to notice the further actions of the Deserters, whom we left conversing near the pile of leaves, under which they had so fortunately eluded a discovery.</p>
               <p>After exchanging several unimportant questions, they came to the conclusion, that to retrace their steps back to the army again, would be prudent. Therefore they commenced their return, and before a week had rolled round, they reached the terminus of their journey, and when about entering the limits of the encampment, a large company of soldiers rushed forcibly towards them, exclaiming with a vociferous voice,</p>
               <p>"The Deserters! the Deserters! come boys, let us hang them."</p>
               <p>At that moment General Washington appeared, and taking his stand upon an elevated projection, he waved his hand and cried out with a voice like thunder,</p>
               <p>"Hold there, soldiers! touch them not."</p>
               <p>No sooner had this short sentence expired upon his lips, than the infuriated multitude relaxed their anger, and instantly came <foreign xml:lang="FRA">en masse,</foreign> begging the General to forgive their misconduct. Of course Washington forgave them, not without giving them a reprimanding, and telling them never to lay violent hands upon a deserter without his command. He then bade the Officer and Henry to appear in his presence, which order they unhesitatingly obeyed, and in the course of the conversation he told them never to flee again in time of battle, and in these words, remarked:</p>
               <p>"You shall be reinstated in the army, and possess every privilege which you did prior to this event. We will have another conflict ere long, and I fear a bloody and terrible one, but let come what may, stand your ground like patriots, retain your position like Americans, and if you fall in defence of your country it will be a greater glory than to retreat ere you have struck a single blow for liberty and independence."</p>
               <p>After listening to this truly encouraging admonition, the reclaimed deserters raised a shrill and enthusiastic huzza for freedom and Republicanism, which seemed to arise and float in remurmuring echoes on the passing zephyr.</p>
               <p>Immediately the entire army concentrated around and hailed with welcome shouts the restored members of their legion, for Henry Weston was one, of their favorites in every-time of battle. He was never known to hesitate from accomplishing more than was really, his share, until the last combat, when fighting bravely in the midst of death and misery, the cowardly officer drew him from the phalanx in which he was so nobly fighting, and induced him to make haste in leaving the army, whispering in his ears in the meantime, that Washington exceedingly disliked his mode of battling,(which was indeed the most satanical falsehood that ever fell from the lips of man.)</p>
               <p>A few days soon passed away, and very early one bright summer's morn, Henry Weston observed the British army silently advancing towards the encampment. Immediately he informed Washington of the fact, and ere another, hour had elapsed the two armies were engaged in furious conflict, and as the lurid battle clouds of dense and murky volumes filled the horizon of the heavens, and the instantaneous discharge of ponderous artillery pealed forth upon the agonized air, the frantic rush of contesting opponents was fearful to behold. Ever and anon the lacteous wreaths of cannon smoke belched forth upon the wings of the igneous atmosphere, followed by crashes like rolling thunder, and the sight of myriad pools of gore and blood which filled every hollow and cavity, was almost sufficient to cloud the mind with awful terror and consternation. Thus the fierce and sanguine combat<pb n="12-13" xml:id="VAC6292-00000007"/> continued for several hours, and finally such was the simultaneous rush on the American side to accomplish a great and glorious victory, that the army of the enemy in indiscriminate multitudes fled with an extraordinary rapidity from the field. And then as the last surviving member of that once powerful host disappeared amid the umbrageous forest which intervened, the victorious American army sent up such a deafening and uncircumscribed shout for the infant Republic, as was never heard before or since in that region.</p>
               <p>But ah! the sight all over the battle field presented a ghastly and sickening appearance. On every side were huddled together numerous groups of the dead, whose distorted countenances very conspicuously indicated the horrible death which they died. Here and there were heaped up vast piles of the dying, intermingled with the carcasses of martyred horses, and as the farewell sunbeams played over many a wretched form yet enduring the agony of a thousand deaths, unimprisoned spirits separated from their earthly tenements hovered gently over the scene, and then winged their flight away to the God who gave them.</p>
               <p>Yet, terrible as was the carnage, Henry Weston escaped unhurt, and as his companions gathered around him they seemed to rejoice, when he informed them that he had not received a single wound.</p>
               <p>But sad to relate, the wicked Officer who so recently had succeeded in enticing his comrade away, was dreadfully mutilated, and before morning dawned, he lay upon the gory plain a stiff and bloody corpse.</p>
               <p>In that battle we lost many a gallant hero, but nevertheless came off triumphant and victorious. Thus terminated the terrible battle of Monmouth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
               <p>"Methinks the service of the highest lady in the land were not degrading," responded Theodore.</p>
               <p>"Listen," said Bocaris.</p>
               <p>"In Genoa, there lived a poor young girl, whose life, for reasons of State policy it was absolutely necessary should be in the hands of the Czarina. Beyond the frontiers of Russia, the liberty and life of that young girl was safe. How should she be lured beyond that fatal boundary into the heart of this dread empire? The Empress Catherine, with the cunning of a fiend, had devised the project. She would send an emissary to the young girl, who should feign love for her and thus win her young affections. The infatuated maiden would be sure to follow her lover into Russia, and once there he would deliver her into the possession of the Czarina. But who would be this purjured villain? Who would act this infamy? Ah! the Empress wanted a smooth faced devil, and his name is Alexander Bocaris. Yes, I am he. That girl is in yonder chamber, and I, yes I, am her betrayer, but still she loves me not. Another, who is worthier than I, claims her affections."</p>
               <p>"But," said Theodore, "did not her innocence disarm you?"</p>
               <p>"Theodore," replied Bocaris, "I was nurtured in a school of duplicity, selfishness, ambition and cruelty. But to see that radiant image of youth, was to love her, and I do love her madly. The love of the Empress is loathing to me; the nearer I approach her hated presence, the more I dislike her. True love has opened my eyes to her and my baseness. Still the chains that bind me to her, were strong enough to draw me back thus far, and to-morrow I must present myself at Court. I leave Eugene to your care; guard her as the object that is dearest to your master's heart."</p>
               <p>"I will lay down my life for her," said the serf.</p>
               <p>"She shall not perish," cried Bocaris, wildly. "Sooner than a hair of her head shall be hurt, I will stab the Empress to the heart, as she sits in splendor upon her throne, surrounded by her armed nobles and faithful attendants."</p>
               <p>With these words, the Count dismissed his truth-confiding slave.</p>
               <p>The next morning, ere the bright effulgence of the rising sun had gilded the Eastern horizon, and while the fair Eugene was sleeping, not dreaming of the perils that awaited her, Bocaris took horse with a few followers, and repaired to Moscow, the seat of the<pb n="14-15" xml:id="VAC6292-00000008"/> imperial Government. Here he was received by the Empress Catharine, with every mark of distinction, while on his part he endeavored, by the earnestness and devotion of his manner, to show that his feelings towards the Empress were unchanged, and that he was overjoyed at again meeting her, after so long an absence. But if his manner concealed aversion and hatred, that of the Empress was equally assumed, for the report of a Turkish spy, whom she had sent to watch the actions of her favorite, had awakened her suspicions of Bocaris' fidelity, and of the tone and condition of his feelings towards the youthful Eugene.</p>
               <p>When asked by the proud Empress, why he had not conveyed his charge immediately to the Capital, Bocaris replied that he considered it proper first to report his proceedings, and await the instructions of the Empress.</p>
               <p>Catharine replied that it was well, and said that she must see Eugene and satisfy herself with regard to her, by a private interview.</p>
               <p>Bocaris' cheek turned pale at the dangerous proposition, but he could not avoid acquiescing in the plan.</p>
               <p>In the meantime, as the day wore on, Eugene had risen, breakfasted and was now seated in the splendid apartment, amused at the strange aspect of everything around. The beauty and striking costume of her attendants, the rude luxury of the furniture and the wild sublimity of the snow-clad landscape, seen through the huge windows, occupied her thoughts at intervals. While she was gazing with astonishment upon the magnificence that surrounded her, she was informed that a Jewish merchant desired to show her some of his merchandise.</p>
               <p>Eugene desired him to be admitted.</p>
               <p>He was an old man, with a long beard that descended nearly to his waist, and bent, less by the weight of his pack, than by the pressure of years. He saluted the lady with humble civility, and then displayed his goods, began to expatiate on their beauty and excellence in a style of true professional exuberance.</p>
               <p>At last, lowering his tone, he asked humbly if he could say a few words to the lady alone. Eugene then dismissed her attendants ants, curious to hear what important business, the old man had with her.</p>
               <p>He then took from his bundle a letter directed to her, and gave it to Eugene. She instantly opened it, and was overjoyed to behold the signature of Henry Weston affixed to it. As she perused the contents she could scarcely refrain from bursting into tears of joy and gratitude combined.</p>
               <p>"Lady," said the merchant, "I have a rare and costly bracelet set with pearls from the Caspian. If I mistake not, I think it will match the one you wear. Will you permit me to look at it?"</p>
               <p>Eugene extended her fair arm and the Jew fixed his eyes upon the bracelet.</p>
               <p>"Good God!" he exclaimed, "it is she."</p>
               <p>Then falling on his knees, he kissed her hand over and over again, betraying the most singular agitation.</p>
               <p>"Are you mad, old man?" said Eugene, surprised and alarmed at his excitement.</p>
               <p>"No, lady, I am not mad," he replied, raising his streaming eyes to her beautiful face. "But tell me, where did you come from? Why is it that you are here? Is the hour indeed arrived?"</p>
               <p>"You bewilder me with your questions," answered Eugene; "I came with Alexander Bocaris from Genoa, where I was born. My name is Eugene Seville."</p>
               <p>"No, no," said the old man, "you are not a child of Italy; this frozen empire gave you birth, as flowers sometimes blossom in Siberia. You are not Eugene Seville, but Sophia, daughter of the late Czar, the step-father of the present Empress."</p>
               <p>"What do you mean?" exclaimed Eugene.</p>
               <p>"I have told the truth," replied the old man. "When but an infant I saved you from the fury of Catherine, who sought your life, for you, the daughter of the Czar by his first wife, was heiress to the throne, while Catherine, his widow, was an usurper. From hand to hand we passed you beyond the frontiers; my noble friends and I raised your standard and fought as long and well as men could for your rights, but we were defeated. I saved my life by hiding till pursuit was abandoned, and then lived in disguise.<pb n="16-17" xml:id="VAC6292-00000009"/> Robbed of my estate property, a price was set upon my head. This house was once mine. I am a landless man now, but what of that? The loyalty that animates my heart repays me tenfold for all my privations, sufferings and sacrifices. At the peril of my life, I have sought this interview with you, but were I to forfeit my existence, I should die happy, in having again beheld the features of my lawful sovereign. Farewell lady, I must go to work, and win for you a prize cheaply obtained by the loss of a thousand such lives as mine: the Crown of Russia."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
               <p>After the enthusiastic acclamations of triumph which arose from the American army, soon after the late bloody contest had ceased to reiterate their oft reverberated echoes on the circumambient breeze, Henry Weston was surprised to behold the mail coach slowly coming towards the encampment, but was much more surprised, when the list of letters was being read to hear the distributor mention his name. Eagerly pressing his way through the crowd of soldiers which had thronged around, he advanced to the coach and received the letter with much more satisfaction and joy than did the most of his companions.</p>
               <p>After breaking the seal, he unfolded the letter and glanced at the signature, and oh! that sweet name almost sent a thrill of unextinguishable rapture through his heart. It was his own beloved Eugene Seville's name.</p>
               <p>He clasped the precious paper to his breast murmuring silently, "thank God, my wish is at last complied with," and wending his footsteps to a solitary tent he sat down upon a moss-enveloped stone and perused the contents of the affectionate communication.</p>
               <p>It closed with the following words:</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <p>"And now Henry, in conclusion, I have always remembered you with affectionate love, even when sorrow and sadness seemed to wrap their dark mantle around me, and when every bright star that gemmed the firmament of my mind was obscured behind the inky paraphernalia of distress, I will never forget the time when I bade you farewell in Genoa some few months since. Ever since that period I have thought of your kindness with a true sense of regard.</p>
                           <p>"If you should come again, remember that I am at present confined in a sort of palace dungeon near Moscow, and I sincerely hope no accident will befall you on your perilous voyage. When the Jewish merchant handed me the letter from you yesterday, I was so overwhelmed when I saw your signature that I could scarcely speak, and in the course of the conversation which took place between us, he acquainted we with some astonishing facts, which I will relate to you when we meet again. Oh! Henry do hasten and free me from the clutches of the hated Empress. I have just understood that she intends confining me in this place for a month. With an anticipation that we will meet ere long, I conclude, ever remaining your devoted and unchangeable lover until death,</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>EUGENE SEVILLE."</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Immediately after Henry had perused the letter he went to the General's tent, and there bowing before him, said, "General, I have just received a letter from one whom I love better than myself, and if you will oblige me so much by permitting me to resign my station in the army, for the purpose of claiming the hand of her who is part and parcel of my existence, I will ever remember you, and if I ever return to this country I shall come back and resume my position in the army." "Henry," said Washington, "I sincerely regret your separation, for I never had a better and braver soldier under my command, but if you are compelled to leave I must comply with your wish. Farewell," concluded the General, "I wish you a safe and prosperous journey."</p>
               <p>Henry bade good bye to his old comrades, mounted his horse and in a few minutes was out of sight. On the evening of the next day he arrived at Boston, when he disposed of his horse and other articles too worthless to take along.</p>
               <pb n="18-19" xml:id="VAC6292-00000010"/>
               <p>He then engaged passage on a large and capacious vessel, which was to sail for Brest the next day. Early next morning extensive preparations were being made for the sailing out. The morning was calm and beautiful, not a solitary cloud was floating over the firmament, and the balmy breezes that circumnavigated the wild and tempestuous ocean seemed lulling into repose the few turbulent waves that arose and-fell in appalling grandeur over the vasty deep.</p>
               <p>At ten o'clock the moorings were cut loose, thereby freeing the giant craft, and as she bounded out upon the mighty waste of waters, like an uncaged bird dashing into the salubrious breezes of romantic summer, she seemed as if anxious to complete her voyage, with the aerial rapidity of a discharged arrow.</p>
               <p>Gaily and proudly did she stem the gigantic billows for several successive days, during which time the weather was extraordinarily delightful. The wind, which frequently is so ruthless and hurricannic, seemed hushed in a doze of quiet and uninterrupted slumber. But soon, ah! very soon, that lovely craft was to founder in the roaring gale, whose destructive auxiliaries were to assist in consummating the dreadful work.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
               <p>After Eugene had listened to the pathetic tale of the old man, she said,</p>
               <p>"And who are you, my friend," not yet recovered from the bewilderment occasioned by the revelation,</p>
               <p>"I am Roulet the bayard," replied the old man.</p>
               <p>"But I must be gone."</p>
               <p>"Stay, stay, I implore you," said Eugene., "breathe not my name, let me still be Eugene Seville, the Italian maiden, happy in the love of a distant friend."</p>
               <p>"Ah madam," replied Roulet, "you will forget love in the dreams of ambition."</p>
               <p>"Never," answered Sophia, (we will call her by this name for the present,) "I am not so anxious to occupy a throne."</p>
               <p>"It was your father's wish," said Roulet, solemnly, "that you should wear his crown, and we his followers have pledged ourselves to maintain you. Can you refuse me now?"</p>
               <p>"Ah, Roulet, I can never aspire to that lofty eminence. If I mistake not, I have an elder sister living somewhere in this country, and I suppose my father willed the crown to his eldest child."</p>
               <p>"But never mind that," replied Roulet, "as you are alive, and as your sister may be dead, we shall strike for you; and now Sophia, I bid you farewell; I dare not prolong my stay, but we shall meet again ere long. Fear not, I have arms and friends."</p>
               <p>Sophia was left alone to ponder over the singular story she had just learned from the lips of Roulet. The thought that she, a young and timid girl, should be the cause of revolutionizing an empire, that blood should be shed for her, filled her heart with dread, and would have dethroned her reason, but for the image of Henry, from whom her thoughts could not be long estranged. When would he come to rescue her from the clutches of Catherine, whose chains of hatred were so closely entwined about her? She was now about falling into the hands of the Empress, by the hellish machinations of Bocaris, who pretended to love her with so much ardor. In this apartment she continues to be confined for several days, when suddenly, one day, the door of the room was opened, and a lady dressed in black, and of a tall and commanding figure, entered, unnanounced, saluted her, and without waiting for an invitation, took a seat.</p>
               <p>"I hope I am not intruding," said the lady, "but I came here to see Alexander Bocaris."</p>
               <p>"He is at the Court, madam," answered Sophia.</p>
               <p>"You are the young lady who accompanied him from Italy," said the Empress.</p>
               <p>"I am," replied Sophia, blushing deeply.</p>
               <p>"It was a bold step, I think, for a young maiden," resumed the lady, whose years seemed to warrant the tone she assumed.</p>
               <pb n="20-21" xml:id="VAC6292-00000011"/>
               <p>"Madam," said Sophia fondly, "Alexander declares most positively he will claim my hand as soon as he returns from Court, but if I can prevent it, I will do so with all my heart."</p>
               <p>"Is he sure of my consent?" asked the lady.</p>
               <p>"I know not," replied Sophia.</p>
               <p>"I have heard," said the lady, "that Bocaris raises his eyes higher; that he loves the Empress."</p>
               <p>Sophia started to her feet. "It is false," said she; "he loves one who is more worthy of his hand than either I or the Empress, and I also know that Bocaris hates the Empress; he narrated to me all the atrocities of which she has been guilty, he went through the long catalogue of her perfidies and crimes, and ended by denouncing her as a monster."</p>
               <p>"Villain! villain!" said the stranger, rising in turn, "dared he to speak thus of me, his sovereign, his benefactress?"'</p>
               <p>"The Empress," exclaimed Sophia.</p>
               <p>"Yes, minion," answered the Czarina; for it was Catherine herself, "and do you suppose that your baby face and blooming cheek had power to gain the heart of Alexander Bocaris? Fool! fool! By heavens, it would be well to scourge this fancy out of you, with the thongs of the knout, and then send you to Siberia to cool your love amid the endless snows. Nay, smile not, my power is despotic."</p>
               <p>"How was it acquired?" asked Sophia, trembling with indignation.</p>
               <p>"By the will of my predecessor," replied the Empress.</p>
               <p>"It is false!" retorted Sophia; "the predecessor, though he married, never loved you. His heart was in the grave of his first wife, and to one of her children he bequeathed the crown of Russia."</p>
               <p>"Where are those children?" asked the Empress.</p>
               <p>"One of them stands before you!" replied Sophia. "I suppose I am the only survivor; I am not willing to accept of the crown of my own accord, but if those you have declared, if possible to seat me on the throne, I must consent."</p>
               <p>"We are alone." said the Empress, with forced calmness; "woman and woman, rivals in love, rivals in ambition. I recognize in you the blood of the Czars. It warms your cheek, it kindles in your glance; you are no longer the timid girl that first met my gaze on entering, but a woman, full of passion, energy and fire. I acknowledge it here in your presence, but beyond your presence I deny. Dare to assert your claims, and I crush you. Nay, more; it was by my means you were placed here in my power. One word of mine consigns you to a dungeon. Beware! beware!"</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
               <p>Life is indeed a frail bark, tossed on the billowy ocean of time. Pleasant breezes dimple the surface or play Eolian airs amid the slender cordage of man's graceful vessel; sweet and ravishing music in strains of convulsive laughter is heard ever and anon as we proceed, and upon the balmy air roll the sweet notes of the aerial tribes, ever charming us with their sweet melody. The golden fruit in the paradise of anticipation, hangs in gorgeous clusters from the bending branches, whose odoriferous perfume throws a halcyon enigma over our future destiny. But amid all this lovely and delightful scenery, death, in his gigantic strides, like a Hercules roused and nerved by ambition and honor's crown, is ever active, and we see him dashing on with fearful speed in his work of affliction and misery. The velvet lepidodptera now cease to flit amid the glittering sunbeams of creation, as the monster's breath spreads over their atmospheric abodes. But I must hasten. We will now return to notice the further progress of our noble ship, which is still upon the crests of the Atlantic surges, gliding along over every rising obstacle with wonderful rapidity. But on the evening of a cool and windy day, soon after the sailing out, appearances indicated a fearful storm. The night was setting in disagreeable and windy; the day, which was rather raw for the season, was in September. Rifts of ragged, gusty clouds driving<pb n="22-23" xml:id="VAC6292-00000012"/> furiously before a strong blast, had chased each other across the firmament, now covering the sun in their murky folds, arid now as they rolled apart, disclosing his cold disk to vision. As night drew on, and the clouds grew darker in the eastern sky, the, gale sang shriller than ever through the rigging of the vessel, whistling wildly along over the fast blackening waters, and making all on board shiver involuntarily at its mournful tone. Nothing could be grander than the scene. The entire horizon was lined with a huge mass of angry clouds, black, wild and ominous, which constantly heaved one above another far into the sky. Heap above heap, pile above pile, embattlement above embattlement, rose the dark purple vapors, only here and there a patch of blue sky smiling through their rugged edges. The luminary of day was just setting, and the wreath of phantom clouds having rolled partially away, he burst out for a moment in full splendor, dyeing the western sky in gold, making the raging billows glitter as they undulated, and lighting up the whole eastern firmament with a strange and almost spectral hue. The incessant shifting of the clouds, the ever varying hues of the sky, and above all, the dreamy aspect of the eastern void, gave an ominous appearance to the scene, which filled the mind with the darkest consternation. Far away the entire horizon was white with snowy foam, while an almost interminable line of light marked the outline of the sky above.</p>
               <p>Presently the murky clouds dissevered away into the East, and the moon bursting forth in unrivaled splendor, the sister luminaries of night and day, were seen at the same time. Directly, however, the sun sank beneath the waters, while a faint streak of crimson lingered for a moment in the horizon. The edges of the clouds above, now grew more and more imperceptibly tinged with gold, and then one by one darkening into the deepest shade, they filled the western sky, spreading broader and higher, and hanging like a gloomy curtain over sea, and heaven. At length the wild wind came tempestuously from the West, and the black and heavy cloud, heaving to and fro uncertainly, broke into mighty fragments, rolled up in solid masses, and went diving away before the gale, while our gallant ship, yielding to the greater press upon her sails, careened towards the horizon and then drove rapidly along, the water bubbling along by her sides, and the ascending and descending spray breaking half mast high over her bow. The breeze now came warmer, large drops of rain began to fall, and every aspect around betokened one of those powerful tempests that so often howl over the majestic Atlantic. Soon the entire sky was clothed in the most tenebrious habiliments, and as the irresistible blast swept like some superhuman power over land and sea, prostrating the loftiest oak to the ground, hurling stately and magnificent vessels into awful concavities, the instantaneous roars and hoarse mutterings of the agitated thunder coming in contact with the fiery flashes of the red and illuminating lightning was sublime to hear and see. Onward and onward the tremendous hurricane swept, rocking the foam crested billows of the vasty deep into tumultuous commotion, and as their mountain pinnacles undulated higher and higher, almost kissing the animated drapery of the storm clouds, other waves of lesser magnitude plunged angrily into the black and yawning vortexes of wrath, formed by heaving billows, and hurling to the raven sky, the thick foamy vapors of recent concussions. Atramental night now arose from oblivious surges, wrapping her black mantel around the scene, and now, as the huge battle clouds were about ceasing the disgorgements of their inundating torrents, the gorgeous radiancy of the half transparent orb of nocturnal nature, ever and anon threw her re-enlivening effulgence over the battling of vehement elements, but to no avail, for instantaneously a portentous vestige of the furious storm stole over her beautiful face.</p>
               <p>But now, where is our vessel? Ah sad to relate, she has certainly foundered in the storm, for she is no where to be seen. Ask of the fragments that cover the sea for miles around. If they could answer, in tones of howling thunder, the voice would say; "The once lovely American craft is no more."</p>
               <p>Such was indeed the fact, for while the darkest and most gigantic cloud was bursting in concentrated violence, over her lofty masts, and pouring its overwhelming flood of water into the sea, the ship careened, now one side dipping the water, and now the other side lifting high into the air, and then as a sudden hurricane of wind swept by, she went over and was soon engulphed beneath the mighty<pb n="24-25" xml:id="VAC6292-00000013"/> waste of tumultuousness, shattering into myriad fragments, and scattering her multitudinous vestiges over the distorted seas.</p>
               <p>Such was the unhappy and melancholy fate of our once pretty and well constructed vessel, in which, the hero of our story was a passenger.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER IX.</head>
               <p>Sophia, who had been listening to the insulting remarks of the Empress, arose and boldly said: "Let her tremble whose conscience pronounces her guilty; I am innocent. Beware yourself, false and cruel woman. Harm but a hair of my head, and the nation will rise in arms to avenge me."</p>
               <p>"The nation!" exclaimed Catherine, mockingly, "they believe you dead."</p>
               <p>"You are mistaken," said Sophia, "they know that I am alive-, and are now within an hour's march of Borodino-and more, my friends are at this moment rising all around, armed as they are, mustering for march and battle. Ere sunset my banner will be floating in the breeze."</p>
               <p>"Before sunset your head will be beside, the block," uttered the Empress." "Here, guards, arrest this traitress."</p>
               <p>The wide doors of the apartment were flung open, and a band of armed men marched in at the call of the Empress.</p>
               <p>"Seize this woman," cried Catherine"bear her to a remote chamber, and there keep strict watch over her till further orders, and you Padries, prepare an axe and block in the court yard; there Will be work for you soon. Let Ivan mount directly and ride for Moscow, and bid the commander march here four regiments of the household guards; we must be ready for all hazards." She waved her hand and the soldiers withdrew with their prisoner, whom they consigned to a strong and secure apartment, at the door of which two guards were posted. The executioner busied himself with the preparations for his dreadful office, while the courier posted to the capital to hurry up the reinforcements to Borodino.</p>
               <p>After her victim had been carried away, the Empress paced the room with hasty steps, like an angry tigress in her cage, and while thus occupied, Count Bocaris presented himself, and kneeling, kissed the hand of his sovereign. "Our trusty Bocaris," said the Empress, with a gracious smile. "Rise, Alexander, here is not the sovereign and the vassal, but the fond trusting woman and her favored lover. Oh, how weary I am of these cares of state; how often I envy the happiness of the very serfs; I wish I wore a peasant maiden, with you for my companion."</p>
               <p>"How proud and happy you make me feel," said the Count, but there was a paleness in his cheek and an anxious expression in his glance that belied his words.</p>
               <p>"Sometimes," said the Empress, in the same gentle tone, "I think you cannot truly love me; I think your passion must be feigned; I look in the mirror, and it tells me I am no longer the Catherine I was twenty years ago; that the soft rose tints have faded from my cheek, and the love light from my eye, and when I see you, young, beautiful and vigorous, I ask, will Alexander Bocaris seek a fitter mate?"</p>
               <p>"Alexander Bocaris seeks no other love," said the Count in a low tone.</p>
               <p>"I believe you, Bocaris," said the Empress, "and hence I will trust you with my dearest secrets. That poor girl I have been compelled to arrest and place in confinement."</p>
               <p>"That, then, was the meaning of the armed men, I saw in the apartment," Said the Count.</p>
               <p>"A hard necessity," pursued the Empress, "compelled us to place in that condition, one who is dangerous."</p>
               <p>"And I trust, madam," said the Count, "that her deprivation of liberty will be deemed an adequate precaution."</p>
               <p>"No, Bocaris," replied the Empress, with a false sigh of regret. "If you will look into the court yard, you will nee that dreadful<pb n="26-27" xml:id="VAC6292-00000014"/> Padries, sharpening his horrid implement of death, and the block being erected. I cannot bear to look on it."</p>
               <p>"Good God!" exclaimed the Count, "what does this mean?"</p>
               <p>"It means," answered the Empress, "that the Princess Sophia dies at sunset."</p>
               <p>"You cannot mean it!" cried the Count. "Dearest Catherine, what has this poor young girl done?"</p>
               <p>"Nothing," replied the Empress, "not for what she has done, but what she is, we have resolved to take her life. She is the rightful heiress of the throne. We know it, Alexander."</p>
               <p>"True, true," replied the agonized Count, still trying to conceal his anguish. "But she has no friends,"</p>
               <p>"I fear you are mistaken," said the Empress. "The country is rising."</p>
               <p>"But you have troops enough to quell a revolt," said Bocaris.</p>
               <p>"My dear sir," resumed Catherine, "you cannot perceive the difference between a revolt and a revolution. Besides, why should I wish to spill the blood of my brave soldiers uselessly? even the lives of insurgents are worth something. If Sophia lives, they will fight with desperation, but if her head is exposed to view on the gates of Moscow, they will surrender at discretion."</p>
               <p>Bocaris threw himself at the feet of the Empress, and clasped her hand. "My gracious mistress," said he, "hear me. Enough blood has been already spilt; you are powerful, but you may be merciful. Spare the life of this poor girl, and your clemency will disarm her adherents, and make her your friend, if indeed she is your enemy. If it be otherwise, I pledge myself to quell the insurrection, if it be attempted, or perish in the effort. By the love I bear you, by the fealty I owe you, I conjure you to grant this request, for your sake and for mine."</p>
               <p>"Rise, Bocaris," said the Empress, "you have asked me a priceless favor. Had you asked me to abdicate the throne, you would hardly have demanded more; but when did I ever frown upon you? Sophia shall not die."</p>
               <p>"Oh, joy of joy!" wildly exclaimed the Count, "Sophia saved; I care not what happens to me now; I would welcome death like a bride to my arms. I will fly to Sophia with the news."</p>
               <p>"Hold, traitor," said the Empress, "I revoke the promise. Do you deem me blind or idiotic? You have betrayed yourself. In that wild outbreak of delerious joy, you stood confessed. What the Turkish spy told me is all true, you are a false and perjured villain, you love the Princess."</p>
               <p>"It is true, devil in woman's shape," cried the Count; "I loathe the part I have so long acted, and I will speak out, were each word a cruel death. There was a time when passion blinded me to your defects, but I long since learned to know you the monster that you are. Nature wished to create a prodigy of wickedness and villany in a form of beauty, she placed the heart of a tigress, she infused venom instead of blood in the veins, she filled the brain with foul and leprous thoughts, and the monstrous creation was called Catherine."</p>
               <p>"Crazy railer!" replied the Empress, with indignation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER X.</head>
               <p>The question may now arise, "did Henry Weston perish in the late dreadful shipwreck?" No, kind reader, he was providentially saved, but was the only survivor of the appalling disaster.</p>
               <p>After the vessel had been overwhelmed in the terrific surges, her bow, for an instant, merged into the air, and at one of these fortunate junctures, Henry leaped from the shattering mass into the billowy sea, and with remarkable presence of mind, clung to a floating timber, and with his kerchief bound himself to it, and when he had regained an easy position, he cried out for others to follow his example. But it was too late! Silence, reigned supreme, with the exception of the wild roar of the agitated deep, and the dying rumbling of distant thunder.</p>
               <p>Henry remained in this unpleasant condition for thirty hours, subsisting on such food as he-had luckily provided himself with before the approach of the storm.</p>
               <pb n="28-29" xml:id="VAC6292-00000015"/>
               <p>Glad must have been his feelings, when on the morning of the third day, he observed a frigate afar off to the left. She was apparently directing her course toward our, hero.</p>
               <p>While the ship was rapidly passing him far to the left, he jerked from his pocket a red sash, which he wore in time of battle, and extending his arm up as high as possible, he waved the ensign of distress to and fro, while at the same time he gave vent to his voice, crying out vehemently, and with stentorophonic power, "Man overboard! Save me, or I perish!"</p>
               <p>Fortunately the captain of the frigate perceived him, and instantly commanded two able sailors to launch the yawl, and endeavor to rescue the distressed one.</p>
               <p>Immediately the boat was upon the turbid waters, and the seamen seizing the paddles, struck, many an able blow. In a few moments they were beside him, and no time was lost in assisting him into the boat. They soon reached the ship, and after aiding him to the deck, bore him into the cabin. Here he was properly attended to by the humane officers.</p>
               <p>This frigate was bound for Brest, France, and was now about two hundred miles from that seaport, which information was imparted to Henry by the kind captain, who then informed the officer that the circumstance suited him precisely, as he was traveling to Russia.</p>
               <p>In a few days the vessel arrived at her destination, and then, as Henry took leave of the kind officers and others, who had contributed so much to his welfare while ill on the ship, he could not thank them sufficiently for their noble conduct.</p>
               <p>Henry procured a horse, and was soon wending his way through the western part of France.</p>
               <p>Suffice it to say, he arrived safe and unharmed at Borodino, Russia, after completing a severe journey over snow and ice, mountainous regions and rocky defiles.</p>
               <p>Here he secretly assumed the dress of a common Russian soldier, and remained concealed in an obscure hotel, and while snugly ensconced here, he endeavored to obtain a satisfactory statement of present affairs and circumstances, which he soon came in possession of by the assistance of the frequently intoxicated landlord.</p>
               <p>There he continued in concealment until some future period favored his innate designs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER XI.</head>
               <p>"And add to your catalogue of crimes," continued the Count, "the murder of this poor girl. But it will be the last, for the day of reckoning is coming. Fierce men, burning to avenge their own and their country's wrongs, are gathering around you a countless host. They are mustering now in the name of Sophia, the heiress to the throne. If her blood dyes the block, they strike for Sophia the martyr."</p>
               <p>"Ah!" replied the Empress, "I have troops and treasure. I have been menaced ere this, but I bear a charmed life."</p>
               <p>"Enjoy your little hour," cried the Count, on your death-warrant is signed."</p>
               <p>"Go, go, madman," said the Empress, "I pity and despise you; and to show you how supreme is my contempt, I pardon you."</p>
               <p>With innumerable curses on his lips, Bocaris fled from her presence, and endeavored to seek an interview with Sophia, but he was repulsed by the guards. In his despair he flew to the courtyard, where the preparations for the death of the Princess had been completed, and there resolved to await the final scene of the tragedy and share the fate of his beloved.</p>
               <p>At length the trumpet sounded, and the large gate being opened, a numerous concourse of cavalry and infantry entered, and marching into the court-yard, formed a hollow square around it. The block, the executioner, and the heart-broken Count, remaining in the centre.</p>
               <p>When the lines had been formed, the Empress, richly clad in furred robes, and wearing the insignia of her rank, appeared upon a balcony overhanging the scene, and commanded the prisoner to be brought forth.</p>
               <pb n="30-31" xml:id="VAC6292-00000016"/>
               <p>A considerable pause ensued, and then the officer to whose charge Sophia had been committed, appeared with a pale countenance in the court-yard:</p>
               <p>"Mistress," he exclaimed, "the prisoner has escaped!"</p>
               <p>"Escaped?" cried the Empress with alarm, "Liar, it is impossible!"</p>
               <p>"It would seem so, your majesty," replied the officer; "her window is forty feet from the ground, but it is open and she is gone."</p>
               <p>"Arrest that traitor!" cried the enraged Empress, designating the Count. "Scour the country far and wide; if the Princess is not found, Alexander Bocaris dies in her place." *   *   *   *</p>
               <p>In the heart of an umbrageous forest, in the centre of a vast area, from which the tall and towering trees had been swept by the woodman's axe, a huge fire roared and crackled, diffusing light and warmth over a wide circumference. The ruddy glare fell upon the bearded faces of a formidable band of Russian soldiers, all armed to the teeth, and a few of them mounted.</p>
               <p>Beneath a canopy of furs sat the Princess, supported on the right by the aged Bayard Roulet, and surrounded by devoted followers. Roulet had ascertained the place of her confinement through his spies, and found means to communicate with Sophia. He had encouraged her to take the fearful leap from the window, while men stationed below had received her light form upon a couch of soft skins, which broke the force of her fall. As this mode of escape had been unforeseen, and the window of her prison chamber was screened from observation by a clump of thick collected vines, they had been enabled to bear her off in triumph. They had now just sworn allegiance to her, and were concerting offensive measures against the reigning Empress.</p>
               <p>"Friends," exclaimed Roulet, "let us strike a signal blow at first; let us seize the tigress in her den. The Empress is at Borodino, poorly guarded by four imbecile regiments. If we cannot storm the, palace, we can consign it to the flames. Once in the open field, we can cut her troops to pieces and make ourselves masters of her person."</p>
               <p>Fierce hurrahs greeted the Bayard's plan.</p>
               <p>"And then," continued Roulet, "to the block with her and her minion, Bocaris; yes, the vile wretch who sought the Princess in Genoa, feigned love for her, and then conveyed her off for the sole purpose of surrendering her into the hands of the cruel Catherine."</p>
               <p>"Death to the favorite!" shouted the multitude.</p>
               <p>"Roulet," shrieked Sophia, "if all this blood is to be shed on my account, then I decline the crown."</p>
               <p>"Retain your courage," said the Bayard. "We will come off victorious without any great loss of life."</p>
               <p>The preparations for the march were soon made; the fire was extinguished, and the rash multitude was formed in column of march.</p>
               <p>Roulet placed Sophia on a horse and mounted another beside her, and the insurgents moved on in the direction of Borodino. As they advanced the ground became more difficult, and the path so narrow that they were compelled to march in single file.</p>
               <p>During the whole time but one thought had occupied her mind, and that was the idea of escaping.</p>
               <p>To move with a body of savage men, who, perhaps, ere long were to engage in bloody contest, was to participate in their crimes.</p>
               <p>Fortune favored her designs. There was a halt in the column, just at a point where a bridle path diverged to the right. Roulet having moved forward to give orders, the Princess, undetected in the darkness, turned her horse to the right, and noiselessly receded from the rank. When so far that the sound of horse's feet could no longer be distinguished, she started him into a gallop, trusting to his instinct to carry her through the forest.</p>
               <p>After riding sometime, she was suddenly startled by the challenge, "who goes there?"</p>
               <p>Wearied in body and mind, her intelligence forsook her, and she exclaimed:</p>
               <p>"Spare my life. I surrender at discretion. I am the unhappy Princess, Sophia."</p>
               <p>"Lady," said the stranger, "my name is Kara, the Turkish spy; I am the friend of Bocaris, and I rode out with a few followers, in search of you. Bocaris is safe, and if you wish,. I will conduct you to him."</p>
               <pb n="32-33" xml:id="VAC6292-00000017"/>
               <p>"I am not so very anxious to see him," replied the Princess, "but as I cannot prevent you, I resign myself to your care and conduct."</p>
               <p>The wily Turk rode at her side, followed by his men. The party soon reached Borodino, where the prisoner was installed in a room she had never visited, as the impression was sought to be conveyed to her that she was in a wholly strange place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER XII.</head>
               <p>As the Princess was anticipating a speedy union with her beloved Henry, whom she thought was now on his way to Russia, the dreaded Catherine suddenly appeared before her astonished eyes. The lips of the Empress wore a smile of haughty and malignant triumph.</p>
               <p>"So, fair one," said the Empress, "we meet again after a brief absence; you are once more in my power."</p>
               <p>"Ah," replied Sophia, "you may doom me to death, but I will be happy in that awful hour."</p>
               <p>"Alexander Bocaris," cried the Empress, with a taunting laugh, "is a traitor, but he loves you. Look here and read the faith of Bocaris."</p>
               <p>With these words the Empress placed in her hand a letter written at Genoa, acquainting the Empress of his arrival and of his first interview with Sophia. This, it will be remembered, was before Bocaris had shaken off the thraldom of his imperial mistress.</p>
               <p>The letter was filled with passionate declarations to Catherine, with regret at his forced absence, and with promises to decoy his victim into the power of her enemy.</p>
               <p>This was just what Sophia expected to learn. The Empress then left her, but she was not left long alone, for Alexander Bocaris came to throw himself at her feet.</p>
               <p>"Dearest Sophia," said the Count, "I come to say a few words to you. I have bribed the jailors, I have bought your guards; the path is open to liberty and love."</p>
               <p>But the Princess shrank from him into the remotest corner of the apartment, and stood there shivering and muttering incoherent words with pale lips.</p>
               <p>"Sophia, speak," cried the Count. "Tell me what paralyzes you thus."</p>
               <p>"Away! away" shrieked the Princess: "Approach me not, you will kill me. Are you not the vile Bocaris?"</p>
               <p>"Your Bocaris," said the Count.</p>
               <p>Sophia, then bursting into tears, said; "yes, yes, you are my betrayer, you speak falsely. Go to the Empress, she is waiting for you. Leave me here to die; you planned my death between you."</p>
               <p>"Sophia," cried the Count, "do have mercy on me. I know I have acted wrongly, but I repent. Will you forgive me?"</p>
               <p>"No, never!" said the Princess. "I have just read a letter which you wrote, and being convinced of your wrongs, I am forever done with you."</p>
               <p>Bocaris said no more, but hastily fled from the room.</p>
               <p>But it was too late. The passage was barred by imperial guards. Behind their close files stood the Empress, towering with pride and passion.</p>
               <p>"To the block with them both!" was her stern mandate; and they were hurried to the court-yard, where the fatal paraphernalia of death were still standing.</p>
               <p>Thither went the Empress, leaning fondly on the/arm of the Turk, Kara, her new favorite.</p>
               <p>"Cruel Catharine," said Bocaris, as he laid aside his rich collar, "you shall see with What firmness a Russian soldier can die; farewell!"</p>
               <p>"Let me die first," said the Princess, kneeling.</p>
               <p>"To the block with Bocaris first!" repeated Catherine.</p>
               <p>The attendants held the Princess, while Bocaris kneeled and bowed his neck upon the fatal block.</p>
               <pb n="34-35" xml:id="VAC6292-00000018"/>
               <p>The next instant the severed head lay on the pavement a mutilated fragment</p>
               <p>Sophia was then commanded to kneel and lay her head upon the bloody wood.</p>
               <p>The executioner reared his glittering axe on high, but at that moment a dull roar, like that of an advancing army of tumultuous waters, arrested his arm, and distracted the attention of even the Empress. Nearer and more distinctly came the sound, and now they recognised the trampling of horses, the footfalls of infantry, and the clash of arms.</p>
               <p>"Bar the gates," exclaimed the Empress, "the rebels are upon us!"</p>
               <p>But it was too late. Before order could be obeyed, Henry Weston, who had just joined the insurgents, accompanied by Roulet and his mounted followers, leading the van of a mighty army, burst irresistibly into the court-yard. In an instant Henry leaped from his horse, and dashing like an infuriated lion into the assembled multitude, he threw his arms around the fainting Princess, and returned quickly to his companions. So sudden and startling was this movement, that the followers of the Empress stood like huge statues of marble, surveying the scene.</p>
               <p>Henry immediately bore his precious burden to a place of safety, and then seizing a sword, led the army forward against the troops of the Empress. Kara crossed his path, but he clove the miscreant from head to heel, and sprang over his prostrate body in pursuit of the Empress, but she, surrounded by her guards, retreated into the palace, the doors and windows of which were closed against the advancing beseigers. Some of her soldiers mounted to the roof and there hurled down huge fragments of stone and heavy timbers upon the partizans of the Princess.</p>
               <p>"Try them with fire!" shouted Henry, whose clarion voice was heard high above the roar and din of tumult.</p>
               <p>In an instant a hundred burning torches were applied to various combustible parts of the edifice, and it was soon wrapped in one vast sheet of lurid flame.</p>
               <p>Some of the soldiers rushed out to meet death at the hands of the infuriated insurgents, while others fled from story to story, pursued, by the devouring element, winning thus a temporary reprieve.</p>
               <p>For a few minutes the palace was a gigantic funeral pyre, and on its loftiest battlement stood the Empress, her garments on fire, and her countenance expressing agony and despair. She tottered for a moment in the ascending volumes of smoke and flame, then leaped and fell upon the pavement of the court-yard.</p>
               <p>At that moment rose a wild shout that shook the ruins of the blazing palace: Long live Sophia, Empress of Russia."</p>
               <p>The Princess then showed herself to her adherants, amidst the deafening shouts and hurrahs of enthusiastic joy, and when she approached and took the hand of Henry Weston, whose noble figure bore traces of the giant-like gallantry with which he had fought, the multitude, with another sudden outburst of transport, added, "And long live Henry Weston, the preserver of Sophia,!"</p>
               <p>With this night of terror ended the trials and troubles of Sophia, and the next day, within the massive walls of a gorgeous and magnificent church, amidst the continuous shouts of the concourse, Henry Weston and Sophia were united in marriage, after which splendid ceremony, the enraptured soldiers struck up a harmonious delightful strain of music, that seemed to resound and reverberate its soft, silvery, but deep toned voice, in grand harmony throughout the expansive atmosphere.</p>
               <p>While the ceremony was proceeding, the Princess was surprised to see the dreadful Catherine in the motly crowd. She indeed conjectured that she had been killed by her fearful leap from the burning palace, but she was mistaken. The Empress escaped unhurt.</p>
               <p>Directly after the nuptial ceremonies were concluded, a beautiful young woman, arrayed in costly robes, approached and bowed to Sophia, and in sweet musical tones, said, "Sophia, I have a few words to say to you, and if you will listen I will proceed."</p>
               <p>"Do so," replied the Princess.</p>
               <p>"Dearest lady," began the maiden, "there is a truth which I am now about to expose to you; it may seem rather strange and singular, nevertheless it is true. I have frequently endeavored to seek an interview with you, but unfortunately have as often failed;<pb n="36-37" xml:id="VAC6292-00000019"/> and now as my wish has been most willingly complied with, I proceed to relate the facts as they are:</p>
               <p>"Seventeen years ago, to-day, I and my sister were playing together in infancy; five days afterwards a lady visited us, and continued her visits day by day, and at last succeeded in enticing us from our room, and after proceeding with us to the gateway, surrendered us into the hands of a few soldiers, who immediately bore us to whence I could not tell. As I was the oldest, my sister often clung to my side, moaning and grieving very much; but despite of our cries and lamentations we were conveyed to a distant city, and there committed to the care of an old resident, who promised faithfully that he would retain us as long as he lived. But one day I fortunately escaped from his presence and wandered off, far from my sister and the old man.</p>
               <p>"That sister stands before me; that building from which we were rudely torn, was the palace which so recently was destroyed; that lady who enticed us from our room, was the Empress Catherine; that old man unto whose care we were committed, was Angelo Harmone. The rest you know."</p>
               <p>No sooner had she uttered these startling words, than Sophia/ overcome with joy, and overwhelmed with surprise, sank back and became insensible.</p>
               <p>Presently, however, she revived, and instantaneously was locked in the tender embrace of her sister. This unexpected meeting can be better imagined than described.</p>
               <p>On the next morning the loving sisters held an interview in the spacious parlor of a splendid oriental mansion. They were alone; nothing around contributed to destroy the sweetness of the conversation.</p>
               <p>About mid-day Sophia's sister rose to leave. "Remember," said Sophia, "that I will gladly relinquish all claims to royalty, in order to assist you in preparing for your station, for you being the oldest, are indisputably the heir of the throne. Go, assume the duties of your office, and may wealth, honor and prosperity attend you. Farewell, sister; we shall never meet again in this world, but if we live right while here, we will meet in the realms of a celestial paradise. God be with you."</p>
               <p>Soon after this affectionate interview, Henry, accompanied by his lovely bride, proceeded to one of the most beautiful cities of Italy, and there enjoying the sweets of uninterrupted love and happy companionship, the loving twain resided, exempt from the trials and troubles which attend absolute sovereignty, and happy in the anticipation of meeting dissevered families in a heaven of pure and endless delight.</p>
               <p>But sad to relate, the beautiful sister of Sophia, was, by a command of the cruel dethroned Catherine, arrested and placed in confinement beneath the marble corridor of the destroyed palace, and then after a series of conflicts, the Empress came off victorious, and amid the shouts of her armies, re-ascended the throne of Russia, (from which she had so recently been expelled,) and for many years she swayed her iron sceptre of despotism and power, over the wide extended possessions of Russia, despite the continual attempts which were made to dethrone her.</p>
               <p>When Henry and Sophia were acquainted of this startling intelligence, they at once concluded to remain, not caring to endanger their lives in another revolt against the cruel Catherine, for it seemed nothing could debar her, and if armed legions of the bravest men in Europe, were to have joined in overthrowing her supreme power, it would not have resulted in any thing fortunate. Therefore, Henry and his beloved companion, concluded that to remain in Italy would be much better than to go and mingle again in endeavoring to destroy the power and authority of one whose tyrannical actions were and are still proverbial in Russian history.</p>
               <p>I will now conclude, leaving the hero and heroine of our story basking in the superlative glory of an Italian sun, with every prospect of joy and happiness before them, while far back in the chasm of the past, reposed those trials, difficulties and vicissitudes of life, which once attended them in their course through the season of danger, and which seemed to be but introductory anticipations of fortune and happiness.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>